Good afternoon and welcome to the 2025
Drestle House lecture. Uh my name is
Vladimir Bulovich. the director of MIT
nano professor here at MIT and I have
truly the honor of welcoming uh this
year's dress house lecture professor
Jennifer Lewis.
Professor Lewis is a vast professor of
biologically inspired engineering at the
Pollson School of Engineering and
Applied Sciences at Harvard. Um she's
also a core faculty member at the V
Institute for Biologically Inspired
Engineering. Her research focuses on the
digital manufacturing of functional,
structural and biological materials.
Multiple startups are initiated from her
work commercializing technologies of her
lab ranging from 3D printed electronics
to kidney therapeutics.
Elected member of the National Academy
of Sciences, National Academy of
Engineering, National Academy of
Inventors and the American Academy of
Arts and Sciences. uh she has received
clearly numerous awards for her work
including the NAS James prize for
science technology integration and today
we will honor her with a dress
lecturesship. Uh, Professor Lewis
exemplifies in so many ways the spirit
of Millie Drestle House, our beloved
Millie uh, who was the pioneer in the
approach to materials research and who
bridged fundamental science and
transformative technology in her own
work.
Milliey's groundbreaking work indeed is
well known and a groundbreaking work of
Professor Lewis in 3D printing and
bioinspired materials continues that
legacy.
I am honored to indeed invite her to
join me up here and indeed deliver the
dress house lecture. Welcome.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Well, I'd like to begin by by thanking
Vladimir. When he called me um to extend
the invitation, I said yes immediately.
And for many people who know me,
speaking in public is actually not my
favorite thing to do, but I I couldn't
pass up a chance to really honor uh
Millie Drestle House. Um we all know her
as an exceptional scholar, teacher, and
mentor, but I have to say for me at MIT,
she was a role model.
I came to MIT roughly 40 years ago as a
graduate student in uh material science
in course three and pretty early on
walking the infinite corridor back and
forth on a daily basis I came across
Professor Drestle House and she always
had a cardigan on and typically it was
red. There was that exact cardigan and
she was weighted down with two heavy
tote bags full of work and hustling,
always hustling. And I didn't know who
she was at first, but she absolutely
captivated my attention. And of course
after those first few weeks of seeing
her in the hallway, I became aware of
who she was, who Professor Professor
Millie Drestle House was, that she was a
force, that she was really a leader in
in material science in in condensed
matter physics. And you know, I have to
say beyond beyond that, she's had a a
large impact on my career. So, first I I
have to say as a as a PhD student back
at that time when there were very few
female PhD students, uh let alone female
faculty, just seeing someone of her
stature and being able to have these
sightings in the hallway was really an
inspiration to me. And then subsequently
when I became a faculty member at the
University of Illinois um I ultimately
led the materials research lab there
which was heavily funded by DOEBS and
Millie Drestle House was really a legend
at DOE. She actually served as the
director of the office of science for
some time and having her support and
mentorship in my role as MRL director
also made a huge impact uh on my
professional development. So that's
really my tie to Millie and uh I thank
her very much for all that she's done
for her amazing inspiration both as a
student as a faculty member and even now
today now many of you might look at this
building and wonder what the heck is
that? That's the old building 12. So I
do have a tie to MIT Nano in a very
loose way. Um you see this uh lab right
there was where I did my own PhD
research. many years ago. We called that
the fishbowl because people would walk
down the sidewalk and looking at us. We
kind of felt like we were fish in a
tank, if you will. Um, but it was an
amazing time. Um, in this period of of
four years, um, high temperature
superconductivity was discovered. Um,
and 3D printing was really born and that
was born out of a collaboration between
Ellie Sachs in mechanical engineering
and my PhD adviser, Michael Sema. And
they really coined the term
three-dimensional printing. And of
course there are myriad methods and
we'll talk a little bit about that in a
moment. Um but from that lab of course
um we we have uh MIT Nano now and what a
fantastic building. I was in there today
and I was reminded as I saw the people
working in the clean room in their bunny
suits that actually my last year as a
PhD student I dawned the bunny suit many
times working uh to create very
primitive micrfluidic devices um in
Raphael Reich's lab. So I have a tie to
MIT Nano, not only in location, but also
uh in in in in reality. Um, but of
course uh back in the day I was working
on devices that were far less
sophisticated than the amazing things
that you guys are building now using
that facility. And I want to give a big
shout out to Vladimir and all those that
really contributed to realizing this
vision because it's had a huge impact on
the MIT community at large.
So the last thing I want to say before I
dive in is to just recognize that a
statement by Millie that says if you
don't have material you don't have an
experiment. So as a material scientist
of course that's the kind of exactly the
kind of thing we want to hear right
without materials there are there is no
engineering right so um with that in
mind let's think about um how as a
material scientists I was drawn into 3D
printing of course I said it was
happening in in the lab in the ecosystem
I was a graduate student in but I really
didn't start working in in this field
until I left and started my own lab and
then I took a different approach to the
binder printing on on a powder said, but
as a material scientist around the same
time in 1990, there was an NAS study
focusing on the materials paradigm and
MERT funings led this study and there
was a big decal report and it really
made this connection that how you make a
material affects its structure and it
affects its properties. And from that
perspective, it was a light bulb moment
for me to think about 3D printing beyond
just prototyping and making shapes, but
really being able to control local
composition structure and properties
across multiple scales. But that also
necessitated some advances in 3D
printing. If we think about the kinds of
methods that are exist, you know, it's
ubiquitous now, but 30 plus years ago,
it was still pretty primitive. The
earliest embodiment of these printing
modalities were really good at just
shaping material. There wasn't really
functional materials coming out of these
printers. Um, and in the meantime, of
course, the field has advanced across
many axes. Lightbased patterning is now
making things like our midsoles for for
running shoes. Um, we've got binder, you
know, printing and laser fusion making
metal parts for high-end fuel jet
injectors for things that are being used
commercially. um extrusion based methods
like uh FDM and and a technique that
we've helped advance direct ink writing
and then inkjet printing uh directly
where you're directly printing jettable
materials that could be UV cur cured and
so all of these methods I think are are
important but what we tried to do uh
early on in this process was really
bring in more function so integrate not
just form but function in 3D printed
components and that really required ired
a lot of uh effort across many years to
develop principal materials to develop
um many components and I'll highlight a
few things today in in the time that I
have basically advances that we've made
across printing platforms across print
path planning algorithms to basically
you know design uh through inverse
design and graph-based tool planning how
we can optimize the print path
themselves multimaterial print heads so
we can integrate functional materials
with structural materials and so forth.
And then really I think at the core of
this coming back to this you need
materials part is we developed this a
really a broad array of visco elastic
inks and matrices that can be printable
and that opened up a lot of the examples
that you saw on that last slide. So
let's start with just some of the
printing platforms that we've developed.
These are extrusionbased methods. The
nice thing about these methods, I think,
from the perspective of being able to
use these in in research capacity to
advance research is that they're very
amendable to a broad range of
functional, structural, and biological
materials. They're really modular ink
designs. You can plug and play multiple
types of building blocks into these
inks. And you can see, for example, here
in direct writing, this is a filamentary
process. So these materials are being
extruded. They're visco elastic in
nature. We also developed a process
called embedded 3D printing where
instead of printing everything, we can
mold some of the components and only
print the functional features. This is
actually a vascular tree. This was very
early on uh back in 2011 where we did
this work, but it really led to us also
then moving away from hydrogel
ascellular matrices to densely cellular
matrices where you can embed vascule
into human tissue. And we call that
approach swift uh sacrificial writing in
functional tissue. So with that in mind
then we also developed different
algorithms for controlling print path.
And one of the ones that recently came
out of our lab is called arrow. And the
idea here is when you are printing these
kinds of embedded printing modalities
there's a lot of starts and stops where
you're moving the nozzle in and out of
the matrix. And you really want to
minimize those starts and stops and you
also want to minimize the disruption to
the other printed features. So this is a
very simple graph uh graph theory based
approach where you can see that it
speeds up the time for printing.
Now complimentary to that we've also
developed a number of nozzles and
printing modalities that all rely on
these same types of materials but either
you know using switching and
multi-noszle uh arrays to do voxillated
printing on demand or these adaptive
nozzles that can go over um nonlinear uh
kurolinear substrates or a rotational
print head that can bring multiple
materials into a single filament to be
able to even give you something like
subboxating control.
So at the heart of all of this of course
is the materials and how do we develop
these materials? They have to have this
appropriate visco elastic response in
order to have this ability to flow when
their sheer yield stress is exceeded
during the printing process. But then as
they exit the nozzle in a quesuscent
state they become rapidly solidike. We
do most of our printing at room
temperature. We're not relying on any
kind of um external fields to to uh
solidify these materials. We're really
just relying on the inherent visco
elasticity of the of the inks in the
matrices.
Now, we also worked very closely with
Howard Stone's lab to look at the design
of the visco elastic matrices for
embedded printing. What are the key
components and considerations as you're
moving a nozzle through a matrix? How do
you avoid um uh locally yielding printed
features that are uh surrounding the
filaments that you've already printed?
And so here we under we unraveled the
role of the sheer yield stress and the
printing speed and how one can tailor
that to enhance the fidelity of the
printing process itself. And that leads
to the kinds of lises that you can see
here where um we can print in three
dimensions very complex architectures.
So, from the perspective of of materials
and inks and matrices, um, as I said,
these are really plug-and-play kinds of
modular designs. And I'm going to
highlight just three examples in the
context of of various applications. Work
that we've done really early on in
developing particle-based inks based on
the gellation of colloidal particles,
hydrogel based inks, and um these
granular building blocks that that serve
as matrices for engineering of
vascularized human tissues. In this
case, you're looking at cardiac
spheroids that have been derived from
human IPS cells. Um and these are
multisellular aggregates.
Now putting this into context, I'm a
material scientist. Roughly 12 years ago
when I moved to Harvard, we opened up
our lab in bioprinting and in biology.
And I had to kind of learn the language
of the biologists. So I'm coming at it
from knowing this very well particles,
aggregates, gilation, polymers, etc. But
how do I make the connection in my own
mind and then more broadly here to the
kinds of building blocks that we think
about on the living side? Well, we can
kind of think in our own minds about
particles being like cells and
aggregates being like multisellular
aggregates and then polymers that we
might use for scaffolds and other things
are kind of like the extracellular
matrices that support the cells
themselves. And ultimately when we want
to write pneumatic networks for say soft
robots or blood vessels for for tissues,
we need some sort of sacrificial
material that we can erase that will
leave behind these channels. And so
that's important for both uh types of
modalities.
I won't go into all the details here,
but this really kind of captures um many
many experiments that we've done over
over a decade plus of time where we're
tuning realology and we're also trying
to tune the resolidification part. How
do we keep those inks that come out of
the nozzle in a filamentary form in in
that form so that they don't wet and
spread? How can we ensure that they
resolidify, that they stay in place,
that we can build layers on top of them
and they don't sag or deform? And there
are many types of of modalities that
we've of of that we've uh really
employed, including just reversible
yielding, thermre reversible phase
transitions. In some cases, we've had to
rely on photopolymerization or thermal
curing. But in general, this
reversibility to the yielding process is
inherent in these visco elastic
materials. And that's what we've really
tried to exploit predominantly.
So I want to take a step back to sort of
the beginning because I think it's nice
to see the cont as a context where we
started and this is work that we started
actually in collaboration with Joseph
Ceserano at Sandia and a talented PhD
student Jim Smay helped to lead. Um and
here we recognized that we could print
these particle gels. So just particles
suspended in water. And as long as we
were at high solids loading and we made
these particles attractive enough so
that they could basically exhibit this
visco elastic response, we could print
these uh with high fidelity. And the
only knob we had to turn was the pH. And
we used that as an adjustment to adjust
the particle attraction strength between
the particles. And you can see that when
they become uh sticky enough, you have a
very high uh sheer yield uh modulus. So
that can be self-supporting and a high
sheer yield stress. And they form this
sort of spanning clusters in
three-dimensional space. Now, we can use
things like confocal microscopy to
really understand what's happening to
these building blocks as they're flowing
through a nozzle. In this case, it's a
simple micrfluidic nozzle that mimics a
print head. And what you're looking at
is this in this square here is this
feature in the turndown ratio between
the nozzle exit and the ink reservoir.
And you can see these clusters. The
highest shear is at the wall and they
start to break apart, right? But the
minute they exit the nozzle, they all
stick together again. And that's why
they're able to support themselves. And
you can see that they can support
themselves across large gaps in the
underlying layers. So we can create
these lattis-like structures without a
support material. And in fact, you can
span very large features with these uh
extruded inks. Um and here again, we're
tailoring this G prime, the sheer
elastic modulus. The higher that value,
the longer the span distance that these
materials can can go without sagging or
deforming.
And that's important for kinds of things
that we did in printed electronics. So
this is actually a filament being
printed out of plane through a 30 micron
nozzle. The step height here is 1
millimeter. So this is over a very long
long gap. And we've tailored these
materials to be able to do that without
without um def you know any kind of
deformation. And you can see that with
these nanoparticle constituents here
it's a silver nanoparticle system that
we can print through nozzles as fine as
one micron the pattern one micron
electrodes and that's in plane this is
30 microns out of plane and with that
then we can make some you know
functional devices like these inductors
planer solenoid and tooidal inductors
shown here and you can see this is an
inplane modality coming out to to a
contact pad. And these are the the coils
of this inductor. And again, this is
about a 10 micron resolution.
And we can do something a bit more
sophisticated. And this is work that we
did with Don Hei Ham several years ago.
And this gives you a sense of the scale.
These are the devices here shown. Uh
this is a coits oscillator, four
oscillators that are synchronized. And
this is a wireless transmitter. And this
one's actually on polyimid, but you can
get a size scale associated with this,
right? So, we can basically print the
electronics on demand.
And with this, because this is a modular
ink design, we can plug and play. We can
re replace any type of particle with a
different particle. So, one of the
things that kind of really caught
attention about a decade ago was the
fact that we were making these uh 3D
printed micro batteries that are lithium
ion based and rechargeable where we have
interdigitated cathodes and anodess. And
you can see the size scale here. Each
one of these batteries is about the size
of a single grain of sand. And we've
done other uh modalities here where we
can create foam based materials. So we
can take these gels and we can airate
them and have lightweight architectures
where now you have a large amount of
bubbles within the ink itself. And then
we can also create these um chain
mail-like structures uh using embedded
printing of these same kinds of
colloidal inks.
So that led us to sort of the next class
of materials that we developed which are
based on polymers. And here we've done a
broad array of polymer designs um both
for matrices and for inks starting with
some of the earliest work where we just
essentially said well we're using
polyelerolytes to stabilize particles
maybe we should just take the particles
out and start working with the
polyelerolytes themselves. It was sort
of like that simple of a concept. And
here we did some very nice work where we
were working with these oppositely
charged polyelerolytes that could print
through nozzles as small as like 500
nmters in diameter because these are
fine scale building blocks. And then we
build upon that to move to hydrogels,
elastimemers and thermosets. And then we
used um fillers both as functional moes
as well as realological aids to make
these kinds of polymer materials
printable.
And so one of the things that I think
we've pioneered is this concept of 4D
printing. Um and Skyler Tidbitz here at
MIT has also uh helped coin that that
phrase as well. Um but the idea is that
you 3D print in three dimensions but if
these structures shape morph then
there's an added dimension of time. So
hence the terminology 4D printing. Um
but we took inspiration from nature when
we started thinking about how to realize
this uh in practice. And so if we think
about the nastic motion of plants,
plants undergo dramatic shape changes in
response to touch changes in thermal uh
conditions or in just hydration. So
these are uh pine cones and wheatons
that are billayer architectures. So with
this kind of uh uh modality in mind we
focused on printing hydrogels but we
wanted to introduce cellulose fibrals
because if we look at plant cell walls
that's exactly what leads to these
anisotropic shape morphing responses.
You have stiff cellulose fibers wrapping
around a hydrogel um outer shell and
that essentially guides the shape
morphing. you have less shape morphing
uh in you have less shape change in the
direction uh parallel to the stiff
features and more accommodated in the
orthogonal direction. So we can use the
shear fields in the nozzle during
printing to essentially control the
alignment of these rigid or stiff
fillers. And so if we can guide that uh
alignment we can then lead to a
programmed shape change. And so we did
this and this was work actually with uh
Maha at Harvard and also with Ralph Niso
um at Illinois. Um, we, it was really as
we were, as I was leaving, uh, Illinois
that Ralph and I started brainstorming
about this whole concept of 3D of 4D
printing. And then Skyler came out with
a big talk that announced that term. And
I was like, but nevertheless, we still
got we still got pretty excited about
uh, realizing that goal. And so these
are just hydrogel materials that again
we have these stiff cellulose
microfibals in. And simply by changing
the bilayer uh geometry this angle here
we can uh programmably define both the
Gaussian and mean curvature and we can
take our measured parameters for the
swelling strain uh along the um parallel
and orthogonal print paths and the
elastic moduli that we observe. And we
can relate that stiffness anisotropy
that we encode into these printed
materials to their swelling anisotropy.
And with that then we can do very
complex architecture such as this
callilly for example which has
continuous changes in both mean and
gaussian curvature. And the predicted
path uh print path from this model um
which is based on inverse design leads
to a planer structure that when it shape
morphs goes into essentially that exact
mo motif of the callilly. And so with
that in mind then we asked ourselves you
know can we extend this to other types
of filler materials again modular ink
designs can we can we control the
alignment of anotropic stiff building
blocks can we do that even when they're
rigid misogens rather than say nano uh
rods or uh short you know fiberfilled uh
structures and the and the answer is yes
we can we can really tailor and and and
program in a stiffness gradient in these
structures. Even when the the features
that we're printing are along a main
chain of just having rigid spacing
elements like liquid crystal mis
misogens and so with that we did a
variety of motifs um shown here and um I
think you know we I think are continuing
to explore how we can leverage shape
morphing in both these kinds of contexts
but also in in tissue engineering.
And so that kind of brings me to I would
say the last example. And here the the
idea is that um we wanted to uh think
about vascule and what we you know rely
on and and use vascule in natural
systems to do. Um when we think about
leafination or the vascule that we have
in our bodies and our organs and
throughout they're bringing nutrients uh
to the cells. They are regulating
temperature and in some cases they're
participating of course in healing local
damage. And our first foray into uh
creating vascularized materials was
really in the context of soft materials.
We were working very closely with
colleagues at Illinois before moving to
Harvard in both printing 3D micrfluidic
devices and also a class of materials
known as self-healing materials. And in
the original embodiment for self-healing
materials, there were micro capsules
that were distributed in a polymer
matrix. But when you broke that um when
you broke that material, those capsules
would release healing agent in the ca in
this case in the form of monomer. But
once that region that had been broken um
was rehealed, it couldn't be broken
again because all those capsules would
have drained and they couldn't supply
new healing agent. And so Scott White, a
pioneer in self-healing materials along
with Nancy Sodto and Jeff Moore, um
started collaborating with our lab to
basically print these vascularized uh
embodiment uh so that just like our
blood continuously flows through our
body, we could have a continuous supply
of healing agents uh in these uh
materials. But as we kind of came to
fruition and realized that goal, it
opened up in my own mind applications
that were far beyond that uh example,
including areas of soft robotics where
now we could encode into the material
that we're building, pneumatic networks.
And of course, opening up a field of
tissue and whole organ engineering,
which is really at the leading edge and
something that our lab has helped
contribute to.
So the very first work in this space was
done by Willie Woo um in my lab at
Illinois and he developed this concept
of you know embedded printing and the
reason why he did that is because
because of course when you're using a
direct write approach you're just going
layer by layer and if we want to create
a true three-dimensional vascularized
network um we want to be able to print
in a free form way in three dimensions
and so this really led led to this
advance and he developed not only a
sacrificial ink but a soft matrix and
this was just a hydrogel matrix at the
time that would enable us to print these
complex levels of vascule and what
you're seeing here is a vascular tree
with an inlet and outlet that follows
Murray's law for those of you who do
work in the biology realm you know that
Murray's law controls basically the the
size scale of your uh vessels as they go
to ever uh uh smaller daughter branches
in such a way that it sets the
dimensions of the large parent vessel as
it goes down to the smaller uh vessels.
So with that in mind then um it was kind
of a light bulb moment for me. We hadn't
really been working on cells in our lab
before that time, but I realized that at
that time that was like a real roadblock
in the field of tissue engineering and
we might have now an a way to actually
address that roadblock if only our lab
could start working with cells and um so
it co happened to coincide with the
opportunity to move to Harvard to do
just that. Um but at Harvard we ended up
doing a little bit more than just
working on the biological side. We also
started teaming with colleagues in soft
robotics. So I'll first describe a
little bit of the work that we've done
to leverage this method for soft
robotics and then I'll talk about what
we're doing in the uh area of of tissue
and organ engineering.
So the the whole key behind this uh
process is engineering a sacrificial ink
that will undergo a thermal reversible
phase change going from something that's
a gel to a fluid uh at at a prescribed
temperature change. And we have two
basic inks that we've developed for
doing this. One is a synthetic hydrogel.
It's a triblock copolymer. It's actually
made by BASF. You can buy it. It's
typically used as a thickener, an
associative thickener. Um, but it melts
upon cooling. And that's kind of
unusual. Most times when you melt
something, you have to heat it up. But
the reason it melts upon cooling is that
it's it's controlled the gel the gel
itself is controlled by hydrophobic
interactions of these blocks that are
poor rich, polyropylene oxide rich, and
the cores are a polyethylene oxide. But
as we as we cool this down, the
hydrophobic interactions lessen and the
myels basically get disrupted and you
have a low viscosity fluid. And when
it's cool, this is when we can actually
evacuate the printed features in order
to open up the channels that we want
running through these structures. Now,
we can also do this in biological uh
gels such as gelatin. This one of course
uh is cool at room temperature and um uh
becomes I mean I'm sorry is cool at low
temperature and becomes a fluid as we
heat above uh roughly room temperature.
And so if we're thinking about printing
a tissue construct when we put that
tissue into an incubator at 37 C this
fluidizes and we can flush that out and
start perfusing the tissue construct. So
these two very simple concepts and
materials formulations are things that
we've used for both printing soft
robotics and human tissues. And so one
of the earliest things that we did in
the soft robotics area in collaboration
with Rob Wood and and benefiting from
some beautiful work also um from George
Whiteside's lab on these uh fluidic
logic circuits was to create a fully
soft robot that operated autonomously.
So the this robot embodies both this
micrfluidic logic but it also embodies
the energy source. So as we build this
you can see that it's in a mold and only
these features shown in red here and
also the reaction chambers which are a
platinum catalyzed uh components that
are sitting here in dark um are are
printed by the embedded printing
process. Everything else is molded. But
sitting in the middle here is a logic
circuit that's shown here. And that
operates as follows. So it has an
oscillating circuit that basically
guides um the fuel which is sitting in
the depot back in the in the back of the
the robot and it's delivering hydrogen
peroxide. And as it moves through the
oscillating circuit um in every
oscillation either the the top or bottom
part of this robot hits the platinum uh
the the platinum catalyst where it
becomes uh vapor where it becomes vapor.
So it becomes water vapor and oxygen and
that is what is inflating um these robot
arms. So this is basically inspired by
an octopus. We called it the octabot. Um
and you can see the fuel depot here. the
fluids moving through the circuit and
the opposing arms going up and down as
it they inflate and deflate. Now we we
built upon this in another way which was
to in include not only the fluidic
circuitry by by printing these
sacrificial inks but to also build in a
sensorized network a smatensory feedback
into these um robotic grippers. So each
one of these is like a finger in a
robotic gripper. But now this finger is
like our own human fingers. It can sense
uh kesthetically uh with proprioception
and also in a tactile way. And here
we're printing ion gels and we're
measuring basically changes in
resistance as we're operating the device
in order to give sensory feedback. And
you can see that it's a fairly complex
design. The bladders are are here. Those
are the ones that are being printed by
using the sacrificial ink for inflation.
And everything shown in red is a sensor
um that is either going to sense
curvature in this case, sense tactile
tacticity with a contact sensor or a
small amount of of a of an inflation
center sensor that basically says are
the bladders being filled or unfilled as
we're activating the the gripper. And
this is what it looks like in action.
So, this is just a three-finger gripper.
You can start to see the readouts from
each one of these sensors that are
embedded in these fingers. Um, they all
look like this in uh, you know, under UV
illumination, but this is what it looks
like in uh, natural light. Um, and so
you can see very nicely that we have the
ability then to basically introduce uh,
sensory feedback into these, you know,
simple elastor siliconebased elastimemer
architectures.
And so I guess the last thing I wanted
to just highlight um is our our work
that we're now doing to try to build
human tissues um starting with patient
specific cells. So starting with you
know human induced puropotent stem cells
which we can then um uh leverage and
differentiate into um any essentially uh
organ type of interest. We've been
primarily working on cardiac um kidney
and uh cerebral tissue and we've been
motivated by two major needs. Uh one is
in the organ on chips uh space to
understand uh and and and search for
drugs through drug testing and disease
modeling. Essentially a fail zero a fail
a phase zero fail fast trial carried out
on human tissues as opposed to animal
models. And the FDA just had a uh FDA
modernization act 2.0 which is really
driving the development of these types
of models. Um and we've been really
focusing on 3D uh versions of this. So
rather than cellular monollayers in a in
a chip, we want either three-dimensional
tubular architectures such as kidney
proximal tubules or blood vessels or
organoids themselves underflow. And then
from the perspective of ultimately a a
sort of grand challenge goal is to
create these tissues for therapeutic use
and ultimately at the whole organ scale.
And the motivation behind that of course
is not only the pervasive need for hum
for human organs, people who have
diseases um such as chronic kidney
disease. Um that also even if you're
fortunate enough to get a donor organ,
you're going to be on immunosuppressants
the rest of your life. And that is not a
fun thing because it knocks down your
immune system. It makes you more
susceptible to cancer. And so the idea
is can we make tissues that are made
from you for you taking your own cells
reprogramming them to a pur potent state
and then differentiating them to
specific lineages of interest whether it
be kidney cardiac brain and reconstitute
those into a vascularized profusible
functional uh tissue and so here I want
to give a shout out to Mark Skyler Scott
who I think was just recently at MIT
giving a a lecture on his work uh in uh
the mechanical engineering course too
and to another pioneering postoc
Sabuzelle who really helped advance this
concept of of swift we call it
sacrificial writing in functional tissue
and the idea is just like we did to
engineer visco elastic matrices for um
embedded printing of functional and
structural materials we can take stem
cells
And in this case, we're taking them in
their plur potent state. So these
aggregates that you see are actually
embroidery bodies. They haven't been
differentiated to a specific lineage
yet. We can take these we can make them
in these um micro wells. We can so we
can make one EV per well and we have you
vast T flasks of these um in order to
create milliliters of tissue um at cell
densities that are approaching
biological cell densities of roughly 200
million cells per milliliter and then we
use our sacrificial writing method to
write in vascular uh uh perfusible
vascule. Of course everywhere you see
red is a is the gelatin ink that I
mentioned earlier. And then once we warm
that tissue up in the incubator, we can
flush away everything that you see in
red. There's an inlet and outlet pin
here, for example. And what we leave
behind are these open lumens. And
without these open lumens, this is a
4x4x4
mm cubed tissue. You see that inside
because these are cellularly dense, you
have a necrotic core. there's only a
very thin zone of viability that is in
contact with this uh the media uh around
this molded tissue. But if we introduce
vessels into this tissue, then we can
keep that entire 4 millimeter thick
tissue alive because we're profusing
media through these channels through
these essentially vessels. Now how this
works is that we take these uh embryoid
bodies or if we differentiate them into
specific lineages we jam them in a fluid
ECM. So initially they're sitting in a
liquid that is also thermmorreversible.
It's suspended in an extracellular
matrix that can be a fluid at the
printing temperature. But ultimately
when we um heat heat up the tissue both
this this ink liquefies but the the ECM
that's fluid becomes solid. So it
becomes like a glue and it holds all the
building blocks in place so that we can
empty the channels without disrupting
the the surrounding matrix. Without
that, of course, all those building
blocks would just flow into those
printed and then opened lumens.
So with that then we more recently and
and Paul's here in the audience um have
taken this a step further using a
technique called coaxial swift so that
we could really replicate the complex um
morphology of of human vessels where you
have a smooth muscle cell uh shell
wrapping uh an endothelium
endothelialized channels. And the the
trick to this, and you can't really see
it in this schematic, is that there's an
extended core that sticks out of this uh
core shell nozzle that is able to
puncture through preprinted uh
structures and connect them such that
you can have continuous um sacrificial
materials that uh can ultimately be
emptied and endothelialized to create
these vessels. And around each of these
are a smooth muscle layer that remains
viable over a multi-day period. And in
fact, these actually have a confluent
endothelium which exhibits high barrier
function which is what our own blood
vessels do as well. So with that as sort
of the background, we then wanted to
demonstrate a functional tissue uh
sample. And this is work um I think from
from several years ago, but it really
highlights I think in the most
compelling visual way that the tissue is
in fact functional. So although we're
working in on extending this now to
kidney tissues in in a substantial way,
I think this is actually a very good
embodiment because it shows in the um as
we differentiate these stem cells into
cardiac building blocks. In this case,
these are multisellular spheroids
roughly 400 microns in diameter. So they
contain many cells per little uh
building block. You can see that in the
post- differentiated state, each one of
these building blocks is beating, right?
It's beating, but it's beating
asynchronously.
We take these building blocks and we jam
them into a much more dense packing that
can support our writing of functional uh
writing of the uh vessels. And then with
that at at at day one, you can see still
each one of those little building blocks
is is beating, but it's beating
asynchronously. After seven days in
culture, these building blocks fuse
together and they become they become a
contiguous tissue that actually beats
synchronously. And uh what you're seeing
here is a let me go to the next slide is
a fluorescent uh intensity of a calcium
indicator that essentially shows this
spontaneous and they're beating under a
spontaneous activity. Um and you can see
that in looking at just like two regions
in this tissue. Initially on day one
they're all beating asynchronously.
Nothing is is synchronized. After um day
seven they are beating synchronously and
we can pace these tissues at say one
hertz and you can see that the entire
bulk of the tissue is responding in
unison and these are just two regions of
the tissue one here and one sitting here
that we were tracking.
So with that one could also ask how do
they respond to drugs? Um and they in
fact do respond in a way that you would
expect if we gave these drugs to
ourselves. um we would expect that our
beat frequency would accelerate and if
we gave this drug we would expect that
the amplitude of our cardiac output so
that contractility would be dissipated
and you can see that in fact as we
peruse these drugs through these tissues
we see in fact that same kind of output
so with that well I guess I'll close by
just saying where we're going is to kind
of expand this not only to different
tissue types
but also building in uh mechanisms by
which we can build multiscale vascule
because these tissues are metabolically
active. They're cellularly dense and the
printed vascule alone may not be
sufficient to keep these tissues alive
over over long periods of of in vitro or
invivo uh maturation. And so we're we
have multiple strategies to vascularize
organoids including using flow including
using genetic uh programming to
orthogonally induce multiple cell types
in these tissues of prescribed uh cell
type uh and then also of course our
embedded and uh direct printing methods.
So with that I'll just end by sum with
this summary. I won't tell you what I've
already told you, but I will end with
something that I hope Millie would love
is that I've modified her statement just
a little bit to say that if you don't
have printable materials, you don't have
an experiment. And I think if if Millie
was here, hopefully she would allow me
that grace. Um, and uh, with that, I
want to thank uh, a number of people
over the years that have contributed um,
to our lab, to the work that you've seen
today. Um it really takes a village and
uh many of these advances I have to give
all the credit to the students and the
postocs. It's really their creativity
and their hard work that have brought
these these ideas to fruition and I hope
have made an impact in a positive way on
the field of 3D printing and on the
field of tissue engineering and soft
robotics and and all the things that
we've had I hope a small role in helping
advance. Um, and I also, you might
notice, uh, up here in the corner, this
was a gathering that we had back in
December. Um, my my adviser was also
there, Michael Sema, and I want to give
him a shout out because, you know, as a
as a PhD student, I learned so much from
him. And, um, we've remained friends to
this day. And, um, I as his first PhD
student, I always say I went through
tenure twice,
but really once I once I realized what
tenure was, like, no, I didn't.
he he bore all the pressure, not me. But
uh but it was it was a lot of fun. And
and um uh with that, I'll thank a number
of agencies that have funded our our
work. And um lastly, I want to dedicate
this to Millie Drestell House, who, as I
said, has been an inspiration to me um
from really my start here at MIT as a
grad student and is still an inspiration
today. So with that, I'll thank you and
I think there'll be some questions. Um
so, thank you so much.
SO MUCH JENNIFER FOR THAT visionary
talk. Um, just some logistics while I
get us warmed up. We have about 15ish
minutes for questions. So, if you could
line up in an orderly fashion and come
up with a succinct way to ask Jennifer
your hard-hitting questions, that'd be
great. So, we can get through as many as
possible. Um, and maybe while people are
lining up, I'll get us sort of warmed
up. Okay. Um, great. From the context of
tissue engineering. So, you know, I feel
like many engineer tissue engineers, we
have like one tissue that we really care
about and it's as much of a art or a
craft as it is a science, right? Like I
know what makes good muscle and I have
all these things in my head. Yeah.
>> And one thing I was curious about that
you were kind of getting to at the end
of your talk when you're going from say
cardiac to kidney to neural tissue.
Sure, you're changing the cells and
you're probably changing the bio inks.
Um, but are you also changing the
hardware and other things in a really
specific manner and every time you
transition to a new tissue, do you have
to recreate the whole thing? Um, just
very curious how you think about that
process.
>> I really I really appreciate that
question. And I want to give a shout out
to Ritu who's doing some amazing work in
in this field of biohybrid robotics um
and also in skeletal uh uh tissue and
and now neuroskeleletal junction. So I
neuromuscular junctions I I want to say
that the way I think about you know
whole organ engineering is it's very
complex um in the sense of let's take
your adult heart or your adult kidney in
the adult human heart. If you look at a
single cell sequencing and the mapping,
you know, there's like 17 different cell
types that one has to put into into a
tissue to really emulate the the
organization and and cellular
composition. And in in the kidney, it's
about 20 different cell types. We've
tried to distill this down in our lab to
sort of key cell types. We realize we're
going to be missing some of those. But
we also always have the philosophy of
let biology do as much of the work as we
can, which is why we start with, you
know, human induced purip potent stem
cells. Not only are they a renewable
source and they're can be obviously
patient specific, but we can harness all
of the exquisite differentiation
protocols that exist in the literature
and hopefully also contribute advances
to those that allow biology to do it for
us. Create the functional architectures
at the sort of nano micro scale and the
key cell types of interests. Are they
perfect? By no means they're they're
not. And when you work with IND, you
know, human induced polar potent stem
cells, you're really following an
embryogenic pathway. So they're not very
mature as cells. So this idea of being
able to perfuse them and mature them
both in vitro and ultimately in vivo is
essential. But your question was also
about the hardware. And I would say
that, you know, we we certainly have um
some ongoing work now to uh bring in
some of the more sophisticated nozzle
designs and things to our our
bioprinting side of things. But I would
say ultimately at least in in the short
run, um we haven't really made as many
as much progress there as as we could
have. Um but certainly that's where we
need to go because for example we really
need to capture these these cells where
we need them in the architectures that
we want. But we try to do that as much
as we can with biology because if you're
going to print a complex tissue with you
know multiple cell types and you don't
have single cell resolution and you you
would it would require months to build
this tissue and you have basically an
hour cells are going to die if they
don't get perused and get nutrients. So,
I don't think it's going to be a pure
hardware play
>> is is is I guess the simple answer to
that. So, long- winded, but that's the
end uh the answer that I would give.
>> That makes a lot of sense.
>> Yeah.
>> Um do you want to get us started on
questions?
>> Um thank you so much for the wonderful
talk. I'm very inspiring and really
passionate about what you do.
>> Um I just wanted to ask like a simple
question. So when do you think we'll be
able to like bioprint
skin into like a scar or something like
that?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. I mean
there's certainly some pioneering work
that has been done here on the on
ascellular uh skin repair and
regeneration. Um you know and there's
also some some work going on now in in
making skin based organoids and the
thing that those organoids have that say
just printing cell monollayers epidermal
dermal layers um which we can do now
we're doing in our lab actually and
we've actually published in this space
is you don't have hair follicles and
that's actually kind of an important
embodiment right so if you start with
like you know these skin organoids they
actually develop their own hair
follicles. So I think that field is kind
of wide open right now. It's very nent
in some ways even though there are you
know commercial asellular scaffolds that
can do wound healing and things like
that for burn victims. But I think
there's it's like wide open space.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Yep. Thanks for your question.
>> Yeah, I obviously want to add that it
was a really inspiring lecture and this
is actually the second time I heard you
speak. I think you were here in 2023. uh
I don't remember if it was the same
lecture series but it's incredible to
see how things have advanced since. Uh
my question I'm a a space systems
researcher so I know absolutely nothing
about this domain but as I'm sure you're
familiar with this is quite a there's
quite a lot of hype around 3D biorinting
or bio printing in space obviously
organoids as well but that's sort of
that tends to be the moonshot that
people bring up when they um you know
try to get investment for example for
space-based um applications and
architectural development. You talk a
lot about sacrificial ink development.
So it is clear that that is something
that if not it's not necessarily the
main blockage or the choke point or a
challenge but it it does impact designs.
I'm wondering how you see the potential
effect of microgravity and whether that
could actually mean a substantial
difference to to justify doing any of
what you do or any sort of bio printing
in space.
>> Yeah, that's a great question. I mean as
we as we build now if we're doing
embedded printing the support bath can
basically provide support for the object
being built right but if you're doing
direct biorinting at some point as you
get above a certain number of layers
that self-weight becomes very important
and it causes deformation in the layers
underneath and so one of the things
that's you know helpful about
microgravity is that self-weight can be
much larger because you're in a micro G
environment instead of a 1G environment,
right? So you can I think create larger
constructs in a micro gravity
environment. Convection of course is
also dominant. So how does that affect
nutrient delivery and these kinds of
things? You know, we haven't done
printing in space so I can't say from
you know firsthand but I think it would
be an interesting avenue to pursue.
>> Thank you.
>> Great. Um and we have some online
questions as well. So, I thought maybe
we could wrap up with one of those and
particularly there's one that's um a
little open-ended. So, I thought we
could end with some philosophy.
>> Um so, this person wants to know how the
sort of creative ideas for new materials
or hardware emerge in your lab. Is it
like you see something odd in an
experiment and then something happens or
is there a big picture application
you're working towards and then you work
backwards?
>> I think it's a combination. It really
depends on the um target
We as I try to highlight I may maybe
didn't do a full job a fully complete
job. We've benefited a lot from
collaborating collaborations and
sometimes those collaborations like we
want a self-healing material that that
has a biomimetic vascule that drives the
advances and sometimes it is like an
insight where you have this light bulb
moment and you're just like wow if we
could do it here we can we can go after
you know humans tissues what is that
going to entail let's get to you know
let's get to Boston to the mecca of
biotech and find out right so I think
you know it's a combin it's a
combination And sometimes it's
serendipity like I have to say the
genesis for embedded printing came much
much earlier than the first paper. I was
in the lab. My student Jim Smeay who was
really pioneering this technique brought
the print head that he was printing this
aquous you know colloidal gel and he put
it into a vial of liquid and all of a
sudden because there was still some over
pressure the filament came out and I was
like oh interesting. We can print under
liquids. we can you know and that sort
of ended up uh to our first you know um
uh polyelerolyte printing paper where we
were using that then this fluid
reservoir to drive coagulation of these
oppositely char so sometimes it's
serendipity sometimes it's being driven
by an application a goal it's a
combination but thank you
>> that's very helpful great um so I'm sure
there's more questions but there is also
a reception um so maybe let's wrap up by
thanking Jennifer for her time and her
visionary
I'll take your question.
>> Yeah.
>> So, uh Jennifer, uh we do want to make
sure that we leave you with a small
momentto. Uh you have indeed inspired
many many of us.
>> We have a little pumpkin made by MI.
Yes.
>> Awesome.
>> Thank you so much for being here with us
today.
>> We look forward to the next time we get
you here.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Thank you so much. Thank you all for
coming.