thank you thank you for invitation uh so
we are at truly s MIT spin-off so like I
have been at a mighty energy Initiative
for the past eight years and this is
where actually started as a research
project and my co-founders are also MIT
graduates and we are also uh down the
street so we are very close very part of
the ecosystem so as I read mention so
this is an industrial decarbonization
platform software platform and we are
very excited to be
here with you uh so let's start about
what's the problem so project planning
whether it's new asset deployment or
change of asset technology so on and so
forth is a hard topic it takes time you
need different groups of people you need
stakeholders uh make scenario analysis
so and so forth and when this is in the
context of decarbonization it it is
harder and why because of uncertainty we
have new technology so the uh like the
previous five talks presented new
technologies right so like which one to
believe which one to use in your
processes so and so forth and you really
need to do a lot of analysis to really
reflect on the uh benefits and
disadvantages of each one of these in
your assets to be able to make inform
and better decisions and this is
basically where Sesame plays a huge role
so we created a software platform where
you can really streamline assessing
different technology options supply
chain options for your decarbonization
Journey including renewable integration
use of different Technologies so on so
forth how do we do it so we created a
platform that brings together all your
uh decarbonization related uh modeling
needs into one single platform and at
the core of this we have first principle
models so we modeled many different
processes many different technology
options uh using physics based models
and then on top of of that we layered
life cycle assessment and cost analysis
so that you can calculate scope one to3
emissions uh for all these
configurations as well as the cost per
dollars per produced uh product uh we
also layered optimization so like you
can optimize and simulate all these
Pathways uh and then for the US context
we also have policy layers so like you
can see the benefit of getting 45p other
tax credits so and so forth uh using the
platform how do you do that so there are
mainly two different kind of analysis
you can perform uh one is more like big
picture comparison and in this big
picture comparison there are three uh
main steps one is configure so by using
our modular way it is I call it almost
like Sim City for industrial
decarbonization you can build your
pathway uh using our user interface uh
and then you can fully customize all of
these and then the second uh and more
important piece is of course analysis
and in the analysis we have three kind
of main analysis one is uh emissions
life cycle assessments scope one to
three emissions levelized cost of the
product and full cash flow analysis we
also provide with the sensitivity
analysis on the key parameters that you
can see the uncertainty limits and third
is comparing these options with other uh
scenarios or other technology options so
this is mostly based on cost of avoided
carbon in the context of decarbonization
but comparison can be on any other topic
as well the second piece of analysis we
perform is detailed analysis and in this
case basically this is especially in the
context of renewable integration uh we
have Global coverage at zip code level
weather data and you can pick any
location in the world and you can
optimize your renewable project green
hydrogen project so on so forth on the
basis of cost uh and also like during
during the uh break please stop by I
will show you we can really do that uh
and uh so in this you will get the
configuration sizing of equipment so on
and so forth and also the full cash uh
flow analysis so so far uh like we have
been having a lot of good traction from
the uh both uh industrial customers as
well as the government agencies uh so
the ask for today is basically like if
you are an energy company utility
company like the data Center operator or
Company please stop by uh so you can
definitely uh join our early adapters
program but also there are uh
opportunities to work work with us uh
and make your life
easier uh so basically in the final 30
seconds so if you have a chance today
please stop by I'm happy to show you the
demo of our product uh on a topic that
you are interested in mostly in the
energy space if not this is my contact
please uh reach out to me and we can
book a time to do a demo a customized
demo with you and your team and we can
take it from there thank you very much