I think that researching policy
surrounding sustainability and
implementing these new technologies um
in an affordable and feasible way is the
next step that will support any future
Generations after
[Music]
me I'm analyzing the different policies
and incentives that New York state has
rolled out to Market participants and
seeing whether or not that actually can
make renewable energy storage possible
possible I grew up in New York and
growing up in an urban area I realized
how important environmental problems are
in urban areas in big cities and just
how energy intensive these regions are
despite so much innovation in the
technology and science surrounding
renewable energy technology what's
actually holding it back is policy so
even though these amazing new solar
panels have been developed and these
amazing new battery technologies have
been developed since they're so
expensive it's not possible to actually
Implement them and no one wants to build
a battery if it's not profitable I hope
that it can help to make New York a
model and the policies that work in New
York can be extrapolated for other
states other countries and hopefully
globally
[Music]