we've developed social robots to
interact and engage and support young
children in learning language and
literacy skills the children don't
actually understand that the robot is
modeling their behavior and adapting
what it does and the kind of scaffolding
they just see the robot as a fun
Playmate but really under the hood the
robot is learning what action to take at
each moment to really try to optimize
the learning and engagement of the child
that's playing these games with nice to
meet you
what is your name um
Alana of course we know that not every
child can have you know the luxury of a
personal tutor but potentially with our
artificial intelligence it's possible to
create scalable affordable effective uh
personalized learning experiences for
all students for more MIT moments from
MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow
[Music]