uberto Fuji Gano research manager and
partnership leader at MIT sensible City
lab to share Advanced research on AI
driven Urban insights uberto the screen
is yours hi gram thank you thank you
very much for offering us this floor
thank you for the introduction CHR and
good morning and good afternoon every
Everybody well I'm very happy to be here
and show you what we do at the senso
city lab uh let me just try to explain
you first of all where we are we are a
lab in the urban studies and planning
department at
MIT and what we are passionate is cities
of course but looking at cities through
the lens of digital Technologies today
we can look at cities like basically
living systems living organisms and for
doing this we actually need new new
types of approach if you look at cities
as living organisms you probably need a
biologist perspective you probably need
a sociologist perspective and this is
what we try to do in the lab we have a
huge team of people uh mainly in
Cambridge we have more than 50 people in
our lab and what I'm going to show to
you today is the collective effort of
all these great
researchers and by collaborating a lot
with cities we also have some
researchers located in some of the the
cities that we study most and those are
Amsterdam Dubai and Realo which are
cities where we develop what we call the
living Labs where not only we we're
allowed to experiment our work but most
importantly engage in a continuous
discussion with all the stakeholders of
the city from the city municipality down
to the entrepreneurial ecosystems and to
the
residents well we of course do this all
over the world with cities with people
and we do it also together with
different companies and we're very
grateful of course to to all the
companies that have supported and do
support our work uh uh and our research
with the cities and with also a lot of
research Partners around so today I'm
I'm going to give you some examples of
our work and I try to categorize them in
in four chapters
basically according to the different
types of technology to different types
of AI that we're using
so the first one in this uh catalog of
different approaches to with AI to Urban
science is what we call Visual AI visual
AI is the technique of having a computer
to automatically understand what's
happening in an image you might be
familiar with something like uh like
it's shown in in this picture which is
simply understanding and uh uh and
Counting how many people how many cars
how many trees we have in a in an
image well this is of course a computer
science result but what if you apply to
urban planning and urban science what
are the interesting problems that you
can try to solve with this we started
doing this many years ago uh I'll show
you something old and something new that
we're doing one of the first question
that we investigated few years ago was
the following one we know that trees are
are very important
to the the cities not only for
mitigating temperatures not only because
they're beautiful but because they
increase biodiversity and they they
reduce pollution but the question is how
can we quantify better quantify The
Greenery and its impact on the city so
initially we've done something quite
simple which was take a picture uh a
Google Street View picture so pictures
which are normally available and uh uh
in and everybody can can use and
download so take a picture select a
portion do some AI use some AI to Simply
quantify the green pixels the green area
and then do it for every picture in the
city meter by meter and create these
kind of maps this is a visible Greener
map that shows at your doorstep where
you live what's the visible green you do
it through the neighborhood throughout
the
city and by doing this you're also able
to compare different cities this was a
great tool that allowed people to really
see face to face and quantify their
exposure to Greenery in their cities
this had a huge social uh influence we
had people debating over social media
that their neighborhood was greener than
another another one that their city was
not green as another city and so this
actually changed developed a advocacy um
exercise of people that through data
empowered with data they were discussing
this this phenomena to the point that we
actually open sourced the algorithm and
now any City can run the algorithm uh
with kuop street view data and have
their City into the rank here so there
was few years ago but one of the latest
work that we've done here is to address
a very dramatic point in our cities so
look at this number 65% of insects are
at the risk of Extinction due to climate
change this is a global number of course
this means that entire ecosystems are at
the edge of collapse uh it could have
really catastrophic impacts on the on
our world and cities are the places
where the the ecosystem ecosystemic
balance is more at risk so looking at
ecosystems today in in cities is more
and more important and being able to
build and plan and use our cities in a
way that more biodiversity uh can exist
it's something that it's crucial to do
right now and that many universities
many practicing our studies today well
the question is how you actually assess
biodiversity in cities well it turns out
that for doing this you just need to
count count insects those little bugs
sometimes they're beautiful sometimes
they're terrifying but it's what really
uh is
um what is really what what what is
really making our cities diverse so how
can we do it in a automatic way and not
simply having a person counting insects
well of course um visual AI techniques
are helping here it turns out that it's
quite easy for a computer to detect the
presence of an insect in a
picture but it's not very easy to
understand exactly which insect it's in
the picture there was basically a gap in
the literature a gap in what's available
in technology so together with our team
we developed a computer uh library that
allows to detect and most importantly
catalog and classify several several
thousands of insect
species and this was the first step
because first you need to be able to do
it with a computer then you need to make
it feasible in real life so we're doing
a lot of research in developing very
small cameras that can be deployed and
uh can do all this processing and this
is not simply a computer science
exercise this includes electronic
engineering for example because you
don't want to have a stupid camera that
streams all these images to the cloud
and then you have all the computations
the cloud you want to minimize all the
streaming on the camera so the objective
here is to have the computations
directly on the chip on the camera and
for doing this you need of course to to
optimize all the
computation and this of course is good
for privacy preserving so that you take
an image you compute the number of
insects and then you delete the image
straight away without even storing
it and when you can do it on a on a chip
the third step they were investigating
is creating some Gardens we're working
with entomologists we're working with
arborologist that are are helping us to
select the right mix of species that
attract the insects that we want to
count so that we can build the small
garden deploy the small cameras leave
them there for uh a number of weeks or
months count the
biodiversity and then eventually move
these Gardians somewhere in the
somewhere else in the city this is very
important for example in case of
Redevelopment of the city we can assess
biodiversity before the the development
after the development and understand if
the the the project the plan was
actually affected so those are all good
examples of visual AI to New City
problems let me go to another big
chapter which is the the sensing Ai and
let start again from a very real problem
that we have in our cities so look at
this map this uh is a a map showing air
quality pollution in in a city it's
something invisible uh we know better we
know pretty much if the city overall is
polluted or not but if you look at the
real data you see something quite
interesting pollution really changes a
lot in space uh look at those two
numbers across simply two blocks so few
few hundred meter distance you have very
good air quality or very bad air quality
and this is normal it's because there
are different wind flows is because the
emitters of pollutants are located in
some specific zones and so even if we
know on average the air quality in the
city it's still very interesting to
understand locally what happens well how
do you do it uh you cannot do it with
fix sensors like on the left hand side
of the screen unless you really want to
deploy fixed sensor every meter in our
in our streets um you cannot really do
it with satellite pictures because
satellite pictures are not accurate
enough uh to to detect their quality in
our streets so what we've uh what we've
done is take advantage of something that
is already moving in our C in our cities
like
Vehicles we design some special sensors
and attach these sensors to Vehicles if
you take vehicles that are already in
the city and they already move a lot
like taxis like uh trash trucks like
like police
cars you basically create a network of
moving sensors in the city well this is
the result you're able to with very very
few sensors create these beautiful maps
that are able to show in this case air
quality in space and time in every point
in the city you show this to people and
you're basically making tangible
something
invisible making people understand
what's the air quality not in the in the
city but whether kids go to school or
where they live well this was the the
first use case but if you keep using
this methodology which is creating
sparse sensing with moving sens sensors
attached to Vehicles you can do many
other things those are some of the
Cities we've been studying and we've
been deploying our technology too uh
Cambridge was the first one 2017 a few
years ago we studied the air quality
there uh in New York in 2020 we were
interested in in quality but
specifically as a social justice with a
social justice point of view we were
interested in understanding how the the
underprivileged U populations were
disproportionate exposed to bad air
quality in Stockholm 2020 we were not
interested in air quality because they
the air quality there is very good but
we were interested in something
different which is heat uh it turns out
that over Sumer the heat doesn't
distribute uniformly in the city you you
have these kind of heat bubbles heat
islands and the population there is
simply not ready to cope with the heat
so understanding this hyperlocal heat
issues was very interesting from the
city and we use the same technology with
a different sensor instead of a air
quality sensor just with a thermal
camera we were able to create these kind
of maps and um and start a conversation
with the city and suggest possible
interventions last example I'm going to
show you on this is Rome uh
2023 where we had again a different
problem um they had a problem with cre
not on the presence of trees but on some
parasites they would attack trees it
turns out that many of the Centennial
pine trees in Rome are getting sick and
are eventually dying because of very of
a very small parasite that is attacking
them well we can use the same um
approach to detect these parasites with
a combination of visible images and
hyperspectral images it's simple simply
a different type of camera there we are
equipping our our sensor with we are
able to automatically detect Tre
automatically understand the Spector
signature of that image which is
basically a proxy of how well the tree
is performing
photosynthesis and do an early detection
of this parasite we're doing it with a
local partner the Italian Carabiner
which are the local Forest Corps and we
equipped some of our their cars with our
sensors and so they go around in their
normal operations and perform these
analysis let me go to a third um chapter
here a third methodology in uh and a
third approach in using AI for urban
science which which was we called The
Crowd AI so not relying on one single
sensor or a network of sensors that we
distribute in the city but really
relying on people going around and again
let me start from a issue that we have
in our cities uh we're talking about
bridges
55,000 more than 55,000 bridges in the
US are considered structurally deficient
uh this is a fact this number is from
the Department of Transport well I'm not
talking about this um every engineer
that is hearing this this webinar is is
familiar with this this was the Tacoma
Bridge back in the 40s this was a big
design fault fortunately we know how to
build Bridges
today you might be familiar with this
the Baltimore Bridge a few years ago
again this was a a problem in the bridge
with a catastrophic consequence but
fortunately not all deficient Bridge
collapsed uh this is a bridge in front
of MIT if you've been on campus the The
Long Fellow Bridge a few years ago they
had to close the bridge because they
found a crack uh of course the bridge
didn't collapse but it was not
considered to be safe um the problem is
that they had to close the bridge for
more than 5 years because they realized
that it was too late and the crack was
actually much bigger than uh than they
realized from a visual inspection so
they closed the bridge for five years
they fixed it but of course if you are
from the Cambridge area you still
remember the the negative impact on the
cities of of closing some such a big
bridge well well what's the problem the
problem is that bridge inspection is
very infrequent and low Tech basically
visual inspection so can we do something
better well we know that every bridge
vibrates uh this is totally normal every
engineer know this and studied this very
well and by monitoring this vibration we
can better understand the health of the
bridge we can know if the bridge is
structural sound or not so monitoring a
vibration is something um that uh that
can that can tell us a lot of things on
the bridge the problem is that it's very
expensive if you want to monitor a
bridge vibration you need to install
sensors like here in this image on the
beautiful Golden Gate Bridge in San
Francisco you need to send people
install the sensors power them transmit
the data and analyze them it's thousands
of dollars just for one Bridge so big
and important Bridges like the Golden
Gate we can afford it but definitely not
for every bridge in the US or in the
planet so our question and our approach
was can we do something different um are
there different sensors that can sense a
bridge vibration well if you think about
it in your pocket you have a smartphone
and in every smartphone there is an
accelerometer when you drive on a bridge
you're basically bringing an
accelerometer as you're driving on that
bridge and that accelerometer of course
it's taking the the cars vibration but
also the bridge vibration so the very
interesting question and a little bit
provocative was can we use normal
smartphones to measure a brage
vibration well we are at MIT we like
these kind of weird questions a little
bit provocative uh so we decided to go
and investigate it we equipped the car
with some smartphones different types
um a professional sensor like the one in
in Orange that you can see and then we
went on the Golden Gate Bridge uh
driving back and forth and back and
forth getting some data well that's one
of the beautiful things of having
students at MIT that are very happy to
do this because of the research so after
more than 100 back and forth of the
bridge we went back to the to the lab we
analyzed data and we discovered that uh
actually good news
cell phones record a lot of vibrations
and we can distinguish the car
vibrations with the bridge fundamental
vibration so we put in a big inter
interdisciplinary team of people and
eventually publish some some major
papers they show this technique of
understanding if a bridge is sound
simply using people's cell phones on
Bridges and then we started a
collaboration with a
with the Italian version of the dot the
Department of Transport we developed an
app we gave it to some to some people we
monitored Three Bridges different types
small and and bigs and the goal was
having something like this uh which is
not telling well the bridge is going to
collapse in two days no that's not our
our our objective the objective is
saying there is something that is not
behaving well in this part of the bridge
you should go and inspect it it's
basically a red light that uh that gives
an indication of you should take care
you should inspect more this part of the
bridge and uh and and send specialized
engineer and this is a beautiful
approach because you're really relying
on people to gather the data and with a
very lowcost approach to be able to do
early warnings predictive
maintenance and then number four is is
AI for the
informal because most of the science and
most of the urban
planning techniques that uh that we
study that Academia study that the
practice study are for the developed
word for the formal word well there is
another part of the word which is called
informal uh look at
this this is in Brazil HOSA one of the
favas those are places where there is no
formal rules for the city to grow and
when uh people basically decide
themselves The Grow of cities you see
something like this which is very
interesting from a natural grow point of
view but of course it can create many
problems this is the whole picture Ora
you see that it's climbing up on a
mountain and when I'm saying that it's
causing a lot of problems it's not only
because of Health for example um Oria is
one of the places in in the world with
the highest concentration of TB TB
tuberculosis simply because in this very
very narrow streets there's not enough
airf flow to make the the environment
safe and so many times they actually
need to take down some of the houses
simply to enhance the air flow and uh
and reduce the number of TP cases but
she don't only have health issues you
also have environmental issues uh look
at this side of the mountains this is
really interesting because you might say
well what happened here why did the the
FAA grow on the left hand side but not
on the central part of the image well um
it turns out that yes the the favel
actually did grow on all parts of the
mountains but this part sided away there
was um there was a huge Landslide and
all these houses basically collapsed
with the population on it to the point
that today in in Rosia it's not
infrequent to
see those uh systems that are simply
there for announcing to the population
Whenever there is a big rain and a risk
of flood so that the population can at
least Escape so those are the phes the
the the issues that we are experiencing
this in these kind of towns but normal
urban planning techniques are not uh
ready to to cope with this um think
about Maps it's very hard to map this uh
these environments simply because a
normal satellite image is not uh enough
to understand the Topography of this
Urban environment that is developing on
the mountains there are no um addresses
of course Amazon doesn't deliver here
because there are no formal addresses
people don't have property titles to um
certifi that they live in that kind of
in in that house so our approach was can
can we generate new data for helping the
local community and scientists to
address this kind of problems so one of
the first things we we thought is
increase the mapping of these
environments of course you don't want to
to go there with with cameras you don't
go to you don't want to go there with
drones of course because people would
not accept that we would take pictures
of of people so we thought a lighter
lighter is a beautiful example of a uh
sensor that is able to create 3D maps of
the volumes but without mapping people's
faces without taking visible
images so together with some with some
local representatives of the community
and together with some MIT researchers
we went to Rosa in Brazil uh mapping the
the fabellas with lighters explaining to
the people why we're doing this and the
choice of this kind of technology and
this is the end result
he
so if you start from a good digital
representation of the environment you're
then able to model and to simulate much
better different phenomena for example
TB we are able to exactly understand how
the airf flow happens and what could be
surgical in interventions for increasing
airf flow for example another example
could be property titles we can start
thinking with the local community of
different types of proper property types
may maybe based based on blockchain or
on different approaches this is
something that should of course be done
with the local community but we see
these Technologies as something that
should Empower uh Innovation and um and
new decisions not from the point of view
of the researchers but to facilitate the
dial
and to basically explore what's possible
and how new digital Technologies can
help and solve some of these
issues well let me just tell you a last
project this is something that puts
together many of the techniques that I
discuss today and it's uh it's taking
place in in Amsterdam if you go to the
beautiful city of Amsterdam we were we
have a lab there and we engage with the
mayor and the mayor a few years ago uh
tked us to rethink and reimagine the
urban mobility in
Amsterdam and uh as everything is moving
towards Electric Mobility and autonomous
Mobility we thought why don't we
integrate Electric in autonomous
Mobility but in a very Amsterdam Way
because in Amsterdam you see more water
than asphalt you have more canals than
roads and so we thought of combining
boats and said driving cars in A New
Concept which we called robot which is a
self-driving boat again it was a very
MIT approach uh move fast and break
things get your hands dirty we took it
literally so in in our lab we started to
assemble small boats equipping them with
some different
sensors then we started teaching these
small boats how to navigate in uh in
water what you see here is the mat
swimming pool where we were testing our
our boats to automatically follow a
trajectory or to automatically avoid
different uh different obstacles that
they might find on the on the way we
have to of course develop all the
algorithms for cell navigation and
multivessel coordination in order to
have different boats to interact with us
and of course this was a big work a huge
work done at Urban studies planning at
the computer science department with
several people
involved and after 5 years of research
we were able to create some new boats
which are functioning and today if you
go to Amsterdam you might jump on some
of these bolts which as you can see are
level five autonomy and are able to
carry around people in an autonomous way
it's interesting to see that reaching
level five autonomy on canals is
actually much easier than on the roads
because you have um slower speeds and
less
congestion the very interesting part is
that once you solve the technological
part which is having a boat that is able
to self navigate you can be creative in
ways to apply this technology because if
you don't see the boat as a boat but as
a floating pixel you're able to un to
create different use cases like like
this one this is same type of Technology
the same boat but for a different use
which could be trash collection we found
that it's in Amsterdam it's hard to
collect trash normal way and so we
thought it moving the trash collection
to the canals in this approach where you
have people throwing a trash in the boat
and then the boat whenever it's full It
autonomously Go and dump itself well
there are many things that you can do
today with this we've done the research
part now this research uh has P out in a
in a startup it's called robot. Tech
where they are uh doing the R&D to the
commercialization of this but there are
so many possibilities the possibilities
of creating new pieces of infrastructure
for example a Urban Street Market or
Urban Water Market having different
pixels floating pixels different boats
to latch together and uh and create new
spaces or solving some of the mobility
issues in Amsterdam like creating um
temporary Bridges whenever you need a
temporary Bridge you can have those diff
different vessels to coordinate and
create a new piece of infrastructure
well those are just some of the things
that we do uh I hope you you understood
a little bit how we can creatively use
technology for addressing different
Urban issues in different parts of the
world and uh and we're always very happy
to think of the next project and think
of the next new exploration of new
digital Technologies in different
environments thank you thank you ubo for
your excellent talk on exploring cities
through AI branding science and design
uh I do get a couple questions here uh
first one is that you uh your lab works
with many cities I remember every year
you publish a book about the joint the
research project with the city can you
see something about the about this kind
of
City collaboration project with cities
and how you select a city and and how
you work with
it definitely well there are many cities
that we are working today and that we
have worked in the past uh as I said
cities are great test beds for our
technology because they offer us a um
sandbox to really deployer technology
and get data
every year we teach a class uh at MIT
where we have MIT students to focus on a
specific Urban science technology and we
offer them the possibility to do real
projects in some of the cities and
that's why with our partner cities
we every every year we have this number
of students that not only focus their
work on those cities but also go and
visit those cities to really have a
360 uh experience of those Urban
problems in those cities and so every
year we do this with different cities
thank you and also next question here is
uh at one of your recent conferences you
have a
concept uh about
proximity and uh that's very impressive
because got this question can also
related to our next speaker research can
you see something about the proximity
concept well well definitely uh
proximity Is Something the the most
fundamental reason why we live in cities
we live in cities
because we we find positive to cross
path with people every day we find it
positive to exchange
ideas and experiences and chromosomes
with other cities living close to us so
it was very interesting for us in in
understanding what are the good aspects
of proximity and what are the bad
aspects of proximity uh when you have
too many people in a place you have
congestions you have traffic and you
have diseases um we tackled during covid
this question in terms of from from the
remote working point of view does it
still make sense to work in a in a
proximity way does it still make sense
to go to the office and meet colleagues
or not well um we had a great
opportunity during covid
to to analyze a very good data set
coming of course from from our house MIT
or people who were working before in a
normal way so in this in the office and
after so fully remote during covid and
understand the interactions among those
people well we discovered that people
that used to talk with themselves what
we call the uh strong ties
um kept doing their work exactly as they
would what we experience with remote
working fully remote working is what is
in in literature is called the this the
weak ties which are the new encounters
which are the the people that do not
normally talk to each other they may be
a cross path once a year or once every
few months but those connections are
very interesting and dramatically uh
useful for exchanging new ideas and for
bringing new Innovation for bringing New
U fresh ideas and fresh discussions in
our social network well it turns out
analizing data that uh only with remote
working you don't have the creation new
wi ties meaning that we always we we
keep talking to the same group of people
and the flow of ideas between different
groups is really really impaired so
those are some of the work that we have
been doing with proximity in the in
trying to understand and the million
dooll question is should we keep going
to the office or not and with which
balance thank you very much we do have
other questions but for the sake of the
time we'll probably leave these
questions for next time