All right. So, my name is Leslie Miller
Nicholson. I have the privilege of being
I think I can walk away. Um, the
executive director of MIT's technology
licensing office. I've been in that
position for nine and a half years.
Previously, I was responsible for the
same sort of stuff way out in the
Midwest. uh University of Illinois in
Champ Champagne Orbana that does also
does some wonderful research. So today
what am I going to be talking about?
Um technology transfer in a university
environment is a lot of things. Um it is
teaching and service. It is graduating
students taking their knowledge into
companies. It is research and
publication, sponsored research, faculty
consulting, and then it's the stuff that
offices like the TLO, the technology
licensing office do, which is licensing
to startups and other companies. And
that's what I'm going to talk about
today.
So,
what I'm going to do is just go through
some basic tenants of what tech transfer
is, what it looks like, how we do it,
and
dive into some of the things that you
might not be aware of because there's
some really cool stuff that happens
through offices like the TLLLO, but the
other stuff isn't actually ever
mentioned. And that's what some of the
stuff I want to highlight. So, in every
research university in the United States
and across the world, there is likely a
a tech transfer office. They may call
themselves something different. And it
is likely that their structure is going
to look something like this. And in the
case of MIT's which is literally just
next door we have 50 staff and it falls
into these five buckets of work. Case
intake sponsor compliance which I'll
talk about fundamental HR IT
infrastructure database management and
that falls under the bucket of
operations. We also have what people
most commonly know about and talk about
which is licensing. That cool stuff,
that really cool stuff that people do.
The case management, the engagement with
faculty, the engagement with sponsors,
engagement with lences, business
development, and all of the things that
go alongside that. And then there's
faculty, I mean, financial and equity
administration. You see, I'm not even
using my notes, so there's a huge chance
that I'm not going to talk about
anything on my 12 pages here.
Um just make sure that I you know give
you value for money and cover something
that I said I would talk about. Um
finance and equity management. The
offices like ours um do a number of
different transactions. Many of them are
with law firms to pay bills for the
patent protection that they're doing on
our behalf. Others are lences paying us
money. Others are related to equity that
we might take in small startup
companies. And therefore that workflow
that funds flow has to be managed by
someone. So there's always a small
financial team supporting that work. And
then there's the intellectual property.
And in the case of MIT, our office also
manages MIT's trademark. So if any of
you have anything on you that says MIT
on it, we license that to the vendor
that you bought that from. And the
revenue that actually comes in from
that, this is not in my notes, but it
might be interesting, actually goes back
to uh student and athletics programs. It
goes immediately back because it is
effectively MIT's name and brand on
branded stuff. But we manage that in
addition to the other IP stuff that
you're very familiar with. It's to do
with patents, filings, protection,
assignments. All of those pieces are
handled through the IP team. and then um
marketing and communications who help in
the messaging and communication
including some of these really cool
slides you're about to see about the
research that's going on the IP that we
are trying to protect and um all of the
other activities. I'm just going to move
a couple of things on this because it's
driving me a little nuts. Here we go to
organize myself. Just talk amongst
yourselves.
All right. One area of activity that is
actually dispersed across the MIT
community but in other universities is
often done by tech transfer offices
is some of the entrepreneurship
activities proof of concept accelerators
even venture investment because in
smaller universities
they don't have the capacity and they
don't have the resources and often they
don't have the alumni who are giving
endowed funds to run some programs that
are fundamental al to an innovation
ecosystem. So in other universities it
falls under tech transfer but here at
MIT as you will all be very familiar
there are many programs in fact over 85
that support the entrepreneurship and
innovation going on whether student
stuff or faculty startups access to uh
NSF I core program Martin trust delta v
MIT the startup exchange is all part of
it and therefore it's not under the
umbrella of the TLO. However, we are
very close partners. We meet together,
we talk together, we ensure that we have
an understanding of what we're all doing
to meet the common goals of getting
technology knowledge out into the um out
into the world.
Okay.
So,
um this is some this is some data from
this past year. We run a fiscal year, so
it ends in June. Um the cycle that you
see there invention evaluation
protection we will kind of go into in a
little bit more detail.
We are one of the busiest offices in the
United Sta States if not the busiest
because of the productiveness and
innovativeness of our faculty and in
receiving 684 invention disclosures. We
are only surpassed in universities by
university systems. University of
California system, University of Texas
system. But as a single university, we
hold the highest number of inventions
ever received. And I will talk you
through the process of what happens to
those inventions. But it is a testament
to the innovativeness, to the
engagement, to folks like you who
participate in the conversations with
our faculty about the work they're doing
and how it might change the world, how
it might be translated into products and
services. We file over last year, we
filed over 600 new patent applications.
We had 282 patents issued. We have a
portfolio of over 12,000 issued and
pending US and foreign patents that
we're constantly working on refining and
trying to license. We market
technologies in a variety of ways
including showing it on our website. We
do transact about 100 plus uh
technologies into licenses and options.
And last year alone we enabled 38
startup companies to launch with MIT IP.
That even for us was a record. Typically
we're seeing between 20 and 30.
I'll also mention just and call out the
223 billion dollars of research
expenditure happening is both Lincoln
Lab which is about 1.5 billion of
research funding and 800 million going
on on the MIT campus. Those are two
distinct entities getting funding from
different sources. And there's a whole
story behind how that IP is managed
which I'm not going to go into. So
you'll just have to ask offline if you
want that story. All right. What else to
tell you? Um okay. So sources of funding
just talk to to you about that for a
minute.
And this is very simplified. So anybody
who knows differently, forgive me for
being going simple. Um
there are typically two buckets of
different sorts of funding that counts
up to that 2.32 billion. um federal
funding which you're probably all very
familiar with given the fact that it's
being talked about a lot and it comes
from the different federal agencies
whether NSF, Department of War, NASA,
the Army, um uh Health and Human
Services, uh or Department of Energy.
And we also get corporate sponsored
research from partners like you all,
research collaborations, massive
research agreements, foundations. So
that's kind of how the money comes in
for each and every one of those
sponsors. A university like MIT has a
responsibility
through contracts and federal law by
Dole Act and all sorts of things to
report to them every single invention
that comes in. So for those 680 blah
whatever I said, we have to tell some
them that we received it. And the reason
for that is there's often contractual
obligations that tie to those inventions
that we have to act on. So, so begins
the invention disclosure process to a
tech transfer office. And that will
happen at any of your institutions
across the world. Something is funded,
something's created, something's
disclosed. And that is the beginning of
what we call technology transfer.
All right. I'm going to give you two
scenarios. The perfect world. We get a
disclosure. We do an evaluation. We
protect it with IP patents and the like.
We market it. We get licenses.
We develop relationships. And boom, we
get lots of money.
You know what's coming, don't you?
The reality.
It's definitely not as tidy as that. And
in fact, I think I wrote down, "It's
messy and definitely not sequential."
So, a disclosure comes in. It's a Friday
night. The faculty member says to us,
"Did you know I have a conference
tomorrow and I'd like this IP
protected?" So, we go, "Sure, we'll file
that patent for you right now." And we
do. And then we have to go back after
the publication or the presentation and
work out what is this invention and how
should we really protect it so that we
can actually get good and robust
protection in place and from that
protection we might actually discover
through conversations with the faculty
that they're interested or their
graduate students are interested in a
startup company. So we don't need to
market it. Whoopdedoo. we have a
conversation but you know what we might
not license it so we do have to market
it and we do that and that is an
iterative process or it could be that
it's a platform technology uh it's one
lency it's non-exclusive licenses we do
one license here we go and market it and
it's it's messy but it's wonderful of
course um and throughout all of this we
have different interactions going on our
licences inform our patent protection
strategy
And throughout it all, we are developing
the relationship because the
relationship is key to a successful
technology transfer.
And then at the end, you see my prior
slide had three dollar signs. This one
has one. That's because sometimes the
revenue expectations
are well, they don't come true for
whatever reason. Whether it's funding,
inability to get to the market, not the
right market, not the right team,
there's a slew of reasons why things
fail, or they just don't get the
traction that one anticipated.
Okay. So, I am actually going to take
you through this process of what's
important and the sorts of things that
you might
be aware of or not. First and foremost,
we are here, and I dare anyone to
dispute me, to help universities get
technologies into the marketplace for
practical use. We do not produce
products. We do not produce services in
so far as the intellectual property that
we're managing. We are enablers and
facilitators to get other people to
develop the technology. And sometimes
the technology is a glint in the eye of
the faculty member and they don't even
know what the practical application is
going to be but it's really going to be
cool when it becomes something. And so
when we get that invention in we have a
slew of questions to ask about. There is
always an IP policy some whether it's a
company IP policy or a university IP
policy it will outline the ownership. We
have to talk to people about when we own
IP, when we might jointly own IP and
that is a fundamental tenant of
education and awareness for our
community. If there are partners, if
there are other universities, if there
are other research entities working with
us or corporations uh sponsoring
research, there may be jointly owned IP
and the complexity of that relationship
will drive what we consider to be best
for the technology whether it's
licensing to that party or another one.
It's important to always have early
communication to set expectations and
ultimately as I said at the outset this
is about us being enablers and
facilitators to get the technologies
into the marketplace. We are not here to
hold on to that stuff because that's not
our role in the world.
Moving on to evaluation, as I mentioned,
is there an imminent public uh
disclosure? We have to ensure that our
obligations to our sponsors are met. So,
we need to know who provided the funding
and we can spend a lot of time diving
into was it one agreement, two
agreements, was it a foundation, was it
federal funding, was it sponsorship? And
as you saw from that graphic at the
beginning, sometimes it's both. We have
to undertake that formal reporting to
the federal government. And I mean
literally this is the technology we got
in and the with the federal government
having opened up their database just
opened up in the last four weeks or
however many weeks it's been since the
government shut down. We've received a
hundred technologies that we now need to
report as of today to tell them we
received them while the government was
shut down. So this is a constant work
and that's why the office as you saw at
the beginning is structured the way it
is so that somebody can take
responsibility for that. We have to
discuss with joint owners the management
of the IP and the licensing and
determine a path for commercialization.
As many of you probably know investments
in patents cost money and we don't have
a lot of money. In fact we are you know
an forprofit. We are basically funding
ourselves through the licensing revenue
that we get in in order to be able to
fund new patents that are filed with 600
new inventions, 600 patent filings.
There's a lot of investment that we do
on an annual basis and then we try to
license it so the lences actually
recover those costs. But the ROI for
that actually getting a return on the
investment from the investment is slim,
not none. But we're not going to get all
of our funding back or our money back
for every technology we might invest in.
So not all inventions are patentable or
should be patented. We do open source,
open access. We bundle knowhow and
technical information. We do copyright
licenses. So why do we file? Well, if a
startup company or an entity is going to
want to develop the technology and take
hundreds of millions of dollars to
develop that technology, they want to be
protected from the marketplace. And
because our technologies are so so
early, then we need to get it protected
as soon as possible so they can begin to
develop their own IP on the back of the
fundamental IP and build portfolios off
that.
And we do and most universities do that
patentability assessment to make that
judgment and to try and ascertain
although we don't have a crystal ball
whether or not there might be
commercialization potential or interest
to marketing.
So there are a variety of different ways
that we market and I when I brought the
when I came here nine years ago there
was no marketing function. The marketing
was considered to be pick up the phone
and that'll be good enough. We're
actually here not just to market
technologies. We're here to talk to
people about what our researchers are
doing, which is why we publish
technologies on the website in a similar
way to how IOP has on its website many
of the profiles of the faculty. We have
that too. And we also have the
portfolios that they have disclosed to
us. So you could look up any researcher
on our website and find out what they
have uh disclosed and what's uh publish
publicly available. Um we coordinate
with them regarding licensing and
business development and we also have a
presence on LinkedIn social media so
that we are elevating the stories of MIT
with regard to intellectual property and
licensing.
And this is the fun stuff. This is the
stuff that when people say tech transfer
and commercialization they go yeah
that's licensing and I've just told you
a little bit about the other things but
it's a iterative process and it requires
as I said good communication and really
well aligned goals between the parties
so who do we license to qualified
companies whether startupsmemes
established companies sponsors of
research and the like can we license to
them is the case is the invention
available
Is it promised to a sponsor? Has it
already been licensed? Uh, is it a joint
invention? And we have an agreement with
another party that says they're actually
leading the commercialization and we
have no rights to go and license it to
someone else. And can we actually
license to the company? Is it a country
of concern? Is it a risk elevated uh
company? Is it something that's been
somebody that's been sanctioned? We have
to do all that diligence before we
actually engage in a negotiation with
any company. What's the
commercialization plan that we've
thought about and what's the company's
business plan? Do they match? Is there
something different? Did we miss
something? And what does the agreement
look like? Is it an option? Is it a
license? Is it research use only? We
develop a term sheet. We get benchmarks
from the market on the IP in the
industry area and we develop diligence
requirements not out of thin air but
from the milestones and we develop the
diligence and the milestones from the
business plan that the potential LE
gives to us. So then we're not making
stuff up. You tell us you're going to
develop a market a product in five
years. we're going to say, okay, let's
put that down and actually let's make it
seven because the likelihood of you
raising funds in two years is unlikely.
That will be three. So, we take the
information we're given and we try and
develop it into um a draft agreement and
negotiate the terms. And then comes the
fun stuff and the stuff that people get
really excited about and I'm not going
to give you numbers. I'm sorry.
Components of license agreements are
similar but the economics the diligence
the structure will vary according to the
business and the business model
but the common components issue fees an
annual fee of some sort to keep the uh
IP alive fees if there's
commercialization milestones met
royalties on products and sales or
service income if appropriate
reimbursement of the patent costs that
we've incurred that they're going to
take advantage of with regard to the IP
sharing of any sublicicensing
and in the case of startup companies in
order to offset some of those earlier um
fees we don't charge large issue fees to
startups for example we will take a very
small share and I know very small varies
according to country in the US very
small is about 3 to 5% if you go to the
UK it might be 20 to 30 so take your
pick I'd say come to MIT But okay, not
allowed to say that. Um, additional fi
non-financial terms. Is it exclusive or
non-exclusive? Is it a field of use or a
geography? We have to retain rights for
the federal government if it is funded
by the federal government. Which means
there will be a clause that says the
federal government can use this
technology for free non-exclusively.
No argument. And that will be in every
single license that you see if it's
fedally funded research that created the
IP. If it was sponsored by a if it was
sponsored by a corporation and they have
rights
but they've decided not to take them, we
will mention it was sponsored by them.
Just to be clear, we will reserve our
own rights so that our faculty and
researchers can go on developing the
research. doesn't mean to say they're
going to do it commercially, but they
have to be able to use it in their lab.
And then we will require performance and
diligence requirements uh to make sure
that the technology is commercialized.
And this is where we differ from
corporations who might patent stuff and
keep it and pick it fence it and do
nothing with it. We have an obligation
based on our mission and goals to get
technology into the marketplace.
Everybody walks into the relationship
with the intention of doing that. But if
stuff happens, we need to be able to get
that technology back to be able to
transfer it to another party to try and
develop it.
And finally, relationship management.
Successful relationships are developed
based on trust and communication being
open. It begins before the license and
auction is finalized. So we are
developing that relationship throughout
and it requires good communication and
align goals as I said previously.
Um it's necessary to ensure the success
of the relationship for all parties. If
we are crosswise with regard to what the
company's doing and what they think our
expectations of them are with regard to
payment of costs are like we're not
going to get on. So it's really
important that we pay attention to that.
And it's more than just financial
compliance. I probably I'll say guess
that within about 18 months of us
enacting a startup company license, we
will amend it. Why? Because the business
changes. They need to pivot. Something
didn't work out they thought the way it
was going to. They didn't get the
funding they thought. And we build in
that flexibility into the way that we
structure our licenses, which is
basically come and talk to us if things
need to change and we can have a
conversation to make sure that you get
as great a chance as possible to be
successful.
So you are all probably very familiar
with this valley of death as it's called
and many universities find that their
startups do fail
right about in that dip
because they cannot get the funding the
technology is not validated
um they just have not got the right
market fit and the like.
But
it does emphasize the need for a very
strong business plan and the ability to
pivot as I just mentioned. But also the
recognition that sometimes it's better
just to call it. If it's not working,
you might just need to say this is not
working. We can't get the funding and
we're going to have to fold. And that
does happen and it has happened to many
university tech startup companies and as
you know from the marketplace at the
moment in particular areas biotech in
particular you're seeing lots of layoffs
and and uh businesses shutting down
because the funding environment sucks or
because the regulatory programs have
changed or whatever it might be.
So
these are not entirely MIT IP developed
companies. Some of them are, but these
are some examples of products and
companies made possible through um
university tech transfer. So the most
obvious one and the one that um P
University of Pennsylvania made a lot of
money off as a co 19 vaccine. Um there
are other drugs on the market that
you'll be very familiar with that came
out of university labs whether it's
couadin remade casi
um uh gardicil lica
uh even the just the the basic um oh
what's it called the um warerin blood
thinner came out of warf um nicotine
patches um some very fundamental um
digital technologies and optics DVDs,
Vixels, lasers, LEDs, Blu-ray disc, DVD.
I could go on and on and on. A lot of
very um uh fundamental battery
technology came out of universities.
And for the land grants, some apple
varieties, grape varieties, corn
varieties, ways in which they can
increase the the um the crop yields
comes from some of the great a schools.
In addition to creating companies and
creating products, there are other ways
that you small companies can have
impact. And these are five examples of
uh over the last 15 years.
MIT startup companies that were bought
by large companies or acquired or or
merged with. Samsung uh took on QD
vision. Johnson and Johnson acquired
Terrace Biomed. Merc over 15 years ago
bought Smart Sales just a few uh weeks
ago. Atlantic Quant um Google Quantum uh
bought at Atlantic Quantum and Red Hat
acquired Neural Magic uh sometime
earlier this year.
So I mentioned briefly
um some of the reasons why people fall
into that pit um that valley of death
and CB Insights did this study um in
2021. It was a fairly small sample but
I'm pretty sure these are fairly
accurate. It's 111 startup companies.
Some ran out of cash or these are ranked
in the highest no market need. Some got
out competed, flawed business model,
regulatory challenges, pricing cost
issues, not the right team. There are a
myriad of reasons. This is a risky
business, but we're in it in order to
try and have impact. And so we try and
stay the course and that's why being
able to get technology back for a
university is so important that we can
actually try again with another partner.
So the takeaways for you, tech transfer
is a partnership.
Not every tech transfer results in
successful products or services. There
are many many stakeholders and from idea
to impact takes time and investment. And
that's all I have for you. Thank you.
[applause]
>> Two questions. Who are the lucky two?
How do you know if the lency is
reporting all of their revenues that
include your licensed inventions? What a
great question.
You want to come work for me?
Um
we have a team we Google alert is a
wonderful thing that we track um and we
use another database called cap IQ that
tracks what's going on in companies that
have licensed IP and to the point that
we can track we can keep eyes on what
they are saying and many of them talk
about their successes um we can get a
sense but we also when they begin to if
they report and you know we you with the
best will in the world. We track as much
as we can, but when they report, we
actually do check that against any
public announcements and if we have any
doubts, we have the right to audit and
so we can go in at any time to audit an
entity. Obviously with many companies
what we do is we kind of give them a
runway and then we begin to see I mean
some people just don't seem to be able
to work out Excel spreadsheets when they
do their calculations and it's a quick
fix and others are kind of like yeah
this doesn't seem to make sense and
others get really technical because
you're actually having to talk to them
about which l because if we've got
multiple patents in a in a company
that's selling multiple products we have
to map the patents to the products to be
able to assess if they're different
products, how much licensing revenue
they actually owe us. So, it is a
complicated process, which is why all of
those teams that tech transfer offices
have are really important to being able
to do that and check that people are
paying us what they're due.
How often does MIT grant exclusive
versus non-exclusive licenses and what
is the high level criteria for such
decisions? Um the high level criteria is
it depends on the technology.
If it is a semiconductor technology that
has ubiquitous use to go in every single
phone device, we're not going to give it
to one company, going to give it to
multiple companies. If it is a
technology that really is so unique that
is going to need a very focused
development program, we may do an
exclusive, but we may because there
could even be multiple application areas
within that thing, but it needs a lot of
work first. We might do mandatory
sublicicensing or we might provide
milestones by which they have to ensure
that they hit if there's five fields
those five fields within x number of
years and if they can't or if we get
someone who's interested in those
different fields we will actually ask
them to give us that field back and we
will license it or they have to
mandatorily license it separately
and I think that's all you got and I'm
getting kicked off the stage. Thank you.