A lot of Indian policy on regarding
clean energy I think and Chinese as well
has been in my opinion quite pragmatic
and innovative right so if you look at
uh cost reductions around solar energy
India is such a large market uh it
really is right it's the fourth largest
wind market in the in the world and
renewable capacity just last year grew
by about 35% in India and I think in in
China solar capacity grew by over 40% uh
last year. So these markets are large
and they are growing uh fast and India
has electrified I think almost all of
its uh railway network which is a system
that carries 20 million people every
day. So it's a like large system and I
think a lot of it has been based on in
terms of whether it makes sense of the
economics along with you know does it
make sense in terms of uh the emissions.