we're going to talk about demand
planning and demand is really the
Catalyst for the whole supply chain and
we're going to illustrate this using an
actual
chain so Chelsea's demand Tim is Supply
and in a sudden onsite crisis demand may
be really high Supply can't keep up so
Tim in the supply role learns from that
and is going to be ready to push a lot
faster so the next Crisis hits he's
pushing hard but demand isn't as high CU
we didn't assess it effectively and the
inventory is piling up in front of
now there could be more than one actor
in the supply chain so I'm going to step
here and play the role of distribution
jealousy starts pulling I don't have
enough capacity so but the but the
inventory is still piling up now the
problem is I didn't pay attention to the
demand signal and have enough capacity
to let the supply flow through this is
why it's so important to have a demand
plan all parties in the supply chain
rely on that demand signal to know where
to put their resources for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow