You know, one of the most important
facts about architecture today is that
um building and the um the construction
and maintenance of building um uh
produces somewhere around 38% of
greenhouse gases contributing to global
warming. And therefore we need to um uh
radically rethink how buildings are made
and how we think about buildings. Not
least because with the global expansion
of population, we are predicted um if we
keep up current patterns to build as
many buildings in the next 40 years as
we have in the last 10,000 years. And so
unless we really rethink how we make and
build um uh we're going to uh get
ourselves in a very unsustainable
position. So um I mean in uh uh in both
my work and in fact in work throughout
the department we're looking at um how
we can reuse materials, recycle um uh
resources from previous buildings, how
we can adapt and reuse buildings um uh
just like our new home in the
architecture department in the old
metropolitan storage warehouse. Um uh
and these are all really important ways
to think about how cities and buildings
can adapt to to the future. One of the
projects I'm best known for is this
project called local code which started
as a way uh as a um speculative project
in San Francisco when I was at UC
Berkeley and it was a study of 1500 um
uh sites in San Francisco that the city
owned but didn't maintain. They were
called unaccepted streets because they
were either rights of way um uh that
weren't um used as streets or because
they were too steep, because they were
dead ends, because they were alleys
between um buildings. And um with a team
of students at at uh uh at Berkeley, uh
we showed how those um uh those sites,
if they were effectively maintained and
used for storm water retention, could
save the city um uh billions of dollars
in uh upgrades and modifications to the
storm sewer system. And so that um uh
project with its combination of both
digital techniques and really looking at
um the natural systems of the city uh in
a new way looking at how 1500 micro
interventions in the city could
aggregate um uh uh to produce a really
powerful effect uh is a an important um
snapshot of how I think about urban
design. Um uh cities are networks of
networks. They're organisms in their own
way. And if we think um along all the
ways in which a city works um uh and all
of its uh networks of of natural-made
systems work, we have a very powerful
ability to make more resilient cities um
to make more um uh more just, more
sustainable cities um as well. And so
that work continued through projects in
um with clients in uh LA and in New York
and is continuing um um even to this
day. Our current project is with uh a
partnership with um uh an organization
called Green City Force in New York uh
that does job training and urban
greening in New York City public
housing. And New York City public
housing is a particularly interesting
urban environment because um you know a
huge portion of the public housing built
in the city after the Second World War
was built in New York City. And if you
take all of New York City public
housing, you have a city itself which is
as big as Atlanta or Pittsburgh. And so
if we can make a small difference in
every single one of those places, we can
make a huge difference uh to New York
City as a whole. One of the um
uh key insights we've had about cities
in the last um
half century is that cities are not just
physical systems. They're combination of
physical, social, natural um uh uh
systems. And these systems all
intersect. And so when you um and the
social reality of the city is incredibly
important. Uh a city can be really
measured by the way in which it takes
care of its most vulnerable population
and uh by the mechanisms in place for
that. We have good mechanisms for um for
care in cities. Even just um uh
accessible and humane street
environments are are good for everybody.
They're environments of of uh care and
the kind of the right kind of of
collective surveillance of how
everybody's doing. Um and so the idea
yes that we um uh uh that we need to
take care of everybody in a city and a
city is itself um an environment where
uh we judge cities by the way in which
they take care of their most v
vulnerable populations. Um not just uh
children but uh older people as well
often uh um best taken care of together.