[Applause]
thank you my name is Sher arriman I'm
one of the co-founders and the CEO at
concerto biosciences where we are making
it possible to tap into one of our
world's largest untapped natural
resources and that is the microbes that
live in us and around
us your body is covered in billions of
microbes and so is the surface of every
object in the world our food animals
plants our buildings so products that
tap into this microbial world are the
inevitable future of medicine food and
consumer
goods creating these products will
unlock an incredible amount of value but
only a small fraction of this has been
accessed today and the major roadblock
that stands between us in capturing this
value is knowledge it is very difficult
to predict which microbes will make the
best or the most effective products so
whoever can rely reliably predict
microbial performance can unlock these
products and then capture this economic
real
estate well if prediction is our problem
we live in the age of AI let's build an
AI model that can take in all of the
possible different microbial products
and predict which ones will be
effective this is a very reasonable idea
and so it begs the question why has this
not happened yet we would argue that a
major deterrent to building these models
is having the right data microbes live
in very complex ecosystems and the same
way that human behavior is shaped by all
of the humans around us microbial
behavior is shaped by the microbes that
are around to them unfortunately the
technologies that we have today to study
microbes don't actually teach us very
much about how microbes interact and
this leaves us trying to build models
with very incomplete
information what we need
is measurements of how microbes perform
in the context of the other microbes
around them but this turns into a
massive combinatorial math problem if
you have a thousand microbes and you
want to measure all the different
combinations you're talking about
millions and billions of combinations of
microbes that you would have to
construct and measure and even the
fastest robots today can't do
that so while we were at MIT we invented
a technology called kchip and kchip
takes in um nanoliter droplets of
microbial cultures and randomly combines
them into combinations we can make
millions of combinations and then
measure how each of those combinations
performs using microscopy like the image
that you see
here with kchip we have breached the
threshold of data sets that are large
enough to tr to train an AI model of
microbial performance the academic
prototype of kchip was already producing
data sets that were 10 times larger than
the next largest uh data available in
Academia and since starting kerto in
2020 we've gained another order of
magnitude making kerto the sole owner of
the data set that enables this kind of
AI modeling of microbial
performance with this data we've trained
a model that we call Kai and most
importantly kchip data whether used
alone or with Kai enables us to find
products that address High unmet needs
applications one of the areas that is
ripe for disruption by micro based
ingredients is skin and scalp care the
majority of ingredients in this space
are decades old leaving consumers
frustrated and bored microbial
ingredients on the other hand offer a
novel gentle and sophisticated approach
to Skin Care allowing Brands to
establish leadership with their
consumers one of the major um microbes
that causes these skin conditions is
staf orius when the skin microbiome is
disrupted staff orus becomes virulent
and it causes dryness irritation and
rashes however the healthy skin
microbiome normally pacifies staff orus
through these interactions with staff so
we can imagine designing um an effective
product to treat dryness irritation and
rash by finding combinations of microbes
that inhibit staff or's
virulence using kchip we made millions
of combinations of skin microbes
measured how they influenc storus and
then used this massive data set to find
a new therapeutic for atopic dermatitis
that's in a phase 1B study now as well
as in um consumer product ingredients
for skin irritation and we're working on
formulating those KP can be applied to
Industries Far Beyond skin and and um
scalp care we've done successful pilot
programs in um agriculture food
ingredients consumer care we're actively
seeking Partners both for our existing
assets and to
co-discovery and scalp care vaginal
health and food um ingredients so be
very happy to talk about any of those
areas with you at the break thank
you so much