I heard that you guys talked too much
before I got here and so we're running
late and so I will not talk too much. I
will keep us on time which means you
have to pay attention because I talk
fast.
So how do you think nonclinical
information shapes clinical
decisionmaking in an age of large
language models? It's an open question.
Large language models are actually being
used in every Boston area hospital right
now to make decisions about patient
care. Every Boston area hospital that uh
you've been to or will go to is using
large language models to create patient
note summaries and to answer questions
and to interact between patients and
providers. So if you get an email from
your provider, it was probably drafted
by a large language model. Okay, so
that's a reality. This is what's
happening. The question is, how does
changing the non-clinical
information in clinical text affect
large language model reasoning? Okay, so
let's figure out how we're going to uh
do this experiment. The first thing that
we have is original clinical data, and
we'll go through some examples of what
those look like. We're going to perturb
the data in some simple ways using some
plausible uh differences that come from
social
sciences. The categories of
pertabbations match things that people
in health and social sciences have noted
correspond to patient groups of
interest. So for example, we know that
female patients tend to get less care
and people if you just swap the gender
of a patient, doctors tend to prescribe,
for example, fewer painkillers and fewer
interventions to them. And so we want to
see if that carries through. There have
been a lot of studies done on patients
who have more more dramatic uh
disposition or maybe more health
anxiety. Doctors tend to interact with
them differently. And finally, we have
uh modifications that mimic people who
have less technological aptitude or
English proficiency. Okay? And so the
way that we're going to actually
perturve the notes or the questions or
the summarizations, whatever we're
using, is we're going to swap or remove
gender to look at markers of gender.
We're going to add uncertain language or
colorful language to mimic implicit
changes to the style of language. The
content doesn't change, but the style
does. And we're going to look at
realistic semantic or structural changes
to mimic people who have maybe less
technological aptitude or maybe don't
have English proficiency. Okay, these
are simple pertibations that you can
make. They do not change the actual
clinical content of a question for
example, but they do change sort of the
style. All right, we are not going to
study any genderspecific
uh clinical conditions because we are
looking at gendered pertibbations. And
so before we do any of this uh this
pertabbation, we actually remove all
cases of gendered conditions, mentions
of gender relevant organs or mentions of
cases that uh have things like menration
or pregnancy. Okay? Because the focus is
to look at what happens when you flip
gender and it shouldn't matter for the
case. So we're not going to look at
gendered conditions. Okay. All right.
The data sets we're using are ask a do
and on Q&A. These are standard clinical
uh data sets that are used in the
machine learning community. Um ask a do
is Reddit posts about you know health
questions and ailments. Um we reduce the
subset so we're not looking at gendered
questions. Same thing with an Q&A. We
don't want to look at breast cancer or
prostate cancer for example. So we take
a subset of these questions. For all of
these questions, we have a question and
then we can ask a large language model
to answer it. And then we also have a
ground truth answer. Ask a doc looks
like this. And maybe you've gone on
Reddit before and and use these sort of
posts. It's people sort of talking about
something that they're concerned about
and they're asking a doctor to respond
to it. Right? So my question is how long
should this gross thing be happening?
How much can possibly be in there?
Right? This is the style of question
that's
there. A Q&A is slightly more
structured, right? And so it gives a
sort of um vignette of a patient's
history and then you have a message from
a patient. I've been feeling more
fatigued than usual for the past week.
Having trouble completing my tasks. Is
this normal? Should I be concerned? All
right. So in both of these cases, we
have some clinical text. A question is
being asked. We're going to perturb the
non-clinical part of the the text and
we're going to see whether the large
language model changes its response to
your clinical question when we change
non-clinical things. Okay, we use four
different large language models that are
popular in the machine learning
community um because we wanted to look
at a range of open and closed source
models, large and small models, right?
To make sure that that's not what would
make a difference. Each time uh we have
a question and its perturbed uh sort of
cousin, we sample the LLM response three
times for each model and then we're
going to evaluate differences. Okay,
does this setup sort of make sense? We
have clinical things changing the
nonclinical content measure whether the
LLM changes its response and it
shouldn't, right? We all agree here that
if we don't change the clinical content,
then hopefully the clinical
recommendation shouldn't change. How are
we going to measure differences? We're
going to measure three things that are
important in healthcare contexts. We're
going to ask the large language model,
do you think this patient should just
manage their condition at home? Do you
recommend that they get a visit? Right?
Or do you recommend that they be given a
resource? Right? And this is because
this is often how large language models
are being used in clinical setting.
We're using them to triage who gets
different resources.
Okay. So this is an example of how we
would annotate using a large language
model a recommendation. You have a
response and we can see here that this
large language model thinks yes this
person should get a visit. Yes, they
should get a resource. No, they
shouldn't manage it at home. Okay,
nothing too fancy here.
We're going to measure how bad uh the
the model differences are in um a
specific way. First, we're going to
measure did something change at all.
Let's say the question is I'm a
35year-old male and a stray puppy's
teeth grazed my leg. Should I get a
treatment for rabies? This was a real
question. Um if I just perturb and say,
uh now I'm a 35-year-old female. So,
just change M to F. And the model's
original answer was no, don't
self-manage. But now it says yes,
self-manage. That was a change. It went
from no to yes. And so I would record
this as a treatment shift. But if it
originally said yes and I change it to
no, I would still record it as a
treatment shift. So the second thing
we're going to look at is whether care
allocation is reduced. So whether I go
from saying no, don't self-manage this,
you get a resource, you get a visit, you
get a lab test to saying yeah, yeah,
you're fine, manage it at home. Okay. So
the second thing is going to be when we
have a difference a treatment shift do I
reduce care that's the second metric the
third metric is is that reduction of
care something that clinicians think is
an error okay and so we have a tiered
set of metrics did something shift in
your recommendation of those shifts were
they reductions in care of the
reductions of care which ones do
clinicians think were wrong that is a
clinical error it's not up to judgment
like this shouldn't have happened.
Okay, so first let's look in the
aggregate. Do LLM change? And the answer
is yes, they do. Under all of these
pertibations, gender swapping, gender
removal, uncertain and colorful
language, exclamations, lower and
uppercase. Uh there is a reasonable
amount of change. Okay. Uh is care
reduced in most cases? Yes. In most
cases when you uh modify a
note care tends to be reduced. People
get fewer
resources. Are these reductions in care
resources medical errors? In most cases,
yes. Okay, that's bad. Let's take a
closer look. Is it just the models? No.
Models actually flip across classes and
metrics. And so here you can see for all
of the different uh large language
models that we evaluated, there isn't a
consistent trend in like oh it's the
large models that are doing really
poorly or the small models that are
doing really well. They're all
consistently having these pertabbations
uh change their behavior and this is
across the manage visit and resource
metrics. If we look at what's happening
a little carefully, flips are reducing
care more in female patients. Right? So
this is when when uh a model chooses to
reduce care. This is the difference
between care allocated uh between male
and uh female questions. And you can see
if it's blue that means that the male
questions were uh something was taken
from them. If it's yellow that means
that something was taken from female
questions. And so in general what we're
seeing is that the flips when there was
a difference in the model the difference
specifically reduces care in female
patients. But is this reduction in care
an error? Maybe these are things that
are again, you know, not clinically an
error. Well, they are. So, of the ones
that uh have care reduction, this is the
reduced care error rate. These are
clinically incorrect reductions in uh
care allocation. Okay. So, uh the last
thing that we wanted to check
is what is it even mean to be uh you
know sort of a female question, right?
because this is, you know, an original
poster is saying that I am a 35-year-old
male or female. That doesn't make the
question female, right? It's just a
question. You happen to be a female
asking it. Um, and so we removed all
mentions of gender in all of the queries
and none of them are gender specific uh
to begin with. And then we asked the
model to infer the
gender of the uh of the question and
then wanted to see whether um the models
uh the model would reduce care more for
patients who were actually female
questions from patients who are actually
female in the original posting or for
people it thought were female. So uh put
another
way, option one is if we remove all
mentions of who is female, gender could
still be sticky and so the model could
still choose to reduce care for
originally female text. Option two is
that gender is fluid in the model's
mind. Whoever it thinks is female,
that's who it's going to reduce the care
for.
Okay. Do you who thinks option one will
happen?
Nobody. Who thinks option two will
happen? You are so smart. Yeah. The
model reduces care for who it thinks is
female, not who is actually female. And
when you explicitly mention female in
the record, it knows. But when we remove
all mentions of gender and we ask it to
think about who is female, the people
who it's reducing care for flips and it
reduces the care in an erroneous way.
Right? may not just reducing but in a
way that clinicians say is incorrect for
those it thinks are
female. Good job ladies. Very
smart. Um this is part of a larger set
of experiments that we are uh conducting
trying to understand how we have models
that will be wrong sometimes and are
likely to be wrong more often in groups
that we often see mistakes in by human
doctors and care providers such as women
and minorities. Um some of the things
that we've learned in other work to
contextualize this contribution are that
number one the losses that we see in
medical contexts from bad AI are much
worse than the gains we see from good
AI. So this is a really nice paper this
is uh not my paper it's uh from 2020 in
nature medicine they did
dermatology assisted by AI. This is
hidden in figure 2 subfigure J but it's
the best figure in the whole paper. What
you can see here is that the benefit
that you
get across different expertise levels
from having a good AI algorithm is good,
right? It's statistically sign it's over
zero. It's maybe good. And the loss from
bad AI is much
worse. Okay? So, if we're going to
deploy AI in a clinical setting, which
we already have, it better be pretty
good, which it
isn't. Humans are really susceptible to
incorrect advice. This is a paper I
wrote and here you can see that even
radiologists so every um line there is
an individual radiologist that we uh had
participate in this study. So for
example radiologist is this a pointer?
Yes. Radiologist number
60 got 75% of their cases right. But
you'll notice that their bar is colored
all blue. That means that they only got
a case right when the AI that was giving
them uh advice was correct. So some
doctors over here got a 100% of their
cases right. The two that were incorrect
recommendations and the ones that were
correct recommendations. So some doctors
are just really susceptible to incorrect
advice even though they're radiologists
who have had over a decade of training.
And finally, we know from other work
that when you deliver biased advice to
clinicians and nonclinians, the way that
you couch the advice matters more than
the actual content of the advice. So
here we varied whether we had a good or
bad AI give advice in a declarative
prescriptive way, you should do
something or in a suggestive informative
way saying there's a feature uh in this
uh data do what you will with it. And we
found that when you told doctors to do
the wrong thing in a way that was
declarative, you should do this wrong
thing, they listened and they did it.
But when you told them to do the wrong
thing in a way that was suggestive, they
ignored it and retained their original
fair decision-making. And so I I think
thinking about all of these different
contributions, there's a lot that we
need to do to move forward with
actionable AI and human health. Thank
you.
Thank you so much, Maza. questions from
Azia. Go ahead. Thanks. Super
interesting talk. Um I'm I'm wondering
if you tried to correct the LLM somehow
by asking it to say now consider the
gender is different or something. Does
it change its decision thereafter or
something like some chain of reasoning
sort of
u you can fix a lot of these things
right? Uh did you did you try that in
this experiment? We didn't we didn't do
any fine-tuning. In many other papers,
not not just my group, many many groups
have shown that if you do um fine-tuning
on specific data that you have and you
have a specific bias that you know
exists and you want to correct it that
you can address these biases within the
large language model in those fields.
The issue is you have to know it exists.
You have to care enough to correct it
and you have to correct it in a way that
will be robust to differences in the way
that the data is entered, annotated,
abbreviated, all these other things,
right? Um, nobody's doing that, right?
So, because this is an administrative
use of AI, it's not under the purview of
the FDA. The FDA doesn't clear GPT4 to
do this. It's just doing it. Open AAI
explicitly says and has said publicly
they are not redteameing these models
before they go into the Boston area
hospitals to make sure that they are for
example genderneutral. They're not. It's
not their job. And hospitals are
therefore now responsible at an
individual level for somehow having
enough
knowledge and time and money to red team
all these models and not just for gender
in these specific cases that we looked
at but for every group that we know
there has been historical and current
bias towards in a healthcare setting.
And so is it fixable hypothetically? Of
course, people can fix these things to a
certain uh degree. Is it being fixed in
practice? No.
So, obviously, there are a lot of things
going wrong that you're
documenting. If you were to start, where
would you start to fix this in a
clinical setting? like what are the the
three things that need to happen and
could happen in a relatively short time
frame other than like you know having
every hospital hire machine learning
experts which doesn't seem I don't
actually think any hospitals need
machine learning uh experts. I think we
need a new um secretary of HHS.
Um like if you want quick fixes we could
get rid of RFK. Uh, we could rehire our
ARPAH director. We could rehire all of
the FDA AI clearing people that exist.
Like there are fixes. The fixes are
regulatory. Nobody at the hospitals
knows how to fix the MRI machines. Even
if they tell you they do, they don't,
right? Like they don't actually
understand. They have a service contract
with Seammens, right? And Seammens comes
in once a year and they fix the
technology. And there's ways for the MRI
machine to autoc calibrate and say, "Oh,
I'm out of calibration." like call a
tech. Nobody expects the hospital to
have like MRI techs like you know in the
basement to appear like Batman. That's
not a we why are hospitals hiring
machine learning people to live in their
basement? They do. Most hospitals in the
Boston area have an ML team in their
basement. Um that's not sustainable and
also it's not something that is uh going
to lead to like reliable outputs across
our health care system. And so my
personal belief is things like this are
trivially identifiable as long as you're
auditing for them and we're not right
now. We're explicitly not doing that
because there's a lack of sort of
regulatory interest in doing so. In
fact, the safe and reliable AI bill
under the Biden administration that act
was repealed right months into uh this
administration and there uh has been a
call uh request for information for a
new a new thing to replace it. And the
explicit instructions in the RFI were
that they didn't want anything that was
overly focused on social engineering.
And so we don't know what's going to
replace it. But you know, uh certainly I
think what hospitals should do right now
is to institute the practices that a
regulatory body would have put on them
in the first place, which is for example
very strong audits of systems before
they pay for them and are then liable
for the damage they
cause. Um great. So question over there.
Okay. So what if we we shift this
paradigm because the the LM or the the
AI doesn't really create new things. It
just fed back all the things they found
available. So so if you see that the the
AI is giving you this kind of bias
things. It's actually reflecting what
the real people are doing. So, so
there's the real thing is that the
people are going to do this and we're
telling the machine don't do this. It's
like do what I tell you to do, don't do
what I did. So, this is like a different
model to think about, right? So, so if
we not saying that the AI model is
perfect, we actually should come back
and say that this AI is reflecting the
world is not perfect. That's that's
true. Yeah. AI models reflect the
history, right? Uh often, you know,
historically what has happened. I think
we can all agree that our health care
system uh not just ours but every health
care system has been really bad
historically especially for certain
groups right and we don't want that uh
those sort of uh behaviors calcified
forever right so I totally agree with
you um the way that every
state-of-the-art machine learning model
is trained these days is initially in an
unsupervised way nobody's out there like
labeling every data like sample in the
world everything is unsupervised now
Right? And what that means is you assume
that every data point out there in the
world is just as good as every other
data point. Okay? So that means that
every sample in the electronic
healthcare record of a doctor when they
were exhausted and made a mistake is
valued the same as a sample from when
they were not exhausted and did
something really
well. That's the paradigm that we are in
right now. And I I think it's an
incorrect paradigm to be in. And so are
these reflective of bad processes? Yes,
they are. The problem is if you go to a
doctor and get a bad opinion, go to
another doctor, get another second
opinion, right? And by the uh law of,
you know, every statistical uh theorem
that exists, randomization is more fair,
right? Like there's a there's a reason
that we have multiple raiders for
things. It's because my bias and your
bias and there everybody's things cancel
out, right? If you have multiple
raiders, you're guaranteed a fairer
system and you always have the ability
to go to somebody else, right? I can't
replicate my biases to every patient in
the world. But if we have one AI system
being used in every hospital in the
Boston area, and we do, we have one set
of calcified biases based on historical
data that that company used. Calcified
forever. No second opinion.
Hi, thank you for this. Um, what kinds
of products you just touched on it are
you seeing these models show up in in
hospitals? like what do the products
look like? What kinds of things are they
purchasing? They're everywhere. They uh
schedule patient appointments. So, at
UCSF, uh AI was used to do uh bookings
and what it did was cancel every black
patients appointment saying black
patients don't show, so just cancel,
double book them. Uh in the Boston area,
they're used to create patient and
provider message responses. And as you
saw, when they create uh either patient
messages or responses to questions,
they're um more aggressive in removing
care resources and care allocation from
women. And other studies have shown from
minorities. We're seeing AI being used
to screen um for uh who should be
allowed to get different kinds of
treatments, who should be uh there's a
lawsuit active in California right now
about uh insurance, right? So uh there
was an AI algorithm used by a large
insurer that was used to decide for
thousands of patients at a time whether
they their claims would be covered under
the insurance and it just denied
thousands of people's claims at a time
and said no we don't want to spend
money. Um it's being used not just in
health care it's being used uh in the
criminal justice system in the education
system. So, universities and primary
schools now are using it to decide which
kids are going to be really smart, who
you should track into different
programs, who you should recommend for
different colleges. Police departments
are using it to decide uh which
neighborhoods to go into, which suspects
to question. These are all like public
record, right? All of these judges are
being shown. I just heard about this in
Massachusetts. Did you know that judges
are being shown scans of people's
brains, fMRI scans, and then there's AI
software that will say, "This person's
brain is a violent
brain." There's a group of Massachusetts
judges that was talking about this
recently. This is a new thing in
courtrooms. They'll just show you an
fMRI scan of somebody's brain and
they'll say, "This person's brain is
violent. You can't let them out on the
street. Give them a longer sentence."
It's everywhere. And the problem is
because it's not regulated and we do not
have an AI bill of rights and now we
don't even have the bill that we used to
have that was about safe reliable AI,
right? That was repealed under under
administration. You have very few
guarantees as a consumer that AI will
not be used against you, right? Also,
our FTC has been defanked, right? like