all right good
afternoon we we can do better than that
good
afternoon excellent all right so I want
to talk to you today about sourcing
Innovation around Ai and using AI as a
tool for that and for those of you uh
who've met with me I know I've met with
number of groups over the last five or
10 years a bunch of the work that I that
I did at that point one of the things we
saw was this increasing usage by firm
terms of external Innovation sources for
digital innovation in particular right
we saw that historically right there was
this much bigger mix where sometimes you
were innovating internally you might
have your um like your business units
doing stuff but that as we got to very
technical things it became increasingly
important to Source Innovation from
universities from third parties that had
particular knowledge in this and so what
I'm going to really talk about today is
that in the context of AI right you you
want to innovate you want to use AI as a
tool to in your company but you run into
this problem which is there's a whole
bunch of expertise needed for that and
so is it worth it should you invest
should you build a bunch of capabilities
internally to do that that might be
expensive right should you adopt
something off the shelf well there might
be some drawbacks to that too and so I
want to think about those kind of
tradeoffs and give you some sense of how
AI is developing and how you should
think about that if you want to be using
it to help do Innovation
okay so I want to start with just a
couple of examples of the remarkable
success that AI has had in helping with
Innovation and I think um this one is
you know
both uh is very important right protein
folding this is the 2018 Discovery by
the Deep Mind Group of being able to do
incredibly good job with this this was
sort of remarkable in the sense that
this was a problem that had
traditionally been enormously hard
people had spent a lot of time and a lot
of computer Cycles trying to do a good
job at this and had really not been that
successful
then there was actually a whole bunch of
initiatives that were out that said
humans were actually still better at
these things than computers let's use
humans for this right and so there was
something called folded at home and
other techniques where people would get
do that Innovation
themselves they were still better not
than this system right in this the Deep
Mind crew did a number of specific
things so first of all they brought in
these these deep Learning Systems these
new AI systems that were able ble to do
things sort of more similarly to the way
that humans had thought about that and
also equally important they brought in
something like a factor of a thousand
times more compute than people had used
to solve that problem before and that
was also incredibly valuable for doing a
good job on this okay so big success
there we
see this is just now last year the
newest version of chat gbd passes the US
medical licensing exam with flying
colors and diagnosed a one in a thousand
condition in seconds okay this is you
know again in this sort of area of
science um most recently AI achieves a
silver medal standard solving
International mathematical Olympiad
problems okay so this is this is
interesting this is kind of a part of a
broader phenomenon that we're now seeing
of spending a lot more time at imprints
right so for those of you who know the
um uh
gp4 uh 01 right has this property that
not only does it try and solve a problem
right in a way that large language model
do in the way that we're sort of used to
them doing with chat GPT but it'll try
an answer and then it might actually
sort of reflect on it so it might ask
this itself like does this seem like a
good answer to the question you asked
and it turns out that even though it
just produced that answer sometimes
it'll say like no that doesn't seem like
a good answer like somehow by reflecting
it does not notices that this is not a
good answer and it can go back and say
okay well you know why was it not a good
answer and then sort of like give itself
almost like another prompt to to try and
to a better answer so that's a
particular sort of narrow example of
something that is coming in more and
more with these mathematical problems
where people put more structure on them
and say like rather than trying to solve
it all at once in one shot maybe I want
to solve it in increments right maybe I
know that a typical way to solve this is
to have five steps and I try and solve
the first step and then the second step
and so on on long and what's been
remarkable is we have seen in areas like
math and science these systems doing
better than they had done before so that
aidea of having those steps might be
very
valuable okay and then this is not
really a science example but I think
it's a nice one just to think about it
so this is a a beautiful example of a an
image created by mid
journey I bring this one up not so much
as I say because it's a science thing
but so much as it's a very sort of quick
ability to produce something like this
which we do see all over the place in
terms of very Hands-On R&D that firms
are doing we see them saying Oh like we
want to design the next generation of
car what should that car look like let's
really rapidly prototype what different
pictures could look like what's the next
sneaker going to look like what are some
rapid prototypes of that you can produce
images with these systems so much more
quickly that that can be very valuable
for very Hands-On R&D that you're
doing okay all right so with that is
sort of in our mind of seeing this plan
out goals for this session are going to
be to understand why AI is being used in
Innovation and sorry how it's being used
and
why and so I want to start you out with
uh a graph that my lab has been
producing about the use of foundation
models in
science so for those who um have been
thinking about this Foundation models
are these large AI models that have
being built they're typically very
expensive right and they're being used
very broadly so chat GPT would be one
example of this mid Journey the one I
just talked about on the previous slide
would be an example of this these are
systems that you sort of say ah maybe I
can use this off the shelf or do some
adaptation and so what we're seeing here
in the four different lines so this Top
Line is probably the thing that if
you've seen most discussions about Ai
and science that's probably a version of
what you've seen which is people citing
these models so they'd say ah somebody
cited chat gbt that must mean it's being
used that is not true right we are
living in an era where there's a ton of
hype and a lot of interest around AI
lots of people site these things without
actually using them right so that Top
Line is more of a reference for us to
say okay well that's what's going on but
the next one down which you can see is
not being as much we're not quite at 1%
yet but that is model use so that says I
have I'm doing some area of Science and
I'm going to actually draw on chat gbt
right so maybe you have like in in your
companies you're saying oh we're trying
to do some drug design and we're trying
to think about where might be there some
other interactions that this drug might
have and we say okay well we want to
scan the literature to get some sense of
does this does this article suggest that
there might be a problem does this
article suggest that there might be a
problem right that would be an example
you use the API from chat GPT and you
could actually Analyze This okay so
that's model uses the next one down is
model customization so this is saying
not take CH chat TPT off the shelf this
is saying you take it then you train it
on some of your own data maybe you do
some prompt engineering to try and get
it to perform better and then the last
one down here is new actual new models
being
released so I want you to take several
things from this graph so the first
thing is just how big a difference there
is between these different sources of
things so citations very cheap right you
can site it you can say like
contextually this is important model use
that's just an API that'll cost you a
little bit of money because you can do
it right considerably less of that but
boy still growing very very fast and
then model customizations that's even
more expensive right then you actually
have to have your own team helping to
customize this model make it right and
you can see again quite a drop in the
the percentage of papers that are doing
that okay so that's number one there are
these big differences between these
things the second thing is you can see
that on the y- axis here we have the
share of papers that are are actually
doing these things and we can see these
this scale is an exponential SC a
logarithmic scale so these are
exponential curves even though they look
linear this is an enormous adoption
happening within science right and so
when I say why is it important to be
thinking about AI in science and an R&D
this is why right it is going up
incredibly rapidly and then the last
thing is to notice this distinction
between all of those lines and this line
about new models being released that's
growing much much more slowly that's
because these models are so expensive to
build right and so that's something
that's going to be important to think
about as you think about the choice
about do you want to design your own
model or do you want to just use someone
else's model for
it
okay okay so it's also interesting to
look look at this picture across
different fields uh within the within
science and what we can see
there is that I think not surprisingly
computer science is the one that is
leading the leading the thing in fact
more than 1% of all computer science
papers are already using TR gbt excuse
me using one of these AI tools in the
way that it's actually been done and
here the these lines represent either
using or adapting for yourself both of
those are included in these
lines mathematics next engineering next
then medicine then biology and then
physics okay so this is again just more
of a reference for I thought might be
useful for all of you when you're
thinking about your particular companies
and what you work in right you can say
well if the main thing we're doing is
computer science right we you are we in
an era where already 1% are using it if
you're in more than an area like physics
right where you'd say okay well we're
still at you know 0 1% quite a bit lower
those models are probably not as
developed okay so huge exponential
increase in the use in
science what's actually driving this
change and for this I want to show a
probably my favorite example uh so this
is from a 2002 excuse me 2022 paper by
Google about the power of scaling up
neural networks so they trained this
model this is going to be model that you
give it some kind of verbal prompt and
it produces an image right so you know
modern chbd you just type this in it
produces an image for you it's going to
be like that and so the prompt they gave
it was a portrait photo of a kangaroo
wearing an orange hoodie and blue
sunglasses standing on the grass in
front of the Sydney Opera House holding
a sign on the chest that says Welcome
Friends okay it's kind of fun chosen
because this is going to require
interpolation right there was no such
picture in the on the internet that it
could just recapitulate right it's got
to try and figure this out so what
happens if you train this on a model
with 350 million
parameters you get this kind of
Chihuahua looking
thing right that that this is not very
good right there's something that looks
a little bit like an orange hoodie like
that building in the background is not
the city the Opera House the sign is
junk like this is not that good a
fit okay now but importantly this is a
model that only has 350 million
parameters and for those who are not
sort of like conversing about these
model sizes this is pretty small now
it's kind of strange to say that because
if you were someone who grew up in an
era where you were doing like
regressions or you were doing
engineering models right you did like
you know Newton's uh equations in high
school right you were doing things that
might have had like three
parameters right and this has got 350
million of them okay so this is where St
firmly in a deep learning AI world but
for these kind of models this is still
pretty
small all right so what if you give it
the same training regime you give it the
same data but now you train it on a
model with 750 million
parameters okay it's a little better
like that thing standing next to it
looks a little bit more like a
kangaroo right the Sydney Opera house
we're now evoking it a little bit but
we're definitely not there
make it bigger
again okay that that's quite a bit
better right that it's still not quite
the Sydney Opera House in the background
but again it's getting closer that now
the kangaroo starting to look pretty
good right the sunglasses are looking
good the orange hoodies looking good
sign is still
wrong right there two signs and the the
one on the uh sort of cardboard
background there if you squint it might
say welcome friends but it doesn't quite
20 billion
parameters remarkably
good okay so this is pretty interesting
right this is telling us that all of
this when you get have these extra
parameters just like we had back in you
know High School physics when you have
extra parameters you can model something
more flexibly it turns out that that's
really important in an era where you're
giving these models literally trillions
of data points in in terms of the inputs
then actually this really
matters and having this flexibility in
the model really matters and you can do
much better okay so this is at different
sizes you can do
better okay so it turns out this has
been really the dominant way in which
all of these AI companies have been
getting better
performance and so I want to turn this
now from sort of like hey abstract
number parameters which might be a
little think about this actually in
terms of Hardware that people are using
okay so for those of you who' sort of
been following this for a while this
paper in 2012 alexnet this is by Jeff
hinton's Lab at University of Toronto
this was really the paper that kicked
off the deep learning
Revolution that
paper ran on two gpus those are the
specialized processors that people use
for six days okay and I remember when
this came out and it was a little bit
like wow that's a that's a lot of
compute to to to put on this
four years later when Google does the
Google Translation
engine six days 50 times as many
processors a big
number 2023 GPT
4 three
months on
25,000
gpus okay so when I say like this is the
dominant way that people have been
getting progress it it is and you can
see that in all of this and so when you
read on the the news about you know like
the state of Virginia saying oh actually
we're going to substantially increase
our projections for the amount of
electricity being used because of AI
right this is what we're talking about
when people talk about all of these data
centers being built this is why and it's
because that scaling up makes such a
difference in fact you can really see
this so anthropic and open AI obviously
two of the really big companies that
work in this space you can see this
explicitly in their discussions of this
so anthropic says inspired by the
University of scaling and statistical
physics we develop scaling laws to help
us do systematic empirically driven
research which is sort of the you know
technical way of saying if you scale it
up you do
better open AI we believe that scale in
our models our systems ourselves is
magic when in doubt scale it up okay and
in some of the work that my lab has done
we find that something like 70% of all
the Improvement in these models can be
explained by the amount of compute that
they're able to harness okay so it's a
big
number all right so with that in mind
then let's now think about building
models right so you're at a company
you're saying okay we have this data we
have this problem that's really
important to us we really want to adapt
that and think about should we build our
own model in order to help do
this well certainly one thing you should
think about if you're going to build
your own model particularly in something
like large l language model kind of
space but can be more General is that
there's a big cost but also big
potential for these so what do I mean by
that
well to give a sense so back when it was
still a separate entity back in 2018
deep learning uh deep Google Deep Mind
was doing this right and they reported
separately and at that point they were
losing half a billion dollars a
year when they trained Alpha go just
building that system just for go was
estimated to have cost 30 5
million and gbd4 was estimated to cost
$100 million to train and it's now the
case that that people building these
large language models are already
talking about build it costing say 5 to
10 billion for the next generation of
models the train so if you really want
Cutting Edge right it can you you should
definitely be thinking
millions and you know if you're if
you're getting closer to large language
models I mean it's billions and billions
but um this is still very very big
Investments that you should be thinking
about if you're training these new
models but as I say these can be big
right so I already mentioned protein
folding right this is just one the Nobel
Prize it's clearly producing a whole
bunch of Partnerships that Google
deepmind has with pharmaceutical
companies and the like um and then you
know these math problems I already
mentioned again you can imagine say
being able to solve new engineering
problems with this that could be very
valuable okay so with all that said I
want to come to an example
so this is a case study that my lab
did and this was a European supermarket
and they had a problem which I think a
lot of you would empathize with right
they're just want to know how much
should I order each week to keep on the
shelves seems like a very basic question
for a supermarket turns out to be an
incredibly valuable question for
Supermarket as
well the way they did that
historically is they had an sap model
that tracked sales over the past and it
would say oh okay well based last year
this time you sold this many bananas
that would get sent to the store manager
the store manager would say ah you know
things have gotten a little like we've
got some new developments around here uh
the weather's getting good okay I'm
going to up that by a little bit they
would send that order in and they would
get
it that's you know not bad but this is
the kind of problem that you'd expect
deep learning to be able to do a lot
better because deep learning is very
good at integrating different data
sources um it's handling nonlinearity so
maybe like you know I cream demand goes
up but then on the like the first warm
day of the year it goes up a lot right
that kind of like unusual circumstances
again deep learning very very good at
that those kind of things so you might
think this is a great
problem so they worked with the
consultant they put in the system and
what happened Well turns out they were
right it was much better the prediction
error dropped by a third that's
huge but costs were so high that they
delayed implementation initially and
then in the end only rolled it out in
the limited
way so what what's going on here so
first of all part of what was going on
here was just training these systems are
expensive right we just spent a couple
of slides talking about that it is it is
expensive to build these
models but the second thing that was
going on there that was really important
was that they hadn't really thought
about the business side of this when
they went in they went into it with a
mode that was like Hey AI is kind of
great let's see what can do rather than
hey what is the exact business need and
why is it going to matter a lot and the
reason I know that this is true is
because after the fact we went back and
we did a bunch of the economics of this
we said okay well how valuable is it to
you to get a better prediction right if
you got a third better that sounds like
a great
result well for some things it's
incredibly valuable right if you bought
a bunch of lobster and that Lobster is
all going to go bad or a bunch of apples
and those apples are all going to go bad
that saves you a lot of money as a
supermarket but if you have a can of
tuna fish on the
Shelf keeping it an extra week doesn't
matter very much right and these AI
systems are can be expensive enough that
you that actually that extra cost of
doing that Cann not might not be worth
it and in fact in this case wasn't and
so what happened when we redid this
economics is we found that about 85% of
all of the value that could have been
created by this system was all in a very
small number of categories and it was a
stuff that went bad really fast and
stuff like that and that made it a much
more attractive thing if they focused on
that but they just hadn't done that
economics ahead of
time okay so I bring this up just to get
back to this idea of when you're
thinking of applying this in in science
you should not think of this as being
just like any other it system and you
sort of put it in right you should think
that actually these predictions could be
expensive that you're going to be making
with these systems and you might want to
take that into account when you first do
it okay because these system are
expensive there are also some
consequences and so this was a paper
that we wrote in science a couple of
years ago about the growing influence of
industry in AI research and that's
because these price tags are going up so
to give you a little bit of a sense of
what this looks like um so here we're
let's focus first on the inputs AI so in
the top left here we have the
percentages of AI phds coming out of
universities that are hired by industry
this is now uh so I said this was now a
couple of years old but um we you know
we were already on on track to getting
to the very highest levels of
engineering so if you think of sort of
any field like this so there's enormous
demand for um for talent and I not
mention many of you are experiencing
this in your
companies um we saw AI faculty being
hired away right and you know we see
this as well like there are definitely
academics who were saying particular
types of research are now very hard for
academics to do because you need the
giant supercomputer in order to actually
even compete in that
area and then these last ones are
showing uh that a computing power so
this is the number of parameters in a
model remember we talked about that with
the Google example and this is just
showing that the average number of
parameters of academic models were very
stable over this time period the ones in
Industry were going up very rapidly
okay and this gets reflected in
outcomes so here what we're showing is
the percentage of the 10 biggest AI
models that come from industry and you
can see back in the early
2000s all none of them were from
industry they were all from Academia and
now almost all of them are from industry
right there is this kind of scale
up we also see this in terms of the
percentage of papers so these are now
computer science papers that have an
industry affiliate and you can see that
for a long long time that was very
stable that around 20% of papers had an
industry co-author and in the last few
years it had gone up to about 40% it's
about
doubled okay so you know you're you're
you're not in in Academia but I bring
this up just to say like these
constraints of these extra costs they do
bind right if you were a small company
this can be a challenge if you are a
large company but you're competing
against someone who has even deeper
Pockets or bigger things this can also
be an
issue okay
um that is what I've just been talking
about is really the sort of scale of the
cost that you have in this I also just
want to bring in a super super practical
thing that came out of some research we
did which I think is really important
and that is just that the structure of
your R&D budget probably needs to look
different if you are using AI to do the
science okay so what do I mean by
that
so as you can see on the x-axis here
we're looking at the share of an R&D
budget that is being spent on computers
and other equipment and this is academic
science but I imagine it's uh pretty
true in Industry as well so on the left
hand side of this graph you see funding
for the NSF for different projects and
so for example for computer science you
can see that the share of R&D done in
computer science about 11% of that
historically has been you spent on like
computers and other equipment and the
other 80 some percent was people right
and I imagine that's probably true in
many of your R&D
operations and so what we did is we used
some e econom economic and econometric
techniques to extract from papers a good
sense of well for stuff in AI what was
the actual ratio of these things and you
get to it's more like a third capital
and 2/3
people so what does this mean
practically it means that in your
organizations if you say to some one of
your divisions we want you to be AI
first right we're going to AI first
innovation in this
area and then you give them the same
budget you've always given them they're
going to be building with models that
are way too small because they're not
going to have the budget to do the kind
of computing that you need to be at the
frontier of this
or they're going to say now okay well in
that case we're going to need to fire a
bunch of
people so to make room in our budget and
you might not want that either right you
might have cultivated that expertise
over time so I just I bring this up
because it feels like a very practical
like when you get into your next
budgeting cycle you need to be thinking
about this in terms of innovating in
AI okay all right so with all of that as
background I now want to come back to
what I promised at the beginning which
is let's think about
buying you adopt and adopting these
models so we've already just talked
about um build sorry excuse me building
and and um and then adopting so we've
just talked about building super
expensive right in many cases let's talk
about now just using something off the
shelf right maybe you can just use chat
GPT as it
is so you could you can do this I mean
online but much much more practically
you could do it with the apis so this is
geminis you can see you know kind of
amazing only about eight lines of code
to bring that in um there have also been
thoughts of like oh well maybe we'll
have a bunch of rappers so open AI had
this the GPT store my sense is that this
has not been much of a success right I
think people have not really used this
very much but both of these are a way to
say okay we're just going to take us off
the shelf and we're going to use it
ourselves what I think is crucial to
understand about this is that AI is not
like traditional it systems so what do I
mean by that well here we're going to
think about the tasks that need to be
done and the success in performing that
task and traditional it has this kind of
form right it does some things really
well basically at 100% accuracy and then
it falls off entirely so you'd say I
have a
calculator right or I have Excel Excel
certain functions that are built in
Excel Excel does really well and if you
say compose a poem for
me it fails entirely right whereas on a
system that is more like a modern AI
system
right it are some things that it does
really well and then performance
degrades but you absolutely can tell it
to write a poem or do math or do a bunch
of other
things okay so I want you to notice a
couple of things about this graph so one
is that there's some space I've left
some space here between the red line and
the blue line in the sense of it's
incredibly hard and Incredibly expensive
to get that last bit of performance on
an AI system to get it to be perfect
right so there's almost always going to
be some error
and so what this means in practice is if
you build this into your system you have
to treat it differently than it
traditionally okay so what like
concretely imagine you have some process
right you said okay we're going to do
the we originally we have humans doing
each of these steps and you said oh hey
we had this big development in databases
now we're going to put a a database in
the middle of that and that database is
going to sort of tell us maybe all of
the purchases that a customer has made
or something like that well we don't
worry that it's like failing to report
some of the transactions that have been
made right that's we we assume that's
basically perfect and so we build
processes assuming that we're getting
the 100%
accuracy but this red line because it's
lower means that you can't assume that
it's going to be perfect you have to
assume that there're going to be some
errors and you have to build processes
that are going to account for
that okay
so I want to bring up uh some examples
that show that you know this is really
what's happening and the way that people
build it into their things so uh Sundar
pinchai said today more than a quarter
of all new coded Google is generated by
Ai and then reviewed and accepted by
Engineers this helps our Engineers do
more and move
faster so the 25% number is really
interesting right it's a big number it
is interesting Google Engineers talk
about this and they're
like they're uh there like yes it does
fill that in but it's almost always like
I've done the hard part and it's just
filling in like the end of the words
like autocomplete right but I'm more
interested in this quotation because of
what he what he says at the the last the
second Clause there then reviewed and
accepted by our
Engineers right this is not saying we
fully automated that process and now
it's done it's saying we had to build in
a process to check it afterwards right
and that's that that problem of having
the the error not be fully
there so another uh another nice example
of this that shows this distinction
between traditional AI uh and what what
these modern systems can do is something
simple multiplying
numbers okay so you type in numbers into
a calculator right you never think it's
going to get multiplication wrong right
you never sort of sit there and question
that so what about chat
GPT
well so on the two axis of this is the
number of digits in your number right
and so if we take for example Le two
digits in each right of the this this uh
experiment that was run it got 100% of
those problems right
fantastic what if you take a 10 digit
number times a 10 digigit
number basically never gets it
right that's kind of weird right like we
think of if you understand how to do
multiplication with two digit numbers
you understand how to do multiplication
with 10 digit numbers and that is true
of your calculator and it's it's not
true of uh these AI models and that's
just because of the way they're trained
right they're trained with particular
examples it seemed tons and tons of
examples of small digit numbers being
multiplied by each other that helps it
bring it together it's seen very very
few examples of crazy long digit numbers
multiplied together and so it doesn't do
as
well okay now this is not an insoluable
problem like if you cared a ton about
multiplication you could give it tons
and tons of those problems and and solve
this right but it does highlight this
important thing which is that like once
you get away from your training data it
actually is not going to do as well and
that could be a problem so I'm this is a
nice another example of this uh so Air
Canada this is just earlier this year
Air Canada must pay damages after
chatbot lies to a grieving passenger
about a discount so this is someone who
call who who wrote in and said hey I've
just had a death in the family I need to
book some flights I understand you have
this discounted rate and the chatbot
said oh yes we do just go ahead and book
a normal ticket anytime in the next 60
days you can go and reclaim your
money except that's not true that's not
how that works you have to do it ahead
of time or you don't get your money
back and so uh Air Canada is defend so
they this person sued Air Canada and Air
Canada said no no no no uh we shouldn't
be liable for the chatbots faulty
outputs seems a little little strange
and in fact the the uh person who was
helping adjudicate this said in effect
air candidate was suggesting that the
chapot is a separate legal entity that's
responsible for its own
actions you may not be surprised to know
this did not this argument did not fly
at all right this this air candidate was
found they did have to to make
recompense to the person but this is an
interesting example right like I'm sure
that they showed it a bunch of examples
of dealing with customers but there was
still this like 10 digit by 10 digit
number problem right where this
particular thing hadn't come up it gave
an answer that seemed very fluid like oh
yeah yes no problem 60 days go ahead
like this sounds like something somebody
might have as a policy it just wasn't
their
policy okay all right so um I I do want
to highlight here just that um we think
this is important enough in my lab we've
actually built uh something called the
AI risk
repository um so you can find this at
air risk. mit.edu
and because we realized that actually
there just wasn't a good place where you
could get a comprehensive s set of risks
and so what we did is create this living
database of now more than 700 risks that
exist from this um Gathering from all of
the people who kind of talking about
this and so and what we found is that
these previous Frameworks were really
only covering a small subset of the
risks that were coming up from AI in
this
okay
so what I told you right was that
building from scratch can be pretty
expensive can be worth it if the value
that you can unlock is big enough right
for the
supermarket being able to do that on the
things that went bad super super
valuable right protein folding super
super valuable other things maybe not
worth it you could take an off-the-shelf
model much much cheaper fantastic but if
it's not exactly on the thing you care
about it could be pretty uncertain right
you could be like hey I tested on some
two-digit numbers that seemed to do very
well not realizing that your customers
were going to ask at 10 digigit problems
and that was going to be
issue okay so the last thing we can
think about here is customizing these
models so we're going to take one of
these models off the shelf that it's
learned a bunch of stuff ahead of time
and now we say but here are the kind of
things that we deal with more more right
here's some of our own data this will
help guide it to be able to do well on
our particular
problems and this can be name called in
a bunch of different ways so fine-tuning
is the version where you sort of take
the model and you actually train it with
some additional data prompt engineering
just says okay like it might normally
give a certain kind of response but if
you give it a prompt you can push it
down in a particular direction and
prompt tuning is actually sort of doing
this more interactively in a way that
does it so for example like the way that
chat gbt treats you all very nicely when
it interacts right that comes from this
kind of uh promp tuning that's
done so the reason this can be important
is the mismatch and so again this was a
case study that we did so this was
somebody who was doing a computer vision
model and the off-the-shelf model was
trained with imag net this very famous
data set that comes from Stanford
University from F Le's lab and what they
were doing was oil drilling in fact
particularly they what they were doing
was the parts for oil drilling and so
you can sort of see here they like this
is a part of the well and you have these
these parts these big metal parts that
are going and when they break what
happens is somebody at the well takes a
picture and sends it to the company and
says send me one of these overnight
because I need to get the well back up
and going tomorrow
now the problem is if you put that like
you know round piece with a you know
covered in mud and broken right and you
put that into the such a model is likely
to come back and be like puddle right as
your answer and that's not super helpful
right because it's actually some
specific you know part
r65 that is in in the database somewhere
but of course image net doesn't have
your parts in that database so you have
to do this kind of customization and so
the problem is that these custom
sometimes these custom labels just don't
exist ahead of
time okay so that process that you need
to do is very common and it comes with
some cost and so we wrote an article for
Brookings recently talking about we call
this the last mile problem in AI it's
very evocative of of course you know
what we have in telecommunications it's
very cheap to get a phone line to within
a mile of your house it's very expensive
to get it that last mile into your house
it's relatively cheap for you to get an
API that allows you to use chat GPT to
things close to what you want to to do
but it can also be pretty expensive to
do that last step and to give you some
sense of the cost of this so we did some
analysis on computer vision and we said
okay well people have been throwing
around some really big numbers about
automation with computer vision how
bigger does that uh different how big a
difference do you get if you take into
account these last mile
costs well you go from about 35% of jobs
having a vision task that you would want
to automate with it down to about 8% of
jobs right so these last mile things can
be expensive so I bring this up just to
say like we talked about the cost of
training and we said oh well adopting a
foundation model helps us do that but it
doesn't fully account for that it only
accounts for part of it right and with
that last bit that you do if you only
have to train it a little bit that that
can be a good deal but if you have to
train it a lot as you have to do in some
of these cases then it could actually be
pretty expensive again okay all right um
I think I'm going to just because I'm
getting close on time here I'm just
going to skip over the details of this
but just to say all of these costs that
I've been talking about with you today
are about overall like how the are the
costs of these things but those costs
are falling and they're falling because
of Hardware Improvement so as PE as
Nvidia for example builds better gpus
right that means that to do one
operation might cost you half as much as
it cost you before that obviously saves
you a bunch of money there's also
algorithmic progress we just think of
clever ways to design these systems and
so you may have heard of Transformers
right Transformers are not fundamentally
doing something that a previous version
of an AI couldn't do but it does it more
efficiently and that allows you to get a
big benefit okay and so both of these
things uh can can come in and make a big
difference and I'll skip through that
okay so let me just conclude
then so I started us out by giving you
these these numbers which I think were
the first ones to produce which says
actually how much is a AI being used in
Innovation and you see that in some
areas like computer science 1% of the
papers that are being published are
using AI actually in that paper and
these in particularly these Foundation
models that but I showed you that deep
learning success depends on the scale of
these models and what you're able to do
and that means that Cutting Edge models
are very big and getting very expensive
quickly but you can take these
Foundation models instead of building
your own you can take these Foundation
models and you can do off the shelf work
that's great but the problem is it can
do pretty poorly outside of its training
regime and our tuitions about when it
will do poorly may not be good right
because we might say oh it looks like
it's doing two-digit multiplication
right I assume it will get
multiplication right in general and
that's not necessarily the
case and you can adopt these models and
adapt them to for what you want to do
the problem is that can carry a bunch of
Last Mile
costs and then finally I said that you
know all of these things it is a moving
picture these costs are falling both
because of hardware and algorithmic
improvements and so a really key thing
for to think about this is not to say
when you do your analysis and say do I
want to use this AI in this particular
area of science don't say like yes no if
you say no I don't want to use it
because maybe the cost is not right then
do a second calculation that says okay
at what time would this actually become
attractive right because in some cases
that might only be a few years away and
you could already start taking steps for
example to gather your data sets or
stuff like that to get ready for when it
will be ready and with that I'll stop
thank you
thank you Neil it's fascinating to talk
you got a lot of questions here I'm just
going to tell the audience we're coming
up on time I know there's a network
reception next door so I know we're not
going to get through all these questions
we'll take one or two of them but if you
do have questions for new please stay
afterwards and feel free to ask him
those questions too okay so I think um
one of the questions I've heard a lot
certainly from a lot of different
organizations that we deal with is do
you have any advice for corporations to
develop AI literacy and to discern the
organizational Readiness and efficacy of
models so I mean it's a it's a super
hard problem right um and it's it's a
hard problem because it's like at some
level many of these problems have sort
of traditional data science problems and
then you have particular AI problems
right and so I imagine you you probably
heard other speakers talk about this but
it's you know if your data is really
poor right it will go really badly if
your processes don't documented very
well it can go really badly so let me
let me be sort of concrete about this I
I mentioned that example of the
supermarket right turns out that even
before they got to the level where they
got the one-third benefit and they were
like okay fantastic the first
predictions that they made were terrible
and in an earlier version of the model
you say well why was it terrible well it
was terrible because almost nothing
about those changes that were made in
the models was captured so I mentioned
that the old system right you said it
predicted the number of bananas and then
some manager put in there and was like
oh no it's a little bit higher today
those extra changes never got put back
in the system so what that meant was
that in practice like you might have a s
the system might say oh we sold this
many right so so say say take it as an
example maybe the manager decreased the
amount that was going be ordered right
and they sold all of those the system
would still think you had five more on
the shelf and they just didn't sell so
we would think like oh that's that was
the level of demand but maybe you could
have sold more that just they ordered
the wrong amount right or you had stores
where they just not recorded when the
store was closed for a holiday or closed
for repairs and so I was like oh every
you know two one Tuesday every three
years there no sales at all and it was
thinking that that was like the right
prediction not that there was actually
thing so this that that sort of like
messiness of your data can be a problem
and so that's hugely important for AI
Readiness if you have bad data on for
some particular area you you need to be
thinking about it but then there's a
second thing about like okay well how do
you actually know that your people have
the right level thing and I don't I
don't think I have a great answer for
that other than to say you know in the
same way that you think about expertise
in other areas you know think about
trying to have build some teams maybe
bring in some external people right
we've definitely seen a bunch of cases
where if people didn't think they were
ready they hired a Consulting team that
Consulting team either did it and then
hinded it off or sometimes even like
left some of their people as a way to
build some of that
Readiness thanks Neil let's ask one more
question this last question of the day
do you uh excuse me what do you think
the graph on different fields using AI
for Innovation is going to look like in
10 years or 10 years from now
ah
so so it'll be a lot higher I think it's
going to converge I don't think we
should assume that just like the fields
that started early are the ones that are
going to end up higher right so um you
know if for example in medicine I think
there are a lot of there's a lot of
potential in medicine for uh these these
systems to be very very impactful but I
think it's you know many of the people
innovating in that space do not come in
with a programming background or data
science background and so I think that
might be an area that will take longer
to get there but I would expect it to be
very high as we get there I also think
we're going to see some new some new
areas right so for example places in
like Material Science I think this could
be very very important for a lot of that
kind of stuff and so those will go up at
time over time but I think broadly what
we're going to see is VE very large
option it is I will maybe just leave
this as a bit of a a hint for some
future meeting but it is interesting
some of the work that we've been doing
in my lab does suggest that actually we
should not expect it to be useful
everywhere that in some areas of science
we see it being useful in some areas not
and we're right now trying to pull apart
exactly why that is in particular areas
to be able to give some insights in it
but I do think it's going to be the case
and in some places actually as AI is not
as good as other algorithms that people
have developed for these
things thank you so much NE
really great talk