Hello and welcome to Today I Learned
Climate brought to you by the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
I'm L Hessie
Fischer. Where are you listening to this
episode from today? Maybe you're riding
the bus on your morning commute or
taking a leisurely stroll through the
park. But chances are if you look around
you, you'll see four walls, maybe a door
or two, some windows because you're in a
building. And we Americans, we spend
close to 90% of our time indoors in the
offices, stores, and factories where we
work, the gyms, and shops and theaters,
and the homes where we relax at the end
of the day. But how often do we really
notice these spaces and how they're
built and why they're built that way?
The built environment has been the
shelter that humans needed throughout
history. Whether it was cavelike
structures, indigenous buildings that
survive until today, creating
comfortable spaces that are also
shelters from the environment. That's
Terra Craka. I am associate professor at
Georgia Tech and director of the high
performance building lab and program at
the school of architecture in the
college of design. He also got his PhD
here at MIT where he worked in the MIT
sustainable design lab. And as professor
Raka says the first thing to know about
a building is that it's shelter. It
shields us from the rain and the wind
and the cold. And the way we build has
always reflected that. Climate
resiliency has been at the forefront of
architectural practices since we have
started building as humanity using the
materials from the environment we're in
and then shaping our architecture to be
responsive to the environment. Think for
example of the adobe houses of desert
regions like in the American Southwest.
The native Pueblo people built their
homes out of the clay in the area and
those clay walls absorbed the hot desert
heat, keeping their inhabitants cool
during the day and warm at
night. And as technology developed, we
found that we could do more than just
shield ourselves from the weather. We
could actually engineer our buildings so
that we're perfectly comfortable all
throughout the day and all throughout
the year. It is really a beautiful
experience if you get a breeze on a
beach. We want to strive for these kind
of experiences in our buildings and
therefore we've invented HVAC. So,
heating, ventilation, and air
conditioning. Look around for me again.
Can you see a fan spinning away or hear
a hum of an air conditioner or a rumble
of a furnace? Our modern buildings work
very hard to keep our indoor weather
precisely the way we want it.
And that is an energy hog. The energy
you need to cool and heat a building is
significant.
A modern building is far more than just
a shelter. It's more complex and it's
busier. We can think of these buildings
as machines. Machines that turn energy
into comfort. So where we're going to
get that energy becomes very important.
Of course, historically speaking, we've
relied on fossil fuels. that is coal,
oil, and gas. Like, does your home have
gas heat? If so, your utility is pumping
natural gas through pipelines in your
neighborhood and into your house. Your
furnace burns that gas, creating the
heat that keeps you snug on a cold
winter night. Unfortunately, like all
fossil fuels, it also creates carbon
dioxide, part of the ever thickening
blanket of carbon pollution that is
heating our planet. Now, think of all of
the furnaces in all of the buildings in
the entire world and all of the coal and
gas power plants supplying those
buildings with electricity.
Buildings account for 40% of carbon
emissions globally. The amount of energy
that we use to sustain our lives in
buildings is substantial.
Which brings us to yet another way to
look at modern buildings as giant pumps
for carbon. Working overtime and all
their many roundabout ways to take
fossil carbon out of the ground and pipe
it into the air. Buildings contribute
more to that carbon blanket around our
planet than heavy industry does. More
than growing the world's food, more even
than cars and trucks and airplanes.
So, is it possible to keep using our
buildings as the miraculous comfort
machines that they are, but to stop
using them as carbon
pumps? Well, there are buildings around
the world that are already leading the
way. For example, have you ever seen a
plaque on the side of a building that
proclaims that it's lead gold or lead
platinum? That's a certification which
the US Green Building Council has been
giving to energy efficient buildings
since the 1990s.
LEAD started at a time where this kind
of benchmarking was not mainstream and
the focus was not on the climate message
or the sustainability message. It was
all about the money that you will be
saving and the prestige of having the
Cadillac of buildings. Yeah. The great
news about lowcarbon buildings is that
owning one can be a big moneysaver. One
of the biggest misconceptions that
people have about sustainable and energy
efficient buildings is that they are
very expensive. Buildings that are
sustainable are typically much cheaper
than regular buildings because you know
what? You are not going to be using
energy in HVAC and heating and cooling.
If there's anything that you should be
knowing about sustainable buildings is
that there is an upfront cost that is
going to pay for itself over 5 to 10
years. So how would we create an
energyefficient money-saving building
with the fancy plaque? Well, to answer
that question, we have to start before
we even dig the foundation. We have to
start with the blueprints themselves.
If we're starting to design a new
building, we have to get the geometry
right first. The relationship to the
sun, the prevailing winds, the
landscaping, the correct orientation to
maximize solar energy and access to
light. Then we have to be focusing on
passive systems. Passive systems are
systems that do not use energy that
comes from fuel. So, for example,
glazing that allows for the sun to warm
up the space and the shading system that
blocks it in the summer. Like the
ancient Pueblo's adobe structures, our
new lowcarbon building is laid out to
take maximum advantage of nature itself.
If you're in a climate where you really
need to heat and retain the heat in,
there's no way around building highly
insulated buildings. And so the choice
of the exterior materials whether it's
going to be uh brick, concrete, fully
glazed facade etc. really matters not
just for the energy efficiency but also
for how comfortable the environment
would be within the interior spaces. Our
choice of materials matters for another
reason too. If you can see a steel beam
where you're sitting or a brick wall, if
you're in a building with a concrete
foundation or aluminum siding, these are
energyhungry materials and the building
industry uses a lot of them. In fact,
there are estimates that about 25% of
the carbon pollution from buildings
comes just from manufacturing and
construction.
Today, thanks to top-of-the-line
buildings like the ones that we're
imagining, there is a growing market for
cleaner materials. Whether that's local
earth and stone or engineered wood or
ingenious new ways of making lowcarbon
concrete and
steel, we also have excellent tools to
deal with the other 75% of our
building's carbon. This is the energy
that we use on a day-to-day basis. All
of the energy that is used in heating,
uh, cooling, lighting, equipment,
appliances, etc., all of these use up
energy. Yeah. Like remember that gas
burning furnace that we talked about?
The same work can be done by an electric
heat pump and which is kind of like a
reverse air conditioner. They are so
much more efficient than furnaces that
they typically cut our carbon pollution
by more than half while still keeping
our buildings nice and toasty. And if we
get that electricity from low polluting
sources like solar, wind, nuclear, and
others, we could heat our building with
almost no impact on the climate at all.
Our buildings might even make that clean
energy themselves, like through rooftop
solar
panels. Because if we get it right, we
can build buildings that rely on their
own energy and don't need anything from
the grid. There are such things as zero
energy buildings that are so energy
efficient that with just solar you can
get the energy to
zero. The highest performing buildings
today have designations like lead
platinum or a living building or passive
house and they are already delivering
modern comfort without the pollution.
The challenge of course is getting every
building to that level and it's a
substantial challenge. If we are to
build all of our new construction
to exceptional standards that would have
a clear impact.
However, more than 50% of the built
environment in the United States was
built before the year 1980. And
therefore we really have to be
considering how to retrofit existing
buildings because the opportunity to
build new buildings in urban settings is
actually very limited.
Okay. So I live in a home built around
1905 and gradually over the years my
family has worked to make this house
operate like the buildings that we've
been talking about. And so we followed
the textbook of what to do when
retrofitting an old building. So, we
added insulation to the outside walls
and flooring and replaced some leaky
windows. We also did some pretty cheap
but effective fixes called
weatherization. Weatherization in the
context of limited resources become
really impactful. So, weatherization
would be, for example, using weather
stripping around the window frame. This
is important because you're no longer
losing energy to the environment. And
with that all done, an old building like
ours can be ready for the newest, most
energyefficient electrical appliances
like heat pumps and electric water
heaters, which is what we have. And over
time, we have found that our energy
bills are much lower and our house is
much more comfortable. Like I don't wake
up on winter mornings clinging to my
blankets anymore.
And yes, because we are nerds and we
track this kind of stuff, we've also
calculated that our home emits much less
pollution than it did before. Now, I
want to be clear, this took us a few
years and we invested money into it and
we were
motivated. But how do you motivate the
owners of the millions upon millions of
buildings that exist out there today or
that are about to be built? Because even
though high performing buildings are
possible and cost-effective and are
being built today, most buildings are
not being built to that standard. It has
become more mainstream. Yes. But
unfortunately mainly for those who are
building in an urban environment as well
as larger scale buildings. those who are
building for example single family homes
in rural settings or uh suburban
settings it's not there yet even though
it constitutes a significant portion of
the built environment. Yeah. Most
buildings are built to code meaning that
they meet the minimum energy standards
that the local law requires. They're not
aiming to be high-erforming buildings.
And it's worth asking, how can more
buildings be built
better? The most climate smart buildings
are also the most comfortable and the
cheapest to heat and cool in the long
run. The materials and the knowhow
exist. And with each new developer who
makes the choice to build a
high-erforming building, the markets
shift a little, opening up the labor and
the materials and the knowledge and the
expectations that buildings are built
this way. We know now about the built
environment more than we've ever known
in any point of history. We have these
sensors that are allowing us to measure
at the circuit level of a refrigerator
at the time span of a second to allow us
to make realtime decisions for energy
efficiency. All we need to do is
activate it like tap into it, have it as
a mindset. And that is basically my
advice. If there's going to be decisions
on building new or upgrading buildings,
we can't really build the same way we've
built 20 years ago, we have to be
thinking about building more sustainably
and keeping carbon emissions as low as
[Music]
possible. That's our episode for today,
but there is plenty more TI climate at
tilclimate.mmit.edu. And as always, we'd
love to hear who you are and why you
listen to the show and what questions
you have about climate change and
climate solutions. Please email us at
tilclimate
atmit.edu or leave us a voicemail at
617-2533566. TI climate is a climate
change podcast at the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology. Aaron Kroll is
our writer and executive producer. David
Lashansky is our audio producer.
Michelle Harris is our fact checker.
Grace Sawin is our student production
assistant. The music is by Blue Dot
Sessions. And I'm your host and senior
editor, L Hessie Fischer. A big thanks
to Professor TK Rocka for speaking with
us. And to you, our listeners. Keep up
the climate curiosity.
[Music]