So to address both of these problems um
we'll be now diving into uh the
technologies and how um by using these
technologies we can generate data and um
that data can help us um answer those
questions.
And so um the first uh technology that
we'll be talking about is um a
technology called single cell RNA
sequencing. uh this emerged in the last
uh decade or so and has really
revolutionized our ability um to
understand cell biology um and um
understand disease.
The second problem is that we know how a
few of these genes worked like for
example um we learned that PDGFRA is
important for cell division. So if you
delete this gene then the padypipes
won't proliferate anymore. um and adipo
Q um is very important for the adiposite
population and so maybe if we delete
this gene then we'll see um less less uh
productive signaling between adapose
tissue and other tissues. Um but the
question is um can we learn for all the
remaining genes uh out of the 20,000 or
so genes in our genome what they too are
doing? Um and if we had a uh technology
that would allow us to uh delete these
other genes and then see what the impact
is on the cells um then that would
really help us uh towards this goal. And
so in parts B and C we'll be talking
about technologies that um really
address this first challenge of
measuring uh every gene in every cell to
understand um which genes are switched
on or off uh in which cells. uh and
secondly uh perturbing these genes or
deleting these genes to see what happens
to the cells um when um um those genes
are deleted. So talking about the first
technology which we used to measure gene
expression in cells uh this is a
technology called uh single cell RNA
sequencing. Um it's really
revolutionized our uh ability to do uh
cell biology and to understand um the
cellular states that uh drive disease.
And so um to simply put um what happens
with single cell RNA sequencing is that
um you start with a population of cells
of interest um and from these you can
measure in every single cell the uh
activity level of every single gene. Um
and so uh the output um that you get is
this kind of matrix uh where uh every
row is a different gene uh and every
column is a different cell. Um so you
would have maybe 20,000 genes for every
gene in the genome. Um and however many
cells uh you profile um in that
experiment. So for one of the data sets
uh in the uh first crunch, this is
roughly 150,000.
Um and then uh each value tells us um
how many um uh RNA molecules or in other
words how active every gene is in each
of these different cells.
And so um going back to uh some of the
cell populations and uh programs that
we're interested in um if this is the
the the pool of cells that we perform
single cell RNA seek on what we might
see when we look at the resulting matrix
is um that the genes PDGFRA and thigh 1
are uh switched on in these two first
cells and so probably then these two
first cells are priiposytes.
And we might also see that the genes
adipo Q and FAB P4 are switched on in
these uh four subsequent cells. Um and
so we might conclude from that that
these cells 3 to six are uh classic
adiposytes.
And finally we might see that these two
lipogenic markers S surbp and fast n are
specifically switched on in a subset of
the adiposytes. um in the last two cells
five and six. And so we might say that
these are particularly uh lipogenic uh
cells among the larger adiposite
population. And so uh as I mentioned we
can profile hundreds of thousands of
cells um with this technology. And
actually uh this is very exciting
because uh the last um 15 years or so um
since the very first uh single cell RNA
seek technology um was published has
seen enormous growth and so we went from
uh a case where uh in 2009 four cells in
uh a four- stage uh blastoir were
sequenced. So in the matrix on the
previous page there were just uh four
columns um to uh today uh this is the
logarithmic scale and showing the number
of cells uh to the case where uh today
or at least eight years ago um we in
2017 we now have technologies that allow
us to profile uh 1 million cells.
And so now um I'll switch gears a little
bit and tell you about um how this
single cell RNA seek um experiment
actually works. Um this isn't uh
information that you'll directly need to
to um um do the challenges but it's very
helpful uh I think for you to
understand.
And so what we start from is a
population of cells. So this can either
be uh cells that are found in a piece of
tissue or cells that we've already grown
uh in a dish in the lab.
Um and cells tend to interact and to
communicate. And so the first step is to
actually um go from this population to a
dissociated um version of this
population where um every cell uh is no
longer kind of attached to other cells.
Um and um we then uh take these cells
and isolate them one by one and for each
of them we can then count um how many of
each uh genes uh corresponding RNA
molecules are found uh in that
particular cell.
So it's this workflow again where we
start from a a kind of population of
cells um dissociate them and then one by
one um are able to measure the RNA
molecules inside each of those therefore
telling us about the genes which are
active there uh and the gene expression
programs in particular which are
expressed
um and so uh I'll tell you a little bit
more now about this isolation step and
how that works.
So um basically what happens is we have
this micrfluidic system and uh cells are
flown in through here uh into this
chamber uh and then they become
encapsulated in individual um water
droplets and what you can see is that um
in each of these water droplets uh along
with the cell uh you also have a uh
colored bead that's encapsulated with
it. Um, and this colored bead um will
act as a barcode so that um um we'll be
able to tell for all of the RNA
molecules inside every cell uh which
barcode it had. So for example, this
cell three here has uh these four RNA
molecules which are shown in red uh
because this cell was encapsulated uh
with the red bead and so that um uh bead
allowed us to barcode these individual
uh RNA molecules.
Okay, so that's this uh method for
isolating cells. And the reason that we
want to isolate the cells is so that we
can individually uh barcode all of the
RNA transcripts that come from a
particular cell with that barcode.
And now we can go back to our overall uh
workflow where we've um done the
dissociation, the isolation, um the
labeling of the RNA molecules. And what
actually happens now is um the the
reverse of what typically uh happens uh
in the central dogma in biology which is
uh where DNA uh is transcribed and
produces RNA. So here we actually do the
reverse process a process called reverse
transcription where we go from the RNA
and for each RNA molecule we uh convert
it um to uh the corresponding DNA
molecule. Uh and we do this for two
reasons. Um firstly mainly we do this
because um DNA is very stable and RNA is
not. Um and secondly this then allows us
to actually amplify these molecules uh
of DNA. Um and so we have a much larger
pool of uh DNA molecules uh that kind of
accurately represent the uh proportions
of RNA molecules um that we originally
detected.
And once we have um these uh DNA
molecules, we can then do sequencing,
which is basically saying for every
single one of these DNA sequences um
going through and seeing um which of the
four letters uh in the genetic code, A,
C, T, and G are at that position uh in
each DNA sequence.
And so why is that helpful? What do we
then do with this kind of sequencing
library? Well, um we now have uh the
human genome project. This was completed
in 2003 and this was a really uh amazing
effort um that uh produced the sequence
of every gene in the human body. And so
um now we have these sequences uh of DNA
that correspond um to scrap that bit. Um
and so now we have uh these sequences of
DNA. What we can do is we can actually
go back to the um human genome and find
out which uh gene each of these
sequences comes from.
And so once we've done that um we can
now count um within this sequencing
library how many sequences we see
corresponding to each of these genes uh
in the human genome. Um and yes, so this
is the expression matrix or the output
of the single cell RNA seek uh
experiment that we've uh seen already um
and is kind of the main data structure
um that you'll be working with through
these crunches.
So um just a couple more uh things to be
aware of with these matrices. Um so
first of all just to reiterate you know
every row is a different gene and every
column is a different cell um and then
the values represent the activity level
of that gene in that cell. And so uh but
one issue with these matrices um with
the output of the single cell RNA seek
experiments um is that they tend to be
quite sparse uh meaning that there are
many entries here where the value is
actually uh zero and um this is a bit
complicated because um in those cases we
can't actually distinguish um between
two interpretations one being uh
biological but um in reality
uh this gene is actually zero in the
cell. Uh and one being just technical
that that gene was uh not detected um at
high enough abundance um to be captured
uh in the experiment.
And so uh basically uh the kind of
pre-processing uh in this bionformatics
pipeline involves uh dealing with this
issue.
And so uh this is typically how we deal
with that. um we want to remove uh cells
that have too many zeros and therefore
seem low quality. And so um what you see
here on the x-axis is uh the cell
basically ordered by this ranking of um
how many uh genes have a value of zero
in that cell. This is uh what we
typically call the number of detected
genes.
um and on the uh y-axis so on the x axis
is this rank of the cells and on the y-
axis is uh the number of genes that were
detected. So the number of nonzero genes
um and so what we tend to do is to uh
remove uh this lower tail uh of cells
that have uh too few genes detected um
and so are probably not very helpful for
uh downstream analysis.
Um and this is another issue now but we
actually also tend to remove the cells
which are at the top end um of this
because uh often these have a
suspiciously uh high number of genes
detected in the cell. Um and what that
suggests is that uh the isolation step
that we spoke about previously
is actually not fully working. Um, and
maybe rather than an individual cell
being in one of those water droplets, we
actually have uh two or multiple cells
in there. Um, so we remove these two
ends uh and we're left with um these
high quality cells uh in the middle here
for our analysis.
Okay. So um this is how we deal with um
the lowquality cells uh in the data.
And then there is also a second issue
that we have to deal with which is that
the total number of uh RNAs that we
count in individual cells uh might be
different from cell to cell. So uh in
other words some cells might have um
higher overall uh gene expression but
this is actually just uh because of
technical reasons. Um and so we'd like
to uh normalize for that. Um and so what
we do is we uh scale the gene expression
per cell such that um it sums to a
100,000 which is roughly how many uh
molecules of RNA we might expect a given
cell to have and then um we uh add a
pseudo count of one uh and then log
transform the data um so that our uh
distribution is uh Gaussian um and this
makes things much easier for uh
downstream analysis.
And then finally uh in this third step
we now have normalized cells only
highquality cells. We can project these
cells onto a uh lower dimensionality
embedding. And so this is uh one way um
using for example UMAP or TSN um that we
typically uh visualize um the single
cell RNA seek uh data set and the kind
of global diversity um uh of cells that
we see there. And so going back um to um
our particular use case uh this is uh
one of the data sets that you'll be
working with um an example of this lower
dimensional um embedding of the cells.
Um and you can see here um that we've
marked uh which of the cells are um
paddypoytes uh and which of the cells
are adiposytes. Um and again we've done
this because now that we have the single
cell RNA seek data we can actually go
and see which genes are expressed in
which cells and what we find is that the
classical uh gene markers of the
priiposytes as well as other genes in
the priiposite program are expressed in
these cells while the classical markers
of the uh adiposite population um adipoq
and fab
um as well as other adiposite um uh
markers. is uh expressed in this pink
population.