Hi everyone. Good morning. I am uh
Philip Kolaris. I'm the COO and CFO of
Fab Zero. Uh we are using applied AI to
solve physical logistics problems
specifically to move boxes from point A
to point B. This is our team David MB
former MIT alum uh 2014
and Vadim Takenov. He's the CTO. He's
based out of Italy.
What is the problem here? So the problem
is nobody wants to be carrying 10 10
kilo boxes for eight hours a day for
five days a week and it's creating a
massive labor shortage on the market.
One of our customers has a statistics
that says that 400%
is labor turnover for them. So they're
constantly hiring people uh throughout
the whole year. We think that we
estimate that there's about a million
warehouses globally and 80% have no
automation whatsoever.
This this this is a market that is prime
for automation and robotics. The problem
is it's it's very hard because of the
random randomization of the boxes.
Whenever you open a container, you're
either going to get a very well stacked
and 99% density in a container or you're
gonna get something like this picture
here. It's completely not efficient
boxes on the floor. So the the the the
AI needs to look at this. We need to use
integrate optics orchestration with the
robots to to to figure out what's the
most efficient way of picking these
boxes.
Now, why are we different? Well, we're
different because first of all, we are a
software company first. We are hardware
agnostic. We are very fluid. What we do
is we we use our software to enable the
hardware. We can redesign the
configuration of the hardware any way to
meet the customer's demands. So, if you
have a customer that has a thousand
warehouses, they're not going to
retrofit just for our solution. What
we're going to do is we're going to
design we're going to make changes to
our design to fit their needs and that's
that's going to enable a lot of scaling
very fast
because we have the software and we can
design multiple different solutions. We
can tackle many different problems on
the warehouse. We are right now looking
at unloading,
sorting and palletizing stacking boxes
up. This is a this is an installed
solution we have at our customer today.
With the software it and the vision that
we have, it enables other things such as
loading to a container, storing and uh
and also uh looking at integrity of the
containers for inventory management.
So you guys got to bear with me one
second because I'm not as technical
here. Uh so so the our tech stack is we
have the simulation our simo it's
realistic simulation to train the AI
model and test systems before
deployment. Percept handles segmentation
models and drives decision making to to
find the most efficient pick sequence.
Robboto creates ARM orchestration that
allows for hardware agnostic operations
and narrow manages the machine learning
and reinforcement training.
The left side is uh is at a customer's
side. The right side is the simulation.
The if you see we're we're very unique
on our design because we have two arms
and we are compared to the competition
with only one arm. This enables us to
pick boxes at a faster rate and also
coordinate the two arms to pick bigger
sized boxes. Now a human is picking on
average an hour 400 boxes. to make this
solution work, we need to be twice as
that and we're currently hitting two and
a half times.
We've uh we've engaged with um three
customers. Either we're work installing
systems right now, we have a working
system or we're talking through putting
a proof of concept in. Every customer
has its unique needs. We have a we have
the I think it's the third biggest
importer of goods. It's a it's this B2C
retailer. They uh they really needed a
solution that would unload from from the
containers, sort and stack the boxes for
storage. We developed a three module
system that does that. The second the
second uh customer is a big parcel ship
shipper and uh they they needed
something that would fit into their
brownfield, something would be installed
and they could scale it up. We're in the
moment we finished the designs. for
installing it at one of their test
sites. The third one is a is a big
online retailer that has needs for
multiple different things. Uh aircraft,
we we have a bid out for aircraft
unloading as well as loading and
unloading of of crates and sorting
boxes.
Uh and and finally, partnerships wise,
we're we're open to meet everybody. We
we'd love to meet you. Uh we have a
booth on the on the other room. Uh we're
looking at scale. We're we're a global
company. We need to be we know that
scale is is the way to go and we love to
get to know you guys.