hi everyone I'm Gaya Saras I'm a postto
here at the broad and I have the
pleasure of just introducing our speaker
for today's seminar
series um today the person that's going
to be presenting is Dr Gomez inclan she
is an early career researcher with a lot
of experience in culture editing and
differentiation of human stem cells her
career has focused on a lot of things
including modeling interactions to
dissect their pathology aiming to Aid in
their prevention or treatment and during
her doctorate over at the University of
Queensland she generated um brain and
liver cultures both Judd and 3D to study
for rare autosomal disease in Axia and
excuse me telling glacia uh currently in
her post-doctoral position at SM smbs
she's using ipscs to generate
hypothalamic brain organoid
models over the last few years um Dr
Gomez inlan has done a lot of work in
her doctoral research identified the
post- transational modification for the
Catalyst proteins that could alleviate
the inflammatory response in patients
with a taxia glacia um in addition to
all of this she uncovered differences in
the tox toxicity of beta amalo peptide
variants in the cortical brain organoids
and focused on unraveling the diversity
of physical and protein
biomarkers of Cellular cence in stem
cell derived mesenchimal stem cells um a
critical fate currently being
investigated by a lot of different
trials and for treating multiple
conditions um I know this is a rather
long introduction but I cannot speak
highly enough of um her work and at the
current time Dr Gomez inclan is
developing a Robos protocol for
hypothalamic organoid differentiation at
SM
sbms and her research is advaned
advancing frontiers of brain disease
modeling um overall in the last five
years Drome inclan has developed a
robust and diverse skill set in the area
of stem cells biology and
differentiation and she has pinpointed
and addressed a lot of critical
knowledge gaps across diverse research
settings um I think that is quite a bit
of an introduction and I have a pleasure
of presenting today's speaker so Dr
Gomez and Clen once you're ready we can
begin yeah thank you very much yeah so
thank you so much for having me here I I
am very grateful with everyone involved
in the organization and also with
Cynthia that I think she was a
contacting point for this talk to happen
so I work at in in Australia at the
University of Queensland right now here
it's like 5:00 a.m. in the morning so
bear with me if my language like goes to
mysterious places um I work at school of
H biomedical Sciences at the um um with
Stefan S he's the the leader of the
group and yeah I'm going to be
presenting you what I have been doing
this past year in my first postdoctoral
position with calian rhythms and
hypothalamic organ so I just want to
give you a little bit of a background of
who I am so and what I have done so
pretty much I was bornn and raised in
Mexico City so for if there is any other
people from Mexico I am ch completely
and I thought to share this beautiful
map of what Mexico City used to look
like when the aexs were around so it's a
map of the N plan um I did my bachelor
studies at theam University of national
autonom Mexico uh and I was very lucky
to do the basic fire medical research
program and I say I was very lucky
because this program allows us from the
very start of our Bachelors to be a
little bit handsome on in different
research um groups so I was involved in
some re Research In The Institute of
biomedical Sciences in The Institute of
cellular physiology the faculty of
medicine and I also did an internship in
the Stars Institute for medical research
in Kansas
City H after that that's when I came to
Australia ER there is this little
product called Vite if you haven't tried
it I would suggest you to have a look at
it it's Str very
interesting and here I started my PhD at
the Australian Institute for
bioengineering and
nanotechnology uh that's where I was
doing a cortical organoids but we also
did liver organoids and also to the
liever and cortical models and then I
just joined like a little bit over a
year ago in the school of biomedical
Sciences so with no further Ado I will
continue we talk of the actual science
so in the lab we focus on the
hypothalamus which is a very small area
of the brain it actually accounts for
around
0.5 four of the total volume of the
whole human brain however although it is
very small it is also very very diverse
so the hypothalamus can be divided into
three four different regions and then
they are further subdivided into nuclei
that are pretty much functional units
within the hypothalamus that are
involved in very important ER
physiological processes such as feing
Behavior thermal regulation body fluid
so this is would be more like blood
pressure and things like that and sleep
wake cycle ER puberty and fertility so
things related to reproduction also the
aggressive behavior and stress response
and the way that usually the
hypothalamus does all this work is
through the re release of neuropeptides
from the hypothalamus to the anterior L
of the pituitary gland and then other
hormones are released from this um gland
to other um organs where it exerts their
um their effects so just to give you an
example here
of one of the pathways for instance with
a cortisol release the um corticotropin
releasing hormones from the hypothalamus
would be released to the anterior L of
the P gland and then it will induce the
cleavage of the pro opium opio
melanocortin hormone that will result in
the generation of this peptide that is
called adrenal
adrenocorticotropic hormone those are a
mouthful and then they go to the adrenal
gland and then that's that's where the
cortisol gets released so I am telling
you uh about this very complex little
area of the brain that mediates many
physiological processes and anyways the
the the difficulties or the complexity
doesn't stop there because these
processes don't happen constantly even
during in a day but instead they are
regulated within a day so just to give
you staying with the example of the
cortisol what we know that is that in
plasma the cortisol will vary right and
we usually have a peak right before in
humans when right before we wake up then
if we go and check for act in plasma as
well you would notice that there is like
a mild increase as well usually a little
bit before the cortisol release and then
what we know about the CR in cereal
spinal fluid in humans is that there is
also small Pig a little bit before the
other two happen however as in my
cartoon I think you cannot see here the
hypothalamus right so this is not a
mistake um um we can actually not access
this area of the brain that easily and
especially in humans like it's not like
we can just like um assess
systematically this stuff so we have
used different models like for instance
here in in rat that we know that the CR
transcript in the paraventricular
nucleus where it is what where it is
actually produced and then it later on
released from um in rats it actually
also varies within the day so these
modulations are very important for our
physiology and um this kind of
of rhythms are called circadian rhythms
and they just called that because in
Latin circadium means about a day so
that means that these are processes that
happen every 24 hours sort of De and the
basic molecular mechanism that regulates
the Cadian rhythms and won a Nobel priz
in 2017 but it is pretty much in a very
few words is a feedback loop negative
feedback loop of transcription
factors so in 2004 there was this
beautiful experiment very elegant where
they fused one of these transcript the
genes of the transcription factor to
Lucifer
is in order to assess in EX in explans
of M how does a Cadian Rhythm looks
like so turns out that whenever these
tissues are outside of the body of the
system of the
physiological environment in these
animals you can see that different
tissues will react differently um so
some of them will keep the Cadian Rhythm
but maybe the amplitude will change
maybe something will happen some other
tissues will almost lose the these waves
um and so maybe some others will still
have waves but they are not exactly at
the same time time as others so this is
just telling us like the the Machinery
of The sadian rhythms and the actual
waves of of the circadian rhythms pretty
much happen everywhere in our body um
however they need to be synchronized all
of them so that all the physiological
processes happen as they are meant
to so how this happens is via the side
fers and I think that's pretty much
German and I have no clue German so
apologies if I am not saying this in the
correct way but they are pretty much
exogenous signals that will indicate
what time of the day it is so there are
cues like light eating and exercise and
this um cues the signals will reach the
PAC makers in the body that is pretty
much the cutting Machinery that will
then inform the rest of the body um to
be synchronized at the same pace
so I just want to stress out this is a
very complex system and we are very
interested in observing a little bit
closer to the hypothalamus and how these
Dynamics with the
neuropeptides
happen both in the hypothalamus and you
already know we are working with organal
how do you pipe it in the
time so if we think about the sight
givers that I was telling you about
light food and exercise well light is
definitely not a goal because we don't
have the Machinery that it requires to
detect light and food could be however
um just like getting rid of the food of
the media or not feeding the organ could
be a little bit problematic in the sense
like it is also supporting all these um
neuronal Network so we are
not keen to do that and exercise is
definitely an
however like second order side givers or
a little bit of the response of of the
first order side givers are hormones or
metabolites and changes in body core
temperature and hormones are already
something that we can actually pipe it
in things like melatonin cortisol and
Insulin um particularly cortisol is
interesting um probably you know this
back in the ' 90s and early 2000s there
are heaps of experiments and heaps of
reports using theosone that is a es that
is very fairly similar to cortisol
people have been using it in many
different initro settings for
synchronizing Cadian rhythms and in
terms of metabolites like glucose and
lipids this this reminded me to the
usage of maybe FBS um that is like also
very commonly used for cardan synchron
ization in initro
settings and so those two could be core
core temperature is not not a good one
just because the fact of the our
incubators in the lab they are usually
not exactly that good at maintaining the
temperature when it comes to very little
changes and that's what we would be
facing so probably nothing more than
0.5 changes of in Celsius so that that
is also something that we wouldn't be
that Keen to to
try so having kind of an idea of how we
would like to do that we just want to
keep in mind that
27% of the coding cycle in at least one
in humans that's kind of the last
report and in the hypothalamic
neuropeptides will probably be cycling
and that's exactly what we want to focus
on so having that in mind I just just
want you to to come back to think with
me about the model that we need to use
for trying to make these studies and so
you already know we are focused on human
that's what we want to study and that's
where the power of the stem cells come
where you actually have these Pur potent
stem cells that you can differentiate
into different into different models
sorry something that is very important
is that theels should must have the
calian machinery uh I have told you that
most of the cells have it but not
exactly all of them so for instance a p
poent CS don't have all of these
expressed so when you do the
differentiation you just need to make
sure that you have them in your um in
your differentiated
cultures now we want to have a system
that is isolated right and so you have
seen like it's so robust system systems
and very complicated systems and the
hypothalamus at the end of the day works
like an integration Hub of a lot of
different signals and then the output is
also so diverse in terms of all the
physiological aspects that it can
regulate so you would have a lot of
confounding confounding variables when
you are dealing in animal models which
of course you can desect and take
advantage even to to some degree o of
them however H we think that having a
very isolated system will be very
beneficial and that is why also we think
um organiz are a very good idea and of
course cellular diversity is a most
foros having in mind the diversity that
the hypothalamus has so there was in
2024 or 2023 there was this report that
there are around 108 different clusters
of neurons in the hypothalamus so it's a
extremely
diverse area of the brain and we would
like to capture at least a little bit of
that
complexity so that brings me to what
people have been publishing before in
terms of hypothalamic models human
hypothalamic models um and there have
been to the best of my knowledge and
probably there are maybe a couple of
more now but 18 research articles coming
from eight different research groups um
and what they have been doing is exactly
taking potent themselves and
differentiating them towards
hypothalamic
regions so as you can see there are 2D
and 3D and something to bear in mind
here is that when you're are doing 2D
cultures and you are differentiating
them ER most of your cell will be seeing
roughly the same things so you will end
up with a very homogeneous nice layer of
cells however when you go to 3D you have
a um yes your cultures are facing still
all the small molecules and everything
that you are giving to them to Quee
towards the differentiation process
however because they are so close
together they will start secreting even
um factors themselves that that will
help the self-patterning and will help
this generate this
diversity of cell types um so for
instance in the organoids um you often
expect to have like some astrocytes some
oligodendrocytes as well along with your
neurons uh but something that I should
also mention is that as any other model
organ are not the perfect model and
there are couple of reasons why so one
of them is that they certainly don't
have a microa the resent microphases of
the brain and that is because of of um
the protocol that that we do because we
cue the differenciation towards
ectotherm so microa is not coming from
that germ layer so we cannot get
microa another thing I will be talking
about along this talk but however we
know that there is people that are doing
hypothalamic human organoids and we
decided to give it a go in our hands so
we just took a one of the protocols SK
2018 and we enriched it with some of the
um other protocol from Merle
2015 and what we have is this um
protocol that as I was telling you first
you cue the differentiation towards
neuro ectotherm this is a very basic
step with a dual smart inhib that people
do for cortical but also for other ER
brain organoids and then you have to um
signal for in what region of the brain
the hypothalamus is right so the
hypothalamus is in the ventral most part
of the brain so it often receives a lot
of signal of Sonic Hedgehog so that's
exactly what you have to add in the
media and then for the anterior
posterior a you need to add a proper
level of wind signaling we do that with
wind 3A so that's pretty much just
positioning or just ske where in the
brain you you want
this um then in the next steps pretty
much a early hypothalamus and maturation
you are just promoting this exit of the
cell cycle for having your neurons and
you're promoting the maturation of the
neurons um and in this protocol we ended
up we ended it at day 1550 and we did
that because that's essentially where
the this other project that protocol
that we based based on
finished something to have in mind is
when we were comparing all the other
protocols that I was showing you before
um the more small molecules the more
cues you add to your differentiation
protocol the shorter it seems to be um
the the time that you have to wait to
have an an end result right because you
are kind of accelerating the
developmental process and there are
protocols for even hypothalamic models
that they add much less small molecules
however they need to wait like around
200 days to to have an organoid which
might be fantastic however we wanted to
have a little bit of a shorter protocol
that we could play a little bit
quicker um so this is how our our organ
look
like and we decided to do single solar
just to analyze what we are actually
getting from there and using some data
from already published articles we could
see that our organoids were um at least
fairly similar to both adult
hypothalamus
andic
hypothalamus and when we have a closer
look to our single cell that
so we are happy to see that we don't
have neurons we have like neuroblast
tdes so that's all good but we also have
a lot of Ria that means that we still
have a lot of progenitors going on in
there so this seems that our day 50
organ which are a little bit early in
development and that brings me to the
second main um concern when you are
using
organoids in research and it's because
they often resemble iic stages just
because the stem cells are pretty much
resemble um very early stages so
something that I can tell you already is
that if we leave this organoids
today 80 something like that then we
start seeing markers for astrocytes and
oenocytes and these are that is very
good and that's is exactly what we want
to have and um they often appear later
in the development very close to the um
POS natal or their pation time so at
least we have those markers now so we
are confident that we have organ that
are good enough to keep going with this
especially because we can also see the
the representation of eight different
nuclei of the
um
hypothalamus which is very reassuring
and we are especially interested for
instance in the lateral a nuclei nucleus
just because this one is very
very associated with
sleep um arate that it has to do a lot
with metabolism
paraventricular that is the one that is
involved with a cortisol and all the
pathway with cortisol so those three we
are particularly interested but to be
honest the more the merrier right in the
ideal world we would like to have an
organoid that recapitulates the whole a
repertoire of cells that we see in in
the human brain and so as we speak and
as we are doing these experiments we are
also trying to improve and our
protocol however this is a protocol that
we have currently and we are fairly
happy with
it especially because we also have the
expression of the sadian jeans that we
were talking
about um and can as you can see it's
pretty much a salt and pepper
expression so that probably means that
our organ although they are expressing
the Machinery they are not synchronized
so the question would be can can we
actually synchronize them and that
brings us to all those things that we
were thinking before of what to use can
we do actually deame methasone or
FBS so that's exactly what we tried um
we took the um protocols from many
papers like there are tens of of papers
doing this kind of synchronizations in
other
cultures and what we could see is that
upon
the treatment or exposure to the
dexamethasone or FBS we could see this
Gene cycling and for the rest of the
talk I'm going to be focusing on the
dexametasone treatment not in the FBS
but um where we're very happy to see
that we can actually synchronize
them then we decid decied to go ahead
and start exploring what is happening
with this organ over time via a
volaric and what we can see here I'm
just showing you six different
neuropeptides so for instance here the
first one this one is hypocretin this
one is very Associated to
sleep um and what we can see is like
this this cycle
and we actually didn't know how it would
happen because like this one is known to
be uppr regulated when we are
awake so that is interesting to see that
just modulating the
Circadian Machinery with xamas we can
see this
increase AP is a favorite of mine just
because this one is V oppressing this
one is the one that is regulating blood
pressure and as probably you are aware
ER problems with blood pressure are very
common ER worldwide but particularly in
our Latin communities that's a big big
public health
issue then we have a CR the one that we
were talking about so the corticotropin
releasing hormone that is um Upstream
from the release of cortisol and H so we
were not expecting a dynamic like up
down up down so we were expecting more
like a dynamic of this sort so we are
very happy to see that it is works
almost like a little bit of a control
that our system is probably actually
working then um G&R is going to dropping
releasing hormone uh this one is
associated of course with reproduction
and fertility and K one is associated
with the onset of puberty so these two
guys are pretty much in associated in
reproduction but we are still not
taching that yet H but that's something
very interesting
that actually one of our PhD students is
kind of going deep into this and the
last one that I want to show you is pmch
because this one is also associated with
sleep and it's also meant to be
increased when one is awake and
interestingly like we can see at Le at
36 hours it seems that it is up both in
hypocretin and
bmch so for this talk like I want to
share with you like our surprise like do
we have in our hands something that
would mimic a sleep model in
hypothalamus that would be we would be
very happy with it to be
honest but it this is a very complex
physiological process so we want to try
to figure out whether this could work as
a model or not so just to give you a
little bit of more insight about
hypocretin so this is exactly how this
looks like and this is in
m so it increases the number of neurons
that Express hypocretin we don't know
which are the cells that usually don't
express it and then express it we have
no clue but we know that there are more
cells that express it and that per cell
there are there is more intensity of
hypocretin also or more content and more
transcription in each of those
cells hypocretin is a a gene that open
translation um it it can get tiffed into
two neuropeptides one is called orexin a
the other one is called orexin B so for
the next slide we tested orexin a bya
immunofluoresence and what we can see is
that over the time in our organ it's
exposed to
theone we can see an increase of orexin
a at T12 and at
t36 and this increas is very evident
and here is just the quantification of
of this signal and we can see that it
follows the same
ER trajectory that the transcript does
this is the same graph that you saw in
the slide
before um we are also doing and this is
preliminary thata we are doing some
Eliza tests where we can see that by
Eliza at least we can detect that 36
hour Peak so again suggesting like maybe
that 36 hour Peck would be very
interesting if if we want to try to
focus a little bit on on
sleep so again because this is a very
complex
um process physiological process we want
to try to figure out other ways where we
can explain it so this could be a
cellular inessence maybe you are
familiar with this like you have to
gather evidence of like many different
uh experiments to say like okay this is
cellular SES I think this that this is
what Wiles need to say like you know we
have a model of sleep we would need a
lot of different experiments and a lot
of different hints that would suggest
that and because of that I found this
paper from
2012 ER where they were pretty much
trying to figure out the transcriptomic
signature of what H being awake would
look like and in
V so how they do how the way that they
did this was pretty much they used
cortex of mouse with sleep deprived
control and recovery and then for the
inra setting they culture the cortical
neurons and they added a cocktail um
that pretty much um activate
synapses um or just synaptic activity
and they call that this is kind of
active awake neurons and this is the
list of genes that in theory they should
be up in vitro as well as they see this
in in the cortex and then there is like
the list of gen that should be down
regulated H please bear in mind this is
mouse not human and this is cortical not
hypothalamus so this is just some of the
thems that I'm trying to come up to
figure out whether this is or
not however interestingly for the set of
genes that are actually or should be op
regulated in when the cells are awake
that means at 36 hours for us
potentially I found this gen being a
little bit higher in expression ER
exactly what this means I'm still not
sure but we are we're going further into
this and interesting it's interestingly
I found like this set of genes that are
actually upregulated at 48 hours and
there are a few of them so I'm not
exactly sure what this means yet but it
might be that this is just like a little
bit of a late
um signal that they this were awake or
that this is a they are awake we because
we don't really understand the Dynamics
of this anyways yet uh for the ones that
are down regulated or that should be
down regulated I found only these three
and it is not that evident but we are
going to continue to check this
further so what other things can I do to
try to figure out this so of course we
need to do imun also for pmch for
instance Al npvf is a good candidate
npvf is it should be potentially down
regulated um during a weake um during a
week
stage um we want to keep doing
transcriptomics and just the analysis of
it um I am a web lab and I am
transitioning a little bit to analyze
this in a little bit of more
um you know computational area so using
a little bit of fire and Python and for
sure I don't know if you guys but I find
that challenging coming from only a web
lab
experience we also want to analyze the
secret via M spectometry just to have
like the full bread of neuropeptides
that we can detect coming out from
those organoids so so far we can detect
by Eliza the ones that we have tried
that are CR and or X in a those are the
ones that we have right but we would
like to have like the full bread so we
have some samples down in Melbourne so
this is happening as we speak so fingers
crossed we will have a lot of data
coming from
this
experiment um we also would like to
check neuronal activity via
multi-electrode array arrays the only
thing is that um often when we think
about sleep we we think about these
waves of sleep problem is those waves
are coming from the cortex not from the
hypothalamus and apparently the
hypothalamus is a rather quiet space um
so I am not sure what we would be
looking at
but any information would be good
information so this is probably anyways
very valuable
information and also another thing that
we should do is check for cellular
metabolism
so we have seor so we are going to check
for oxygen consumption but also we would
like to check for maybe a mitochondrial
activity because it has been seen that
it is usually of regulated when one is
away comp to when we are
sleeping we have some other future
directions
um so for
instance how much of this is meditated
by synaptic activity so we are already
doing some experiments with some
Inhibitors in there just to try to
figure that
out um what is the effect of different
sight givers in on different cell types
so we are currently doing those
experiments with melatonin and we are
going to be starting with a
insulin um is
there a hierarchy in the response of the
hypothalamus because like the the main
contribution or or the major um sight
Giver would be light right and light
will it directly go to the hypothalamus
and regulate there but it also is
receiving these cortisol signals and we
can very well see that it is responsive
to cortis very evidently so what kind of
of hierarchies are there or maybe there
are not hierarchies and they are just
integration of signals for but how they
happen we don't really
know are there differences in males and
females in the hypothalamus there there
are um differences for instance we have
women have more one neurons remember
one is the is a peptide I told you
that is involved with puberty so we have
more of those neurons compared to males
and what happens with different genetic
backgrounds or even in disease like what
happens with narcolepsy like for
instance in narcolepsy often or a lot of
the patients have a mutations in the
hypocretin
gene um because of my background and
because of how the the climate the
biological CL climate that we have is
what happens with in other cultures like
what did we do organoid of different um
parts of the body like how comparable
would be the responses to these site
givers and this is even longer term but
we would be very interested to see how
this plays out because for sure there's
going
to happen like how would it look in an
body on a chip so that means like what
if you put organ of different areas of
the body and you connect them all of
them and then what if you set time in
the different ones and see how this
whole system um react so pretty much
just dissecting every single way of this
machinery
and that that is what I think would be
happening in in the future like I don't
know like five to Years hopefully and
hopefully we're there to see that
happening or make it
happening so without further Ado I want
to thank you all for your attention of
course I want to thank my B Stefan and
asati that she's my partner in crime in
a lot of these things that I have been
showing you today and I'm ready to take
questions
thank you very much for the presentation
um I just want to mention that there's
going to be a short survey and if you
can please fill it out it'd be greatly
appreciated uh first question is from
Daniel Gonzalez a very interesting model
maybe I missed it but how do you
reconcile the lack of sensory Machinery
with the Circadian changes observed in
the organoids do you think the organoids
behave like this regardless of their
environmental
cues um okay and so we are actually
running the controls where we are having
our organ without any cortisol during
the whole span of the experiment so we
are taking organ every 12 hours as well
just to make sure that the Baseline
doesn't um
cycle however the data of the Single
Cell an6 suggests that they are all that
they are not synchronized so that
shouldn't be an issue but let me know if
that is
what you meant and if I actually
answered your question and maybe the
other aspect of your question that um
because I did say that there are some
cells that do not have the Machinery but
we can certainly tell that our organists
do have the Machinery so that should be
up and running I hope that that answered
okay any other questions um is a very
interesting talk sure I'll I'll throw a
question in um for the secretome it's
it's amazing that you're considering
that as a future direction are there
other things you want to look into in
the secret tone Beyond proteins like are
you thinking perhaps that there are
different things being um secreted out
from the cells yeah so with the secreton
what we are doing is that we are
depolarizing the organoids just to make
sure that they release all the goodies
that they have in there about to be
released and what we would like to see
is pretty much the whole landscape of
the neuropeptides that that could be
released at a given time and that is
because we are very interested in the
metabolic aspect of of it and like just
a very physiological output of it so
it's so such a diverse group of cells in
there that impact many things that are
actually associated to many problems
that we have right now as major public
health concerns worldwide that we want
just to try to make sure that we pay
attention or that we can see as much as
we can in terms of all these
neuropeptides that can be released in
our
model fantastic thank
you how uh how many different
environmental stimuli have you applied
to the models to see if it disrupts Circ
at the three so
dexasone FBS and
melatonin and we are using melatonin as
well because it's also pretty much
physiological right I mean it is
produced by in the penal gland so it's
not exactly coming from the hypothalamus
so we can deliver it
extrinsically to some extent so that is
why we wait we went with that so when
artificial setting we're trying to mimic
as good as we can the the
physiology we do have another question
in the chat um for the type of model
that is used how consistent would it be
to measure the markers from rat and
organoids I guess rat and human
organoids the type of model it can you
repeat the
question I think there's something
missing but um the question is for the
type of model that is used how
consistent would it be to measure the
markers from rat and
organoids okay so maybe the com the
comparison between models um you know
what uh probably fairly similar but we
have to pay attention to something very
basic rats for instance are nocturnal
and we are dial and that different that
difference happens in the
hypothalamus so just for the sake of
starting
sleep the things will be like the other
way around and where where the
connection becomes different between
nocturnal and dial it seems to be coming
from the interation of the
suprachiasmatic nucleus that is one of
the nucleus of the hypothalamus to the
paraventricular nucleus where the actual
Z is actually released from um
but we're not entirely sure how that
Machinery works so that that's why we
have such a big issue at the minute in
that level of complexity when you want
to go more granular that's where using
other animal models it might be a little
bit tricky to make the full
comparison however for sure like all the
animal models are very valuable and will
continue to be super valuable but you
just need to think about what exactly
you're asking and whether
it actually makes sense to compare it in
that particular to to answer that
particular question that's
it that's very true and it's I mean
keeping those details in mind is really
important before we come to a
conclusion yes
yes okay I'm going to give people maybe
a few more minutes to drop questions
um speaking of models you said you
wanted to compare male versus female um
biology when it comes to hypothalamus I
I think there was a paper circulating a
little while ago saying that there is a
distinct difference in terms of the
hours of sleep or how much rest is
needed how do you think that's going to
impact potentially the findings that you
get you know that's a very interesting
question I am not too sure and the thing
is that b males versus females is more
complex than it looks like because it
not it doesn't only come with just the
chromosomes that you have during
development for instance we have waves
of um estrogen and testosterone flowing
that apparently regulate to some extent
the identity and the function of the of
the hypothalamus for later on so at this
stage what we are doing is first like
trying to figure
out do we have the proper model for
analyzing males versus females
that is more physiologically relevant
that it is
not only having the correct chromosomes
so that is something very important
particularly for the hypothalamus
because it is invol with all these
reproduction systems right ER how would
it play out later on say we have a a
good enough model that we consider that
we want to move forward with it and just
check up the sleep
I'm not too sure I'm I'm thinking it's
going to be very different like I hate
to say this but my partner like he it'ss
like crazy and he doesn't gain weight uh
but anyways I'm always very hungry and
and he's not that like that kind of
things like we often see in the in in
just like the people that we have around
um they a lot of that is happening from
the hypothalamus like all this hunger
this like how much intake but how much
weight you gain and so it's all wired in
there I'm not saying that it's the only
contribution but it's definitely in
there so for sure we're going to see
differences in there also another thing
is that after menopause there are heaps
of metabolic changes happening for for o
um so how to model that that's another
question and once you can model
it I'm not too sure what we're going to
see but for instance like when women hit
menopause the incidents for instance for
Strokes go so high just suddenly
so I'm not sure and that might be
related to blood pressure and that might
be related to vasopressin that by the
way is actually released from the
hypothalamus so there are many different
aspects But first you need to kind of
tune down what is the model that you are
going to use and that's what we are
trying to set up first like just a
reliable model that is as
physiologically relevant as we can make
and and then make this very what seems
very basic simple questions that
actually they are not that
simple it's true I I had a question as
well um do you plan on inducing some of
the genes associated with psychiatric
disorders because there's a
disregulation in circadian rhythm
sometimes with um psychiatric disorders
like schizophrenia
bipolar no not at the meane what I am
trying to do via
um Viper so and with clap is try to
modulate a gen associated with actually
obesity so box P2 S one those are things
that are happening in the hypothalamus
that we would potentially be interested
to to do um things that are
psychiatric not at the minute I'm aware
that there are a bit of things happening
in terms of
autism and like some papers that have
come like out with things like that
especially with epigenetic
modulators but we are not addressing
that at the minute but why like do you
have do you work with that is that
something that we should actually be
looking at uh yeah so um it's
a with psychiatric disorders it's it's
anecdotal but like psychiatric patients
particular bip po different they do have
like a circadian disruption and their
tiny boxs are off right so we don't know
like from a genetic standpoint like yeah
so my colleague asati she's working with
Parkinson disease and pretty much a lot
of the neuro degeneration diseases that
we have that are major concerns are also
having a Saran
disregulation so it seems like it is a
very sensitive to some degree system
although it is very robust because
people are still alive and what not but
it seems like it is fairly easy to
deregulate it seem like even like with
addiction like what happens in in in
terms of The calian rhythms in there it
seems like it is not it it is modulated
somewhere in there so that is something
else to have in mind
that pretty much is regulated yeah so
thing with psychiatric disorders it's
always like a chicken or egg scenario
like are they having psychiatric
disorders and their behavior is also
disregulated their ccan Rhythm or is it
dis Arcadian rhythm is disregulated and
IND these things right and having an
isolated system then helps you out to
figure out which is the chicken or the
egg right exactly so that is why these
kind of systems are relevant for doing
this very basic ESS here and there so
yeah I I didn't know but that is
something to keep in mind thank you and
are you planning on a longitudinal
long-term study and keeping your Organo
as long as you can to see how
disregulated time and age causes changes
1,00% 1,000% so for instance in my
previous lab it we were leaving cortical
organs over a year to have a good model
for what we would like call
aging um so that is something that
absolutely I have some organoids in the
Inc
that I'm just like keeping there forever
and then and I'm just going to have a
look at them later
[Music]
on but yeah that is very very
interesting as well so what is happening
to us at the minute with this model that
we just set up is that there are too
many interesting questions that we can't
tackle so we are just trying to spend as
much as we can
strategically and feasibly do for the
yeah and we are of course open to
collaboration so if anyone here is like
oh we should really do this and let's
write a round about
it we would we would probably be yeah so
my lab is working on PWS and one of the
target tissues is the
hypothalamus oh there you go yeah that's
very
cool that's very very nice maybe we
should stop yeah so the the manager of
that who does all the wet lab work was
here so he he might be in contact so
I'll I'll follow up with him oh
fantastic
yeah all right do we do we have any more
questions or anyone else wants to chime
in I just wanted to thank Cecilia again
for waking up so early and doing this
talk and being so bright and perky at
the same time um if not uh we can call
it in like a minute and you have one or
two minutes to put your
questions yeah I think that was uh
perfect and it sounds to me like the
best thing that you can go to a seminar
uh has happened which is new ideas for
research and potential collaboration so
it's fantastic all
around awesome thank you so much for
having me guys