Well, in a world advancing towards
globalization, strong competitive
pressures force companies to operate as
if there were a single world market with
the same prices for goods, capital, and
labor. After decades in which the costs
of distance declined and countries
lowered the border level barriers to
trade, globalization is now reversed and
global markets are fragmenting. MIT
Institute professor Suzanne Burer will
give us insight into the main causes for
this shift and help us understand how in
a world characterized by new border
level barriers including tariffs, export
controls, import controls, and
immigration restrictions, national
support for domestic manufacturing,
which was dismissed as unimportant only
a decade ago, has now become a key
objective in all countries. Please give
a warm welcome to Professor Suzanne Ber.
[Applause]
[Music]
So I have a presentation in two parts
and one part I'm will present this
afternoon and the next part uh tomorrow
morning uh uh because what I'd like to
explain to you this afternoon is why it
is that manufacturing has become
critical in all countries today. What
are the changes in the international
economy that has made it seem imperative
for us to uh uh in fact regrow and
transform manufacturing in our own
national economies and then tomorrow uh
with my colleagues uh from MIT we're
going to talk about what we can do to
transform manufacturing and how we hope
again to be able to create uh new
manufacturing that will be significantly
more productive, significantly more
resilient, and produce better jobs uh
for those who work in this sector. But
this afternoon, I'd like to talk about
why this change has come about. Because
as Randall expressed, when I talked here
at um at an earlier session of of of
this of this group uh 12 years ago, we
had to even defend the idea that
manufacturing mattered at all. Uh we
were at a time when uh when when an
economist like Larry Summers uh former
president of Harvard um said we really
didn't need any manufacturing in the
United States at all. We could just all
follow the model of Apple. Apple's model
seemed to be design in the United States
and distribute in the United States and
produce everything somewhere else. So
how have we moved from a world where you
know 15 years ago it just didn't seem
important at all to a world in which
it's it's absolutely critical and I
think that these changes have come about
uh because globalization is really
disappearing uh and disappearing
rapidly. Uh in
1914,
globalization disappeared once before
and that was after another period from
1850 roughly to
1914 in which globalization again had
been dominant between 1850 and 1914. And
in that time in
disappeared globalization disappeared
over the course of one week between July
31st when the London Stock Exchange
closed and August 4th,
1914 when the English government
declared war on Germany. And we now know
that the
consequences of that war and the
consequences of that end of
globalization
uh were uh enormous for the world. Uh
they were enormous in many many ways.
But if we focus simply on the economy,
what was critical was that the levels of
crossborder flows uh between countries,
flows of capital, flows of labor and
flows of goods and services. They did
not return to the level of
1914 until the early
1980s. So even if we consider only the
economy, Yes. First of all,
globalization is
reversible. And secondly, once you start
reversing it, it becomes extremely
difficult to bring it back again. And I
think that just as people in that
earlier period
underestimated what was at stake uh in
uh in for the economy. Uh I think that
today we are greatly underestimating the
costs and dangers that the end of
globalization is likely to have in our
own time. In fact, we don't even really
agree on what is happening. Many people
claim well the level of uh goods and
services uh has not really fallen that
much. uh we still if we're not getting
it from China, we're getting these goods
from Vietnam and and and Mexico. Are we
doing delobalization or do we have
something like regional variance of
globalization? Uh do we have
organization some kind of international
organization that for example uh we know
that Apple is still stuck in China. We
know that many of the goods that used to
come directly from China are now making
detours through Vietnam and and Mexico
and other countries. And uh so I think
there's a lot of uncertainty, but I
would like to suggest today that we are
truly seeing an end and that that is
really what sets up the the the
imperative of restoring and renewing uh
our domestic our domestic economies. And
as a social scientist, I'd like to
suggest that the a simple definition of
globalization is really the most useful
for us. In a simple model of
globalization, we can imagine that all
firms have to operate as if there were a
single world model, a single world
market rather, in which the prices of
goods, services, and wages were the same
everywhere in the world. And of course,
we know that no such world ever existed.
So what did exist? and has existed over
the last 40 years is a world driven by
competition to reduce prices and above
all the prices of goods, services and
wages. It's as if each firm believed
that they had to compete in a world in
which we were heading towards a single
world market. And uh it that that
dynamic today is being destroyed and
it's being destroyed simply because
governments are setting up barriers at
the frontier. Governments are uh uh of
course have always in a way used border
level barriers. Governments used to use
tariffs as a way of raising revenue. Um,
governments used to use uh uh tariffs as
a way of protecting one or another
domestic industry. But in the past, it
was usually natural barriers, distance,
and time that did the heavy lifting of
protecting national economies against
flows from above, flows from outside.
And I think today we're in a world where
technology has basically conquered
distance. Technology has made
communication between countries
instantaneous. And so we can no longer
count on natural barriers. In fact, we
need to imagine that politics and border
level barriers uh import and export
controls are going to be doing all the
heavy lifting on protecting domestic
economies against against the outside
against the rest of the world. And it
was in fact the new technologies of the
1980s and the 1990s that in fact made
this uh uh uh pressure to behave behave
as if there was going to be and in fact
there already was something like a
single world uh market that destroyed
the
containerships, the uh internet um all
of that did the work of destroying the
barriers, the natural barriers of
distance and time. And we saw in the
early 1990s that once you had
digitalization that it was and once it
was possible to send a digital file that
some chip designer in California had
made to a factory in Taiwan that would
actually make the semiconductor. Once
that was possible, that's what everybody
tried to do because that reduced the
cost of labor in your own country and
the cost of building factories in your
own country. And so on one hand there
were the technological changes that made
it possible to outsource and offshore
just about everything. And then there
was tremendous pressure from stock
exchanges, from financial markets, in
fact to outsource and offshore just
about everything. So those countries
that got rid of those companies that got
rid of uh the maximum of factories and
the maximum of workers, those were the
companies that did the best in stock
exchanges. And you could see that um in
fact those companies that did the most
outsourcing and the most offshoring did
the best in markets. And uh that was the
advice that it was virtually impossible
uh to to to do otherwise or so at least
companies
uh companies uh believed. And so we
moved into a world in which financial
markets uh desired and rewarded pure
play businesses. And that was a world in
which the
dominant companies of the
1940s 50s60s and 70s those were uh those
were vertically integrated companies.
They were companies like IBM, like
DuPont, uh like uh Texas Instruments.
And these companies had been vertically
integrated ones. And the pressures for
pure play investment, the pressures to
get rid of factories and workers broke
apart all of those countries, all of
those companies. And what we have been
left with at this point are core what
business uh uh language calls core
component competence companies. Core
competence companies focus on a single
activity. And so it's this world of core
competence companies that we now have to
imagine rebuilding uh manufacturing
with. And so I think today we are moving
in a very different direction from the
past 40 years. We're moving into a world
in which all countries are raising
political barriers that surround their
territories. And while the overall level
of trade has
been descending but not very rapidly uh
and that's why some people still
disagree
uh that globalization is over. I think
the direction is really pretty clear
that we're um raising barriers not only
to what comes from China, we're raising
barriers to what comes from our allies
uh and uh uh from those c countries that
have been closest to us over the past uh
70 years. And so of course these
pressures are going to be perhaps
greatest on American uh companies who
are now facing tremendous disruptions
and very very rough rides uh today with
President Trump who I think we might
call the great disruptor. Um, but I
think we should not delude ourselves
that uh the tariffs that were passed uh
in the first Trump administration
uh were never discontinued during the
Biden administration. On the contrary,
during the Democratic presidency of
President Biden, the barriers got
higher. uh the the uh policy that Jake
Sullivan announced of a high fence but a
small yard that is protecting uh very
little but protecting it with uh high
barriers. In fact, the small yard kept
getting bigger and the fences kept uh
getting bigger even during a Democratic
Biden administration. So I think that
waiting it out is not a rational
strategy. This is not a situation that
is likely to change even if the
Democrats return to power. And that
again, this is sort of a a lengthy
preface to the story that I want to tell
tomorrow in our workshop about why it's
so critical for us to be able to uh
transform and revive manufacturing in
our own countries. Now focusing on why
globalization has um has been destroyed
both by Republicans and Democrats in our
own country and I think many of you see
uh here in Austria some of the same uh
some of the same uh pressures. I think
there really were three reasons that
were have been at
work over the past uh 1015 years that
have undermined globalization. First of
all, um uh globalization was great for
many of the peoples of this of this
earth. There were millions who uh were
raised by globalization. Millions in
Asia who uh who were raised from abject
poverty to lives of dignity and and
work. But in fact, globalization was not
great for liberal democracies. uh the uh
waves of imports from lowwave low-wage
countries led to uh firings and job loss
in all liberal uh economies. And I think
we saw a tremendous reaction to that in
Britain with Brexit and in the United
States with massive movements of uh uh
uh anger and uh a very divisive forms of
political uh polarization. Uh
globalization meant that parts of our
country uh Youngstown, Ohio, Detroit,
Michigan, parts of Wisconsin, uh these
were parts of the country that were
basically single industry uh cities.
They became wastelands. The iron uh rust
rust belt and we see the same phenomena
in many many other countries. Secondly,
there was CO and CO taught the public
that there are severe dangers in a
production system based on just in time
production. just in in time production.
Basically, the Toyota production system
uh has as its single most important
enemy eliminating waste and waste is
inventory or inventory is is waste. And
I think what we all learned during COVID
is that some inventory really can be can
be a very good can be very good
resilience. We've learned from COVID to
value resilience and the basic firm type
that we had developed in the United
States uh the uh core competence company
depended more than ever on its suppliers
and that dependence on suppliers was
critically challenged during the during
the co during the co uh uh period. All
of these c companies that had been uh
once had been vertically integrated that
hadn't been so uh reliant on their
suppliers. The GE the Texas Instruments
uh they suddenly uh uh saw how dependent
they were on suppliers that had become
that had become far less reliable and
far more difficult uh to access. That
dependence was critically highlighted by
co and I think that uh the co called
into question also the production mantra
of the last 40 years. Lean
manufacturing uh had emphasized both the
elimination of waste, the elimination of
inventory and the idea of optimizing
uh uh optimizing in the sense of
eliminating
redundancy. That redundancy which we
came to value in the course of COVID had
been the specific enemy of the lean
manufacturing model. And I think we've
now also come to
understand that lean manufacturing firms
that valued lean turned out to be as uh
basically hostile in a sense at least
hostile to innovation. If you are
concerned with eliminating waste, if you
are concerned with optimization, you
don't want to have a quarter of your
factory floor exploring new options, new
ways of doing things. It messes up the
the factory floor. It uh it's expensive.
Uh it it screws up the scheduling of of
the rest of your of rest of your
activity. So what we observed over this
period is that uh companies that were
heavily into lean and six sigma in fact
became far less innovative even as they
uh followed these mantras of production
and today I think this is a way in which
we have come to re-evaluate a lean and I
I I don't think any of us really knows
what we should be putting in place of
lean but I think it's it's a moment
really of reconsideration of its values.
So uh what what has been the result of
of of of these changes? I think COVID
and um outsourcing really
um produced manufacturers at least in
the United States that were extremely
risk averse. Companies that have seen
their sector shrink. Companies that have
lost uh six million workers over a
10-year period become companies that are
really focused on survival. They're not
focused on innovation. They're not
focused on uh they're not focused on
change. So what we have been left with
are riskaverse firms uh and a
manufacturing ecosystem that's been
thinned out, drained and depleted. Let
me tell you about uh a visit I made with
my colleagues. We've been visiting firms
uh and sampling manufacturing firms uh
uh firms uh firms particularly that uh
hire that have fewer than 500 uh uh
workers. So these are what we call small
and medium manufacturers and I I want to
tell you about a visit to a firm that uh
we actually found ex an excellent
company in its way its product was
excellent. it. It's a firm in Ohio and
they make screws of very high techch uh
screws. And
um when I asked this manufacturer what
he's looking for when he's hiring, he
said, "I want someone who will come on
time and uh and and and stay." And uh he
said, and I said, "How how much you
paying?" He said, "I'm paying $13 an
hour." This was in this was several
months before uh right before COVID hit.
He said, "Unless an Amazon warehouse
opens down the street for me, then I'll
have to go up to $15 an hour." I asked,
um, do you ever think about hiring any
of those, uh, uh, guys coming out of
community colleges who've had classes in
robotics and 3D printing? He said, "What
would I do with them? I don't have any
robots. I don't have any uh 3D printers.
In fact only even today only uh
10% of all US manufacturers have even
one robot and that's exactly how how
many they will have just just one. He
said I don't have 3D printers. I don't
have robots. I want them to work on the
machines I have. So then we toured his
factory and he had Davenport milling
machines that his grandfather had
purchased in the
1940s. some of there were a few new CNC
machines sprinkled in there, but
Davenport mostly Davenport milling
machines. And in fact, he was buying
when companies went out of business. He
bought their Davenport milling machines
of the same generation so that he would
have parts to repair and replace in the
ones he owned. Now, imagine this
situation. We have young workers who are
in fact being trained in some of these
new technologies, but he has no interest
in hiring them. He wants to hire people
who know how to work on the machines he
has. And yet it would make no sense for
our community colleges or worker
training programs be training people how
to work on the machines of the 1940s.
And so in research that uh Ben Armstrong
and I have done together, we've tended
to describe this situation as a sort of
low-end
uh uh equilibrium trap. We have low
skills uh low tech and low wages so uh
uh connected to each other that it's
very hard to imagine how we can break
out of this of this sort of trap that
we've somehow gotten ourselves into in
manufacturing. And I think the reason
that
um this matters now is that now with um
with the war in Ukraine and with the
possibility of conflict in with China,
uh that uh we now realize that this
manufacturing system that we have is not
up to any of the challenges of securing
our national defense. American
policymakers are moving to more barriers
at the border exactly because of this
national security situation. But if we
actually look at the what the defense
industry is capable of, we realize that
even in supplying arms to Ukraine over
the past years, um that there has been
significant difficulty in getting even
the arms manufacturers in the United
States to produce the quantities uh that
the United States at least up to the
present has been willing has been
willing uh to send. So in the defense
industrial base, we have a few great
companies, Rathons or Lockheed Martins.
There are some new high- techch Silicon
Valley companies like Anderil uh that
have been mentioned here or Palunteer
but these companies are really still in
their infancy and not really able to uh
they're in no way able by themselves to
meet the challenges. And then there are
the myriad of suppliers to the defense
uh to the tense economy. And these
suppliers, they are the very same
companies that I just described to you.
Well, when we have gone to visit the
small and medium manufacturers of the
Middle East and the rest of the United
States, something close to half of them
do defense
contracting as well as contracting to
the civilian economy. So our defense uh
uh industrial base is largely the same
industrial base that we in which we have
identified so many weaknesses. So as we
look at this system and as we uh try to
take into account that globalization is
disappearing just exactly at the same
time that we need uh that we need to uh
in some ways secure supply for our own
for our own national economy and for our
national defense. This seems to be an
extremely serious and dangerous
situation for our domestic for our
domestic economy. Think of just the
domestic component of this. If we are
without those cheap goods uh that China
had provided us, if today we actually
had to make uh shoes and socks in the
United States, how much do you imagine
that it would cost to make something
that today comes from China for so the
problem of inflation, the problems even
of the domestic economy, let alone of
the defense economy,
that we can see emerging on the horizon
as globalization recedes are really
significant. I
um there was a French economist who gave
a talk that I attended a month ago who
said uh Europe is going to need to learn
to live without the partner of the
United States. And I think that the
problem actually is far worse. Uh that
uh the rest of the world is going to
have to learn to live with the great
uncertainties and the deep disruptions
that US policy is generating. The
international economy
basically rests on a foundation of rule
of law and trust and that foundation is
being deliberately
uh demolished at the present time. And
it's in this international environment
that we have to situate the imperative
for
rebuilding manufacturing in all of our
economies. This is this is not I think
we have to acknowledge this is not
necessarily a good this is not a happy
this is not a happy story but it is the
story and the imperative that we face
now and I think that the presentations
that you've heard from colleagues
earlier today h have to be seen as a way
that as as as ways and and levers
that we can use to address this
situation. But we should not we should
not be we should not neglect to mention
how much we did profit from
globalization. how much we did profit
from being able to exchange not only
exchange goods and services be able to
exchange ideas living in an open
environment of scientific exchange and
exchange exchange of ideas and so I
think it's imperative that we face this
new situation and face it with clear
eyes but it's perhaps has uh an
underside that is that also has a sort
of that also has a tragic dimension.
Thank
you. So we have time for questions. I
expect you're going to have a lot of
questions, but given the reverse trend
of globalization and the underlying
drivers of such change, what can drive
costs of remanufacturing down to be
competitive and prevent relocating
abroad?
Well, I think we hope since we hope very
much that of the the array of
possibilities, the menu of changes that
uh we saw presented by by our colleagues
today really will present uh ways of
lowering the costs of manufacturing. And
we hope to continue uh uh discussing
some of these some of these uh
technologies and changes uh that uh
tomorrow in tomorrow in the workshops.
But I think we see very promising uh
possibilities for uh for lowering the
costs of manufacturing even as we create
uh even as we create good jobs in
manufacturing. I think the goal of new
manufacturing ought to be to create
firms that are more productive. That is
firms that uh actually can afford to pay
good wages. It's an opportunity to
create manufacturing firms that are more
sustainable and don't contribute toward
the problems of of the environment and
climate. It's an opportunity to create
firms that are more resilient and so are
able to do with able to deal in
situations of shortage and and so I
think the under the opposite side of the
coin of why we have to do it the
opposite side of the coin or the other
is the opportunity to create
manufacturing that really can contribute
both to uh uh uh alleviating the
problems of climate change, providing
good jobs and and providing a more
resilient world.
Now, what industries are likely to
benefit most from this shift toward
domestic and alli based manufacturing?
Well, at the
moment, unfortunately, I think the
answer is defense industries.
uh uh and so I mean if we look at for
example the situation in Germany today
exactly as auto production plants are
being transformed into defense
production plants I think we have to
acknowledge that it is the external
security situation that will probably
drive uh drive drive change.
Do you think fragmentation of global
markets will lead to a reduction in
global inequality or exacerbate social
economic divides? I think that's the
huge that's the huge question and the
one on which I think we as a as a as a
team at at MIT we are most committed to
trying to think of the ways of you using
using these new technologies in a way
that reduce inequalities and and and
because we have seen in our own country
how divisive how inequality has produced
a situation of of polarization,
divisiveness. And so I think that should
be one of the things we are most careful
about with these new technologies. How
do we imagine technologies that could
both make firms more productive but also
raise uh the salaries that produce a
better uh that produce a better division
of shall we say the the rewards of
productivity uh uh among all those who
are stakeholders in the system?
Yes. Was there no role in massive
Chinese debt, corporate and municipal,
effectively hidden state aid, which G7
economies could not match, driving the
outsourcing you've identified?
I don't think the G7 countries were
actually interested in counteracting
Chinese growth. In fact, when we think
about how at least American
manufacturers were keen to profit from
uh Chinese from Chinese growth and uh it
was only the business community in the
United States uh were um were actually
determined to block any uh uh any any
sort of barriers uh to their uh
outsourcing and offshoring in China. And
it was only at the point in which the
Chinese government and the Chinese uh
manufacturers themselves started
blocking the expansion of US uh
manufacturers into higher level products
and higher level industries. Uh uh that
that the American business community
suddenly decided what's happening in
China. Maybe this is maybe maybe we're
not so happy about this.
Well, Dr. Burgerer, I want to thank you
so much for joining us again. It's been
a pleasure after 10 years about. Thank
you.