Okay. Um, so today we're going to talk
about the the large civ. So la last week
we introduced the large civ and we
explained how it's kind of analogous to
um the projections theorems that we
proved in finite fields and the
projection theorems that we proved in
uklidian space. Um and today I wanted to
explain to you some of the applications
of the large civ in in number theory. Um
so the original application of the large
civ uh was was by Lynn and he was
interested in how quadratic residues are
distributed and um I wrote that one up
on the homework. So the homework problem
is to re retrace Linux steps proving
about how quadratic residues are
distributed.
Um and then a second um uh important
influential application has to do with
how prime numbers are distributed modulo
q. Um so that so that's what I'm going
to tell you all about today.
Um okay so first we'll do some
background of uh I'll talk about uh
first we'll talk about um what is known
about how prime numbers are distributed
modulo q
[Music]
[Applause]
All right. So let's say pi of n is the
number of primes up to n.
Okay. And then we can look at the modulo
Q for some choice Q and see how many of
those primes are in each moduli class.
So pi n q a
is the number of p prime
p less than or equal to n and p= a mod
q.
Okay. Now um some of these moduli
classes will be quite some of these will
be quite small. um like if a and q have
a common factor then there will be only
finitely many primes in this moduli
class. So the the main focus is on the
ones where the gcd of a and q is one. So
focus on my case. Um
uh so I'm going to write it that A is in
ZQ star. ZQ star is the set of A and Z
mod Q where A is relatively prime to Q.
Okay. Um
so numerically and theoretically it
looks like the primes are pretty evenly
distributed among all of these residue
classes and it um is relevant to say how
many there are. So that's called fe of q
the cardality of zqst star the number of
different a that are relatively prime to
q. Um okay so if the primes were really
well evenly distributed among the moduli
classes then you would expect uh so I'll
write this way so we see even
distribution
and that means that the actual number of
primes in the moduli class is close to
the total number of primes divided by
the number of moduli classes.
Okay.
So how would we measure this precisely?
We define delta Q of N the sort of
defect of equidistribution to be the
maximum over all the residue classes of
the difference between the actual number
of primes
and this naive estimate.
Okay. All right. So when we ask um you
know how how evenly are primes
distributed modulo Q quantitatively that
means how big is this thing?
Okay. So this question was first
addressed by Dirishlay who showed that
in a certain sense uh that this is close
to this. Here's what he proved.
um he proved that for any Q if you take
the limit as n goes to infinity of um
delta q of n it's sort of asmintoically
smaller than n / q. So this limit is
zero.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So actually let me say
we talk about these being
equidistributed we're going to mean that
this is small relative to what? Um well
um you know this is a good approximation
of this if this error term is small
compared to the main term.
So uh so equidistribution
would mean that uh delta q of n is much
smaller than the main term which is on
the order of n / q
or n over maybe n over log n.
Okay.
Um so durishlay's arguments you can make
them quantitative. um instead of having
a limit you could say if n is
sufficiently big um and they were made
quantitative by Zagel and Walfish which
involves some additional ideas
and so this line of thinking led to the
following theorem. Um so uh so for any q
delta q of n is bounded by okay so let
me say it this way so so for any a
there's a constant c sub a and delta q
of n is bounded by c sub a n
log of n to the minus a.
Okay. Now, when is this useful? When
does this tell us that delta q of n is
is much smaller than n over q? Well, q
cannot be too big. So, uh so delta qn is
much smaller than n / q if
q is smaller than a power of log n.
Okay. So I'm not going to talk about the
proofs of these theorems in in the
class. Uh dear so Durishlay invented L
functions. You may have heard of
Dirishlay L functions in in order to
prove this theorem. And all of this work
is based on L functions. Um
okay. Okay. Um so that those are
those are nice theorems but they only
work when Q is pretty small compared to
N. Um what happens if if Q is bigger?
Well um experimentally what seems to
happen is the following. This is
conjectured by Montgomery.
Um so for every epsilon bigger than zero
delta q of n is bounded by cepsilon n to
the epsilon it's like a fudge factor and
then there's n / q to the 12.
So this is a pseudo random behavior. So,
so a good reference point you know
sometimes people ask like sort of do are
primes distributed do they does it look
random the way primes are distributed.
So a good reference point is um there
are about n over log n primes up to n.
So instead pick n over log n random
numbers reduce the mod q and see what
happens. So this is what you would see
if you had random numbers. So this is
sort of a pseudo random conjecture.
Okay. So this is much stronger than we
could prove. Um and it implies
incidentally that delta q of n is much
smaller than n / q. So we have some
pretty good expert distribution as long
as q is smaller than n^ the 1 minus
epsilon.
So there is a a huge gap between this
and this.
All right. Um
so this result I think was proven in the
1930s and it is still today the best
result of its kind. So we cannot
increase this to say n to the n to the
epsilon.
Um uh if we are willing to assume the
remon hypothesis or something that the
generalized remon hypothesis then we get
much stronger information although still
not this conjecture. So it says for
every epsilon bigger than zero delta q
of n is bounded by cepsilon n to the
epsilon*
n^ the 12 looks sort of like this but
with no q in the denominator
and that's good enough to imply that we
get some some amount of equistribution
if q is smaller than n half minus
epsilon
Okay,
so it gives some idea of how difficult
this conjecture is that even with the
remon hypothesis, we're sort of only
halfway there.
Okay. Um, so this is everything that is
known if you want to have a theorem that
definitely works for a particular Q and
having
run into a barrier there that's has been
difficult to overcome. Uh people started
to think about well maybe we won't prove
a theorem for every single Q but we
could prove a theorem for most of them.
So that's the the main topic of the
class today. So theorems for most Q.
All right. So this theorem
uh I'm going I want to credit Reni and
Bombi Venogra.
I I read about the history yesterday. So
this is usually called the Bombi
Venogradov theorem. Um the first person
to prove a theorem of this flavor seems
to be Reni and then various people
improved the parameters in the theorem
building up to Bombi and Vograov.
All right. So it says the following
thing for every epsilon bigger than
zero. Um
and
okay so if I take the sum on Q up to N
to the 12 minus epsilon
of delta Q of N.
Check the exact phrasing.
Um
A then this is bounded by
constant depending on epsilon and a n
log of n^ the minus a.
[Applause]
Okay, so let's digest this a little bit.
So the job of epsilon is that we can
almost go up to n to the 1/2 but not
quite.
And then um the job of a is that um
uh so so okay so this so this tells us
that for most not all but most uh of the
q up to n to the half minus epsilon
delta q of n is bounded by well I divide
both sides by the number of terms um and
so it would be I could put here um n / Q
log of N to the minus A. So which is
indeed much smaller than N Q. So
informally for most Q we get good
equidistribution of the primes modulo Q.
Okay. And um
and it so happens that the height of the
the size of the cues we can get up to
here matches the size of the cues you
can get up to if you knew the remon
hypothesis. Um and so this is sometimes
summarized as being like it's definitely
not as good as the remon hypothesis, but
it's sort of for most for most version
of what you would learn from the Remont
hypothesis.
Okay, good.
Okay. Um, so my goal today is to tell
you the ideas of the proof of this
theorem. There are certain things that
are a bit messy and I won't do all of
the messy things, so we won't do a
complete proof. Um, but I'd like to
address a couple questions like what
does this have to do with civs and
projection theory? And um, another
question, what does it have to do with
primes or how will we use that they're
they're primes?
Okay. Um,
right. Okay. So,
it um, since we're only trying to prove
things for most Q, we're sort of looking
at all of the different Q's. So we have
one set of primes and we're projecting
at modulo Q for lots of different Q's.
So that's the setting of projection
theory where we can bring in things like
the large civ.
Um so I wanted to recall
that the so the large civ um allows us
to prove the following kind of thing. So
we have the set x contained in the
integers up to n and I look at pi p of 1
x and I'll take the high part of that
and then this thing is small
for most uh p
and pm. So this PM
put it. Okay. Yeah. So PM
is the set of P prime
P around M.
Okay. So this looks on the surface like
a similar sort of thing. We have a set
X. We project it modulo P for many
different primes P and we throw out the
constant part and just look at the
variation from being constant. And this
is saying that this projection is pretty
evenly distributed
for most of the primes.
So it sounds similar to this and indeed
this will be crucially relevant. Um
now this is a statement about every set
X
in particular. You could put the primes
here. So you got a theorem about primes.
Um but it's true for for every set. Um
this theorem is definitely not true for
every set.
So I make a remark
that the the theorem
is not true
if you replace
um the primes
by just some set x of numbers up to n
with maybe roughly the same size as the
primes.
Um okay so there's a simple example but
I think it's instructive to see.
So the example is like this. I'm going
to try to build a set where I can reduce
it modulo every prime and whichever
prime I reduce it by I will see one
moduli class which is extremely over
represented. So here's how we build such
a set. So for every p in primes of size
around m is just a free parameter here.
Um I choose some a
and z mod p
and then I'll make my set x is going to
be the union over all the primes
and then I take um the set of n up to n
so that n is equal to a mod p.
So for each prime I pick a moduli class.
I take all the integers in that moduli
class and I take a union over all the
primes in my set of primes.
Okay.
So if I were to take pi p 1x of a
well uh x contains all the integers in
this moduli class up to n. So this is
basically n over p which is around n /
m.
Um and that's much bigger than average.
If I if I if I the average would be the
size of yes actually let's figure out
the size of x. So the size of x is at
most um there will be about n over m um
numbers in this moduli class. Um and
then there are about m over log m
primes.
So something like this.
So this is you know a smalish fraction.
It's much less than all of them. Um so
this is way smaller than the size of x
over p.
So this guy is seriously over
represented and it happens for every P.
Okay.
Okay. Great. So
so this theorem is we'll see the large
civ is absolutely crucial thing in the
proof. It's the main idea. But this is
not a theorem about arbitrary sets. It's
a theorem about prime numbers. And so
the proof needs to use something about
prime numbers.
Okay,
cool. Um, okay. So, um, so the main
character is a concept called
multiplicative convolution.
And I think this is a nice concept to
know about. It's a cousin of regular
additive convolution. And I'll try to uh
we we'll see that it interacts with all
the things in our story. So
multiplicative convolution interacts
really nicely with prime numbers
describing what are prime numbers. It
sort of comes up naturally u and it also
interacts nicely with taking projections
and so it interacts nicely with the
large civ and fitting all those things
together is the is how we prove this
thing.
Okay.
Okay. So what is multiplicative
convolution?
All right. Um, so suppose f and g are
functions on the natural numbers.
If I take the multiplicative convolution
of them,
it means I add up over all the pairs n1
and n2 whose product is n and then I
take f of n1 g of n2.
So let's compare that with regular
convolution. So regular convolution say
on the integers would be the same thing
but I would have the sum over all the
pairs n1 n2 who add up to n and the
multiplicative version is we replace the
sum here by a product.
Okay so that's multiplicative
convolution.
Okay.
Okay. So, so we have to see um how
multiplicative convolution connects with
primes
and we have to see how multiplicative
convolution interacts with projections.
[Applause]
We'll put that together and that's how
we prove the the thing.
Okay, so let's start with primes.
Okay. So, um you know the the large civ
inequality um we use this word civ and
uh I will explain to you now what what
does where does the word civ come from
and it comes out naturally when you
think about primes.
Um,
okay.
So, um, so how would how do you find the
prime numbers? Suppose I wanted to make
a list of prime numbers up to n. What
what would I do? I would start with all
the natural numbers. Then I cross off
the multiples of two. Then I cross off
the multiples of three and so on. And
then what's left are the prime numbers.
Um, so that process is called siving.
Um,
I think siving physically is where you
take like
a a thing full of sand and somewhere in
there has a little gold or diamond or
something and you shake this thing and
the sand falls out until eventually
you're just left with the diamonds. So
the image is you have a thing full of
sand which are all the natural numbers
and you shake it and you take out the
multiples of two and the multiples of
three or whatever and then eventually
you just have the prime numbers left. as
the image.
All right.
Um
Okay. So
to find the primes,
we start with the natural numbers.
Then we
cross out
multiples of two. Then we cross out
multiples of three and dot dot. All
right. Okay. So, we can all imagine
that. Now, let's try to describe this
process using formulas. And we'll see
that the formulas that naturally appear
are formulas involving multiplicative
convolution.
Okay. So, I'm going to write one of n to
be the characteristic function of all
the natural numbers.
And then the next character I'm going to
put is a function called difference
subp.
So it's one if n= 1 and it's -1 if n is
p and it's zero otherwise.
Okay. Now let's think what would happen
if I took all the natural numbers and I
did a multiplicative convolution with
d2.
So this would give me so d2 has sort of
a delta positive delta function at one
and a negative delta function at two. So
when I do this I'm going to get
characteristic function of all the
natural numbers coming from this one
minus the characteristic function of two
times the natural numbers coming from
that one.
Pause there. Does that does that make
sense? Does that fit with the you know
plugging in the definition of
multiplicative convolution?
Let's do it slowly to be sure. So what's
the definition?
One convolved with d2 of n is the sum n1
n2 = n of 1 of n1
times d2 of n2.
All right. Now d2 is only non- vanishing
in two cases. So we actually only have
to consider that n2 is 1 or n2 is 2.
So um the one is always there.
So that is 1 of n * d2 of 1.
And then uh if d is even
so so this is what happens if if n is
odd.
Um and then if n is even
then n2 could be two. So we get one of n
one of n / two sorry we get we get the
um so this is with cases one of n d2 of
1 minus one of plus one of n / 2 d2 of
2.
So this is just one and this is 1 minus
one which is zero. So we're left with
the characteristic function of the odd
numbers.
Okay, let's go one further. If I take
the characteristic function of the
naturals, I do a multiplicative
convolution with D2. Then I do a
multiplicative convolution with D3.
What happens? Well, this one gives me
the characteristic function of the odd
numbers and then I'm convolving with D3.
Now what happens? I get the
characteristic function of the odd
numbers minus the characteristic
function of three times the odd numbers
when I do this.
So I have the odd numbers but now I'm
going to cross out the ones that are
multiples of three. And so this is the
characteristic function of um n is
relatively prime
to two and three.
Okay. So this shows by example that this
process starting with the natural
numbers crossing out multiples of two
crossing out multiples of three it
corresponds to convolving by these d's
over and over.
Okay, cool. Okay, so now let me make a
little notation.
[Applause]
All right.
So, we're going to do civ for primes
general version.
All right. So suppose that s is a set of
primes
and then rp subs of n that stands for
relatively prime to s.
This is one if um
P and N are relatively prime for all the
primes in my set. So it's one if if my
number n doesn't have is relatively
prime to everybody else and it's zero
otherwise. So it's zero if there exists
a prime in my set that divides out.
Okay.
All right. So let's make a remark.
Um so if s is the primes that go up to
the square root of n
and little n is um let's say bigger than
the square root of n but at most n
then either n has a prime factor from
this list or it is prime.
So in that case
our r our r relatively prime s of n is
just p of n whether n is prime.
Okay.
So this thing uh if I'm interested in
the primes in a certain range say from n
/2 to n I can detect them using this
function.
And this function we've just seen is a
big convolution.
So lama um
so
if if if my set of primes is p1 up to p
r then um relatively prime subs of n is
one convolved with dp1
convolved with dpr. These are all
multiplicative convolutions.
I think
there
1 x of a is n / t like why why we need
to count like contributions from like
are the kids.
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is coming
back to this example. We built a set
whose projections uh projection onto
every prime has one place that's really
big. Um so um in X is made as a union of
arithmetic progressions.
Um now this X is a set. It's not a
function. So you know these these
arithmetic progressions might overlap
but if they do the point where they
overlap in this formulation only counts
once although that is it's not super
important but um so if you look at um pi
p of 1x of a that's how many elements of
x are congruent to a mod p
and so so all of them are already
>> and some of the other p might also
contain some of these elements but it
doesn't count anymore. Oh, okay.
>> Though, if it did count anymore, it
would just make this phenomenon even
more extreme than it already is.
Okay, cool. Any other questions or
comments?
All right. All right. So the um so the
characteristic function of the primes is
a special function probably in lots of
ways and the way that's relevant for us
today is that the characteristic
function of the primes is basically this
function which is a big convolution a
big multiplicative convolution and so
the bombier venograph theorem is mostly
a theorem about functions that have the
structure that they're they're
convolutions.
Okay, cool.
Okay, so that is how multiplicative
convolution is related to primes. Next,
let's think about how multiplicative
convolution is related to projections.
[Applause]
All
right.
Okay. Um,
so here there are a bunch of a bunch of
different fairly simple lemas.
Okay.
And and all these lemas have the flavor
that doing multiplicative convolution
and doing projections fits together as
well as you could hope. And I I think
basically the reason for that is that
the projection operation is a ring
homorphism from the ring Z to the ring Z
mod Q. And we'll be talking about
multiplication. So being a ring
homorphism, it means that the projection
uh respects the product operation. And
so the multiplicative convolution is
defined in terms of the product con
operation. So it all fits together.
Okay. So lema one says that if f and g
natural numbers go to c um then
if I take the projection of f convolved
with g I get the projection of f
convolved with the projection of g.
Okay, I guess this one requires a
definition.
um if I had been savvy in general I
might have defined multiplicative
convolution in the first place for any
multiplicative
I don't monoate or something um but
anyway let's just say what it is for Z
mod Q is it is what we think um
okay so um so if I have maybe capital F
and capital G functions on Z mod Q
Then
multiplicative convolution of a class A
is the sum over all pairs A1 A2 that
multiply to A of capital F of A capital
G capital F of A1 capital G of A2.
Okay.
So this is the first lema
and the proof idea is you just start on
either side and write down the
definition and unwind everything and you
use the fact that that um reduction mod
q is a ring homorphism and it all fits
together.
Okay. So I think that my saying that is
clearer than if I were to write it out.
Yeah. Do you not get like big issues
from double counting them like the left
side because you're supposed to make the
kernelism?
>> Yeah. Okay. Okay. So, this is a
homorphism but with a kernel. Um, let's
write it out and make sure that this is
this actually is okay. Um, I'm going to
put the proofs on this board so that
eventually we'll just have this list of
lemas that will be handy.
Okay.
Um, okay. So, here's how I like to think
about the proof. I'm going to think of f
as a sum over n1 of a delta function at
n1 weighted by f of n1.
And I can do the same with G
sum over n2 delta function of n2 g of 2.
What happens when I take their
convolution?
[Music]
Uh the multiplicative convolution is the
sum over n1 and n2. I have a delta
function at n1 n2 weighted by f of n1 g
of n2.
Okay, let's check that this is the same
definition as before. So if I want to
evaluate this at a point n, um, well,
when I evaluate this at n, it only
appears if n1 * n2 is n. So I'm summing
over pairs n1 * n2 that multiply to n.
I'm summing up f of n1, g of n2.
Does this look okay to people? Let me
let me maybe let me add you know when I
write um
delta n1 that's a function of n and it
means it's one if n is equal to n1 and
it's zero otherwise.
So this this delta function to this
delta is a delta function. So f is this
and g is this and f g is this.
Okay. Um okay so now what is pi qf of a?
It's the sum over n1 of a delta function
at n1 mod q of a f of a1.
So I actually so I like the image of f
and g as some kind of density. So we
think of f as like a description of some
stuff and there's f of n1 stuff located
at n1
and same for g. So what does the
projection do? It just takes the stuff
at n1 and it moves it to n1 modulo q.
And stuff is coming to n1 modulo q from
several different places and it just
adds up.
And what does convolution do? It takes
every bit of stuff here and every bit of
stuff here.
It takes a bit that's at n1 here and a
bit that's n2 there. Takes those uh two
bits and it makes a new bit at n1* n2.
And the weight of the new bit is the
product and there may be several new
bits arriving at the same place and we
add them up.
Okay, so that's what the projection
does. Um okay so now if I take the
projection of f convolved with the
projection of g at a it's the sum over
n1 and n2 the delta function uh uh n1 *
n2
mod q of a f of n1 g of n2
and then that's the same
as um
um that's this that so then that's the
same as pi q of fval
yeah so all it boils down to is I have
these these this bit of f and this bit
of g and I could first reduce them each
mod q and then multiply them together or
I could first multiply them together and
then reduce mod q and those are the same
as each other because reduction mod q is
a homorph
okay so that's the first step
Okay, second lema says
so eventually we would like some L
infinity bounds. Um but so far in
projection theory we've mostly seen L2
bounds and they're related to each other
by basically Koshy Schwarz. Um so it
says that if I have f and g on zq
then a multiplicative convolution of
them if I take the l infinity norm on zq
star
that is bounded by
l2 g2
okay so in lema 2 I think it's important
to put this star here that um
multiplication
um
you know so we leave out zero and and we
leave out things the common factor with
Q if you included zero there are a lot
of ways to have a product that makes
zero and I felt a little worried about
how that would go um so that's why we
have this star here let's prove lambda 2
proof of lambda 2
um so if a is in zq star
Then f convolved g of a is going to be
the sum b in zq star.
f of b g of a b inverse.
Why? Well, we're adding up over pairs
that multiply to a.
And since a is in zqst star, a is
invertible. Each of these has to be
invertible. So b had better also be in
zqst star. And so we get this sum.
Okay. And then we use Koshy Schwarz
and we found that by FL2GL2.
Okay. Um there's a small technical issue
uh about ZQ or ZQ star. So we're going
to like break something up into a
constant part and the other part.
Constant part and the high frequency
part. And it's slightly different
whether you do this on ZQ or ZQ star.
This just a minor technical nuisance. Q
is even usually going to be prime. So
I'm just going to be leaving out zero.
But let me just write a lema that says
that this isn't such a big deal. Um so
okay, so a little notation. So suppose I
have a function f on ZQ.
I might be interested in f just on ZQ
star. So I'm going to call that f star.
It's just the just the restriction of f
to
star.
Okay. Now I could split either one of
these up into a constant part plus a
leftover,
but the constants would be slightly
different. So f is f plus f high and f
star is f star plus f high star.
So fnot and f star are constant and the
other pieces have mean zero but in
slightly different sense. So if I add up
fh of a over z mod q I get zero. But if
I add up
[Applause]
f* h over zqst star. Okay, I guess.
Okay,
so I felt like I had to say this to be
kind of honest at some point, but it's
not really a big deal. And lema 3 says
that the
L2 norm of the star part is the uh the
high star part is at at most the L2 norm
of the regular high part. So this one
lives on CQ star and this one lives on
CQ.
Okay. And then the last lema
um says that the high part commutes well
with multiplicative convolution.
So if fstar and g star are on zqst star
um
then
there's going to be a lot of stars in
this formula.
The high part of the convolution
is the convolution of the high parts.
Okay, we could prove all these things if
we feel like it. They're they're not
difficult. Um I think I want to leave it
for now because I've put an excessive
number of details on the board and then
and try to uh step back and have a
bigger picture and then pause and check
it.
Okay, so all of these lemas imply the
following proposition.
[Applause]
Okay, so maybe I have some convolution,
some multiplicative convolution f
and I would like to reduce it mod q for
different q's. So I look at it projected
mod q and then um I'm only going to be
interested in the star part. So I'm I'm
going to look at the I'm going to
restrict it to zq star and I want to
know whether that's almost constant. So
I'll look at the high part of that and I
want to know that that's small
everywhere. This is the kind of estimate
that we are asking about in the bombier
theorem right because our set our set of
primes is morally multiplicative
convolution and I'm taking the set of
primes and reducing it mod q and looking
at the different classes that I have in
zq star and I think that that's going to
be almost constant. So I'm going to
subtract off the constant part and now I
want to know that what's left is very
small everywhere. So that's an L
infinity norm. So the bombierograph
theorem is about estimating this kind of
thing and the proposition says that that
is smaller than um
pi q of f high l2
piq of g high pi oops piq of g high and
l2.
Okay. And it's just it's assembling a
bunch of those lemas.
So um
so the projection of the convolution
high part is the
so
proof uh of proposition
have the
projection of the convolution
restrict it take the high part this is
the projection
star high convolved with the projection
of G star high. So that's lambda 4
high parts and that's
no sorry. So this is sorry this is piq
of f convolved with piq of g
restricted to star high. So that that's
lema one
convolution plays well with projections.
And then lamma 4
says that that's that.
And so now the l infinity norm is
bounded by piq of f* high l2
piq of g star high l2. That's lema 3.
And then that's bounded by or that's
lamma sorry that's lamma 2
and then that's bounded by just
pi q of fi l2
pi q of g pi
and that's lema
Okay. So, let let me summarize a little
bit and then pause to check in. Um
so
so issue that we're dealing with is like
L2 norms versus L infinity norms. So
we're trying to prove something that's
true for every uh moduli class. So it's
an L infinity norm. But our techniques
that come from for analysis and so on
usually tells us about L2 norms. So if
you have a bound like this, it tells you
that pi q of f is pretty evenly
distributed
at most a and you're trying to prove a
bound like this that says that the
projection of this thing is pretty
evenly distributed at every a.
Okay. And the point of this proposition,
it says that if piq of f and piq of g
are pretty evenly distributed just at
most a, then the projection of their
convolution is pretty evenly distributed
at every.
And so that's why being a convolution is
helpful.
Okay,
cool. So, a little pause for questions
and comments.
Okay, cool. So, now let's go on. And
these two things are controlled by the
large civ. The large div tells us that
if f is some function, then this L2 norm
is small for most Q. And so we're going
to write down that bound and see how
small it is. And then we're going to
plug it into this proposition. We'll get
a bound for this.
Okay. So large sip
remember that P M is the set of P prime
P around M.
Okay. And so we proved in class. So and
so we'll always have a function which is
defined on the integers up to n and it
goes to c and we proved in class that if
you take the sum p and pm of um so that
so in class we thought about what
happens if m is smaller than the square
root of n then we got the sum
pi q of f high l2
and that is bounded by n / m * just half
l.
Okay. Um m could be bigger than n to the
half and that will be relevant in in
this story. It's often relevant and the
proof idea is the same but the then it
works out a little bit differently. So
if m is bigger than n to the half then
this same sum is bounded by m * f2.
So this one was in class
and this one is on the homework.
So I' I've posted the homework for for
next week. And the first problem is to
do this mostly as a way of thinking
through how the large civ worked. And
then the second bit is about the Linux
thing about quadratic residues.
Okay. Cool.
Okay. So now we are going to um plug
these things into here.
Um so we get al together I guess I'll
call it a theorem. Um
let's say like this.
So suppose f is a function on n1 up to c
and g is a function on numbers up to n2.
And so if I take their multiplicative
convolution that will be a function on
the integers up to n where n is n1 * n2.
Okay. And then um I can take the sum
p and pm
of
um f convolved with g. I project it mod
Q. I maybe take the high take the star
part. That doesn't matter if you do it
or not, but in our application, we'll do
it. And then subtract off the constant.
Right? So the idea is that this thing
should be pretty close to constant much
of the time. So we look at the
non-constant part.
Okay? And then that is bounded by
there's an expression that's slightly
messy. And then we have FL2
and GL2.
Okay. And the thing that goes in here
when you work it out is um I have to
check
Yeah. When you're defining uh f the
convolution of f and g as a function
like integers up to n like how is that
defined for the the product pair one
times like n
f and g are individually only two right
>> yes yes so you should that's right so
you should imagine f and g being
extended as zero beyond that
>> yeah
So, so the question was how to define in
the definition of this we'll have all
the pairs little n1* little n2 that
multiply to n and it could happen that
little n1 or little n2 are too big to
lie in this in this region and and then
we just set set f to be zero there.
Okay. Um, oh, and sorry. And this is L
infinity. It's not L2.
[Applause]
Okay. Um,
so, so one thing that I
find a little a little difficult about
the proof for teaching the proof is that
it is the formulas are a little bit
complicated.
Um but the idea of this is to just
combine the large civ and this
proposition right. So if you start with
the left hand side and you just apply
this proposition
um
then we get yeah I guess we don't don't
need that. Um we get a sum p and pm
of pi q of f high l2
pi q of g high in l2.
So the proposition just said that this l
infinity norm is bounded by this
product. I copied down the sum.
Um and then this looks a lot like the
input of the large civ. So if I koshy
schwarz it I get the sum
pi q of fi l2^2
to the 12
uh and then the sum
pi q of g pi l2 to the 12
and then I apply the large civ.
So the largest civ gives a bound for
each of these things and I plug it in.
And then what makes it a little bit
messy is that because there are two
cases the bound for this is a sum of two
terms and the bound for this is a sum of
two terms.
So then I multiply that together I get
the sum of two terms times that sum of
two terms.
Okay. Um,
now in the setting of of our main
theorem about primes,
the theorem of Reni and Bombi and
Venograov. Um, the size of f
and the size of g would be around one
where they're defined. And so the L2
norms of f and g
would be around uh around n1 and n2 and
squared would be around n2.
Um so if you plug that all in then we
get our sum l infinity would be bounded
by um
n / m + the square of n1 n plus the
square of n2n
plus
m root n.
Um
and um
uh
and then our our goal
would be that this sum is much smaller
than n. So it's it's good
as long as m is less than n^ the 1/2
minus epsilon. That's where that
condition comes from, the range of Q.
And as long as N1 and N2 are much
smaller than N.
Okay. Um, so in this part, you know, I I
did I I I redid the computation at home
and it's a little bit messy. I did spend
some time trying to think
if there's a way of saying it without
computing to see when when it works well
and when it doesn't work well. Um I have
a couple comments about that. I don't I
don't feel like I know how to see
everything that way yet.
Um so one comment is that it doesn't
work very well if n1 or n2 is almost n
and there's a conceptual reason for
that.
So suppose n_sub_2 was n that means n1
would be one.
So my f is supported just on one and my
g is supported all the way on up to n.
And when I convolve them together f I I
I just get g times the value of f at
one.
So so in that situation there's no
special structure of this function. It's
a it's a totally arbitrary function.
Um and since our this kind of theorem is
not true for arbitrary functions, it
can't work in when n1 and n2 are really
close to n.
Okay.
Um so as long as n1 and n2 are kind of
even, there's there's a meaningful
convolution going on. As long as neither
of them is close to one, neither of them
is close to n, there's a meaningful
convolution structure going on. And in
that setting, these terms are okay.
Um, this term here is okay as long as M
is big. We need M to be M is reasonably
big. We need M to be reasonably big so
that we're actually looking at many
different projections because we're just
looking at one projection. We can never
say anything about it
just using projection theory. Okay. And
here we need M to be not too much bigger
than the square root of N. And the
reason for that is
um so one important case here is when n1
and n2 are equal. So they would both be
the square root of n.
And if m is bigger than the square root
of n m would be bigger than both n1 and
n2.
And when that happens
um the theorem might still be true but
the proof doesn't work very well. You
see if m is bigger than n1 and n2
you know I have this function f that's
defined on the numbers up to n1 and then
I tried projecting at mod q where q is
around m. So q is actually bigger than
n1. So this projection operation is
extremely uninteresting
right I just the the first n1 elements I
copy down and the rest I put zero.
So since that projection operation is
trivial,
no theorem from projection theory is
going to say anything useful here.
Um the um the gain that we're getting is
that if as long as so you know I need
either n1 or n2 to be bigger than m in
order to get off the ground. Once n1 or
n2 is bigger than m say let's say n2 is
bigger than m then when I look at these
projections most of them are almost
constant
that's where the mileage is coming from
so these guys are almost constant these
guys might or might not be almost
constant it's okay either way and then
when I convolve it together the
convolution is almost constant and in a
strong sense it's everywhere almost
constant instead of just most places
almost constant Actually
another kind of visual thing is so so
say this guy is almost constant but not
everywhere. So in most places it's
almost constant but a couple of places
it has a big bump. When I take the this
convolution
then at any gi to evaluate the
convolution at any given point I have to
look at the contribution of this at
every point and so those couple of
places only contribute a little and
mostly I see the contribution of the of
the of the places where this is small.
Okay, so that's what's going on. And
then you do have to do some algebra uh
to see just how much we learned from
that.
Okay, so now let's go back to our
theorem.
All right. And this last part, I'm not
going to do every detail, which even
gets a little bit messier, but I'll just
say the the skeleton, and then we'll
pause.
Okay. So, let's say that s is the primes
uh up to n to the 1/2. And then remember
that um
that
if say n / two is less than p is less
than n or actually just n^ the 1/2 is
less than n is less than n then rs r
relatively prime to s of n is prime. So
we can basically study this function by
studying that function.
And then we also know that relatively
prime s of n is one convolved with dp1
convolved with dpr and these are all
multiplicative convolutions.
So if I want to make this this whole
thing is is like a ton of multiplicative
convolutions. But if I just want to see
two of them then I could say it's this
guy convolved with that guy.
Okay. Now this function as written it
goes on forever and this function goes
on forever but I only want to evaluate
this up to capital n. So
um you know
this guy at n1 and this guy at n2 will
only after they they come together in
the convolution they'll only be relevant
if n1 * n2 is less than capital n. So
what I'll do is I'll write this as a sum
on i1 of f times the characteristic
function of i1. So I'll just divide up
the numbers into some intervals
and I'm going to convolve that with a
sum over i2 of g characteristic function
of i2
and I can open up the parenthesis. It's
the sum i1 and i2 of f i1 f i1 convolved
with g i2.
Okay.
Um
and now if I only want to capture this
up to capital N. So let me say that N1
is the maximum of I1 and N2 is the
maximum of I2.
Um
so for little n less than or equal to
capital n rps of n will be the sum over
i1 i2 of uh f characteristic function of
i1 convolved with g characteristic
function of i2
and here I can assume that n1 * n2 is
less than around n
uh because otherwise the the product of
these two maybe I should make this the
minimum.
Yeah, because otherwise the product of
these two intervals will be bigger than
capital n. So it won't have any
influence here.
Okay. Um
and um so then for each of these we
apply the theorem
[Applause]
theorem a that theorem there and it
tells me that when I reduce these things
mod q for most q's the non-constant part
is small in l infinity
okay so this works for most of the terms
that works as long as n1 and n2 are much
bigger than one and much less than n.
But it could happen a part a piece of
this would be this guy
with i2 very close to one or even just
the point one convolved with that guy
that's in there too. How do you deal
with that? Well, this function f is
itself a big convolution.
So um so then I can take f and I split
it up and I keep going.
All right.
So if n1 is almost n and n2 is almost
one use f is f_sub_1 convolved with
f_sub_2.
So this part gets a little bit messy.
Um and um
uh to be honest, I'm not positive
whether this exact thing works. This is
a possible project. Um the what what you
what so what I read in analytic number
theory books is a slightly fancier way
of taking this function characteristic
function of prime numbers and uh writing
it as in terms of some multiplicative
convolutions. And for the slightly
fancier way, there end up being less
terms here and it it it works out more
cleanly, but it also at least I had a
little bit more trouble motivating it
and seeing how people thought of it. Um
anyway, so I I'm not positive. I think
that this may work in all details or or
or maybe not quite. Maybe it requires
more fidgeting.
Um but nevertheless I think it shows the
main ideas that go into proving the
bombier vineigra theorem.
>> Sorry I'm still a little confused. So
what are those intervals I1 and I2?
>> Yeah what are the intervals I1 and I2?
Um so at f you might first try diatic
intervals.
And um
um
and so mod modular technical details
that's good. Um but actually there's a
little problem with taking diatic
intervals that wherever you stop you'll
get um this function will be exactly the
function that we want up to capital n.
And then it'll go a little bit beyond
capital n and there'll be some stuff
that's uh not exactly this function
anymore. and then it'll die off.
And we'd like to prove that you just
take this function and sharply cut it
off at capital n. We'd like that to be
evenly distributed.
But we have this extra sort of junk at
the end.
And um okay, so that's a problem. And
the solution to that problem is we could
we can greatly reduce the amount of junk
by replacing diatic intervals by
intervals that are somewhat narrower.
Um, if we make i1 and i2 kind of narrow,
then whenever i1 times i2 crosses over
n, it will only cross over a little bit.
So, we'll have only a little bit of
junk.
So, that's who I are.
>> Yeah.
>> Can we recap what properties of RPS we
we used?
>> Yeah. The question was can we recap what
what properties of RPS we used. Okay. So
the first property is that RPS detects
primes and that property is written
here. So S is the primes that are less
than N to the half and on this big
region RPS of N is the same as just
characteristic function of primes tells
us whose prime. Okay. Um but this
function is nicer than this function on
the face of it because it has a second
good property which is that it is a
multiplicative convolution of a whole
bunch of things together.
Um and so we in particular can split it
up like this and we see it has this
multiplicative convolution structure.
I guess another thing that I used
without saying it as clearly as I should
have is that we use that pointwise f and
g are bounded by around one
and that comes about for the following
reason. Pointwise all of these functions
are bounded by by one uh from the
definitions. Um and then if you look at
f at a point n
well there are different ways of
factoring n and so they contribute
different amounts. Um, and there aren't
very many ways to factor a number. And
so, and so f of is pretty small.
Um, and I think that's it. I think
that's all that we used about RPS and
about primes.
Proving things about primes is a funny
business because we don't know that much
about primes. And so, you know, you you
theorem, you know, some something about
the primes, you could ask, well, what
what input about the primes did we put
into this theorem? And there's not that
many different things that we know how
to use as input. Um, anyway, and so for
today, it was this thing.
>> Yeah. in the coaching shores
on water. Do you always know something
or situations?
>> Ah, good. Good. Okay, there's a great
question and I'll there was a specific
question but the the big picture
question was at what steps in this
argument did we lose something? Right?
So, we proved a theorem uh here. It's a
nice theorem but it's not the whole
truth. We put at the beginning the
conjectures of what we believe are true
which are way stronger than this in
several respects.
Therefore, we must have lost some things
in this theorem. Where did we lose them?
Let's think through the proof.
Okay, so this is an equality. The primes
really are this thing. And this thing
really is a convolution. So we haven't
lost anything yet. We can now break the
convolution up into pieces like this. I
don't think we lost too much here. There
there is this very annoying business
about the I1 I2 going over the edge and
having to make I1 and I2 small. So there
there is some loss associated to that
annoying business. So that's one one one
piece of loss. Okay. Then let's just
focus on one of one of these pieces.
Um that piece got fed into theorem A. So
let's switch to ports.
[Applause]
Okay. So now we fed our piece into this
theorem.
Okay,
this theorem is not usually sharp. So f
and g are two particular functions and
for those two functions um probably
something much stronger is true.
Um let's think about where we lost
something.
All right, so we wrote down the left
hand side. So far so good. Then we
applied the proposition
at basically we said this is a
convolution and you can bound the L
infinity norm of the convolution by the
product of the L2 norms by Koshy
Schwarz. This step here is a big loser.
This is I didn't bring my I didn't bring
my red chalk but I would put a big red
star here. Uh this is a big lossy step.
Um
right so so remember that this this guy
is a high part so it has average zero
and this guy has average zero when we
convolve them together there are a lot
of positive and negative signs that
appear usually there will be
cancellation there but our we don't
didn't take advantage of any of that
cancellation we just used the triangle
inequality and so we got this upper
bound that's that's probably very lossy.
So for our particular functions f and g
that step was probably very lossy.
Now this this more general theorem holds
for any functions f and g which is nice.
If you could choose any f and g then for
one particular q that may well have been
correct. You could rig f and g so that
for one particular q this uh koshi
schwarz uh was sharp. But I don't know
how to rig f and g so that for most of
these ps or q's um something like that
happens. It sounds even unlikely to me
that that is true. Um so it's plausible
that without any more input about prime
numbers it's plausible that there's a
much stronger version of this theorem.
Um
but I have no idea how to prove it.
Okay. So that was our big lossy step.
Then we went on to the next step. We did
this koshi schwarz. I don't think this
one is so bad. Um for for this Koshy
Schwarz to be sharp, we just means that
um it would it would be sharp if for the
different PS all these L2 norms were
about the same as each other. I think
that usually happens
and then we applied the large civ um and
the large civ itself is
is usually not lossy in the key in the
key ranges. So this is the really
important loss here and require a big
new idea to do better. Cool. Nice
questions everybody. Um let's let's
break there but I'll also hang out for
office hours if there are more things
that people want to talk about.