All right, thanks D. Yeah, it's it's
really great to be back. It's been a
long time since I've had a chance to
give a talk at MIT and um one thing I
remembered from organizing the Lids
collopium was that we strategically put
the seminar at the end of the day and
you know that was like it's like you're
running the seminar speaker through the
gauntlet during the day. This is the
most like the most endurance testing
approach to seminar design, right? Like
you know I really appreciated that. It
was great meeting a bunch of people
during the day. I had a lot of fun. Um I
I do think it's um RIDs is just in an
incredibly exciting place. So it's like
really fun to see all the stuff that's
going on here. So yeah, I'm very excited
to tell you about this work. Since we're
starting a little bit late, I'm just
going to jump right in. Um the talk is
about experimentation in marketplaces.
Uh one thing I should say though uh is
it's joint work with Hannah Lee who was
a postoc here some of you may have met u
a current PhD student Anushka Morti
who's in MSN in my department and then
Gabriel Winrob who's at the GSB although
uh as of Thursday uh has just left
Stanford and is moving to Chile. Um so
he's a longtime collaborator of mine.
Okay. So um the talk is about
experimentation really under inventory
constraints and the specific example
I'll keep referring to just in terms of
the language I use when I deliver the
talk is inventory constraints in the
context of marketplaces where guests for
example may arrive to a site like Airbnb
and be looking to put listings but
there's a limited inventory of listings.
Um but I just want to point out a couple
of other sort of types of things I've
worked on where I think similar issues
arise. One is in the context of
healthcare clinics where you have many
patients few providers. So those
patients uh uh interact with sort of a
capacity constrained system that's you
know where care is mediated through a
small number of providers. Another one
uh ongoing collaboration with Netflix
that's related to uh congestion that
occurs at exit from their data centers.
Netflix serves like depending on what
part of the country you're the world
you're in somewhere on the order of like
a quarter of the bits on the internet at
various times. And so like there
actually is real congestion in the exits
from their data centers um where you
have competition between the same
streams. So if you randomize viewers in
an experiment, they're actually
competing with each other for scarce
resources. Um so again, like I said,
I'll use the language of marketplaces to
talk about capacity constraints, but I
don't want you to sort of overindex on
marketplaces. I think I'm going to try
to abstract from that a little bit. Um
okay, so what is the talk about? So talk
is about the fact that marketplaces will
commonly use experiments to assess the
value of interventions and so uh you
know typically referred to these things
as AB tests because the tech industry
has a new name for everything. So AB
tests are just randomized controlled
experiments. Um in two-sided marketplace
platforms you know you might ask
questions like what's the impact of
changing the checkout flow? What's the
impact of changing you know the amount
of information I provide? What's the
impact of changing other aspects of the
market design? In all of these cases,
what you're typically asking yourself
is, what do you think would happen if
you rolled the intervention out to the
whole market versus, you know, you
didn't roll the intervention out to the
whole market. So that difference, the
difference between the entire system in
treatment versus the entire system in
control is what's called the global
treatment effect or the global average
treatment effect. And that's what's
called the est demand of interest, the
the target quantity of interest. And so
we're running experiments to try to
estimate this quantity when we have a
new intervention.
Um, so something that's been well
studied at this point, I've got like a
small caricature you may have seen
before actually because these are
Hannah's slides, uh, that these first
few slides uh, date back to Hannah's job
talk. Um, something that's been well
studied up to this point is the fact
that because there's a common inventory
of listings, uh, you have statistical
interference that's created if you
pursue standard estimation techniques in
this setting. So, let me just make that
more concrete because it's a bit of a
vague statement. So imagine a world in
which I have a set of listings and just
two customers in the world. Highly
caricatured world um and I'm testing a
new feature that makes treatment
listings more attractive. Okay. So um
I'll represent that sort of by the idea
that you know these are more attractive
less attractive in global treatment. I
want to estimate what would have
happened if everybody was seeing more
attractive listings. Global control
everybody is seeing like the vanilla
plain listings. Okay, this might be
something like more attractive profile
pictures for the listings or something
like that. So if I randomize customers
to treatment and control, just to keep
it simple, imagine this customer is in
treatment, this one's in control.
There's only two customers.
Randomization is pretty simple here. So
um let's imagine this customer, they'll
see the world as if it's in control. The
two listings they're considering are
these two. They see them as if they're
in control. This customer is in
treatment. They'll see these two
listings as if they're in treatment.
Okay, that's what randomization means.
Now you can you can see kind of that in
a world in which the treatment customer
arrives before the control customer for
example um the booking outcome of the
treatment customer has a direct impact
now on what happens to the control
customer. So for example if the
treatment customer is more likely to
book maybe they book this middle listing
but then that reduces supply to the
control customer which is the textbook
definition of interference because now
the treatment status of one customer is
impacting the outcome of another
customer. Okay. Um, in this case in
particular, you can actually go a bit
further than that. And one thing you can
see is that the treatment customers are
seeing a relatively less competitive
market in the experiment than they would
see in global treatment because they're
seeing fewer customers that are more
likely to book than they would in global
treatment. And the converse is true for
the global control folks. Uh, in global
control, the market is is um is more
Sorry, I think I said this backwards.
This is a more competitive market than
this one for the treatment customers.
This is a less competitive market than
this one for the control customers. And
because of those effects, you actually
overestimate the treatment effect. Okay?
You overestimate the rate at which uh
the treatment customers book. You
underestimate the rate at which they
would book relative to the respective
globals. Would you run this uh like AB
testing on a very small subset of
population? It shouldn't matter. Like
basically this interference effect is
very small. Yeah, that's a good
question. um you know for the purposes
of what I'm talking about here you
should certainly be thinking about
situations where AB tests are being run
at scale even when they're run in small
populations usually they're run in small
populations that are subsets where
interference is a problem so it's for
example uh there are some tests that are
run at 10% at global scale for example
so maybe that's a place where yeah
that's that's legitimate the kinds of
things I'm imagining are something where
yeah I'm running at 10% but 10% is
within a cluster like New Zealand is
often highlighted as like a like a you a
a textbook country that we experiment on
before we roll thing out to the entire
world. There's like old old articles
written about new, you know, Facebook
experiments in New Zealand for this
reason. I think this is a legitimate
point though. I mean, one thing I like
about this space is that uh there's lots
of degrees of freedom. And so pretty
much everything that you guys will ask
me is going to be something that I don't
have a great answer to. I haven't
thought about, you know, thoroughly.
Yeah. Um Okay. So, um I'm not going to
spend a lot of time uh rehashing related
work on on bias. The main thing I'll say
is that most of the emphasis of of
existing work on this topic has been on
um on sort of focusing on either
quantifying the bias that's created or
doing something about it. Okay. Um so
that would range like you know sort of
how large is that bias but also what are
alternative experiment designs I could
use alternative estimators or both
together that I could use to do
something about this bias. Maybe the
point of this talk is actually somewhat
different and it came from a very
concrete issue that arose when I tried
talking about this work with this work
was uh the initial work that Hannah and
I and Gabriel did was together with the
data scientists at Airbnb. And one of
the things that came up when we were
then sort of presenting these results
more broadly um there and elsewhere is
that people were asking the following
question. Well, you're you're showing me
this caricature where the treatment
effect is overestimated. Is that bad?
because if the treatment effect is
overestimated, I'm not getting the sign
wrong. And if I'm not getting the sign
wrong and I kind of care about launching
this thing, is that really that big of a
deal? And I thought that was a really
good question. Like it's a very simple
but compelling question. And I should
have a good answer to that question. Um,
which we didn't at the time. And that
was really the departure point for this
work. I mean, one of the things that
prompted me to think about was just how
would I answer the question, you know,
does interference matter if I want to
make a decision? So that's the title of
the paper and the talk and that's really
what we'll focus on today. The main
takeaway and I want to I want to qualify
this a little bit I'll try to tell you
where the qualifications around this
claim are. But one takeaway is that for
a wide range of treatments interference
can actually be beneficial and you want
to like I think if you hear that type of
comment on a slide you want to take that
in with the right grain of salt. So I'm
not claiming that this first of all I
mean just as a basic thing I'm not
necessarily claiming this undermines my
own research in the area. Okay so that's
important. Um and I'm also just not I I
don't think I'm claiming that work that
we do on interference and debiasing and
alternative designs is a dead end as a
result. That's not really the point. I
think for me actually the more
compelling takeaway is that this this
kind of work makes it pretty clear to me
that you want to be pretty thoughtful
about exactly when you invest the effort
into a debiasing designer estimator. and
I hadn't really appreciated that sort of
distinction before. Um, and so that that
I think is where I'm hoping there's
something compelling. Besides that, I
just found sort of the methological
aspects of some of this work kind of
interesting to do. So hopefully that
that'll come through. Okay. So um brief
outline, the rough way we're going to
follow this is we're going to build a
queuing model that represents a
caricature of the platform and we'll use
the queueing model and instantiate three
different ways for treatment, for
control, and for an experiment. And then
we'll do everything else in that world.
Okay. Okay. So I'll tell you kind of
decision-m we'll follow frequentist
hypothesis testing and then I'll talk to
you about sort of the
implications. All right. So what's the
model? Um essentially as I just said uh
we'll think about two different
inventory constrained systems as
treatment and control and
experimentation is going to be a mixture
of these two in a way that I'll make
precise in a second. Similar models
studied in a in a range of different
papers. I put H and S here because these
are two different lees. So this is
Hannah Lee who I already mentioned and
then this is Schwanging Lee. Um so you
know all of these papers in different
ways use uh use sort of these kind of
stateful queuing models underneath
models of experimentation. I hope people
here are familiar with this pair of
papers by Vivc Fryas Tani Pang Andy Jang
and few others. Really really nice work
that I think starts connecting the dots
over to reinforcement learning. And I
think that's a very good sort of toolbox
for us to be thinking about with with
these kinds of problems. Okay, inventory
dynamics. I'll I'll summarize quickly by
saying that the inventory dynamics are
birth death chain. And the only reason
these slides exist is to give a little
bit of notation to that birth death
chain. Okay. So what's the birth death
queuing model? Um customers arrive over
time. They can book listings if one is
available. So crucially it's a birth
death chain with a finite buffer finite
inventory of listings available. The
state over time will be the number of
booked listings of this chain. uh
customers can they they arrive as a
pluson process. Now one thing we do
allow in the base model is that
customers can be heterogeneous and I
want to point out here this is
heterogeneity that's sort of irrelevant
from a math standpoint because I can
that better not do that uh that I can I
can aggregate poson processes I still
have a plus on process that's not
interesting the the reason to include
the heterogeneity explicitly is just as
a modeling point that heterogeneity
among customers that's unobservable to
the platform is allowed as a matter of
like the conclusion that I'm drawing one
thing that's not part of the model
priori is listing heterogeneity and I'll
return to that hopefully I'll have a
minute to spend on that at the end of
the talk before I before I wrap up.
Okay. Um now the overall arrival rate is
denoted lambda which is just a sum over
these different
types and then like I said I have a
fixed capacity of listings K listings
and that's the total inventory. And so
what's happening over time is customers
book listings which means the available
inventory at any given time is less than
K. It fluctuates over time. That's the
birth death chain, right? Um I make kind
of a few other primitives that I need
are just how do I book and how do
listings become available? Because of a
birth death chain, I need birth rates
and death rates. So where do those come
from? So the birth rate comes from a
booking probability of arriving
customers. So this is the probability
that an arriving customer is books when
there's k minus k listings available or
equivalently little k listings already
booked. And I'd expect that to be
decreasing in the number of available
listings. Okay. Um that's kind of admits
almost every model of interest to us
probably is going to look something like
that. And lambda of K is just the
aggregation of that uh net booking rate
over over um over customers right um so
customers arrive they book and then you
know as you can see like if you think
about the thing I said at the beginning
of the talk because customers arrive and
book that changes the state of the
system as seen by subsequent customers.
So this is in some sense like the
simplest model in which you can easily
see the inter temporal interference
effect that was outlined at the
beginning in that in that like toy model
right simplest stoastic model. Um, okay.
And then the other thing I need is like
a a a rate at which listings become
available again. So that for when K
listings are booked, that'll be tow of
K. And the only thing I assume about
this is that this is also not decreasing
in K. Like one simple example would
would be if every listing is held for an
independent exponential time before
becoming available, then the the tow
rate would just be constant times the
number of booked listings. Okay, but you
know you could have an MM mm1 type model
where it's a constant uh death rate over
time as
well. Okay. Um so number of booked
listings with this kind of definition
then becomes a continuous time birth
desk chain. Okay. Up to this point I'm
not saying anything very deep. I hope uh
if if LID's education today looks
anything like it did when I was here
that should all be standard for for
folks that that are in the room. I hope
um like the simplest Marov chain that
you would see. Okay.
What's that? Dangerous. Oh, no. Don't
tell me that. Don't tell me that. All
right, let me pause for a second. So,
uh, have I said anything that anyone
wants to ask questions about, especially
after saying that, nobody's going to
raise their hand. So, let me summarize
the model so I don't put anyone on the
spot, right? So, the model is I have a
markoff chain whose state is the number
of booked listings. This state moves up
when a customer arrives and books. Okay.
So the one subtlety you have to keep in
mind I think that'll be important when
we define the data is that um I get to
observe all arrivals and the data will
be the booking outcome of customers
which is zero or one. So that's one
sense in which it's different than a
classical birth death you know data
model because I'm also getting data from
customers that don't book that don't
change the state of the system. Okay. Um
but other than that the the state
changes if customers arrive in book uh
that that reduces the number of booked
listings sorry increases the number of
booked listings and then the number of
book listings goes down by one every
time a listing becomes available again.
The rates of that happening are lambda
of K and toao of K. That's the model.
And what is the treatment? Okay, good.
So, I'm getting there. Haven't gotten
there yet. So, right now, this would be
like two instantiations for treatment
and control. Um, the treatment is going
to be on the booking probabilities,
right? So, uh what I'm imagining is that
I have two different systems that change
the booking probabilities. And I'm going
to use subscript one and zero to denote
treatment and control. Lambda 1 of K is
the booking rate in state K in the
treatment system. Lambda zero of K is
the booking rate in the is the arrival
rate in the control system. So if I
normalize by lambda then these are the
steady state average booking
probabilities. And kind of the
interesting thing from an interference
standpoint to see sort of uh as a matter
of algebra is that treatment changes two
things. There's the direct effect of
changing the rate and the indirect
effect of changing the steady state
distribution. And so the question really
from an inference perspective is can I
estimate both of those two things
together. Estimating the direct effect
is usually the easy thing. The hard
thing is estimating the indirect
effect. Okay. All right. So uh two
slides of of data randomization and
estimation um that are I I think you'll
only need to track the notation on these
these couple of slides. Uh so we run an
experiment with n arriving customers
that I newly randomized to treatment of
control. So y is the booking outcome of
the i customer and um uh the treatment
assignment of a customer you know berni
randomized n1 n0 are used to denote the
number of customers in treatment or
control
okay all right any questions on any of
that notation does that make sense so
first n customers that show up um I'm
going to just you know bully randomize
them over time and then allocate them
now notice that what's happening here is
that means that the effective system
created in the experiment is a mixture
of the two birth dust chains because the
booking rates will be dependent on
whether I got randomized into treatment
or control. Hopefully that's clear. All
right. Um so estimators the estimator of
interest to us in this talk is going to
be not an interesting estimator. It's
the difference in means estimator. So we
just literally take the average booking
in treatment, average booking in control
and the difference of the two. Um the
associated variance estimator that's the
typical thing you learn in stats 101 is
just this like pulled variance uh here
where you know I've got the sample
variance in the treatment group sample
variance in the control group normalized
by the by the sample sizes. And I think
one I want to point a couple things out
on this slide. First of all like why
focus on this? This is by far the most
common way that people form estimates in
industry. Okay. And second, um, it's
interesting to us because there's been a
lot of emphasis on what goes on with
this estimator under interference.
There's actually been not very much
attention paid to what happens to this
estimator. And one interesting thing to
see is that this estimator also has
problems with interference because it
ignores all correlations and obviously
like outcomes are correlated between
customers. So one of our things that
kind of mini problem that arose here was
to understand does interference cause
you know problems for us because this
estimator is also biased and we you know
what's the impact of that. So that was
like a thing that as far as I could tell
hadn't really received much attention um
in the
literature. Um okay and then the last
step is decision- making. So we use in
the same way that these are by far the
most common things that are done in
industry. When I say most common, by the
way, like obviously you may control for
coariantss, right? So there may be like
pre-treatment coariants, things like
that. I'm I'm obviously leaving all of
that complexity out of here. I I think
one could easily start thinking about
models that are more complicated from a
like regression controls perspective,
but it's not changing the fundamental
property that modeling the interference
is not a thing that's usually done with
the naive
estimators. Um, so what do the what does
the decision maker do? They form a t
test. That's the again the most typical
thing or t test statistic. They'll look
at the DM estimator, difference in means
estimator divided by square of the
variance. And then the decision rule is
something like look at your test
statistic and reject it if the magnitude
is large enough. I mean all of these
pages could be taken out of like you
know the first three pages of a a stats
book or something. Yeah. Is there any
general relation between like bias in
the difference in means estimate and any
bias that's in the variance estimate?
That's a great honestly I was wondering
that I don't have an answer to that
question. I think it's a super
interesting question. I'm going to try
to show you at least what we found in in
and um part of that I think one has to
be a little bit careful there because
I'm going to I'm going to split the
problem unsurprisingly because I'm
looking at hypothesis testing. I'll
split it into false positive probability
and power. Um so I'm going to sort of
tell you different things in those two
regimes. uh I don't know if there's sort
of general results on um bias in the
non-null setting and the variance. um we
obtained some interesting there there's
one thing that's not in the talk or the
paper which again I don't think this
should be surprising but I couldn't find
it anywhere which is that intuitively
one should expect the coariance between
successive customers is negative because
if I book then I've reduced inventory so
I should make you less likely to book
and it takes a little bit of work to
show that but that's in fact correct
intuition
um and then because the coariance is
negative one would think that maybe that
would push forward into being able to
say something about the way in which the
variance estimator um the the variance
estimator is biased by missing
correlations. The the issue that we ran
into is that uh that would be true in a
world in which both systems are
identical. So we leverage that for
analyzing false positive probability.
But if the two systems are different
that that effect interacts with the
treatment effect and that we weren't
able to come come up with any nice
expressions. So yeah, I don't have a
good
answer. But that coariance business that
I just mentioned, none of that is in the
talk or the paper. Um, okay. So
returning to the decision rule, the
decision rule is always like reject if
the test statistic is big. Now what does
big mean? The usually the way we think
about big is we fix a desired size,
which is our false positive probability
target that might be like 5%. that then
we do a look up against a normal or a t
table and we end up with a number 1.96
and we reject if it's bigger than 1.96.
Okay. So what's the net output of all of
this? Like what is the decision maker
looking for when we do these kinds of
things? What we're what the decision
maker if if they really believe what's
in a stats book then what they what they
think is happening is if the truth is
that the gte is zero then I should not
reject the null. Right? the the null
being the GTE is zero. And so if the
truth is that the GT is zero, then I
want my the chance that I reject to be
controlled at alpha, which should be no
more than alpha. If the truth is that
the GT is not zero, then I want that to
be as high as possible. Okay? And that's
these two statements. So basically the
two informal goals, and I'll clarify why
they're informal in a second. The two
informal goals are that false positive
probability is controlled at level alpha
and that your statistical power is as
high as possible. It's basically
hypothesis testing is binary
classification and these are the two
goals that I have in binary
classification. Um why is it informal?
It's informal actually because H0 not
true and H0 true are not well-
definfined things to condition on. When
H0 is true, right, what does that mean?
The gte is zero. In my setting, there's
many systems that can give rise to the
same booking rates, booking
probabilities that are different from
each other. And without a distribution
over those systems, like putting this to
the right of the slash doesn't mean
anything. So that's not a well-
definfined event. And more commonly,
this is the case certainly when looking
at alternatives. This is standard,
right? That if I look at power, I have
to talk about power at a specific
alternative, which I did not make
precise here, right? So one of the
things I'm going to first focus on false
positive probability and getting like
ask like try to tell you a little bit
how do we tackle this composite null
problem. So the composite null is the
fact that h0 is this composite of many
possible system pairs that give rise to
a a difference that's zero. Um now
before I do that I just want to say one
thing and then and then pause a second
for
questions. This is a weird
decision-making framework. I think we
should all agree on that. It's like
weird and like very commonplace at the
same time, right? And this is a a thing
I was wondering working on this too.
Like I think there are two motivations
for this kind of work. You know, either
where you want to end up is you want to
come up with a decision-m procedure
that's so unambiguously better that
everyone should stop what they're doing,
like run and trash everything, all the
code on their systems and start over
with what you just came up with. or
you're seeing something that everybody
is doing and the only question, the
scientific question is what is the
implication of what you're doing? In
that world, I'm not spending a lot of
time asking myself whether what they're
doing makes sense. I'm really just
trying to understand the implications of
what they're doing because I got to be
honest with you, I have a lot of trouble
with sort of accepting, you know, null
hypothesis, significance testing as the
right way to make business decisions.
But that's not my call. Like a lot of
people do this every day. So because a
lot of people do it every day as a
matter of science at least understanding
why what the implications are what
they're doing is worth it. I just want
to make that clear to everybody because
I think a common reaction at this point
would be I just don't think that's the
right way to do things. That's fine but
then we should run out and develop this
like alternative world killing strategy
that's way better than what they're
doing right now. And we haven't been
successful at that over 100 years of
trying. So I think that's part of the
problem in industry I feel is getting
people to a place where they understand
the consequences of the decision proc
decision-making procedures they're
using. Um so this something I think I
find very interesting. That's one of the
reasons I got into this work was that I
think there's a lot there um to be able
to take you know for example one thing I
would love to see more of is uh a more
basian perspective to decision-m where
past experiments inform uh you know
allow you to form a prior before you run
your next experiment. That would be a
much more sensible way in my view of
thinking about decision-m but that's not
typical. It's not that doesn't happen
and there's certainly large companies in
particular I think that have done that
but this is still extremely common place
right okay let me pause there for a
second questions on any of the setups so
far okay so birth death chains for
treatment and control experiment is a
mixture of the two I get some data out
and then I use the data form the
difference in means estimator the
variance estimator run a t test and and
then use that to reject the null.
Why do you run a t test? I mean, what
guarantees of
nothing guarante?
Yeah, nothing. That's the whole point of
the talk, right? Is like they don't they
don't have that, but they do other
things. I mean, there's like bootstrap.
There's a million other things that one
can do. Yeah, it's interesting actually.
So, bootstrap is one that I was really
surprised wasn't more commonly used. Um,
I think there's a couple reasons. Most
of them stupid honestly, but they're
important to highlight. Um, so one of
them is that these test results are
typically populated into dashboards that
are continuously accessible. And like
does it need to be that way? I don't
know. That's a different question. But
rerunning Bootstrap at scale for all the
experiments that a company has running
is like something that experimentation
platform teams typically aren't
prioritizing against like you know other
sort of needs. So that's one reason that
I bring up is like the fact that they're
running these and then that raises a
whole host of other issues because now
you've got effectively like sequential
testing happening, right? Another one
that I found somewhat surprising, I
think maybe interesting to some people
in the room, but it isn't certainly not
part of this talk is just the fact that
there's um
um like every team that I've talked
virtually every team I guess not all but
virtually every team I've talked to that
builds experimentation platforms in
companies is a cost center. They really
only exist to serve other business
units. they're not generating any
revenue on their own. And that actually
turns out to have some really important
implications. I think the thing it's
closest to is sort of like the stuff
that Stephen has thought about a little
bit with like principal agent hypothesis
testing where what ends up happening is
that a lot of the statistical
infrastructure they're building is in
response to the demands of data
scientists that have very strong
incentives in play for what they're
asking for. And that creates like an odd
an odd sort of environment in which what
gets built actually is the outcome of a
game that we don't understand very well.
And and uh and so I'm not going to say
any more about that, right? Like to make
sure I finish on time, but I do think
that there there's like deserata maybe
is the best way to say it. There's
deserata in the construction of the
environment that go well beyond what
what we would do as methods people. But
that said, as narrowly as a methods
researcher, that question of like what
what is going on with this choice is
what motivated the talk. Yeah. Okay. So,
let me talk briefly about maybe the one
big assumption that I'm going to make
and then what that gets me and we'll see
how I do on time. Um, hopefully I can
get through most of this. Okay. So, I
already said this that there's many
potential treatments that can yield a
gte of zero. Um, and so one thing that
we do, I think this is maybe I'm going
to try to convince you that this class
of treatments is interesting in its own
right and it has the property that if I
if I know in advance that the treatment
lies in this class and I tell you the GT
is zero, then it collapses the null to
being a point null instead of a
composite null. Now monotinicity, the
the phrase we use is monotonicity. I've
actually in another talk I got feedback
that maybe that's not the right phrase
to use. So I'm open to workshopping
this. But what does monotonicity mean?
Um it basically means that the treatment
is monotone if uh the the sign of the
change of the booking rate is the same
in every state. So roughly speaking in
words what does this mean? That the sign
of the change is is not state dependent
averaged over customer types. So here's
a case where like for example some
customer types may go up some go down.
I'm just saying that on average across
customer types um in each state the sign
of that change is is the same. Uh there
were similar things that were studied
some in an empirical context by Dave
Holtz and then others in sort of more
methods papers here. One of we had uh an
early definition like this in our paper
from 22. Um one I'll call out here is
this paper by folks from Lyft uh where
they were looking at shadow price
adjustments to deal with interference.
They do their analysis under an
assumption like this one about the
treatment. Okay. Um now there's many
examples of treatments that could be
modeled this way. It was funny because
initially like when we started working
on this it was just like a methological
of methological interest to us like what
what is an interesting assumption that
gets that gets to a point null but then
I realized actually you know most things
that you do fall in that class. There's
like some things we do that are
genuinely state dependent but many
things are not. Um so you know
increasing information in introducing
new payment flows changes to the user
interface the vast majority of these are
really like state independent if I think
the sign of that is something and
there's no particular reason to think
that depends on how many things I have
available or certainly not in a first
order way. One of my favorite ones here
a key thing about all of these is that I
also may not know in advance the sign of
the effect. Okay that's important. Um
and so like one of my favorite ones
about this is this Etsy one. Etsy
offsets carbon emissions from shipping
and packaging on this purpose on this
purchase. And that's one where certainly
I think like depending on where you live
in the country. That is like a pro or a
con, you know, that uh that that's
that's what they're doing. So um so I
think I think you know for us it was
interesting to then see that there's a
wide range of interventions that
potentially could fall in this class.
That said, I do want to say for the
purposes of this talk and it's a lids
colloquium that like you know I think
the interesting thing about that is that
kind of what it gives us um from the
perspective of our model is a class of
treatments that's plausible and
interesting and that has a property that
really then makes analysis tractable and
lets us say some interesting stuff.
Okay. So I think it wouldn't be
interesting to say what I'm about to
tell you if it wasn't plausible and it
wouldn't be enough if it was plausible
without any technical
consequence. Um and of course there's
the classic box quote that's mandatory
on any slide like this. All right. So uh
what is a monot what do we get out of
monotonicity? We get that if the
treatment is monotone then the if the
gte is zero. So if you have monotone
treatment and the GT is zero then the
booking rates have to be identical in
the two systems. Um so this is what's uh
sometimes known as the Fiser null or the
Fisher sharp null that the data
generation process under treatment and
control is identical. Okay. Um and one
one thing I just want to point out for
those of you that care about this sort
of thing. One one reason I found this
project fun is that I learned something
about birth death chains that I didn't
know before which is really cool because
they're like again like I said the first
you know one of the first Morov chain
models you learn. So birth death chains
actually have a very nice property which
is called stochastic monotonicity which
is that uh if you if you initialize the
chain in two distributions one of which
stoastically dominates the other that
property is preserved for all time and
you know continuous time analoges of
birth test chains exhibit the same
behavior. This is a very nice very
interesting property and it turns out
for us that's ideal because if you
combine that with monotonicity of
booking probabilities it it sort of
gives you exactly the machinery you need
to get this type of result right so that
was that was kind of nice okay so the
first thing that I want to tell you is
then what do we get as a consequence and
now I can look at false positive
probability but under this restriction
of monotone treatment yeah so um the
assumption
that the time it takes for the uh the
book looking to become reavailable. Ah
that that doesn't change with treatment
doesn't change with the treatment. Yeah.
So one of the reasons that that's the
case in this paper is that we're looking
at randomization on the customer side.
And so it's hard to imagine sort of like
how treatment on the customer side can
then get fed through to changes in just
those rates. it feels like I would need
a much higher state much higher
dimensional state representation where
I'm tracking what type of customer
booked me and that's having an impact on
my and so yeah that's I think one thing
is that I believe that most of what I'm
about to talk about is true even if you
focus on listing randomization where the
listings are what's treated and allow
that type of thing but you would need a
a very different model like so
qualitatively I believe it but it's just
a conjecture I don't I don't have theory
that fills that
Okay. So, uh I'm going to keep one eye
on the time here and I just want to make
sure I'm able to get through the
results. Um but now that we've got all
the setup, the results are a little bit
quicker to present. So, I think a simple
way to think about what I want to tell
you is um I want to talk about false
positive probability and power and I'm
looking at a test statistic that
involves a difference in means estimator
and a variance estimator. And so one way
to think about that is there's I care
about these two quantities under the
null and in a non-null setting. So
that's kind of what I'm going to try to
tell you. Okay. Now under the null, it's
pretty obvious to see that the
difference in means estimator has mean
zero. So that's not that comp. The two
systems are identical. So that's easy.
What surprised us is actually the
variance estimator is unbiased for the
true variance of the difference in means
estimator. And remember that should be
surprising even under the null where the
two systems are identical. At least to
us it was because there's no correlation
included in the difference in means
estimator, sorry, in the variance
estimator. And the proof of it also is a
little fun and cute because it combines
ideas from Fischer and Neon which like
for those of you that know didn't get
along and so it was nice to it was nice
to actually like figure out a way to
like combine sort of some of the
statistical ideas from each of them. And
the rough idea is that we prove this
result actually in a great deal of
generality. it it's sort of for
arbitrary dependent observations. This
is true and the the trick involves first
applying a random permutation to the
data which converts your arbitrary
dependent observations into exchangeable
observations. And what's key is that if
if the you're under the fiser null, the
fisher null can be restated as treatment
is independent of the data
generation. And so if that's the case
and you apply this random permutation,
you haven't changed the distribution of
the test
statistics. So effectively I can assume
without loss of generality that my data
is exchangeable. And once I do that,
Namon has this paper from 1923 where he
proves a variance decomposition under an
assumption of constant causal effect or
constant treatment effect uh at the unit
level. And we can use kind of a variant
of that algebra, elementary algebra to
basically get this unbiasedness of the
variance estimator. So it's like is it
we looked for a while to see if this
exact result was in the literature and
the best of what we could tell it's not
there yet because it again it combines
kind of two odd sets of ideas together.
Usually this exchangeability arises in
the context of permutation testing or
randomization inference and you know
non's sort of variance decomposition
shows up in sort of different places. Um
so anyway, I'd love to hear from anyone
if you've got references to sort of
related things that we should look at.
Um but that that's kind of the key
output is the variance estimator is
unbiased. Now variance estimator is
unbiased. The difference in means
estimator is unbiased. One should expect
that in fact like false positive
probability behaves well and indeed
that's exactly what happens. This I
won't belabor but basically we show that
asmtoically um the test statistic is
normal under the null. And this is
really nice because one of the things
it's telling you is that you you you
don't have to worry about the inflation
of false positive probability. So the
intuition we got from the toy example at
the beginning now we should be leaning
into more because if false positive
probability is controlled and I'm
telling you the treatment effect is
overestimated. I'm feeling pretty good
about myself and the only thing that
could break things now is if the
variance is poor and so we'll talk about
that. Um just one note here. One thing
again that I couldn't find in the
literature is that um there's sort of an
interesting thing going on here is that
we have marovian data and we're
analyzing a central limit theorem for
the difference in means estimator and I
couldn't find that result either because
central limit theorem for the difference
in means estimator. It was interesting
talking to Stefan actually. He just
finished a very nice causal inference
book, Stfan Wagger. And in the beginning
of that book, there's a proof of the CLT
for the difference in means estimator
under IID data. But even he had trouble
finding that proof, you know, in it's
not the proof isn't hard. It uses
elementary techniques, but it's just
surprising. I think some of these like
basic instruments are things that are
not available in textbook form, which is
mostly an ad that Stfan's causal
inference book is amazing. So you should
definitely look at that if you haven't
already. All right. So okay so that's
false positive probability we talk about
power. Now I've kind of already given
you a hint of this type of result that
the treatment effect is overestimated
when we have and and the generalization
of the toy example at the beginning is
under monotone treatment. So if the
treatment's monotone in this way I
described then you you indeed get this
result that the that the uh treatment
effect is upward biased the estimate is
upward biased. Um uh one thing I guess
that I'll just say here is that that
type of result there's some similar
things in meanfield settings. What's
nice for us is that we can use that same
stocastic monotonicity to prove this in
finite samples that finite sample bias.
Um and exactly for the intuitive reason
that I described treatment is
overestimated and control is
underestimated. I'm glossing over some
things that I think are important
technically but not in the talk which is
it matters what the initial distribution
is for example. So you have to
initialize if you think about the
distributions as living in this lattice
of determined by first order stochcastic
dominance you have to initialize it a
distribution that's between the
treatment and control steadyst state
distributions. Uh so you can't you can't
sort of arbitrarily uh prove such a
thing but you know we thought for the
paper I think what we put in is an
assumption that the initial distribution
is the control steady state distribution
sort of imagining you you know start
from control and run the experiment or
something. Okay, so that leaves just the
variance. And so what I've shown you so
far is that the treatment effect is
being overestimated. Now, overestimated
relative to what? Relative to the truth.
So one way to think about that is if I
had an unbiased estimator, then the
numerator of a test statistic using the
difference in means estimator is larger
on average than the numerator of an
unbiased estimator. Okay, so that's sort
of that first statement. Now I've got
the variance is this naive variance
estimator that I wrote down. What
variance do I want to compare against if
I want to look at an unbiased estimation
strategy? Well, one thing we imagine is
like suppose the decision maker
alternatively had access to an unbiased
estimator and had access to the correct
variance for that unbiased estimator.
Okay. So then you know what what we
imagine then is they could form a
different test statistic and use that
instead. And you know I think for us
sort of like all signs were pointing in
the direction this has to be terrible
and indeed it is. And the question was
just how do you get there and that was
when um we came across this paper by
Vive uh the first paper and in that
paper one of the things they do is they
prove a chrome lower bound which is
actually interesting to me. Um I had a
paper from from uh Nerfs a couple years
before that that had a nonparametric
maximum likelihood estimator for Marov
chain um experiments that actually
exactly matches the career lower bound
which makes sense like that we you know
that that should have been the career uh
sort of variance um achieving
estimator. Um so what they do is they
basically say okay you know in the worst
case like we can construct an example of
a birth death chain where unbiased
estimation has the property that the
variance will blow up exponentially in
the size of the state space. So if you
look they essentially construct a
sequence of birth death chains which
have the property that if you had an
unbiased estimator then the variance of
that estimator is going to blow up
exponentially in the size of the state
space. But their system is sort of
tailorade to get that behavior. And
unfortunately, one of the things that
one needs to note is that there also
exist examples of systems with larger
and larger state space where that
doesn't happen. And so for us, like what
we wanted to show is that that's a
generic phenomenon. And so what we do in
the paper is that we consider any
sequence of moni of you know systems
essentially pairs of control and
treatment systems with um the the sort
of systems approaching a mean-filled
limit as the size of the state space
goes to infinity. What do I mean by mean
limit? Informally, the way you could
think about this is that if I have the
size of the state space going to
infinity, then what I'm asking is that
the booking probability curves and the
the the death rate curves approach an
appropriate limit approach functional
limits as as the state space grows to
infinity. So that seemed like a pretty
benign assumption and and from our
perspective that feels like a pretty
generic result that the exponential
growth of the variance is unavoidable. I
also want to say like that exponential
growth and and by the way by as it's not
hard to see this but because the booking
outcomes are binary the naive variance
estimator is clearly bounded by a
constant and so you have this like
exponential gap in the variance and the
numerator is overestimated so one would
expect yes that like your power is much
better using the naive strategy over any
unbiased strategy. Um so let me just
first show you this is like one curve
I'm actually not going to spend a lot of
time on this graph. This is one example
of like particular parameters where the
power the power this is the log of the
false negative probability. So false
negative probability is one minus power.
So you want this to be small and you can
see like the gap is enormous already
even in this example at like k equals
70. Now our treatment effect here was
like 0.02 in the booking probability. I
I think putting all that aside, it it's
an extreme result like this exponential
growth with the size of the state space
says it's just sort of so good it almost
wouldn't have mattered actually if you
were overestimating the treatment
effect. So I want to be clear what the
main takeaway is here. The main thing
we're trying to say is that relative to
being unbiased, you're overestimating
the numerator and you have a massive gap
in the
denominator in your favor. That's
probably not what you would do if you
were debiasing. If you were debiasing,
what you would try to do is remove some
bias, but like most things you would do
that do that will introduce some
variance. And so like one example of
this is the DQ estimator from Vake.
That's a much more plausible thing to do
than to be fully unbiased. And that has
a pretty favorable bias variance
behavior relatively speaking if your
interest really was in debiasing. But
even that has the property that you know
the naive variance estim the naive uh uh
treatment effect estimate will be larger
and the variance will be smaller. Right?
So sort of like I think what I'm trying
to say is this is the most extreme case
of the bias variance trade-off and both
the numerator and denominator are
working in your favor if you're using
the naive sort of test statistic in
increasing your power. Right? So what
are the takeaways? Like if the
treatments are monotone and the decision
maker uses a naive test, your false
positive pro probability is controlled
correctly and your statistical power is
like much higher than it would be with
any unbiased approach. So this is what I
meant at the beginning of the talk when
I said you're strictly better off not
debiasing. Just to drive home again,
reducing bias tends to increase
variance. Not always. It's a bias
variance decomposition, not a trade-off.
So you know, maybe you do something that
actually gets you both. But in general,
this would be the case for most of the
proposals in the literature. And so most
lowbias estimators probably still are
going to fall on the wrong side of this
boundary. So I don't think that my point
is I don't think that's the right way to
think about how am I going to do better.
Like somehow I'm going to evade this by
coming up with a slightly lower bias
estimator that actually gives me good
enough variance and I'm better off. I
don't think that's the right way. I
think the right way is to focus on
monotonicity. Like what's the role of
monotonicity? Okay. And here it's
important to know that if you get
outside the monotone world things can be
arbitrarily
bad. Okay. So in particular think and
and getting outside the monotone world
is also not that hard because you could
imagine something like I choose to do
this like price intervention where
whether I raise or lower prices depends
on how much inventory is available. So
maybe when there's not a lot of
inventory available I'm going to raise
prices. When there's a lot available
I'll lower prices. Now that's clearly
state dependent. And using interventions
like that in the paper, we show that the
absolute worst case. In fact, there are
treatments where the true GTE is zero,
but your false positive probability
approach is one. And that's basically
because of the bias and the difference
in means estimator. There's also
treatments where the true GT is non
zero, but your false positive your
power, sorry, stays very low. And that's
because essentially because your naive
estimator maintains a GTE that's an
estimate that's around zero. So your
power never really grows. Okay. So
things can be arbitrarily bad which
obviously prompts the question sort of
how state dependent is my treatment. And
that's the sense in which I was saying
earlier. I think a key takeaway from the
work for me is you know as you're
thinking as as a platform thinks about
the value of debiasing. A lot of that
comes down to the extent to which you
think this type of state dependence is
really a primary driver of of the
treatment effect. and that that's sort
of that would be at least one reason
that the takeaways in this talk are not
the right ones for for a platform. A
couple of quick comments on
modifications. Um I won't say a lot
about this. If listings are
heterogeneous, the stochcastic
monotonicity properties of birth death
chains no longer apply. So you need and
and basically the issue there is that
you need some substitution pattern
across different types of listings. In
that case you have a multi-dimensional
queuing system. And so for that you know
we um we uh um um sort of rely on a
multinnomial loit choice model that we
introduced in an earlier paper in 22 and
look at appropriate def definition of
monotonicity and the meanfield limit um
then sort of we're able to get some
related results to what I've already
shown you in the talk in that setting.
And so our conjecture is that we end up
with sort of a similar power result and
we're able to show that one does
actually have correct control of false
positive probability in that setting. Um
this is a simulation that kind of
demonstrates similar behavior in that
setting. Um another interesting thing is
that uh we can accommodate some types of
non-stationerity and that's because the
stoastic monity of a birth death chain
holds at every time point. So the birth
death chain itself could have some
variation in the parameters over time
but you still have stochastic
monotonicity. So there's like an easy
ability to incorporate some
non-stationerity into the result. Um but
you have to be careful about what the
estim is there. So the estim of interest
or of that that you can say something
about there is the insample estimate the
estimated during the time horizon of the
experiment. All right. And then finally
um what about other goals? So, you know,
I think it's clear that this isn't sort
of all that goes on in decision- making.
And I think like the two big things I'll
highlight. One of them is that often
when we're making a choice to launch or
not launch something, we're also
thinking implicitly about the cost of
that thing or maybe even explicitly,
which means then we really care about
the treatment effect estimate. then then
it's not the case that you're just
seeing is it different from zero because
if you're looking is it above C then you
know you've got to think about what
what's the cost what's the treatment
effect relative to the cost and then the
other one I think is that um uh you know
there are other metrics of interest
which don't obey this inflation effect
the one one that's I think primary in a
lot of work that we've done is thinking
about profit or revenue when you change
prices up demand moves down and uh
because of that effect. Um, it's
possible that you get the sign wrong
because of of the same kind of
interference phenomenon. And so when
you're getting the sign wrong now, you
can't rely on the same types of claims
I'm making in this talk. So I think
that's another case where the decision-m
framework has other issues, but it won't
fall in the class of what I've talked
about.
Um, so you know, I think to summarize
sort of our our takeaway is one that to
anyone who like takes the whole pipeline
view or the statistical decision theory
view of statistics isn't surprising,
which is that you should start by being
clear about what your goals are and then
use the goals and like the intervent
your knowledge of the intervention to
inform exactly what you do. And I I
think it is sort of useful at least to
sit back. Maybe one of the things for me
that came out of this was that blindly
thinking about correcting interference
is not the right thing. Like you really
want interference correction to be a
targeted methodological goal that
focuses on the the sort of nature of the
intervention and the desired sort of
decision-making goal to motivate why
you're doing that, right? And that
hasn't been something that I certainly
prioritized up until uh doing this work.
Um so hopefully kind of the takeaways
make sense. If there's any questions,
I'm happy to take them. I know it's
already five. Um, so let me stop there.
[Applause]