Ready to learn some uh AI and software
engineering today? Good. Uh my name is
Jim Flynn. I am a program director here
at MIT corporate relations and I want to
welcome everyone to the MIT AI in
software engineering forum. Since uh
this forum is being sponsored by MIT
corporate relations, I'm just going to
take a couple of minutes to talk about
the program that we have here and then
we'll kick it off.
If you hang around campus enough, you'll
hear the term men's at Manis and uh that
is the MIT motto. And what that means is
mind in
hand. And uh what we're trying to
emphasize with that is that we not only
focus on the accumulation of knowledge
but the practical applications of it.
And that spirit infuses a lot of what we
do here. Some MIT students doing things
with their mind in
hand. And uh that's also helped to
create what we call the MIT innovation
ecosystem. Uh a couple of years ago, a
few of our colleagues over at the MIT
Sloan School of Management identified
the key stakeholders that you need in
order to create something like the MIT
innovation ecosystem, the sort of hot
bed of innovation that surrounds that uh
where you are right now in uh Kendall
Square in Cambridge. And uh it not only
is centered around a
university and this is true of other
hotbeds of of uh innovation but also
includes the
entrepreneurs that are come out of that
university. Either they could be
students or people attracted to the area
by the university like faculty members
as well as the risk capital, the venture
capitalists, the investors that fund the
ventures and then uh the co corporate
collaborators or as I like to say the
customers that will buy those
innovations.
uh as a major research university, the
government support that we've
traditionally had here.
So MIT is organized into five schools
and just recently in 2019 we formed
another college that's the Schwarzman
College of Computing and with that was
created actually mostly uh in order to
promote AI and then infuse that into
other disciplines across campus. So at
Schwarzman, you might have a mechanical
engineering professor using generative
AI to create new designs sitting next to
a philosophy professor who's looking at
AI
ethics. In addition, within these five
schools in one college, we have 65
significant lab centers and programs.
And the key takeaway I want you to know
from this slide is that whereas
wonderful things come out of this
ecosystem this uh uh this institute it
is very chaotic uh in a way and that's
part of what the creative process is and
very decentralized. So navigating
through MIT is challenging and that's
why we have jobs here because what we do
at MIT uh in the industrial liaison
program the sponsor of this forum is we
help companies to engage across that
ecosystem.
Uh, I like to say that I could talk
about what my job is here at MIT for two
days or I could sum it up by just saying
matchmaking. So, we try to get the our
corporate partners, our ILP members
engaged with the best place on campus
for them to work with. It requires a
significant knowledge of both MIT and
the company's business.
And uh there are over 200 ILP members.
As you can see, unsurprisingly, we have
a pretty significant presence in North
America, but also we have a pretty large
footprint in East Asia as well as in
Europe and in upand cominging uh of
increasing presence in places like
Southeast Asia, Latin America,
Oceanania.
Now uh the ILP was formed in 1948. So we
are over 75 years old. Makes us one of
the oldest industry engagement programs
around. But about uh I think it was
eight or nine years ago. We realized
that there was a gap and that gap was
that while a lot of innovations that are
happening in our labs today will be
reshaping industry in four or five 10
years from now what a lot of our ILP
members the companies you saw on the
last slide they want to be able to find
things that they could use now so
somebody had the brilliant idea of
saying let's leverage this
entrepreneurial ecosystem that we have
around MIT all the startup ups that we
have in in tremendous
frequency and create the MIT startup
exchange and we can introduce those
companies to our ILP members because
they're taking the innovations that
happened in our labs and they're
creating real products and services that
you could use today. So we have so
there's 800 MIT connected startups.
These are startups that are founded by
MIT faculty in many cases MIT alumni uh
where it could be even a company that
just licensed MIT intellectual property
a patent.
So uh in this slide what I want to do is
emphasize the fact that the ILP for
companies that wish to engage across the
MIT ecosystem. The ILP is the only
industry-f facing program we have at MIT
that covers the entire institute entire
ecosystem. So we don't provide any
research ourselves here that we try to
engage companies with. Our job is solely
to connect you to the most the best
place at MIT for you to engage with. So,
uh I apologize in advance for this slide
because uh one of the things I tried to
do is create one that shows all the
different parts of MIT that are working
on AI uh and put it on one slide. The
problem is that out of those five
schools, one college, 65 labs and
centers, it's really hard to find
somebody that's not working on AI. Uh so
in in just about every one of those
places again it's infused across campus.
Uh but that makes this point that if
your goal is to not simply engage with
one lab but engage across campus and
across the ecosystem uh then the ILP is
a great place for you to go.
So, in just uh wrapping things up here,
I I know that uh uh at least a quote
that's attributed to Charles Darwin is
that it's not only the strongest and the
smartest that species that survive, but
it's the ones that can handle change the
best or the most adaptable in other
words. So, uh probably why human beings
have survived because we are an
adaptable species. So, and and that's
really the point of the ILP is that we
help our ILP members adapt to change.
So, if you are an ILP member and you
want to again leverage your ILP
membership, you should talk to your ILP
program director. Uh that would be
somebody like me or somebody like Jose.
Can uh any of the program directors
raise your hand right now? Okay. if if
if you're not an ILP member or if you
are, you can you could talk to a program
director about the about it. If you're
ILP curious, meaning that you're uh
probably should be an ILP member, uh
then you could talk to us as well. You
can go to our website
ilp.mmit.edu or just send an email to
askpmit and we will help you adapt to
change.