Awesome. Thank you, Manish. Um, yay.
Thanks so much for having me. Thank you
all so much for taking the time to come.
Um, so I am going to give you a talk
that I may or may not have written
yesterday on the train. So, please be
patient with me and kind. Um, we'll see
how much of it I get to and how much of
it I don't. Uh, hold most questions to
the end if you don't mind, but if
there's anything that you don't
understand about what I'm saying, please
let me know during. I'm happy to clarify
things. Um, so yes, I will get right
into it. Um this talk is mostly going to
be about some of the things I've been
thinking about evaluating and thinking
about generative AI harms. Um I come
from as Manish said sort of trained in
algorithmic fairness type um work. Uh
and
um as you guys might know, you know,
when we thought about harm model harms
and fairness in traditional AI systems,
we had sort of a lot more structure in
the way that these models work that
helped us understand both how to maybe
test whether or not something nefarious
was going on, but also um evaluate to
the extent to which that nefarious thing
was going on. So we had you know
structured inputs that we had to get
into some specific um you know uh format
and then we also had an output that we
at least decided upon what it was going
to be right and a lot of that time that
was maybe a binary output. A lot of the
fairness work focused around that and so
we had some ideas about how to kind of
like test for different forms of um you
know model harms. I f focused a lot on
fairness where we were thinking about
disperate treatment or disperate um
influence uh impacts uh along uh
different demographic groups. So we had
um we had definitions like demographic
parity which is you know do you have two
demographic groups for example men and
women uh given opportunities at the same
rate um from a model's decision process
stuff like this right so we had kind of
ways that we could think about the
outputs from our models and uh think
about whether or not they were causing
likely to cause harm or causing harm
right um and then now we have a lot of
generative AI systems uh And uh you put
in kind of whatever you want and you
kind of get out whatever you want. Um
and you don't really have to tell it how
to do what you want it to do. And uh you
can change how it works and what you're
asking it to do at any point while
you're using it. And uh basically
there's like a lot more generality here,
a lot less specificity, right? And so,
um, I think that this has really
impacted the way that, uh, we think
about whether or not a model is causing
harm. And it has really brought about a
paradigm shift and stirred a lot of our
thoughts about how we can think about
whether or not a model is acting in a
harmful way and how to understand um,
how to quantify that harm. So, you know,
what I used to think about a lot and
still think about a lot in traditional
AI systems is how do we define whether
or not a harm is occurring? If I think
about some way that a model might be
hurting someone, how do I measure it?
How do I evaluate that measurement? How
do I mitigate that behavior? And what
legal tools do I have to make sure that
people will mitigate that behavior? Um,
and I think generative AI systems change
the way that we think about a lot of uh
each of these things. So for the fact
that we have such flexible outputs means
that there are new modes of harm that
the model can bring about that maybe are
not fully encapsulated by the ways that
we had thought about model harms before
when we had more structured models. Um
the way because also of those flexible
inputs and outputs evaluation is crazy
as we'll talk about a lot during this
talk as well. There's so much
flexibility that it's hard to understand
whether or not you have a reliable
signal of whether some behavior is
happening or not. um and bias
mitigations for a lot of models where
you don't have access to what's going on
inside for proprietary reasons or just
because it's too expensive to train and
look at yourself. Uh what can you do
besides prompting? I think that's
something that people are trying to
figure out a lot right now as well. Um
and then finally people I think are
really
confused about what laws do and don't
apply to generalized systems and how
they apply. So in this talk I'm going to
mostly talk about these three. I've been
thinking about how to think about model
harms and general AI a lot. And for
anyone who's interested in and wants to
talk to me later, I'm happy to talk
about all four things or different
things about each of these three things.
But generally, this is where my mind's
been at. And I'm going to talk to you
mostly about these three that I've
circled. Um, and in particular, I'm
going to talk to you mostly about a
paper that discusses some technical
pitfalls in generative AI harm
evaluation and how that interacts with
some legal frameworks and how that kind
of makes things uh sometimes more
difficult from a policy and regulation
perspective. Um, so that'll be the
majority of the talk. I'll then talk
very briefly about some uh ongoing work
that I have where I talk about uh some
other legal frameworks that are relevant
to gender AI systems and how they can be
used to um incentivize
companies to prevent harm. And then if I
have time since this is a new talk, uh I
will make a hard left turn and talk
about some other kinds of model harm
that I've been thinking about that have
less to do with the law, at least that
I've thought of so far. Um so hopefully
that sounds good. Um and I'll get
started.
So first I'm going to talk about within
this work um with some collaborators at
Colombia uh some of the technical
pitfalls and legal pensions around
generative AI harm evaluation. And so
first we're going to talk about a little
bit some of the mismatches between the
frameworks that exist and have existed
for preventing decision-making harms uh
in the law and some of the ways that AI
mocks that up a little bit. So, um, one
thing that I think people have been
making a little bit of a halaloo about,
uh, is that the at least the
discrimination law statutes that we use
most for preventing discrimination in
all kinds of decision-m including AI
systems work to prevent discrimination
in allocative decisions. What do I mean
by that? Um I mean you know if I have an
opportunity like a job or I have a loan
the an allocated decision is who is
getting allocated the opportunity who
gets hired who gets the loan right and
if there is a disparity among who is
allocated those decisions that's where
uh traditional anti-discrimination law
in the US at least steps in and says
like hey unless under very specific
circumstances you can't have large
disparities between the uh rate at which
people in different demographic groups
are allocated opportunity. And so um
there are some asterisks there that are
important and deal with a lot of work
that Manish and I have thought about but
uh that's kind of the the basic way
things go. Um and so traditional machine
learning models that had more structured
inputs than outputs fit in well with
this paradigm because if you have a
binary classification result from a
model, you can just say hey this model
would suggest to allocate opportunities
to people at different rates. And so we
can very easily slap on so that some of
those definitions that I showed you guys
earlier and say okay this seems to be
acting in a discriminatory fashion that
works well with the law. If you have
definitive outputs where say you know if
we take a hiring example you have a
resume summary instead of an actual
decision about whether or not someone
gets hired or someone is a good match
for this job then there is at least this
question that comes up that's like uh
can the generative AI model be held
liable for maybe a discriminatory
summary. doesn't seem to really fit in
well with this framework of how
discrimination law has work works in the
US. Does this make sense? This like
distinction between allocative and
generative output. Okay, cool. So, um
TLDDRO no TD will come later. Um so, uh
that's one kind of tension is this this
difference between allocative and
generative kind of outputs from a model
and how that matches up with the
discrimination framework that we have.
Yes. I just want to
>> Yes. is the difference that's passing
through a manager before the decision is
the thing that's making it.
>> Yeah. So like before we could kind of
see directly of a traditional model as
acting in a discriminatory fashion and
that but we could match that up with
this discrimination law frameworks
because we could see directly what the
decisions the model was making and be
like hey this seems to be like leading
to disperate impact right this seems to
be leading to a difference in the way
people of different demographic groups
are treated in a way that is legally
relevant here like as we'll discuss
later you can still check if this
overall process is leading to
disparities, but like
creating kind of legal pressure to make
sure you're specifically debiasing your
gener generative AI model when you can't
really directly test to see if it's
influencing allocation in any kind of
direct way that's um leading to
disparities in terms of like who
actually gets in opportunities makes
this harder to match up to the framework
that we have.
>> So it's not leading the decision and say
okay.
>> Yes. Does that make sense? Okay. Cool.
Cool.
Um, another kind of tension that exists
is that uh there's kind of um a problem
in both directions where the regulations
there are fewer than existed a few
months ago, but the regulations that
still do exist that ask for um AI
evaluation are really vague and
inspecific, which allows for potentially
some gaming. So that kind of just says
like do an evaluation according to some
standardized protocols which as we'll
see later can sometimes lead to um with
a lot of instability can lead to
unrealistic or un um kind of
untrustworthy results. But also at the
same time there's this um problem where
the evaluations that do exist at least
in the academic literature so far are
both unstable and don't really um map to
how models are used in real life. Um, so
this is things like, you know, a lot of
evaluation techniques are based off of
single turn interactions where you just
have one round of conversation with a
model, but if you go later to
multi-turn, this doesn't generalize. And
so both like the specificity in the in
the regulation that exists is not really
enough to make sure or at least to try a
little bit to prevent that the um
valuation that's done won't be gameable.
Also, the evaluation strategies that do
exist don't meet some of the few
requirements that are in the regulation,
which is like please try to make this
similar to your deployment environments.
And I don't think that that's happening.
Um, and then finally, this is a little
bit of a lesser point, but uh the amount
that you can change a gen model as
you're using it in the real world also
um heightens this tension that has
existed in the law for the long a long
time, which is who is responsible for
the discrimination that is caused. It is
the person that is making the tool or is
it the person that is using the tool? So
it is the person is it open AAI that
made the baseline model that's being
used by an employment agency to make
their hiring decision or is it the
employment agency? Um there are lots of
situations where it's mostly the
employment agency and I'm happy to talk
about that um offline about you know
problems around that but there are other
situations where there's a lot of um
this is kind of like an active area of
discussion and the fact that you can
change model so much as you're using it
I think really heightens this question
of like how can you possibly ask a
developer to do enough testing to make
sure that it will work reasonably well
on the ground but also you still need
the developer to do a lot because it's
unclear how to make sure a user
understands how to prevent those kinds
of behaviors. as well. Um, okay. So,
those are kind of some I would say 2.5
tensions that I'm going to talk about
three tensions uh in this first part.
So, the first question coming from that
um tension with discrimination law is
kind of uh are gen systems harder to
regulate due to their non-allocative
outputs like they have these more
flexible outputs that don't clearly
match the discrimination law framework.
Um, and then there's this policy for
deployment relevant evaluations that's
being unmet by current unstable and and
evaluation practices, which I'll talk
about a little bit. And then also
exacerbating this deployer versus
development tension. Um, okay. So,
really quick, no, actually not really
quick, I'll get into kind of talking
about this first tension in some detail.
Um, which I think is really related to
some of the problems with quantifying
harm. So, defining what your harm is in
generative AI systems. Uh and so coming
back to this first sentence that I spoke
about um the traditional discrimination
law apply to the generative outputs that
we get. Uh TLDDR yeah
um I think like
legally if you have a discriminatory
decision-m system you can still check
the end outputs right of whether and who
is getting allocated which decisions.
The thing that becomes more difficult in
terms of regulation is understanding
where that bias is coming from and
preventing it in practice. Right? So
like the law still applies. You still
can't have discrimination in your hiring
practices, in your loan application
practices, in your uh housing
distribution practices, but like you can
see evidence for discrimination at this
stage and then trying to understand
where in this overall decision-making
system the bias is coming from if it's
coming from your generative a model
becomes more difficult. And this is
where the issue of how do we actually
measure harm comes in because when this
becomes harder, it's kind of more
difficult to practically reduce the
discrimination that's going on that
you're still liable for. Does this make
sense? I've seen a bunch of people,
myself included, at times being like,
"Oh my god, maybe it doesn't apply. It
does apply. It does apply. Let's all
remember that it does apply. The law
still applies." Um
so again right when we had uh more
structured output we could be like okay
let's look at the differences in rates
in which people are allocated an
opportunity and now say that we have a
resume summary that's coming out of a
large language model and say that we do
see we we want to understand like how do
I think about evaluating my LLM um
resume summarization model to see if it
might cause harm in a way that's like
legally relevant, Right. Um so
we my my people that I worked with my
lab and I um and our collaborators did
some experiments to think about um how
we would test this. Uh and so just to
kind of run through what the
experimental setup is. Um so this is to
understand whether or not uh this kind
of more flexible generative output was
discriminating against people of
different groups. We created some ré
templates from randomly sampled traits.
We created groups of um like kind of
yeah resumes based off of those
templates which were all the same. We
followed um you know procedures from the
social science literature on adding
names that were tied to stereotypical um
uh cereal names for different
demographic groups to different resume
templates. We then asked generative AI
model to make a summary. I'm sure you
guys have seen stuff like this before.
But then what we did um is that we also
asked a decision maker to make decisions
based off of those ré summaries. So we
have one sort of AI model that's takes
um a resume like we have like maybe five
or six or 10 I don't remember how many
different templates a lot of equivalent
like the exact same resume with
different names from different de
demographic groups. We create a summary
for all of those resumes and then based
off of those summaries, we ask a
different decision maker, a more complex
AI model in this case to make a decision
based off of those summaries. Now,
if you maybe don't think about model
harms all the time like me, uh you would
say, okay, how am I going to think about
trying to understand if these Oh, I'm so
sorry.
The summary does contain the names, but
we did an experiment to make sure that
what the doubt that you have is not
true. So, I will show a slide with that.
I'm pretty sure I can predict your
question. Yeah. Am I right that you're
like, is it coming from the name? Okay.
Okay. Word. Um, okay. Uh, yes. So the
summary contains the name, but we show
based off of an experiment where we
create the summaries without the names
and then add the names on them
afterwards and test the bias of the
decision maker that the bias is not
coming from the decision maker but from
the summary. And I'll show you a graph
of that in a second. Um, okay. So if you
were um you know not obsessed with model
harms like me, maybe you would be like
okay maybe I'm going to test like kind
of decision uh summarization accuracy
across people of different demographic
groups and make sure that the model is
summarizing people like giving at least
the like the same factual information
about all these different people in the
same way. Right? So I I'm going to use a
um a score that's very common in the NLP
literature root score which basically
checks how accurate a summary is. We use
the resumeumés that the summary was
based on as the ground truth. And we see
that um for these different models that
we were testing uh the root score within
each model was not changing too too much
um uh between demographic groups, right?
But the interesting thing is that if you
look at the selection rate difference
and these are on different scales. I'm
so sorry this is 2%, this is 4% and 6%
just so that you all know. um the
selection rate difference in the
downstream decision maker actually did
have a larger difference in the um rate
at which it selected different people
for the eventual interview that it was
being asked to choose between people
for. So if you see in particular based
off of these results maybe you would
have gone with the llama model because
none of them seem to have that big of a
difference in their root score um
root score. uh but if you but these two
models are kind of roughly
interchangeable I would say but from a
selection disparity perspective this is
the maximum selection disparity across
any two demographic groups that we were
testing there actually can be a big
difference right um so what is this
coming from uh right hopefully that was
clear um everyone is people good on this
so far great uh is the unfairness coming
from the hiring manager which I assume
was your question in the back because we
did give people the resume. We did give
the the the resumeé summaries with the
name to the decision maker. Um and the
answer I think is no. Uh because we gave
we created ré summaries without giving
the name and then we attached the names
onto them post talk so that it would be
the same or very similar baseline
summaries and we saw that the hiring
manager did not uh choose people with
very different uh selection rates across
demographic groups. So hopefully that
answers your question. Yeah. Awesome.
Okay. So it was in fact coming from the
summary, right? And so we didn't see it
in the rouge score. Um then the question
kind of here is all right. So by
checking this downstream process, we
know that the harm that we're trying to
prevent this like overall access to
opportunity is this bad thing is
happening. We weren't able to see what
the root score. Um what are what are
some other things that we can do? Right?
So maybe we want to understand how
exactly this discrimination was
occurring. Um, if we look at two résumé
summaries that were based off of the
baseline, the same baseline resume, but
one for a white applicant and one for a
Hispanic applicant, what we basically
see is that there's a lot more kind of
flowery language kind of description
used in the white applicant summary,
which maybe speaks more to her character
for some reason, whereas for the um
Hispanic applicant summary, uh, it's
much more factual, right? And so this
influences the um the sentiment uh and
um LM as a judge things that we did like
rankings, people emotional intelligence
and reliability which might be necessary
qualities for the job. This was we did
all of our um experiments based on a
social work job. Um and so you can kind
of see this is like like you know it's
sneaky, right? This discrimination is
kind of sneaky but you can see how it
would influence a downstream decision
maker. Um, and I think, you know, it's
not a perfect um answer by any means. I
think it's definitely an intermediate
step, but I think one thing that we did
see is that if you um have a suite of
metrics that's more um related to the
downstream task that you're actually
using the large language model for. So
in this case, we had um sentiment,
length because length of a positive
thing, you know, indicates probably more
positive things said about that person.
LM as a judge ranking for emotional
intelligence and reliability. Even
though there hadn't been much of a
difference on RE score between the um
Gemma and the Llama models that seemed
interchangeable, you start to see a
pattern of difference between these two
models where maybe you would have made a
different choice. Right? So I think
TLDDR um it's hard to figure out how
harm is happening from large language
models. But since this paper, something
that I've been more interested in and
have been thinking about a lot more is
kind of how we can do more contextual
evaluations for generative AI systems.
So if I think about where the decision
for this model is going, how can I more
accurately reflect the important parts
of that context in how I'm evaluating
the model? Um, and I guess the other
thing that I'll say is, yeah, it's hard,
but if you're like, I don't know, maybe
building a startup or thinking about how
to make sure that you don't build a
discriminatory AI system, um, make sure
you test the downstream thing that is
the thing that might uh, actually cause
harm in the real world and maybe the
intermediate evaluations are a little
bit less important than the overall
system. Yeah.
>> So, you have this counterfactual
pipeline set up. I'm wondering if this
suggests an end to end thing where you
can say something like from people's
decisions I can back out things that are
associated with their decision making.
So for example, emotional intelligence
is
>> so just from data a bunch of summaries
and a bunch of decisions
>> what would have been important
>> characteristics are associated with
people's decision making and then you
could take that set of metrics and go
back to your factual test and run that
say does the name at the top of the
resume affectual intelligence
five metrics are strongly associated
with decision is that like a viable end
so
>> I think So I would have to maybe think
about a little bit more detail. But I
think that that sounds like the kind of
thing that I would yeah definitely just
prescify a bunch of possible metrics
that could be associated those are the
right ones
>> versus like yeah actually verify. I
think yeah I think that that pipeline
sounds like a good way to go about doing
this definitely. Yeah. Um
okay cool. Any other questions on this
part? Yeah.
um we did several Good point. I'm going
to talk a lot about um evaluation in the
next couple of slides. We did definitely
do that. The appendix of this paper is
very long. I don't have all the figures
up promote, but uh I I think I have the
paper name on one of these slides. I'm
happy to talk to you offline about those
different checks that we did. I do also
know for a fact that we reran the entire
experiment several times and came up
with the same answer because we kept on
forgetting to set speeds and stuff like
this. So, I can also just speak from
experience that we got similar results.
Um,
okay. All right. Um, so that's kind of
like I guess my takeaway from that.
Measuring harms is hard, but I think
contextual evaluations are something
that I'm thinking about moving forward.
Um, okay. Now, we're going to talk about
evaluation instability and related
policy repercussions. So, let's say
you've thought about the kind of harm
you're trying to prevent a lot. You know
what you think is relevant to it and now
you're definitely going to be trying to
prevent it, right? But, so now you have
your measurement, but how are you going
to make sure that that phenomenon is
actually happening or not? Um
so uh then the next kind of case study
that we talk about in this paper has to
do with this method of preventive uh
testing for certain kinds of model harms
which is red teaming. Um I just in case
you guys don't know what red teaming is,
there's basically a um one language
model that is used to come up with kind
of adversarial questions to query a base
model that you're testing the toxicity
of and you basically see the rate at
which you do get a toxic response to
those adversarial questions. So this is
red teaming. Um in the uh end of the
Biden administration where a bunch of
like um executive orders were coming out
about how to prevent harm in AI systems.
Red teaming was mentioned quite a lot.
People were like do red teaming. Red
teaming is amazing. Red teaming all the
time. Um and so I think both it is at
the very least one of the most
well-known bias evaluation techniques
spoken about amongst policy folk. Um and
so uh it was not ideal then uh when we
kind of showed that depending on what
model you chose as your base um your
base model that's querying the uh sorry
which model you choose to query the
model that you are testing for
discrimination. So what model you're
using for your red LM that's coming up
with the potentially toxic questions,
you can get kind of different responses
um from uh that different uh answers
about how discriminatory your model is
and which might be the best model to
pick. So here we were testing for bias
against women. Um so we were asking
potentially uh questions that were
leading to kind of a disrespectful toxic
answer. And the nice thing I guess is
that we did actually see a pattern for a
lot of it. But there was a situation
where um we you could very easily come
up with a reasonable construction of a
um of a uh
measurement of this particular kind of
toxicity harm uh that would show you
that a model that seems to usually not
act super fairly is in fact acting the
best of the three that you're choosing
from. Is that a question
>> in this case rather than just taking the
one answer?
>> That's a good question. I don't know.
I think you could do it either way. I'm
not sure how we did it in this
particular um test. I think that there
are like toxicity classifiers that are
used sometimes to decide that. Um, I
think part of the issue that we were
talking about in this paper is that
while like the general setup of red
teaming is clear, it's like ask toxic
questions, get answers, measure those
responses, how you do each one of those
steps can influence the results. So, I
think that's another area where there is
kind of like a vector of difference of
how you decide to evaluate those model
responses and that could lead to
instability in and of itself as well.
Does that answer your question? Yeah. Um
so, um right, uh it's very easy whether
you were trying to or not to come up
with an answer that would allow you to
deploy a model that is potentially
toxic. Um even if you were either trying
your best to find one that wasn't or
trying to find metrics that would show
you that it is fair when it's not. Um,
and I think you know that this is I'm
sorry this slide is kind of ugly, but I
think that this is based off of the
underlying instability in model
responses to any kind of question, not
just adversarial uh toxic questions. But
I'm sure you guys have seen some papers
on this. This is just a particular
example from one uh piece of work that
I'm working on right now. depending on
exactly how you query your Genai system,
um it will make different decisions
based off of seemingly meaningless
differences in um how you form that
question. Right? So here we had a we
were trying to create an LLM to
give advice about whether or not someone
was likely to have diabetes, I believe.
And so here are all these tabular
features. And depending on what
metaprompt we use to ask the model to
give us the decision of how whether or
not it's likely that someone should go
get checked. Um we can get you know
different answer we can get different
answers um in uh in the models uh
decision-m about whether or not someone
has diabetes for something as seemingly
unrelated as um
exactly how we put the system prompt
together. Right? So I think that that's
where this variability and and red
teaming is and I think a lot of people
have been paying attention to this
instability um instability uh in large
language model outputs based off of
semantic changes in prompt and other
kind of seemingly unrelated things. And
I think the next thing that I'm really
interested in also is why does this
happen and can we find patterns? Can we
find a way of kind of exploring the
space in a meaningful way? Um but in
terms of the policy repercussions of
this instability, one is um this thing
that I call dehacking, which I had a
paper on. Um gosh, I really am so bad at
putting my papers in the bottom corner
of my slides, but I swear there was a
paper on this in fact a few years ago.
uh where you know we notice this even
with traditional AI systems but if you
have an unstable evaluation procedure
and you want to pass some test where a
policy document says make sure you do
some evaluation impact assessment of
your model to make sure that it's not
causing harm to people. If you can just
tweak some parameters to design a test
that says, "Hey, I think that this has
lower has low disparity and is safe to
um deploy. If that evaluation process is
unstable, you can find a way to deploy a
model that might actually be harmful um
even if it doesn't look so in that like
one example that you managed to find."
Right? So, we call this dehacking or uh
discrimination hacking. Um and the fact
that LLM evaluations are even more
unstable than traditional AI systems
means that uh this happens even more
when you have standard AI models. So
that is not great. Um oh I guess that's
the only slide I have about the policy
repercussions about that. But uh oh the
other policy repercussion sorry actually
um is that
so the instability of the model's
decision um the model's output itself is
like kind of one axis of instability
that makes dehacking uh worse. But
another downside of instability that is
exacerbated by how much people can edit
models um can edit models uh as they're
deployed on the ground means that
even if you have a relatively well-made
evaluation set up for your model, um if
people are using that model in
complicated ways, that evaluation might
not generalize to the way that people
are actually using that. And that in
turn can kind of complicate this dynamic
between who is liable for that model's
behavior, the developer versus or the
deployer, right? Um so on the top here I
have some um this is essentially we
repeated the red teaming experiment from
the previous slides, but we did it over
multiple turns of an interaction with an
LLM. So, you know, if we saw that one
model was slightly less discriminatory
than another model um on like a one
round interaction, um this should start
at one, but it starts at zero, I guess,
cuz we're computer scientists. Uh but as
you have more turns of interaction with
the model, which model is the least
discriminatory over interactions with
multiple turns can change, right? And so
people in the world are most often
interacting with large language models
more than just asking a question once.
They might have several follow-ups or
kind of engaged with the model over a
longer time period. And if you're only
kind of like that's that's a reasonable
way to use a model, but that's hard to
develop a test for, right? And so if you
are um you have this added instability
from the way the model is used in
practice being much more unpredictable
but also a lack of predictability leads
to a lack of generalization of your
evaluation outcomes.
And the same problem happens when we
have hyperparameters that are left open
to the user. So this is an example from
an image model. Um I forget which exact
image model this was uh but there's a
guidance scale um which is kind of
similar to temperature for the image
model. Uh temperature being controlling
essentially like how how much
stoasticity you have in a model's
outputs. The guidance scale for an image
model is closer to um how kind of
creative you're letting the model to be
in a way. Uh and so we see if you are
evaluating um how much uh kind of not
safe for work images. Is that me doing
all that jostling?
I hope not. Okay. Um
if you have a uh if you're trying to
evaluate an image model for how many
kind of not safe for work images there
are by demographic groups um of women uh
you know you might at a lower guidance
scale find that you can not perfectly
but somewhat control the disparity among
different racial groups but as you go to
higher guidance scales disparities for
certain groups can really change right
and so these these hyperparameters that
are open to the user can also change the
robustness and the kind of viability in
a sense the the reasonleness of trust in
these evaluation methods as well and
again also um increase the tension
between who's liable for the uh for the
discrimination that's being caused.
Um okay. So um as I kind of said what I
think that this is kind of there are uh
takeaways both for policy people and for
um kind of more computer sciency people.
Um something that I'm interested in
after doing this work is thinking about
ways that we can create more tech
contextualized evaluations. But I guess
contextualized evaluations uh hopefully
and where we don't have to think of it
individually for each context. think it
would be nice to come up with ways of
general ways of creating contextualized
evaluations. Um, and then I guess for
instability issues, what I've been
telling people when like you know
business people come to me asking, well,
what do I do about all of this? I
usually say look for patterns of good
behavior and not just one example. This
isn't new advice, but I think it's even
more important with generative AI
systems. So, perturb your evaluation
setup a bunch of times and make sure
that you see a pattern of good behavior
and not just one go. And then um you
know in order from a research
perspective I think this is kind of a
ripe area. I think that the problem has
been kind of shown but thinking about
how to
understand and navigate why this is
happening in a principled way is
something that I'm really interested in.
Um so lots of work to do. Um okay how am
I doing my time? Great. Um I will now
unless anyone has any questions. Yes.
question
about the students of those
um in some sense like for example we had
TV even
right some redeemers are better than
others like that so is it really
instrument building or is it is you kind
of like is there any hope for example
coming up with if you set your system
problems in this particular way like if
you do certain things you'll end up with
a strong red team or you'll end up with
a strong whatever or do you feel like
there's kind of not really much holding
them back around that they have to do
these sensitivity analys
like I think red teaming in general is
not my favorite evaluation method
potentially um but I think like the to
me it seems like the more basic problem
to figure out and understand how to
navigate is like where the instability
and the baseline just model responses
are coming from and then hopefully you
know there have been some paper that
I've seen recently that show like which
semantic patterns seem to be important
to the model in terms of leading to a
difference in opinion or um or outcome
and so if we can maybe a little bit more
in a more principled manner map the
kinds of changes that seem to be
important to how the model outputs
things that'll give us a clue to at
least at first get a stable answer to
the things that we're asking and then
there's a separate question of making
sure that we're asking the right thing
which is I think more the question of
like the first experiment. So I don't
know if that answers your question, but
I think like first understand like why
we're getting instability and then use
that to make sure that when we're doing
a contextualized evaluation, we're
getting a reasonable response. Yeah,
great question though. Yeah. regard
like the situation is framework
or is that like
>> I will tell you in about two minutes.
Yes. Um any other questions on stuff
before I move on? Maybe real curious
about that. Oh, did I sorry my little
blind? Yes. Go ahead.
It seems to me like part of the problem
is coming up with like a set of
standards and like what is the base
truth for what makes some concept toxic?
So are there any efforts to
>> are there any efforts to sort of catalog
like what makes something toxic to
>> That's a really good question. I think
that uh some companies are trying to
figure out stuff like that. um uh
um and I think that there are large
scale user studies that are being done
by tech companies to try to understand
what's the what's the
line at which some content becomes
toxic. I think that there are for when
you are using a um any kind of model for
a
important decision-making task for
example in employment there is like an
entire area of research called
industrial psychology IOCs that has
thought about what is kind of the right
way to make a decision about whether or
not someone's a good fit for a
particular job everyone has different
thoughts about to what extent
IOCsychology
people have thoughts on that I have my
I'll be happy to tell you offline but
there is research that is has been done
to kind of see you know what do we think
is like a valid way to make this kind of
a decision what do we think is a
reasonable thing to rely on all that
kind of stuff so I think that the answer
would be there are some situations where
people have thought about this in a
careful way and then I think there are
some places where people are starting to
but um I think there yeah there's
interest for stuff like toxicity I know
that there exists the literature for
employment I think it's kind of like a
area by area thing if that makes sense
>> okay I
would probably benefit from like some
sort of standard for like considering
questions.
So
I'm sure we can talk about that offline.
Yeah. Yeah. Um okay. All right. Uh so I
got a question about um other unless
there was another thing here. Other geni
relevant laws. Do you have a question?
No. Sorry. Um okay. Uh so we talked
about discrimination law relevant to
gender AI um and how it still applies
but sometimes not a good fit. Are there
any other legal um frameworks of note
that can help deal with the harms that
happen in these systems because
obviously uh you know not all donated
systems are being used in housing credit
and employment which is where the main
discrimination statutes in the US apply.
Um and uh yes I think so. Um so there is
a um there is a consumer protection law
uh called um mudap um which is unfair,
deceptive or abusive practices. This
comes from a couple of different places
in the law. One is the FTC article 5 um
and then the other is the DoddFrank Act
which is the act that came after the U
2008 financial crisis to make sure that
banks were not doing crazy things. Um
and what this statute basically says is
that it uh wants to prevent unfair,
deceptive or abusive um practices of
consumer products. So it's protecting
consumers from these types of behavior
in products that they have access to. So
what do they think of as unfair? Um it's
an act or practice uh that causes
substantial injury to consumers. um they
can't be reasonably able to avoid this
injury and the injury can't be
outweighed by counterveailing benefits
to consumers or competition. This is
similar to the disparate impact
framework that I talked about earlier,
but it also has some important
differences. I won't go into that too
much. Uh the deceptive prong. So this
this I think is great because it has a
wider coverage than discrimination law,
traditional discrimination law has. So
it could um apply to some journal harms
in a wider range of of products. But I
think something that is really
interesting that I'm going to talk about
for an extra 30 seconds um is this
deceptive prong which is uh that there
is a some kind of there's some kind of
practice that is likely to mislead the
consumer. Uh the consumer has to it has
to be kind of like a reasonable
misconception. Um and you know this this
materiality thing that the fact the
representation is material just usually
means that it needs to be written down
or visible in some way. Yes.
Like in the hierarchy setting the
consumer would be the employer not the
candidate. So I have to show that it's
forming or is it could be other?
>> Um it is usually I the the cases that
I've seen have largely been for the end
consumer but I'm not sure that's a good
question. I don't see why it wouldn't be
able to think of a company as a
consumer. But I'm honestly not familiar.
I don't know. I can't give you a 100%
answer to that question. But certainly
end and um end consumers like us, right?
Um
uh
the abusive prong is also cool. I won't
talk about it as much. Um but yeah, I
know that I've said this twice already,
but the thing one of the things that
makes this cool is that it applies to
all consumer products, which is much
less limited than just housing, credit,
and employment um uh um decision-m
systems. And those laws also have kind
of the way that they're written
sometimes can put really big
restrictions on who is liable for a
discrimination that's caused. So like
for example in the employment setting,
you can only hold an employer or kind of
like a staffing agency liable. And so
this has led to a lot fewer employment
discrimination cases happening in
practice even when we see employment
discrimination related activity from say
a big tech company because they're just
not the kind of entity that has
historically been held liable. Um and so
this leads to a lot of kind of less you
know less action than we might hope for.
Um but this UDAP adoption potentially
could um have a wider reach. The
downside of course is that no one has
really thought to use it for these kinds
of things before. But the bright side is
which I'll talk about on like the
penultimate slide uh is that several a
couple few states Massachusetts, New
Jersey and I think one other have
explicitly said that they are looking to
use the UDAP statute to prevent AI
discrimination. So I think if it hasn't
happened yet, it might happen in the
next couple of months or years. Um so
specific specifically why do I think you
know this unfairness thing I think is a
wider way that we can attack
discrimination in AI systems and genai
systems but what I think it's
particularly interesting um for
generative AI systems is I think that UD
also can be um a tool to prevent harm in
hallucinations. So this deceptive prong
um
if you have say a um if you have say a
uh
chatbot that's on some website say you
have it on some health care website like
an insurance provider or a hospital and
you ask some question like does my
insurance cover this procedure and the
model says yes it does absolutely I'm a
chatbot on your um on your uh on your
insurance providers this website and I'm
going to say yes, it does. But there is
this little uh
message down here that says, "Hey, by
the way, small print, this is generated
by AI and might not be accurate medical
advice or accurate insurance advice,
right?" Um, and so there's very clear
legal precedent that from the UDAP
statute, a what's called a pro-forma
disclaimer, which is something that's
like a generalized disclaimer, um, you
know, that's not changing based off of
the information that's provided to you,
is not enough to, um, to, uh, cure
otherwise messages or practices. So
basically what this what the case law
says is that if the overall vibe of the
information you're getting is that this
is a trustworthy piece of information
which generative AI systems are really
good at doing. They're really good at
giving you information that seems very
plausible but might not be right. a like
state a a small disclaimer that doesn't
like fully change that impression is
definitely not enough to get you out of
this deceptive um deceptive liability
framework. Yeah,
>> statistic words then it might be right.
>> Yeah, that would that would be the case.
Yeah. Yeah, I think you could still make
the case. I think it would be weaker.
Yeah. Um so this is something that I've
been thinking a bunch about. Um feel
free to talk to me about this. this work
is unpublished still. Uh so
be nice. But yes, I'm really excited
about this and I hope I think that um
you know
this uh this um
this is some coverage showing that there
have been state attorneys general that
have specifically called out that they
are willing to use UDAP to prevent
discrimination in AI systems. So I'm
again excited about where this might go
in the next couple of months or years.
Um, and I guess something that I want to
say a little bit more broadly is I know
that this can be a little bit of an uh
trying time uh thinking about preventing
harms and AI systems, but laws still
exist and are still very much being
enforced. Um, here's just a smattering
of some of the state and local laws that
are preventing discrimination in the US.
and again statements about uh state
authorities being poised and ready to
use the uh statutes that they do have
and every state has the UDAP statute uh
to um use the laws that they have to
prevent AI discrimination on the ground.
So not all hope is lost. Don't fret too
much, you know, or at least try not to.
Um, and then I guess one last thing that
I'll say because I think I should
probably be wrapping up soon, um, is
that if anyone wants to talk to me about
it later, um, another just PSA that I
want to have out, uh, that is also
relevant to some work that I'm doing
with, um, Charlotte Burrows and Jenny
Yang, um, uh, who used to be at the
Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
and Pauling Kim, um, who I think we have
some friends of here as well, uh, is do
not, you know, overread into the
executive orders that have come out that
seem to be pushing against um
discrimination law that exists right
now. Uh so in particular, there's a
pretty concerted effort to push back
against disperate impact liability. Uh
and I think two things to remember here.
Um one is that this is just enforcement.
So the law still exists at least for
now. But two, um I can go more into this
if we want to talk offline, but uh the
the case that these executive orders
make uh is basically that um disperate
impact liability uh requires a company
to essentially make a lot of changes to
a decision-m system if there's any
evidence of discrimination of disperate
impact of differences in allocation
rates between different demographic
groups. And that's just factually not
the case. written into the law of
disparate impact is the fact that you
only need to do so if there is no
business necessity that um that
essentially excuses that discrimination
in that particular instance. So I think
that's just something to keep in mind.
One, you know, uh executive orders don't
change the law if you're not, you know,
famili it can change enforcement but not
the law because it's the executive
branch. and to um you know the claims
that are being made are based off of a
very gross and inexcusable misreading of
the law. And I am working on a piece
with um Charlotte, Pauline, and Jenny
about how both, you know, explaining why
not to read into these um executive
orders too much, but also uh making the
case that at least in the case of
employment, um the laws that exist on
the books actually do require you to uh
debias an AI system as you are creating
it. Um I'm happy to talk to um anyone
about this offline, but basically
because employment requires a model to
be valid and that it's making its
decisions in a reasonable way. This
validity requirement actually
necessitates that you uh debias as
you're creating a system. So that's
another strain of work that I'm kind of
excited about, but also just wanted to
have this PSA, you know, um about these
things that are going on. Um so I had a
time permitting piece, but as I might
have expected, I won't be getting to
that. Uh if anyone wants to talk to me
about generative monoculture,
multilingual prompting, feel free to
talk to me offline. Um which is cool and
fun. Uh but with that, I will end. And
if you want to talk to me about any of
these things, uh please don't hesitate
to reach out.