all right let's uh let's get started
today we are going
to start a new part of the course and
introduce really A New Concept that will
guide a lot of what we'll do for the
rest of the
semester um so what we're going to do is
return to our supply and demand
framework but within that framework
we're going use it to turn to talk for
the first time about normative economics
remember positive economics is the way
things are normative economics is the
way things should be we haven't given
you any tools of normative economics yet
we will today so let's start with uh The
Standard supply and demand equilibrium
and what happens when you
shock shocks to demand and Supply we now
know where the demand Supply curves come
from we deal the demand curve from
consumer Theory the supply curve from
producer Theory you should be able to at
your leisure uh if I give you the
Primitives like the utility function and
prices or the production function and
prices and the nature of the market you
should be able to derive demand and
Supply curves so let's start with a
standard Market which is the market for
gas okay so figure 91 has the General
market for gas on the x-axis you have
quantity which is gallons of gas in the
y axis you have price which is dollars
per gallon you've got a demand man curve
which measures the willingness of
consumers to pay for the good so it's
the marginal willingness to pay each
point on that demand curve represents
the amount consumers are willing to pay
for that next unit you have a supply
curve which is the producer's marginal
willingness to supply each point on that
curve represents the producer's
willingness to supply that next unit
okay demand curve slope up I'm sorry
demand curve slope down
because as the price goes up you're less
willing to buy the next unit Supply
curves slope up because as the price
goes up firms are more willing to supply
the next unit okay and equilibrium is
the point where Supply equals demand
where both consumers and producers are
happy at the point P1 q1 consumers are
willing to buy q1 gallons to the price
P1 that's on the demand curve producers
are willing to supply q1 gallons at a
price P1 that's on their supply curve
therefore you're in equilibrium at Point
little
E1 okay that's our basic framework
that's literally going back to the first
lecture we did this graph for Roses
rather than gasoline I've now told you
where those curves come from in the
first lecture we just talked about the
demand Supply framework I've now built
up the perimeters to tell you where
those curves come
from now what I want to ask next next is
what happens if there's shocks in the
demand and Supply framework how does
that affect the equilibrium how does
that affect prices and
quantities so for
example suppose The Taste change
remember what determines the demand
curve is utility function and your
budget constraint utility function is a
representation of your
preferences suppose your preferences
change okay suppose for
example that people suddenly start to
want to drive big cars so you say look I
like having a big car I feel safer on
the road it's better in bad weather I
want to start driving SUVs and minivans
and other big cars okay and that we'll
call that a preference shift so utility
function has changed people have more
preferences or big cars well what does
that do to the market for gas well big
cars are a
complement to gasoline because big cars
more gas so if you want a big car you're
going to use more gas what that means is
that you're going to see a shift
outwards in the demand curve for gas
people want big cars big cars use more
gas the demand curve shifts outwards
from D1 to
D2 okay at any given price of gas
consumers want more because their tastes
are for a bigger car that uses more gas
so so if we imagine for a minute the
price being
unchanged imagine the price stayed at P1
what would happen well at P1 suppliers
are still willing to supply q1 but
consumers now want q1
Prime since they want to drive big cars
if the price of gas is the same they
want more gas the problem is producers
won't produce it so we have what we call
excess demand the difference q1 Prime
and q1 is excess demand consumers want
more
gas than producers are willing to
supply so what happens well the market
equilibrates what happens is you slide
up the supply curve from point E1 to
point
E2 suppliers seeing the excess demand
say hey I can raise prices cuz consumers
suddenly want more gas I can raise
prices consumers as prices rise want a
little less gas because the demand curve
is after all downward sloping and that
continues until you reach Point little
E2 at Point little E2 you are back in
equilibrium because at Point little E2
given the new
taste consumers are happy with Q2
gallons of gas at a price P2 they're
willing to pay more to get more gas
because they want more gas guzzling
cars producers are still in their supply
curve so they're happy as long as
they're in supply curve they're happy so
basically what happens is when there a
shift in demand you instantaneously in a
shift outward in demand you
instantaneously create excess
demand suppliers respond to that by
raising the
price and you eventually shift to new
equilibrium where once again both
parties are happy
okay you can't keep the price constant
because given new consumer taste that
would lead to excess demand for
gas okay questions about
that okay let's do the flip side let's
say that the supply curve shifts imagine
there's suddenly a war in the Middle
East okay and suddenly gas gets much
harder to get the marginal cost of
producing gas goes up for example
because it's more expensive to ship it
from the Middle East to the US or
because for example we can't buy from
Middle East sources anymore and we have
to buy from less efficient higher
minimum average cost sources like the
US so because of that the marginal cost
of producing gas has gone
up the supply curve is the marginal cost
curve above the shutdown point so that
means there is a shift upward and inward
of the supply
curve in other words producers are
saying given the higher marginal cost I
need to get a higher
price to produce any given quantity of
gas so producers are saying look if the
price stays at
P1 I'm only going to produce q1
Prime I'm going to produce the price
stays at P1 I'm not going to produce as
much gas because it's more costly to
produce gas so I'm going to be further
down my curve
well at that point consumers still want
q1 producers only want to produce q1
Prime so what do we have again excess
demand excess demand this time not
coming from a change in preferences but
from a change in the underlying cost of
production so what happens with those
excess demand what in this case you
slide up the demand
curve
consumers knowing that they have extra
Dem man say look we're willing to pay
higher
prices producers say well if you pay
higher prices we're willing to produce
more and you end up at the new
equilibrium little
E2 at little E2 once again both parties
are happy consumers are happy because
they are still getting they're on their
demand curve they're will their marginal
willingness to pay for Q2 gallons is
P2 producers are happy because they're
happy to produce Q2 gallons that at
P2 now you might say to yourself well
gee how can consumers be happy life's
changed well I'm not comparing their
happiness across the two equilibriums
I'm just saying they're equilibrium
we're going to come that's exactly what
we're going to talk about in a little
while which is what has this done to the
well-being of
consumers what I'm talking about now I
shouldn't even use the word happy I
should say in equilibrium consumers are
willing to pay that price to get that
quantity but you should immediately
think gee consumers look like they're
kind of worse off here okay and we're
going to come back to that that's what
what we'll be talk focusing on this
lecture Okay now what's an important
thing to note if you look at figure 92
and
93 in both
cases the price went
up yet in one case quantity went up and
in one case quantity went
down the bottom line is you can't tell
from a price increase alone if there's
been a Supply shift or demand
shift okay this is a lot of what drives
empirical economics you can't just
observe the one feature in the market
and say I tell you what's going to
happen to the two outcomes no you still
observe both price and quantity to tell
me if there was Supply shift or demand
shift
okay now let's ask why do these curve
shift why in general we'll give you lots
of fun examples on tests and problem
sets of Shifting demand and Supply
curves what do they why do curve shift
well why do demand curve shift they
shift fundamentally for four
reasons first your income changes if
People's income change it shifts their
demand
curve
okay the second could be the change in
the price of a compliment good change in
the price of a complement
okay change in the price of a complement
there could also be a change in the
price of a substitute I did a complement
example but you should be able to see
what for example would happen if people
suddenly wanted smaller cars and why
that would lead to the main curve to
shift in the other
direction and then finally as we cover
in our example A change in
preferences okay so those are the
reasons why demand curves can shift
why do supply curve
shift why the supply curve shift are
really just for two simple reasons one
is a change in input
prices and two is a change in
technology so these sorts of outside
outside influences can shift the demand
and Supply
curse in the video that it coveries this
lecture I do a fun
example which is what
happened when Kim
Kardashian who has more more Instagram
followers than there are people in
France plus England at this
point uh decided to post that you could
lose weight by exercising in a corset a
course it is a medieval thing women used
to wear to tighten their waists okay
fortunately couple hundred years ago
women didn't stopped having to wear
those things but Kim Kardashian posted
in fact if you wear a corset while you
exercise you lose weight now in fact
she's
wrong okay there is no evidence that
corset while you exercise you lose
weight but she's an influencer as they
say and immediately there was a surge in
demand for corsets at that time there
was one corset company because they're
medieval okay and that Corsa company
started making gobs and gobs of money
why and because
since demand shifted out they raised
their prices and raised the
quantity and they started making a lot
of profit so that's an example of a
preference shift that shifts demand but
what do you think happened
next I mean later we realized it was a
bad idea but before before that what
happened in the market for corsets
next
yeah what's go ahead there's a price in
increase I said that that's right and
more profits but what happened after
that yeah remember our La last lecture
firms entered when there's profits it
causes entry so suddenly there was a
bunch of corset companies that popped up
and eventually drove the price back down
so much profit be made in the corset
Market they're presumably all bankrupt
now I don't know okay but basically
that's an example of the Dynamics of how
preference change
can change the functioning of a market
the preference change shifted the demand
curve out that led to higher prices
those higher prices led to an increase
in profit for the one manufacturer that
led to more entry because it's a free
entry Market there's low fixed costs in
making corsets that drove the profits
back
down okay questions about that
yeah can you go over the first bull
point for what demand what if it was
demander the fourth one or all of them
the first one is a change in income I'm
sorry change in income income or
preferences changing influences uh
demand
okay so now with that in mind let's talk
about how all this
depends on the shape of demand and
Supply let's talk about how all this
depends on the shapes of demand and
Supply okay
let's once again talk about an inward
shift in Supply like the war in the
Middle East that raises the cost of
producing gas figure 93 shows what
happens with a standard supply
curve with an inward shift in Supply
prices rise quantity
Falls what however if the if demand was
perfectly
inelastic perfectly inelastic demand is
a good where the quanti demand is in
sensitive to price an example we talked
about last time was insulin for
diabetics where you know you're not
going to risk your life over a dollar
here or
there okay if you can afford it I don't
be too glib insulin is very expensive
but if you can afford it you'll you'll
you'll pay for it regardless of the
price that leads to a perfectly
inelastic demand curve for insulin a
vertical demand curve for insulin now
what happens when the supply
shock well Supply shifts from S1 to S2
quantity does not change because
quantity can change because it's in
elastic all that happens is price goes
up so we have a um we have a flat if we
have a perfectly elastic demand curve
remember I talked last time that'd be an
example of something like McDonald's
versus Burger King in that case if there
Supply
shift it doesn't affect the price why
doesn't it affect the price because
remember the perfectly elastic demand
you can't change
price okay you can't change price price
price is fixed because if you charge one
penny less everyone will buy from you
buy one penny more nobody will buy from
you okay so these are the extreme
examples and obviously we have cases in
between okay so that's where the
elasticity of demand comes in as we
think about shifts in the demand and
supply
curve okay so that's just a little
background to the main highlight of
today's lecture which is not the
screaming gorilla but rather uh thinking
about consumer and producer
Surplus as I've said so far in this
lecture we have Focus purely on positive
economics the way things
are How firm how consumers decide for a
given set of price and income how many
cookies to eat how producers decide for
a given set of input prices and a
competitive market demand how many wi
widgets to
produce we've not talked about
how we feel about that the normative
side is that good is that bad in
particular let's say a particular
extreme example we showed in the long
run with a perfectly competitive
market there are zero
profits well how do we feel about that
well on the one hand for consumers
that's a pretty good deal the price is
as low as it possibly can be you are
buying at the lowest possible price
because the Bret producing efficiently
is possible for producers not not such a
good deal they're making zero profits
and maybe that matters maybe we care
about the companies maybe we care about
the companies in America who have to
hire us and give us our jobs maybe we
don't just care about the consumers who
buy the goods so how do we think about
whether that outcome is one we like or
don't like and the answer is we turn to
the tools of what we call
welfare
economics welfare economics now
sometimes people use welfare to refer to
money we give to poor people I'll come
to that later the semester when I say
welfare almost always the semester I
mean it's an economic term for
well-being welfare is the welfare of
society it's the well-being of society
welfare
economics is the normative side of
economics and basically the idea of
welfare economics is to
measure the actual well-being that's
created by different
circumstances now to do so technically
we would measure the change in oodles so
we'd say in the two different outcomes
how do people's udel change but I told
you already utils are
meaningless utility is an ordinal
concept not a cardinal concept so this
sty Economist for a long time how do we
measure well-being when we can't measure
utility until they come up with a very
clever
idea and the clever idea was to use what
we call compensating
variation which basically means instead
of asking how happy or sad I am ask me
how much money I would pay to be that
happy or pay to avoid being that
sad use a concept Economist called
revealed
preference don't try to measure my
preferences get me to tell you what they
are by getting me to reveal the prices I
will pay for different changes in the
environment okay so consider my demand
for my favorite band The
Killers
okay let's say the killers are on tour I
saw them three times their last tour
okay let's say they're on tour and let's
say I get huge utility the first time I
see them a little bit less utility the
second time a little bit less than the
third still very positive but it falls
okay
because you know I've just saw him the
night before or whatever but I have I
have diminishing Marge utility of killer
concerts like with any other good okay
so then you ask me John how much would I
have to pay you to miss a killer
show or alternatively if the tickets are
sold out you can ask me John how much
would you pay me to go to a killer
show okay those are the kind of
questions that reveal my preferences
and in particular they reveal my
consumer
surplus my consumer surplus is the
benefit that a consumer gets from
consuming a good above and beyond the
price they've paid the benefit the
consumer gets from consuming the good
above and beyond the price they've
paid so for example imagine I could get
a ticket to a killer show for $100
if I if my marginal willingness to pay
for that show is exactly
$100 well first of all if my marginal to
pay for that show is $90 what do I do I
say no okay what if my marginal is to
pay is $100 well then I'm indifferent
let's say I say yes let's say it's $100
and one cent so let's say I say yes but
I get no consumer surplus because that
was pretty indifferent between going and
not going but let's say my marginal need
to pay for Killers concert is more
realistically for the first show at
least more like3 or
$400 okay which I'd happily pay to go
see The Killers so they came back around
again okay well then I've derived a huge
Surplus because my marginal link to pay
was $300 but they're only charging me
$100 I have made
Surplus I am better off than if that
opportunity never existed if the ticket
was 100 and I was willing to pay 100
then I'm no better off off for the
killers coming to town I'm indifferent
but the ticket was 100 and I was willing
to pay 300 then I'm better off because I
got to see the killers at $200 less than
I wanted to pay so basically consumer
surplus is measured by my willingness to
pay well economically how do we measure
willingness to pay what how do we
represent that someone raise their hand
and tell me how do you represent
willingness to pay in our model so far
yeah the demand curve we already have a
measure of willingness to
pay so the consumer surplus is simply
the demand
curve above and beyond the price that's
paid so look for example at figure
96 okay suppose that my
demand for concerts is given by the Blue
Line okay I am willing to pay you know
about 500 bucks for the first concert
and so on all the way down I'm willing
to pay $100 for the fifth killer concert
that's probably about right for me okay
so basically what does that mean that
means that the consumer
surplus is the the area above the price
line below the man curve so for example
for that first killer concert I get a
surplus of the
triangle that is a a a base of one and
it it it it goes draw a line from 500
over to the Blue Line the triangle above
that is the Surplus I get from that
first Killer's concert that little
triangle or in other words I'm willing
to pay for that first Killer's concert
more than $500 it's hard because it's
discreet let's say
$500 well that ticket if the ticket's
only
$100 then I make a huge
Surplus for the next concert I'm willing
to pay somewhat less but I still make a
surplus by the time we get to the fifth
concert
I'm
indifferent I'll probably still go
because I'm a Nut but I won't really
I'll be sort of indifferent about it I
won't get any
surplus so the Surplus is what I get
from all those earlier concerts I was
able to go to where the amount I valued
them was above the
price
okay so basically consumer surplus is
how much it's sort of a weird it's a
theoretical concept but an important one
think about any trade you've ever made
any good you've ever
bought you have some underlying
willingness to
pay if your value of that good was below
the woms pay you didn't buy it that's
easy but you probably didn't think about
gee you probably many times in your life
said wow what a great deal I would have
paid a ton for that okay I saw an
awesome concert last night that cost me
50 bucks I would have happily paid twice
that for that concert I got a big
Surplus okay so basically we run this
all the time in our lives
now that questions about that about that
concept
yeah for you is it something that kind
of time that's a great question think of
it right now as your your well-being
that you get from that purchase it's a
measure of utility it's a measure of
your welfare so right now just think of
it as an abstract measure of welfare how
happy you are made that's why I
shouldn't use the word happy before I
should have said equilibrium this is
happy
how happy you are made by getting to
make that purchase so it's the fifth
concert I am not made Happy by buying
it okay but the other ones I am yeah
speak up so folks can hear so do ins
buyers great question we'll come back to
that so let's talk about let's turn from
Individual consumer surplus this is my
individual consumer surplus to Market
consumer surplus in figure
97 okay now we're back to the market for
gas now we have a whole Market we have
the quantity of gas and the price of
gas now let's not think now about each
gallon of gas a person buys let's think
about people lining up on this line
let's think about a simple case where
everyone wants one gallon just to make
life easy everyone wants one gallon of
gas then this line you could do gallons
equal
people okay you could do gallons equal
people and what this says is the first
person the highest demander is willing
to pay a ton for that gallon of
gas but as you go down the demand curve
you get to people who care about gas
less and
less ultimately there's a price of gas
of
$3 I'm gonna say that represents the
1,000th consumer what I'm gonna say is
that person is indifferent between
buying gas for $3 a gallon and walking
or doing their bike or whatever else
they instead or just not going
out what that means is everyone to the
right of person a won't buy gas we knew
that already they're willing to to space
below the price whatever to left the
person a gains welfare they gain
well-being because they got a good
deal
okay and it's really this is our measure
of utility in the real world remember I
said you can't measure utility can't
measure utils well now we're measuring
it I have just given you a measurable
quantity we know how to draw a demand
curve
we know mathematically how to represent
a domain curve you can mathematically
compute the area of this triangle I've
mathematically come to this question
earlier I've mathematically represented
your welfare your well-being because we
can compute this triangle and now I can
make normative statements before I could
only make positive statements because
utils were meaningless now with this
idea of compensating variation consumer
surplus I can make normative statements
I could talk about how well off you
are okay so let's talk about two
applications of this consumer surplus
idea first is what if the price Rises so
for example look at figure 98 imagine
the price of gas Rose from $3 to 350 a
gallon well now what happens two things
happen first of all fewer people want
gas we knew that already we know that if
this price goes up demain curve slop
down so we want fewer people want gas so
now the marginal purchaser the person
room Surplus is zero is the 900th person
and person 901 to 1,000 no longer buy
gas person Beyond a th000 didn't buy gas
anyway so what has happened to consumer
surplus two things have happened first
of all fewer
people are getting the Surplus it used
to be a thousand people got Surplus now
only 900 people
do second of all everyone the this those
900 people are getting less Surplus
because the price has
risen so the there's a loss in consumer
surplus of the entire gray triangle of
the entire gray um uh
polygon
okay the L the
rectangle is the rectangle is the amount
that the first 900 consumers lost they
still buy gas but they're less happy
about it they get less utility from it
not less utility less welfare from it
because the difference their willingness
to pay and price has shrunk the little
triangle represent the Lost consumer
surplus because some people aren't
getting consumer surplus anymore so a
price change causes this last this lost
trapezoid of consumer
surplus through those two
mechanisms
okay now let's come to another question
and the answer is already given here
when is consumer surplus large or small
well that's going to depend critically
on what the elasticity of demand is
going to determine whether the super
Surplus is large or
small okay so let's look for example at
figure
99 here we have two downward sloping
demand
curves but one the curve that um is
further to the right on the x-axis and
further down on the y- axis that curve
is steeper
it is more
elastic so that curve the one that's
further to the right that has intercept
further right on the x-axis we should
label these curves for next time uh
Andrews one and two or something so I
can refer them more easily um the curve
that that curve is more
elastic so let's look consumer surplus
that's provided by each of these two
curves so if you look at the more
elastic curve the consumer surplus is
the area under the
curve okay the the area under the curve
above the price line that's the dark
triangle now as demand gets less
elastic consumer surplus goes up so it's
actually the opposite of the intuition
that this person gave earlier the more
inelastic the more Surplus why or the
more elastic the less Surplus indeed
with perfectly elastic demand there is
no
Surplus why
with per think about the case for last
demand McDonald's versus Burger King
imagine you're totally indifferent it's
trivial to shop between
them why in that case is there no
Surplus
delivered
yeah yeah you're never going to pay more
in equilibrium because the equilibrium
price anybody who charges you one set
more just switch you're always your
price is fixed there's no
Surplus now consider
insulin with insulin
it's all Surplus because your demand is
eventally infinite and the price is some
level so subject to your resources the
demand for insulin is it's huge
Surplus because you've got this entire
infinite rectangle Rising above the
price
line so the size of consumer surplus
will be determined by the elasticity of
demand okay essentially consumer Surplus
will be inversely related to demand
elasticity okay question about
that okay people aren't the only thing
we care about in this economy we care
about firms
too okay so now we turn to the other
side which is producer
Surplus producer Surplus
okay basically producer Surplus is the
flip of the analysis instead of saying
producer we consumers we say the Surplus
there is between their willingness to
pay and the price for producers it's the
difference between their price and their
willingness to
supply if producers get a price above
their marginal cost they make a
surplus okay you could see that for
example in fig
fure uh
910 okay in figure 910 this is an
individual
producer imagine that the price this is
indidual gas producer the price of gas
in the market is three and let's say
that producer at that price wants to
produce 100 gallons okay that is the the
their point of supply curve with a price
of three their marginal supply is
100 well that means that for the first
first 99 units they made
Surplus why because for the first 99
units the price was above their willing
to supply which is what what does supply
curve
represent what is supply curve marginal
cost so for the first 99 units price was
above marginal cost so they made
Surplus now in a perfectly competive of
equilibrium we know marginal cost equals
average
cost so what is that mean this shaded
triangle is can anyone tell what the
Shaded triangle also
represents it's say if the line is
average cost if it's a price line it's
price minus average cost what we call
that profit so in a long run perfectly
competitive equilibrium producers
Surplus is way easier to understand the
consumer surplus not some vague measure
of well-being it's dollars it's profit
literally in a perfectly competitive
long run equilibrium produce Surplus
equals profit now in the short run it's
a little complicated and it's not c as
complicated but roughly speaking okay
there's by and large no harm they can
produce Surplus being profit it's a lot
easier to understand and you can really
put your hands around it unlike consumer
surplus which is harder to sort of
conceive
of okay so likewise if we go to the
market in figure n 911 you see there's a
market supply
curve and this goes back to what I
talked about last time about why in fact
with heterogeneous firms with firms of
different production functions there
might be an upward sloping supply curve
even if there might be an upward sloping
supply curve even in perfect competition
in this case at a price of three there's
a bunch of firms producing The Firm that
produced
there should be a Josh there should be a
big q1 on the x-axis The Firm that
produce big q1 which is where that dash
line hits the x-axis the thir that
produces big q1 that marginal firm earns
zero
profit the price equals a margin cost
equals their minimum average
cost but all the other firms the left
earn profit they're the Pakistan cotton
producers all the other firms that left
are earning profits because the price is
above their marginal cost which is their
average cost
C so if you think about a
market there's profit being made by all
the particularly efficient producers as
long as
demand hits the supply curve at some
point above the first
producer this is profits being made this
is like the example I did with cotton
but instead of a stepwise supply
function it's a constant Supply function
a linear Supply function and what you
see it's the same intuition that there's
a bunch of providers of gas on the on
the very left is the most efficient
provider of gas
their marginal cost is
Epsilon they can produce gas for Epsilon
yet they get $3 a gallon that's all
profit to them $3 minus
Epsilon As you move to the right
marginal cost Rises so profit Falls
until you reach point a for that
producer marginal cost equals average
cost equals three which equals price of
profits or zero so they're indifferent
and no one enters to the right of that
this is a linear representation the
stepwise example we did last
time so consumer surplus is your wellbe
produce Surplus is profits questions
about
that okay now armed with that we can go
on and prove what Paul Samuelson
modestly labeled the first fundamental
theorem of welfare
economics Paul Sam said besid being a
great Economist was was not a humble man
I think his thesis was called something
like econom you know what remember
something like you know discovering
econom inventing econom you know
something like that like he he knew he
was properly proud of what he was doing
and he called this the first fundamental
theorem of wealth economics which is
that
competition
maximizes
welfare competition maximizes welfare
it's a bold statement
that says that the equilibrium we got to
last time in a positive sense we showed
the equilibrium last time is also in a
normative sense the best possible place
we can
be to see that let's go to figure
912 this shows a demand and supply curve
in equilibrium in competitive
equilibrium at Point little
E1 where there's q1 units per year year
being produced at a price of
P1 okay that's the initial
equilibrium you can see and the consumer
surplus in this
example what well somebody tell me what
is consumer use the letters there what
is the consumer surplus at Point E1
someone raise their hand and tell me
what letters represent consumer
surplus yeah R plus v exactly same
person what letters represent producer
Surplus
exactly so producer Surplus is R plus v
so consumer
surplus equals R plus v producer Surplus
equals s+ t plus u okay you can
see that the sum of those
two is
maximized at Point
E1 and we're going to Define
welfare as just the sum of consumer
Surplus plus producer
Surplus Samus said look I I have no
strong feeling about whether she care
more about consumers or producers
producers higher workers we care about
them too let's just use a indifferent
let's just say social welfare is the sum
of the two let's just say that the total
welfare societ is just a surplus
produced on both sides of a
transaction a transaction produces
consumer surplus it produces producer
Surplus We'll add them up and call that
welfare well you could see that concept
we maximized at Point
E1 so let's do a simple example imagine
that you are someone who says that's
ridiculous welfare is always better if
prices are lower these consumers get a
better deal so I'm going to set a price
cap I'm G to say producers cannot charge
more than
P2 a price ceiling of
P2 well what happens
at
P2
producers say well look if you're G to
make if you can only give me P2 I'm only
can produce
Q2 I have to be on my supply
curve I'm willing to supply P2 is Q2 so
I'm will to produce
Q2 okay so the market has Q2 at Price P2
well what happens in that
situation well what happens to consumer
surplus it falls it falls by the amount
V it falls because there are
transactions that make consumers happy
that are not happening it's critical
this is the key thing with welfare
economics for consumers or for both
sides a transaction that produces
Surplus that goes away is welfare
reducing here's a transaction that
produces Surplus consumers got benefits
from going Q2 to q1 they no longer get
them so consumer Surplus is down by the
area
V producer
Surplus is down by two things first of
all producers no longer have
transactions that made them happy they
wanted to sell between Q2 to q1 units
and that gave them a surplus of U that's
gone but that's not
all what also is gone is that now they
lost the area s
but is that gone is s gone what happens
to S
yeah it becomes consumer
surplus s goes away and gets added to
consumer
surplus so what has happened here is two
things first of all by doing this
intervention by setting this price
ceiling we've taken the area s and given
it from producers to to Consumers see
that look at the new consumer surplus
the new consumer surplus is S Plus R so
we've given s to
Consumers that is what we call a
transfer we have
transferred Surplus from one party to
another in this case we've transferred
Surplus which we can measure as dollars
we transfer that amount of dollars s and
take it away from producers give to
Consumers now how do we feel about that
well we're indifferent about that right
because all we care is consumer plus
produc Surplus we don't care about
transfers so the movement of s from one
to the other is irrelevant for total
welfare because welfare is the
sum so transfers are relevant for
welfare if you take something from one
party give it to
another that doesn't matter what matters
is that along the way the and you have
disappeared literally they're
gone we call that dead weight
loss dead weight loss dead weight loss
is the net reduction in welfare from
trades that are not
made when there are trades that would
make both parties better off and they
don't get made that is bad that is a
loss in welfare we are worse off as a
society in this perfectly competitive
market if there are trades that would
make both sides better off and they
don't get
made we are worse
off that is why the competitive
equilibrium maximizes welfare because
every trade people want to make and the
firms are willing to do with them gets
made anything anything else takes away
trades that make both parties better off
and by definition that lowers
welfare a trade that makes both parties
better off or at least makes one party
better off and the other party no worse
off
technically should
happen that raises
welfare
now this is of course a conclusion under
a very particular set of assumptions we
can go back to the very first
lecture under these assumptions we
should let people sell their kidneys on
eBay okay the more person who sells
their kidney is better off the rich
person who buys it and stays alive is
better off that's a transaction made
both parties better off we should let it
happen we discussed in the first lecture
why I might not like that for reasons of
equity or because the market might not
work well well those are all reasons why
the model we've discussed so far breaks
down we're not getting there yet well
we're remember economics I said the
beginning is fundamentally sort of a
right-wing science maybe I didn't say it
maybe I'll say it now for the first time
so fundamentally a right-wing science
science economics starts with the market
knows best it starts with the First
Fundamental welfare
theorem which is that under this under
the set of assumptions of perfect
competition the best thing to do is just
let the market
rip we will come back in a couple
lectures start talking about why those
assumptions might not be true but let's
not jump ahead let's this is our
starting this is our jumping off point
for all of economics
this fundamental theorem is that the
market knows best that welfare is
maximized by just letting the perfectly
competitive market
rip okay that's the key conclusion here
we'll stop now no class on Monday uh and
I'll see yall on Wednesday