okay so using spatial transcriptomics we
can measure 480 genes inside the cells
in these colon tissues but what about
the remaining genes so now let's
introduce a complementary technology to
spatial transcriptomics called single
cell transcriptomics or single cell RNA
sequencing and single cell RNA
sequencing is also a new technology but
it's a little older than spatial
transcriptomics and single cell RNA
sequencing allows us to measure the
expression of all 20,000 genes inside
individual cells so how does this work
uh let's look at the experimental
workflow together so we're going to
start with a solid tissue like the colon
and we're going to take a piece of the
colon and we're going to take that
tissue and we're going to dissociate it
into the individual cells that make up
the tissue so the tissue is being
dissociated into single cells and then
we isolate those single cells meaning we
spatially separate them this often takes
place by placing the cells inside liquid
droplets uh the cells are now isolated
and then we can extract from every
single cell RNA and this is going to
tell us which genes are expressed inside
that single cell now there's a lot of
details here but maybe the most
important detail is this step which is
that we have to dissociate the tissue
and so when we dissociate the tissue
we've lost all spatial information
meaning we don't know in the colon which
cell was next to which cell anymore
because we've broken up the tissue into
individual cells isolated them and taken
out the RNA so that's one really
important thing to uh remember here is
that single cell transcriptomics or
single cell RNA sequencing does not give
you any spatial information and that's
what actually spurred some of the
developments in spatial transcriptomics
which was people wanted to know where
the cells are in the tissue but this is
still a very powerful technology because
we're measuring all 20,000 genes in the
cell so let's finish this up now we have
the RNA that's been extracted from
single cells and we can use an enzyme
from viruses called reverse
transcriptase to make that RNA molecule
into a complimentary DNA molecule DNA is
a much more stable molecule to work with
and we can make many many copies of it
which is what's needed to carry out next
Generation sequencing and in Next
Generation sequencing we read out the
sequence of the DNA and that's a T C's
and G's and once we've read out that
sequence we can go and look up What gene
that sequence came from because as I
said earlier the entirety of the human
genome has been sequenced so we know
where all the genes are in the genome
what their sequences are and to some
extent what those genes do so once we
look up these sequences we can say you
know what Gene was expressed in what
cell so this is the type of data you
would see from a single cell RNA
sequencing experiment where the row are
each of the 20,000 genes in the human
genome and uh the columns are individual
single cells and for each cell I can
tell you how many times I counted a gene
transcript so in cell one for instance I
counted the gene transcript for a tcf7
three times versus in cell three I never
saw it in contrast uh in cell one we
don't see very many copies of epcam the
epithelial cell marker but we see a lot
of copies in cell 3 and so this
generates a very large data set you know
you have 20,000 genes we can look at
10,000 or 100,000 cells at once so you
have millions and millions of entries
here so this is a really really rich
data set so now let me give you an
example of single cell transcriptomics
applied to Uli colitis so this is a
study uh performed by Dr romik Xavier
who is one of the organizers of this
Challenge and he's at Mass General
Hospital and the Bro Institute and in
this study the Xavier group took uh
patients with ulcerative colitis and
took tissue biopsies and prepared each
of those biopsies for single cell
transcriptomics so now every single cell
that comes from this uler of Kida sample
is going to have 20,000 genes expression
measured so every single cell is a
vector of 20,000 measurements and we
have thousands of these cells and here
we're showing these cells projected into
a low-dimensional embedding called TSN
this is a nonlinear dimensional
reduction technique and the idea of this
technique is that if two cells have
similar gene expression in the high
dimensional space then when we show them
in the TS and embedding in two
Dimensions those two cells are going to
be close to one another in that uh
embedding so here we have uh the cells
colored by the cell type and if we look
at this blue cluster here we see that
the genes that are being expressed here
Mark B cells and if we look at the uh
kind of pinkish cluster we see these
genes are uh expressed normal in t-
cells and finally in this green cluster
we see genes that Mark myoid cells so
this is a good way of sort of looking at
single cell data and what you can really
recognize is that we're getting you know
thousands of cells and lots of data
because we're getting 20,000 genes per
cell so this is a really high
dimensional data set and again we're
getting 20,000 genes and not just the
480 genes that you would normally
measure doing a spatial transcriptomics
experiment okay so now let's recap what
you've learned uh these three sections
of lecture two uh the first thing we
talked about is that gene expression
programs are groups of genes that are
expressed together during a biological
process and that they can dramatically
change as we go from Health to disease
so comparing normal colon to ulcer
colitis or normal colon to colorectal
cancer the gene expression programs have
dramatically
changed and then the second thing that
you've been seeing is that there are
many technologies that we can use to
profile and measure human tissues so
we've introduced uh what PA ologists do
which is take tissue and stain with h&
to look at tissue structure we've
introduced the zenium spatial
transcriptomic experiment where we're
able to measure 500 genes and their
locations in space in the tissue and
we've introduced single cell RNA
sequencing or single cell
transcriptomics where we can measure the
expression of 20,000 genes in a Cell
however we lose the spatial information
so I think what you probably appreciate
is that each of these Technologies has
different strengths and weaknesses
and a common approach we take in biology
is to apply multiple Technologies to a
tissue in order to leverage the strength
of each technology and get a more
holistic view of what's happening in the
tissue and what's going wrong in
disease so we've covered at this point
biology and technology and in the next
lecture series we're actually going to
go into what data you will be provided
with during the competition and what the
actual crunches are what are the actual
problems going to be working on with
these data sets