all right welcome back to 61200 we
continue probability and not only that
we continue on expectation today that we
also get to a second measure of distri
of random variables which is variance
but first most of today will be uh
expectation remember what we did last
class so uh for random variable X over a
sample space s this is just a function
from s to real
numbers uh we had three different
formulas at least for expectation in
different scenarios first one was the
definition sum overall outcomes Omega
probability of the outcome times x
evaluated at that outcome sorry this is
a Omega
uh or we could rewrite that sum
according to the distinct values of
capital x and so sum over the range of X
and take the probability uh that big x
equals Little X multip by Little X
that's equivalent um and in the special
case where X is a function to natural
numbers then we could write this as an
infinite series sum of I equal 1 to
Infinity probability of X greater than
or equal to I and that turned out to be
equivalent to this thing by expanding it
out so if the CDF is nice that's a nice
formula if it's in the special case z
over natural numbers for independent for
uh indicator random variables where X is
zero or one another special case then
the expectation is just equal to the
probability uh equaling one which is
like probability of the event that this
is an indicator for and the big thing
was linearity of expectation which told
us if we summed and also multiplied by a
constant uh inside the expectation we
could push the expectation inside and or
pull the sum and the multiplication out
so this we're going to use all of these
things today uh and see how they
contrast with other other fun properties
um but I'm going to start out with some
motivating examples to give us some
interesting uh problems to think about
uh so let's talk
about a bunch of events
uh
E1 up to e
n so these are subsets of our sample
space and we can think of those events
being uh a good things or bad things uh
maybe uh these are different ways in
which your computer could fail or your
algorithm could fail or maybe they're
good things maybe these are uh you'd
like at least one of these to happen or
you'd like at least half of them to
happen happen or whatever uh so we're
going to think about um in
particular the number of events that
happen so let's Define a rener variable
n to be uh the number of EI
events that
happen and uh first problem is what is
the expected value of n so what is the
expected
number of events in
general there's a nice formula for this
which is sum I = 1 to n of the
probability of event
I okay this is pretty much a warmup it's
very similar to things that we did last
time in fact we did a special case of
this last time uh but let me remind you
those techniques and let's actually do
it for this example so um remember the
technique was if I have some random
variable that is tricky to analyze and I
want to compute this
expectation uh write split it up into a
sum of different random variables so
here there's a pretty obvious way to
split it up n is supposed to count the
number of Eis and so each of these uh
suggests we should count them
individually let's define an indicator
random variable I
subi uh for each
event uh and that that is counting among
all the events that are known as EI
there's only one of them how many of
them occurred zero or what did it occur
or not so then n is going to be just the
sum uh IAL 1 to n of I I I I captain
then uh we can compute the expectation
using all these fun things so we've got
the expected value of
n is uh by linearity the sum of the
expected values of the
IIs uh and the if because the IIs are
indicator random variables their
expectation is exactly the probability
that they're equal to one so this is sum
IAL 1 to n uh probability sorry I keep
forgetting my x's in next to my e uh I I
equals
1 uh and that's just by definition of
the IIs that is the probability of
EI okay so very easy proof just but
refreshing how we use all these fun
facts we did a special case of this last
time which was if all uh we were
counting if I flip a coin n times and a
prob probability of heads is
p uh so this is biased
coins uh heads probability
P then the expected number of
heads uh was equal to P *
n that's something we computed last time
in exactly the same way so this isn't
terribly new but this is more general
form each the events here all the events
were the same probability now they could
have different probabilities still you
sum them uh cool we'll use this again as
well all right so that's simple warm-up
problem just counting the number of
events now we'd like to understand a
little deeper how many events are going
to occur in particular a really
interesting uh question is when does at
least one event occur so if you think of
these for example as being different
failure modes for your system you want
to know what's the chance of anything
failing out of all the different ways
that things could fail and those events
may not be independent so uh all of this
works even if the Eis are dependent on
each other maybe they're all the same
who knows but uh this summation is
exactly the right answer for expectation
by
linearity uh so let's start with with a
very
simple upper
bound called the union
bound on the chance of something
happening so this is
probability of the
Union hence the name Union bound is at
most the
sum of the
probabilities of the
events okay in other words using the
terminology from over here the
probability that at least one event
occurs that's the probability that n is
at least one is at most the expectation
of the number of events because these
two things are equal by this previous
theorem
here so uh these two statements are
equivalent because the number being at
least one that's the same as well that's
at least one event occurring that's the
same as the union of these
events Okay cool so this is like uh like
the some rule but some rule had an
equality and was only um when the events
were disjoint this works all the time
but it can give a very weak upper bound
depending on your events this sum may be
larger than one so that doesn't tell you
very very much to say probability is
less than equal to one it's like yeah I
knew that uh you didn't have to do any
work let me um in parallel write some
examples here uh so let's do
our same example of n
independent coin
flips uh probability of heads is
p
then the union
bound says that uh the probability of at
least one head
is at most P * n right that's this
expectation that I just wrote down over
here P * n was the expected value for
the number of heads so in particular the
probability is at least one head is at
most P * n so as soon as p is bigger
than one over n this is not a useful
upper bound right the the true
answer
actual uh
probability there's at least one head
this
is uh 1 - 1 - P to the N easier to
compute the chance the probability that
there are zero heads that's the same as
saying that there are N Tails so uh this
is the probability of a tals one minus P
raise it to the nth power we get the
probability of Nils we take one minus it
we get the probability that there're not
Nils and other words there at least one
head so these are close for very small P
but not so great for uh uh even for
small P maybe not so great I don't
know all right um so this is an example
where Union bounds not so
helpful um maybe I'll
do I'll come to other examples in a
moment let me tell you uh a nice
property on the other
side uh which I'll call Murphy's Law
it's not the official name
but probably heard of some form of
Murphy's Law in the past uh whatever can
go wrong will go wrong this is a
formalization of that so
if uh the N events we have are mutually
independent this is the first time I'm
making this assumption other than that
example uh
then probability of the
Union is at
least uh 1
minus 1
over e to the sum of the
probabilities of the
events okay this
is without any uh n terminology but
maybe a nicer way way is to write it uh
in terms of n probability that at least
one event
occurs is at least 1 - 1 over e to the
expectation of
n Again
by this theorem relating the expectation
of n to the sum of the it is just a sum
of those
probabilities so um the union bound
gives an upper bound we want to the
chance of some event occurring like some
failure happening uh this tells us it's
at most something and this tells us it's
at least something but this theorem
assumes Mutual Independence so doesn't
always apply but in this example it does
apply so we can apply Murphy's Law
here and it gives us the probability of
at least one
head is
wrong
page at least one minus one/ E to the
PN right again the expectation is PN so
1 minus 1 over e to the PN so uh the
bounds tell us it's somewhere between
this uh thing that's kind of close to
one especially if this exponent is large
so this is the point is here this
uh denominator increases exponentially
with
expectation so
uh that means this is going to be very
small if if expectation of n is large um
and so that means this is very close to
one right so when the expectation is
large the union bound doesn't tell us
anything useful says it's at most one or
whatever but also Murphy's law says it's
actually pretty close to one so maybe
the union bound wasn't so bad after all
that's the idea um I mean in particular
we also know that it's less than equal
to one so those two facts combined are
maybe okay when the expectation is large
so uh what can go wrong will go wrong
with high probability assuming Mutual
Independence and assuming expectation is
large I guess that's the formal version
of Murphy's
Law okay uh cool let's do to a
particular example of this that I think
is instructive which is suppose that
um each event occurs with probability 1
n so this is same thing but I'm just
plugging in P 1 n then with the Union
bound I get uh the probability of the
Union I'll write it one more
time is at most one exactly so it's
useless um Murphy's
Law tells me the probability is at
least uh 1 minus 1/ E to the
one which is
about
63 so they're they're pretty close
they're within a factor of two of each
other uh one and 63
and the right
answer
uh well I guess is this thing 1 minus
one/ n to the N I'm not sure it has a
nice nice formula it depends on N which
one is more correct but they're both
they're pretty close so they're both
pretty
correct uh here
is maybe another
example so we did two examples at the
end of last class with
randomized uh phone returning
at some terrible school where you get
where you get a randomly selected phone
when you go home um and then we talked
about a version with a turntable or Lazy
Susan
uh where either everyone gets their
phone back or no one does and it was
kind of weird because in expectation
these were the same the expected number
of phones that went back to the correct
person was one independent of how many
people in phones there were as long as
number of phones equals number of people
which is kind of funny expectation was
always
one um
so
uh yeah this is an example if you recall
we wrote down uh there was an indicator
random variable I forget what we called
it let's say I sub I uh which was does
the I person get back their phone and we
computed the probability of that
equaling one
here and here and in both cases it was 1
n so these are actually both examples of
this
picture okay I should say uh if mutually
independent I wanted
to in this example I didn't want to
assume Mutual Independence this holds in
all cases this holds if the events are
mutually
independent uh because here the events
are not necessarily mutually independent
right in fact they're not in both of
these examples they're different levels
of Independence I would
say but it's they both satis they're
both special cases of this property the
probability of each event is exactly one
over n the probability each person gets
their phone back is one over n both with
random permutation of the phones and
with random rotation of the
phones um and here I will give you the
actual answers the
probability
uh that any phone is returned
correctly that's this probability of the
Union of the different uh
events uh in this
case uh well it's easier to compute the
probability that no one gets it
correctly this is like the uh no
repeated serial numbers in the dollar
bill kind of um there so for the first
person they n minus one choices out of n
where they get the wrong phone back and
then the second person there's nus 2
choices out of nus1 for them to not get
their correct phone back and so
on and get my cancellation
shock uh n minus one's cancel nus 2's
cancel nus 3's cancel and so on we're
left with 1 - 1
n okay which is in between these two
values so that's
good uh and it's actually very close to
the union
bound uh closer to the union bound than
the other one so I would say yeah um I
don't know these are uh pretty
independent is my fancy
analysis uh yeah maybe they're
independent if you look at it the right
way it depends how you define the
problem exactly
um over
here what's the probability that any
phone gets returned correctly this is
actually a really easy one I rotate the
phones on a
table what's the chance that anyone gets
their phone back
correctly yeah one over n there just n
possible outcomes here and one of them
everyone gets their phone back so
capital N equals little n and in the
other situation zero people get their
fund
back so this seems to
violate uh this lower bound right we
said it should be at least 63 so uh in
order to do that it means that they're
very
dependent I mean it's it's very hard for
events to be more dependent than them
being equal in fact the first person
gets their fund back if and only if the
second person gets their fund back if
and only if the third person gets their
Fone back uh so indeed the events are
equal to each other here the same single
outcome and so that's why this is
breaking
okay uh I wanted to prove Murphy's Law
and then we'll come back to one more
example uh where we at over here
like where does this exponential come
from it's an
approximation so uh it comes from one of
these
fun uh facts that we've used before so
just like in this last
example um instead of computing the
probability that at least one things
happens let's compute the probability
that zero of the events happen and then
do one minus it okay so I'm going to
compute uh the probability
complement of this event is that n
equals zero so no events
occur okay in other words the
probability uh that E1 does not occur
and E2 does not occur and uh e n does
not
occur
okay
uh well um the E are independent are
mutually independent and one of the
things we we mentioned uh and may be
proved in recitation I forget back when
we were doing the independence lecture
is that if uh events are independent
then also their complements are
independent if E1 and E2 are independent
from each other then E1 complement is
independent from E2
complement uh and so
um we from the product rule this
probability of intersections for inde
and mutually independent events events
is just the product of the
probabilities
okay uh what else so this probability is
of course one minus the probability of
EI and now we're going to use this fun
fact uh which is this is at most e to
the minus probability of EI
by this uh fact that 1 - x is less than
or equal to eus x uh for x non-
negative we've used this few lectures
ago I think uh this was the Taylor
series expansion of e to Theus X you
take the first two terms it's a very
good approximation when X is small which
is kind of an interesting case we're
thinking of these probabilities
individually as being small but there
might be lots of events then this will
be a good approximation uh but it's
always true that it's at less than or
equal to in all cases so this is fine um
and so now we have a product of
exponentials and by properties of
exponentials we can pull the exponential
out and sorry this is less than or equal
to e uh to this sum
minus uh sum I = 1 to n of probability
of
EI okay which if you stare at it long
enough that's exactly what we got here e
to the minus is the same as one over e
to the thing this sum and because we are
Computing the complement event we have
to do a one minus at front and instead
of an upper bound this was an upper
bound on the failure uh this is a lower
bound on success if success is one of
the events
occurring Okay
cool so that's where the exponentials
come from it's a way to product of one
minus something is ugly there's no nice
way to simplify that but if we use this
approximation then we get a product of
exponentials and life is good so um for
fun you know as we're winding down the
class uh I think it's time to enjoy
music video so uh the application is
we're going to think
about uh we have some probabilities of
failures and here this is a really cool
rubbe Goldberg machine made by the rock
band okay go
uh and there are about over a hundred
different components in this rub
Goldberg machine so the the Challen what
you want to think about is what's the
probability of at least one of those
components failing in a single uncut
video
[Music]
[Applause]
can't you let me get you
and they can't keep
ding
[Music]
around ground
can't why would you want toally
[Music]
the the m
let
go
[Music]
to
let
[Music]
go let me get you
down let me get you down
to
[Music]
[Applause]
so good
[Music]
so uh if you haven't watched all of ok
Go's music videos I highly recommend
instead of studying for the final you
should watch them uh amazing stuff I
actually I've watched this video like 10
times in the last day and I only just
now realized how many references there
are to other okaygo music videos so if
you watch them all you'll get extra
appreciation then watch this one again
and you'll see them all um cool so I I
happen to be friends uh in particular
with Damien who's the the lead singer
and I was chatting with him like
how how how did you make this work
because uh he's in many talks that he
gives like he has a TED talk it's linked
in the lecture notes he said okay uh
there about 130
components in the
setup uh so if you imagine each uh fails
uh
with probability say
10% reasonable if you engineer something
well should work like 90% of the time I
don't know if you ever built a rub
Goldberg machine even that's difficult
to engineer it's very easy to get more
like 50 70% success rate uh but let's
say you can get 90% success rate then uh
what's the probability that uh there is
a failure number of fails is at least
one well you know it's the same thing we
had before uh one
minus 1 - 1 minus P to the N this is the
actual we won't use any approximation
here uh it turns out to
be uh
99.999
89% which is exactly one in a million
chance that this video will come out
good
so uh that's
terrible uh and then you know and his
talks he goes on it's like yeah so you
know we've really go to um we got to
take chances and you know uh just
explore and not be um not worry about
failing it's the main point of his talk
but then he never explains like well how
did you make the video if there's a one
in a million chance that it comes out
right did you do a million
takes uh and I don't know how many takes
uh they did he didn't just didn't
remember uh
but he said the the secret for it
working was to do the math after you've
made the video instead of
before uh maybe a little unsatisfying uh
but on reflection um I mean you could
work out some other probabilities right
if you say okay there's only uh 1% of uh
chance of
failure then the probability the whole
thing succeeds is uh or the probability
of failure overall is
73% still not very good but doable like
you could do four takes and then one of
them will be good in expectation uh but
99% reliability is challenging it's only
when you get to like if if you get to
99.9% success rate then this starts to
get impressive you only a 12% chance
that something fails um but apparently
the in hindsight what worked well for
this video is because the the effects
the interactions get big and bigger
towards the end of the video because
they just wanted to make them more and
more impressive with bowling balls and
giant things and you know huge
interactions huge interactions actually
fail less often because something like a
bowling ball is less affected by air
currents in the room and stuff like that
so the bowling balls were super reliable
they were probably down here in the very
very like maybe several nines uh
Effectiveness whereas some of the very
early effects in particular The Dominoes
which open the video I'll just play that
again because I love watching this video
um they failed almost every single time
so um this this very first move
apparently dominoes are extremely
unpredictable so doing this in a way
they said they set up the dominoes
roughly six billion times I think that's
an exaggeration but uh that's I guess
the other answer is to do uh six billion
uh takes and then you'll be set and they
got one take with everything in it which
is pretty pretty amazing despite the
odds
all right so that was just a fun
diversion but I love an opportunity to
talk about rub Goldberg machines and
stare at
them all right uh let's do some more fun
things
about uh
expectation
products so it turns out there's a
product rule just like for probability
but for expectation it relies on the
random variables being
independent and then it's exactly what
you expect the expectation of the
product is equal to product of the
expectations so similar to probability
in fact this is really just a
generalized version of the product rule
for probability
maybe I'll give like a quick sketch of
the proof how's my time yeah let's do it
uh so this expectation of X product y if
I just write out the
definition uh we just take all the
possible outcomes we don't know anything
about them but x * Y is a function we
evaluated it at that outcome this is the
same thing as taking X of the outcome
and multiplying by y of the outcome
that's the definition of this product
function uh and then we multiply yeah we
multiply by the probability outcome sum
them up that's the deal uh just like
with this
formula we can rearrange the terms in
that sum to where here it was by x value
but we could do it by X and y value so
we can rewrite this as a sum over uh X
and a sum over y other words a sum over
pairs X comma y uh of this
thing uh but now so there are a bunch of
probabilities of outcomes that have the
same X and Y so we're just going to
write the probability that x equals
Little X and Big Y equals little Y and
multiply that by x * y
okay that's rearranging uh terms with
the same X time X and Y value like we
did uh last class and then this
probability is a product right by the
product rule for for probabilities X and
Y are independent means that these two
events are independent for all X and Y
and so uh we can rewrite this as
probability of X equaling little x times
probability of Y equaling little
Y and now we have a s a double sum over
some things involving X and some things
involving y sorry for the pun I didn't
mean to say some all the time there uh
things involving X and things involving
Y and we know from way back in our
summation formulas we can separate out
the summation over X from the summation
over y take their product and if you do
that you get exactly uh this formula
with X and with y
and so I didn't write it here but this
is x in the range of X this is y in the
range of Y and so that's uh that's why
this works so it's really just using
product rule for
probabilities cool uh let's do an
example with
that suppose we've invented a new game
which is We Roll two independent
uh six-sided
Dice and then the score is the product
of those two
dice not a typical game usually some but
uh let's say we take the product what is
the expectation of that product well if
they're independent we know it's the
product of the
expectations and expectation of a die
roll we covered last time it's a
3.5 so this is 3.5
squared which
is
uh
12.25 okay weird number there it
is whereas
if I take the expectation of D1 * D1
also known as D1 squared D1 is not
independent from D1 in fact is the most
dependent it could be they're the same
same random variable uh I claim I do not
get 12.25 even though each of these
individually has an expectation of
3.5 uh let's just compute that or get an
idea how we would compute it think could
just use the the definition we have or
really the summing uh summing over X in
range of X so we have six possible
outcomes for
D1 and we want the probability that D1
equals Little D times Little
D right that's the the second version of
expect second formula for
expectation uh this is just 1 six for
fair
dice I I didn't mention fair but I
mentioned I meant to say fair dice so
this is the Aver uh sorry didn't get
this right I'm missing a a product right
this is this thing so sum over the
different die rolls but now we have D
squ
here okay and I can never remember the
formula for sum of d uh sum of squares
but we get 1 16 times that sum of
squares you know 1 2 + 2 S Plus
3^2 up to 6^
S
which uh turns out to
be 15.1
1666 so
bigger kind of weird but there you
go all right so this was product rule
for for two random variables of course
if you take the product of n random
variables you can do the same thing uh
if there's product of nxis here you just
get a product of n expectations of
XIs so when things are independent life
is good what about division we spend all
this time adding and multiplying
probabilities and
expectations can we divide
them uh the short answer is no never
divide random variables ever I'll show
you
why uh
don't divide
okay one reason is um expectation of 1
/x this is sort of if if we could do
this we could multi we could multiply it
with something and end up dividing uh
does not equal one over expectation of x
uh in general or probably
usually and here's one example uh where
this
is uh
particularly striking they're very
different um uh suppose you have X this
is almost a uh an indicator random
variable but it's going to be instead of
one or zero it's going to be one or
minus one so let's say it's one with
probability a
half and it's minus one with probability
a
half okay what's the
expectation
zero it's just the average because
they're equally
likely uh so one over the
expectation is not a very good number
it's like infinity or something this is
bad one over zero uh whereas if I take
uh
expectation of 1
/x well one over one over one is just
one one over minus one is also minus one
like one over doesn't do anything to X
this expectation of 1/x is expectation
of
X which is zero so this thing is like
infinity or just undefined and this
thing is zero so they're very different
from each
other and in some sense uh you should
just never do this this is a reasonable
quantity to think about don't don't
think about this one although that seems
backwards given here given what we
showed here um here's here's a more
here's a real world example this is
based on a a paper in computer
architecture where they're trying to
argue that one
architecture I don't know if it was P1
or P2 I think this a little divorced
from the original
example um so there were two different
processor architectures for solving
three different possible workloads these
were like benchmarks that they could
evaluate them on and uh processor one on
workload one took 10 seconds to complete
processor 2 took 16 seconds uh and so on
there's a table here you run each of
these processors for each of these
workloads and you see what you get let's
say these are each uh equally likely 13
probability of
occurring and you want to know which one
is
better and this is one of those things
where you think well either I should
take the expectation of the ratios or I
should take the ratio of the
expectations um if you let's compute the
the expectations individually first so
if I add these up I get 30 there's three
of them so the uh expectation is 10 and
here it's also
10 okay so in fact the the ratio of the
expectations which I think is a
reasonable thing to do so let's just
call this P1 performance over
expectation of P2 performance
uh is one so in fact these are equally
good in
expectation okay this is because if
they're equally like the intuition why
you should do this is in each if you
assume that these workloads are equally
likely then
uh yeah you you should be Computing how
long will your process take given a
randomly chosen workload according to
that distribution okay so you should be
summing all these up before you do any
kind of ratio
but what the paper
did was take the expectation of the
ratio and with these particular
carefully chosen numbers but they
roughly match those at the paper uh you
get a funny
fact which is uh if you take the
expectation of P1 over P2 this is a ton
of arithmetic so I will not do it uh we
get 10
over9 so it looks like um these are
running times so smaller is better that
looks like P2 is better than
P1 but if you take the ra the expected
ratio of P2 over
P1 it's also 10 over
9 so clearly P1 is better than
P2 uh why is this happening because
expectation of ratios is just something
you should never do and is meaningless
okay or takeen a different way if you
want to lie with Statistics here is a
great way to do it take expectation of
ratios you can make you could support
any story you like uh at least with
these if you're lucky the numbers are
close then uh you get this funny funny
Behavior this is what you should do if
you don't want to lie and you want to
compare
performance okay don't divide random
variables I think this is all you'll
have to do with dividing random
variables uh cool but multiplying is
good as long as they're mutually
independent any
questions
cool so the last topic for
today is
variance so expectation was a way to
take a whole function a random variable
and reduce it down to one number now
we're going to talk about how to take a
whole function and reduce it down to two
num
expectation and variance and I'll say a
little bit why these are maybe the first
two numbers you might care about there
are more of course you might care about
the whole distribution and in some sense
what we've been doing what we did with
the these guys the union bound of the
Murphy's Law was trying to capture a
little more than just the expectation
but just trying to understand how much
is at the zero spot versus everything
else and next class on Tuesday we'll
we'll talk about a generalized form of
that where there's some cut off and we
want to know how much how much
probability is out beyond the cut off
those are called Tales of a distribution
but today we're going to just in the
rest of today we're just going to look
at one more number that measures some
kind of like well
variance uh it it tries to measure how
good of an approximation is the
expectation that's I think a good way to
think about
it and I'm sure you've seen variance in
some form before but uh maybe motivating
example
is
investment AKA
gambling sorry for the Dig uh but uh
let's consider an investment process XI
which is um plus I with probability a
half going to be a generalized version
of the one I just did uh and minus I
with probability sorry not
I2 probability
one2 okay
uh so like X1 is like I invest $1 and
50% chance I double my money 50% chance
I lose my money uh x 100 is I put in
$100 and 50% chance I double my money
50% chance I lose all my money or I
could put in you know a billion dollars
do are these exactly the same investment
strategies I mean you would probably say
with when I is larger this is a higher
risk investment if I put in a billion
dollars that's very scary I could
potentially lose a billion dollars of
course I could also win a billion
dollars so that's like high risk High
reward if I invest $1 like yeah I'd play
that game why not it's for just for
fun okay uh so if we look at the
expectation we learn nothing expectation
of all of these is zero just like it was
in the eal one case
uh variance is going to try to capture
uh something involving
I okay let me Define
variance it's kind of a big formula but
not too big once you stare at it long
enough so many brackets though
alternating a square and round all right
so uh what we're going to do is
take the deviation from the mean x minus
the expectation of X so this is a random
variable it's it's just like X but we
subtract the expectation of x and by
linearity of expectation that means this
may be worth writing down the
expectation of x minus the expectation
of this braced quantity
here is is
zero because uh linearity says well this
is expectation of
x uh minus the expectation of the
expectation of
X but uh the expectation of the
expectation of X is just the expectation
of X
because um while X is a random variable
I mean expectation of X is also a random
variable but it's doesn't change right
expectation of X is a single number
uh you reroll your dice the expectation
doesn't change only X the the X the
value of x can change because it's a
function but expectation of X is a
constant thing so its expectation is
itself okay so these
cancel okay so in other words I'm taking
X which has some expectation but then
I'm shifting it over so it's uh now its
expectation is zero I'd like to Center
things on zero additively then I'm going
to square it which is maybe a little
weird we'll talk about why in a second
uh and then I take the expectation of
that because while this thing is
constant this thing is not so if your
expectation happens to be zero this is
just the expectation of X squ whereas
before we're taking the expectation of X
now we're taking expectation of x s and
for X squ to be nice we're going to
first shift it so that its mean is zero
okay those a lot of words uh in this
example the expectation was already zero
and so the variance of XI is just the
expectation of x i
s which
is uh get this
right oh yeah fun thing about square is
it makes positive and negative numbers
treats positive and negative numbers the
same so the what is x i
squ it's always i^ squ
no matter how the coin flip occurred if
it was plus I the square of that is I
squ if it was minus I the square of that
is I squ okay so U this is part of the
magic of variance that we treat negative
and positive numbers the same and so uh
the expectation of I squ I I squ doesn't
depend on anything so it's just I
squ and for this reason we also often
Define uh the square root of variance to
be the standard deviation
uh which we usually write Sigma subx
here is going to be square root of the
variance of X so you can use whichever
of these you want I mean they're the
same up to a square root or a square uh
but it's a second number Sigma subx I
here is equal to
I so while expectation told us nothing
about the risk of our investment Sigma
told us exactly what the risk is and
this very set simple
setup
okay
let's go on to the next topic which is y
squared try to give you some intuition
okay uh y^
2 there are many possible answers to
this
uh but probably the simplest thing is to
try what if I didn't put this Square
here and I left the formula otherwise
the same what if I did
expectation of xus expectation of X what
would happen
then yeah zero I wrote it right here
expectation I I saying oh this shifted
things over so the expectation was zero
so if you remove the square you just are
going to get zero this would be a
useless number right so we want to put
something
here one one possible answer now uh
there different things you might try to
do um one would be uh
expectation of x minus expectation of
x to the P for
some uh number P what we did just did
was
two another thing you might try to do to
to fix it is absolute
value and just for fun we could also
raise that to the PE
power and uh so these are natural things
to try I would argue especially if you
know anything about Norms or you know
geometry and stuff um and it turns out
all of these are interesting
question yeah
i s or are you setting the expectation
of ah I uh I wasn't setting anything I
was claiming that x i squ as a random
variable is always I
squ because x i is either plus I or
minus I and in both cases the square of
that is i s so this is inside the
expectation yeah and therefore the
expectation doesn't have anything to
do it's a constant not a not much of a
random
variable okay back to these guys uh
these have names this is uh for p
greater than one this is uh the PE uh
Central
moment uh and this one for p greater
than equal to one is the
pee uh probably Central this one's not
talked about nearly as much uh but I
would call it the absolute moment
and they're all interesting uh for this
one p equals 2 is called variance that's
the one we're talking about uh P equals
3 with some normalization which I'm not
going to do here it's called the skew of
the distribution P equal 4 is something
it's got a really fancy name just
showing off my my English knowledge is
called curtosis uh I assume people
looked at other
uh moments too although usually they
just called you know first moment second
moment third moment whatever these are
all very interesting quantities they
capture different things about the
distribution variance is how far from
the mean are you on average in some
sense skew is sort of how to the left or
to the right is your distribution
cryosis I have no idea I'm not a uh St
statistician but they all have some
meaning and you can do the same thing
with absolute moment you can also do it
without this uh normalization term then
you remove the word central uh these are
interesting cool quantities so there's
no particular reason two is special and
in fact if you do absolute values you
can even go down to one and you get a
reasonably interesting thing um but
often we really like uh the version
without absolute value because it's
smooth because it's infinitely
differentiable whereas absolute value is
not differentiable so it's just uglier
to work with analytically so
historically this is why we go here I
think this is also a very interesting
measure and you could use it just we're
not going to use it in this class
okay they give you
different they give you different things
because this square is exaggerating
larger differences right if you square
something that's big it has a bigger
impact than if you square something
that's
small so if you care about deviation
from the mean and you really you care a
little more about big deviations than
small deviations then raising this to
some power is a meaningful thing and
that's that's why we do it
uh there are some other reasons um if in
in the stat statistics world if you know
that X is normally distributed which
actually is kind of common Even in our
world if you take a sum of a bunch of uh
bruli trials this is
um uh has some name right not the bruli
distribution so like brui trials are
coin flips you take a sum of them you
get uh a binomial distribution I should
know that uh then uh there's something
called a central limit theorem that says
that's very close to a normal
distribution normal distribution is you
know gaussian bell curve uh and it turns
out if you know the expectation and the
variance of your distribution and it's
normal then you know everything about
that distribution so because Normal
distributions are frequently occurring
in nature both in real life and in
mathematical life uh like when we sum a
bunch of uh coin
flips uh these this expectation variant
are often the first two things you
should care about maybe they're the only
things you need to know if you want to
understand your
distribution and then because I'm a
geometer I have to say because we live
in a because we're living in a ukian
world you know in ukian world uh you you
square things and then you take the
square root at the end right this is
this is the norm this is actually the
distance between two points in uh size
of s
Dimensions okay I'm a I'm I'm usually a
two-dimensional geometer maybe three
dimensions but if you're crazy you can
live all the way up in size of s
Dimensions where you can represent you
can represent a function as just like a
big Vector very popular these days um uh
just you write down all the possible for
every outcome you write what x is that's
a vector in s dimensions and if you also
write down for every possible outcome
what expected value of x is uh it's the
same every time it's mean mean mean mean
mean mean mean very
mean then and you take the distance
between those two vectors that's exactly
variance or sorry standard
deviation so if you live in ukian world
that's why two is natural of course you
can live in any P norm and then you get
all these other
things all right let me tell you some
cool properties of
invariance uh here
some of these I'll prove some of these
I'll just State and you'll prove them in
recitation tomorrow but we'll see some
we'll use them to analyze some
examples okay so our first one is
translation and variance
so what I'd like to do is
um take some random variable X and add a
constant to it now when I add a constant
to X I change the
expectation right it also shifts over by
linearity with variance it actually
doesn't change the variance of X plus C
equals the variance of X that's a nice
property probably true of all of all of
these definitions
all of the moments but we'll just do it
for
variance
uh so let's prove it so as I said the
expectation we need that in order to
compute variance expectation is always
what you should do first by linearity
this is expectation of X Plus
expectation of C but expectation of C is
just
C because it doesn't change depending on
the random
event so
variance of X plus
C we just plug in the definition
here uh so we want expectation of x
minus the expectation of X but now X is
X plus C so we want
expectation of first term X is so I
guess this is going to be for the square
then uh the first X is actually X+ C and
then we have minus
the expectation of X plus
C uh and then that's squared and then we
close the expectation and this thing is
what we just computed here so we have in
inside the Parn here we have x + C
minus uh expectation of
X plus C in
parenthesis and get my red chalk
the C's
cancel right so we end up with x minus
expectation of x squared and expect
expected um and that's exactly the
definition of variation of X variance of
X okay so that's kind of nice
okay couple
more one is here
is another way to compute variance
uh I can't say I have a lot of intuition
for this one but it works out nicely
mathematically variance of X is the
difference between the expect the
squared value expected and the expected
squared the square of the expectation
versus the expectation of the
square with this sign turns out to be
right uh I guess this is sort of related
to whether you do things inside or
outside the expectation this is going to
exaggerate larger values of X more and
this uh adds them all up first and then
squares so it's less dramatic and the
difference in those dramas are exactly
the variance turns out so we're not
going to prove that you'll prove that in
in recitation tomorrow but let's do a
simple example of it so suppose we have
a bias coin
flip uh where the probability of heads
is
p and uh take an indicator random
variable H or equivalently this holds
for every indicator random
variable uh
H we know the
expectation of H is just probability of
one which is
p the
variance is quite nice to compute with
this formula because again with with um
indicator random variables they're
always zero or one and so when you
square them nothing
happens right so this is
uh if according to this formula it's
expectation of
x^2 of
h^2 minus uh expectation of H outside
squared and H squ is equal to H because
if you take zero you square it you get
zero if you take one you square it you
get one so this thing is just uh
expectation of H which is
p and then we have minus expectation of
H squ well expectation of H again this
is p so this is
p^2 so P minus p^ 2 also known as P * 1
minus P looks a little bit more
natural um it's probability of heads
times the probability of Tails turns out
to be the variance in this case if you
look at standard deviation it's the
geometric mean between p and one minus P
which is kind of a nice
number
okay next one uh do I want this
example I might
let's go over
here so expectation had this nice
linearity property how about variance
well it has this nice nonlinearity
property it's not usually called
nonlinearity of variance but it's kind
of linear is uh
so the the nice
part
um yeah all right let's start with this
part the less Nice Part the less linear
part so while variance was scale inar it
was um translation invariant is that
what I called it yeah if I add something
to X it doesn't change the variance If I
multiply by something it it better
change the variance right I mean that's
the whole point of the investment say If
I multiply XI by a million that has
higher risk so variance should go
up uh and it's a little funny because
everything's squared so it doesn't go up
linearly it goes up by c^ squ instead of
C of course if you take standard
deviation it is linear in this special
case like if you take standard deviation
of C * X it's going to be C * standard
deviation of
X okay
cool but what if we add
to to random variables um here
unfortunately we need Independence so if
X and Y are independent random
variables
then uh the variation the variance of
the sum is equal to the sum of the
variations okay so it's not as nice as
we had with expectation where it just
always holds but still pretty
good so if you sum things and multiply
them by things it gets a little weird
you've got to square all of these
coefficients but these are sort of the
analoges of the things we have in
expectation this is again something we
will uh you will do in
lecture uh so I'm going to just do an
example
two
examples related
examples okay so uh let's say we have n
mutually independent coin
flips and I want H to be the number of
heads this is what we were calling n
before and maybe on this board H we've
often called this H we've counted this
before we've done the expectation uh
twice now we did it last lecture and we
did it at the beginning of this lecture
the expectation of H is p * n if the
probability of
heads is
p okay what about the
variance uh
and the idea just like when we computed
expectation we split up H as a sum of
nhh where hi was uh an indicator ROM
variable for whether the I flip was a
heads
hi is indicator ROM variable for I
flip being
heads uh and so then we just took the
sum here and so each of them had a
probability P of occurring we so we got
n of them got P * n let's do the same
thing with variance because we're
assuming these coin Clips are
independent with the expectation we
didn't have to but with variance we have
to so we can use this property this is
going to be equal to by this kind of
linearity of variance uh sum of variance
of hi for IAL 1 to
n cool so then we just need the variance
of each individual coin flip which we
just did right bias coin
flip uh probability P of heads variance
was P * 1 minus
P so we get n * P * 1 -
P
okay uh I find it a little hard to have
intuition for this but uh it's a number
here's here's another example last
example will give you some intuition for
why this is
interesting back to gambling I mean
investment uh let's
say you have n doll you want to invest
back to my great investment strategy
here you can you can let's this xn now I
could either invest I I could invest n
in this thing and I get a Varan of n s i
could win n lose
n okay but now suppose there's not just
one investment like this Suppose there a
whole bunch of Investments like XI let's
call them stocks right you have uh K
different stocks and I can choose I'll
invest so many dollars in this stock so
many dollars in this stock so many
dollars in this stock and let's just
assume like this in great investment uh
setup that each of them will either
double your money or you lose all your
money does this make a difference is it
any different to invest in K different
stocks equally versus investing in one
stock
everything okay I claim they're
different so let's do it in general and
then we can plug in different values of
K so let's say we have K different
stocks and we're going to equally uh
split our investment
of$ across those stocks
and let's say that each
stock
SI is plus let's just do plus one and
minus one simple of course you could
generalize each of these occurs with
probability a
half just like our previous Investments
but now each stock is uh let's say
they're
independent
mutually independent
this is probably not a reasonable
assumption do not invest in the stock
market with this advice but if we assume
that they're mutually
independent
then uh what we get if we want the
variance of our overall outcome which is
uh sum IAL 1 to n of n / K time SI
right this is how many dollars I assume
you know the basics of investment if you
invest more dollars then you're G to
either get more back or lose more just
like this uh XI but I pulled the pulled
it outside so if we invest n overk
dollars in this stock then we get we end
up with this many dollars in the end we
add it up over all stocks okay now we
want to know the variance of this
investment strategy which I'm going to
call risk
so probably risk is standard deviation
but if variance is lower so we standard
deviation uh so the variation of sum if
they're mutually
independent uh is exactly the
sum of the variations of the uh insides
which is n over K *
SI that
was uh First Property um and then the
second one if we want to pull this
outside it gets squared so we get sum I
= 1 to n of n / k s time variance of Si
variance of
Si is one I think this was the early
example we did in general the the
variance of this x i we're we're
interested in the case I equals 1 over
here uh the variance was i^ s so that's
just
one okay so we get the sum of something
that doesn't depend on on I so we just
get n of these things we get n cubed
over
k^2 this is our variance and if you take
the square root you get the standard
deviation okay and if you hold n fixed
of course the more dollars you put in
here the more risk you expect uh so it
turns out to grow uh if you're doing
standard deviation um you get n to the
1.5 risk so don't invest a lot of money
maybe um we get divided by K the cool
thing is the bigger K is the smaller you
risk so this is why I conjecture this is
why Financial people say diversify your
portfolio because the more things you
invest in if they're mutually
independent it reduces your
risk uh it's kind of a fun conclusion to
variance of course if they're mutually
dependent which stock market tends to be
somewhat then you don't get this as much
of a benefit but you probably get some
benefit by diversifying so it's a good
thing to do when you grow up and uh
invest your money all right that's it
for today one more lecture on
probability Tuesday