so we are really very pleased to be able
to offer the opportunity for you to get
to hear from three of our most recent um
graduates of the enin program um I'm
going to have them actually do quick
introductions in a minute but I do want
to um just say that we recognize that
this is an investment for you and while
your primary focus is going to be on the
academics and learning the technical SK
skills that you need both in terms of
you know the deeper quantitative Finance
as well as just understanding how
markets behave modern finance that after
all was um basically started here at MIT
um these are important Concepts and so
while we know that that's a a big Focus
the reality is that the program and
again it's primarily designed to be
delivered in 18 months with an
opportunity to FastTrack in 12 months
that time period goes by so so quickly
I'm sure my alums will attest to that
and as soon as you start it's a summer
term so we start July 1st it's in person
fully residential there's a lot that you
have to cover in the in the whether it's
12 or 18 months and while you're doing
all of your cours work you're then
jumping right into um recruiting
essentially looking at what your options
are going to be if you're in the 18month
of Summer internship um or if you're in
the 12 month full-time opportunities so
you really do have to hit the ground
running um and it's important to be
prepared and thinking about that even
before you arrive to MIT what are some
of the you know career um or banking or
Finance functions that you think you're
more interested in and when you look at
the employment reports you know you can
see that we have students who
quantitative Finance as well as more
traditional I Banking and as it turns
out our alums that we have today for the
most part are in on on the lad but um I
think it's important to get a sense from
them of how they were able to best
utilize the resources that are available
to them both from the CDO as well as
just other things that they may have
done on their own I'm going to ask Emily
if you want to kick things off and
introduce yourself tell us where where
you were before you came to the mfin
program graduated did you have a
particular focus when you were in the
mfin program maybe you did a
concentration or if not that's fine and
then what you're doing now yeah of
course I'm happy to kick this off hi
everyone my name is Emily I before
joining M program I graduated from
Georgetown University straight from
undergrad
with a a few internship uh with a few
internship opportunities and experiences
um at Ming I completed my Corporate
Finance certificate with um I guess my
focus would more so be on the corporate
finance banking site instead of PA as uh
Laura and Diane previously mentioned I'm
currently working at pii Global Partners
which is in Boutique Investment Bank
specializing in power energy and
infrastructure I joined here around six
six months ago time
tce that's great I know well they're all
recent grats as you can see so it's all
good though um Arjun I'm GNA have you go
next yeah absolutely uh so I graduated
from UCLA after which I worked for a
couple of years so I worked at ernston
Young after my undergrad uh in Los
Angeles as well as the Cayman Islands
and while I was doing that I used to
audit private equities and hedge funds
and I really loved the way they they
valued their positions and I realized
that I need some more experience in uh
in that line so I came into the infant
program and after my infant program I've
joined a company called Stout we are
basically an investment bank and a
valuation advisory and my role is a bit
specific like I value complex
derivatives happy to tell you more about
that in the Q&A perfect thank you Arun
and last but not least George everybody
I'm uh a George uh before in fin I
studied engineering at the University of
Texas um I actually came into the infant
program thinking I wanted to do more of
a quantitative role and uh ended up
actually going the corporate finance
track and I'm now at tap advisor in New
York at the boutique Investment Bank I
sit on the TMT and digital
infrastructure team excellent thank you
so much so um Laura did you want to go
ahead and ask some more questions I know
you had a few that you teed up through
our Lums but we want to also keep this
as you know a little bit more informal a
little bit more loose let them talk a
little bit about you know some of their
experiences too um so I'll I'll give you
let's say a softball and just want to
know how did the m program prepare you
for launching your careers George you
want to go first I mean I guess I can
you already knew um the uh I honestly um
I know that the panel as Dian was saying
is largely in the corporate finance side
but I think the overall breadth of the
program allows you to take extremely
quantitative uh uh courses as well all
the way from uh you know in the
mathematics Department to any other uh
courses you can take you know at Sloan
as well at through cross registering at
different schools within the Boston area
so any kind of uh curriculum that you
kind of want to set for yourself I think
is uh will ultimately prepare you to at
the highest level of degree that you
could really go um I think it's a lot of
the invins that come out whether that is
on a trading or Quant research or a i
banking role does uh it is pretty
astounding how well uh they teach you uh
in the infant program I uh I sometimes
think I wish I did my undergrad in the
infant program too and you know just
stay there for four years but uh you
know it's a it's a tough one sure I can
go next yeah I mean like George said
just seconding that an incredible
experience learning so much from people
like yourself as well and yeah but I
would say that if I were to pick
something that was very particular it
was the Futures and options class
because that really taught me depth into
financial instruments and I use that on
on a day-to-day basis today at my job
and I wouldn't have been able to do that
had I not done the infant program like
learning nuances of different financial
instruments yeah I think I think sorry I
think adding on to that it's I
definitely agree that there's like a
Quant portion of like the the curriculum
like the python requirement and
everything but for someone like me that
has like a corporate finance or like a
banking perspective there are like some
valuable coures that I've taken um sort
of like like Paving my way basically to
like banking or like valuation or like
how like the indry will look like so
that's definitely something that's also
like a balance between like the Quant
side and also uh the corporate side of
like banking or
Finance so I I spoke briefly to how
career is everywhere at MIT and you're
touching upon some of the courses um can
you think too maybe about a networking
event another class or faculty member
action learning was there something that
really impacted you and you feel that it
contributed to your career your growth
as a student and to where you are today
love to hear about what comes to
mind um oh think oh
I'm ladies first oh sorry George um I I
was gonna mention um I remember like the
M thing networking I um that was
definitely one of the top hits in my
mind because we our firm actually just
went there it was I think the past
Tuesday um that's where I met my current
firm and they you know they um come down
to come up to like Boston and they like
I network with them I talk to them
that's like one of the great ways to
know some of like the firms that aren't
really necessarily post like their job
postings anywhere um like I know that
our firm didn't really post a lot of
openings online but they would offer to
like M students because um MIT or M
program is one of our
targets um another thing um in terms
like courses I'll probably flag the um
Pro seminar classes that we have at MIT
I took the investment banking Pro
seminar
with um and it was a very exciting
Journey we partnered with one of the
investment Banks gox to do one of the
projects that's where I definitely
learned and gained some like real
hands-on experience by like doing the
modeling the process um and
talk to them um or like whoever is
really working the industry every week
so that's definitely one of the most Val
thank you George arjent is there
something that comes to mind that really
impacted you during the program for your
career growth oh yeah um absolutely the
the networking night was wonderful and I
think for me personally it was meeting
the professors and getting a perspective
from them about like what exists in the
market because prior to coming in MIT I
didn't even know a role like Stout
exists and a professor really educated
me about this because I'd come in from a
Consulting background where I loved
advising clients but I wanted to know
more about finance and specializing onto
like financial instruments and doing
more work like that and that's something
that yeah I got to know about that field
to begin with and then she was kind
enough to introduce me to a a person
who's a director of my current firm and
that's how I was able to like land this
role so yeah very grateful and that
yeah I think uh just one more to take
home would be the the overall SL
Community it's know it's extremely
divers
and everyone is extremely collaborative
as well so especially if you know if
you're one of the people you know on
this call that's just uh finishing their
undergrad and you're able to come you
know to these infant program I think
it's really amazing that you're able to
work with uh or get just advice from you
know people that are far older than you
in the different programs like the MBA
theas NBA the executive NBA you know
these except these are people at all the
different stages throughout their career
that are going to be you know in some of
these classes with you they're going to
be uh you know grabbing coffee next to
you and the ultimate uh ability to just
kind of ask questions to these
individuals that have you know built an
entire career in you know Quant trading
or you know have built a firm in the
early stage VC like I think that uh that
is a tremendous opportunity for uh
getting a level of insight that you
really can't get anywhere else other
than Sloan
you know especially at just before you
know coming out of your undergrad and I
you understand too if you're further
into your career as well I think there's
plenty of opportunity to collaborate
with them as
well you've each talked about in a way
how you learned about opportunities that
you didn't know existed until you came
in the program or you discovered your
opportunity through an event from the
program or you transitioned what your
original goals were you went through the
program can you speak to how those
resources um impacted you and how you
were supported in making those
Transitions and experiencing that growth
you know how how do you feel that you've
benefited professionally from that
growth and those resources in the
program I I'll throw it back in um I
think it terms uh I think multiple
avenues that were extremely helpful for
my group uh growth personally whether
that's you know I think is talked about
the action learning Labs uh you're you
get to work with um you know these these
you know amazing companies and you're
going to their offices and meeting with
them and actually being able to solve
you know real problems and they're
giving you you know their data where
you're able to actually feel like you're
doing something meaningful and I think
that was a you know kind of an excellent
uh kind of like a test round before you
really hit the real you know the real
market and maybe you're still figuring
out which you know is the exact pathway
you want to take in the infant program
and I think that provides you a really
great testing point to what you really
want to do and no I think the the
overall um support that you get uh with
from the CDO and all the different
faculty you know within the m0 uh just
um group is is pretty tremendous I think
uh you know I heard you can have
unlimited career advising appointments I
abuse that uh quite a bit so yeah
there's you know lots of
support um I can chiming here um so I
think the opportunities that's like
George mentioned like the CD
opportunities like appointments I
panicked during my first summer when I
saw everyone else it's like um
recruiting like filing out online
applications so I threw a lot of emails
at CDO people I was like can I have an
appointment and yes I also abuse that um
and I also use a lot of like the resume
editing and stuff like that which is
definitely helpful another thing that I
want to mention would be um CDL in a
good way like CDO kind of pushed you or
at least me push me to like look for
more opportunities checking with me to
see if I landed on like interviews with
the status of my current recruiting and
it feels like like coo people are like
more in a rush than I am actually so
that's like definitely good to always be
on the spot like sort of like being a
little bit I wouldn't say like being
pressure but always like someone is like
kind of like asking you to reach out to
make sure that you're doing the job not
just like being you know sort of like
lazy on the end just doing school work
not recruiting so that's definitely one
of the thing that I think CD did really
good at least on me by asking me the
progress by giving me like appointments
by checking with
opportunities um so sort of that and I
do remember that there are like weekly
emails from CDO career development that
we um there are like open opportunities
listed online with like the links to the
applications so that saves me a million
hours basically from like just like
looking through Linkedin or like other
career opportunities um another thing
that I do want to mention is the
community
of the M students
um like all of us were basically very
Hands-On in terms of recruiting
everything so that Community would
definitely drove at least me um sort of
like to keep recruiting in mind not just
to forget about that because besides
cours workk we would talk about
recruiting we would talk about
interviews so that like that Community
sense definitely fer my sort of like my
progress on recruiting as
well yeah definitely absolutely
seconding both of them and just adding
on a couple of things so I so the the
mbas I believe have this program called
New York Finance day where you get to go
to New York but I just wanted to say the
CD was so proactive and because I had
enough work experience under my belt I
they actually put in my name and I was
allowed to accompany the mempin for that
program which is very very helpful and
uh get in front of all the prospective
employers so I just wanted to put
Testament out to how proactive and
incredible the CDO is and secondly just
uh going further into what Emily touched
upon like the even the students that you
study with are so incredible like I
didn't come from like any sort of a quan
background at all and I still don't know
a lot but uh but my interview needed me
to know a little bit of option math and
I was fortunate enough that I had my my
fellow students training me before the
interview and stuff and I was able to do
well enough so yeah so please take
advantage of like the people around you
yeah yeah well and also um it was our PR
our privilege to work with all of you
there was no abuse of our advising
that's what we're here for but it was
always nice to see each of you in our
offices um I want to leave time for
questions in the audience so I'll my can
I give one last question Diane yes
absolutely great I just want to think
put yourself back uh two years ago when
you're deciding to apply to M fin you
know what's one thing you wish you knew
um then that you know
now I probably say prepare more um I
think there's a there's a bit of a
buffer uh between when you're accepted I
think it's usually around early March
until you start in July um I would be
remiss to say that you shouldn't use
every second that you have preparing for
the program um because as Ian said as
well earlier the the the summer that
converts into when you are you're taking
it is an accelerated timeline over the
summer and you are going to feel a lot
of pressure with the recruiting
timelines so the more prepared you'd be
going and on all the kind of topics and
honestly The Faculty does an amazing job
on making sure that they get you
everything you need to prepare for so
utilize the materials that are given to
you before you start just so you can
it'll allow you to utilize the time that
you have in the program while you're
there because it is it does go by fast
St feel like man I'm s yeah as Emily
said oh my God it's already been six
months
that's great advice again we can't
overemphasize that
enough yeah I think one thing that I
wish I knew before joining would be um
definitely reach out to MIT people um
you know working at an investment bank
right now we receive a lot of like
networking emails um and if there's like
an email from MIT email address no
matter it's you know no matter it's for
like networking or if it's for like a
general chat into the banking industry
or if it's asking if we have any open
opportunities we would answer to those
especially if you know we study at the
same
school if like you know user alarm
Network for sure um whenever I see like
an MIT email coming through I would
respond to it um although that might be
like a delay response given how given my
email volume but yes we would um answer
that not even even if we don't have any
openings you know like email us with a
resume we'll keep that on file if
there's an opening we can probably think
of you and then we can go from there so
that's definitely one thing that I do
want to uh let everyone know that if
you're an MIT kit uh email us we'll
respond great yeah absolutely I I just
second both of them in fact I just did
like an a referral for somebody who
applied at the firm so yeah
definitely yes and we talk a lot about
the network and engaging in the
community so even you know while you're
in the program being able to leverage
all those resources not only your fellow
mfin classmates but also anyone you
engage with uh when you're participating
in clubs or attending conferences
speaker series um all of the different
activities that are open to all of our
students really um can help to build
that additional community and networking
that's so important so I'm going to go
through there's um quite a few questions
some of them I think Laura may be more
for you but um let me see if I can find
um a couple of those that you could
answer and then for the alums as well so
um there is a question around
pevc and um you know enin students being
able to launch their careers directly
from enin into that and I know that I
know Laura we understand that industry
pretty well but I'll leave it to you to
respond to that
one okay sure happy to take that one so
you'll see in our employment reports you
can look at year after year we do have a
small percentage of students that go
into private Equity or Venture Capital
following the program it's usually
hovers around four or five% of the class
each year what what's true about the
private equity and Venture Capital
industry is they often like talent that
has a few years of work experience under
their belt already and so a lot of our
enin students aspire to go into private
equity and Venture Capital but they'll
do it by going to banking first and then
after two or three years pivoting into
that space um others also go through the
strategy Consulting route those tend to
be the most common Pathways to break in
there that's true for the US market it's
broadly true internationally as well
there can be some more opportunities to
go directly into PE in the European
market it it varies but generally we do
have a lot of EMP interested in that
space more in the medium to longterm um
career goals yep yeah absolutely and
again this also is important as it
relates to what we just talked about
engaging in the community getting
joining the pebc club networking with
you know our mbas executive mbas all
many of whom may have already had work
experience in that industry and they can
be you know again for your future you
have that mit.edu after your email um it
really is a very powerful um way to to
develop those networks in that community
so there were a few questions around the
rise of fintech of course and Ai and
other technological advances um what are
we seeing if at all um and maybe this is
for you Laura too but if the panelists
have any thoughts on it you know in
terms of how this is impacting the work
that they do or
careers great question I can let um the
panelists speak to the work that you do
in terms of how AI is impacting as far
as the career support and recruiting
opportunities it's something that we're
seeing a lot of our students leverage
for additional practice there's a lot of
ways that AI can help you prepare it
gives you additional practice it can
help you with your research it can help
you with feedback um and so we are
helping educate students on how to
utilize AI to help really accelerate um
their preparedness
also sourcing job opportunities I've
seen some uh AI leveraged as well for
that yeah and I mean I will also add to
that just what you know MIT is after all
research institute hence there is a
tremendous amount of um work and
opportunities to engage in the community
here around AI fintech we have the
gallab center for finance um and policy
research that does a tremendous amount
of work in fintech space um we've got
the lab for financial engineering and
then just throughout MIT because keep in
mind while you're at MIT Sloan um and it
often times you can find yourself
getting you know sort of caught up in
the bubble of MIT Sloan there's the rest
of MIT um that has a ton of work that's
being done in this space so there's lots
of ways for you to engage um and just
learn what's happening in terms of the
research as well as potential
opportunities anything else from our
alums on this topic
yeah I think um luckily if at least on
like a banking perspective like if
you're going to a more Boutique firm
imlet like uh like we're at I think the
you're you are able to leverage more of
use of using llms in some way uh you
know any kind of Open Source uh uh
format there and then implementing you
know a level of using Python and some
tasks like they're especially when you
know you are given a lot of data from
clients or there isn't some kind of data
analytics uh or kind of route that needs
to be done I think you are given a bit
of freedom to do so you know even in
like a a banking side but from like
maybe a broader industry I know it is
being used from like a more bulge
bracket perspective on helping them you
know like automate certain of tasks on
their reach out or automating on some of
the pitch deck creation where it's a
little bit easier on that side um and
then on the Quant side I think yeah it's
it's just going to be uh ultimately the
being at MIT as D was saying is
definitely the best place to be in terms
of getting a kind of a Competitive Edge
going into that market where having the
level of understanding and the level of
competition is going up and your great
understanding of how a lot of things
working uh I mean I I I took like a an
an LP class in finance and it was you
know I was with all of uh all my team
were went into you know Quant research I
was a very lucky to be on their team um
but I think yeah I think they there's a
lot of opportunity there for you know
MIT to prepare you whether you're going
the Quant side or the banking side
because of the different Dynamics I'm
going to keep you on the hook for a
minute George I know you'll you'll be
fine with this so one of the questions
for you
specifically was around the fact that
you know yes you're in corporate finance
but you you know had came from an
engineering background sort of what what
made you kind of sort of what put you in
the direction of the career choice that
you made launching your career and and
let me just preface it not to answer the
question for you but keep in mind that
this program is it's not just about the
first job out of the gate it's an entry
point for you into the field of finance
and so hopefully we'll give you the
skills that you need to really um have a
lifetime career in finance and that
could go in a number of different
directions but that said I'm going to
give you an opportunity George to
respond to
that yeah no of course I think in uh uh
I think ultimately for me like I had to
be very honest with myself with what I
was most interested in doing long term
uh I think a lot of the people that are
coming in the program that are more
focused whenever I you know I did come
in thinking the you know i' just done
engineering The Next Step must be the
financial engineering and ultimately
from taking the summer classes I found
that I was actually much more uh
oriented to wanting to do more of a
corporate finance track where it be more
the banking or the or something in in
those regards and definitely fell in
love with a lot of the banking side I
know yes you work you know long hours
and all those things but I find the job
very rewarding um so ultimately be yeah
just had to be honest with myself I
think other people coming into the
program that have the idea that I want
to you know work in a pod and a hedge
fund and or be a PM uh for and I see
that as a long-term career choice then
yes I think the um you know the more
quantitative side is definitely the the
way to go and you know honestly the I
know I saw the the median uh you know
base salary coming out I could
definitely is far higher on the if
you're going on the quantitative side
the uh it is a very attractive pathway
but uh but yeah for me I think it's it's
also playing to your strength I think as
you can tell from the call I'm probably
better interacting than uh you know than
am against some of the people in uh you
know in some of the financial
mathematics classes so yeah that's great
thank you George appreciate it and Arjun
it looks like we have a question for you
about um a little bit different Tac but
um how did you position yourself as a
good candidate without having a
quantitative background I'm not quite
sure that that's exactly what you
intended for them to understand about
your background but let let let's
suffice it to say that when we talk
about quantitative background from an
admission standpoint we're looking for
individuals who can again if you've had
an opportunity to look at our
application which I encourage you to do
if you're really interested it's live
there is some relevant coursework it's
these are not prerequisites but having a
solid foundation in what's one of our
finance faculty likes to refer to as
Elemental mathematics um linear algebra
calculus probability statistics these
are going to set you up to really um you
know be able to take advantage of
everything that MIT and mm fin has to
offer without feeling like you're always
catching up and so Arjun I'll let you
sort of uh no no absolutely fair
question uh so I uh so I we made a
conscious effort before replying so I
had done uh I learned a lot of python on
my own firstly but secondly i' had also
taken two college level math classes
which are after my undergrad like where
yeah so that really prepared me uh to be
fine enough for both yeah basically for
the first class and so forth yeah yeah
great great now thank you Arun and yes
coding a while again it's not a
prerequisite um it's really helpful to
have some familiarity with python in
particular and in fact as part of the
admissions process there will be um an
assessment if you advance in admissions
um past the application there will be as
part of the whole interview and
admissions process there will be an
assessment that includes a little bit of
coding and some mathematics so again
this is these are just foundational
we're not asking you to have advanced
python um but some coding familiarity
and of course just again a strong
foundation in
mathematics um so I think there were
some questions around uh ESG and impact
investing I don't know if any of our
panelists had an opportunity to take any
classes or maybe um got to do a course
somewhere or even an action learning
lab did anyone
hear yeah I did a u I did an action
learning lab with was with u tzp Group
which is a small uh private Equity Firm
in New York and it was basically the uh
studying the impact of uh how carbon
credits can be uh used in alternative
investing and which was I thought it was
a great experience um you know it was it
was not only uh you know being able to
come to New York and work with the the
team and but also kind of learning about
their investment approach and how they
were looking at opportunities in this
space and kind of how they could
leverage the existing uh like especially
like the EU ETF where there's a lot more
built out uh than it is in the US aside
from you know California having a bit of
a system there and I definitely had uh
there is plenty of opportunities far
beyond uh impact in you know just in
that you know one action ring line at
sure yes and we we actually thank you
George and we have an impact um Finance
club we have an impact Finance um
concentration within the program that is
optional so if it's an area or space
that you're very interested in pursuing
there's definitely um as George
mentioned many opportunities to engage
in that so we're getting close on time I
want to finish off our with our alums um
and for each of you um I thought this
was a an interesting question because we
talk a lot about the program and the
academics and the curriculum while of
course this is the primary focus but
love for each of you to answer the
question of how did you balance
coursework and any social fun activities
that you got to engage in as part of
being at MIT in the
community oh yeah absolutely I think
that's a huge part and uh one of the
clubs which I never failed to go for was
the wine club so I was a part of the
Sloan wine club during my time there and
yeah that really helps me out even today
when we go for networking events and
they clients out so yeah so that's so I
think MIT and the sloon community gives
you a lot of opport unities whether it's
like just your work or you can go wine
ceiling I think a lot yeah unbelievable
opportunities so yeah so definitely take
advantage of those yeah but certainly
test your time management skills correct
yes yes yes yes please don't go for one
if you have an exam the next day yeah
exactly thank you
Aran Emily George oh go ahead George oh
yeah yeah um I think the luckily the the
the structure of the program kind of
indirectly allows for like a super
tight-knit Community within the infant
program because whenever you do come in
over the summer you know in July and you
know the weather is beautiful in Boston
uh infant is really the the only you you
kind of have slown to yourselves uh for
that summer term and it kind of and of
course it being accelerated I think uh
the study rooms are usually always
filled uh all day long and late end of
the night so that kind of environment
allows you to get really close to people
and kind of find your you know find your
kind of close Community while also being
uh connected to the broader Community
within the infant program as well uh and
yeah you tend to just you know people
are always you know Fridays you know
going out and hanging out or you know
you you can sale at MIT as well I know
some some of the friends in in the
program absolutely love theiling um they
ask me probably every day to go out with
them uh it's there's a lot of
opportunities there okay great
Emily yeah um one thing that I didn't
get to do I didn't really have the
chance was um selling I really wanted to
do it but somehow I didn't really get
that course so for whoever's interested
definitely register early um I think
other than I mean I had a lot of fun
when I was in Boston course work versus
recruiting versus you know your own time
I think it definitely is hard when
especially when with kick off like in
summer when it's like an accelerated
summer as George mentioned and it's also
like packed study rooms at SLO
everywhere um but meanwhile like besides
that if you work for like you know the
whole day until
like 5 or 6 p.m. then you know have fun
with your classmates or like friends for
like a dinner and then maybe I don't
know some wine um it's it's it's all
doable it's not going to be like 247
you'll be grinding or like studying but
it does require a lot of like commitment
into study but it's it's not like that's
the only thing so don't be scared um I
think that I think that definitely
course design um you know we had the
choice of basically choosing what
courses we want to take in terms of like
uh what's required versus what's you
know like the credit thing that we have
to fulfill but overall like you do have
the choice of um choosing you know like
how how busy you want it to be like this
semester uh balancing off like a
recruiting timeline so I know my friends
and I basically chose lighter end of
like course load like dur fall semester
given the recruiting schedule and then
once we secured offer luckily um spring
semester was when we chose probably a
little bit more like more difficult more
time committed classes so we did have
the option to balance off cour work and
recruiting and fun and fine and that's
exactly what we want students to do is
to be able to really again it's it's a
balance and it's sometimes not easy to
strike that balance but it sounds like
all of you were able to take advantage
of of a lot of things at MIT