you know now that I'm speaking and then
transitioning I'm going to just pause
maybe change my tone of voice for for
you Bruce but I I'm really excited that
Bruce Lawler is here Bruce is uh the an
MIT Alum uh from leaders the former
leaders from manufacturing now the
leaders for Global operations program
and he had has had a wonderful career in
Industry as an entrepreneur um in
software and now in kind of software
Hardware mix um he's the current
president for digital at at rebuild
manufacturing he's also the leader of of
mimo at MIT which is um short for
machine intelligence manufacturing
operations and he's been the U you head
of this F fascinating study that I've
been an observer of for the past few
years on how manufacturers are using Ai
and other forms of machine intelligence
in their work so if I had this zoomed
out high level view of manufacturing
Bruce is going to be able to zoom in and
give you a more detailed look at at
individual manufacturer so I'm excited
for your presentation Bruce and and
thanks so much for joining
thank you very much for having
me um so today I want to talk about uh
practical applications of AI and
analytics for competitive advantage and
I will um you know our objectives today
are going to be really to help you know
where to invest to start and sustain a
digital
transformation um I want to explore some
practical and successful applications of
AI and
Manufacturing and also I want want to go
over some new generative AI use cases
that are emerging
because you can't really have a
presentation today without generative Ai
and there are actually some really uh
surprisingly powerful uh applications
that there are merging and I think
people need to to know about them so
they can start to adopt them um I'm
going to come from as Ben said two
perspectives uh one is from rebuild
manufacturing and I I'll talk a little
bit more about that in a minute
and U so that's the small and to medium
and then medium to large is more what we
cover through our research with MIT of
um you know how is AI in analytics
really being adopted in manufacturing
and uh operations and where is it
growing so first of all um rebuild
manufacturing is a a new firm we coming
up on four years old
and what we're doing is acquiring small
and medium um manufacturers but really
mostly small and building them into a
conglomerate where we think the whole is
greater than the sum of the parts by the
way we're assembling the different
companies but most importantly we're in
injecting technology uh a new management
style and capital to develop a new
manufacturing model one that we think
will scale uh within the US and allow us
to hit a lot of the issues that you know
both John and Ben have have talked
about um you know we are uh you know
it's very important that we have
manufacturing here as as I think you all
know and and Ben just said um I don't
think we've covered this I missed a
little bit of the presentations but you
know 98% of us manufacturers are small
and medium yet they generate almost half
of the industrial output and as Ben
mentioned you know it's about 9 to 10%
of the overall Workforce so it's
a you know these small and medium
manufacturers are very important and
we're trying to develop this new model
of industrialization that will work in
America and allow us not only to do
domestic production but domestic export
as as
well the fundamental problem that that
we see um isn't as much about
productivity although that's obviously
important but very much in the near term
is really a labor shortage so if you
just look at these numbers from June um
only
65 you close to 70% actually jobs are
filled so that leaves almost 30 35% of
jobs unfilled so the manufacturing
unemployment rate is at
2.4% so yeah like a third of the
positions are unfilled and that's like
600,000 jobs that will grow to 2.1
million by 2030 and so that uh that
concerns us greatly so for that reason
we need to get more productivity for
worker the second big problem we face is
the skills Gap and um you know some of
our most skilled workers are are aging
out um so we're losing 11,000 Americans
roughly per day or 4.1 million a year
and and I really liked what John was
saying it wasn't so much the handing
down of the skills but kind of leveling
up people but we also need a way to hand
the skills down um and then as this last
chart shows as a result of these
shortages uh wages are increasing yet
again driving us at a capital level to
try to figure out determine how do we
get more productivity per worker um
we're really doing three big things that
I think are a little different
um what you're hear me talk about in the
rest of the program is more on the
digital and the technology piece but we
think there are three main components uh
the first of which is kind of the tried
and true lean uh which is continuous
Improvement respect for people uh and
it's all about simplifying and
standardizing so we very much believe
simplify standardize then automate so
that's that's a core principle we have
to do that first and and uh rebuild as a
company has taken that very aggressively
we have a chief lean officer um and
that's driven through all of our
factories um very aggressively and it's
it's having an impact the second thing
um is training and and certainly John
covered this quite a bit um we see the
same gaps we've done our own training in
terms of lean and Six Sigma
fundamentally we're trying to teach
people how to do datadriven decision
making rather than a hunch or an opinion
um how they do data driven decision
making and then lastly there's lots of
tools out there that are relatively
simple uh just power automate is
a two products from Microsoft we use it
because we happen to use the Microsoft
Suite so powerbi for analytics power
automate just for automating repetitive
front office tasks uh then of course AWS
iot tools python we do use those as well
um
but
um and when you put all of those
together we see that does lead to
increased productivity so it's not just
one or the other it really is is all
three and and I think you know if
there's one message to take away from
from this talk actually it is you have
to think about these three steps even
though I'll primarily talk about the
digital
aspect and I won't go into great detail
um on this but I wanted to put these
slides up these are kind of the two
books that we at rebuild follow in terms
of our lean practice I wanted you to at
least see them and we are not talking
about lean as tools we are talking about
lean as a transformation in how you run
your business how you treat your people
how you let them lead the
improvements so let me show you some of
of the results of those three things put
together um this first one
is a thermoplastics composits line uh we
had very high scrap rates uh to the
point where we decided to stop
manufacturing uh digitize the line uh we
put a hundred different types of sensors
in looking at things like
um pressure temperature Uh current draw
thickness
and you put that system in place we
started the line up again um no surprise
that we had a similar scrap rate to
before but we were very quickly able to
drive that scrap rate down because we
could start to tie
defects to process parameters that were
incorrect
so super helpful and once again it was
kind of the the lean plus people
understanding how to use the tools uh
plus the digitization putting all three
of those things together where each one
alone would not have worked uh but it
was the summation of them that did work
in this
case this is more on the automation side
so um this is an example
of U improved scheduling and improved
nesting automation so this particular
Factory um uses laser Cuts uh sheet
steel among other things but this
particular project is about laser jet
and water jet cutting uh so what would
happen is the the in this case actually
the person running the plant would come
in and sort all the work orders for the
week um on
Sunday put them in batches and give them
to the program on Monday morning the
programmer would program all of the ways
the laser cut would cut out the sheets
of Steel as you can see here in this
diagram on the right but then we
wouldn't start production until Monday
or Monday afternoon right so you know
that was a waste so you combine lean
with how do we get rid of those wastes
and that what we're able to do with
automation
is
optimize the the actual batching of
these and the grouping putting the
things that are most similar together
this is the the thing the plant manager
was doing themselves we were able to do
it um
automatically and then uh send all that
work out to um to a layout program and
then send it to the floor so we took 10
hours a week out we reduced material
cost by 3% because we're get able to get
better utilization so those are just a
couple examples really from the factory
floor working from a small and medium
Enterprise
so now I I'll talk about the research
work that Ben mentioned um and it's part
overall of what we do at MIT mimo uh
we're really about finding the shortest
path from data to
impact and in what we do in mimo is we
really have three uh main pillars um
research education and
collaboration uh
so the research is the type of research
I'll talk about today but we also do uh
projects for major major manufacturers
like Nissan and
um um Analog Devices we actually also do
a project for uh meta on how to
optimize um data center operations which
is another type of operations so we we
it's not just manufacturing it's it's
operations for at large uh education
I'll talk a little bit more well
education is certainly today and then
collaboration I'll talk about our
symposium
and we are part of the leaders for
Global operations program which I'll
talk a little bit about as we go through
this and I will I I will bounce back and
forth between research and some of these
different programs because I want you to
see uh the resources that are available
to you and things that you can
participate in learn from actively
collaborate with others because we think
collaboration is super important so
you'll see me kind of move up and down
and I also will put some QR codes up so
you guys can um email me and um we can
get you to be part of the
conversation so this is the study that
Ben mentioned it's a longitudinal study
we ran the first study in
2021 uh we finished one in
2023 uh and then we're kicking another
one off actually right now so we'd love
to have some of you participate or most
of you um and we do this in
collaboration with McKenzie Andy
because it helps us get both the
academic and the business perspective uh
when we look at the the companies it's
literally everything from McDonald's to
Vista Print um Amgen Analog Devices I
mentioned and we look at specific
kpis different use cases the types of
business outcomes that people are trying
to achieve and then we look at the
enablers the types of things that
um that you do so it's the the people
you hire the data you collect your
governance practices are these enablers
and obviously the money you
spend so what we've found
[Music]
um is
that there's a big Delta in KP
performance um so in 2021 leaders who
who used Ai and leaders we Define as the
top quartile and we're we're presenting
them the top quartile versus the the
bottom two quartile so 2021 there were
roughly three times better uh
performance and then by 2023 we saw it
Forex so the leaders are starting to
pull away they were already ahead but
that's
accelerating and from what we can see
that Trend will continue um
for the leaders to accelerate I'll talk
a little bit more about some of the uh
the bright spots that I think are are
good so if you're not a leader today um
it's actually a great time to start so
and I'll go into that in a
minute excuse me so we look at 21
different uh
kpis um from efficiency to cost Revenue
obviously responsiveness lead time
things like that customer experience net
promoter score um energy performance
energy utilization so it's a pretty
broad evaluation of the types of things
we look
at and and that's what we're seeing as
as the
results um how do the leaders get those
kinds of results and here you see a very
stunning difference in training so
amplifying what John has excuse me John
had said so the leaders in this chart
are shown in in black and the bottom two
cor tiles are shown in uh the light blue
so leaders have very heavy training for
engineers division leaders managers
Executives and line workers across the
board
um whereas we find the bottom two ctil
simply do not do that and we think that
um it's that training in digital
Technologies at all levels and the fact
that the leaders do trust as a result of
this trend they actually trust their
employees and they give them the tools
like
um you know powerbi Etc excuse me just
one
second I apologize it's allergy season
here um
so and what John was talking about is
more this line worker training and you
can see that for the vast majority uh
they can't afford to have their own
programs so what he's was talking about
is super impactful in my
view another thing that leaders do well
that make them uh separate out is that
um they collect data
and so the way to read this chart is um
they collect almost 60% of them collect
data on more than half of their
equipment so uh you know a significant
amount of data and and what we find is
that the more data you collect the
better you treat your data the cleaner
it is the more tools you have to do
something with it so they all they all
kind of uh relate to one another but you
know it's just better organization and
and better scalability and and data is
very much like especially in an AI
context like a factory I think we all
know that if I put a robot in the middle
of a factory and I don't automate what
comes into the robot or what goes out of
the robot I don't get the effectiveness
out of the robot that I would like data
is the same way machine learning needs
to learn across the whole process and
have you know a labeled data set is what
we would call it but a a good bad
indication at the end of the line and so
if I only do one cell in the middle and
then I don't do an inspection until much
much later it's very hard for me to to
know what process actually caused the
problem so you know collecting data and
and doing some level of checking along
the way whether it's a test of some sort
is very important to have data improve
your overall process so you if you can
chain it all together that's the best
but the more processes you put together
the better and and that's what you're
seeing in this this data here
um no surprise uh leaders uh spend more
um and they've been at it longer so
although not as much as you would think
so
[Music]
um if you look at leaders stand out here
in terms of they're representing light
blue here um you know they've greatly
accelerated their investment uh but in
the other categories it's not not quite
as as big so you know everybody's
accelerating but the the leaders the way
to read this is the leaders are doubling
down right and that the the time frame
that they're getting those object is a
little bit quicker than others
so accelerate investment based on a
positive outcome so if you're not
accelerating your investments in Ai and
machine learning then obviously you're
you're going to fall
behind so another very important thing
that leaders do is they focus on common
vision and common use cases and why is
that important there are some things
that Ai and machine learning are better
at than others and also there are
several places where there's lots of
tools that are available
so you'll see here in a moment I'll talk
about
the tool usage and the availability of
of vendors to do things and that's super
important because unless you're one of
the top companies it's very difficult to
attract um data scientists and data
analytics people and and to pay them a
competitive wage it's it's just harder
and harder to justify so what you see
here is uh you know
forecasting uh Transportation Logistics
optimization and predictive maintenance
are three of the top use cases that
everyone does or the leaders all do in
this particular case and then there's a
whole group that most of them
do and so for any of you starting on
your journey I would certainly suggest
picking things that other people are
already doing um you've got better
benchmarks and better
tools and
so this is just a small snapshot um what
we do for all our participants is we
make a customized Playbook uh for
everybody or for each participant and it
shows how you performed it's proprietary
to you no one else sees it um how you
performed against the rest of the uh
your industry and and the rest of the
participants overall but more
importantly than than benchmarking is
it's really designed to give you a guide
of what things you should think about
next so you know if you end up being an
emerger in our category we have four
categories I didn't get into it uh and
you can read more about this if you go
to our website uh there's links to
Harvard Business review article there's
some links to other articles where you
can learn more about the study
um but we group people into four
categories and you essentially
transition from one to the next and we
give you some guidance on what you might
want to think about next like training
as an example or data data collection
right so uh this is available I'll give
you a link here at the end on how to
participate in the study and and we'll
generate this playbook for
you um so another resource that that we
have in as part of the leaders for
Global operations program is a use case
library because the question that's
often asked is well how do you use it
what does that mean um what kind of
results can I get how should I approach
it and so in conjunction with the
leaders for Global operation program and
these manufacturers we we're creating
this use case
Library uh based on a six-month on-site
research program so the lgo program the
students get a master's in engineering
and an MBA from Sloan and as part of
their two-year program they go onsite to
one of these companies listed here
and essentially do research Implement
some solutions and then uh see the
results and write a thesis and so that's
what's captured in this use case library
and to give you an example I said
forecasting is one of the top use cases
right and so here I went into the
database and found uh six uh thesis that
address AI in forecasting and the the
three big themes were how do I increase
sales how do I reduce in inventory and
how do I use
um uh forecasting to inform where I
should invest so some of these are
really kind of Interest some you would
predict and some are pretty interesting
like one of the partner companies
predicts garment Siz mix based on the
text description and characteristics of
the Garment that they've designed so
they design a new garment they write up
a description of it they characterize it
you know in short sleeve long sleeve
pattern whatever and then the algorithm
predicts how many small mediums and
larges or two four sixes and eights they
should make of that particular uh of
that particular um design um you know
another one at the bottom informing
investment is uh how do I predict EV
charging demand so I know where I need
to build additional
distribution facilities for my
electricity
so a wide range of things I won't go
into all of them right now but I think
you get the idea of the the broad
types I guess the big takeaway from this
slide is there's lots of different ways
to use AI in manufacturing it's not just
a chatbot for generative Ai and
predictive maintenance uh which is kind
of what people tend to gravitate to uh
generally so I want to give you a couple
of case studies from our past mimo
Symposium so every year we run uh AI
accelerate impact um uh at mit's campus
we hosted in conjunction with
manufacturing at MIT so um ours will be
May 6 and their Symposium will be May
7th uh we'll focus on AI and
Manufacturing and they focus on on uh
new manufa Advanced manufacturing
technology and policy uh and we uh we
host AI
acceleration accelerate impact in
conjunction with Cale so we bring not
only the the best of manufacturing but
the best of AI uh from within MIT
together uh for this Symposium so uh
I'll have a link at the end hopefully
you'll be able to join us but I'll now
give you an idea of of some of the
things that we talk about
so North American stainless uh sits on
the Ohio River south of Cincinnati um
normally you would think it's not a very
Advanced company they make stainless
steel for beer kegs and refrigerators
they bring in um scrap um stainless
steel and then they convert it into
these different products and they do it
in massive U foundary furnaces like this
that you know the electricity demand is
almost half of of their expense so being
more efficient is is obviously very
important to
[Music]
them what's really interesting about
them
is they have six people in their data
science team out of 1,400 employees but
they have 70 employees that are um data
literate they can write a SQL search
they can do um you know use analytical
tools do those kinds of tools
which shouldn't surprise you I want all
of you to think just for a minute how
many sensors do you think they have
throughout this Factory that they ingest
into their data
Pipeline and I know we can't really do
raise of hands but I want you to think
of a number before I tell you the answer
the answer is 30,000 so there's 30,000
sensors throughout this platform Pro
Factory and so that presents a problem
for them of how to know where to focus
and so they've partnered and I'll
emphasize you know some different people
you can partner with but in this case
falconry and they've taken these um data
points in they've looked at historical
data seen what kind of fluctuations are
normal based on Seasons demands Etc and
then they're able to figure determine
which ones are abnormal so doing anomaly
detection and so in this particular
chart the yellow are anomalies and
essentially what we're trying to do with
this cloud-based ml product is to blow
away the hay and leave me with a stack
of needles that quote actually came from
the senior VP of manufacturing at Nissan
on a project we were doing there but
it's the same thing here when something
starts to not be
right I'm not at the point where I can
have ai correct it but I can certainly
have ai help me where to go look and so
in this particular case at the timestamp
shown in red I would start to look at
things that are in yellow because they
are statistically different from what
I've seen over the last two years and
that's super valuable in terms of of
troubleshooting so I'll switch now I've
got uh a few minutes left here um to
talk about generative Ai and large
language model um types of applications
there's really three big ones I'll talk
about so multiple choice Innovation um
today when you think about design you
design toward one Optimum what you'll
see in the future is you will Design
many things um generatively and then use
machine learning to help you down select
which ones are better
um and you can actually if you're even
more sophisticated you can use
reinforcement learning to help you
actually sort through those even faster
um I think we've all seen task
automation of of just what generative AI
can do today primarily in terms of words
um but there are lots of tasks that that
certainly we can think about automating
um and and many of them have constraints
so I can test whether I have a good
output or not and that's that's very
important and then the last one is a
co-pilot for workers how do I help less
skilled workers become more skilled how
do I bring the expertise of the many uh
to the the the vital
few so the first uh multi- Choice
Innovation uh this use case is actually
from BMW although these are not BMWs the
objective is to design uh a a new design
and
I I pick on the Pontiac Aztec because
it's particularly unappealing design but
in this case generative
AI generated a set of designs that are
likely to be desirable uh based on a a
diffusion model essentially was doing
this and then they also trained a
classifier to predict uh consumer
preference so they had people look at
different designs and determine which
ones they liked and then this class fire
was able to uh predict what it thought
people would say so in this case you
know it's like a Chevy Tahoe people
rated it 2.44 preference uh the model
predicted 2.27 same thing for I don't
know what the lower one is maybe a Ford
Explorer um type of thing and then use
that classifier to look back at all
these designs that were generated and
Bubble Up the ones that seemed like
humans would like the best and then
designers can use that as as a starting
point for new
designs um this next use case is super
impactful it's from uh the Panasonic
North parasonic energy of North America
Factory in Reno Nevada uh they make 5.5
million battery cells a day um a lot of
them go into Teslas or maybe all of them
go into Teslas or Tesla products um they
have 350 maintenance technicians uh
servicing these machines the machines
have you know about 10,000 Parts each
and they have a hundred of them so it's
a lot to maintain and what they were
able to
do
um I'll give you two examples so this
first one was they recorded maintenance
technicians doing different
tasks
um and then it was able to automatically
generate document ation it did captures
out of the video it transcribed the the
text and allowed it to quickly generate
documentation on how to do something
whatever the thing was so they could
very quickly create documentation and
then that is still reviewed by a human
but it takes much much less time to
review and edit than to create and and
do screen grabs out of it and and this
was in
um partnership with pal paler using
their AI industrial base plate
product uh this next one is AI powered
maintenance and repair so what they did
here is they they took uh a million
trouble tickets so what was the problem
and what was the description and then
what was done and they trained an a
generative AI model
to give guidance to these 350
maintenance technicians and so
now they're able to bring somebody in
and that isn't as familiar and really
reduce the amount of wrench time uh
onboard people um you know instead of
years down to months
so you know it does help them solve real
issues uh because if any of you have
been to Reno it's not necessarily A A
manufacturing base this is one of the
the comparatively few manufactur firms
there so they had to bring people from
hospitality and other Industries and
train them to to be in these roles so
tools like this are super important for
them so got a few minutes left I'll talk
what's new uh what's coming and or here
um so we've all well maybe not but uh
it's a thing called a foundation model
which is some of these more basic models
that are the foundation of other things
and so we're training new ones so a
company called Landing AI is making
domain specific large Vision models so
if I look at the vision models that are
trained today they're trained on uh
General things from throughout the
internet
and you know bananas trees dogs cats Etc
and then we try to use them to do things
in for this in this case semiconductor
Wafers well I think we know that in a
factory things look different so what
Landing AI is doing is they're training
Foundation models based on the things
you see in a factory so now it's more
able to recognize the things you see in
a factory uh what ground light is doing
is they're using visual language models
to to interpret ask questions of scenes
and get answers back and so we're now in
an age where we can ask what the the
measurement is on an instrument so I
actually put a camera on a gauge and get
a reading of it um
using new generative AI models and so
they're a company working in that area
and then what sensible is doing is a
video language model so they're looking
at video and you can ask questions of
the video of what is going on and that
can specifically be used to characterize
assembly operations here it's a
logistics operation so these are what
what's coming um they're actually in
some cases here today um you know
generative CAD we're seeing more there
this
is CAD files generated from text prompts
why is that important because we're
seeing that large language models can
generate code um you know they can
generate python C all things that
co-pilot that's actually one of the
first and most popular applications so
now imagine we can train it to write
code that then
writes CAD files so I'm almost finished
here I know I'm at time um draft Aid
they make uh 3D
models or they take 3D models and
produce 2D production drawings from them
which we all need out in our factories
and then uh two companies doing uh
generative tool path creation so
certainly at rebuild and other companies
CNC programming is a bottleneck
companies are starting to use that um
using generative AI to create their new
tool paths for CNC
programming so with that I'd like to
invite you to join the conversation you
can either uh go to that URL memo.
mit.edu cont or hit that QR code with
your camera and tell us that uh you know
you'd like to participate in the study
we would love to have you no matter
where in the world you are or what
you're Your Role is and then we'd love
to have you attend this Symposium on May
the 6th 2025 in Cambridge thank you
wonderful thanks so much Bruce and I
think you're you're kind of you have a
wealth of examples and uh not only
examples of you know what we might think
of as uh applications of narrow Ai and
Manufacturing but also just examples of
you know good data science and and how
to build the workforce to support these
types of Technologies so thank you very
much for sharing