it's a great pleasure to basically give
a a general background introduction to
what Victoria is going to talk about in
the the second uh more detailed part um
and what I'll I'll basically try to do
is is focus indeed on the the big
picture of how can we use and uh
computational amics to decipher the
chemical language of the
microbiome what is the the chemical
language of the
microbiome well um of course in
microbiomes in Animal microbiomes Plant
microbiomes Human
microbiomes uh we see that there's a lot
of interactions going on between uh
bacteria between bacteria uh and the
host uh between beneficials and
pathogens Etc uh and many of these
interactions are actually mediated by
molecules uh very frequently specialized
metabolites but sometimes also uh
uh like primary
metabolites here you see some examples
in in the in the context of a plant
microbiome where we know that for
example pathogens May uh produce
molecules like pathogenicity factors
that actually facilitate the infection
process um there may be other uh
bacteria that actually inhibit the
pathogens by making molecules that are
actually for example um antimicrobial or
antifungal U there's also interactions
between the microbes and sometimes also
the host actually interacts with the
microbiome itself through such
metabolites and these metabolites you
could consider them as the chemical
language of the
microbiome um and they fulfill all sorts
of rules so
traditionally um many people mainly
thought of like antibiotics as the the
key kind of function of um of these
kinds of metabolites and of course there
are many antibiotics and antim Rials uh
out there that do play a role in in
microbiome interactions but I think uh
recently it's become much more clear
that the whole range of different
functions of these molecules is also
much broader of course uh it's well
known that you have molecules involved
in communication like form sensing
signals for example but also for example
U molecules that had initially be
thought of as as toxins like doxy Rubin
is a cytotoxic molecule that is actually
an anti-cancer drug
was recently shown to actually play a
key role in in Fage defense so the
ecological role may actually be quite
different from the biological activity
that was initially U measured similarly
there is many molecules that are
involved in nutrient AC acquisition you
see here also at the at the bottom right
you see fenin which were traditionally
known as kind of weak
antibiotics um but Diane y's group from
CCH actually showed that there actually
Redux active molecules that play a role
in mobilizing
solubilizing nutrients like like
phosphorus so lots of different roles
that all of these molecules have and
that also explains why they're so
incredibly uh diverse so actually when
you look across uh bacteria in
microbiomes you see that many bacteria
that have basically the same 16s
sequence that are part of the same
species these bacterial strains can
sometimes have vastly uh different uh
metabolic capacities with regard to
these specialized uh metabolic functions
so they may make quite different uh
molecules so we can also see this by
looking at the way the production of
these molecules is encoded in in genomes
for example for secondary metabolites we
look at what we call biosynthetic Gene
clusters so these are clustered groups
of genes that are adjacent on the
chromosome and that encode for all the
entic Machinery to make these molecules
uh also to transport them out of the
cell U Etc and you see often there is a
a correspondence between the chemistry
of these molecules as well as the the
genes that are part of these Gene
clusters here you see for example uh
this this Moy in in blue cumarin Mortin
rubbery is shared with this other
molecule in semyon and you see also
between these Gene clusters U their
their Corr responding uh the
corresponding genes that are responsible
for making that part of the the
structure are also
shared so looking at the genes within
these Gene clusters can therefore tell
you quite a bit uh about the
chemistry and this also tells us if we
look at the genomes of these organisms
that indeed um yeah very frequently
these Gene clusters are gained or lost
within species or they horizontally uh
transferred and that actually leads to a
lot of ecological uh specialization
and because of this actually the the
whole repertoire of these molecules is
extremely diverse so there's really many
hundreds of thousands uh or maybe
millions of different bacterial
molecules uh out there and we recently
teamed up with the group of Nadin seat
in in tuban uh to basically do an
analysis for the secondary metaboli B
synthetic Gene clusters of how diverse
are they really and and what percentage
of all these molecules do we
already known and that was done uh by
basically identifying across publicly
available genomes all of these bi
synthetic Gene clusters then grouping
them into families through a clustering
algorithms and actually we Ed two
independently uh developed clustering
algorithms one in my group Big Slice and
one from The helal Institute
pharmaceutical research in Germany
called customatic but as you see they
actually gave similar results these were
used to group the gene cluster family to
group these Gene clusters into families
uh in a way that ideally all of the gene
clusters in one family correspond to
Pathways that are making similar uh
molecules and we did that at the level
of granularity that was calibrated or
fine-tuned based on a database of
chemical structure called the natural
product Atlas uh so that in cases where
for a gene cluster the chemical product
uh was known we made sure that gen
clusters with uh chemical products that
are part of the same chemical classes in
NP Atlas would also end up in the same
family so uh in that sense Gene clusters
were clustered in at the same level of
granularity that the molecules were
clustered in NP Atlas as as chemical
classes so if we then do a rare faction
analysis we can predict how many of
these chemical classes are out there in
the biosphere based on currently uh
available U gen
information and according to this
analysis you see that you end up with a
prediction of well between 70,000 and
100,000 different chemical classes of
which at the moment only two and a half
thousand are known and that equals
around yeah 3% of the the predicted
chemical space as being known yes can I
ask in this context for the max um what
environment are they covering and did
you was there some quality filtering
involved to where there only high
quality ones or also lower quality Max
so what was the genome assemblage
quality of those yeah so the analysis on
the left that was uh based on only Isola
genomes and then of course we also
checked and that's the analysis on the
right uh like if we look into metagenome
assembled genomes that may cover also
part of the uncultivated uh majority of
microbes um yeah does that actually
change the situation and of course it's
a bit difficult with mags because
actually very frequently these Gene
clusters are missed in mags because they
are uh often strain specific and if you
have a combination of strains in the
same metag genomes they will not be
correlated in terms of abundance with
other conts of the same genomes um but
yeah if we looked we looked here at uh
at several high quality Mac collections
that were available um at the at the jgi
and that's what what Satria did the
person who uh who worked on this um and
yeah basically what what he saw is that
of course in terms of known types of
gene clusters that are in this database
my big and I will tell a bit more about
that later of known bthe Gene clusters
with known products there're only
there's very limited overlap with uh
metag genome asemble genomes and there's
also quite a bit of quite a substantial
fraction of King Cluster families that
are only found in the metagenome
assembled genomes and not in any isol
genome know which would actually
indicate that maybe we know less than 3%
of everything that's out
there
yes so then the question becomes like if
indeed it's really the vast majority of
the microbial chemistry in these
microbiomes and in the microbial
biosphere that is yet unknown is how do
we mine that um that diversity how do we
figure out uh across these millions uh
of Gene clusters and these tens of
thousands of chemical classes that are
uh likely out there which are the ones
that really matter because of course we
can't go after them one by one because
well actually characterizing
structurally characterizing um one of
these molecules elucidating the
biosynthetic pathways that's uh yeah
that's at least like multiple PhD
projects and if you multiply that by
tens of thousands you can uh kind of
calculate that's a few centuries of of
work likely still with with current like
um biochemical Technologies but we'
really like to find out like where are
the the hidden gems inside um this
biochemical diversity and this is a a
picture that was made by an artist from
nature review genetics when we had a a
review there and it kind of nicely shows
the process of what we call genom mining
so we have the DNA sequence here that's
going in this m shaft uh and it's it's
lined by a lot of stuff but only some of
that stuff are the the hidden gems and
what what would be the hidden gems and
and I would say there there will be two
things uh two general categories that I
would I would see as important things to
go after one of them is how to find
those molecules that can really explain
mechanistically and functionally the
microbiome Associated phenotypes such as
phenotypes associated with with health
and disease uh and second uh of course
also molecules that uh could lead to uh
for example the development of new drugs
or new prop protection agents or other
molecules of societal
relevance so in this process of minding
um the biochemical diversity of the
microbiome um I will lead you through
three three steps in terms of the
algorithms and tools that we use for
this first of all is the it's the
identification of these Gene clusters
second is how do we chart their
diversity across large data sets of many
genomes or metag genomes and thirdly how
do we start predicting uh functions and
that really boils down to prioritizing
that large diversity to the specific
Gene clusters uh and and molecules that
really
matter so let's start at the start like
the identification of these metabolic
Gene clusters um and this is something I
actually started with when I was a PhD
student myself uh yeah a little bit over
15 years ago uh when there is just there
were just a few genomes uh available uh
and I was given one uh streptomyces
genome uh myself to to look for
biosynthetic Gene clusters and I was
doing it some kind of semi-manually by
doing like blast searches and and these
kinds of things and I found it very
tedious and and boring and I thought
okay it should be possible to to make
this more automated and actually at the
time there was a project here at the
broad Institute where people were
sequencing like 20 genomes and back in
those days like 20 genomes was like how
do you even start analyzing that right
uh that's that's just
impossible
um but uh we did start working on it in
collaboration with um group in in
Germany KY blin and and silmana um and
we basically used a general strategy
that is still being used in in many of
the tools today simply because it really
allows a very precise tuning of the uh
identification of these Gene clusters
where you start with an input uh genome
sequence and then you use a rule based
approach uh it's basically by finding
specific combinations of protein domains
that are cooc adjacently in the same
chromosomal region on the same
chromosomal Locus within a defined uh
distance and that uh that specific
combination of domains is indicative of
the presence of a certain certain type
of bthe Gene clusters because these
domains represent like the key enzimatic
domains that catalyze the key reactions
for such type of pathway for example
here we have like three key domains for
a given pathway types A B and C and you
might then create a rule that says okay
if we find either or domain a with
either domain b or domain C then we're
going to trigger the detection rules
saying okay this must be this and this
um kind of pathway and these kind of
logical rules you can tune uh yourself
and and U and also fine-tune calibrate
in a lot of detail uh and in in a
relatively complex space it it really
allows you to manually kind of draw a
line around your data points uh so to
say to very accurately uh predict
well-known types of mice Gene clusters
of course this um may not be the the the
best approach for finding entirely novel
kinds of pathways
um but actually when we look at most of
these types of gene clusters the type
the key the core enzymology is very well
defined and that actually makes this
generally more accurate than for example
um machine learning uh methods uh which
are very useful for finding Noel things
um but not so U much for for finding
these well-known types of gene clusters
based on relatively small amounts of
training data so this is formalized uh
can I hi yeah can I ask a question
please um with these rules like how
often do you I don't know this kind of a
vague question but if you're just
looking within a genome sequence and you
have these rules versus when you're
looking in a metag genome and it might
be that A and B are in one bug and C is
in the other and now would that be
considered passing the rule or is this
all just within a genome sequence this
is all within one chromosomal Locus
within one region in a chromosome so
generally it kind of the Assumption is
that all of the genes are clustered in
the in the same genome in the same
genomic location and that is in bacteria
for these kinds of Pathways It's usually
the case and 95 99% to another part of
the genome like a b is here and C moved
somewhere like I don't know a million
bases away or something that's rare
that's very rare in bacteria so actually
uh evolution somehow tends to optimize
for the the genes to be very tightly
clustered probably because they uh
they're co-regulated in this way they
they move together because there is also
a lot of horizontal Gene transfer and
there's there's a couple of reasons why
why this is likely the case if you look
at other organisms like plants actually
for example like maybe half of the bisy
synthetic pathways are not clustered in
plants and there we actually need to
rely on other things like coexpression
uh to connect these genes and you can't
just rely on the the co
localization so in uh so this anti-
smash software which yeah uh I started
working on as a PhD student is U well
actually has undergone many uh many
versions now we're about to release
version eight where not only does it
identify the bthe gene clusters but
there are also a range of different uh
follow-up analyses to to kind of
annotate the gene clusters in detail in
terms of the the enzymes encoded um
comparative genomics etc
etc so I was just saying that for for
most of the biosynthetic pathway types
we can actually very accurately detect
them in this way I think for for the the
majority of the the canonical secondary
metabolic pathways and and Gene clusters
we anti- smash detects them like with
more than 99% accuracy there are also
some kinds of Pathways that are actually
more tricky uh and more difficult and
that's because they don't very work very
well with this this kind of rule-based
concept because there is not uh domains
a b or c that are always uh present uh
and in particular this is the case for
the ribosomally synthesized and
post-translationally modified peptides
which also often play key roles in in
microbiomes and these are also called
rips short so that's the abbreviation um
and the thing is how these these Gene
clusters are are put together is you
have this tiny precursor peptide
encoding Gene like a a gene that encodes
for the production of a small peptide
and then you have some transporter often
to to transport it out of the cell some
modifying enzymes but they could
actually be anything uh so that actually
makes them really diverse so there's not
of course within specific classes of
these rips you find the same modifying
enzymes um but it's becoming clear that
um yeah there is really many dozens or
maybe hundreds of these classes out
there that all use different modifying
enzymes so there is very little in
common in terms of protein domains
between like the full breadth of these
types of gene clusters and that makes U
these specific types of gene clusters is
actually more uh challenging uh to to
detect
yeah so these modifying enzymes they
they could be anything and also for this
reason we we actually came up with a
specific um like alternative way of of
approaching this to find these types of
gene clusters are we actually start with
a machine learning model that first
tries to identify these precursor
peptide encoding genes trained based on
all of the known precursor peptide
encoding genes and actually see that
there is a number of physical chemical
properties related to their amino acid
composition charge characteristics and
and others that actually sets them apart
from uh from other small genes um so
there are certain physical chemical
characteristics that these um peptides
they tend to have in order to to be
stable not to be protea uh
like degraded very quickly um and also
to be to be
bioactive and in in that way we can
actually separate uh Rel ly well
potential pre R precursor uh encoding
genes from other small genes but of
course there's so many small genes out
there that even if you can do this at
99% accuracy you'll get still a lot of
false positives so we had to also
combine that with other criteria uh and
we do that by also looking like are they
within an are these putative precursive
peptide encoding genes are they located
in an operon structure uh with uh with
other genes that are enzyme encoding and
we're not limiting ourselves in this
case to specific enzyme families but we
just want to see enzymes because that
indicates that there is something
enzymatic going on um and another
Criterion is that many of these Gene
clusters actually are flying in and out
of genomes so they're usually not part
of the core Genome of a species or a
Genus so that's why we can also measure
that with a like an orthology
conservation score saying if they're
part of the the core uh of a Pang Genome
of a species or genus then they're much
less likely to be rips because these are
often specialized functions that are
strain or species specific if they're
part of the accessory genomes they're
much more likely to be and if we combine
uh basically all these criteria and we
decate it by removing all of the stuff
that we can already identify with uh
with anti smash U that actually uh yeah
gives us um a data set that you that is
actually small enough to manually go
through and highlight uh basically
candidate uh new classes of rip M
clusters and we did this a couple of
years ago in strepto mes which is a
model bacterium for secondary metabolism
and already there in this one genome we
or in this one genus uh we found around
40 to 50 candidate new classes of um of
rip biosynthetic Gene clusters and that
corresponds to actually thousands of
biosynthetic Gene clusters in these uh
in these genomes and by now we've also
run this on a range of other Genera
including Genera from the human
microbiome um and there is really a lot
uh toh to discover in this way still so
that's that's pretty exciting can I also
ask another question um is the ordering
of genes important and also what
strength the gene is on so can I have
basically have a bio synthetic Gene
claster with genes on different strands
and would that be considered um
somehow yes so sometimes my synthetic
Gene clusters can be pretty large like
some of the largest ones can be 100 or
200 kilobases uh and then you might have
10 or 20 upper arms that are pointing in
different directions uh but they're
still clustered so yes that's totally
possible um the order of the genes um I
don't think there's actually been a a
good paper to quantitatively uh prove
this but actually quite frequently the
order also matches the order of
reactions um not always but more
frequently than not uh and this probably
has to do with like being able to
quickly make molecules that enzymes that
carry out the first steps need to be
synthesized first they start carrying
out the first reaction and then in the
meantime the next proteins are also made
Etc can I ask another General question
um if you look bacterial species where
more is known like eoli or and you try
to I don't know identify the fraction of
the genome that's biosynthetic Gene
clusters or that makes rips like what is
that fraction and then like how does
that fraction compare to just like the
average genome that you take I don't
know say in an environmental metagenome
sample and you try to like annotate
things like how
much there like a really well studied
genome where we can annotate everything
compared to one where we know much less
I'm just trying to like so so all of
this is I don't know at a high level
kind of based around homology is that
kind of right yes so I'm just kind of
curious like how much we need to know
for an environmental sample you think
most of these enzymatic pathways are
actually uh pretty ancient so they're
it's really the same families of enzymes
that you find like in model organisms
versus uh cultivated ones although I am
sure that there will be stuff that is
very like um specific to a specific clay
um but then these are usually also less
widespread types of pathway so there are
stuff that we're missing probably in
this sense but if we look at like the
widespread General classes of bis
synthetic Pathways um yeah I don't think
there is a big difference in our ability
to annotate them in eoli versus um like
uncultivated ACO bacteria or
something thank and the like the
percentage of the genome devoted to it
it can range from like 1% to 20% uh or
yeah in that order of
magnitude
yeah so then at some point we also
became interested and and this was in a
collaboration with with Michael Fishback
who was currently at Stanford University
and I spent some time uh in his lab
about 15 years ago when I was a PhD
student and he um he basically came to
me and said well actually in the gut
microbiome there's so many of these
primary metabolic Gene clusters that are
also frequently strain or species
specific and really drive the ecological
ecological niches of uh of the bacteria
that that Harbor these types of gene
clusters for example you have Gene
clusters for uh converting primary to
secondary B acids their Gene clusters
for short chain fatty acids production
amino acid catabolism etc etc um so yeah
that's basically what started the
project that Victoria will tell more
about where we made like another version
of U or flavor of of anti smash which
was called gut smash which is really
focused on finding um all of the
well-known types of catabolic uh Gene
clusters and their their Pathways uh
that are also relevant to to gut
microbiome research yeah Victoria will
tell a lot more about that in Heron in
the meantime we're also working on other
flavors for example uh we've been
recently building and that's about to
come out um risos smash which is for for
plant microbiomes where we actually look
at catabolic Gene clusters for the
catabolism of a root Exodus because like
plants they exud 20% of their
photosynthetic carbon uh to the
rizosphere so actually a lot of organic
acid sugars um Etc they're exuded to
actually recruit and modulate their
microbiome so understanding like what
kind of um catabolic Pathways and Gene
clusters that the members of the
microbiome has and in this case also
tell us like how can plants recruit
which U microbes to their their
microbiome
okay that brings me to to The Next Step
um and that is really charting the
diversity of these Gene clust
um because of course you can identify
them in single genomes but of course
yeah generally we don't work with single
genomes not even with 20 genomes like in
uh 2010 but maybe 20,000 or 20 million
genomes um and for that we actually
together with International
collaborators build an extensive
software ecosystem of tools that are
interoperable with each other that
really allow this kind of large scale uh
analysis I already mentioned briefly the
the big slice clustering algorithm at
the start which groups Gene clusters
into families um in general we we start
with the the gene clusters that we can
predict or identify in genomes with anti
smash dut smash Riser smash um then we
have databases like mayic for known B
synthetic Gene clusters which at the
moment hosts about 3,000 Gene clusters
with known chemical products and then we
can start grouping these Gene clusters
into families with either with the
sequence similarity networking that's in
big scape or with vector-based
clustering approaches like in in Big
Slice when you do it with big scape you
get these networks where each node
represents one bis synthetic Gene
cluster or metabolic Gene cluster and
they're connected to each other uh if
their Mutual similarity based on a
number of distance metrics and I'll come
back to that in a moment uh is higher
than a certain threshold and in this way
you can with graph clustering also group
them into families to know which clust
ERS across a set of genomes are actually
closely related to each other and are
likely to encode for the same kind of
pathway so coming back briefly to this
this database of of known bog Gene
clusters uh this is also really fun
project which has really been uh an open
science uh initiative so uh earlier this
year we actually ran like massive online
parallel annotation marathons so we had
like um
um halfday Zoom sessions with more than
250 people who all came online to
actually annotate all of these gen
clusters in a standardized way um
they're subdivided into teams based on
their expertise we had a review system
to actually ensure also the the quality
of the annotations and in this way we
can really get a lot of information that
is out there uh in the literature uh in
into this database in a standardized
format and it's really also the basis
for a lot of the um followup like
prediction algorithms that you can build
within this
space so then to to Big scape the the
clustering of these Gene cluster
families the key trick that we employed
there is that we start by basically
translating the sequences of these Gene
clusters to strings of protein domains
to kind of have a small scale uh
representation of a gene cluster so you
do protein domain calling and then you
have let's say strings of protein
domains that represent a bis synthetic
Gene cluster um and in The Next Step
these P cluster representations they can
be
um uh compared to each other using a
couple of different metrics the simplest
metric is just to say okay jard index of
the protein domains like if you have a
pair of these Gene cluster protein
domain strings what fraction of the
protein domains are shared between both
of them or are unique to either one or
to the other you can also do that with
pairs of adjacent protein domains which
tells us something about the
conservation of of order uh and that can
be done with uh also with triplets for
example um and then finally uh but also
importantly we want to have some
indication of how similar uh these
domains actually are to each other in
terms of sequence because some of these
protein domains can have very broad
functions and you actually need to know
how closely related are they really uh
in sequence because that tends to
correlate pretty well with the chemistry
and the catalytic activity of the
enzymes of course so this is done
sometimes you have different copy
numbers of the domains and that also
needs to be taken into account so yeah
we in case there's like two domains in
one gene cluster and one domain in the
other Gene cluster we' regard like the
the best scoring pair of these uh to
take the the sequence identity between
them and the other uh we would basically
give a zero so that the duplication
index is also taken into account and
then for the sequence identity uh itself
U of course the sequences need to be
aligned and actually the the by far the
quickest way to do that is to align them
all against the Prof Mark of models with
which they were detected at first so
initially we did it using multiple
sequence alignment like muscle and math
type of sequence alignment but that
scales horribly because you have all
versus all comparison uh and it BAS
Bally takes a lot of time um but by
actually aligning aligning all the
sequences against um U the hit marov
model
profiles uh actually it it uh it's
almost linear in terms of runtime when
you go to larger samples so that makes
makes a big
difference and then we can visualize
this of course so here is um an output
of uh first version of big scape where
you get U this kind of uh
output for in this case 120 genomes you
see like an absence presence Matrix of
families of Gene clusters across uh
different genomes can then also go to a
specific type of Gene cluster like in
this case a type of Pathways related to
PKS poly ketide synthesis um and here
you can interactively really also in um
browse and and explore these kinds of
network for example also by typing in
keywords like the molecules that are
related to these known bthe Gene
clusters reference bgc's from my big and
it will highlight it in the network and
you you will immediately see which other
gen clusters from certain organisms are
closely related to this and you get a a
multilocus fenny also of these Gene
clusters to see what are the how they're
related and what are the key
similarities and
differences at the moment we're uh we're
bringing out a second version of this
which is uh going to be a lot faster
about 10 times uh Faster
by through a number of additional uh
tricks and also through local storage of
all the intermediate data uh you can
actually use this to hundreds of
thousands of uh Gene clusters easily um
so yeah basically without Ram
limitations okay I'll briefly skip this
this um because I want to have a little
bit of time to go for to the the last uh
part of my talk which is a bit of the
forward-looking part which is how do we
really predict which of these Gene
clusters actually matter what are their
uh what are their likely functions um
and I think this is really one of the
key questions in this very large genomic
space so there's so many of these
metabolic Gene clusters out there which
have all sorts of functions and we
really need to predict for example in
microbiome setting um which ones really
matter to explain a certain microbiome
Associated phenotypes this is really a
key challenge that I've been tackling
with my group as part of an ERC grant
that is U uh finishing next year already
uh it's called the decipher uh where
we've been following a couple of
different strategies to try to predict
functions of these my sythetic gen
clusters the first strategy that we've
been following is actually expression
based so sometimes you have um like a
range of samples and you have phenotypic
metadata on them for example um Health
disease metadata and you can actually
look at for example the expression of a
BGC and C is that associated with the
phenotype or not very simplistically and
in this case if you have the the
microbiome Associated phenotype here at
the left across samples and you see that
the expression of this red Gene cluster
corresponds much better to the phenotype
than the expression of the blue Gene
cluster so yeah from that you you might
think okay maybe the red Gene cluster is
more likely to be involved in mediating
that
phenotype but what you could also do is
actually use the Expression uh patterns
of other genes and other Gene clusters
either within the same genome or across
genomes of different members of the
microbiome and use these as uh as your
phenotypes so when whenever a certain
Gene cluster is expressed what happens
in the rest of the cell what happens in
the rest of the microbiome uh could that
be causally uh related
essentially and for this uh Zack writes
former post loock in my lab um developed
a tool called Coco Locus which generates
these coexpression networks of metabolic
Gene clusters and other genes in the
genome here the large uh nodes are the
gene clusters in a given genome and
they're represented by say an igen
Vector of the expression levels of their
constituent genes and all the gray
smaller notes there other genes in the
genome that are strongly correlated in
expression uh with at least one of these
uh metabolic Gene
clusters and you can also already see
that there's groups uh forming of Gene
clusters that tend to be uh coexpressed
and you can also um d into that further
by also including regulatory information
for example transcription Factor binding
sites and here you see for example and
this is work of of Hana who is down here
uh who actually annotated this this
network and saw that like all of the
genes and the gene clusters over here
they all have binding sites for this
specific regulator called dmd1 which is
involved in in Iron uh response and
actually two of these three Gene
clusters uh these two two of these three
over there they're actually encoding the
bi biosynthesis of known cidera fores
which are iron Scavenging molecules
which also play a key role in like the
battle for iron between microbes and the
host and the
microbiome but at the same time she also
saw another Gene cluster in that same
part of the expression network uh of the
co-expression network which was an
unknown uh Gene cluster for which we
didn't know a function yet um and she
made crisper cast workouts of all of the
genes in that Gene cluster and it
actually turned out to be also involved
in sad for biosynthesis which really uh
indicates that indeed uh you can use
this kind of inference uh to predict
functions for a gene cluster
specifically this uh Gene cluster which
you see over here it's the top Gene
cluster is working together with one of
the other Gene clusters to produce a
specific subclass of these well-known
sedor called desferoxamine
the the acid capped um deser
oxim and actually when you knock out
this Gene clusters then you see that
there's no effective production of these
sedera for in I think what is really
cool is that um not only can we predict
the function of a gene cluster but this
was also in a model organism serto color
which has been studied uh in terms of
its B synthetic Gene clusters for
decades and this specific pathway for
deser xamines is also a very well-known
model pathway for seder fores which
people also have studied for a long time
already and still nobody had ever U
known or hypothesized any role for this
particular Gene cluster and based on the
combination of coexpression and
co-regulation we could really uh figure
out this function so I think this this
is a promising strategy to figure out
what these kinds of Gene clusters are
doing I also mentioned like species
correlations and how they can be helpful
and and Robert ker in my lab is pursuing
that further he has been trying this out
with a number of model uh synthetic
microbial communities and one of them is
uh a synthetic Community from uh that's
a model for a rizosphere microbiome it's
composed of these three bacteria zamonas
koranis um Flor bacteria neonia and
basilla
serus and when you actually look across
the whole range of
co-cultures like both dual co-cultures
triple co-cultures mutants in different
conditions Etc you actually see that
there's also specific cross species
correlation and anti-correlation in the
expression of the metabolic Gene
clusters for example this zamonas has a
gene cluster for a molecule called cor
enin and this is an antibiotic and
whenever zamonas makes that antibiotic
it's seems that the basilla strain
actually responds by turning off all its
cider for production but it's also
highly positively correlated with these
two Gene clusters over here which
actually encode the production of of
molecules that are U known to be
protective against uh Redux stress uh
and also against Redux stress inducing
antibiotics called basil so whenever the
antibiotic is produced by am Monas
billus will start to basically produce
these uh protective compounds and at the
same time it also um uh increases the
expression of efflux pumps and other
kind of defense mechanisms and in this
way um yeah we're we're thinking that
this can also be a way for example to
find antibiotics so whenever uh a
certain one bacterium in a microbial
Community uh expresses all of these
defens mechanisms uh it's likely that
there's another member of the community
at the same time that is producing some
kind of antibiotic and by looking at the
cross species correlations of expression
uh it it should be possible to also in
hopefully that's the next step that
we're going to do in more complex
communities to unravel these
antagonistic interactions between
microbes and the the genes and Gene
clusters that are mediating
them and finally um one other strategy
that we're uh using uh to to predict
function for these metabolic Gene
clusters is basically through prediction
of the structures of course there's many
databases of bacterial metabolites and
their chemical structures uh and often
also associated with functional metadata
like biological activities we know that
for example bcam rings are very often
associated with antibiotics you have
these Keating Moes that are binding
metals that are often associated with
metallophores or specifically sedera
fores Etc uh so we can find Association
of of substructures of molecules with
specific types of uh biological
activities at the same time we can
actually predict also structural
features from Gene clusters by for
example Subs specificity predictions of
enzymes or by finding these sub clusters
these groups of co-evolving genes within
Gene clusters that are associated with
the biosynthesis of a specific chemical
myy and thus we can also get predicted
structural features from the gene
clusters and then we can see is there a
match between let's say the predicted
structural features from Gene clusters
and Association of these structural
features with uh certain uh types of
activities of
interest and as an example uh Zach whom
I mentioned earlier actually formalized
this for metallor so these are molecules
that are metal binding uh by in detail
looking at all of the uh subpathways
within uh more complex bis sythetic
Pathways that are involved in making
substructures that are metal binding so
these keading groups they are called
here you see uh in this panel B all of
these keying groups and their B
synthetic Pathways and for each of these
keying Group B sythetic pathway made
like uh anti- smash rules to detect the
specific combination of enzymes so to
really detect within a complex
biosynthetic Gene clusters are there the
genes are there genes present for making
these specific uh substructures as part
of the
molecules and um yeah so this actually
works pretty well so um get an F1 score
of 86 very high Precision meaning that
if these path these subpathways are
present then it's almost always a
metallor sometimes you miss things so
the recall is a bit lower because and I
think there was a question earlier um
occasionally these genes are elsewhere
in the genome so if these genes are
outside the gene cluster elsewhere in
the genome you might kind of miss out on
uh being able to predict this
functionality there was a previous paper
uh also from uh UC Berkeley on using
transporter genes for prediction of of
metallor bioactivity this this works a
bit less well U but you can actually
also combine these like looking at the
enzymes and the Transporters and
together actually works even a bit
better with an F1 of 0. n um yeah and
this way sa was also able to do like a
to get a global sense of like across
many genomes like how many uh of all
these te clusters actually have this
kinds of functionality um and we're able
to actually functionally annotate in
this way a pretty substantial
fraction of the gene
cluster at the same time to also expand
this to other key types of biological
activities um and ideally you would want
to do this also with uh with for example
machine learning methods where you're
not dependent on these rigid
associations with a specific chemical
substructure and and a specific
biological function of course it would
be really cool to to do this in a more
generalized way um and I do think there
is a lot of potential also for for AI to
to help with this um at the same time
and this was highlighted also in this
piece in nature I think two years ago um
that there is really a lack of large
scale standardized data to do this well
and this is also U yeah something that
came up in a in a workshop that we
organized in in Leiden uh a couple years
ago on like how we can use AI uh for in
this case drug discover
from these natural products um that
there's really a need for these high uh
high quality large scale standardized
data sets and um I'm I'm happy to say
that by now there's really initiatives
going on with large scale collaborations
to get this going also for example with
large libraries of purified molecules
that can be tested across a range of
standardized essays to to really get
better activity
so now that Marx already payed me the
way to talk about uh metabolites and
algorithms I wanted to start by delving
a little bit deeper into the human
microbiome and the metabolites that they
produce most of the bacteria that H
reside in our gut are anerobic bacteria
so they are the responsible of producing
this uh wide range of
metabolites um these metabolites are
important for either micro poost
interactions or for micro micro
interactions and depending on the
concentrations they are produced they
can have either beneficial effect for
our health or
detrimental and this for example um as
an example of this is andol for example
this is a molecule that is produced in
the gut and in low concentrations it it
can have beneficial effects for the
immune system but in high concentrations
this molecule can translocate into the
brain and then it can via the gut brain
barrier and then it it can disrupt the
the motor activity of the host and we
have other examples like p fasol v acids
that can help uh digest lipid um
metabolites and short chain fatty acids
that are well known also for having
beneficial effects for the for the head
for the gut uh by helping tightening the
cell Junctions and promoting the immune
um immune system but there's a still a a
large black box that we don't know like
which kind of molecules these microbes
are
producing and this is actually not only
the case of the human microbiome but it
also applies to other types of
microbiomes like the oral microbiome the
risos spere as manx was was talking
about so it is very important to know
actually who is doing what in these
communities which are the actual
mechanisms that are triggering the
specific phenotypes that we are
interested on because if we know we can
answer these questions we will be in a
much better position to actually
understand and manipulate these
communities as
desired
and as Marx was already mentioning
before one of the peculiarities of these
metabolites that the the gmic bacteria
produce are known to be encoded in
metabolic Gene clusters mgc in shorts
and these are actually the genes that
are closed together in the genome and
they are responsible responsible for the
regulation the synthesis transportation
of the of the
metabolite and and this is actually very
interesting but since there was no to to
be able to predict such uh metabolic gen
clusters we decided to tailor the anti
smash break more that was already
working very well for uh biosynthetic
genin clusters for secondary
metabolism um into gut smash uh which
mik already briefly mentioned before so
we tailored anti smashed into guts smash
to be able to predict specialized
primary metabolic Zin clusters from
anerobic B
and all the and and we actually um yeah
modified and generate new
functionalities to be able to um
properly annotate and and identify this
kind of te
clusters and how gut smash Works uh it
uses logic detection rules these logic
detection rules are Pam combinations
that uh work together in a way that are
uh relevant because they dis they are
the signature of a specific Redux um er
um Redux uh mechanism or or or pathway
so for example in this case here we have
pfl like domain and radical D radical
Sam domain or bfl acetate and radical
Sam domain if we find this combination
of B FS within a within 20 KBS this is
the signature uh reaction for the pway
to acetate last for me pathway and then
once we we identify the the the cin we
extend the the the gluster on both of
the flanks to be able to include the the
other cor biosynthetic gen clusters that
might be uh
nearby and we actually have two
different types of uh of rules one that
are known to be specific to known
pathways
so this would be for example uh yeah um
Pathways that see that have the same uh
core enzyme activity but having like a
little bit of flexibility within this uh
pathway so that we can yeah still
predict from different organisms and
then we have the general rules that aim
to Target important Redux enzymes in
certain context that seem to be relevant
and this could be for example a flavor
enzyme which is
find together uh with a short chain
dehydrogenase this could be for example
a novel cluster related to lipid
catabolism but of course the the
specific function is is yet
unknown so we started from a collection
of non Pathways that were previously
calized and and and they were published
so we could have access to the to the
catalytic reaction of this pathway we
knew which were the the core en
timeses and and we have a yeah a a
collection of these Pathways that here
you have a a representation of these T
clusters as you can see they look pretty
different from each other some of them
are very short some of them are very
long and also in terms of reactions they
are very different and examples of them
are for example the triamine producing
Gene cluster the P forol Gene cluster
ethanol pathway
Etc and so we had uh 43 different
Pathways that we uh used to build uh the
known path the the the detection rules
for these known
Pathways and how did we actually uh
build this uh detection worlds well so
we started with from this collection of
known uh of known um Pathways from there
we could identify the core genes and
then discern the core genes from the
auxiliary ones from here we could we
could also see that some of these G je
were actually repeated between different
Pathways so then in those cases we could
generate the uh pyogenes for these t
protein families and in here we included
protein sequences from different sources
one was from our collection of uh of uh
specialized uh primary metab clusters
then we also uh included the the protein
sequences from the experimentally
characterized uh proteins that were uh
in unipr and then we also included a
representative um protein from from the
Pam
database and from here we could identify
the the specific clades that we were
interested on and this help us to build
a specific phmm so we customize the phmm
to be able to Target um the the enzymes
that we were interested on and discern
between these ones and for example the
housekeeping uh related sces that could
uh be involved in these protein
families and then from here once we had
the phmm build we had a preliminary set
of detection rules
created these detection rules were then
tested on a on a collection of uh
taxonomically diverse uh
genomes and then Marx as as was
mentioning before we have this uh with
with this tool in in the group called
Big scape that allow us to group each of
the predicted gen clusters that were um
predicted by the by the same rule we uh
classified them and then we run big
Scape on each of these subgroups and
this help us to um classify the or group
together the gene clusters into Gene
cluster families and we manually analyze
the the output of of the the big scape
to be able to find uh the taxonomic
diversity of the predicted gen clusters
and also if there was any outlier that
we can uh see uh in the in the from the
from the output Network for example
and we also um and and from these
results we were also able to check for
example in niture if we if what we were
predicting was actually known or not
known and from here we did a couple of
uh well this allowed us to uh actually
refine the detection rules and we did a
couple of back and forth rounds of
validation and refinement and then we
had the final version of gats
which included uh different different
types of rules uh such as the specific
to known pathway uh pathway rules and
the general rules
also so the general gut smash workflow
then would be to start from a bacterial
genome then uh we use the bacterial
genome either in J back format or fasta
format as input then that smash uh
identifies the Gin cluster by iterating
over the detection rules then this gin
cluster is
um is um um well compared to a database
of other thing clusters that we have and
I will talk a little bit more in detail
later and then we annotate the the the
te
cluster like the genes into different uh
functional Gene categories and finally
we we build the interactive
output that one can see in the in the in
the
results so to be able to do this
comparative genomic analysis we also
constructed to different databases and
these databases uh are known as known
cluster plus which contains
experimentally characterized set of chin
clusters and in here we have the for
example this is the output of noncluster
Plus um here is the the quer sequence
and you can see uh for example in here
um to which Pathways of this database
the the query sequence looks more like
and you can actually see also in
particular which gen are the are the
ones that seem to find more um that seem
to find more similarity or
not and then we also have the cluster
blast uh tool for database that uh
predicts in cluster that has been it's a
collection of uh gin clusters that have
been predicted from our reference
collection using gut smash so in this
way what we can do is to compare
um compare the query sequence to a lot
larger um database of P clusters and in
this way we can we are able to see a
little bit the taxonomic distribution of
this T cluster and see for example if
this uh T cluster is uh preserved or not
uh in or it's only found in the same
gener for example or it's a little bit
more
widespread okay so once we had the tool
we decided to test it out in a in
a in
a data set that contain uh microbial
genomes from healthy donors and that
help us to h Profile the metabolic
potential of the human microbiota and
for that used more than 4,000 genomes um
more than 200 uh 300 genomes came from
the h&p data set then we took also the
CGR collection genomes that were
isolated from
sto and then we also included an extra
set of CIA genomes to account for their
variability and all of these uh all of
these genomes composed that
taxonomically diverse collection of
xomes and these were used as input for G
Smash and from here we could we were
able to pull actually uh the known gen
clusters from the put putative gen
cluster thanks to this uh datab basis of
uh of noncluster blast and and this
comparative genomic
analysis and here are the results um so
for ex um here in
the sorry I lost my pointer so here are
the different um Pathways that we have
and here are the different bacteria the
main bacteria that we could find in the
in this uh reference collection here is
the total number of Pathways and each of
the do represents the the percentage of
the bacteria that actually encode for
this specific pathway so if we find a
large um dot it means that more than 50%
of the bacteria from this uh gener
actually encodes for the pathway and if
the thought is small it means that less
than 50% of the bacteria and this was
just a simplify and actually and the
colors represent the different types of
Pathways that we have based on the uh
output
metabolite and for example what we can
see in here is that clust
rium and that
is
here here sorry uh so clust rium is the
genus that actually displays uh a more
metabolically metabolically diverse
genome hi en codes for 43 different
Pathways
and and then it's followed by uh the
enterobacteria members which include the
entac and salmonella uh Genesis and
actually it's interesting because um we
also can see that despite these are the
two geneses that display uh a remarkable
metabolic diversity and there are still
many of the pathways where they do not
overlap so that means that they have
actually different strategies also to to
yeah to to cope and to grow in the in
the in the human
gut and and this is actually important
because depending on the resources that
they have in the in in the gut they can
actually proliferate more or less and
this shape the composition and the and
the and yeah of the of the human gut
micro can I ask a question to that um so
for the metabolomic pathways that you
were learning on right that where your
ground truth from known Pathways or
known databases the have you seen there
also a taxonomic bias towards some
enterobacter AC that have been better
studied in the lab and which could also
explain why you see a high number of
pathway matches for them or Clum may be
studied well in the lab so that so would
you basically say that for the other
bacteria there are potentially other
metabolic pathways or they can also have
a high number but we are not covering
them yeah of course that plays a role
also on the on the identification I
think that the the rules of how they are
being designed they allow some
flexibility but of course if that
differs a lot from from what we know
then it's not that we are not going to
predict them but probably this is going
to be not classified as known because
based on this comparative genomic
analysis we of course have to set
thresholds on okay if this is my
reference genome we want this to look
more or less similar so yeah definitely
but still like doing in this way we
could still see that for example some of
the pathways that were
originally um studied from an organism
could be found in
another and then also here I have a
similar plot but in here um instead of
um the Genesis I have the specific uh
species and and in here instead of uh
combining the the dots
into more than 50% of the of the
isolates having the pathway or not these
are actually row counts and what we can
see in in this plot also is that we
could find strain specific um patterns
of uh of uh of primary metabolism
meaning that some of the for example in
here that it's in cluster um alanes I
think um for for some of the pathways
that gets my was uh predicting not all
the isolates actually encode for this
pathway as you can see in here some of
the dots are very small implying that
not all the isolates were having this
pathway and this is actually very
interesting as well because then it also
remarks and highlights the the
importance of not just considering
genosis but also like Str specific
traits that that are important
and
yes so for the for this plot uh uh map
and then the the the previous one uh how
much different would it look if you did
a instead of the the I guess phenetic
tree here if you just did like a little
cluster mapping right if you did like a
little hierarchical clustering uhuh um
because I'm wondering like how much of
this is you know different
you knowa or
whatever yeah like are you are do you
have like this specialization occurring
at like you know the level of you know
genetic similarity or is it sort of like
you know you have different branches and
then you know further up and then based
on wherever they happen to end up being
they specialize into whatever
KN I think that's very I didn't try this
I think that maybe it would look a
little little bit different but also
based on these analysis we could see
that for example there were some like
that
actually each of the clades or or
Genesis have very specific uh functions
in the gut so it it's restricted also by
by by Genesis that doesn't imply that
then within cuses or or strains we don't
have differences also but I think that
the major differences are between
taxonomical groups in the higher part of
the phogy so
yeah okay and then we also decided to
analyze a little bit the the the
predicted um gen clusters that that were
generated with well that were
differentiated from the known Z clusters
and here um this is a network actually
that contains um 12 uh th000 different
putative thing clusters that's because
we don't know the the
the the function Associated to them they
have been classified according the key
Gene that they encode for and in this
network what we can see is that there
are actually truly novel thing clusters
but there is Al we could also see that
for example there were s clusters that
were not covered by any specific rule
but the that they have been
characterized before so it was not in
our initial uh set of uh Pathways so
then yeah we couldn't we couldn't
predict that as a as a specific pathway
but it's good to see that still with our
um general rules we are able to um
predict this uh interesting CH clusters
and then of course there there are the
distantes of the nonn nonn Clusters that
this was uh Mar's question that uh yeah
of course like if if there are some of
the T clusters that look very different
to our uh reference they were not
annotated as known but they were
annotated as
bu and
then we also did a more specific uh
analyses on some of these uh putative
train clusters and in here I'm
highlighting four uh four of them so in
here on the um right hand side you have
the network where the pathway has has
been has been extracted from and H for
example this this specific one in here
that it's from OC cluster citroni this
one encodes for a for a flavor enzyme
and the actual neighborhood where you
can find this flavor enzyme seems to be
very interesting because it's associated
with an binding protein and also and a
silco dehydrase
and yeah we wanted to highlight this
kind of Pathways because we think are
interesting and that uh these are
actually Pathways that might uh be
characterized further and might um help
to uncover novel novel Pathways and yeah
other examples are for example this
Doria one which actually uh which
actually encodes for a uh uh pH fer
Toxin and it's and it's actually also
close by um yeah theam par phosphate
enzyme which is also very interesting
for example and but this is just to
point out some of the some of the some
of the pathways that we could find
interesting so in summary from this part
um I hope that I can I showed you that
the gut smash can help profile you uh
the human microbiome and can help
understand who is doing what in this
environment
um also that the bacteria are very some
of the bacteria are very versatile and
we can see strainer specific patterns
and also that the general detection
rules are are very useful to predict
Noel in clusters in bacterial
genomes and can represent interesting
candidates to study
further I also wanted to mention that we
build the B smash web server to be able
to just online analyze your genomes
without the need of having to install
and all the all the dependencies and and
and and the databases and everything and
it's hosted in the gats smash. by
informatic NL um web page and there's
also a bunch of information in in these
tabs in here if you click the well you
will find information how to download
interpret the results and
everything so now that we know who is
doing what in the human microme we were
also interested on who was actually um
contributing to this a specific
phenotypes so and for that we need to
know how abundant are these Pathways in
the in the communities and if these
pathways are actually differentially um
abandoned across the across the samples
because as I was mentioning at early at
the beginning also like the metabolites
have a specific concentration to be able
to trigger this phenotypes so this
information is
important um and yes so if we are able
to know if these te clusters are
differentially expressed or not we will
be in a better position to actually um
understand the role of these
metabolites and I want to highlight that
this is actually the tool that I'm about
to explain that is called big map it's
not only used for the cut microbiome but
also for other typ of
microbiomes so big map is a tool to
assess gen cluster differential
abundance and expression across samples
and we do that by using um the predicted
gen clusters by cutm or any other smash
um uh tools and we use this in
combination with metag genomic and meta
transcrip toic
data
and this this work by the way was done
with uh together with Hannah and Kun
that at the time were Master students
and big big ma consist of four different
modules the first one is called the
family module and performs a redundancy
filtering on a given given set of gin
clusters so we start from a gin cluster
collection and then we run um a
redundancy filtering using mash and then
we uh we to take a
representative uh using meal calculation
and then we cluster the metal the
representative thing cluster with big
scape again to be able to get the Gin
cluster
fam also for the in case we are using
metatranscriptomic data we also atmm
searched the Pam database for five
different housekeeping scenes to be able
to have a baseline of expression levels
of these uh of the things that we will
later compare to our
expression
levels then we have the download module
uh that downloads the fast files
Associated uh to an Sr ID this uh step
is optional of course if the user
already have the meta genomic data or
metat transcriptomic data the that can
be skipped and then we map the reads
onto the representative T cluster using
Bai and yeah basically what we do is to
uh either align the metag the
metagenomic RS or metat transcriptomic
RS into the representative think
clusters to be able to have
um an
alignment and from here we uh normalize
and further process the the map reads to
be able to visualize the the
output and this is actually how the how
the output looks like
um this is for example this is an
example when taking different
metagenomic um data from a data set that
contain um Chone disease samples and
unhealthy samples in here in the here in
the in the right you have the
significant genin clusters that were
found with bigmat in the top bar you
have the comparing groups so in this
case green is for um Chown disease and
yellow for healthy uh samples and here
we have a bars just indicating the lock
F chains that uh were found between the
the two comparing
RPS and then here we have the coverage
values of the of the chin cluster so the
higher is the number the better uh
covered the chin cluster is VI
rates and sorry can I ask again um so do
I also get the information by using that
tool for examp which part of the
biosynthetic gene cluster has which
coverage so for example is the
transporter up regulated but the
metabolomic metabolic component is not
yes yeah but
so that's not part of the output of of
Big Mac per set but this is something
you can process later with a with a with
intermediate files that we generate and
just visualize it with other tools this
is actually something that I've done for
the gut smash paper and I think that I
visualized that with the sushi art
package I think it's
called so yeah definitely then you can
easily see which are the the the parts
of the Gin cluster that actually have
more Heats yeah and this is something
that you have seen often so that for
example also based on met
transcriptomics data Transporters are
regulated but the rest of the um
synthetic cluster is not we haven't
looked at that
so as I was saying in this specific case
we can see here that there are two
specific chain cluster one that is known
and one that is unknown that seem to
have different
um abundancies in terms of um
metagenomic RS aligning these gen
clusters they are both so in here for
example the more yellow the more
abandoned the the pathway seem to be and
they seem to be more abandoned in the in
the healthy samples than in the um cron
disease ones and the coverage uh of the
of the Gen cluster also seem to indicate
that they are pretty well covered so
these are good candidates actually to
maybe study further and I also wanted to
mention that actually this is
a h this can also help us to prioritize
which are the putative Jin clusters that
we want to study further because we have
here an extra layer of evidence saying
that these Str clusters might be playing
a role in some of these phenotypes that
we are interested
on and this is actually the the heat map
that would output big map for metat
transcriptomic data so here we have used
the same data set uh so in green the
here in green are the CR dis samples and
here the the healthy samples the only
difference in here is that we have added
this extra uh column in here which
depicts the expression levels of these
house five housekeeping genes and that
that is only to be able to compare our
expression levels of our Pathways with
this housekeeping je one for example and
again in here we have a a gen cluster
that is a putative one that seem to be
that is significantly H associated with
cron disease that seems to be more
abandon in Cron's disease it seems to be
related to fatty acids uh metabolism and
yeah this is another good example of of
a team cluster that can be H important
for yeah for for this specific
P well now that we know that we have the
means to to actually know how abundant
are these te clusters we wanted to know
how that would translate into the human
gut
microbiome and for that what we did was
to predict the Gin clusters or use the
predicted gin clusters from the from the
collection of uh these three different
reference collections in combination
with the 100 one uh,
1,100 35 metagenomes from healthy
samples was this is the the data set
from the lifelines deep cohort and this
was actually the input for the big map
um tool
and in this way we could assess the
abundance and prevalence of the of the
pathways that were predicted by gut
Smash and we also wanted to see if the T
cluster abundance was able to correlate
with the metabolite abundance so for
that we also used um big Maps results
with in combination with the MS data of
uh these same
participants these are the results of
the pathway prevalence and so in here in
the x-axis you have all the all the
pathways and in here in the y axis all
the the prevalence of the pathways again
classified into the different
uh categories that we that we Define and
in here it was nice to see that we were
able to uh capture most uh most of the
pathways that were known to be found in
healthy Vol in healthy samples we were
able to see them in
almost hund in all of the in all of the
participants that was very interesting
to see for example these are the this
um cin uh fatty acids producing
Pathways uh all of them seem to be yeah
prevalent in the in all of the in all of
the in all of the samples and then it
was also interesting to see that for
example the B operon that actually um
transformed the Chic acid into the the
oxy colic acid it is known to be encoded
in very low abandon bacteria in the gut
that it's Clum syons and it was
interesting to see that also despite
being very low abundant in the gut we
were able to find it in most of the in
most of the samples
also and then of course it it was also
interesting to see that for example for
other Pathways that are known to be uh
detrimental for the human H health
uh such as
the H propal utilization that for
example is en goed in salmonella or um
the picol synthesis pathway they were
found in a h in a lot less number of
samples and then when we looked at the
at the abundance of this Pathways uh of
these Pathways across this data set we
could see that some of the pathways very
con consistently found across all the
samples at high abundance this is
actually the case of p42 this is the
third pathway in here and and also this
is a case of all the pathways that
actually have a a
very small box uh box plot and with a
very short whiskers also but then we
could also find Pathways that differ a
lot in abundance between individuals and
that's for example the three into
propionate pathway um and this was
actually um making us question if the if
the metagenomic abundance actually would
correlate with the metabolite abundance
because if we have such differences
maybe we could see those differences
also in the in the metabolite
concentration and this is actually a
work that was done together with liming
Chen and in here on the on the top part
of the plot you can see the correlations
between metabolite aband abundance and
and the pathway abundance and these
three lower ones are from FAL content
and the rest are from plasma content so
we also wanted to see if that was
actually having an effect on the on the
correlations that we were doing and yeah
basically we couldn't see
a correlation between um between the
metabolite abundance and the pathway
abundance
and uh not in the plasma neither in the
in the fal content despite in the fal
content I think that if if you compare
because these are for the same
pathway it improves a little bit on the
on the when using the fal uh Ms data and
that might be because in there the
concentration of these metabolites it's
higher
and this lack of correlation might be
due to different reasons and one of them
can be due to dietary differences
transcriptional regulation differences
diffusion dynamics of the metabolites
secondary fermentors that maybe use some
of the end products of some of the
pathways and are convered to other ones
so and from this we could also see that
uh the importance of using metat
transcriptomic
data so that's why we decided to analyze
another data set I ask a question
actually yeah um in the previous slide
is it that there's only one pathway
that's making the metabolite that you're
measuring in the plasma or the fecal
sample or could there be multiple
Pathways that make that that metabolite
and so even when one pathway is not
abundant maybe the other pathway is and
that's why you see the metabolite even
when the path way is slowly abundant and
therefore you just will never get a
correlation no we actually did all the
combination so we have indeed different
Pathways that for for example produce
acetic acid and we did all the
combinations and we also pulled them all
together and then correlate the but the
the results were the same still so
yeah and yeah by analyzing so we have uh
we wanted to analyze and this ihmp data
set that actually contain uh paired um
data so there was 81 samples that have
uh metagenomic data metabolomic and
metatranscriptomic data then there were
uh 271 metatranscriptomic data that were
only Associated to
metabolomic data and all of these
samples actually also um come from
healthy ulcerative colitis and Chron
dise sample so we had different
phenotypes in here uh but the
interesting part is that we were having
different types of pair data and and
metat transcriptomic data
also and this was the together with the
predicted gen clusters um uh predicted
by gut smash we used this as input for
big map and then with the PMS data we
could we did the same analysis to be
able to correlate the Gen cluster
abundance
an expression with the
metabolite and this is uh these are the
results so in here in this first uh
plotting here we have an overall
correlation uh plot so here is for the
um 81 um metag genomic samples the green
one is for the 81 metat transcriptomic
samples and the the yellow one is the
271 metat transcrip on examples and you
can see that
correlations range between minus 0.3 to
almost 0.4 so not very high correlation
still
and and we also highlight it in here in
different colors I'm not sure if you're
able to see the different dots in
different colors and these are actually
the pathways that are represented here
just to highlight the Feld and and if we
analyze this specific um curent
corations in particular we because these
are actually one of the highest
correlations that we get we see that
still um the MTC abundance and the
expression do not correlate well with
metabolite abundance still in general
despite having
maybe higher values for for The Meta
transcrip value uh data sorry but
actually when we splited the data set
into the three different phenotypes that
we could find
we got better results and actually the
correlations increased up to almost uh
0.60
so um yeah it seems that uh the
phenotypes have actually they role in
correlate on these analysis right so
it's important to actually split uh the
analysis using these three different uh
phenotypes and also that the expression
of some of these path pathway seems to
be indeed predictive for some of the
metabolite abundance but not all of them
since there's still a lot of them that
are close to zero or or very
low so what do we learn from this
analysis um well metabolic inferences
are difficult to make from metomic or
meta transcriptomic data alone and this
is important because there are tools
actually that make such inferences so we
all they might be very useful but we
have to be cous also about um how we
interpret these results and then they
need to better understand the the the
influence of diet genin regulation
secondary fermentors and everything to
be able to make such predictions more
accurately and then finally uh to wrap
up um I will uh I wanted to highlight a
few take home messages one of them is
that h g smash can get uh deeper
insights on who can do what and can be
useful to be to do this uh metabolic
profiling of the human gut bacteria but
we have also actually uh applied it to
different um microbiomes such as uh ship
ran for example oral microbiome so it's
not just uh restricted to the cut
microbiome human G microbiome then also
that uh uh using metagenomic data put
for bigm can be very useful to
understand how AB how pathways are are
which pathways are actually more
abundant which are not and the role they
play in the in the phenotypes
um I want uh metabolite outcomes are
difficult to predict from metagenomic
data or metatranscriptomic data alone
and then that I think that integrative
fic approaches are the way to get uh to
go to be able to understand complex
ecosystems and inir causation