and um you'll remember probably it's all
gone because it's like what a week ago
uh P at 4 was mostly about the topic of
equivalence classes
equivalence in
music what were some of the things that
we were talking about back then cuz this
is just going to keep coming up all
semester what are some things that we
could say in some context that two notes
or two pitches are different but in
another context we might say they're
equivalent to each other yeah OCT
octaves great let's just let's just
shoot out perut
permutation
cardinality transposition inversion and
the one that's not part of the optic
spelling good good where uh just while I
put some things on the board shout out
some more things we talked about in
class that we didn't put on the problem
set what were some other things that we
s say things are the same even though
they might sound
different instrumentation
instrumentation yeah we s say hey that
note's a c and it's like no that note
was on a on a piano and this one was on
a trumpet good other
things and harmonics and harmonics yep
that goes with as a special class of
spelling good good but it's good to use
that term else
so I said it doesn't matter how long the
note is it's still a c right yeah so
duration when we're talking about notes
good good so uh I can't apparently lead
a discussion and write things on the
board but I want to talk about two
things that uh came up a lot um one of
them I don't need notation for and one
of them I do one of them is much better
B Sharp for to I don't know it doesn't
really matter but it's FP 5 you were
asked to write a pro prr to
automatically generate the interval um
on well sorry you were asked to write a
program to automatically generate the
interval of anything and this was one of
my hidden test cases that um I think
it's the only problem that over half
maybe three qus of the class uh the
problem uh came up with what's which one
of these two notes is the problematic
one take a guess B good good now BP is a
problematic note the way Esh is right
but it also has its own special
problematic things what what's bsharp 4
what note does that sound
like C5
good
so the issue that came up a lot um is
the only thing what what should this
interval be let's let's think about that
first what should the interval
be yeah diminished fifth diminished
fifth so let's think about that
diminished fifth good yeah what's what
would be the interval if it was C5 to
F
anybody augment
augmented fourth good so the four and
the five are changed around based on uh
the number of distances in the step
spacing which you all did great on um
but now we have a different problem and
so what came up a lot um from various
things I saw a lot of um D D D D D D D D
D is that the right number D D D um
12th I think that might that might not
be enough D's because the issue is that
the BP is something that sounds in kind
of octave five but it's not so always
when you're thinking of you know how's
your screwy Prof going to try to screw
you up think about these things that
cross over the boundaries between
octaves or sound like one thing not the
other um a lot of a lot of times what
what happened was you needed to do
something mod 12 at a certain point add
an offset depending on how your
algorithm works and then mod 12 it again
so this sort of double mod 12 at this
point we're we're going to be working
for algorithms that get things right we
can work on efficient algorithms as sort
of um you know more efficient ones as
kind of a project later good the second
one that came up um had to do with
asking you to uh This was done by hand
um to come up with a pitch set that was
equivalent to the one I gave you using p
permutation and T transposition but
without octave inversion or cardinality
um equivalence and most of you are like
I don't even want to think about
inversional um you know equivalent so
that's good and cardinality equivalence
just means that I gave you three notes
how many notes should you have three
three good good so the hard part so this
was A4 E5 C
4 what I'd like you to do when you have
a problem like this is go back to do it
the oldfashioned way first get out staff
paper or use finale Muse score whatever
you're using and try to make sure that
you're seeing what the notes are so
where's A4
go stop two stop stop okay good
A4 what's the next one
E5 stop okay good go slower puff right
and then what's the next
one
C four
right stop
what's the common name we would call to
this If This Were a
chord A major first inversion in first
inversion yeah so oops I got to jle this
otherwise was blood red yes first
inversion um okay so then what you need
to do you want to do is something
that and it had to use both now you I
think I tried to say it in such a way
that even an MIT student wouldn't be
allowed to say well you know uh not
arranging anything is not rearranging
anything is a permutation and
transposition by Perfect Unison is a
transposition but you needed to change
them in some way so one of the things
you could do uh so one of the things
that happened a lot was that the octaves
got changed and so that ended up being
about 40% of the errors that we saw so
you can do is you could first re permute
things and probably the rep permutation
that I would do first is let's just put
it in ascending order so that's probably
the permutation you'd like to um have
your computer do
anyhow and then let's just shift
everything up um one way you can do it
well in this one you I was going to say
shift everything up a space or a line
but the E is the problem so let's just
transpose up a a major second what are
we going to get
here dsharp
B FP good not um because well no this
one we had implicitly because everything
on this we had spelling or and that's an
S not a five a spelling equivalent so
yeah so D Shar 4
B4 and F five so um when you get that
back that's there any other questions on
problem set
four hardest programming problem set so
far no no two two was harder for some
people anyone vote for one no okay if if
if one was the hardest uh probably
you're not here uh now um but sorry I
shouldn't yeah um but yeah so prom set
six will be announcing today it is also
a slight programming one uh it's
designed to give you a little bit of a
break and it you'll I'll talk about it
in a bit but it's uh more of a um the
only sort of participation grade type of
problem set than uh trying to get the
exact results so we're going to have a
little bit of a break um coming up for
things somebody want to volunteer what
electronic corpora did you find
online Adam yeah we did musipedia
musipedia great what's what is that it's
a dual database and search query
data cor cool great another another
group yeah uh we did ultimate guitar
ultimate guitar great how's how's that
that encoded um I mean they started off
with just like text um ask key guitar
tab but then they kind of expanded and
Incorporated more advanced software oh
cool yeah I remember when it was a lot
of asky guitar tabs I think everybody
had their own parser for the ultimate
guitar at some point uh good uh anybody
else
Vanessa video game music database video
game music database fantastic great
great repository what's what were things
mostly encoded for that almost
everything was in min5 almost everything
was in mini files why why do you think
that was I think it's like generally a
standard and it's relatively small file
sizes so it's easier to like Mass pop a
whole bunch of different it is also
that's probably how they were encoded in
a lot of especially the early video
games they were encoded so when you're
ripping from or something like that uh
but definitely not encoding Sharps and
flats good one last one Su your group oh
um we did a jazz it was a jazz database
a jazz database fantastic fantastic what
werein coding for that um they had a
variety they had like the transcribed
sheet music for a lot of jazz solos and
then also a CSV file that just had every
notes offset from the very beginning and
its pitch as a number cool uh what
you'll find is a lot of um a lot of
these data sets they really have their
own sort of oneoff make your own format
because like I I don't think that that
one's a standard but I've seen lots of
these because um that's how uh things
things uh you know tend to tend to go
great uh where we're going to get to
right back to
representation uh in just a bit uh we' a
special guest Michael good who knows a
little something about representations
being the creator of Music XML and uh
sort of uh found and BR Bell also from
the Dean's office um and um and so if if
you guys can stick around for 10 minutes
we're I'd like to before we do that
let's get sort of warmed up for probably
the thing that are on some people's mind
right the downgraded midterm which is
now I'm calling quiz because I'd like to
divide this into two smaller low lower
stress things and that will be on
Wednesday uh we'll start recording about
uh 30 40 minutes in I'm designing it to
take 30 minutes if we take a little bit
longer that's okay it's not all about
the rush but we will do one type of
thing um that uh is about sort of recall
so the um the the the quiz will be not
about your programming skills but about
the reading and we want I want the
quizzes to be more about the readings so
that you keep thinking about ideas that
you're going to be doing in your
projects as we uh keep going with uh
further um with further problem sets
each one of them will start having a
little bit of uh what do we call it uh
sort of assign yourself your own um your
own problem and start it okay we got
some sound going we don't really need
that but we can turn that down for a bit
who's done cahoot
before okay who knew that MIT apparently
let their cahoot subscription uh lapse
uh sometime between the last time I'm in
here so I'm only able to do 10 players
so can you all uh can you all pair up
and do in teams with the other I know I
know I I I was trying to fill out the
subscription form right behind class so
can you team up one two three three
three four five six seven eight actually
you can be your own team n or do you
want to do it with Michael stu okay we
might have one more thing do it okay oh
yeah uh use any nickname you want just
make it family
safe oh you can you can decide if you
want to
be
okay so this is ju this is just to judge
how much time you feel like you might
need to spend reviewing uh the things
okay we have 1 two 3 four we have
nickname nickname too great
um five
six okay we'll do a little bit of the
background music but although
maybe okay we have eight anybody anybody
waiting on two more people want to be
loners go on their own okay now that's
good we're going to get
started oh we got winners okay
oh and okay great super um here we go so
about 20 or 30 seconds on each one
there's uh 11 questions I think 13
questions
maybe which of the following is a binary
music representation
so this is your time if you haven't done
this before lock in something no points
for
wrong three
two what do we have midi mid is the only
one that is typically represented in
binary code and not in
text okay okay I know you you would have
thought I would have made the answer
music XML to honor our guest but you
didn't you knew it wasn't music XML you
knew it wasn't music XML because you
studied that well enough good let's keep
going okay hey Nick the creative
nicknames are up top according to cook
what is ironic about the timing of the
rise and fall of comparative and
computational musicology
hey most we got it comparative
musicology which is kind of designed
well for computers declined at the time
computers came
up okay that's Nicholas Cook's
comparative and computational musicology
to review if that one wasn't obvious
we'll keep going okay we got much more
on the board
who was not a composer whose music was
discussed by cook who was not in
there this is a hard one this is about
as hard
as 3
seconds oh most people got it voger no
liity was the one with all the graphs
showing when things come in and out and
the hideen one heyen was used as the
example for um for the German
nationalist song he was the composer of
the music but not the
lyrics okay we got one
fire fu
[Music]
fu the music 21 iterator talking about
my own stuff that returns offsets from
the start of the part is
[Music]
you got one more
person two
seconds hey almost everybody got
flattened I know you know that we Cur
somebody was trying to trying to do the
the thought experiment that I like
recurse better I keep telling you use
recurse but in this case flatten is the
better
one
oops
okay who wrote about musical codes in
the introduction to Beyond MIDI
[Music]
oh done
done M Michael good does have an article
in that book but no you don't know that
was the next virtual score what I wrote
before starting
okay getting
close Dimitri tasko criticized me for
all of these things about music 21
except what this is hard
[Music]
and oh no the one thing he didn't
criticize me for is the worst feature on
it it is really hard to install but
somehow he already got it installed so
he didn't care about
that okay so that was that was one that
shook shook things up the
Snowman here we go um we're half over
halfway there this is an extra credit
from an optional reading so don't worry
but take a guess on this one Donald bird
created his extremes of music notation
uh thing to show that notation
what yeah good good good okay we don't
need to discuss that even if you didn't
do the reading it's really cool article
if you haven't had a chance to flip
through it some weird things in there
Craig Sap's name good guy good guy
appeared in this class for his creation
of
[Music]
what okay what do we get yes the
illustration of the same passage of
Music in dozens of encodings also known
allowing you to translate from one
coding to another called the Rosetta
Stone yep um we got um he now runs the
hum drum thing but it was David here on
here um nobody did this one and uh yeah
I don't know the answer to the
red yellow exist um yes I believe so
somewhere I this is from the reading for
today so we'll see if we got today's
reading what do David Luen call his
unifying rule for species
Counterpoint okay a lot of people gold R
those who said Golden Rule by the way I
am going to misspeak and call it the
Golden Rule a lot because I do that but
um yep we'll talk about it a little bit
more the end of class
today common or conventional music
notation also CW MN consists of
what Seven Answers
[Music]
yeah it's I know all of the above is
almost always the right answer when you
take a guess but no in this case it was
just um things that traditional western
music notation in some way so that you
can write down non-western and you can
ENC as you all know you can encode many
things into the computer that are not
that so great we're doing we're doing
well
now okay three
more oh
wow nice we don't need to do that
[Music]
anymore Arden and hon showed how
European folk song varied across genre
times locations
[Music]
functions hey yep we almost always got
that this was the article that showed
the geographic information systems back
when that was very very hard to do we
should be able to do this more easily
with Google Maps and
things
okay before we do the last one uh before
we do the last one just to know the quiz
will not be a bunch of these little
factoid things that's just all I can
figure out to do on cahoot it will be
actually about conceptual issues and
ability to apply these ideas but um
let's finish this oh it's about uh
Sophia son and me showed connections
between music and emotion using what
types of musical scores
[Music]
answer oh no I know I do too many V
crows and I do medieval music but it was
lead sheets uh so yep oh yeah read great
so we have on the
podium third place nickname three
anybody want to claim their Podium
nicely done nickname too yep and
top I guess this shows that some people
spend their time not thinking of
creative names but just reading the
Articles congrats everybody so we've
been talking a lot about encodings and
what you'll be doing over the course of
the semester sometimes is working with
these strange encodings and maybe as
we're starting to get well let me say
you've had some problem sets where I've
given you questions and you've given
answers right and now you've given two
problem sets that encoding one and uh
this corpor one where you've been doing
the research to find interesting
problems but I haven't been asking you
to actually get an answer you didn't
need to make a corpus a par parser for
guitar um ultimate guitar in order to
answer any questions so we're getting to
the end of the semester we'll be
bringing those two things colliding
together and doing more um on how you
can come up with your own problems and
come up with your own Solutions Michael
would you like to come up and talk for
just a little bit I'd like to introduce
Michael good who's uh MIT grad and the
inventor of Music XML up here who's
[Applause]
Vis you all have seen an interview with
Michael right so just wanted to to talk
the interview is a couple couple years
old now I think we did it during covid
um yeah so what's what's been up and
interesting in the world of anything
with computer music but especially you
know music the encoding anything that
you've been finding or oh that's I I
retired um in January so my mind has
sort of gone out of the music notation
area
CL I mean some of the things that were
in these projects were really cool the
uh the body percussion en coding stuff
and I was like oh pretty pretty great
yeah do you do you feel like like now
now you got to come out of retirement
and find a way to put all these things
into music XML not yet
okay so but in the future but what what
are some ways that somebody could get um
you know a particular musical project if
they're interested in you know
non-western music or something else and
get get such a standard um sort of
musical encoding as as you've created
what what kind of advice would you give
for that well
you to develop a standard for a music
representation you need to have multiple
people who are using it right and you
need to have I think tools that that
support it so that becomes if it's non
standard that becomes more of a you know
less common repertoire that becomes more
of a chicken and an egg problem so look
for something that has at least two
applications that are doing that type of
music and see if you can do maybe there
one's an application you wrote and one's
an application somebody else wrote and
tried to put something in between I mean
when I was starting music XML a lot of
people had tried to do a standard common
western music notation format and I knew
that if it was if it didn't work with
either finale or cilus because those are
the two programs people cared about then
if it didn't work with at least one of
those two programs I was just going to
give up go home and find something else
to do because nobody would care about
music XML if it didn't work with one of
those programs nowaday be M score Oro or
things like
that so if you're trying to do a
standard music representation then you
need to have a community of people who
are using it and applications that use
it um maybe more interesting is just to
you know at this point is to come up
with cool things that could be
represented and and and do some analysis
there and and try to figure out ways
that these representations could be
useful for the musicians
uh who are doing these type of
repertoire great so Michael was um you
did music when you were at MIT oh yeah
what what kinds of things well I was a
trumpet player nowadays I sing my wife
my wife my wife and I met in the MIT
concert band she's an electrical
engineer right she's she's uh the one of
the 40 top engineers at Analog Devices
so she just was talking with race dat at
her company
conference a couple days ago so she's 61
I'm 63 uh I'm class of 79 she's class of
82 and she played Piccolo I played
trumpet and I played trumpet in the band
The Orchestra Festival Jazz Ensemble
chamber music Society musical you know
anything that needed a trumpet laptop
Ensemble played it there was no there
was no laptop laptops were not
invented I was I ter the the coolest
thing I did my my thesis in the
experimental music studio with Professor
Barry burko which is now the media lab
one of the groups that became part of
the media lab and the coolest thing was
we got to use t52 terminals instead you
know video terminals instead of the you
know paper terminals that I was using
for all my other classes so I got to use
the coolest computer technology that I
had seen at that point in my computer
music class so that was awesome so
Michael here's a a question I haven't I
I don't think I've ever asked you so so
you did music while you were at MIT and
you did other things and then um but
music wasn't your primary um sort of you
know putting money in you're in a bank
for a bit um you could ask a little bit
about what that was but what made you
want to come back and do it and is there
anything for anybody who's not thinking
of graduating this year next year
whatever and doing music but might
follow a career like years well yeah
following a career like line is kind of
I mean it's a whole different time now
when I I was doing my bachelor's thesis
at the experimental music studio was on
one of these alpha alpha numeric
encodings um which is now called Scott
it's actually still still shipped I
think as part of sees sound and I was
rewriting it from an earlier version
called Soo but this was in 1979 so there
was no midi right there was no computer
music technology industry okay New
England digital was doing some clavet
but you know that was know one tiny
company so there wasn't any industry to
go to for a job so I started to do
usability work as for my grad school I I
got my masters here too and I did
usability work until 2000 when it you
could see that everything was going to
this is when the web was coming up and
you know everything was going to be
moved this app over to the web from from
from Au GOI and the first time I did
that it was a lot of fun and but doing
it a thousand times was going to be
really boring so I looked at you know
there was an opportunity to do a
standard music notation format there was
downloadable sheet music starting to
happen it was IND decent uh thing so
there was obviously a demand for uh a
standard computer music because it was
silly you could download the music and
all you could do was use it in the
player or print it out and it's was like
you should be able to share it back and
forth between programs like HTML and
midi you know if you don't have a
standard it's it's nothing for for that
type of common things
so that was the motivation to do it you
know that I I wanted to use downloadable
music in any
application and I but I had the
financial uh ability to do that because
my wife worked for Analog Devices and
elect engineer and their company did
really well and so if I totally failed
it didn't matter financially so I mean I
was in extremely lucky position there I
me nowadays though you can you know you
got each other all interested in music
technology and there's all sort I
mean to go through I mean if IID had a
class like this I wouldn't have had a
class like this because you didn't I had
to spend all my time like building
infrastructure now you can do the cool
things on top of you know the cool
problems on top of it so find find cool
problems that people are interested in
uh I mean if you want to make a career
if you if you're just studying you know
find a cool problem that you're
interested in well that's I guess the
starting point anyway find a cool
problem that you're interested in
because if you're not interested in it
you won't be able to make a living at it
you'll just be terribly bored and then
find if somebody else is interested in
that or something
adjacent one last question before I let
you go if that's if that's okay um you
know it's hard for us to think of you
know that that you went from the
essentially teletype era things you
don't see things on screen you have to
type it onto and then it all comes out
on paper and stuff in of what 30 uh
bytes per second uh modems and and and
things like that to I mean until two
months ago when you retired you were
still totally on top of of like 99% as
many percent of the new technologies as
anybody can do and things and someday
it's hard for us to think but these will
seem as outrageous as a teletype or a
horse and buggy and stuff what not just
for music people but how do we keep up
how do we keep up like you with all the
changing
technology if you're a tech person like
I think you you kind of do
that live in Silicon Valley you gota but
stay with you know what's going I mean I
have this usability background so I was
always interested in user interface
Technologies but I mean I don't know
anything about machine learning
outside of applications for it I mean in
the music space I'm excited to see what
sound slice is doing for using machine
learning for optical music recognition
What audio Shake is doing for Source
separation of of audio which everybody
tried to do and nobody would they're the
first ones who are able to do it and
they're very clear about which problems
they can handle and which problems they
can't and why it's a good market and why
it's supporting musicians so we were
talking a little earlier about with
generative music things sort of to sum
up what you're saying is make make sure
that there's a problem that you're
trying to solve yeah a problem that
you're trying to solve that isn't
putting musicians out of work would
be well thanks Michael for I wish we
could have had you earlier when we were
specifically talking music XML but we
can't go you can't go six weeks into the
semester without knowing music XML so
even knowing you're coming now uh it's
still it's so great so thanks and
and feel free to stay feel free to move
on we're going to uh unlock intervals
we're going to be moving on to the
shortest topic of the semester and that
is a voice leading you're going to get
just a little bit for me today you're
going to have the world's shortest um
not the world's shortest but a pretty
short problem set and then we'll do talk
about it a little bit after um after the
midterm on Wednesday and that will be it
uh it's very important topic we're going
to keep working on it it's why it
deserves to have its own number um but
uh what um when we're talking about
voice leading we're generally talking
about how yeah we just need one staff
for
this how
multiple parts are moving at the same
time
so this would be pretty bad voice
leaning maybe very dissonant but
something we're talking about not what's
happening
here and not what's happening that one's
hard to do
here but the combination of the two and
why voice leading becomes a particularly
interesting problem for computers is
there's two general ways of inter of
iterating um both and both um
both flatten and recurse are in some
ways well no sorry uh recurse is sort of
the you go through one part or one voice
and you go through everything and you go
through the other part and the other
voice and you go through everything and
then you have something like flatten
which in the
end especially if everything is just
quarter notes you're going through one
slice going to the next and going to the
next
slice so voice leading is a particular
problem requires you to be constantly
moving back and forth between I'm moving
according to Voice or according to part
and I'm looking at what's happening at
one time or
another um one of the classic
applications for uh sort of starting off
computational voice leading is to work
on a topic called species Counterpoint
has anybody who has done species
CounterPoint in one of their classes
some instructors do it some don't not
everybody has so there's it's a um I
think it's invented it's an 18th century
way of learning to write music like they
wrote it in the 16th century so not 100%
relevant to um to music composition
today but still sort of a fundamental
skill like um you practicing your scales
or something Mozart and Brahms uh
practiced species Counterpoint uh every
day sort of keep up their chops um the
earliest the first species that we tend
to call it is something is all in whole
notes let me see if I can compose one um
while
we're
um how many notes I write 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 nine good classic ones tend to be
around nine notes long and then against
this in first species you're going to
write one whole note for every
note with particular conditions and some
of these conditions will be horizontally
constraining like for
instance uh yeah now this that
particular one
don't do that why
not trone Yep this case augmented fourth
um or diminished fifth usually not
allowed also especially in this context
good so some of these things are going
to be based on that and on on one case
and some of them are going to be based
on vertical things this would not be
allowed why
not sorry I need to two
colors what's what somebody said it I
just didn't
hear no no I think I think I heard it
properly seventh yeah so um in first
species the rule is all horizontal
vertical intervals must be consonant and
all vertical intervals must be
consonant but then there are other
strange little
rules
like this is a consonant
interval this is a consonant interval
this is a con I I was going to do red
this is a constant interval all these
intervals are consonant what's the
problem here with these
two for anybody who's done this yeah so
parallel fifth so what's the interval G
to D perfect fifth e to B perfect fifth
so two perfect fifths in a row um so I
just want to give uh there for anybody
who wants to um I don't have a
formalized extra credit for this but um
if you can writing
software that can solve any given what
we call the this is the part that's
given to you there's always one part
that's given to you it's called the Kus
fmis or the fixed song in Latin and so
you fixed you can't change it and one of
the classic things is to write um
nowadays in computers is to write
software that can solve the other part
that can give you the other part there
and that's one of the ones if you're
interested in in optimization and
algorithmic things that this is one of
the cases the first cases in this class
where it is easy to write something that
will do it properly but for a 20 note or
40 Note One won't be able to generate it
in the time that the Universe um before
the heat death of the universe so it's
something where uh algorithmic
complexity comes in you are not going to
be given that assignment this year um
you all have worked pretty hard right
this this class is yeah okay so not
doing that seems like a good thing but
instead we're going to be
what you're going to be asked to do uh
over between now and next Friday is to
um come up and encode some of the basic
features underlying how you might solve
a problem like this and specifically how
you might avoid things like this uh
there's one or two uh things on this the
this is not get an everything correct
problem set but um looking quite down
the road to the second probably the
second to last problem set in this class
problem set nine will this will be
foundational knowledge on it and that
one problem set nine you're going to be
given a piece and you're going to be
asked to remove all the passing tones
and all the ornaments and leave it just
with the block chords and so being able
to identify voice leading moments is
pretty
important okay so let's unlock intervals
you've been working a lot on them
so unlocking
interval let's go ahead and from music
21 import uh Corpus which we'll use just
at the very end if we have time note
pitch and the brand new interval
module is that big enough bigger
better okay um we'll start with the wor
worst variable name ever I equals the
interval module so it's
lowercase and the
interval class in there P5 let's start
with a perfect fifth these are all
things that you've been
doing within the interval module by the
way there are interval classes called
chromatic interval diatonic interval
generic interval all these things but
the interval class will let you do
basically almost anything in there great
so now you've created a P5 interval you
can get its name which is very unhelpful
it just tells you what you just put in
but you can get its nice name uh with a
capital N in the
middle perfect fifth um so it's just a
little bit more helpful Let's uh keep
going we can get its directed nice name
so this is Allin snake case or camel
case whatever you want to call it
directed nice with a capital N name with
a capital m and
get us sending perfect fifth so there's
sometimes we care about what direction
the interval is and sometimes we don't
uh in Melodies we care or don't
care take a guess when you're talking
about Melodies do we care which
direction the interval
is yes when we're talking about the
notes of a chord do we care no not
usually right because we're just talking
about uh what things are great so if we
want to create um a descending interval
we can create interval.
interval
P5 and get its directed nice name you
don't have to type all things I'll put
this up later if you're not a fast
typist but you can do that um also
because I can never remember which one
we prefer uh you can do negative P5
because I I don't know which one of
those is actually
better okay so that the most basic way
of doing things um
let's try to get the intervals um from
pitches first off so let's create two
pitches we'll create um pitch. Pitch
B3 P2 pitch.
pitch C5 so not little hard but not too
hard and you don't need to type the
question marks we're going to get the
interval interval.
interval
interval between P1 and P2 so you can
instead of putting in a string you can
give it two pitches or something and I'm
going to name this variable after what
the name should be the interval between
B3 and C5 what should I call that
somebody who hasn't already gotten ahead
in the computer what is that interv
always try to do things in your head the
first time
nth minor 9th so I'll do lowercase m n u
I do like naming things according to
their interval or according to what
they're representing it does hit my anal
retentive uh like must be everything
must be in order streak that when we do
have something that should be a major
third it's capital M but then I go
Capital should only be used for classes
and you know um but SI we have to do
that okay so we have do we get
yep minor ninth how many semitones in a
minor
ninth uh 13 13 13 so dot semitones will
give you the number of semmit tones in
an interval which is often quite helpful
um obviously m9n name will give
youname will give you M9 but M9 dos
simple name also in C snake case
so when you're dealing with compound
intervals there is something called
Simple name that would be very helpful
for working through things
um there's um now there's there's some
some slight difference let's um let's
come up with another interval this one
I'll call
p8 and I'll just show so you can do some
of these things here we can also create
an interval from notes not just from
pitches uh that's probably a mistake in
my taxonomy morony whatever it is but um
it's been there for a while so p8 should
be C4 to C five good the only difference
why I'm creating a octave I should have
just call it octave right um is that
sometimes that the octave simple name is
perfect Unis P1 right but um sometimes
we care about the difference between
octaves and Unison in a way that we
don't care about uh seconds and nins so
there is something called p8 dosi Simple
name I wish I had spent some more time
coming up with it which basically is
exactly the same as a simple name except
that things that are multiples of
octaves get squished down to an octave
so a double octave also becomes an
octave in the semi-simple name whereas
the 9th's semisimple name is my minor
second I think there's also things see
if I still have all these in here semi
simple nice name yeah okay so there's
there are all of these things in there
great um
let's let's stop typing so much and
let's create some aliases Alias um we's
just capital I is the interval. interval
class so now we can call I and get new
interval and P the pitch. pitch class
not a pitch class the class pitch inside
the module pitch right is that able to
be
seen great so now we can create like
minor
third just like that just a capital I
parentheses and slow down okay slow down
slow down yes a little bit okay good
great pause for a second on this
so far so far this is great uh except
for being able to get the interval from
two pitches which will probably be very
helpful for you uh there's not too much
you can do once you have an interval
object so let's start creating some
things that um might like so don't have
to type all these things but this is
probably a nice one to do the interval
of a minor third is consonant now this
is probably a mistaken term before I hit
enter Because all of these things are
consonant in some of the world's
traditions and some not in some of the
other world's traditions in fact um some
of the early proposals of Music 21 said
oh and then you'll be able to have a
context objects which will be able to
affect how these things are so if you're
in 14th century Europe This will be
false and if you're in some part if
you're giving it a southern uh Southern
Indian context it might be fals or you
depending on what the time is and I've
never actually fully implemented that so
right now unfortunately this privileges
the Western um sort of classical music
context what should this be if it's in a
western classical music context minor
thirds are constant or dissonant con
Conant good I programmed something right
um now let's try something else a major
sixth consonant or dissonant consonant
consonant
good and um
sorry I'm just going to I'm typing a lot
here you can probably assign things
variables uh the number of semitones in
a major
nine nine good now I'm going to create a
diminish sth I lowercase
D7 and number of semmit tones in a
diminished
7th
11 one guess another guess n
nine so diminish seventh is
consonant false so one of the things
built into the music 21 ontology that's
different from um so Dimitri Chacho's
optic default ontology is that spelling
matters this case so diminish 7th sounds
the same as a major sixth in isolation
but it's not considered
consonant that's important to know and
uh I think uh I think last year there
was a month that went by without
somebody reporting this as a bug to the
music 21 list but most most months one
to two people um put that in not see
that so it definitely means that you
know um you uh I don't know an augmented
sth is not consonant either even though
an augmented second seventh is another
way of
saying octave perfect octave great super
um basically anything in traditional
theory in traditional tonal Theory
anything that is marked as diminished or
augmented or doubly diminished or doubly
augmented or whatever is considered
dissonant now the weird
one um that we can always debate is the
perfect forth who thinks it's
consonants who thinks it's a
dissonance a lot of people not voting
I'm glad for either way people voted um
in this case music 21 regards it as not
a consonants perfect forths are
generally they're the one weird interval
they're generally considered consonant
when they are melodic but dissonant when
they're harmonic and above the
base so it's take take Medieval music
with me or speo um you can figure out
the whole history of how this happened
and why it's in the one weird double
position but it's the only perfect thing
that is not um consonant in some
circumstances
okay um what are some of the things you
might do with interval uh class well
let's start with let's create the
perfect fifth one
P5 hopefully I've created that good um
and what we can do is let's say uh C4
we'll just C this equals P
C4 and now P5 can
transpose pitch
C4 so you have a perfect fifth creating
that as an interval object storing as P5
we can create a pitch object these just
because of my aliases C4 start C4 then
P5 can transpose the C4 transpose pitch
on C4 and gets an a pitch object that's
G4
now once you've done that if we look at
C4 that object is
unchanged so transpose pitch creates a
new pitch that is not uh that is not the
same pitch so if you wanted to do
something useful with this you would
probably store it as G4 equals this and
then you can do something with
with your new pitch obviously if you
knew what the pitch was going to be
coming in and what the pitch was going
to be coming out you wouldn't need to do
this right you can just create your own
damn G4 but um but this would work sort
of in general if you do want to
transpose in place um and I don't think
we've seen this in music 21 but you're
going to start seeing it all over the
place there is a keyword only argument
that means you must type this as a
keyword in place equals so C4 will now
be transposed
and nothing will be returned we run it
but now
c4 is a really terribly named variable
right C4 is now a
G4 um if you're ever doing a demo you
all remember when we took two notes we
inserted two notes or we removed them
from the stream and then everything was
screwed up uh so I always I'm going to
remember learned from that experience
and make C4 uh equals C4 right
again but sometimes we want to just have
a generic P equals um here this time
I'll write it out so that we can copy
and paste this pitch. pitch
C4 and uh we still have P5 let's just do
this for I in range 13 we don't actually
need I you can some people like to have
underscore as a dummy variable but we're
just going to for 13 times let's take
the pitch and
then uh we can no since we just done it
P5 transpose pitch p in place equals
true so we create a
C4 13 times we're going to go through
and um transpose
it so what is p
now C
B
10 is that what it
is oops not c um what do you call it
P F double sharp 11 because if you
notice we were Printing and then
transposing was my little uh little
trick thing just to just to make sure
that we're all following things yeah so
by the way this is one of the weird
reasons why um why I wanted you to work
early on with weird octave numbers like
10 and 11 and -2 and things like that
because quite often it is simpler to do
an operation like this like let's all go
around the circle of fifths and then
we'll just print the step of it and not
care about the octave number and then we
in the end we can bring it back down a
bunch of octaves later but sometimes
you're going to end up in there and
sometimes you're going to end up in in
double sharp territory triple sharp
territory before then transposing down
back the other way or doing some other
path so some so almost never is
um is you know F quadruple sharp 22
going to be a useful thing to think
about musically but sometimes it's a
useful point in the mid in the midpoint
of your work and by the way that's how
imaginary numbers came out first that
they were first used to solve I believe
Quint equations in a way that U made it
very easy even though they were NE in
the intermediate stages even though they
were never the answer at the end um so
think of quadruple Sharps and octave 22s
and stuff as like that okay
um so a couple couple things is C4 still
C4 yep good um you can also
transpose uh do the opposite way way and
this is a this is a real something that
python allows that other languages I
haven't been able to do it in so instead
of taking the interval and saying tr.
transpose pitch and the pitch you can
take the pitch and say transpose that by
the interval and that's sometimes pretty
helpful so music 21 object. transpose by
an interval class and um if you don't
care about efficiency you can always um
put in um just a string and it will
create a interval for you and so
transposing up an augmented 223rd gets
you g Shar 35 is that right doesn't
matter okay um by the way um okay uh
looking at the time one or two last
things uh if you ever
want something when you um when you're
working with the this is the interval
object again perfect fifth there are
things like specifier in here and you'll
be able to um do a you know how to do
dur on a um uh what do you call it on a
object to see everything um that's in it
but these are probably the most useful
things you'll see so how many scents how
many hundredths of a semitone is it and
yes you can do microtonal intervals if
you care about such things uh what's the
chromatic interval what's the complement
if you have a major sixth the complement
is
a remember it's minor thir it's the
thing that fills out the octave dionic
is it a skip is it a step can we reverse
the interval all these things so you'll
find some of these things in here um but
the last thing I'm want to do is to
think about uh this spelling non-s
spelling thing so implicit dionic we'll
say um let's create the interval of four
semitones so all I car is that it's an
interval of four semit tones and here's
where um what do we call it polyvalent
um polygamus whatever whatever we call
the interval it will take um I that was
a joke um it will take an integer
instead of a string so we can say the
int four and if I just look at this I4
right now it looks like hey it's just a
cheap way of saying major third but it's
actually a little bit different from
that so if I take the pitch C double
flat
um so pitch C flat
4 and i' say I4
transpose that pitch so take cou flat 4
and take it up a major third I don't
care about the accidental but what's the
F what's the step have to be if you're
going up a third from C
something e e so it should be uh what is
that e double flat 4
and instead you get a D4 so there's
something where if you initiate an
interval just by saying the number of
semones you're telling that interval
that the dionic interval the minor major
uh the major third is implicit that is
to say um when you want to know if it's
a major third yeah it'll be a major
third but I4 will say no feel free to
change this to anything that is for sem
tones up that is logical um and easy to
use so that's something that people will
um see in there whereas if we take the
perfect fifth and see which we created
it with the P5 thing and see if it's an
implicit
dionic false perfect fifth will always
take the one that we created with the
string P5 will always make sure that
something is a P5 uh I'm looking at the
time so I won't demonstrate last thing
which is music 21 still has a
restriction that it won't go above
quadruple sharps or quadruple Flats so
at that point even the dionic one will
say uh forget what I said let's make it
work and round
things uh great I'm um that's that's all
the time that I have if you transpose a
whole score uh you'll see that the key
signature is transpose with you which
can be kind of helpful and I'll I'll
post my um I'll post my what do you call
it uh the the thing where where I have
that demo to the class right