Welcome to everyone. I'm uh super
excited to get this started and look
forward to two really uh great days of
amazing science and stimulating
discussions. I still can't imagine a
better time to be in science. The drive
particularly in AI and biio medicine is
going to be too strong. It's going to
move at an amazing pace, you know,
faster I believe than advances in in in
the genome um took place.
Being here is just a dream come true for
me cuz I come from a pure computational
background. So I saw a lot of legendary
names that I only read on the
manuscripts as the principal
investigator in real life. So the
tremendous surprise and honor to be here
and it is really really inspiring
conference symposium overall a ton of
discussion that's just really
stimulating and inspiring.
>> I thought it was very interesting seeing
the scope of problems that people are
thinking about how to learn from like
hundreds of thousands of images or like
thousands of like spatial transcrytoics
or single cell data sets. It was very
inspiring to hear how big people are
thinking about big problems and like the
solutions to those problems. And one
more good thing about this conference
was usually you go to academic
conferences you may find some academic
top people but this here I also saw many
people from industry who are working on
academic but kind of uh somehow making
sure that industry and academia are on
the same page and
>> I think the poster sessions and like the
short talks for younger junior
researchers are really helpful for kind
of like showing our work to like this
broad field including like people from
industry and academia. I believe like AI
is is addressed in many contextes
today's but we still have a gap when it
comes to applying AI in the biology and
we we could see that many talks address
this topic and into different
applications the way AI we reshape how
we believe and how we conceive science
is going to be massive in the next years
>> it's on the intersection of machine
learning and bio which is like right
where I'm at home and I'm enjoying that
So many people with different
perspectives come together and have
different ways of thinking about
problems. So usually it kind of inspires
me.
>> I think the best part was also be having
the hallway conversations being the at
the poster sessions talking to people
about science that you're doing yourself
and getting inspired by many new ideas
seeing how people are really engaged in
that field and just being very excited
about what the future for this field
holds. It's really cool seeing the just
different diversity of topics that all
these different researchers are talking
about and it's really giving this sense
that biology is reaching this like stage
where we can start to think about how
these different scales start to interact
with each other when different data
modalities like in the morning we saw
people talking about images and then
later we saw people talking about
tissues but there's a lot of shared
themes that I think are really
interesting.
>> Dr. Emma Lombberg's talk is like already
like very illuminating and also like all
the talks like from like Ellen Institute
like with all these like amazing
institutions like doing all the cutting
edge research even though I'm reading
literature like this occasion really
brings me a lot of different perspective
to really illuminate my research
general. I think this is really great
and I have a lot of fun like just
attending it especially in person and
like communicating with all these
different experts.
>> It's great to follow up on past
collaborations. um but also think about
um what I could start in the future get
some inspiration on the interface here
from sology to machine learning and how
other people think about it.
>> There are many similar project uh to
what I'm currently working on on spatial
armies data and I talked to several
speakers get more understanding of the
area.
>> I'm really looking forward to this event
just going on and on so we can keep
coming back to it. Yeah, I hope to come
back next year. Thanks,