uh so I do want to start with a couple
caveats uh the first is that my natural
metabolic pace is quite fast I tend to
accelerate as I go sometimes I I'll try
not to but it does happen uh and so if
you have questions you know just
interrupt me uh I much prefer to take
questions like as there are points that
need clarification rather than waiting
to the end as Emily mentioned I'm part
of the asiba which is the human mamalian
brain Atlas project led by Eden at Allen
Institute uh we also have our own U1
that's a no cost extension a lot of the
stuff I'm going to show comes from that
and then there's this new ni brain
connects initiative that we have a U1
and anastas Andi has a um1 that we're
part of um and so I'm I'm going to give
so I have two talks listed here really
not two talks it's really like half a
talk and three qus of a talk something
like that but I can go fast enough that
it fits in one so and so the Sy this
stuff is going to be kind of background
for the second part um and the other
thing I'll say is that when I I was
talking with Kiku and Emily about what
to present you know they um they wanted
to make sure that I knew that this was
for a diverse audience and including a l
audience and that's fine and so the talk
is kind of Geared for that and so I'm
not going to go into a lot of technical
detail but I'm happy to like if anyone's
interested in model architecture or
whatever I'm happy to talk about it at
any level that you want and uh I'll try
to show people as I go this is work from
a ton of people over a lot of years and
I'll I'll you know these are the kind of
the primary ones but I'll Point people
out as I go
okay
so there's some issues with trying to
use modern deep learning particularly in
the world of MRI clinical MRI uh and
it's kind of easy to come up with this
kind of list we need a lot of of
manually annotated data like two or
three data sets is not enough five or 10
is probably not enough you can do a lot
with five or 10 but if you have a
thousand you can do a lot more um
annotation quality varies a ton uh if
anyone here has ever tried to label 3D
data sets it's an awful thing to do it
requires years of therapy for the rest
of your life after you've done it for a
while because we as human beings are
terrible at this like we have no um
phenomenological or or
um it we have no reason to have any
confidence say this at at taking 2D
sections and stacking them together in
our head in 3D and if you've done this
what you do is you label one slice and
you look at it you're like oh my God
that's perfect it's brilliant and then
you label the next slice you're like
that one is a work of art and then you
flip it into that different orientation
and it looks awful like there's no
consistency from slice to slice and so
this is just a hard thing to do to
generate ground truth data um this one
is a big problem for MRI in particular
that is if you train on a particular
type of data you will always be biased
towards it so if I change the way my
acquisition looks a little bit then the
network accuracy will go down and so if
all my Alzheimer's are scanned with one
type and all my controls are another am
I finding an effect or am I just finding
the fact that the images are different
um even if we really good at annotation
some stuff is really hard to annotate
like six slice MRI if I have 7 mm slices
and the spacing of my cortical folds is
2 mimers that's hard to
do and then lastly even if the data
quality is high there are some things
that are just intrinsically difficult uh
we see like the growth of lesions over
time and so you have a voxel that's
maybe a little bit brighter on time one
than it should be and on time two maybe
it's a tiny bit brighter than it was on
time one is a part of the lesion like
these boundaries are kind of fuzzy and
vague and so we're not very good at man
annotating them and I would argue that
this has been a problem for us
clinically it has been uh the primary
barrier to our ability to distribute
things in the clinic and to have
Radiologists get you know automated
measures of hi cample volume and to me
this is a failure of capitalism in
medicine because in
Radiology people pay for scan slots not
for time like ad Martinez would pay by
the hour but if you go and get your
brain scan you will pay for an MRI scan
and if that MRI scan is five minutes or
an hour it's the same price uh and in
MRI you like MRI is not like photography
the process of acquisition is kind of
accumulating information over time and
so in an hour we can acquire a much
better image than we can in five minutes
but if we acquire a much better image
now the radiologist has to read five
times as much data and that's also a
financial hit for the hospital and so
there are these incentives there these
capitalist incentives for crappy data in
the hospitals and U you know we fully
meet that that bar and routinely acquire
crappy data and so the question is what
can we do with it are there things that
we can do with the crappy data now with
the Advent of deep learning that
previously we
couldn't okay and so this part of the
talk um I'll talk about various
synthesis based deep learning I'll
explain what I mean by that um I think
the biggest challenge in the development
of this stuff is
this slide that I stole from Anastasia
yiki which is that it takes so long to
train these things you know you have an
idea and you're like oh this is going to
be great and you set it train and then
two weeks later it's converged and you
run it you're like oh my God I did
something stupid and then you fix it and
you start it again and then two weeks
later you know it repeats and so the the
the development cycle has really slowed
down because of
this okay so what do I
mean by the synthesis stuff and why do
we need it so Mr is a wildly flexible
technology if you don't know much about
Mr the reason it's so popular is that we
can derive contrast from many many many
different things in the anatomy from it
so here's an example of what we'll call
Mr modality so T1 weighted light matters
bright gray matters dark uh T2 weighted
you get the inverse contrast prot and
density weighted is kind of somewhere in
the middle this is a sequence commonly
used at MGH for um deep brain
stimulation targeting we you know you
can you have the flexibility to null
certain tissue classes so we want a
technique that works for all of this
stuff but NR we can do a lot of other
things even within the class of two
unweighted images there are a lot of
other image types that we would all call
to un weighted but they have different
contrast properties the gr matter is
darker it's brighter um in Mr we
frequently play the game of sacrificing
SNR for CNR that is we trade off signal
we trade off increased noise for
increased contrast uh and so this for
example does NP ra which has higher
contous to noise than a flash scan but
lower SNR than the flash scan and then
we can mess around with the resolution
right we can change the the the
orientation of our slices so this is an
axial acquisition a coronal a Sagal one
um we can skip space in the slice we can
take a 3mm slice skip a millim take a 3
m slice or we can just take thick slices
and so we would like a technique that
works for all of this stuff and that's
hard so one approach is just to build a
supervised CNN these days that usually
means a unet units pretty much
outperform anything uh on at least image
analysis stuff uh so I can take a
supervis CNN take this type of input
manually label a bunch of outputs and I
can create a a a nice CNN or unit that
can
automatically label axial T1 scans right
and that works if I can you know
manually label 20 or 50 or 70 of these
but it falls apart if I apply it to
something else so if I apply this actual
scan to a chronal scan this is the
result like everything just Falls to
Pieces um and of course it even gets
worse if I apply it to a different
contrast like to a a T2 weighted scan
okay so what's the alternative well
sorry uh and so this this is the case
across kind of broad changes in contrast
but even for small changes in contrast
networks are super good at picking up
tiny details images um they're great at
cheating if you have't ever trained a
network networks are are the best
cheaters you you will ever encounter uh
and so you have to watch them like a
hawk because they will learn a way to
solve the problem that is not the way
that you want it to solve it and so this
is an example uh this is hipocampal
volume uh compared to ground truth so
this is this is a dice score so one
means perfect overlap between the ground
truth and the automated and zero means
no overlap uh and this is was kind of
our state of the-art before the Advent
of deep learning and if you train a unit
on just the two unweighted images just
this class of t18 images these MP rages
you can do pretty well you can get 88 89
you know close to 90% accuracy and if I
take this network and I apply it to a
flash scan which is a two1 weighted scan
like the the white matter is bright the
gray matter is intermediate and the CSF
is dark um you get this catastrophic
loss of accuracy and it's because the
network has learned these subtle details
of what it means to be an rage these
frequency filters that we that we
implicitly apply on them and it doesn't
generalize so this we generally call The
Domain Gap that is a network train for
this sequence doesn't work well for this
sequence and this is you know a little
bit of a toy example there there are
things that I can do to make this better
I can augment my input data I can add
noise I can you know mess around with
the contrast and that will help but I
think you will never get away from the
bias of the MPR ra sequence because
that's what you're trained on and you
and even worse you will never know if
you got away from bias because we can't
ever prove a lack of bias right proving
a lack of bias would be proving the null
and so all we can show is that there's
no bias at a certain level okay so what
can we do about this we'll skip this so
we could manually label every single
type of scan Under the Sun but that's of
course not
tractable okay so the proposed solution
uh is something this this was actually
Adrian Do's idea uh and it came from
this process of trying to augment the
data and augmentation in deep learning
means taking your training data and
making it worse in various ways adding
noise espcially warping it adding you
know shading uh intensity artifacts over
space this kind of thing and at some
point after kind of making these
augmentations increasingly wacky Adrian
had the Insight of why do we need the
images at all and so the way we train
networks these days is without any real
data so the way it goes is we start with
a 3D anatomical segmentation like this
the segmentation doesn't have to be
manual segment a it doesn't even have to
be that accurate because we're not going
to pair it with image
data then from each one of these we'll
sample a spatial transform to create you
know a subject so we'll warp it in some
way so here are a bunch of different
subjects synthetic subjects warped and
then for each of these tissue classes we
will sample a set of intensities so I'll
sample a mean and a variance to the
white matter a mean and a variance for
the alus and for the basil ganglia and
I'll just make up an image right and
this is what the images look like and
the images are are crazy uh and you know
Benjamin Benjamin B who I'll show in a
second who
that here's Benjamin um Benjamin was uh
uhen glacius a grad student when he
wrote this stuff he was now a postto
across the street with poina goolan at
MIT and Benjamin had trouble publishing
this and the reason he had trouble
publishing this is people looked at
these images and they kept saying well
that doesn't look like an MRI your MRI
simulator is awful what are you up to uh
and for some reason we could never
explain to people efficiently that we're
not trying to simulate a realistic MRI
all we're trying to do is kind of span
the range of variability we expect to
see in the input sequences and then and
the idea is that if this data is kind of
more variable more difficult to segment
than the real data you know that the
network by the time you get the new real
data like this is easy uh and I I'll
show you kind of some more quantitative
analysis than my you know head swipe
this is easy but it turns out that
that's the case that if you that in the
cases where we took this data and we
tried to make it more realistic we found
accuracy went
and that we're better off kind of
spanning this range of of wide
variability than we are trying to make
things
realistic um and so this works so here's
a set of uh images that were all
segmented by the same unit the unit was
trained without ever being exposed to
real MRI just all these synthetic data
sets that we created um and here's you
know increasing resolution or sorry
decreasing resolution increasing boxal
size so 1 mm to 7 mm and then two
different types of scans and yet you get
pretty much the same segmentation
so it's pretty much invariant to the
input data and of course you know if you
have 7 mm slices you're not going to
extract as um as sensitive information
as you are from the one millim data but
we're not biased towards one or the
other and this is just to show that that
point that here's here's the data set
that it was trained on and when you
train a unit on that data it does great
but this thing shown green is the syn
stuff and you see it maintains high
accuracy across every different type of
Mr sequence and you can even give it a
CT scale and it'll do something
reasonable even though the CT shows no
contrast between
gr okay so that's one game we can play
another is something that yeno was up to
which is um synthesis so I'll skip this
um and this is kind of important for
some of the ban stuff which I'll explain
why in a second and so the idea here is
that we're going to do the same thing
we're going to start with a pool of
label Maps uh we'll sample a label map
we'll warp it to create an individual
subject but now instead of throwing out
the image intensities I'll use the image
intensities of targets so this is the
real scan that was acquired for this
subject you know it's deformed in the
same way as this one so these
intensities match that then I'll oops
sorry then I'll take this scan and I'll
do all sorts of awful things to it I'll
I'll blur it I'll I'll you know create
thick slices I'll put maybe some subject
motion into it I'll add noise um I'll
change the contrast so it doesn't look
right uh and then we'll do regression
and so the game we play is uh this is
input to the network and this is the
target
output and so we'll try and um
synthesize what a highresolution 3D 3T
scan would look like from any input data
and this works pretty well so here's an
example of three different input scans
there's a 6mm flare there's a 5mm
sagittal turbos spinco and a 4mm coronal
tu2 and we can turn them all into
something that looks like a 1er MP rage
that we can then kind of put through any
anatomical analysis package world
and in ban specifically we've been
applying this to these low field scans
we've been getting um from a hyperfine
scanner so the this is part of Eden's
Yom one and Christine McDonald and Dirk
Kean bought and cited a low field
scanner a hyperfine scanner in the
autopsy Suite in Dirk's autopsy suite
and so every brain that now comes to
autopsy uh gets wheeled into the scanner
and gets this type of low resolution T2
weighted because that's all we can get
on the low field scanners 3 m isotropic
but with this technique we can take this
30mm low field scan and turn it into a
3T EMP and further we can take this 3T M
and stuff it through free Surfer and
segment you know the cerebellum and
motor cortex and whatever you can get
these kind of detailed anatomical
parcellations that are registered to
this autopsy
sample and this
is well that was a slow transition um
this is what I was chatting with Kiku a
little bit at lunch um this is kartik's
work we can so Dirk will take photos of
the um the slabs after dissection but
before dissection we run a surface
scanner over the brain and we get this
type of 3D mesh and it only gets a
millimeter or two into the folds it
doesn't get into the depths of the folds
because we can't see it from the
exterior but it provides us with enough
geometric fiducials that we can take
these 3D slice or sorry these 2D
photographs of these 2D slices and stack
them up into a 3D Volume and use that to
register to the hyperfine scan and now
we have a path to go from any invivo
Atlas The Narrow Path right and so
that's what's shown here we've taken um
I guess this is our standard cortical
parcellation and projected it onto the
Narrow Path and now we can say to Dirk
we want you to take out a slab that's in
motor cortex or maybe it's in the
default mode Network maybe it's the
frontal component of the default mode
Network we can bring kind of the full
power of invivo Imaging to guide the
neuropath and of course we can go in the
other direction too once we have the
neuropath
results any questions on that stuff
before I
continue okay uh
another thing we can do is we can detect
change so change detection is if you
talk to a neuro radiologist they will
tell you that they spend the majority of
their time trying to detect change in
the brain that is they'll look at two
scans and they'll try and find the same
slice and they'll say has anything
changed has the legion grown are The
ventricle bigger is the hi smaller
because these are the biomarkers for
things that are going on in the brain
and if
you so Hospital information systems so
if we do a research study we are very
careful to prescribe every single thing
that we can think of to stay the same
over the course of the study we'll use
the same scanner we'll use the same um
head coil we'll use the same receive
coil we'll use the same sequence we'll
try and position the subject to the same
place in the scanner um that's all out
the window when you get a clinical scan
the clinical scan you will not get you
will not even be on the same scanner
like there's no provision in the
hospital information systems to say I
want this to be a 3T semen scan with
this head coil so your time one scan may
be a GE 1.5t and your time two is 3D
semens and the result is that if you
compare the images there will be huge
differences between them and the vast
majority of those differences are
technological in nature they have
nothing to do with the brain they just
the fact that the way we acquired the
data was different and so we've been
looking at um trying to synthesize our
way out of this problem because change
is a very difficult thing to label in
the brain like what real anatomical
change is and so here what we do is we
take a Time One scan in the same way we
did before uh sorry time one label map
the same way we did before we'll
synthesize the time two scan from it
like we'll move it in space a little bit
and then we'll introduce a little bit of
atrophy somewhere in the brain and
because we know exactly where we
introduce the atrophy we have ground
Truth for the training uh and further we
can introduce all sorts of um intensity
artifacts we could add noise we can make
the contrast different we can add you
know bias Fields blur the data and then
the question for the network is can it
take the input pair and find the true
anatomical change in the presence of
this kind of sea of technological
artifact uh I should note this is work
with sha Young
and this also seems to work pretty well
so these are real scans this is a
multiple sclerosis a subject with MS and
here's a subject with Alzheimer's
disease and if I take these two scans so
time one and time two this is real data
and I rigidly align them and I just do a
pixel-wise difference like I look at
just the absolute value of the
difference in the pixel intensi is
you'll get stuff everywhere so you get
all this stuff outside and this has to
do with um back shift and Mr um but then
you get all this stuff kind of in the
brain as well and and this stuff is not
real anatomical chain there's nothing
going on you know out here in the
whatever the bone of the skull uh this
is just the fact that the Mr scan is
different but the network does a nice
job at finding kind of these ventricular
changes and also this growth in um in
some white matter hyperintensity and the
same thing with the MS
leion okay almost done with the
synthesis stuff um so this is some work
that was done and this this stuff I'm
going to show in the second part of the
talk also so this stuff pay a little bit
of attention to uh this is worked from
Adrian dka so Adrian's PhD work was on
doing nonlinear registration with deep
networks um you call box amorph this is
also across the street Adrian is now
faculty at MGH and he and Malta
developed this technique called synor
and in synor we have these two synthetic
images and they're from the same subject
and we can distort them a little bit so
there's some nonlinear Distortion sorry
they're not necessarily from the same
subject um so there there's a nonlinear
warp that relates them and we would like
to recover that mountain War um the
problem here is that the image
intensities are somewhat random and
there aren't really good cross modal
similarity metrics in kind of image
registration world that work well for
nonlinear registration work pretty well
for rigid and linear but it's a little
bit ill posed to try and recover a
nonlinear warp in the presence of a
nonlinear change in the intensi uh and
so what Adrian and Malta observed is
that in the synthesis framework we don't
have to compare these images we don't
have to say what transformation
maximizes the similarity between this
image pair because each one of these
comes with an Associated label map and
so instead of comparing images what we
can do is compare label maps and say I
want to recover a nonlinear deformation
that aligns hippocampus with hippocampus
and migal with Mig and phalus with
phalus and I don't care about the images
that the network jobs to figure out what
that means in terms of image intensities
and this works quite well um and further
so uh I'll come back to this in a second
we don't even need brain images we can
make up the input label Maps so we can
make up images like this this is kind of
multiscale pear of noise so the network
can take we can take this image and then
warp it and then train a network to
recover the deformation between them
because we have both labels that give
rise to this image and the image itself
and this will be important because
sometimes what we want to register is
not a
brain and we did a parametric study on
how well this works so this is the uh
this is the target of a deoration shown
in the bottom row this is the source of
a deoration shown in the top row this
was a a scan that we have a forward
model for image formation and so we can
actually synthesize images with
different contrasts this is a T1
weighted image and this is a fully PD
weighted image and now I'm going to run
image registration on each of these
pairs and look at the accuracy of the
resulting alignment okay so left to
right is kind of more and more cross
modal like this pair is the same
contrast this pair is completely
different contrast and then these are
different image registration techniques
and the blue one the top blue one is the
synth morph that was trained on brains
and the second blue one is the synth
morph that was trained only on shapes so
it's never seen a real brain image and
what you can see is that the accuracy is
pretty flat even out here uh where we
lose contrast you know where the gray
white contrast is largely gone the
accuracy stays pretty high and so we can
generate nonlinear registrations kind of
between any pairs brains and further
between any pairs of shapes and I'll
come back to that in a little
bit okay that's the end of the synthetic
deep learning stuff
any questions on any of
that okay on to multiscale stuff so this
is really the kind of core of our
contributions to ban and brain connects
um and in the end I think probably like
a lot of people here we want to
construct a multiscale allice of the
human brain and it to do that you know
one of the things we were discussing at
lunch is uh the crazy array of spatial
scales over which structures of Interest
occur in the human brain you know from
nanometer to multiple centimeters right
you know ion channels to cortical
patterns uh and we want to account for
all of these things so we would like to
build an array of image acquisition
types that reveal the these properties
of interest and that could be you know
genomic or proteomic or transcriptional
or functional or anatomical or con
connectional uh we want to register
things so we want to build registration
tools that'll accurately align these
different image types across scales and
contrast and it's worth noting that you
know this has to be cross contrast
there's a reason we're doing the Imaging
you know that we're doing a lectin stain
for example you know because we care
about the vas cure or we're doing a new
end stain because care about the neurons
and so by construction our images show
different things and so the contrast is
inevitably going to be different across
these registration
targets um once we have the registration
we want to build individual subject
level modeling tools so that we can
situate the results of whatever we're
acquiring into the context so what
cortical layer is it in what column is
it in what cortical area this kind of
thing and then finally once I have all
this data at the individual subject
level how do I put it all together into
an atys um and register my different
subjects together to build an atlas that
is representative of these of these
properties that I've just observed in
this unique data set and the thing
that's part about this is that we want a
tool that can register stuff that it
doesn't see and what I mean by that is
you know you can imagine a by can study
where we you know do a complete um
transcriptional characterization of you
know the substantial uh this is
Emily's project um and we find different
cell types in the right and and
now we have another subject and we want
to register them such that those
populations of cell Al line cells align
across subjects well that's fine for xal
studies in which we've done this
transcriptional analysis but what if I
want to do it in in inv Vivo what if I
want to apply it to Parkinson's patients
then I want a technique that aligns
these areas without being able to see
them right we want to be able to align
things that we could only see during
training and not necessarily at
inference time and I'll I'll talk about
how we do that in a little bit okay and
as as I mentioned this is part of this
um you one sorry U1 that um H Wang and I
have at MGH and David Boaz at bu Patrick
ho at Mount Si and franisco poni at um
in Florence and so in this project
requiring XV MRI we acquire Optical
coherence tomography which I'll describe
in a little bit because probably people
aren't familiar with it um we were doing
a Buu in the previous Grant in the
connect instantiation qu is building a
rig at MGH for it uh then we do light
sheet microscopies so florescent like
sheep micros me at FL
um uh there's some stereology that goes
on some deep learning to segment cells
and then we want to put them into a
coordinate system where we can start to
make statements about human variation
like how many neurons are in this layer
in broker area for
example and then as I mentioned before
we're also part of this agba grant the
human mamalian brain Atlas that had Lane
runs that at the Allen Institute and
this is where we're doing the low field
scanning and of course this stuff is of
interest because you know St was here
there's a grant here um looking at
similar things and then Casey Chung
who's across the street is any day now
can get funded also for a um1 to start
looking at um proteomics and generate
Micon scale images of entire human
brains okay so in general in
neuroimaging we have been historically
kind of left with this choice of doing
coarse images on lots of subjects on the
whole brain or doing unbelievably fine
scale images on a few samples in tiny
little bits of brain and we haven't been
able to put them together and so this
kind of goes from em to things like uh
light sheet floresent microscopy and O
and two Photon Imaging we have built
this program at MGH where we use our Mr
scanners as incredibly expensive
microscopes uh so we have a 7t scanner
and we use it pretty much every weekend
that's probably an exaggeration use it
many weekends where we stick a brain in
the scanner Friday afternoon and then
Monday morning we come and take it out
and this is again because in Mr uh time
is SNR and if I want to get the small
voxels I need to scan for a long time
and by long I typically mean 70 or 80
hours and so we'll we'll put a brain in
and we'll get this is a 100 Micron scan
we got with Brian edlo a few years ago
we'll get something on the order of 100
Micron isotropic across the whole brain
and this ends up being and actually in
the O as well end up being kind of our
intermediate spaces that we use to
facilitate take registration because
it's really hard to take a 2d light
sheet data set and register it to you
know an invivo atlas I need some interim
targets from for that registration and
that's what the ooc and the XR
present so this is an example of the Mr
we've been doing this is Divia Vin's
work you know when we were starting this
we kind of thought 200 Micon isotropic
was about where we could get and Diva
just totally insisted that was not true
she was like we can do 120 uh and the
difference between 200 and 120 in an SNR
sense is like a factor of I don't know
four in SNR I'd have to calculate it you
lose SNR really rapidly in Mr as you
increase voxal volume or decrease voxal
volume rather but Diva was right um and
if in particular she came up with a set
of techniques that allowed us to measure
these tiny little distortions you get in
samples so Mr is a magnetic um image
acquisition technique and so if you have
something that's magnetic in the field
of view it will distort the coordinates
system of the image and in particular
iron deposition in the tissue causes
these micro distortions almost
everywhere um and so mostly people don't
care because your Distortion is like two
300 microns and your voxels are 2
millimeters so who cares about 200
Micron Distortion and so Divia had to
invent this set of techniques to measure
and remove these distortions and for us
it makes a big difference so this is the
cerebellum of um a language using so I'm
not allowed to use her name of a
language using great ape that died of
natural causes who scanned a few years
ago whose name you probably know if
you've seen any of the television series
on them and you can see the impact of
the Distortion correction all of a
sudden we can see you know three layers
in the cerebellum where it was really
difficult to before and the same thing
is true in the cortex um we lose I'll
talk about vessels a lot in a little bit
but we lose a lot of the vessels if we
don't do the Distortion correction right
you can kind of see them but you can see
how they're blurred but they get much
sharper after Distortion correction and
the same thing is true of cortical
layers here's a band of B that we mostly
don't see in the Distortion I guess this
is probably um Street of jari in V1
maybe um but you can see how much
clearer it gets after we correct this
200 or so Micon
Distortion we've also been pursuing this
technique called Optical coherence
tomography which um most of you probably
have not heard of and this is stuff that
David and I started way back when uh
Caroline came as a postto and she's now
faculty who I also came as a postu and
she's now faculty I showed these slides
to Caroline and she's like why are you
showing 15-year-old slides um in part
because I had it but in part because
they're just beautiful like this is an
image of the human medulla with o so the
background image I think is like I guess
it's four Micron pixel size for the
whole thing but if I zoom in we could
also require higher ones we like half a
micron and so we're really almost at the
defraction limit here um and the nice
thing about o is that in contrast to two
Photon in O we acquire an entire line at
a time so we inquire a an entire line in
depth it's not a point wise measure
and so it's much faster than two Photon
and so that lets us do these large field
of views I'll show you what I mean so
here's uh OC of the the medial temporal
lobe and there's a little inset here
which I'll zoom in on so you can see
kind of the astonishing resolution we
get with the large field of view of
these Mossy fibers in the hip
campus and then the other game we can
play with OT is we can put polarization
on the incoming light and the reason
that's important is that the
polarization state of the return light
will tell you something about the B
refringent properties of the thing you
imaged and milin is B refringent and so
by putting polarization on the incoming
light we can recover the optic axis of
the thing we're Imaging that is the
orientation of the axon that we're
Imaging that's what's shown
here um this movie is playing so there
are two two critical things about the o
one is this polarization so polarization
sensitive OC that's say directly image
axonal orientation and the reason this
is critical particularly in regions like
the human brain stem if you have tightly
packed fibers even if you can resolve an
individual axon if it was sitting by
itself you know with no friends and
crying softly at lunch or something uh
you can't image it if it's in a densely
packed region because it just looks all
white right to image it you would need
the resolution to see the milein Sheets
if you wanted to accurately label
individual axons and that's you know an
order magnitude more resolution that's
probably sub um you know 100 nmet or so
and I'll show a little bit of that later
on but o doesn't suffer from that
problem because o directly images
orientation so even in tightly packed
regions we get an accurate measure of
the orientation of the axons okay the
other important thing about o play this
move
again is
that in OC we're Imaging a a cut block
of tissue um potentially whole
hemisphere but we haven't ever built a
rig to do something that big but the
Imaging is with laser light the Pates
the cut surface it penetrates about 200
300 microns under the cut surface this
is like formul and fixed tissue and so
the game we'll play is we'll acquire a
line in depth of a couple hundred
microns and then we'll cut off the top
layer and we'll acquire another line and
this of course is the reverse of what
you do in standard microscopy where you
cut and then image and so we're Imaging
and then cutting as opposed to cutting
and then Imaging and you know image then
cut cut then image it doesn't sound like
a big deal but in fact it's everything
and the reason it's everything is that
we're Imaging before we introduce s
specific distortions and so to generate
a 3D Volume of obct all we do is stack
up the the optical images and that's
what's shown here play this movie again
so here's a little spinning
movie of the OT and you can see that you
can't see the Imaging plane we can't
tell what orientation we have the data
at and these are three orthogonal views
through the same tissue so this is the
plane of sectioning XY the optical plane
so this is what we would call an on FAS
image but if I take this and flip at 90
or a different 90 you can't see the
slices um and this is because there is
no Distortion because we're Imaging
before we cut and physical distortions
are really hard to remove and the fact
that the ooc doesn't have these physical
distortions means we can use it as kind
of a vertical coordinate system we can
take things like light sheet data and we
know exactly what distortions are
induced because we have an image of the
tissue at Micron scale that doesn't have
those distortions
any questions on the OT stuff before I
continue or on anything else for that
matter
okay uh we're also doing a bunch of
light sheet Imaging and this is stuff
that goes on in in Florence with
Franchesco and aren and den and
Josephine beatric so here we've been
playing with this lipophilic die called
D and Di likes uh myin environments and
it will bind to um myelinated fibers or
even very lightly melinated fibers and
the result is that we can get images of
axons with the light sheet floresent
microscopy and so for The Connect
projects we're doing di that's shown
here but we're also doing maybe new N I
don't know what your experience is with
new n for us new is really finicky um
there are samples that it just doesn't
work on for reasons we don't really
understand um and so there are other
stains that we're still playing with for
neuron
stains and then finally at the highest
resolution um the lens group is working
on um two Photon after expansion
microscopy and so on the left I'm
showing what we would very much like to
do is do the two Photon Imaging on the
tissue that we already did the light
sheet Imaging on it's not EXA it's not
completely clear that's going to work
they've been working on it and they've
gotten to about 3.5x expansion and that
looks pretty good this is what 4x
expansion would look like and so here
you can see Mile and sheets right so
here we can actually see individual
axons at the scale that we can actually
label them right and so this is kind of
our ground truth and this we're not
going to get you know we'll get this in
like millimeter cubes of tissue we're
not going to get this in centimeters but
the light sheet we'll get over the
entire human brain
stem
okay I'm going to talk about
registration stuff if there's nothing on
the
acquisition okay so for no particular
reason I'm going to go from kind of
biggest scale to smallest scale so part
of the hmba project is
getting uh human hospice patients to
consent to being scanned prior to death
and then to brain donation um and there
are an unbelievable array of basic
questions in Neuroscience we have been
unable to answer because we've never had
this data so for example um NY kisher
whose lab is across the street and and
Brandon kogai has been pursuing uh human
functionally defined cortical areas for
decades she has a spot in the in the
inferior temporal lobe called the fusor
face area um there are various other
ones but in the end is it a cortical
area is the face area a cortical area we
don't know does it have a different
connectivity profile than stuff around
it does it have different molecular
properties you know are the cells
different there than a neighboring
cortex would we see some boundary and
the answer is we just don't know and
it's because we've never had this paired
data and so one of the things we've been
working on are tools to register inv
Vivo and xvivo data this is stuff that
lives I
did that's not supposed to say that
that's supposed to say lii um and here
we built some tools to register in Vivo
and xvivo data um and this is hard
because you can see the dramatic
deformation uh that happens X Vivo so
when you do uh an autopsy and you take
the brain out you cut into the the dura
you know the CSF spills out kind of
gravity takes over things sag there are
these large scale deformations that
occur in the tissue but we would like to
establish a pointwise correspondence we
would like to know that this point in
the invivo is exactly this point in the
XO right and so one observation that we
made um I should thank the group at UB
Who provided this data this is from the
ACT study um is that if you do a
cortical surface reconstruction of the
invivo data and the XV data you can
again kind of see the change in overall
geometry like this one the shape of this
is pretty different than the shape of
this but the red green patterns are the
cortical folding patterns so this is the
central sulcus the red are suside the
green or Gyro and and you can see that
the folds are pretty much perfectly
preserved that is you know here's like
the Omega the typically the human hand
area um and you can see it like right
there right so there's this kind of
large scale deformation that occurs but
the folding patterns are preserved and
so if we can align
folds then we can account for the vast
majority of the nonlinear deformation
that occurs across death and actually
the truth is that this registration is
much easier than the cross subject
registration again because the topology
of the fold is preserved and I'll I'll
talk about that in a minute so here's an
example this is the invivo scan an MP
rage um that we've already warped to be
registered with the XO this is the 200
Micron xvoo and I'll go back and forth
so you can see that they are pretty
perfectly
registered right and this now lets us
use this scan um as kind of a neuropath
magnifying glass that is I can look at
the scan this is Brian edlo who's a
neurologist at MGH I worked with for
years and Brian looked at this mic on
scan he said oh look at the white matter
here this white matter is rarified like
if I had seen this on the invivo scan I
would have recommended something some
Downstream um followup of it and if we
go back to the invivo scan we can see
that it was there there's kind of this
darkening of the white matter here but
it wasn't Salient enough in would be
picked up by radiologist and neurologist
time and the same thing elsewhere so
here's a bit of white matter that's
bright brighter than it should be and
again if we go back to the invivo scan
we can again see it was there but we it
just wasn't seen at the time it wasn't
in
red okay um so now I'm going to talk
about registering the XO data and here
we're going from 1 to three Micron light
sheet rest of microscopy uh or the 75
nanometer to two Photon which we don't
have much of yet so we haven't really
done anything on this all the way out to
the full brain or the whole hemisphere
MRI and as I said this is a challenging
problem it's nonlinear it's crosscast
kind of by Design because we want the
different images to tell us different
things about the brain so they have to
have different information um contained
in them um and it's wildly cross scale
you know it's like one Micon pixels to
120 Micon pixels so whatever that is 100
cubed difference in voxal volume between
these and those and then the 1
millimeter of course are even coarser
okay the O is a critical interim Target
because it should exactly match the
light sheet data so the O we take the
image we cut it and then we do light
sheet on that cut and so the ooc image
is exactly the same tissue as the light
sheet data but the light sheet is
deformed by clearing cutting and
mounting this kind of thing okay so as I
mentioned before there are cross cross
model similarity metrics things like mut
information and correlation ratio um but
they're not great for nonlinear
registration you can get them to work
but they're kind of flaky and it tends
to be a little bit osed that is you can
generate nonlinear registrations that
are the wrong one that will minimize
those things or maximize them if you're
trying to maximize them and so we would
like to kind of um find a metric that's
more robust than
this but of course we already know how
to do this because we've done it with
the synor shapes right we we've
generated these synthetic networks that
know how to do nonlinear cross modal
registration and they've figured out
their own similarity metric because all
we told them was make sure the labels
line and they figure out what image
intensities what what matching of image
intensities result in label
alignment okay so here are some examples
um this is U Wang's work used another
post that came from across the street he
did a PhD with just Solomon in kind of
geometry processing here's an example of
a caltin stain this is light she
fluoresent microscopy this is O of the
same tissue and you can see why this is
a hard registration problem right
there's a lot of deformation between
these two they have different contrast
properties there's all sorts of stuff
going in the light sheet all sorts of
intensity artifacts in light sheet data
you know these kind of exponential light
attenuation and um these areas where the
the tissue wasn't quite flat and so we
lose signal um and so for this we don't
again we don't build our image matching
based on image intensities that is I'm
not trying to say bright stuff here
should align with bright stuff there
instead what I'm doing is segmenting the
boundaries of the tissue and maybe the
white matter and then trying to align
these
segmentations and this is how that
looks that's what the warp looks
like and this is the accuracy of it so
works pretty well so we can generate a
pretty good alignment between um the Cal
rtin stain light sheet image and the OCD
and kind of another amazing thing that
you did is he he derived a kind of
general purpose lassan solver that is
incredibly fast and in general when you
use a lusian solver you you either use a
direct solver where you give the problem
set up and it gives you a solution it's
not terribly accurate but if you want
accuracy you have to use an iterative
solver and your iterative solver
basically recompute the solution until
you achieve a desired accuracy so if you
say your tolerance is 10 Theus 7th it
might run for four hours until it gets
there um but you developed a direct
solver that has the same accuracy as the
additive solvers and the reason that's
important is that for us I mean I think
it's important for a lot of things um
the reason it's important for us is it
allows us to do this registration in
real time and that is he's deriving he's
built a technique that estimates a Time
varying velocity field that encodes the
deformation
and if any of you do n your registration
time bearing velocity Fields take hours
to integrate like to get a solution
takes hours of this size images um but
use technique takes about a second uh
and this is this was the slide I was
waiting for this morning
Emily because you was working on it till
this morning this is like a python demo
we're gonna we're going to integrate
this into our visualization environment
this is not integrated at all but it
shows that this technique can be
interactive and it's fast enough that I
can take so this is the source image
this is the target image you can compute
the initial warp and then iteratively
improve it by picking point
correspondences so you can say this this
blood vessel is that blood vessel and
this spot in the brain is that spot in
the brain and it will iterally recompute
the registration um to update the
accuracy so there's the initial
registration and I'll note the actual
registration is faster than the movie
plan registration takes about a second
then you can pick correspondences you
pick a point there and a point here and
it will update the warp
and then pick another couple points and
it'll update the
warp and so we're going to integrate
this into our visualization tool and I
think that for byan this will provide
most of what we need because what we
need is not to register you know a
thousand images an hour we need to
register kind of a handful of images
accurately
okay uh then from
the right so now we can image the light
sheet to the O we register the light
sheet to the oct now we want to register
the OT the MRI so here's an OC scan
here's the MRI the O is not very
distorted these are gentle nonlinear
distortions mainly because when we do
the Imaging we're kind of physically
distorting the tissue a little bit we're
putting in a bag or a tube or something
and so there are residual and nonlinear
distortions between them uh and this is
mol's work um this is quite old now this
he did like earlier in the week I think
Wednesday uh and so he just took the
synor shapes that I showed you before
and he applied it to this pair and it
works pretty well so here's the
deformation that's induced again it's
pretty gentle um and here's an example
of the accuracy so I go back and forth
you can see that the Mr and OCT line up
pretty well
right okay so this is where we are now
um we can generate pretty good
registration from single Micron light
Che data all the way out to 100 micron X
MRI from the 100 Micron X MRI we can
kind of go anywhere show you that in a
little bit and by anywhere I mean like
inv Vivo atlases um and the registration
is pretty accurate but it's accurate at
the scale of a millimeter or so like if
you look at it you can see that there
inaccuracies particularly in the
interior of uniform regions and that's
understandable because we don't have a
lot of information in the interior of
the white matter we can't tell where the
superior longitudinal piculus is or
something right we can only tell that
it's kind of bright or dark or whatever
and so we would like to improve on these
techniques to align at least mesoscale
features columns layers microc columns
mini columns this kind of thing okay so
how are we going to get there well we
know that vessels occur at almost every
spatial scale in the brain so down to
the four Micron capillary bed where you
know a single red blood vessel can fit
into a capillary vessels occur from
there all the way out to you know the
four five millim peel vessels that run
along the surface of the brain that
neurosurgeons use to find or avoid motor
cortex for example and and so if we
could segment the vasculature this in
this array of images we could use
vessels as endogenous fiducial markers
and we could say I want the vessels to
align across different image types right
and of course the vasculature is super
interesting in its own right you know as
we were discussing at lunch it's what FM
is based on knowing where the blood is
um and lots of pathologies um are
vascular
pathologies okay yeah so I already said
this so here's an example of an to O
registration um I think Adrian and wrote
this some time ago and this is an
example of why registering vessels is
important so I'll show on the left this
is a pure Mutual information based
registration so I'll go from the OT to
the MRI and on the right we trained a
network with mutual information but also
telling it align vessels and here we
manually labeled a set of vessels in the
source and Target and so we kind of um
we encourage the network to find a
registration that also aligns the
vessels and you can see that The Vessel
there are a lot of vessels around but
they're very small features and so a
general intensity based metric won't
align them unless you force it to so
here's just go back and forth and so you
know like here you can see that that
vessel doesn't line
up unless whoops wrong
way unless you force it to and if you
force it to then you get a similar
registration but now the interior of the
stuff is lining up as well and so if we
could segment vessels in this array of
Imaging types
we could embed them in the registration
and tell the registration I want you to
align stuff but I really want you to
align the vasul okay and so this has led
us into a many years
long um hobby of segmenting vessels This
was um yels work initially and now K
Mori anden G are engaged it so as I
mentioned vessels occur in every spatial
scale and so they're present in every
image we acquire in every brain region
but they're super hard to manually reg
manually annotate um you know I I said
before you know we owe years of
therapies to our Ras uh who we forced to
do manual annotation we owe Decades of
therapy if you've been trying to
manually label vessels and it's because
because of their um properties because
they occur at the edge of the resolution
you can see in every Imaging modality
unless you're getting like Micron images
so in like 120 Micron Mr there are you
know 150 Micron vessels that you're like
is that a vessel I guess you know in the
10 Micron OCT five Micron vessels that
we catch glimpses of and so at every
scale it's really hard to see them and
they're everywhere this is my favorite
quote from Yale vessels everywhere and
nowhere and that's because they occur in
every bit of the brain but they're only
like less than half a percent of the
brain by volume of the tissue volume and
so because they're so small by volume
they don't they don't naturally line up
using image-based intensity metrics for
similarity for registration okay so we
decided we wanted to register them uh
sorry we wanted to segment to embed them
in registration um I not have on the
next slide and as I said this is just a
super hard task you know and we were I
mean we've played this game so many
times in the past couple of decades
where we want to segment something so
we'll go out and manually label a bunch
of them and then we'll train and out
them based on the manual annotations and
that completely failed for vessels and
the reason it failed for vessels is that
the manual annotations just weren't good
enough um and it's not because the
manual annotators failed it's because
it's too freaking hard and you can see
that here so this is an O so this is an
on FAS image this is um in depth you can
see the the striations that occur by the
exponential light attenuation and so
this was a super careful labeling I
think Caroline Manan did this and she's
super good at this she's so diligent and
works you know hours on these things but
even after working hours on these things
it's easy to find ones that are missed
here and here and here and here and even
this labeling of ones that I miss like I
missed ones right there's probably one
there one there one there one there and
the only way to tell that their vessels
like these little dark spots is to go
through slices and say well does it look
like it travels through slices is there
a tubular structure in 3D that I caner
that I can infer is present in the
sequence of images and that's really
hard okay so in OC it's really hard
here's a similar example in X Mr like
you know these bright white spots or
vessels the vessels can occur um as
bright spots in Mr but they can also
occur as dark spots so there was a dark
vessel there I'll play this movie again
you can see some diving one there was
the diving vein there probably there's
one here and it's just kind of random
depending on whether uh there's any
blood left in the tissue because the
blood has iron content and that makes it
bright on this type of Mr but if there's
no blood it's just kind of an empty
space and it looks dark and so it's even
harder because now you're looking for
bright stuff or dark
stuff okay so what can we do about this
um and the answer is kind of the same
answer as before that was a very slow
transition is we can synthesize our way
out of the out of the problem so we can
generate completely synthetic vascular
trees and this was stuff that Yale did
Yale wrote this code where you start
with kind of a root vessel uh and then
you randomly select like a caliber
tortuosity um a probability of branching
and then you let it branch and you grow
these vascular trees here's one with
high density so density is one one
parameter uh and here's one with low
density uh and then eten and Kiara have
been working on this since then etan has
been working the O side and K working on
the XR uh but the game we'll play is to
take this synthetic vasular tree and
build a synthetic image around it this
is what a synthetic image looks like for
Mr there's a synthetic Mr image and then
we'll embed our synthetic vessels in our
synthetic Mr image so here's the
synthetic image these dark spots are the
vessels the red shows where the vessel
location is the same image with and
without the vessel labels um and now we
know exactly where the vessels are and
we get the advantages of the whole
synthesis game which is that there is
never a mismatch between the image and
the labeling because we construct the
labeling sorry we construct the image
from the labeling so the labeling is
always exactly correct and and but then
the question is do these images capture
enough of the variability we see in real
Mr uh to generate a good vascular
segmentation and the answer is a
qualified yes so here's an example um
this is a manual annotation this is no
sorry the other way this is a manual
annotation this is the network and this
is the overlay and so it works pretty
well um it works pretty well for some
cases for some
sequences but it doesn't generalize that
is if I tried a different kind of Mr it
would fail if I give it hpct it might
fail um
okay so as I said this works pretty well
we've got it working reasonably well on
o we've got it reasonably working well
in some XMR but there are a ton of
things we would like to register and so
there are a ton of things we would like
to be able to segment vessels in you
know the XV MRI showed you there's a ton
of inv MRI done in the vessels mostly
the contrast is generated by moving
Blood by the fact that you know that the
blood is moving this is kind of the the
feature that invivo angiography uses to
to um generate contrast in the vessels
but there are other kinds you know in in
EMP rages we see vessels for reasons I
want to get into it they're quite bright
in OC we see them in light sheet we see
them in many different stains they um we
see in the two Photon and confocal um
h& you know there's new hip CT data that
shows the vasculature in just beautiful
detail I don't if people have seen the
hip c um coming from Clare Walsh and
Peter Lee but it's just lovely and then
you know Jeff lickman is getting microct
and EM that we also see the vasculature
in so we would like to segment them in
all of these
modalities and if you work hard this is
Kiara's work you know and Kiara has done
a great job kind of trying to tune the
synthesis
both the vessel synthesis and the image
synthesis to work in different Imaging
modalities but it's a pain and you have
to each time you have to you know and
when a network fails there's no easy way
to know why it failed like except just
looking at the data like well I guess
the vessels in my training set weren't
large enough caliber like they didn't
see these big vessels out here so maybe
I'll tweak my synthesis so that the
vessels it sees are larger caliber you
know and then I'll wait two weeks and
try it and hope my results get better um
and that you could do that and and it'll
work on you know time of flight images
shown here it'll work on XMR and O this
is around the central sulcus this is a
different type of type of flight this is
a kind of more standard MRI M magnetic
resonance and geography slightly thicker
resolution um I think this is a phase
contrast and then we got some hip C from
the London group and it works after a
little bit of tuning it works pretty
well on the hip C also but we would like
not to do this we would like not to have
to play this game where every time
someone gives us an image we have to
figure out why our tools fail on it and
what we can tweak in the image synthesis
in order to improve
it okay so how can we solve this problem
how can we learn to segment vessels
without handcrafting the synthesis for
both the image type and the the vessels
um there are a giant number of
parameters that go into the synthesis
you know Benjamin did an amazing job um
in the original synthes paper at
optimizing this but he had you know I
don't know 20 25 degrees of freedom you
can't do a grid search in 25 dimensional
space when every Point takes two weeks
to to to generate
um so more generally we would like to
learn to modify the synthesis to
optimize the accuracy of the
segmentation on real data and this is
distinct from learning a synthesis that
optimizes the accuracy of the
segmentation on sythetic data this is a
very different problem and I'll talk
about why that's the case in a second
um uh and then of course this would be
super interesting because it would tell
us something about how networks learn if
we can optimize the synthesis if we look
at the what the Learned synthesis is
doing we could find out what's important
for networks during training and you
know we always kind of had this idea and
it kind of underlay a lot of the
synthesis research that if you train a
network in a difficult environment it
will grow up to be a happy Network um
and I don't mean that to be General
parenting advice you know if Danielle is
watching or regini that doesn't mean
anything about parenting um but this is
was kind of the basis of the synthesis
stuff is that we would show the network
such difficult stuff that by the time it
got to real data it was easy okay so can
we show evidence of that and I'll show
you what I mean in a
second okay so this is work with yel and
Jing this is kind of the normal
synthesis framework that is I set have a
set of labels call them z um I stick
them through my synthesis augmentation
engine that generates an image I'll call
x a synthetic image X I'll stuff that
through my segmentation Network it
generates a prediction why um and then I
put it in loss and the loss says
compares the ground truth labels to the
predicted labels and says well they
don't know they that that well and so I
update my network parameters to make the
segmentation more accurate on the
synthetic
data okay and then the general
optimization procedure we go through is
messing around with the parameters of
this thing and hoping that it'll get
better on real
data so what we did um is embed this
optimization into the entire network
training and this is a difficult problem
because so here I have a segmentation
Network this is the same segmentation
Network so I just copy the weights from
this down to here and then I can apply
it to real data right so I I can take a
real data set I can stuff it through the
segmentation Network I get a real
prediction I compare it to some ground
truth labels I have um but I can't
optimize this with respect to the
synthesis because the synthesis isn't in
this Loop that is if I change the
synthesis it doesn't change the output
here so the gradient of this with
respect to the synthesis is zero there
is no gradient flow that goes back to
the synthesis engine um but what yeld
yelds um kind of aha moment was that I
don't need to go into details about this
but basically the the change in this
with respect to the change in the
weights is not zero and so if you keep
around the weights from kind of the last
gradient step you can flow the gradients
back from real loss into the synthesis
and now I can build a learnable residual
Network that is an image I add to every
synthetic image that optimizes not the
synthetic loss but the real loss and
critically these real labels never go
into this network so this network has no
ability to learn from the real labels
all it's learning from is what to do to
the synthetic data to optimize the
accuracy on the real data okay and the
reason I say that this is very different
than optimizing the accuracy on the
synthetic data because optimizing on the
accuracy on the synthetic data would be
easy right I just make it a binary image
where my vessels are one and everything
else is zero that's not what I want okay
so this um Works astonishing well at
least in early days this is again about
a week old um but if we take um kind of
a a standard synthesis and we train a
segmentation Network we get a dice
accuracy so this is this overlap here
between the automated and the and the um
predicted segmentations without the
learn to synth stuff we get an accuracy
of around 53 54 um and and this is a
little bit of a straw man because I
didn't I didn't tune this at all I
didn't add noise to it I didn't do a lot
of augmentation I wanted that all in the
synthesis Network um and it also I just
kind of randomly we have should I should
be pointing these out and I haven't been
we have 7 64 cubes that have been
manually annotated mostly by Caroline
Manan but also by our interns um thank
you interns for this thankless task um
and what we found on the manual
annotation side is that the only thing
we can really do is segment very small
blocks that is what I showed you earlier
was like a 300 Cube we can't do 300
cubes or too many vessels in it um and
so we do either 32 cubed or 64 cubed and
that's small enough that you can go
through it exhaustively kind of time
after time and try and find these two
other structures that are and I think I
happened to pick two that are pretty
difficult for that ground Truth uh for
the kind of standard um segmentation
Network without the learn to syn so what
does it look like these are what the
results look like this is the manual
annotation and again you can see kind
hard in the lights maybe like this
should be one
vessel but because the images are noisy
this is what the images look like there
are breaks in it in the manual
annotation because the manual annotator
kind of lost it for a little bit and
then found it again this is what the the
initial segmentation looks like and this
is what it looks like without learn
descent sorry with learn descent and so
what is the learn descent doing if I go
back here to the
diagram I'm essentially learning an
image that I add add to the initial
synthetic image that I'm going to give
to the network right so what is the
image that I'm adding the initial
synthetic image that makes the network
more accurate on real
data and this is pretty interesting so
here's what the initial image look like
so this is the initial synthetic image
with the initial labels shown in blue
hard to see the blue here this is it
without the labels so this is the same
image so these are vessels here this is
just noise these are synthetic
structures that are not vessels um the
Learned residual it's like this I'll go
back and forth and so what it looks like
is like a photographic
negative that is what it's learning to
do is make life hard for the
segmentation
Network and so if I add them together
this is now the input to the
segmentation Network this very low
contrast image and so again this is
early days you know this is a result
that's like a week old and I don't know
that'll hold up but it seems like the
answer is make life really hard for your
networks during training and then your
infrance will get
better and there are a lot of things to
be done in this like we we we very much
want to add parametric variations so for
example vessel caliber should be a
learnable parameter what is the range of
vessel calibers that optimizes the
accuracy on real segmentation um because
for example in the hip C we see all of
the vessels we see vessels from like you
know the 4 millim peel ones actually
probably we've taken the PE surface off
so we don't see that but you know
millimeter scale vessels down to you
know 10 Micron vessels um but in the o
or the exor MRI we don't see the 10
Micron vessels because our image
resolution is
120 so I think there's still many games
to be played um and this is a
quantification of so this is the
learning this is training across time so
Epoch and this is sorry this is negative
accuracy so down is better here for no
very good reason except that I made the
slide like two days ago um and so this
is the accuracy on the synthetic data
and this is the accuracy on the real
data and what you can see is that the
network learns to improve the accuracy
on the real data about the time it
learns to decrease the accuracy on
synthetic data so it's kind of some
quantification of of what I mentioned
before okay that's it on the vessel
segmentation
stuff questions
or
yeah person to person oh man I wish I
knew the answer that question you know I
I
think that's funny there was a when I
was a post at MGH there was a post named
Rick hog who's now at Montreal and
he he was very interested in Bas Imaging
and he was like we should build an an
atlas of of like super Bas and you see
how it varies from person to person and
I was like that's a great idea you know
that was 30 years ago and we haven't
done it um and you know there are lots
of basic unanswered questions about the
vure so for example do the vessels
follow the fical if we could segment the
vessels would we know where the major
fical are from the brain maybe I mean
you expect their supplying profusion
like it might be that if we had a
vascular map we wouldn't need diffusion
MRI we could just look at the vessels
and know where the major tracts are I
don't know you know do they do they
delineate cortical areas um you know
dioa did these India ink stands that
that seem to show lots of vascular
change in some regions you know a lot of
it was V1 V2 and of course V1 changes
along every Dimension from every other
area but it may be that the vasculature
tells us something about cortical areas
like where are the boundaries between
this and that cortical area so the
answer is I don't know like I would love
to know the answer to that question but
I don't
know okay another question mentioned
these white matter
hyperintensities um I guess there's
those are still kind of like oh sorry oh
yeah you mentioned these white matter
hyperintensities which are still as far
as I understand kind of a mystery object
and one of the theories is that they're
vascular in
that there's some kind of vascular
defect what just curious what you think
yeah let me start by saying I am I am
absolutely 100% not an expert on this
but you know I have like spent time
close to some experts so I know a little
bit just from like EES dropping um so I
think that there are different kinds you
know when we look at these lesions on Mr
sometimes they're like a little on a T1
weighted Mr they look a little darker or
a little brighter on a a T2 or flare or
something but sometimes they're like
black holes and I think those are
probably have different Origins I think
the black holes are probably like dead
tissue um whereas the other ones maybe
you know some inflammation I also think
that they they change in different so
like in Ms we see them and that probably
is different than the ones we see in
aging and Alzheimer's um but in the end
I don't I don't know that we know the
answer to that you know one of the
things that like Dirk Keen was excited
about when we first started this whole
project is we can find them where them
are like for the neuropath they're hard
to study because you don't know where
they are you don't see them on the slab
but we see them in Mr and then we can
project that onto the slab and then you
can go and take that out and look at it
and in fact we did that with the case I
showed you it's just the neuropath
wasn't very interesting in that case so
we we don't typically show neuropath
findings for that but the techniques are
all in place to do that like use the Mr
as a spotlight to tell the
neuropathologist something's going on
here can you check it
out you could find a slab with one and
then go in and dissect it straight to it
yeah yeah I mean the the one caveat is
that we typically need
do the best that we can do we typically
need some type of image of the whole
brain um whether it's photos of every
slab or an MR before it was taken out or
or a 3D surface scan like once you
remove parts of the brain we can no
longer recover the topology of it and
topology is a pretty strong constraint
um so that that helps us a
lot okay okay on to individual level
stuff okay so let me go back to this so
here we would like to increase the level
of details for years we we've done
anatomical modeling of you know Cate
paman and and hippocampus and Miga and
we've extended that to things like um
you know subfields in the in the
hippocampus May nuclei but we would like
to extend it in individual subjects that
we're doing this type of highr Imaging
on so that we're not just saying it's in
you know the frontal lobe but we're
saying it's in layer three of Robin area
44 for example and so we've been trying
to extend the scope and level of detail
of our models to kind of incorporate
these mesoscale anatomical features into
them um and this is work that um tell
Zang has done where we've done some
manual labeling I will again thank
interns because interns were involved in
manual labeling here um so the game we
play here is we do we image the entire
hemisphere at 120 Micron we project our
inv Vivo estimate of where area 4445 is
Brokers area um I'll explain how I do
that in a little bit um and then we a
block out we do the O we do the light
sheet Imaging um and so we would like to
start analyzing not just the G matter as
a whole but layers within the cortex and
on the XMR if you can appreciate it here
we see the boundary between
infragranular and supergranular cortex
almost everywhere it's a pretty Salient
feature you know there's theories about
how they developed separately and came
together and this and that um but for us
it's a feature we can see across the
whole brain and we can manually annotate
it um and so we've done
let's see how many so this was 15 I
think we're up to about 20 now where we
have hemispheres manually annotated
infragranular supergranular cortex in
brokus area we also have two hemis where
we've done kind of a scattering of
slices elsewhere and this is a huge
amount of data 120 Micron across the
hemisphere um you know at at one
millimeter we get you know something
like a million voxels in the brain so at
120 Micron we would get like a thousand
times that I guess so it's a lot of data
and it's not feasible to manually anate
the whole thing and so we've been trying
to develop techniques and by we I
completely Mean Taylor whose idea this
was um techniques that use manual labels
where they're available so supervised
training but also benefit from the rest
of the data set where there aren't any
labels um right and Taylor estimated
that it would take like 20 years to take
our existing Personnel to label every
slice and every brain and none of us are
that patient um okay I see this the next
slide yes okay so the way this works so
Taylor developed a technique that's
semi-supervised that is it uses the
labels and label regions but it uses the
unlabeled data as well and the way it
works is this thing called uh cross
pseudo supervision which is one of these
deep learning things that I would never
have thought would work and the game he
plays is that instead of training a
single Network you train like a little
uh Sibling Group of networks like three
of them at the same time and you sample
of box from the brain and you say is
that voxel a labeled voxel if it's a
labeled voxel I'll train all my networks
on a label if the networks make a
mistake I'll penalize them but if they
make the same mistake I'll really
penalize them like so it's what he calls
an error diversity term that is he wants
the networks not to become one network
he wants them to learn different things
then if if he samples outside of the
labeled region he has each Network train
the other and so there's no ground truth
out there um
and I would have thought this thing
would converge to nothing very
interesting but in fact that's not true
in fact it works um here's an example of
a whole hemisphere
segmentation here's the quantification
of it um so these are different cortical
areas these are our estimates of what
broadman area we're in um this is ENT
rhal this is V1 and V2 and you don't
have to look at all of these U but the
interesting ones are this so the other
thing I'll add is that this is a multi
resolution unit Cascade so we give the
whole data set at low resolution to the
first unit and then the second unit
looks at uh two-fold upsampling uh and
also gets the whole brain context and
and the next one is another twofold
uping until we get to the original data
resolution and so the last unit has the
benefit of the whole brain context plus
the highest resolution we get to um
anyway so that's shown here in purple um
NN unit it's kind of a popular Baseline
that people use and so you can see that
most of our labels are in 4445 and they
all do pretty well there you know 4445
has its own architecture it's it's five
layer cortex there's no layer FL it's a
granular um and so if you take this
network train there and run it in V1 or
V2 it completely fails because it's an
architecture it's never seen it's atic
architecture that's just different
enough in the training set um but the
cross of supervision keeps this accuracy
pretty high and so we now have tools
that in the x 120 Micron XMR do a very
accurate job at labeling infragranular
and super granular and probably we're
not going to do a lot more not clear but
we we don't see six layer many places at
120 M we see it some places but we see
it everywhere in the light sheet data
and Patrick Hoff and the group in lens
Iran costantini are generating Manual
labelings of all six cortical layers
that we're going to look at but so how
much use is this if we can generate
accurate infragranular supergranular
segmentations on 120 Micron xvo data
when we're not going to get 120 microns
in Vivo anytime soon you know if we
struggle like crazy we can get I don't
know 4 Micron like that's a long scan
it's very sensitive to motion it's very
difficult to get beyond that resolution
in Vivo and even 400 microns is really
pushing it and so what we've been doing
and this is O's work is we've been
looking at how accurately we can predict
these boundaries in the absence of
Imaging
data that is if I can tell you at this
point in the brain the layer 4 boundary
is always 1.3 mm from the gray white
boundary I don't need to see the
contrast I know where the boundary is
and so here's an example I'll go through
the details what this means so the let's
see which is which the ground truth
is yellow so the yellow is the one that
was generated by the manual labeling and
then the green and the red are two
different cortical two two different
more two different models of cortical
folding formation one is called ISO
volume one is called ISO distance and
essentially they're used to to estimate
the orientation of columns and how far
out the cortex uh different bound
boundaries are from each other and they
both fit reasonably well probably the
iso volume if we just do a single fit a
single parameter of the whole brain ISO
volume is probably a little bit better
um but if we do a vertex-wise fit that
is if every point in the brain we fit an
ISO volume and an ISO distance model
that's what's shown here this is an
error map this is the distribution of
Errors they're about the same so vertex
wise you know if we if we use our 17ish
subjects to fit the models at every
point in the brain we can do a pretty
good job but predicting the
infragranular super granular border uh
and whether we use an isog distence or
that's the volume doesn't really matter
very much but more importantly if I fit
a fit a full linear model just based on
Geometry so T here is the thickness of
the cortex K1 and K2 are the principal
curvatures and so here this is a linear
model you know I want to recover these
betas um at every point in the brain we
can do an excellent job at predicting
where the infragranular border is so you
know what is this like the mode is
around a tenth of a millimeter you know
and this so so if we can generate
accurate surface models we can predict
where the boundary is even if we can't
see any contrast that separate super
granular from
ular um we have a question online Bruce
if you don't mind um so the question is
can the can the approach your group
developed for training on synthetic data
for brain mapping be applied to other
organs like the heart and what
challenges might arise in translating
these methods to other
systems uh the answer is yes I mean so
the so the shape stuff is not organ
specific it's completely synthetic um
you know cardiac deformations are a lot
bigger than cross- subject variability
in the brain so I expect there's some
tuning that would have to be done I
think Kiara has applied The Vessel stuff
to non-brain data I think she applied it
to some kidney data I think I'm not sure
so in principle yes in practice we
haven't done a lot of it because we're
so brain Centric okay okay so we have
put this whole thing together at least
on the individual subject basis well
we've we've acquired light sheet data
we've acquired stained data we've
acquired OCT we've acquired Mr we've
registered the whole thing we put it
into the same coordinate system uh and
now I'll show you a fairly gratuitous
fly through just to so that's the Mr
that's 120 Micron Mr that's the 55
Micron Mr From the Block this is the
three Micron ooc and then we zoom into a
nissl state in in motor cortex where we
can see you know every neuron in motor
cortex and then we could start to
quantify this stuff oops done Play It
Again
we can start to quantify this stuff um
this is so the stereology was done by
Patrick Hoff the light sheet was done at
Lens the oct was acquired locally
probably by David buz but possibly by k
w um but we can project this light sheet
data through the OC so here's the light
sheet data through the registered o or
rather the registered light sheet data
to the O and then back out to the Mr we
have cortical surface models of
different layers in the cortex and we
could start to make maps so this heat
map is basically stereology at different
layers on the cortical surface so this
is all the way out the PE surface so
think layer one and then down here to
layer six and so we can count uh I think
this is new n yeah so this is like all
neurons so how many neurons are there in
layer one this bit of the cortex in a
human
brain okay almost at the end any
questions on
that no okay so I'm going to talk about
individual subject stuff
um so there are a series of papers
published in the N late 90s early 2000s
um by um this is actual sler paper but
mostly by um katr and the late great
Carl zillis who was an amazing neur
anatomist who died a few years ago and
they developed this te technique they
called Observer independent 2D histology
so this is a photo micrograph of a
nissle stain every dark spot is a neuron
they they fit the surface the gray white
surface the peel surface they solve the
CL equation that gives them a streamline
connecting the two and then they built
what they called a GLI which is a
greater level index and basically it
says how many neurons would there at
this spot in the brain and they built a
technique that looked at changes in this
GLI so these Peaks are changes in the
GLI um that represent potential
boundaries in the data so where's the V1
V2 border where's the V2 V3 border at
this kind of Point um they published a
series of quite influential papers in
the 90s looking at this in various
cortical areas and they used it to try
and characterize human
variability and there was a set of
papers this these are I guess two of
katrin's papers looking at Robin area 17
18 44 and 45 uh and generally the
conclusion was that the micro structure
is variable in ways we don't have access
to using macro structure that is we
can't use micr structure to predict micr
structure boundaries um and they
quantify this so this is V1 this is a
heat map so red means they have 10
neurologically normal subjects that come
to autopsy they do unbelievable amounts
to work of work to generate this stuff
um red means all 10 subjects agreed that
this spot was V1 you know and yellow is
whatever this is six subjects agreed so
even in V1 which is the most
architectonically stable feature of the
brain it's always in the Cochran sulcus
it has you know one of the few
architectonic features we can see with a
NE neg ey the of jari even in V1 there's
this tiny little dot in the middle where
all 10 subjects agree in this coordinate
system so this tar is a kind
of was a standard coordinate system in
neuroimaging um it's less so now now
anyway even in V1 in this coordinate
system the v1s don't line up like my 10
subjects don't overlap that much and I
go one step up in the cortical hierarchy
and I don't have any red like majority
distribution is like four or five
subjects and then I get out to language
cortex 44 and 45 and this blue means no
two subjects agreed like every spot was
in a different cortical area in a
different subject um so krin was kind
enough to give us that her data uh we do
registration differently in the brain we
don't use image intensities we use
geometry so this is kind of a an outline
of what we do we have surface models of
each subject this is for subjects we map
these surface models onto the sphere so
these red green patterns red this the
central sulcus uh the red are folded in
the green are folded out and then the
game we'll play is to extract summary
statistics across subjects and shift
these red green patterns around on the
surface of the sphere until they line up
so that I can and I get a different a
diff morphic transform with of these I
can go out here and then back out to any
individual subject and it's a coordinate
system that kind of maps it normalizes
out the variability of anatomy we see in
cortical foldings okay so this is fairly
old at this point I don't have a
citation I have a citation I don't have
a citation uh we published this I don't
know 10 years ago or so where we got
krin's data we did the exact same thing
I changed color scales I'm sorry so this
this means 100% is all 10 subjects
agreed and gray means um no two subjects
agreed we did the same study we just
analyzed the data mapped it to to
surfaces registered the surfaces and
counted how often the subjects agree
this is V1 or V2 or whatever and when
you can see is that in V1 cortical
geometry is a perfect predictor for the
architectonic boundary of V1 V2 this
isn't surprising like we know V1 isn't
the Cal uh in V2 it's still quite good
and even if I get out to 44 and 45 you
know there's some variability here
there's this large core of the area
where we're 100% certain in this
architectonic region and so we have some
confidence that we can predict AR
tectonic identity um just from geometry
um we replicated this so this is a
photomicrograph of a nissle stain so
this is the pl surface this is the white
M boundary and control subject this is
an Alzheimer subject in entor rinal
cortex ENT rinal is devastated in early
ad this is an this is like the earliest
clinical clinically diagnosable form of
AD and 60% of these neurons are dead in
ler to an rhal we went looking for an
rhal cortex with XMR this is 100 Micron
X in the mle tempor lobe and you can see
oh sorry I should mention back to this
aninal has this bizarre architecture
these aninal
islands there know cell dense clumps and
then like a 250 Micron cell po area and
another cell Clump um as far as I know
this this architecture doesn't occur
anywhere else in the human brain we went
looking for them with xar here they are
in XR these little bright spots uh and
this let us find the boundaries and say
are they predictable with Mr and the
answer is yes we can predict where
aninal cortex is and further further we
can take this data and map it to
alzheimer's data this was Data Randy
Buckner gave me um and we can predict
where anal cortex is and see if there's
thinning and so this is the thickness of
the cortex controls this is the
thickness in Alzheimer subjects and so
you can already see there's dramatic
reduction in cortical thickness in these
very mild aler subjects and if I take
this Roi and I translate just a
posterior a centimeter posterior this
effect goes away so it's not widespread
thinning across the whole brain it's
actually in this predicted architect
region
we'll skip this okay so we would like to
establish a common coordinate framework
um that does cross optic alignment of
some relevant properties what properties
we would like to do it even if we can't
directly observe them at inference time
um JS I won't talk about and then we
would like to be able to extract summary
statistics you know what's the average
human look like in this in this
coordinate
system so what properties would we like
to align well there are a lot of them we
like to line side architecture and my
architecture and Vaso architecture and
you know the vasculature and
you know molecular properties and
geometry Etc but we don't even know if
this is possible we have no way to get
these things line up with each
other so how can we improve on what
we've already done well we we tried this
years ago Paulina and I with Thomas yo
who was a grad student who's now back in
Singapore and meru who's in um at
Cornell
um Cornel Tech uh and the idea was that
maybe all folds aren't equally
predictive of all areas I mean it's not
it's not a deep idea like we know that
calc is predictive of V1 but can we
build a computational framework that'll
let us extract this information and so
the idea here and this is Andrew Lee's
work is can we train a deep Network that
is given a map of cortical folding
patterns and you tell the network I want
you to align the folding patterns like
this is what the network sees these are
the things that go through the
convolutions but I also want you to
align this other thing and I'm not going
to show you the other thing I'm just
going to tell you how well you did right
so think you know I'm going to use FM as
an example but it could be anything it
could be mapa areas it could be you know
um some proteomic image whatever so you
give it the folding patterns it
generates an alignment you apply that
alignment to some other pair of images
and then you tell the network no your
thing sucked do it again uh and so the
only way it can solve this problem is by
building a predictive model of the thing
it doesn't see from the thing it does
see right so it has to learn to predict
this unseen feature set from the feature
set it
sees
uh yeah maybe I'll skip this one I'll
just add that we also learn an atlas at
the same time so we don't register to an
atlas but we extract an atlas from the
data set of both the Unseen feature set
and the seen feature set over the course
of
learning um and this is an example um so
this is stuff from evina federenko and
Greta who defended like two hours ago so
I hope it went well for her I didn't get
to go to her defense because it was
today uh and so this is human language
fmri and human language fmri Studies
have suffered from the fact that
functional area in the language networks
don't line up across subjects from a
long time for a long time that is I do
an FM study of a bunch of subjects I get
robust activation in everyone I line
them up in some common coordinate system
and I get nothing and so this has made
life difficult here's an example so you
know you usually get these like three
areas in frontal cortex and then we get
this broad swath temporally um this is
an average that we do that we made with
kind of our standard registration tools
you can see that despite these robust
activations I don't see anything there
um but what's interesting is if I look
at every one of these subjects there's
like a little divot here it's actually
not a divot it's a fold out so this is
the precentral cus this is the middle
frontal gyrus and there's this little
Interruption here in like every subject
that has a functional activation when
you do a language task right but we lose
that because it's a small feature it's
variable it doesn't line up and so when
we do geometry based alignment we lose
that feature and it doesn't line up
across subjects and so the underlying
functional activation that was there
doesn't line up but we can learn to line
it up whoops I'm too many um and so this
is kind of our standard registration
this is with this learned Atlas and
learned registration and you can see it
recovers this these kind of three spots
um quite nicely and so this works for FM
but it could work for any unseen feature
set okay and that that's all I tried to
mention people um as I went through a
lot of people contributed to a lot of
this I also wanted to say thank you to
our interns so this was our fall 2024
cohort um from lots of places in the
area this was the spring
20241 this was 2023 and 2021 we did it
in 2020 which was a crazy time as you
might imagine um and we don't have
pictures from that uh and then I also
wanted to thank uh R and regini who are
the ones that run the internship uh
Julie who's copi with me of the r25 that
funds A lot of it and Allison who
basically makes everything happen um as
I think you guys know we have a
partnership with My Brother's Keeper
which is down the street and they're the
ones that really helped us do this uh
and then Sarah Who's involved early on
is still involved and enormous help and
Ted across the street and then I want to
thank Kiku who if you don't know uh was
chair of the pp working group which is a
typically thankless task anyway so thank
you Kiku for doing that I know that it
doesn't help your career in any way so
it was a kind thing to do and that's all
thank you
any other questions now that we've come
to the
end yeah I'm curious to know I'm curious
to know if you've identified any spatial
variations in gene expression that kind
of help your models oh man you guys have
to tell us that uh no so we don't have
that data yet I mean I think Allan is
trying to get that data um but no we
have very you know we've been working on
the kind of glue glue infrastructure for
this stuff um and the glue is just
starting to dry I'm going to take that
metaphor too far um but so no we haven't
applied it I don't think there's much
data on that yet but what would be your
best bet on um this Imaging phenotype
could be linked tightly to the spatial
or any any type of gene expression no no
it's an interesting question I know that
um I remember giving a talk so I wish
Randy Buckner was here um I remember
giving a talk once showing like how we
can parate frontal cortex and rany's
response was I don't think there are any
areas in frontal cortex it's just like a
broad slow gradient like there are no
sharp
boundaries maybe he's right I don't know
maybe's not wrong very often um but
maybe he's wrong like we just don't know
we don't have that data and so you know
it is astonishing to me that here we're
almost in 2025 and there's the stuff we
don't know like we we've segment
broadman areas 4445 is it really a
cortical area does it have different
functional properties you know most that
stuff is from like vascular lesion
studies done in the 1800s or we just
don't know um and so one of the things
that I think is exciting about Bon ban
is is this real push to start to build
the infrastructure needed to answer
these basic questions that have such
implications for you know how we treat
diseases you know how the normal human
brain works um and I wish I had an
answer to that one but I
don't yeah
so you you mentioned this really
interesting work you guys are doing in
that project of like functional Imaging
near the end of life and then kind of
having that functional Imaging guide the
dissection of the samples yep so um I
guess I had two questions about that one
is is there are you guys doing any other
measurements near the end of life like
cognitive measurements or things like
that that could then be correlated to
the functional data that's a good
question my guess is not very much I
mean are very sick people yeah and so
it's not clear they can tolerate the
Imaging know even the Imaging
itself you know we're very parsimonious
with what data we're going to try and
get because they're not going to be able
to tolerate very much so there may be
some of that going on um but I don't
know so that would be a question for
people that you dub and have you have
you guys as a team yet been able to test
the hypothesis that the
Imaging um Imaging guided dissection
gives you sort of like more similar
molecular results than if you hadn't
done than if you had just sort of done
it U
naively definitely not I'm trying to
think how we would even do that um it's
hard because we don't know what the
answer is to like we don't even know
what we're looking for yeah yeah I guess
you could just have a simple metric that
like if you really nailed the
registration then things would be more
similar across people than if you didn't
right unless they're not I mean I know
Katrina MZ always used to tell us that
the variation in
architecture across areas is much less
than the variation in architecture
across people and I really hope that's
not true like if that's true it's big
trouble for us um but maybe it's true I
don't know I mean there's just you know
in neuro Neuro Imaging in general we
always think of cross variability is the
single largest source of variance uh and
that kind of drives the way we do
analysis because of variability um but
anyway the answer is some variants of
no um so no we haven't done it but that
data is going to be amazing if we can
get it you know that will be super
interesting I mean the other question is
how we sample like you know we've had
tons of discussions on how we sample and
that depends on what the underlying
hypothesis is you know what are you
trying to test and there different ones
we would like to test we're not going to
be able to test them all what are some
of the Imaging phenotypes that show the
most variation across people that's not
just predicted by like age or something
like that oh cortical folds I guess
would be the first one folds are hugely
variable for reasons we don't understand
but even things like you know
ventricular volume like you look at a
subject with large ventricles you know
some people without ad have large
ventricles some people with ad have
small ventricles I mean it's one of the
reasons why Radiologists use change as
their measure of choice because then the
kind of Baseline values fall out right
you don't care if the ventricle was
bigger or small in in an absolute sense
you just care that it's getting bigger
or smaller um yeah but you know in fmri
there are people that are good
activators and people that aren't good
activators what does that mean I don't
know but repeatedly I mean Nancy camire
earlier in her career was getting imaged
all the time because she was a great
subject um I don't know maybe she was
just really dedicated and didn't move
but maybe there's something about her
vascular Anatomy that lends itself to
being imaged well I don't
know all right I think we're all set
then thank you so much Bruce for a
wonderful talk and thanks everyone for
coming thank you it was fun