(logo whooshing)
I am Andreea Bobu.
I lead the Collaborative
Learning Autonomy Research Lab
at MIT or CLEAR Lab
and we work on autonomous agents
that can do tasks for,
with, and around people.
This work really applies to any domain
where you have a human
and a robot interacting
and collaborating and trying
to do a task together.
Maybe the human wants the
robot to do a task for them.
So this pertains to personal
robotics, so a robot at home,
assistive robotics, so maybe robots
helping with elderly care or
with people with disabilities.
LLM agents, which we all
use all the time nowadays,
or self-driving cars.
In our lab, one of our research interests
is about making personalized robots
and how to efficiently give
human feedback to the robots.
Using only a single
modality of human feedback,
we have to use a lot of data.
To reduce that burden,
one of our research
is about using multimodal human feedback.
We are trying to improve the
efficiency of robot learning
by doing that.
An autonomous agent is really any system
that can perceive the world,
then make decisions
autonomously about the world
and then act upon those decisions.
How can computing make
people's lives easier?
How can computing amplify
people's abilities?
How can it help humans do
tasks that they don't wanna do
or that they can't do easily?
When I was very small, I really
wanted to be a scientist.
I didn't know what that meant.
My only exposure was "Dexter's Laboratory"
but that's what I wanted to do.
I guess it just made natural sense
that I gravitated towards not
just robotics and autonomy,
but specifically human robot interaction,
where we're thinking about
how do we get robots to help
and assist and do tasks for people
and make their lives easier.
I almost didn't apply to MIT
because I thought I wouldn't get in
and actually I decided December 31st,
so the day before the deadline
or the day of the deadline
to apply, I think it
was the holiday spirit.
I was thinking, "Okay, like
why not just give it a shot?"
And then I got in.
I progressively majored in 6-3.
I knew right off the bat that
I wanna do computer science,
but then I decided what
kind of computer science
a little later on, I started
taking more courses in AI,
machine learning, and
then I started doing a UOP
with Professor Polina
Golland, who's also in CSAIL
doing medical imaging research.
And I really loved it and
decided I wanna keep learning
and I wanna be in grad
school and do more research.
Working with Andreea is great,
we have really good communication
and she's really
supportive to the students.
And for me, I think I have the freedom
to choose the topic that I wanna work on.
It was just really nice.
Coming back to MIT as a PI
started being a walk down
memory lane initially.
All of these people who
used to be my professors
and my mentors and I
used to look up to them,
are now some of them
my colleagues at CSAIL.
So it's really rewarding
and exciting to be in
this full circle moment.
My favorite thing about
MIT is really the people.
It's this intellectual
curiosity, the drive,
the quirkiness, the
camaraderie that everyone
around experiences in
the pursuit of science.
And that's really what
is at the core of MIT
and I think it's why MIT
is, at the end of the day,
the best place to do research.