R and Computing cir a social ethical
responsibilities of computing we're
going have a bunch of talks and um uh
sort of discussions um on topics related
this kicking off with kadim Nori who's a
postto here at MIT in eccon right and um
and going to tell us about whether or
ask us the question of whether
algorithms will make the world more fat
give it up for
[Applause]
awesome thank you I really appreciate
the introduction um so uh just uh so I'm
a future of work postto in the econ
Department um and generally what I do is
I'm a labor Economist uh and you know
specifically I'm interested in the
economics of talent selection and talent
allocation uh in the economy um the
title will algorithms make the world
more fair o sorry about that does anyone
happen toh think they have an answer to
that
question yes no
okay okay uh I think uh yes I think I
heard a yes that's uh that's correct I
guess I'm done here um no um no and and
it depends that's actually pretty much
going to be the answer that I'm going to
come to but we'll get there um the
subtitle uh you know a wide- ranging
discussion I think also has some meaning
here uh My Hope Is that uh as I go
through this talk I'm actually going to
be able to get some questions and
thoughts from you all uh and so there's
going to be prompting um there's going
to be less uh maybe a lecture and more
of a structured uh conversation about uh
some of these Notions of algorithmic
fairness and what they mean in practice
uh okay so uh I you know I start I think
a lot of people are thinking about this
question it's a question that's uh in
the culture RIT large and so it's not
uncommon to see uh headlines like this
you know the rise of AI puts Spotlight
on bias and algorithms um or you know
headlines that let me look something
like this um you know AI machines they
might be
racist um maybe even areas like health
or life insurance there's uh questions
of bias and so for years I've been
seeing headlines like these that suggest
that you know things are bad potentially
you know maybe algorithms are actually
going to make things worse um the only
challenge is that um you know it's
almost equally common to see headlines
that look something like this biased
algorithms are easier to fix than biased
people um or you know five ways AI is
making the world a safer place um you
know uh and you know Fair AI why why
everyone should profit from the AI boom
and so there's at least as much um you
know for every concern there seems to be
somebody that thinks that this is going
to ultimately be a Panacea and so what
are the different ways of thinking about
um algorithmic fairness whether or not
it'll make the world fairer or or better
um in this discussion what I'm hoping to
do is I'm going to walk through two
concrete case studies of algorithm use
that is are closely related to my
research um and that's going to be using
AI in recruiting for Tech workers and
then also uh algorithmic cohort
selection um with an application to
admissions uh and you know through that
I'm hoping to discuss what it means to
make algorithms fair in these contexts
um I'm going to the discussion part is
underlined I've mentioned this uh I'm
going to you know be asking questions
and asking you guys to contribute there
are going to be no wrong answers here as
you've seen there's a wide range of
views on whether or not um algorithms
are are fair and so I really am hoping
this will uh you know spur different
people to give various
ideas I'm also going to introduce four
types of fairness that are discussed in
the AL algorithmic fairness literature
to give us um you know some common
language to maybe talk about these
things intelligently and then uh at the
end I have a bonus where uh I would like
to discuss what might what might what
might make humans distinct from AI in
the context of work um I can pretty much
say right now I think that I'm probably
not going to have time to get to that
bonus but we'll see um okay so the first
case which comes from a topic I'm
researching uh is it's about considering
humans versus generative AI in
recruiting so in order to understand uh
this application you need to know a
little bit about the hiring process for
Tech workers and for Tech workers
specifically software Engineers um and
so the first part of this process it
starts with a recruiter screen um and
there what happens is that generally a
human is looking at a resume and they're
asking is this resume good or is it good
enough is this somebody that I should
give an actual interview to
roughly in the data that I've worked
with roughly 50% of people pass these
kind these kinds of uh screens and then
the next part would be a technical
interview where you actually do a coding
test and um the interviewer
decides can you code well enough to move
move Beyond and for us to consider
hiring you uh and then the final thing
would be uh the actual hiring decision
of the people who make it through these
two screens do we uh make a decision to
hire and
a question that a number of companies
are asking themselves is um should the
recruiters uh be replaced with
generative Ai and by this I mean systems
either built on or similar to chat GPT
clad Gro some of these uh large language
learning um large language models that
have that have been Incorporated
and you know in particular so I'm going
to be focusing this discussion around
this first part where you're doing a
recruiter screen one thing I should say
is that um there are a lot of reasons
that organizations are interested in
using AI in this part of the hiring
process oftentimes um recruiters don't
necessarily have technical experience
but they're looking at resumés and
they're making judgments on who should
get a technical interview and so there's
reasons to think that there are mistakes
made and so you know it's not it's it's
I think there's some justification to
try and use generative AI here it makes
a lot of
sense okay so let's think about if we
were to use AI in this context what the
hypothetical recruiting problem actually
looks like so imagine that you have an
applicant pool and uh you're what you're
ultimately trying to do is Select which
candidates deserve an
interview you can also Imagine uh you
know that AI can observe um in this case
I'm just going to simplify things and
there you know they're they're
individuals that are orange and white
I'm going to assume that those colors uh
are representative of some identity
characteristic so you can think of that
as um a demographic characteristic it
could be it could be gender uh it could
also be
race they also observe resumes in this
case so and that's going to have your
education your work history
Etc and so you know the first discussion
question that I'd like to ask the
audience is what are the various ways
that AI recruiting decisions might be
considered unfair um at this at this
stage um and you know what I originally
was going to do is I was going to have
you guys turn uh to audience members
next to you and have a discussion about
this given the distribution of the
audience not everybody has someone
sitting next to them um but I I would
actually you know love to get answers to
to this question if anyone has thoughts
as the
AI is making decisions about who to
interview um what are ways in which you
might imagine this this decision being
unfair given these
contexts um yeah sure actually that so
this would this would be if you guys can
um form into groups um you know how many
MIT uh P people does it take to be able
to figure out how to form into groups I
don't know but if you guys can hand
handle that problem then I'll give you
guys five minutes to have a discussion
here
well
still
us
some
all right we have one one minute left
Pro br
okay we are we're at time it sounds like
there are some uh pretty uh intense
conversations going
on so I'll give like 10 seconds
no no this is great um the actually
given your enthusiasm um do you guys
want to share a little bit about what
you guys talked about I'm just I'm
curious the various elements of somebody
has a sort of synthesis
then um if the AI says well generally
the orange people have more of the
talent of the white people it's going to
be insensitive to the particular
distribution of talent within the orange
people say than the white people because
maybe you're a white person who's uh got
lots of this kind of talent being looked
for um and so um and then there was a a
sort of push back to that as well what
else can the AI do I mean because all
the characteristics looking at are going
to be characteristics so generally
people um with this characteristic have
talent it's not going to be able to look
at the individual in the um full
specificity so there there was a kind of
push
back that's um that's awesome so you
know in that back and forth there
actually are a couple of ideas um that
are that are common in the fairness
literature so one of them was being sens
itive to the possibility that the AI
could make different decisions across
the orange and white groups that would
be akin to what's called group fairness
and there are different ways of thinking
about group fairness but you know the
tension associated with like say
qualifications or ability across groups
um the tensions the tension there gets
towards uh individual fairness um or
what's what's often times called
individual fairness or is represented by
the similar treatment principle people
who are similar um should get the same
sort of outcomes and so if you know two
people are equally qualified you'd
expect them to get sort of treated um
similarly so so it sounds like you know
some of those ideas were floating around
there um does does any other group uh
want to share maybe additional ideas
that were raised
um yeah in the back
yeah separation orange and white people
and people have um even with two people
have different experiences or the same
experiences people may have have
different types of lived experiences
that where they're bringing an extra
store or their different different um
perspective or they see a particular
bias that's a glaring
flaw that that people are not looking at
and that could be I was telling him an
example like in the the automotive
industry where so many women and
children were been killed by the airbags
and they wondering why are they kill why
are they dying and they b a female
engineer in the first six because you
know most women and children are not as
tall as men and you're suffocating
breaking the rases just suffocating and
why don't you I it sounds something
simple why don't you just adjust it to
the fact of who who actually is in the
car like oh you know we didn't think of
that and it's not it's just an example
of having from different viewpoints and
different live experience that that can
contribute to you know a a
group that that's uh great as so that
actually adds some additional Concepts
that um I'll talk about a little bit um
but that are also uh very uh important
so um there could be a narrow sense in
which you're thinking about hiring
people based on like measures of ability
but that might not take into account the
fact that there are um other dimensions
of ability that actually contribute to
being able to do something better and so
that would be um think generally in the
area of uh of outcome fairness um and so
you know one example that I I think of a
lot in the um in the late 40s um the uh
Coca-Cola uh actually uh pioneered in
marketing they they hired a um uh a
black marketing um manager into their
company and um a at a when a lot of
organizations weren't doing that um and
the reason that they did it was because
they were like hey I mean um uh we're
trying to sell products now COC is not
necessarily great for you so that's a
caveat to this but we're trying to we're
trying to sell products and we we don't
really know that much about black
communities and so maybe this person's
perspective would add something to our
team that would make it easier for us to
you know Market to these groups and so
that was a case where actually uh you
know by I mean I don't know if I've seen
quanitative uh exact analysis of this
but at least by their reports um it was
very helpful that they made this
decision and they were able to actually
sell their product more widely now yeah
I like safety as a as a better example
um just because you know Cocola but um
is is are there any other ideas that uh
you know seem additive to this
discussion things that maybe haven't
really been discussed so
far really one identity characteristic
but there's a lot of other hidden
metadata like be observed by the AI that
can also be used to make things less
fair or more bias right just from uh you
know things associated with where where
you went to school where you work where
you live uh there's a lot of stuff
that's even though it's not explicitly
called out it's going to be embedded in
there and AI will definitely find it and
use it uh in its decision making that
that's that's a great point so yeah I've
I've uh made this a simple example U you
know about One identity characteristic
and that's the focus but of course you
can infer all sorts of different
identity characteristics something as uh
simple as a name could have information
about both say your race and your gender
um and so that's a that's also a great
observation okay so this is is is anyone
else want to want to contribute any
ideas I don't want to cut anyone off
yes divided physical attractiveness or
not physically attractive that neither
Abraham Lincoln nor Jack Maul would have
jobs um okay so um I actually think that
that does raise an important
consideration what kind of
characteristic is this um characteristic
uh you know that separates between
orange and white so you might wonder is
it a protected characteristic so that
would be like race and gender that might
have different implications um
particularly legally um or is it not a
protected characteristic so I think
technically um I don't believe that
attractiveness is a legally protected
characteristic though I could be wrong
about this um and uh so and you know but
still we have these intuitions that um
you know maybe that's not the right way
to be selecting people um but that's a
that's a really that's a it's a good
point um okay so I'm going to now go oh
yes
we're talking about uh AI survices uh
here but the thing uh AI need to follow
someone's instruction of doing uh this
hiding processing so what happen is uh
that particular individual or company
actually is the another bias Source
because it will give certain instruction
how AI should behave how AI should
select right mhm and that another source
of like biases to totally so actually
that um we've covered all of the now
we've covered all the four um different
sorts of fairness I wanted to talk about
so previously we talked about individual
fairness um group group fairness um and
then outcome uh fairness but the last
one is actually uh called procedural
fairness and so um part of the procedure
of deploying the a AI requires somebody
giving some input into what the AI is
doing um or what counts uh as you know
you know um uh as as an outcome that
would you know be good um and so there
are other elements there but I I I I
appreciate adding that as well um so you
know right now I just wanted to make
sure to get all of these Concepts on the
table and and uh see whether or not uh
the four buckets that I'm going to
discuss seems to encapsulate um most of
what we've said so first concept as I've
mentioned individual fairness um and a
lot of what people leverage here is
something called the similar treatment
principle um at the individual uh level
you know if you have two individuals
that are very similar in a number of
characteristics um this could this could
mean like sort of merit-based measures
or measures of performance then uh you
know one way of thinking about fairness
is that those people that are similar
should be treated similarly
um but uh another aspect would be group
fairness and so here there are a variety
of Notions that actually often times
conflict so the first one um that's
often times used in the algorithmic
space is what's called statistical
parity and so what statistical parity
says is that the um judgments made by
the algorithm should be the same on
average uh across the groups so if we
had white and orange and it's uh
interview decision um they should both
get they should both be equally likely
uh to be given an interview um
regardless of their group now now you
know in the first group that talked I
think raised some things that are
concerning about this what if there's
differences in uh capability across the
groups or qualifications this notion
ignores ignores these kinds of concerns
um a more refined notion is something
called equalized odds and so here the
idea is that um if you are qualified for
the position or if you um uh are you
know if you will be deemed as worth
hiring in a technical interview um you
should have the same likelihood of being
given an interview regardless of which
group you're in and so this is slightly
different and it actually takes into
account um you know your underlying uh
qualifications for the position in this
case
um the this it's a related notion is
this idea of counterfactual fairness
which is the prediction that the
algorithm makes or the Judgment it gives
whether or not you get an interview
should not be affected if you were to
just shift the person's identity
characteristic and so that's um also
closely related to this equalized odds
notion and then you know one other thing
that I'll mention is this idea of
intersectional fairness so we were
talking about one characteristic but
there could be many demographic
characteristics and you might care about
not just um you know having fairness
across the two characteristics but
fairness with those two characteristics
interact and so um so it's basically
applying the same Notions but let let's
say you're thinking about race and
gender you're doing it for all the race
and gender categories
um so the third um notion of fairness
outcome fairness um a couple there a lot
of different things that you could put
in this category but often times uh
things like diversity and representation
are included into this so here um you
have some goal of uh representing some
group and that's a kind of outcome uh in
in the organization for example you want
to make sure you're like nationally
representative or something like this um
or you would like to achieve some sort
of diversity there are lots of reasons
that relate to further outcomes why you
might want this like the example of
somebody bringing in lived experience
making you more productive um but then
you know there are other kinds of
Notions that are related to this so um
we want to make decisions that um are
beneficial to the people who we consider
the worst off or the most disadvantaged
so aian notion would also fall into this
uh category um and then finally
procedural fairness uh so here I'm
thinking about things like the actual
algorithm training process um or the
data being used are are we using data
that already has certain kinds of biases
in it uh something like what was raised
just a second ago the person who's
making the decisions about how the
algorithms deployed would also count as
part of uh the process and we might want
to make sure that that's um fair in some
way are there any okay so are there any
other things that um you know are
outside of these four buckets that you
know you guys maybe want to add because
I don't necessarily think this is
comprehensive posed it okay but I would
think that the the PO problem is we
posed a little bit too narrowly okay in
the sense that you're assuming that uh
the applican pool is the same is fixed
right or you're assuming that the number
of people who get chosen from the a
African pool is fixed right you know for
a given job or something and and in fact
though you know these numbers are you
know they're not fixed right because
some disadvantaged people don't apply
don't they won't even try to apply to
something that you know so now they have
they now there no disadvantage applic
because none of them you discourage them
all and they won't apply so I mean there
are these feedback groups I think that
go beyond the confines of the particular
Pro problem that you posed in that uh in
that way yeah just one example suppose
you the goal of this whole process
should also be that uh if if there's
historically disadvantaged groups right
you want the outcome for that
historically disadvantaged group to be
better you know in some sense overall
okay so I mean that's a kind of group
fairness the way you propos the drout
group fairness okay so let's say you
have some job which you're trying to um
uh hire one out of a million people okay
so what I'm saying is that the cut how
sharp the cut is is going to determine
some kind of fairness right because uh
if you're trying to hire one out of a
million people or let's say two out of a
million people you're going to choose
two candidates out of a million people
okay and now you say
I'm choosing one man and one woman okay
so now it's perfectly fair with respect
to
gender right because you chose one man
and one woman okay but the problem is if
you're trying to overall uh improve the
status of women kind of doesn't help I
mean it's great for that one woman who
got chosen but um you know what about
the other 9999 you know uh people so you
know it doesn't have a a a a a
significant outcome for for the grp
fairness so that's what I would say
that's uh I appreciate uh that
conversation actually is a natural
transition to the next point that I want
to make which is um about um whether or
not these kinds of fairness um do they
conflict with each other uh in in
certain contexts and so I think you
actually just posed a great example of
um a case where you might have
statistical parity amongst men and women
um and you know you you hire 50/50 or
you've achieved some sort of diversity
there um but uh you know if it's the
case that you're try you care about
outcome fairness uh in in the sense that
you're trying to improve the status of
women through this decision um it might
not have very much of an effect there
are actually cases where it might have a
negative effect so an example would be
imagine if the uh the woman that gets
selected um is uh through a want of
fairness you make it you you have this
equality across gender but the woman
that gets selected um is uh less
qualified and um let's say that that
makes the company less likely to make
that kind of decision in the future and
so then it actually could potentially
hurt uh women moving forward and that
would be a case where you end up with um
group fairness at the sacrifice of a
version of outcome fairness um the these
are just these are just hypothetical uh
examples but people you know rais them
in the real world in in General I think
that there are lots of uh tensions
between these um uh these different
Notions and it's difficult to have
processes that hit everyone's notion of
each of them and so in general this uh
part where you have overlapping um you
know you you you have an algorithmic
process that is fair in all of these
Notions I'm not saying there actually
are none but in general uh you're often
times making sacrifices and you're not
going to get all of these Notions at the
same time um okay so keeping this in
mind uh actually like to jump back to
the example um that I've I've been
running with which is that of recruiting
and so um what I'm going to do now is
I'm actually going to show you some uh
information and I'm going to try and get
reactions on whether or not uh you know
it changes your thoughts on whether or
not using an algorithm in this case is
fair um and so going back you know you
have the orange group you have the white
group and imagine that you actually
deploy AI to make recruiting decisions
and the first thing um that you see is
that you actually see the differences
and the likelihood of being interviewed
if you're in one of these groups and so
here the white group is being
interviewed uh you know 55% of the time
uh here the orange group is being
interviewed 50% of the time um you know
what does this does this give you uh you
know any information
uh that's useful for assing the fairness
of using the algorithm in this Cas does
anyone have reactions to
this could be something depending on how
large your sample is if it's four is not
going to be meaningful sure uh but it
may be you may also want to look at all
the other all the other fairness the the
three other ones at least to see where
you know how it's behaving sure s does
trade off so yeah I think um uh based on
the definitions that I've given you know
this violates statistical parody but
whether or not that's like you know the
right thing or the wrong thing how does
it relate to other Notions I think more
more information is probably needed um
so you know the next thing that you
could reveal oh one thing I should
mention is I've done four and four here
but I'm actually not you know the groups
could be much larger than this or not
I'm I'm mainly doing that for graphical
representation but um but I don't want
people to over index on the fact that
it's just eight people um okay so now
imagine that you get U additional
information so um what this is is it's a
a resume score what the company has done
is they've taken all of the
characteristics of historical resumés of
people who go through this recruiting
Pro process um and what they what they
do is they predict um whether or not
you're going to actually pass your
interview based on that uh that
information and then they assign um uh
people what this is is the the average
percentile within the different groups
of that score um and so you know the you
know it looks like you hear the white
group um has a significantly better
resume along this Dimension than the
orange group like does this change the
way that we think about the initial
difference in the decisions
the I think the the sort of natural
thing to me when I if I were to see
something like this would be
um maybe it's the case then that there
are actually qualification differences
across the groups and so the fact that
you're seeing um a higher likelihood of
being interviewed from the white group
is in some sense Justified um at least
that's I think a way of looking at it um
the final thing that you you know you
could reveal here is actually the true
pass rate in the technical interview so
remember the um recruiters are making
decisions about who gets interviewed and
then what if you knew the actual ground
truth um likelihood of someone from each
of these groups passing the interview um
you know uh and here it actually the the
the likelihoods look actually mapped on
to uh are very similar exactly the same
as um the likelihood of being
interviewed does that change your uh you
know your view of whether or not the
decisions made by this AI are
fair um among people who've already got
part the first that's a good that's a
good question so I should I should
explain so um this uh this information
is uh it's it's on exact numbers but
it's based on a study that I'm um
actually currently working on and here
uh actually you know what we have access
to is we have access to um interview uh
the interview pass rate for everybody in
the sample and then we um we go and we
get uh AI to make judgments about um who
would they interview um you know based
on the resumés that they're given and so
here you don't have this selection issue
where you only have outcomes for uh
people uh who were selected by a human
to get an interview but there's no
reason that's not a natural like usually
that's not going to be the case but for
this thought experiment you said that's
that's actually the ground truth
information for um Everybody um do you
do you have a thought does that does
that make a difference
and the AI is performing the same way
the human
interviewers that the AI is making the
same judgments as the human interviewers
which doesn't necessarily mean that it's
all Fab it just means
that if it's if this bias is sheded by
the AI ad sure yes and so I should I
should be careful to so the AI is making
decisions about who gets an interview
and then um the interview pass rate
tells you the actual interview that it's
given whether or not humans pass it so
what you're saying is right that the AI
is making decisions that are similar to
the downstream
interviewers um and you know if you
think about that is what the AI is tring
trying to do like they're trying to pass
people who will be passed in this actual
interview yeah I think that you know
maybe it does uh mean that this is um
the AI is like performing well so to
speak
yes SC uh you are basically using AI to
do this job uh what about if it's a
human uh did the like a scolling is
there any uh difference uh there that's
another angle to look at yeah so it is
so you know one thing that one could
point out is like the seeming
discrepancy between the differences in
the rasme score and the differences in
the interview pass rate which is not
quite I'll get i'll get to your exact
point but um what that would suggest is
that you know you're using some sort of
a tool that's telling you how good this
resume is and you're using uh you know a
population to make some sort of
prediction here but in this particular
sample it actually doesn't seem to you
know uh be that effective you would
expect that the white group would do
even better relative to the orange group
in the actual interviews um which that
happens all the time you use historical
data to make a judgment of the quality
of the resumés but you know in a
particular sample that you're looking at
those predictions don't necessarily um
pin out now um the uh so I'm so whether
or not humans uh are scoring the resume
versus whether or not AI is doing it is
something that I'm actually not going to
comment on I I think I think that could
be an important um aspect of this but I
do think that it's important to keep in
mind um that all this information um
this is information that's about using
AI to make judgments uh on these
applications but you can use AI or you
can use humans and so there's actually
another comparison um that might be
important for understanding whether or
not it's fair to adopt AI um how would
humans make these kinds of decisions
and so what I've done here these are
exactly the same um because I'm assuming
that there's the same resume score and
that the actual ground truth hasn't
changed this is exact the exact same
sample that's being judged um but there
are differences between how humans are
making um you know interview decisions
and how the AI is making interview
decisions so I think perhaps the most
notable difference is that um the uh the
magnitude or the the sign of the
difference is actually flipped between
the white and orange groups humans are
actually saying the orange groups should
be interviewed at higher rates um and
you know based on our previous
discussion you know it's kind of it
might be difficult to justify that based
on the ground truth performance or the
resume scores like um it would it would
appear that the white group is sort of
more qualified on both those Dimensions
um and uh I before I move forward I want
to see does anyone have any any thoughts
um on how adding the human information
maybe uh you know complicates things or
changes the way we think about this yeah
there's also might be in this whole
problem an opportunity cost you know
whereas if you decide you know that
maybe the humans are figuring that they
may get some Opportunity by interviewing
more of the orange group and you know
you can't measure opportunity cost it's
you know so so there's kind of a bias in
the statistical judgment that you're
you're going on the information you have
rather than the information you don't
have sure um I I think that there are a
a few ways that the notion of
opportunity cost plays in here so um one
is thinking about uh how costly is it
actually to have humans review these
resumés relative to the AI it takes time
and humans could be doing something else
and so if you use AI you it could be a
cost-saving thing um I think what you
you were referring to is um you know
maybe there's a maybe there's a hiring
initiative where what what you're trying
to do is you're particularly trying to
promote a particular kind of candidate
and so you're more likely to be able to
make an offer to a candidate from one
group or another and so we don't observe
that and so that's the kind of thing the
human might care about um I think those
are those are great uh observations I
think the the last thing that I want to
reveal about this is um yes
question uh the initial grouping of what
you uh do here like in terms of I don't
know initially how do you cataliz into
this two population of Orange versus
white right but if you differentiate
that into another uh angle like looking
at this population divide into a
different group then the data you
generate uh could be uh different too so
that's another thing I would uh look at
how you uh do the division of grouping
uh yeah yeah so I've left the grouping
vague kind of um on on purpose um and
and you'll see why in a second but um
but yes if if you were to group people
differently these numbers would look
different um like let's say this is um a
gender differentiator like the the the
white versus orange that's going to lead
to certain results but you'll say you
then Group by um you know something like
soci economic background or something
like this um then it's going to give you
uh you know different um uh different
results that's a that's a good
observation um the okay the last thing
that I want to reveal on this is that um
uh so imagine that uh now um the white
group is what what I'm going to call an
over represented group so in in my
context um it's over represented um
racial groups in Tech so that would be
uh both um Asian and white uh applicants
um but then the orange group actually
represents um under an underrepresented
group so this would be underrepresented
races particularly Hispanic and black
applicants um does that change um this
picture at all once you know exactly
what characteristic or what kind of
characteristic you're looking at
yes what kind of job are
you what kind of job are they being is
it this is a software engineering job is
what you should think of
yes it seems to me that actually human
selection shows that they are trying to
create more diversity than the AI
selection try to create more inclusion
than the AI
selection yes if if I if I were if I
were to have um uh you know tried to
tried to plant someone to give like what
I was looking for as an answer that's
basically um the kind of intuition flip
that I think U I also had so I think
going to this project I think that
there's um you know a thought uh what if
AI can debias humans um and I think
generally that's seen as a good thing um
that debiasing is a good thing um in
this context uh it would appear that hum
actually do have a bias um and they have
a bias that's in favor of an
underrepresented group um and um in if
you if you know you take these numbers
to uh be real they're not exactly right
but they're qualitatively correct if you
were to make the decision to switch over
to AI selection um it might actually
hurt the underrepresented minority group
but it eliminates bias actually um if if
um you're thinking of bias as uh you
know uh
um you know different judgments relative
to the ground truth of uh you know your
your qualification on the thing that's
being judged and so um to to me I was
like when I you know when I saw this it
was um actually pretty s it was pretty
surprising it made me sort of reth
rethink some of these um ideas um and I
think uh so you know one question I'm
I'm not going to make you guys go into
groups again because actually this part
has taken longer than I anticipated um
but um one question that I I wanted to
raise to the audience is can
discrimination be fair or is it always
unfair by definition um if you see you
know evidence of a bias Can it can you
know can it be fair what sorts of things
might make it fair and so you know the
second question that would go along with
that if no why if yes you know what are
some examples
um
uh I don't know if anyone happens to
have thoughts uh on either of these
questions right
now sure this is your um I wonder if
understand well I wonder what what your
decisions or thought processes around
the extensibility of the fairness
concept versus viewing fairness as one
element in a larger strategic set of
things right because fairness winds
interacting with other what I would have
thought of as other strategic priorities
right
and so that liberates you from having to
use spess to explain certain kinds of
dynamics
that maybe it might be hard to use those
four categories of fairness to explain
or yeah totally so I this is a talk
that's focused on fairness um no no I I
actually think but there's a totally um
you know different thing so when I when
I talk about outcome fairness it's a
closest I get to talking about something
like just you know trying to do a good
job in the
yeah exact exactly and so I think like
productivity concerns concerns or like
you know what you're actually trying to
accomplish is another piece of this I
actually think um uh you can bring it
into a conversation about fairness um by
thinking about things like um overall
societal welfare so one place where this
oftentimes gets raised is in the context
of certain um very uh you know uh
physically demanding jobs that are like
uh that matter for safety for example so
um you know there might be certain parts
of the military where um it's actually
the most fair thing if you think about
protecting a country is to just have the
people that are physically the strongest
or something like this so I do think
that those uh kind of more strategic
concerns can come into a conversation of
fairness um I've excluded them primarily
uh in this discussion but I think that's
a good point um anyways maybe I'll I'll
leave these as questions to ponder as
you guys go about uh your day uh as
opposed to forcing you guys to give me
answers um okay um so I'm actually
pretty close to time so what I'm going
to do is I I I wanted to introduce an
area so so that was an example where um
using AI while it might be helpful in
some ways it's
ambiguous uh whether or not it's making
things more fair um based on the data
that I showed you guys and I want to
introduce a context where maybe it's a
little bit uh less ambiguous uh and a
case where actually maybe AI can help um
you know move us towards a fairer world
and so there um I'm thinking about
cohort selection diversity uh and
algorithms um this is really kind of a
project about admissions uh and I'm
going to I'm going to go through this uh
you know fairly quickly but um
you know and since the Banning of
affirmative action and college
admissions a lot of or a lot of
organizations schools in particular are
interested in figuring out how to
diversify their college classes without
um using
race um in the current climate there's
uh a lot of criticism of demographic uh
divers diversification uh and so
criticisms of um what's called Dei uh
but you know it's still something that I
think is quite popular around different
organizations so this is a concern that
maybe is worth trying to figure out if
algorithms can help uh the last thing
I'll say on this is that the people who
criticize uh demographic diversity of
oftentimes also have their own Notions
of diversity that they're interested in
so this is an example of an organization
that has a Libertarian leaning heterodox
Academy that uh is interested in
Viewpoint diversity or ideological
diversity on campuses which is a kind of
uh diversity and so um it seems like a
lot of different sorts of organizations
whether it's demographic diversity or
other forms of diversity are interested
in figuring out how to um select diverse
uh groups of people um and my thinking
about this started when I was working
with a a prestigious scholarship um
called uh actually I can't tell you guys
the name uh I have an NDA I can't I
can't share that information but I'm
going to refer to them as uh the program
for the sake of this and so they were a
scholarship that um was interested in
finding 15 to 18yearold uh Geniuses like
people who are right tailed Talent
across different C countries to support
uh them going to college uh they also
they give lifetime funding uh and
support if they want to start
organizations they have seed funds that
kind of thing and it's a the selection
is based on a competitive process um
that's based on applicant projects they
tend to be Tech oriented projects um and
I started working with this organization
uh because they were interested in
optimally trading off between diversity
and performance how do they how do they
select people that in a way that you
know accounts for both these elements um
and they also had Fairly clear Notions
of uh performance and diversity so for
performance they have these scores that
they give all the projects and uh that's
what they were thinking of as per as a
cohort's performance just sum all the
project scores of the people in the
cohort they select um forers University
they were interested in selecting a
cohort that was close to you know 50%
female 1 poor 1th first generation and
they they have a lot of different
countries there over 100 countries that
apply to the program and so they wanted
uh one person from each uh applicant
country as well uh and so this was this
was their sort of notion of diversity um
and so they were they were trying to
figure out
um if we were to move in the direction
of meeting our diversity goals um what's
the optimal way to do that how do we do
this in a way that minimizes um you know
losses in terms of uh performance uh and
um you know I ultimately uh you know
attempted to help them solve this
problem um I think the what you know
what I'm what I'm going to do is
actually I'm going to skip over this
this simple example for the sake of
time actually I think I'm G to let's do
this so the simple way of thinking about
what their problem actually is is they
want to select a cohort of some size
from a set of uh you know applications
they care about two characteristics both
performance and diversity um I've talked
performance it's a sum of their project
scores but diversity um what I'm
conceptualizing as a multi-dimensional
pro proximity to the organization's
compositional Target so if they want
50/50 gender um if they uh you know say
um have you know 6040 you can
characterize the distance from their
goal or the proximity to their goal or
if they want um you 20% to be poor let's
say they only have 10% that are poor in
a particular cohort you can you can
characterize that distance and create um
a multi-dimensional proximity uh score
um and then you know the organization
really should just be surveying all the
potential cohorts that they could
construct that gets closest to their
most preferred over these two
characteristics um the and so the way to
think about this kind of a problem is
that um you know there are lots of
different potential cohorts in diversity
performance space um the ones near the
top you know top left those are ones
that are high diversity but low
performance the ones bottom right those
are high performance low diversity um
what you can do is you construct you can
construct what's called a selection
possibilities FR an tier it's the
maximum achievable diversity for every
level of uh cohort performance and what
the organization what they're going to
want to do is they want to select their
favorite cohort on that Frontier and so
the nice thing about being on this
Frontier is that um there are no cohorts
that dominate if you're on the frontier
there aren't existing cohorts that are
both better in diversity and performance
which you certainly want to eliminate um
uh you do not want to select a dominated
cohort um
now the problem that we ran into and
this is where algorithms start to come
in um is that technically uh calculating
the selection possibilities Frontier is
uh a is complex it's a hard problem um
and the reason of the reason for that
actually has to do with this diversity
component um it turns out that each
person's contribution to diversity is
going to depend on the identity of every
other member in the Co in the group and
so there's no such thing is individual
diversity it's a group concept um and so
because of this in order to determine
which is the most diverse cohort or the
one that's closest to their ideal you
actually need to com you need to look at
every possible cohort you'd form and
figure out which one gets closest to
your um desired uh composition and um
the challenge with that is that there
even when you have small sample size
small numbers of applications um you end
up with effectively uh you know very
difficult to count number of
applications so imagine in our context
there are 2,000 applications you're
choosing a cohort of 500 um and it turns
out that this would require uh actually
evaluating comparing uh um you know 5.6
* 10^
486th um number of cohorts in order to
know which one's the closest now um
there are estimates of the total number
of atoms um in the known universe and
this number is about that number raised
to to the sixth um so it's an
intractable problem to say the least um
and so uh you know formally you know for
people that are interested in computer
science or complexity Theory the problem
is um NP hard uh and um which means that
there's no algorithm that can compute
the answer in a reasonable amount of
time or an exact answer um there are
some special cases so if you just have
two groups for example um then uh you
can solve this uh you know quite simply
but in general the problem is complex uh
and so just to I'm I'm now just going to
you know o give an overview of kind of
how algorithms help uh solve this
problem so really there's like a you
know effectively an infinite space of
different cohorts you can look for and
you have to search in order to get to
the frontier what an organization
typically will do in the wild is kind of
uh select the one that's uh seems best
to them but they're leaving a lot of
potentially better cohorts in the table
um
and what would be nice would be able to
estimate uh this Frontier to have some
sort of procedure that can get you
closer to this Frontier so that you
could do substantially better um and so
um what I ultimately do in this project
is I actually generate an algorithm that
attempts to estimate this Frontier um
that's based on what's called uh greedy
optimization um and it uses this
procedure uh you know um over and over
again again to in order to trace out a
frontier
um the just to give uh you know a brief
overview of what you know what is greedy
optimization um what what a greedy
optimization process is is it's you make
a series of iterative iterative
decisions where you try and maximize the
increase in some objective function at
each choice um and you don't you
basically don't care about Global
optimization and so the way that you can
apply it to this problem um is that you
can actually have an objective function
which is the weighted sum of performance
and diversity uh and you start with an
empty cohort and you add people um who
increase the subjective function the
most it's a it's a it's a very sort of
um
uh almost simplistic or naive approach
to trying to solve this problem but it
ends up working fairly well um and then
um once you keep adding people till you
get to the total um cohort number um you
know you finish once you actually you
know you get to end members which is the
number that you want to have you do this
process now waiting diversity and
performance differently so you um first
you initially wait only performance and
then you give a little bit of weight to
to diversity and then you give a little
bit more weight to diversity University
and you do this procedure over and over
again and that gives you different
points um on the frontier one way of
thinking about this um simply is to say
um essentially what this does is it
gives bonus points to people who are in
particular groups that you want to
represent but it adjusts those points as
you get close to the number of uh people
that you actually want to uh represent
in your group and so if you met the
target you no longer get th those
additional bonus points in your cohort
um and so you know what that ultimately
cashes out as is um you know you have uh
this estimate of the the frontier you
know how do you get this you um run this
greedy optimization procedure once you
get a point on the frontier you run it
again again you get another point and
this allows you to trace out the entire
Frontier um and the idea is that now you
can EST you can actually pick a cohort
that's closer um to the you know the
actual uh selection possibilities
Frontier um the you know to sort of
conclude um and and and show why this
actually mattered in an actual
organization what I could do is I can
estimate um this Frontier of diversity
vers performance for the scholarship
that I was looking at and I could
compare the actual cohorts that they had
been selecting and so you can see that
um for the you know first cycle they
selected someone well with within the
estimated Frontier that I that I had um
that I had calculated and so you could
have improved diversity substantially
without reducing performance um or you
could have improved performance without
changing diversity um you see the same
thing in the second cycle that they left
a lot of these gains um on the table and
uh what I ultimately do is I gave them
access to this technology that I had uh
developed with my co-author and in the
third cohort you see different story um
so in the third cohort you see them
select very very close to the frontier
and the reason why I'm you know this
example is one that I'm I'm getting
really excited about for research is
that it's a case where actually there
were improvements on what people would
consider Merit and what people would
consider diversity um you didn't
actually need to sacrifice one of those
dimensions and I think I'm I'll conclude
with this you know I asked or not
algorithms are going to make the world
more fair at the beginning uh I think in
some cases it's uh it's it's hard to see
whether or not they will I think the
context matters a lot but the thing that
I think makes me optimistic is that
there are a number of problems that are
simply intractable for people to be able
to figure out that are fundamentally
fairness problems that the kind of
characteristics algorithms have I think
make them um much better at trying to
solve those problems in cases you know
like like this um humans left to their
own devices uh maybe we're doing
something both less effective and less
Fair um so I'm going to wrap up with
that I know I'm I'm way over time there
were some th questions for you guys but
thanks for having me