hello open course Weare Learners my name
is Michael cubert and I'm the professor
of a classa MIT 21m 383 computational
music theory and Analysis I'm so glad
that you're going to be joining us in
this course and it's just absolutely
great to have people learning about how
computers can help understand music and
especially music theory from throughout
the
world I'm making this recording about a
year after the class is done to welcome
you and to say a few things along the
way throughout the class the first thing
I wanted to let you know is we had some
technical difficulties on the first day
and so you'll see that the lecture sort
of begins a few minutes in and and that
the video quality especially of the
Powerpoints and my live coding isn't up
to the Quality we would like to have so
I'm going to be re-recording a few
things here and there and when you see
me looking like this this is something
that's made just for you on open
courseware I'll come back and talk to
you from time to time for now hope you
enjoy the class