so I'd like to now introduce our first
company sciteex citec AI powered patent
platform solution it provides smart
cities with a full spectrum cyber
security and presenting for sciteex is
CEO and co-founder Andrew sillo Andrew
was CEO and founder of omni Channel cpg
company Atlantic Coast Brands and
co-founded marante systems Andrew is a
lecturer in Innovation and Technology at
mit's operations Research Center welcome
Andrew
well thank you Trisha it's great to be
here um I'm I'm glad to be included
because uh any planning for smart cities
certainly needs to contemplate cyber
security um if we think back to um the T
the sidewalk Toronto program which
failed back in 2018 it didn't fail
because of funding it failed be because
there was a lack of trust uh between the
citizens whether or not the city would
be able to safeguard their data so if we
think about uh the vulnerability and the
challenges face uh Smart City Planning
and just urban planning generally um
there is a the threat surface has
increased exponentially with iot devices
connected partner multiple Network
systems uh utilities uh partners and so
forth has increased the the threat
surface uh exponentially and so uh we
need to ensure that there is a a
coherent and cohesive cyber security
plan uh to safeguard
uh the city's data and uh and the
citizens as well so we've taken a system
engineered approach to cyber security so
we cover everything from the from device
to Cloud connected Partners um and also
uh from a compliance perspective uh
actually oversite as well so real time
everything that we do needs to have
realtime monitoring um to ensure that
there is this no now uh no now uh um
visibility into what's happening across
the Enterprise or across the city
so this includes network security Cloud
Security app security Dev SEC Ops
compliance certainly uh one of our
recommendations is that every every city
should require their connected partners
and their uh departments to comply with
some kind of framework uh and then we
actually provide the facilities through
which you can actually monitor that so
what does this mean so uh we've taken a
data-driven approach to cyber risk uh
and GRC so from one central location
uh we've taken a lot of the mystery or
the confusion out of multiple
applications and multiple vendors to
consolidate a view into one place so you
actually know exactly what's happening
on the network what's on devices through
connected Partners uh which means
continuous uh monitoring of your
connected Partners public facing um uh
assets um and also empowering uh our our
partners with an AI powered um uh
security co-pilot and we call our
co-pilot Leo um Leo's been trained on
six different personas everything from
SE level executive uh threat andt
analyst compliance manager um and ceso
so this is an example of how it works um
you can see the person the personas here
will select ciso in this instance all
the risks then are aggregated here and I
can select one let's say ensure Hardware
MFA is enabled um then Leo will will
return several prompts
uh what would you like me to do write a
synopsis write a poem generate a summary
we'll say write a synopsis Leo goes to
work and then returns a result in
language and with information that's to
that role of ciso right so what is the
mitigation what's the prevention
probability of happening uh technical
references and so forth but then taking
that a step further not just the Lang
not natural language prompt but also
let's say write the remediation code so
this becomes a real Force multiple
so Leo evaluating the environment and
the risk comes back with the specific
bash code here uh bash script rather um
with instructions so that uh the the
Enterprise is much more efficient and
we're solving problems in real
time we've also taken this a step
further because one of the um challenges
of any framework is the lack of real
time monitoring um so one of our uh one
of our inventions is is a um a solution
we call aify aify actually allows for
the real time from a governance
perspective so at the city level you
could actually um query in real time
through a multi-tenant interface the
actual disposition uh for the framework
down to the control level at your your
connected partner so for instance if
you're the uh uh city manager and you
have a vendor um you could run a script
that that then PS back and shows you
exactly where are with maybe a smart
cities framework or uh ISO or uh the
various n Frameworks as
well here's a a a great uh case study um
anonymized to protect the innocent um
but this is a a major uh City watery
Authority the challenge that they had is
uh again you're you're trying to monitor
multiple systems multiple networks uh
across a wide Geographic as well as uh
digital landscape so the solution was
really to take aifi and our platform
approach um to give real-time visibility
um and monitoring down to the uh device
level uh networks uh and so forth so you
can actually know in real time if there
is a risk vulnerability uh or if there's
a deficiency and then take action to
remediate that so um if you want a
future proof uh a smart city if you're
thinking about Smart City technology
which I think everyone is um the public
trust is something that we have to be
very conscious of so we provide full
Spectrum insights um no now visibility
and real-time monitoring um across uh
Enterprises and also through covered
entities which would be connected
partners and so forth so with that um
love to open it up for for any questions
I try to get through this quickly out of
respect for everyone's
time thank you
Andrew now we have a few questions that
we'll dive into so could
you describe a little bit how city
planners can work with citex to
implement the smart City's compliance
framework sure so that's a great
question the first thing we start with
is a risk assessment we take a
risk-based approach right so um I think
everyone uh we've never gone into a risk
assessment where we didn't uncover
deficiencies that weren't known and
that's really because of the uh the
nature by which we solve for cyber today
which is multiple
applications um I think the average
average company has 26 applications so
we start there so we do a a risk
assessment um we can partner with the
the city and do that and then identify
really priority wise where do we start
um I I I will say that we've never not
saved money for a client um by virtue of
the fact that uh it with this cohesive
solution we're able to eliminate maybe
some redundancies that we're paying for
already um so uh they can reach out to
me directly uh we also have a
partnership with MIT cyber defense
Clinic um as well as um some other
universities as well so uh e either
through us directly or through one of
our University Partners excellent
fantastic I think we have time for one
more so here's a question we already
have a cyber security Tech stack and
cyber team can citec complement our
existing stack and if so is there a
little detail you can share around that
100% And I think that's where uh the I
think intelligent use of artificial
intelligence specifically with Leo our
our AI co-pilot um we're going to be see
the we're going to start seeing kind of
uh a generification of of of uh of of AI
coming here and I think that's going to
create additional vulnerabilities so um
sensible Sensible uh deployment of
artificial intelligence is something
that we can help with number two um we
are a force multiplier the the fact that
we have over a 100 Integrations with uh
pre-built Integrations with all of the
name brands that you're familiar with so
we play nicely with others um and our
average implementation is is very short
seamless fantastic well thank you again
Andrew and and thanks to sciteex for
joining us here today thank you Trisha