everybody looking forward to chatting
with you guys all today um and thank you
so much for having me so I'm Daphne I'm
the CEO of here on AI and I really
believe that companies like yours with
all of these resources affect change on
a global scale really every single day
but are the resources that you guys have
being utilized as effectively as they
possibly could well what if I were to
tell you that in the next decade over
75% of accounting professionals plan to
retire and I'm sure many of us probably
rely on accountants anybody here for
strategic growth reporting end of month
yeah me too um and so really what is
going to happen is because there are so
many people who are planning to retire
this is going to leave a very large gap
in business analytics and let me give
you a quick example Steve is a VP at a
Fortune 100 company with over 200 staff
underneath him and he handles about 500
million dollars in business every single
year but Steve still relies on Legacy
software and also Excel um and Steve has
a bunch of people that he has dedicated
to keeping the financials on track but
even still he finds that it can take
anywhere from two months to four months
to prepare the reports that he needs for
uh some important meetings and this all
culminates where um his team gives him a
5 inch thick binder with 150 different
tabs and a one-day meeting where where
the CEO flies down over a hundred
different um senior Executives sit down
together and go line by line through
this to make decisions that take months
to implement does this sound familiar to
anybody I know that when I started my
first company it was really all too
familiar for me I was generating
literally gigabytes of data every single
day to evaluate the health of my
business things that were more or less
pretty simple like cash flow statements
piano all those things but then things
that were more complicated like board
reports scenario analysis and things
like this and it took too much time I
honestly felt a little bit overwhelmed
by the amount of data that we were
collecting and I actually have a PhD in
this stuff and even after we did all
this it still took a lot of time to
actually Implement these
decisions so I did what any sane person
would do and I spent months building my
own system and yes it is okay to laugh
and with this new system not only could
we actually provide a client portal so
our own clients could come in and look
at their data and strategic plans that
we had built for them but now we could
actually use the data that we had to
Spotlight were there any areas for
improvements could we utilize our
resources any better in terms of
potentially maybe we could reduce
dependencies or diversify our income
streams and we could actually do this
now in terms of minutes rather than
months today we call this hereon Ai and
we used Advanced machine learning
algorithms to dive deep into your data
and our co-pilot is one of the most
intuitive real-time analytic tools that
is currently available on the market and
this gives um intuitive and Powerful
analytics that provide instant
understanding of your data so Steve
switched over to our co-pilot he was
able to connect a bunch of his different
applications that he uses as well as any
of his Excel sheets that his team was
using and he was able to get instant
insights and this was relevant in terms
of Revenue inventory accounts receivable
better estimates of his burn and was
able to do this in literal seconds
versus months so we know right now that
81% of Corporations still use Legacy
software and Excel in some sort of
capacity and if you're like me or if
you're like Steve and you want this to
be done instantly rather than in a few
months especially for the critical
information that you guys need to make
these data driven decisions then uh feel
free to use my email send me an email
and I'm happy to kind of talk through
this with you guys so you can optimize
every opportunity for growth and value
creation thanks
everybody D thank you so much um and
again please post your questions in the
Q&A Tab and indicate the startup that
it's for so um two key important things
security and confidentiality how do you
handle that a little more if you could
expand on that yeah super important so
especially because we focus on financial
analytics uh we're we're actually in the
middle of sock 2 type 2 um certification
right now so we are about to have our
certification probably by December of
this year um and already we are about
90% compliant with h sock2
currently great thank you and how
customizable is here on AI for specific
Industries yeah it's a really good
question um so actually the way that we
have built here on AI we actually do a
lot of fine-tuning based on company
specific data so although right now
we're pretty specific for companies that
that have a Reliance on accounting firms
but actually because of the way that the
infrastructure is built based on the
data that you have provided for us our
system will be able to learn from that
data and be specific to the insights
that you're looking for so for example
if this was um manufacturing or
something along those lines based on the
data that we're providing Ed we could be
very specific for manufacturing or for
accounting and just quickly
um uh how is it similar or different
from the Microsoft uh co-pilot um yeah
you must get that all the time I love
that question so it's a great question
and if anybody hasn't read um Microsoft
recently put out a document maybe a
month ago at this point of the Microsoft
llm and how it actually goes through and
analyzes data in its spreadsheet um and
one of the super exciting things is that
we have actually compared our pilot to
their pilot and we're actually faster
and more accurate we're about 16% more
accurate currently than the Microsoft
co-pilot so absolutely makes a lot of
sense to come and hang out with us
before thinking about
Microsoft okay thank you