Yeah, this is going to be co-odderated
by Anna and myself. Anna gave me the
questions. Um, but before we start here,
just uh congratulations to everybody.
Thank you for staying f you know, Friday
afternoon 4:30. That's an impressive uh
turnout. So, we're not going to uh this
panel needs no truly no introduction, I
think. But what we're going to do to
start is we'll start with one question.
We also did not rehearse this, so none
of the panelists have had time to think
about their answers. So you're going to
get it fresh which I think can always be
interesting but I thought uh I'll give
the first question ask all of you to
respond but from your own context right
because you all have different context
and what you have represented here are
you have two from academia with Wendy
and Anna you've got small with you've
got small to large biotech with John or
John's sort of done everything and large
pharma of course with um Fiona so I
think we have a really nice um
cross-section of people who've lived in
this ecosystem so the question is uh
historically um everything fails. 99 out
of a hundred things that are conceived
of in the lab fail before they get to
approval. Are we better? The science is
better today than it's ever been. Are we
better in terms of those odds or those
statistics? So, uh maybe I'll start with
you Wendy and uh
uh anyway,
uh I'm Wendy Chung. I guess the academic
uh one of the academic representatives
um representing children especially with
rare diseases. Um so I I don't know at
large in terms of all of pharma. You
guys probably know the statistics better
than I do. Uh I do think because we're
getting to things that are getting to
the root cause if you will. So not just
symptom relief but getting to the root
cause from a genetic point of view. uh
there are a lot of parameters but if we
can get in at the right time uh which
was said earlier uh I do think we're
showing much better success in terms of
uh efficacy safety and I think we're
going to be going forward I think the
big key to me is getting in at the right
time right time and that getting in at
the right time means it will take less
time or just will have a higher
probability of success uh I think it'll
have a higher probability of success and
uh the right time I'll just be
provocative and say is sometimes even
before the onset of symptoms.
Yeah.
So, yeah, I think we are getting better,
but we still need to get much much
better. Uh, to Wendy's point, addressing
the cause of the disease helps. To
Fiona's point, understanding the
genetics better also helps to design
clinical trials in which you enroll the
right patients and you may get the
outcomes that you're looking for. But
still, even within the genetic diseases,
as Wendy knows, there is a huge
diversity even within one gene that is
mutated. So to understand that
diversity, to be able to address the
symptoms that are specific to that gene
within that diversity is still very
complicated and we still need to
understand how to handle it within a
clinical trial and obviously in the
commercial landscape.
So Anna, actually want to go to Anna
next. Oh, I'm next. From where do you
sit, does it feel like we're getting
better? You're you're driving this whole
thing to try to make it go better. Well,
you know, the the inspiration for, you
know, starting the ladder secures
accelerator was really uh to try to
bring all the uh members of the
ecosystem together. So, we just like
what we're doing today to sort of
exchange ideas in ways that might
actually uh accelerate our path to
therapies. But speaking from our sort of
broad perspective, if you will, um I
will say that uh every major discovery,
you know, that anyone here has been a
part of is founded on fundamental
discoveries that happened in the lab,
right? And so we can't possibly skip
that step in order to accelerate our
path to therapies. I think that's true.
And I think, you know, I'll put a plug
in for sustained funding for fundamental
research is really important if we're
going to continue, especially now. I
feel like we're in a golden era in biio
medicine. We've never had more tools as
been represented by all the talks today.
And so now to not have adequate funding
for those fundamental sort of
mechanistic studies that will enable
therapies would be of course a grave
mistake I think and a lot of it happens
in the not only but it a lot of it
happens in the academic setting. Um but
I think that what from my perspective uh
is something that I would like to see us
do better is especially all of us here.
We're sitting in Kendall Square. we have
all of us around and yet of course we're
all busy in our own sort of domains but
if we could find ways to break some of
these silos and have more communication
uh I think that there are many many more
opportunities to um you know meet each
other where we are and learn from each
other so that maybe we can accelerate
our path to discovery so uh it's my hope
that initiatives like this can help us
get there so we'll come back to that so
John you've seen everything here well I
mean I in terms of probabilities and and
and and so forth I mean I think that um
you know if you integrate human
genetics into an R&D effort and also
have a modality which has true platform
characteristics and I'm partial to what
you know we were able to do with RAI um
you can you can generate outsized
um uh success rates um and you know from
IND to positive phase 3 results at Elnum
we were at
62%. Uh which is a remarkable number
compared to the industry averages which
are under 10. Um and and that that is a
playbook that um can be can be used um
in many other examples. So can you go
back to the early days of SINA because
Al Nylm was many years in development
and those early days and the failures in
the Can can you just talk a little bit
about the failures in the early days and
I asked because to your point once you
got the platform working? Exactly. Yeah.
No, we had to fail a lot for about a
decade um and spend a lot of money to
figure out how to um ultimately get that
modality to be operative. But once you
get there, and it speaks a little bit
to, you know, Anna's comments about the
academic side of it. Um, in our case, we
took took this on uh maybe earlier than
we should have as a translational
effort, but we took it on as a company
um and had to really figure out how to
make drugs out of
sas. Um, you know, probably would it be
best done in a company in hindsight? I
mean there are things that companies do
around um understanding pharmaceutical
properties that I think may be best done
in in a company but uh it took a long
time before it was ready for prime time.
And in that context the translation were
you too quick or too slow to go to the
clinic?
Well, I think we could have we could
have pivoted a little bit faster but not
much. Not much. um the the key
discoveries that that would have enabled
us to make that pivot could have enabled
us to do it um a little bit earlier, but
we first needed to be hit by a 2x4 when
the pharma industry left the field. Um
uh and so that was helpful. Maybe we'll
come back to that serendipity. So Kiana,
you manage more programs than anybody
here. Um I mean if you look at the total
number of drugs getting approved every
year it's not going up and a lot more
money is being spent. So there's
something sort of not there's something
missing really from that point of view.
Uh I think there's several things here.
One is we do have incredible opportunity
because we've got all these incredible
tools thanks to companies like Alm of
sticking with them and getting them the
tools to work. So I think most targets
now are druggable by one of the
modalities that we have. I think Wendy
you're absolutely right. We're much
better at safety. Uh much fewer there's
less attrition through safety because
we're much better at understanding that
and and predicting it. Um but I think we
are trying to do much more difficult
things than when I first started doing
symptomatic treatment. We really are
trying to get to the the heart and the
cause of disease and even really trying
to get you know a a cure if possible but
certainly long-term remission or drugs
that you know can really change your
life so that you can forget about your
disease. this is a high bar and so we
we're it's good we're we're all pushing
ourselves but I think what we need more
of what worries me a bit is that a lot
of these new tools are just going back
to the same old targets that we've sort
of drugged already and sometimes there's
a benefit of coming with a new modality
but I think where there's a real
opportunity for academic uh research and
and institutes like the broad and the
work you do is coming up with those new
completely new targets new approaches
that we haven't uh drugged before.
So, are we technology deficient or
target deficient? I would say target
deficient
others. Yeah, go ahead. No, I I I'm just
nodding voraciously because uh the
frustration that I have is what I call
too rare to care. Um so there are just
so many literally thousands of
conditions that are really not
commercially viable. Uh they're too rare
and they're too hard right now. And so
instead what I see is companies go after
the things that'll be incrementally
better because there's already the
market patients have already been
identified. You know there's something
that is softening in terms of that
whereas we're not really making the
inroads into the tough problems. But
once we make the inroads I am optimistic
that we'll be able to like a step
function step up and bring a bunch of
conditions with us. But but I am worried
that as you said we're going after the
same things over and over again. Yeah.
But it's interesting as you translate
things and understand the genetics
better, it becomes smaller, right?
Because the So if you treat diabetes,
you still don't really understand why
people develop di you have hypothesis.
You may know some genes, but you're not
treating the genetic cause of it. You're
treating the symptoms. As you go smaller
and smaller to the too rare to care, you
understand the biology better, but it
becomes too small. And how do you tackle
that? I'd like to challenge you Fiona
and next year when you publish your
report and you're starting it with the
renal diseases publish how many new
patients did you treat with disorders
that have never had a treatment before
and if that incentivizes you then maybe
you'll be care more caring about rare
um well I was going to take the
discussion in a slightly different
direction in the sense of yes I think
it's targets that we're missing and um
maybe you know As academics, we tend to
research targets in our labs, right? And
we do work to try to understand those
targets. But oftentimes we don't do that
with a view of what is what Fiona needs
or what John or you know, uh, needs in
order to develop a program. Maybe
because we have never been part of that
process, you know, justifiably so. But
I'm curious and this is very
future-looking and I don't know what the
answer will be but I'm interested in you
know many many of our colleagues here um
you know we're thinking about ways in
which we can use uh machine learning and
AI to try to understand um you know uh
paths to targets better and one of the
thoughts that I have is can we imagine
like this is my sort of you know dream
about sort of the R&D engine of the
future which actually combines someone
like me who works in the lab or any one
of or uh colleagues who work in the lab
with a co-pilot who never forgets
anything about they've ever read read in
the literature, right? And can help you
uh do hypothesis uh driven work like we
do, but without really forgetting any of
the facts that you knew from before and
you know papers that you have read
before and that you have seen. Can we
imagine combining those tools and having
a co-pilot that uh can lead us to more
um better testable hypotheses which of
course would have to be adjudicated in
the lab. Um I'm not saying this in a
vacuum. I actually have discussions with
my colleagues at Deep Mind about this
all the time and there is a world in
which this is not really just a a vision
that it's actually something that can
become a reality. But now you can
imagine combining that with what I call
biology at scale which a lot of it we do
here which is testing multiple
hypotheses at scale rather than one by
one like when I was a grad student. So
if you combine biology at scale with a
scientific co-pilot who never forgets
anything you know maybe there's a way in
which we can get to better target ID
faster. That's what I'm dreaming about.
You know I'm not sure if it will be
possible but I would love to be a part
of that journey. So let's dig on that
just a little bit. Um but in the context
of rare okay I mean AI and of course
drug discovery at large is maybe a
bigger topic but the role of AI machine
learning in rare is that going to open
things up in a way that a step function.
Well, I I I think it's I mean I I I I
think we have to sort of make sure we're
out of the hype cycle with with AI and
you know I think it is mostly step
function. Um important super important.
Um I I think we're far away from a day I
I've you know uh Demi had some
interesting comments on 60 minutes and
talked about curing all diseases within
a short period of time. I I love that,
but I I think it'll be a little bit
longer than a short time. Um, and we're
still far away from being able to, you
know, type in a disease of interest into
a computer and have it spit out a small
molecule that you ought to synthesize to
treat that disease. I mean, that's we're
still a little bit away from that um
realistically. And part of the reason is
biology is really complicated. Um and
the model systems that um are used um do
not necessarily do all the experiments
the right way. We have to feed biology
with the right experiments to ultimately
inform models at the end. And to that
point, does that make rare one of sort
of at the lower part of the list as
opposed to larger diseases with more
data that would drive perhaps more
informative AI use?
I yeah I I I think you you just have the
power of genetics that's so powerful
with rare that I think you know informs
a better um set of hypotheses than what
you have in larger complex
diseases. That's my view. I don't know.
I can just add when we're developing
therapies genetic therapies for
neurodedevelopmental disorders. I'm
trying to think if there's a time in the
development process that we went through
that I felt that I needed more
information or AI help and at the moment
I will say no but I don't know what I
don't know so maybe I'm wrong I I'm a
bit more of a fan of AI and I we are
using it really across all of the pieces
of work that we do so I think one thing
from in the context of rare is much
better diagnosis of diseases earlier on
um so people who don't have access to
have you know whole genome
sequencing. I think that there where you
can already start to see AI very good is
di diagnostic of rare diseases. Uh and
so that's one area I I think and then
that goes to also then some of the
biomarkers where AI can help with
imaging for example and and reading
scans and subdividing what we thought
was one disease into five diseases. Uh
so it turns out what we thought was a
common disease actually is made up of
lots of rare diseases. uh AI is very
good at doing that and we've already
seen a number of publications there for
example uh designing molecules uh we're
working with isomorphic uh so that's
another area where we're showing and
also predictive safety and then in trial
design we're using a lot of AI to design
the trials what you can do is look at
all the different parameters of a
protocol of how you recruit people into
a trial and how changing those
parameters will alter the rate of
recruitment and so that hopefully is one
of the ways you and really speed up uh
clinical development. Okay. So let's u
I'm going to go back to the community
here but I want to start with um so
should children's the broad and novartis
all be doing the same thing and the
scientists right I mean noartis at large
is doing things different but at the
research level is the research lab at
children's novartis and the broad are
those
no question we should not be doing the
same things we should we're each good at
different things right but on the other
hand to the points that were made
earlier. It's kind of ridiculous. We're
in not that I mean 20 minutes from each
other, right? But how often do we get
together in terms of actually
brainstorming and figuring out our
synergies and what we could do
collectively together? Unfortunately,
not very often. Um, but we clearly have
different strengths and weaknesses.
Maybe we'll go into them, but they're
people that are close to the patients.
And the people that are close to the
patients ultimately know what are the
critical factors in terms of what are
the unmet needs, what are the pressure
points, how do you find patients,
recruit patients, how do you design a
trial that they'll actually do and be
able to comply with, you know, what's
reasonable in terms of this and at the
end of the day, what matters most to
them in terms of an outcome measure for
the FDA. So, I mean, you need the
clinicians who really know these
conditions extremely well. On the other
hand, I can say and you know this is
somewhat self- serving and maybe an
unabashed advertisement. I mean, excuse
me, Children's and the Broad Clearly
realize that we are complimentary and so
we're strategically partnering uh to be
able to put these pieces together and to
know that some of the technologies, some
of the scalability that's here is going
to get us there faster. And so, uh,
we're, it's clear that we should be
partnering. And then, I mean, we would
love to be able to partner with whether
it's Noardis or quite honestly anyone
else who wants to come to the party
because we just have too much work to be
done. I mean, I'm sitting in the
hospital and I've got 200 kids with rare
genetic diseases that desperately need
treatments. And so, anyone who wants to
come to the party, come on over.
So Diana, yeah, I mean I I think that
all working on the same problems is a
good thing because you actually want
different perspectives and different
approaches to tackle the same problems.
I think we're more likely to get success
when we are thinking about a problem
together and then coming at it from
different directions, bringing our
different types of expertise. Uh and
even doing the same experiment in
different places is actually pretty
useful. I mean it just builds that
credibility and and certainly you know
if you if you've done an experiment and
you see somebody else doing it you
actually feel more confident about the
results. So I I don't think duplicating
is is necessarily a bad thing but uh of
course there are different strengths in
different labs and then how how we can
carry carry on working together. I think
this is one and sharing the expertise uh
where we need it. Especially I think
what we're not good at is sharing the
expertise of when things haven't worked
very well. We tend to share the
successes and celebrate them which is
great but we don't always share the
learnings of the failures very well. So
the same mistakes get made over and over
again and that's what I think is very
wasteful in the work that we're doing.
We don't have time to all be making the
same mistakes this over and over again.
So uh this is next question skirts a
little bit on that and maybe we come
back try to put a bow around the need to
work together probably doesn't require
much of a bow. Um, John, how important
is the business model here for the rare
disease? Uh, I think it's hugely
important. Um, and I I wish it weren't.
Um, but it it really is. And it it um I
mean, for example, I I think, you know,
until we have more commercial
successes with some of these therapeutic
approaches, we could see, you know, many
many um very very promising treatments
and cures. not ever get funded. Um, and
I I I think um
unfortunately um you know that reward
system is super important to um support
the investment that's needed even for
small rare diseases, it's still a
significant investment that's needed.
And if there's no meaningful reward
system, then people will just stop, you
know, investors will just stop putting
money behind it. Um so it it is a um big
concern of mine um because it would be a
tragedy. I mean, you know, many of the
of the modalities, you know, gene
therapy, gene editing, and so forth are
cures and and and you know, will we get
to a point where society says we we
don't can't fund cures anymore um
because um they're too expensive or
whatever the case might be or we we
don't we want to create obstacles around
their adoption and so forth. That would
be a tragedy. That would really be a
tragedy.
I'd like to put a plug in for parents as
well. Lisa, are you still here? Lisa,
Lisa Manister from the Kakna 1A
Foundation. Patients are doing it.
They're not waiting for us anymore. And
we cannot ignore it. And what's
happening now is that once there was no
cure, no no therapy, no option. Now
foundations are fun, patient advocacy
groups are funding research, moving
things closer to the clinic, moving the
bottleneck to the clinical studies, but
still there's no one that will pick them
up and help them commercialize it. So to
John's point, as a society, as a
community, it's our responsibility to
help these therapies get to market
because they work. They will make a
difference in famil family's lives. And
we need a way to to fund these and to
get these to patients.
What did we learn from yesterday's case
and how do we extrapolate from there?
This the KJ case everybody was talked
about earlier and of
one thought on that. Yeah, I mean I'll
just say cautious uh but optimism,
right? I mean it's very early days in
terms of this. Um, you know, it's sort
of I can't tell you my email box has
exploded over the last 24 hours in terms
of every it feels like thousands of
patients I've ever treated all saying is
this going to work for me and when. Uh,
so there's hope uh which is I think
incredibly important for the community.
On the other hands, there is this
measure of realism we need to have so
that people uh don't have unrealistic
expectations. Um it is and and I would
love to have anyone in this room who can
help us think about this because I do
think that just as a if you think about
an editing technology there are enough
editors now to take care of the majority
of mutations at least DNA sequence
mutations. Um the problem in part is
delivery and safety and long-term
knowing about the durability and if we
can get to saturation in terms of the
cells that we're trying to target uh in
in the brain in particular uh that's
hard in terms of being able to know that
we're going to get to enough of them. So
I can think of about I don't know a
couple dozen sort of combinatorial
problems you need to solve that if you
could solve all of those and I know
that's a lot but if you could solve all
of those you can actually think about
you know 10,000 rare genetic diseases
that within the next whatever period of
time are potentially treatable if you
can diagnose them and treat them early
enough. It gets to the point as I think
about that with scalability. How much
does it cost for each of those? Will the
FDA and other regul regulators will get
to a point where you can literally dial
in the sequence for the guides? Uh, and
you're going to have the same
manufacturing technology for delivery
systems and we'll know enough about that
safety to be able to bring the cost of
goods down significantly. I don't know.
But I would love to be able to before I
retire. I've given myself that. I give
that 20 years for any of you who care.
We've got 20 years to be able to get
this done.
Are they learning? So the only thing I
would comment about that it was heroic.
I mean anybody reading that um one two
it was incredible the willingness of the
different parties. So multiple five I
don't know how many different parties
had to step in to make that happen and
happen in a short period of time. There
is no business model for that. Um that's
not scalable what happened uh yesterday
which is why most of these emails will
go um without the hope being fulfilled.
But um it clearly falls in that realm of
if any group what wherever the line is
that it is too small needs a collective
effort. And my impression of government
putting aside our current state but in
general
is I think we need to present ourselves
to the government in a way that says we
have the solution. We're just missing
the funds. They pay one way or another.
It's you know depending on where you are
in the system. But if you could organize
the rare disease world in a way that
said you know there's a super fund for
this kind of thing. I mean those kind of
things can be done but they get created
when pe when they become real. You know
they don't nobody creates a super fun
around an idea. It needs to have a
certain level of tangibility. So I mean
for me the hospitals are actually the
key here. the leading children's
hospitals, I mean in the UK, Great Orman
Street and Boston Children's Hospital,
uh who see these newborn patients and if
you can get the diagnosis quite quickly,
um and have the funds to provide the
technology which if it's like all
optimized so it's an efficient system
that maybe you've actually got in the
hospital. I I don't see this as a farmer
type of commercial opportunity at all,
but I think there could be a lot of
other creative ways centered around
hospitals. I mean, you talked about
surgery as a an equivalent, but it is it
should be a service that a hospital
specialized hospital can provide that is
part of the you comes with whether it's
the insurance or the hospital, but you
know, we pay for other health care
interventions. Uh and this should just
be one of those in my view. Okay. Uh it
saves money in the long run. This is the
thing. I mean, so if you actually do the
economics of how much it would take to
care for many of these children, um it's
worth it. It's a good point. Yeah. The
only thing I want to add to this is, and
again, building on what Wendy also said,
um I mean, this is the place where David
Lu conceived of a lot of these editors,
Christopher, you know, Fun Zang, of
course, here at the Broad. So we feel
like we have a unique role to play in
partnership with with children's for
example and we've actually formalized
this um it's always about the people
Wendy and I got together and um the
teams got together and we found that
there's a lot of opportunity so it's
just the beginning but it speaks a
little bit to what I said earlier in the
day about you know like maybe we can
think about this as a nodal technology
or a platform programmable therapeutics
that are you know you don't reinvent the
wheel every which time for every
mutation but rather you find the
commonalities the nodes and you harness
them to develop these therapies. But of
course, the business model or how one
funds something like this and whether
there's a super fund or philanthropy
that plays a role in this remains to be
explored. But maybe this to bring it
back is in some ways why we have to all
get together and brainstorm about these
things because it's not going to come
from you know not sort of being as part
of a dialogue and bringing all the
stakeholders together for how we're
going to you know eventually achieve
these goals whether it's for more common
rare diseases like the ones that Fiona
is working on or whether it's more of
these sort of like end of a few if you
will to help a few children um who are
waiting. So, so maybe it's 425. Maybe
that's a good place to end on. Um, the
biggest challenge for rare is rare and
you got to deal with the numbers and uh
collectively is often the best way to do
that. So, thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
Okay. Well, this is going to be very
short in terms of closing our day. Thank
you each and every one of you. And I
know there's many of you, probably
hundreds of you online from what I hear.
So, thank you all for being here with us
today. It was a wonderful day of
exchange of ideas. Um, I hope that we
were able to celebrate um some of the uh
recent uh successes of these early seed
programs that the latter seekers
accelerator has been advancing. There's
much much more to do of course uh but
we're hoping to uh grow this initiative,
develop uh relationships with everyone
in the ecosystem. So, to each and every
one of you, thank you and see you next
time. Have a good evening.