good morning everybody good
morning I'm Todd Glickman senior
director of MIT corporate relations and
our industrial liaison program I am
delighted to welcome you to the second
day of our annual R&D conference and in
celebration of the 40th anniversary of
MTL uh it was 51 years ago that I
entered MIT as a freshman and I was
delighted to hear on this video that MIT
helped invent modern meteorology because
I am a recovering meteorologist I
registered in the department of Earth
atmospheric and planetary Sciences
president R course
number 12
right turning the tables a little bit on
him from when he would welcome The
Freshman all those years it's um really
interesting opportunity to talk to you
today about the intersection of what our
industrial liaison program does and some
of the Premier Laboratories here at MIT
but as a very quick introduction you are
sitting in one of the most innovated
places on Earth Kendall Square Cambridge
where MIT industry government all come
together to invent the future in MIT we
have a beautiful view of Boston that's
where our roots are from 1861 we moved
across the river here in
196 the main group of buildings then
spread its wings all across Cambridge
all the way to the the Eastern side of
Kendall Square where our office is
located and now the Locust of all the
life sciences and Pharma companies right
here in the center of Kendall Square
look at the kinds of companies that have
flourished here because they wanted to
be surrounding
MIT MIT does three things obviously we
educate students how many alums do we
have in the
audience excellent we do
entrepreneurship we do Innovation but I
think most importantly we do research
and Discovery and I want to spend a
couple of minutes talking about What
discovery means here at MIT and a tip of
the hat to my colleague Randall Wright
who brings this to the Forefront every
time that he talks to ILP members and
that Discovery is the act of
participating in the ongoing discourse
on campus you hear differences of
opinions you debate their impact on
society and when you as members of
Industry come here to MIT you
participate in those discussions and
that can be critically important for the
future of your organization because when
you become a part of the discourse on
campus you as Executives get to learn
the relevant and breakthrough
discoveries that could be transformative
to your company you learn the emerging
technologies that could transform or
disrupt your company over the future you
get to learn about them before you hear
them at conferences read about them on
websites because you are part of those
discussions as these Technologies are
emerging and here at the MIT industrial
liaison program we provide actively
managed and facilitated access to all of
the resources at MIT all five schools
the College of computing the dozens and
dozens of research centers and
Laboratories from those that are very
small with just a few people to the
biggest ones that have hundreds and
hundreds of
people now as I mentioned ILP brings
access to all of MIT to our corporate
members and often these discussions are
facilitated by us resulting in companies
partnering with Laboratories like MTL
and it allows them to Deep dive into the
critical Technologies while maintaining
their overall MIT experience through the
industrial a and program MTL it's been a
training ground for thousands of
students many of whom have become
leaders in Academia in industry and
Entrepreneurship the lab's Partnerships
with global companies have accelerated
the translation of research into
practical applications ensuring its
impact reaches beyond the lab now in
celebrating its Legacy MTL stands as a
testament to the power of
interdisciplinary collaboration and
Innovation continually shaping the
future of technology and addressing some
of society's most pressing challenges
its contributions over the past four
decades exemplify the profound impact of
academic research and Industry and the
World At Large ILP is especially proud
of its role in working with MTL
leadership over four decades in pursuit
of making a better world it's now my
pleasure to introduce my colleague Miss
hongfan who is going to be talking a
little bit about the program today thank
you and welcome
[Applause]
thank you Tod hello
everyone my name is hfan I'm a program
director at MIT copy relations and MIT
industry Leon
program and uh I want to say thank you
all so much for joining us today either
in person or online for this very
special occasion commemorating together
the 40 years anniversary of exceptional
lab MIT Microsystems technology
Laboratories at MIT and it's truly honor
that we have many Visionary leaders
pioneers and distinguish speakers
joining us throughout the day so I
encourage you to take full advantage of
this great opportunity for a very
interactive
engagement we will use pigeon hole as a
tool for Q&A a sessions today if you
look at the screens on both sides of
room you will see the
instructions it's very simple go to
piging
hold. and enter the passcode for today's
event
rd24 and that's it very
simple all right so without further Ado
let's get the celebration started please
join me in welcoming director of MTL
professor Thomas
[Applause]
paros thank you thank you H for for your
very kind introduction and for all the
partnership that we've enjoyed over the
last year with ILP young for many
decades as we build the this event
together good morning good morning
everyone my name is Thomas palaos and
I'm a professor in electrical
engineering and computer science here at
MIT and
since December 2012
2022 I've had the honor and the
privilege to working with the amazing
community at the Microsystems technology
Laboratories ER MTL as the Director
today is a very special day H for all of
us as we commemorate the 40th
anniversary of the founding of
MTL it is great to have you all here old
and and new friends to celebrate
together the accomplishments impact and
exciting future H for our
lab as you all know semiconductors have
really been key to transform our society
many many times in the last 75 years
they are responsible for the computer
Revolution for the communication
Revolution for the internet for the AI
Revolution that we are going through
right now members of the MTL
Community students faculty staff and
alni have played a critical role in
every one of these
revolutions when when I was studying
microelectronics as an
undergrad I I was pretty depressed I I
used to to Envy the the 60s and the 70s
of of the past Century I I used to to
tell myself that the that time period
was when everything in semiconductors
was discovered when the seminal
textbooks were written and the most
successful companies it
started I no longer think in that way I
was completely wrong the conversion of
new materials with extraordinary new
properties Noel heterogeneous
integration approaches and Technologies
Advanced packaging and the use use of AI
and machine
learning enabled by
microelectronics and used in micro
Electronics is quickly making today the
present time the most exciting time for
semiconductors and Microsystems in
history and the MTL Community is ready
for the amazing future ahead and during
today's celebration we are looking
forward to to sharing with all of you
that passion uh uh and the vision that
we have for for that exciting
future we have a very busy agenda that
combines panel discussions about the
history and the future of of MTL and
Microsystems research with exciting
talks about the new technologies and
materials that will transform the field
in in the years in the years to come all
the way from Energy Research to AI
Quantum and everything everything in
between please remember that this
celebration of the 40 Years of history
of MTL is also a really important call
for action for all of us we need your
help to continue to innovate and to
continue to invent the future of
Microsystems and we will be talking a
lot about how to do that over the next
few few
hours but before we we get the the
program started I I would like to
sincerely thank Charles Sue Elizabeth
green Megan Melvin Jimmy mitcher and PR
kins viw as well as our colleagues of
the MIT industrial Leon program for
really making today's a celebration a a
reality and I'm sure you will all
enjoy and to get things started it is a
a a tremendous honor to be able to
invite president Rafael RI to this stage
to to say a few welcome
remarks Prof Professor RI and president
RI was the 17th president of the
massachus Institute of Technology MIT
from 2012 to
2022 before his presidency Professor R
served as the Director of mit's MTL
where he played a pivotal role in
advancing research on semiconductor
devices and fostering multi
multi-university collaborations in Advan
and environmentally sustainable
semiconductor
manufacturing as MIT president
Professor RI Champion initiatives such
as MIT
Nano The Innovation initiative and mit's
online learning platforms including
edx his extensive academic career
includes groundbreaking contributions to
3D integrated circuits microelectronics
fabrication and low temperature epital
growth of semiconductors or all those
developments are actually at the
Forefront o of today's semiconductor
industry
Professor R's a leadership from his time
at MTL to his transformative H
presidency exemplifies a lifelong
commitment to education Innovation and
Global impact president RI thank
[Applause]
you thank you toas for the kind
introduction
but do not assume Thomas that that
introduction will make me forget or
forgive that you took my lap space in
building 39 when you arrived at
MIP what Gody head it is a tremendous
honor to be here and to celebrate the
40th anniversary of MTL with all of
you I vividly
remember or perhaps Dimitri I Viv
imagined remembering in December
79 almost 45 years ago receiving a phone
call from Demitri
antoniadis I had just gotten to the
Cambridge Boston area to start at MIT on
January 1st and I was looking for a
place to
leave Dimitri called to share the
absolutely terrific news that MIT had
decided to establish what was then
called if I remember correctly an LSI
fabrication facility which later became
MTL I was thrilled and it was obvious to
me Dimitri was thrilled too Dimitri had
been recruited to MIT a year and a half
earlier to reinvigorate mit's efforts in
Silicon technology and came I came after
him sometime afterwards and before MTL
formally open in building
39 mtl's celebrated sense of community
was born in Building
13 Steve Centuria faculty colleague of
ours organized what he called and again
Dimitri I may imagine all this but I
think I remember it with what he called
then the gang of four as he clead
Dimitri and myself started meeting every
week it was the beginning of the micro
lunch which I'm delighted to say
continues to this
day then in
1984 building 39 and MTL open their
doors and some of us with offices in
Building 13 Steve Centuria Hank Smith
Demitri antoniadis Charlie sodini Harry
Lee and myself moved from there to
MTL those were exciting days at MTL and
40 years later
MIT MTL reminds a tremendously exciting
place to teach to learn to discover and
to
invent meld has done a lot of good at
MIT but also nationally and
globally there are many many MTL
graduates many of you here today who
became key leaders and drivers of the
micro and nano technology industry in
the US
and
abroad I could not be prouder of my MIT
beginnings and my growing up at
MTL my colleagues here were and are the
very best and inspired the best out of
me and of every one of us the
collegiality of MTL was unar then and it
continues to be unar
today the MTL graduate students what
many of you were some time ago
created their own wonderful community
that exists to this day from the very
beginning they interacted with each
other ATL not just within the research
groups but beyond their research groups
as
well in fact I just returned from a trip
to
Taiwan there I met at their request with
a group of MTL graduates from different
MTL advisors who are doing a spectacular
job
advancing at the semiconductor stateof
the art in industry and Academia in
Taiwan and it was to me an immense
pleasure to feel at home at MTL home so
far away from
MIT MTL in my very unbiased objective
opinion is a role model of an academic
interdisciplinary research laboratory
and Community should aspire to be and
I'm thrilled I played a small role in
his
creation and thank you toas for inviting
me to speak
today thank
[Applause]
you thank you thank you president Ry for
for everything you have done for for the
MTL community over the last four four
decades
I would like now to to invite to the
podium Professor anantha Chandra kasan
Professor Chandra kasan is the dean of
engineering at MIT as well as mit's
inaugural Chief Innovation and strategy
officer but even more important than
that D Chandra kasan is a proud member
of the MTL Community since joining The
Faculty here in
1994 and he has been a a director of MTL
from 2006 to 2011
[Applause]
vendra good morning
everyone and thank you Professor palasio
for the kind introduction and for
organizing this amazing event it really
is a tremendous pleasure to be here to
join the MTL Community as we celebrate
an incredible milestone
40 Years of groundbreaking contributions
to
microelectronics this includes
fundamental advances in materials
devices circuits Packaging Systems and
software this anniversary is a testament
to the remarkable Community we have
built and the continuous innovation the
Microsystems technology Laboratories has
fostered over the
decades the impact of MTL is profound
and I'm honored to be here today to
celebrate one aspect that makes MTL
unique is the close collaboration with
the semiconductor industry I'd like to
thank the Microsystems industrial group
for their incredible contributions to
shaping supporting and driving the
vision of MTL for the past several
decades this collaboration has ranged
from engaging our researchers closely on
joint projects supporting our
infrastructure access to advanced
process Technologies providing
internships and job opportunities for
our students and post talks
collaborating on road maps and much more
my own research group has proudly been
part of MTL as as Professor palasio
mentioned since I first joined the MIT
faculty more than 30 years ago my office
was initially in building 39 which had
the iconic fabrication facility where
thousands of students were
trained over my tenure at MIT I have
seen firsthand how extraordinary L
strong the community is I greatly
benefited from the deep
collaborations with faculty members and
students given the breath of topics in
MTL my students and I have always found
an expert within the MTL Community who
could provide valuable advice and
help MTL researchers have had a TR
transformative impact in the field of
microelectronics in areas such as low
power Computing and
Communications Health Care energy and
most recently in the field of
AI what I found most exciting is the
systems view all the way from the
process technology and circuit
optimization through the systems and
software MTL is also a continuous source
of distin uish leaders as many of our
faculty have stepped into higher
leadership positions at MIT and
elsewhere this includes Professor Rafael
R who served as mit's president
Professor Martin schmidth who's
president of RPI Professor Evelyn Wang
Who currently serves as the arpa
Director our graduates have been highly
successful as well in Industry whether
as CEOs
or other leadership positions of public
companies as well as creating new
ventures in my role of MTL director I
had the honor to learn from our past MTL
leaders including professors Demitri
antoniadis Professor Rafael R and Martin
schmidth they've always been kind to
provide valuable advice and
mentoring I also want to acknowledge the
TR tremendous role that staff plays in
supporting the MTL Community from
fabrication and compute staff to the
research staff that we have to
administrative staff who support the
operations and the various programs the
contributions of our MTL staff has been
the key to the success of
MTL MTL is also in a terrific position
to impact the future of semiconductors
and Beyond with the expanded interest
through the chips act in the US and
similar efforts
worldwide of course we're excited to see
the continued focus on technology
Innovations for conventional seos based
systems but mtl's impact is well beyond
that innovating in materials devices and
hybrid systems there are many
opportunities to drive and expand key
strategic areas let me pick three
areas first I see the opportunity to
Advan Hardware Technologies for
artificial intelligence and embedding AI
into different
domains this will range from new
materials and devices to efficiently
store and perform the rec required
computations to new Computing
architectures and algorithms
Professor Jesus dilal and Dr OD Oliva
are leading an AI Hardware Consortium
within
MTL second semiconductors plays a
tremendous role in the future of Life
Sciences and health this includes the
early detection and prevention of
diseases continuous monitoring and
therapies yesterday professors palasio
and Professor bahai organized a
wonderful event on the role of
semiconductors and Life
Sciences third there is an enormous
opportunity to shape the future of
climate and
sustainability this includes optimizing
energy sources storage circularity and
energy efficient
conversion I should point out that MTL
is well as aligned internally to the
presidential priority areas including Ai
and generative AI Quantum
manufacturing life sciences and health
climate and sustainability and so on
once again congratulations to the MTL
community on this remarkable 40th year
Milestone I look forward to the exciting
future ahead thank you so much