hi everyone thank you for having me um
my name is Emma Flynn I'm from the
University of Pittsburgh where I work in
Dr David CO's lab so in our lab we
develop computational tools for
structure-based drug Discovery so in
structure-based drug Discovery we want
to use our knowledge of a Target protein
structure to find a ligant that can bind
to this protein for some therapeutic
effect so how do we find this Li so
there's two main categories of
techniques one is virtual screening and
in Virtual screening because you're
screening because you're screening
databases of known commercially
available molecules then whatever you
find is commercially available and ready
for testing but the drawback of this is
that it takes a really long time to do
the screening and that time scales with
the size of the database the other
category is denovo ligan Generation so
recently there have been deep learning
models that have emerged that are
capable of creating new lians for a
given protein pocket in just a matter of
seconds but the field has found some
issues with the validity of these
molecules and the synthesizability and
finding a synthesis pathway if one
exists for this molecule is very timec
consuming so in we're really excited
about pharmacophore search which is a
subcategory of virtual screening that
takes a fraction of the time a pH a
pharmacophore consists of spheres of
interaction that are described by 3D
coordinates and a feature type such as a
hydrogen donor um and then the Spheres
of interaction can be customized to
align with certain features in your
target protein pocket that support ligan
binding so then you can use the phor to
query databases of molecules in order to
find results that match with your phora
and eliminate a large fraction of the
ligans to save a lot of time so
traditionally these pharmacophores are
made by using a reference Lian as you
can see here with our reference
pharmacophore and then domain expertise
is required to basically tweak the
Pharmaca for so you can get a unique set
of Lian results so we wanted to design a
way that we could more easily and faster
generate Pharmaca fores that give us a
set of high quality and unique Lian
results when we query with them so to do
this we created PHA Forge which is a
diffusion model that's capable of
generating a Pharmaca for for a given
protein pocket with a user specified
number of
centers um so with phic for we're able
to generate 30 plus Pharmaca fors in a
couple of minutes the animation here
shows the sampling process for
generating a new Pharmaca for That's
Unique from the reference liant but is
able to come up with lians that will
bind to this pocket as well the main
issue that we faced with this project
was evaluating Pharmaca for Quality so
we can have we can measure the validity
of the Pharmaca for and make sure that
there exists a corresponding structural
feature in the pocket that will match
with our pharmacophore centers but a
pharmacophore is really only as good as
its performance and downstream screening
tasks so we screened with our
pharmacophores and compared these
results to denovo generated lians
specifically pocketo and diff sbdd where
pocketo is an autoaggressive based
method and diff sbdd is also a diffusion
method um so we generated 30 plus
pharmacophores for um the uh due data
set which consists of 102 protein
targets and then we screened the kemell
database with our pharmacophores and
compared these results to the NOA
generated lians for all the duude
targets so our initial results can be
shown in the top half of this violin
plot the lighter color um and this shows
the minimization which is the local
optimal pose for the protein for the LI
in the pocket so from this we can see
that we perform about the same as diff
sbdd while pocket Simo outperforms both
methods so we were still happy with this
result because this means that our
pharmacophores are capable of finding
lians that bind with as that bind with
as high Affinity or high predicted
Affinity as Li generated specifically
for the pocket but one of the things
that we notice when we visualize these
molecules the top performing ones from
all methods is that the generated lians
were often in highly strained poses and
red very tightly into the pocket um so
we calculated the strain energy for all
of these for all these molecules and
found that the generated lians had a
higher strain energy than those from the
phic for query so we REM minimized and
docked and found the results on the
bottom half the dark color of the plot
and we see that with the D strain
molecules in the minimized poses the
phic forge ones stay about the same
which makes sense cuz these are
commercially available already existing
compounds but the generated lians show a
decreased affinity for the pocket
because in order to have the high
Affinity they needed to be in unnatural
poses so this is a promising result that
shows that with Pharmaca Forge we're
able to overcome some of the main
problems facing denovo generation of
ligans and that our pharmacophores are
able to find quality ligans that bind
with high predicted definity to the
pocket if you're interested in learning
more please come see me at my poster
thank you