All
right. Well, welcome to the first math
lecture. Uh the topic today is linear
algebra. And what I expect is that for
most of you the topics will be very
familiar. At least we'll be covering
basic fundamentals of vector algebra.
Then dealing with uh special matrices,
matrices that are used in applications,
igen vectors and igen value uh
decompositions,
singular value decompositions, and then
uh finally uh the peron froinius
theorem. And what's really neat about
quantitative finance is that linear
algebra can really be very useful in
understanding different computations we
want to do. So uh it makes our life
easier. Well, let's just begin with a
discussion of basic linear algebra
concepts. Um I'll use a notation where
often I'll have a bold vector notation
for or bold letter for note noting a
vector. Uh so this bold v is a vector in
m dimensional space and it just consists
of an ordered list of numbers and it we
can think of it as a column vector
typically sometimes we'll think of it as
a row vector but uh special cases of
vectors will be the vector of all zeros
and the vector of all ones. Uh and we
can think of a graphical representation
of
a vector um
where we can think of it as perhaps just
a single point in in this case
two-dimensional space
or with an origin. Here we might think
of the vector representing the directed
line segment from the origin to that
point where this is v1 and this is v2.
Um depending on our application uh both
of these can be useful. Um
and
a basic example for us would be could be
the closing prices on a given day for
all stocks in the S&P 500 index. So we
can think of P boldface being a vector
of 500 values corresponding to the
closing price of stocks that are in the
S&P 500 index.
Importantly uh the prices are positive.
So that's where the R plus comes into
play. And if we consider a portfolio
holding shares of the S&P 500 stocks,
we can represent that with a vector Q.
And the value of such a portfolio at the
end of the day is simply the sum of the
quantities, the shares times the price
per share.
Now um with this
uh and later on we'll see that um sort
of Q
dop the dot product of those two vectors
gives us the value of the portfolio.
Um
what we're going to find useful um is to
actually add to our 500 stocks the value
of a cash holding in the u in the
portfolio. So we can think of p 0 of t
just being a fixed $1
and then q knot tells us how many
dollars we hold. And so um our portfolio
value
uh will
be given by this number. Um and we can
think about rebalancing portfolios,
computing portfolio and loss on a daily
basis.
And
we can characterize rebalancing the
portfolio as shifting from shares held
at the end of day T
um
QJ of T+1 to be held through day T + one
by adjusting the quantity for each stock
by a delta J. And if we constrain the
sum of the change in shares
across the J stocks
and cash and the PJ multiplying by the
PJ of T, we can constrain this sum to be
equal to zero. So this would correspond
to a rebalancing of the portfolio.
um and uh
basically not taking any sort of
distributions from from the account. Now
uh with the net gain
um let's see this terminology PNL
uh it's in a sense a misnomer I think
because it's really pro profit and loss
uh but it's referred to as P&L portfolio
net gain. We can just look at the change
in value from day t to day t + one. And
this will have this simple form for uh
the change in portfolio value. Basically
the shares that are held from the end of
day t to t + one times the change in
price from day t to day t+1.
And uh so this is uh the portfolio uh
net gain. And
here we're talking about portfolio
management maybe on a daily basis where
at the end of the day we make a decision
as to how to rebalance our portfolio and
there's a net gain during that period.
um one could adjust the period of
rebalancing to be intraday on a regular
or irregular basis and you know we'd
have to have extra notation to do that.
Um now
with with uh vector uh concepts
um if we multiply a vector V by a scalar
C then we just multiply through each of
the components of V by that scaler. And
if we add two vectors,
we simply comprise the sum of components
uh element by element. And the
dotproduct between two vectors is simply
the sum of the product of the two. So
this allows us to work with
vector algebra associated with
portfolios.
If we have two portfolios
uh we can consider
um let's see we can think of a uh
a QT and a in this notation a WT
as two different portfolios.
And with each of these portfolios,
we can determine what the profit and
loss is of each portfolio.
So for Q, it's the value at the end of
day minus the value at the beginning of
the day. And similarly for portfolio W.
And it's
useful to include in the notation here
this sort of BOD and EOD to represent
beginning of day, end of day. And what's
um
relevant actually is that um the uh QT
uh
portfolio composition is while it's
indexed uh by T um it's actually uh
determined at the end of day t minus
one.
And so uh
one needs to be careful in doing
computations with portfolio value
measurement that you're always using
portfolios that are defined using only
information up to a given time point. So
if we're going to be rebalancing at the
end of the day uh for investment the
next day um we can't know what will
happen on the next day.
All right. Well with these portfolios
that are just um simple vectors we can
look at their difference. And so if we
look at
dt equal to qt minus wt.
Okay, this defines another portfolio.
We often constrain portfolios to be long
only meaning the Q's and W's are
positive or zero. Um but there's no
reason why we can't allow component uh
weights in uh portfolios to be negative
and in this case it's negative shares
and so one can have a long short
portfolio
that
is given by D and we can calculate the
profit and loss of that D portfolio by
subtracting ing the profit and loss of
the Q and W. Um, now let's see with
uh short selling in markets. Um, let's
see who in the class might offer a
description of what it means to sell
short a stock. So suppose that we have
DT
sub 2 is equal to say minus 200
What would that
mean? Or, you know, can we actually
realize a portfolio where we're short
one of the
stocks by 200 shares?
I'm sure someone Okay. What's your name?
>> Okay. Thank you, Alex.
>> I believe it is someone else's stock.
>> Yes. You basically sell first, buy back
later, and you sell by you don't have
the stock, so you uh borrow it from some
seller. And
uh brokerage accounts that have margin
allow you to engage in this kind of uh
transaction. And so the policy
of the brokerage is is that if you want
to sell short a stock, they need to
locate some shares for you to borrow.
And what's rather neat about that
selling short is that your brokerage
account gets credited with the sale of
those shares. So your brokerage account
will um have a positive cash flow due to
the short selling.
And with such a positive
uh contribution to the uh brokerage
account, you can actually invest long in
more than say 100% of your wealth that's
in the or of your bank account or
brokerage account. So um so that's quite
advantageous and allows for very uh
interesting trading opportunities.
All right. Well, an important special
case of a long short portfolio
is a zerocost portfolio.
And this would be one where the sum of
basically the values of the long and
short positions balance each other
perfectly.
And so we have a portfolio DT in this
case which where the D components are
not all zero but the value the net value
of the portfolio is in fact zero.
And we can
hope for the possibility of an arbitrage
portfolio,
which could be a portfolio that has zero
cost but has a positive
profit and loss
over a period.
And this kind of opportunity
generally uh well it it's doesn't exist
sort of inefficient markets but markets
are never completely efficient and so it
can be feasible to
identify portfolios that may be close to
an arbitrage portfolio.
Um
what in fact happens is that this profit
and loss of a zerocost portfolio will be
random
and depending upon the market model that
applies to the u market we're trading
in. Um it may be that there are
opportunities that uh yield a positive
profit uh all the time in which case we
would say that's an arbitrage
opportunity. What we'll see later today
is the question of under what conditions
is there
no arbitrage in a given market
and uh how do we characterize
prices of assets in a market with no
arbitrage.
And ultimately it turns out that uh
option pricing theory
that that was intro or mentioned last
time of black shores and merin is all
based upon arbitragefree markets and the
implications of that and uh we'll see
that uh in arbitragefree markets there
does not exist any arbitrage portfolios
and what will be neat as to understand
why that's the case. All right. Um
All right. So, we have random uh prices
at the end of day t. Um and so the
profit and loss is going to be random.
uh
I guess it's relevant to note that there
are strategies of of statistical
arbitrage
and those are strategies where we have
sort of portfolio
specifications D star for which this
random profit and loss is a distribution
that tends to generate positive returns
and so there's sort of a statistical
likelihood of making money. Uh but it's
often uh not sort of a pure arbitrage
but what we might call a statistical
arbitrage.
All right. Well, let's uh review just
some other concepts of vectors. We have
the norm of a vector
being the uh
length of a vector. So if we have a
vector V here
and um
the norm of V
is basically the length of this vector.
Um and if we consider what the
dotproduct is between two vectors
uh we have this cosine sort of formula
for what the dotproduct is. It's
actually the length of V times the
length of W times the coine of the angle
between the two. So if we have another
vector
W here
then uh the dotproduct corresponds to
that formula.
And what's interesting about that
formula is that it actually corresponds
to
um the dotproduct sort of corresponds to
the length of the segment along W that
is closest to V.
And so um with this uh dotproduct
notation we actually can talk about
orthogonality between vectors in uh n
dimen or md dimensional space and those
can be very useful. um we'll actually
see this sort of orthogonality applied
when we talk about regression and le
squares regression. So you may be
familiar with some of these topics from
that discussion.
All right. Uh well
with with vectors a really important
topic is whether vectors are linearly
independent
of each other. And so if we have two
vectors V and W
they are linearly independent if
the only linear combination of the two
which gives us the zero vector is
the linear combination with C1= C2
equals zero.
So um
linear independence is uh
essentially the case that um we have a v
and w that aren't uh aligned with each
other in two dimensions um and uh at
least vectors emanating from the origin
having that property. And the utility of
linear independence is that we can
work with a vector space
capital S here. And the definition of a
vector space is that
any vector can be rescaled by an
arbitrary constant C and it's still in
the space. And with any two vectors V
and W in the space, their sum is in the
space.
Um with with a vector space what's very
useful is a basis for
the space which corresponds to linearly
independent vectors V1 to VP
such that the only linear combination
giving the zero vector is the linear
combination where all the coefficients
are equal to zero.
All right. Um
well, let's just uh you know go through
sort of all of matrix algebra pretty
much. Um we can extend from vectors to
matrices
where we have m rows and n columns in a
matrix a a rectangular matrix.
And one very useful representation of a
matrix is as a collection of column
vectors that are stacked one after the
other.
And so um we can denote bold a sub one
through bold a subn as the column
vectors.
And with uh matrix algebra um let's see
well let's see we can multiply a matrix
capital a by a constant and we end up
multiplying each of the components
elements of the table of a values by the
same constant c um with a transpose
operation. A transpose is simply to flip
rows and columns.
And so um if we have a subig j being the
i row, j column element of a then a j i
corresponds to the j row and i column.
Now um if we think of the transpose of
each of the column vectors in A
um that's a row vector
and uh our transpose of the matrix A can
be thought of as stacked row vectors
corresponding to the same uh vectors A1
through A N. Now, one of the reasons for
thinking of a matrix as having a being a
composition of different column vectors
is that when we multiply
a matrix A by
a vector V,
then this corresponds to the linear
combination of the columns of A with
coefficients.
uh corresponding to v1 through vn. So we
have a linear combination of a's columns
and uh this
representation of matrix vector
multiplication turns out to be very very
useful. Um
perhaps less useful is that if we look
at the uh
matrix vector product, it's also a
vector of dotproducts of A's rows with
V. And so being comfortable with
dotproducts is uh potentially useful. uh
but for the moment thinking of linear
combinations of columns of a um is uh is
very useful. So um I guess you know if
we think of the columns of A
corresponding to potentially a basis of
vectors
then AV corresponds to another vector in
uh the space spanned by those columns.
All right. Now when we multiply two
matrices together
um we actually have
a matrix A and a matrix B
each with their respective columns
vectors and we can basically expand the
matrix B into B1 through BP and then do
the matrix vector product for each term.
uh
this is equivalent actually to looking
at element CI which are just these
double sums. When I learned linear
algebra decades ago, um I used these
double sums which were not very
intuitive to interpret.
um although one with the simple algebra
notation can prove everything but things
are much easier to prove u with this
other notation. Now what's important
when we multiply two matrices together
is that the matrices have to be
conformal meaning
we need to be able to multiply a times
the column vectors of b. So the
m byn matrix
um of uh
uh a has to be able to multiply the uh m
byp matrix of uh of b.
So um actually I think there's a
or let's see yeah sorry n there are n
columns in a and n rows in b and so the
result is an m byp matrix.
All right. uh well with um different
matrix operations. You learn in linear
algebra all of these rules, these laws
associated with matrix uh algebra
computations.
Everything is pretty obvious except
maybe when you transpose a product,
you reverse the order of the product of
transposes.
And if you consider
reversing the order of matrix
multiplications,
if one can sort of reverse the order, if
A and B have the same number of rows and
columns, it turns out that uh you the
commutative law for multiplication
doesn't apply to matrices. So you want
to be careful with uh those
distinctions.
All right. So special matrices. Okay,
there's the um when we have a symmetric
matrix um then it's transpose
equals itself.
So the matrix has uh
basically uh
di well let's see the off diagonal
entries are matched one by one
with a j equaling a ji. Um the identity
matrix is a matrix with ones along the
diagonal.
And it can be convenient to represent
this as the matrix of columns
where E subj
is a simple matrix or a simple vector
which is all zeros but then a single one
where this is the J row
and uh different computations
um can be made easy with that sometimes.
Now um there's a notation of using the J
matrix to be the matrix of all ones. Um
and the matrix J turns out to be a
vector one times its transpose. Um
and we have diagonal matrices where
it's the matrix is all zeros except for
the diagonal entries which may or may
not be zero and are given by the list d1
through dn. All right. Okay. Well, now
we can turn to some applications
of
uh that use matrices.
And the first one we want to discuss is
uh stochastic matrices.
So these are matrices um which um we'll
consider uh a stochastic matrix that
square
and the columns of a sum to one.
So,
so we'll have an a with a1 a2 up to a m
or a n.
And um basically the sum of a iig j i i
equaling 1 to m is going to equal to
one.
So this uh
this kind of matrix is associated
uh with marov chains where we think of
there being uh m possible states
and we can think of um so we basically
have m rows and m columns
and we have this notation
AIG or lowerase AI is equal to the
probability that the state the next
state
equals I given the previous state equals
J
um
is given by this AIG. So um so we have
um let's see for each column J we have
if the previous
state at time t was j
then there's a transition to a state at
time t + one
and this
transition these transition
probabilities ities uh in some cases can
be assumed to be stable or stationary
over t.
Um and with a marov chain we can think
of there basically being different
states
um
which are indexed from one
two up to m.
And
we might think of these as
being sort of nodes
in a graph.
And there's a probability of moving from
one node to another
for each time point.
And
um these probabilities of transitions
might be stationary in a stationary
marov chain model. Well, if we have a
vector
pi,
which is going to be uh basically pi of
t equaling pi 1 of t, pi 2 of t down to
pi m of t.
So this uh m vector pi tells us at time
t what's the likelihood of being in any
of the states.
Then um if we want to compute the
probabilities of states at time t minus
t + 1 then it turns out to be simply the
matrix vector product of a * pi of t.
So this uh formula gives us
the model for how the probabilities of
states occurring changes from time t to
t + one.
Now
if we consider
what is the probability vector at time t
+ 2. Well, we have the same matrix
vector model where the stationary
transition probabilities a are
multiplied by the vector of
probabilities at t + one. And we can
substitute in what that
product is, which is a pi. And so we
basically get the square of the
transition probability matrix times the
pi vector at time t.
Now what's interesting to ask with marov
chains is if we start out with
a pi zero vector at time zero
and we have the model that the
likelihood of different states evolves
such that the sort of t- period
transition
uh probabilities uh from
pi 0 to t is given by this formula. Then
does this limit exist or not? And so um
let me just ask
um
that question to the class. Anyone
remember from
stochastic processes perhaps or linear
algebra whether that
has a limit? Yes,
>> if it exists, it's the stationary
distribution.
And so
basically if if pi star is the
stationary distribution is equal to a pi
star.
So that we're at a limiting distribution
where there's no change in probabilities
continuing sort of from t equal to
infinity to infinity + one. Um then this
would be the formula.
Now uh
are there circumstances where such a
stationary distribution doesn't exist?
Yes. Okay. And when is that? I see some
solid nods. Yes.
>> What is periodic? Yeah. So you could
have cycles in the process and
you know a simple case would be two
states that just alternate even odd
being one state or the other as an
example. So we need to have um asyclic
distributions or or the uh transition
pro or the what the mark of chain needs
to be as cyclic. Um and uh so uh and
actually it's all these topics are quite
interesting when you study them. Uh it
turns out that you can prove that a uh
uh a markoff chain is as cyclic if um
all of its components of the A matrix if
every single one is non zero.
So that there's always a possibility of
transitioning from one state to another.
That's a bit too restrictive. But it
turns out that if you consider a
particular power of a
that for some power not necessarily very
big but there's at some point of looking
at powers of a the a to that power is a
matrix of all positive entries. So it's
sort of interesting just how these
mathematical
uh features um can be shown.
Now um
let's see all right so if it does exist
we have a stationary distribution
um and uh that's that's nice. Um let's
see let me just point out that I guess
in the first problem set for the course
that's been posted that's due a week
from Friday. So this is a good healthy
amount of time away I hope for
everybody. Um we're asking you to look
at some simple Markov chains and explore
the stationary distribution of those
cases. And uh um the Markov chain model
is used for modeling whether uh say
trades um at the buy or sell side uh um
or whether trades successive trades in a
stock will be at the buy side or sell
side depending on what the previous
trade was at. All right. Well, let's
move on to another class of matrices
that's of interest. And actually um
actually before doing that I'm going to
jump ahead just in terms of topics but
um this formula for the stationary
distribution
is a formula
that's very specific
to
igen values and IGEN vectors.
And so if you think of the matrix A
having Igen values and IGEN vectors,
what's the igen value and what's the
igen vector in this case?
Does anybody?
Yes. Kai value of one. the vectors would
be all the five stars are satisfied.
>> So, so this so this basically is a case
where one of the igen values is one or
sorry one of the igen values is one and
this is satisfied.
Um we'll see uh later that um
basically the other igen values may be
smaller than one and when you multiply
the a matrix by itself
to many many powers then it's only this
one
vector that doesn't get shrunk to zero
in the limit. So all right well let's
turn to positive matrices. Um positive
matrices arise in economics where we
think of there being say prices of goods
under different sort of states of the
market
um or costs of goods under states of the
market. And those are all uh positive.
And we can think of this arising
um in a single period market model
where we have
uh n assets indexed by i
and um
let's see we have uh two periods or
sorry two a single period with a
beginning and and t0 and t= capital t.
And um if we think of what is the
price of assets at time zero
um we may know what those are at time
zero and then what are the subsequent
prices at the end of the single period
um capital t and um
those prices may or may or may not be uh
known. And so let me just uh give an
example here with two assets.
And um so we're going to think of the
two period model
and we're going to have n equal to two.
And
for um
we're going to consider um basically
a bond
B
which um
takes on values
that will be B 0
um
at t equals z and BT
at time capital T.
And we'll consider the case of a bond
which
basically pays interest at the interest
rate RF.
So this
B 0
price of the bond at time zero grows to
B sub capital T which is basically
growing at a simple interest rate of RF
and
um let's see we can talk about RB
the return of this just being BT minus B
0.
So this is um the absolute return
and we could also um define the percent
return
which would be um looking at
r subb equal to
the absolute return divided by the
initial value. So this would be the
percentage uh return
and uh let's see if we subtract this
here we end up getting that this is um b
rf
* t.
So this turns out to be equal to simply
RFT
as the percent return.
And
let's see
we can also talk about the simple
rate of return
which would be given by um
well let's see actually maybe here I
should write R subb
um and here R subB
instead of R subf because I want to
define R subf to be equal to um
the uh basically one over t the average
rate of return. So it's equal to this *
bt minus b 0 over b 0. And so this is
simply in this uh case um is equal to
that rb. Um and
I guess I'll be using a notation of
characterizing an interest rate as being
a risk-free interest rate. if
this bond is sort of guaranteed to have
that final value. And so um in
quantitative finance we often talk about
risk-free rates and um the risk you know
nothing in the world is risk-free but uh
when governments can print money to pay
off their liabilities then it
essentially is sort of a risk-free rate.
um and we worry less about it uh with
countries with stronger economies. Now
this is um the first um asset. Let's
also consider a stock S which has at
time zero a value of S0
and then at time t
it's going to be random.
And so we have s subt is going to equal
different possible outcomes.
And we'll consider a special case where
it's stu
and std
where
we have an underlying state being an up
or a down market.
So
we have a random outcome for ST.
We're not yet specifying what
probabilities are associated with these
different states. And so there are two
states
at time t.
Omega equal to
well maybe I'll just write u and omega
equal to d for that and so um
in thinking of a single market model
with n assets not just two
we are defining basically two assets
I guess I'm using j for the assets
instead of uh i but um we basically they
have known asset prices at time zero and
potentially random prices at time uh
capital t.
And so we can model this by
associating different states
at or scenarios at time capital T that
are indexed W1 to WM.
and uh we then
can have uh different prices in that. So
so here's the framework for this right
now. Um
and at least the framework with two
assets
and we can also uh characterize
portfolios
of the n= 2 assets.
And we can define a pi vector
being simply equal to a weight in the
bond and a weight in the stock.
units of the stock, units of the bond
given by this vector.
And so
what we can then do is
deal with modeling the outcomes
of
this portfolio.
Um
if we uh
consider sort of v 0 the value of the
portfolio at time z this would be just
pi b * b 0 plus pi s * s0
and at time capital t
Then our portfolio
would have values pi bt
plus pi s
time s tu
for the up case and pi bt
plus pi s * std
when w is equal to d when the state is
down. So
this
value of the portfolio
will be random depending upon the
likelihood of these up and down states.
Well, um,
with this setup,
it's useful at this point to introduce
you to some cont concepts
which is contingent claims
and
replicating portfolios. those
portfolios.
And so um suppose that we have a um
a contingent claim C
which has a value C 0
um is the value at T equal to zero
and CT
will be the value of this contingent
claim
depending upon on whether we have an up
or a down. Actually, I'll reverse it. A
down or an up market.
The uh
what we end up doing in uh these market
models is being able to
model the prices of contingent claims
when we can replicate the contingent
claim
with a portfolio of the underlying
assets.
And so um
you know so we can ask does there exist
a portfolio
of B and S
such that
pi B
um
V + pi S
uh
T U
um equals
C uh CT
D and pi B V plus pi ST
uh I've got these notations wrong
equal CTU.
So
if this were the case
then
if so then uh we could have c 0 equaling
pi b
0 plus pi s0.
and we would replicate this contingent
claim payoff at time capital T.
Now, mathematically,
can we solve for
a portfolio
coefficients that satisfy this
contingent claim?
Any
thoughts?
Well, let's see. If we look at CT
versus CT U,
and here's the origin.
Um,
if we had a portfolio that was just
um the uh the bond, we might have BT T
here and BT here.
And here's the point corresponding to
BTBT.
And here's the vector corresponding to
the portfolio. That's just the bond.
And if we look at the
stock,
the portfolio, that's just a the stock.
Um, we might have STD here.
And then way up here, maybe S TU, the
value of the stock when the market is
up.
And so
this would be our ST vector in the
two-dimensional space corresponding to
down market state versus up market
state.
Now given this
figure um
if we think of just
an arbitrary point in this space of
contingent claims,
can we construct a portfolio that
matches that? Yes.
>> Can you explain what
>> Yes. Um Okay. The contingent claim
is a payoff
that is contingent upon
the state of the market at that time.
And it's either a down market or an up
market
over the one period.
And the payoff if it's an up market is
CTU. And the payoff if it's a down
market is CTD.
And in this space of contingent claims,
we can draw vectors corresponding to the
stock and the bond
as these vectors.
And so what's curious to think about is
suppose we have a contingent claim
that
well let's see suppose we consider a
call option
uh contingent claim
so C
well let's see okay so so let's see the
uh there would be a strike
price
of uh
let's see
a strike price of K
to uh
to buy the stock
at time t.
And in order for this to be of interest,
we might have K
being smaller than STU and greater than
ST
D. So we have a call option with strike
price K to buy the stock and the
contingent claim of the call
would be
zero if uh we have
the down market and it would be STU
minus K if it's the up market.
So we could consider zero in the down
market and
um basically maybe this would be CT
minus K here.
So this vector here would correspond to
the payoff of this call option.
So under what circumstances can we
take a linear combination of these two
vectors and get this vector?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. I mean basically we can solve for
this here
by substituting in for this
zero and p minus k and then just solve
it to get our two equations and two
unknowns. So if this system of equations
two equations and two unknowns has a
solution then we can solve it.
And what is interesting um is to uh
consider sort of what are the space of
all possible contingent claims. And let
me uh let's see just turn to this uh
note.
This is on canvas.
But this note that's been posted in
canvas talks about a one period economy
with two assets in section one. That's
what I've just outlined on the
chalkboard here. One can generalize that
to a single period model with
more than two assets. That's chapter
section two. And then one can generalize
to uh not generalize but one can
consider visualizing the assets and
portfolios in section three here.
And so
what I
do in the last section here is looking
at the vector of payoffs of the bond and
the stock colored differently. Um, and
so this is a bond that may pay off the
same amount in the down versus the up
market. And the stock pays off more in
the up market than the down.
And then one can consider collections of
portfolios
that sort of weight the bond and the
stock
so that the positive weights sum to one.
And so these vectors correspond to the
payoff vectors of those long portfolios.
Um and if we consider
well let's see looking at those long
portfolios
instead of representing vectors as
pointed segments from the origin one
could just represent them as points in
the space
and that representation is helpful when
we want to consider a variety of other
uh portfolios in the mix. And so here's
a graph showing
the uh
value
of the payoff. If we consider portfolios
that can invest
um up to 100%
in each
of the bond or the stock or both. And so
um
if we invest 100% in both we basically
get the payoffs that are really high and
um if we don't invest much uh close to
zero in both then we get the zero
vector. Um but this uh this graph sort
of shows the contingent claims that are
mapped
or equivalent by replicating portfolios
of these types.
And so if we then allow for shorting,
this sort of extends the contingent
claims to allow for negative payoffs.
um which uh
are graphed here basically over the
payoff in the down market versus the up.
And what's of interest here, although
it's not quite easy to see, but is um
let's see, there are portfolios where
the initial value of the portfolio
um is zero.
And so that would correspond to a long
short portfolio that um is implemented
with zero cost.
So um and then um let's see. Okay, so
this is sort of the payoff vector at t
um and looking at the value where we uh
sort of white out those portfolios that
have zero cost. Um now what's useful
here to see is that um with these kinds
of portfolios we can
replicate different contingent claims
which correspond to different points in
this space.
If we were able to invest
sort of more than 100%
of our portfolio
long or short, then we could actually
realize
any point in this space in some cases.
And so any contingent claim could be
solved for, you know, with this
equation here.
And that's rather neat, but it also is
reasonable to consider if we make
certain assumptions on the market such
as as you buy more of an asset, you
don't change the price of the asset.
There's basically a fixed price is
suitable regardless of how much. And
there's no constraint on shortselling uh
the asset that you can do that with uh
liberty. So so there are um these kinds
of properties that arise. Now um
with the case of extending from the bond
and the single stock to
m
sorry little n assets then everything
generalizes and we end up having a
positive price matrix
um at time t corresponding to different
payoffs of the individual assets at time
capital t for different states omega 1
through omega m.
And uh
with this kind of setup
um
one can
represent sort of the initial value
of
a portfolio
Q
being the sum of the Q weights times the
initial prices in the A0 vector and then
the payoff of the portfol folio at time
capital T
is given by the same weights QJ times
the time capital T prices but we have
different prices depending upon what
state
uh occurs and so um in this case we have
um basically our matrix A * Q giving us
the vector of state dependent
values at time capital t.
And so with this model
um we can
contemplate there being a an arbitrage
portfolio
where the initial value is not positive.
I guess one could constrain this to be
zero, but it's easier to just say less
than or equal to zero.
If this initial if we have a negative
cost that means we get paid to
implement this portfolio
and it will be an arbitrage portfolio if
the likelihood of a negative
payoff is zero
and there's some likelihood of a
positive payoff.
So this port such a portfolio would be
risk-free in terms of downside risk. We
never lose money. We either make money
all the time or uh in at least one of
the states. So this is an arbitrage
portfolio.
Now
with this model there can be um
conditions that ensure that there's
there is no arbitrage in the market and
um
so so that's one issue to think about
what conditions would ensure no
arbitrage
And another condition that's of interest
is called market completeness which is
are there portfolios
that can realize any payoff vector.
So in looking at the contingent claims
payoff,
can we sort of span this space fully
with portfolios of the underlying assets
in the in the market? And so if we can
uh represent any contingent payoff as a
portfolio then we say that the market is
complete.
And it turns out that
the conditions of
no arbitrage
are a and market completeness are
related to whether a pricing measure
exists
on scenarios.
And so
think about Qstar being a probability
distribution
over the underlying states. Omega 1
through Omega M.
And um
it turns out that
if the initial
price
of the J asset
is sort of the discounted expected
terminal price of that J asset across
the different states
then this is QST star is called a
pricing measure. measure. So, our
initial prices equal a discount factor
times the expected terminal uh
time t values.
Um
if such a pricing measure exists then um
there's no arbitrage
and um let's see. Okay, so it's no
arbitrage if all of the QJ stars are
positive. So if this pricing measure
gives positive weight to each of the
underlying states, then there's no
arbitrage
and we say that the market is complete
with no arbitrage if this pricing
measure is unique.
So it's uh it's an interesting set of uh
properties that actually are quite um
well useful to know about and these
models actually underly
uh uh option pricing theory and
arbitrage uh relationships in
quantitative finance.
Um
so um and in this single period model uh
note that we have distributed there's
this reference
of this book by Albanese and Campoleetti
uh where they go through proofs of these
and they can get a bit technical but but
the basic ideas I think are relatively
um accessible.
Now let's see
moving on um to other applications of uh
matrices um we can
consider systems of linear equations
and their solution where we basically
have
m equations
in n unknowns.
And so um the uh with these m equations
um we have ax= b a b vector and um to
solve such a system of equations. Well,
one case where we can solve these is
where our
number of unknowns and number of
equations are the same.
And our coefficients matrix A in the
system of equations has full rank. So a
being square and a full rank
has a determinant that's non zero
and it's inverse
matrix exists. And so we can actually
just take our system of equations and
multiply both sides by the inverse of a
and get our answer. um when the number
of equations
is smaller than the number of unknowns
then we have an undetermined system of
equations. When m is greater than n is
overdetermined and so forth. So these
are different cases that you likely are
familiar with from your study of linear
algebra. Um
all right uh the uh next topic in our
remaining few minutes is uh let's see
igen values and igen vectors.
Um when we have square matrices A,
uh we can consider the existence of an
igen value lambda and a igen vector V
such that the matrix A * V is equal to
just the scalar lambda* V. So the matrix
vector product just rescales V by the
factor lambda.
And one can solve for igen values and
igen vectors by just reexpressing
the igen value igen vector relationship
as this system of equations.
And so this system of equations
will um
correspond to
uh
let's see this system of equations will
uh let's see can be solved
um by saying that the determinant of a
minus lambda i is equal to zero. And so
um if lambda equals one of the roots of
this polomial
then um that lambda will be a uh an igen
value and one can then for that fixed
igen value uh solve for the igen vector
v that satisfies that
Um now uh
there are properties with igen values
and igen vectors that are very useful.
Um you know one of which is that um the
uh
maximum
value magnitude corresponds to the
maximum length of av for vectors v that
are of length one.
Um
and
when we have uh a matrix A that has
independent igen values or igen vectors
then uh in this special case we can
consider defining the matrix S to be the
matrix whose columns are the different
igen vectors.
And if you look at this
equation here, if we multiply
the original matrix A by this S matrix,
then each column of the product is the
corresponding
igen value times the corresponding igen
vector. This
this equation here is very
straightforward from the notation above.
And if we consider the inverse of this S
matrix
that exists if the igen vectors are
linearly independent,
then we can write A to be S lambda S
inverse.
And this representation of the matrix A
also gives us the way of diagonalizing
A by pre and post multiplying by S
inverse and S respectively.
And so with powers of a diagonalizable
matrix A, they have a very nice form.
We basically got cancellation of s and s
inverse in the products of a times
itself. And so powers of a simply are
the same ve matrix s times lambda the
diagonal matrix of igen values to the k
power time s inverse. And so these are
very uh useful in defining uh state
equations and common filters.
So um all right. So let me just uh I
guess I'll finish there. Um there's um
some interesting key theorems in the
remainder of these notes. I think
they're pretty readable. Um and I'll
maybe point out these during our next
lecture. Um but um there we are also um
let's see I posted a uh an R studio
program that computes
uh portfolios
of S&P 500 stocks and looks at the
changing value over time. And so I hope
people can sort of explore those
programs and try to use those in the R
Studio cloud.