Okay. Uh so hi everyone. I'm Pablo. I'm
uh teaching Lar's lecture this week. I
hope we are all here to learn about
projection theory. And the plan for this
week is to talk about Bugans projection
theorem uh which is an extremely
important theorem with applications uh
in many areas of mathematics including
some pretty striking recent ones and
okay I think Larry has told you at least
a bit about it and well uh we won't be
able to do a full proof because it would
take way too long but what I'm going to
do is explain um okay so you've seen the
analog of this theorem in the final
field setting and I'm going to state it
uh to so as our starting point and then
the plan is to go through the steps in
the strategy in the final field setting
and see what goes wrong and what are the
ideas that one uses to overcome what
goes wrong. Okay. So recall uh how this
theorem looks like in the finite field
setting and by finite field I mean prime
prime finite field prime order because
otherwise it's not true.
Okay. And the statement was hopefully
something like this. um given
t between 0 and two and s between 0 and
one t I want it to be neither zero nor
two because there wouldn't be anything
to say s has to be positive could be one
uh there exists
some epsilon that depends on these two
parameters
and is positive
with the following properties. If X
is in FP squared
and has size P to the S. So sort of S
dimension an S S dimensional set in some
sense. And D is a set of directions.
Let's say a subset of FP and it has size
P to the T. So sort of dimension T.
uh then
so I use the notation
pi theta of x uh to be the projection
and we can write the projection in this
way I guess just x1 plus theta x2
so from fp² to fp
then um
we can find uh sorry I missed messed up
the parameters already So the size of x
is between p to the zero and p^2 and t
is between zero and two. So this should
be t this should be s. Okay. Uh then
there is a large pro large between
quotes projection. Uh then the maximum
over theta in d of the size of the
projection of x is at least
p to the t / 2 plus epsilon. So we gain
an epsilon over t / two and t p to the t
over two is sort of the obvious lower
bound and I'm going to come back to this
obvious lower bound uh in a minute.
In fact uh there is a stronger version.
I think you proved this in detail and uh
you discussed the stronger version.
So let me state the stronger version
because well first of all it's important
in itself for applications of the final
field result. But I would say it's even
more important in the uklidian case.
Not only we can find so at this size we
can find the direction so that the
projection is large the projection of
the whole set but moreover we can find
the direction so that if we project any
dense subset of x the projection is
still large. So if we take the maximum
over now the minimum so we look at the
worst possible subset which is dense. So
we take the minimum over subsets of X
which are dense in the sense that they
have relative density
uh P to the minus epsilon
and then we look at the projection of Y.
So we try to make the projection of a
dens set of X as small as possible but
we can't even if we have this additional
robustness of going looking at all
subsets of Y we still have a gain over T
/2.
Okay. So this is Bans protection theorem
in the finite field setting
and you have proved at least this
version and I think discussed this
version. If anything I say is not
correct or if I say something that you
are not familiar with or you don't
understand anything please just ask.
Okay. So now we want to uh Okay. So
before moving to the uklidian case uh
let me make this remark
on the trivial bound.
So the trivial bound is p to the t /2
without the just without the epsilon for
this. So this theorem is not true if uh
p is p square. If we replace P by P
square or anything which is not a prime
because if you look at FP square for
example then FP sitting there and um
if we take F to be XP and D to be FP
sitting in FP squared we don't escape FP
because FP is a sub
uh so this is not true
but without the epsilon is true in any
field and the argument is trivial so uh
okay so one should never use the word
trivial but I will use it in this case.
So everything is trivial once you've
understood it and nothing is trivial
before you've understood it but uh I
will still use the word trivial here. Um
so if D has at least two elements so
same setting as above so if D has more
than one element so let's allow P to the
S where S is positive just two elements
then the maximum
over theta in B
of the projection
of X is at least
the size of X to the 1/2. So if the size
of x is p to the u t would be at least p
to the t /2 and again we will see that
this doesn't use the fact that p is
prime.
So it's much more general. Okay. And and
this is trivial because just take two
elements. Okay. Again trivial. I will
explain it and then once you've
understood it you will see that you will
agree that it's trivial. Um okay so know
that. So just take two elements. So D
has at least two elements by so let's
just take two elements theta and theta
prime in D and then uh so the
observation that makes this trivial is
that uh if you map X
to the projection in direction theta
comma the projection in direction theta
prime. So this is small x an element of
xp squ.
Uh this is injective.
So we can recover a vector from two
projections
by linear algebra.
So this means that the image of X under
this map has size at least
the domain because if you have an
injective M map the image has the size
of the domain. Okay. So this implies
that the size of x is at least the size
of the projection in direction theta of
x times
the size uh of the projection in
direction of theta prime. So at least
one of these two has to be at least
square root of x square root of the size
of x.
Okay. Uh so this is the proof of the
trivial bound and I hope you will agree
that it's very easy and it uses
literally nothing. Well uh it uses that
this map is injected but this is a very
general fact
in particular this is true on any finite
field it doesn't have to be prime but
for this we need it to be prime okay so
now we want to uh have a uklidian
version of
this statement and we will see that okay
so maybe let's discuss the uklidian
setting so I will start with the setting
uh which is the way in which nucleidian
setting has appeared in this course
before but then I will rescale things uh
to a setting that I like better but
let's start uh with the following so we
have a parameter r which is the scale or
maybe one / r is the scale
and then we have our set x is contained
in the ball of radius r let's say center
at the origin or really any any ball of
radius r it doesn't make any
And let's suppose that X is a union
of unit balls
and D let's say in 01
maybe one two would be slightly more
natural but it doesn't really matter
much is a one / r separated set.
Okay, so G is a finite set of
directions. They are separated by the
scale one / R
and X is a unit of unit balls MBR. So we
measure X by le measure. We measure it
by cardinality and use bars in both
cases. I think this is the convention
you've been using in this course
and well we would like the following
well we would like that right. So uh
except that now x is not in fp square
but in br and d is no longer in fp but
in 01. So pi theta is still the same. So
pi theta of x1 x2
is x1 plus theta x2.
We could look at orthogonal projections
but up to a parameterization
uh is this is actually easier to work
with. It's not important. Okay. So we
can ask does the same happen?
So just all the bars mean different
things now. So when we project X we are
looking at the measure measure one
dimensional measure of the image and so
on. So do we have any hope of proving
the same theorem in this generality?
So does anyone want to guess could this
theorem be true in this setting? It's
not true because the and the balls are
closely packed into kind of a kind of a
ball radius root r. Okay, great. That's
a great example. But that great example
and I will come back to this still
satisfies the trivial bound. So can the
trivial bound happen in this setting as
written?
Because yeah, yeah, if you have
everything is is packed into a smaller
ball, if you project, you still have an
interval of size the square root. So
you're right, that fails. I'm going to
come back to your example. That fails,
but this still holds. Can the trivial
bound be true in this setting without
assuming anything else?
There are only two directions.
Okay. Uh yeah, two directions. Maybe
it's asking too much. Let's say there
are Okay. What is P to the T and what is
P to the S? It would be row to the T and
row to the S. Uh not not row R. R to the
T, R to the S. Let's say there are R to
the S directions. Let's make it a little
bit more. Yeah. With two directions. Uh
maybe. Okay, let's say there are r to
the s directions which are 1 / r
separated. Can the trivial bound hold?
Okay, what is an example of a set that
has one very small projection?
So what is a set in the plane that has
one very small projection?
>> All of the balls in a line.
>> A line. Okay, it cannot literally be a
line because it's a union of balls. But
we put the balls in a in a long segment.
So uh so an example that should make us
kind of scared is
a 1* r rectangle. So packed with balls
in this way as someone suggested.
Then if we project literally down we get
something of of size one which is much
much much less than square root of r.
But if we perturve the vertical
projection by r to the s the projection
will have size r to the s and if s is
less than 12 it will be less than square
root of r. So,
so instead of projecting in this
direction, if we project in a nearby
direction, uh this is still bad. So,
so if this is x
and
okay, so I think actually I chose a bad
so this projection cannot be written in
this way. Oh yes, it can be written in
this way. Just theta is zero. It can be
very well written in this way. Uh okay.
So and if theta is let's say uh minus r
to the s r to the s
then the projection of x will have size
of the order of r to the s
and well s could be positive but less
than 1/2.
So this this is very bad. Okay. Uh so we
don't want okay this is not theta this
is d
so this is very bad so we don't want d
to look like an interval or to be very
concentrated in an interval or something
like this so we want to avoid such such
a situation okay so this is bad it makes
even the trivial estimate hopeless
so maybe we'll come back to this if
there is time maybe not but maybe as an
exercise for to uh not exercise for
marks or anything but you can think at
not now now pay attention but you can
think later what goes wrong with this
argument because in R2 it's still true
that two projections even if the angles
are very close determine
the the original vector so why why so
how is this compatible so you can think
about this and then you will understand
many of their well not many one of one
of the important reasons why things are
much more complicated in this ukidian
warp.
Okay. So now suppose that uh we avoid
this in some way. Uh can we have a hope
of having the theorem and the answer as
you said is still no. So this is one
example we should be worried about. Uh
here is another example we should be
worried about
where x is essentially let's say a ball
of radius square root of r. It can be
really any radius between zero and one
but just two. Okay. So x should be a
union of this joint unit ball. So we
just pack
in a very dense way unit balls in a bowl
of radius r to the 12.
So the volume of X the area of X is
roughly R.
But if we project it in any direction.
Okay. So we have to get rid of bad sets
like this. But let's get rid of bad sets
like this in the strongest possible way.
Let's suppose that G is everything.
So here we can so we are we are focusing
on what can go wrong with X. So let D be
absolutely everything.
Well, here every projection
is going to be a segment of length
roughly r to the 1/2.
So if you look at the projection of x,
this has size roughly square root of the
size of x
and this is for every theta.
So in fact if you avoid this in a
suitable way we recover the trivial
bound but it is no longer trivial. Uh
maybe we'll come back to this on
Thursday depending on how we are doing
with time. So the trivial bound is no
longer trivial even in the best case.
But if we want to go beyond the trivial
bound uh we also need to assume
something about x. So we need to avoid
this and we need to avoid this. And you
see that in both cases uh what's going
on? So the geometric
picture is different but in both cases D
is
an interval X is a ball. So we want to
avoid X D looking like an interval or X
looking like a box. And if we do that in
a suitable way then we can indeed get
a similar statement. So let me actually
state it.
[Applause]
Okay, let me say that Bugan didn't state
it in this way but
okay this follows from what he proved.
Okay. Um suppose that
same same setting as before. So,
so we are still assuming this
would have been faster to just write
everything down again. But okay, but we
need to have some assumptions uh to
avoid these web examples.
So uh okay, so first of all we need some
quantifier. So given
zero t uh so t is strictly between zero
and two and s
larger than zero there exist now two
parameters so I could do with one
parameter so you see that even here I'm
using epsilon for two different things
for the growth and for the robustness in
passing to subsets here I'm going to use
two different letters because they
denote different
thinks
so there exist epsilon
and ita both depending on s and t and
both positive such that the following
holds
okay so suppose that we have x union of
unit balls in the r
uh 1 / r separated set of directions
uh okay and then we need to assume
something because otherwise it's not
true so we need to assume that x and d
are not very concentrated in small balls
or small intervals. So this is what we
are going to assume.
If we intercept x with any ball of
radius r
we see only a small piece of x and the
smaller the r the smaller the piece and
the range of this little r is between
one and big r because x is a unit of
unit balls and it's a subset of the r
ball. Okay so this should be less or
equal than what? Well, on the one hand,
we want to compare this to the natural
scale, which is R. So, this tells us how
much smaller the reference scale is
compared to the global scale. And let's
put the T here, which is motivated by
the fact that okay uh
okay, so X has area R to the T and D has
cardinality R to the S.
Okay, so this T matches this T
and then I have the size of X. So this
is saying if R is much smaller than big
R. So if if R is big R, we have all of
X. So we can we cannot get any gain
because X is contained in the ball of
radius R. But if we are intersecting X
with a smaller ball,
we have
a big decay sort of power decay with
respect to so
only a very small part of X can be in a
small ball compared to the whole of X.
Okay. And it turns out that it's very
important for applications to have some
leeway here. And this leeway is given by
this parameter EA.
So this leeway says that actually
we don't need to assume anything if R is
very close little R is very close to big
R because if R is very close to big R
this will still be bigger than one and
then we have a trivial trivial
inequality. So this is saying the global
scales don't matter. Okay and a very
similar story with D.
If we intersect D okay balls here are
intervals but I'm going to
still the notation for balls this is at
most again we have our ley r to the
epsilon
and then row is between zero and one so
here the right thing to write is row to
the s
times
okay so the size of x is actually r to
the t but still I want to write it in
this way so it's clear that when we
intersect with the ball we are seeing
only a small piece of X
and same thing here.
Okay, so these are the conditions that
we impose to avoid these bad control
examples and you could say that they are
overkill and we are avoiding not only
this but okay put it in a different way
there is a whole universe between this
and this and yeah this is true and in
fact these conditions can be weakened
maybe I will make some remark about this
but anyway so these are the assumptions
then
there exist one direction and once there
is one direction there are many ctions
are such that we have the same uh
conclusion.
So if we look at the infyom
over all dense subsets and dense means
with respect to this so this parameter
it so it is like a tolerance parameter
it gives us some leeway at different
places to play with.
So y sorry yeah y is a dense subset of x
with this leeway r to the minus epsilon
then we project this subset and we get
the gain.
So the trivial now is no longer trivial
but sort of natural lower bound is t
over two and we beat it by epsilon.
>> Yes. Does Y also have to be a union of
univolves?
>> Uh, that's a very good question.
>> I don't think so. But yeah, just in
case. Yes. Just in case I'm too tired.
Yes.
Yeah. Let's say yes. Let's say yes.
Yeah. So, we're going to restate this in
a different language soon. Uh, where we
will get rid of balls. Yeah, let's say y
is also unit balls.
Okay, so you see that there are lots of
parameters. It's kind of a technical
statement. The assumption looks a bit
strange if you have never seen this
before, but nevertheless is again an
extremely important theorem with an
unbelievably range of applications and
we keep discovering applications and
something which is also important to
remark is that all the applications
really use the statement as a black box.
they don't okay it's sometimes people
also get inspired by the proof but it's
not a situation where the proof gets
used really the statement gets used so
it's a very very powerful statement and
I guess in the rest of the course with
Larry you will see some some of the ways
in which it is very powerful okay so how
does one prove this and by the way I'm
going to sort of as I say sketch the
proof skipping pretty much all details
but the proof I'm going to sketch is not
Bans proof
It's it's a
uh yeah maybe a new proof that I'm
writing together with Hong Wang that
takes ideas from different places. U
so it's is not Bhan's original proof.
Okay. So um the general scheme will
follow the steps that you've seen in the
final field setting but there are very
significant challenges. So what I'm
going to do is go over each of the steps
and explain what the challenges are and
what can one do to fix them and then you
will have to trust me that indeed they
they can be fixed. So I won't go into
the details. So
before doing so, so uh
you saw that if we want to go from
finite field to
uklidian settings,
uh sometimes you have to add more
assumptions otherwise things fail
because of some easy examples. But this
is not always the case. So there are
some some statements in the finite
setting that extend pretty in a pretty
straightforward way to this uklidian
setting. So
um so in order to do this uh I'm going
to sort of change the language a little
bit and
uh maybe rescale this. So instead of
looking at union of unions of unit balls
in the R ball, I'm going to look at so
basically I need to rescale the set down
by one over R. So X is going to live in
the unit ball and then it will be a
union of one over R balls and of course
you have to rescale if you rescale you
have to rescale everywhere else in the
statement. But instead of looking at the
volume of uh the set X, I'm going to use
the delta covering number. And for the
directions, instead of assuming that
they are disjoint, I'm also going to use
the delta covering number. So I bring
both. So basically X and D, I want to
use the same language and same scale to
make things more homogeneous.
So let me spend a couple of minutes
uh talking about the data covering
number. Suppose that X is a subset of
really any metric space but let's say RD
then uh okay so this is I guess
definition or notation
XAR delta so bar with your subscript
delta
is the smallest
number of delta balls
needed to cover
could be infinite but we only so in all
this business we are only looking at
bounded sets in which case this is
finite. So everything we are going to
see is going to be a finite number.
Okay. So this is a basically uh our
measuring resolution is delta. We cannot
distinguish anything that happens under
scale delta. So this is a natural way of
measuring the size of the set.
Okay. So, some just just a definition
but some observations.
Well, uh the first one I think I should
never use the words the word trivial but
I hope I'm justify justifying saying
that this is trivial. If x
is to make it really trivial two delta
separated
then the delta covering number is just
the cardality
because for each point in the set we
need a different ball.
Okay. So this will be the case for d. D
is delta separated but delta separated
to delta separated doesn't make a big
difference. So if the set is delta
separated is morally just the
cardinality.
Okay. If X is a union
of delta balls
then
the delta covering number is well you
use the balls to cover the set and okay
you need to normalize to pass between
measure and counting how many balls
there are. So
I think this should be delta to the
minus D. So this is the ambient
dimension where x lives times the le
measure of x.
Did I get this right? And it's not
actually equal. It's comparable.
>> Yes.
>> Or does x have to be a disjoint union of
delta balls?
>> Yeah, that's a very good question. No.
uh is easier to believe if it if it is a
disjoint union of delta balls and it is
also true if it's a non- disjoint unit
of delta balls and the reason is that if
you have a non- disjoint unit of delta
balls you can cover it by finitely
overlapping okay if the if you have a
disjoint unit of delta balls I hope this
is clear because the best way to cover
it by using those those balls
if you have a finitely overlapping
collection of delta balls then well you
just cover by the finally overlapping
family and you lose and any any union of
balls you can cover by a finite
overlapping. So I guess you need some
covering theorem to make it precise.
Anyway, it's true and we are not going
to use it. But you can convince yourself
that it's true. Again, easier to believe
if the balls are disjoint, but also
true. If balls are disjoint is equal if
the PS are not disjoint, there is a
wiggle. In fact, the wiggle I guess that
maybe depends on the ambient dimension
D.
Okay. So I'm just making these remarks
to say that to to sort of explain how
this relates to our previous setting
because now from now on we are going to
measure everything by the delta covering
number and the point I want to make is
that this recovers the volume and the
cardality when the sets are delta
separated or unit of delta balls.
Okay. So another way of thinking about
the delta covering number is as a box
counting number. So let d delta
uh be the covering of our d by delta
cubes.
So
so this is delta k
plus z delta
maybe let's make it half open so that
this is a partition to the d
where k is in z to the d.
So I'm I'm just doing like a diadic
covering. Delta doesn't have to be
diatic, but I'm So this is this is a
how do you say the tiling of RD by cubes
of size delta.
I make them half open so they are
disjoint but it's not really important.
Okay. So uh
the delta covering number
is up to a multibility constant the
number of cubes in the delta that are
hit by the set.
So the cardinality
of the cubes in the delta
which intersect the set.
So this is why this is called box
counting number as well.
Okay, why is this true is because if you
cover by cubes in an efficient way, so
if you know how many cubes you're
hitting, well, you can cover each cube
by a a finite number of balls of radius
delta.
Again, this wiggle may depend on D. So D
is a fixed parameter. It will be one or
two for Bansuction theorem. So I
consider it as a constant. So you can
cover each each of these cubes by a
finite number of delta balls and vice
versa. If you have a delta ball, you can
cover it by a finite number of cubes.
So that's that's the proof proof by
picture. Okay. And one nice consequence
of this is that this allows us to snap
any set to a grid and then this allows
us to apply uc non- ucleian uh integer
results discrete results. So
let's define
so what is x supperscript bracket delta
is the set that is obtained by snapping
points to the grid. So if uh x
intersects this this cube then this
point will be an ex in x delta.
In this way I I snap it to the latis.
Okay. Formally this is all the case
such that the cube delta k plus 0 delta
to the d intersects x.
Okay. So anytime there we see something
here we look at this point. Okay. And
then uh because of this
the delta covering number is roughly up
to a multiplicative constant the same as
the cardinality. This is now a finite
set and it's a finite set in a latis. So
it's just the not just not just a latis
it's just the integer latis scaled down
by delta but it's just the integer
latis.
Okay. And by using this uh one can
extend many results that are true um in
ZD to delta covering numbers.
[Applause]
So using this
in particular the following three things
which are three very important tools in
the proof of the finite field case of
bans projection theorem and also in the
uklidian case uh the rua triangle
inequality
the punic rou are
inequalities
and the valuic theorem.
They all hold for delta covering numbers
by putting bar delt. So when you see bar
you put delta. Okay. And you lose
multiligative constants because of this.
So where you have equality you no longer
have equality. But this is very
harmless.
Okay. For example, I'm going to state
the RA triangle inequality as a model
and then you can imagine how the other
two behave.
Um, so we have okay so we have three
sets
in the same RD.
Let's say bounded to make sure that the
delta governing number is finite. Then
let's see if I get this right. If not,
you just let me know. Okay. in in the
original. So in the discrete triangular
inequality here we have inequality here
we have inequality up to a constant. So
this is the only thing we have to
change.
Okay. Did I get this right? Is this the
correct statement? Okay. So this is an
example. Just put delta delta delta
delta and take equality by equality up
to a constant. And how do you prove
this? Well, you
you snap it to the grid. You have to be
a very like a little bit careful because
you can snap A to the grid. You can snap
B to the grid and then you can take A
minus B for the snapped versions and
that's not going to be exactly the same
as snapping A minus B to the grid. So
there is something that doesn't exactly
commute
but it almost commutes. So almost
commutes. So I'm not going to another
exercise is for you to convince yourself
that this is true. So okay. So you see
that for the projection theorem
we really need to impose assumptions if
we wanted to hold in the nuclean
setting. But this is not always true.
Here we have three very important tools
and they basically work in the same way.
Okay. So now we can start going over
the steps in the proof of the theorem in
the final field setting and seeing what
the obstacles are and what one can do to
overcome the obstacles if one wants to
follow the same scheme of proof in the
uklidian setting. Any questions so far?
[Applause]
Okay. So in the finite field setting
what was the first step in the proof? It
was to prove expansion
using a polomial for just one set. So
let's recall what uh this was. So if we
have a and fp okay I guess let's state
the quantifiers first. So given s
01 there exists an epsilon
such that the following holds uh if
we have a subset of our of our prime
field so here it has to be a prime field
this already fails if it's not the prime
field and well I'm going to come back to
this point several times okay and
suppose that it has size p to the s
then uh There exist a polomial
actually uh
there exist a polomial which is fixed
for all s for all epsilon and for all a
and it can be x1 x2 x3 - x4 x5 x6 so
that polinomial works but it doesn't
really matter which polinomial it is so
let's call it q
okay and
if we apply q to a we get expansion
Okay. So I think what you did with Larry
gave the following polinomial.
I think it was clear from what you did
with Larry that really doesn't matter
which polinomial it is as long as you
have some polomial because at the later
stage one is going to apply pura to
bring down the polomial to the simplest
possible polomial.
Uh so that was a later step at this step
any polomial works.
Okay so this one works but it's not too
important which one it is. Okay how how
did you prove this? So we can see to
what extent things go wrong in the
in the uklidian setting and to what
extent we can recycle some of the ideas.
So idea of proof
if I claim that you saw something with
Larry and you didn't please let me know.
Uh he told me and showed me notes but I
could still be wrong about something.
Okay. What was the idea of proof behind
this? Uh so one looks at
maybe let's call it x a minus a over a
minus a and here uh we skip zero we
don't want to divide by zero and then
there are two possibilities either x is
everything
and then
one can conclude in some way I'm not
this is not I'm not going to recall how
to do it and the other possibible ility
is that X is not everything.
And if it's not everything,
there exists some uh little X in X
such that X + one is not in X
because it's not everything and then one
can also conclude. So in both case this
one has to work. I'm not saying it's
trivial, but this was the structure of
the proof. And this extremely innocent
step is what distinguishes
FP from FP square. If we were working in
FP square, we would not be able to do
this because FP square
has a
subgroup which is FP. So you cannot
escape FP by adding one.
So this extremely innocent adding plus
one uh distinguishes okay so
distinguishes
FP and FP square let's say
okay so
we want to do something similar
and so let's say uh we have an A.
Well, first of all,
it's very likely that we will need to
assume something about A. In fact, we
need to assume something about A in the
UK setting because if A is a is a
segment,
it does like any polinomial check, it
doesn't grow. So, if X is
1 1 + R 1 1 +
delta to the
1 - t something like this, just just a
small small segment. If you add it to
itself, multiply by itself, you get
slightly longer segments. There is no
real growth is exactly the same issue uh
as we had when we were projecting uh an
X which was too concentrated in a large
ball. Okay, but now we sort of know how
to get rid of that. We need to assume
that A is not too concentrated inside
any segment. Okay, but even assuming
that we do that, uh we see that we have
lots of problems if we try to do
something like this.
What are the problems? So can you tell
me some problems? Why? So some
challenges in
trying to do something like this. If now
a is a subset of let's say 01 or one two
let's say 01 it doesn't matter.
So what things you should be worried
about?
Yes.
>> Uh x could be unbounded.
>> X could be unbounded. Yes. So a so in
the final field we need to avoid zero in
the denominator but in the ukidian case
we don't only need to assume zero. We
should be very worried about small
denominators not just zero but small
denominators because this is going to
blow up and yeah this is certainly an
issue.
Are there any other issues one should
worry about?
What does it mean to equal FP?
>> That's right. Well, I mean, okay. Yeah,
that's Yeah, what does it mean to equal
FP is not clear. And I would say what is
even much less clear is what does it
mean to add one
because
I don't know R is certainly not I mean R
is invariant and they're adding one and
it's not I mean this doesn't live in 01
anymore. If we force it to live in 01 by
intersecting with 01, there could still
be something. I mean, if we add one, we
could still land here. So adding one
doesn't seem like a good idea. And from
a conceptual point of view, there is
something that is even more worrying,
which is here it is crucial that FP
doesn't have any sub additive subgroup.
So it's a simple group. It doesn't have
any non-trivial subgroups because if it
had a subgroup, this wouldn't be true.
Now does R have any subfields or
subgroups
or sub rings?
Well, first of all, it does have
subgroups, additive subgroups.
It does
of any dimension. Okay, so of course it
does. All of our rational numbers,
number fields, but okay, number fields
are countable. So we are interested in
larger things, but it does have
subgroups of intermediate size. It does
not have sub rings of intermediate size.
But this is a difficult theorem and in
fact it's a consequence of bhans
protection theorem. So we cannot really
use it. So here we are escaping because
x is not a sub ring. But it's not so
clear if there is a subring type
structure here in R. Okay. All of these
things should make it very scary and a
normal person would give up at this
stage. uh but there is a paper by Larry
Guth and uh George Zal my colleague at
UBC and Netscats where they managed to
extend this idea to the uklidian setting
not to prove transportation theorem to
prove some different related theorem. So
let me tell you what they did to
overcome
these obstacles. uh but first of all uh
I should define something that I should
have defined before.
So we have these non-conentration
conditions. So we call this
non-conentration conditions because it
tells us that X and D are not
concentrated in both. So
non-conentration conditions. So looking
at this uh we are going to write a
definition
which is inspired by this so that we
don't have to repeat these sort of
conditions every time.
By the way, even in in in the final
field setting, uh what Bangatan Tower
did was also not this. So this this idea
came later. Uh so it's originated from
GV which is after Bangkawo proved
something like this. So Bangas did
something much much more complicated.
Okay. Um definition
the subset of the unit ball in RD.
We just want to fix some region of
space. So why not fix the unit ball uh
is a and okay let delta be uh between
zero and one not zero and maybe also not
one. Uh so we say that this is a delta.
Okay. And then we have a parameter t
which is between zero and d. And then we
have a constant which is positive.
Let's say at least one. Okay. So we say
that x is a delta s c d. So this d tells
us the ambient dimension. And I will
probably forget to write it down or it
will be clear from context. Set
if the following holds
if we interet x. So note I'm not
assuming X is a union of all. I'm not
assuming X is delta separated. I'm not
assuming anything and I'm not assuming
anything because I'm using to use the
delta covering number to measure things.
So this is nothing about the delta
covering number. You don't need to
assume anything as long as you remember
to write the bar delta. Okay. So uh if I
intersect X with a ball
and measure it by the delta covering
number, this is at most C. So C is the
tolerance the leeway that I have times R
to the S. So S measures the degree of
concentration of non concentration the
degree of non concentration. So the
larger the S, so R is going to be
between zero and one or between delta
and one. So the larger S, the smaller
this is and the stronger this condition
becomes times the size of X.
So again this says that a ball cannot
contain too much of x and this is for
every well but for every center and for
every
radius between delta and one.
Yes s
>> sorry. Yes.
Well it could be s or t but one has to
fix one. Yeah. S. Thank you.
Okay. So I hope you agree that in the
statement of regress projection theorem
this is the condition we have on X and
on D. On X we had a T and on G we had an
S. But this is the condition that we had
and so we can bring them both under the
same umbrella using the delta covering
number.
Okay. This is saying X is not too
concentrated inside small balls and the
strength of the concentration is given
by S and there is a tolerance given by
C. C could depend on delta. So C is
anything in particular it could depend
on delta and in the statement of BAN
projection theorem. So in ban projection
theorem this in fact is going to be
delta to the minus EA. So you have a
leeway that increases as a power with
delta very small power but nevertheless
a power. Okay. Uh so now we can state uh
something
I don't know
uh
lema. So it is the analog of the first
step in the proof. So it's the analog of
this
Given an s between zero and one
there exists an epsilon
and all these epsilons can be taken to
depend continue they depend continuously
on s. So this is important in the so
okay uh well I started saying the
sentence I'm going to finish. So in the
final setting one does this and then
what is the next step? one iterates this
and then one keeps growing. In order to
know that you keep growing, you need to
know that this epsilon
remains bounded away from zero as long
as the exponent remains bounded away
from one. Okay, so the same is going to
be true here although as we will see
next time I think next time uh it's much
more much much more complicated to
iterate in this case but okay let's
focus on this uh for today. Okay, given
S there is an epsilon
such that the following holds.
Suppose A is in 01.
The delta covering number is delta to
the minus s
and a is a
delta
s
delta to the epsilon minus epsilon set.
So it's is very nonconentrated because s
matches the size. But on the other hand
there is quite a bit of leeway in this
delta to the minus epsilon.
Then
oh okay so there exist a polomial
Q
it could be the same Q. So that that Q
if you want
any polomial so really it doesn't matter
because you can always apply polic but
let's say that polinomial but any
polinomial will do then
we have we have growth I'm just putting
delta governing number everywhere and we
get growth
so we get minus delta minus s which was
the size of a but
We get a delta to the minus epsilon grow
over that.
Okay. So it looks very very similar uh
to that to what to this except that we
need to add this non concentration
assumption. We certainly need to add
something because otherwise if a is just
an interval is not true. It's not clear
between interval and this what happens
but okay with this assumption it is
true.
Okay. So how can one prove that? Uh so
we want to use this strategy but we saw
that there are many problems. So I'm not
going to do the whole proof, but I'm
going to tell you how to solve
okay two of the problems or to some
degree I will tell you how to solve two
of the problems.
Okay, one is really cheating but okay so
I guess what I'm going to tell you is
that cheating doesn't always work but it
does work in this case in this
particular case.
I should finish at 225. Is that right?
Okay. Plenty of time.
Okay. So, idea of proof. I'm not going
to prove it but
okay. So
uh with in the final field setting this
works here we have the problem that uh
the denominators can be very small and
then this could be huge. So well we are
going to do two things at twice to try
to at least uh reduce the issue. So
we're going to define b in the following
way.
It is essentially a over a a minus a
over a minus a.
Okay. So we pick some gamma and the
gamma in the proof has to be picked
carefully so that things work out and
I'm going to go into the proof but you
we have to pretend that there is a gamma
so that will work. Okay. So first of all
I restrict the denominators
to being larger than delta 2 the gamma.
So in this way
well I got rid of the worst possible
case where the expansion is too much.
But even then this could escape the
interval 01 and I don't want to escape
the interval 01.
So I intersect it with the interval 01.
So this B is going to play the role of
X.
And by doing this I'm avoiding again I'm
avoiding two related but not exactly the
same issues. One is that this could
escape our sort of reference interval
and the other is that the denominators
could be too small. They can still be
quite small because so gamma is not
zero. So this can still be small but
so there is a trade-off.
If we allow too small denominator things
blow up too much but we still have to
allow small denominators otherwise we
are missing too much of a minus a over a
minus a. So this gamma is gives us the
tradeoff.
Okay so that's one thing we do uh but
the most important thing to understand
is
what do we do instead of this? So really
adding one doesn't really make sense in
this setting. So what do we do? And here
comes a very easy but absolutely
critical lema.
So in the same way that
the method in FP doesn't work in FP
squared
what works in R. Okay, this is a remark
I should have made earlier but uh I
don't think we have the statement
anymore. Yeah, we don't have the
statement of bug prediction theorem
anymore. But bug prediction theorem is
not true over C because over C you could
you could take X to be essentially R
squared living in C square and you could
take D to be a piece of R living in C
and because R is a subring of C you
don't escape. So there is no growth. So
it's exactly the same reason why it
doesn't work in FP square because FP
square has an intermediate algebraic
structure. C has an intermediate
algebraic structure which is R and
because of this it doesn't work
and
here we use that FP doesn't have an
intermediate algebraic structure. So
actually this lema is very crucial in
the sense that it is what distinguishes
R from C or for many or okay from many
other things but in particular from C.
Okay.
So there are many ways in which R is
different from C and we will see that it
is the order structure uh what
distinguishes R from C in the lema in
the proof of dilemma. Actually dilemma
can be proved in many ways and some of
them do not use the order structure but
in my proof I will use the order
structure. Okay. So here is the lema. Uh
suppose that B
eventually we are going to apply to this
B that's why I call it B. But a priority
is any B it's contained in 01 and
suppose that zero is in B zero is in
this B because A1 could be equal to A2
okay and then uh
let row
be the largest gap
in B.
Okay, what is the largest gap? So a gap
is a
is a connected component of the
complement. So we are in R. So connected
components are segments.
So the complement is a union of
segments. Well could be points. I mean B
could be dense but let's imagine B is
closed. I think it doesn't have to be
closed. Maybe let's say closed.
It's not really important.
Okay. If it's closed and the complement
is a finite or contraable union of open
intervals. Each of them has a length and
we take the supreum maybe
okay everything is going to be fi like
finiteary because in our application but
let's say the largest in the sense of
the supreum of the length of the gaps in
B so is it clear what this is we just
look at the complimentary intervals and
we look at the largest one then
there exist B in B
such that either
The distance from B / 2 to B is at least
row over four
or
the distance from B + 1 / two
to B is at least row over 4.
Okay. So proof,
let B prime be B / 2 union B + 1 / two.
And this means what you expect it to
mean. So you take little B in B divided
by two and you do that for every little
B in B. And then you take little B plus
one over two for every little B in B. So
I hope it's clear what this is.
Okay. So this is contained in 01 as well
because B is contained in 01. So this is
contained in 0 1/2. This is contained in
one half one.
So we have zero, we have one, we have
1/2 and 1/2 is in B prime because zero
is in B.
You will see that this is important. So
zero is in B. So one half is in B prime.
Now what is the largest gap in B prime?
So by definition the largest gap in B is
row. So that's the definition of row. So
what is the largest gap in B prime?
>> Row over two.
Here the largest gap is row over two
because I'm scaling down by a factor of
two. And here the largest gap is row
over two because I'm translating and
scaling down by Yes.
>> Could actually there be a gap of size
row if B has a big gap at the ends of
the intervals?
Okay. So I guess uh
maybe let's assume that one is also in B
or something like this. So I mean there
could be an infinite gap.
Is is that what you're worried about?
>> That yeah there's a gap from like one
minus row to one or something. But if
one is in in B then uh
>> let's say zero and one are in B. So one
is also here because you could take A3
and A4 to be A1 and A2.
So one is in B.
Uh if you define the gap in a way that
avoids this issue, you don't need one to
be in B. But let's it's not important.
Okay. Why is it important that one half
is in B? Because here the largest gap is
has size row over two. Here the largest
gap has size row over two. But if one
half wasn't here, there they could be
combined to form a larger gap going
across. But it cannot go across because
there is one half is there. Okay. So now
um
now let's draw the largest gap or the
gap that approximates the largest gap.
So this one has size let's say row minus
epsilon
and okay so this is the center of the
gap. So this is the gap in B not in B
prime in B. And now let's write let's
draw
an interval in the middle of length row
over two.
Maybe a closed interval.
This closed interval contains an element
of B prime because the largest gap of B
prime is row over two. That means that
any interval of length row over two
contains a point in B prime. Okay. So
maybe let's write this down. So largest
gap.
So this interval contains a point in B
prime.
But this point is a distance at least
row over four from B
because this gap is double the size. So
even if the point was at one of the end
points, so the point could be here. But
even if it was at one of the end points,
this is row over four. This is row over
four.
Okay. So maybe let's do a larger
picture. So this is row minus epsilon
gap in b.
Okay. And this is a row interval.
So it contains
some point in b prime because the
largest gap in b prime is row. And this
interval has length row. So it cannot be
completely empty otherwise it would be a
larger gap. Okay. Whichever point is in
this interval is at large distance from
B because there is nothing in B here.
So that's the proof. So you do the
calculation is at least row over four.
Uh
maybe row over five because you need to
take into account this epsilon. Maybe
row over five just in case
it's not it's not important.
So you see that this is a simple
geometric argument but it very very
strongly uses the order structure of R.
So this argument doesn't work in C
because there is no order and in fact it
cannot work because what we are going to
prove using this is not true over C.
Any questions about this?
Okay you can prove this lema in other
ways. So Guat and Zal in their paper I
think they don't do this proof but I
think this proof is easier and shows how
the order structure is fundamental.
Okay. So
hopefully I have proved the lema.
Okay. So of course a point in B prime
has either this form or this form
because that's the definition of B
prime. Okay. So here we have a B prime
in B prime which is far from B. that B
prime is either this or this because
that's the definition of B prime. So
that's how one concludes the proof.
Any questions again?
Okay. So
now what the idea is to use B over two
or B+ over two instead of
B+ one.
So why does B+1 work? So what is
important about b+ or x + one? So what
is important is that
again it's a polomial in this case is a
linear polomial but
that that takes something in x and lands
it not in x. Well the same is true for b
over two and b plus one over two.
you take something in B and it lands far
from B.
Okay. So, uh
let's say first step of proof. So, I'm
not going to prove but
well, we have to pick a row in 01
carefully.
In fact, it's going to be a power of
delta as usual. Some power don't
remember which power. One has to choose
this power carefully. And then there are
two cases that sort of morally
correspond to those two cases.
B now is that B that B up up there. Not
an arbitrary B. that be is row dense.
Row dense means that the largest gap is
at most row
or if you take the row neighborhood you
cover everything everything is 01.
So any questions about what row dense
means?
Okay. And here we use an argument which
is similar
to the case x - x /x sorry uh it's not x
it's a minus a
over a minus a equals fp
to get growth
which I'm not going to show
this is the sort of easier case
I here was also the easier case.
Okay. And the other possibility is that
there exist a B in B such that either
B / 2 is far from B
or
B + 1 / two
is far from B.
in this sense.
So there are two cases by dilemma.
Okay. And then we use B over two or B
plus one over two in a similar way to X
the way that X + one was used in the
final field setting
to get expansion.
And it works. is much more complicated.
So the the actual details are much more
complicated than in the final field
setting
but it works and
I would say the overall idea is very
similar but the details are much more
complicated.
Okay. So, so far so good module, lots of
details, but uh this was the first step
in the final field setting and we can
replicate it. So, it seems that things
are going well. But now we have a much
bigger issue.
Maybe I'm going to explain the much
bigger issue and talk about how to
overcome it next time because this is
maybe the biggest issue, the biggest
difference. Okay, you can see that this
was already a big issue and a big
difference in the proof. But now comes I
would say a bigger issue.
This was the first step in the final
field setting. What is the second step
in the final field setting? Iterate in
the first step and you just iterate.
Nobody's preventing you from iterating.
So you get that Q of A growth. So you
can do Q of Q of A.
So here
maybe let's call it the second step.
You look at Q of Q of Q of Q of A
and this is very large.
So uh you can make it as close to P as
you want
in terms of powers.
I don't know
I don't know it. So for any ita if we
iterate enough times we keep growing and
we can reach any power we want. In fact,
we actually eventually in the fin
setting we get all of all of the finite
field after iterating finite finitely
many times. I don't know if you saw this
but anyway so this is clear because we
just keep iterating.
Okay. So now let's go back to
sorry did I ever state
uh
[Applause]
oh here it is okay so here is the lema
that
I told you we can prove using this idea.
So then this is the lema. So we have a
delta s delta to the minus epsilon set
of size delta t to the minus s. Then we
apply q and the size grows.
Okay. So what's the problem?
We would like to iterate but we cannot.
So why can we not iterate? Well,
apparently we cannot. I'm not saying in
the end we will iterate but why why is
it completely unclear whether we can
iterate?
There's no guarantee that Q of A will
satisfy the spacing condition.
>> Exactly. That's the issue and it is a
big issue. So we know that the size of Q
of A grows.
But here we have this additional
assumption and we need it or we need
some assumption. We need the assumption
that A is a delta S delta to the minus
epsilon set. So in order to iterate we
would need to know that not only Q of A
has grown in size but we would need to
know that Q of A is a delta S plus
epsilon delta to the minus epsilon set
and we don't know that a priori if we go
over the proof the proof doesn't show
that so when we okay so I haven't given
the proof of the lema only gave a very
rough sketch but you have to trust me
that if you go through the proof we do
not get any non concentration for Q of A
we literally only get get growth at
scale delta.
Okay, so let me write this somewhere.
[Applause]
Big issue
We know
Q of A grows
in delta covering number.
But
the proof
does not show
that Q of A
is a delta S plus epsilon could be a
different epsilon that's we did the same
epsilon but we need some epsilon if we
want to iterate here
Okay. So we are going to talk about some
of the things we do to overcome this uh
in the next lecture. But let me say that
I think in fact it is not true that Q of
A has to be a delta S plus epsilon delta
2 minus epsilon set.
It is not even true. But what is true is
that Q of A contains a delta S plus
epsilon delta to the minus epsilon set.
Okay. And this is good enough because we
just just take that subset and use that
to iterate and then we then we can
iterate and the second step will work in
the same way. But this is a big issue
and somehow we have to go through the
whole steps of the proof in the finite
field setting
just to get this and then we have to
sort of do the full so one has to sort
of cycle through all the steps twice in
this proof. The first cycle is to solve
this issue. So we have to use valuedic
hours for example to solve this issue
that comes much later in the proof in
the finite field setting and then we
have to use it again once we have
expanded
a lot uh by iterating okay so I'll
explain uh the ideas behind this on
Thursday yes for showing that QA
contains the delta s plus epus epsilon
set does that set have to be kind of
very close to the size of a and like an
s plus epsilon or delta spacing level.
>> Well, it needs to be much okay. Uh
something maybe I should have say but I
didn't say is that a delta t c ignore
this for a moment. So a delta t cz set
has size at least delta to the minus t
because you apply the definition of
delta t cz set at scale delta. This is
something I should have mentioned. I
will try to remember to mention it next
time. So this set that is contained
actually has already size bigger than
the size of a but in addition to having
larger size it has good spacing.
But yeah one question is that I'm going
to answer next time is how how come that
something contains so this notion of
delta s set is bad in the sense that it
is not monotone. So you can so if you
take a set which has this non spacing
condition or non concentration condition
and make it larger you may lose
the non concentration condition and
that's kind of bad. So we'll see how to
get around this next time.
Any other questions?
>> Yes.
>> I wonder like in the two cases you wrote
so in the first case you said the set is
dense. So somehow it is large but in the
second case what's the intuition behind
okay I have one element that is far away
from the set and then we can get the
set. is really very similar to what you
did in the final field setting. In the
case when x is in a minus a over a minus
a and x plus one is not. You use that to
show that some projection of the
original set is large.
>> Okay?
>> It's it's a very similar idea except
that you have to fight with small
denominators and but but morally it's a
very similar idea. Okay.