[Music]
this is what if it works coming to you
from the MIT energy initiative and
looking at the energy solutions to
climate change I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Robert
[Music]
Stoner and to start today I'm going to
throw out two words that are going to
sound I'm guessing kind of insane to you
here are those two words carbon tax and
you're thinking hm doesn't really feel
like a carbon tax is an idea with a lot
of currency right now but hear me out
this is a story with unexpected twists
and
turns there seems to be this pretty
pervasive perception in DC circles that
carbon pricing just will not work in the
US it's not wholly pervasive there have
been bills introduced every Congress um
including bipartisan bills but we wanted
to really try to get people out of that
DC narrative that's Katherine Wolfram a
former Deputy assistant secretary for
climate and energy economics at the
treasury Department she's also an
economist at the MIT Sloan School of
Management and the DC narrative she says
is based on the fact that people tried
to get carbon pricing during the Clinton
Administration and during the Obama
Administration but here's the thing as
she noted in a recent piece in the
Washington Newspaper the hill reality
and perception have shifted since then
look the beginning of the Obama
Administration was 15 years ago a lot
has changed since then I think a lot
more people are being exposed to climate
change in damaging ways I used to live
in California we had the blackout Suns
from the wildfires you know many
Californians experience wildfires in
their backyards that's just one example
she notes that among the G20 Nations
even though they have varied types of
governments and Leaders with a wide
variety of views everyone has carbon
pricing or is actively considering it
except that is for three nations the
three countries are Russia Saudi Arabia
and the US so just kind of not good
company for for the us and not only does
that set kind of a political example and
prove that it can be done but more and
more countries are adopting carbon
border adjustment mechanisms which I
think we'll get into and so that will
really Force our hands but you may be
saying very few Republicans would want
carbon pricing so isn't the concept kind
of Dead on Arrival well consider this
Wolfram says in an effort to extend the
Trump tax cuts one of the big questions
will be how can you pay for this tax cut
which is where carbon pricing could come
in there is a Republican bill Senator
Cassidy from Louisiana has it's called
the foreign polluters fee Act that that
would impose tariffs on Imports
proportional to the carbon intensity of
their production and there's a
democratic side Bill Senator White House
has introduced it with several
co-sponsors the one big difference is
that in Senator White House's Bill he
includes a fee on domestic production as
well where Senator Cassidy doesn't in my
experience in DC nothing gets more
bipartisan interest than being
anti-china
we know that China's production right
now is quite carbon intensive I will say
that China's pretty good as an
authoritarian government is kind of
turning on a dime so they've been
decarbonizing not quite as rapidly as we
have but but pretty rapidly so I think
we need to be a little bit careful about
getting too entrenched in this mindset
of China as this dirty you know monolith
and it isn't going to
change um Let me throw um a quote at you
on this issue of carbon pricing um we
talked not that long ago with Ernie mon
who like you spent some time in
Washington he was Secretary of Energy
and we asked like what do you think
about carbon pricing what do you think
of where it's headed and it's kind of an
interesting take to see what you
think I think that something like this
eventually is going to happen where the
big tension will be in how the revenue
Vue is
used I cannot name the name but let's
just say I not that long ago spoke with
a
prominent former Republican government
figure well respected in the Finance Tax
Arena and I was quite surprised when
this person said unequivocally he
supported the carbon
tax and we talked more
and then we found where there was a bit
of a breakdown uh in our views namely
his view was all the funds should go to
deficit
reduction well that of course is
completely
regressive in the end that may be the
negotiation how much of this funding is
returned uh to the population in a
progressive way how much goes to budget
balancing if I had to guess I would
guess that we may end up with that that
as the final
negotiation I mean that is sort of
aligned with what you said that maybe
you have people on different you know
sides of the aisle interested in this
but maybe they have different approaches
does that what mon said does that sort
of resonate with you I'm thrilled that
that's what mon said I think I've
updated my forcast of the probability of
carbon pricing passing by several
percentage points that's that's amazing
your hope casting has now like morphed
into forecasting okay okay yeah so I
mean I don't remember anyone responding
favorably to the federal government
raising taxes in this country or just
getting used to it I mean there's
enormous political pressure not to do
that the late George Schulz who's a good
friend to Mighty and was on our Advisory
board for many years chaired it used to
talk about a revenue neutral carbon tax
whereby everybody would pay these taxes
but then the Social Security mechanism
would be used to send everyone a monthly
check refunding all of that additional
Revenue to the people so that it
wouldn't be an additional source of
Revenue what
happened so yeah Schultz is a very
prominent proponent of the baker Schultz
idea and and the revenue neutral carbon
prices there as an economist the most
important thing to do is get the tax in
it actually doesn't really matter from
an economics perspective what you do
with the money let's put it back into
the 2025 framework where we're thinking
about these tax cut extensions one of
the tax cuts we're thinking of extending
is the child tax credit that's very very
Progressive and was shown you know it
was expanded during the Biden
Administration was shown to have
tremendous impacts on reducing childhood
hunger so if you use the revenue from
the carbon price to pay for a child tax
cut extension that's the even better
than the the Schultz idea right because
it's it's very Progressive it's not
giving everybody a check it's giving
low-income people a check and it's
something that both Republicans and
Democrats have really said yes we should
not only give that credit but it should
be more than it is so I you can see that
the there are multiple constituencies
from different places that could say
like yeah let's make that tax credit
$5,000 6 you know yeah if we have the
money to pay for exactly exactly species
of car or Revenue neutral tax in the
sense that the money is going back out
they're not using it for other purposes
or the general budget yeah but you're
not getting a check that says this is
your carbon rebate yeah so you can't
compare them well maybe that's bad I
mean if you can compare them you say hey
I made money on carbon this month yeah I
think there's a lot of research on like
what the best way to give the money back
is and there's some research from Canada
that suggests that even you know getting
a check that says this is your carbon
rebate people don't put the two things
together that when they're at the gas
pump they see you know higher gas prices
and don't remember that they got the
check there's also you could flow it
back through electricity bills and so
then it's kind of a line on your
electricity bill and and people see that
their electricity bill is
lower as I say I think the most
important thing is to to get it in and
so like whatever helps us solve the
political Dynamic and and get you know a
bunch of people in Congress on board
that's my main ambition is to get it in
place and and so I think whatever works
in terms of using the money that gets as
many people on board that that's that's
what we should go for but it sounds like
you feel like there's been enough
disruption in people's lives from flood
you know whatever it is that things have
changed like it's not the Obama
Administration anymore you know that
people have moved enough
on climate change that they're like yeah
okay I'm I'm willing to do something
that's what the polling suggests yeah
okay yeah so let's talk about something
I know you both have thought a lot about
which is you know so okay so we're
talking about potentially implementing
you know a price in carbon in this
country but as you were
saying lots of countries have already
done this we're kind of way behind so
how are other countries doing this and
is it working out yeah in general there
are two ways to implement carbon pricing
one is just a straightforward tax and
and basically they're kind of equivalent
from an economics perspective there are
some subtle differences the other way to
do it is more complicated the idea of of
what's called cap and trade and
essentially this involves the government
creating essentially a chit that says
whoever holds this chit has the right to
emit a ton of carbon but it only creates
a limited number of those chits and then
kind of reduces the number of chits over
time Europe is on a path to reduce the
number of chits to to zero to get to Net
Zero by 2050 and then companies whomever
wants to emit the carbon have to trade
those chits you have to hold one of
those chits for every ton of carbon that
you eventually Emit and essentially the
market determines the price um it's much
more complicated to set this up than to
you know as I said add to our existing
excise taxes but the advantage is that
it creates something of value these
chits essentially and a perspective
Global Market in chits if people find a
way to sort of move them around yes yes
and so I think that's one real Advantage
for lower income countries because then
people in higher income countries can
buy their chits so potentially somebody
in a poor country has these little chits
and they can give them to wealthier
Country for a bunch of money and then
that oil driller can drill for oil but
in in in exchange that poor person has a
bunch of money now yeah yeah which is
okay the idea being it's cheaper in
those countries to make some of the
mitigative measures that that could
reduce their emissions what do you mean
well you know a lot of countries in
Southeast Asia for example burn coal to
generate power with practically no
abatement of any kind whatsoever and
very inefficient
uh combustion systems so you can improve
those combustion systems without
spending a lot of money whereas we're
already kind of at a much more
aggressive level I see in the developed
world and that the extra ton the
marginal ton costs a lot more to aate
here than there so okay I'll pay you to
do it right okay okay okay yeah so cap
and trade how well does that work us
like trading you know I have a oil
drilling business so I pay you a bunch
of money to buy basically permission to
emit a bunch of stuff does that work
well yeah yeah there's tons of economic
evidence either the carbon tax or the
cap and trade system really helps reduce
emissions you know of course the higher
the price the the more it helps you know
getting back to our conversation about
DC's resistance I I do think the thing
that frustrates me most is when people
say well carbon pricing just doesn't
work because that's counter to all the
economic
evidence we do to get to you know Net
Zero by 2050 goals we would need pretty
high carbon prices but I definitely
think that we need an all of the above
strategy and and carbon pricing is an
important part of the the all of the
above I would say I mean just further on
what you're saying about the us falling
behind Europe and Europe being more
Progressive I
mean the the approach that we're taking
in this country which is kind of the
this the national spirit and it's kind
of what this program is is about is to
innovate like mad to find a way to
develop technologies that are not more
costly but are far less carbon intensive
and there's a great deal going on here a
great deal more going on here I would
say than in Europe so you know it's a
it's a different way of thinking about
the problem I would see the European one
is more
punitive that's often the way it's
characterized Europe did have and still
does have a lot of subsidies as well so
this gets back to my point that they
work together well I don't think it's an
either or proposition if you have carbon
pricing it encourages those innovators
to you know find ways to avoid paying
those prices so they can work well in
tandem yeah so what have other countries
and the way they've implemented a price
on carbon because you said there's like
different ways of going about this what
have they taught you about if we were to
do this and the president were to say
what would you what would you advise how
should we do this what would you advise
that's a good question so all of the
bills that have been introduced I'd say
in the past like five
congresses maybe not literally all but
but there's definitely been a trend in
the US away from cap and trade and
towards carbon taxes so the the most
recent Congress I think all the bills
are for carbon taxes and not for cap and
trade I'm not quite sure why that is but
I kind of tend to defer to people who
understand politics better than I do and
imagine that that's for good
reason administratively it is easier to
to implement the carbon tax if you have
the cap and trade system and you create
these chits there's political pressure
to give away those chits so then the
carbon pricing scheme doesn't end up
raising as much
money I do think the experience in
Europe highlights one advant AG of a cap
and trade system that is worth noting
and that is that it's flexible and it
basically responds to changes in the
environment so for instance before
Russia invaded Ukraine the carbon price
in the European Union cap and trade
program was about 20 um dollars a ton 20
euros I'm not
sure after Russia invaded Ukraine
natural gas got a lot more expensive and
so it was harder for electric power
plants to switch from coal to natural
gas and so after the invasion carbon
prices basically quadrupled they went
from $20 to to $80 wow during this
crisis right and so you could never
imagine if it had been a tax system the
European Parliament getting together and
saying okay let's quadruple the price of
using carbon in this time when we're
facing a huge energy crisis because of
the The Invasion but there was no you
know I I was kind of scanning because I
was worried about this there was no
obvious pressure to get rid of the cap
and trade system um at the time of the
invasion or in the immediate aftermath
but as I say you know the price kind of
adapted to the fact that the energy
situation was different and and Rose
dramatically so if if um carbon pricing
was implemented in the US in the way
that you think would be best as regular
consumer how would I see that show up it
depends on how exactly it's um
implemented but say we carve out retail
gasoline and I've done some modeling
work on this you probably about meaning
we're not going to touch the price of
retail gasoline okay yeah basically like
because like people are too sensitive to
that they freak out when exactly yeah
the US is so sensitive to gasoline
prices so you functionally the way it
would work is refineries would get a
refund proportional to the amount of
retail gasoline that they sold and so
the prices of retail gasoline wouldn't
go up you know I honestly think that you
wouldn't notice it that much our
modeling suggests that adding a modest
$15 a ton carbon price that that kind of
increased gradually over time would
increase the average US households
electricity gasoline kind of total
energy bill by by 1% so so would it
mostly show up in like my monthly Energy
bill
it would show up there it would also you
know the industries that would really
feel it are Industries like cement Iron
and Steel aluminum and so the Iron and
Steel the metal that goes into making
your toaster would become more expensive
but you don't buy toasters that often
and metal isn't a huge part of the
toaster cost so you know maybe your
toaster becomes like 2% more expensive I
I don't think that you would notice that
okay homes though maybe maybe like home
and building construct I'm just trying
to think what uses a lot of Steel cars
maybe and but also like if you were
building a highrise or you were building
okay so maybe the cost would go up but
maybe the Builder would say huh the
design that uses a lot of Steel I don't
like that quite as much maybe I'll go
with this different design that uses
some alternative building materials and
and so you wouldn't see the price
because they've done you know what we
want them to do and and use less
carbon so let's take a quick break here
we will come back and talk about a
totally new approach uh that Europe is
taking to getting carbon out of its
Imports we will be right
[Music]
back you're listening to what if it
works I'm Cara Miller in conversation
with Rob Stoner and Economist Katherine
Wolfram and we're talking about Crea
cretive economic incentives to reduce
carbon emissions one of which is an idea
that Europe has adopted it's called cbam
the carbon border adjustment mechanism
and what it does is basically at the
border imposes an adjustment for imports
proportional to the carbon that's used
in in making those Imports so imagine
your Europe and you're importing let's
just say Chinese steel say it takes 3
tons
carbon dioxide to make a ton of Chinese
steel and say you're a Chinese steel
maker trying to send your steel to the
the EU before the cam you had a huge
Advantage because the EU steel makers
were paying for their carbon emissions
the Chinese steel makers weren't so with
the seam it basically says when you try
to export your Chinese steel to the EU
you're going to have to pay proportional
to the the CO2 that you've used to to
make your steel and so it completely
erases that kind of competitive
advantage that you described we we can
no longer it's no longer cheaper to buy
things where carbon isn't priced because
we're doing this border adjustment to
make sure that all the carbon is priced
the other thing I'd like to say about
cbam is and I think this is where the
real beauty of the cbam comes in it
credits exporters if they have already
paid a carbon price in their home
country so going back to these Chinese
steel producers if China expands its
carbon pricing scheme to cover the steel
producers then whatever it's paid
whatever the steel producer has paid
domestically gets credited and it pays a
lower border adjustment this seems like
it gets complicated very fast though
right I mean you're a steel producer in
China China charges a different level of
tax in France you pay it or so the
government says like
a they may have a completely different
they may charge a third the tax you know
and so France is like well that's not
enough I'm sorry like we we want 3%
you're charging 1% is not going to do it
and also we don't even know whether
they' believe you like have you really
paid it the government says you have you
say I'm not sure like that there's tons
of trust with many countries and the
government that they're very very T
closely tied into industry I don't know
what I mean tell me how this works
yes I agree with the potential negatives
that you've laid out I have some
thoughts on that let me first articulate
the positive okay and we are seeing this
is that the EU bam has just really
galvanized a discussion worldwide about
carbon pricing so turkey for instance
half of turkey's total manufacturing
gets exported to the European Union
turkey did the calculation that it's
Industrial producers were already paying
a carbon price they were just sending
the check to Brussels if Turkey put on a
carbon price you know nearly as high as
the European unions it would collect the
revenue and keep it locally instead of
sending it to Brussels and so that kind
of logic is is just percolating
throughout the world and there are a lot
of countries that are thinking since the
seam about implementing their own carbon
prices so you know one thing you said is
what if the exporter hasn't paid as high
a carbon price as they would pay in the
EU then you just get credited for
whatever you paid okay to pay the
remainder you have to pay the remainder
and so again that incentivizes the
foreign country that the exporting
country to the EU to increase their
carbon price to the level of the EU so
that they keep all the
revenue you you articulated the concerns
about monitoring yeah I think those are
real and I think there are are
measurement
challenges I guess I would say two
things one as I said I think the the
beauty of the seam and you know it has
this funny acronym it sounds very
esoteric very complicated I frankly
think that it's the most important thing
that we've seen in global climate
mitigation circles in the last like
couple decades I think it's it's really
really important and is really helping
solve a lot of the problems involved in
getting Global carbon mitigation
so I think one thing you can do is not
say I'm going to try to measure for
every single ton of Steel how much
carbon was used but I'm going to look at
the whole country where it came from and
charge them based on kind of average
carbon emissions in China and so you
might think that that's kind of messy
and and then individual steel producers
don't have an incentive to reduce their
carbon but what it does give an
incentive to and where the bite of the
cbam is is it gives policy makers so if
you're charging every single export from
a country based on the country's average
carbon emissions then the country has an
incentive to to reduce their overall
carbon emissions or impose a carbon
price so for instance I like to say that
the the ideal SE bam is a seab bam
that's never implemented because every
country is encouraged to charge their
own carbon price domestically and you
know then you're all paying carbon price
and and there's no need to to border
adjust your point about do we really
believe like is some foreign country
actually collecting the money are they
actually really charging the carbon
price I think that is a real
concern I am encouraged by the
developments that there have been in
Satellite monitoring I mean it's sounds
kind of like 3D and futuristic but we
have satellites out there
I have a former graduate student who's
running an entity that that's measuring
kind of factory by Factory and seeing
what carbon emissions are coming out so
you know harder to hide it's harder to
hide it's really harder to hide so a lot
of the countries were talking about big
exporters to Europe or the United States
for that matter are lowcost producers
and these are typically emerging
economies
um and what we're doing with those taxes
is trying to push them in the direction
of developing low carbon Manufacturing
capacity and just generally low carbon
economies but that takes a lot of
capital so there's this sort of conflict
that I struggle with where does that
Capital come from if you were a poor
country you may be up against your debt
limit for example yeah that's a huge
issue in global climate circles um
climate Finance how do we essentially
transfer money to low and middle- inome
countries to the global South um to help
them decarbonize and help them as you
say kind of grow in a in a low carbon
way
if I were president of the world I would
basically use the seam as a reason to
get a bunch of high emitting countries
together and talk about what kind of an
ideal structure looks like and in my
view part of that ideal structure would
be using the revenues from the seam from
carbon pricing in the global North to
transfer money to the global South as
you say I think there are two reasons to
do that one is economic as we've talked
about there are more opportunities for
lowcost mitigation in the global South
but the second is really moral the
global North was able to develop using
carbon you know huge proportion of the
carbon that's already in the atmosphere
comes from Global North
emissions and the global South is
predicted to Bear the brunt of carbon of
sorry climate change so you know hotter
temperatures plac like India are really
really going to be hit by those higher
temperatures and it's essentially the
global South is suffering from a problem
that the global North has created people
talk about this idea of a carbon budget
that we've only so much carbon that we
can emit over the ensuing several
decades you're thinking is then that we
would make more of that carbon budget
available to emerging
economies so that they could develop
through their initial stage at least and
get rich enough to make these sort of
large Capital Investments but doesn't
that mean that we're imposing a higher
carbon tax on
ourselves um and and are we ever going
to do
that you mean like it's more expensive
to make a toaster is that what you mean
and then we have to pay for that or yeah
well somehow I mean if we're if we're
going to constrain our emissions in
order to make more room for them to emit
then we're going to have to increase our
carbon tax yep so so to I'm trying to be
an economist here yeah no that's exactly
right exactly right so so you know we're
we're we it's it's a funny way of
transferring Capital but that's
effectively what's happening we're
taking it in through taxation and
transferring it to those countries by
giving them more space if this is again
if I were president of the world I would
I'd vote for you thank you thank you I I
would be very focused on climate change
but if I were a president of the world I
would allow for kind of a graduated
carbon pricing scheme
so coming back to the cam you could
imagine designing it so that lowincome
countries get credit for kind of 5x
whatever carbon price they charge so if
the European price is 100 then a price
in mosm Beque of 20 would get them out
of of paying the European carbon price
and effectively that is letting those
countries use more carbon than we are
giving more as you say of the carbon
budget to lower income countries when
you talk about the kind of economic
unfairness it's a little you know what
we're saying in some ways is like okay
you all get refrigerators okay now we're
going to start everybody's going to have
to start paying a lot more to get a
refrigerator and everybody in this
country is going to have to bear that
whereas these people already got theirs
yeah yeah right and it that doesn't seem
fair it sounds like right yeah so let
them get their refrigerators for a
little bit less right it's not going to
be a lot more these are all kind of like
rounding around the margins and yeah but
but we're going get let them get their
refrigerators reflecting a lower carbon
price but I thought the thing that you
said before about turkey was really
smart that like turkey sends a bunch of
stuff to let's say Italy and it was
getting taxed and so where does Italy
send it to Brussels where the EU
headquarters is and turkeyy is like well
we we want it to stay in Turkey so we'll
just be more like efficient with our use
of carbon use less of it then we'll
we'll ta ourselves you know get it all
in our to keep it stay in our country
and then send it over when you know it's
pretty clean we'll send it over to Italy
yeah right yep I have a policy brief
that shows basically counts the number
of times carbon pricing cap and trade
decarbonization those words have shown
up in the press in countries that don't
currently have carbon prices and that
aren't the US and you really see that
after cam it it quadruples it's it has
literally started a global conversation
about carbon pricing not only about
carbon pricing we also track things like
green steel and decarbonization and
clean energy so it's as I say it sounds
esoteric but I'm super excited about
cbam how much is cbam influencing US
policy we export some stuff to Europe or
not that much I don't think I think the
US is a little bit insular to be honest
you you know continue to hear well
carbon pricing is impossible and yet
lots and lots of other countries are
doing it but right now the EU cbam is
kind of in a pilot measurement phase no
money is changing hands it will be
implemented in
2026 as I say there are all these other
countries that are thinking about it and
so I I do think between that and between
the conversations about how to bring in
money to pay for the Trump C tax cuts
that conversation will take place in 202
I you know that's why I'm hope casting
some kind of carbon pricing I mean we've
been talking mostly about like what
should the US do what's Europe doing
these kind of wealthier more mature
economies but I just wonder on the other
side of this you've got countries where
all the time lots of people are moving
into the middle class their poorer
economies but they're getting you know
richer faster we've kind of already been
through that sort of gross spurt I
wonder how you deal with the fact that
there's a lot of the world when you
think about like pulling carbon out or
emitting less carbon there's a lot of
the world that's still on the growth
trajectory and I mean what does that
demand look like from your
perspective yeah so this is something
I've done research on people when when
you're very very poor if your income
goes up you spend more of your income on
higher quality protein for instance or
or just higher quality calories but as
you come out out of poverty and enter
the middle class you start doing things
like buying a refrigerator buying a car
buying a a motorcycle and those things
all require energy so you do see this
kind of you know step change in energy
consumption as more people come out of
poverty and enter the middle
class that said we've been talking about
this from a climate change perspective
so that does is accompanied by more
carbon emissions but it's also
accompanied with people getting access
to refrigerators right and and
refrigerators are great because they
keep food cool keep medicines cool and
you know being able to drive gets people
to better jobs so those things are
associated with economic progress which
we want to cheer for th those are it's
great when people come out of poverty
and and come into the middle class you
know the hope is that we can get to a
point where Energy Systems
don't emit as much carbon or don't emit
nearly as much carbon so that as people
come into the middle class they're
buying refrigerators made with green
steel or they're driving you know
electric mopeds and so the the kind of
increase in carbon emissions isn't
associated with with that economic
growth does that feel realistic if
you're talking about millions of people
or tens of millions of people entering
that like a wealthy sort of phase I know
we're hoping that we can mitigate the
amount of carbon in the air we can
produce less but does that feel
reasonable when you look at countries
that are on that upward sort of growth
trajectory on the one hand fossil fuels
have been used because fossil fuels have
lots of great properties I know that
sounds funny for someone from a climate
with for someone with a climate
perspective to
say but you know oil has become so
dominant globally because it's a very
very it's a very good energy storage
mechanism basically it's not that heavy
you can use it in a car transportation
and and the energy you get out of that
oil is is is super valuable for the the
weight of that
oil um that said we are making a lot of
progress on making electric vehicles
cheaper making batteries cheaper making
things like solar panels cheaper
and I will
say I think we don't we can't paint the
global South with one brush there are
parts of the global South where you know
solar and wind is super abundant if you
think about Africa right now leaving out
South Africa over half of the
electricity is made with renewable you
know Hydro or um geothermal
um electricity
so and and they have very great solar
potential coming back to the seam I
heard at cop a NGO that the head of an
NGO from Africa
describing his vision for green Le
African growth he was saying that it
used to be the case that in Europe
energy flowed from the East to the West
you coal mines in Poland and they were
feeding the auto manufacturing plants in
Germany his vision is that in the future
in a world where we're pricing carbon
where that coal is really expensive to
use he hopes that we will see energy
flowing from the south to the north that
African potential to have you know very
abundant solar abundant wind will help
fuel the the production you know maybe
some of that production will actually
move to Africa and Africa can become you
know a green steel Powerhouse and send
that steel to the the consumers in
Europe so kind of transform the way
energy flows based on the huge renewable
energy solar potential that we see in
Africa Rob you've spent so much time in
Africa I don't know I wonder if you have
some of those concerns of like oh this
is great people are doing better but
then the pr pressure that that puts on
you know as as Katherine said I mean
fossil fuels there's a reason people use
them like coal oil these are very very
effective easily transportable like
there's lots of things that are good
about them um except for the obvious
yeah well there always ironic that
Africa is a big producer many many parts
of Africa are big producers of oil and
gas and yet they benefit very little
from that I mean the present day carbon
footprint of Africa is so trivial that I
think it's not an issue um and the
emphasis should be on economic
development however you can do it in in
at least the foreseeable future um that
but you know beyond that stage they
certainly have to get onto a a renewable
track a lowc carbon track and I think
they can but they really stand to be
beneficiaries of what we learn in the
next couple of
decades I guess finally you know we've
talked so much about um economic policy
and I wonder if what we have looked at
on the men you in terms of like the
these are the carrots and sticks or as
Ernest mon said the carrots and twigs
that we're using do we have like the
right things on the menu I
think it depends what you describe as
the menu like if the menu is the set of
things that policy makers can choose
from I think we have the right things
yeah carbon pricing is an old idea in
economics it's been around for over a
hundred years it it's really kind of
econ 101 answer to an externality which
is what we have we have a global
externality with climate change you know
what policy makers are ordering off the
menu I think is the is the challenging
part and it's a global
problem
globally without something like seam
every individual country has the
incentive to kind of sit back and hope
that other countries really take the
lead and so that's why I'm really
encouraged by cbam it it it pushes
countries not to as economists would say
free ride around along with other
people's or other Count's policy
initiatives but join those those policy
initiatives and so yeah to use your menu
analogy I think that the the cbam and
related initiatives will help policy
makers make the right choice off that
menu as I've said I think it's an all of
the above strategy I think as we' talked
about subsidies are great subsidies and
taxes are even better so I I would love
a world that had both yeah carrots and
sticks I wonder too if there's there's
something of a kind of outsize influence
of like when Europe says we're going to
tax carbon and so turkey says well in
order to sell our stuff to Europe we're
going to have to reconfigure things
around here or as you said you know
we'll Tex carbon ourselves and then
we'll get all the revenue and then we'll
sell Europe and they'll be like okay
great the tax was levied okay perfect
come on in I wonder if then you get this
kind of domino effect where even if we
don't even if the US just has too many
divisions we cannot get together
politically it can't happen all the
stuff we get from turkey and Vietnam
like it's already been taxed for carbon
because in order to sell to France and
Italy and the UK they have to do it
anyway yeah and I think the the real
domino effect that's exactly the analogy
that it it becomes kind of tipping you
know positive feedback cycle and if
Canada and Mexico imposed SE bams the US
would pay attention we export a lot to
those countries we don't export that
much to the
EU I hope that it doesn't take that
though I yeah I think that's kind of
part of of what will get politicians
attention but as we talked about at the
beginning I think the revenues that
carbon pricing introduces as well as as
kind of seeing that this is what's
happening around the world I I think we
can kind of forecast that it might
happen that we would be taxed by by
Canada and Mexico instead of waiting
until that actually happens and
hopefully we'll kind of get off the the
ground quicker than yeah waiting for
those I'm developing this image as
you're talking of countries segregating
their manufacturing into a clean part
that goes to Europe it's not worth it
you know it makes me think of like when
California says well this is how cars
are going to have to be what are you
going to have a a plant where you make
the cars for Utah time like one for C it
doesn't make sense California keep all
your coal plants in China and say okay
well those coal plants are going to run
all of these factories and these solar
panels are going to run those ones we'll
export that stuff to Europe well and
we'll export the the coal there's some
dominoes that'll probably just fall
because it's just too complicated but
maybe there's some that that wouldn't no
and as you say if enough countries do it
it helps the Technologies get cheaper
that's exactly the the the California
analogy yeah I like that yeah I agree
with you I'm just trying to cast a doomy
or
gloomy conversation hope casting
wishcasting we're hoping wishcasting
[Music]
Katherine wilri is the former deputy
assistant secretary for climate and
energy economics at the treasury
Department she's an economist and
professor of energy economics at the MIT
Sloan School of Management Katherine
thank you so much for taking time and
being here thanks so much this
what if it works is a production of the
MIT energy initiative if you like the
show please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen and remember to
subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu SLP podcasts and
you can learn more about the work of the
energy initiative and the energy
training transition at energy. mit.edu
[Music]
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob S thanks for listening