All right, so my
name is Bill Green.
I'm the Director of the
MIT Energy Initiative.
I want to thank you all for
coming to our first seminar
of the semester.
The MIT Energy Initiative
sponsors this speaker series
to try to help the
people on campus
keep informed about
what's happening,
to try to decarbonize
our energy system,
and also to help people
recognize the urgency of motion
to try to make change happen.
And we have a
speaker today that's
going to talk about some
pretty urgent work going on
to try to make change happen
here in Massachusetts.
The MIT Energy Initiative is the
hub of energy research at MIT.
And one of its roles is to bring
leaders of industry, government,
non-profits, and academia
to come to campus
to talk to the community, and
also to participate in workshops
and research projects
and conferences
with the people actively working
on the energy transition here.
The global energy system is,
of course, super complicated.
It's complicated with
today's fossil fuel system.
It's going to be
complicated in the future
with a coming clean
energy system.
And there's many,
many different parts.
And today we're going to hear
about one really important part
that's particularly important
for Massachusetts is offshore
wind.
So different parts of the
world have different resources
and different situations.
And one resource we've got
plenty of here is wind.
And particularly in the
south coast of Massachusetts,
it's really windy.
And it's really fantastic for
providing clean energy here.
The entire energy system is, of
course, extremely complicated,
as I said.
And one part of it is
providing electricity.
And that's what we're
going to hear about today.
Today we use fossil fuels
for many, many, many things,
not just to make electricity.
And so many people on
campus are doing research
on all sorts of other
parts of the energy system
because we have to
really change everything.
And so the scientists
and engineers
here have a really
big role to play
to help develop the
technologies that
will become the real
industries of the future.
Today we're going to hear
about industry of the present,
I guess is like the time is
now to put in the windmills.
And we'll hear about that.
But we have many
other technologies
that are under development
here at MIT or from startups
or technology that's
spun out of MIT that's
going to help to change
other sectors of the economy
and clean up the other sectors.
But here in Massachusetts,
offshore wind
is the really big story.
So the legislature has
decided that that's really
the biggest future contributor
to clean energy in the state
and has passed some special
laws to try to help that along.
And in response to that,
a lot of companies,
including Vineyard
Offshore, which
we're going to hear
about today, are
working to try to
actually make that real,
to get the windmills out
there, get the wires connected,
get the electrons flowing to
power MIT, to power Boston,
to power the whole state.
Today's speaker
is Alicia Barton.
She's the CEO of Vineyard
Offshore, which is currently
involved in offshore wind
projects here in New England
and also in California and
I think maybe off New York
as well.
Before Alicia took
her present position
leading Vineyard Offshore,
she worked in other parts
of the clean energy sphere.
She was previously the CEO of
the Massachusetts Clean Energy
Center.
And she was president and CEO
of the New York State Energy
Research and
Development Authority.
And even more recently, she was
CEO of Firstlight Power, which
is a New England Based clean
energy producer and storage
company.
As CEO, Alicia is
responsible for developing
Vineyard Offshore's portfolio of
six gigawatts of offshore wind
projects, which
currently includes
a site 15 miles
south of Nantucket
and Martha's Vineyard
in Massachusetts,
and a second site
proposed for 29 miles
off the shore of
Nantucket, and also
another proposed site off the
shore of Long Island, and then
a different site off
the shore of California.
During the presentation,
you can submit questions
that we'll ask the
speaker after the talk.
You can submit them
electronically using
the QR code.
Is it on the screen?
Not yet.
It will be on the screen.
Or else you can just type the
letters Poll, capital P-O-L-L,
ev.com/mitei, M-I-T-E-I. And
then you go to that link.
And you'll be able
to submit questions
for the Q&A. So please join
me now in gratefully welcoming
Alicia Barton.
Thank you.
I'm going to grab this clicker.
OK, maybe I'll
stand here to start.
And then we'll go there for Q&A.
Is that what you want to do?
Great.
Well, good afternoon,
good evening, everyone.
So nice to see people
here interested to talk
about offshore wind, which
certainly is an incredibly
important topic to the energy
future of Massachusetts,
and certainly well beyond.
I really appreciate that
generous introduction.
Bill, thank you also for
inviting me to be here
to talk about this topic.
I'm going to fast forward here.
You did a great job
highlighting our portfolio.
And I have a map,
which maybe will
make it a little bit
easier for folks to digest.
And so again, just a little
bit about Vineyard Offshore.
Maybe Bill didn't
mention, we're 100% owned
by Copenhagen Infrastructure
Partners, which
is a private equity fund
based in Copenhagen,
as the name implies.
That is actually the
largest private equity fund
that's solely dedicated to
greenfield renewable energy
development.
It's about 10 years old.
Offshore wind is a core
part of their business.
And we serve as the US
offshore wind development arm.
The US being one of their
larger global markets.
But they have projects
all over Europe and Asia
and truly all over the world
in offshore wind, as well as
other clean energy
infrastructure.
So our portfolio, as
Bill was outlining,
includes the Vineyard
Wind One project,
which I'm going to talk
a little bit about.
And that's a project that's
under construction, which
is incredibly exciting milestone
to be able to say finally
after many years of many
people working very hard to see
that day come to New England.
And then we have the
site further offshore,
which we have proposed as our
Vineyard Wind Two project, which
was recently awarded a new
contract from Massachusetts.
And I can talk a little
bit more about that.
We have our Excelsior
Wind Project,
which is off the coast of
New York and New Jersey
and plan to interconnect
onto Long Island.
So helping in that case New
York meet its very aggressive
clean energy and offshore
wind specific targets.
And then we have this
project in California.
And that's on up on the
northern coast of California.
It's maybe a little bit
hard to tell from this map.
But it's actually pretty close
up there near the Oregon border.
And that is a project
that, unlike the other ones
on the East Coast, will
be deployment of floating
offshore wind technology.
So on the East
Coast, we're talking
about all fixed
bottom offshore wind.
I'm going to assume if
you came to this lecture,
you know generally
what offshore wind is.
You know that
there's a lot that's
been deployed in
Europe and globally
and not very much that's
been deployed here.
And that's kind of
the story that I
wanted to start by telling.
And then I really would
prefer to spend more time
in conversation with you, Bill,
and taking audience questions.
But I think thinking about
the topic of the talk
and finding a new
era of success,
the way I was thinking
about this story is really
to zoom out from
necessarily our projects
and talk about the arc of
offshore wind in the US
and where we are
today, what's hard,
and what's been challenging,
and where we're struggling,
and then also where
we're succeeding.
And I do think there's actually
a lot of exciting things
that are going to happen in
the not too distant future.
I didn't bring any other
substantive slides.
I just brought some nice
pictures of our projects.
I love these pictures.
So just indulge me
in sharing them.
And I'm not going to share
all the captions or anything.
But these are real
world pictures
of the Vineyard Wind Project.
So Vineyard Wind is 800
megawatts and as I said,
is in the midst of construction.
Some of you probably
also read that we
did have a construction
accident over the summer
with a blade that broke.
I can talk more about that.
But generally speaking, I would
say prior to the blade incident
getting a lot of
attention, really
known for being the first
large scale offshore wind
project in the US to move
forward to construction.
And it really has been
a long time coming.
So thinking about, again, that
arc of offshore wind progress
in the US, I was
thinking about it
in my own personal history
working on offshore wind, which
goes back 15 years, which for
the US is quite a long time.
15 years ago there
weren't that many people
working on offshore wind.
There weren't that many
people talking about it.
But Massachusetts was.
And so I was thinking about
this in a few chapters.
And the first
chapter, I would say,
was really Massachusetts'
initial efforts
to launch offshore wind,
which were centered
on a prior project called
Cape Wind, which some of you
may recall.
It was extremely well known
and extremely controversial,
had significant political
opposition and local opposition
on Cape Cod, including from
significant political figures,
like Ted Kennedy amongst
others, as well as
opposition from well known
people, like the Koch
brothers and the like.
There literally have been
many books and movies
written about that project.
So you guys can check that out
if you want to dig a bit deeper.
But what Massachusetts
was doing at the time
was really placing
a bet that if we
could get one project launched,
then the rest of the projects
would follow.
And that was a strategy.
It was a purposeful strategy of
saying, we just need to get one.
We need to show this as real.
And then things will take off.
And so I won't belabor
all the details.
But the utilities in the
state were essentially
coerced or encouraged to
enter into long-term contracts
with that project to
make it financeable.
More significantly, I
think, as we sit here
today, the state made a
very long-term effort,
sort of took the long view and
made a significant investment
in the first offshore wind
port facility in the US.
So this is in New
Bedford, Massachusetts.
Maybe you've heard of it.
Maybe you haven't.
But back then, when I was CEO of
the Massachusetts Clean Energy
Center, we on behalf
of the Commonwealth
took state bond funding
and invested at the time
$130 million into a
port in New Bedford
to renovate it to be the first
purpose built offshore wind
facility in the US.
The offshore wind requires very,
very specialized capabilities,
including heavy
loads for the cranes
and the size and scale
of the components
that we're talking about.
So that project, just
to place it in context
to this first chapter, I'm
talking about Cape Wind.
Think of it as
2007 to 2015 or so.
We finished the New Bedford
Marine Commerce Terminal
construction in January of 2015.
Cape Wind failed and canceled
its project in January of 2015
as well.
And so that was a
very painful episode
and an extremely clear to
some of us that were there
growing pain of the industry
and one that at the time,
many people said, will there
be offshore wind in the US?
We tried.
We had this strategy.
We were going to
build a project.
That project failed.
Has the whole strategy failed?
And I think that was an
open question for some time.
But then we entered what
was the second chapter.
And it really was,
I think, a lot
of work amongst
policymakers, stakeholders
to think about, OK, this isn't
really just about one project.
This is about our
climate targets.
This is about the
fact that this is
a mature technology in Europe.
This is about jobs
that can be created.
And that started to catch on.
So when I was the CEO
of Mass CEC from 2012
through the end of 2015, it
was a very lonely conversation
when I would talk to my
peers in other states.
And I would go to New
York, for example,
and say, you guys should really
think about offshore wind.
And they're kind
of like, yeah, I
think we'll watch how it goes
for you guys first and think
about that a little bit later.
But then in that next phase,
the Massachusetts legislature
passed a bill in 2016.
And now I'm thinking
about basically 2016
through 2020 as this next
chapter, passed the first bill
that set up a procurement.
So this was a
different strategy.
We're going to have competition.
We're going to invite
multiple parties to bid.
We're going to see
what the prices are,
see if we can imagine this
power being affordable.
That was a big concern at the
time and run that playbook.
And as they started doing
that, some other states
started paying
attention as well.
New York called me
back and said, OK, we
want to do offshore wind.
Would you want to come
over here and work on it?
And that's when I went to
take the job at NYSERDA,
leading New York's
climate efforts.
And a lot of exciting
things happen.
I mentioned Massachusetts
passing that legislation
that set up the procurement.
That was the procurement
that led to the Vineyard Wind
Project.
So that was a PPA that
was awarded back in 2017.
So again, just keeping
the time horizons in mind,
Vineyard Wind would
ultimately start
using the New Bedford Marine
Commerce Terminal in 2023,
so eight years after we
finished the construction.
So we were definitely
early on that.
And another six years after
the initial procurement
to give them the
contract to get going.
But New York passed a
landmark climate law
that I'm extremely proud
of to require the state
to fully decarbonize its grid.
We were picking up
momentum in this time.
And it wasn't just
Massachusetts and New York.
It's the other
New England states
had started issuing contracts
as well down into Maryland
and Virginia.
And we started to see momentum.
But real progress was still a
little bit elusive in this 2016
to 2020 time period.
And it may be intuitive.
But that also coincides
with the first presidency
of Donald Trump, who is
not a fan of offshore wind
as presumably many
of you are aware.
So we had the states
moving forward.
But we lacked a partner
at the federal government
that was really going
to help us get there.
And I was trying to get
new leases issued off
the coast of New York
in my role on behalf
of the state of New York.
And we were frankly running
into brick walls there.
Vineyard Wind had its
power contract now.
Massachusetts came up
with this new policy.
They competed.
They won.
And yet still they couldn't
get their permits out
of the federal government.
And so some of you may remember
during that time towards the end
of the Trump presidency, had
to withdraw their permits
essentially and undertake
a fairly risky strategy
to try and bet on a
future administration.
And so we then went
into what was definitely
the most exciting time we've
had for offshore wind in the US.
So when President Biden
takes office in 2021,
he issues the New
York Bight leases.
He starts issuing permits,
including very soon
after taking office the
permit for Vineyard Wind
to allow the project
to go forward.
And so in 2021, 2022,
and starting into 2023,
all these things were happening.
We started to get a
massive number of projects
contracted for power with states
up and down the East Coast.
We started to see the federal
government issuing new leases,
record prices.
The New York Bight
lease, the one
that I had tried to extract
from the Trump administration
on behalf of New
York, ultimately
cleared many billions
of dollars in revenue
when they ran the lease sale.
And it was more than any
offshore oil and gas leasing
effort previous in history.
So that was incredibly exciting
and validating for the fact
that not only, again, is
this a climate initiative.
We know that there's
real capital that's
ready to work to do this.
And then amidst all these
positive things happening,
including Vineyard
Wind finally getting
to financial close, which
is a critical milestone
to allow projects to move
forward and start construction.
We ran into the
story that everybody
knows around interest rates,
inflation, global supply chain
crunch, and, again, started
to hit more of a down cycle
for sure.
And that really came
to a head in 2023.
And then here into
2024, we saw projects
canceling their
PPAs with states.
They were saying, essentially,
we contracted this previously
at prices that we can no
longer deliver on when
we go to the supply chain.
It's extremely crowded globally.
And one thing people
should keep in mind
is that we're a new
market here in the US.
And we're competing
against projects
in a global marketplace.
So when we want to place
an order for turbines
or high voltage
electrical equipment,
we are competing against
projects all over the world.
And the US candidly is
viewed as a risky market.
We're newer.
We don't have a
significant track record.
We have, unfortunately, ongoing
political risk with change
in administration risk.
So those things tend to
drive up the costs as well.
So we saw a lot of
contracts canceled.
We also saw-- and this has been
super unfortunate, I think--
the number of commitments for
supply chain manufacturing,
domestic manufacturing in
the US backtrack away from--
that's been one of the
policy goals of advocates
of offshore wind has been
to set up a domestic supply
chain to create the jobs,
not only in construction
but manufacturing jobs as well.
And there's strong long-term
rationale for that.
The components that we're
talking about are so massive,
it really does make
sense to manufacture
them close to where they will
be deployed rather than shipping
them all over the world on
highly specialized vessels that
are extremely scarce.
But we saw, for example, in
New York, for my company,
we'd contracted with GE to
build a next generation turbine.
And they were going to do
manufacturing for blades
and the cells of the wind
turbines in Upstate New York
and decided that they
couldn't make that work
and had to cancel
those plans, which
led to further power
contract cancellations,
including our project.
And so, I think, to me, it's a
very clear story of two steps
forward, one step back.
Every time we're making progress
we've found a new growing pain
for an early industry, found
additional challenges that maybe
sometimes could have been
foreseen, maybe they couldn't.
One of those challenges, and
I touched on this already,
was also, as the first large
project to go to construction,
we did have a
construction accident
this summer where we had one of
the blades on a single turbine
fail catastrophically and break
and shed debris into the water.
This is not something
that's super common
in the global offshore
wind industry.
It has been pretty
common in onshore wind.
There are quite a lot of
blades that break historically.
But when that happens
on land, the debris
lands and settles
in a certain spot
rather than being carried
to many places, which
is what occurred with
us over the summer,
where we had debris washing
up on the shores of Nantucket
and Cape Cod particularly.
I think that incident
has gotten what
I would say is maybe a bit
outsized attention everywhere
I go.
But, of course, people know
what I do for a living.
It comes up a lot.
I want to put the impacts
of that incident in context.
I think it's
important because I do
think the media has been a bit
misleading on this at times.
So there were no injuries.
There was no private
property damage.
Our blade was damaged but no
private property, no vessels,
no docks, nothing like that.
We have no evidence of any
species being injured or, again,
sort of killed or anything
like that you see.
We did have one day of beach
closures on part of Nantucket
in an abundance of caution.
But they were reopened
the next morning.
And we've been hard at work
with debris recovery ever since.
So, again, when you
put that in context
of the environmental damage,
I think, from, frankly,
any fossil fuel plant that
is constantly emitting--
well, you know what
fossil fuel plants emit.
Let alone oil
spills and the like,
I think it's important to just
keep this relativity in context.
But at the same
time, we're new here.
We're the new industry,
and all eyes are on us.
And, undoubtedly, this was a
setback in a learning experience
that hopefully will make
the industry stronger
and that we will learn from
as we go to this next chapter.
Now, this is the part that
I'm really excited to share.
And it's easy to
lose track of it.
So, again, you kind of, I
think, hear about offshore wind.
You hear, OK,
Vineyard Wind's going
to construction, that's great.
All these contracts are
getting canceled over here.
That doesn't sound so great.
What's really happening?
If you look at the pipeline
of offshore wind projects
in the US, this next
chapter is going
to start in 2025, which,
of course, coincidentally
coincides with the start of a
new presidential administration.
And we don't know which
administration that will be.
But whichever administration
it is, we have, essentially,
8,000 megawatts or 8 gigawatts
of projects that have
their federal permits,
have power contracts,
and are reaching financial
close and going to construction.
So next year, in the first
term of either Trump or Harris,
whoever ends up taking
the White House,
we will have 8,000 megawatts of
offshore wind under construction
in this country, which is just
an extraordinary maturation
and finally catching up to where
we've hoped to be all of these
years.
And it's sort of--
there's a weight to
that as an industry that
is very, very
different than what
we've confronted in the past.
And so I get a lot of
questions about what
happens if Trump gets elected.
Does that mean offshore wind
will never happen in the US?
And I would say, absolutely not.
And, again, we're going to
have 8,000 megawatts under
construction, which
is extremely sizable.
I mean, that's enough power
for four million homes
just to give you a sense of it.
And I think it'll
be hard for anyone
to want to slow
down or curtail jobs
that are actively going for
folks in the construction
industry.
The Vineyard Wind Project,
some great statistics--
we've already created just on
our one 800-megawatt project,
so, again, about 10% of what
I'm talking about for next year,
1,200 union jobs and closer
to 5,000 total jobs in terms
of the construction
of that project.
And we do rigorous
tracking of the jobs
because it's a really important
part of the validation of why
states are investing in this
technology and supporting it.
So I think that's
a game changer.
I don't mean to suggest that
it doesn't matter, though.
And I think if you
look at, again,
that sort of arc and
the story that I'm
telling, having committed
public policy that
makes long-term investments
is really critical.
And that's been part of
what's been successful,
Massachusetts investing in
New Bedford over a decade ago.
But realizing the benefits of
that now, where, for example,
we have multiple other
offshore wind ports
that are now being constructed
or under construction
and soon to be completed
in Massachusetts to support
the offshore wind industry-- so
we made the first investment,
and others have followed.
And, again, you see that
up and down the East Coast.
And I can go into specifics for
other states if it's helpful.
And so I think with a supportive
federal administration
and supportive states-- and we
aren't seeing states really slow
down.
Part of the reason I think
they're not slowing down
on offshore wind is
that there aren't
a lot of good alternatives
to decarbonize dense load
centers on the East Coast
of the United States.
I think we could talk
about possibilities.
But the way I look at it
and have spent a lot of time
looking at it over
the years, I do
think offshore wind is
absolutely needed in order
for us to be able to get
to a clean electricity
grid from New England down
through the mid-Atlantic
for sure.
So there's a lot to
be positive about even
despite the challenges that
we continue to navigate.
And I'm really excited to see
so many people paying attention
to the industry.
It's a joy to try and paint
a picture of what's really
happening for people,
sharing pictures
like these that are reality.
Maybe some of you have
driven by a New Bedford,
and you've seen these things.
I mean, they're massive.
The other one is if you take
the Acela between New York
and Boston, you see
the New London Pier.
And they have offshore wind
turbine components there
in and out.
And it's really fun to see.
When I'm on the
Acela with my kid,
I'm pressing my face
up against the glass.
And everybody's like, what
the heck are they looking at?
But these are tangible
signs that we are actually
taking steps to decarbonize the
electric grid for the future.
It's not happening fast enough.
And we have definitely had
setbacks along the way.
But we're starting to
put the pieces together.
And I have a lot of
thoughts about how
we can make this next chapter
the one where we do things
faster and don't have so
many of the same challenges
that we've had.
But I think I'll leave
it there and maybe
get into the discussion.
All right.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
OK, thanks.
So we're going to sit in the
front here and do a little chat.
And please email in--
I don't know where the--
the QR code up there to--
you can show how to do--
I think it was--
--with your phones.
--back here, right?
There we go.
Look at that.
So you can send
questions in that way.
So thank you again
for the nice talk
and for your hard
work over many years,
in many roles, all culminating
to this important project.
And maybe you can comment, what
do you think in the long term--
what are the most important
ways that energy markets
have to change to support
these large-scale deployments
of offshore wind and other
large, large projects like this?
Yeah, I mean, the
energy market question
is one that I think
we've gotten hung up
on quite a bit over the years.
And it's not an
easy one to solve.
So, again, the states that
we're talking about primarily--
and I hope I don't go
too far into the weeds--
but are in what we consider
regulated electricity
markets, where you have,
essentially, wholesale markets
really premised on
competition and, by and large,
merchant power sales that rely
on those markets to function.
And then here comes
offshore wind along
with some other renewables and
says, well, that doesn't really
work for us.
We need certainty.
We need a 20-year contract,
a 30-year contract.
And the states have
gone along with that,
which has teed up a
bit of a collision
between competitive
wholesale electricity markets
and long-term contracting.
As I said, I think
to some degree,
I think, we've maybe
overworried about that.
And we'll see whether that
turns out to be right or wrong.
But, essentially,
right now we're
in such a cyclical upturn
in the need for power
that having multiple
avenues to do
that, including the
existing wholesale energy
markets plus new contracting
efforts, seems to make
seems to make sense.
There's been quite
a lot of discussion
about carbon pricing in those
wholesale electricity markets.
And that is something
that the New England
ISO has studied
extensively, New York ISO
has studied extensively.
It is a good idea
and could work.
And it has zero political
support and essentially
no chance of happening
any time soon.
So I think people aren't
wrong to point out
the benefits of carbon pricing.
It would be there.
But we're not in
a political moment
right now where we can afford
to wait for something like that
to come along.
And so our pitch
to the states is
to continue to put in place the
contract structures that will
allow projects to move forward.
We have lots of specific ideas
about how those contracts should
be structured.
I think, interestingly,
one of the things
that you hear
increasingly from the ISO,
who's in charge of grid
reliability here in New England,
is that we hear a lot about
winter reliability and gas
pipeline constraints
because we're
at the end of the pipeline.
And in the winter gas supply
gets taken up for heating.
And then there's not
enough for electricity.
But the biggest thing we
can do to shore up winter
reliability is to build as
much offshore wind as we can.
ISO New England has been
pretty increasingly clear
about that in recent years,
which is extremely helpful.
So you have to think about
it from the multiple angles
of reliability, affordability,
and also decarbonization,
which under the
current construct,
those wholesale markets
aren't really legally allowed
to take cognizance of.
So we're in a bit of
an imperfect situation,
I would say, with the contracts
maybe not fitting neatly
in competitive wholesale
market structure.
But I think on balance,
that's where we need to be.
Maybe just two follow
ups about that.
So one is, it seems like
the offshore wind is maybe
analogous to nuclear that it
needs gigantic amount of capital
upfront and, therefore,
some special arrangement
in the market.
It's not the same as a little
merchant gas turbine coming in.
But then I'm wondering why you
think the carbon pricing would
be so impossible.
I mean, the state legislature
able to intervene, set up
a market that's going to
make it possible for the wind
to come in--
you'd think they could also
intervene and do whatever they
wanted with the carbon pricing?
I mean, again, I think it's one
that kind of perplexes people
at an intellectual level because
there's a lot of rationale
for those arguments.
And, again, you have
credible neutral entities
like ISO New England or New
York ISO making those arguments
and saying, this would
be a good way to do this.
But what we've seen-- and it's
been in New England states
and New York and down
in New Jersey as well--
to your point about
nuclear is some
of those plants needing to
get state contracts in order
to keep operating.
And in many cases,
those contracts
have been justified on the
basis of retaining jobs,
frankly, which tend to
be a little bit more
politically motivating than
more esoteric discussions
about the needs of
the electric grid.
At least that's been
somewhat my experience.
I can't say for sure exactly why
carbon pricing hasn't taken off.
I'm sure we all have our
own theories about it.
So I know when I was working
in New York for the governor's
office there, they looked at,
for example, carbon pricing
ballot initiatives
in other states,
including Washington
State-- maybe some of you
have followed-- had, I
think, three different times
taken a carbon pricing
ballot initiative to voters
and failed every time.
It's just really considered
politically unpopular.
It's like a gas tax or
something like that.
I was thinking not for
general carbon tax.
Just in electricity, it seems
like the consumers apparently
aren't aware of what
controls electricity prices.
So let's put the carbon tax
in there just as a way to--
I think, at the end of
the day, the governors
have to get
comfortable with that.
And I think that's
been a hard sell.
Changing topics, what are some
of the important research areas
that you think that
MIT and the engineers
here should be working on?
Great.
Yes.
And I meant to say
at the beginning--
I'm always so nervous to
speak to an audience like this
because I am not a scientist.
I'm not a technologist.
And I can't answer
very detailed questions
about offshore wind technology.
I'm definitely more on
the business, commercial,
and policy side of things.
But we do support--
and in my prior
roles-- and, in fact,
I was just talking to DOE
yesterday or something
about what is most impactful to
industry in terms of R&D funding
and what are the
challenges that we need.
And there are a bunch.
It's an extremely long list.
I would say, for
example, going back
to the Vineyard
offshore portfolio,
looking at California
and West Coast markets.
Floating technology is a
place where a lot of R&D
is still really needed.
That's a newer
technology globally,
where, again, fixed bottom,
more traditional offshore wind
has been deployed.
There's 40 gigawatts built in
China, 20 in the EU, another 15
the UK, I mean, massive
numbers, lots of projects,
whereas floating
is still-- we're
talking about a
handful of projects
and a small number of megawatts.
So in order for that
technology to catch up--
and that's everything from
constructability of the floating
platforms, how do you get
manufacturing and port
infrastructure that can actually
handle those types of logistics?
What's the anchoring technology
at various water depths?
Truly, you could go
on and on and on.
And it is a big focus of DOE
to continue to advance floating
technology, which will be
helpful to that next generation
globally.
But even for our projects
on the East Coast,
there's interesting
R&D happening around
how vessels, frankly, do their
work in a market like the US,
where we're a bit
constrained to the Jones Act.
I don't know if people
know what the Jones Act is.
But, essentially, it
places restrictions
on having workers on
foreign flagged vessels.
And, again, the
vessels that we rely
on in the offshore wind industry
to date are foreign flagged.
There is a single wind
turbine installation vessel
under construction in the US.
That'll be the first.
It's not done yet.
And so you have to come up with
creative feeder barge systems
to move components to
and from these vehicles
without going back to shore
in the US, which is not
allowed under the Jones Act.
And so there's actually
very interesting research
and demonstration projects
around things like that.
Grid integration and getting to
better points of interconnection
and more seamless
interconnection of offshore wind
to a grid that
really wasn't built
to take offshore
wind in the places
where it's going to
go near the coast,
that's another place that we've
been urging DOE to take action.
And I should say that DOE
recently awarded the New England
states almost $400
million for this power
up proposal to actually
do a number of things.
But this also includes
new substations
for offshore wind
injection capacity
that DOE will be funding under
the Bipartisan Infrastructure
Law.
So those are some of the
things that we see as needs
and addressing real pain
points that we have today.
That's great.
Maybe we can talk
about the blades.
Everybody wants to talk
about the broken blade.
So we recognize that
the blade is not really
a major issue from the
environmental point of view.
There's some cleanup.
But compared to
other things, it's
really pretty small potatoes.
But I do wonder, what does
it mean for your development
schedule for your project?
And, particularly,
I think that GE also
has another blade break in UK?
So it suggests that
maybe something's
wrong with the design,
or I don't know.
So, again, I'm not trying to
minimize the blade break, which
is a real setback
and, gosh, really just
unfortunate on a
number of levels.
So as you alluded to,
GE is the manufacturer
of the wind turbines, including
the blades that are being
installed on Vineyard Wind.
They are also deploying those
same blades and turbines
on a project in the
UK called Dogger Bank,
where they did have, in
fact, two other blades break
this summer.
Those have gotten some attention
here because of their connection
to what happened at
Vineyard Wind in Europe.
They've gotten very
little attention
from the public, which is just
its own interesting contrast
to how we react to
incidents in the US
versus other parts of the world.
Each of those, GE has provided
some information publicly
about the cause.
And they are not
actually connected.
So there were no installation
issues and error basically
in lifting the blade in
one case on Dogger Bank.
But the issue at Vineyard
Wind GE has disclosed
is a manufacturing error.
So there was
insufficient bonding.
The blades are-- they're made
of fiberglass, foam, and wood,
very similar to boats,
extremely similar to boats.
So, again, it is unfortunate to
have that debris in the ocean.
But there's actually quite
a lot of similar debris
already in the ocean,
which is not a good thing.
But it is the reality of it.
Every time people do maintenance
on boats and other things,
there's a lot of similar
debris that can occur.
And so that's something
that we are still
assessing the full ramifications
of in terms of the manufacturing
issue that has been identified.
The safety regulator,
federal safety regulator,
is highly involved.
And we are going
through a process
to re-review and inspect every
single blade on the project.
And we don't have
a certain timeline
for when that will
be complete, which
means I don't have a
certain timeline for when
the project will be complete.
I hope you--
I think it should be next year.
I just don't know--
I just don't know which month.
To what extent has local
support for offshore wind
and for the associated
industry and jobs
helped with the construction
of Vineyard Wind?
And during the Cape Wind
era, the local opinion
was the opposite way.
And it caused a lot of
trouble for that project.
Can you talk about--
Yeah.
--the public perception
in the local community?
I think it's super important.
And it's definitely
not monolithic.
There's a lot of
different views out there.
But it is really relevant.
And it comes up in
terms of a project.
I'm thinking not just
about Vineyard Wind.
But as we're developing
our next projects,
can we get host
community agreements
where we need to land the cable?
Can you get local permits?
And it is really important.
It plays into the federal
permitting process.
And I think our company
actually really tries
to pride ourselves on
what we call a community
first development approach.
And we focus on
purposeful partnerships.
And so when we brought
forward our recent bid that
went in New York
about a week ago,
we had over 100
letters of support
from different organizations
and communities
and elected officials that
were supportive of the project.
And that takes a lot of work.
Typically, where we've seen
the opposition historically,
there's some view
shed opposition.
And that is still a thing.
There is also concern
from the fishing industry
about impacts of offshore
wind on restricting
the areas at which
they can do their work.
I think it's really
cool to point out
and not super well known.
But we've actually hired
a ton of fishing vessels
on the Vineyard wind project.
They do things for us in terms
of servicing the project.
They also help with--
we have requirements
under our federal
permits to monitor
for protected species, the
North Atlantic right whale
but also others.
And so we hire fishing
vessels to be out there
and be our eyes and ears
for protected species.
So there is economic opportunity
for fishing industry,
in addition to mitigation
payments that we also make
available from the project.
So that's one version.
There is a--
I want to address it.
There's a lot talk
about whale impacts.
That's something that
increasingly comes up
in the media.
And I'll be pretty
blunt about this.
By and large, it's
just fake news.
That is just fake news.
There has been a
tremendous amount
of purposeful
disinformation that's
being shared about whale
impacts or whale deaths
from offshore wind, none
of which has been verified.
It's been reviewed.
I mean, every
allegation has been
reviewed by federal
officials at NOAA, so
the National Oceanographic and
Atmospheric Administration.
Many independent
researchers at universities
have been reviewing
the evidence.
And it's just not there.
There's a couple different
versions of the story
that you hear.
One is that the vessels
are making too much noise.
And that's harming the whales.
The other is just
that, I don't know,
the vessels are striking
the whales or something
like that as part of pile
driving or something.
And there's truly
not much behind that.
What there has been
validation of is-- actually,
Brown University put out a study
that's fascinating on this,
tracing a lot of
the whale stories,
and I'm just going to say,
tied it back pretty clearly
as part of an
investigative effort
to fossil fuel funded
industry efforts.
And there is a very purposeful
disinformation campaign
on offshore wind and whales.
And I don't say that lightly.
I'm not just making
an idle allegation.
You can go to the
Brown University study.
It's been written
up in The Boston
Globe and numerous other
credible media outlets.
There's an agenda here to fight
change, fight energy transition,
fight progress.
And one of the--
I don't think I would have
imagined this or foreseen
it a few years ago.
But one of the tactics that
they've really centered on
is trying to highlight this
potential impact to whales.
I have to say, I've
learned multiple examples
of dirty politics
in clean energy.
It's really a little
disheartening, actually.
But I we have dirty
politics in a lot of things.
So maybe that shows us
part of the mainstream now.
Will the power grid and
transmission infrastructure
be ready if you guys really
do build 8 gigawatts?
Is that a thing?
It's a thing.
Yeah.
I would say there's a lot
of work going into that.
But we do have work to do.
And I mentioned, for
example, the power up
proposal where, again, some
utilities and others are
trying to build new
substation infrastructure.
There are transmission
projects in New York that
have been greenlighted,
both on Long Island
and in New York City,
to hardened transmission
infrastructure specifically
to allow for offshore wind.
So those things are happening.
They also take time.
Building a new substation,
building new transmission
on Long Island,
that's not something
that happens overnight.
And so if those projects
are significantly
delayed for one
reason or another,
that definitely poses
a risk to the delivery
of the offshore wind power.
Again, I think this is a larger
issue for the renewables energy
industry.
Everybody hears a lot talk
about transmission, for example,
and the transmission needs.
And we know that FERC is
taking on these issues.
They've issued significant
orders on queue reform.
Queue reform is an
important aspect of this
as well, making
sure that there's
realistic timelines for projects
to be able to interconnect.
So a lot is happening there.
If it doesn't go well, there
is potential cause for concern.
But I'm heartened that I know,
again, the federal government,
the states are putting resources
to this, to try and solve
this challenge too.
[INAUDIBLE] just a
question on [INAUDIBLE].
Could we [INAUDIBLE]?
Sure, go ahead.
Sorry.
I work on that a lot.
So is there a way to invest
in utilizing the existing
grid better now?
Instead of [INAUDIBLE]
You get these $200 billion
dollar [INAUDIBLE] from
New York and so forth would
take 10 years.
But a lot of researchers at MIT
are looking into better software
to use in a more flexible
way, [INAUDIBLE] and so forth.
Can you comment on that?
Yeah, I mean, I think, I'm
glad you're working on it,
I guess, is my comment
because absolutely.
There is a lot to squeeze
out of the existing grid.
And, exactly, if you can squeeze
more out of the existing grid
or make it more efficient--
AI poses significant
new opportunities
to get better
visibility, for example,
on the electric grid
that could help reduce
some of the need for upgrades.
All of that needs to happen
and, again, I think, would
be squarely in that category
you asked about before,
what should researchers
be working on?
What should DOE or other
government funders like NYSERDA
be funding?
Again, we have such
a challenge building
infrastructure in this country.
And, again, offshore wind
is one version of that.
But we have many
versions of it that I
think the more we can utilize
existing infrastructure,
for sure the better.
And maybe you can
talk about that.
How is your company using AI and
sensors and other modern tools
to try to make your
operation work better?
Yeah, so we're doing
some small things.
And I think we're, again,
monitoring the status of it.
But, for example, as part of our
recent bid into Massachusetts,
we partnered with the Engine--
so I don't know how
many people here
are connected with the
Engine in some way--
but, obviously, sponsored by MIT
originally but also partnered
with a couple of
the companies that
are funded by the
Engine that might
have applicable technologies.
And so we've made
commitments to work with them
during the course of
development of our project
to see whether their technology
would be ready and available
for our project.
One is actually on a different
topic, is a company called
Sublime systems that's
working on low carbon cement.
And there is, again, cement
and various components
of our operations.
And we've been working with them
to see whether we'd be able to,
again, try to reduce
the overall carbon
footprint, obviously,
of our infrastructure
by utilizing that technology.
Another company's
called VEIR, essentially
trying to make transmission
lines more efficient as well.
So those are not--
we haven't got to the
finish line on those things.
But we're very open to that.
And hopefully other
developers are
looking at those
opportunities too
because we're going to
have to try some of this
out and get some
advancement in real time
as we look to
build the industry.
Great.
Maybe for a minute
you can try to pretend
that as of January
22 or something,
somebody in administration
calls you up and says,
what policy should we put in?
Do you have a suggestion.
What do you think?
Yeah.
If I had just one
thing and it was
a new federal administration--
I think that's
what you're asking.
The pace of permitting
for these projects, this
has been the challenge all the
way back to Cape Wind, in fact.
But we haven't gotten
where we need to be.
And so I would say, better
funding the permitting agencies
that are doing work
on these projects
as well as trying to
streamline that process,
that would be my
single biggest ask.
There's a lot of things
that need maturity.
Maybe another technology need--
this isn't exactly
that question.
But just going
back to that is, I
mentioned how we have
fishing vessels looking
for protected species.
We had an experience
on Vineyard Wind
last summer where there was
significant fog, just unusually
large amounts of fog.
And then there was also
the Canadian wildfires.
That all significantly
reduced visibility
and inhibited our ability
for those protected species
observers to do their job and to
identify any marine species that
might be in the area, which
actually stopped construction
because we weren't able to meet
the permit condition to do that.
So we've been pressing
in those conversations
with federal permitting
agencies better ability
to rely on drones or other
remote sensing technology.
Other technology-based
solutions that
won't be defeated by fog or
wildfires is the kind of thing
that, we've got to try and
move our permitting processes
and our environmental
protection processes
into the more modern
phase, I would say.
All right, well, I
want to thank you again
for helping to move us
all in the modern phase.
And I'm looking forward
to using your electrons.
Yes.
Thank you.
Yeah, thanks.
[APPLAUSE]
And before you leave, I
just wanted to announce,
our next speaker
would be October 16.
It's a Congressman whose
name I forgot now--
Sean Casten.
Sean Casten--
Cool.
--from Illinois,
who was previously--
That's great.
--in clean energy
industry before
he got elected to Congress.
He'll be coming, talking.
We'll have announcements
about that.
The following day,
I think, October 17,
if I have the date right, is
the public on-campus discussion
of our fusion report about the
opportunities for fusion energy
and what conditions have to
be satisfied for fusion energy
to really help decarbonize
the electricity grid.
And right now, I want
to invite you all
to come join us for some
refreshments outside
and some further chat
with the speaker.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]