Uh next we're going to hear from Ania
Kamargo who is uh associate director of
thermal networks at the building
decarbonization coalition to talk about
that rapidly evolving policy landscape.
And there's a little clicker.
>> And there's clicker up there, I think.
>> All right.
>> Okay. Hi. Good afternoon, everyone. Um,
so I you see I have geo there in
parenthesis and that is because most of
the legislation that has the legislation
that's passed to date uses the term uh
thermal energy network. So you will be
hearing me say that, but in general I'm
talking about the broad category of both
geothermal energy networks and thermal
energy networks. And I'm just going to
give you a picture of what's happening
nationally.
So here is how a bill becomes law. This
is real. Um it is just never a straight
line. It's very messy. And the reason
why it's messy is kind of what delegate
Shakudin was saying. It's about bringing
stakeholders together with different
interests and making sure that all of
their interests are being met. So rarely
does the start end up like the finish.
But the really good news with uh thermal
networks is that states are learning
from each other. So this is coming
becoming a little less muddy and uh
legislation is moving really fast.
Um so again I'm going to start with this
one on like what's the general journey
that we're seeing in legislation and
again I have the word utility up there
because the only uh anyone can build a
thermal network right now uh
municipality lots of colleges and
universities a hospital anyone except
for a regulated utility. And so we have
to pass legislation to allow gas and
electric or water companies to sell
thermal or to build thermal networks. So
the way it starts is exactly like uh
delegate Shudian said it's in all the
states that were working or that are
passing this legislation. It's really a
group of advocates. In her case, she was
the legislator who started, but then she
worked with all the people here. As you
heard this morning from Kelsey, it
started with mothers out front. Um and
then the underpinning of this for the
legislation that has passed so far is
that all of the states so eight bills
have passed all of the states have
significant climate commitments of at
least reducing total emissions by 75% or
more um and greening the grid um so RPS
commitments and seven out of the eight
that have passed have future of gas
proceedings meaning the regulators have
said hey gas companies how are you going
to meet these commitments so this is
what's happened to date, not necessarily
will happen in the future, but this is
the kind of bills are very attached to
our missions. Um, once legislation
passes, there's a whole process that
kicks off with the regulators, which you
will hear after me from Sher Van
Nostrin, but it's a it's a kind of a
negotiation between the utilities and
the regulators looking at the
legislation that passed, saying, "Okay,
what needs to happen for us to be able
to move forward?" At the same time,
you're going to have to be working on
the, you know, the workforce, supply
chain, making sure there's community
outreach, etc. And then you can get to
construction. Um, so so far only one
project, which is here in Massachusetts,
has made it through construction. And
all of the bills that have passed uh
require data collection and pilot
evaluation. So this is this is again,
every state is different, but this is
the broad thing that we're seeing across
the state that gets uh legislation
passed. And here are the eight bills um
the eight states that have passed.
They're listed there on the right. Uh
you will notice uh 2021 Massachusetts
passed the first bill that allowed uh
network geothermal. And just this year
2024 four bills passed as well as
several states did another round of
passing legislation. Uh and then you see
there dark blue considering legislation.
Actually uh just this month already five
new states have filed legislation. So,
we are expecting this to continue to
grow.
And this, you don't need to read this.
Uh, it's just to give you a sense of
what's in these bills. You see the
states across the top, and you can sort
of see what the provisions are. And the
key thing about here is the states are
learning from each other. And this is on
our website, so you can check it out.
Um, all right. So, now I'm going to
combine it. Like, what does this all
mean? And it's really about how does the
the technology and the stuff on the
ground relate to the legislation and the
regulation. So here's a great uh diagram
that heat put together. It's a gas
system. And you can see that very cute
little section of green. That's the
thermal network. And so this is the
demonstration. All eight bills uh either
allow or mandate pilot. So everyone is
starting with demonstration. So what's
the kind of uh work that comes with
that? The bills include
um a whole series of things that are
about these pilots, right? So the
definitions uh ownership is really
interesting in starting with New York.
The the legislation actually says gas
and electric utilities can own and
operate thermal energy networks. And
then several of the states after that
implemented the same thing. Uh
Massachusetts, we just passed
legislation 2024 that allows the selling
of thermal energy by the gas utilities.
Um some include environmental
protections, labor standards. You just
heard from Ryan in New York, that group
of advocates, one of the core uh members
of that group of advocates were labor
leaders. And so they're very strong
labor standards in the New York bill
that are about the geothermal workforce
in general, but also about the existing
gas for uh workforce and how that how
they're going to be transitioned as part
of this um consumer protection. I should
say also environmental justice in there
that uh many of the bills again starting
with New York require at least one pilot
to be in an environmental justice
community and uh several of them say
that they the customer should not have
to pay more than what they're currently
paying on their bills. All of them
include cost recovery. So the pilots can
go through the rates, but the issue is
what's included. And so the states vary
in that. Here in Massachusetts,
everything could go through the rates.
In California, for example, all of the
behind the meter costs, which are pretty
significant, all the retrofits uh
cannot. And so they're struggling with
how we're going to pay for that. Um and
then pilot data collection and
reporting. I guess I already said
they're all doing this anyway. So this
is sort of how this works. Next step
um is development. And this is now where
we're starting here in Massachusetts.
It's like you grab what you learned from
that first pilot and now we're
expanding. And how's that going to work?
And so through that, some of these bills
are starting to pass and there's some
conversations. Um interim rate design,
how are we going to design the rates to
deal with this? Uh amending the
obligation to serve. This is a huge one.
Many states file legislation to try to
change this. and a full uh I I I'm going
to explain what that is, which is if any
one of those little house green houses
says, "No, I want to stay on gas." It
means that the gas system has to stay,
you can't pull it back. And so amending
it so that the gas um utilities can
expand their service to not just be
about gas, but also to be or to sell
thermal energy allows them to then say,
"Okay, we're going to provide you
heating and cooling, but it's not going
to be with gas." And so so far two
states have touched that. Uh Washington
state for thermal energy networks are
allowed to meet the obligation to serve
with thermal. And California has a
really interesting one where they said
60% if 60% of a street or the segment
that they're taking the gas pipe out of
says that they want a thermal network
then they're allowed to meet the
obligation to serve that way. Um gas oh
so then uh joint electric planning. This
is uh our commissioner uh chair van will
talk about this but basically the one of
the biggest benefits of putting in these
thermal networks is the impact on the
electric grid and so being able to have
that joint planning and prioritizing of
where these things should be built is
really important and so we're starting
to see that already and not only in
Massachusetts but elsewhere and thinking
of okay which like if you're going to
replace a pipe that's an obvious place
uh if you if you're going to build a
substation an electric substation
because you're running out of capacity.
Maybe that's a great place. So, that's
starting. Um, and then of course the
full system transition, which is what we
all want, is going to require a lot
more. And this uh really hasn't started.
I mean, we've filed some of this this
cycle for two years from now here in
Massachusetts. But creating a thermal
market, allowing folks to buy and sell
energy, uh, integrating utilities, gas,
electric, and potentially even water.
like water has the water utilities also
have a lot of thermal energy. Uh waste
heat recovery, how is what's the what
are the rules going to be around that?
Uh tactical transition plans for whole
cities and regions. And so this idea
that you can map out, you know, how old
your pipe is, you know, what's going to
have to be taken down, what's going to
make the most sense for everything and
how can we transition the whole system
thinking 10 years ahead and not just
five or two. Um and then the final rate
design you know still in consideration
and I I'm involved in a few dockets
across the country in some places the
combination of the electric I mean I'm
sorry of the thermal and geo rate makes
a lot of sense right it's being covered
by all the customers some folks are
fighting that and saying no it should be
by itself and then in New York there's
one utility who's saying it should be
covered by both gas and electric because
the electric customers are the ones that
are most benefiting. Um I I talked about
allowable cost recovery and then big is
the the voided cost uh uh integration
into the thermal networks because what
is happening is that the that benefit on
the electric grid means that we're not
going to have to build out the electric
grid but the costs are on the network
geothermal installer like so so the
benefits and the costs are not aligned
and so we have to figure out how to do
that. Um, so that's sort of how the
policy and this thing is we're hoping
it's going to roll out. Um, and I just
want to say remember only eight states
have passed legislation, but this map
looks a lot better than that, which is
utilities across the country are really
interested in doing this. Um, regardless
of whether legislation has passed or
not, this is the a map of the utility
net geo collaborative and both blues are
actually members of that collaborative.
Um and uh they are basically exploring
the exploring what this looks like for
them. And the the maps the light blue is
states where at least uh one utility has
filed a pilot. So far there's been 22
pilots filed with the regulatory
commission. And then I just also want to
end with this map which I hope you'll
all check out because you can click on
what type of owners, what the status is
and the type of thermal networks and
just see that actually we have a lot of
projects in this country and that
there's huge opportunity for learning
across projects and that is everything.
[Applause]