The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Before we move on to the rest of the
topics, uh maybe just a some
administrative stuff about the next
assignment. Uh so the idea is to model a
system right? Uh so the idea is to pick
some sort of the old system. Um
in the past people have picked stuff
like applying for college because they
knew all about that. Uh they you know
people have talked about uh an example I
give is you know running a nuclear
reactor or something. That's basically
there's a there's a uh but hey, you
know, if if any of you are new to
science majors, you know,
>> Oh, perfect. Okay. All right. Well, one
of one of my favorite 2 games was was
actually uh nuclear reactor simulation.
It always melted down. That's why it was
fun. Awesome. Um but yeah, you know,
pick pick a real world system to model
um to start uh modeling. Obviously,
you're trying to find a fun. Obviously,
you're trying to make something that
people are going to enjoy playing. Uh uh
but the the idea is to start from a
slightly different place from where we
had uh uh um in the first assignment.
Now, a couple of you guys already did
that for the first assignment though. I
mean, things like picking up girls at a
party. I mean, you're modeling real
system in a sense. Uh still haven't
played the genealogy game yet. So So, so
we're going to play that tomorrow. So,
so
we'll see that. Um the the survival
horror game I would say is not a real
world system.
>> It was a system.
>> Tasers.
>> Yeah. Or wizards enemies.
>> But uh so so yeah, pick pick something.
Um uh we've seen games um uh negotiating
around like negotiating uh greenhouse
gas emissions. There was there was one
uh which was really really cutthroat as
you'll probably imagine.
>> Yeah.
>> Um actually I'll try to I'll try to get
the team to come in late in the semester
to talk about the card game. Uh this was
a freshman team on Periscope.
Um let's see. Uh you on Wednesday we're
going to do the usual brainstorming
exercise in the second half of the of
the class. You know everybody throw out
your ideas come in with a bunch of
ideas. We'll try to build on that. Um
but uh this time around you're allowed
to actually pre-build your team. You
you're allowed to to to ask people, you
know, hey, you guys want to work
together? Um you don't actually have to
like figure it out on the spot if you
don't want to. Um I don't really care
how you do it as long as by Friday you
know who your team is. Um and and who's
on team sizes are are the same.
So
any questions? Are we able to simulate
things that aren't from like this era?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Like like from history?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Not from like the future.
>> Oh,
>> no.
Future.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Sure. It's like this is how
things are going to work.
>> Well, well, I mean I mean Okay. So, so
yes. Yes. Absolutely. Historical stuff.
Uh um and but you do have some
liberties. Uh I'm not saying that your
game has to be a faithful simulation. Am
I getting a little bit more into
simulation? say um but it doesn't have
to be a faithful simulation necessarily
of what you're talking but you know in a
sense you're trying to like capture the
spirit of it um you know if if if the
point is I'm running a nuclear reactor
and you can sort of capture the oh my
god it's so dangerous or the oh my god
it's so boring aspect of it uh have you
actually worked on nuclear reactor
>> well there
>> and I know like the mechanics of it but
I think there I I've been told it's not
necessarily the most exciting job in the
No. Yeah, you just sit there and do your
homework and every once in a while you
look up
very reasonable
>> and they get paid for like I know 12 or
13 bucks an hour or something.
>> Yeah. So, so you know if the whole idea
of the game is let's try try try to get
as much homework done without
>> that might be more entertaining than
just like
>> cool
critical
>> um
but I got my problems then
>> just plus one points you have to do
homework while you play
>> Wow
Terrible be the worst game Whatever.
What happens if you
>> guys
may be too meta at that point?
>> And besides, but I think we still have a
time limit like half an hour or
something like that. You know, it's like
homework.
>> We have really easy homework.
>> Um, let's see. Just a reminder for
everyone who hasn't uh who's been
falling off on the forum post, please
make sure that you keep up on your forum
post. Those things actually do affect
your grade. Uh so um again we're
expecting one in person not one team. Uh
so if you have any uh opinions since
we're in between reading uh assignments
right right now you can write about the
assignment but if you wrote up something
let's say a reflection on how the past
assignment went. You know that that's
fine. We're not expecting more than one
forum post a week. Of course, feel free
to comment on other people's forum posts
as well. And those if you want to like
if you if there's a discussion or a
point that's been raised that's kind of
interesting and you want to kind of
develop on that, you know, put some
thought into it. Write something
interesting that's going to keep on the
conversation that that counts too. Um
and and that's fine.
Okay. So, puddles. Um
so, Brenda's Okay. So actually before I
start the renders, let's let's start
with Scott's Scott. What what what were
some of the definitions or some of the
things that Scott King was mentioning
that were good for puzzle design?
>> I was reading
>> that was in the book or not in the book.
>> Uh this was the the the web page
>> web page
difficulty
>> fun and has the right answer.
>> Yeah,
>> that's actually a solution. Yeah. could
actually create.
>> He he he he didn't really differentiate
between like kind of like puzzles that
could be generated uh you know like a
sudoku or something where you have you
kind of have an algorithm that lets you
create multiple puzzles and but as long
as that that particular iteration had
right answer. Uh so that was really
fair. Um anything else you remember
talked a lot about difficulty.
>> Mhm. make it accessible but not super
easy,
>> right?
>> And targeting a specific audience.
>> There's also the ability to uh change
the difficulty. Was it dynamic
difficulty?
>> Uh so some areas may actually be easier
easier settings and then actually what
they want it to be in harder settings.
>> I think that was Brenda's but yeah.
There's there's also the distinction
between sort of like type of difficulty
like you know things where
>> you know the letter puzzle that he has
at the beginning where it requires
>> sort of like thinking about it figuring
out how
>> yeah it's it's it was patience versus
something else I can remember
>> but then you have things like mazes
where it's all patience where you have
to like be very like careful and and
your way through
>> and sometimes they're like bringing in
information from from other domains from
outside from outside of the console it's
just like all the information that is
currently in the puzzle. Um
uh but but the interesting thing about
the puzzle that he particularly shows is
that he shows a range of different ways
to actually solve it. None of which are
actually satisfying except for that
final answer which which he irritatedly
does not tell you like gives you another
puzzle.
Um but um you know it's kind of
interesting to think about actually
what's the audience for those kinds of
specific puzzles. I mean there there are
magazines out there like games magazine
in particular but um sometimes you see
um stuff nestled into magazines um uh
that are not just about games. you see
stuff like cross word puzzles and
newspapers and everything like that and
now things like Sudoku and all that are
becoming way more popular um that are
you know that are meant to be really
really mass audience whereas a magazine
that is specifically targeted at puzzle
enthusiasts can be like super hardcore
but of course if the whole magazine then
you can have like a whole range of
different difficulties in there you know
the the assumption that you can solve
something not so
>> out of interest does anybody know like
really actually know how people in
newspapers generate cross word puzzles
and pseudo puzzles? Like does anybody
know what the actual process behind that
is? Cuz I don't know, right?
>> I think
>> I mean I imagine how you might do it.
You might start with the filled out
thing and then like remove bits to get
your sudoku
>> or you might brute force dictionary
search to come up with words which fit
together in order for
>> what they do with sudoku now is they
have some like computer algorithm to and
has scales difficulty and it generates a
random sudoku puzzle from your input
powerful
>> sudoku is solved enough that you can
actually just algorithmically generate
for like
>> a an actual ual, you know, numerical
difficulty.
>> You scale it from, you know, like 1 to
10. 10 being where
>> where there's like literally only one
step to take at each point.
>> Oh, the one the one that takes three
months that took him three months to
solve or something.
>> But but like cross there's there's
people actually just get paid to sit
down and generate those.
>> Will shorts
times takes submissions from other
people. That's why it says edited by
Will Schwarz because people submit stuff
and then he kind of like just touches it
up.
>> So he he kind of crowdsources cross word
puzzle
>> generation. I'm sure I'm sure
>> in the past you had to created it own.
>> Yeah.
>> But I mean so the difficulty in a cross
word puzzle isn't just like in the sort
of geometric layout of how the words the
words go is the the specific clues that
they give you can be more or less
obuscated in some ways. And New York
Times in particular with this is, you
know, they they'll give you like two
words that don't that that with with no
grammatical context about how that's
supposed to fit in.
>> Well, it gets harder during the week.
So,
>> yeah.
>> Yeah. So, so so and and and so you you
you can actually compare and see how
that difficulty scaling is just by
looking at the clues, not even looking
at the puzzle itself. Um and of course
the other thing about crosswords is uh
you know just just to bring up a point
that we talked about in earlier class
you know it's that the cross words that
we're familiar with at least are
dependent on the redundancy of the
English language right you know there
you don't need every single letter in a
in of a word in order to figure out what
that word is so that if there's a word
that you couldn't otherwise have gotten
from the clue you can still get it just
by seeing the letters that are available
that's because English language is kind
of about 50% redundant information. If
you dropped every single vowel in in in
in a sentence, you could probably still
make out what that sentence said. And
you don't necessarily get that with
Chinese, for instance.
How many folks here have like some or
there probably are other languages here
where like every single character can
mean means a word or something like
that?
>> Hebrew has no vows, right?
>> Well, they do like third grade and they
start dropping them after that. So it's
basically because it is understandable
without vowels, you eventually just stop
using them.
>> Oh yeah. So that's interesting. If you
had a cross word in Hebrew that where
you expected to write in the words with
vowels, you probably could actually uh
do it one very similar to to an English
one.
>> It's difficult because the vowels in
Hebrew are attached to a letter, not a
separate character.
>> Below letters or barow.
>> No.
But you wonder if in the in a cross word
in a letter can make a different sound
with both.
>> Mhm.
>> Soft C or hard C
>> because a V can be vo or va or they you
don't know. You only know by context.
>> English like C could be a hard soft
>> or G could be J.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's true. that although in
English in particular the phonetic
meaning
the the way how a certain word is
pronounced isn't necessarily uh isn't
necessarily essential for solving a
puzzle puzzle unless the clues happen to
be phonetic clues you know sounds like a
fish uh so so so
that may not come in so much play when
it comes to English in particular
>> um Jason you had your hand up earlier
about
>> it There's going to be count
algorithmically generated.
>> Well, also one thing about algorithmic
about Sudoku difficulty, a lot of it
comes on the selective removal of
numbers. It's not what is the final
number, the final pattern going to look
like. That's actually the difficulty.
It's how do we remove the numbers in a
way that gives multiple possible answers
uh or multiple possible dead ends uh
because really there's only one solution
at the end of it. Um I'm not actually
familiar with the algorithm which does
so but it seems to be very clear that
there are at least two algorithms. One
of which is very easy which is just
provide a a legitimate pseudogu solution
and then one slightly harder is which
now which numbers to be removed so that
it's still solvable.
Um can people take picross? Um yeah,
>> some someone want to describe it for the
folks who haven't aren't familiar with
with with it. We can use the whiteboard.
>> Sure.
>> Um I think on the
>> I think the green one works better.
>> Yeah, I remember read
only familiar across 3D.
Yeah, that's the best way.
>> Sorry to put you on the spot.
>> The idea is that you'll have words and
poems
>> and then they'll have some number.
>> Oh, this
>> this one you fill in the blocks.
>> Okay. And then and then given this
information we have to work out which of
these blocks is filled and which can be
removed.
>> And the idea is that
>> the numbers
>> the number tells you the number of
blocks in that row or column which has a
filled block in it.
>> So it's like
>> so in this case like
>> they're also given
>> nothing in this column
this column and that column can have
anything in it. Um and this is probably
not actually example because it's
probably the numbers are
>> the subs are not the same.
>> But yeah,
>> so
you get the idea.
>> It's not going to work, but you get the
idea. And then things can get more
complicated. So the
>> additionally, if there's just I think a
three, then it means that there's a
connected block of three. So for
instance, this that and that might all
have to be. Um, but if there's a three,
which I think is in like a square or
something along these lines, that means
that there are three in that column, but
there's a gap in there somewhere. And
then if it's like a three in a circle or
something else complicated like that,
then it means that there are three, but
they all have gaps between
where they have a list of numbers and
those are the
>> there are consecutive blocks of that
length. Yeah.
>> So, so, so, so for one column you might
say like 2 three five which means there
is a block of two followed by a block of
three followed by a block of five
>> and they have to have a gap between them
>> and they will have a gap in between
them. So, it's not like if there's
actually a block of eight in there
somewhere.
>> But but that's the but the whole idea is
that you know you've got this um
information that that is actually
redundant. you know, you've got more
information in there than you
necessarily need to be able to figure
out which blocks in the solution should
be filled and when it should be empty,
but you know, it's presented to you in
this opuscated way. The the evidence the
the clues that are given to you in a way
that you know that requires you to
perform these algorithms in order to
figure out which one is created and
usually that's an algorithm that you can
use yourself. Uh although you know like
um I think Kim was the one who was
talking about pattern matching although
was
uh but you know eventually as you get
good at these things you start to you
you start to recognize patterns right
off the bat right like that's a zero oh
wow okay so that entire row is empty
that that that's that's that's the sort
of thing that you that becomes automatic
after you you you
>> um so let's see I'm not sure if I much
more to talk about Scott Kim, but you
know these are these are more like
generated stuff. Tip over has
so this is this basically is um it's
along the lines of what uh Scott Pin uh
is talking about, but obviously this is
more physical, not a pen and paper kind
of thing.
>> Can you move for the coffee yet?
>> Oh, move the coffee.
>> No, I just want you to look at this.
>> Okay, good.
Look at this first. Don't look at that.
Uh don't look at that. Um so the basic
idea is let me just start with one. Um
you get a card that's actually a a
puzzle. Um I wish we were doing this
outside now because I could have zoomed
this out. Um but the puzzle basically
just tells you how you're supposed to
set up your board initially. So there's
a Oops, wrong.
There's a green guy there. There's a
green guy there. This is supposed to be
an easy puzzle. I hope it is because I'm
really bad at this.
Red guy goes there, I think. Yeah. And
that's the puzzle.
And then and there's one with a little
square on it and then you have this
chat. What?
>> That's cool.
>> That's awesome. So the basic idea is you
tip over the pieces so that um so that
the guy moves um and you don't want to
be tipping over the pieces in a way
where uh the um where the guy can't move
anymore.
>> Um
>> yeah. So you're you're tipping over
things to make a path that he can walk
along, right?
>> Yeah.
>> And then make a closed loop
>> and he has to touch every piece.
>> I think he just has to get to this one
get to the red one. Um,
>> there's a plus mark.
>> So, knock it that way and then green
this way.
>> Yeah. Yes, I agree.
>> Yeah. I'm not exactly sure how to solve
this one.
>> So, yellow that way, green.
>> Yeah.
>> Yellow that way.
>> Wait, you're allowed to tip him over?
>> Yeah.
>> Did he die?
>> My understanding is that he needs to
fall onto another piece actually.
>> Oh, so let let me just confirm I set
this up right actually. Yeah, I did.
>> No. So, you push the yellow that way and
then the green that way and the other
green that way.
So with the yellow one goes.
>> So do the green ones first.
>> Yeah. I don't understand the rules for
yellow.
>> Exactly. And then
>> there.
>> No, it doesn't.
>> Yeah. I I
>> How does he
Yeah, he he's he's actually allowed to
move on anything that that's
continuously connected. So as long as
you can continuously
connect up to this, you're fine. So tip
tip the second green over.
>> So tip that first green.
>> No other way.
>> Yeah.
>> Doesn't that wrong path right now? If
you tip that.
>> Are you sure tipping over means move on
spot or not?
>> Well, if it doesn't then you can't reach
the red effort. Yeah, I am absolutely
sure it means that you're supposed to
tip it over in a way that might be a
>> screw. Tip the yellow over first and
move the move the guy onto the green,
then tip over the green.
>> Oh, right.
>> You think you are? I think you are.
>> What? Why?
>> That was crazy.
>> That was why That is why it's supposed
to be a beginner puzzle. You can
actually do it. You can actually do it.
This is This is why this is puzzle one.
>> Uh you don't have to fall on top of
anything.
>> It's bizarre.
>> Yeah. Like the instinct is you know you
want to build a path that you can walk
makes no sense.
>> Yeah.
>> The guy does not make any
>> but you know this is not entirely unlike
the kind of puzzle that Scott does. I
mean, sure, this is there's this one
particular uh uh piece of plastic that
uh that the game is designed to work
with, but basically it's just, you know,
it's like a book, right? It's like a
book of puzzles. Um
so there there are also solutions in
here, but I I find the solutions harder
to read than others.
>> Pad recognition was in the book.
>> Was it brand book?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, actually that's um
that's probably a good a good excuse to
switch over to Brenda's. Uh well,
actually before that I want to talk a
little bit about tangs. I mean everyone
play the tangs.
>> No. Okay. So, you know the basic idea is
you got these shapes. Um is this
magnetic? Yeah, it is.
>> Cool. Um, you've got these shapes and if
you assemble them right, as the box,
this is usually displayed on the side of
a box somewhere. Where the heck are we
on the inside?
>> I I've got a big P picture on the side
is that um you can actually fit all of
these uh shapes inside that square. So,
these are basically just a square that's
been divided in in in a specific way.
So
once I got this assembled, everyone can
just like pass this around. Anyone who's
already seen it can pass it on. That one
doesn't fit very well, but I think it's
cool now. Hey, that's tada. Hey, so this
is the basic set. This is No.
Um, this is now this is how it's been
sold at least is that this is actually a
calendar. So every day you get a
different shape.
>> It's a cute little thing. You know, some
of them have pretty rudimentary like
geometric shape. Some of them have like
I think this is supposed to be a sphinx
or some kind. Yeah, it looks like a
frog.
>> But this looks like a Pac-Man.
Um
you know and you know
um so the idea is that uh you know you
rearrange those particular shapes into
all of these different shapes and uh you
know it's it's you could play the game
without getting these puzzle solutions,
right? And Scott Ken talks about a lot
about like first if you've got a toy
that's worth playing with, now you've
got the beginning of something that
would be a good thing. The nice thing
about tipover is that it's kind of fun
to tip over things.
And the thing about tangs is that I
actually had more fun playing with tangs
than trying to solve specific problem
just like just trying to rearrange
these. Who hasn't seen these before?
Get a sense of
>> wow.
be ashamed to yourself
and uh
>> and all the work that you did is gone.
>> But that's the thing is that you know as
a toy you know it doesn't really matter
right because it's just it's just a it's
just a piece a set of pieces that can be
configuring anything and you kind of
want to take it apart and you know make
new shapes with it like little house.
Um,
so you know, if you've got something
that's kind of fun to fiddle with to
begin with, you've got possibly the
beginning of a game in general, uh, but,
uh, the way how Scott was talking about
it, there's this intermediate step where
it's a puzzle, you know, it's this it's
a toy with a specific solution that
you're trying to get to. And then gaming
is kind of like one step beyond that
where now there's like multiple
solutions and competitive uh at least
that's that's how he was constructing
it. He's not really a game theorist. He
just puzzles.
>> He talks about in terms of a goal,
right? So that with a toy that you don't
have a goal but then with a puzzle you
have
>> you have you have one goal with no
interaction and then a game is many with
interaction
>> and possibly multiple goals as well. I
don't know but but again it becomes more
and more directed whereas toy is very
free form. So, so there are people who
describe games uh like the Sims for
instance as actually toys, you know, and
in the same way that you describe a
dollhouse as a toy, the Sims is kind of
like the digital uh digital dollhouse.
But later versions of the Sims kind of
like added more and more specific roles
like you know and now you have to throw
a party with at least five people in it
uh or you have to attain career level
you know five or something like that. Um
I can't remember exactly how you how you
mentioned it but then that kind of like
has that whole we are going to give more
and more specific things for you to work
towards but it but the Sims is very
careful not to lose its toy sense the
sense of you can if you really wanted to
just dig around with these guys just go
right ahead just just just uh just uh uh
just play around with them and see what
happens. Um, so yeah.
>> Why is there a distinction for physical
objects between toys and games? But for
like video games like Minecraft is
technically still a game, but it's
different modes. Yeah,
>> I guess it has different modes, but it's
more of a toy. I think
>> I would say that that's entirely
marketing. That's the only reason is um
people haven't figured out how to sell
digital toys and there are games idolis
in like Best Buy and and so well there's
this fun thing I'm going to put in the
game section. Everyone starts calling it
games and that's kind of the same the
same thing with the Sims is like really
the Sims should be its own genre but you
can't sell its own genre that well. So
was there a hand over here?
Um,
okay. So, so that's um that's some of
the stuff with Brenda's uh uh with it
starts reading. First, let's move on to
Brenda's. Um, and she's very specific
about the kinds of puzzles that she's
talking about. There's these things that
get in the way of a very specific
narrative experience that a game wants
to you to to guide you through. She she
describes them more as roadblocks than
anything else. um but you know things to
sort of like make the challenge higher
but possibly so high that no one's going
to be able to get past it. Um, some of
her examples are things that come up as
sort of intermittent but optional
mechanics like hacking in bio in in in
Bioshock. And sometimes there are like
things that you have to solve. Uh,
especially in adventure games, there's
this you have to combine this object
with that object and bring it to a
specific location and then now you have
to, you know, uh, and now you you you
can proceed with whatever narrative
you've got. She had this spec this
specific axe to grind against.
puzzles having meaningful rewards or not
being completely blocking. So for
instance, she says you should never have
a a puzzle being required to open a
door. She said solve a puzzle and then
get some kind of tangible reward like or
something. This is after I spent like
the bus ride to New York City playing
Professor Leon
which was like nonstop. We found a door.
It's got a lock on it. looks like a
puzzle.
So, I wasn't entirely sure what to make
of that. I thought that like my
professor Leighton experience was fine
and I didn't need to get fat laton loot
from
>> that's that's actually something. Yeah.
And and uh there's a really good article
actually written by Clara over in our
lab that actually was an article. It was
a it was a transcript of the talk that
she gave at Austin GDC. I I'll send out
the link to everyone about how you can
integrate and why you should integrate
puzzles really really well in the
narrative. It's like really why is there
a puzzle in your game at all unless it's
been integrated into narrative. Um and
Brenda seems to be sort of providing a
cautionary
uh you know tale of the but if you do it
badly no one can get on with the story.
No one can enjoy the rest of the game.
Becomes this one thing that prevents you
from proceeding. Is there anyone who
kind of had that moment and then
>> about 5 minutes into mist
>> I think three
>> I don't know they had sort of some cool
like live action video and stuff and it
looked like it could be like an
interesting story and I was kind of
amused by the technological prowess of
integrating like video into 3D and then
suddenly I like looked into the picture
and I was on an island and and then
there was nothing happening and I had to
turn things to face each other and I
couldn't figure it out.
>> I definitely had that when I originally
played The Legend of Zelda the original
one where so I don't know if you don't
so they didn't tell you anything pretty
much. And so the temples you have, you
just walk around. There's something
that's like, okay, there's a tree in a
forest. You're supposed to cut, you're
supposed to burn this particular one.
And and there's the entrance to the to
this temple that you can't perceive
until you do this thing. And so it's
just like, how am I supposed to know
that I'm supposed to burn this
particular tree in the middle of this
huge map?
>> Did you beat any of the other
>> Yeah. And they didn't say anything. No,
I mean the others.
>> Yeah.
>> Actually, yesterday we are time again.
So,
>> I mean that tells you
>> I was just saying so the interesting
thing is so most people nowadays they
end up playing like the Ocarina of Time
and George Mass and start moving
backwards. So then end up playing Zelda
the first Zelda after having played
these old ones.
>> So you sort of know that you're expected
to do these random things to get like
across. So I feel like it's easier for
people. But then,
>> but with the original Zelda, the you
know how in new ones they have like it's
like let's say a wall you can blow up.
It's discolored or something. And the in
this one
>> every tree looks exactly the same. They
use the same sprites.
>> If I remember correctly though, it's
placed such that it's like in the center
of your screen, right? So it does look a
little bit different.
>> No, no,
>> it was like
>> it was just a random tree.
>> Band of trees.
>> Yeah, it was just a whole bunch of
trees.
And so you just you really just have to
get a whatever like a type of thing to
burn it and a specific one
>> and burn it. Usually that place is a
little suspicious. So I think there was
like a one tile column like you could
like navigate around just like this like
loop you just entered and was
suspicious.
>> I feel very frustrated by games that
like require walkthroughs in order to
play them. Sure. And that was the other
thing that she said that she suggested
some game designers do. They put the
solution in the the the Prima guide so
that you have to buy the Prima guide in
order to otherwise.
>> But it's also
deal with the
>> Well, you must have Oh,
>> yeah.
>> There's actually say official on the top
for a reason.
See, it's also ironic because modern
Zelda games like they they hold it's
very obvious that you have to use this
or that item.
>> You got a key. Use this key to open.
>> Oh, you got this item in the dungeon.
You had to use this item to kill the
boss. That sort of thing. Like it's
blatant.
>> Well, for people who are really really
hopeless, there's the little fairy.
>> Hey, listen. Listen. is usually less
less useful than
>> but I mean I mean so one big difference
between the old Zelda games and the new
Zelda games it's just this continual
refinement in the user interface um and
you know in it goes all the way from
like little things like um like the like
the notes that you hear when you find a
new dungeon you know and when you hear
exactly when precisely you hear the
sound of you know
if I think
um you know as a clue that now you have
opened a door um that that that's one of
those things that if you if you look at
postmodms of ocarina time I think
there's a couple on gamma sudra exactly
when that sound plays is a decision that
was very carefully designed um and uh it
seems to me that in digital puzzles in
those kinds of like especially in some
sort of narrative structure like in
opera um that's the big problem that you
have to solve you have to give enough
clues you have to give enough UI
feedback and you have to think about
your UI so hard um in a way that is
going to make it possible for people to
get all the information they need. So
say that burning fire tree situation if
there's nowhere else in the world for
you to get that information that's bad
design puzzle. If there is a guy in I I
can't remember the Zelda one, but if
there is a guy who actually tells you
that that's the tree that you need to
burn, but it's not obvious, especially
for someone who hasn't encountered that
guy, that that's where you get the
information. It's still a bad design
puzzle, even though now that's the
solution. Um but thinking about and some
examples will be u in a lot of textbased
adventures as well as graphical text
heavy graphical adventures you have a I
can't solve this puzzle but what my
character says to the player about why
you can't solve the puzzle itself a clue
it's like I must not have had I I must
not have the right item like you know
maybe there's something else I can use.
That's a huge clue. I feel like digital
puzzle games have gotten really good at
integrating hint systems
um in recent years,
but I can't think of any physical
puzzles that I've come across, though I
may just not have caught it like been up
to speed with physical puzzles that have
that kind of
not totally revealing the solution, but
giving you a gradual hint which can help
you figure it out. Well, mystery hunt
puzzle is kind of
>> Oh,
this
describe the mystery hunt for folks who
don't who
>> uh it's basically it's a competition run
at MIT over AP where uh teams of people
compete to solve a bunch of puzzles like
70 puzzles that kind of build on each
other. So you have, you know, say 20
base puzzles and you solve those 20
puzzles, you get 20 words as solutions
and then those 20 words become a new
puzzle and it's a meta puzzle and it
keep kind of keeps going like that for a
couple layers. But the point is the
winning team from the previous year
writes the next year's mystery hunt. So
like you get all kinds of varying
puzzles of varying difficulties and
styles and a very well-designed puzzle
actually does that because you have this
thing called flavor. Oh, I guess I
should say that the puzzles aren't like
sudoku or crosswords. You literally just
get, you know, something on a screen or
something on a piece of paper and you
have to figure out what to do with it.
You're not given any instructions for
how to solve it whatsoever. And the the
only clues you get are either by the
title of the puzzle, by like the group
of puzzles that it's in, or by this
thing called flavor text, which is like
they say some kind of random phrase that
seems to not have anything to do with
anything, but that kind of gives you a
clue about what to do in the first
puzzle.
>> So that's it's kind of like what you're
describing. That's interesting because I
mean it's really challenging when you
don't have any mechanism for like giving
feedback to the person who's working on
a puzzle. It in Zelda or what have you.
You can see that they've spent a long
time
around.
It's kind of a double-edged sword in
that particular case because you had so
many mechanisms and now you're expected
to use all of them. Uh in in in in a
game like like you have to use sound,
you have to use contextual buttons, you
have to use the inventory, uh the
position of the player matters, you
know, sometimes I've seen games where
the the main clue is what is the the
character looking at for instance, you
know, and if you walk around, why does
my character keep looking that way every
time I look at it? Oh, that's the clue,
you know. Um so so yeah for us in a lot
of like um physical stuff um I would say
that one of the reasons is if you're
starting if you're starting to build
these physical games from toys um you a
lot of the affordances
a a lot of things you could possibly do
are kind of built into the physical
object. Uh, and if you're building a
puzzle based on what you could do as
with these things as a toy, um, then
you're necessarily already using the
constraints of what you can do it do
with it as a toy in order to try to to
to create a puzzle.
Um,
this might be a good exercise actually.
We have time we we we we could take a
shot at this and just like you know
trying to come up with a puzzle and see
but instead of doing of imagining one in
a digital space trying to imagine one in
physical space and because I suspect
what you actually get is that you get a
lot of free you get a free ride with
physical puzzles because things
physically
have interactions that puzzle
I feel like uh played Portal recently
and that's a game where like
the the puzzles are it's not in a I mean
obviously it's still a digital game but
the puzzles are very much physical
puzzles like you kind of have an idea
about what has have people played Portal
of course or know the idea
okay um I mean you have these two
portals and you like do you understand
what the physics is going to be like so
the puzzles aren't frustrating in the
sense that it's like oh you pull you
realize there's like this random statue
here and if you like pull a lever it
like raises the water level or something
like that like it I don't know what it
but it's like it's very intuitive and
it's it feels like a physical puzzle in
the sense that I know what will happen
if I do this and I just figure out have
to how to put the pieces together and
also in portal what I think does a
really good job of as well as what some
physical puzzles do is having a learning
curve like tanagram will have some basic
puzzles or I'm sure the following thing
a lot of them we can do physical puzzle
things we like I don't know have to jump
over pieces or whatever basic levels,
basic uh boards where they show you
various techniques and you only have to
figure out one technique and it's very
obvious what you have to do and then
later on you have to use those
techniques.
>> Well, I mean in zippover this particular
example does something that portal also
does really well is that the very first
puzzle that we did earlier only has one
solution and you do not you do not get
that solution unless you understand all
the mechanics. Yeah. like we like we
tried to solve it a bunch of different
times and it's like because we didn't
quite understand the rules, we couldn't
get it until we understood the mechanics
of the game. Now we can sly solve it. So
from level from puzzle level two
onwards, we can be confident that we
actually know like Portal and even
actually just about any well-designed
game, but I'm going to say Portal is a
fine example. you've beaten the game,
you can play through the game again with
developer commentary. And you will and
when you hear that, you will actually
realize that um every single fairly
intuitive physical thing that that that
you pick up in the game had to be taught
to you. And they've designed the level
very clearly. So, right at the beginning
of the game, if uh folks can remember,
um you're trapped in a little cell,
right? and uh the the uh GLaDOS talks to
you and a portal opens and you can walk
through it. What do you see out of the
first portal that opens?
>> You see yourself going into the other
one.
>> You see yourself going through the other
portal. It is like they force you to
have to look at what the basic game
mechanic is going to be before you can
do anything else in game that's
productive in game. uh you know you can
pick up the radio but yeah
so so you know u so you know that's that
that was a design decision they could
have made that they they could have
decided not to make it they could have
made you just go through that into a
different room and you and and and a
learning opportunity would have been
lost right there um so if you got a copy
of portal I would suggest go back and
play through the the developer comment
tries because they're they're hilarious
and they're also really really good for
demonstrating
in this room. This is what we had to do
in order to make people get it. Um, I'm
also thinking of things like Mario World
one where like you don't get to you
don't get very far unless you get the
basic game mechanics down and but they
make it really gentle in that I don't
think there are any pits that instant
instantly choke you.
>> Yeah, that's exactly what I was
thinking. Mario World, the first Gamma
Suture article we read on uh like game
distractions from Rich Mario World that
he's like you expect the same kind of
actions to be consistent all the time
jumping and I guess you kind of look at
like different things there like double
jumping like that specific puzzle
also. I mean a lot of Mario's things uh
uh worlds are made up basically as
spatial puzzles, right? and it's like
you know you have to get there but you
don't know exactly how you're going to
use all the mechanics that you got.
>> Um in Mario 64
I think their way of solving the the
impass problem of not locking off all
the content from the game because of one
puzzle you can't get giving you so much
to do that even if they don't really
tell you and even if a good 30 40% are
going to remain mysterious to you and
you're not able to figure them out
there's so much to jump around between
that you're never locked off from a
significant amount of content. So you
you you've got the hublike structure of
like you can do any one of five
different things at any given time plus
all plus you have sort of secondary
solutions like you can always go back to
a world that you've been before and try
to put all the stars.
Um I think that's kind of what Brenda
was kind of indicating of the you don't
necessarily want if you're putting
puzzles in your game. she was advocating
for Brenda and Ian were were advocating
for something that wouldn't that that
wasn't necessary to progress on on to
the next one. But I think that's
I think that's not a requirement. I
think that's a if you want to make your
life easier, this is what you do. If you
decide that you're up to the task, you
can achieve some really amazing effects
by having your puzzles narratively
important. Um, so there's um,
uh, has anyone heard of the game called
Eternal Darkness? It's, uh, sort of the
craftian horror game on the Gamecube?
Uh, I'll sort of describe it, but
basically the whole basic idea is that
you have four gods all waring, all
waring against each other. Three of them
hate one of them, but then those three
of them hate each other. and and most of
the puzzles are just sort of
understanding that there is this there's
this mystical logic you know one god
defeats another god defeats another god
in a rock paper scissor circle and all
of them hate this one other thing um so
um early on in the game there's actually
a puzzle there are actually a number of
different p uh p puzzles where you see
the symbols of these gods and you have
to kind of rearrange them in the correct
order and the rest of the game is all
going to be like variations on sort of
understanding what these gods do to each
other. So those those are all puzzles
that inform you about how the world
works. Um that and that's that kind of
works in two ways. One information that
you've already gathered about the world
about how this world works gives you
clues on how to beat the puzzles.
Beating the puzzles, finding the
solutions for the clues gives you
information about how the world works.
And that's that's kind of like the holy
grail of a puzzle designer in a digital
game is that you're going to design a
puzzle that's going to reinforce how the
world works. Um we there's a chap um who
gave a talk and I believe his name is
Jeff Howard. He came to um he came to
camp and gave a talk last
>> last year and um and he makes this case
that games and the logic in that that
you present in games uh do basically uh
the equivalent of what magic does in of
what magic systems actually do in the
real world. you know, um what people
like like like
oultists or astrologers or they
basically give you logics on, you know,
uh that that that explain how the world
is going to work. One that may not
necessarily be obvious, but if you knew
this knowledge, you'd be able to
understand how this will work in you.
But more importantly, you'll be able to
do things in the world that you know
that that allow you to accomplish things
uh uh that you wouldn't otherwise do.
Learning a game is very much like like
like like that. You know, it's like I
don't know how this world works, but if
I understood these particular rules, I
could be able to accomplish greater
things. Um and puzzles can be one of
those things where where it becomes a
test, right? It becomes a test of just
exactly how well do you understand this?
uh even if it's like in a combat game
like uh Quick or God of War or
something, you know, I can understand
how the combat system basically works if
I just keep mashing the X button or
something or just like shoot everything
with rockets. Um but if I really really
understand the combat system, I might be
able to hit something that I wouldn't
necessarily be able to hit. I might be
able to um I might be able to take down
a a horde of enemies instead of like
taking them down one at a time. Um I
might be able to beat a boss. And
actually a lot of boss boss battles in
digital games are actually puzzles.
There's not it's not how well do you
generally react, it's can you figure out
the pattern. Um but that pattern makes
no doesn't mean anything unless you've
already figured out how all your other
combat skills work. So, a boss battle in
Zelda only makes sense if you figured
out how that one item that you picked up
in the dungeon works really, really
well. You know, okay, it shoots fire.
That means not only does it hurt things
from distance, it also lights certain
things on fire. And that's what a Zelda
boss battle basically is. Combining this
latest ability that I got with
everything else that you've done before
into taking it down. That's why boss
puzzle battle is kind of like a puzzle.
Um,
one thing I wanted to say before I go
on, you're asking about like hints in a
physical puzzle. And the one thing that
jumped to my mind was um, a couple years
ago, the weekly dig, I don't know if
anyone reads it, it's like a free Boston
newspaper. And there was a cross word
puzzles for the longest time. They were
thematic. And so you would have a guest
cross lord and uh, like the first one I
ever did was Hulk Hogan. So all of all
of the hints in the cross word puzzle
are related to Hulk Hogan. So it's a
question of like not what does this mean
to me, but what would it mean to Hulk
Hogan? And um and they don't do it
anymore, which is really depressing
because every week it was somewhat
different. And it kind of it was like a
built-in hint, right? As you weren't,
you didn't just think about it
literally. You have to kind of
contextualize it. You can think about
all the things that come with the puzzle
as potential in players introduced sense
like the title like the play the text as
you were describing the fact that it's
in the like like the fact that you get a
puzzle and mystery hunts immediately
clues you in that maybe the solution for
this lies in a different puzzle that not
the one that I'm currently looking at
right now because that's how mystery
hunt things are. Um,
uh,
Metal Gear Solid is, uh, has a really,
really bizarre one where, uh,
>> look in the back case.
>> Yes. Where they tell you, oh, there's a
specific radio frequency that you need.
It's written in the back of the box and
it's like the back of the box
or antipiriracy.
>> Yeah. I mean, yes, but it's still a
puzzle, you know. It's like, you know,
to solve that. I mean, they were pretty
obvious because uh or maybe it's just me
because it took me about half an hour to
figure that one out.
>> Took me some hours.
>> I mean, Middle Gear Hell did a lot of
like meta puzzles like that. Like when
when you fought Psycho Mantis the first
time
>> Well, so the thing you had to do is you
had to unplug your controller and plug
it into the second port because he would
read your movements
>> and it it was just like it was this cool
like physical layer of it where like
you're playing the game, you realize I
have to interact with the physical
world. so that he can't see what I'm
doing.
>> But but actually that one had a clue
because if you had a in that particular
example, that one gave you a very big
clue because right at the beginning of
that match, uh that boss tells you to
put your controller on the ground and he
said that I'm going to control this this
controller with my mind and actually
just right.
>> That's only if you have DualS. So since
it was on PlayStation,
>> uh if you didn't, he just ignored that
part and you didn't you didn't get that
clue at all. Yeah, that and that's a
problem. But but it's still it's still
very
>> there were other clues.
>> There were also other clues like you
would talk about how you had been
playing certain games by reading saves
on your
>> I think it was on your notion
of the night.
>> Those are the ones.
>> So So basically it's it's telling you
it's giving you a clue that there
there's going to be something better
about the way that you're currently
playing. Uh, the funny thing about the
radio channel one is that that one
really did not give you any clues that
it was something better. It just told
you about it at the back at the back of
the box. It is like and it didn't tell
you the back of the case, the the video
game case, right? It's not going to be
that explicit. It's a CD case
specifically.
>> Oh, CD case.
>> Yeah, I appreciate I I was really
confused cuz I think mine came in like a
slip of paper or something.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Yeah, if you buy it used or something.
>> Wow. So, it's anti-use game protection
as well. But uh yeah, mine was Yeah, I
think mine actually said at the back of
the CD case, but I was playing like a
re-release or something and that came in
the the DVD case. So, I didn't make that
connection, but you know, if you look at
the back of it, you see the you you
you'll see what the radio frequency is
in a um in the screenshot. What one of
the the eight screenshots that they show
to demonstrate this is what the game is
all about. There's a number just right
in there and then you keep
>> behind our
play of those like breakout games where
you just lock in a room you have to
>> escape the room
and you find you like find a paper.
>> So um actually who who doesn't know what
these are about escape the room.
>> Okay. So, escape the room. Actually,
could we bring up something on the
computer? Let's do that. Grab the video.
Well, the video cable. I mean, the after
my office. Oh, okay. Cool. Um, well,
that
um escape the room games are typically
flash games. Uh, and and they're kind of
like adventure games. You um only
because there's usually only one room,
although sometimes they have multiple
rooms. It's a much smaller world than
most adventure games, but the basic idea
is the same. you pick up objects, you
use objects in in in in in in a room and
you try to make things happen, you know.
Um, if you haven't made anything happen,
you are not progressing in the game. If
you made something happen, you're almost
certainly making forward progress in the
game. Um, and and there is actually a a
guide for playing adventure games
written by Rob Roberto Williams within
the original series. and her guide is
like, "Pick up everything, go
everywhere, use everything on
everything." It's like, that's actually
what the escape room game is, but
there's a little bit more humane escape
to room game because there just not that
many places that you can explore because
the idea is that you're stuck in a room.
Um, and uh, and basically it comes down
to just use everything on everything
until you figure out what what turns
out. Rarely isn't logical. Often it
often pretty entertaining because
they're animation heavy. So every time
you do something right, you get some
crazy animation. I put the fish into the
male slot and then out appears an
octopus.
It's like it's fun to watch. Um whereas
the kind of combinatorily
opposite of those are the grow games.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Um and there there is a series of games
called Grow. Um I think the guy who does
them called eyes maze and that's like Z.
Um and and um and the whole basic idea
is that um imagine that you have a
flower pot and every time you add
something to it, something happens. But
the order in which you're adding things
to it makes different things happen.
>> And there are solutions basically in
making the optimal number of things h
happen if you if you if you do it if you
do it right. So what you can do is not a
mystery at all. You know, you you have I
have these six things that I could add
to my part and it doesn't and and I know
that's those are the only six things I
could add. The question is what order do
I do them? Um and doing them in
different orders gives you different
different results. I feel that
these these two genres are kind of
linked, but they're not uh but they're
playing off very different things. One
of them is I don't know what I'm going
to do. Uh, but I know that whatever I do
is got to be in the space. And the other
one is very much I know exactly what I
can possibly do. I just don't know what
order to do them. So couple of puzzles
that you see online. These are fairly
encapsulated things. One one game is one
series of puzzles. There's no it's not
like a professor kind of encyclopedia
puzzles kind of thing.
Okay. Um, let's see. I I think I'm
actually going going to grab a few more
puzzles and bring them in. But, uh, I do
actually want uh, uh, to try to see
whether we can put together a list of
the kinds of puzzles that we haven't
talked about today. Uh, these could be
physical puzzles. These could be puzzles
that you've seen in the book, but like a
genre. Um, logic puzzles, you know, of a
certain kind that you either really
really like or you really really love.
Um, and just just break up in groups of
three, four, six, seven, eight, nine.
I'm going to bring you guys to do this.
10 12 13 15 16 17 people. 17 people.
That doesn't divide at all.
>> One group.
>> Okay. Two or three. Groups of two or
three. And just like
>> uh Jason should be back.
>> Okay. Then groups then groups of three.
Um and uh right
>> and
come up with yeah just like
>> you know just a couple of puzzles that
we haven't discussed and you know and a
description about what they're like and
we'll just quickly run through the class
to sort of like give everyone an idea of
what
>> a as a toy playing with a Rubik's cube
is more fun than the algorithm to solve
it. That's not fun at all in my opinion.
>> Yeah. Like it's probably you can also
solve it but there's algorithms there
very
>> yeah one of the things you're talking
about was interactive fiction
>> and uh
>> like text
>> yeah text text adventures and how um
sometimes it could be considered just
like if you're playing a regular
adventure game but just with text
instead. And so um the puzzle could be
how you interact with the world or it
could be trying to figure out what
actions are available to the user. Like
sometimes not all actions are there but
also um in some games the nature of text
gives you different ways to have a
puzzle like in a lost pig because you're
playing in fork. He doesn't know English
very well or like doesn't doesn't have
full control of language. So you're
trying to decipher his words to figure
out what he's actually saying.
>> An example they can do give that to make
it
>> um I haven't played
>> in that game. There's uh one part where
he's describing a box and it has a slot
and you you you put something in it and
then it gives you something out. But
like the way he's describing it, you
don't really know what he's describing
until you realize he's talking about a
vending machine.
Okay.
>> He describes it as like a tall box with
that slot in it.
>> Um, and another example we were talking
about was the game Isle, uh, which is
you're you're this guy in like a grocery
store and you you have it gives you like
this big, uh, prologue and you have one
action that you can do. So after you
type in your one action, it tells you
what happens and gives you an epilog
and then the and then the game starts
over. But then using using the
information from that epilog, you you
have a different choice of actions that
you can take and different keywords to
use. And so by playing it over and over,
you're like uncovering more of the story
until you get somewhere.
>> So the puzzle solution.
>> Yeah. Isle A.
>> Yeah. I want to play
for the
game.
Um, we also thought about puzzles that
were
games and put into a very contrived
scenario like bridge puzzles or chess
puzzles or back when the duelist
magazines still existed there. Magic the
Gathering puzzles.
>> So, so like like chess puzzles are like
here's this board. What was the move
that that that
black to win in three moves?
>> Yeah.
>> Something like that. So that's like you
you are now placing additional
constraints on the game.
>> Yeah, exactly. It already puts you in a
situation like pretend you're in this
game now. We promise you there's a way
you can automatically win. You have to
find it.
>> Yeah. There's a number of uh sort of
computer games like Choo Choo Rocket and
everything where that's like just a
completely second.
>> Chuchu Rocket. Chuchu Rocket. Too rocket
is a frenetic fourplayer. Um like uh
>> it's it's a mice hurting game.
>> Mice mice hurting game.
>> Get them into rocket ships.
>> Yeah. So they can go into space.
>> It is
for the dream. It's so good.
>> Oh really?
>> Really?
>> The idea is just a whole bunch of mice
wandering around the screen and each
player gets to place like three arrows
and whenever the mice run the arrow they
follow the arrow. So you want to get all
you like want to get the cats and the
other chips and they eat their mice.
>> And puzzle mode says you have three
arrows in these particular directions.
Figure out where to place them. As much
time as you want, but there's only one
one right answer. And that immediately
shows you the difference between game
and puzzle where they all
>> cool.
So uh first off, I don't like jigsaw
puzzles, but Michelle loves them. And
then we also talked about who donuts.
And I really love redemptance because
it's like what you have to pay attention
to detail in the story is like the one
thing that like I guess the example that
we were talking about is if there's a
mailman it happens to be on a Sunday he
probably committed the crime because
they don't have mail on Sundays like
small details like that.
>> Are you talking about mystery books or
just like little paragraphs?
>> Well, it's usually like a story and they
say like, "Oh, here's the scenario.
Here's the background story. Who is the
who is the murder? Who's the murderer?"
>> They compiled it though to you. Yeah.
Yeah.
>> Feels like you told us at parties like
that like for at parties, right?
>> That's very true.
>> Yeah. How
>> I didn't see you was talking for a
second. That was
talking.
>> Did we actually
you guys?
>> Okay. All right. Uh, another puzzle we
came up with was uh the the ones that
you did in elementary school with like
the the big grid and you would have, you
know, like someone's name and maybe
their favorite food and you'd be given a
bunch of clues and you have to match
them.
>> Yeah. With like the checks and the exits
and stuff.
>> So,
I think
>> they're just generally called logic
puzzles, I believe. And it's just you're
given the the incomplete set of
information, but enough constraints that
you can figure out the rest of the
information. And really the the way to
solve it is just like write everybody's
name, all all the characters that you're
given in a piece of pros. Write down all
the characters on one column. Write down
all the things that you're trying to
figure out like who's wearing what
colored shirt for instance. So just
write out all the colors on the other
column. And just by the process of of
elimination, just figuring out um
usually these the answers are usually
exclusive, right? So like if somebody's
wearing a red shirt, the person cannot
be wearing a green shirt. Um, you know,
uh, so yeah,
>> like they're like much harder on like
every fourth statement is fault. Like
you don't know one state is definitely
false. I've seen ones where every
statement is false except for one. They
like I can bring in my book and they're
just like hideous.
>> Uh you the worst version of that is
figuring out how how to see people in
the wedding.
>> Is that in 6034? Did that last week?
>> Oh, cool.
>> You guys want to throw any?
>> Sure. Um, we started by trying to think
of all the puzzles that we really
dislike and uh we came up with a couple
here. The sliding square puzzles. You
have like a
they're basically just a variation on a
jigsaw puzzle where the rules are more
constrained. Um, I don't like jigsaw
puzzles either.
Like mine did there. And then John had a
couple like lights out. I guess there's
a lights out
certain areas and you have to like flip
them.
So, so you got a like like a grid of
buttons and every button you push will
invert the all the neighboring buttons
like in I think the top bottom left and
right will
>> yeah and then I guess a similar well
maybe not similar but there's why don't
you describe the concentric circles
>> yeah their puzzles are similar that
we're um taking an action on um one item
in the scene will um these are going to
be dual puzzles the concentric circle
ones um will uh have effects on other
things in the system. And um uh
typically these are used in games where
there'll be like a center podium with a
pathway leading off of um the center one
side of the podium. Then there'll be a
concentric circle around that a
concentric ring with a pathway off of
that ring and another angle and then you
know more and more circles um to each
side and uh you get to uh rotate
individual circles and that will rotate
the other circles in different ways.
need to
>> create every time I rotate one something
else is going to rotate.
>> Yeah. And there's always like it's
always thrown like right before like a
boss battle game is like, "Oh, damn it."
>> I guess three of those are examples of
games where like you have to take action
on an environment, but your action has
indirect effects,
>> you know, throughout the environment and
it's just really annoying figuring out
how to optimize that.
>> But they are predictable effects. It's
like every time I rotate this one left,
that one's going to rotate right.
I think it's kind of funny how like the
context has a lot to do with whether
these puzzles are employed or not
because like I do enjoy Professor
Leighton quite a bit.
>> Um it's like it's the most uh you know
arbitrary narrative like justifying that
there's puzzles in the world but like
it's just fun like your intentionality
when playing the game is that you're
going to be solving puzzles and that has
something as well. like in the middle.
>> Yeah. The way that also the way that
that is presented kind of makes it funny
in math as well, right? So like the
mafia goons come up to you and say,
"We're going to stop you from coming in
here unless you can solve this puzzle.
Shouldn't you just shoot me?
Solve all your problems." No. No. Solve
this puzzle.
They're making fun of themselves even.
>> All right. Cool.
Uh, okay. I'm not sure if we really
commented on what we liked or didn't
like, but the some things that we came
up that haven't been brought up yet are,
uh, cryptics, which are kind of a
combination between like crossword and
riddles, uh, riddles, um, comatorial
games as a puzzle genre,
um, logic puzzles in general, not just
like typical logic puzzles like that.
you can have like
state machines or pseudohoo or any type
of numerical puzzle. We also wanted to
differentiate that uh a lot of those
games or some of those games are
spatially oriented and some aren't
>> which we thought was an important aspect
but not necessarily definitive of a
completely different genre.
>> I'm not sure if seen escape machine
puzzle actually outside of like computer
science text. I know some
>> I really like
>> I'll have to ask you suspect it's gonna
be more involved than we have time for.
>> By by combinatorial puzzles you mean
stuff like like you have
>> comtorial games like
>> all the games that fall under comtorial
game theory.
>> Okay theoretically puzzles
>> like everything.
>> Cool. That's a lot of games.
>> See we also have exploration. So games
where you have to see everything around
you to know what is available for use.
Now on the the braith in the book they
talked about exit Zelda.
>> Okay. and just other so a game like
situation in game that I didn't like is
you're playing a game and something
happens you don't step too fast or
something
>> and because of that you get to an
irreversible spot where you don't have
the tools necessary to beat the enemy
right in front of you but you also are
trapped and can't go back it happened to
me one time it was a Star Wars night of
the old republic and there's an enemy
there's an enemy I couldn't go forward
>> there was the enemy you couldn't go
forward and the door or like there was a
cliff so you couldn't get back up
>> and so since I couldn't do anything I
was forced to just completely go back to
like the last save.
>> But is that a puzzle or is that just a
bug?
>> I mean it was like it's it's the type
where it's exploration and item is an
item use. So, you need to get an item to
go ahead and like if you had this item,
then the enemy that you
>> I think it was like a rancor or
something.
>> You could beat the rancor or at least
put it to sleep and walk by it. But
without it, you had to try and just beat
it or it would kill you.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, so it was an item that would
have made combat easier basically, but
then it was kind they kind of made made
it this one way.
>> It's like Yeah. So, so yeah. So, you see
a lot of puzzle games where they have
like easy reset, right? It's like, you
know, you you you can try start trying
to solve it and you realize you screw up
something along the way, you hit reset
and go back right back to the beginning.
Nice of the public has no easy reset. Uh
you live with the consequences. I guess
that's what they were trying to go for.
But,
>> all right. So, we also had a loading of
sliding puzzles either either with
numbers or with pictures. Both of them
are equally annoying.
It's easy.
>> But but on the other hand, Alec loves
rush hour and and
>> it's the travel.
>> You have to slide cars out of the way to
form a path.
>> In Professor Leighton, there are an
awful lot of sliding puzzles that have
like differently shaped pieces or oddly
shaped pieces,
>> which is slightly more interesting or
less annoying than sliding puzzles, but
like regular sliding puzzles, but it's
still incredibly frustrating. Well, I
think the difference there is that when
you have differently sized pieces, like
when when you're doing just like a
sliding puzzle where you're trying to
recreate an image, there's definite
patterns that you keep using over and
over again because you're just like
rotating spacesh
>> um so it's not actually interesting.
Whereas rush hour, you actually have to
like think about how things fit
together. So, one other puzzle type that
we haven't really mentioned that I
actually really enjoy is like uh
pictographic puzzles where it relies on
on sort of your association with visual
images and like word play and stuff.
Like for example, you'll have a puzzle
that's just, you know, an image of an
eyeball uh a bumblebee and a screenshot
of Jiggy Dench in like in a James Bond
movie. And the idea is it's IBM.
So like I I love puzzles like that.
>> Puzzles.
>> Yeah. So stuff like that where where it
relies on on someone like a human being
actually associating information with
something visual rather than it being
just like a straight logic puzzle where
you have this this you know this
information and we use this to derive
the rest of the information.
>> Yeah. Re rebu
and of course those are very language
focused even though they're image based.
So, uh, but like the one that has the
two lines and then read in the middle.
>> Well, you
>> Well, things like that. Yeah.
>> Yeah. you have reverbs where you're
trying to like basically reconstruct
something and then um I forget what uh
the what's the classification of puzzles
where you're given some assembly of
images and you're trying to like you
know um god uh uh if if if I if I wrote
in what's
this this is not a good puzzle but just
to give an example if I put you know
feels.
>> Yeah, this is kind of fun. I think there
is a a specific word for these kind of
things, but the whole idea they're
trying to reconstruct this reconstruct
sentence from from the so um so um
so uh yeah, I mean the these are they're
usually spatial to to to to begin with,
but uh I think there was a whole game
show in the 80s that was just all Yeah,
that's awesome. That's that's great. Um,
in Australia they had a triple
catchphrase which was
>> I think catchphrase was the short
>> so we we wrote a big list of different
types of puzzles. So we've got let's
just run through right we got lots of
different sliding puzzle variants. We've
got hidden object finding. If anyone's
done the words wallow then it's kind of
a similar deal. Um we have riddles
various kinds of logic puzzles
particularly two which we've mentioned
before somebody who is has several
people witnesses give statements one of
them's a liar which one's a liar so find
an inconsistent person and there's the
um thing with property X is next to
thing with property Y what order are
they sitting in that kind of puzzle
there's a million of them in professor
there's um these kinds of
um unraveling or reverse engineering
type puzzles where some system has been
permuted and you have to restore it to
its original state of which Rubik's cube
is like the canonical example I guess
but then there's a bunch of other
different work on how chess games can
fit in that can
>> there's like tile rotation and swapping
puzzles like one example of this is
hacking but then there are a million
other variations on exchanging tiles or
swapping them around or this kind of
thing. Lots of different kinds of math
puzzles. Um, this particular word
transformation puzzle type that I that I
used to see all the time when I was a
kid where you by changing one letter of
a word per step, you have to transform
one word into another. Um, mazes,
jigsaw puzzles,
>> code breaking, nobody even mentioned
yet. Um, and then also these kind of
thought experimenty type puzzles. I
don't know how else to categorize them.
Give us an example.
>> All right. So,
I'm trying to remember
how this works, but I think it is. Does
this one This one popped on up on Day
Nine's podcast the other day. I don't
want to give it because otherwise
>> if I get it wrong, then people will go,
"Oh my god." and try and puzzle it out.
>> Let me see if I can.
>> So, it has to do with a piece of string
and burning.
>> Oh, the 15 minutes.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you remember Do you remember exactly
how?
>> Yeah. You okay? You have two pieces of
string. Uh you know that the whole
string takes an hour to burn. Uh but
it's not linear. So like you don't it's
not linear. Uh you have an infinite
supply of matches. How can you measure
15 minutes with the strength?
>> Those are lateral thinking puzzles.
Yeah, they're all thinking puzzles. I
guess
>> I think they're I I would classify this
under riddles, but we have two identic
>> identical identical pieces.
>> They both No, they're identical, but
they both take an hour.
>> They don't have to.
>> They don't have to be, but they both
take an hour to burn. Nonidently,
>> couldn't you just be lighting matches
the entire time and see how many matches
you can burn an hour and after that just
take that number? No, but like
>> but then how are you going to measure
that original hour?
>> This this assume you want to measure.
>> But you know that thing takes an hour to
burn. Yeah,
>> the whole thing.
>> It takes slightly longer than the amount
of time.
Well, we could, but then it would be
nice to give people time to think about
it, too. So, so
answer on Wednesday.