hi uh I'm John Williams I'm professor of
information Engineering in the
Department of Civil environmental
engineering at
MIT and my background is basically in
physics that uh I grew up in the UK I'm
from Wales which is um basically steel
and Mining so uh I ended up in Oxford
University played rugby uh there for
Oxford so I got Oxford blue they call it
and uh we happened to beat the springbox
who were the world champions at the
moment in rugby uh but that was a long
time ago and so my journey went through
uh
UCLA uh where I studied physics and
basically got fascinated with how we
could simulate
physics and I ended up going back to uh
Wales and did a PhD in Swansea
University uh and that was the place
where they invented the finite element
method
uh a guy called zenovich Professor
zenovich there was the world kind of
renowned in fite elements and so I
became embroiled if you like and
fascinated by
simulation and after the PHD uh I went
into industry for eight years and did
two startups um one in Colorado and we
basically were
simulating the oil rigs up in the Arctic
so I spent some time in the Arctic um
which is a place where the one thing you
want to do is get out of there it's
great for about 3 days and then it
becomes pretty pretty hellish um so I
spent time on offshore rigs there uh and
we were simulating in our company the
impact of ice on offshore Rigs and the
big thing about ice mechanics is that
it's not continuous that you've got
basically most of mechanics is based on
this Continuum Theory and the
assumptions of Continuum Theory don't
hold for ice that you've got it
fracturing you've got pieces of ice and
the key problem with the offshore rigs
was that the ice would ride up on the
sides and possibly take the deck off um
the ice was about 13 ft thick so these
are not small pieces of ice you know
this is the the height of a room um and
when they hit you shake the whole rig um
my first night on the rig I was really
scared it was shaking uh it was like a
leaf um but the uh structors they've
done a pretty good job I guess of
Designing them because they survived um
but that's how I became embroiled in or
fascinated by non-continuum mechanics so
this is where you've got pieces like you
might have a soil um or sand or powders
so drugs for example um and in the
company we invented something called the
discrete element method um which is
basically lots of particles and the
trick is how to figure out how they
interact so computationally it's quite
expensive um but we made some uh we
developed a a commercial code actually
called SE ice that was uh sold to the
oil companies and so after that um we
sold the company um didn't make a lot of
money had lots of shares that we could
paper walls with but eventually uh they
they came good um but then I applied to
MIT for a job in MIT and I became a
research scientist here so that's how I
ended up in MIT that's the short story