my name is Ricardo heral on behalf of
the Rene Salazar speaker series and
latinx at bro and we are a group a
latinx community and the mission is to
build community among latinx broes and
allies and empowering members of the
latinx communities this this is also
Hispanic Heritage Month and we had
several events for Hispanic Heritage
Month including the apple picking and we
had craft chica today so we have a lot
of events associated with Hispanic
Heritage Month and promoting latinxt
individuals in science and research
so the role or the goal of the Rene
salsar speaker series is to highlight
latinx and diverse researchers within
and outside the broad we want to Foster
collaboration and we want to allow
visibility and role models for diverse
individuals we also want to allow
opportunities to network and promote
research and from there I wanted to
introduce our speaker so our speaker is
Dr Victoria Costa Rodriguez of the ni
and the talk will be entitled circadian
interventions to promote healthier
longevity of mammals
Dr Victoria cost Rodriguez received a
PhD in chemistry from the National
University of Ora in Argentina and
during her PhD in the laboratory of Dr
Mario Guido she investigated the
Circadian control of phospholipid
metabolism using an invitro model of
peripheral clocks she joed she joined Dr
Joseph Takahashi at UT Southwestern
Medical Center for a post-doctoral
training to understand how organisms
coordinate their met metabolism at
specific times of the day to promote
well-being first she designed automated
feeders to demonstrate that by
restricting calories mice not only eat
less but also shorten their feeding
window she then discovered that feeding
time is critical to maximize systemic
benefits of caloric restriction or like
on lifespan and maintenance of robust
orcadian gene expression as mice age all
together her findings challenged the
prevailing view that pro- longevity
benefits of caloric restriction come
from lower intake or fasting alone
instead she found in hands benefits are
achieved when feeding fasting time is
aligned with the natural active phase as
dictated by Circa clocks and these
findings reveal circadian clocks as
potential targets for delaying the onet
of age related diseases so in 2024 Dr
aasa Rodriguez joined the NIH as an Earl
stman tenure track investigator where
she leads the Circadian biology of Aging
unit and she's also NH distinguished
scholar since 2024 so take it away Dr
Victoria Costa Rodriguez so thank you so
much for the opportunity to present uh
the research that I've been doing since
my uh PhD but mainly in my post talk and
specially In This Very Special month for
um me because it's the her Spanish
Heritage H month and so as um Ricardo
said I have a long interest um long-term
interest in understanding how circadian
clocks can influence health status in
mammals but how did I started so I I'm
originally from Argentina I was born
here by the Andes on the mountains in
this city called sanquan and then I
moved to Cordova to do my uh
PhD that H after my PhD that was focused
on understanding the Circadian h control
of fpid metabolism I moved to Dallas
Texas to do my post talk looking for a
more broader um aspect of the Circadian
biology not just looking at one specific
metabolism but rather what it's
happening in the body the systemic
control and then recently like as
Ricardo mentioned I just started my um
Pi position at NIH but how do we get
into circadian biology and aging and
this is because of food so caloric
restriction was the first and is the
most studied intervention known to
promote health and lifespan in mammals
okay and what CAU our attention is not
just um the this remarkable prolongevity
um benefit but rather it's unusual
feeding
Behavior I
have sorry can you see my Pon yes okay
so basically we became interested in
this intervention not only because of
this remarkable prolongevity
intervention that show shows that when
mice are eating 30% less of the calories
as compared to Anum controlled mice mice
can leave significantly longer but what
was very interesting for us is their
unusual feeding Behavior so in this case
the mice were allowed to eat in the
morning from 7:00 a.m. to 9:00 a.m. a
time at which mice nocturnal mice do not
normally eat because it's the normal
rest phase and also the food was
provided three times a week instead of
so this unusual protocol is because
these longevity experiments in mice are
time consuming it requires to feed the
mice one like every day seven days a
week throughout the entire duration of
the experiment that in this case is like
over three years so to overcome uh these
difficulties in performing this type of
experiments I developed an automated
feeder system with this system I could
control exactly how much and when a
mouse is allowed to eat and the system
was also coupled with the wheel running
activity which is an output of the
central clock the internal timee keeping
of the organism which again in mice is
nighttime so we
can simultaneously record these two
behaviors that H feeding and wheel
running activity in this activity
recording that we called actogram that
shows minute by minute resolution every
day across multiple days of
experiment so with this system we asked
how do mice under caloric restriction
behave and this is first the control
group that is at libitum just to see
what's happening in the control
conditions so under at libitum condition
H mice are exposed to a 12 hours light H
that starts at 7:00 a.m. and 12 hours
dark cycle starting at 7 p.m. and what
we can see is like both wheel running
and feeding Behavior are mainly
Consolidated during the night time 75
80% of the activity is
nocturnal which is
expected now what we found is like after
the first quick of at libitum if we
limit the amount of food we removed 30%
of their normal intake and now the food
starts at 7:00 a.m. in the morning like
the previous protocol that I showed that
PR of longevity we can see that mice
Goods rapidly consolid at and eat their
food within 2 hours since the food is
given yet the activity remains nocturnal
so basically this protocol can somehow
um uncouple this feeding and not and whe
running activity that is normally
nocturnal in mice and the same thing
happens if now the food starts is
limited amount of food but it starts at
the beginning of their normal active
phase at night there is still till 2
hours consolidation so basically what
this experiment showed us is that under
classic caloric restriction protocols
the mice were not only eating less but
also they self-impose a severe Tim
restricted feeding in which they have
prolonged fasting periods and the timing
of the food intake it also matters if
you start at the beginning of the day or
at the beginning of the night so our
question was okay since we know that all
these three feeding factors how much
when and how often we eat they have
influence of many this chronic diseases
that are associated with age we wonder
which of these three feeding factors
that are all combined in a single
protocol which of them was actually
contributing to longevity so to address
this we did a comprehensive uh feeding
protocol in which we tested six feeding
groups so here I'm just showing the all
and the first group is the control group
mice are eating all they want whenever
they want then we have two control
groups that are the classic protocols
that we showed before that self impose
two hours
feeding and then to get around this Bing
eating Behavior we were able to actually
spread out now the food to 12 hours
during the day or during the night and
very importantly with this system we
were able to actually have a caloric
restriction group that has only
reduction in calories but with without
any fasting or feeding cycle continuous
feeding and then we asked which of these
intervention was actually promoting
lifespan what is important in this case
is all of these groups all these CR
calorically restricted mice are eating
exactly the same amount of food every
day is regular CH and and the only
difference between these groups is
actually the feeding pattern that mice
experience so um this is just to show um
like an activity recording of three
years of continuous recording for a
representative mice and their ad lium
group that basically we can see that the
mice are nocturnal but the activity the
nocturnal activity basically declines as
they
age and for all the other eating
conditions regardless of when they were
eating we can see that the activity is
still nocturnal meaning that that the
internal clock of the organism remains
locked to the
nighttime now we can also see that for
each of the feeding conditions the
feeding pattern that they adopt early in
life is actually maintained throughout
the experiment meaning that some uh even
for this a very strange continuous
feeding in which mice are continuously
eating throughout the day so the
question um then we can actually
quantify all of these behaviors and
basically we can see here in the top we
are seeing the 24-hour profile in whe
running activity which is regular
locomot activity or exercise and we can
see that in all the groups just like we
said but in a quantitative way the mice
are nocturnal but the activity declines
as they Edge
whereas H the feeding patterns basically
H are opposite for instance for the day
eaters so we can also quantify the total
intake and we can see that the ad lium
um remains like more or less constant
after 400 Days of age and all
importantly all this calorically
restricted groups are eating exactly the
same amount throughout their entire
lifespan and in terms of wheel running
activity we can see that an age related
decline in wheel running activity that
is happening mainly in the at libitum
and restricted group and all the
calorically restricted groups are able
to maintain higher activities at older
ages but the another H aspect that we
measure here is body weight and
basically the body weight regulation
followed the food intake so there is an
age related increase in body weight and
a in the control group and after 20
months of age there is um a decline in
body weight and this is very interesting
because if you remember the mice are
actually eating exactly the same amount
yet they are starting to lose weight but
what is important is like for all the
calorically restricted groups they are
able to maintain lean bass throughout
their experiment suggesting that if
there is any difference in lifespan and
it might not be related to body weight
maintenance so the big question is okay
so how long do this mice uh live and
what we were able to find out is that
caloric restriction alone without any
fasting and feeding cycle it's only it's
able to promote is sufficient to promote
lifespan but it does so only by 10% this
was actually very surprising because in
the field we thought that um the
longevity benefits of this protocol it's
because of the reduction of on calories
now if instead we also impos a fasting
period even if the food is giving at the
wrong time of the day now the extension
is a little bit better
20% and what was striking for us is that
if now we align all these factors eating
less with a fasting and feeding period
but also the food is given at the normal
active phase of the mice which is their
night time now the extension is
35% so basically what this experiment
tells us is that the same intervention
in this case caloric restriction can be
optimized or boosted its benefits just
by simply um adjusting the time of day
at which we do our
intervention okay so next we also try to
find out uh
using necropsy trying to find out what
are the lesions that are associated with
this lifespan extension and what
basically what we found is like all the
tissues have the same regardless of the
feeding condition all the tissues have
the same estop pathology the only
difference that we saw is that the um
longest Liv groups the onset of these
pathologies were detected later in life
and something that we also learned from
these H pathology studies is that the
liver was the tissue that Harbors most
of the lesions that we found um in the
animals that died in the survival
experiment so we looked at the liver for
our followup H studies trying to
understand what could be the molecular
signatures that are associated with this
increasingly um benefit of a timed
caloric restriction
and for that we used a gene expression
approach which was basically doing mRNA
sick in the liver but in this case we
did a circadian collection for mRNA sick
basically what we did is we collected
samples every four hours throughout two
days so and we did so in young and aged
mice so meaning that we had like at
least 24 samples per group
and initially we did differential gene
expression analysis just to see what are
the genes that were up or down regulated
based on the age and what we found in
the control group is most of the genes
were actually AB regulated up to 14% of
the genes were uppr regulated and 4% of
the genes were down
regulated then our Gene onology analysis
was very very very clear the genes that
were up Reg were mainly targeting immune
system and inflammation and here we can
see an example of Representative genes
of these on the other hand downregulated
genes relates to metabolism amino acid
lipids or
carbohydrates um this was also like very
very striking like two specific type of
H genes but then our next question was
how so this is in the control group so
what it's happening in all the other
interventions that are promoting
lifespan and basically what we this is
just the summary of what we saw under at
lium at least 18% of the genes are
differential expressed between a young
and aged liver and what we can see is
that um the interventions that that are
living the longest they only have four
4% difference between a young and aged
transcriptomic
suggesting that aligning the the the
intervention in this case diary
intervention to the normal active phase
of the organism is able to promote
um H basically to maintain a healthier
transcriptomics in the liver and this is
actually what correlates exactly with
lifespan so we next tried to find out
since we have all the dietary
interventions that have all of them have
caloric restriction we try to paino what
was the effect of actually eating less H
that it's basically um benefiting at
least half of the genes that were
related to aging 12% of the jeans are
basically rescued by caloric restriction
and this mainly relates to all the genes
that were up regulated in inflammation
Pathways or down regulated in metabolic
pathways such as these two genes that
I'm showing here as representative genes
in addition we found like around like of
almost 160 genes that are related to
thermogenesis are um able to be rescued
only if there is fasting uh in the
intervention and importantly there is
only 68 genes that can account for this
extra benefit is associated with
circadian alignment of food intake and
i1 beta is actually a poster child of
the gene that shows like a very
beautiful um time um Trend in which it's
highly up regulated in the at libitum
control group but it's only maintained
at low levels in the groups that are
living the longest but now the question
is okay so this is all in terms of
overall gene expression as I mentioned
before one of the advantage of this H
data set is that we collected samples
throughout the day so what if we now
analyze this data in terms of time of
day and this is because we are
interested in circadian biologist and
circadian rhythms are um circadian
clocks are distributed throughout the
body and Cadian um rhythms
are very important for adaptation to
Earth as a consequence of the earth
rotation we have we um mammals and other
species have developed internal timee
keeping mechanisms that allows us to
predict and anticipate recurrent changes
in the environment which is basically
about a
day
and these um circadian rhythms can be
span at different levels from molecular
to behavioral levels and the most common
one is feeding and fasting cycle or
sleep wake Cycles but they go all over
until molecular mechanisms and this is
because um circadian clocks are
genetically encoded meaning that there
are transcriptional factors clock and
Bal that are able to activate the
expression of 100 100 of genes
throughout the
genome in specifically it activate they
activate the expression of parent cry
that can act as their own repressors so
this generates a transcriptional
translational negative feedback loop but
what is important that is self- sustain
but what is important about this system
is that it's not only these four genes
that are regulating their own 24-hour
cycle in gene expression but also they
target multiple genes that are
associated with nutrient sensing
Pathways for instance cins a MK and M2
and on the other hand they also Target
directly main trans key transcription
factors that are Master Regulators of
energy metabolism in the body including
glucose and um lipid
metabolism but there is more so there is
also a lot of connections on how
circadian clocks control multiple
metabolism but in particularly genes
that are related that have been
associated with longevity so one of the
um evidence that we knew when we were
doing this experiment is that as we age
as organisms age Circ these 24-hour
cating rhythms damp with aging and
interventions such as caloric
restriction have been thought to promote
uh amplitude of these circadian rhythms
and therefore promote
longevity we also as as I mentioned we
also knew that these circadian clocks
are autonomous and are genetically
encoded but what is important to this H
experiment is that also dietary um
interventions that promote nutrient sens
and Pathways H that can delay aging um
they also have direct interactions with
the Circadian components of the clock
and importantly if we were to look at
genes that have been Associated as to H
favoring or delaying
aging we can also see that sorry that
they undergo um circadian oscillations
and with tissue specific signatures so
the next question is like what is
happening with the circadian rhythms in
all of these conditions that we know
that they are promoting a longevity in
different
ways so again what we always look that
is what is happening in the control
group so basically these are different
time points 0 48 hours each of these are
time points in The Young and the Aged
groups and basically what we can see
right away is that in a completely
embased manner the number of cycling
genes would H is reduced in the Aged
organism and basically what we can see
also is that at least 15% of the genes
are
suggesting that chances are that if we
measure things in the morning or in the
afternoon we can get different results
and this is not a insignificant number
it's at least 15% of the transcriptomic
in the liver that is exposed to this
daily
variation so next we look and in the
interest of time I'm just going to show
a few of the genes only but basically
what we can see is now when we looked at
the 24-hour profile by plotting the
expression throughout the day what we
can see is that the age group shown in
red they have what we call damped
amplitude basically they still oscillate
they always pick at the same time of the
day but now the the full change of the
oscillation is reduced but now what
happens with the other conditions that
we know that we're leaving the longest
and again in the interest of time I'm
just going to show
the Aged group in the longest Le group
what we can see is that it there is like
robust oscillations that basically
resemble the young group and always the
peak is happening at the same time of
the day however the intervention that is
not as efficient in promoting lifespan
even though they are benefiting from
partially from caloric restriction we
can see that uh the amplitude is reduced
but also the peak of the expression
happens 12 hours later just because the
food is giving at the time that the mice
is are not supposed to be eating so
basically this intervention which is the
most common intervention that we've seen
in the literature not only reduces the
amplitude but also shifts the amplitude
of the any rhythm that happens
throughout the time and what this is
also telling us is that now it's also
very very important that when we are
comparing gene expression in a in
multiple tissues but specifically in the
liver if we sample during the morning or
in the afternoon we can actually get an
opposite conclusion so for instance for
these genes and 15% of the genes in the
liver if we were to sample in the
morning we would say like the condition
blue actually up regulates the
expression of this chain
12 hours later our conclusion would be
the opposite so sampling time is also
very important a factor uh to consider
when we are planning our
experiments and the now our next step is
trying to get like a map of what is
happening in the liver transcriptomic
not only looking at the genes that are
changing through a as we age in overall
levels but also looking at what are the
changes that are happening through
throughout the day and H these are the
all these genes um organized in term of
um longevity and we can see that uh in
the at libitum control group most of
these genes that regulate metabolism
circadian clocks or even aging related
Pathways they all have D amplitude in
the Aged Group which is shown here as a
dashed line and these groups that are
the the longest lift in which the food
is actually aligned with the normal
Cadian phase of the organism we can see
virally no difference between the young
and aged 24hour
profile okay so as a summary what we um
found is that H targeting circadian
clock might be a promising intervention
that we can H use to promote healthier
and longer lifespan in mice and we Pro
as a proof of principle what we did is
we used caloric restriction and we
basically distributed the food intake um
differently throughout the day and one
of the intervention was the winner which
is basically giving the foot during the
normal H behavior of the mouse which is
nighttime and this might be a little bit
difficult for us humans because now we
need to rethink when we are doing the
intervention in the
mice um and these changes in lifespan
have also been Associated um with
benefits in locomotor activity but also
at molecular level in terms of gene
expression because nighttime feeding in
nocturnal animals can promote metabolism
that could always decline with age or
actually prevent age related up
regulation in inflammation Pathways and
very importantly for us H promote higher
time of day oscillations between um
metabolic
pathways and then let me see yeah I
think I'm good so now also from a
circadian perspective we know that the
Circadian clocks are distributed
throughout the body but not all the
clocks are the same so there is a
central clock that is located in the
brain that mainly responds to light to
changes in light dark cycle
but there are other peripheral clocks
such as the liver which is the most
studied H peripheral uh clock that is
mainly H influenced by feeding and
fasting cycle just like we saw before we
change the feeding fasting cycle the
liver H gene expression is going to
change its behave its
expression and what we thought also is
that misalignment Mis line so basically
eating at the wrong time of the day in
which these two environmental cues are
in conflict with each other can H
promote um metabolic disorders just
because there is a
miscommunication between these clocks
basically only the clock in the
periphery are going to be shifted to
this misaligned feeding fasting cycle
and the question that we had is so okay
so most of the information we know is we
we know because of the liver but what is
happening with all the peripheral clocks
that we know that are distributed in the
rest of the body so to do this we also
used our automated feeder system and in
this case we um compare H day versus
night feeding with or without caloric
restriction and we all um we looked not
only at the liver but also the
hypothalamus where the central clock
resides and other peripheral tissues
that are very important in maintaining
energy homeostasis and glucose
homeostasis in the
body so and here is uh basically this is
um just a control just to show that even
time restricted feeding if we restrict
the food intake to 6 hours H the mice
are H eating less it doesn't matter if
it's day or night just by restricting
the feeding window even though the mice
can eat all they want they would
self-impose this caloric restriction
basically this is the opposite of what
we showed earlier if you limits the
calories mice self-impose time
restricted feeding the opposite is also
true if you limit the feeding window the
mice at least mice are going to be
eating less 80%
less and this lower intake in the time
restricted group is also correlates with
body weights but then what was important
for us is also what is happening in
terms of gene expression in all these
metabolic tissues so for this we started
uh doing um qpcr and we picked two of
the genes that we know that have very
beautiful oscillations throughout the
day which are DVP and rever Alpha
basically what we can see is that for
the control groups the night ears we can
see they all have beautiful oscillation
and Peak around 8 hours after the lights
are
off but the day eers are completely
shifted now the peak happens 12 hours
later which is basically at the time
that they are not
eating so this was the liver we knew for
the liver so this was our control why
the Theos tissue the same daytime
feeding would shift 12 hours the 24hour
profile of these jeans but what was very
interesting for us is that the prown OS
tisue remained completely insensitive to
this feeding time so these genes remain
beautifully oscillating but at the same
phase meaning that they would still pick
at the same time of day and this was
exactly what we knew that was happening
in the hypothalamus so what this T told
us is that daytime feeding not only
uncouples rhythmic G
between the central clock in the
hypothalamus and the liver but also can
cause a internal misalignment between
peripheral
clocks so we became very interested
about this and we looked at other gen
that are um important for the physiology
of the Prados tissue and we looked at um
genes that are H that are related to
thermogenesis and lipid homeostasis and
we can see that some of them were
actually completely insensitive to the
feeding
time such just like the clock core clock
genes in the brown
depos however other genes that are
mainly metabolic seem to be shifting so
this was also telling us that daytime
feeding basically eating at the wrong
time of the day in the organism can
cause like a traumatic um misalignment
even within an specific tissue in where
some genes are able to readjust their
24-hour profile uh to the new feeding
fasting Cycles whereas the other one are
unable so we are creating this
uncoupling that could potentially be
influencing um metabolic H
disruption um so again this was qpcr so
we said okay what is happening
genomewide so for this we compareed a
mRNA sick across all the 24 48 Hours
sampling between the control group and
the C day which was most different one
and what we can see in this uh
24hour in this what we call frequency
plot what we can see is like most of the
jeans 18% almost 18% of the jeans are
oscillating in the aditum control even a
little bit more than the
liver and what here what we are seeing
is that most of the genes that were
oscillating would actually have its peak
of
expression 8 hours after the light
during the normal rest phase of the
organism however when we do daytime
feeding we can see that the they still
have this
most of like many genes are
still picking at ct8 but then half of
the other genes now are picking 12 hours
later what means that this internal
misalignment that we were seeing with
few genes that we saw before it was
actually something more
widespread and when we looked at uh gene
expression um geneontology analysis of
the genes that are cycling in the Prados
tissue
uh what was very interesting for us is
that even within um each Pathways we
could find jeans that were completely
insensitive to the feeding time we can
see that both day A Time feeding and the
control at lium have exactly the same
profile whereas others have completely
shifted and this is true not only for
this pathway but basically every pathway
way that um that is cycling in the pros
show this a split dual Behavior so now
we still have a lot of questions as to
what this is happening and one of them
is of course is like if these internal
splits uh in the Prados tissue rhythms
caused by misaligned feeding can be
actually H contributing to this
detrimental H Health toll that we see
when we eat at the wrong time of day so
basically this is like a little summary
so my are nocturnal so we can um adjust
their feeding time when we so mice are
nocturnal meaning that they normally eat
during the night time but now if we are
forcing the mice to eat at the wrong
time of the day when we go to the Animal
Facility and we do our experiments like
really during the day day time this can
be um causing an unexpected changes not
only in Behavior like we saw before but
also at molecular level by shifting few
not all of the rhythmic genes that we
are expecting to
see so with this a a conclusion for this
is that the timing matters but basically
it's important to look what are the
tissues when are we doing the
intervention and when are we sampling
to keep all of this in consideration to
H try to really deeply understand what
is the effect of um an intervention on a
particular Gene of
interest and with
that H this is basically a followup
experiment now what we are actively
trying to look for is like whether this
internal split in the brosious is
because there are two cell types one
that is responding to feeding and one
that is responding to the local clock or
if instead there are different
transcription factors that can
differentially regulate the expression
of those
genes and this is just to give like a
larger perspective as to why H do we
care about all of this during the aging
process is that we know that we are
living longer than ever and we also know
that now aging has
exposed has been um shown that aging is
a major risk factor for basically
developing many of the chronic diseases
and there is a lot of efforts um
suggesting that basically we are like at
least one 30% of our life living
unhealthy so now there is a lot of
effort from the science H scientific
Community but also from the Health Care
system a lot of effort put into how can
we actually reduce this um amount of
time that we are unhealthy and our H
goal in the Circadian biology of Aging
unit is we are going to try to
understand circadian biology of aging
and try to promote um healthier and
longer life spans by targeting these
circadian
clocks and basically we are going to H
look at many uh different aspects from
multiomics to behavioral readouts trying
to identify which could be Cadian
markers that we can use to track aging
progression and if we can understand how
the clock H system ages whether we can
fix it and hopefully reverse or at least
delay a whole marks of aging and of
course most of um the studies normally
Target one population usually c57 black
6j mice but the question is like whether
we are able to find interventions that
are actually working uh not just from
one specific strain but also that art
can be universally um used in females in
different genetic backgrounds and
hopefully H in
humans and this is our team at the
Cadian biology of Aging unit we just
started
um eight month ago and we are basically
trying to tackle using Mouse models and
hopefully humans eventually H trying to
tackle very broad questions for instance
how that do circadian clocks age and
contribute to the onset of
um basically virally any um chronic
disease that is associated with aging
whether we can find biomarkers in blood
or in different tissues and what it's
happening when we are doing intervention
either dietary or phac or a combination
with pharmacological interventions and
we can track um the entire duration of a
um a
lifespan and hopefully in the future not
too long from now uh we are going to try
to see whether this the basic science
that we see in mice it's also applicable
to humans and makis and this is because
here it would be very very important to
consider actually how mice are nocturnal
and we are diona so with that I would
like to thank all of you but also my
mentors um Joe and Carla because that's
when I decided that yes we could
actually do big big big H experiments
take advantage of all the resources and
this massive project and yeah that's it
thank you
all thank you very much um so we're
going to go on to the Q&A portion so
Cynthia too asked a question have you
had a chance to see how different
circadium Rhythm affects body
composition clean versus fat
Mass Yes actually yeah I didn't include
it here but yes um basically we don't
see an effect we only see an effect of
caloric restriction so all calorically
restricted group have less um fat Mass
compared to the ad libitum but there is
no difference between um CR groups that
kind explain lifespan
differences yeah I think that answered
question I had a question myself
actually so
um have you like have you also monitored
um metrics in blood like uh LDL
cholesterol like these things might go
like your metabolism might not function
as well because you're under stress from
not sleeping so is that really uh
something you can measure
yeah so we did not measure col so we do
we do have measurements of glucose um
that's the only rout that we have and
hormones so we didn't do any lipid
um panel for the blood um what we know
so overall levels again glucose is the
same so the CR groups have lower glucose
levels in circulation that they ad leave
but there is no difference between the
them when we looked at the overall
levels but now when we looked at the
24hour profile we can see that it's the
opposite
um glucose levels are slightly elevated
when the organism is
eating um same thing happens even more
dramatically with insulin and leptin
levels as soon as the might switched
their feeding Behavior whenever they are
forced to eat at the wrong time time of
the day the 24hour profile it actually
shifts you had a question from an
anonymous attendee from your liver RNA
seek were there any Pathways that were
affected by aging that actually
improveed by
ciria if there is any pathway that we're
actually uh yes so any Pathways that
were affected by aging that were
improved by Circa or
yes
so yes and this was mainly related to
immune function also like a further
Improvement on of immune
function so that that also corresponded
to like reduction in inflammation and
inflammation
biomarkers
yes
um did you also are you also planning a
looking at massolution signatures as the
interface between environment and gene
expression yes so actually we did and
now I do have mutilation clocks uh in
all of these groups and again what we
can see is the age prediction for the
calorically restricted group is younger
than the atli but I don't see difference
between the C RS among them but now what
I'm trying to do is actually since I
have DNA methylation and gene
expression now trying to match these two
and see whether I can find like what are
the minimum number of genes or sides
that can actually account for these
differences very good
question do you expect to see I used to
work in a methylation lab so do you
expect to see um kind of like a overlap
or convergence between the genes that
are methylated and the ones that have
differential expression
yes especially for those
um that are jeans that are down
regulated with aging so I think like in
this case might be more for the
metabolic genes but I'm not sure for the
immune function genes which are the ones
that usually pop up
so any other questions so um I assume
you're going to do this at the Single
Cell level so you're going single cell
sequencing in different tissues of the
brain and maybe like the liver and some
other
tissues yeah so for this I
um yes so I'm trying to
select what are the tissues that are
going to be more
significant because of course a single
cell is very very expensive and I also
want to do two time points at least 12
hours apart because I'm not only
interested in like changes in overall
but actually how the our ability to tell
time changes as we age so yeah I think
like yeah definitely looking at the
brain liver we know a lot about the
liver but maybe another more interesting
Gene and tissue would be white fat and
brown fat because you know we start
multiplying the number of tissues with
time points and yeah I think it's going
to be interesting to know this at single
cell
11 yeah it is expensive and when you do
lot the tissues it compounds very
quickly the the the price tie comes up
it's super
interesting um if we have any other
questions we can take now if you can
post your questions in the Q&A so it's
very interesting and very very relevant
it's also in the media a lot caloric
restriction for um
longevity
um so is a plan to use a single cell
sequ thing and also like metabolic
markers are you going to dig deeper into
the pathways and specific cell types to
figure out if um uh you know if there's
a a certain biomarker or cell type that
is more
susceptible to to caloric
restriction right so I think like one of
the aspect and taking advantage of being
here at NIH that I can do like
longitudinal um studies we are actually
setting up a circadian
behavioral um
room um it's yes trying to do like
longit static with more
biomarkers and yes collecting tissues
for single cell like
U yeah the the question I had was um do
you think a 12h hour sampling has enough
resolution to pick up these
fluctuations no to pick up 24 circadian
rhythms definitely not but to pick up um
information on things that are different
throughout the
day yes but definitely is not enough
even four hours is actually the limit of
the resolution that we need to detect
circadian
rhythms so uh if no one else has any
questions we are coming up to the hour
thank you very much once again for this
very interesting
talk okay thank you