that was a a a quick intro to what is
coming over the next few hours as we
celebrate accomplishments and
opportunities for the next few decades
in
Microsystems and materials and
semiconductors as we transition to to
the next ER part of our
program the next in in our agenda is a a
part
discussion about the past present and
future of our
community a panal discussion moderated
by Professor Jesus
delal a professor delal is the Doner
professor of electrical engineering at
MIT and a leaden researcher in Nano
Electronics specializing in compound
semiconductors white banga and ultra
white banga materials as well as Noble
devices to revolutionize AI Hardware
accelerators he earn his
telecommunication engineering degree
from the poly Technic University of
Madrid and his Masters and PhD degrees
from Stanford
University after working at NTT in Japan
he joined MIT and the MTL Community back
in
1988 and serve as director of the
Microsystems technology Laboratories
from from 2013 to
2019 Professor Delo is a fellow of i e
APS and mrss has been an editorinchief
of i e electron device letters and he
has received numerous Awards including
the Intel outstanding researcher award
and the IT play C brunetti award please
join me in welcoming professor delal and
his panel
[Applause]
thank you to much good morning I'd like
to welcome my panelists to uh to the
stage uh let me tell you who they
are Professor Rafael RVE has already
been introduced today he's the professor
of ECS former director of MTL department
head of uh former department head of ECS
Provost and president of M from 2012
from to 2022 and under his leadership
MIT Nano was conceived LOD and I will to
focus on on the topic of the panel
discussion I will make this introduction
very very brief then we have ra race
data I it's right
here race data what is
it ah there he is all right race data is
the founder and chairman of Analog
Devices he's also founded statea Venture
Partners rais a graduate of MIT and has
had a long lifelong Association uh with
MIT good
morning he he has been a stone supporter
of MTL over its entire existence and has
served as in the MIT Corporation for
many years and contributed to build the
Ray and Maria sta Center at MIT and then
we have Professor Dimitri Anis MRI
appropriately Dimitri is the Reay am
Maria sta professor in electrical
engineering at MIT and he he co-founded
as we as we he today and served as the
first director of MTL and then we have
Professor Vladimir bovich
Vladimir good morning good morning
Vladimir is the far boards Massy
professor professor in emerging
technology and a professor of electrical
engineering at MIT he's a former
director of MTL and the founding
director of MIT n um we don't have
microphones here oh you are miked yeah
yes you are okay excellent good good uh
all right let's uh let's get started uh
so it's been it's been 4 years as as
thas told us today and actually it only
seems yesterday that we celebrated the
30th Anniversary uh of MTL and so indeed
this is really an occasion to celebrate
as as I think to has really showed us
very well MTL has been a runaway success
over over many years in research and
education in Microsystems and nanot
Technology now in this panel we want to
reflect a little bit on the making of
MTL some of the early Visionary design
decisions that were made that brought us
to where we are today and that are also
shaping the future through MIT Nano and
through the future MTL now I wasn't here
in the early days as you saw in the in
the in the timeline um I came soon after
and I I see if I reflect back on Mt I
see five key design principles that uh
in my view profoundly shape the place
first one was the integration of
technology and system design as as thas
has explained very well the fact that we
build a share facility for everybody to
come together and share share the tools
and capabilities and the NOA and also
the computation and cut tools a focus an
initial focus on Silicon technology
although that evolved the integration of
research and education as opposed to
keep them separately and a very close
partnership with industry which endures
to today so so I think these design
decisions have endured to today but have
also evolved for example uh with my hire
uh MTL introduced compound
semiconductors into the into the
facility and that was sort of the
beginning of a major expansion and
diversification in the Technologies and
materials that MTL was to handle over
the years and and perhaps the best
Testament of MTL success is really MIT
Nano This truly amazing facility that we
have on campus deep in MIT Nano is
really the DNA of MTL but anyway rather
than me uh making all these Reflections
I will I think we all want to hear from
our distinguish panelists so let me let
me start I would like to start with
Dimitri as founding director of MTL so
Dimitri you were in MTL uh from the very
beginning and actually even before MTL
was MTL uh can you tell us about the
challenges that had to be overcome to
get MTL of the ground and some of the
early designed decisions that were made
for the lab and it's
facilities well the um let's start with
the early
uh uh design
considerations it was thought that this
new laboratory that would uh bring
together systems and semiconductors in
particular silicon
semiconductors was had to be
Central so the facility had to be
somewhere in the core of the
campus but of course as always happens
at MIT there's never enough space so we
had to evaluate several um
locations
including a um non-operational um uh
wind tunnel at where the u high uh hotel
is is now um I think perhaps it uh we
also looked at the
TRW uh old factory building somewhere in
this area that has long been torn
down uh Lincoln laboratory was also a
consideration um because there were very
strong supporters from the beginning of
establishing a strong silicon
facility but in the end what uh um
carried the day was uh actually a
relative courageous but Visionary um
decision at the time of the
administration take building 39 the most
expensive solution because we couldn't
tear down the building but uh it
um with the idea that uh Computing was
now becoming more and more uh
diffuse the building that was originally
designed to be a computer um Center
facility uh became pretty much available
there were some other offices in there
so that was the early um challenge that
we had to uh overcome but of course uh
always with consideration of how much it
was going to cost how we going to raise
the the funds and and all those uh
aspects so uh that that was the early
beginning
um perhaps I should mention that at the
time other
universities as well as MIT had silicon
facilities mostly teaching facilities
Stanford was perhaps the most uh
Advanced Berkeley as well and uh at that
time the thought at was we must have a
very strong presence in uh silicon so
that's why the original name was
uh LSI laboratory which been changed
yeah thank you uh Ray uh you were an
early champion and supporter of MIT in
its quest to set up a new program in
microelectronics uh in fact Analog
Devices was a founding member of the
Microsystems industrial group that has
supported MTL and in fact has remained a
member to this day we really we really
thank you for for your stone support of
MTL now back to the early 80s uh By the
time ntl was founded the micro industry
was already well on its way and so some
ad MIT thought it was inappropriate to
invest uh in a in a technology that was
already in research and educational
programs on a technology that was deemed
to be already quite mature now
fortunately uh those voices did not
Prevail and so what arguments did you
use you played a key role in this what
arguments did you use to sway these
decision in the direction of launching
ntl with the parameters that we have
been
discussing so so in the uh mid 70s uh
there was a group of companies in Boston
that got together called the
Massachusetts high Technology Council
and our objective was collectively to
influence uh the environment in such a
way that uh the high technology U
industry could continue to thrive and
develop here in
Massachusetts uh there were several
parts of the program but one of them was
uh the relationships between
universities and
Industry um and uh in looking at the
landscape of course MIT was a very
important part of that and uh we noted
that uh uh MIT was lagging in the
Silicon
area uh so as the first president of
mhdc I was given the mission of meeting
with the leadership of MI
uh to try to uh lay out at least
industry's view as to why that was not a
good
direction uh so U we had studied it and
uh uh had a good story uh we presented
that story to Professor gray was the
president at the time and others who
were concerned with this area uh and
made our case uh I'm not too sure uh
that uh what we had to say uh had a
tremendous impact on what was decided
but one way or the other I think um MIT
and in particular eecs uh begin to to
change the focus and to bring uh uh
silicon technology to the Forefront in
terms of research and
education um and um so that's how it
that's how we got going now uh Analog
Devices had a vested interest in MIT
becoming more vital in terms of silicon
technology uh we uh uh established a
professorship uh to uh help recruit uh
faculty from other universities who were
a little bit ahead of us and uh and as
it turns out the first recipient of that
is sitting right here Raphael uh when he
left uh Stanford to come to MIT uh he
was the first recipient of that
fellowship and uh you know later uh my
good friend here was also and and
several others uh not just what analog
did but the industry in general uh TR
did uh what we do to support uh MIT and
uh uh in research and education and this
area and U the uh the amazing thing with
within a relatively short period of time
uh MIT went from sort of nowhere at
least uh in in terms of the the views of
many in terms of silicon technology uh
to becoming uh you know a major player
uh and uh and that turned out to be just
in time uh as the government industry uh
put some very serious funding on the
table to help uh
universities uh to uh accelerate the
development of the
technology um so it all worked
out thank
you Rafael perhaps uh the most visible
manifestation of the runaway success of
of the MTL Venture is MIT Nano our new
nanofabrication facil
even today there is no facility that I
know of in any University environment
with the size and capabilities that MIT
Nano offers to us now colleagues or
other universities tell us that they
they find daunting the notion of
convincing their Board of Trustees to
put together something like MIT Nano in
their own campus you were president at
MIT you were president of MIT through
the gestation and the launch of MIT Nano
how did you accomplish this what what
were your arguments and and was it hard
I assume me was and what were your
greatest concerns when you try to sell
this
concept did you ask was it
hard how much time do we have three
minutes five
minutes look I think I think the
argument the argument was very simple um
it was and it was not that hard to
sell I think at the time um uh the
word word in the street in the street of
silicon Valley to begin with is that
software eats hardware for lunch if you
remember um the the mo the fundry model
already has been established fabulous
companies as thas mentioned earlier has
been established so the trend the
funding trend for this kind of effort
for Hardware stuff for for processing
for technology for hard technology was
beginning to erode companies were
becoming less interested because they
were looking at the value added which is
designed um however a few of us
certainly I was very much uh one of them
felt like that was a mistake and that
was going to come back to hurt us to
hurt the us so we felt strongly I feel
strongly that we had to have a presence
on the advanced technology of the modern
era um and that is what eventually
became MIT Nano the the luckily for us
uh the MIT Corporation supported the
view once they understood the vision um
and and my esteemed person at the right
uh had a lot to do with that um so so
that was not that hard but it took a
while and again it's a it's a leap of
faith that you will build it and they
will come uh because again the funding
was not there the the the funding agency
from the federal government were not
there and so forth um once that was
decided and we moveed forward I mean the
the Miracle of MIT is that we had an
individual who was driven like crazy to
make it happen and that's Vladimir
bulovic who worked very very hard for
this to become a reality um and and the
truth is that time proved us right um in
two years ago some of you may remember
uh while the chips and science Act was
moving uh in Washington the US Secretary
of Commerce uh wanted to see a place
like this and she came to see MIT Nano
by herself and she was so extremely
impressed that by the end of the visit
she turned to me and said the US needs
10 MIT Nanos so I think I think it went
full circle but but time Prov us right
it was an aggressive uh decision that
the might made but I'm delighted that we
made it and I'm delighted that we're
here today celebrating not just the 40
Years of MTL but all the accomplishments
that we will be able to move forward
thanks to MIT Nano
thank so Vladimir your name has been
mentioned you are the founding director
of of MIT Nano you led the way in
conceiving this project and bringing it
to fruition as Rafael told us now in the
early days most critically you help
Rafael to sell this concept to the MIT
Corporation mit's Board of
juses this must have been a very
intimidating request uh given the
complexities of the project and and its
and its size so can you tell us how you
approach it
um obviously you were successful but how
how how the meetings
went thank for thank you for asking
because I really I'm a junior partner
here uh my president president r at the
time uh was indeed a key mover and
Shaker Mary Schmidt the Provost um was
the other key mover and Shaker my job
was to imagine ways to tell the story
and add to their voices that were
already very powerful um you know the
key to Innovation is human friction uh
the key to us launching next set of
ideas is because we happen to bump into
each other and we do a lot more when we
are together than we stand alone so the
result of it was the key is well let's
map where the inventions are made on
this campus and we made a heat map a
couple of years before we inv invented
even MIT Nano and realized that the
buildings on campus that are easy to
reach and that mix multiple disciplines
happened to be just the hot spots of
innovation so the key to building a
might Nano it needed to be right in the
center of Campus it needed to be
connected to every discipline and it
needed to be able to be reached by every
discipline so those are the metrics so
how do you reach them because you are
asking to build in the middle of Campus
it's about 20% more expensive than
choosing a spot outside right well the
very simple answer is for all of our
drive to make a community as the driving
force you needed to come up with
technical reasons it turns out that
vibration in the ground at the site of
MIT Nano is the lowest vibration on the
campus available sites and when it comes
to management of chemical affluence it's
easier in the middle of a campus than in
a residential area at the edge of the
campus there are many other elements
just like that and guided by my
colleagues like VI diuk uh we were able
to Think Through various elements that
justify the physical reason the next
thing is simply let's make sure the
culture of it indeed will be able to
Encompass everyone because it just turns
out that MTL tools at the time at the
time that I was director 20% of the time
we did use them to make micro electronic
devices analog and digital circuits but
80% of the time we were inventing new
medical devices new Energy Systems those
very same precise nanoc skill tools were
opening new Vistas that we couldn't even
imagine so let's make sure the space is
enabling us to have everyone step into
it and the easy way to do that if it's
going to be in the center of campus and
connected to all the buildings let's
make sure no one has an office inside
this building no faculty at least staff
needed and that way generate a community
today that has 1,500 users from 40
different departments labs and centers
well that was a vision um we could again
pin it on the opportunity and the
opportunity was build communities and
that human friction that leads to
innovation like we could never do before
uh through the words of what Rafael and
Marty were able to do indeed Corporation
was convinced and I think all of us and
the world are way better for it yeah
yeah
thanks Dimitri coming back to the uh
early days you as the first director of
MTL you were in charge over the
formative years of a lab and how the
ideas behind the mission of MTL evolve
as the operation uh got going off the
ground and what were the major
challenges that had to be
overcome well the original ideas uh came
from the U fact that U silicon was
becoming uh ubiquitous in uh
microelectronics um MIT had uh as race
had you know lagged
behind um other universities for sure
and um the
um the design of a new LSI facility at
MIT was to address uh this connection
between design of large scale integrated
circuits that was
becoming um more and more popularized
through the um uh M corway uh system and
uh
um the Advent of seamour of course and
um the uh device research MIT had a
strong device research in the area of 3
five materials photonic
materials uh but it did not have a
strong effort in um uh silicon devices I
should mention however that Steve
Centuria had the beginnings of MS also
in uh his uh
um his uh chemical sensor transition
that was built actually in a educational
facility in Building
13 so the original idea was that we will
connect with the design Community
within uh
MIT in the on the computer science side
there was a lot of support at the time
uh for that
and as we were building the facility so
the facility was designed actually the
centerpiece was a 6,000 um square feet
um class 10 sorry class uh 100 facility
with localized class stands and um that
was to do simos fabrication you have to
also realize that at the time the
concept of fabulous
didn't quite
exist and uh many companies that had a
strong presence in microelectronics felt
it necessary
to
establish
silicon microfabrication
facilities and um so that actually
helped at the time you know with as Ray
was saying in uh raising the profile of
the need uh here at MIT and uh the
initial
support
however if I go a little uh further down
the line
maybe within u a year or two that we
started uh putting the facility together
it became
obvious uh
that it would be more than just making
circuits in uh in Silicon
in fact uh I remember very uh well
sitting down with uh my colleagues and
trying to think what should we call this
new facility that's where the name of
MTL came
Microsystems so make it all encompassing
even though at the time we're thinking
silicon
based and um the discipline that we
tried to establish was all simos driven
and uh
the evaluation of Technologies to
undertake in the lab and so forth was
all based on how do we maintain the
cleanliness necessary to achieve large
circuits these were the um early
thoughts behind how the building was
designed with a um integrated circuits
uh lab on the second floor and then the
fourth floor for being the more um the
more uh liberal lab if you like this is
where Rafel put his EP reactor for
example um and um then the individual
faculty Laboratories that eventually
absorbed the
Microsystems uh the sorry
the circuits lab the the um Building
13 yeah
Ray uh so here we are uh 40 years later
and as I like to tell uh the students in
my classes the microelectronics industry
remains as useful as
ever uh but it has been transformed many
times over so as an industry leader as
and as an investor and champion in
startups in this domain what new
opportunities do you see ahead of us
that we should be getting our students
prepared
for help me a little bit what was
I for the future what that for the
future oh the future
yeah well we we see
U uh a great opportunity in phonics and
uh being able to integrate uh
photonic technology more fully with
electronics uh there's been some stabs
at that uh but we're nowhere near to
where we can be will be so frankly I
think that's one of the areas that uh uh
we look forward to uh working in and
making some
progress um the other thing is that as
we move to untethered devices battery
operated devices uh there's no such
thing as uh low power it's ultra low
power so I think we have to go back and
revisit uh both the technology and the
circuit uh architectures to see what we
can do to uh minimize uh the the power
requirement of a electronic
circuits uh there's another uh
phenomenon uh Brian author is an is a
scholar who's looked at the various uh
waves of Technology development and the
electricity and chemistry and aviations
and and and there as as try to uh
discern whether there's some kind of uh
commonality uh what goes on in in uh uh
Innovation development and uh anyway he
he came to the conclusion that uh in
every one of these waves there was a
what he calls the Tipping Point where
the uh focus of innovation shifts from
the parts to the whole uh and what he uh
called calls uh combinatorial
Innovation uh the performance of the
parts uh for many applications is quite
adequate uh but you can do a much better
job um if you uh integrate these into a
a systems element and I think uh we're
well into that we see this uh at our
company uh in terms of what customers
want they don't want to buy a bag of
parts and figure how to put them
together they saying that's your job uh
so they're pushing back on the
semiconductor suppliers to provide more
complete
Solutions um and we're just sort of at
the um beginning of that uh you know the
chipet technology is is one of the ways
of of U fulfilling that vision and uh
right now now there's uh a hundred
different ideas about how to uh create
Advanced packaging and ship of
technology and I think that the extent
to which that can be more
standardized uh the more quickly we can
move along and I think uh there's a
contribution that uh universities can
make in uh bringing together industry
and and coming to some
agreement uh about uh how to do that in
a more uh Universal way I remember
perhaps 15 20 years ago Charlie sodini
uh gave a talk about uh you know what
what's going to be the next uh big thing
in terms of consumer consumer uh
electronics and uh he concluded it was
going to be medical devices and I think
here we are today with our smart watches
and our smart
Rings uh and we're at the very very
early stages now of fully exploiting uh
the capability of uh of electronic
devices photo electronic
devices uh for U enhancing health care
and the hospitals just can't afford to
expand
indefinitely uh so having uh a hospital
at home remote uh
Diagnostics uh a lot of things where it
doesn't consume capital on the part of
our hospitals is kind of where we're
heading and uh there's a just a
tremendous opportunity for the
development of more sophisticated uh
sensing
devices um a more uh holistic uh uh
system solutions to U health care
problems so there's a long way to travel
there I think today the size of the
semiconductor industry is estimated to
be on the order of $500
billion and I think those who study
these various Trends and try to put them
together uh believe that the industry
will be uh1 and half trillion dollars by
2020 that that uh 2030 that that may be
a bit
optimistic uh but nonetheless uh
uh an industry which is
substantially multiples of the size that
we have today is surely in the future so
we have uh We've Just Begun to Fight uh
nobody quite knows or understands what
the implications of AI is on all this uh
but clearly uh there's uh there's
inklings of uh of great happenings there
which will require U hardware and
software and new uh new combinations to
accommodate uh that whole
opportunity so it isn't uh really most
of the companies in this business today
are not struggling for
opportunity uh the the problem is
there's it's like a kid in a candy store
I mean it's just there's so many uh
delightful things
uh to to uh to munch on uh that the real
trick is being smart and trying to
figure out which of these are the ones
that from a commercial point of view are
going to Blossom sooner than others uh
and as I say a lot of that will have to
do uh with the uh coment oal Innovation
more complete uh Solutions that's not to
say that there still aren't great
opportunities for a continued
Improvement of Technology at the
component level I mentioned power
consumption as just one of of of many
aspects of that so I think we're in for
a very exciting decade ahead uh one of
the uh concerns we have uh I is that uh
because of the the great appeal of
computer science and artificial
intelligence you know all the smart
young students are running in that
direction and uh when we look at the
enrollments here at MIT and e or things
that would be a little closer to the
semiconductor technology it's atrophied
and I think we're uh we're struggling
with figuring out ways to convince
students uh that there really is a
future in semiconductors uh because not
everybody believes that and certainly
many students don't in comparison okay
to the unknown appeal of the AI uh so we
have some work ahead of us in industry
and in universities uh to keep this
thing going um and uh to take the full
advantage of what uh uh semiconductor
technology uh can can bring to bear on
our society and I I I think it's
predictable that more and more and more
uh the technology where oriented
products of any Dimension is going to
have um uh electronics as the
fundamental supporting technology thank
you Rafael so continuing to think about
the future uh you play a you played a
decisive role in in
DC uh in the formulation of the chips
and science act and through the chips
act as we know the US is making a big
push to reclaim semiconductor
manufacturing leadership and through the
science act the US is to invest in
research to sustain that leadership into
the future now we see the chips sack
well on its way but the science act
seems languishing in in the halls of
Congress um why does it seem that it was
harder to sell the science Act is is
there a chance that we can save
it you hear
me you hear me now yeah
um the the uh what became the Chiefs and
science act actually started maybe seven
years ago eight years ago or so and and
thas when he started his presentation he
showed the beginning of everything in
fact he even claimed that that happened
at MTL which is a transistor the
semiconductor transistor uh in
1947 right um but but but that's an
that's an excellent point because that
was the beginning of all the Innovations
in technology in so many areas up to
today when we talk about AI we need to
build those huge data centers and and
you have to buy thousands and thousands
of gpus from Nvidia and they come from
that little transistor that that thas
mentioned in
1947 so what I was thinking is um what
kind of scientific infrastructure or
funding infrastructure is needed to come
up with the equivalent of the transistor
for the next 75 years because we have
lived from that idea for the last almost
80 years or so and and and when you look
at that Discovery uh which got a Nobel
Prize it was not really a discovery I
mean the baps researchers were asked to
replace the vacuum tube find something
that was less less Les less bulky
consumes less energy be much smaller and
go and create that and think about how
to advance the science to make that
possible and there were several groups
competing to replace the vacuum tube
that unobtainable goal and this group
won and got the semiconductor I think it
was germanium at the very beginning so
that concept of looking for an
unobtainable and having people Advance
the science to get there that's what I
thought we needed to bring back there is
no baps uh we do have Google and
Microsoft and they spend a lot of money
on on basic science and research but not
the same kind so what I thought we
needed is what what what we call in the
scientific Community use inspired basic
research so you have an unobtainable
goal Advance the science to get there
and that was the concept that I was
trying that I was selling in Congress
and uh uh it was a little harder to sell
Congress on that than to sell the MIT
corporation on MIT Nano uh but but we
were making progress um and he was
advancing U Senator Schumer uh then
minority leader of the Senate but then
became Majority Leader uh he Advanced
the concept and he called that the
endless Frontier act in honor of of
vanar bush so that was moving and then
we had
covid Co showed that we all of a sudden
didn't have a supply of the chips we
needed from other countries uh and even
from our own home country so it it it
atifi the problem that we said earlier
that we had to bring back with M might
Nano identify the fact that we don't
have Fabrication in this country not
enough of it so then that that required
a movement that yes the future is fine
but the present is in trouble so let's
bring manufacturing back to the us and
that was I was okay with that as long as
we also fund the research to advance
from this point on so to bring a five
media technology to America and leave it
there in 3 years will'll be behind the
the technology ology anyway so I was
fine with bringing that back as long as
we have also the funding to advance it
from here on so that was the chaps part
of the chips and science Act and the
endless Frontier part for the future was
the science act so basically there were
a bunch of senators that like the
science part were a bunch of senators
that liked the te Chiefs part Senator
Schumer a brilliant politician brought
all of them together and say you want
your part then vote for both and and
that's how the chips and science side
became a part of what we are today and
and it was
bipartisan all that is the Good News
Congress recognizing the importance of
this for the economy of the nation
advancing in universities the role of
universities I also wanted that a new
director an NSF to be created to fund
this use inspired research which
actually happened all that is great news
the less great news is that when it came
to
Appropriations the cheapest part got
appropriated the part of bringing
manufacturing back and the part of
advancing it from here for packaging and
so forth that was
appropriated the science part the part
for the next 75 years was very little of
it was appropriated and and we're still
working on that but now it's going to
become harder and harder so that's the
story for the Chiefs and science act
yeah yeah thank you Rael we're running
our of time and I am I'm really itching
to to to ask you a question um and I
find striking that former ntl directors
have gone to Great achievements and
responsibilities at the highest levels
of University Administration you as MIT
president marish smid as Provost of MIT
and now president of RPI anatha Chandra
as of engineering so there is probably
no other unit at MIT with this kind of a
legacy what's in the water in building
39 what what makes this job of MTL
director uh such a ground to then
achieve uh such great responsibilities
in at the highest level of University
Administration there must be something
in the water right I mean um look I
think you saw uh uh I think Tomas made a
terrific job when he showed a slide
showing the number I forget how many
pictures of professors you had on that
slide working in MTL and there are 30 40
50 there just a large number of them
coming from all over MIT I think you
know I think if you have uh the job of
director which Dimitri had and I had and
a few others had and you have to Corral
uh 50 MIT professors from different
parts of MIT to work together and to
share a facility if you think that's an
easy job I'll tell you you're wrong so
if you have the skills to do something
like that you have the skills to do
anything else at
MIT thank you thank you Rafael uh all
right I see that we have one minute left
and I see that there is a question that
has come in U I'm not sure that we have
time for all to answer but the question
is two pieces of advice maybe let's s on
one one piece of advice per panelist for
each of you to that would solidify the
future plans of MTL and the MIT
Community given the extreme impact that
this community has had one future advice
let's start with you I I think the
strength of MTL is the fact that it
integrates Microsystems uh it's the fact
that there is a device there is a system
there an application the vision is
always there uh techn economics is even
a part of it I think it's incredibly
powerful that's the key to what makes
MTL such an incredibly powerful
intellectual organization
yeah which is microphone microphone oh
yeah continue to support
multidisciplinary research which was
actually the what we went through uh in
the development of Mt yeah we started
from Silicon and we became this wide
Community uh grabbing from all kinds of
places of MIT that didn't even imagine
at the beginning yeah uh Ray Ray yeah I
one of the uh great learning lessons
from the uh Focus Center research uh
program that was in the 80s and early
'90s
is the
uh tremendous benefits uh when uh
industry and Academia really uh
collaborate on a uh on a deep level uh
with the best Minds in the industry and
the best mines in uh Academia get
together around well defined
areas uh and and then with the uh the
funds from the government governments
and Industry and other sources to have
the resources uh to work to get
constructively to solve problems so that
uh that lesson I think we can apply as
we go to the Future and must apply as we
go to the Future and and find ways of
bringing uh industry and Academia
together in in much closer
collaboration learning to solve the
conflict of interest problems and
competitive problems as we did very
successfully in the
semiconductor period uh but the kind of
progress that was made in that 10 or 15E
period was quite remarkable I think
unprecedented in history uh and so we
need to repeat that uh uh uh along
different dimensions but still uh seeing
the mutual benefit of working together
and and having policies in the federal
government that understands uh the value
of that and provides the kind of support
that's needed yeah thank you Rafael
finish with
you look I the the U the advice that I
can think of is almost not an advice but
a wish um whether for MTL for MIT Nano
or or for the whole of MIT which is you
know think think about that discovery of
the
transistor just just imagine that period
in which people were still playing with
vacuum
tubes my my aspiration my wish is that
the brain power of this place can think
of the
unobtainable something we need something
we we we demand to have uh that is going
to help Humanity help us whether it's in
the medical domain or whatever think
about that that we need an advanced the
science to get there that's that's what
we do great and that's what we should do
more of and that's what we should just
dedicate ourselves to yeah with that
please thank these uh the panel for a
very enlightening discussion