like a lot of architects throughout
history, um uh I'm a practitioner who
also looks a lot at history. And so I I
like to uh um just like architects in
the Renaissance looked at Roman
examples, um uh I've learned a lot
especially from the uh thinking about
the history of technology and the
history of um of thinking about the city
um as I've tried to imagine new and and
important ways of practice today. So um
uh you know one example um uh in in the
local code book that I wrote about the
um at that point the over 3,000 designs
that we' produced using these kinds of
systems. I also looked uh historically
at at three um uh important figures uh
who influenced the work in in their in
their writing. Some of them were very
well known like the urban um uh urban
thinker Jane Jacobs very revolutionary
thinker thinker in about the city in the
20th century um famously duled with
Robert Moses um uh then uh also uh an
artist like Gordon Madlark who was doing
work with um they parcels in New York
City in the 1970s but also um actually
right before his death was very
interested in community education and
engagement.
around these sites um in particular on
the Lower East Side and then less known
figures like Howard Fischer who was the
inventor of modern GIS as an architect
uh uh at the Graduate School of Design
um at Harvard um but then whose work was
taken and and transformed into modern
mapping systems in a way that he um did
not appreciate and was against the
earlier kind of collective spirit of his
work. So all of these things um uh uh
are important to me in terms of making a
link between um historical ways of
thinking but also how we need to change
them to practice effectively in the
present. I mean I think for me the the
kind of intellectual history is pretty
important. So lots of people know about
Jane Jacobs, but lots of people don't
necessarily know that um uh you know her
only uh uh formal education um uh was
actually um uh uh involved a great deal
of learning about evolution evolutionary
biology and natural systems and how they
worked. So when in her famous book death
and life of great American cities at at
the um you know at the very beginning
she says I won't use a single metaphor
in this book in this book cities need to
be thought about as they are but then
constantly throughout the book she's
using words like ganglia and uh uh uh
and vessels and and and all kinds of
words from natural systems and and what
she's really doing is making an
assertion that a city is uh to a certain
extent a natural system or we need to
understand it as such something that's
evolved over time uh just like our own
complex bodies and needs to be treated
as such and not you know in her terms
you know hacked around and and amputated
and and uh uh as many urban designers
were um at the time she was writing or a
figure like Gordon Madclar is you know
famous for cutting buildings in half um
uh and a range of artistic practices but
um what's less wellknown about him was
first of all the the grounding of a lot
of his art artistic work in a kind of
critique of urban redevelopment because
it was urban redevelopment that was
making you condemned homes available to
slice up and do things with. And then
also that again right before he um died
too young in 1977, he was shifting his
work towards um community education in
the context of abandoned sites in the uh
building sites or vacant lots in the on
the lower side. And this was a very
important pivot in his work. So, um, you
know, we always, uh, uh, one great, um,
uh, truth of, uh, of, uh, the world of
ideas, if is if you think you understand
something, you're probably wrong. And
so, uh, you know, I always like to kind
of dig under the surface of these things
that we think we know. Um, especially
things that are fundamental to thinking
about certain kinds of practice that I
care about. And and usually the the
truth is way more interesting.