our first speaker is Professor Chris
zaras a leading expert in urban mobility
and head of mit's Department of urban
studies and planning please join me to
in welcoming Professor zes for the open
remarks um thank you very much Graham uh
huge thanks to ILP for organizing this
event and allowing us to feature some of
the work of our Department um and of
course thanks to everyone in the
audience for attending and for your
interest uh I just was going to give a
very brief overview of dusp the
Department of urban studies and planning
here at MIT some of my own perspectives
on this idea of a smart City based on my
own work but mostly talk about some of
the works of other colleagues in our
department um other than the great ones
that you will actually hear from later
on uh today um can you please and we are
advancing so I do have to uh we are
advancing remotely so I do have to ask
to please advance to the next slide uh
we're uh dusp is an amazing intellectual
community that I'm really honored and
privileged to be a part of we have an
impressively diverse faculty that
represent a range of fields and
disciplines Urban Design to anthropology
engineering to economics uh law
epidemiology computer science planning
among many others um and while we are a
highly multi-disciplinary faculty who
truly span the globe in our research um
in our teaching and our collaborations
we are united in our mission if you
could please advance um and that is to
prepare leaders to plan design and
create communities in places that are
socially economically and
environmentally just uh we we've
operationalized this message through
sorry this m mission through four
strategic priorities achieving racial
and economic Justice um tackling the
climate crisis and enhancing
multi-racial Democratic governance um
and um we uh aim to fulfill this Mission
if you could please Advance through all
aspects of our teaching research and
departmental culture and external
collaborations with three basic guiding
principles if you could please Advance
um this includes um providing a learning
environment that can nurture the next
generation of
leaders um generate knowledge through a
range of methods and disciplines working
closely uh through long-term
Partnerships with people in specific
places for a global scale impact if you
could please Advance the
slides
um I guess maybe the slides are not
advancing um uh and integrating across
our teaching our research Arch our
external Partnerships to always Foster
um a supportive and inclusive culture of
creativity and experimentation um if you
could please Advance uh we have a broad
and thriving research ecosystem that
operates through a range of
action-oriented labs some of whom you'll
hear from today including sensible City
lab and the city form lab um and I what
I think is somewhat unique about our
work relative to MIT um more broadly and
it's because it's fundamental to the
field of planning is is that we have
direct and deep engagement with
stakeholders um uh this includes um
community members um uh government
agencies uh Transit operators other um
public private Partnerships and of
course a range of private companies uh
through work of some of which you hear
today again like sensible City and the
city for lab and the Civic data Design
Lab um typically we we have to engage
across these and other types of
stakeholders when we do our work um when
we think about City Planning
um you know the Enterprise of the city
development we're trying to maximize
quality of life through the provision of
Mobility Health livelihoods shelter Etc
um and we engage in this work through a
range of um methods tools and means
including economic and financial
analysis Community engagement the design
of cities physically and of course we
use Computing for design analysis
machine learning for inference etc etc
these are not mutually exclusive methods
in fact typically we bring them together
um uh because you know we can use for
example computer D driven design
analysis and you'll hear a little about
about that later on today from my
colleague Andre seon um if you could
please Advance our our research
ecosystem as I said is pretty rich we
have a range of types of projects these
projects do focus in our strategic
priorities that I mentioned earlier and
I you'll hear a few of these today I
encourage you to go look at our website
to um where you can learn in much more
depth the range of research projects
that we've been undertaking over the
last decade or so at least now if you
could please advance I want to get to
this topic of smart cities um when we
think about smart cities I think we
normally start thinking about Computing
and devices data science and AI right of
course that's a key piece of it um DP
itself has been very much at the
Forefront of integrating Computing into
planning since the very early days in
fact um and we all know that these
capabilities are not just changing today
the way we do planning um but also uh
what we um um what how we plan what
we're planning for um I view always I
think we need to view competing as the
means to the ends you know and if we
think about this in terms of um the four
dimensions that I think are relevant for
data um for for planning this includes
data visualization data collection
modeling and simulation uh visualization
and control and
optimization um again I said that's has
been at the Forefront of this this
includes it recently we have a
partnership with the College of
computing um um and the computer science
department with an undergrad degree in
um we call
116 um uh urban planning and computer
science uh or sorry Urban science and
planning with computer science and
currently we're in the midst of a search
for a shared appointment with the
College of computing in the areas of
computing and health of the planet um if
you could please Advance um well I'll
skip over this in the interest of time I
think what I want to just keep in mind
here this this this um Cube that I I
show here puts the values front and
center once more I think any our our our
leveraging of computing of capabilities
to help do um the work we need to do to
create a a high quality of life for
people is always driven by our values
that believe in equity accountability
transparency and and inclusivity um if
you could please advance to the next
slide once more when we think about
smart cities I think many of us
immediately think about devices and the
power epitomize for example in a
smartphone um and if you could please
Advance my own work has actually been
relatedly focused over time um you know
oh I we have these Computing
capabilities how might we use these to
plan better but I think I'd like us to
step back a little bit if we may just
for a moment to inspire a bit this this
concept a bit more profoundly um you
know I think we should fundamentally
revisit this premise if you could please
Advance um cities have always been smart
right they're the smartest places on the
planet because of the concentrations of
people and firms and the spillovers that
we're all familiar with that we can call
marcelian economies or glomeration
economies C cities are where Innovation
happens and so I'd like us to be
thinking about people Centric people
first smart cities dusp is fortunate
enough to have many colleagues uh who
are pioneering work in this field I
highlight for example the work of
Mariana Araya who's a planner and a
social epidemiologist she led the
development of the healthy neighborhoods
Consortium which is an initiative which
actually starts the research Enterprise
first and foremost with close
collaboration with communities this idea
of generating resident researchers
mobilizing and co-developing projects
with them her work has proved to be in
in incredibly pre for example in
predicting where covid would outbreak
first and who would be most Gravely
affected by covid because um the the
sensors the most high resolution sensors
are actually people in place um and so
this work leverages this um she's
currently doing some work with
communities and colleagues in
architecture on how we can model
building energy retrofits for the most
benefit of the people who live in those
buildings as another example um if you
could please advance another great
example comes from my colleague cath
diasio who's worked quite closely with
regional networks um across Latin
America both activists and Scholars and
the work has been focused on how we can
reduce the exposure to violence
particularly violence against women um
and the nature of the work uses AI to do
a better job but to identify the
violence that's not otherwise observed
um so AI comes in the back end here
through machine learning classifiers and
so forth but the critical Dimension is
that the whole process is participatory
um the the building of the technology um
and um designing what the task actually
should be how to construct for example
proper samples for training data how to
create the schema uh for uh for labeling
data um for the evaluation of the
approach and for further guiding
additional data collection and a
critical aspect here has not only been
the technology but more importantly I
would I would say she would agree with
me has been the community that has been
generated across the region that is
actively working with these tools on a
critical dimension of um that's
affecting the region if you could
advance I just wanted to talk quickly
about one other project my colleague
Caroline Crockett who has this project
that she calls um hacking the archives
so hacking of course is a very MIT uh um
um uh uh typical MIT inherently MIT
approach but it's merged with this
historical Memorial AR approach of
archiving which is a basically aimed at
challenging traditional knowledge
hierarchies and social exclusions if you
could please Advance sorry that should
have been at that next slide I won't
have time to get into it in detail um
but just a a few if you could Advance
please um if you um
uh um one more slide please so her work
through a participatory process is focus
on topics of fundamental concern to
communities such as the racial wealth
Gap um so she's generated projects that
have focused on this uh particular
Dimension if you advert it merges
essentially the social and the digital
if you could advance to another slide um
I just in the interest of time I'll have
to jump over this if you could Advance
also to the next slide um she's uh
including focusing on issues of cultural
relevance such as um the the history of
jazz um uh please advance in short I
believe her this work that I've
highlighted quite briefly represents
just another critical and
underappreciated and underutilized
approach to the traditional Smart City
rhetoric and practice right bringing
traditional methods merging them with
the Advanced Digital Technologies um to
actually bring projects that are deeply
meaningful to the people that inhabit
the places that are fundamental to this
whole concept of smart city so if you
could advance to the last slide i' just
like to end to highlight a few
principles that I'd like all Smart City
practitioners aspirants and others to
keep front and center in the pursuit of
their work this um is um you know
starting with a fundamental theory of
change of what we think we're trying to
achieve with this work recognizing that
we're often working in communities that
made reconciliation and reparation all
of this work should be transparent it
should be deeply embedded in context and
history epitomized in the work for
example of um Carolyn Crockett focus on
uplifting the assets and the agency of
the communities that we're working in
protecting those same people from um
potential violations or concerns with
respect to how we do research and then
ultimately sending uh centering the
leadership of communities in this type
of work not only in doing the work but
decisions based on this work again the
work the the the the projects that
Mariana Araya has has led um epitomize
this and then always in a fundamentally
Pro a fundamental process of continuous
critique and self-reflection again
involving those same communities so that
we are we are sure we're actually
embracing the smart city
concept with a people first perspective
um I appreciate so much your time thanks
gram for the invitation I Greatful for
the opportunity to share some of this
with you today and looking forward to
the rest of this event thank you very
much Professor Zoras for the inside for
open
remark that actually set up set the
perfect stage for today's discussions