the MIT energy initiative presents Joy
d08 bridging careers in Aerospace
manufacturing and Fusion Energy with a
focus on intentional inclusion written
by Turner
Jackson a big theme of my life has been
focusing on intentional inclusion and
how I can create environments where
people can really bring their whole
authentic selves to work says joy d08 as
the head of operations at Commonwealth
Fusion systems an MIT spin out working
to achieve commercial Fusion Energy dun
looks for solutions to the world's
greatest climate challenges while
creating an open and Equitable work
environment where everyone can
succeed this theme has been cultivated
throughout her professional and personal
life including as a young Global leader
at the world economic forum and as a
board member at out for undergrad an
organization that works with LGBT Q Plus
college students to help them achieve
their personal and professional goals
through her careers both in Aerospace
and energy D has strived to instill a
sense of equity and inclusion From the
Inside
Out developing a love for
space dun's childhood was shaped by
space I was really inspired as a kid to
be an astronaut she says and for me that
never stopped dun's parents both of whom
had careers in the Aerospace industry
encouraged her from an early age to
pursue her interests from building model
rockets to visiting the National Air and
Space Museum to attending space camp a
large inspiration for this passion arose
when she received a signed photo from
Sally Ride the first American woman in
space that read to Joy reach for the
stars as her interest continued to grow
in middle school she and her mom looked
to see what it would take to become an
astronaut asking questions such as what
are the common career paths
and what schools did astronauts
typically go to they quickly found that
MIT was at the top of that list and by
seventh grade Dunn had cter sites on the
Institute after years of hard work Dunn
entered MIT in the fall of 2004 with a
major in Aerospace aeronautical and
astronautical Engineering Aero Astro at
MIT she remained fully committed to her
passion while also expanding into other
activities such as Varsity Softball the
MIT undergraduate Association and the
alpha Kai Omega sority one of the
highlights of dun's college career was
unified engineering course 16 a
year-long course required for all
aeroastro majors that provides a
foundational knowledge of aerospace
engineering culminating in a team
competition where students design and
build remote controlled planes to be
pitted against each other my team
actually got first place which was very
exciting and I honestly give a lot of
that credit to our pilot pilot he did a
very good job of not crashing in fact
that pilot was Warren hoberg 08 a former
assistant professor in aeroastro and
current NASA Astronaut training for a
mission on the International Space
Station pursuing her passion at
SpaceX dun's undergraduate experience
culminated with an internship at the
Aerospace manufacturing company SpaceX
in the summer of
2008 it was by far my favorite
internship of the ones that I had in
college I got to work on really Hands-On
projects and had the same amount of
responsibility as a full-time employee
by the end of the internship she was
hired as a propulsion development
engineer for the dragon spacecraft where
she helped to build the thrusters for
the first dragon mission eventually she
transferred to the role of manufacturing
engineer a lot of what I've done in my
life is building things and looking for
process improvements so was a natural
fit from there she Rose through the
ranks eventually becoming the senior
manager of spacecraft manufacturing
engineering where she oversaw all the
manufacturing test and integration
Engineers working on Dragon it was
pretty incredible to go from building
thrusters to building the whole vehicle
she says during her tenure Dunn also
co-founded spacex's women's Network and
its LGBT affinity group out and Allied
it was about providing spaces for
employees to get together and provide a
sense of community she says through
these groups she helped start mentorship
and community outreach programs as well
as helped grow the pipeline of women and
Leadership roles for the company in
spite of all her successes at SpaceX she
couldn't help but think about what came
next I had been at SpaceX for almost a
decade and had these thoughts of do I
want to do another Tour of Duty or look
at doing something else the main
criteria I set for myself was to do
something that is equally or more world
changing than SpaceX
a pivot to
Fusion it was at this time in 2018 that
dun received an email from a former
Mentor asking if she had heard about a
Fusion Energy startup called
Commonwealth Fusion systems CFS that
worked with the MIT plasma science and
fusion Center I didn't know much about
Fusion at all I had heard about it as a
science project that was still many many
years away as a viable energy source
after learning more about the technology
and Company I was just like holy cow
this has the potential to be even more
world changing than what SpaceX is doing
she adds I decided that I wanted to
spend my time and brain power focusing
on cleaning up the planet instead of
getting off it after connecting with CFS
CEO Bob mum guard sm15 phd5 Jun joined
the company and returned to Cambridge as
the head of manufacturing while moving
from the Aerospace industry to Fusion
Energy was a large shift she said her
first project building a fusion relevant
high temperature superconducting magnet
capable of achieving 20 Tesla tied back
into her life of being a builder who
likes to get her hands on things over
the course of 2 years she oversaw the
production and scaling of the magnet
manufacturing process when she first
came in the magnets were being
constructed in a timec consuming and
manual way one of the things I'm most
proud of from this project is teaching
MIT research scientists how to think
Lake manufacturing Engineers she says it
was a great symbiotic relationship the
MIT folks taught us the physics and
science behind the magnets and we came
in to figure out how to make them into a
more manufacturable product in September
2021 CFS tested this high temperature
superconducting magnet and achieved its
goal of 20 Tesla this was a pivotal
moment for the company that brought it
one step closer to achieving its goal of
producing net positive fusion power now
CFS has begun work on a new campus in
Devon Mass Massachusetts to house their
manufacturing operations and Spark
Fusion device dun plays a pivotal role
in this expansion as well in March 2021
she was promoted to the head of
operations which expanded her
responsibilities Beyond managing
manufacturing to include facilities
construction safety and quality it's
been incredible to watch the campus grow
from a pile of dirt into full buildings
in addition to the groundbreaking work
dun highlights the culture of inclusive
as something that makes CFS stand apart
to her one of the main reasons that Drew
me to CFS was hearing from the company
Founders about their thoughts on
diversity equity and inclusion and how
they wanted to make that a key Focus for
their company that's been so important
in my career and I'm really excited to
see how much that's valued at CFS the
company has carried this out through
programs such as Fusion inclusion an
initiative that aims to build a strong
and inclusive community From the Inside
Out dun stresses the impact that Fusion
can have on our world and for addressing
issues of environmental Injustice
through an equitable distribution of
power and electricity adding that's a
huge lever that we have I'm excited to
watch CFS grow and for us to make a
really positive impact on the world in
that way