main question is like how can I help my
people when I came to India I saw this
potential of for example how technology
is affecting people's life here from
medical schools from universities even
if you go to a small shop there is like
integrated of technology and that was my
main motive to get into computer science
and from that point onwards I was
thinking okay I have learned all this
stuff for free now how can I give it
back to my community
[Music]
welcome to open liners a podcast that
tells the stories of Learners all over
the world who use mit's open courseware
I'm Emanuel Li kasigi an open larner
myself from campala Uganda in East
Africa and I'm Michael Jordan Pilgreen
an open learner from Memphis
Tennessee hey Emanuel how are you doing
I'm good Michael I'm good excited
excited excited as we just heard in the
clip my the top of the episode today's
learner is all about using what he
learned from ocw to give back to his
community do you want to tell us a
little bit more about him yeah sure uh
today's guest is lad F andish man he's
originally from Afghanistan and is
currently living in India he has a
bachelor's degree in electrical and
electronics engineering and has
completed a number of ocw courses in the
computer science and computational
thinking field he's currently working on
his MIT micr Masters in statistics and
data science with the support of
emerging Talent after completing his
micr Masters in December Lula plans to
continue studying artificial
intelligence at a doctoral level and as
we've already mentioned one of Lula's
motivations for studying computer
science and technology is so that he can
create products and applications for
people in his home country of
Afghanistan he is particularly
interested in wanting to create open
learning resources that are taught in
the languages people in Afghanistan
actually speak that way everyone can
benefit from open learning the way he
did and he's made that hope a reality
earlier this year L fulla help launch
hosman lab an online learning
application that provides online
learning programming classes taught in
pan and Topol of FL FL Engineers the
software himself which is quite
impressive yeah it's really cool and it
took a lot for him to get to the place
where he's launching his own app in our
interview he tells us about how he used
to use the Moonlight to guide him
through his small Afghani Village to
learn chemistry from his uncle Before
Dawn and he's really never stopped
learning ever since I'm excited for our
audience to hear more about L's
curiosity and generosity his our
conversation with L andish from
Afghanistan
as AF
[Music]
asence hello everyone my name
is and my last name is andman I'm from
Afghanistan currently residing in India
and here I my I'm pursuing my
education and my main focus
and my main area of education is
computer science and artificial
intelligence uh so usually we like to
ask people you know how was your life
before finding open learning what were
you doing were you working were in
school like could maybe give us a brief
background on that when I was in
Afghanistan I used to live in a village
a place where there were plenty of
Natural Resources Rivers the mountains
and the clean ear a peaceful place to
live we the beautiful EOS of birds added
more to its richness everything was in
harmony with the nature but there was an
issue we did not have access to the
internet and there was very little
electricity my father always used to say
to me that we did not have this
opportunity as you have now please don't
waste it by the meantime when I was
living in my Village I had an uncle who
was very good in chemistry in fact
basically he was the best in the subject
during the day as he was busy with his
own work I was not able to reach him and
ask him for help but during night I was
used to go go to his house and ask him
to help me in my studies especially in
chemistry basically because uh we did
not have that much of electricity and I
used to rely on the Moonlight to
navigate to his home sometimes when
there was no Moonlight I had to take the
help of Walls by touching those walls
and go to his home and on the other
instance for example we had a religious
scholar which he was far away from our
own village he used to teach on that
vage for one hour about Arabic and some
information about our religion and I had
to wake up before the dawn of the day
and I have to be there before everyone
else because his main responsibility was
to teach to those people not for me but
I had to be the first one to reach there
and take my lessons and come back to my
home just a quick question so like how
did you go from your village to uh Cabo
like how'd you like get into the
traditional education and what is the
traditional education in
Afghanistan from first grade till
seventh grade I used to study in my
Village so we are having schools and
then up to 12th grade we will be
studying in schools and after that we
will be having an exam to go to
universities if you pass that exam and
then when I was in 7 and eighth grade
that amount of resources were not
sufficient for me and my father used to
push me to go more and to learn more and
through him I got those connection for
example that religious scholar and then
my uncle was obviously he was my
relative so he was there to offer and
help me and then after seven and eighth
grade because my uncle told me like you
have to move to cble because there we
had like for example electricity
internet was there then have had access
to better education then for four or
five years I used to study in kab so
when did you first
encounter ocw was it in any of those
grades or was it when you're heading
towards University at what point in that
educational Journey for the first time I
had to study too hard to get into
University and then when I passed that
exam I went to the university and
basically the curriculums were mostly
similar to the US because the kble
University was uh mainly supported by us
universities and Japanese universities
and we had some sort of same subjects
and then there we had one subject physic
one the curriculum was almost the same
as what we they used to teach in the USA
and then one day my friend brought one
lecture series and he showed me that
have you seen this uh then we started
looking for around 30 minutes into that
lecture series and then I asked him from
where you got this and do you have all
of these lecture series and he said yes
and then asked him please can you
transfer all these lecture series to my
flash card and then I got those lecture
series and like for around two months
three months I was watching them and
really I was stunned by the amount of
passion uh the easiness of understanding
those lectures that was the first moment
watch which I came to know about mitw
that was through a YouTube channel you
can say and then there was not that much
of high speeed internet in Afghanistan
we had this kind of Internet collapse
where there is a high speeed internet
and then if we pay for some amount then
in the exchange we will get for example
for 1 hour or 30 minutes of high speed
internet and then for example whenever I
was curious to know about something or
had difficulty in my studies I used to
go there and search the first time I
used to go through mitw website and then
I was looking whether this course is
available or whether something related
to my question or my subject is
available in the
mitw and if something was there then I
used to download PDFs I used to download
videos and come back to home and watch
all those lectures and read all all
those materials oh wow so you discovered
it through YouTube first me too me too
um I discovered through YouTube then
later I found out there were all these
other you know websites and so many open
learning resources that's a very
inspiring journey I wanted to ask
something about the language in which
the
traditional education back home was
storing you said yes they had a lot of
American influence in the education
system in Cabo but was it all in English
or it was all in Arabic and then because
ocw is in English and I wanted to know
how that was for you I would say this is
a point where most of us are finding
difficult to follow these lectures
because not all people are familiar with
English
and the language which we used to study
in Afghanistan is Persian and pasu in
kab it was Persian even though the books
were in English but uh teachers and
professors used to teach in Persian oh
persan and then for us it was a bit
difficult to follow the mitw lectures
unless we had previous education and
previous background in English some of
us used to follow private courses in
Afghanistan to learn English and luckily
I was one of those which I could uh
follow the lectures and understand the
concepts and the lessons and you know as
you started using uh these open
educational
resources did it start changing um how
you were performing in your traditional
education as well like were you getting
better
grades um or were you just learning more
about life in the world and it just made
you feel better as a human being maybe
you could talk about how it was making
you feel as you found this stuff how is
it affecting you personally yeah in fact
uh apart from getting uh good grades or
helping me in uh getting good grads in
in University in fact like it was kind
of an eye openening moment for me it was
not like just okay I will follow this
few subjects which I had in the
University but in fact it had opened my
eyes on different subjects on different
areas for example I didn't know anything
about computers are programming really I
didn't know like we didn't have that
much of idea like how much this computer
science and technology is changing the
world because in Afghanistan we we are
not that much advanced in the field and
we are not that much taking advantage of
this Fields so that's how it's not that
much famous in Afghanistan but through
mitw courses I came to know about
computer science and
programming and I feel that education is
not only about getting great in fact if
you're curious about something to know
more and then you are going deeper into
it and you getting better materials to
help you to understand the world uh that
that that's what matters the most for me
it's not only about getting grad you've
mentioned you had no idea of computer
science so I wanted to know did you end
up inevitably because there are some
things you're working on in the computer
science related field is that what you
are studying first of all in University
and then transition position into like
this whole new field of computer science
how was that for you no in fact I was
studying electrical and electronics
engineering so in Afghanistan especially
we don't have that much of subjects in
related to computer programming first
there I came to know about discourses
and then when I came to India here we
had subjects in this field in
programming even though the branch was
the same but because of different
curriculums we had a few subjects from
computer science as well there is a
course from intro to computer science
and programming using python from
MCW and there are different versions of
it for example one was released earlier
and I like that one actually because
that Professor used to go more into
behind the concepts he used to teach
maths and later on for example now we
are having only slides and I don't like
that I like more of the traditional way
of using that white chart and Blackboard
yeah me too I like the sound of choke on
board it's really it's
therapeutic uh so you mentioned you did
electrical was that a passion is that
something you wanted to do is that
something that's widely done in terms of
your passions in life like the things
you like has ocw contributed a lot to
that outside the things you have to
learn you know because we all have
things we have to learn you know either
for the job or to get grades or you
mention something like that but any
other thing outside like something you
just enjoy learning yeah about my Branch
it's not that popular in Afghanistan in
fact they're more of civil engineering
and construction then as I mentioned
earlier that the way of navigating to my
uncle home so I was like okay can we do
something about electrical engineering
so that I I can help people to have more
electricity in my Village and then yeah
that was the main motive for me to
pursue electrical and electronics
engineering and honestly when I came to
University that was not what I thought
like there were like different
misalignments between what I thought I
will be getting into universities and
then what was really there uh coming
through the your question about was
programming was part of my passion in
fact yeah there also like always I see
like how can I my main question is like
how can I help my people that's my main
passion when I came to India I saw this
potential of uh for example how
technology is honestly affecting
people's life here and from everywhere
every from medical schools from
universities to the even if you go to a
small shop there is like there is
integrated of technology and for example
Computer Sciences there people are using
it and making the people's life easier
there and that was my main motive to get
into computer science and
like I was trying to how can I help my
people there and from that point onwards
I was thinking of okay I have learned
all this stuff for free now how can I
give it back to my community and then I
came about an idea of like uh having an
online platform where students from
Afghanistan can learn about programming
and computer science because it's not
that much familiar for s in Afghanistan
and then even if it's their people will
find difficult to get resources in their
own languages as I mentioned earlier one
of the problem which we had in about
mitw and most of these materials out
outside of Afghanistan is that most of
these materials are available in English
and many people in Afghanistan don't
know English so like I thought of how
can
I not make a clone
of which I cannot just for example few
subjects which really getting them to
the uh uction to the computer science
and learn about computer science okay
this computer science is existed and
this really can help them in their
future and help other people in
Afghanistan as
[Music]
well you know you talked about how open
educational resources changed what you
were doing and your vision of the future
and you're working on this app now is
there anything else on the app you're
developing that you want want to tell us
about yeah basically that web
application is not a mobile app it's an
a web application where I have recorded
videos and I will put those videos in in
that application and then related to
that we will be having assignments we'll
be having GitHub repository with related
to each lecture where they can go and
grab the code also as we go on if the
people like the material we will be
having online classes like just for
example you are having from University
so that there will be a direct
interaction
between instructor and between the
students I think that can be more
helpful rather than just putting the
contents there nice and you're planning
to do all this in Persian English Arabic
yeah the content will be completely in
Persian because our native languages are
Persian and PTU mostly the people are
using these two languages and for now I
will be adding uh the contents in
Persian language and then later on I
might do it in p as well but for now it
will be in pers that's really awesome
one question we get uh from the director
of MIT open course whereare but if you
had magical abilities you had a magic
wand is there anything that you would
want to see happen with open educational
resources at MIT I feel I want two
things to happen first one is I want MIT
ocw to be Universal knowledge of where
all students can come and learn from it
on top of that I want all the lectures
be there from mitw because now all of
them are not there I want all the
lectures to be there for example if the
lecture is recorded today I want them to
be there in the
mitw and then the other thing is just it
would be my wish if we have lectures in
all
languages for example in different
languages so that everyone can
regardless of their native language can
come and learn well you could help
because I'm seeing Pion is spoken by
around 70 million people so yeah who
knows but I also feel you on the languag
is bit yeah yeah I would also suggest
the same how does your vision of the
future and the future of the world
change when you think about open
educational resources do you see there
being many more opportunities for more
Learners like you or what do you kind of
see when you think of the future now
that you've used open educational
resources yeah honestly speaking it
helped me to understand that if we
Empower other people without expecting
something in return definitely if that
return is not directly to us and that
will help other people's lives
and then sometimes seeing all this
cruelty around the world and uneven
distribution of resources and
opportunities around the world it makes
me sad to think that we are living in
this world and then seeing courses and
institutions like MIT Stanford car
millon where they are putting all their
contents for free for other people to
learn that makes me believe more into
the humanity and there is Al fredman I'm
listening more to his podcast he always
says that I believe more that humans
will prevail and I believe that in to by
seeing this all contributions from other
institutions from MIT and I feel that as
long as we are helping each other we can
have a better world and our Humanity
will prevail for sure I feel you
education should be it's what's actually
Chang in the world it's how we change
the world and clearly we have examples
of that working your own journey is a
clear Testament to that I really liked
your journey all the way from like the
ruler part you know studying by the
Moonlight I can relate to that I also
grow up in the village then you come to
like the town part of your country and
then so in all this I just wanted to
know do you see yourself continuing
first of all to use ocw materials first
and foremost that would be my first
question and the second one maybe would
be how do you see yourself now you know
a lot has changed okay first of all
about am I still learning I think I'm
young and even though it doesn't matter
that much how old or how young you are
as a human being we should always learn
and be more curious to know about our
universe about our nature
and definitely yeah I do I do honestly
like as of now this mitw and open
education resources from other resources
these are these are my main resources
where I'm learning and getting my
answers yeah my advice would be for my
younger self
to believe in
yourself believe in your guts which you
can do any anything possible and do not
restrict your imagination to these
things which you can see around there
are many things and more things uh which
you can explore and do just not related
to your
[Music]
environment another great conversation
manual L fulla's life really changed a
lot from using the Moonlight to to guide
him to chemistry classes that his uncle
would teach at his house to living in
India and starting his own
application and I love how he's so
dedicated to paying it forward for his
community what's your biggest takeaway
from our conversation with Le fer I
agree with you Michael my biggest
takeaway I guess would
be how much a person can achieve you see
laf has done a lot not only did he just
power through the Limited of his
environment to go and Achieve great
things go to India on scholarships but
he's also doing a lot not only did he
plan to develop a platform to give back
home but he engineered it himself which
goes to show the heart that some of our
Learners really have and how much they
really enjoy these resources that they
feel that they should give back to the
community for a person who was just
receiving courses on a flash dis to a
person who's now giving back that same
service that same reward to his
community that to me is a really noble
cause and something that's really
inspiring to the rest of our Learners so
anything else you want to add Michael
what was your takeaway from this story
yeah I think lul is a living example of
what the open Learning Community is all
about especially at MIT uh we have all
these resources open
courseware um but everything can be
better and the idea behind open learning
in general is what can you add to this
story now and Lula has added a lot so
you know translating everything that
he's learned to Persian on its own is a
Monumental task but then creating an
application to share that information
freely was just another layer of
extraordinary giving back to the
community and I think it is a great
example for all of us to drive to is if
you benefit from these
resources if you benefit from learning
figure out how to share it with your
community with your family with your
friends and don't stop there just keep
going because when you pay it forward it
always comes back to you I hear you I
hear you uh thanks to everyone for
tuning into our conversation with L
andish man originally from Afghanistan
and is currently residing in India don't
forget to check out latas applic hman
loves we'll put a link in our show notes
just to make it easy for you and we'll
be back in two weeks with another story
from a different Learner in the global
ocw Community see you
then open Learners is produced by alexas
hot special thanks to the supporters and
donors who make ocw possible to learn
more about mit's Open courseware and to
check out the courses mentioned in this
episode visit the the ocw website at
ocw.mit.edu
[Music]