Technology has transformed the outlook
for the disabled. The main problem of
communicating for people like me who
can't speak is what is called the baud
rate. That is the rate at which
information can be conveyed. One might
be able to operate a switch two or three
times a second. This would mean that one
could send information at a rate of two
or three bits a second. One bit of
information is the answer to a yes no
question. By contrast, normal speech has
an information flow rate of between 50
and 75 bits a second. However, the real
information flow in human speech is much
less than this. In the case of political
speeches, it is practically zero.
For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe, or