in this video we'll look at a beautiful
result that provides us with the
existence of graphs with high girth and
high chromatic number and it's a very
nice demonstration of the power of the
probabilistic
method we'll recall some definitions
given a graph G its chromatic number is
the minimum number of colors we need to
color the vertices of the graph G so
that no Edge has both end points
receiving the same
color the girth of a graph G is the
length of the shortest cycle for example
the following
graph has scur
four because the shortest cycle in this
graph has length form and there are a
couple of
them another
example is this graph
here there are many cycles but the
shortest one has length three it is this
triangle up here so the girth is
three if the graph is a
tree then he has no cycles in which case
we say that its girth is infinite
okay so what can we say about girth and
chromatic number
well suppose your graph contains a
click on K
vertices then just to color this click
we need at least K different colors so
then the chromatic number
is at least
K can we say something in the reverse
Direction suppose we have a graph with
high chromatic
number would it be possible to deduce
some local information
about the graph for example would it be
possible to say that if we have very
high chromatic number then there must be
a triangle somewhere in the graph or
there's some fairly dense structure
that's very local in this
graph so the main theorem that we'll
present in this video gives a definitive
no to this question
and it is a classic result due to Paul
erish from the
50s and the statement of theorem is the
following for
any positive integers K and
L there exists
a
graph there exists a
graph with
girth
L girth bigger than L and chromatic
number
bigger than
K okay so let's pause for a moment and
think about what this theorem is saying
so given any K&L no matter how large we
can find a graph there exists a graph
for which there are no short Cycles no
cycles of length and most L and
furthermore to properly color the
vertices of the graph you need at least
you need strictly more than K colors
so even though this graph has very high
chromatic number around every vertex if
you only look not too far away then the
graph locally looks like a tree because
there are no short
Cycles so in particular having high
chromatic number does not give you local
information and eror shows that there
always
exists counter examples to such a
statement if we want some local
information from High chromatic
number okay so the rest of this video
will concern the proof of ERS
theorem it's quite a miraculous result
and certainly before ERS proved this
result there were other resulting graph
theory that constructed very explicit
graphs that have some large chromatic
number and girth but not for all values
of K and those constructions are in some
sense very Hands-On it tells you how
exactly how to construct these graphs
but they were not able to get
arbitrarily large girth and chromatic
number A's Insight is to use Randomness
use the probabilistic method and show
that by appropriately modifying a random
graph one can achieve the desired
outcome so let's see how this works
we'll Begin by taking an random graph
GNP so this is the a
r random
graph
and there nend vertices
and um The Edge probability is
p meaning that we flip a probability P
coin for each possible Edge and put down
an edge
independently with probability P between
every pair of
vertices
right so let G be drawn from this
distribution so G is this random
graph now
let's take a specific choice of
P being log n^ s Over N turns out other
choices of P work as long as P Falls in
some range but for concreteness we'll
take this very specific choice of P so
this is a random graph and let's
construct the random variable
X defined to be the number of
cycles of
length at most
l in G okay so these are short Cycles in
G and these are the cycles that we want
to avoid because we want to construct a
graph with girth strictly larger than l
so we really do not like these
Cycles it will be nice if there were not
too many such Cycles so let's compute
the expected value of
x for this computation we use linearity
of
expectations and look over all possible
cycle lengths from 3 to
L right so I is the target cycle length
and for cycles of length
I there are n choose I different choices
of
which I vertices the Cycles can
involve and once you specify those
vertices there are IUS one factorial
different permutations circular
permutations of these vertices and we
divide it by two
because a cycle could be counted in two
different directions and they will
correspond to the same
cycle so
so this quantity here is the number of
cycles of
length I in the complete graph on N
vertices with all edges
present for each such possible cycle the
probability that the cycle appears in G
is p to the I so the second term
here is probability
that
this
cycle
appears in
GMP okay this is some expression it's a
little complicated but we can simplify
it and do some approximations to Upper
bound this
quantity so you see that the
um n choose I if you expand it in terms
of
factorials one can upper bound this
quantity by n to the I so incorporating
the um the first two
factors and then leaving P to the I
factor
intact
okay we chose P so that P * n equals to
log s of M and
so we can rewrite this quantity
here like
this okay uh there are L terms here so
let
me furthermore upper bound this
expression by L Times log n to
the 2 L here L is a constant so this
quantity here is some growth and the
rate of some power of a log and
certainly
much slower growing compared to the
function n so it's little o of n okay
it's a fairly crude approximation but
will be sufficient for our
purposes so this is a calculation
conclusion can be read as the expected
number of short Cycles is fairly
small well if there are few short Cycles
we
can get rid of all of them to get a
graph without short Cycles so this is
the basic idea of the alteration method
in the probabilistic method okay so
start with this GMP this random
graph it's not going to get us what we
want right away but we're going to do
something to fix the defects in this
graph in this case get rid of short
Cycles to that end that is known that by
markov's
inequality the
probability that the number of short
Cycles here short means length and most
L the probability that the number of of
short Cycles X is at least n / two is
upper bounded by the expectation of x
divided by n /2
and because expectation of X is little o
of n this final quantity is little o of
one is the case to zero as n goes to
Infinity okay
so this is a good sign right so means
that typically the graph does not have
very many short Cycles has fewer than n
/ two and then eventually we'll be able
to get rid of one Edge from each cycle
to get us a graph with still fairly
large number of vertices but there are
no short Cycles left in this after the
alteration now let's think about
chromatic number so we want to ensure
that the graph that we end up having has
high chromatic
number to that
end we'll recall the following
fact if we give you a graph
G then the chromatic number of G so this
is Kai of G so that's the chromatic
number well the chromatic number is the
minimum number of colors that one need
to color the vertices of the graph so
that no Edge has the same color on both
sides in particular every color class
right so if you look at a single color
like red and look at the vertices
colored by that
color these vertices have no edges
directly between them and so they form
an independent set so each color class
is an independent set and so the number
of color classes you
need then should be at least the number
of vertices divided by the independence
number this is the size of the largest
independent set so this Alpha of the
independence number is the
size of the
largest independent
set indeed each color class is
independent set and each independent set
has size at most Alpha of G and
therefore the number of colors you need
should be at least the number of
vertices divided by the independence
number
okay now for
every
H the probability that the independence
number so after here see that it makes
sense to think about the independence
number the probability that Independence
number is bigger than
H
is and most the following so here we'll
use Union
sound for
each H vertex subset of which there are
n choose H such H vertex subsets the
probability that those H vertices from
an independent
set is the probability that there are no
edges appearing among these H vertices
and that's 1 minus P raised to the power
H choose
two okay so this is some expression and
we can do some manipulations to simplify
this
expression yielding an upper bound of n
to the H times so the latter expression
we can simplify it as so upper bounded
by e to the minus
p h h -1 / 2 right so 1 minus
p
is less than e to the minus p
okay simplifying further we see that
this expression can be
Rewritten this
way and now let's make a choice for what
H I want to set so let's set H to be the
quantity which for now seems a little
mysterious but it turns out to be a
natural thing to set after we see what
the calculation looks like so we set H
to be this quantity three * log n over p
and knowing what P was from earlier uh
this quantity is 3 n
over log
n if we set H to be this quantity here
then you see that here in this
expression the numerator here um can be
simplified and the
result is that this expression de
case According to some rate which is n
to something that is a minus
constant something on a constant word in
particular it goes to zero as n goes to
infinity and that's really the only
thing that we need for uh that we need
out of this
calculation so if we set H to be of an
appropriate quantity then typically one
does not have independent sets of size
at least H in the
graph
okay so let's regroup so we proved a
couple of
things first we show that typically so
when I say typically I mean with
probability approaching one as Ang goes
to Infinity so typically this graph does
not
have short Cycles meaning cycles of
length and most L and also typically
this graph does not have large
independent
sets okay now let us put everything
together
so by
choosing and sufficiently large
we can
simultaneously ensure that the
probability that X the number of short
Cycles exceeds n /2 is strictly less
than
half and the probability that the
independence number
exceeds H is also strictly less than
half okay so both of these are quantity
quantities that decay to zero as n goes
to Infinity so by choosing sufficiently
r n we can make sure both probabilities
are strictly less than 1/2 and therefore
there is some possibility that lie
outside both
events thus there
exists a graph
G
with
fewer
than n / two
cycles of
length at most
L
and furthermore its independent number
the size of the largest independent set
is at
most H which we said earlier to be 3n
over log
n okay so we have such a graph G that
has these nice
properties well we're looking for a
graph with high girth well here G has
not too many short Cycles so we can get
rid of one vertex from each short
cycle to remove all the short Cycles so
remove a
Vertex from each short cycle the each
cycle of
length at
most
l so remove one vertex from each such
cycle and
doing so results in a subgraph g
Prime and then we know that the girth of
G
Prime is strictly larger than L because
we got rid of all the short
cycles and furthermore the chromatic
number of G
Prime is by what we saw earlier at least
the number of vertices of G Prime
divided by its independ
number well the number of vertices is at
least n / two because we removed at most
n /2 vertices from G to obtain G
Prime the independence number of G Prime
well the independence number of G
Prime is at most the independence number
of G because any independent set in G
Prime is automatically independent set
in G and here we saw that
the independent number of G Prime is at
most H which is three log n over 3 n
over log
n so we have in the denominator 3n
over
login
and whole expression simplifies to log n
/ 6
which is bigger than the constant that
we were given K as
long as n is sufficiently
large
and thus G Prime
satisfies the desired
requirements okay this finishes the
proof of this theorem of airush that
there exists graphs with arbitrarily
large girth and arbitrarily large
chromatic
number to review some of the key ideas
in this proof we use the probabilistic
method with alterations to construct
first a random
graph with various parameters so that
this random graph typically has very few
short
Cycles so that we can then remove one
vertex from each short
cycle and get rid of all the short
cycles and this is a way to ensure large
growth to obtain High chromatic number
we note that this graph typically
has typically does not have large
independent
sets and so its independence number is
typically small and therefore the
independence number of the subgraph must
be typically small as well and having
small Independence number implies High
chromatic
number okay so it's a beautiful
illustration of the probabilistic method
with alterations that allows us to
deduce this highly counterintuitive
result
which was U quite surprising because in
previously various researchers have
tried to construct such examples of
graphs by hand explicitly but
successfully and ERS brought this
beautiful Insight that introducing
Randomness by looking at random graphs
one can indeed prove the existence of
graphs with highly counterintuitive
properties