So I I decided to teach 18156 this
semester about something called
projection theory. Um I think that
projection theory although it's not
usually highlighted in graduate real
analysis is a fairly fundamental thing
in analysis a little bit like like the
isoparametric inequality or the solef
inequality. maybe not quite that
fundamental, but uh but a a fairly basic
thing that comes up in a lot of
different places. Um and um I was
excited to teach you about it this
semester for a few reasons. Um uh so one
is that some some of the like core basic
question one of the core basic questions
in projection theory was just figured
out in the last couple years and it's
something that I'm excited about
learning about. Um so I wanted to so for
so that was one reason I was excited to
teach about it and the other reason is
that I have gradually seen it appearing
in more and more different places. Um
and so I wanted to sort of highlight the
way it comes up in a bunch of different
parts of math.
Um so today in the first class I'm going
to tell you do like an overview of
projection theory. I'm going to tell you
what like what it is um what the
questions are and um about some of the
different applications and maybe a
little bit about some of the different
ways we think about it.
Okay.
I guess it's a little crowded in the
back. Uh are we I guess the seats are
full. I'm going to start slowly. So if
you want if you want to grab a chair or
anything, feel free.
Okay.
So,
okay. So, the setup is that we are in RD
or maybe also a vector space over
another field later. And then we have
orthogonal projections. So V in RD is a
subspace
and pi subv is the orthogonal
projection.
Okay. Um and so so what we're going to
do is we're going to consider some set X
and RD and then you can take the
orthogonal projection of X in many
different directions for many different
V
um and we sort of study how that all
fits together
X and this guy
for
many different
So a slightly corny metaphor for what
we're doing is we're studying some set
and you can kind of look at the set from
many different directions. Um and we
want to uh sort of uh put together the
information from these different points
of view.
All right. So let me make a picture.
Um
red
So we'll come back to this picture a
bunch.
So maybe X is a set of red dots.
Okay. And then we can take the
projection of this set X onto different
planes.
So if I draw sort of a I'll draw one
plane over here. And if I project X onto
this plane.
[Applause]
Okay. Then I will get this.
So there is pi V1 of X.
Okay. But I have rigged this. So if I
project it onto a different plane,
something uh a bit interesting will
happen.
[Applause]
Okay.
So
here is a a different plane V2. And if I
project my set onto V2,
all of those points will kind of line up
on top of each other.
And all of those points will kind of
line up on top of each other.
And all of these points kind of line up
on top of each other.
Okay.
So here are my observations about this
situation.
So x itself is eight dots. And when I
projected x onto v1, there was still
eight dots.
But when I projected it onto v2, there
were only three dots because there were
a lot of coincidences where dots got
pushed on top of each other.
Okay. Now uh intuitively v2 is kind of
special and v_sub_1 is more typical. So
most most of the v's will be like v1 but
there'll be a few exceptional ones that
are like v2.
So intuition
is that uh v2
uh type situation is rare
and one of our goals is to make that
precise make a precise question and and
say precisely how rare is that sort of
behavior.
Okay. So, so informally if the set X is
kind of spread out, most of its
projections will also be kind of spread
out. There could be a few projections
where X gets kind of squished together.
And a projection estimate means we'll
try to quantify how often that happens
and show that it's rare.
Okay. So we will u make this precise in
a bunch of different ways. Um and um I
think the the most uh simple to ask
question is when the set x is a finite
set.
So so now let's suppose that x is a
finite set.
Okay. And I'm going to use a notation
that absolute value of x is the
cardality of x.
Okay.
Um
all right. So here's my setup. I'm going
to take X in R2
and E subs of X is going to be the set
of V. Oh, let me actually let me mention
another piece of notation. So, you know,
we're going to talk about all these
different subspaces V. So, there's a
name for the family of all subspaces.
It's called the Grossmanian.
Um so another piece of grossman is
notation is that the grossmanian of k
planes in RD
this is the set of uh v and rd where v
is a kdimensional
subspace
okay so e subs
is the set of v these are going to be
one-dimensional subspaces in R2
with the property
that
the cardality of pi v ofx is at most s.
Okay, so going back to our basic
picture, if these red dots were just
points, um then this v2 would be in e
sub3 of x because pi v2 is only three
points.
Okay.
So the first question if you like of
projection theory would be estimate
how many of these directions there are
the size of E s of X
in terms of
S and the size of X.
Okay.
So, what would be an interesting set X
to consider? What would be a set X of of
points or red dots that in many
different directions things would get
squished a lot?
Do people have any thoughts? What would
be an interesting X to look at?
>> Grid.
>> A grid. Yeah. Okay. So as an example,
let's look at a square grid.
So x is going to be the set of pairs a b
where a and b are integers and they go
from one up to n.
Okay, good. So, this set has small
projections in a bunch of different
directions. Let me make a a little bit
bigger.
Um, okay. So, so X has n squared points,
16 points in my picture. If I project it
down, I only get four points. If I
project it to the side, I only get four
points.
Um, if I project it at 45 degrees, I
also get rather few points.
Um, I project it at 45 degrees, the
fibers of the projection will look like
this.
And they'll each have many points.
And so, the projection itself will be
pretty small.
Are there other angles as well
where I could project it and uh it would
be pretty small?
>> Yeah, some rational angles. Yes. Okay.
So
if we project
x at a rational angle
um then uh
high v of x would be small.
I'll draw one more um which I think is
enough to get the to get the idea.
I remember when I first saw it I I could
see the 45 degrees and the vertical and
the horizontal. Um so if I project it
perpendicular to these orange lines
where it has slope like left one and up
two.
Um
all of those fibers will will also be
large and so that projection will also
be small.
Right?
Okay. Um cool. So we will compute it
tomorrow in the overview class. I'm not
going to do computations with you. But
if you do that, you will find the
following thing that ES of X
is around S^2 over the size of X for a
big range of of values of S.
So in between X to the half and say half
of X.
Yeah, for the grid.
Okay. Um, Erdos did basically this
computation in the 1960s and he made a
conjecture that the grid is the shape
that makes these the biggest. He said
slightly different language, but his
conjecture implied that the grid is the
configuration that makes these sets the
largest. Um and that turned out to be
true and it was proven in the early 80s
by Sami and Troder.
So they proved that if X is in R2 and S
is at most size of X over two um then
the size of ES of X is at most is at
most 1 plus a constant times what you
see for the grid.
Okay, so this can be considered in a way
one of the fundamental theorems of
projection theory. Um and I'll mention a
couple interesting things about the the
proof. Um okay so one so one thing is
the background of these people Erid Sami
and Troder um the these are people who
come from cominatorics. So this theorem
represents a connection between
combinotaurics and and projection theory
and we'll talk about some other aspects
as we go along. Um however this proof is
is not a
at least at the time was not a
traditional combinatorial proof. So they
first played around with a lot of
cominatorial things double counting and
things like that and they couldn't prove
it. Um and then the proof eventually
uses in a crucial way the topology of R2
a sort of interesting uh connection
between um topology and and and this
stuff. Um so I I'll just put here proof
based on topology.
Okay.
So this story uh is one important story
in projection theory but it's a very
discreet story about finite sets and
there's another more continuous more
analytic story which will be important
in our class um where instead of taking
a finite set and projecting it we take a
function which you can think of as like
a density function
before I transition there actually let
me pause here and see if there are there
any questions or comments so far.
>> Yeah. Um so for that theorem that the
grid is kind of the maximizes es of x
like is is that like kind of the the
only example or a kind of big class of
other examples that also reach that
bound.
>> Okay cool. So the question is um is the
grid the only example that's kind of
tight for this theorem or are there lots
of other examples? Yeah. So another
actually a third thing I like about
projection theory is that it's it's full
of open questions. So it is a
long-standing open question whether the
grid is basically the only example or
whether there are lots of others. Um in
terms of other examples that we know
about there are a few but I would
describe them all as very minor
variations on the grid and we can meet
them as we go along. Um but in terms of
a theorem in the other direction we know
very little. So it could it may or may
not be the case that there are many more
examples out there.
Nice. Um, other questions?
Okay, great. So, okay. So, now let me
describe a much more analytic framework
that also involves projections and and
we'll see that it's sort of related that
it's related to this.
[Applause]
Okay.
So now instead of having a set suppose I
have a function on R and D say complex
value um and um I'd like you to
visualize this as a density function.
Um, so actually a good a good thing to
picture is a cat scan. So inside of your
body there's
something that they'd like to scan. Uh,
where are the bones or something? And
um, uh, and so there's a like some
density of that thing. Um, and then the
cat scan will shoot rays through your
bodies in different in different
directions and it will integral of that
function along the ray.
Um and um uh so if you you know if you
stand in front of a screen maybe you
just have an X-ray X-rays go through and
what you see on the screen is the amount
of stuff that that that that X-ray went
through. Okay. So that's what we'd like
to do with this function. Um all right.
So suppose here is our subspace V and if
I have a point in it Y um then the
orthogonal projection maps this fiber
onto Y. So that there is pi V inverse of
Y.
So pi v inverse of y will be an aphine
subspace
and it has a volume measure
which I'm going to call dv volume um
subf the letter f stands for fiber it's
just to distinguish it from dv volume
which might mean the volume on the whole
space
okay so then the way I will define the
projection of the function of y is I
will integrate over the fiber
f ofx d volume of the fiber.
So another way to think about this uh
projection of the function um is that if
I were to integrate
the projection of f
um on some set u in the in the fiber.
So maybe over here I have a subset u in
my fiber.
>> Um
yeah, it's a dv volume of the fiber of
y. Yeah, this thing you could call dy.
Uh
is that okay?
Then this would be equal to the integral
over the pre-image of u of f ofx dx
d oh I'm sorry you are right. Yes that
should not be d volume of the fiber.
Yeah thanks l. Right. So this so yeah
this is just dy or if you wanted to put
d of something it should be dv volume in
the space v of y but not in the fire.
That's absolutely right. what I wrote
made no sense.
Yeah. So if you if you integrate uh the
projection of f over this region u
that's the integral of f over the the
whole parameter.
Okay.
So do you feel like you have a a an
image of what this means?
Okay. Okay. So now we can play the same
game. We start with a function and then
you can consider many different
projections of this function.
Um and there's a phenomenon which is
similar to this phenomenon.
Um but the way it plays out in this
setting of functions is that most of the
projections are smoother than the
original function. And I'll illustrate
that with a proposition.
So proposition
um if f is just an L2 function in R
seven
um then
for almost every V which is a
onedimensional subspace in R seven
if you look at the projection of F on to
V uh it is a C2 function.
So this function on R seven is an L2. It
doesn't have to be continuous anywhere.
Certainly doesn't have to be
differentiable.
You project it onto various
one-dimensional subspaces.
Now not everyone there are there are
some bad ones where it's only L2 or
maybe even worse. Um but for most of
them the projection is C2
and if you play around with these
numbers if you make this bigger you can
make it even smoother.
Okay so I want to try to Yeah.
>> What's special about our seven here that
makes this true?
>> Uh seven is not that special but
increasing this number uh makes it
smoother.
>> Yeah. So it's I mean there are similar
theorems in any dimension.
Yeah.
Um, okay. So,
so let me try to give some intuition
about why that is and uh to try to
convince you that that is a closely
related phenomenon to the phenomenon
that we started with that that appears
in the semary trarthur.
Okay. So, what's um what's the intuition
about this? So I have this
highdimensional function which is quite
irregular and um because it's quite
irregular you could picture it having
many peaks and valleys being very
jagged.
But then when you integrate it over the
fibers if you integrate both a peak and
a valley they cancel each other out. So
a lot of those peaks and valleys cancel
each other out and you could hope to be
left with something smoother. All
right, let's try to make a a picture.
I got a picture. I'm going to erase
this, but I'm going to draw a very
similar picture.
All right. So, in my picture, my f is
going to have it's going to have uh
peaks
on the red dots just to help me
visualize. So this function doesn't
exactly have valleys. It's like to
picture a flat landscape but with lots
of little peaks. Um and so here are some
red dots to make them a little bit
fatter.
Okay. So I think I'm not going to try to
draw the function, but if you what I
want you to visualize is like there's
the plane of the blackboard and then
there's like a peak coming out over each
of these things.
Okay. Now
let's try to visualize what happens when
I project onto this space V. And in
yellow I'm going to draw um the function
pi V of F. Okay. So um to help myself
draw put some little guidelines.
Okay. So out here pi V of F is just zero
because there were no peaks. And then
it's going to go up as I see this peak.
And then as I get here, there there are
two peaks. So that's even taller. And
then here a little shorter. Here a
little taller. A little shorter.
Looks something like that.
You might notice already that this is
not as jagged as the original thing.
Actually, probably it would be better if
I did something like this.
And because of sort of the law of
averages, if I stick these around or if
I stick them around randomly, then
because of the law of averages, this
will be pretty steady.
And even if I don't pick them randomly,
if I choose V randomly, there's a
certain amount of the law of averages,
and this is going to look relatively
steady.
Okay. Um,
cool. Okay. So qualitatively this is
kind of similar to the sum trot theorem.
It says that uh there are only a few bad
directions and except for those bad
directions when I project this down I
will see um I will see things kind of
averaging out.
Okay. Um, and this this proposition is
one way to make it precise, but actually
we'll spend some time thinking together
about various ways to make this precise
questions or comments.
>> Yeah.
>> Is it like possible to prove statements
like this based on the
versions? Yeah, good question. Okay, so
the question is um can we go back and
forth between these two worlds? Can we
take say the summer troder theorem or
something like that and use it to prove
some continuous estimates or vice versa?
Can we take some continuous estimates
and use it to prove things like this?
Yeah. Um
okay. So both of those things are
sometimes possible. Um but both of those
things h have some difficulties and in
particular there's a big story in the in
the field in the class um that people
spent a lot of energy trying to
translate this into the continuous
setting um and um and the the original
proof doesn't definitely doesn't work
and and and and we had to think a lot.
So, um, maybe we'll come back to that a
little later in the class, but there's a
a story I want to share with you about
how it's difficult to get from this
discrete setting to the continuous
setting.
Yeah.
Okay. Um,
actually, let me say a little bit more.
So you know th this example is really
pretty typical. So you you can suppose
that your function is a sum of bumps on
different little balls. And so it is
just a question about how how these
different balls small balls are
projecting down. And it sounds at first
very similar to have like a bunch of
delta balls and project them down to
have like a bunch of points and project
them down. But the thickness of the
balls is really important and it makes
it it it it um um
it makes it makes things different in
ways that we'll talk about.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry, but you might say a bit more
about So if I understand correctly,
you're saying in the typical case
setting you have some in the typical
case in the discrete setting, you
recover all the points.
Could you say a bit more?
>> Yeah. Okay. Great. Great. Okay. So the
question is so the observation is that
um in the discrete setting we had a
theorem that says in for most directions
of projections the images of the points
are uh different from each other. They
they stay spread out and in the
continuous case we said something else
that if you have a bunch of these of
these peaks then in most directions when
you project things kind of average out
and are spaced evenly. And how are those
two things connected to each other?
Yeah, that's a great a great question.
Um,
uh, okay. So, so one part of it I think
is kind of clear. One part of it I I can
explain easily and then this won't be
everything. But if my if my balls were
arranged in such a way that when I
projected
um, they went on top of each other. So
right then the projection of my function
would be really big here and then it
would be zero. Then it would be really
big here and it would be zero and then
it would be really big there. So that
would not be smooth. It would be
oscillating violently. So if you have a
direction which is bad in the sense that
these balls are landing on top of each
other then it will be bad for this
analysis problem.
Okay. But um
uh but uh a set could be bad for this
analysis problem in another way that you
know there could be like two balls over
here and one ball over there and two
balls over here and one ball over there
and then the density would still be
oscillating a lot but the image wouldn't
be particularly small.
Um so okay so that that will require
some additional ideas. Uh but it still
turns out to be the case that trying to
prove stuff about this um the ideas the
ideas from ruling out this case are are
are related.
>> Yeah
>> probably relates exactly to the problem
relating these two. But is there an
analog for distributions?
Um yeah um yes there's an analog for
distributions. Um so okay so the
question is what if f was a distribution
instead of a function? Maybe it was
something messier than being an L2. Um,
so, uh, yeah, you you could still say
things. Um,
um, I wasn't planning. So, um,
so I I think all of those questions you
can reduce to something about how how
balls get projected and then if you if
you want to you can say something about
distributions.
Okay.
Okay, so the next character in the story
I wanted to mention to you is the Forier
transform that in this continuous setup
there's a very close connection between
this projection operation and the forier
transform. Um and that that brings fora
analysis into projection theory.
[Applause]
All right.
Okay. Um so the connection with the fora
transform is the following lama.
Well, actually, let me make a Yeah.
Um,
okay. So, here's our space RD and in
there we have our subspace V. So, our
function F lives on R to the D and and
the projection of F lives on V. Now, how
does the for a transform work? Um, so
here's for a space.
So, for a space is also R R to the T. So
f hat will live on r to the d
and um the forier transform of something
on v
lives on on v as well. So in this r to
the d I'll draw here I'll call it v hat.
Guess if we wanted to we could call this
r to the d hat.
Okay. So if I have this function RD to
C, then F hat is a function R to the D
hat goes to C.
The projection of F is a function from V
to C. And the projection of F hat is a
function from V hat to C.
And then the lema about how they are
related is that if you take the
projection
for a transform of XC,
it's just fhat xc
for any c and v.
Okay. So, let me write down the sketch
the proof of this lema. Um,
it has a simple explanation. Um
so pi vf hat of c is the integral over v
pi vf of y e the minus i c doy d y.
Now what is pi v of f? Well it's the
integral over the fiber. So integral
over v integral over pi inverse of y
f ofx d of the fiber
e the minus i c do y d y.
Okay. And now notice that we have a
double integral. We're integrating over
the fiber and over y. So if you put
those together, you just get a dx.
Um now what happens to this e to the
minus i c doy?
Um so remark
that since um x is in pi v inverse
of y
that tells us that x minus y is
perpendicular to v
inverse
>> goes on the pi. Thanks.
So,
so over here is Y. Here's the fiber and
in our fiber we have X. So X minus Y is
perpendicular to V.
On the other hand,
we also know that the frequency C is in
V. C is in this copy of V over here.
So x - y is perpendicular to c.
x - y x
- y doc is zero.
Okay. So that means I can change this c
doy for x dox and I put these volume
forms together. I have the integral of f
ofx e minus i c dox dx which is f of c.
Okay.
Okay. Cool. So that's an interesting
connection between projections and for
analysis and it was used classically to
solve the problem of recovering a
density from the cat scan. So
mathematically the problem would be
you're given pi v of f for every v and
you want to recover f and the way you
can do it is because of this formula
you can recover if you're given if you
know all the pi v of fs then you can
compute their for transforms. So you can
compute fhat of c for all the c and v
hat but you have all the different v's
so you put it together now you have
computed f hat so you can find f
oh
[Applause]
um cool but this connection with the
forier transform also can be used to
study this continuous projection theory
problem and it's used to prove this
proposition here.
Yeah.
>> V.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Okay. So, the
question is uh what's the difference
between V hat and um I'm not sure it was
helpful to put the hats. It might be
clear if we remove the hats. So, here's
another copy of R to the D where the
variable C lives. And here's the same
space V.
And um
maybe it's clear to remove all these
hats.
Yeah.
Okay.
Um, okay.
So, we mentioned before that this
continuous problem has something to do
with what happens when you take balls
and you project the balls instead of
projecting points. And it's a little
tricky to formulate exactly what the
question should be about projecting
balls. I want to take you through the
first steps um and just see why it's a
little bit tricky and what direction
we're going to go in.
[Applause]
Okay, so I have projection theory
for unit balls
maybe first steps or something like
that.
All right. So, let's say that X is a set
of disjoint
unit balls
in a big ball of radius R and R2.
Okay. So then um
uh
so we could consider the projection in
different directions and we'll have sets
of unit intervals more or less.
Um and we could ask for like the number
of directions where something or another
happens. Actually, let's step back a
little bit. So, okay, so we have a set
of unit balls. Um in in this context,
I'm going to use the absolute value of x
to denote the area of x or volume in
whatever dimension. And um hopefully
that will be helpful and not confusing
compared with before. If you have a
bunch of unit balls, its area is more or
less the same as the number of unit
balls.
Okay.
Um, so then if we look at pi v of x,
that would be the length
of p of x.
All right. So now I want to make a a a
question like the summar troder
question. So I could look at the set of
directions where the projection has
length less than s. Maybe
um maybe I'll I'll do that.
So x might be set of v
g12
so that um
pi v of x has length at most s.
Okay. But it would now be silly to ask
for the number of elements of this
thing. This thing is very likely
infinite if it's not empty. If you make
a tiny perturbation in v, it will have a
tiny effect on pi v of x. Um so there's
a natural sort of discretetization.
So we note
that if the angle between vub1 and v2 is
less than 1 / r then um pi v1 ofx and pi
v2 of x are basically the same as each
other. And so it doesn't make a lot of
sense to count them separately.
Um so um if we want to count something,
one trick we could make is we could have
this fancy V be uh a um be a set of R uh
V's in grass one two that are evenly
spaced.
So I just I just draw
sorry our different lines through the
origin evenly spaced at an angle about 1
/ r. Okay. And then my new question will
be
um
uh if X is a set
of disjoint
unit balls
in the ball of radius R and R2. Um then
estimate.
Yeah. So actually let's let's um change
this definition. We're not going to
count all of the V's, but we're going to
count the ones in this set V.
And that's see like a more fair
comparison to before.
So, we're going to estimate the size of
the S of X
in terms of S and the size of X and we
can compare it to the S8.
Okay.
So we could ask is it still always true
that this is bounded by that expression
there? I'll write that down.
Okay.
So is it true
that es of x is bounded by 1 + s^2x.
Okay. And this is not true. There's a
configuration of unit balls where e s of
x is much bigger than this.
Um what can we do with unit balls that
sort of wasn't relevant before when we
had perfect points?
What other example might we look at?
>> Um, yeah. What do you think?
>> Integrate functions over them.
>> We could. Yeah, we So, we can integrate
functions over them. Um,
>> yeah. Okay. So, here's a configuration
of unit balls that kind of doesn't have
an analog when you're just looking at
points. But what we're going to do is
we're just going to pack them into a
larger ball. So here's the example.
So here's our big ball
and then inside of it I have a smaller
ball and I pack the smaller ball full of
unit balls.
So add x.
All right. So the area of X or the
number of unit balls is around n^2.
And no matter what direction I project
this thing in,
it's going to kind of fill in an
interval of length n
about n.
So for every v, I'm going to have pi v
of x around n, which is x to the 12.
Right?
So if I make s equal to uh x to the 12
or a bit less um then e s of x is the
whole thing every direction.
And so
the size of es of x is r. It's all of
them. It's as big as it could possibly
be. Whereas if you plug in S is the
square root of X here, you would get
one. So it's sort of actually sort of as
bad as possible. The prediction of some
readyated trottery is one. And the truth
is everything.
Okay. Um
right.
Okay. So these small balls are not
really behaving like points uh because
of the fact that they've been packed so
densely into a big ball.
And um so if we if we so okay it is
perfectly reasonable to analyze this
situation and answer this question. We
will do that in this class. There is an
answer to it and it's worth knowing. Um
however as you insist that these small
balls are spread apart apart farther and
farther then they start to behave more
and more like ideal points and
eventually this is true.
Um, so a a goal of this part
is to add hypothesis
that the set of balls is spread out
and then get stronger conclusions.
And probably next class we will play
around with how to state some precise
hypotheses and what kind of conclusions
we might expect.
Um but the big the big progress that I
referred to at the beginning of the
class in the field is that in the in the
last couple years people proved um let's
say the main conjecture about this
question for unit balls in R2. Um, and
we'll try to flesh it out because you
could imagine many different hypotheses,
but I think the theory gives a fairly
complete picture of how this works for
balls in R2.
Different hypotheses about how spread
out they are and what you can conclude
about how often the projections uh have
things piled on top of each other.
Okay,
cool. Um,
okay. Now, there are there are many
variations on these on these questions.
And because this one is a little bit
difficult to state, I thought I'd
mention one other which is a beautiful
open problem and it's pretty clean to
state. Um, and well, let me explain one
of the key difficulties.
Um, okay. So, so these questions make
sense over any field. I started with the
real numbers because I was kind of used
to it because I'm an analyst. Uh, but
you could ask about about any field, any
vector space. Um, and actually a very
interesting case is finite fields.
[Applause]
Okay. So, cousin problems.
All right. So, let's say FQ is the
finite field
with Q elements.
Okay. And if I write FP
that will mean P is a prime. So it's FP
of a field with a prime number of
elements. And FQ is a general finite
field. Q will be some prime val.
Okay. Um
so here's our question. Oh, okay. So now
I should say what is an orthogonal
projection? Um so it's not hard to say
what a subspace is over finite fields.
We don't have obviously a notion of
orthogonality. Um, but orthogonality
isn't really
isn't really the crucial thing. The
crucial thing is just that we have a lot
of linear maps from our vector space to
a lower dimensional vector space. We're
really looking at all the possible
linear maps. So in terms of what are the
possible projections, I can um
parameterize them just like this. So if
t is in fq,
pi t would be a map from fq ^2 to fq.
and pi t of x1 x2 is just x1 + t * x2.
Okay, so those are a bunch of linear
maps.
Okay, and you know, actually you might
say, why don't I write all the linear
maps? I could have t1 x1 plus t2x2.
Those are all the linear maps. Um but if
you multiply t1 and t2 by the same
factor then you've just uh taken a
linear map and then composed with a
linear map from fp to itself. So those
are all going to be sort of equivalent
for us. And so that's why we just we
just set this to be one and let this be
t.
Okay.
So now let's say x is in fq ^2
and
e s of x is the set of t. So the t just
live in fq with the property that pi t
of x is at most s.
And now we can ask the same question.
Um
question
estimate
the size of ES of X
um in terms of
uh S and X
ideally and I guess maybe Q.
All right. Now, an integer grid still
makes sense over a finite field. Um, and
um, and so and it works the same way as
in summary and troder and over the prime
fields. That's the best example that we
know. So there is a conjecture
if x is in fp^2 and p is always prime
but it's important here. So I will sort
of add it. Um then
the size of es of x is bounded by 1 +
s^2x.
Okay
matching that.
But
this is not true
uh in fq ^2.
Q is not prime.
Okay.
So let me show you an example.
[Applause]
And this example uh plays a big role in
the theory.
Um
okay so here's the example.
Suppose that q is p ^2. There are
similar examples for higher powers but
this is a simple concrete.
Um so FP is a subset of FQ. It's a sub
field of FQ
and our set X is going to be FP squ
which is a subset of FQ^2.
Cardality of X is P ^2 which is Q.
Okay. So now notice
that if t is also in fp
and x is an x then pi t of x which is x1
+ t * x2. Well all of these characters
I've assumed to be an fp and fp is a
field so it's closed under addition
closed under multiplication. So this is
an FP.
So that tells me that if T is in FP,
pi T of X is is FP is contained in FP.
It's actually all of it. And so the size
of pi T of X
is at most P which is Q to the half
which is much smaller than the size of
X.
Okay. So we conclude that the size of
uh e p of x is at least p. So there are
p traces t that all lie in ep of x
and that's uh that's much bigger than
the bound in the conjecture for what
should happen over primes.
Yeah. So if we were to plug in these
numbers up here, S would be P which is
the square root of Q and X would be Q.
So this would be one.
Over prime fields, this should be order
of one. But over this not prime field,
it's much bigger.
Okay.
Um
so this shows that projection theory is
also connected to some I don't know
algebra algebraic structure questions of
of whether fields have sub fields
um and this issue which is uh okay so so
this is an open conjecture and it's hard
for two reasons um the first reason is
well you look at it you say okay it's
like some trotder but over a prime
field. So I should try to take the proof
of try and that proof completely breaks
down. Um that proof was based on the
topology of R. We'll go through it but
the topology of R and the topology of FP
are very different and it just doesn't
work at all. The second reason is that
uh the statement of the conjecture
really requires this to be prime. And so
it's not true for any field. It's only
true for prime fields. And so you have
to wonder how are we going to use that
in the proof. Um and a lot of methods
uh a lot of methods have don't
distinguish between prime fields and not
prime fields and therefore they can't
prove the whole thing.
Okay. And in in in the real analysis
setting actually there's the same issue.
So these um theorems that I wasn't able
to state precisely for you today
they are true over R2 but they are false
in C2
because the complex numbers have a sub
field R.
So um so the complex numbers play the
role of like FQ where Q is P ^2
and so over here also we need to do
something to distinguish between the
complex numbers and the real numbers. um
and many many techniques don't do that.
So a bit surprisingly these these real
analysis problems that eventually get
used in in um uh in like estimates and
for a analysis with integral operators
that really look like analysis. They
take something from these questions over
finite fields. These are these are more
closely related to each other than
either one of them is to that first
semired trotder theorem.
All right. So at the beginning of the
class I will teach you some classical
techniques, some double counting
techniques, some for analysis
techniques. Hold on a second. Um and
they prove interesting things and they
work over here and they work over here
but they don't distinguish between the
prime fields and the not prime fields.
>> Okay. Yeah. Was there a question?
>> Yeah. Does the fact that the wheels have
the rationals as a sub field matter for
this or does the topology argument?
>> Ah okay. So the question is so the
observation is I said that the situation
for f
q when q is p ^2 is kind of complicated
because fq has a sub field namely fp
and then I tried to say there's
something similar going on with the
complex numbers and the real numbers.
Okay. Now the observation is the real
numbers have many proper sub fields. One
of them is the rational numbers. You
could there are many more number fields.
Um
and doesn't doesn't that matter? Yeah,
that's a good thing for us to reflect
on. It turns out not to matter that much
and it's because those sub fields are so
small. Um the the real numbers are an
infinite order extension of the rational
numbers. I think even an uncountable
order extension of the rational numbers.
Um whereas FQ is a degree two extension
at FP.
Um
right so one way people talk about it is
in in terms of housed dorf dimension.
So the the real numbers have sub fields
but their house dwarf dimension is
either zero
or one if it's if it's the whole real
numbers and not in the middle. Anyway,
we'll we'll have a look at it.
Yeah.
>> Do you have any intuition about why
these types of things are for small
fields?
>> Uh why why you can't do something with
small bad with small fields
>> or yeah if I understand the intuition
correctly like the real numbers are fine
because they're large enough extension
over the rationals but so I don't know
I'm just wondering if you have about the
size of this.
>> Correct. Right.
Yeah. Okay. So, here's an analogy for
you. Uh, so what if we didn't have P^
squ? What if we had P to the 17th?
Okay. Now, at FQ still has a sub field
FP, but it's kind of a small sub field.
We could do this same computation. We
would see that this doesn't fully hold.
Um but for sets that are pretty large,
for sets that are a lot larger than
that, um we would still we might still
hope for pretty good bounds. And I think
that I think that the situation for the
small subfields of R is similar to that.
>> So is this conjunction known for any
prime number or is it every prime
number? See, so I want to prove this
conjunction for okay.
>> Um, right. Right. So,
[Applause]
okay. So, we stick this tilda here,
which means there's a missing constant
factor.
>> We do that to be safe. I guess it
probably is true with a small constant
factor, but strictly speaking, you can't
falsify it with one prime number. Okay.
But that that's not the that's not the
real reason. Then you might say, you
know, if you take a medium prime number
like 101, could you check it
numerically?
Maybe for 10. Well, even for 101, you
know, I don't have any wisdom about how
to do this. And if you literally did it
by brute force um and checked all the
possibilities X, you really couldn't go
very far.
Um and um I'm not sure if we'll address
this but that there is a computational
question like you know maybe I can't
prove this conjecture but do I
understand it well enough that I could
prove it for a particular P faster than
brute force
um I don't and so we're not able to have
much numerical evidence. Yeah.
Yeah,
it could be worth looking for counter
example on the computer. The evidence is
not that strong in favor of this
conjecture.
Okay, cool.
Okay, in the last 15 minutes, I wanted
to mention to you some other parts of
math that this connects to.
Um
uh okay. Um so one connection is to a
part of combinatorial number theory
called sum product theory which we'll
see sort of fits in naturally with this
issue. Um
yeah so it turn so in this in this
example this set that we're worried
about is closely connected to the fact
that that fq has a interesting sub field
interesting subset that's closed under
addition and multiplication
and the field the the the sum product
theory and combinatorial number theory
is about what happens to a set under
addition and multiplication
um so initially it's over r over the
reals but then we can ask
Okay. So let's say that R is a ring. So
we can define sums and products. And A
is a subset of R. So A plus A is all of
the sums you can make. Two elements of
A. So it's the set of all the A1 plus A2
where A1 and A2 are in A. And the
product set A times A is similar. It's
the set of all the products.
All
right. Um, okay. So, actually motivating
this from before, what what was so bad
about this set FP as a subset of FQ? The
problem was just that um well,
if if these three guys are in FP, then
X1 plus T * X2 is still in FP. So, the
problem was that FP is closed under sums
and under products.
Um
so it raises the question are there
other sets that are maybe not exactly
closed but roughly closed under sums and
products.
Um
okay so so the idea of some product
theory is take a subset A and R.
Um could it happen that both A plus A
and A * A are pretty small?
Um okay so let me mention a few
examples. So if a is a subset of the
real numbers which is generic
then a + a and a * a would both be
around the size of a squ generically
there would be no coincidences in the
sums or in the brackets. Um okay but it
could happen that a plus a is quite is
not very big. Um so if a
is an arithmetic progression
then the size of a plus a is only around
two times the size of a
but in this case a time a would be very
big.
Um on the other hand if a is a geometric
progression
then the size of a time a would be
around two times the size of a but if a
is a geometric progression then a plus a
would be very big.
Okay so based on these few examples um
and saretti conjectured that always one
of these guys is big. So here's their
conjecture. Uh as is still an open
problem. Um if a is a finite subset of
the wheels,
then the maximum
of a + a and a * a
is at least c epsilon a 2us epsilon. So
for every so at the beginning I should
put for every epsilon bigger than zero.
Okay. So it's not quite a squ. That
example comes from taking the numbers 1
to n. Then a plus a is clearly quite
small. A * a is many of the integers
from 1 to n^ squ. Uh but not all of
them. Some of them have a prime factor
that's bigger than n. So they're not in
the list. And computed that carefully.
So he said you need the epsilon.
Okay.
Um
so So this type of problem is connected
to progress to projection theory because
of this type of example.
Um and the connection goes in both
directions.
Um
so in one direction
uh there's a okay there's a theorem of
alakish about the sum product theorem um
so we can't prove this but um any
exponent here that's bigger than one
would be non-trivial and we can prove it
with exponents that are bigger than one
and um historically there was a big jump
in the quality of the exponent when all
proved this theorem
So he proved
a is a subset of r which is finite
then the maximum of a + a and a * a is
at least a to the five quarters.
Um and the key ingredient in the proof
was some ready trial.
Uh that's not the whole proof but the
the uh proof uses some ready trial and
and not much else. it's quite short and
so if you know something about
projection theory you can say something
about some product
um but later things went in the other
direction
um so there's a theorem
of Borgan cats and toao
which says that not only a prime field
does not have any sub fields which we
knew but it doesn't have anything that's
even close to being a subre.
So
P is prime
and A is a subset of FP
and um A is not too big.
So it's not super important what this
number is, but a is significantly
smaller than the whole field. Um then
the maximum of a + a and a * a um is at
least the size of a to the 1 plus
epsilon where epsilon is a small but
explicit number I think something like 1
over 20.
Um
this theorem is actually more accessible
than projection theory in general.
Having these sums and products gives you
a little bit more structure. Turns out
to be important but it shows that in FP
over FP there's no example which is too
much like this example. You can't just
choose a subset of FP which is almost
closed under sums and products and then
mimic this argument.
Um, and it's not immediate, but this is
used to to improve
the projection theory
in FP squared. And something similar
will also happen for problems about
balls in R2.
Okay, I wanted to mention some other
applications, but I don't want to cram
things in too much in the last five
minutes. I'll just say a few words and
then I'll pause for final questions. Um
so one one application or story is um
from civ theory in number theory. So in
civ theory you have a set of integers
instead of a set of points in a vector
space. And when in civ theory we study
what happens if you take the set of
integers and you reduce it mod p or mod
q for many different numbers q.
Um, and there are some questions about
general sets like could it happen that
you have a set of integers and whenever
you reduce it mod q for any q you you
always get something small. What could
you say about your set of integers?
So an interesting example of that are
the square numbers. If you take the
squares and you reduce it mod p for any
prime start with primes you get the
quadratic residues which is only half of
the residue classes. So whenever you
reduce it mod p you only get half of the
residue classes. How many other sets of
integers can you think of that? Whenever
you reduce the mod p you only get half
of the residue classes.
Um how big could such a set of integers
be? How you know how what fraction of
all the integers and so on. So there's
one one set of questions about this. Um,
and there's another set of questions
where you take a particular set of
integers that you might be interested
in, of which the most famous is the
primes, and you think about what happens
when you reduce the set the primes mod q
for many different q.
Um, so it appears to be the case that
the prime numbers are evenly distributed
mod q for every.
Um, actually depending on how you
quantify it, that's a that's a theorem.
Um, so if you fix a Q and you take the
primes mod Q and you take primes up to X
where X is much much much bigger than Q,
they will be evenly distributed among
the residue classes mod Q that are
possible, the ones that have no common
factor with Q.
But you could ask you you might also
want to know uh if you take the primes
up to some fixed X and you reduce the
mod q for many different Q. Um, it it
still appears it appears that those are
evenly distributed for quite big q.
even Q Q's that are only slightly less
than than X.
Um, okay, we can't prove anything like
that. Um, but there's a line of thought
that maybe we could relax what we're
trying to prove a little bit and try
instead of trying to prove it for every
Q, we could try to prove it for most of
the Q.
And now we're in this setting uh uh
where we have one fixed set and we're
looking at how it reduces mod Q for many
different Q and and that problem is very
similar to the projection theory
problem.
Okay. So anyway, so we'll so we'll teach
some core techniques of projection
theory that were developed by people in
geometric measure theory in the 60s7s
and 80s. And those are almost those are
very closely parallel to the classic
techniques of civ theory that were
developed by people in the 40s 50s 60s.
Um and so okay so interesting
connections there and in civ theory
there are lots of uh lots of open
problems.
So that's one set of applications if you
like or connections.
Um
and the other one I wanted to mention is
to dynamical systems. Um so Elon Alon
Linden Strauss last year gave the
Simon's lectures and one of the things
was about taking orbits in homogeneous
spaces unipot so I don't have time to
say what all the things are but you take
unipotent orbits in homogeneous spaces
then they distribute very evenly um and
um so there are some classical important
theorems about that and the recent thing
he and Amir Mohammadi were trying to
make it more quantitative and a new idea
a in their proof is they brought in
projection theory. Um so so anyway so I
will tell you the story I'll slowly
first of all what is the question and
then what does it have to do with
projection theory.
So those are some some applications I
was thinking that it would that I'd like
to to talk about with you.
>> Okay. Um any last questions or comments?
>> Yeah.
Right. So the question is the the
summary trider theorem is usually said
in a different way actually a more
general way where you have a set of
lines and you look at the points that
have many lines going through them. Um
and we'll see that this is a corlary or
special case of that.
like
they are quite different.
If you're just
>> Yeah, let's talk about that after class.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, good. Let's stop there for today.
Um, and I will see you on Thursday.