[Music]
okay so now let's talk about how our
immune system uh works and how it
responds to cancer so our immune system
is classically divided into two
different branches the innate immune
response and the Adaptive immune
response and you can think of the inate
immune response is this really rapid
response to um some threat so for
instance if you get when you get a cut
uh you know you bleed but then you have
these neutrophils uh that quickly travel
to the sight of the cut and uh protect
you from bacterial infection so that's
an an example of innate response then
the Adaptive response is uh slower but
what's amazing about it is it can learn
to recognize uh threats that your body
has never seen before so for instance if
you ever had influenza infection or SARS
K2 these are things your body has never
seen before and your adaptive immune
response can respond to that now in
cancer uh the main sort of fighting U
cells uh against this disease are the
tea cells and the tea cells are really
uh remarkable uh and so let's talk about
how they work so uh this is uh what you
know a healthy cell could look like in a
cartoon schematic and in these green
squiggles are your genes and these genes
make little proteins that get displayed
on the surface of the cell and this is
called self
anen so our T cells on their surface
have a t- cell receptor and this is
scanning uh the surface of healthy cells
and the t- cell receptor has learned to
tolerate self antigens so it just
ignores them and goes away however in
cancer there are mutations that happen
in our in our genes and this leads to
this sort of red squiggly uh uh genes
here which get made into proteins and
now these proteins are different from
anything your body has seen before and
these are called nonself antigens and
now the te- cell jumps into action and
the t- cell receptor recognizes that
that's not a an antigen that came from
healthy cell and this leads to the t-
cell signaling and starting to kill the
cancer cell and remove it uh from the
body so each t- cell has this uh t- cell
receptor and the t- cell receptor
actually has a unique specificity that
recognizes the nonself antigen so in
theory our bodies can make a huge
diversity of these t- cell receptors up
to 10 to the 19 so this is a really
mindboggling number and what's awesome
about this is that this diversity gives
us the ability to kind of sense and
respond to really diverse threats that
the body has never seen before so this
can be viruses this could be cancer and
other pathogens uh and so here is a
scanning electron microscope image of
te- cells attacking a cancer cell and
each of these t- cells has a t- cell
receptor and this t- cell receptor can
recognize uh this non-self antigen on
the surface of the cancer cell so in an
acute infection like influenza or mild
SARS kv2 what happens is our te- cells
will recognize that this cell is
infected they'll start to uh expand and
kill those virally infected cells and
then once the virus is cleared uh the
tea cells return to normal and they just
uh return to this resting Baseline as
the infection is cleared however in
cancer this process is greatly altered
and the killing response of te- cells is
blunted
[Music]