Good afternoon everyone. Um I'm Insong
Kim uh from political science and this
is joint project with Yon Donkel uh
who's sitting right there uh from
mathematics uh department. So our
project is titled tentatively as
mathematics of law making in the United
States and we are hoping to share some
of um preliminary results that we have
uh with you guys and hopefully uh you
will see something very interesting
about the law makingaking in the United
States.
uh special interest groups uh engage in
lobbying to influence the legislative
process in the United States. Um there
are actually more than 12,000 bills that
are introduced in each congressional
session. 12,000 bills. It's not only uh
Obama healthc care bill or Trump tax
bill uh or IRA kind of bill uh that we
all know uh but there are also other
so-called micro bills uh where special
interest groups are lobbying to affect
the legislative politics at the very
very granular
level. We know uh based on our data
collection effort that most of these
bills uh are actually lobbyed and then
we collect our data according to the
lobbying disclosure act of 1995 which
legally requires all the interest groups
to report uh their lobbying activities.
And one of those uh lobbying activities
include which type of the legislative
bills that they have lobbied
on. And this is a great opportunity for
researchers like us to uh systematically
measure the competing interest uh in the
legislative politics which we all agree
probably will be very very
important. However, there exists very
few empirical studies that examine who
supports or who opposes which bill. uh
whether supporters and opponents
dominate at different stages of the
legislative process and or which
political actors are more or less
successful in advancing their
legislative goals. These are all very
very important questions to ask and
answer uh but very few empirical studies
exist. So my question to you all is
why given what's happening in Washington
DC these days I guess we all want to
understand
this and there's a vast uh literature in
the field of political science or
computational social science in general
um uh that have examined um interest
group politics in Washington DC for a
long long period of time but from
empirical perspective there literally uh
no studies arguably to systematically uh
study these uh at a large scale. You can
see a journalistic coverage of one of
those uh questions uh every now and
then. But we are talking
about systematic um uh extensive study
of the entire legislative bills for
example that are being considered in
Washington DC. So the answer to this
question is that it is extremely hard to
identify which bills interest interest
groups
lobby. Even when we can find who lobbies
on which bill, interest groups are not
legally required to uh disclose whether
they have supported or opposed bills. So
despite the significance of these
questions, it's very uh difficult and
therefore few studies exist to examine
these
questions. So in this project uh we are
trying to overcome these challenges.
The agenda for today's talk is to just
visually show the data that we have
collected so far uh and motivate the
importance of studying the uh interest
group positions based on the signals
that we have observed and then show you
just a simple descriptive stat regarding
the unequal representation in the US law
makingaking uh so that we can all think
uh together about the importance of uh
the representation uh in democracy.
Y so this is actual data uh that we have
collected uh during last 15 years uh
based on the lobbying disclosure act of
1995. You have the federal filings uh
that specifies which clients in the
first column that is you can think of
this as uh Apple um the company interest
group and then registrance uh who
represent the client Apple uh in this
case the K Street lobbying firm in
Washington DC. You also know the
identities of individual lobbyist who
have been hired by these law firms to
represent the interests of the client
Apple. You also uh have a measurements
uh of how these lobbyists are linked to
uh different government agencies like
FDA for pharmaceutical industry uh or
SEC for financial um uh industries and
so forth. In terms of whether a lobbyist
has any revolving door connections uh or
experiences in those agencies, we also
have a me measurement uh of the
connection political connections between
the lobbyist and the legislators uh at a
very very gr granular level. So if a
lobbyist has ever worked as an intern
for a senator a for three months uh then
we observe that. So you can imagine
extremely granular measurements of the
political network and very high
dimensional um uh data that we need to
analyze the lobbying uh disclosure act
and then the derivative database that we
have uh created uh lobby view actually
uh captures a lot of interesting
signals and this is just a visualization
of what's happening um we're not going
to read all of this but I want to draw
your attention to this part for example
when there was a 911 um uh you see a lot
of uh lobbying spike represented by this
dark shaded red um cell uh involving
aviation and airlines. Okay, so this is
just uh just a predictive validation if
you will where we are actually capturing
something very meaningful in terms of
what's going on in Washington DC in
terms of the issue area. On the right
hand side you can also see uh
differences across the different
administration. So you see uh the Trump
the first Trump uh is uh associated with
a lot of lobbying happening regarding US
customs and border protection. Okay. And
then you see that uh by gathering this
highdimensional data, you can actually
map not only what's going on in
Washington DC, but also map the
political communities, if you will, um
that are uh driving uh the law
makingaking in Washington
DC. I'm going to move on to measurements
of interest group politics. So we know
what's going on. uh we know who's
lobbying on which bill but we want to
know whether certain interest groups are
taking particular positions uh toward a
particular legislative
bills. So to that end we are also
creating a new data set for lobby bills
and committees. Here is an example of
what's actually being reported in
lobbying report. You can see that uh
interest group uh lobbyed on HR 83 which
is a house bill uh 83. So what we are
doing is by parsing through
automatically parsing through the
universe of the lobbying reports filed
by all interest groups to identify which
uh interest groups have lobbied on which
bill. You may think that is very easy to
extract out this information but this is
one of the reason the difficulty of it
is one of the reasons why uh we spent
last 15 years uh to even create this
data set. You can see this HR83 um uh
being a bill from House of
Representative but uh there are 110th
Congress 80 uh HR83 111th Congress HR83.
So just because you observe HR83 doesn't
necessarily mean that you can correctly
identify the
bill. Therefore, in this case, it's very
important to compare and contrast the
bill number and bill title and so that
we can correctly map this HR83 213
Congress bill. And of course, we do more
sophisticated u uh algorithmic
approaches for measurements such as in
this case affordable care act uh with
with no bill number listed. Uh we're
going to look at the text difference uh
distances between what we have observed
here uh with the universe of um the bill
titles database uh to be able to
correctly identify the bill number as
well as the
title. So we consider uh over 108,000
congressional bills introduced since 106
Congress. We for each one of those
lobbing activities we identify um uh the
the lobbing activities based on over one
million lobbing report and we then link
uh these reports and the instance of the
lobbing to committees that consider each
bill and also the individuals who are
serving on uh in the committee
congressional committees to consider
this bill which will then be used to
create the highdimensional network data
that I presented earlier.
So once you have uh the measurement of
uh which bill is lobbyed by which
interest group now is the next step is
to see the traditional uh measurement.
So let's look at the top part. Um the
lobbying report uh actually um reads uh
endorsement of the hidden figures
congressional gold medal act. So in this
case we know that this is in support of
passing this bill. On the other hand,
another case where defeat S 23, the
Senate bill number 23 and HR1249
uh which is a clear indication that the
interest group uh is opposing um uh the
bill, right? Of course, not all the time
we observe this. Um so what we do is to
manually measure uh this type of the
leanings uh oppose opposition or support
of the bill. uh and then we uh use a
large language model to go through um
the each individual uh text to have a
its own measurements of the support
opposes etc. And then we can then
compare the performance of the large
language model to tune its performance
uh to have a proper measurement of the
support oppose.
For those on the bottom side for those
where we do not have any uh textual
information about the position of the
bill what we utilize is to uh is uh
analyzing the systemic p pattern
revolving around the bill level
lobbying. So in this case we know that
this particular interest group uh has
lobbied on this bill based on the
earlier measurement strategy. Uh but we
do not know whether um it has lobbied
for or against even when uh we were able
to measure for some of them. So what we
then do is oh let's look at uh you know
the history of the lobbing activities
and then involve the lobbyist and the
lobbying companies and then history of
the position taking that we have learned
from this upper part. So the idea is
that if um A and B uh are lobbyed on
similar bills in the history and then we
know that they have taken a similar
position and then now we have a
measurement of A's position toward the
bill let's say support but we do not
observe B's uh position toward the bill
but it's reasonable to at that point
respect that B B might have also shared
a similar type of the position position
toward the bill and that's how we
utilize this highdimensional network
data to be able to predict uh the
positional uh leaning of each individual
interest groups even when they do not
disclose uh their
positions. So once you do that then some
interesting patterns will emerge. What
we found is that upper part is the
enacted bills in Washington DC. Uh we
see that there is a uptake here in this
purple which um uh captures the
monitoring activities. So we see that a
lot of interest groups start uh
monitoring the implementation of the
past bill. So it is not only that you're
allowing to affect the bill making but
also how uh you are going to affect the
implementation of a you know public law
once it is uh enacted. You also see on
this bottom figure that once the bill
have been passed on the floor before
presidential action like a veto for
example uh you see an uptake in
opposition. So you see that uh interest
groups that are trying to block the bill
start uh collectively uh gathering
together to mobilize to oppose uh the
passing of the bill. This is we believe
is a very important finding. uh in fact
that what we are trying to do is to uh
characterize this high dimensional data
as u a function of a multiple
conditional probabilities um from
mathematical modeling perspective and
one of the conditional probabilities is
to see whether firm size is related to
the lobbing activities what we find is
that not surprisingly larger firms but
the positive on the right hand side of
this particular line means that larger
firms are positively associated with
this activity. So we see that larger
firms are positively associated with the
lobbying activities. So larger firms
will tend to lobby more but we f what we
found here is that smaller firms are
more likely to oppose. So this suggests
that uh in the legislative process big
firms are lobbying to influence uh the
agenda setting and introduce a lot of
bills but it is a small interest groups
or very small actors that tend to be
very reactive uh by uh start opposing in
the later stage of the uh legislative
process. So this is this bottom part is
one of the first times that actually
social scientists uh will be able to
look at uh the differences in the
political activities as a function of
the firm firm
size. Finally I just want to share with
you uh a brief um sort of uh descriptive
stat on the unequal representation in
the US law making. So this is the
lobbing report again another example of
lobbing report and I told you that in
lobbing report uh we actually observed
all the all all the lobbyists who got
involved in lobbing this particular
activity. Um the lobbyists are listed by
name on filing but we know very little
about who they are. So what we went uh
what we did was went to the web page of
this particular K Street lobbing firm
and then tried to find who these person
uh persons are and then sort of put the
uh pictures of each individual lobbyist
involved in this particular uh lobbying
activities which is the representing DAO
chemical uh company. It's a chemical
multinational company. Do you see any
pattern from these pictures?
Yes. Uh major lobbying firms uh tend to
hire overwhelmingly uh larger number of
a white male lobbyist.
Um so what we have done is to
standardize and dduplicate uh uh based
on the all uh various name identifier uh
try to identify each individual
federally registered lobbyist to learn
about the composition uh of the
lobbyists in terms of their racial uh
and gender
distribution. Of course this has been
very very difficult and uh even when
you're using cutting edge algorithm
sometimes the measurements is not quite
correct. So what we're doing is to find
each individual lobbyist in the LinkedIn
data and then uh and then uh connect uh
their information uh the name name
information with their education uh
gender ethnicity and then history of
their employ uh employment and so forth.
So we have a very very granular
measurement of them. But just to show a
simple stat you see on the left hand
side um this is uh the distribution over
racial groups and the uh the light blue
represent the uh population proportion
and then dark blue represents the actual
distribution in the lobbying industry.
So against the population distribution
uh for the white uh you can see that uh
overwhelmingly larger number of the uh
Washington DC lobbyists are actually
white and it uh that unequal
representation becomes even more severe
uh if we uh wait that based on
experience in lobbying that is that you
know how long uh the lobbyists have
worked in the Washington DC. So what we
learned is that uh the senior lobbyists
are even more disproportionately
represented by uh white uh white
male. So this is just a descriptive uh
uh uh stats that I've shared and
hopefully this gives you an idea about
what we are working on. I look forward
to uh Q&A.
Thanks. Thank you very much. some
questions.
Hi. Uh to add even more confusion, uh
one thing that goes on in um Congress is
that sometimes the representatives
change their uh trade their votes.
They'll say, you know, you vote for this
bill and I'll vote for that bill. So,
you know, it could be that a lobbyist
convince uh a senator or representative
to vote for a bill, but then they trade
away that vote, you know, on something
else or because of party machinations.
So, does that also throw you off? Yes.
Uh that's definitely very uh very
important. Um first of all, people
weren't able to even measure whether
it's a for. So, we are moving forward in
that regard. regarding the uh for
against uh and change of the positions
as a result of the lobbying. One of the
good ways to look at is the history of
the legislative bills. So uh there are
12,000 bills that are introduced in
Congress as I mentioned uh but only a
few hundreds are actually voted on the
floor. So what happens to all these
other uh 12,000 um uh bills um that have
been introduced? It turned out that a
lot of those so-called micro bills, the
text within those bills are cut and
pasted onto the later so-called omnibus
bills uh to reflect this low lowering
behavior. Basically, I uh uh support
this bill uh not that bill, but if you
agree to include the text from this bill
that I support in the later bill that I
might uh support this bill. So given
that we can actually uh look at the
history of the bills and then the
positional um taking of not only the
interest groups and associated
politicians will be able to actually
answer that but we haven't actually
quantified that yet. Okay. So what
you're saying is that there's basically
a record of that trade. Uh well uh uh
it's not a record of the trade. uh you
have observed a pattern that might
reflect some of those uh you know uh
under the table trade happening. Okay,
thank you.
This is um a bit of a very grounded
question, but is what is the legal or
formal definition of lobbying? And I'm
curious how comprehensive a data set
like this would be for lobbying type
efforts or if given the constraints
implied by like the language of the law
everything that we might think of as
labeling is covered by these reporting
mechanisms.
Thanks. Uh so based on the lobbying
disclosure act of 1995 uh the lobbying
is defined as uh the defined in terms of
lobbyists spending their time. So if you
are spending uh certain I forgot the
exact number but let's say that 50% or
more of your time representing uh
interest of uh your client then that is
uh defined as a lobbying activity and
then if you satisifi if your lobbing
activity satisfies that definition then
you are legally required to file
quarterly the four times a year report
describing your lobbing activities. that
said that um that definition does not uh
fully cover all the other um uh you know
let's say the 5% use of your time
representing uh your client interest
might not satisfy the definition. Uh and
therefore it's true that there are a lot
of other lobbing activities that are not
being measured. Uh so there will be um
uh you know the cases like that but from
researchers perspective it is is that
one is we cannot really measure right.
So what we are doing is to start with
this uh lobbing activity based on the
legal definition of the lobbing and then
try to capture the universal lobbying
from that perspective and uh the
government auditing agency um uh
frequently audit the behavior of uh
individual interest groups lobbing
activity. The last time that I saw the
report, uh their report says that 97%
um uh of their targeted uh investigation
uh has shown that 90 97% of uh interest
groups have properly reported their
allowing activity based on the
definition of the law.
Further
questions? Thanks. Um, I guess this is
sort of a two-part question, but I am
curious seemed like you're not really
able necessarily to identify the client
in all cases, but I'm wondering do do
patterns emerge where certain lobbyists
tend
to represent certain types of clients or
certain types of causes or certain types
of political um movements or
perspectives?
Uh, yes. Uh but I I don't know what made
you think that we do not I might have
just not I might have just stepped away
when you shared that. Yeah, we do
observe the clients uh individual uh
lobbying activities. Uh and we do
observe their position taking for
individual bills. Uh maybe this will be
an interesting um uh example that I
prepared. So you know that drug
sentencing is a perhaps the most
egregious uh example of systematic uh
discrimination in American policym. Do
you know about this uh this story about
uh cocaine, powder cocaine versus uh
crack cocaine? Um it turned out that
there is like a 100 to1 ratio in
punishment differences. Um uh where uh
the crack cocaine users will be 100
times more punished. And then it turned
out that uh uh the although the white
and black Americans are uh use drugs at
the comparable rates uh the crack
cocaine users are overwhelmingly black
and powder cocaine users overwhelmingly
white. And what we were able to do is to
look at this particular legislation in
2009 uh house bill number 34 uh25 and
then see uh in this case the left hand
side is um uh NA uh CP and the right
hand side uh is a lobbying by FOP right
and then uh given the lobbying
activities we were able to uh measure
whether one is a support uh and the
other is opposed and then we were able
to uh see that those who has opposed one
in that the actual uh law making
reflected their interest. So we can go
this far uh in individual individual uh
bill we know the universe of the
interest groups at least based on the
definition of the lobbying uh who oppose
and support it how they're distributed
how they organize their lobbing activity
is differently in terms of the uh the
timing of the lobbying like a later part
or beginning part and then for those
bills that have been actually voted on
the floor and then passed into a law uh
we'll be able to also systematically
measure whose interests or either
disproportionately or proportionately
represented in the law making.
Yeah. Um my questions are probably a
little a field from what you're what you
talked about, but there's a lot of or
number of things in legislation for
economic uh bills where it's worded in
obscure ways that are pretty hard to
figure out what's going on, but designed
to benefit a single firm. Yes. And I'm
just wondering if that's something
you've looked into and can recognize
when things look like they might be
benefiting a single firm. Yes. Um so
what we have done is uh for each
individual uh bill uh we know who's
lobbyed, right? So we counted the number
of interest groups that have lobbied on
any given
bill. If you give me a random bill and
then uh we are going to count the number
of the all uh interest group that have
on that uh particular bill. What do you
think it is the median number for any
given bill? We're going to count the
number of interest groups that have
lobbied on a given
bill. That's a very uh aggressive
prediction. Uh the median number is two.
um often the the one is a subsidiary of
the other. So uh the point that I'm
trying to make is you're exactly right.
There are all these micro bills uh that
are representing the interests of a very
very uh small number of interest groups.
And if you interview a lobbyist in
Washington DC, everyone knows that oh
this bill is Apple bill, this bill is a
Google bill. We just don't know because
there's just one sentence says that oh
if a company uses this technology A then
revenue generated by the technology A
will be
taxexempt and it turned out that there's
only one company in the world that uses
technology A then that particular line
in the legislation could be seen as a
private good of that particular interest
group and our goal is to try to uh uh
create a connection between uh you know
that micro bills and then Individual
interest groups