I'll be talking about specifically
scheduling considerations in the US
asylum system. This work has been led by
my PhD student when Wang and it is also
joined with uh David Houseman who is an
professor at UC Berkeley Law School. The
motivation of this work is twofold. On
the one hand, there seems to be based on
these headlines
uh a lot of people that believe that the
US asylum system is in some way broken
or needs
fixing. And a lot of this relates to
issues that for an operations management
person or a scheduling optimization
person relate to issues with the asylum
system as a service system. Meaning
there are jobs that are coming in
applications they need to be processed
and this is not happening in a fast and
efficient manner. Now the people that
usually study service systems don't seem
to study the asylum system very much.
This is just uh different search terms
and the number of results that you
get when you look at uh informs pups
online that is like the online library
of the operations research and
management sciences main journals and
you can see that in there's a lot of
studies on hospitals because a lot of
people in our fields study scheduling in
hospitals. There's a lot of research on
mobility because a lot of people study
transportation and bus schedules and
there's a lot of results that study any
kind of scheduling problem but there are
barely any papers that even include the
word
asylum. Now before I get to our own work
let me just start by highlighting what
is asylum because not everybody may
know. In the US, asylum is one of two
primary humanitarian immigration
benefits. The other one is that of the
status of a
refugee. So, in order to become a
refugee, people have to be one outside
of the United States. Two, they need to
demonstrate that they were persecuted
due to one of several protected
categories. And finally, they need to
not already be firmly resettled in
another
country. Now, in order
to receive asylum, one needs to meet the
definition of a refugee except for one
needs to already be physically in the
United
States. There are two pathways to
asylum. Gets a little bit wonky here.
One is affirmative asylum. This gets
adjudicated through an interview with an
asylum officer at USCIS. And this is for
people that don't currently have
deportation proceedings against them.
And the other is defensive asylum, which
gets adjudicated in immigration court.
And it is for people that already have
deportation proceedings against them.
Both of these settings actually have
quite interesting scheduling components
to them and we've done some work on
these. My focus will really be on the
first one, the affirmative asylum
setting. I will try to give you a little
bit of background on the affirmative
asylum
adjudication. I tried to show you some
idiosyncrasies of this setting and how
scheduling affirmative asylum cases is
really quite different from scheduling
surgeries in a hospital.
I'll try to describe a mathematical
model of the affirmative asylum system
and this is going to be more on the
conceptual side to be clear and then I
will highlight the effect of different
scheduling policies and their efficiency
properties highlight fairness
considerations in the scheduling and
show you how some of this plays out
historically on actual data. So how do
affirmative asylum cases get
adjudicated? It begins with an asylum
seeker submitting a form I589 and their
biometrics and then USCIS scheduling an
interview. This little arrow here could
take weeks or it could take years. That
is the big scheduling
question. Then there's an asylum officer
that needs to prepare for the interview.
that in includes reading the
application, learning more about the
country of origin of the asylum
applicant, doing background checks,
preparing interview questions. Then is
the actual interview and that is
supposed to check for credibility and
eligibility and make sure that there
aren't any other bars to asylum. I won't
go into the details of these, but there
are various that exist and could
preclude somebody from being granted
asylum. Based on the interview, there's
some uh written assessment that gets
checked by a supervisor and then asylum
is either granted, the case is referred
to immigration court or it's
denied. Now, there are various
operational goals of the asylum system.
I want to focus on the ones that are
most operational in nature that are most
closely related to the scheduling which
are timely processing and efficient use
of resources. What are resources? It's
the time of the asylum
offices. Now, timely processing, if you
look over the last 15 years at the
backlog of affirmative asylum cases,
it's gone from a few thousand to more
than a million.
That means that a lot of cases clearly
are not being processed in a timely
manner. Now it also means from an
operational perspective that we have a
service system that is overloaded.
Meaning that the arrival rate, the
number of applications that are being
filed is much larger than what we would
call the service rate, the number of
cases that are being adjudicated.
In operations, we usually think of
various solutions to such an overloaded
service system. One can try to increase
capacity. One can try to reduce demand,
for example, by increasing the cost of
an application for various political
reasons and practical reasons. That
seems to be complicated or that is
complicated in this application.
But there's another aspect that is
different about this
application and that is that applicants
actually receive a work permit while
they wait for the interview. They don't
receive it immediately. About 6 months
after applying, one can receive a work
permit. What does that imply? It implies
that for some
applicants or some potential
applicants there might be a benefit for
having a longer wait. Why would that be
the case?
Because if one believes that one won't
necessarily be granted asylum, then
having a longer weight would mean that
one would be able to work legally for
longer.
And that means that the idea that we
would want a short backlog and short
wait times is actually not shared by all
potential system
participants. This may sound like a
crazy notion but U Jadu who was director
of USCIS during the last administration
actually highlighted that this was found
to be the case. Some individuals
realized that due to processing delays,
they could file non-marriitarious asylum
applications and receive employment
authorization before their cases were
reviewed. So at least it was being
suspected that this was happening. Now I
want to highlight sort of how this
changes the dynamics of a service
system. Traditionally when we think
about a service system, for example,
this box here could be a Starbucks
store.
We will have people that arrive and they
will decide whether or not to join based
on the difference between the benefit
from the service. If it's a Starbucks,
that would be drinking a latte and the
cost from waiting in
line. So, we have some people that don't
want to wait. If there's a long queue,
that means there's a long wait. If
there's a long wait, some of these
people will leave and the queue gets
shorter. That is how we think about
service
systems. Now, what if there's utility
from waiting? Well, if we have a
somewhat long queue with a long wait,
then we're going to have more arrivals
leading to an even longer
queue. And if we have a short
queue with short waits, then we're going
to have even fewer arrivals and an even
shorter queue.
So, not only do we have here an
overloaded service system, and of
course, I want to highlight this is
very, very
stylized, but it's an overloaded service
system where traditional approaches to
optimize scheduling don't
apply because traditional approaches
don't model people that are seeking to
wait. They model people that are
avoiding weight, which to be fair is
what happens in most other settings that
we can think of from Starbucks to
hospitals to anywhere
else. Now, we're trying to model this in
the following way. We'll have an
iterative model that evolves over
periods.
In every period, the scheduling policy
together with the rate of incoming
applications will determine how long
people wait. This could be a fixed
number or it could be a distribution
over different
numbers. But then in the next period,
the previous weight determines the rate
of incoming
applications. And we will be interested
in the equilibrium of this meaning the
limiting behavior as we keep updating
this. How many applicants how many
weight seeking applicants do we or
weight driven applicants do we
observe? And in particular what we would
like to answer is how is this affected
by scheduling policies and how does the
initial rate of incoming arrivals affect
the outcome.
Now there's a informal theorem statement
here written but really what we're
trying to get at to to summarize it is
that there are two possible outcomes
under both a FIFO and a LIFO scheduling
policy. FIFO is what you think of at
Starbucks. People get served in the
order in which they come in. LIFO would
mean that people get served in reverse
order. The person that got in last gets
served next.
Um this is illustrated somewhat in these
plots and you can see that
for FIFO there's a point where FIFO
converges to a congested equilibrium
while LIFO converges to still the no
weight equilibrium. And on the plot all
the way over here, you can see that both
converge to congested equilibria, but
the life for one is actually
smaller. In our model, at least this is
not a
coincidence. In fact, we can prove that
across all scheduling policies, LIFO
would minimize the arrival rate and the
the queue length, whereas FIFO would
maximize it.
Now, should
USCIS schedule arrivals in a life for
manner? Meaning, should the most recent
applications be processed
first? I mean, most people would say no,
that's a very weird suggestion, but that
is actually what's been
happening. So, for most of the last 30
years, that has been the scheduling
policy. There's a letter signed by more
than 60 representatives of the US House
from four years ago highlighting that
this causes significant harm. In
particular, older meritorious cases have
languished for years. As a result,
individuals who have experienced
significant trauma are left in limbo,
often separated from their families
while their applications are
pending. Why does that happen? Well,
under LIFO, if you're in an overloaded
system, if you don't get processed,
you're stuck in the backlog
forever. So, we now have people that
have entered the backlog 10 years ago.
And if we continue to process by LIFO,
there will always be other people that
get prioritized before
them. How does USCIS react to that?
Life was a critical tool in controlling
non-mritorious or fraudulent
applications filed only to obtain
employment
authorization. Going by our theoretical
results, that is a reasonable
response. But then they also say that
they actually haven't been using
LIFO. Rather they allocate some
resources to the completion of the
oldest cases and some resources to the
completion of the newest cases.
So in a sense they are doing a hybrid of
life and fifer. They split their
capacity between oldest and
newest which begs the question if that
is the right way to interpolate between
the
two. We can again look at our
theoretical model and we would like to
measure the fairness of such a hybrid
policy and the way we want to measure
fairness and this is to some extent
subjective. This is how usually people
think about fairness in a queuing system
is how often does somebody waiting in
line experience that somebody who joined
after them gets served before them. It's
a reasonable fairness definition. I'm
not going to claim that it's the only
one. If you go with this fairness
definition, something weird happens.
This hybrid scheduling policy that's
trying to interpolate between FIFO and
LIFO can actually be worse than just
LIFO.
Meaning in this direction things become
more
unfair. In this direction the backlog
grows larger. As we said before FIFO
maximizes the backlog, LIIO minimizes
the backlog. But in terms of unfairness,
we can actually be strictly worse than
we would be if we had just used
LIFO. Now, um let me just wrap up by
showing you a few uh plots that are
based on data in New York.
On this plot, I'm just showing you the
quarterly number of decisions and
filings in the four affirmative asylum
cases in the New York
office. To the left, the LIFO policy was
in place. Over here, the LIO policy was
in place. In between the FIFO policy was
in place in between those red bars.
Now as you can
imagine in between when we had a lot
more applications than we had decisions
the backlog grew
significantly but what I'm showing here
and that is the blue line but what I'm
showing you here also is the black line
which shows you the
unfairness and there I think there's an
interesting insight here which is that
when the backlog is
all. It doesn't matter so much whether
you schedule in LI for or FIFO
ordering because you're not skipping
that many people in line because there
aren't that many people in
line. When this backlog grows
large, then LIFO is very
unfair. But of course there's a question
of whether the growth of the backlog
here had the change of the scheduling
policy to FI for at least as a
contributing
factor. So I'll conclude here there's an
interesting aspect to asylum scheduling
that traditional studies of service
systems haven't incorporated. At the
same time, there's a lot of expertise in
computing and operations to design
scheduling algorithms.
Hopefully this work can lead to more
research that aims to actually improve
the system and practice and um
highlights that there are
significant decisions in immigration
that are really operational decisions
and that have really significant impacts
on people's lives. I'll stop here. Thank
you very much.
[Applause]
Thank you. Questions for Daniel.
Um so one question in the LIFO strategy
are you able to process more
applications than in the other one? No
the intuition that you should be
thinking of the the capacity is the
same. So that's a a great question. I'm
not trying to change the capacity of the
two systems. However, under
LIFO, there are more people that end up
not joining the system because they fear
not getting the work permit. And that
makes them less likely to join. And that
then leads to a smaller backlog.
I'm just curious if anyone has proposed
a maximum wait time at which point the
asylum claim would be automatically
approved. It seems like that might help
with the fairness problem.
Yes. Uh I think that's that's a
wonderful question and uh here I clearly
leave the extent to which the the my
research would provide insights. Um I
think to some extent what you're hinting
at is really that the system has moved
from one
equilibrium where
the processing rule was LIFO but it
didn't really matter much because the
weight was short to another equilibrium
where it doesn't really matter what
scheduling policy you you I mean I don't
want to say it doesn't matter but like
the backlog is there now and there needs
to be a way to deal with it. At this
point, I think most policy makers and
most academics in fields that usually
study immigration would agree that what
is needed is more substantial
immigration reform rather than sort of
some change to the scheduling
policy. Okay, let's thank Daniel once
again.
[Applause]