Good afternoon.
I'm Anantha Chandrakasan, MIT's
Chief Innovation and Strategy
Officer and the
Dean of Engineering.
It is my honor to introduce
our panelists and moderator
for the session
on collaboration.
Our panel brings together global
luminaries in biotechnology
and health care.
And they work with us right here
in the Boston Cambridge area.
They've each received numerous
prestigious awards and honors,
and you can review them in their
detailed biographies online.
During today's
discussion, our panelists
will explore the rapidly
changing landscape
of life sciences research
and how we can collectively
embrace and shape the new
challenges and opportunities
that lie ahead.
Moderating our discussion
today is Dr. Noubar Afeyan.
Dr. Afeyan is the
Founder and CEO
of Flagship Pioneering
and co-founder
and Board Chairman of Moderna.
Because of COVID,
virtually everyone
knows about Moderna, a world
leader in mRNA technology.
Some of you might not know as
much about Flagship Pioneering.
Flagship Pioneering empowers
entrepreneurially-minded
scientists to invent solutions
to health and sustainability
challenges that seem unsolvable.
The result has been the
creation of more than 100
first in category
bioplatform companies
that are having significant
real world impact.
During his career as an
inventor, an entrepreneur,
and a CEO, Noubar has
co-founded and helped
build over 70 life science
and technology startups.
Terrific to have you
moderate the panel today.
Noubar will be joined by our
four distinguished panelists.
Dr. Anne Klibanski is
the President and CEO
of Mass General Brigham,
or MGB, a world class,
nonprofit, Boston-based
integrated health care system.
It is the largest private
employer in Massachusetts.
We all know that MGB delivers
world class health care.
However, it is also a
leading hub for innovation
in health care, helping
to bring academic research
from the lab to the patient.
Anne and her team have overseen
substantial investments
in leading edge research
as well as the creation
of more than 300 companies.
With Anne's leadership,
MGB is building
the integrated academic health
care system of the future,
and it's a system
that puts patients
at the center of it all.
Anne has been instrumental
in shaping the MIT MGB
collaborations.
It is truly a pleasure
to work with you, Anne,
to work on advancing
health care.
Robert Langer is the
David H. Koch Institute
Professor, one of only nine
Institute professors at MIT.
Bob is a world renowned
biomedical and biochemical
engineer who has pioneered the
development of new materials
for controlled drug
delivery systems,
particularly for continuous
controlled delivery
of genetically
engineered proteins.
He has written over 1,600
articles and 16 books and holds
more than 1,500 issued
and pending patents.
His patents have been licensed
to over 400 companies.
As an academic, my favorite
metric is that he is the most
cited engineer in history with
an H index of 327 with 437,533
citations, at least
as of yesterday.
[LAUGHTER]
It is estimated that
Bob's research--
[APPLAUSE]
It is estimated that Bob's
research has improved
the lives of over two billion--
with a B-- people and counting.
I'm very grateful to Bob
for all of his advice
in the creation of MIT.
Christopher Viehbacher
is the president and CEO
of Biogen, one of Cambridge's
leading global biotechnology
companies.
Chris has extensive
international experience
in large pharmaceutical
companies,
including GlaxoSmithKline
and Sanofi,
where he was the global CEO.
As the co-founder of
Gurnet Point Capital,
a Cambridge-based health
care investment fund,
he also values the
role of startups
in moving good science
out into the world.
As CEO of Biogen, Chris
is creating a new path
by broadening the
company's investments
in advancing innovations in
immunology and important--
increasingly important
field of research.
We're delighted to have a
long-standing collaboration
with Biogen, as we've
heard this morning,
and delighted to have
you join us, Chris.
Finally, Dr. Reshma Kewalramani
is the CEO and President
of Vertex Pharmaceuticals, a
global biotech company that
was founded here in Cambridge.
Now it's headquartered
in the Boston seaport.
Reshma is literally on her way.
She'll be here in a
couple of minutes.
With training in internal
medicine and nephrology
and extensive
business experience,
Reshma's leadership bridges
the medical, biopharmaceutical,
and the drug
manufacturing domains.
Using this expertise,
she has helped
vertex from increasingly
effective cystic fibrosis
treatments to a new
CRISPR-based gene editing
therapy for sickle cell
disease and transfusion
dependent beta
thalassemia that FDA
approved within the past year.
It's been a pleasure to work
with Reshma, who's here,
and brainstorm how academia
and industry can work together
in this space.
We're very delighted to have
this incredibly distinguished
group join us today.
And now I will turn
it over to Noubar,
who's going to make some opening
remarks and lead the discussion.
[APPLAUSE]
Well, thank you, and I feel
like introducing Anantha
after that very elaborate
introduction you
made for all of us.
Thanks for your
leadership, Anantha,
for originating this
initiative and for allowing
me to participate in
this very special event.
I just want to make a
couple of framing comments
and then we'll get right
into the discussion.
I came to MIT in 1983 to
pursue a doctorate thesis
at what was then the beginning
of this awkward marriage
between engineering and biology.
You heard about that from
Phil Sharp this morning.
It was called biochemical
engineering at the time,
and I had the great
honor of working
with one of the founders
of that field, an Institute
professor, Professor Danny Wong,
who unfortunately passed away
a few years ago.
I came here as an immigrant
fleeing a Civil War in Lebanon
after a few years
in Montreal, where
I did an undergraduate degree.
But 40 years later,
I had the honor
of delivering the commencement
address just this spring,
and just as great an honor
to be here with you today
on this very special occasion.
As the saying goes,
what a country.
And even more
appropriate today, what
an Institute MIT has become.
As a visiting committee member
in biological engineering,
chemical engineering,
and biology,
those of you who are
on MIT know that this
is a very important part
of MIT'S governance,
I've had a front row seat on
the two decade long discussion
about how MIT should best go
about becoming more relevant
in the biotech ecosystem.
It is already extremely
relevant, but how could
it do more?
How could it be more
impactful, not only here,
but in the whole world?
And looking at that today and
participating in the program,
I think that HEALS is a
very appropriate response
to that challenge.
As was announced by President
Sally Kornbluth this morning,
my wife Anna and I were
pleased to contribute
in a small way to
this initiative
through supporting fellowships,
graduate fellowships.
This is our way
of paying forward.
I did a degree here.
I have two daughters who have
done three degrees between them
here.
And I think that
everybody here who
has the means to
contribute through HEALS,
whether it's through
involvement or otherwise,
I would urge
everybody to do that.
This is the beginning and
it's got a long way to go.
And Anantha didn't ask
me to make this plea,
but I want to make it
because I think everything
you saw today is really--
it's hard to fathom,
but I get to see in many,
many other institutions
similar presentations.
And as I was saying
during one of the breaks,
most basketball teams have
one seven foot player.
None of them has 12
seven feet players.
And what you saw today
were the equivalent
of seven foot tall players
in every single area.
So we couldn't be more pleased
with our ability to support.
Now, as a segue to
this session, we're
going to have a
very important topic
to discuss to wrap up the day.
And I wanted to share
with you one last thought,
which is a curious, coincidental
connection between the words
that start with the
letter C. In addition
to curious, coincidental,
and connection, bear with me.
I am a bit of a
geek, so I went here.
So I call these the C's
that drive the biotech--
world leading biotech
position of Cambridge.
Now, let me try
these out on you.
Concentration of capital,
culture, connections,
creativity, community,
critical mass.
We have the critical
mass in this field,
in my view, bar none.
Competition and collaboration.
And it's that last C that this
panel will be talking about.
We're going to do this by my
asking them a few questions,
and then we'll have a
discussion, which I hope and I'm
sure you'll enjoy.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
So we're going to
start-- we're going
to go down this group here.
But let me start, Anne, with
you to talk about the research
mission of Mass General.
Obviously, Mass General is
a huge research institution
in addition to being among the
best hospitals on the planet.
How do you think about the
differences in this mission
when that's being
done in a hospital
setting versus academia,
and how is it different,
how is it similar?
Let's start with that.
Yeah, so I love starting
with Mass General Brigham
because we are an integrated
health care system.
And we start and
end with patients.
So when I think about
health care innovation, when
I think about
collaboration, when
I think about all of the
things that we are all here
to think about, it
has to, in the end,
begin and end with patience.
So starting with the
health care system,
thank you for that
because I think
that is a fundamental thing.
And just as an anecdote,
I've spent my life
before doing this job as a
researcher, as a clinician.
Just today, and I
do this sometimes,
I like to walk
around the hospital.
I can walk around Mass General,
or the Brigham, or Mass Eye
and Ear, or McLean,
or Spaulding,
any of the institutions
in the system.
And it's always wonderful
to just go and walk
on one of the floors,
talk to a few Fellows.
I talked to a few
oncology Fellows today.
I talked to a few nurses who
work in labor and delivery.
What does that do?
It grounds me, and it should
ground all of us in, ultimately,
these phenomenal people who
are 100% focused on patients,
whether it's through
the research they do,
the training they do, the
clinical care they deliver.
So I just want to
emphasize that part of it
because I think that
is just so critical.
To get to your question
about research,
when we think about
the missions, certainly
the missions of
Mass General Brigham
and this is the missions
of so many, particularly
in the academic
health care system,
it's really providing the
highest level of, really,
integrated quality care
and an academic system.
You have to go to that
mission and tie it
to the next mission, which
is research and innovation.
And what distinguishes us and
other academic health care
system is that tie.
It's bringing the best of
research and innovation
and infusing it, instilling
it into clinical care,
that highest level
of clinical care.
And the other missions,
when you think about it,
when you think
about training, when
you think about
servicing community,
they all come together.
Research is the fundamental
driver of the system.
And we are the largest
academic health care
system in the country
in terms of NIH funding.
We have an enormous amount
of funding, and most of it
is federal funding.
I'm going to take a
pass on where that's
going to go in the future.
That's an important topic
very much on our minds.
But that's not
really your question.
Your question is, what does it
look like in an academic health
care system?
So I would say that research
and the, again, infusion
of that research
into clinical care
is what that looks like in an
academic health care system.
Now, in contrast to many
academic health care systems
around the country, we
are not under a university
or a medical school.
We are affiliated with Harvard.
But the grants,
the research, that
is all done on our campuses.
That's something that I think
is very special because it ties
together that research
mission, the researchers
with the clinicians,
they sit together.
And in fact, when you look
at a lot of our clinicians,
particularly those in
the subspecialties,
they spend a lot of
their time in research.
So this translation of
research into those things that
will really affect
people, the new therapies,
the clinical trials, the new
discoveries, the new devices,
the diagnostics, it's
being lived in real time
at the hospitals.
So if I think about what this
looks like in a university basis
or in a hospital basis, I'm
putting that all together
and saying, the phenomenal
work that gets done here at MIT
is absolutely ripe
for that collaboration
to come to our hospitals.
But every day these things
are a real life laboratory.
So taking all of the
work that goes on
and bringing it to
another laboratory,
that is the clinical laboratory.
And I think, sometimes,
the challenge,
when we think about this,
is they're still in pieces.
And some of it is a bit
of linguistic dissonance
because the language
of the basic scientists
may not be the
language of clinicians.
We hear a lot about that.
These are things that
you can overcome.
But living all of
that together means
that every day, top
of mind for the people
who are delivering care, who are
trying to solve those problems,
are deeply embedded,
living with, connected to.
And it can be a
geographical collaboration,
a conceptual collaboration.
There are many, many different
forms of collaboration.
I'm looking at that
word collaboration
and thinking of the many,
many things that means.
Some begin with a C, some don't.
And just thinking
about what we can
create with a university
like MIT, and part of it
is the people.
You bring the people together.
Part of it is the ideas.
But I have found,
certainly in our system,
the way to get the best
and the brightest people
working together is to give
them a problem to solve.
You give them a
problem to solve,
and that's where you get
the energy, the passion,
and the talent working together.
So basically, we're going to
try to fill in the Charles
River between MIT
and MGB and increase
the lanes on the Longfellow.
That's basically what we
have to do with HEALS.
We can get the urban
planning folks involved in--
They will solve that for us.
That's right.
So the other thing we
heard on the introduction
was that MGB itself is heavily
involved in a lot of translation
and a lot of companies.
How is MGB going about
thinking about another form
of collaboration, which
is between industry
startups and the kind of
science that's done there?
It's interesting.
I was the Chief Academic Officer
before taking on this role,
and that was back in 2012.
And when I started,
I had spent my life
as a researcher
and most of my work
was NIH funded, although
because I was in rare diseases,
I was very interested in
partnering with industry.
So I had a lot of collaborations
going with industry because I
knew that for rare
diseases, you really
weren't going to get anywhere
unless they had an industry
collaboration.
That was sort of a given.
And I think when I
think now about MGB
and how it's thinking
about it, the reason
I'm going back to 2012
is because I really
think there has been a cultural
transformation in the thinking
of a lot of our scientists,
and that's not unique to MGB.
And there are a lot of ideas
about why that is taking place.
But let me start by
what is taking place.
The cultural transformation for
many, many of our investigators,
and we, again, have thousands
of investigators, many of them
have spent their lives focused
on the research in a singularly
focused way, which if you
think about where it leads to--
and this is what I was
taught when I was first
doing my training after clinical
fellowship-- it leads to grants.
That's good.
Ideas lead to grants.
And that leads to papers and
that leads to promotions.
That leads to an
academic reputation.
That leads to making
important discoveries
in a field, whether basic,
whether they're translational,
no matter what they are.
So the end was that piece of
scholarly work and its impact.
The shift is to broaden out
what impact really means.
And I think the cultural
shift among many--
and it's interesting,
some of the surgeons
were way ahead of this.
They would come up with
ideas and they were more
keen on seeing that instrument.
What's that new instrument?
How do I operate better?
What is that invention that
will make things happen?
There were always a bit
more focused on that.
I don't want to
overly generalize,
but that's what I was saying.
But it was really getting
all of those investigators
to understand the full
life cycle of an idea
and how to have the
biggest impact on patients.
And that, I think, was
a very different way
of thinking about
industry, thinking
about pharmaceutical
companies, startups,
how do you actually take that
idea and bring it to patients?
You can't do that by yourself.
You can't do that
only with a grant.
What you have to do is have
those critical partnerships
and go through the
life cycle of an idea.
And it has to go to a company
or start a company or a partner
with a company.
You need to get a
product in the end,
whether it's a drug or
a device, whether it's
an algorithm,
something that then you
can bring back to patients.
And I think for our
investigators, particularly
those who are more
translational, but also,
some of the more basic
science investigators, that
understanding that if you really
wanted to impact human health,
you had to think more
broadly, and I would just say,
complete the circle.
So that's the cultural
change that took place.
And I think at Mass
General Brigham,
it is just now fundamental and
very much core to who we are.
I would also say that if you
look at a lot of our trainees,
they're already there.
They don't need it.
They're already there.
They come in and they're
already thinking,
how do I take this idea?
Where does it go?
What's the result of it?
How do you partner?
And some will actually start
companies and go there.
Some will join industry.
People have very
different career paths.
But I think it speaks to
the broadening of what
that circle looks like and
the interdependencies of all
these different sectors.
So the concept is
academics are not
an endpoint in and of itself.
Super.
Bob, you cover a lot of these
same topics from the MIT angle.
You run a lab that does basic
research, applied research,
engineering, translation,
and a lot more.
But you didn't
start out that way.
So how and when did unmet
clinical need and translation
get into the way you think
about research directions?
And also, how would
you-- because we
saw a lot of younger
academics who
don't come in with connections
to the clinical world,
how have you forged these
kinds of relationships
with the clinical world?
Yeah, well, it's
a great question.
So for me, I mean,
Noubar knows this,
but I got my degree in chemical
engineering in 1974 at MIT.
And then, when I got it,
almost all my colleagues
went to work for oil companies.
They had a lot of jobs
that paid a lot of money.
Anyhow, I ended up doing
something very different.
I wasn't that excited about the
oil companies and I had lots--
and I ended up getting a job as
a postdoc at Children's Hospital
with a surgeon
named Judah Folkman.
And by the way, for chemical
engineers at that time,
nobody did anything like that
because it paid so much less
and it also didn't look like
a very smart career move
according to everybody
that I talked to.
But I was fascinated by it.
And so I went there
and I was actually
the only engineer in the
hospital at the time,
and certainly, in
the surgery lab.
And the way I got
started, he had this idea
that if you could
stop blood vessels,
that maybe that would
be a whole new way
to think about treating cancer.
people.
Thought he was crazy.
They didn't think
that made any sense.
But at any rate, there
was no way to study it.
And so what I--
so we had to develop
what's called a bioassay.
And to do that,
we had to create,
we thought, tiny
little particles
that could deliver
a large molecules.
And Dr. Folkman would
talk to different experts.
At that point, drug delivery
was hardly done at all.
There was only one company
in the world working on it
and he went-- he was
an advisor to them
and he asked them
if they could help.
And they just said this
delivering a large molecule
would be impossible.
Anyway, I spent several
years working on it,
failed hundreds of times.
But finally, got a
way to get it to work.
And then, we published
articles in Nature in 1976
showing that you could
for the first time
deliver large molecules,
including it was the first paper
to deliver nucleic acids.
And also, we published a
paper the same year in Science
showing that you could use
it to stop blood vessels.
So that was kind of my
first taste of everything.
And of course, it took many,
many years before those--
I mean, the first one took
Genentech doing great work
building on some
of the things we
did before that would lead to
Avastin and many other drugs.
Second one, of
course, that's where
I got involved in starting
some companies, including
a number with you, Noubar,
using drug delivery
techniques to protect and
deliver different molecules,
including messenger RNA.
And Noubar and I
have shared that.
But the thing is to
try to figure out
what the applications are,
That's, a team effort.
I mean, all these things have
very broad potential uses
and figuring out what the ones
that are going to be important
you don't necessarily know.
Certainly, when we publish
those papers in 1976,
we had, obviously, no
idea that messenger RNA
would be important, that
COVID would even exist.
And so, really, it ends up being
a team effort over the years.
And also, to go over part
of your question, what
was great for me personally
was being in a hospital
with a lot of clinicians
working next door to them,
and it would lead to
more and more ideas.
And some of them are
my best friends, even
today, 50 years later.
So another one was
Jay Vacanti, who
started at Children's
and went to Mass General.
He came to see me one
day and said, Bob,
could we make new
tissues and organs?
And we came up with
this idea that would
lead to tissue engineering.
And again, we didn't
the right applications.
He was talking
about liver, but it
would lead to a lot
of other things,
including organs and
tissues on a chip.
And of course, the other
great thing about what's
happened in terms
of clinical things,
and this is, I think,
the beauty of Boston,
you have MIT and all
of the hospitals.
You get all these
incredible Fellows
who come to your lab for
several years from Mass General,
from the Brigham, from
Children's Hospital and Beth
Israel.
Jeez, I mean, I've probably
had about 20 or 30 summer,
[INAUDIBLE] Traverso,
professors at MIT now
and some have started companies.
So it's just been-- so
you just get ingrained
in that because of all
the great people around.
So on the company
side, then, you also
have been a prolific founder
of a number of companies.
And I'd say probably
so much so that it
must affect how you train your
students and the postdocs,
or at least what
exposure they get.
Because if they
want to be like you,
most academics who
don't do startups
have their graduate
students and postdocs
being trained to be like them.
Well, in your case,
they also need
to learn how to
start companies, how
to influence large companies.
I ask it seriously.
How do you think you
have incorporated or have
you some of the things you have
learned in the startup world
into the way you actually train
the students and run your lab?
Yeah, well, I mean,
part of it to me is--
I don't know that
I do that much,
but I think probably--
as my wife would say,
I'm probably the opposite
of a micromanager.
I try to come up with
big ideas and give people
a lot of freedom, but with
clear objectives in mind
and try to get big
papers and big patents.
And that does happen,
to your point.
But people see,
it's not just me.
I mean, Noubar, again,
knows a lot of this.
I started a couple
companies back in the '80s.
And then, like Jay Vacanti,
he said, well, can we do one?
And then, I had this
postdoc, David Edwards,
who you know and he said,
well, Bob, I want to--
people-- so it kind
of gets ingrained.
And so it's not just me.
People see the older graduate
students and postdocs
and colleagues doing it,
and it kind of just happens.
I think, a lot of times with
companies, people don't--
like if you go to some
other universities,
they think it's like,
how could you ever do it?
It just seems almost impossible.
But when they see people a few
years older than them do it,
they think, well, yeah,
that could be nice.
And when we started,
I think it was
AIR, which was David started.
Jeez, I don't know how
many people from the lab
when they graduated went
there and they ended up
doing very well.
And so I think it just--
they'd see that by example.
And then, finally, we
have great seminars
as we had Noubar once give us a
lecture and I still remember it.
He starts out about
entrepreneurship
and how everything, really,
with entrepreneurship, almost
every scientific-- every
scientific discipline
is really embedded in that.
And some of the examples
of the things that you did.
And sometimes, with me,
sometimes with many others.
And I think people
just see that.
And I think that--
so having role models, I think,
ends up being a really big deal.
Super, Chris.
You've been in large
companies, you're
in a slightly less
large company,
but it's still really
large compared to startups,
and you've done a lot in
the various hats you've worn
partnerships with academia.
Talk about what you've
seen works in that arena,
the value of such partnerships.
We're in the collaboration
section of this day.
It'd be great to get your
insights on that, plus maybe
some things that you've found
over the years doesn't work.
Yeah, I mean, Andrew Lowe
gave a really nice synthesis
about how drugs get developed.
And there is
certainly, OK, you have
to have some idea of
what causes a disease.
And, then you're going
to find a target.
You find a molecule and
you do a clinical trial.
But in actual fact,
there's just a never ending
series of puzzles that
present themselves to which
you have to find an answer.
And pretty much developing any--
particularly first
in class drug,
there is no pathway to follow.
And even if you find
a molecule, well,
how do I deliver the molecule?
If it's a small molecule,
how do I make it soluble?
I mean, do I need a device?
What's an endpoint?
Even if I have a
molecule, how am I
going to measure whether
this is working or not?
Even if I know that, then I
might have another problem here
to solve on scaling up in
manufacturing, for example.
We heard the presentation
earlier about nanoparticles
and what a role that played
in getting mRNA, actually,
to where it needs to go
to make the mRNA vaccine.
So even after we figured
out mRNA and what it does,
we still had to deliver it.
And so when you're
in the company,
you're really focused
on value creation,
as we heard from one of the
entrepreneurs this afternoon.
So your job is really
trying to take that molecule
and move it as fast,
but you don't really
have the capacity to do an
awful lot of basic research
and a lot of discovery research.
But in some ways, a
lot of these things
you have to discover
just to solve them.
And that's where you
need these partnerships.
How do you solve these problems?
And you're not going to
always have the capability
inside your own company.
Now, a lot of companies
do think they need that,
and that sometimes is a problem.
But generally, I mean, you
look at all the cool stuff
we heard today and all the
different technologies.
And you think about,
Bob, you haven't just
developed molecules,
you've developed
how to get things to places.
And that's where you
got to figure out,
what's the right combination of
people who are trying to drive
something to an endpoint and
people who are really having
the time and maybe the risk
capital or the government
capital to actually solve some
of these basic problems that
need to be done?
Now, it happens to happen is
some level of trust has to exist
and a sense of common purpose.
And you were saying it starts
and ends with the patient.
And that has to be for
everybody in the chain.
You can get hung up on things
like intellectual property,
for example, can get in the way
of some of these collaborations.
And that's where a
certain amount of trust
is going to be needed
to try to figure out,
how do we share some
of these things?
Because if different people
and different organizations
are solving different
parts of the problem,
somewhere there has to
be return on all of that.
Otherwise, they
can't survive either.
And so, sometimes, that might
be an advisor at Mass General
and they're doing
clinical trials for us
and they can advise us how
to-- where's the unmet need?
How should we design
this clinical trial?
It might be coming to MIT to
solve some of these delivery
problems.
So there's sort
of a never ending
series of these collaborations.
It's not just one project.
It is creating a porosity almost
between the organizations.
Now, you also find that all
of this depends on people.
And I always say,
running companies
would be easy if it weren't
for all the people inside them.
[LAUGHTER]
And people really create
the complexities in this.
And you get egos involved.
You get different incentives
that are not aligned,
and that can cause problems.
Personalities.
And so there has to be, in some
ways, some sort of alliance
management, generally, to try
to smooth those problems out.
One of the things that
you don't want to create
is a sense of one is a
subcontractor to another.
There has to be a respect for
the intellect, the talent,
the capability on both
sides of a collaboration
to say, OK, we are not going
to succeed without the other.
So you have to create a lot
of the right people dynamics
to make this as well.
Sometimes we can
get carried away
with the science or the
problem, but the number
of times I've seen
collaborations
that don't work that just come
back to basic people problems
is a real issue.
And so, certainly,
whenever we start one,
create the relationship and
build the relationship over time
and build it on the respect
and capability of what
the other brings.
But as I say, if
you don't do that,
you're never going
to get to the end
because these
collaborations just don't
start at the very beginning.
Because in Andrew's
model, it was sort of,
hey, there's the idea,
you create the patent,
and then, it goes
to the companies.
Well, it's not quite so simple.
It's these constant
collaborations.
And that's why I think it's so
helpful to be in this ecosystem.
Biogen is across
the street from MIT.
We're across the river from MGH.
And when you talk about
those relationships,
that makes it a whole lot easier
when people know each other
and see each other all the time.
And I do think that is
this proximity of all
of the talent and
people that we have
make those people issues a
whole lot easier to deal with.
And I think that's what--
since collaboration
is so critical
and people issues
are so critical,
I think that's what makes
this work here super.
And Reshma, you're are
leading a native kind
of Cambridge-born
company, Vertex,
one of the great
standout successes
of the biotech industry,
really, in the biotech era.
You're not literally
in Cambridge,
but you're in the
greater Cambridge
area is kind of how we view it.
And so with that
in mind, give us
also your view on this topic,
if you don't mind, on industry,
or at least Vertex's
collaborations with academia.
And in particular,
obviously, you
have David Altshuler
from MIT, you
have Doug Milton from Harvard,
and many leading academics
who have gone into industry.
So give us your sense of
this dynamic of collaboration
between biotech and university--
research universities.
Yeah, I think a lot has
been said about this,
so maybe I'll point out two
or three additional points.
The work that we
do in biopharma,
biotech, the work
of drug development
is a very particular
kind of work
and, honestly, doesn't
happen in academia.
I left academia because after
my own circuitous journey,
I realized that when I started
as a physician scientist,
I thought what I wanted to be
was a triple threat, run my lab,
see patients, teach students.
I really thought that's
what I wanted to do.
And I fashioned my
entire life to do that.
Until I actually did
it and I realized
I was doing research in
areas that didn't actually
interest me.
But that's where
the funding was.
That's where the
grant money was.
And I just decided one day
I was not going to do that.
And then, I realized when I said
to myself all those years ago
that I wanted to do
research, I actually
meant I wanted to
make medicines.
I didn't know how to
say it prospectively.
But when I was there, I realized
that's what I actually meant.
And then, once I decided that's
what I really wanted to do,
it turned out to be extremely
difficult, if not impossible,
to do in academia.
You need to have all of
the basic science discovery
infrastructure, which I
think academia has in spades.
Then you need clinical
development, regulatory affairs,
manufacturing, and a
whole lot of capital.
That was not
available in spades.
And then you need
another group of people
who could take that medicine
and actually bring it out
to patients around the globe.
You need access, you
need health economics,
you need a sales and
marketing infrastructure.
And I actually left
for that reason.
When I went to my
chair and I told them
all this exciting
stuff I wanted to do,
they said, OK, you are at--
I was at the Brigham
at that time.
You have 20 hours of
statisticians time.
20 hours.
I wouldn't even be able to
write one protocol in 20 hours.
And that's what drove
me to go to biotech.
And I went to a company
on the West Coast.
And the collaborations
that I saw there
and the collaborations
we do at Vertex
are along these lines of
the very best innovation,
and we have
fantastic scientists.
But given the vast amount
of science that can be done,
it cannot all be done
within the walls of vertex.
So we partner often
with academics,
with small biotech companies,
and with others who
are just doing basic
science research.
We also collaborate
in-- then in-license
and/or acquire companies because
that company, that technology,
their asset works perfectly
for what we want to do.
And then, the third
way we partner is there
are some unique
problems that come up
that you don't expect to
come up along the lines.
We might be making a
medicine for cystic fibrosis
or we might be making a medicine
for sickle cell disease.
But along the way,
you realize you
need some data set, you
need some algorithms,
you need to understand how to
do certain off-targeting work
that we don't know
how to do inside.
We just know that it's
a new problem that's
come up along the way.
And working with
academia, institutions
like MIT and Harvard, has
been incredible for us.
One of our medicines that
was just recently approved
came from a partnership
with CRISPR Therapeutics,
a small biotech
company right here.
Another one of our
programs that's
just in phase III development
as of the last couple of weeks
came to us by purchasing
Doug Melton's company.
So if you said, look,
you've got to do work
without collaborating, I'd
say patients would suffer.
It is absolutely
essential to what we do.
Super.
So staying with you.
The other thing
that MIT contributes
and as such
universities contribute
to Vertex and to Biogen and
others is human capital,
is the students.
And with HEALS
today and what we're
kind of celebrating
and launching,
I know that MIT very much is
interested in what more it
can do to better prepare
students, graduate students,
postdocs, everyone to be even
more impactful in biopharma
industry.
So with a lens towards the
future, what types of things
would you expect
that MIT could maybe
add to its arsenal of how
it's preparing students?
I think President Kornbluth's
focus at MIT on life sciences
is really critical.
I happen to be
married to an engineer
and it's not that awkward.
We do OK.
[LAUGHTER]
But I realized that we actually
think completely differently.
To be a fantastic
practicing physician,
you need to connect dots.
And you need to
repeatedly connect
the dots the same exact way.
Photophobia, neck, pain,
fever, you think meningitis.
And you think that
every single time.
Otherwise, a patient will die.
So it's a lot of
pattern recognition.
It's not that good to
be all that creative.
As an engineer, my
husband sees every problem
and he sees the
most, I don't know,
this-- a small, obscure
piece of evidence
that he wants that to be proven
to him based on first principles
that it's true.
And all I say is,
photophobia, neck pain,
fever, that is meningitis.
[LAUGHTER]
I think there is a lot of
benefit to bringing engineering
into the life sciences,
and the best element of it
is something that Anne
said, it helps patients.
You can use engineering to make
tires and pencils, I suppose,
but there's no better cause
than to do this in health care.
What I think that does
mean is introducing
physicians like myself
to engineers, to math,
to technology.
In our medical school existence,
we don't learn a whole lot
about that.
And ensuring that
engineers, even if they're
mechanical engineers and
not biomedical engineers,
have a good, strong
foundation in biology.
I find that a lot of
engineers are turned off
by biology because they
think it's rote memorization.
And as a physician,
I have to admit
I'm a little turned
off in my earlier days
from engineering
because I thought it was
about oil and building bridges.
[LAUGHTER]
So I think that
there is a lot more
we can do to make sure that
engineers know mechanical,
computer science, electrical
that there's a lot of great work
that they can do in biopharma.
And the only way we can do that
is to make sure that, one, we
talk about it, two, we
have seminars like this,
but three, internships
and fellowships,
there needs to be a lot
more movement of engineers
into biopharma.
There already is
quite a bit of that.
If you're a PhD in
the life sciences,
there's actually an
entire Vertex program
that welcomes you and you have
the opportunity to do that.
We need to do more to make
that opportunity for engineers.
Chris, same question to you.
Yeah, I think I've been
a trustee, actually,
of Northeastern
University for 10 years.
And I think one of the
interesting things they do
is they've got this
experiential learning, which
used to be called interns.
It goes back to something
I was saying earlier.
A lot of the problems in life
are really people problems.
And if you can get the
people to work together,
you can solve an
awful lot of things.
But the higher you go
up in an organization,
the more you're going to be
focused on getting people
to work together effectively.
And I think younger
students, often,
it's a question of
how much do I know?
What's my technical knowledge?
What's my capability?
But at some point, if you're
creating these collaborations,
or at some point, you're
going to lead a team,
you have to develop some
of these softer skills.
And I think that's important
to start to introduce even
in engineering and sciences.
I don't think that
often gets enough.
Some of that can be through
the fellowship program
that you've
generously sponsored.
We've got fellowship programs.
We have an intake
of MBA students
and we bring them through.
But there is an element, once
you get inside a company,
you are in an organization.
And once you're in
an organization,
you have to learn
about culture, you
have to learn about leadership,
and the other element
I would say is business acumen.
Andrew's omics were fabulous.
I mean, economics
is fundamental.
I mean, you have to raise money.
You've had to raise money.
You deal with omic economics
a lot at the hospital.
We do it as company CEOs.
And the reality is nothing is
going to happen without capital.
And so I remember I had hired
one guy when I was at Sanofi
and he was one of the first
MDs to do an MBA as well.
And at Harvard, they
almost said, well,
why are you doing that?
Now, today, that is
a lot more common,
and you see these
combination degrees.
I think Wharton,
for instance, you
can get a combined science
and finance degree.
But people certainly who have
the scientific capability, who
bring these other human
capabilities as well
as the business acumen, I think,
will really go a long way.
So continuing the
discussion, we've
gone 30 minutes without
using the AI expression.
So we see we're disciplined.
But now I do want
to turn to that.
Because we heard today that
this was the 50th anniversary
of the Cancer Center here and
how much molecular biology
influenced all that.
And then, we heard about how
engineering got involved.
And now, we're all kind
of-- not only do we
have to combine
biology, engineering,
patients, clinical
care, but now we
have to get into AI or AI omics
if Andrew's expression works.
But that's kind of unfolding
in front of our eyes.
So taking out AI as it
relates to productivity gains
in our regular life, how are
each of you thinking about this
as--
or are you-- as a
pillar of what you're
building on in the future?
Obviously, at MGB, you go from
the data generation, data access
set of issues that
AI raises all the way
to many, many
other applications.
So maybe, if you
don't mind, I also
wouldn't mind because
this is being filmed
that we take a little
bit of the opportunity
to just project a bit over
the next 10, 15 years.
And so when this group HEALS
gets together and celebrates
their anniversary,
we can look back
and they can make fun
of what we projected.
And with that, tell us
the current reality,
how you're thinking about it,
and how you see the future.
So you brought up a
lot of different things
that come together.
When you think about a patient
from a purely clinical point
of view, you're always
thinking about bringing
in multidisciplinary
strengths to solve a problem.
I'll just get to
the problem-solving.
So you could have a
patient and no one
really knows what's going on
and there's an internist there.
And someone will say, yeah, I
think I know what's going on,
but I'm wondering if maybe
this relates to endocrinology.
Then the endocrinologist will
come in and say, well, no,
this is not endocrinology at
all, but I think it's this.
So at the end of
it all, you might
have five different
medical subspecialists
all with their own point of
view, their own expertise,
their own view of the world, and
their own learnings who are all
focused around the patient.
So then, if you broaden
it out, you get more
into these themes of, it's not
just multidisciplinary in terms
of medicine, what else
are you bringing in?
And then, you get into the
technologies, the engineering.
Now you're bringing
in multidisciplines
of a different point or a
different part of it that's
all focused in.
So when you talk about this
in terms of the clinical care,
the AI, the engineering,
et cetera, I just
want to put the
patient at the center
and think about
these things that
are going to be wraparounds
in terms of how you ultimately
solve the problem of
what's the diagnosis, OK?
What's the treatment?
How do you find the
right treatment?
How do you get the
treatment to the patient?
All are wrapped
around the patient.
So when I think of AI right now,
and I'll try and summarize this
maybe in three
points, number one,
it is, what we doing
in terms of AI that
is helping the clinician?
That's the easiest thing to do.
So that is, how do you
take and deal with burnout?
How do you look at
different data sets
and put them together
that are already existing
that will help the
clinician do what?
Write a better note?
OK, well, that's
great, actually.
But that is here and
we want to go here.
So if I look at the parts
of this, number one is,
how do we broaden out
the knowledge base
beyond the physician,
their own experience,
to the five physicians
in the group,
to the medical literature,
to what we all based
on these different articles,
different observations,
and be able to have a massive
amount of data all compiled
together to put it together
in the most objective form?
So number one is, how will this
help us in terms of diagnosis?
And there are a lot
of issues about this.
I mean, there's a radiology
conference many years ago that
basically said,
will there be a job
for radiologists in five years?
That's not really the question.
The question is, how do we put
together lots of different data
sets in--
that are huge, that have been
applied in a gold standard way
that are validated.
What does that mean?
That are equitable so
that you can actually
make a real diagnosis.
So I think the diagnostic
possibilities--
because we're already seeing
it-- are extraordinary.
And it's going to be hard
because of all the issues
that we have with AI that we
could spend another hour on.
So I think the second thing is,
how do you personalize therapy?
How do you match
therapy to the person?
That's been one of the
single most pressing
therapeutic problems.
We look at drug trials.
We have broad answers.
But then, there's that subset
that could have done this.
It's the personalized medicine
that we keep talking about
that we're not there.
AI can definitely
help us get there.
So I think the
predictive properties
of this in terms of
diagnostic accuracy,
in terms of looking at targeted
therapies, drug discovery,
I could go on and on.
But honestly, I think it's going
to revolutionize health care.
I was at a Microsoft
meeting about two years ago
and they had a presentation
about AI in the car industry.
And I learned more about
the application of AI
to health care in
that presentation
than I'd ever thought of before.
And you could say,
how is that possible?
It's the car industry.
Because the concepts that they
were talking about in terms
of data and how you view
it and what it means
and how you can envision the
future needs were extraordinary.
Super.
Bob, maybe put on the kind of
science if you look forward--
maybe just take the
forward question.
If everybody had access to all
the knowledge you have gathered
and your imagination
in the form of ability
to create new patterns,
how do you compete?
And then, what does
that look like?
Yeah, well, one other
thing I was going to say,
and because I wasn't--
I was talking to students and
thesis committees all day,
so I didn't hear some
of the earlier sessions.
But I hope it was
said at some point,
if it was the 50th anniversary
of the Cancer Center, jeez,
I think MIT has been doing AI
research for way more than 50
years and really deserves a lot
of credit for pioneering it,
people like Seymour
Papert and others.
And we ourselves
have used it for--
I mean, again, in science,
things-- actually,
for Chris's point,
like about solubility.
We came up with ways of
doing high throughput
systems for solubility
with Mike Simon,
looking at thousands and
thousands of combinations
and analyzing what you could--
and keep iterating
until you get something
that does make the
drug soluble enough
with FDA approved excipients.
But I think, going forward, the
way I think about it is, I mean,
I don't know if
it's what I know,
but I think it's like to me, it
does go to the science like--
to data, where can large
amounts of data be very useful?
One of the things I do
feel, like when I mentioned
this idea of tissue
engineering before,
is you could have-- to the
extent that you can make organs
and tissues on a
chip that really do
simulate the human
model, which are doing
quite a bit of that at MIT.
I could envision that
as the years go by
could just screen thousands,
maybe millions of molecules
and find new targets, find new
drugs using things like that
and use AI to predict
what's the next iteration
to the next iteration till you
maybe would have someday help
Alzheimer's or other things.
Because right now, if you have
to do everything in humans,
that's pretty tough.
But we're working with
Li-Huei Tsai, for example,
with the postdoc, Alice Stanton.
So we have a brain on a
chip where we could take,
actually, anybody's
cells here, and actually,
with Merit Cudkowicz,
we're going
to be talking to her about--
I was her pre-med
advisor and now she's
head of neurology at
MGH about maybe using
it to find new targets for ALS.
And so I just
think, again, where
you could take these things
and get thousands and thousands
of molecules, maybe
millions, and then
use it to find new targets
and new molecules that
could treat disease.
Super.
Maybe, Chris, to continue with
a view towards maybe a little
bit the present and a
lot more of the future.
And it's OK to speculate.
On the area of drug
discovery, drug development,
and the delivery of
clinical products,
how do you see this play out/
Well, first, I would go
back to the economics
before we go anywhere.
Because some of us were
at a dinner last night.
Sally and Susan,
various 50 members
of the broader ecosystem here.
And there was a lot
of concern raised
about the threat on innovation.
Certainly, we have a
current new administration,
but I would argue that
innovation was somewhat
under threat even before.
But now we're talking about
overhead recovery rates
and grants.
We're looking at pricing
implications for our industry.
And I think when you look
at the federal deficit,
you look at the
percentage of people
who are going to be over
the age of 65 by 2030,
it's going to be significantly
higher than where it is now.
And I'm sure, Anne, you would
agree that, actually, it's
those people that are pretty
heavy users of health care.
And we see already that Medicare
is potentially not solvent
just when I'm about to join it.
[LAUGHTER]
There is a massive amount
of economic pressure.
And when you go back to the
presentation by I think it was
Professor Lauffenburger this
morning where he started-- well,
we start with-- once we
actually get it out of academia,
we're still looking at
10,000 molecules to get one
that's approved.
And somewhere, I think, we have
to be changing fundamentally
the model of how we're doing
research and development.
Because society is telling
us that pricing and cost
is important, and we're going to
have to do this a whole lot more
efficiently.
If I look at clinical
trials, as much innovation
as we do on the molecular
level, we have done very little
on the actual process level.
And so what we're doing
at Biogen, for instance,
we have dry labs.
If you're in small
molecule chemistry,
you can actually now use
AI to, actually, develop
a more optimized molecule.
We used AI to create
virtual waiting rooms
for hospitals to actually find
patients for clinical trials.
Today, if I'm going to do
a study with 400 patients,
we're going to have to go to
400 or 500 clinical trial sites.
I mean, that's crazy.
Who does that?
If we could do 400
patients in 100 sites,
you have a massive
benefit on productivity.
So I think AI is not
just a cool tool,
I think we have to figure out
how do we reverse engineer now
how we're doing
research and development
because I don't think that
this pressure economically
on us as universities, as
biopharmaceutical companies is
going to go away any time soon.
And AI strikes me as a
way we can revolutionize
how we're doing things.
Reshma.
Maybe I'll give you
some practical examples
of what we do.
I think that there's
a lot of scope today.
We don't have to envision too
far into the future for AI
in imaging.
So for us, part of what we do
when we do our type 1 diabetes
cell therapy, our scientists
will describe the cells
as fluffy, cloud-like, plump.
And some of those are good and
some of those are not good.
And right now, you have a
scientist looking at a tube
to see if it's fluffy,
cloudy, or plump.
That we are
converting reasonably
with ease into an
imaging AI model that
will tell us these are the good
cells, these are the bad cells.
I think that is
already here and now.
We try to do that with studies
in clinical development
when you have to take biopsies.
I think that's a good place to
go and that's easy to do now.
I think the other place
that's really ripe,
it's not exactly now, but it's
maybe the day after tomorrow,
in manufacturing,
now that we're going
from chronic small molecules
or biologics molecules
that you take by
mouth every day,
biologics that you may take
once a month to these one
and done curative therapies,
the manufacturing of those
and the quality release of those
is an enormous human task, far
better done by computers.
But it's actually manual.
We still write batch
records in a log sheet
by one human being who is
then checking the same thing
to other human beings because
that's all we have right now.
So we don't need fanciful AI.
We just need not to be faxing
things back together or PDFing.
We just need to automate
simpler things like that,
and that'll get us a
huge bang for our buck.
In the distant future, right
now, we do what Bob describes.
We have really
smart people taking
30, 40 years of
experience and recognizing
that that carbon
moiety or that oxygen
atom in that spot,
that's where it usually
triggers a signal for maybe
a drug-induced liver injury.
It would be great to
catalog all of that
and to have that be a
little bit more automated.
It's not as bad as
I portray it to be.
Even today, we have
software and we
have algorithms that tip you
off to this is a red flag.
When you have this
moiety in this corner,
it's not going to work out.
We have ways of making things
more soluble or less soluble.
But I would say we are 70%,
80% human, 10%, 20% computer.
And there is a lot more
ability to do that.
But if we just tackle the simple
stuff, like in manufacturing,
like in batch records,
like in imaging,
and I agree with Chris
on clinical trials.
Today, when you do clinical
trials and now we're doing
clinical trials of
30,000, 40,000 people,
because the effect
size is smaller,
because we've made health
care better, there are people,
doctors, physicians, scientists
who are reading through reams
of safety data.
That's called line listing
review because we literally
review lines of data.
That is far better
done by a computer.
It's not there yet, but
that's the low lying fruit.
Super.
Well, look, we're out of time.
I think this has just
been a glimpse of what
interdisciplinary collaborative
discussions will look like.
Hopefully, it will happen at
every classroom and every corner
of MIT going forward.
And please join me in
thanking our panelists
for this discussion.
Thank you, guys.
[APPLAUSE]