Okay, continuing with this segment, our
next speaker will uh be Armando Solar
Lzama. He is a distinguished professor
at the Schwarzman College of Computing
and also the chief operating officer of
the computer science and AI lab, CESAL,
at MIT. Armando is going to speak to you
about how AI is transforming uh so
software engineering. Thank you. Thanks
a
[Music]
lot. Very glad to uh very glad to be
here. And in my research lab and uh you
know generally myself we have been
working
for about 20 years now on this problem
of how to bring more automation into
software construction. and how to
leverage computing power to help people
deal with tricky problems that arise
when you're writing uh software. And I
have to say it's been quite a ride. Uh
when we started working in this area,
the dominant question was why are you
working on this? This is never going to
work. It's too hard. You need too much
cleverness to write software. How is a
machine going to help you? And suddenly
about three years ago, it switched very
abruptly to why are you working this on
this? This is a solved problem. uh
there's already all these companies
doing this. Um there is really no need
to uh uh to be doing this in in academia
and it certainly has been quite a
change. You know the very first paper we
published in this topic uh you know
trying to get machines to help us write
programs. A running example was well
what if you want to drop every third bit
of a stream of bits which is you know
not the most ambitious of targets but at
least it worked. uh to today where
people are actually seriously wondering
do we actually need to learn how to
program? Does anybody need to learn how
to program? Um are we just about to make
programmers obsolete? Right? And um we
have this enormous gamut of production
quality fully deployed tools and
widespread use across industry. And it
raises the question so what is there
left to do for academic research in in
this uh in this space. So this is a
question that we've been fielding a lot
in the last few years and as it happens
uh just last week we released um a
report on the challenges and paths
towards AI and software engineering. try
to give a summary about what are some of
these open problems and what are some of
these directions where current tools and
current models still have problems. Why
do you still need uh humans helping you
write uh helping you write software? If
you're interested uh definitely a lot
more detail there than in the 18minute
talk,
but very broadly speaking, what are some
of these uh open challenges? One really
important one comes with out of
distribution domains. What does that
mean? Uh programming that doesn't look
like the bulk of code that you can find
in GitHub or you know out on the
internet in general, right? Turns out
everybody's code looks different
especially when you go inside companies
that uh you know as a rule tend not to
like to uh open source all the code
they're writing. You know, oftentimes
you end up with code that looks very
different from the code that these
models have been trained on. Program
understanding especially at scale turns
out to be quite u quite a challenge. Uh
these models have become quite good at
reasoning about code locally. And uh in
fact uh just two years ago we released a
benchmark showing that models were
really not very good at reasoning about
the behavior even of small fragments of
code and basically it took a few more
months for industry to catch up and
actually um essentially make this
benchmark obsolete. Um but when it comes
to uh reasoning about software at scale
that is still very much an open uh
problem. Similarly along that vein is
this question of software design. Right?
Software is often designed with a wide
range of goals. Not just does it produce
a right answer uh but keeping in mind
how you expect the code to evolve
possibly over decades into the future.
And good software design is something
that is really critical for good
software engineering. It's something
that uh is uh is not uh specifically one
of the goals for many of these uh many
of these tools. Similarly, when it comes
to reusing code, there's a very basic
mode of reuse where you have a function
that does X and somewhere else you need
to do X and the model tells you, yep,
here's the function that does X. That's
the simple case of reuse. But the real
sophisticated case of reuse, the kind of
reuse that you would expect from a
skilled programmer is the kind of reuse
where you know that this new
functionality that you try to implement
can be um assembled by you know taking
this little bit of code here that was
actually written for a completely
different purpose and this other little
bit of code over there that was written
for a completely different purpose. And
that if you take this routine over here
and you generalize it in just the right
way, then you can bring all of those
together and get your new functionality
writing very little code. Right? That's
the kind of sophisticated reuse and
sophisticated reasoning that is really
today still beyond the scope of many of
these tools. And the big one and really
the crucial one is the specification
challenge. How in the world do you
actually tell the machine what it is
that you're trying to uh what it is that
you're trying to do? What is this
software supposed to uh to do? And um
you know it is a little bit of common
knowledge in uh you know the broader
community that everything changed with
the advent of LLMs. There is very
clearly a before and after in the world
of program synthesis and uh machine
learning for software engineering right
when uh you know GPT3 came out and it
became very clear that this was going to
be a very powerful technology for
working with code but there's actually a
lot of really compelling ideas that come
from the research community even before
then that still have a lot of relevance
in this period for example Um, you know,
back in 2017, we were actually working
on this problem of how do you deal with
code that has complex functionality
where it might actually be difficult to
describe exactly what you want it to to
do, right? And you know, today we live
in a world where there's lots of code
out there, lots of code that is ready
for you to reuse it. uh so that you can
implement very rich functionality
without actually having to write a lot
of code. Uh and this is great until you
actually try to find this code and then
until you actually try to go and figure
out how to reuse it and when you
actually realize that it kind of almost
does what you want but not uh not
really. And when you're dealing with
relatively complicated functionality
that can be hard to describe, you know,
today we can use natural language. But
even natural language is not often
sufficient to convey what uh what we
want. Uh uh you know as a simple example
we used the case where we had a code
editor and this code editor had this
plug-in system that allowed you
to do very simple uh with very little
extra code uh implement things like
syntax highlighting for new languages,
new programming languages that you
created, right? Very powerful uh
framework, very powerful functionality
until you actually try to uh reuse it.
And so what we found was that well uh
something as simple as I want to reuse
uh the syntax highlighting functionality
requires you to know that there's
something called the rulebased scanner
that you have to extend with your own
scanner. But then you have to go to
something called the source viewer
configuration and override it with your
own source viewer configuration that
internally has to instantiate something
called a presentation reconciler.
There's actually something called a
damage repairer. And suddenly you're
wondering like what do these things have
to do with the syntax highlighting,
right? Um it's uh it turns out that the
whole framework has its own internal
language and its own internal logic and
once you understand the logic everything
makes perfect sense. For example, in
this case the editor has this view of
the world where there's a very nice data
structure that reflects the state of the
code. Every time you type new code,
you're damaging the relationship between
the view and the data structure. So you
have to repair that damage to
rehighlight things. Oh, okay. That makes
sense. If you didn't know that before,
how would you know that? How would you
know what to search? How would you know
what the right uh keywords are? How
would you know what the right classes
are? And it goes back to this problem of
yes, all the code is there. How do you
find it? Right? And LLMs are supposed to
be the solution to this. You can go and
describe what it is that you want to do.
And you know out comes a very nice
tutorial together with all the code
together with all the information that
you need about how to uh how to do this.
Uh you know sort of because it's a lot
of code and very quickly you run out of
buffer space and it cuts off in the
middle. Um, but even more problematic,
you still have to have a very specific
prompt describing very precisely what
you want, using the right uh class
names. And you know, here we're talking
about a very well doumented API. This
was a framework that lots of people
used. There were blog posts. There were
tutorials. It's an ideal case scenario
for this kind of tool, right? What
happens when you have to do the same
thing but for your internal company API
that suddenly doesn't have all of these
uh resources. Turns out API versions
turn out also to be a huge problem for
this. uh if the API has gone through
five different versions as most widely
used APIs uh have then suddenly you're
going to get some mishmash of pieces
that work with one version and pieces
that work with another version. And uh
this actually turns out to be quite uh
problematic. But more importantly, there
is this highle problem of how do you
tell the system what it is that you want
to do if you don't even know what is the
internal language that it uses in order
to do this. So one of the ideas that we
uh we actually experimented with was
allowing you to just take another system
that was built using this framework and
just start working with it. And at some
point you get to the functionality that
you like and you press a button that
says, "Hey, I'm about to show you
something. I'm about to show you the
thing that I want." And you can go and
exercise these functionality and then
press another button and say there, you
know, that thing that just happened,
that thing you just saw, that's what I
want you to figure out and tell me what
to do, right? And that turns out it
requires this very different way of
interacting with the system, right? for
those kind of situations where using uh
just natural language is not enough. You
really want to be able to give those
live demonstrations. You really want to
be able to show look the functionality
that I want is like this one, but in
this other uh context, but we're still
at a very early stage in terms of being
able to rely on these richer forms of uh
feedback. And in fact, one of the things
that becomes really essential to deal
with that kind of a problem is having
multimodal support through our language
models. We're starting to see some of
that in the uh uh frontier models today,
but one of the problems that you've run
into is that there's not a lot of really
high quality data, especially when you
go out towards the long tail of lesser
used uh frameworks matching the actual
code with the actual behavior, right?
And this is an example for example from
a project that um we just completed. Um
this was uh really led by my colleague
uh Voych Matusk uh and his students uh
his student Bon uh Lee. But the idea of
this project was that we wanted to
target the kind of uh texture generation
infrastructure that is used for things
like video games, right? where
essentially what you have is this little
program that describes how to turn
random noise into a nice um texture that
uh that you can use to wrap your your
shapes in in a video game, right? So, it
turns out there are uh widely used tools
that designers can use to design these
kind of textures. And on top of these
tools, there's also Python APIs. So you
know as soon as there's a Python API you
know that this is something where LLMs
can can help you but what we really want
is the following. We want to have a
system where you can take a picture
let's say of the carpet down here and
from that picture you want to feed it to
your language model and get out the code
that when you run it is going to give
you the equivalent texture. And often
times, right on the first try, you're
not going to get exactly the same
texture. You're going have to do a
little bit of local optimization in
order to get really the right uh
texture. But this is within the
capabilities of modern LLMs except for
the fact that even though they've seen
some of these Python code, they haven't
seen enough of it to really understand
how it works. And in particular, they
haven't seen enough data matching the
code with the actual behavior that you
want. Right? And this is where you
really need uh to uh actually do some
data augmentation. We actually had a uh
a pretty sophisticated pipeline to
generate uh about um half a million
programs such that every one of these
programs could be fed through a renderer
to teach the model about the
relationship between when the code looks
like this. This is the kind of texture
that that you get out. When you do that,
you can actually get uh some pretty nice
uh behaving system, right? These are
some examples from some textures uh
written in uh Blender comparing uh the
input image with the
uh image generated by the code produced
by our system compared to a bunch of
different uh baselines, right? And you
can see that certainly most of the
baselines uh you know even uh
sophisticated frontier models just don't
do a very good job again because they
haven't really seen that relationship
between the code and the behavior of
that uh of that code. Right? Here's a
few more examples from uh textures
produced by different uh by a different
framework. Here's actually some examples
directly from pictures, right? uh actual
pictures taken from a texture and what
the model is able to uh to produce.
Right? So on the one hand this shows
that it is possible to bridge this gap
between uh you know these different
modalities of interaction and uh code
and that uh you know fine-tuning a model
that does this is within the reach of an
academic uh lab like uh like ours,
right? Um on the other hand it uh it
also highlights some of the limitations
of you know just business as usual. So
where do we see things going forward? On
the one hand I think programming tools
will become more and more essential
right to the days where you could be
competitive as a programmer just writing
code in VI with absolutely no tool
support beyond your compiler or
interpreter. I think might uh be
reaching uh their limit. On the other
hand, there is still and we believe for
a very long time going to be a very
crucial role for human expertise
particularly the flexibility that humans
can bring to the table in terms of very
quickly being able to learn uh new
things is actually going to be quite uh
quite important, right? And you know AI
tools for coding can truly be enablers
of creativity, right? Allowing you to
write code that otherwise would have
been just too uh too difficult to write.
But I think there is uh care that has to
be taken in terms of protecting the
health of the software ecosystem. What
does that mean? Well, if you have a tool
where the tool works way better, if
you're using the old version of the
framework for which there's uh hundreds
of blog posts and hundreds of tutorials
compared to the new version of the
framework that just came out, that
suddenly introduces a lot of inertia
into the system, right? Right? And if
you can't nurture the ecosystem for you
know those tutorials and those uh help
forums to keep up to date with the new
tools and the new frameworks then I
think there is uh there is some risk
going into uh the future and finally I
think we're going to start facing some
important questions around uh you know
this question of technical debt right uh
we have these tools that we can use to
dramatically improve our productivity
and help us produce code that is much
better structured, that is much more
maintainable, that is freer from bugs,
or we can use it to build lots and lots
of really really bad code very very
cheaply and very very quickly, right?
And which one is it going to be? Uh both
of those are possibilities, but I I have
to say I much rather live in the world
where we pick option one as opposed to
option uh two. And so um with that I
would like to uh now take some
questions. Thank you.
[Applause]
So this is a really good question,
right? What role will software engineers
play in an industry where AI is
increasingly generated generating code
and how can they adapt to maintain their
impact right so um I think there's many
different uh answers to this question
depending on what kind of code you are
talking about right so first of all
there's a kind of sort of frontier code
that is you know difficult challenging
to write that really requires all your
creativity and brain power that looks
really different from all the code out
there on the internet. I don't think
we're going to be writing that code
entirely by hand. But I think the
development of that code is now going to
involve a lot of, you know, figuring out
how to set up the problem, figuring out
how to orchestrate all the compute power
to really focus it on how to solve that
one uh problem. Right? Today uh you know
we see these very impressive results of
tools
uh solving you know competition level uh
programming tasks. What we don't see is
the enormous amount of effort and
investment that went into actually
setting up the tools and you know
targeting it towards that particular
kind of programming. I think there's
going to be a style of programming that
is really more about orchestrating the
tools and setting up the thing so that
you can now let your uh cluster run for
a day and have some confidence that
after a day or after a week of running
you will actually get a piece of code
that does what you want. Now um arguably
most people today are not writing that
kind of code and in fact uh you know
people talk about what's going to happen
when we have this revolution in
programmer productivity. We already had
uh not just one but multiple revolutions
in programmer productivity. One of the
most recent ones happened when we moved
to managed languages which made it
possible to actually not have to write
lots of complicated algorithms all the
time. Right? Most algorithms get written
once, get put into the library and now
it's just a matter of knowing how to
call the right library and knowing how
to use it. So writing these very very
unique algorithms has already for many
years been a bit of a very high-end but
somewhat minority uh pursuit. When it
comes to the broader volume of code, a
lot of that is really about figuring out
what do we want to build? What is this
program supposed to do? And how do we
navigate the trade-offs between
performance and cost and
usability? And how do we uh adjudicate
all of these conflicts between what this
customer wants and what that customer
wants? And programming is a way to
settle those questions with very very
high precision, right? To say this is
what the solution is going to be. That's
not going to go away, right? We still
have to figure out actually what it is
that we want to build. What is it that
the service is supposed to do? What is
the service how is the service supposed
to react when this particular uh crazy
situation happens? So programming is
going to be very very different. But a
lot of those fundamental questions
around system design are still very much
going to be there.
[Applause]