If a child is lucky and
is allowed to be curious
and to imagine, that's a
nice way to let the child grow.
I am the fourth of four,
There is a big gap between them and me.
So I spent a lot of time
by myself in the backyard,
which is a piece of dirt and
just plain imaginary things.
I had that very vivid imagination.
It was wonderful.
I mean, I grew up in a
city called Maracaibo.
And when I was nine, my
family moved to Caracas.
I loved being with my
peers, my classmates,
and my friends from the neighborhood.
I remember evenings in
which, as a teenager,
I would go Friday
nights to a little place
that sold ice cream, and it
was just sat there and chatted
and drink ice cream, and
then go home close to midnight.
It was just safe and fun.
I was curious
academically about everything,
but the only thing
that I did have a sense
of going to high
school was that I eventually
have to have a job.
You know, when you're growing up,
all you know is what you see around you.
You don't come up with
ideas of how the world is.
You just learn the world that you see.
And the world that I saw,
there's not too many
people going to high school,
not too many career-oriented people.
I thank my brother for that,
because he opened that window to me,
and I saw that as an opportunity.
What I did is I looked
to what does the country,
what does Venezuela need?
And at the time, Venezuela needed a lot
of electrical engineers.
So bingo, I'll be an electrical engineer.
I remember my days as a college student,
borrowing books from the library and
borrowing the MIT books.
I thought MIT was a person.
I had no clue that that was a university.
For me, that was M-I-T.
I thought this is an
author that wrote those books.
I mean, I had no clue.
And I realized how special it was for me
to be studying from the books written
by those who created that knowledge.
And now I'm in this
place that creates knowledge.
And once I came here, I never went back.
I mean, I was just so happy.
I just didn't leave.
I didn't know a place like this existed.
I mean, it was just such a
wonderful experience for me,
even right now, saying, give me chills.
I mean, at this place, I was impressed
by the richness of the
variety of groups of people
and cultures here.
Nobody here speaks English properly.
They all speak with a funny accent.
And they are interviewing another one
with a funny accent.
So there is something
very interesting about this.
I've had so many conversations with people
from different cultures
that have been brought up
with different narratives.
And they can see a fact.
And they can interpret
it in different ways.
I cannot think of everything
because I have blind spots.
But if I have enough
people around me collectively,
collectively, we don't have a blind spot.
There is no richer place because every
point of view is here.
That is what makes this place so special.