Okay. So let's continue discussing uh
the proof of burgans production theorem
and how it's similar and different from
the corresponding statement in the final
field setting. Um so just as a quick
review because we are going to keep
working uh with this concept uh a delta
S C
D set
is a subset
of let's say the unit ball
or maybe the unit cube. It doesn't
really matter. So it has to live in some
bounded region of space such that
if we intersect X with a ball
and look at the delta covering number,
this is controlled by well first of all
this tolerance constant C then the
radius of the ball to the power s
and then the size of all of.
So it is a spacing condition and
although this is not part of the
definition
it's convenient to imagine that the size
of x is maybe delta to the minus s
although it doesn't have to be but it is
in the setting of bugans projection
theorem as I stated it
and speaking of bugans projection
theorem as I stated it let me state the
version well not the version it's really
exactly the same theorem I stated last
time but using this language. So,
Borgans projection theorem again. So,
it's really exactly the same statement
just using this language
and rescaling.
Suppose that X is in the unit B2
and is a delta oh sorry quantifiers. So
given
t between zero and two
is strictly positive at most one there
exist or there exist two parameters
epsilon and ea positive depending on t
and s so that the following happens
if x is a delta t delta to the minus ea
uh set in R2 2 with
size
delta to the minus t
and d the set of directions
uh let's say in 01
[Applause]
is a delta s delta to the minus ea set
then there exist a direction
in our set of directions
such that if you look at the minimum
over all subsets of X which are dense in
the sense that the delta covering number
is at least delta EA this tolerance
parameter
times the delta covering number of X and
we project
the subset then no matter how I choose
the subset
We get a gain over the between quotes
trivial bound which is less trivial in
this setting but nevertheless
uh this is at least delta to the minus t
/ 2 minus epsilon. So epsilon is how
much we gain and delta to the minus ea
is our tolerance.
Okay, this is really the same theorem as
last time. Last time x was in the radius
r and it was a union of unit balls but
we just scale it down by a scale of 1 /
r and by the equivalences for measuring
the delta covering number that I
mentioned last time this is really the
same statement.
Okay.
Okay. Okay, so last time we saw that the
following is true even though we didn't
actually prove all of it.
Last time we saw that there exist a
polomial
uh which is just x1 x2 x3 - x4 x5 x6 or
okay that works. So exist a polomial
such that for every
s between zero and one
and okay I didn't state it this way last
time but maybe let's introduce also the
two parameters here last time I stated
it with just one parameter of course you
can just take epsilon and it to be the
same by taking the minimum so the whole
statement if you replace epsilon or and
ora by a smaller number is still true so
we could just take the minimum and have
just one parameter but I sort of want to
distinguish them because they play
different roles. Okay. So there exists
epsilon anita such that
if a is
delta
s delta to the minus ea
set
maybe contained in 01
and maybe let's assume also that the
size of a is delta to the minus s then
the size grows by applying this polomial
Okay. And we discussed that uh this is
not enough to iterate because in order
to iterate we need to know that Q of A
also satisfies these assumptions and
this is not clear at all and in fact is
not true. So need to improve
to
Q of A contains
a delta S plus epsilon delta to the
minus EA set.
If we knew this then we could iterate
and keep growing. So keep adding epsilon
and because epsilon is continuous in s
we can get as close to delta to the
minus one as we want.
Okay. So uh today we will discuss how to
do this. So let me say that it's not
going to be the same epsilon and ea. So
they're going to they're going to yeah
they will become much smaller
but same order of quantifier. So there
exist s for every s there will exist eta
and epsilon. So that this is true.
Okay. So this is what we are going to
mostly discuss today and hopefully then
go briefly over how to uh finish the
proof. But I would say this is the main
difference with respect to the finite
field setting where we don't have to
worry about any of these. Okay. So
before coming back to this we'll take a
detour and then uh we'll come back. So
let me state a lema with some basic
properties
of delta s c sets.
Suppose that x
is a
delta s c set in any dimension.
Then we make the following two fairly
easy but important observations. So
maybe I should have done this last time
to get some intuition about what this
concept does. First of all, X is large
at all scales. So the row covering
number of X is at least C to the minus
one row to the minus S for every
row between delta and one.
I mentioned in passing last time that
this is true for row equals delta, but
in fact it's true for every row.
And two, this concept is robust and
they're passing to subsets. So if X or
maybe Y is a subset of X and the delta
covering number
is let's say 1 / K times the delta
covering number of X
then Y is
delta S C * K set.
So the constant C gets worse by
the parameter measuring how dense Y is
in X always using delta covering
numbers.
[Applause]
Okay. So the proof of this is fairly
simple. So let's do it. We have to prove
something. Well, we need to show that
the row covering number is something. So
the definition of the row covering
number is the smallest number of row
balls needed to cover the set. So let's
cover the set by row balls.
And let's see how many balls we need. So
let's say we cover the set by
m balls of radius row.
Well then the delta covering number of
a. So the delta covering number is
subjective. Something which will be very
will come out repeatedly today. And this
is just because if we have a delta cover
sorry a row cover sorry a delta cover we
are covering by reduce delta now if we
have a delta cover of each of these we
can put them together and we get a delta
cover of this. So for this reason the
delta covering number is sub additive.
Okay, so the delta covering number of a
is at most
the sum of the delta covering numbers of
a intersected with these balls.
But by definition of delta covering set,
each of these is at most c row to the
s times the delta covering number of a.
So we have a uniform upper bound that
only depends on row. So the center
doesn't matter. So this is just the
definition of
a being a delta c set.
Okay. So this is at most m c row to the
s
delta covering number of a. So we see
that we can cancel out the delta
covering number of a and we get the
claim one.
So we get that m is at least
what is on the right hand side there.
But the smallest possible M is by
definition the rock covering number.
Okay.
Okay. And two is even easier.
Well, uh we have to show that y is a
delta uh dc of course should be s.
So we have to y satisfies the definition
of delta covering number. So of delta is
set. So we intersect with the ball
of radius row.
Well y is contained in x. So this is at
most
the same thing with x instead of row.
But x is a delta s set. So this is at
most
c * row to the s times the delta
covering number of x
but the delta covering number of x is at
most k times by the delta covering
number of y by assumption.
So this is at most ck
row to the s delta covering number of y.
So we have checked that y is a
delta s ck set.
Okay. So what what information have we
gained regarding our task? So we need to
show that q of a contains a delta s plus
epsilon delta to the minus ea set. Well,
if it contains such a set, then Q of A
must satisfy the conclusion of the first
part of the lema. So the row covering
number of Q of A has to be large. We
have proved that the delta covering
number is large. But it is necess it is
ne it's not sufficient but it's
necessary to show that Q of A grows at
every scale. Right? We want to show that
it contains a delta T over 2 plus
epsilon
something set. So it needs to be large
at all scales.
[Applause]
Okay. So uh we see that
we need
q of a a scale row to be larger than row
to the minus t / 2 minus minus epsilon
for every row between delta and one and
a purely we only know it for delta. So
what we discussed last time is that this
is true for delta
and again this is not sufficient. Yes
that say row to the minus s minus
epsilon
>> row to the okay so now okay so this this
is was a general statement about delta
sets and now I'm going back to what we
are trying to achieve.
Oh sorry s yeah yeah so there is sorry
yeah so this is still not buggans
production theorem we are working with
just one setting 01 thank you
okay um
we need this to be true
and okay so one could think that we have
it for free because why can't we just
apply
what we know at scale row
So this is a question for you. So why so
again uh this is necessary is not
sufficient but okay let's try to focus
on getting this first. So why why do why
don't we get it for free?
So what is the difference between row
and delta?
So that's the assumption that we have
over there.
Yes,
>> because we don't know that a
sum.
>> Well, okay. So, the assumption is that a
is a delta s something set. And you're
right. We don't know that a is a row s
something set. Uh there is another thing
that could be a bit worrying. I would
say is less worrying which is that delta
to the minus epsilon is not row to the
minus epsilon.
We would need row to the minus epilon.
Delta to the minus epsilon is much
bigger. This last thing is not so
serious because we can always
okay the last thing is not so ser okay
okay neither of them is so serious in
some sense but okay the second one maybe
we'll come back to discussing later but
it is less serious the main issue is
that okay so we don't get this for free
Because
a needs not be
and delta row delta to the minus epsilon
set.
Okay. And we also would need row here.
But let's ignore this for a moment. And
my parameters are all wrong. Row s delta
minus epsilon set.
And also okay even if we did uh we still
have the issue that this is necessary
but not sufficient.
So this condition is necessary but not
sufficient for Q of A to contain the
delta S plus epsilon delta to the minus
EA set.
Okay. So we are going to overcome these
two issues by passing to what is known
as uniform sets. So now we make a new
detour and we are going to study uniform
sets and so uniform sets and
uniformization come up all the time in
studying these type of problems not only
in this proof. So maybe will come up
again later in the course but it is what
we are going to use to overcome these
two issues.
Okay. So,
Okay. So let's start by defining what a
uniform set is. So definition
um okay so maybe before definition
uh let's
let's do some notation so we can write
the definition.
So this is from last time but recall
that I was denoting the delta
to be the delta mesh cubes.
So we split RD into cubes of side length
delta and one of them has a vertex at
the origin.
Okay. So let's define dta of a set x
to be the cubes. This is in any
dimension. So the cubes that are heat by
x.
So these are the q cubes of sin f delta
with heat x.
And let's define a box counting version
of a delta covering number by looking at
this. So uh let's define x delta star to
distinguish it from the delta covering
number
to be the cardality of this set.
How many delta cubes the set hits. And
we discussed last time that up to a
multiplicative constant that could
depend on the ambient dimension but we
don't care. This is really the same as
the delta covering number. So in some
sense they are the same but in order to
work with uniform sets is this version
is better
as we will see.
Okay. So we are counting how many of
these are hit by the set X and we can
compare cubes with balls. And this is
why these two things are comparable as
we discussed last time.
Okay. Now we can give a definition
of uniform sets. So a set x and now our
reference bounded part of space is going
to be the unit ball not the unit ball
the unit cube not the unit ball the unit
cube. So 0 one to the d
is
delta m uniform.
Okay. What is delta is a parameter in
01. So it's a number in 01 and what is m
a natural number
and you should think so I will maybe
come back to this but you should think
that delta is fixed but m is not. So we
fix delta and let m go to infinity
something like this. So we're going to
fix delta and then m will grow. But this
is just a definition.
if
uh the following happens.
So for every jet
between zero and n minus one
and for every
cube of
size delta to the j that intersects x.
We look at how many cubes of the next
generation hit X and the next generation
is delta to the J + one cubes.
So for every
scale delta to the J. So we're going to
look at scales delta to the J. For every
cube of one of these scales that
intersects the set, we look at
How many sorry star how many cubes
of the next generation scale hit X and
this is some number that depends on the
scale J but it doesn't depend on the
particular cube Q.
Okay, let's draw a picture. So,
let's draw a picture to understand
what's going on.
And I guess we actually want delta to be
not just a number in 01 but actually a
diadic number. Okay, this is a
definition. So but in practice want to
get a diagic number. So things are
nested. Okay, so let's draw a picture to
understand what's going on. Suppose that
delta is 1/2
and we are in dimension two.
Okay, so uh we look at okay we have a
set X. Let's say that X hits this three
diadic squares of first level but it
doesn't hit this one. Then R0 will be
three.
There is only one cube of first level
which is the unit cube by the assumption
that Q lives in the unit cube. So the
unit cube has size delta to the zero and
x hits just one of those because it's
contained in the unit cube. Okay. Now we
split each of the surviving squares
again diagically.
And what uniformity means is that the
number in each of these three cubes that
are hit by x is the same for all three
cubes. But the actual cubes could be
different. So for example
X could hit this one, this one, this
one, this one, this one and this one.
So this is a possibility and in this
case R1 will be two.
So every of these three cubes that
survive survived in the first generation
hit two cubes of the second generation.
And what is important is that it is two.
Two and two. The same for all the cubes.
This is what makes it uniform.
Okay. Now we could keep going. So maybe
in the next generation every one of
these will hit just one.
It could be anywhere.
Okay. Then R2 would be one. Okay. Is it
clear what a uniform set is?
Okay. So uh we can see the set x as a
tree where the root is the unit cube.
The vertices of first level. So the
children of the unit cube are the
squares of size 1/2 hitting the set. The
cubes of size
1/2 square. So delta square will be the
children of the
vertices of the first level and so on.
Yes. How does this work when delta isn't
the reciprocal of an integer and you
have this kind of data
>> otherwise things don't line up exactly
it's not the end of the world but in
practice okay in practice we will see
that we are free to pick delta
satisfying certain well at this stage
delta could be anything but yeah we are
going to pick delta by addic
no not just reciprocal of an integer but
reciprocal of a power of two just just
in case yeah otherwise things are not
exactly nested and this picture is not
as neat okay so these numbers are Okay,
we call them so we can view as a tree X
as a tree and for this reason we call
them branching numbers.
Okay, I'm having a very bad Blackboard
management.
So let's show this again for a second.
So in general
if we have a row s delta sorry a delta s
c set it does not need to be a row a row
s c set but if the set is uniform it is.
So this is one big advantage of working
with uniform sets. So let's say so this
will
overcome this issue and also actually
this issue. If the set is uniform then
this condition is not only necessary but
sufficient
for the set to be
yeah so I if we knew that Q of A is
uniform which we don't but okay we we we
have to work a lot to actually make this
work for us but if we have a uniform set
then both of these issues are overcome
so if the set is uniform and it is a
delta SC set it is a row is slightly
worse C set
and if the set satisfies that is large
at every scale then it is a delta SC
set. So both of these issues are
overcome by working with uniform sets.
Okay, let let me state
how it works.
So let okay lema.
So let x
the be delta m uniform
and the delta big delta to the m.
So again at some point we are going to
fix big delta and then this is not a
restriction. This is really not a
restriction because delta will be a
constant. So if delta small delta is not
big delta to the m we sandwich it
between big delta to the m and big delta
to the m plus one and work with those
powers. So this is not a big
restriction.
Then if
the size of X is large,
let's say 1 / C
row to the minus S
for every row. But in fact, we don't
even need every row. Let's say for every
row in one delta
delta to the M. So we only need this to
be true for powers of delta. But the
point is if we know that the size of X
is large at every scale then
X is
delta
S
and not quite C set but uh
well up to some constant that depends on
delta but because delta will be fixed at
some point this is harmless.
So for uniform sets
it is sufficient to be large at all
scales for the set to be a delta s c
set.
Okay. And what was the other issue that
we wanted to overcome? It's it's
oh okay and this one as well.
And if
X so X is a uniform set. If X is a delta
S c set
then X is a row S and again
not quite C but we lose something that
depends on delta. So we are happy
set
for every row between delta and one.
Okay, maybe an exercise for you is to
think about why both of these claims are
false if we don't assume that the city
is uniform. It does have to be uniform.
It's not true in general.
>> Any questions?
>> Yes.
>> I was a little bit confused like if acts
like
in the world that would cover like you
said like one problem is like X is not a
row S something.
>> Yes. Um what if like like if f if x was
like row s that's why does that imply q
x
has
>> okay so what we saw last time is that if
a is a delta s c set if forget about
what is the c then q of a at scale delta
grows.
>> Yeah. Well,
that is true for every delta. So if the
original a was also a
row s c set, then we could apply what we
did last time with row instead of delta
and get this conclusion.
the polomial is fixed. So in the order
of quantifiers, so maybe this is still
on some board. Yeah, you see the
polinomial comes first. The polinomial
is fixed. So it's actually a a minus a a
>> the polinomial doesn't depend on s
doesn't depend on row doesn't depend on
c doesn't depend on anything. It's a
completely universal polinomial. So it's
really a a minus aa or
>> there are other options.
Yeah.
Okay. Um,
okay. So now we are seeing both dilemma
and you sort of see why dilemma will be
helpful. Although one has to be careful
and we will be careful because
in order to
uh overcome this we need a to be a row s
something set. So if a was uniform we
would be happy. But for the second one
we need q of a to be uniform. Not a but
q of a. So to overcome one issue we need
a to be uniform. To overcome the other
issue we need q of a to be uniform. So
we still will have work to do. But okay
let's go step by step and let's prove
this lema.
And the proof of dilemma will also help
us understand and sort of work with
uniform sets.
Okay. So the idea is to do everything
just at the scales powers of delta and
any other scale we can sandwich between
powers of delta because delta is a
constant the sandwiching will only lose
a constant depending on delta. So uh for
the first okay let me just give it
letters A and B.
[Applause]
So for a um well let's consider row some
power of delta
then uh what is so we have to look at
the intersection of a with a ball of
radius row but instead of a ball of
radius row let's use a cube of size row
and again we can always pass between
cubes and balls losing only constants
and this makes sense because we want to
use the assumption that the set is
uniform okay so let's take a 2 in
delta
d delta to the j of
I guess I called it x.
Okay, we fix one of the scales delta to
the j. We fix a cube that intersects the
set and
what is this delta is delta to the m.
So here we are jumping from scale delta
to the j to delta to the m. When we jump
from scale delta to the j to delta to
the j + one,
we have r j + one children.
Each of those children has r to the j +2
children
and so on up to r m minus one
with the star. So you see what I have. I
want you to have the star. Without the
star we this would be true up to
constants.
Okay, so every time we go down one
scale, every cube splits into R
depending on the scale number of
offspring. And the point is it doesn't
matter where the set is with the number
of offspring is fixed but the assumption
that the set is uniform.
Okay. So let's write this as R1
R MUS1 divided by R1
RJ.
What is the numerator?
Sorry, zero. We start at zero.
>> Yes.
>> The delta not covering number of x
because we start at the top and we go
all the way down to the bottom.
So the numerator
is the delta covering number of a.
And what is the denominator?
Sorry, actually we start at J because of
the way we define things. So we stop at
J minus one. So J J J J J J J J J J J J
J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J J
J J J J J J J J J J + one I think now is
correct. Yes denominator just the del
capital delta to the j covering of a
>> exactly this is the
delta to the j covering number I guess
we would start
because we split into r o uh children
then r1 and so on and if we stop here we
stopped at the scale delta to the j big
delta to the j okay and now we use the
assumption in part a the assumption is
that sorry I keep switching around a and
x
the assumption is that this is large so
the fraction is small so the assumption
is that so this is smaller actually a
constant because now I'm going to go
back to standard delta covering numbers
uh this is c
row to the s
delta covering number of n
x sorry
so we are done.
So we took a cube of size
uh delta to the j sorry
delta to the j. So this is row s. So we
took a cube of size delta to the j. So
delta to the j is our row and we show
that the delta covering number of that
is a constant row to the s and the delta
covering number of x.
Okay. So this shows
X is a
delta C set
at scales
one delta
delta to the M.
So it satisfies the condition of being
delta S maybe 01. O of C O of 1* C at
these scales. But then we sandwich
a scale row
in delta 1 between two of these
and we are going to lose some power of
delta
by this sandwiching. We are going to
lose a power of delta in the constant.
So this is why the constant in the claim
depends on delta.
Okay, an exercise is to fill in these
details. But hopefully this convinces
you that this the claim is true.
Any questions?
Okay. And the second part of the lema
say is that if the original set was a
delta s set then it is also a row
slightly
worse c set.
Okay. And um
it is a very similar argument.
Okay. So it is really the same argument.
So we do exactly the same thing again
except that now instead of delta we have
to write row. Okay let's do it again but
it's it's basically the same argument.
Okay. B. So assume
that row is delta to the J. Otherwise we
sandwich before
maybe delta to the J zero.
Okay. And then we have to look at x
intersection. Okay. So now we take a j
uh which is
at most j0 because we have to see what
happens when we intercepted x with cubes
or balls of size larger than row. Now
and let's pick a cube
well of size larger than row.
Then we intersect X with Q. And now we
look at
the row covering number.
But it is exactly the same story as
before. So what is this? This is R J0
blah blah blah R J minus one.
>> Does it start at RJ and goes to RJ 0us
one?
Yes.
Okay. And this is R1
RJ 0 - one.
Sorry. R0 R 0* R0
R J minus one.
And this is
the covering number at scale delta to
the J0
divided by the delta covering number at
scale delta to the J.
And because the set is a
delta s c set this is at most after a
constant because I'm going to now delete
the star
uh this is at most
c
let's write it like row to the
sorry
Okay, let's try to do this correctly. So
what is this? So here we start at the
top and go up to scale delta to the J0
which is row. So this is actually a the
original set
At scale row,
we start at the top. We go down to scale
delta to the j zero.
>> A or f.
>> Sorry, sorry about that. X. I should
just call it a and then but if I call it
a in the statement then I will write x.
So it's not going to work. It's x. There
is just one set which is x.
Okay. and the denominator is a delta
to the j covering number of x. Okay, in
the numerator I just write uh the row
covering number of x without the star
and for the denominator we use a
previous lema. So uh we previously see I
think it's not in any board anymore or
maybe it is yeah it is there we saw that
if we have a delta SC c set then the row
covering number is at least row to the
minus s divided by c. So we use that at
this scale. So this is our R.
Okay. And so
uh so this has size
r equals delta to the j. So we have
shown what we wanted.
So now if we replace
cubes by balls and we interpolate
scales. So we use just powers of delta
we get that
x intersection evol of radius r
row covering number is at most a
constant at most a constant that depends
on delta that comes from the sandwiching
the original constant that is here then
this is actually row to the minus s in
the denominator
r to the minus s in the denominator so
we get r to the X and then the row
covering number of X and that's the
definition of being a row
is
slightly worsey set
questions.
Okay. So we have seen that uniform sets
are much better behaved. We can
well first of all if it is a good set at
scale delta it is a good set at coarser
scales as well and also it's enough to
know that the set is large at all scales
to know that it has this spacing
condition. So how do we find uniform
sets? So this is the content of the next
lema which is simple but extremely
important and has uh lots and lots of
applications all over the place.
in particular for what we are trying to
do.
Okay, let
little delta be big delta to the m
and let x be a subset of 01 to the d.
So we assume nothing about x and what
the lema says is that x contains a dense
between quotes uniform subset.
Okay. Uh so what does what does dense
mean? Well, it means different things in
different settings. So, I'm going to
prove a slightly more general versions.
So, let mu
be a subaditive set function
finitely
set function like like a measure. But
the only aim I assume is that mu of a
plus b is less or equal than mu of a
plus mu of b. nothing nothing else.
And
a very good example to keep in mind
which is one of the examples where this
is useful but not the only one. This is
why I state a more general version is
that mu of B can be the delta covering
number of P.
So this is not a measure because it is
not additive. It is extremely far from
additive but it is sub additive.
Okay. Then uh there exists
y which is contained in x which is
well two things happen. One is that y is
delta m uniform
and the second thing is that y is large
measured by mu.
mu of y
is large compared to what compared to mu
of x. So mu of x could be anything. We
don't know what it is. Mu is something
very general. Okay. And we do lose
something. We lose something like 2
delta
log 1 / big delta 2d sorry 2d is the
ambient dimension
to the m to the minus n.
Okay. Okay, so here the point is that
the scale is delta to the m and here we
have log of 1 / delta to the m. So we
lose something exponential but if delta
is small is a very small exponential.
Maybe let's write it in this equivalent
way. This is delta to the minus
sigma mu of x where sigma is logarithm
of 2d logarithm of 1 / delta.
So it's a double log
divided by log of 1 / delta.
So if we make delta small enough, we can
make sigma arbitrarily close to zero. So
in practice at some point we are going
to choose this delta so that this is
small enough for our purposes and from
that point on delta will be fixed but m
will not so m will go to infinity.
Okay. Uh proof of dilemma
says delta to the minus sigma m. Is it
just delta to the minus sigma
>> plus sigma m? Sorry.
Yeah.
Yeah. So the measure, it doesn't have to
be a measure, but the measure of Y is
not much smaller than the measure of X,
but not much smaller. Okay. Depends on
your point of view. So we do some we do
lo do some exponential thing. But this
sigma is as small as you want by
choosing delta small enough. Yes. So you
said we we fix sigma fixing delta and
then we let go. So does that not
>> Yeah, it blows up. So it's not a Yeah,
it's Yeah, it blows up, but it blows up
like a power but the power is
arbitrarily small. Sorry. Ah, sorry. Bad
day with typos.
Delta to the sigma.
So small delta is big delta to the m. So
big small delta is big delta to the m.
So this okay sorry about this. So this
is delta to the sigma
by definition of sigma
and actually it is delta to the minus
sigma.
Sorry this is delta to the minus sigma
by definition. This is the definition of
sigma. So this is delta to big delta to
the sigma n. Big delta to the sigma n is
small delta to the sigma. So yes as n
goes to infinity delta goes to zero.
This goes to zero but it goes to zero as
a power which is arbitrarily small. So
this is the way which you think about
this
sorry
is it is it correct now.
Okay. Okay. Okay, so the proof is I'm
clear clever pigeon holing starting from
the bottom of the tree. Okay, so the
proof is trim the tree starting from the
bottom.
[Applause]
Okay. So we have the set X and let's
call it XM and we are going to construct
by pigeon holding from the bottom we are
going to construct
a nested sequence of sets
all the way down to X0 and this is going
to be our Y that we are looking for
okay so let's explain I'm going to
explain how to construct X minus one and
then we just continue the same way by
induction ction.
Okay, so we have XM which is X really
and
okay. So,
so we have all the cubes of size delta
to the n minus one that intersect the
set but the branching numbers could be
different. So this could be four, this
could be one, this could be two, two,
and so on. And we want want them all to
be the same. So we are just going to
pigeon hold the sort of the most popular
value and okay because there are too
many values we are going to do it
diadically. So that's basically the
proof. Okay. So let's write it down. Uh
so let
x m n minus one l
be the union
of all the q's
which are squares
of level
n minus one that intersects the original
set
such that the branching number so the
number of descendants of generation
M so Q intersection X delta to the M
star covering number is roughly 2 to the
L.
Okay. And what are the possible values
of L? Well, it could be zero because
there is at least one because the cube
intersects X. There is at least one
descendant. And uh the largest it could
possibly be. So the largest 2 to the L
can be is
delta to the minus D.
So each time we go down one generation
uh we subdivide into relative scale one
over delta and we have D dimensions. So
L ranges from zero to the logarithm
of
well the logarithm of 1 / delta.
Okay. So we pigeon hole. So okay mu is
sub additive. So you see that this is
what we use. So mu of x is this these
sets cover x. So mu of x is at most the
sum over l of mu xm.
So it is x but let's write it as xm. So
it's clear how to continue inductively x
-1 l
and l takes d log one / delta possible
values.
So there exists
some L such that mu of X minus one L has
measure at least maybe let's put a tilda
just in case 1 / the log of 1 / delta
times the measure of X.
Okay. And so what the situation now? Now
we know that the number of offspring is
constant up to a factor of two. So here
there could be seven, here there could
be eight, here there could be five.
Well, in that case we are going to keep
the four with the largest mass which
again we can do by sub additivity of mu.
Okay. So inside
each uh Q
which is a subset of these. So the ones
that survived keep
2 to the L
cubes
exactly 2 to the L. So there are between
2 to the L and 2 to the L plus one. we
give exactly 2 to the L cubes of size
uh delta 2D.
Okay, by doing this we lose another
factor of two. So this is why we have 2d
log of one over delta. Maybe should be
four or something like this. But of
course it doesn't matter. Okay. And
let x n minus one
be the union of all of those.
Okay, so first we do diadic pigeon on
holding because if diatic pigeon holding
things are constant up to a factor of
two then I trim against to make it
exactly constant then I only lose a
factor of two. So by doing this
now uh we have our set xm minus one
and the size sorry the size in terms of
the measure so the measure could be the
delta covering number but it could be
other things. So the measure of x n
minus one is bigger than 1 / 2 the
log one / delta
time the measure of x
and this set is now uniform at the last
scale. So every
every Q
that intersects this new set
has some fixed number. Let's call it R N
minus one descendants.
So this will be two to the L for the L
that we pigeon hold.
Okay. And now we take X minus one and we
keep going up until all the way up to
the top until we get X0. And then we
have to convince ourselves that X0
works.
Okay. So uh one thing is clear every
time we iterate we lose this factor. So
we lose this factor m times and that was
the second part of the claim.
and the second claim is that uh the Z Y
is uniform.
Well, uh every time we do this, it
becomes uniform from one scale to the
next and the only thing that needs to be
observed is that this is preserved. So
when we go up from scale n minus one to
scale n minus2 we don't mess up the
uniformity that we already had and okay
let me do a proof by picture. So
let's say that in the first stage we
chose these two these three
cubes
and each of them has the same number of
descendants.
In the next stage we might remove some
of these
but it doesn't matter. So the ones let's
say that we remove this one in the next
stage. So the ones we keep still have
the uniformity. So we don't destroy the
uniformity as we that we already obtain
in at finer scales when we go to coarser
scales. So it is uniform.
Okay. So
this is the proof that given any set we
can find a dense in this set then up to
delta to the sigma subset which is also
uniform and well by taking mu to be the
delta covering number it is literally
dense in the standard way but sometimes
it's convenient as we will see or maybe
not depending on time uh it is
convenient to take other muses this is
why I stated it in this Any
questions? Again, all of the tools that
we have been discussing today are useful
not just in this proof but all over the
place in projection theory. Yes,
>> I'm not being confused like by this
construction. Yeah, I can believe um uh
on like
uh on level one everything uh the the
degree is the same. But if you do
induction for each sub tree, you can
only guarantee that the degree inside
each sub tree are the same. You cannot
guarantee the degrees between different
sub trees are equal. Right?
>> What do you mean different sub trees?
>> Uh like like first you you divide this
this unit cube into four cube and you
choose the three yellow ones and these
three yellow ones have the same uh same
same number of smaller boxes. But then
then yeah like as my understanding you
kind of do inductive argument for each
of the three yellow boxes.
>> No we start from the bottom. So what is
yeah what is confusing you? You're
thinking about starting from the top
>> and you cannot start from the top
precisely because of what is confusing
you.
>> If we don't I mean it's you cannot make
it work but we start from the bottom.
And this is exactly why we start from
the bottom.
>> Okay. when we go from the bottom to the
top everything every uniformity that we
gain is preserved when we keep iterating
moving in the up direction.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So in the remaining uh 14 minutes
let's try to go back and see how all of
this helps us deal with the issue that
we had.
[Applause]
Maybe let's keep dilemma.
Okay. So, let's go back. So, now we go
back to our goal.
So, a
is a delta s. So this c is delta to the
minus ea but that's not where the issue
lies. On the other hand, if you want to
write the things correctly, you have to
keep track of many parameters and how
they change and I'm not going to be able
to do that today. So let's ignore this.
So we know that Q of A
has large size at scale delta.
Okay. So the first thing we do is uh
we replace so Q of A is AAA minus I AA.
So by using same similar techniques or
basically the same techniques that you
already used in the finite field setting
uh we can get the following conclusion.
There exists one a in a such that a plus
little a grows.
Okay it's not the same epsilon. So every
time I write epsilon is a different
epsilon.
Is that okay? Or do you want me to write
epsilon one or
we we lose a lot. So this epsilon we
lose a lot. Okay. Uh so this is similar
to the final field setting. This uses uh
ras triangular inequality.
I guess the main thing it uses is pluner
rouia and as I explained last time all
of these things are still true for delta
covering numbers.
So it uses plunic
triangle inequality
and I guess maybe some double counting.
So I'm not saying this is trivial but I
hope you did something similar in the
final field setting.
Okay, great.
Okay. Uh second we can assume that a is
uniform. Maybe okay maybe this should be
so first we assume that a is uniform and
sec second we do this maybe this is
better so a is uniform
and okay so we have to choose
at this stage delta small enough
um
so
here okay so here the mu is just the
delta covering
So we apply the uniformization lema.
So we start with the delta SC set. Now
we pass to a uniform subset. The uniform
subset is dense up to a factor delta to
the epsilon not epsilon delta to the
sigma where sigma is as small as I want.
Dense subsets of delta s sets are still
delta s sets by the lema that we saw
before. This is why we can assume this.
Now this constant is going to become
worse by a factor delta to the minus
sigma
because that's the density.
So C gets worse
by delta to the minus sigma but sigma is
arbitrarily small.
So I'm going to ignore it.
So you have to keep track of all of
these parameters but they are not the
real issue. You have to be careful but
they're not the real issue. Okay. Then
this a still satisfies the assumptions
of what we did last time. So this is
really the first step and so we know
that a for the uniform one a a minus a a
grows. So already this grows.
Okay. And
but a is uniform. So in fact uh
because a is uniform by dilemma that we
used about uniformity this is true at
every scale.
So in fact we have this at every scale.
Okay. The third thing that is going to
be important is that a priority we only
have one a in a but in fact once we have
it for one a in a we have it for almost
all a in a. And maybe you have seen this
sort of uh argument in the finite field
setting. But this is true for
almost all
a and a because uh we define a bad to be
the points in a such that the conclusion
we want. So the second step is not true.
it doesn't hold.
And if this set is large, we can apply
the same argument to this set and get a
contradiction.
So a dense subset of a delta S set is a
delta S slightly worse C set. How much
worse the constant is depends on how
dense a body is. So if a body is too
dense we get a contradiction. So it
cannot be too dense. And this means that
very few A's are in are bad. So almost
all are not bad.
Well, the step just two
two a bad
and we get the contradiction.
Okay, the first step is maybe the key
step. So we are going to upgrade the
second step to not just saying that a
plus little a a is large but so what is
a plus little a is pi a of a * a. So we
are going to upgrade this to say that
this is still true true if we pass to a
dense subset of a * a. So first step
if
x is contained in a plus a and it is
dense in the sense that the delta
covering number doesn't okay so at some
point there should be a parameter it
completely ignoring maybe at this step
we want something like it aa square
dense
then if we reject X, we still have
growth
and in fact at all scales or almost all
scales. Maybe instead of epsilon the
grow the growth will be epsilon over two
but there will still be growth.
So okay let me try to explain uh the
first step in the last five minutes. So
this is really as we will see the
absolutely key step. We need to make
this estimate in the second step robust
and they're passing to then subsets and
we will see maybe next time why this is
what we really need to do in order to
conclude what we want. Okay. So suppose
that one is in a and this is just for
notational simplicity.
Okay. So there are two possibilities.
One.
Okay. So we want to show that there
exist an a with this property. One a in
a with this property.
I guess step three should maybe be a
later step. So or maybe we want to apply
it at at many steps. So many steps we
prove that something exists but once
something exists actually almost all
elements in a have this property. Okay
let's say we want to prove that so at
this stage we want to get one little a
in a so that this is true. Okay so maybe
we are lucky and the first thing we
choose and let's call it one works well
if it works it works. Okay so first case
a equals one works.
So it has this property.
Well, if it works, it works. We are
done. So let's assume that one doesn't
work.
What does it mean that a equals 1
doesn't work? It means that there exists
some x in a * a which has size
bigger than delta to the ea square or
something like this times the size of a
time a but the projection is small
okay uh we have to do this for every row
but okay let's let's let's do it one row
at a time and next time I will ex let's
do it for delta next time I will explain
how Why is true for for every delta in
some sense?
Okay, let's assume that for the
particular scale delta there is no there
is no growth.
Well, this reminds you of what?
So there is a theorem that you've seen
before that this should remind you of.
So we are projecting
sorry and a is one actually a is one. So
this is just the sum.
So we are so if if one one is in a
either it is good if it is good we have
proved what we want because something is
good or it's not good. If it's not good
this is what it means by definition of
not being good
bsg. So this is exactly the assumption
to apply value toic hours.
So a has size delta to the minus s.
Here we have a dense subset of the
product set
which has small partial subset. The pi 1
image is small. It doesn't grow. So
these are exactly the assumptions that
we need to apply valuic hours.
Okay. And I ran out of time. So uh so we
are in the middle of the most important
argument. So uh maybe on Tuesday, sorry,
you will see me again. I will start with
step four from the from the top. But
maybe as an exercise you have five days,
you can try to imagine how this will
continue. So at least try to well just
write down what is the outcome of aloxic
hours and try to think how we can use
that to eventually get what we want. At
least this claim then I will explain how
this claim together with uniformization
lema allows us to conclude what we want.