Okay, thank you. Uh thank you again for
doing the work, the reflection and and
trying to engage your mind and and hand
in this activity. Um next coming up is
the propeller case study. our first
session. Erdin is going to moderate it
with uh the actual CEO of Propella, John
Conson. And what we'll do for this,
we're going to have a very interactive
no slides workshop. Um you have all
received the uh the case brief
description of the case study. Hope you
had a chance to look at it. Um and we'll
just set it up in a second.
That's great. Thank you very much.
Can we proceed with the with the case
study? Yeah. Okay. Great. John, thank
you so much for being here. Uh you may
not know this, but the students here
know you already through the case study.
So here is why we're doing it. Let me
just make a few remain. John, uh you can
uh make yourself Yeah, please. Um all
right, folks. So here here's the deal.
Entrepreneurship is neither science nor
art. It is a craft. And in a craft,
learning from mentors, learning from
leaders is essential. This is why we are
doing this is why we are doing case
studies. They're going to be very
interactive. The goal is for you to
express what you think, to argue and
debate. Uh expect cold calls. So, we do
expect you to have read the case studies
before the case presentation. So, be
ready. And the reason we're beginning
with this case study is this. Let's
let's make no mistake about it. the the
the
field of addiction doesn't provide a lot
of hope for us at the moment and I think
that's just the reality of it. Uh we we
cannot yet say that that there are
solutions that are going to be uh
certainly be able to address those
problems. We're in a state of this
perhaps hopeless stasis and and that's
and that's what it is. And so as we were
designing the program together,
one of the things that we were asking is
what can we do to give people hope?
Because entrepreneurship and innovation
begins with hope. And when we learned
about Propeller and what John and his
team are doing, we just said, "Oh my
god, this is this is the way. What a
great case to really bring to life this
the importance of hope." Um that's
number one. And number two, really there
is a lot to learn from this case study
about how technologies get
commercialized, how leaders steward
those technologies. So let's thank you.
Thank you very much.
Um let let's begin Marco. May I please
summarize have ask you to summarize part
A of the case where the background of
John is described in the healthcare
field.
Have you have you read the case?
Okay, that's that's fine. Who who has
read the case? Raise your hand. Yeah,
Sarah, please. Will you will you
summarize uh John John's background? How
he came into the healthcare field
yesterday. So I look you see the best I
can. Uh John is someone who has uh
really started corporate America. Um so
large organizations
where um mobile just it is 3M um
essentially lot going on that company so
computer products sticky notes uh but
also has uh quite the the healthcare uh
arm as well. Um and so looks like how
did this gain the track recorders
through that through that preparation to
really focus in healthcare uh which is
where he he started career
and Billy started subping in solely on
on healthcare uh and developments on it
the part um
that's fair That's that that that that's
all fair. And so the goal is going to be
we we're going to go through a a set of
questions to set up the case and then
John will offer his reflections on your
comments. That's going to be key and
then we'll have a Q&A with everyone in
the group. Now so as you can see John is
coming into this field into a startup
that eventually became Propeller from a
corporate background. Now Mark, if I
could go to you for a second, you are
going into the field of SUD
entrepreneurship from the academic
field, right? You you are a faculty
member, a Rockefeller, you're spinning
out your company. How do you think your
pathways well your pathways are
different from Johnson even though you
are in a sense ending up in a similar
destination, but how do you think how
you think, what the skills you have, how
you think about the world, how is it
different from John's? I think they
probably
actually here here's a
I think they are probably 100%
different. Um I'm sort of coming from
the molecular mechanism aspects of it.
Uh not so much from from any uh any
business uh development side
and I feel like I understand the basics
of what needs to be done but not
probably how to do it.
And I hope I will make progress on that
quickly.
Okay. And so how do you how do you think
about it in your company right now? What
skills do you acquire about bringing
additional team members? What skills do
you need to nurture in yourself as the
entrepreneur leading event? And that's
an important question for all of you.
You're partly you are to meet others so
you can identify additional skill sets.
You're also to bro yourself. How do you
think about it?
Well, I definitely need uh everyone that
is uh focusing on on different aspects
than than just the research itself.
Basically, I will need advisor. I will
need uh probably at some point a CEO
that has experience in in the field
ideally in the field of healthcare and
then maybe even more in the field of SUD
if possible.
Why why would you like a CEO instead of
you being the CEO yourself?
Well, because that's that's not what I
will do best. Uh maybe I can try it but
I don't think it would be efficient for
the company to be fast to be to be yeah
to be moving as quickly as possible.
Okay.
Now um who would like Thank you. Uh who
would like to summarize uh part B of the
case where the technology is described?
please.
Yeah.
Um my name is Tomokco. Nice to meet you.
So um the B is about the the scientist
discovering um
an obs made an obser observation which
came to an idea where it could um
channel into the sorry I'll take my
notes
into the baby suffering from
irregulatory breathing and
um is Dr. P Da he did say it right
Dr.
He really narrowed into the interest
that he discovered and um he found a
niche which was the opioid exposed
babies and um
yeah and there was obviously a need uh
unmet medical need in in the research
that he he has continued and he
developed actually a medical device that
can um that have seemed to give result
in the
experiment. It's it says experimental.
So, I'm guessing it was some kind of uh
clinical trial or something that they
did. They actually seen a positive
effect on the medical device that he
made and then he made the connection
with um John who has then yeah wanted to
make this into the market.
Great. Let me push this a little
further. What does the UI
Oh yeah. I also
wanted to highlight was I done this
really interesting a lot of medical and
scientific advances. Um the point about
serendipity and observations with this
great uh which really actually gave
science into
the health applications um to like
um you know like other famous examples
are you know aloning pencil like an
observation of something like really
crystallizing everything.
That's a great point. Now let me push
again on the technology promoting
in in this book is in general does
technology as
okay
so first we need to describe it in ways
that are simple understandable also
comprehensive. So what does a technology
do?
So
it
Yeah.
Uh so whoa. Uh so basically uh sto
stoastic resonance
um and the idea of using that as a
signal amplifier.
Um
yeah. So, so leveraging that uh
technology uh in combination with uh
some of the discoveries in uh biology
uh in relation to the squid and and what
was observed in in in
um a completely different uh uh area of
expertise and kind of uh connecting
those dots together in order to uh
leverage that in a in a way that can be
used to
uh help
uh treat substance use
uh sufferers. Yeah.
Okay. Good start. Now, let's let's do
this again. Hey, uh if I'm if I'm
pushing this is purely with the goal of
land, there's nothing else going on.
This is this is a goal, right? But put
yourself in the in the shoes of Dr. pay
the P right you've identified this
interesting Panamani you're fascinated
by it you've also been working on it for
a number of years you've been working 15
years so there is something near you
that be care that it goes somewhere and
it is important for you that someone
like John gets interest
you need to find a way to kind of date
in a way John is not a scientist he's
been around technology but we're not a
scientist We need to explain it to him
in a way that can dispense and more
importantly he feels compelled by right
so let's lend describe this to to John
and what John is going to do he will
tell you how Dr. Pedapha presented in
the game because there is a reason he
got interested right and one of those
reasons is Dr. the beta for and how he
described it. So, let's let's Oh, do you
need the mic? Yes. What? No. Yes. Yes. I
I will be using it. I'm sorry. Yeah. No.
So, you go and and then let's go with
you again. Yep. And
sorry about that. Yeah.
Wait. We do actually.
Yeah. Oh, there. Yeah. Yeah.
So let let's let's do it. Let's describe
it the technology in a way that raises
the interest
and is understood.
So this technology it there is um the
signals are very weak and usually it's
too weak for normal uh devices to pick
up. So it's impossible to measure these.
But by utilizing this particular
technology, you can amplify it as Corey
said and put it in a form where it's
very easily detectable.
Um, and that's powerful because you're
putting from impossible into something
that's real. Um, realistic.
Um, boom. Right. Everyone observe. She's
saying
that was impossible before. With this
innovation, it is.
All of a sudden, John is interested,
right? What he needs to know now is that
that impossible thing is also valuable,
right? Do you want to give that a shot?
Right? So, not all possible things are
valuable.
Why don't you give it a go? Yeah.
That was good. Impossible is not
possible.
Okay. Um
uh let's see. Uh
can can you reframe that one more time,
please?
Right. So what Tomoka said, she said,
"Hey,
uh signal amplification of the sky was
impossible before this technology."
And if I'm speaking loudly, it still
doesn't help, right? Because
No, dude. I need the mic. Could could I
use the mic just for uh for media
purpose? So right what what Toma is
saying hey there is this interesting
technology that we've been working on
for a long time and by the way this is
not just in our field this is now a
general phenomenon that physicists are
aware of that biologists are aware of so
it's real and signal amplification of
this kind was impossible before it is
possible now so John is interested huh
something that was impossible is
possible now but he needs to know that
this is valuable as well that there is
value in signal amplification. What do
you say to him?
So there's there's uh this idea of of
stoastic resonance has has been around
um for a really long time. It's it's a
proven technology and it's a it's a it's
a proven way of of amplifying signals
that are otherwise undistinguishable
like um and the noise and uh this is
something we can apply to to many
different problems and uh can capitalize
on on some further investment.
Okay.
Uh do you want to give that a go?
Hi Jeff. There you go.
Yes. So my name is Gifty and I just
wanted to add on that at least in the
case study it mentioned that you know
current um technology so with the
stoastic resonance it was used to like
help with motor functions. So that was
one evidence of why that technology may
work. Um, and then as you referred to
earlier, I forgot the name, but um, it
did mention how um, was it Corey?
Cory.
Cory, yes. With the vibrating insoles.
So, that's all examples as well as the
squid um, you know, reference that was
made. So, that's all evidence that, you
know, there's somewhere, you know, you
can go somewhere with this technology.
Yeah. All right. Uh, so now Melanie,
let's go to you. Thank you. Uh so
Melanie you're now John and
you're speaking with Dr. Peter you
you've heard about this tech
you want to ask questions what questions
do you ask Dr. paid for because right
your mindset is not purely scientific.
You're wondering hey can this become
something commercial.
What are the questions that you ask?
Um sure good morning uh my name is
Melanie Jimmerson. Um I think in a
response to a question I'd asked would
first start with the mindset and the
mindset is that progress is not linear
but it's more of a momentum or continuum
of everything that we're continuing to
work on. Um and so I would ask next is
for this viable idea how could we
continue the continuum of the
progression of the technology that we
have and in what scales? Yeah. So um how
will the technology develop? Right.
How will the tech develop?
Other questions?
Hi, I'm Dr. Ray Denny. It's nice to meet
everyone here. Other questions I would
ask, how reliable is this technology? If
we're going to be administering it to
premature babies, it has to be reliable.
Also, it has to be reproducible.
uh define reliable. Reliable in what
sense?
Reliability when it's detecting the
signals, how likely is it to detect the
correct signal
and how basically how safe is it? Right?
Is it reliable? Is it safe?
Okay.
Um how can it actually be deployed?
What do you mean? So
what do
manufactured? What is it going to look
like that's usable? So even if
that's your job
doesn't know the answer to those.
Oh okay. Okay. So he wouldn't be asking
the question
because if if you as a business person
go to a science person and say hey how
will you take it to market?
That's you're not proving a value.
So I'm asking I'm not asking how you
take it to market. I'm asking what is
the vehicle for this technology to be
actually introduced into the real world.
So like it's so the technology is there
but the the they put it into a bassinet,
right? So I think the question would be
but I mean I'm assuming that this came
to John before the bassinet was fully
developed.
How do you productize it?
How do you productize it? Yeah.
How can the technology be okay? I got
you. That that's fair. How would that
be deployed?
I thank you.
B says
yeah. Uh
well you have this in front.
Um one of my question is how is it
differentiated in particular? You have
vibrating solutions, random noise
generators that are available in a
consumer goods space that have no
regulation associated for them. So what
are the discoveries that have been made
that could differentiate this and apply
this through to warrant the additional
cost and overhead required to make this
into a medical device technology. And
then this leads directly into the
question about intellectual property.
What about this resonance or particular
form of resonance is going to be
optimizable or going to be patentable
such that it's not obvious to anybody
who's been developing bathing suits that
were already in the market at that time
such that there is a moat formed through
intellectual property.
Okay. Right. So now you're introducing
IP and what we need to start thinking
about all of us is John is already
thinking when he is hearing all that
he's thinking who do we need on the
team? We need IP who the right crack the
folks to go that for that
we need manufacturing right so we need
to start thinking about team composition
okay Dr. seems coming to you. Thanks
Mark.
Perfect. He already said my two points
really which were
from a regulatory perspective. What are
the predicate devices that you would be
referencing in filing a 510K
so that the FDA can understand hazards
and efficacy are the only two things the
government I mean are the core
foundational issues and then on the
intellectual property landscape um it's
just vital to spend dozens or hundreds
of hours searching the entire IP
landscape that could be relevant to this
because uh you know the business model
has to hinge on
uh not just excellence but protection.
Yeah. Uh and could I actually put you
very quickly on the spot? You've been in
the shoes of talking about your
innovations at MSG to potential
licensers of that technology. How do you
how did you present those innovations,
sir? What what high level advice do you
have for the folks here as to what's
important? Um
that's that's too big a question. um
because it depends I guess on whether
you're starting from the health care
organization and let's say a consortium
of neonatal intensive care units who
meet regularly and identify unlongfelt
needs and they could be the pulling
function to bring the technology into
existence as opposed to the technology
ology push which is from the research
labs and companies with a cool new thing
and we always said at MGH that the magic
space the serendipitous space is how you
match up tech push with clinical pull
and so that's the highle way that I
would think about it as opposed to just
how you would present it I mean that's
more like hey is there a particular
neo neonatal intensive care unit that's
very very interested in
in certain issues with premature infants
and has all is eager to be the first
pilot site for a clinical trial once we
figure out whether this is a 510K
application because there's strong
predicates or whether it's a PMA or an
IDN
which our friends can explain all of
those pathways are very complex and of
course I'm sorry to keep babbling but
there's the um
the uh the institutional review
committees for
the trials uh for human studies which
this would be the first um if one was
doing a study of the device in a
clinical setting then you've got to have
institutional review board approval and
the IRB is going to say, "Hey, is this
uh FDA approved or not? If not, then
show me that you've done your homework
as far as uh the pathway." So, it gets
complex
and and then to you, Leonardo.
I was just going to say some additional
questions that haven't really been
touched upon. Um, how much does it cost?
What's the market size? Um, are there
already patents in place? And who else
is on board?
I uh Adams
is
on board.
Okay, let's uh go last to Leonardo and
then John had you come take center stage
offer reflections on on the
perspectives. So please
very briefly um one question and then
John I'm sure will uh comment why why we
care about the technology is there a
problem to solve and we will also
discuss and John will present there is
actually no predicate so we have to be a
pioneer in creating everything creating
regulation and negotiating with FDA and
that's really suffering so but why we
care about that and then I'll pass it to
John
yeah John uh
please join us if you here. So I want to
make sure there's uh there is a great
deal of time to interact with you saying
welcome by the way. Thank you so much
for for
um
Dr. Cy you're raising your hand. Just
one other loose topic is the management
of conflict of interest to the extent
that it's invented somewhere by somebody
and you need that person the inventor in
the new in the startup in order to
provide domain expertise in which case
the management of conflict of interest.
If the inventor is a employee of a
provider organization like Rockill or
Mass General, then that's a whole space
that has to have a lot of uh attention
pay to it.
Would would you have a comment for that?
Yes.
And several more. Um so I don't want to
start with that. I'd like to start more
at the beginning and then jump into this
and we'll come back. Is that all right?
So yeah in that case let's let me ask
you John would you offer
some perspectives on the journey that
are not in not in the case study it
perhaps offer more to the students.
Sure. Sure. And in fact I was uh taking
some notes so let me reflect on those.
Um
what came up in early was uh hey what
kind of abilities do you need to really
get a venture going right and abilities
are very important right we hear about
knowledge skills and abilities all
throughout our lives you need to develop
knowledge you need to develop skills and
you need to have abilities and I think
synonymous with skills are traits right
and
starting a venture
whether it's focused on substance use
disorder or something else requires I
believe
first and foremost a trait of
resilience.
Resilience because nothing goes the way
you expect it to go.
There will be setbacks along the way.
Things that you think are slam dunk are
not. You will be surprised
and it's your ability to take a step
back,
learn from that setback and then set a
new more powerful course to succeed. So
resilience is absolutely key to the
success of your venture in this space
and any other startup space. Got it?
Startup. Another trait I'd like to
reflect on is actually
reflected and written about long ago in
a book by a gentleman named Jim Collins
called Good to Great, who did extensive
research on what made companies really
successful over a sustained period of
time.
He concluded among many things that
leadership at the top of a company needs
to be humble but driven.
And I think we've seen countless
examples especially the last few years
where you can say to yourself, "This
person is really driven
but maybe not so humble,
right? This person's really brilliant
and they know it, but perhaps not so
humble. And while they may have great
success, it's the companies that endure
that are most important to us. The
companies that
provide innovation after innovation that
return great stockholder wealth, but
also improve human lives. and the CEOs
and the CEOs in lineage of those
companies
if they're humble and driven typically
provide and deliver on those kinds of
promises. Right? So traits resilience,
humble but driven.
Okay. Uh thanks for letting me get that
one out.
It's all about technology meeting needs.
So we're going to talk about payar for a
second. Right. So he's down at Woods
Hole and he discovers that every time
the table shakes, the squid that he's
doing an experiment on, the axon fires.
And he wonders why why does this axon
fire every time the table shakes? And
the table shakes because it's trying to
maintain a saline temperature bath at a
constant level. And to do that, it stirs
the saline. That saline uh tub is next
to the table. And when it stirs, it
makes the table shake. but just ever so
slightly. And at first, Dr. Pedapar
didn't even realize that the table was
shaking.
So, he couldn't figure it out why. So,
this is an important trait, too.
Collaboration.
What did he do? He didn't sit back and
just say, "Whoa, what could it be?"
He went to go see another Collins,
believe it or not. Only this one happens
to be at MIT.
And he says, "I noticed whenever this
table shakes, this axe on fires. What
the heck is it?" And Jim Collins,
another one says to him, "Oh, it's
stochastic resonance."
And at this time, maybe stochastic
resonance is around 10 years old as a
field of science. It just celebrated its
40th year anniversary in 2021, by the
way. So, it's a 42y old known technology
now.
And Pafar says, "What the heck's that?"
And Pafar is no dummy, right? physics,
undergrad, MD, Duke, UNCC,
had Harvard, right? Practicing
physician, now chair of neurology at the
Dell Medical School. So, he's pretty
bright guy, but he's humble enough to
listen to what Dr. Collins has to say
and he dives in and he starts his
journey of, well, I want to have this
apply to helping babies breathe. Now,
where did he come up from with that
idea? Well, it just so happens back in
the 70s, there were a couple guys at
McGill University who wrote some papers
on mathematical modeling of human
respiration
and Dr. Pedafar through his experience
in looking at babies in the NICU knew
that there were breathing problems
and so he thought, well, if I can make
this work to help babies breathe, that
could be really something. So he did
further computational modeling
and then developed the very first device
and back in 197475
published his first paper with one
neonate that said hey guess what this
stochastic stimulation seems to work now
he didn't have it all sorted out he
didn't know what the amplitude he didn't
know what frequency but again he was
humble he was driven that led him to
work at Harvard
and the V institute where they developed
better prototypes.
They did first investigational device
studies on humans. They expanded the
number of babies that they were looking
at and went from that one and they did
in 2009 a study with 10 preterm infants
and showed, yep, we're actually seeing
improvement in breathing control in
preterm newborns. Fantastic.
All right, so stop there. That's a big
important story about I think Dr. Pafar
does it help and I'm coming back here we
good any follow- on question about early
innovation
so now we'll go so this is the
innovation this is the technology now
there's the next phase right which is
okay from technology to I'll call MVP
minimum viable product and now and and
Dr. pafar turdan's you know explanation
upfront isn't a business person he's not
literally thinking about well what is
the product
right I I I know I've got a concept here
of this pad that baby can lay down on to
improve breathing but what what really
is the product so that's really the
second phase of this development right
and serendipity with the squid love the
word serendipity for me right I just
left running a company for four years
out on the west west coast that happened
to be my was my first experience in
electro stem right for pain management
couldn't get the board to go in the
direction I want CMS had dropped
coverage of our number one device which
was tens to treat low back pain they had
covered it for 20 years and 60% of our
revenue disappeared in a period of 4
months you have 600 employees and when
60% of your revenue goes away in a very
short period of time, you better
scramble. You better be resilient.
So, we did. We got the company. We
stabilized it. We survived. But it was
time for me to move on because I
couldn't get the board to expand into
other areas, other technologies to
address pain.
Fast forward to the end of 2016. My
stepson has an overdose
in our house in the bathroom.
We discover him blue. Luckily, because
he had been going through counseling, we
had Narcan in the house. We revived him.
He's doing great. He's living in
Michigan. Happy that he's alive. A month
later, after I had been working with
Harvard on a microbiome project, they
called me and said, "We got this other
technology we want you to look at. We
don't know how to get it to market. We
can't get any of the big companies
interested. Why not? You've worked at
big companies. Tell us what we're
missing. I go down. I look at it. Within
a day, I tell them why. No company's
going to look at it for a while. They
believe me. About two weeks later,
impressed with what it could do for
opioid exposed babies. Barbara and I, my
incredible spouse partner, agreed this
is what we were supposed to do.
went back to Harvard said I want it. I
want to bring it to market. They said
okay that started the MVP journey. What
is the MVP? Right? Luckily some of the
skills that I had early in my career was
as a marketing analyst.
Right? Okay. What could this become? How
do customers what is the niku? What is
the market size? What is the
application? What's the competition? All
those things that I learned as a
marketing analyst early in my career, I
started applying to this opportunity and
started thinking about
how to bring it to market.
I thought this is going to be easy,
right? I'm going to put together some
slides, PowerPoint slides. I'm going to
get in front of some angel investors.
I'm living in Boston. I'm living in
conquered mass. It's former CEO, 30 plus
years of experience in medical devices.
Harvard technology with MGH, right? And
University of Massachusetts, the three
institutions collaborated on it.
Got a real market need. I got
investigational devices developed. I've
got clinical studies. I've got patents.
I'm going to get $2 million right away
after my first presentation or two.
[Music]
Fail. Fail. Fail. Right. angel
investors. They're great. They're
wonderful, right? But at the end of the
day, they're hobbyists that are looking
to make 40 $50,000 investments, maybe 10
or $20,000, and they want something a
little bit more proven, and they want a
whole lot of your equity up front.
So, somebody told me about how to write
a grant, and I'm like, well, wait, how
do you spell grant? Even though I was a
former CEO, I didn't really know how to
spell grants,
let alone write one.
So, I went on the internet. Oh. Oh,
yeah. There's these things called SBI.
Oh, yeah. I'll write one. No problem.
Spent a couple days, tossed it in. This
will be easy. All the same assumptions I
made with angel investors. I get this
feedback. I don't know. Couple months
later,
it wasn't scored. Wow. That that must
mean this is great. It was so good. They
didn't even score it,
right? No, dummy. Means it was so bad,
right? that nobody even wanted to give
it a second look. They didn't even want
to waste time discussing your grant
application.
Oh man. Okay, angels aren't going
anywhere. I'm not getting any love on
the grants. Oh, start a substance use
disorder challenge, NIH, sponsored by
the National Institute on Drug Abuse. I
think I'll apply for that.
$10,000 award.
Applied. get it and I get the $10,000
and I'm really excited about it. But you
know what the real benefit is sitting
right here in this room.
The benefit was oh you're going to get
to learn how to write a grant. Oh,
super.
And we're going to teach you how to do
it.
And I get on the phone with Elena
and she basically tells me, a former CEO
of a midcap company who developed a 35-y
year career with many of the world's
best companies in medical devices, is
going to teach me how to write a grant.
She lays it on the line. This is going
to be tough.
You're not going to like it. You're
going to do everything I tell you to do.
You're going to do homework. You're
going to submit it. I'm going to
evaluate it. I'm going to critique it.
and you're going to write it again.
And that went on for
six months.
Write, rewrite, write, rewrite, write,
rewrite.
Submit the grant after it.
Wasn't perfect.
Wasn't a really great score, but I got
scored. And I got Naida to step in and
give us our very first grant.
Amazing. This set the foundation.
To date, we've won over $8 million in
non-dilutive awards and grants.
Yeah.
[Applause]
And taking exactly what she told me and
working at it year after year after
year. The last grant I applied to was
scored an 18. And we'll know in a couple
weeks if we've got that grant.
And if you're not familiar with grant
scores, they go from 10 to 90.
Lower is better. Usually 30, you're in
the ballpark to get funded. So getting
an 18 is pretty darn good. Going from
not being scored to 18 is fantastic. So
why do I bring up this important
element, right? Because in order to go
from an idea and a technology and
investigational devices to an MVP
towards commercialization, you need
money,
right?
And there in my opinion, my humble
opinion, there is no better source of
funding for a startup in this space than
the NIH and NIDA specifically.
This is absolutely America's seed fund.
And the support that you receive, and by
the way, I'm not getting paid for this.
Nothing on the side, all right? is
immeasurable
as long as you remember to stay humble
but driven. Right? What does
non-dilutive mean? It means that you're
not picking up the phone every week and
talking to 10 different investors who
are saying, "Why aren't you moving
faster?"
Okay? It means that you have time to
think about how you're going to go to
market. means that you have credibility
when talking to physicians that are
interested in using your product or your
technology. It means that you have
something to show to people struggling
with addiction that there is a promise
that you are working on something that
will help resolve an issue.
That is really what you get. And oh, by
the way, after you get these other
things sorted out,
it's an incredible backdrop to
investors.
It's proof. It's a proof source that you
know what you're doing and that you have
a path forward towards success and
you've been successful in the past and
in all likelihood you'll be successful
in the future. It's a fantastic proof
for source to get grants. by the way
you can't answer these questions
right really really well until you write
a grant because you've got to answer all
these questions when you apply for an
SBI grant all these things that we
talked about what's your price what's
your go to market what what's your IP
right what's your cost of your product
what margins are you targeting how big
is the need
What's the adoption rate? What's going
on with reimbursement? What's going on
with regulatory pathway? You have to
understand all those. And in my opinion,
humble opinion is the best person to
write the grant is the person that's
leading the company. I can't tell you
how many people I call me up over the
last two years, oh, I see you've done
really well with some grants. Who do you
use?
And I go, I write them. No, no, you
don't write them.
You're an NBA from the University of
Colorado.
You don't write them. Come on.
By the way, when I went to Colorado for
my NBA, they used to say, we used to say
it's the best NBA program in the Rocky
Mountains. Try and name another. Okay.
So, um, so yeah, I can't tell you how
important it is to develop that skill in
writing grants
and how valuable it is. It's not just
about securing the funding and the
relationship. It's also what you learn
when you realize, oh, I've got to write
about this
now. I've got to I've got to write about
in innovation. Oh, I've got to write
about significance. Oh, I've got to
write my commercialization plan. I've
got to write about my team. I've got to
write about our facilities.
And you've got to write it in a
convincing way so that you get a low
score. All right, Erden, go. So in the
moment that um I want to ask you about
is
Dr. Pafar approaches you what strikes
your interest? Why are you beginning to
think hey this is not just a great
technology this can be a product and
once more this can be a successful
business.
Um so the quick answer is oh my gosh
you're talking about something that a
baby lays down on and it helps them.
Gee, babies laid down a lot in hospitals
and at home. This could be amazing,
right? It was one of the first
opportunities that I saw in my career
where there was a potential medical to
consumer crossover
that really got me excited. also
the evidence that they had developed the
link between here's the technology and
the explanation of the mechanism of
action for that technology to the
results that they were seeing in
investigational studies. All right. And
to be clear, what we're doing is we're
talking about what stochastic resonance
does at this level because it's not just
generic stoastic resonance. Okay. It's
for in this application at what
frequency, at what amplitude. All right,
we're talking about a randomness in
terms of the up and down movement, which
by the way is less than half the
diameter of a human hair. I brought a
device for you to see it break so you
can feel it for yourself. And you're
talking about a randomness in a
frequency bandwidth, a speed between 30
and 60 hertz. And it randomizes in that
speed and it randomizes in the up and
down movement. And that is the
brilliance of what Dr. Pafar discovered.
It was that stimulation at that level
which actually improved breathing. And
he discovered that yes with it started
with the squid and also he proved it
computationally through mathematics
which I can never do.
Please.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So why did I say um well
some of it had to do with whether or not
I was even really ready to I mean you
know it it it at my age after my career
most people say
time to cash in, join a country club,
play golf, you know, hang out. and um
and I knew that even if I were to secure
some investment right away, it was going
to be a big hardship potentially on my
family. Um so that was a big big element
of it, right? Um the other element
was I didn't feel that the clinical
studies were robust enough to take me to
clearance as fast as I want. By the way,
point of clarification. All right, we
discovered during our journey that it's
not 510K, right?
It's a denovo, right? A denovo is not a
510K. A ven denovo means what? New to
the world. New. So the FDA says we want
all this safety testing, nonclinical and
clinical. And we want efficacy, right?
And we want you to present this to
obvious. And I was feeling like I didn't
even know it was going to be a denovo. I
thought it was going to be a 510K plus
clinical studies is what I thought
initially. Um, by the way, resilience we
applied for denovo in April 2023. We
said they said no. FDA said no because
the clinical study that we used was too
small.
they felt and we knew we were at risk
and they moved the goalpost on
cytotoxicity testing from a qualitative
test to a quantitative test and by the
way there is an ambasset pad in the US
now in any niku that passes the new test
but that didn't matter to them they
wanted us to pass it and that's okay
right um a month after the FDA told us
no in April 2023 they knew another study
was coming out study was published in
Jamma pediatrics 181 newborns and what
this technology does is it reduces as
shown in the JAMA pediatric study which
is what we're submitting with our new
denovo soon to go in is that it reduces
the amount of morphine that is required
to help calm these babies. In fact, it
over a 21-day period, these babies need
44 less fewer doses when they're on our
pad. So that's two a day fewer doses of
morphine to calm them down. That's a
good thing. It reduces their length of
treatment as well. And we're just about
to start analysis on a new study that we
completed at TUS.
There wasn't one baby who started
following birth that was on our pad that
was ever treated or ever required
treatment with morphine.
So a different study than the one that
was just published in Jamma Pediatrics,
which by the way started five years ago.
So those are two principal reasons.
Thanks. Great question.
Please.
Um, one of the things that I noticed in
the case study was, um, kind of the
burden on the hospitals. So, like, you
know, I mean, my my twins were in a
NICU, I experienced firsthand the
craziness that the staff deals with. So
I'm curious, was there any when when you
guys were going to these different
institutions for the clinical studies,
what was kind of the response that you
got from the hub? Was there a lot of,
you know, uh push back with a concern of
uptake? Because that's generally a big
problem. Um, and did did any of the
studies also look at, you know, were was
there decre decreased resources like
were they discharged from the hospital
quicker or like did were any of them?
So everybody got the question. And it
was, you know, basically infants that
are exposed to opioids after birth as
they experience withdrawal, which is
neonatal abstinence syndrome, sometimes
called neonatal opioid withdrawal
syndrome, right? Placed a heavy burden
on the staff at hospitals. So what did
we investigate? What did we find? What
were hospitals saying about the
situation? Well, I'm going to go back to
the very first grant, right? Which is an
SBI phase one. And what does an SBI
phase 1 do? It tells you you need to
tell us two things. You need to tell us
is your technology feasible? Can it be
reproduced? The question over here, can
it be done accurately?
Can you produce a device that's going to
consistently perform the way it needs to
to develop and provide the efficacy that
you think it provides? And the second
part of an SPR phase one is what's the
commercial feasibility?
And the commercial feasibility goes
right to the heart of what
the users of the product babies but in
this case because they can't really talk
about what they need. They do cry really
well though. But there are caregivers at
hospitals could explain to us what the
burden is in caring for these babies and
whether or not our device had promise in
helping them with the burden that they
had. So
during my phase one grant, that's what
$222,000 gave me, the opportunity to do
technical feasibility and commercial
feasibility. And as part of the
commercial feasibility, we did several
things, but I'll just reflect on one
experience. I went to Bay State Medical
Center in central Massachusetts. I spent
a day with the head of the neonatal
intensive care unit and the pediatric
group uh physicians there.
And the day ended with a two-hour
session in a nice room where we talked
and they also did surveys, completed a
survey before we did our talk, etc. And
there I met Dr. Raja Singh.
The feedback was incredible. They told
us that they would love something like
this to help them care for their opioid
exposed babies, which was a big issue to
them. And they explained what the burden
was. And they explained how constantly
they had to hold these babies and how
the morphine doses for some babies was
just burdensome, etc. Which is all great
and good. You get that in the surveys,
right? You you you got that information,
but it was the end in the hallway,
right? That mattered so much to me. Dr.
Sing came up to me and she looked at me
and she said,
"Whatever you want, however I can help,
just let me know."
Fast forward,
we get another grant. We're going to do
the study at Rainbow Baby Children's
Hospital in Cleveland. The head of the
uh NICU leaves for a position at the
NIH. They can't do the study because the
new head of the program can't do it. I
need to find a replacement. Literally,
where am I going to have the study done
that we had gotten basically the
go-ahhead from Naida to to do? I call up
Tus Medical Center because it's in the
back yard here for me.
And no, I call base Bay State Dr. Singh.
She's going to help. Well, she's no
longer here.
Where where'd she go? Oh, she went to
TUS.
Oh, okay. Call toughs. There's Dr.
Singh. Sure, we'll do it.
Relationships, collaboration, right?
Support. Those are the things that, you
know, you just need to stay on top of.
So, long- winded answer, apologize. Um,
in the studies themselves, the JAMAP
pediatrics looked at length of stay. It
looked at time on crib. It looked at
morphine doses, cumulative morphine
doses. On the new study that's going to
be published in the next year coming out
of TUS is going to look at length of
stay, length of treatment, and whether
or not any babies were where their
symptoms were so severe they needed to
be treated with morphine. And as I I
already kind of stole it a little bit. I
know just at a very high level, we
didn't have one baby move on to morphine
treatment at TUS, which was amazing.