Okay. So last time we um we looked at
power series.
So you have a sequence uh am
uh this is a sequence
And then for each
for each x you form the the new series
you form the series
um and the series is where a n * x ^ n
and then you're summing you decide
somewhere to start and then you're
summing to infinitive like that.
So something like this that's a power
series and we looked at a particular
case u where the a ends so example here
is where a n is equal to 1 / n factorial
uh and so we got the function
e of x which is a sum from n =0 to
infinity of x ^ n divided by n
factorial.
And then we
we use this
to we observed that we observed that uh
e is bigger equal to zero
for x bigger equal to zero.
And we also observe that e of uh of zero
is equal to one.
And we defined little e to be e this
function e of one.
And then we defined another function
um uh e to the q where q here is now a
rational number.
Right. And uh it was defined in
particular E of zero was defined to be
equal to one. E of one was def was uh
was just defined to be E right.
And uh then we also we assumed which we
will prove today that e of x plus e uh e
capital e of x + y is equal to e of x *
e of y.
So we assume that
and then we saw and and then we defined
right. So this little e this function
based on the little e in particular e to
some power m if m is an integer
is just e * itself
uh m times
and then we defined um
uh e to a power 1 / n here
to be uh the positive number. This was
defined
to be
a positive number
so that uh alpha is saying so that alpha
raised to the power n is equal to e.
uh and and and we also defined
um e to a negative integer
and this was just to be defined to one /
so we defined e to minus m to 1 / e to
the
so this way we defined uh uh we this
function here the power series was
defined for for all x and we defined
another function little e of q uh on all
rational numbers q right and then
we saw we assume this here we saw that
uh that these two functions so e of x is
equal to e this function here is only
defined on rational numbers so
it's they're equal when uh for at
rational numbers. So we saw that
and then in in the P sets
P set five I think it's for both of them
you will show or maybe it's one for four
and one for five you show that E is
continuous
[Applause]
uh and uh you will also show that that E
is the so it would also Show the
following
that if you have if f and g are two
continuous functions
uh and h so they are defined both of
them f both f and g are defined on the
real numbers.
and you assume that if you restrict them
to the rational numbers then the two
functions are equal.
So if they're both continuous and they
agree on the rational numbers then
actually they must agree everywhere
uh on all
Okay. So in other words,
this one here,
you know, this is a function by P sub5.
It's a function that's continuous on all
of R. It's agree with this function. And
so this is the the only extension of
this function
to be continuous and defined on all of
them.
Okay. So now, but we still needed to
prove
we still needed to prove this
relationship here that we assumed. So
let's try to prove this one here. And
I'll just do a the main case of it. Um
and so we're going to prove so theorem
prove that E of X * Y is equal to E of X
time e to the y
and I I'm going to show this proof
uh in the case
where
where these are non negative numbers
both of them the general cases is once
you have this is the general case is not
very difficult but I won't do the
general
Now how are we going to prove that? So
to prove that we're going to use
another theorem. So the other theorem is
that so we take two suppose you have two
um suppose you take two series of non
each of them are of non- negative
numbers.
So,
so the setup is so again this is going
to go into the proof of that theorem
over there but the setup for this is
is more general.
I take a series A N
and I take another series BN
and I'm assuming that both A
and B and for all N for is are non
negative
so for all
n
so these are series of non- negative
numbers and then I form another series.
Um I will form
a third series
and that third series is going to be
defined from from the two previous
series and and the third series is
called it CN
like this. And now CN here is going to
be the sum
of a i
b
uh n minus i i i = 0 to n.
So this has the effect of that that the
index of this plus the index of that is
always adding up to n. Right? So the sum
of the two indices is is ex is exactly
in right.
Okay. So that's so obviously so note
note that
that the C ends here of course also non-
negative that just sums of non- negative
numbers right?
So this is a new series right of non-
negative numbers.
And then the theorem is so the theorem
is
the theorem is that if
if these series here
this one here and
this one here
uh are convergent.
Then this series here
is also converging.
And and uh we also have that the sum
here that this sum here
that this sum
is just a product of the two sums. So
it's a product of the sum here
like that.
So again we have these two series of
non- negative numbers. From those two
series you form a third series and the
third third series the idea is that the
third series is kind of like a product
of the other two and it's uh the CN in
the third series is given where you take
the sum of the products of the of the
elements in the other two so that the
index is is at n
and then if these the two series you
started with are convergent then this
you know product series is also
convergent and the sum of the product
series is is really the product of the
sum of the other two series. Okay.
Now so that's what we want to prove and
then once we have this we're going to
use it to prove this the term here.
uh and so so now to prove it let me just
first observe that so let me observe
over here that um
right so uh let me make a couple of
definitions and then making an
observation let me start with
with making some definitions
that is useful in the proof.
So
we will I'm going to define s n a
just kind of like we usually do where we
summing here from i = z up to n of a i
right the the superscript is is come
from the series the a series and then
likewise I define uh S and B to be the
sum here
of the B eyes and then I'm defining
uh S and C to be the sum of the C eyes.
Oops. Up to like that.
And so of course you have that we know
that a i, b i and ci
are all non- negative numbers. So this
means that convergence
so convergence
of any of these series
right so convergence say of this one is
the same as saying that these numbers
here are bound right that's by mono
converter so convergence of any of these
series is equivalent
to that
that the corresponding S n a b or c a b
c is uh are bounded.
Okay. So that's just an observation and
again this is the monot convergence of
this is by
Mon.
Okay.
So that's a monotone convergence
theorem. Uh the other thing
uh see I thought of something else I
wanted to to note. Um
right okay so let's try to prove that
so to prove it
let me just
try to
think about it for a second here so if
I'm looking at a1
say a2
plus
up to a n
suppose I'm looking at this here. This
is like this is like SN
A, right?
And I have that SNA and suppose I'm now
looking at the SNB.
This here is the SNP.
Now if you just multiply out the product
of these two right then you would get
and I should have started at zero sorry
let's start at zero because that's what
we do up there like that
okay so now I multiply out and you see
that you're getting a zero
uh b and you're getting then you can
kind of if you try to do it. So, let's
try to multiply this out, but let's do
it in an ordered way. Okay? And when I'm
talking about ordering way, I'm not
talking about just multiplying this one
on that. Uh I mean, you could say that's
very ordered, but it's not it's not uh
it it's not related to what the the C
series. So, I want to just group things
so that they remind us of the C series.
But if I do that, so what I starting
with this
uh is is this multip multiplied by this.
Then I take this one here multiply by
that. So a z b1 right
this here is the only one where this the
index the the subscripts are non-
negative integers. This is the only one
where the sum of the two subscript is
zero. Right? If I'm looking at where the
sum of the two subscript is one, this is
one of them. But there's another one and
that's where I take this
multiply by that. So I sort of group
those together. So a1 b 0.
And now I want to collect the ones. So
those are the only two where the sum of
the subscript is one. Then if I'm
looking at at the when I'm multiplying
out where the sum of the subscript is
two well I could start with this one but
then I have to pick b2 so I take plus a
z b2
then I could take a1 b1 right that's has
also sum of subscript two and the last
one is if I take a2 But then the B have
to be the zero first. Right?
And now I proceed like this. So I'm
grouping it like this.
Okay? Now of course there's going to be
a little bit of an issue. So for a while
everything is you see that this thing
here this here is what we call C0.
This here is C1.
And this here is C2, right? And then we
presumably also get C3.
But then there is a point where uh where
we sort of run into trouble
if we want to really do it like this.
So,
so what we get is that. So when you do
this multiplication what you will see is
so you see like this a z plus a1
a n
what you will see times b 0
b1
up to bn what you'll see that this
pattern here it's continue for a while
and you're getting that this is equal to
c 0 c1 C1 plus C2
up to CN.
CN in the CN, right? This is again where
the sum of these indices could be this
one here multiply by that the sum of the
subscript will be N. Right?
But if you're now looking at the next
one that correspond to CN + one, you're
not getting all of the CN + one because
like one of the CN + one would be like a
to the N +1*
B 0. But you don't have that one here,
right? So what you get is that you're
getting all of these plus something
additional.
Okay. And the additional is because
everything is non negative. The
additional thing is a non- negative
number. Right.
Okay. So what we have established here
is that we have so this here show that s
n c this is here this here is let me
just write like this. This here is sn.
So you see that and this here this here
was SN
this here
this here was S this here was um right
this thing here was SN A and this here
was SNB right so what you have is so
this inequality just tells you that S N
A time S NB is equal to S N C plus
something positive not negative.
So in other words, this number here is
lesser equal to the product of these
two. So this imply that SN c is less or
equal to this here.
But now you see you already have
something because these here was
increasing
right they were increasing because the a
was all non negative so these here are
increasing and they are lesser equal to
right there the series was supposed to
be convergent so you have that sorry so
I'm here I'm using that the sn
a is is monot increasing up to the limit
here,
[Applause]
right? And likewise the SN here monc
increasing up to the limit,
right? So this thing here so this is
smaller than the limit. This is smaller
than the limit of that. So this thing
here is less or equal to the product
of um of these guys,
right? And so you see and that's that's
supposed to be just a real number this
here. So you see that these guys here
are now bounded.
So this means that because they're
monotone it means that that series is
also convergent.
So what we have concluded here is so
what we have concluded here is
that uh that the series uh that this
series here
is convergent
and we have that uh this infinite sum
here
is lesser equal to the product of the
other ones.
Right. This is what what this gave us.
[Applause]
Right. So this is what we have so far.
Okay. Now
we we want to we want to uh right we
want to get the reverse inequality also.
Right. So we want the reverse inequality
of what is over there. So that we can
say that those two things here are
actually equal. Right? Now let's try to
see how do we prove this the reverse of
this inequality. The reverse we proving
by examine more closely what that
product was.
So you see so what is this additional
thing here?
So again,
so we have we're looking at this thing
here.
And what we got is that this here was
equal to
the sum here of
C N. But then we have some additional
terms right and the additional terms is
the thing is that if you start looking
at the additional terms so what are the
additional terms you're getting a a1
bn right that's one where the sum here
is n + one right and then you also get
so this is coming from this uh sorry
that one here multiplied by this you
would also get a a2
b minus 2 you get a a3
b sorry not n minus2 n minus one b3 n
minus2 right etc right
so but all of these here
all of these here and then right so you
get that
And but you don't get again you don't
get the one that is missing here
is a z b n + one. This one is missing,
right? And the other one that is missing
is this one here.
But otherwise you get all of the ones
that was in the CN + one and you don't
get anything more. Right? And so this
path continues.
So like the next term would be like a2
sorry yeah then you get you would also
get something where the sum of the
indices was two that's like a2
bn right but here you would be missing
more right you'll be missing a z bn + 2
you're missing a1 b n + one right but
you don't get anything more Fine. And so
the thing is like when you continue like
this, the last one you get is like when
you're multiplying that by that
and that's a n * bn those here the sum
of the indices is two
two n sorry right it's 2 n but you're
missing a lot now right you only have
one of many many terms right but they
they but it is a term that all appear
and this one would appear in C 2n.
So in this way what you have is that
this here is less than s to the power 2
n c right they are all in there but you
will be missing terms but all terms are
non- negative right so this means that
you have that in quarter right so you
see that now we have now what we have
here is
that we have
what we established before
was the inequality
that uh s n c was less than s n a * s n
b. But what we have now here is that
this thing here, this product is less
than s 2n c.
This one here is squeezed between this
one here and that one here. But both
these here converts to the same. Right?
They both converge to this infinite sum.
Right? So these here converts to the
same. This means that this here the
limit of this here must also be the
same. Right? And so this proof this show
that this here is the reverse
inequality.
So proof
proof over there, right?
Okay. So now so that's
um okay. So this is this is this that if
you take two series and you form the
product
then that also converge if the two
series is non- negative numbers. So let
me just make a corner of this
that of course if you take a series here
uh and it's a I'll just do a trivial cor
but you can see how you can use this
and this is kind of used in proving the
general case. So we we will only yeah I
mean so okay so
so suppose I take two series here
so this is a trivial
corary of it suppose I take two series
here and I know that this one here that
they're both absolutely convergent
If they're both absolutely convergent,
then if you take this series here,
CN C, sorry, CI.
Well, uh, this one here I claim is also
absolute converted. Again,
this this sort of trivial color is is is
the key ingredients in proving a more
general statement that would be used say
to prove this inequality here when x and
y are non negative are not assumed to be
non- negative but I won't get into that
but I just make this observation that
would get this
so I claim that this thing here is also
absolute convergence right so again I'm
not assuming now a sign on these but I
am assuming that they're absolute
convergence
and so if they're absolutely convergent
so prove
so absolutely convergent
convergent.
This just means that the series here,
this one here
and this one here
are convergent,
right? That's what absolute convergence
mean.
But now if you're looking at CI,
the CI says this here is the sum here I
= 0 to N of A I sorry A I
B N minus I
okay
but this means that CI
absolute value here is less than
this thing here
absolute value
like that you can take the absolute
value sign in under the summation sign
so this is less than sum here from i = z
to n and then a i * b n minus i like
that
But now you see that this here is a this
here is the series. This here is the
corresponding
C. So that so you could call you could
now define
uh you could now define
so you start with the sequence AI
and I now define a a new sequence
bi
bar and I do it by just taking the
absolute value like that. So I know that
this new series is convergent. Likewise
I defined bi bar
to be the the BI absolute value
and I know that this is convergent
and then I defined a sequence here
CI
bar which is just the absolute value of
the CIS
and I know that this one here so I know
that
that this here
is converging that's by assumption.
This one here is convergent by
assumption.
And this inequality here proves
that this here that the CI bar is also
convergent because this one here is the
one where you form the products of these
two convergent sequences. So this one
here is also converting. So this here is
also converting
by the
okay anyway there was just an an
observation that we we're getting this
sort of statement out of it.
Okay. Now this is also related. So why
do we have non- negative here right or
why do we talk about absolute
convergence? So this is a simple fact
that if you take a serious if you're
trying to sum infinite numbers right we
now know how to sum infinite numbers. If
you're trying to do it
if the numbers that you're summing are
all non- negative then actually the
ordering doesn't matter. You can check
you you know you can take the fifth
element first and then the seventh and
then the 119 and then come back and take
one. It doesn't matter what order you do
it in.
But if the numbers are not non- negative
then and the and the series is not
absolutely convergent now it suddenly
matters because you could end up taking
all the negative numbers first and then
you get really really far down to you
know to minus towards 9 minus infinity
then you take a few of the positive
elements and then you take more of the
negative and so then you would actually
stay very far down towards minus
infinity
and and you would never be able to come
up again. I mean so so this is like a
basic fact that if you take a series
and the series are of non- negative
numbers then actually the and it's
converging then you can rearrange the
ordering and it will still converge and
it will still converge to the same
number. If you're trying to sum infinite
numbers and they are not non- negative
and they are don't converge absolute uh
and they don't converge absolutely then
the ordering does matter okay and this
is related to why we assuming that all
of these ai bis are non- negative
numbers and okay but we won't get into
this I mean you can read about it it's a
sort of standard fact it's it's
certainly somewhere in the book but it's
not Yeah.
>> Yeah. So I mean so it's related to
it's related to so so
I mean it's a you know again this is not
part of the sort of syllabus but I think
it's a useful thing to keep in mind
because it also sort of explain why
we're doing it in a certain way. Suppose
you take the the alternating harmonic
series, right? Remember that this thing
here, that's a harmonic series.
This here is is divergent,
right? I actually proved I I proved or
at least I outlined in class why this
series here is convergent.
And this is um okay. And it's just again
the idea here is that if you take so you
have something which is called the
alternating series test.
So this is a I'm coming back to your
question just a second but but but but
and this is closely related to that. So
the alternating series test
is that if you take a sequence a n of
non- negative numbers
and a end converts to zero.
Let's say that a n converts to zero
monot in a mono way. Right?
So, so an example here of this would of
course be where a in is one away right
these that's a mono uh sequence right so
if you take a mono sequence like this
but it doesn't need to go very fast to
zero this one does not convert to zero
very fast right but if you have that and
you're now looking at the alternating
series based on
This one here is convergent.
And why is it convergent?
It's convergent because of the following
thing. And this is exactly what I did
you know when I when I try to explain
why this here is convergent
that you're starting somewhere let's say
starting at zero then you're looking at
the first element right if you're
summing here let's say you're summing
from one to infinity. If you're summing
from one, then the first element here,
this here is minus one. This is non
negative. So this is a negative number.
So you're going down. You're starting at
zero. You're going down. Right? The next
element
that will be positive because it's true
here. So it's positive. It will go up.
Right? But it's monot. So you don't go
as much up as you're going down. So
you're going first you're going down
then you're going up but you're going
less up then you're going less down then
you're going less up etc. And that
actually is forcing it to converge.
Okay.
And so now why is this related to your
question about how do you reconcile
these? So you see like if you're looking
at something like this and you now took
all of the you know if you first took
many many of the of the positive
elements and then you know one or two of
the negative and then many of the
positive element again then actually you
could
for this series if you rearrange the
order of the things you're summing in
then you could either get it to diverge
or you could get it to convert to pretty
much anything you want.
Okay. So, so this hopefully explain why
when the series is not non- negative
numbers why you know the ordering really
matters and and again this is related to
very closely related to to this with the
product of things. Why is related?
Because we're getting this, you know,
we're getting this remainder term,
right? We're getting we got something
that was kind of like the remainder and
you that's the remainder that you want
to be small in order to say that things
are converging to the same thing and and
you wouldn't have that necessary
in general unless you assuming that the
terms were not necessary.
Okay, so let's come back to that was
just a little bit of sight
but I hope it makes things a bit more
clear. Let's come back to this theorem
here. How do we prove this? So we're
going to prove it from the theorem that
we did with that if you so we're going
to use this theorem we just proved
which is this theorem here. So we can
use this theorem here to prove that
theorem up there.
So now it's just a matter of identifying
the right series.
So right so we have so this is what we
want to prove.
This is what we want to show. And this
one here, this is the infinite sum i = 0
to infinity
x + y to the power n sorry over uh
uh i
uh
let's call it this sum from n i
like that. That's what what that series
is.
So, and this one here,
that's a sum x n
factorial. And this one here is some
uh y
uh n factorial. Right
now,
so I want So, if I want cn. So the idea
is that if I'm writing CN as X + Y ^ N /
N factorial
suppose I write CN like this and I write
a n
X n / n factorial and I write bn
y
n / n factorial. Right? Suppose I write
I define them like this. I already know
that this here is convergent and that
here is convergent. I by by the way of
course I also know that this here is
convergent
but but I now have
that but I don't have
I haven't proved
so but I claim now that this CN is
really kind of form in this way. Okay.
So let's see. So CN here if I define CN
to be this in here
by the binomial formula. So x + y if you
take this here to the power n
this thing here is the sum here of x i
* y n - i
and then the coefficient is sorry
x i * y to n - y i = 0 to n and the
coefficient is n choose i. That's a
binomial formula.
Okay.
Now what is what is n choose i?
Well, n choose i.
n choose i. This is just n * n - 1 down
to
n - i
+ one. Right? This here gives you n
elements and then divided by i
factorial.
Right?
But you can write this in here as n
factorial. If you do that then you
included too many. So you have to divide
by n minus i
factorial and then of course you still
have the i factorial in the denominator.
So you can write it like that. Okay.
So this means that the CN here our CN
is so we define CN like this X to the
power + Y to ^ N / N factorial
and if we use the binomial formula then
it was equal to that. So this here was
equal to 1 / n factorial sum i = 0 to n
x i y
n minus i and then n choose i like that.
Now I write in this little this little
equation here and so I get that 1 / n
factorial
summing from i = 0 to n and then n
n - i
factorial * i factorial
x to the i * y -
Okay. And now you see that the n
factorials here cancel with the n
factorials. So you're left with i
= 0 to n.
And now I can group it. I can group it.
I can write it as x i / i factorial
* y / n - i
factorial and this is to the power n
minus i like that.
But now you see that this here is
exactly this here is exactly when we
defined
uh a n like this and bn like this. This
here is exactly the sum from i = z to n
of a i
b n minus i.
Right? And so you see that what we have
is that this thing here that so so e of
x + y with our definition of the c's
this was just defined to be equal to
this limit
but but it's also the cn is also given
by the product of these two other series
but this means that it must be the
product of the two
like that.
It's product of the two sums. Infinite
sums
like that, right? But this thing here is
of course just
e x and this is just e y,
right? So this proved it, right?
Okay. And again this here I was just
assuming that the X and Y are non
negative but given what I said also this
colorary it's not very hard to prove the
general case from that
okay so now
um but I won't do that but let's so
let's um let's just talk about a little
bit more
about continuous functions so let me one
more time just remind you about it and
then let me give you a sort of wild
example of
of um
of a function.
Um so so so first let me remind you with
continuous
so continuous right is a really
important concept also in in this class.
So I have a function and it doesn't need
to be defined.
It's defined say on some subset of R
into R
and then we say that uh and then we have
some point X0
in the domain and we say that f here is
continuous
at X0.
If the following hold
if the following holds that for all
epsilon
for all epsilon greater than zero there
exist
delta greater than zero such that
If um x
is in the domain and x - x0
is less than delta then the images
deviate at most by epsilon. Okay. So
this is again what it's say to be
continuous and here unlike the previous
couple of times when I define it here
it's really defined you see it makes
total sense on any subset of R it
doesn't need to be a interval even right
doesn't need to be all of R but it
doesn't need to be an interval
um
yep
now so this is what it means means uh
for a function to be continuous. Let me
give you an example of a sort of
somewhat wild function.
Uh and
so continuous is a very nice property.
It's continuous if it's continuous at
all points. You know, usually continuous
is a nice property to have.
Often it's sort of the minimum bare
minimum. It's often not enough. you
know, you want something more than
continuous,
but but of course other times you you
know,
you may have much less. So here's an
example.
So this is an example. So it's a
function. So it's a function defined on
all of R.
Example of a function
defined
on
all of R
that is
is nowhere continuous
by nowhere continuous I mean that it
that's not a single point where it's
continuous Okay.
And so this is the function f ofx
and the function uh is uh if x here is
uh is a rational point
uh then f of x is sure and if uh if x
here is a irrational point
then I setting it equal to one.
Okay, just a pretty simple function. And
so I claim that this is not continuous
at any point.
And so the thing is that
see if you take any points, let's take a
rational points first.
So suppose here suppose you take a
rational point here. This here is x0 is
rational
then you have that if you are looking at
square root of two we know that this
here is this here is not rational. We
proved that
right. We showed that this here is not
rational. And so in fact by if you take
if you take uh one over sorry
square two divided by n where n
here is sufficiently large then you can
make this thing here very close to zero.
Right? So you could look at and then you
could add this thing here. So you could
look at x0 and you could look at square
root of two over n for n really large.
If n is really large, you can make this
thing here. So this is 2 plus x0,
right? So you can make this really
really close to x0.
This thing here would be irrational
and so the value of the function here
would be one. Okay, let's make this
precise a little bit more precise,
right? And so
let me maybe say just before I make it
more precise. So let let's just draw the
graph here. So we have here x0.
We have here this this here is this
irrational number which which you could
think about but it doesn't need to be
this number. It could be anything that
is irrational. This one here is
irrational. And by making n super large
right this here is super close to x0.
The value of the function here is zero.
The value of the function here
is is one.
Right? And so you see that you have
these points as close to this point here
as you want but the value of the
function is very different. Right? So so
again just to kind of spell it out
um
you know given an epsilon
you see that if epsilon here
If epsilon here was was smaller than one
then you would have that uh f ofx
minus f of x0 this here is uh a rational
point. So this here is this is zero. So
this is just f of x
and if this here is irrational. So if x
here is irrational
then this here is one.
So you would have that you would have
that you can choose this irrational
point. So for any delta
for any delta
we can choose
uh x which is irrational
and so that x - x0
is smaller than delta. But we have that
f of x
here is actually equal to one. And so
this but this difference here was
supposed to be smaller than delta.
That's a that it's not the case. Right?
If I if if epsilon smaller than epsilon
if epsilon is bigger smaller than one
it's definitely not. It's it's one.
Right?
And so similarly
if you take so this was proving so this
showed right. So this proof
this proof
prove that f is discontinuous
at all
uh rational points.
Now let's prove that it's discontinuous
at all irrational points. So so if
x here zero is is irrational
then we have of course that f of x0
is equal to one. But we but but we also
know that arbitrary close. So for any
for any uh delta greater than zero there
exist
there exist a
uh rational point
a rational number
x
uh so that x - X0
is smaller than delta. Right? But now
again we have that f of x minus f of x0.
This thing here is one. This thing here
is zero. So this difference here is one.
And so you couldn't make it strictly
less than one right by having this delta
sufficient small. So this pro sort of
same thing. It proves that the function
is also discontinuous at all
um at all irrational points.
Okay.
Now let's talk a little bit more. Right?
So this is uh okay. So let's talk a
little bit more about some of the
algebraic rules that we we we discussed
last time.
and I wanted to single out two of them.
So,
so we had
so if we had the following if
f and g are continuous functions
and c
is a constant.
Then last time we talked about uh the
following. We talked about that f plus g
the sum of these two functions is also
continuous.
We talked about that if you take a
function and you multiply by constant
this is also continuous.
We talked about
that if you're looking at the product of
these functions
that's also continuous.
The ones we mentioned but we didn't
actually I mean you know these here was
so elementary. This one here I sort of
outline and let's talk about the last
two properties. One is close to what we
had for sequences and that was that if f
here does not vanish is nowhere
vanishing
then one / f here is also continuous.
And the last one which is sort of
different from anything we had for four
sequences is that
um that if you take if you have now a
function so if uh so you have these two
functions f and g but now I'm thinking
about f here as going from say some
subset of r into r
right but it may starts right by into
some set D. This is a subset of R. This
is another subset of R. And then I have
G here goes from this set into R.
Right? It needs to be right. So you need
this here to be defined on the images of
F. If you have that and these two
functions are continuous then if you
form the if you form the composition. So
this is g of f ofx this new function h
here is also continuous.
Okay.
And so I want to in a few remaining
minutes uh I want to talk about uh these
two properties
and I I will start with the last one
because that's somewhat different from
stuff we tal about last time.
I mean for for for uh for sequences
So let's try to prove that this
composition here is continuous.
So proof of five.
So given epsilon
given epsilon right well we know that
the function so you sort of have to
start backwards given epsilon you know
right sorry uh let's before I take given
let me just say that I want to prove it
let's show
that um that h which is a composition is
continuous
at x0. Okay.
And and uh so I want to prove that and
for for for convenience I'm just going
to call the image of x0 under f and
we'll call that y.
Okay.
So now given epsilon
given epsilon bigger than zero.
There uh since
since uh g is continuous
at y zeote
that this is
this is y z. So since G is continuous at
Y Z there exist
at delta let's call it delta G.
So that if y - y0
if this is less than delta g then there
images
sorry on the g
f but on the g.
So then their images g of y
minus g of y0
the images under g is smaller than
epsilon.
Okay.
So this is just because g is continuous
and I'm using that it's continuous at y
z.
Now I kn need to use that f is
continuous.
So now
so now I'm thinking about this delta G
as my epsilon that in F right so from
from delta G
and
the continuity
Okay.
Uh there exist
there exist uh
there exist um delta
of f
such that
if x - x0
is less than delta of f then the images
f ofx
minus f of x0 the images is less than
delta g
right
but now you see now I have this thing
here f ofx this thing here this is f ofx
uh and this thing here
f of x0 was y z right so this is the
same as this
but now you see that so that I have
these two points that they are and where
one of them is y zero and then I have
this other point and their difference is
bounded by delta
g
so I'm in this iteration
So it means that the images of these
two. So this imply that the images of
this thing here under G and this here on
G. So G of F of X
minus G of F
sorry G of Y zero.
This thing here is less than epsilon,
right?
This is just because I that was how
delta G was chosen, right? And you see
that one of them one of these two points
have to be y zero. But that's exactly
what it is over there.
So I have this but you see this thing
here
but but this thing here is just
But you see that f g of f ofx
this is just the composition. So this is
what we call h of x
g
of y 0. Well y z was
defined to be f of x0. Right? So this
thing here is g
of f of x0
but that's just a composition
at x0. So you see what we have now is
that so so therefore we have
that if x - x0
if this thing here is less than this
delta f
then we have
we have this thing here right but this
thing here is h of x
minus h of x0 Z
is less than epsilon.
Right? And so this prove that the
composition of these two function is
continuous. Right? And so again when you
have when you have two function and you
look at the composition, it's really
important to first check
that the second one is defined. So the
second one should be defined
where you end up under the first map.
Right?
So
okay. So now
um
so now let me just say a few words about
the other one
number four.
But that's the number four is closer to
things we had for
for
the sequences. So you so we are now pro
of four.
So what we have is we have this
function.
It's never zero
and we have some x0 in the domain.
And we know that f here is continuous.
We only need it to be continuous at x0.
And then I want to show
that 1 / f ofx is continuous.
And so I'm looking at um so I want to
estimate this difference here
and I want to say that I if I pick an
epsilon then I can pick X as close if if
I pick X to be within delta but delta
sufficiently small of x0 then this
difference here can be smaller than
epsilon.
So now just let me just estimate this
thing here
and so this thing here is just by so now
I just put it on the common denominator.
So I have f of x0 minus f ofx
divided by f of x0
uh f of x
right and now it's sort of the usual
problem but but now we we maybe not so
worried about that usual problem the
usual problem is this s x x0 is fixed so
this is just some number. So that
doesn't really matter too much. This one
here is not fixed, right? But so that's
a usual problem. I mean this is problem
we've seen before. We saw it in three up
there and we saw it in the similar
things for sequences.
But now the thing is that
that since
since uh
f of x0
is not equal to zero
then you can just take so then now you
can first take so we're going to uh
right so now we just going to we we're
going to pick the delta in uh in uh the
delta we want in in two in two steps the
first step is since this here is not
zero then we know that they exist
at delta 1 greater than zero. So that if
x - x0
is smaller than delta 1, then the image
between f of x and f of x0. I can make
that smaller than f of x0.
over two. Right? You see I'm just using
this one here first as my epsilon.
Right? Once I have that, but this here
implies of course that f ofx
see I have f ofx in the denominator
and I want to bound this here from
above. Right? Right. I want to bound it
from above. So I just need to get a
lower bound for f ofx. Right? So f ofx
here.
So I have that f ofx
uh plus
um I can write sorry I can write um
using this I can write f of x0
as uh f of x
minus
uh sorry f of x0
like this minus f ofx
plus f of x right obviously I can write
like that
and so this means that f of x0
taking slabbing absolute value sign on
it this here is less than f of x0
- f ofx
plus f ofx,
right? And so now I can move this one
here over on the other side. So I have
that.
So I have that. So if I move this one
here over on the other side, I get that
f ofx
absolute value is bigger or equal to f
of x0
absolute value minus this difference
here
like that. Right?
But if I make x and x0 delta one close
to each other, then this difference here
is at, you know, it's actually less than
this thing here. So there's still
another half. You see this one here must
be bigger equal to
of f of x0,
right? Because this here takes up
strictly less than half of this thing
here. So there's still another half
left. Okay. And so this give us a lower
bound for this. And now we're out of
time, but this give us a lower bound for
this as long as we make sure that X and
X0 is delta one close. And once you have
then you can just treat this here as a
constant. And so now it's clear that you
then make another choice of of delta
possibly even smaller than the one this
one here. And then for this smallest of
these two numbers then you can now
conclude that this fraction here is
smaller than epsilon. Okay.
Any questions?
>> Yeah. Um, I have a question going back
to what we're talking about.
>> I was a little bit confused because like
we're defining it to be like non
continuous
>> but like by definition of continuity
like if you had if you picked some um
like two x's near each other that were
both rational.
>> Yeah.
>> Like and f of x is both zero then
wouldn't that be continuous?
>> Right. So, so the first of all, let me
say that if you were to picture this
function, right? I mean, of course, it
wouldn't be very easy to picture it, but
but you would sort of if you were to
draw it, right? Then actually, it would
look it wouldn't look like a function
anymore because like you would have it
on all the rational numbers here, it
would be zero. On all the irrational
numbers here, it would be one. So, if
you picture it, it would look like two
lines. But of course it wouldn't be two
lines because it's right but the points
are just so close together that you
couldn't really draw it right. And so
the thing is that but it also means that
if you this picture here illustrate what
you're saying that for if you take here
if you take a rational numbers well all
the rational numbers that is really you
know any rational number whether it's
close or not it will all be zero on
those. So that's not where the problem
with continuity occur. The problem occur
because you also have irrational numbers
close to it and it has to be for all
points close to this that it the value
had to be almost the same. Right? So
it's really for the irrational numbers
that the problem occur with continuity
in a rational numbers and vice versa.
for an irrational number. If you're
looking at continuity around an
irrational number, the problem is not
from other irrational numbers, but it's
from the rational numbers.