thank you everyone for attending the
Rene Salazar speaker series hosted by
latinx at the broad and thank you for
the broad Institute for allowing us to
do this series just a brief introduction
for the latinx community so latinx abroo
has a mission of building Community
among latinx brodies and empowering
members of latinx communities so we host
events regularly today we have also a
movie
viewing and the purpose of the speaker
series is to highlight latinxs and
diverse researchers within and outside
the broad Institute we want to Foster
collaboration and allow ibility and role
models for diverse individuals and we
also want to allow opportunities to
network and promote research from our
community please feel free to post your
questions in the Q&A and they'll be
answered live or you can just put it in
the chat and we can answer the or we can
ask the question as we go now I just
want to give you a brief
introduction of uh our speaker today so
our speaker is Dr Philipa Rio ferer and
is an assistant professor of infectious
diseases and vaccinology at Berkeley
Public Health with a joint appointment
in the molecular and cell biology
Department immunology and molecular Med
medicine Division and for her malaria is
a major symptom and it's a very focal
area of her research such as sleeping
sickness and she combines molecular and
parasytes mosquito development and
Immunology and Neuroscience to ask
questions about the role of circadian
rhythms in the evolution of pathogen
Genesis of parasitic infections so her
Focus will be on circadian rhythms and
providing and how they provide an
advantage to organisms from bacteria to
humans and this will deepen our
understanding of the daily biology of
parasites and it'll enable us to design
effective interventions so take it away
Dr Ria
Ferrera thank you thank you so much
Ricardo and it's an honor to be here and
celebrate with you this wonderful
Community I feel like also the the past
few weeks have been of uncertainty in
science and just kind of uplifting each
other celebrating our scientific
achievements and paying it forward for
the next generation is very important
for me so I'm very grateful to have the
opportunity to share with you our
research on circadian rhythms in
parasitic
diseases we are as Ricardo said based at
out Berkeley and we are mostly focusing
on malaria uh but you will hear a little
bit about sleeping sickness too
so life on Earth is sh shaped by
circadian rhythms and the earth rotation
really creates these very predictable
cycles of light and darkness that shaped
how many different organisms evolved
ways to anticipate this uh environmental
Cycles to regulate our sleep wake cycle
our metabolism our immune response this
is all controlled by our circadian
clock clock disruption itself is quite
detrimental either through genetic uh
disruption or
through um environmental uh input such
as chronic jet lag it leads to higher
incidences of cancer and metabolic
syndrome also half of the genes in our
body are under circadian control and 75%
of clinical trials that tested time of
day treatment showed benefits at
specific times either for example for
lower toxicity of drugs or higher uh
Effectiveness however a lot less is
understood about how the circadian clock
regulates infections in malaria it's
really a striking example and that's
because malaria's main symptom it's its
periodic
fevers we knew these to be a
characteristic of these infection before
we knew it what caused by a parasite for
since the Asian Greece you had descript
of a disease that had fevers that would
come and go at certain times of the day
that now we know are really a
consequence of a synchronous bursting of
parasites out out of our red blood cells
so this is a phenomena that you have
this unicellular plasmodium parasites
coordinated in their Invasion their
replication and then the burst out of
the red blood cells that releases
millions of new parasites and triggers
our immune system to respond with the
fever in different plasmodium species
have the cycle last either 24 48 or 72
hours so all multiple of 24 which is
quite an interesting number when we
think about this circadian clock and so
for the longest time we had assumed that
Paras diseases that had this rhythmic
phenomena were really a consequence of
the host rhythms because most of these
parastic diseases do not have any free
leaving stage but what if parasites had
ciran clocks well this would matter
because it would change how we think
about their biology but potentially
would open possibilities for
interventions so how could we test that
um we can actually leverage a lot the
biology of the host the Maman system is
very well uh understood and amazing
tools have already been developed so if
we focus for example on the clock of the
Mouse as a model organism you can
simplify it by having two key
transcription factors uh activators
clock and Beal uh that are binding to
the promoter of multiple genes and
activate their transcription and amongst
the genes that they transcribed are
their own repressors this is the
families of cryptochromes in Period
whose proteins then translocate back
into the nucleus and hold the
transcription the clock and bile they
activate transcription of multiple other
sets of genes that act on different
Pathways and that's how the core is so
Central to Maman physiology but this
Loop is really intrinsic meaning that it
still
lasts 24 hours even in constant
conditions and that is the definition of
an intrinsic clock so during my post
talk in The Takahashi lab I was able to
leverage these amazing tools that exist
in the Circadian field such as for
example mice that lack uh two of these
repressors the cryptochrome one and two
and these animals now once without
environmental cues in constant Darkness
they lose all their rhythmicity so their
sleep awake Cycles become disrupted
their gene expression and so on and so
we were able to take advantage of these
Mouse model and infect them with
plasmodium parasites we put them in the
in constant Darkness we waited for five
days after we infected them and then we
started collecting blood samples every
four hours to assess uh by RNA
sequencing the parasite transcripton and
that was to really ask the question what
was going on on the parasite rhythms
were the parasite rhythms uh going to be
as rhythmic as they usually are in Wild
type hosts or now in these arhythmic
mutant m Are The rhythms going to be
disrupted and so once we analyzed the
RNA sequencing of the parasite we
realized that as expected in Wild type
animals even in constant Darkness the
parasite biology was highly rhythmic and
you can see here uh in this heat map uh
4,000 genes that are being rhythmically
expressed across the day so expressed
picking once a day and these are uh 80%
of the whole transcriptome of malaria
parasites but interest interestingly
even in these a rythmic hosts there were
still about 3,000 genes that were
showing these rhythmic expression
patterns really letting us to conclude
that the parasites rhythms are intrinsic
to the parasite and not simply a
consequence of the host
clock this refrains how we think about
this infection malaria is transmitted by
a mosquito so this is a three organism
interaction the host the parasite and
the mosquito and each of them have an
intrinsic clock and how we um are now
trying to understand a lot more in
detail how they communicate with one
another but on that original uh
um um discovery about their intrinsic
rhythms we also start testing if these
you know reduction from 80% of the
transcriptome cycling to 60% if that
reduction was exactly as we would
predict from a a non circadian system
and so what we know from other model
organisms of the Circadian uh clock is
that at the populational level if we
were are for example considering a group
of cells all these cells are showing as
an average a daily Rhythm once they are
exposed to these environmental cues
happening in a predictive and rhythmic
pattern however once in constant
conditions because it's an intrinsic
property the Rhythm still persists but
as you can see the amplitude of the
oscillation is increased and that is
because there is a slow
desynchronization amongst the cells that
are um encompassing this
population and here you have that
representation uh experimentally so here
this is an amazing tool one of the
pioneer uh
circadian uh tools that are that have
luciferase let me play it again that
have luciferase fused uh to uh the P one
of the the repressors period proteins or
under his promoe
and you can see once a day Lucifer is um
so light being uh expressed in these
cells and this is a a slice from a
tissue from the hypothalamus the
supermatic nucleus but if you now
dissociate the neurons of these 20,000
urans you dissociate them and you put
them in culture without any any external
stimulus what you can notice if you were
to follow one particular neuron is this
beautiful rhythmic tray
but if you now look at the whole uh
petri dish you can see that there is
some unsynchronized Christmas light
going on right and that you can now also
represent multiple individual neurons
and if you were to to trace a line for
their average you would see this flat
black line so that is what is expected
is that each individual neuron has a
clock but if you don't have any
synchronizing cues they will not
um rhythmically in sync with one another
so we decided to take again malaria uh
infection of this arhythmic mutant
mice and follow what happens later right
we knew that until day seven they were
very bmic but what happens later are
they also going to be uh uh becoming out
of sync and so what you have in this
plot is representing one of the stages
morphologically that will be the ring
stage so the Beautiful one at the top
sorry my cursor didn't seem to work so
the first one at the top of that little
illustration and if you look at 9: a.m
you would see most Almost 100% of the
parasites all in this stage and as day
goes by uh that continues in Wild type
animals but in a rythmic mutant animals
that eventually stops happening and John
Abel from MIT modeled these with us and
uh compared it even to the
desynchronization rate that would be
expected from other uh circadian systems
and it seems that plasmodium is at in
par or if even even slower at
desynchronizing based on his modeling so
that you would have a decline in The
rhythms at the populational level
potentially due to a synchrony between
each individual parasite but what
exactly so that us to conclude that the
host still matters right for some
synchronization but what what would be
those potential cues of the host that
were helping parasites being syn with
one another and there have been two
beautiful stories uh on proposing that
the food and the timing of the host
feeding were the main cues and that is
because when um when they were testing
again the ring stage type of of plotting
when they were monitoring when parasites
were at that ring stage at nighttime
feeding animals or in the opposite uh
forc daytime feeding so swapping the
time that food would be available to
mice you would see a shift of the
parasite timing proposing that the
timing of food intake is defining when
parasites uh rhythms is happening so we
decided to test how important was really
the food timing for uh plasmodium
rhythms and for that we actually were
able to take advantage of a different
feeding regiment which we described it
as spread outfit so we would have um
animals uh access to food through an
automated fether system that was
actually developed uh during my postdoc
by Victoria Costa Rodriguez who's now at
the
NIH and uh what Victoria's system allows
is not only to monitor exactly when
animals are eating but program when they
can have access to food and so we can
then take advantage and have the food be
delivered at um a regular interval
throughout the day abolishing feeding
rhythms and so how we actually uh read
this out is through do Behavior essays
which we call actograms so we can
monitor here on the left side you have
the white bars represented the day light
window and the black bar at the top
represents the dark and you have the
multiple days of recording and in Black
you have the animals activity by
monitoring how much they go to their
running wheel and you can see that M are
nocturnal most of the activity happens
at nighttime and uh with her automated
feathers we can now also man monitor
when the animal is actually taking the
pallet for for eating which is
represented in red which you can see it
also coincides during the the nighttime
but then in the right panel you have the
now the actogram of the spread out
feeding regiment in which um during the
first few days animals are allowed to do
what they want so they still eat and are
active at nighttime but once we impose
the feeding regiment they still choose
to be active during the nighttime but
they have to now to take access and they
are taking now the pallet every 1 hour
and 42 minutes so they eat the same but
the pattern is clearly disrupted which
you can see Quantified on the most right
graphs so once we impose these U and
then we infected them with plasmodium
parasites we went to see what would
happen to parasite
rhythms but not much happened right if
you see on the morphological side
parasite rhythms were still very obvious
uh across um morph morphological
assessment but also at the gene
expression there were still about the
same number of genes cycling in both
these conditions and the overlap was
really massive so very little was
changed on upon the spread out feeding
meaning that the timing of food intake
is not a driver for The rhythms and
potentially is something else that is
being modulated by the timing of food
and not the actual U feeding itself so
it uh this study led us to conclude that
indeed plasmodium has an intrinsic loock
but the molecular mechanism and the host
cues that really help parasites being
sync remains
unknown and plasmodium is not the only
parasite that has an intrinsic clock
actually sleeping sickness uh uh which
is caused by tranos Bru is another
example of a parasite that has uh an
intrinsic clock and this was actually
work that I did early on during my uh
PhD and it is a much simpler system so I
thought it was uh worthwhile um telling
you a little bit about it because this
parasite is extracellular so we can even
culture it in the lab without any host
cells and so that made it quite uh quite
um yeah much easier to assess if it has
rhythms because we could monitor uh the
parasite transcriptome without any host
cues and what we found is that indeed
even without host cells even without
environmental CU changes in constant
condition there were about 10% of the
parasite transcrypt Tom that was rmic
expressed and most of these were
regulating the parasite metabolism as
you can see here in terms of Pathways
and that translates into two rush hours
of metabolic activity for these
parasites when we measure for example
ATP levels in in cells and we tried to
understand a little bit about like why
why uh and what could be the
consequences of this rhythmic biology
and because a lot of the antiparasitic
drugs act on metabolic pathways of
parasites we decided to do amongst uh
different challenges a challenge for
treatment with drugs and so surine is a
drug commonly used in the clinic to
treat these a blood stage um sleeping
sickness uh infection and so we decided
to do a dose response curve but
initiated at four hours apart across the
day and what you can see here is that um
there is of course killing of parasites
uh as you increase the drug
concentration but there are shifts in
these dose response curves um
translating into changes in ic50s were
of about two and a half fold depending
on when you're initiating which you can
see here represented in that um little
fi showing the the automated the
increase the full change so overall that
two different parasites have clocks and
that regulate their biology but why why
would parasites have evolved in
intrinsic clocks is still a big question
and we can speculate multiple advantages
for parasites perhaps it's really to
anticipate the nutrient waves they're
going to need to have uh their
replication for their replication
they're going to need to have essential
um um amino acids we are ultimately
their source for nutrients we eat at a
certain timing that could be important
as an evolutionary pressure could be
about the immune response the last few
years have been quite uh remarkable in
identifying many different immune
regulatory Pathways that are under
cirtin control in terms of uh cells
coming out of the bone marrow at certain
times of the day Migra ation and also
fosic activity of many different um
aspects of immune system and so that
could be an evolutionary pressure for
parasites to be rhythmic could be
matching the biology to the vector time
or of biting the two examples of
parasitic diseases that I mentioned
involve a vector that transmits the
disease if the parasite transmissible
forms were to be around at the time of
biting they would most likely be more
efficient at propagating the
disease many of these hypothesis uh uh
that we have actually different projects
in the lab uh that are Guided by them
but we are also able to think about that
beyond the fundamental aspect of being
quite interesting that perhaps the
existence of intrinsic clocks in
parasites could be useful for
interventions and that is the example of
the treatment time that I just mentioned
to you uh regarding ing um camine as a
proof of principle especially
considering that a lot of the
antiparasitic drugs have short half life
but we can also think about the parasite
clock as potential therapeutic Target
since there is going to be very little
overlap if any to our own clock and so
that could be another source of
opportunity and in our lab we are very
interested in understanding the
interactions between host parasite and
Vector but the the first question we
tackled uh in our lab one once we
started was really whether the parasite
clock modulated malaria transmission and
this was this is the uh the exciting for
me the exciting work we have now uh
finalized that I would like to share
with you so we've been thinking about
malaria transmission we cannot ignore
the mosquito cell glands so malaria uh
starts with a bite of these aniles
mosquitoes usually during nighttime
during that uh bite uh both parasites
and saliva is injected and the saliva of
mosquitoes has this amazing
pharmacological cocktail of proteins
that modulate our own biology it
modulates our coagulation patterns
platelet aggregation there's imuno
modulation and
even modulates the the mosquito host
sticking
Behavior once uh in our skin parasites
quickly make their way to the liver
where they would replicate and progress
to the blood stage where they'll be able
to be uptaken upon the next blood meal
so the salivary glands by harboring
parasites and also the the proteins that
are going to allow for these efficient
blood meal are really key drivers of
malaria transmission so we focused on
these tissue so what we've done was to
had mosquitoes um feed on Infected
animals so they become infected
themselves wait 18 days until the
parasites reach the salivary glands of
mosquitoes and then start collecting
samples every four hours for RNA
sequencing in mosquit that are house in
normal light and dark conditions and in
constant
Darkness once we sequenced the the for
RNA sequencing we were able to assess a
lot of the biological functions of the
mosquito themselves and what we found
was that about half of the salivary
gland gene expression was under
circadian control you can see here these
heat Maps these are about 5,000 genes
that are cycling expressing uh once a
day in both light and dark and constant
Darkness conditions in these
mosquitoes many of the pathways that
were being regulated rhythmically is for
example uh
glycolysis which about um which nine out
of the 11 um genes that encode enzymes
in this pathway which are here all
colorcoded were being co-expressed
usually picking around sunrise and
empowered or inspired by our reviewer
too we also went and looked
for the protein abundance across time
and we saw that some of the proteins in
the glycolysis pathway were also being
timely
regulated later on during the day so
more around Sunset we noticed that there
was this coexpression of a lot of the
blood Mill Associated genes which you
can see here as their profile in Orange
pecking be
before night onset and you can see the
each individual Gene profile very
beautifully rhythmic once a day and I
highlighted also two different genes
that we know are involved in modulating
malaria infection and showing these
beautiful rhythms so these are the pro
the genes en coding the proteins that I
mentioned that have are involved in anti
claing vasod dilation and
anti-inflammation but what about the
parasites parasites Within These
salivary glands have for a long time
been considered
quient and that is um that is also
because in part we couldn't really know
if they were um or they were fully
quiescent or just non-replicative
because the tools were lacking and so
image Bento from Maria mat's lab uh took
the lead to create a themine kyes
parasite that basically now allows for
detecting incorporation of edu analoges
to track DNA synthesis so the parasites
um lack these and so that was one of the
one of the reasons why cell cycle
studying Studies have been Limited inl
modium parasites but now we were able to
create this line and confirmed um that
they do replicate early on which is what
you have represented here on the red
panel you have the circles highlighting
the parasite uh and you see a lot of
little red dots in their nuclei early on
in the mosquito but then once we look in
the salivary glands parasites do not
incorporate uh this edu meaning that
they do not replicate within a 48 hour
window in which we assess uh these uh
parasites so they are really
nonreplicative during the salivary gland
stage but what about their gene
expression so what we find is that even
though they are not undergoing cell
replication they are very actively
transcribing their genes as you can see
here represented many of the genes so
you can see the raw data in Gray and the
Circadian algorithms fitted colors uh
over in red and
yellow so about 20% of parasite
transcriptome is under uh rhythms of
gene expression and that is uh many of
those 20% of genes are
encoding uh genes that are quite
important for parasite uh motility and
transmission and that's for example the
case of circum sporo uh Gene which is
the key Target of the two current
malaria vaccines and you can see their
profile here so we've been thinking
about
then if there are going to be rhythms of
transmission we could think first about
trying to assess um how exactly the
mosquitoes are feeding and uh choosing
that in the lab as as well as in the
wild the mosquitoes choose to
preferentially bite at nighttime and we
also were able to show that those that
actively fed they also are able to
ingest higher uh blood volume when we
monitor hemoglobin levels at nighttime
Additionally the the load of parasites
in the lever so the first organ that
they go and infect is higher if
mosquitoes are allowed to feed during
that nighttime but this is a complicated
and complex phenotype right this could
be because either mosquitoes are
injecting more parasites at night or
whether the parasites are able to reach
or invade the lever more efficiently at
night or whether the host is just more
susceptible to infection at this time
and so to further dissociate these
different um possibilities we went and
studied in vitro and take take U
parasites directly onto aite and we show
again that transmission is also more
efficient at
nighttime and so to further disentangle
the contribution of a parasite clock and
a host clock we started doing a
mismatched infection so taking advantage
of uh
inverted uh inverted cycles of light and
dark we can have either infections from
morning or evening in either match or
mismatched conditions and what we see is
that uh infection is more uh efficient
in a matched situation at nighttime so
ultimately uh suggesting that both the
hose and the parasite clocks impact
infection efficiency and that perhap and
proposing that perhaps there has been
this co-evolution of clocks between
these three organisms to modulate
malaria
transmission so
altoe ciran rhythms of poost parasite
and Vector matter and together they
modulate the malary transmission and
pathogenesis and there are many um
outstanding questions that we are trying
to address uh we are highly interested
in understanding how are parasites
sensing time what are the evolutionary
pressures and host cues that drive their
rythmic
biology how does a mosquito clock impact
infection and of course on the parasite
side what are the parasites clock genes
that regulate their beautifully rythmic
biology these is um an very interesting
aspect of biology because circadian
rhythms have been described in organisms
across the Tree of Life Soo bacteria
fungus plants and animals but the
activators and the repressors are unique
so there's no hology they have been
evolved through conversion Evolution and
so we do not know what would be those
for these early carots protest parasites
but we hypothesize that it's still going
to rely on uh transcription translation
feedback loop because that is actually
conserved across your cariot but this is
still uh very much uh under exploration
so I would like to finish with that
perspective that we do think that the
circadian clock is Central to
pathogenesis and transmission of
circadian diseases s of sorry of
infectious diseases and that disrupting
the clock is likely going to be
disrupting the fitness of these
parasites and potentially can open new
ways for
interventions and I would like to finish
with um a call to action and so just uh
there are of course I've been telling
you all about parasites but there are
amazing work and research being done in
this circadian subfield of infection
showing that there is a lot of time of
day aspects of a bacterial load viral
load depending on the time at which
infection is initiated there's also um a
lot that we don't know and so if you're
interested I think this is quite an open
and exciting new feel but also even if
you're not uh particularly interested in
timing if you can just take something
from this uh conversation is that keep
track of when you're doing experiments
because time matters and finally we
would just like to thank my junior lab
especially Brian perington and rashing
Pascal and in bentu who led most of the
work I share with you today and our
funders thank
you that was very interesting I think
we'll go straight into questions uh but
before we go into questions in the chat
I'm just going to say that um there's
going to be a survey coming around and
the survey is to get your feedback on
the talk so I'll drop that in the chat
but in the meantime we have a question
from Clarissa Schaefer did you test
different plasmodium species could their
circadian rhythms explain why they cause
different lengths of fever
Cycles yeah we have uh so in Mouse
models the most rhythmic plasmodium is
the one we chose and they have this
24hour rhythms but we are actually uh in
the lab trying to to test a little bit
of that like trying to look at different
now human plasmodium species that have
different lenses and trying to
understand a little further why would
that be the case we do not have an
answer quite yet but we are highly
interested in the same type of question
I think it's one of the big questions
why different plasmodium species have it
done differently could it be that they
are just slower at the replication and
they are keeping track of when still
being exposed to the same cues as the
others but just take longer their
replication we don't know the answer
yet second question is uh from an
anonymous attendee really Co cool
findings on food entrainment since the
parasites are more prevalent in tropical
regions do we know if temperature can
also entrain their rhythms one night
night night parasite host infection in
mice considering that humans are dial is
it safe to say it will be day day in
humans yeah these are two two very
interesting comments and uh I do I do
have that preferred same idea of
temperature and that is because of many
different reasons I do think temperature
is in part responsible for the defect
here even on that food timing uh but we
and we have projects testing that also
there has in my sleeping sickness
project that I mentioned briefly I
didn't point that out but that was one
cue that we gave to the parasites in
culture and that worked so there is a
precedent also for temperature to
regulate uh rhythms uh in parasites
which I think it is quite possible that
it happens also to plasmodium in terms
of the the day and night aspect and mice
being nocturnal and humans dial uh that
is I think you could U anticipate that I
think you don't need to think about so
much if we start stop thinking about day
and night and start thinking about
activity and rest of the host I think it
matches very
well
interesting um I had another question um
if you were going to develop a
therapeutic or an intervention for this
how would you implement this into
therapy development this information
well I do think for example there's
could be two ways uh we can think of for
example let's give the example of the
surine treatment that I mentioned for
sleeping sickness right so um the the
treatment to sleeping sickness currently
is actually quite toxic so if we can
think about a time that you don't need
to use such a higher dose and you still
achieve the same um effect on the
parasite that could be useful right so
just defining when to give a drug would
have potential impacts either because
there's less toxicity to it or that you
can achieve better elimination of
parasites because whatever the target of
that drug is is highly expressed at a
certain time during parasite across your
day right so that could be the two very
simple actionable ways we can think
about these uh research having potential
in the intervention easy uh easily but
ultimately longlasting type of future
goal would be if you are able to show
what are the
molecular clocks of parasites and if
these are really Central to their
biology meaning that they allow them to
anticipate aspects of our own biology
instead of Simply responding to our
rhythmic biology but anticipating it
like other organisms have evolved to
anticipate the environmental predictive
cycles of their environment we could
then disrupt those clocks right and not
allow them to anticipate which will be
detrimental for their Fitness if that is
all true then you can start thinking
about having small molecules that also
act on these clocks and disrupt their
ability to anticipate and be less fit to
infect us hopefully tilting the scale to
the host to better control them
uh so we have two more questions um
claer again that was a super interesting
talk one more question if I may do you
have hypothesis on what factors
associated with food uptake influence
the parasitic Rhythm and what about
other physiological modulations such as
inflammation rate or sleep deprivation
did you test different lengths of
circadian Cycles shorter light and
darkness Cycles
um so on the first part so we have why
would food timing shift parasite timing
but it spreading the feeding would not
disrupt
rhythms what we have noticed is that if
you do the spread feeding intake a few
uh and this this is again a lot of the
work we've done it on plasmodium but we
also have done it with Victoria Costa
Rodriguez for um metabolism assessment
of liver right and what we know is that
once you give this spread out feeding
regiment a few for example hormonal
patterns like insulin become a rythmic
but a lot or spread out flat but a lot
of hormonal rhythms still become very
rhythmic with the normal um activity so
meaning that the same profile even if
you're spread it Still Remains the Same
some shift so I think there's going to
be a very
complex
um integration of that timing of feeding
that is happening in the the Maman body
that is not necessarily just about
nutrients right and so we do not know we
are having now a an approach to look in
vitro to try to now test each of these
potential um hormonal rhythms nutrient
rhythms that it's a lot less convoluted
and intricate as it is in v in Vivo but
in terms of like the the second part of
your question could you remind me
Ricardo oops yeah sorry sorry yeah
second part of the question um so do you
did you test different lengths of
circadian Cycles shorter light and
darkness Cycles yes perfect and yes for
that we did
test by using so we tested in
Vivo uh also in our original um story
about this taking advantage of other
circadian mutants that have a longer
period so instead of having their
rhythms be 24 hours they have their
rhythms be 26 hours which actually about
five days in constant Darkness they are
now in opposite phase to the usual time
because they are like waking up think
about it that they would be waking up
later and later two hours a day and so
what we find is that the parasites fully
uh are synchronized to these long period
mutants we have now been doing in the
lab also with short period mutants and
uh and we are wanting to do that also in
vitro so for sure they are very much
plastic in their ability to integrate at
least in a normal range in terms of just
like you mentioned in terms of light and
dark Cycles uh very recent manuscript
from Sierra Reese's lab was testing
these with um environmental changes
instead of uh genetic
changes cool okay so we have another
anonymous attend very interesting talk
were you surprised to find that only 20%
of sport uh sporozoite genes seem to
cycle this seems to be a smaller
proportion than in blood stages or in
other organisms you
described well actually I was not
surprised I was excited because the
reason is that in the blood State
there's also the parasite replication
that is happening right and there is a
lot of the gene transcription profile
that is happening because of a cell
cycle and not necessarily about a
circadian cycle so I was happy to now
see a lot less uh
in being rhythmically regulated in the
parasites in the salivary glands where
they do not
divide 20% it is definitely a lot less
than 80% but it's actually at par for
example of the amount the percent of
genes regulated in the liver so our um
most well studied organ is the liver has
has about 20% of its uh trans cryptone
being rhythmically regulated and it
poses a major effect on our metabolism
right so it really 20% is still quite a
significant portion I probably would say
that uh in our body there's about 50% of
genes being regulated but it's not
necessarily in the same cell it is like
across many different tissues that
anywhere in our body that you would have
about 50 so it's actually around the the
expected
number so uh
sorry so if we don't have any other
questions we can move forward um thank
you again for this talk and I find it
super interesting have you applied it to
other tropical diseases zika virus was
very popular a few years ago um when I
was in the Caribbean so I was wondering
if you like looked at zika virus or if
you looked at any other mosquito born
illnesses uh I did not and I do I do
agree with you that this is quite
interesting and I would imagine that
other Vector born diseases are probably
going to be U having this pretty much
predicted expected time of day
transmission pattern that people have
known not studied we are not looking
into it but I would imagine that you
know and also another interesting thing
is that for example zika is transmitted
by AIS species meaning that is a dial
type of mosquito so I think that would
be quite interesting to look at the
salivary gland uh of these mosquitoes
whether blood meal Associated genes are
now with an inverted uh expression
profile I would predict so uh based on
their uh function and what they are
being regulated to do and I do agree
with you that this could be quite useful
to think about uh other viral infections
there are some studies that had been
done I think in vitro in terms of of
viral load meaning that the ability of
the virus to replicate inside the
mamalian cell that has been shown to be
rhythmic I think that is in many cases
expected right if you know our own um
replication Machinery a lot of the
pathways that the viral will need to
hijack to establish within our cells is
uh dependent on host and if the host
biology is rhythmic there is an expected
link that was observed but it's
definitely not being studied at all in
the more mosquito side of
things super interesting um I think
that's it for now uh if we don't have
any other questions we can uh log off
but thank you once again for your talk
and it was super interesting and it was
really nice to see and and thank you
again for doing this talk in light of
everything that's been happening it's
very encouraging to see thank you thank
you so much I hope you guys continue
these I think it's quite inspiring for a
lot of people