Okay, good afternoon everyone. Uh this
is the final stretch. Uh thank you all
for uh staying with us. I think it's
been a lot of um interesting and
exciting conversations. Um as you have
probably noticed uh throughout the day,
we have actually uh brought the voices
of all relevant stakeholders um in our
latter secures uh accelerator ecosystem.
uh we've had um of course um academic uh
you know leaders uh like Jonathan
Weisson for example who gave an amazing
lecture this morning uh and then um you
know we had uh Jimmy Oligary who gave a
fantastic talk from the patient
perspective uh a cickle cell disease
patient who uh scaled Kilimanjaro so you
know remarkable story and so now we're
hearing from um uh Fiona Marshall uh who
actually represents for us another very
important stakeholder in in this
ecosystem that we're all a part of and
that's of course uh the biioarma uh
component and that will be a theme for
uh our conversation during the panel
discussion that David Miker will lead um
a little later this afternoon. So I
think uh Fiona Marshall needs no
introduction but I will go ahead and
introduce her. She is the president of
the uh biomedical research at Novartis
um the job that's a senior faculty
member once told me is the most coveted
job in Kendall Square. So um uh she
actually there leads uh uh more than
5,000 scientists uh in six research
sites uh dedicated to the discovery of
uh biio medicine across the Novartis
ecosystem and across the entire pipeline
leading uh basically R&D development uh
for Novartis. Uh prior to this uh
position uh Fiona served as senior vice
president and global head of discovery
and early development at Merc and prior
to that she was the founder and uh CSO
of Heptarkus Therapeutics a UK based uh
company that was focused on
structure-based uh drug design. So she
has a rich uh background from which to
draw for all the discussions that we've
been having today. It's really a great
honor to have you here today Fiona. So
thank you very much for coming.
Thanks so much for inviting me Anna and
thanks for everybody being here on a
Friday afternoon. So it's a privilege to
come to the broad and just such such a
wonderful uh uh institute that I've
obviously followed for for many many
years actually since its inception. So
um I'm going to talk to you about some
of the work we've been doing at at
Novartis but particularly tapping into
some of the themes of this meeting uh in
rare disease. Obviously as a company we
work very broadly across uh uh many many
different diseases ranging from some of
the very most common through to uh very
rare diseases. Uh this is really just a
sort of overview of the company. Um so
we have focus in four main therapeutic
areas. Uh cardiovascular renal and
metabolic fall under one therapeutic uh
construct oncology immunology and
neuroscience. Now we don't have a
separate rare diseases unit which some
companies have uh although that changes
in the industry quite a bit but what we
do certainly work in rare diseases but
within these core disease areas uh and
then we do certainly try and combine
expertise uh on our platform
technologies and and share that
expertise and knowledge across the
different disease areas. One of the
fortunate things of working for Novatist
is we do do a lot of different
modalities probably more than any of the
other farmer companies. Uh so as well as
the small molecules and and biologics uh
we do have gene therapy uh XRNA as we
call it which can be many different
types of olgonucleotide therapy uh as
well as gene and and cell therapy and we
are a global company one of the largest
biioarma companies and uh you know
really for us we are trying to deliver
high value medicines uh also to as many
people as possible. So as well as and
and thinking really about uh the the
highest unmet need, we also do a lot of
work in the global health area and I I
was really pleased that we uh won the
award for the the highest access uh to
patients last year. Uh so uh Novatist
medicine's reached 300 million people
around the world and that included over
30 million who were in low to middle
inome countries. So we do try and uh
enable access uh whenever we can.
uh one of the things I'm sure we'll get
to talk about on the panel is sort of
alluded to on the on the final column. I
mean there are a lot of headwinds in
terms of execution uh of uh delivering
new medicines. I would say it is getting
harder. I've worked in the industry a
long time. uh and we are continually
trying to challenge ourselves to improve
R&D productivity and from a research
point of view uh choosing the right
targets and making sure those are the
right targets for the diseases that we
want to treat uh is really the the way
that I think about how to improve
productivity. It's really removing all
those or certainly reducing the numbers
of failures that we have. So this really
summarizes what we're doing in
biomedical research. So uh yes I I am
very lucky to have this job. I I would
agree with that part of it. Um we do
work across these incredibly important
uh and and interesting and challenging
disease areas. Uh so these I have the
disease area heads. Uh we also have a
group called DAX which is supposed to be
sort of any disease area that we think
there could be a breakthrough. And in
fact interestingly that's where we have
our our renal uh portfolio now a growing
one which I am going to tell you a bit
more about. Uh and then a new group
which I've set up uh since joining
Nevada is called DARE which is diseases
of aging and and regenerative medicine
and uh that's thinking still about these
same diseases but in an orthogonal way.
Why is it that aging contributes uh to
so many different diseases and what are
those pathways and we'll probably talk
about nodal biology later but I do think
that aging and certain parts of the
aging process really are key nodes in
diseases of aging that we can target. So
again we work across many different
therap technology platforms and I'm
going to describe some of these in a bit
more detail and particularly the ones
that I think are most relevant to the
rare diseases
space. Hence this slide. Okay. So let's
start with gene therapy. Uh AAV gene
therapy. So uh we were fortunate enough
to be able to bring Zolenma uh AAV9 gene
therapy uh to market. Uh when we
acquired AEXUS and we first started
working on AAV9 of course we did think
it was going to have a lot of
opportunity in many different diseases
and as we already heard from our
previous speaker um you know that hasn't
been as easy as we first hoped. uh one
of it is the of course the im immunity
that some people have to AAV but also
the tropism of those capsids especially
to CNS neurons was actually much poorer
than we first expected so we've put a
lot of effort also into engineering new
capsids both internally but through
additional business development we work
with Voyager who many of you may know uh
and we recently acquired a company Kate
Therapeutics and they very much focused
on uh the
musculardrophies um so really evolving
myotropic hit capsids that can deliver
uh genes to both muscle sceal muscle as
well as cardiac muscle. I'm not going to
say too much more about that but happy
to talk about that in the questions. Uh
one of the modalities I'm going to focus
on today uh is sir. I think this for me
is one of the most uh exciting
modalities uh for the treatment of a
wide range of diseases. I think the next
generation now is not just about
delivering sirna to the liver, but it is
about more targeted delivery to specific
cell types. And we've been doing a lot
of work in that area uh to really try
and uh tie down um different
opportunities across again both rare as
well as common diseases. Now, uh coming
from a structural biology background, um
I still really like small molecules.
Oral small molecules are a drug that you
really can easily deliver to to patients
around the world. But what's fun now is
all of the incredible extra knowledge
that we have from structural biology
through techniques like cryeleron
microscopy, but also now predictions
like alphafold really really allow us to
design chemical compounds that can
change protein function either to
increase or decrease or alter expression
levels or alter protein protein
interactions in very unique and novel
ways that are really allowing us to
target pathways that were not before
possible. And a sort of an extension of
that is also the targeted protein
degradation uh where you can really
essentially knock out a protein by
causing its degradation. And again a pro
a project that I w didn't have time to
talk about today but I'd like to is on
our cickle cell disease where we are
using a degrader of a transcription
factor um that actually converts adult
and fetal hemoglobin and that's now in
clinical trials for cle cell disease.
But again we focused on that as a
modality by thinking about who are the
patients that need this drug. So one of
the considerations on choosing a
modality one is what problem are you
trying to solve but also who needs that
drug and of course all of the patients
we we actually have stickle cell disease
is a part of our global health portfolio
and we think that uh you know treating
those patients with an an oral small
molecule is is the one that will give
the most
access. So going to say a little bit
about what we're doing in the genetics
field because this is another area that
I've grown significantly since joining
um Novatist being a real believer in the
power of human genetics to inform on
target selection not just again for rare
monogenic diseases but also you know
much broader diseases. I mean there
there really I don't think is a disease
that doesn't have a genetic component
and we're still really learning that uh
the more we look and dive into the data.
Uh but one of the areas that we're doing
is really to set set up a new group. Um
some of you may know Jeremy Jenkins.
He's the head of our target ID group.
Within target ID, uh we have a genetics
group. And really the objective here is
to try and find new targets, test out
new hypothesis and interrogate those in
different ways to try and prioritize our
selection uh for drug discovery. We work
very much matrix now across the
organization. So very close interactions
between the research and the development
and our commercial colleagues. We do we
do have to take them uh their view into
account. Unfortunately there are some
rare diseases which uh are too small for
for us to work on. Um but we do work uh
really as as a as a group together
thinking about what is the high patient
unmet need. What what are areas where we
can really add value uh and work on
together. A lot of this comes down to
data. One of the things which is very
exciting now is the quantity of data
that's available in genetics and you
know I I I'm old enough to have been
there around the sequencing of the human
genome all the expectations that we had
in 10 years time everybody was going to
be treated uh with and have all the you
know DNA sequenced well that didn't
happen in 2010 we're now 25 years later
but I do feel that we are really getting
there terms of the amount of data that
allows us to get these incredible uh uh
you associations and genetic
information, but the data is still not
in all the right format and we're still
not very good at asking the right
questions. So, where do we use genetics
now? Actually, it's across many of the
things that we do. And it's not so much
about those monogenic disorders,
although we are working on those, but
it's really about those genes that alter
your risk, either increase or decrease
your risk of uh uh broader diseases that
we're working on. So we're trying to
identify targets uh target validation
from databases and and genetic cohorts.
We're also using it for biomarker
discovery because again I think terms of
clinical trials ideally we want to
really accelerate clinical trials by
having much better biomarker readouts.
Another thing we could pick up on the
panel also use genetics to enrich trial
design. Uh and also use genetics to
really understand about target safety.
uh and there's a number of different
ways in which we're doing that but
overall what I really want to do is try
and shrink that timeline I mean a
timeline that you showed of how long it
takes to get those and those should have
been fast timelines in a in a disease uh
you know like uh musculardrophe our
timelines really need to be short much
shorter half the time I mean not 10
years five years and we need to do
everything we can to make that
happen so again one of the big things
for me is getting all of the data that
we can uh and human genetics data is one
of Of course, single cell data, single
cell profiling data is another getting
all these multimodal data that can come
together is what gives you that
confidence uh to move forward in a
target. I'm not going to go through all
of these different data sources that
we've invested in. They all have
different benefits uh in terms of the
types of patient populations, the sizes
of the data uh sizes of the population
but also uh whether we have access to
health records to exom sequencing data
uh to samples also whether there's an
opportunity to recall the patients when
we make interesting observations and
also whether you can also then trace
back uh the family history is also
incredibly useful. uh and I'm glad to
say that you know there's a lot of
public data and public initiatives and
public private partnerships uh where we
work together particularly with other
farmer companies um on these types of
programs. So again I've got a few slides
keep going back to the same problem. It
is the data is the data in the right
place is it in the right architecture uh
how can we search across different data
sources and compile these? One of the
things we've done is a big effort uh
which we call data 42. It's to construct
a a data lake of all of our clinical
trials data uh over essentially the last
20 to 30 years of Novatis. So we have
huge uh clinical trials database and in
many cases with uh all of the health
records, biomarkers, what trial were the
people in, how did they respond, were
there any safety issues. So this is
incredibly uh helpful for when we go and
try and understand new problems. If a
safety issue comes up, we can see
whether it's happened before. Uh and we
can do our own uh sort of studies
reversing information from clinical
trials back into the research uh
portfolio. But as you know, you know,
those of you, I'm sure everybody here,
what we're looking for are these strong
genetic associations whe and trying to
understand uh whether mutations, what is
their functional consequence uh and
doing a lot of work on that in silico
which is informed by things like
alphafold where you can map mutations
onto a protein and predict it as well as
actually of course doing the wet lab
work which at the end of the day is
something you always do have to do. more
complicated is all of these mutations
that are in the non-coding regions. You
know, what are they doing? How do you
understand their
function? So, it's really about closing
that gap between these genetic
associations and the mechanism. And um
well, this is a really great example
which I haven't sort of put a slide on,
but I probably should have done. Uh SLC
308. So this is a zinc transporter
protein and a G-W was study was
published to say that this was
associated with your risk of getting
type two diabetes but there wasn't it
was literally at that sort of level just
a whole load of genes associated with
type two diabetes working with uh
collaborators in other pharma companies
as well as the hospitals in Pakistan um
100,000 uh people in Pakistan we have
their whole exom sequencing we're able
to look and see were there any people
who had mutations in this protein
And actually within that cohort there
were 15 human knockouts of this and that
ranged from homozygote total knockouts
through to heterrozygot and different
degrees of loss of function. And we then
were able to call those people into the
hospitals and study their glucose levels
as well as do glucose tolerance tests.
Turned out if you had a loss of function
of this protein zinc transporter protein
you had reduced basil glucose levels.
But in the glucose tolerance test, you
were much better at mounting an insulin
response. So this really helped to
validate that initial G-W was study in
humans uh both from the point of view
this could be a good target in diabetes,
but also it's safe. There are human
knockouts, perfectly healthy walking
around. So that really gives us
confidence to go forward in a target
like that and beautiful when you can
actually get this gene dependent
correlation with function which we saw
in this case.
So, I'm now going to give two little uh
snapshots of a few things that we're
doing. First of all, in the neuroscience
area and then in the kidney area in
honor of Anna, I thought that would be a
good one to pick. U so starting off in
in the neuromuscular diseases and I
think the I'm trained in neuroscience.
These are the ones that I think
especially in children are are some of
the most heartbreaking diseases and ones
that really can either be fatal or cause
lifelong um disability. So the disease
I'm just going to uh tell you about is
shakcomar tooth disease uh CMT-1A
disease and this is u actually
relatively common it's one of the most
common uh inherited neuromuscular
disorders uh and it's due to uh not a
mutation but actually a gene duplication
in this protein
PMP22 which is a myelin protein and it's
interesting there are diseases also with
the same protein where you get a loss of
function but either gain of function or
loss of function function results in
abnormal uh myelin and so then you get
uh abnormal axonal con uh impulses
delayed conduction and in these uh
people what happens is uh in early
childhood or adolescence uh these this
is really most important in peripheral
nerves um you get tingling and then uh
you know loss of proper muscular tone
and function uh in arms uh wrists and in
legs so then it causes problems with
walking and and trying to be involved in
sport and the disease does progress uh
over the
lifetime. So one of the ways where given
that this is a gene duplication of
course what you want to do is knock down
the gene but back to normal levels. You
don't want to knock it out completely
and this is much easier to get the
titration of a knockdown uh with an SA
than it would be with a gene therapy. So
this is a technology but we need to
deliver that sirna to the right tissue.
It's not the liver. We need to deliver
it to the motor neurons. Uh and so this
is a company we acquired DTX based in
San Diego. They had developed uh the a
libraries of lipids uh which could be
conjugated to sirna and then those
different lipids would actually be taken
up preferentially into different cell
types and and you could select out the
lipid conjugates for different cell
types but also lipid liver dtargeted.
And we call this the Falcon platform
fatty acid lipid conjugated. Uh an
example here isn't from the CMT-1
program. This is actually for delivering
to the CNS tow proteins. This is for
Alzheimer's disease. And you can see
really nice knockdown of tow right
across different uh neurons in the
brain. So going back to shomar tooth
again further validation. We've got the
genetics which is pretty clear, but
let's just check if silencing PMP22 or
at least knocking it down in a mouse
model of CMT1 will give you the expected
functional benefit that you would be
looking for. This also helps guide what
you want to measure in the clinical
studies. So what you've got here is a
mouse model. It has an overexpression of
PMP22. So pretty similar to the human
disease. Uh has the same sort of
phenotype. It has it from birth. Starts
to develop muscle weakness. Uh and you
can look there. I don't know if this has
a it probably doesn't have a pointer but
anyway you can see um uh that those
sections are through the nerve fibers.
So you've got the wild type big thick
myelin insulation around and then in the
disease a loss of the myelin but also
then axonal loss as well. And then uh
down in the bottom right hand corner. So
that's the treatment with the sa for
PMP22 you get remielination or or
reduction in loss of myelination and
axonal protection. This improves nerve
function uh and it also most importantly
improves locomotive function in this
case in the mice by beam walking or grip
strength. And these same measures all of
these you can use in the clinical
study. So this is the the candidate
molecule that we've designed
EDK060. Uh and so this is an SRA to
PMP22 with a lipid conjugate that
delivers it to neuromuscular tissue. uh
and again this is now taking that exact
molecule into an animal model but now
you've got to put in the human gene. So
this is overexpressing human PMP21 and
you can see exactly pretty much similar
data to what I showed you in the last
experiment. Uh reversal of the uh loss
of myelination axonal loss really nice
again this nice dose dependent dose
titration which is going to be very
important when we go into the clinic. Uh
again dose related improvement in nerve
conduction uh and in the grip strength.
So this is at the point where we
literally are about to go into the
clinic and we'll be measuring all of
these same end
points. Okay. So let's switch now uh to
kidney diseases uh and uhacopan
uh which is a molecule that we've now
brought forward as a drug uh to the
clinic. Fabouta is its uh name. So the
node here if I'll call it that is the
complement pathway. compliment pathway
is I think one of well one of the most
interesting and complicated pathways
really fundamental uh to our immune
system our innate immune system uh 50
different proteins all very carefully
coordinated and in a cascade and of
course this this coordination of all
these proteins a lot can go wrong uh if
you have mutations in these that alter
this carefully coordinated uh process
then you're you are going to have
compliment mediated problems maybe you
don't mount a proper immune response and
you're susceptible to infection or maybe
you have an overactivation off of the
compliment pathway and so a whole range
of genetics associates different
polymorphisms deficiencies in the whole
range of compliment genes in a whole
range of disorders. Now there's multiple
complement pathways but the one we're
most interested in is the alternate
pathway uh known as AP for short uh and
the drug that we've been working on you
can see there works as an inhibitor of
factor B that's part of the C3 convert
so it forms the enzyme that creates the
downstream cascade and ideally I think
in nodes Anna you probably agree you
want to hit up at the top of a pathway
because then you can cover everything
down below it so that's Why we think in
this case hitting factor B is a good
idea rather than going down to the
things at the bottom. And the
alternative pathway genes are associated
with the range of diseases here. Macular
degeneration
uh number of different kidney diseases
uh and and other uh hemolytic
disorders. So just focusing in on what
is the evidence for the alternate
pathway complement pathway in these two
kidney diseases. First disease on the
right this is C3 which stands for
compliment. So probably is related to
the compliment pathway C3 glomealopathy.
Now these patients many of them do have
direct genetics of overactivation of the
compliment system. But some of them have
acquired the disease through auto
antibodies that are activating at the
complement pathway. But basically when
you do a kidney biopsy what you what you
see is a whole load of accumulation of
compliment proteins in the glomeulus.
They basically act to block up the
filter. uh and so you get an
accumulation uh of protein and
proteinura and that triggers then kidney
damage. Another disease which I'll say
more about a bit about later but I just
want to show you again the compliment
here. This is different. It's not driven
by compliment that isn't the the this
the uh driver of the disease from the
genetic point of view. In fact in this
case interestingly the genetics shows
certain complement polymorphisms are
protective in the disease. It turns out
that compliment is downstream of this
disease. Uh the actual cause of it is to
do with it's an autoimmune disease. Um
but then you get compliment activation
that adds to the disease. But
nevertheless, compliment is still the
green accumulating uh in in the
glomeila. Uh and patients have elevated
compliment um proteins especially the
the downstream ones showing compliment
activation. So, LNPO23
uh this is what tacapan was called while
it was still in the lab. Uh this is an
inhibitor very nice inhibitor again
optimized by structure-based design oral
molecule very potent and this is now a a
model in rats. It's a general model of
glomearul and nephritis. What you do is
you actually take renal extra I looked
up this model carefully so I could
understand it before I came to tell you
about it. You take, you know, extracts
of the kidney, inject it into rabbits,
and you get a a polyclonal antibbody
response. When you inject that back in,
of course, those uh antibodies basically
go straight and block up again the
glomerilus cause uh a lot of damage very
similar to those uh you know human
diseases. And so you get protein ura uh
es increasing over time after this anti-
FX1A injection. And what you can see in
the blue lines is this is now treating
with hippacapan really reducing the
protein ura. And what's interesting is
it will actually work whether you give
it be after the antibbody has been
given. So after the disease is ongoing
but it can also be preventative and
prophylactic. Now that's important when
we start to think about when would this
drug work. So normally you'll start in
clinical trials in later stage disease
but those people have already lost a lot
of their kidney function. So ideally you
want to move it into early disease as
quickly as possible and stop people
losing uh their their kidney
function. So now going into the clinical
trial. This is in the C3G
uh and the panel on the left. I won't go
into too much detail but this basically
confirms that C3G is definitely due to
activation of the alternative pathway.
You can distinguish that through EGTA
and EDTA, but also shows that
LMPO23 can really normalize all of these
uh complement fragments uh within the
serum and most importantly then produce
this really nice reduction in proteinura
uh over time actually 45% reduction uh
over this uh 80-day trial.
So then going back to iigan and this is
really the most common form of of
primary glomer rulan nephritis. Now what
happens here is that certain people for
some reason and there is some genetics
here produce galactose deficient
antibodies uh galactose deficient IgA.
So they're not glycosillating those
antibodies properly but the antibodies
are fine. They're fine and you could go
around with that and you wouldn't even
get the disease. But then certain people
who have those some of those people also
have certain aspects of their immune
system. Maybe it's HLA related or
whatever will form auto antibodies to
those uh glactose deficient uh IGAs. Now
you've got a horrible complex of the
glactose deficient AGA with now IGG big
complexes in your blood again blocking
up your kidney filtration system uh
causing a lot of kidney damage. Now you
get compliment coming in and so then the
compliment is adding to those complexes
causing more inflammatory mediators to
come in and really causing a lot of
damage within the kidney. So if you can
block there's different stages here. You
could go for a B cell therapy to try and
stop those auto antibodies. Um but you
could also try and stop the compliment
uh as also really another way of
delaying the progression of the disease.
uh and you can see here again in the
phase two study uh a really nice uh
impact on uh protein ura uh and also
really completely blocking the these
these compliment this is the terminal
part of the compliment pathway in these
patients. So finish up with this slide.
It can happen. We can get drugs for rare
diseases uh all the way through to
market. Uh and we we're really pleased
that we actually this year uh only a few
weeks ago got the first approval for uh
fabala as it's now called uh as an oral
treatment for C3G. uh and also uh we we
also previously got approval for I GAN
uh in the US and now of course we're
trying to uh roll this out around the
world but make sure these patients are
also getting diagnosed especially as
early as possible because uh a lot of
kidney disease can continue uh before
you actually get the proper diagnosis.
So getting that that urine test done uh
on a routine basis is is really
important.
Okay. Thank you. Thank you.
That was amazing. Uh, thank you, Fiona.
Um, questions for Fiona before we maybe
we in the background we can put the
chairs out. Thanks, Katie. Um, any
questions for
Fiona? Uh, if no one else is asking a
question, I will ask a question while
we're putting the chairs up. Um, so I
think this, you know, thank you for
being a kidney example, but I think it
is like a very recent success. Um and I
think it it really speaks to the fact
that you know we've been talking about
all day today about the idea of you know
uh well-defined causal biology which of
course often based on genetics as you
said is a way to understand mechanisms
and some of our colleagues here brought
wonderful examples from all kinds of
different fields and diseases but here's
an example in which you actually it sort
of plays out right like you understand
maybe a more genetically defined more
rare entity like C3G but then actually
interestingly This is the story that I
wanted to understand better from a
development perspective so we can all
sort of understand from you how that
works. How is it that it was approved in
IgA nephropathy before C3G and how did
you manage the development of the drug
from this rare more defined entity into
something that's more common? Clearly it
had to do with your preclinical
development path but I'm curious if you
can say more about it. Obviously the uh
we were doing both in parallel in fact
because we knew that there was already
that strong complement biology. So it
made sense to go and and you know one of
the things we actually are doing in
farmer now is we used to just do one
disease at a time and then if it worked
in that disease then we do the next then
we do the next well we don't have time
to do that now um you know and so we try
and do everything in parallel which is
more risky but if it works then you've
got you know all of those indications
right from the beginning. So uh we did
start both uh at the same time but you
know Ian is a more common disease uh and
so uh it was easier then it becomes
easier to recruit the patients and uh so
you know and then you know then then
you're still having the discussion with
the regulators on what are the end
points uh as you know you got proteinura
are you going to get approval just on
that um is there going to be any effect
on renal function through GFR but of
course that's a very long trial in these
disease they are slowly progressing
diseases as well so you know that's
another consideration but you know
luckily and I think it makes total sense
because we know that proteinura is a
direct measure of renal function so we
did get approval based on that fabulous
oh uh Raj you have a question you can
ask while we're assembling our is that
okay assemble our panel so I'll ask uh
Wendy and John and David to come up if
you have a question you need to get
please do casual we're trying to be very
Okay, easy going here.
Thanks for the great talk. Um, I was
wondering your opinion about whether or
not academic labs should engage in like
the drug discovery development process.
Here, you know, we're we're good at
target discovery for rare disease and,
you know, we publish the paper, but if
it doesn't immediately catch fire, then,
you know, we start to think about, you
know, should we pursue finding the
therapy? And I don't know if you think
that's insurmountable. Uh, no, I don't
think it is insurmountable. And I mean I
have seen where that has been done you
know reasonably success well not
reasonably where drugs have come to
market just from academic institutes
that has happened uh particularly in the
cancer area actually. So and I think in
some of the modalities are getting
easier for academic labs to do. I mean I
I would argue an SA is probably easier
than trying to do all the chemistry and
toxicology and and all of that. So it it
is doable but of course you need the
funds from somewhere and you need to
have the right people brought in with
the right knowledge. Uh but uh it
certainly is doable. Yes.
Do you Yeah, you can ask a question.
You're popular. So yeah, one more
question. Yeah, go for it. Yeah. Hi. Um
you mentioned that one of the
applications of human genetic data could
be um better trial design. Yes. Um could
you perhaps elaborate on that also like
in the context of rare diseases? How
could human genetic data
Yeah. So I mean we we as I say now we
know with all the the G-W was studies we
know that people with particular um you
know mutations or polymorphisms may be
better responders to drugs or not. Uh so
it making a decision about which genes
you're going to actually have sequenced
as you enroll patients. Now you can
either do it where every it's everyone
comes in the trial but then you
afterwards work out what all the
different genetics are or you can select
and of course in the in the case of the
um the rarer diseases let's say
Huntington's disease is another disease
we're working on at the moment I mean we
want to understand you know what the
number of uh repeats exactly what their
status is from a genetic point of view
because that actually alters the rate of
progression of the disease as well. So
it is very important to understand the
status and uh you know even when we have
a drug that could alter the you know
isn't is mutation independent if you
like it's still very important to to
capture that information and then see
separately how patients with different
mutations uh will progress. Thank you.
Thank you.