okay so this concludes our today's event
um I'm really excited uh about all the
talks that we have heard and you know
this is the third year of um uh our
Symposium the broad um machine learning
BR J Discovery Symposium and today we
actually I just learned that we have
around 220 uh inperson attendees and 900
online attendees which is really
exciting to all of us um and this you
know the success of our event is um is
uh it's impossible without your
attendance and presence so really want
to thank everyone who um came today and
I also want to thank all the you know
speakers um who gave the wonderful talks
today um you know the talks went across
different topics from you know small
molecules from proteins and what have a
diverse Community uh people from diverse
Community we have um from uh drug
industry from Academia we also have
people from background from you know
machine learning or Ai and those who
came from you know Med cam who are more
uh familiar with uh the problem uh and
AI people are more uh excited about the
methodology and I really feel that you
know our event uh and our the goal of
this event is to try to you know con
build connections uh to have a venue
that can help people from you know
different backgrounds to mingle and to
really exchange you know thoughts so
that we you know know hopefully to you
know work on things together so yeah I
besides um the wonderful our wonderful
speakers I also want to thank our
sponsors wushi fiser B AI tandem Ai and
selfa for their um uh for the uh
generous support and also want to thank
uh the organizing committee and advisory
committee for you know this planning
took uh a year and uh there are a lot of
people working behind the scene I really
espe especially want to give a big shout
out to Erica who's not in the room she's
outside who been you know um underhood
you know making um planning all the
logistics and you know providing the
food um you know getting the food and
it's really uh a lot of work and really
really appreciate her uh effort and also
want to thank the AV team uh who it's
also behind the scene uh although we
knock at the door often but I actually
work on you know do some AV sometimes
and know it's really hard like things
just break you know that just this is to
me this is the biggest touring award
prize that you if you can solve the a
problem you you deserve the big prize um
so but I really want to thank today's
event went really smoothly and um really
thank for a team for their big support
and also want to thank the BR Institute
for provide providing us this uh space
with the new stage and uh you know they
renovated um the auditorium uh earlier
this year and have um much better you
know lighting and um and making everyone
more comfortable here so with that I
would like to uh conclude today and
we'll have our Network and reception
outside feel free to you know uh step
out and you know enjoy the posters enjoy
your um fellow colleagues and enjoy um
the rest of the day thank you very much