I'm so delighted to be here with you
guys today not only am I a native
houstonian but I went to high school one
mile away from here at Westchester High
School those of you that are younger
might remember uh Stratford High School
I was actually in the first class that
graduated from Stratford High School um
and then Westchester closed and now it's
all one big High School area so maybe
some of your kids go to Stratford um my
dad was a professor at the University of
Houston so I remember the University of
Houston sign uh I was a professor at the
University of Texas for a few years and
about seven years ago I moved to Boston
part-time I live in Austin part-time uh
and I run this research group at MIT
called cyber security at MIT Sloan I
have to tell you that I've had a very um
colorful career I guess not only as a
professor but also as a practitioner
I've been a CIO I've been a consultant
I'm started my career as a systems
analyst I was very techy and then when I
did my doctoral work I moved into the
behavioral side of Technology how we use
people uh in our organizations and how
we marry people's skills with technology
skills and that translated really well
into this role in cyber security uh when
Professor madnick maybe some of you know
Stu madnick when you were at MIT still
there uh he's a Meritus which means in
his world he he doesn't go play golf he
just does his research so instead of 80
to 90 hours a week he does research 40
hours a week and uh and we work with him
he is our faculty adviser so uh when Stu
asked me to come on and be the executive
director of cams um I told him sure but
I didn't know anything about cyber I
know about it that's where I spent my
career and he's like oh don't worry
we'll teach you the Cyber stuff and it's
so got I drank the Kool-Aid it was so
fascinating for me I've started up my
own research um which I'm going to
report to you today and uh um I'm also
the executive director so I keep the
trains running I make sure we um have
money to run our research and we hire
the right people and all of the
operational things that have to happen
so today what we're going to talk about
is cyber
resilience so let me just start with a
little audience participation so raise
your hand if you are in a cyber security
role in your company anybody here a
cyber person couple people okay awesome
don't worry I'm not putting you on the
spot I just kind of want to get a sense
of who you are um any of you ever
received a fishing email I expect 100%
here okay so you all have a little
experience with uh you can hear my Texas
accent yall have a little experience
with cyber security okay um is your
company make you take has your company
make you make you take a training class
in cyber security almost all of you and
I assume most of those are either an
annual check the box requirement or
maybe when you started your company it
was a um orientation kind of of program
okay all right so I don't have to tell
you that cyber security is a big concern
you know this already you've seen the
headlines you probably remember while we
were all pandemic Facebook was was
breached 90 million people's information
was poured out on the internet we all
got really nervous that our information
maybe our kids information was out there
but if your words with friends player
Zinga was breach if you've ever stated a
Marriott your your information was
probably collected in this um breach in
2020 if you drive a Honda or you drink
Jack Daniels you might be interested to
know that they were victims of Ransom
weere you might remember Twitter being
hacked uh back in uh while we were all
pandemic this was 2020 they took over
some famous people's account and they
said if you'll give us a mill $1,000 in
Bitcoin we'll give you $2,000 in Bitcoin
and when you say why would you do that
well we're rich and we know you're
struggling and we want to help you and
you'd be surprised how much money they
made so solar winds was another hack uh
that really threw a a wrench into the
way we thought about cyber security
because it came through our supply chain
it was supply chain hack the Federal
Trade Commission uh uh had this article
about log 4J a new type of attack that
hit our logging systems all of our
computers do what they do because they
are logs that keep track of what it's
doing and that's the system that was hit
there the point here isn't each one of
these headlines the point here is all
the headlines we're probably immune to
so many of these different headlines at
this point because cyber is such a um a
pervasive risk that all of our
businesses take on and we spend tons of
money trying to manage our cyber
security even in this case the uh uh
right before this one the US Department
of Homeland Security had a hack if they
can't keep themselves secure what chance
do we have so uh Stu madnick published
this article uh earlier this year at uh
Wall Street Journal saying you know if
companies are so focused on cyber
security why do we see the number of
data breaches still rising and that is
the question we spend so much money
trying to manage our cyber security
trying to prevent the bad guys from
getting into our system
and yet we still see all of these
breaches and we still see all of this
damage and we still see all of this risk
so the good guys are getting good are
good we're the good guys I hope I hope
you're all the good guys we're the good
guys we get we're good but the bad guys
continue to get better faster than us
they are very Innovative they are very
organized you don't have to actually be
a programmer to be a bad guy all you
have to do is be a business person with
bad morals you go to the dark web you
can buy all the software you need you
can even get a help desk to tell you how
to launch the attack you want to launch
it's not that the that that they some
some bad guys are technical I'm not
saying they're not but you don't have to
be that so it's really easy to be a bad
don't go do this but it's really easy to
be a bad
guy the incidents are increasing in
sophistication and in frequency and
frankly AI promises to speed this up
that's the bad news AI promises to make
this even worse because the bad guys can
now imitate the good guys they can do
things like deep fakes they can pretend
to be your boss and ask you to send
money someplace and you wouldn't even
know that it wasn't really your boss
that's asking for the money our families
and our our organizations large and
small are all inadequately prepared we
don't even know where where it's coming
from we don't know what the next bad um
attack Vector is going to be and it's
impossible to be 100% protected and yet
we keep throwing money at protection we
keep saying we need to up our um
identity and access management we need
to do more penetration testing we need
to find new defenses to put in place to
keep the bad guys
out then and the true fact here is
recovery once you've had a breach I
nobody has to answer this question but
anybody experience a
breach yeah it's pretty costly it it
brings your company down it could hurt
your reputation it could have a
financial impact it could hurt your
operations it could destroy your
reputation I mean the recovery is very
costly if it's even possible we see many
organizations particularly small and
medium Enterprises struggle to recover
from a cyber incident cyber security
today is more than stealing credit card
information it's more than just trying
to get your customer information it's
really about making money for the bad
guys malware disrupting your business
through things like ransomware or maybe
using you and your business to get to
your customers businesses that's supply
chain it might even be about nation
states trying to steal your IP and
particularly in this world in Houston
with all of the energy
and and oil and gas and Innovative
things going on here many of the cyber
attacks that would be facing you be
facing would potentially be uh IP nation
states trying to get at your uh your IP
so that's where we come in my group is
called cams cyber security at MIT Sloan
we focus on the managerial
organizational strategic governance the
business side of cyber security Now
Technologies on our name we MIT we are
we're technical my backg is computer
science and Applied Mathematics um my
colleagues are computer scientists but
we really focus on the managerial issues
that are uh that that we face and we
like to look at the really tough
questions in cyber security leadership
we're funded by a Consortium model so
companies like yours join our Consortium
you can see some of the companies here
uh and uh and the money that we raise
through our Consortium is what funds our
research so not only do we do we try to
answer the most difficult questions but
we're very action oriented our goal is
to produce actionable insights that
management that companies particularly
our our Consortium companies can use so
that they can be more cyber
resilient so the main the main idea I
want to leave you with today is we need
new mechanisms to be cyber resilient and
our research looks at these four areas
um our beag you might remember Jim
colins from many years ago talking about
Good the great and so I took on this
concept Jim Collins was a class of mine
actually at Stanford before he was
famous and uh and so I love his work on
a big hairy audacious goal and our big
hary audacious goal is to create
groundbreaking ideas for cyber
resilience resilience being the key word
here now here's a list of the most
common types of cyber attacks from this
year this is sort of my throwaway slide
I'm not going to go into each of these
You' you know what most of these are
you've seen them you've read the
headlines um but the the attacks are the
same it's actually the same list from
2023 I looked at it last week just to
make sure they hadn't changed they
haven't changed malware denial of
service fishing and social engineering
those are the top three and those are
the ones we keep throwing money at to
try to keep the bad guys from doing that
but today AI introduces new types of
attacks I'm not actually going to show
you this YouTube video but if you
haven't seen it you should go take a
look at it and you can just do a search
on YouTube um uh Jordan Peele the the um
prolific and very out there guy did a
video where he um was a uh it was a deep
fake of Obama and it really drives home
how accurate and how the naked eye our
eyes and our brains cannot differentiate
between a deep fake and a real video of
somebody so I'm not going to show it in
the interest of time but if you haven't
seen this I encourage you to go to
YouTube and take a look at it and it
really shows us how AI is really
changing the playing field once again so
if we can't keep our organizations
completely protected from cyber attacks
what do we do what can we do we're not
defenseless we need to we need to put
defenses in place don't hear from me
that I I'm not telling you not to be
protected I'm telling you be protected
but what I'm telling you is we need
something else because it's not adequate
and the something else that we talk
about at cams is cyber resilience now we
talked about supply chain resilience
earlier this morning and supply chain
resilience is actually uh a component of
cyber resilience but we think about
cyber Supply chain resilience is not
being attacked from our supply chain
building a resilient supply chain from
the cyber security perspective I'm not
actually going to go into that here
today but I'm happy to answer questions
about that later I want to talk about a
few other things about what resilience
looks like at a higher level in our
cyber security work so I'm going to talk
about a few projects that my research
team is doing at MIT right now so that
you can get a flavor of the kind of um
of actionable insights and hopefully I
leave each of you with something you can
do differently when you go back to your
office tomorrow so first of all
protection mindset is a bit different
than resilience mindset protection
mindset says let's keep the bad guys out
let's put on all these protection and
many of you may know that the prevailing
way to protect our organization is
called defense in depth we put defense
after defense after defense in in a in a
sequence and the bad guys have to wind
their way through our defenses to get to
our crown jewels and that works to a
point but every time we put in a new
defense the bad guys come up with a new
attack and it gets around that defense
and it's just not adequate and we can't
invest enough in our defenses so we need
a new way to think about it and what I
propose is resilience mindset which says
the bad guys we need to keep the bad
guys out but we need to for a moment
assume that the bad guys might get into
our systems and what are we going to do
about it we want to be prepared should
the bad guys get into us and we going to
be resilient we would like to see
ideally um no uh uh oops that wrong
slide we'd like to see no damage to our
reputation we'd like to see no Financial
damage no operational shutdowns no
compromised passwords no data stolen
wouldn't it be awesome if we had a Cyber
attack and nothing happened that's
resilience thinking it's not that they
that that we don't put Protections in
place it's that we built so many so many
um responses that we could respond if
not instantly pretty
quickly so we've written about this um
in uh Sloan management review published
an article for us on how to be cyber
resilient and um we talk about many
different ways you can do that and I'm
going to dive into a few of those in the
next few minutes here so these are the
three projects I'm going to cover very
quickly I'm again happy to answer any
questions for you but these are three of
the components of building cyber
resilience the first one is around a
culture of cyber security now we talked
about culture earlier this morning I'm
going to take a little bit different uh
uh angle on culture and talk about how
do we create a culture of cyber security
in our organizations cyber security
thinking our hypothesis is everybody in
the organization has a role to play in
keeping our organization secure now not
everybody's rle is the same I wouldn't
expect most people to figure out what
the identity and access management tool
ought to be but I would expect every
single one of you who raised your hand
that you've got a fishing email to not
click on it or to report it or to do
something that's Ro appropriate to help
keep our organization
secure so we asked uh in 2017 what does
that look like and we've come up with
this definition of a cyber security
culture it's the values attitudes and
beliefs that drive behaviors in our
organization values attitudes and
beliefs that drive cyber secure
behaviors and this is the model that we
have for building a culture now many of
you think do things like training your
your people you all took a training
class your organizations think if we
train you you will will be secure and we
know and you know that's not enough you
might have sat through the training
program if it was something that you had
to do for compliance for example you
might have been sitting through the
training program with your phone open
answering emails because who has time to
take an hourlong class we've got to be
doing other things to that are directly
related to our work and so you're
absorbing some of the information in the
training program but you're really not
absorbing everything training programs
are super important for setting
guidelines and they help to change the
oops
wrong button they help to change the
values attitudes and beliefs they tell
us some things we should that our
organization thinks are important but
what we really need to know from this
model is that to really change behaviors
we need to think about how do we set the
right values attitudes and beliefs and
those values attitudes and beliefs are
driven not only by training programs but
by things like what Executives do you
know you as an executive in your
organization your words are super
powerful and if you turned your uh to
your team and you said to them you know
I know we do this project or this work
but it's also important for us to be
cyber secure and I want you to think
about how you can be cyber secure in our
company that that you're going to change
behaviors you're going to change the
values attitudes and beliefs people are
going to know it's important to you if
it's important to you it becomes
important to the people below you that's
not training we also see things like um
uh reward systems one organization we
worked with uh they rewarded people who
came forth with a cyber security idea
they rewarded them with cookies not the
electronic kind the chocolate chip kind
and they ran out of cookies the the
Evangelist who was doing this project
ran out of cookies within an hour he had
dozens of cookies but people were so
interested in getting the reward that
they took on the task of coming up with
cyber secure behaviors that they thought
would be useful another organization an
oil and gas company that we worked with
that's um from this area they punished
people who couldn't do cyber secure
behaviors they use punishment they use
the stick method in their world if you
click on a fishing email the first time
you get a warning the second time you're
forced to take a little module an in
micro module of learning that would
teach you um what you should recognize
the third time you met with your boss
the fourth time you met with HR and the
fifth time you click on a fishing email
a test email you're fired now you might
say wow that's that's really punitive
and in their in most worlds that culture
that wouldn't work but in their world
clicking on a fishing email was too big
a risk in their world an industrial
control environment something could blow
up an offshore oil rig could go down if
you got malware into a system and they
couldn't take a chance on having you be
someone that couldn't learn to not click
on fishing emails now that doesn't work
in every organization that's not the
culture I'm not suggesting you fire
people who click on fishing emails but
I'm saying you can see the impact that
that would have that's not training but
that does Drive behaviors
so once we realize that it's values
attitudes and beliefs that drive
behaviors we have a whole bunch of other
managerial mechanisms that help us
change values attitudes and beliefs and
that's what this research is all about
so this research has been around for a
few years um we've now extended it in a
number of different areas and I'm going
to talk about maturity culture maturity
and ai's impact on culture in just a
minute but I want to point out that it's
also been used it's been cited by almost
a hundred other Studies have cited our
research and building a culture of cyber
security we're really proud of this fact
that our work has really impacted not
just the managerial and the the
organizational side but other research
has come off come have been has been
generated by these ideas so let me talk
a little bit about this project going on
right now and if you're interested in
this project I have a QR code you can
literally jump in today and contribute
personally contribute to our research
and I'll tell you how so we looked at
culture and we said okay culture this
makes sense we have certain set of
values attitudes and beliefs we can look
at managerial mechanisms and see what
your organizations are doing we can even
um we can quantify that but it doesn't
mean that your whole organization is at
the same level of maturity maybe some
parts of your organization are more
mature cyber security maturity than
others and some are less maybe your
organization is more mature than your
competitor's organization is there some
way that we can measure maturity of of
uh culture we came up with this five
different different stages in stage one
uh we call it ad hoc um that's where
cyber security is thought of in an
organization as a technical term it's
something that um you that your
technology people put in place and
everybody in the organization believes
that technology people are going to keep
us safe it's not their job uh and uh um
employees are told what to do in
training and awareness it's just sort of
ad hoc it's something that it's part of
your Technology Group and then you can
see progressing through a few other
levels here where they gets
progressively more mature for I you
might have a manager identified who owns
building a culture of cyber security uh
and that person is taking it Beyond just
the technology people you might have uh
managers actually getting involved that
are not part of your cyber organization
and they're helping promote cyber
security to all employees um at stage
four cyber security is a top priority of
your leaders and they talk about cyber
security and they and they promote the
concept of values attitudes and beliefs
that drive cyber secure behaviors I have
an example there of a company it's a
bank um of course nobody's going to do
business with a bank they don't trust so
you're already in an environment you're
in an industry where cyber security is
critical and in that bank the CEO not a
technical guy starts every All Hands
meeting with a cyber security moment he
sometimes tells a personal story I read
this headline and I wanted to bring it
to your attention he sometimes tells
tells a uh a personal story you know I
got this fishing email did anyone else
in the room get it sometimes he brings
up somebody else to tell a story but the
point is he starts his All Hands meeting
not a cyber meeting with five minutes on
cyber security what do you think that
does to the
organization well it tells the
organization that the CEO thinks cyber
secur is important and if the CEO thinks
it's important his direct reports think
it's important and it just trickles down
the organization so that's an example of
of a stage four company where cyber
security is a top priority it tells the
whole organization that the CEO really
not only says it all of our CEOs say it
nobody's going to say cyber secur is not
important but he actually devotes time
and resource to it and then stage five
which we're still playing with we're not
quite sure what that looks like but in
my mind it's some sort of dynamic
culture that shifts as our environment
shifts as AI becomes a threat the
somehow the culture knows the culture
changes to U en engulf the threat that
cyber security has it's sort of dynamic
not quite sure how that works yet I
don't I don't know one company that does
it but I could imagine that kind of um
of of
culture so um the tool that we've come
up with we're calling Maps it has a
management uh component it has an
attitudes values and beliefs component
has a policies component has a strategy
component let me tell you I struggled
with the name for this because these
letters also spell spam but I didn't
think it was a good idea to call a cyber
secur tool spam so I'm call it maps and
the idea here is that each one of these
four components is something we can
measure we can measure through a survey
we might be able to measure through
observation management would be mo
ownership and motivation for culture
things like is there a culture leader
are there resilience plans attitudes
would be things like Unwritten rules is
there individual empowerment do people
feel individually responsible policies
are things like rules and procedures is
there training programs is there
compliance is there microlearning are
there rewards and consequences and
strategy would be things like goals and
plans is there group collaboration is
there funding for cyber security you can
see where this is going so I have a
survey I know you don't have time to do
it right now but if you're interested in
helping us with this project this is a
QR code and this is a link that I would
love for you to to go to you can do it
after at the break or tomorrow whenever
you have time it's a survey we're
testing out so you would be completing
our survey which is basically asking
questions about all the maps components
and it'll help us to fine-tune this
measurement tool that we're going after
I promise you this is not spam I'm not
tricking you there's no trick here I'm
really trying to figure out if the tool
that we've come up with if the qual
trick survey is working or not so if
you'd like to help us out please do we'd
love to have your uh your input our goal
is to fine-tune this survey and then to
build uh not only a tool that that you
could use and that we could publish and
that would be open to the public but
also once we know what level you're at
to give you prescriptions about how to
get to the next level so if we evaluate
you as a you know level two here's three
things you could do to move your
organization to a level three maturity
that's our goal that's where we're
headed with this
project okay let me talk quickly about
two other projects and then I'm happy to
answer any questions um I know the topic
of this whole meeting was about Ai and
we do have a project one of my
colleagues says AI sucking the air out
of every other topic in in the world
today so you can't come on stage and not
mention Ai and I do have a project that
looks at Ai and impact on culture we are
in the process right now of publishing
we have a working paper and we're
publishing we're trying to publish it in
an academic Journal um so I want to
share with you some of the thoughts from
that project so this is the same model
that I just showed you we have external
influences managerial mechanisms values
attitudes and beliefs and behaviors and
we identified five ways where AI might
impact culture
AI could um generate new external
influences like the bad guys maybe
building deep fakes of um that that
impact our our
organization um AI can modify or change
our values attitudes and beliefs people
might want to start using Ai and that
would make them think that they don't no
longer responsible for some of the work
that they are responsible for or it
might enhance the way they're doing the
work that they're doing so it might
change how they value um or or or use
technology tools
digitization um AI can generate new
managerial mechanisms it can offer us
some guide rails that we can use to
promote cyber secure values attitudes
and beliefs um it can stop the creation
of values attitudes and beliefs again it
could be either through the um use of AI
to generate um uh uh messages um
individually tailored messages that to
individuals based on how they best learn
things that would change the values
attitudes and beliefs that they have or
it might uh get in the way of executing
different values attitudes and beliefs
we could see AI building new barriers so
in this work here we've come up with
five themes we did this through a survey
with one of our research Partners me one
of the members of cams we surveyed about
150 Executives over a couple of months
period we did some follow-up interviews
and we see five surface five themes
surfacing one is that um uh AI cre
creates visibility we can um find those
needles in the hay stack that we
couldn't find before because with AI we
know that the the this the AI can find
the anomalies that maybe we didn't know
to look for we know that AI we found
that AI can increase efficiency it can
reduce the toll of repetitive tasks
through automation uh not replacing
people but U making people more
efficient making our cyber activities
more efficient it can um quantify things
that we couldn't quantify before this is
similar to visibility um but by using AI
tools we can start to build metrics that
we we couldn't have used before because
we have insight into behaviors that we
didn't have um and it can um scale it
can take and and scale actually also
works with personalization one of the
the most interesting themes to me was
this idea of personalization we can use
AI to personalize our messages to our uh
employees uh in a way that they will
most most likely understand and and use
for example um if I'm a person who's
more into videos and I need some
behavior modification the AI could offer
me a lesson in a video format that it
might offer Kathleen in a reading format
or somebody else in a conversational
format or a Class A Course format it can
personalize the messages that go to the
employees that would change their
behaviors so these are five different
ways we're seeing AI being used used in
organizations to modify our cyber
security values attitudes and beliefs
and drive different
behaviors this is a white paper if
you're interested in a copy of it send
me an email remind me that you heard it
here I'm doing several talks this month
so just remind me where you heard it and
I'll send you the right
paper okay and let me quickly tell you
about this last project it's about
preparing for cyber crisis
Communications um this project we
published an article in Sloan management
review earlier this fall on Cyber crisis
communication most of you have business
continuity plans you have crisis
communication plans but what we learned
through our research is those aren't
adequate for a cyber incident for
example one company we talked to they
did have a business continuity plan they
had a cyber incident that locked up
their computers where do you think the
Cyber where do you think the business
continuity plan
was was on the computer they didn't have
access to it they had one it was great
it was perfect but it didn't take into
account what might happen in a cyber
crisis and so they didn't have their
continuity plans available and so a few
years ago we talked about this and we
came up with this the the we didn't come
up with the concept but we realized that
people need to practice you need
tabletop exercises that put you through
cyber um incidences so that you can
start to make decisions ahead of time
and then if and when God forbid you
actually have a cyber crisis you've
already built those muscles to respond
you're never going to see exactly what
you practice it's just like you never do
the exact um uh engineering problem that
you did in your homework but you have
the muscles you have the knowledge
you've built the basis the foundation so
that if and when you have a cyber crisis
you're able to respond quickly well the
same thing happens with Communications
turns out that with your Communications
plan is probably not adequate for a
cyber crisis because of some unique
characteristics of a cyber crisis that
would be different than say a flood or a
tornado or uh uh some other type of
business outage that that you might
experience Communications in uh cyber
security are a little bit unique because
of these four areas first there's a time
crunch um when you have a cyber breach
or a cyber incident or cyber uh uh
activity your ecosystem really wants to
know information and they want to know
it fast and you don't have all the
information at the time about what
happened you might not even have all
that information if you had a hurricane
I mean we get those here in Texas
particularly Houston but everybody's
having a hurricane and so it it when the
hurricane hits so there's a little bit
more understanding of what's going on
but in a cyber crisis it's not
necessarily the case you don't have
concrete information about what's
happening you just know your systems are
down you may know that there's malware
in your system you may not know how far
it's penetrated your systems but you're
getting an influx of stakeholder
inquiries you might even have the Press
depending on who you are you might have
the press in your face trying to get
answers and what you say at the very
beginning can create huge problems later
on you might say well we had a cyber
incident and we're looking into it and
the word incident might be something
that your lawyers come back and say oh
no you know no no no don't call it an
incident once you call it an incident
that sets up all sorts of dominoes and
we don't want those dominoes in effect
so you might say well we're looking into
what happened well now your stakeholders
aren't very happy because you haven't
given them enough information so you can
begin to see that the words you use are
really important and it's not the same
as a general business um crisis and the
stress levels are really high even if
you're not the Cyber person in your
organization if you're a marketing
person you want to make sure that your
customers are happy and that they know
what's that that you're on top of it
that you're helping you want don't want
to erode trust um you might want to uh
think about the words you use so that
you're not setting up future problems
future litigation we've seen several
companies where the initial response
wasn't exactly accurate the it the the
event was muddled through but the fact
that they use the wrong words at the
beginning set up secondary and tertiary
problems later down they their
stakeholder lawsuits that came up that
really shouldn't have ever come up
because of words that were used in the
the very beginning so um we we w we
talked about uh six common impulses that
are wrong terminology being one of them
avoid getting ahead of the facts saying
that you your your team is on top of it
we've already solved the problem when
you haven't solved the problem
equipping your front lines for Success
giving them the terms the words they can
use letting them know what they need to
say in a cyber crisis so that they
aren't setting you up for failure in the
secondary or the third wave of the event
um staying appraised of what your media
narrative is if you have multiple people
in your organization speaking to the
press or possibly speaking to the press
or even on social media or even talking
to friends who are not going to say
anything but maybe do you want to make
sure the narrative is consistent
conveying dedication to cyber security
um and and assuring your stakeholders
that um what what you're doing is
appropriate but not over committing to
things and staying cautious of your tone
you want to keep it serious but at the
same time um you don't want to keep it
so serious that you worry your customer
base or your other stakeholders so
consistency of message and applying it
to different audiences is key my partner
in this was obviously a Communications
person that knows a lot more about the
communication strategies than I but the
IDE idea of really thinking through the
the appropriate angle of the message to
each of your stakeholders is really
critical here and in this project um we
talked about building a Communications
Playbook so that you have a plan for
cyber crisis communication and then
testing it with a maybe tabletop
exercise on a cyber crisis because what
we've learned is cyber crisis as I
mentioned earlier are different than
regular crisis and you want to put your
head in the game of a cyber incident so
that you can test the different
components of your response with a cyber
crisis in mind and we published this in
Sloan back in September this is also
available on our website so if you're
interested in this paper you can email
me about that also okay so just to kind
of conclude here resilience thinking is
a little different than protection
thinking I think I've I've I've pounded
that into you in the last 20 minutes so
hopefully you've seen couple of examples
of how it's a bit different it's about
response planning through things like
tabletop exercises and fire drills
putting your team together whether maybe
your team includes external people like
law enforcement or your customers or
cyber experts you know if you're having
a cyber crisis there's a good chance
somebody else is having a cyber crisis
and the resources you expect to be there
for you might not be there for you they
might be helping another customer at the
same time so you want to check you want
to do your tabletop exercises with your
whole ecosystem that you use cyber
critical Communications planning is
different than other business recovery
plans you want to make sure that they're
not just on your computer that they're
accessible should your computers be
locked up and other other messages you
want a design for cyber security you
want to make sure your products your
services are secure should there be an
incident you know we talk about
technology fault tolerance in our
technology and we build our technology
systems so that if one component goes
down the whole system doesn't go down we
need to use that thinking for our
organizations our processes need to be
resilient our organization structures
need to be resilient how do we think
about those how do we design for
security not just in our products and
our services but in the way we deliver
those products and services to um our
customers and our and our um uh and our
uh ecosystem and then finally and this
is another area that I've written
extensively about is about board and sea
level reporting um the biggest risk we
report the wrong things to our board I'm
on a board I'm on two boards I'm looking
for my third board if somebody's looking
for a board member um the we report the
wrong things we report at least uh some
boards that we studied they looked at
the the the dashboard the board gets
tells them how many people failed the
fishing exercise and how much better
we're going to do tells them what
investment we've made in cyber security
and how we compare to our colleagues our
our compet our um similar companies our
our competitors um it tells might tell
us what technologies we've invested in
which frankly as a board member if I
didn't trust that you were making the
right technology decisions you wouldn't
be in that job anyway what I want to
know as a board member and what most sea
level Executives that aren't in cyber
maybe some of you that aren't currently
in cyber want to know is what's the
biggest risk and what are we doing about
it you know what is the biggest risk to
our supply chain from cyber security and
what are we doing about it how are we
managing that risk what is the biggest
risk to our financial cash flow and what
are we doing about it what is the
biggest risk to our organization our
people or from our people and what are
we doing about it so it's the biggest
risk it's a risk discussion it's a
business level discussion question and
what are we doing about it so the way we
report cyber security is about
protection and what we really want to
think about is resilience what's the
biggest risk where are we where are we
most um vulnerable and what are we doing
about it so I hope I'm I'm giving you a
sense of what resilience thinking is all
about here so here's my call to action
for you guys here's four things you can
do tomorrow one you can start to measure
your cyber security U maturity your
culture maturity different parts of your
organization may have
maturity you can start to take a look
and see how how do your employees think
about cyber security and is it what you
want them to be thinking about and maybe
change the way that their values
attitudes and
beliefs uh uh uh cover cyber
security make Heroes out of the be he
people doing the behaviors that you want
to see as a leader if you make somebody
a hero if you give them recognition
maybe you want to give them a chocolate
chip cookie like this one company did
maybe you want to give them a badge that
puts goes on their email that says
they're a cyber hero maybe you just want
to call them out in a meeting but if you
make Heroes out of people that are doing
the right stuff that's another way you
can propagate the values attitudes and
beliefs about cyber security look at
your Communications your cyber your
crisis communication plans what do you
do do you know what what you're your job
would be if your company experienced a
cyber breach and you were shut down what
is your specific rule what do you do
first who do you call what if you can't
use your phones do you email them what
if you can't use your email what are you
supposed to do and if you don't know
what you're supposed to do most people
in your company probably don't know what
they're supposed to do so think about
what your communication plan is
internally externally make sure that
it's cyber uh ready and then finally
create a cyber resilience mindset think
about this from a how do we make sure
that we can respond and recover in
addition to making sure that we're
protected that's it happy to answer any
[Applause]
questions yes sir
stand like N and cobat is there some
interplay is there some interplay
between n and cobat and your work yeah
so we uh use the N framework all the
time in our talk and what we talk about
and what we do um we're not we're kind
of orthagonal in the sense that we're
not using those models as it management
models we're looking more at the
managerial side not the control side the
controls are really important that's
where Coit comes in um at the NY mile is
definitely the n model is all about
resilience the this model is overlap in
terms of tabletop exercises and maybe
red blue some overlap but most of the
Coit ones I've seen are more like fire
drills for technology not managerial and
board level tabletop exercises okay so
but if you think about the nist model
the N cyber security framework model has
six components
identify protect detect respond recover
and govern protect and detect is the
protection mindset respond and recover
is a resiliency mindset it's exactly the
same thing Le when I go to conferences
they talk about the tabletop as yes a
part of yeah and and people use the term
tabletop I do too Loosely it's really
about practice so um it's what are you
practicing obviously could practice
there's a whole Continuum of what you
could practice what I'm suggesting you
practice is the organizational response
okay I see yes yeah other questions yes
sir so from your like you know survey
and experience like where is the biggest
like you know Pitfall and like you know
following the cyber security practices
because I see a lot of people try to
follow the N framework and stuff
somewhere like know they take like
compromise some of them but is there
anything that like you see that like
know where typically like know they fail
to recognize versus like you know hey uh
the management doesn't actually like you
know give enough like you know funding
to do certain things so I I think the
question is where do I see the biggest
need the biggest hole and I think the
biggest hole is to have non-cyber people
Embrace their um capability to impact
the Cyber in a company I think most
people think that cyber is not their job
they do everything else they do whatever
their job is finance marketing
operations and somebody else is worrying
about cyber and I think that um the
biggest hole is people feeling that
cyber is a technical question and that
belongs with the it or the Cyber people
and it really isn't it's an
organizational issue and once we can see
that cyber is an organizational isue we
can start to close the gap because we
really need everybody on board it's like
safety it's like safety really finally
after what 30 years permeated all our
companies and everybody's thinking
safety but cyber isn't quite there yet
and I would like to see cyber permeated
just like we see safety permeated last
question yes sir yeah I was just
wondering what are your thoughts as far
as uh fishing attacks on cell phones I
have I've seen zero effort whatsoever on
that either when I have a company cell
phone and I get those fishing there's
nothing from IT department there's no
nothing governing that it's just me
reporting the junk and that's the end of
it but also on my personal cell phone
same thing like every day even my
daughter is 16 she's getting those
things I'm getting them zero effort from
the carriers to even attempt to actually
uh you know combat all those messages
we're all getting on our cell phones
cell phones um both text messages and um
emails everything else on cell phones
yep I'm seeing I get them all the time
too um okay so I'm going to say
something that's probably not very
popular I think it's our responsibility
to train ourselves to respond to those
appropriately I.E delete them and I
talked at the very beginning sometimes I
give this talk to organization people
that aren't all business people and I
say cyber isn't just a business problem
it's a family problem you know we got to
keep our kids secure we got to keep our
spouses secure we got to keep our
parents secure I can't tell you the
number of people I I often tell a story
I'm the only cyber girl in my Social
Circle my friends are lawyers and
doctors and dentists and nail techs and
real estate people and teachers I mean
they're they have normal jobs just like
the rest of us but I'm the only cyber
person and because I'm these are my
friends and I they know what I do every
now and then I I send them an email of
something a head a headline I saw or a
story or something just by me sending
that to them raises their awareness and
makes them a little bit more secure and
they're my friends they're not cyber
people and they're not my employees
they're not my teammates I'm not
responsible for the Cyber breach that
they may or may not have but I think
it's all of our responsibilities and I
think that's part of my drinking the
Kool-Aid too it's our responsibility to
help all those around us be a little
more secure because we know how
important it is we see through that
Looking Glass about all these these
vulnerabilities and once you see those
you can't ignore them whether it's for
yourself or for your daughter or for
your family or your friends and so I
think that that that's the answer I mean
I don't know that the carriers are doing
anything I I really I mean I don't see
it but it's not my research so I can't
really comment as an expert there but I
do think as individuals who understand
that the headlines aren't going away and
the the threat vectors aren't going away
we got to help all those around us also
so okay I'm around round I'm going to be
on the panel later thank you so much for
your time and hope you enjoyed our talk