[MUSIC PLAYING]
GIOVANNI TRAVERSO: Whenever
one is able to bring together
different disciplines and
different bodies of knowledge,
we really stand to have
a transformative impact
on major problems.
I see myself as both a
physician and an engineer.
To me, bringing
those two domains
together is what really can
help transform and accelerate
our capacity to develop
new biomedical devices
or new therapies for
a range of conditions.
My dad is from Peru,
which is where I grew up,
and my mother is from Nicaragua.
And we left at the end
of the '80s at the height
of the instability and were
able to emigrate to Canada.
When I was in high school, I
had the incredible opportunity
to actually spend time in a lab.
I really fell in love
with molecular genetics,
and I really loved the lab
environment and that ability
to investigate a very specific
problem with the hopes
that those developments
will eventually help people.
I started medical school
right after high school,
but in England at the
University of Cambridge.
I interrupted my medical
training with a PhD
at Johns Hopkins.
I had a tremendous
interest for the applied,
but I decided to go
back to medical school
and then pursue further
medical training.
And then I moved to Boston.
I had the tremendous
good fortune
of being offered the
faculty position here
in the Department of
Mechanical Engineering.
Being embedded in the Mechanical
Engineering Department
is this incredible opportunity
to engage with students, as well
as faculty, in the development
of the next generation
of medical devices.
And at the heart or the
core of many of those
medical devices are fundamental
mechanical principles.
Major areas that we are
contributing in, one of them
involves the development of an
ingestible electronic device
that can stay in the
body for over two months
to release a payload.
That payload is
actually a bacteria
that can help treat
traveler's diarrhea.
Multiple domains are
integrated to make this work
in mechanical engineering,
electrical engineering, material
science, and synthetic biology.
Another big area is
developing devices
that enable the delivery of
drugs like insulin, but orally.
Beyond that, we're now
pushing that envelope
into the area of
adjustable electronics
and how electronics can
interface with the GI tract
for stimulation, but also for
sensing of different conditions.
As a physician, we're
extremely fortunate to be
able to have the opportunity
to help individuals.
As a scientist and engineer, not
only can we help individuals,
but we can help populations.
It's really about trying to
help others, including students,
to see that arc to help
stimulate further development--
[MUSIC PLAYING]
--to make people's lives better.