small satellites are the size of a small
kitchen appliance if you only have a
couple big satellites you're not going
to be able to see the same spot on the
earth for a few days if you're able to
put many satellites in orbit and have a
constellation those satellites can get
revisits as quickly as an hour these
days satellites can look down and decide
what I'm seeing right now when I take an
image is just clouds so I'm going to
either wait until I come around again
and it's not cloudy or send a command
over to a neighboring satellite see if
there are no clouds there there are
different domains where these
applications are valuable we can make
surface maps at very high Precision you
can look for effects of storm systems
flooding wildfires in defense certainly
watching logistical activity it allows
people to get a much faster response
when something negative happens for more
MIT moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow