so basically uh we proved that
essentially if you follow the steps we
followed so far in the course and derive
the perfectly competitive outcome uh
equilibrium outcome that's the best you
can
do now the best way to understand this
example is to ask how it gets messed up
by by government
interventions in this world of perfectly
competitive markets The Government Can
Only screw things up okay the market
knows best The Government Can Only screw
things up and so I going to talk about a
couple examples of ways the government
could screw this market up before coming
back in a few lecture telling you why
the government isn't always the bad guy
but but thus far it is okay so for
example let's go back to our market for
gas and let's look at figure 101
imagine you're initially in equilibrium
the market for gas at P1
q1 Point E1 is equilibrium everybody's
Happy on the demand and supply
curve and as I proved last time that's
the welfare maximizing outcome that's
the outcome that maximizes the sum of
producer and consumer
surpluses now imagine there's a war in
the Middle East as we unfortunately are
about to are having uh and that raises
as it will raise the price of gas the
price of gas is rising in the US it will
rise now because of these terrible
events uh the Middle East um and that
results in a higher cost of getting oil
that shifts up the supply curve and that
leads to a higher price for gasoline so
we went these Dynamics last time how
that would happen uh and you move from
E1 to
E2 now what does that do to
welfare positively we know what it does
we've derived that what about nor
atively what's due to welfare well
before this Supply shift consumer
surplus was a plus b plus d plus e so
before so we're talking about now
government
interventions so let's say this's Supply
shift so consumer surplus before the
price
rise before the
war the consumer surplus was a plus b
plus d plus e and the producer Surplus
equal consumer surplus and the producer
Surplus was C+ f plus
G what has happened now well the new
equilibrium
E2 consumer surplus has fallen to just
a we've lost that entire trapezoid B
plus d plus
e producer
Surplus has um producers have gained the
area B Because prices are higher but
they've lost but producers have lost um
uh f plus G so producer Surplus has lost
f plus G but they've gained
B okay so overall Society has lost um uh
Society has uh lost D plus e plus f plus
G that entire sort of if you will sort
of sideways trapezoid
fdeg is gone it's
disappeared uh because now the price is
higher okay and that's our welfare
analysis and right now we're talking
about good bad we're not talking about
how we feel about this we're just saying
what happened positively what happened
positively is welfare fell by that
trapezoid
fdeg now however imagine that voters are
said about this President Biden's up for
re-election in a little bit more than a
year he may be worried that higher gas
prices will hurt his chances as they
often uh people terms out people's in
feelings about inflation are heavily
shaped by what happens at the gas prices
and he says you know what we ought to do
we ought to limit this price rise in gas
why don't we just tell the gas producers
that they can't raise their
prices why don't we set a price ceiling
at P1 and just say look price of gas was
I don't know 350 50 before these latest
events 360 you can't raise it it's got
to say 360 a gallon you can't raise to 4
450 whatever it's going to go to and
then the voters will be happy because
they won have to pay more for
gas okay well what would that do we can
show that in figure
101 little in figure 102 little
two so what is the effect of price seing
let's walk through this slowly first
thing is they said a price sailing at P1
suppos it's a price cealing set at P1
first question is at a price cealing of
P1 how much gas gets produced and why
someone tell me at a price sealing of P1
if the government says the price can't
go above P1 how much gas gets produced
in
why what quantity of gas is produced in
the
market and
why yeah
you got to speak
up a lower specifically what quantity
lower quantity what Q3 is produced and
why is Q3
produced yeah basically because in this
situation of dise
equilibrium where at that price Supply
does not equal
demand firms are in charge you've
basically said look we are going to
assist the price above p is P1 consumers
are like super we want to continue
consuming q1 and firms say no we're not
interested in producing q1 we're going
to produce Q3 and that's all we're going
to produce that's all you get it doesn't
matter the consumers want q1 so we're
out of equilibrium we have excess demand
but unlike the case last time with an
excess demand led the equilibrium to
adjust it can't this time because the
government set a price cealing so now
the new equilibrium is at E3 with only
Q3 being
sold so the key point is when you're out
of
equilibrium you've got to look
at who is the constrained party who's
going to determine what happens well
basically it's going to be whichever
party wants to produce or consume less
it doesn't matter how much consumers
want to consume producers only produce
Q3 okay so only Q3 gets produced and we
knew equilibrate
E3 well what does this do well there are
two
costs and one
benefit okay the cost the first cost so
what so the government intervenes
there's two
costs the first cost is an efficiency
reduction is an efficiency
reduction what is the efficiency
reduction well let's
return so if you look at this
diagram in the disequilibrium outcome
only E3 gets
produced okay so what is the new only so
only Q3 amounts of gas are
produced this I'm comparing compare
equilibrium E3 to equilibrium E2 now
remember on the previous diagram the
bottom of the previous page we talked
about E2 was worse than E1 but that's
done the war has
happened we're now at E2 if the
government doesn't do anything so now
the relev comparison is not to E1 E1
doesn't exist anymore it's E3 to E2 so
want to ask what happens to Total social
welfare we moveed from E2 to E3 well the
answer is that
consumers only get Q3 amount of gas at a
price of P1 so consumer
surplus has gone so consumer surplus
without the government intervention at
this new price would be at this new
price without government so at each two
consumer surplus would be v+ Y at
E2 okay and producer Surplus at
E2 would be uh W plus Z Plus
X at
E2 okay now we move to
E3 what is the new consumer
surplus can anyone tell them what the
new consumer surplus is at
E3 yeah V plus W excellent because it's
the area under the demand curve above
the price line but only for units sold
it doesn't matter that the area Y and
the area Z is still under the demand
curve above the price line that's
irrelevant because the units aren't sold
you can't derive surplus of something
you don't
buy so consumer surplus is now V plus W
so consumers lose Y and they gain w
but what about producers same person
what's the new producer
Surplus X producers have lost w and
z so what has happened W has been
transferred from producers to
Consumers consumers are gaining W
because they're now paying lower prices
for
gas but y+ Z is lost y Plus plus Z is
what we call dead weight loss remember
from last time what's happened to y+ Z
they are trades that would make both
parties better off that are not allowed
to happen look if you stay at
E2 both producers and consumers would be
happy to sell all the gallons of gas
between Q2 and Q3 but you're not letting
them therefore you're reducing welfare
you're reducing the total social welfare
by not allowing those trades to
happen Okay so that is the first cost
this government intervention trades that
don't get made lead to an efficiency
loss trades that would make both parties
better
off but that don't get made lead to an
efficiency loss okay there shouldn't
this radical
idea if you've got your your two you
know uh your two uh playing cards you
like and your friend is two playing
cards they like and you'd be happy to
have your friend's card and they'd be
happy to have yours but your mom's upset
with you and won't let you make the
trade you're worse
off okay you're worse off if you can't
make trades that make you that make both
parties happier that's a simple
intuition Society has lost and what have
they lost they've lost this deadweight
loss amount y plus Z questions about
that but that's not the only cost
there's a second cost which is
allocation
inefficiency and this is a new idea but
it's really following from the intuition
we've already developed in this
class which is that in a world of
equilibrium we never have to
ask who gets the good and how much they
value it and who doesn't get the good
and how much they value it we know from
the diagram so if you look at figure 102
without the price
ceiling basically we we know who gets
the gas everyone who values it at above
P2 we know who doesn't get the gas
everyone blows it below P2 you're
done but now look at the new out of
equilibrium outcome
E3 you have Q3 units of q1 units of gas
people want but only Q3 that's provided
so what determines who gets it it used
to be you didn't have to worry about
that the price determined it people who
want it above the price got it didn't
want to place didn't get it but now
you've got more people who want it at
that price that is actually supplied so
you've got a new question who gets it
and the problem is answering that
question creates a new
inefficiency because it's inefficient
having to figure out how to allocate the
good okay so for example in the 1970s we
put in a gas price ceiling there was a
gas price shock due to the formation of
the organization of petroleum exporting
countries or
OPEC the uh countries in World got
together and formed a cartel we'll talk
about all this in a couple lectures
formed a cartel and that cartel reduced
the amount of oil being sold raising the
price of gas the US government was upset
gas had been cheap forever so they put
in a gas price ceiling what happened
well what happened was more people
wanted gas at that low price than the
gas stations willing to sell so what
resulted was giant lines of cars with at
gas station huge snaky lines of cars you
could wait 15 20 minutes in a line or
longer to get your gas why because it
was only Q3 amount of gas and q1 people
wanted it so the only way to allocate it
was to wait in line well that waiting in
line is
inefficient why is it inefficient that
people waiting in line for
gas what's the efficiency cost
yeah the opportunity cost they could be
doing something else clearly that is not
the use of their time that makes them
happiest I highly doubt there was anyone
who said woohoo I want to go wait in the
line for gas okay they could have been
working they could have been having fun
whatever they could have been doing it
would have been better than waiting line
for
gas there's also a second order in
efficiency cost second order means small
which is they're using up a lot of gas
waiting in line for gas remember we had
big gas guzzlers then that got like
eight miles to the gallon so you could
use up probably a gallon of gas waiting
to get your gas sitting in line idling
okay but that's the technical point the
main point is there was a huge
opportunity cost that opportunity cost
is inefficiency
that is destroyed social surplus social
welfare that is happiness that could
have been derived working or in Leisure
that's gone so that's an additional
inefficiency that comes from this kind
of government intervention not only is
there inefficient amount of gas produced
you're destroying efficiency further
through the mechanism that allocates the
gas why doesn't that happen in a
competitive equilibrium because the
mechanism is the price you look at the
price you either get if you want or you
don't if you don't don't it's easy you
drive by the gas station if you want it
you pull in you get the gas if you don't
want it you drive by now if you want it
you got to wait in line because there's
not enough to satisfy the demand so that
government intervention has caused a new
efficiency loss the opportunity cost of
people waiting in line for
gas Okay now what's the
benefit the
benefit of all this
presumably is
equity presum the government's decided
that they care about
consumers more than producers you can
call it Equity you can call political
calculation whatever you want but the
idea is the benefits government say well
yeah you got all efficiency but look we
got to transfer W from those awful oil
companies to these wonderful consumers
who happen to
vote okay and isn't that a good benefit
and the answer is well maybe and what
we've learned so far it's not what we've
learned so far social welfare is just a
sum of produc or consumer surplus so
transfers do not affect social welfare
okay that's the key in our framework so
far we defined welfare as simply
consumer surplus plus producer
Surplus then transferring from one part
to the other doesn't help that's just
inefficiency but voters and politicians
may not feel that way and maybe we
shouldn't NE this raises the really
interesting question that we will come
back to
about the fact that in reality we might
not be indifferent between these two in
reality we might be willing to have a
little inefficiency to get Goods in the
hands of people who we think deserve
them
more in other words in reality we may be
willing to sacrifice some efficiency for
equity and that is the heart of what we
call the equity efficiency tradeoff that
we'll discuss later the
semester so in reality we might be able
to make this trade but from what you've
learned in this class so far we're not
with this definition of social welfare
we are not willing to make this
trade okay and this is a fundamental
doand uh Concept in economics now let's
question about
this let's go through some real world
examples let's talk about ticket
scalping okay a few years ago Adele went
on tour for the first time in four years
to back up an incredibly successful
album and folks there was huge pend up
demand to see her live
she said look I want to make sure my
fans can see me so I'm G to price the
tickets affordably tickets are going to
be start at $40 and no ticket we more
than
$150 which is unbelievably cheap for
major concerts these days okay she said
look I know my fans willing to pay
thousands of dollars to see me so I want
to give them some Surplus I'm not going
to pay more can pay more than 150 or
even 40 if they want to sit in the cheap
seats okay but did the fans get that
Surplus no what happened was as soon as
the tickets went on sale they were all
immediately bought by
scalpers scalpers are basically
secondary ticket sellers who set up Bots
to instantly buy all tickets available
if they feel that they're below if
they're priced below market value they
then resell them through places like
stubhub.com and other places at the
actual market value so what happened was
the price forell ticket was actually not
sure if you got on and managed to beat
the Bots you got it for 150 but if you
did in went tub Hub was
$1,500 okay which is because that's what
people willing to pay to go see Adele
then we started on Taylor
Swift okay Taylor's tickets were priced
between $50 and
$500 okay they actually um the uh the
tickets are now sold between $800 and
$111,000 to go see Taylor Swift because
that's what people are willing to pay so
everyone's like oh Taylor Swift set her
tickets $500 that was too cheap that was
cheaper than the what the market wanted
the market was willing to pay much more
now it didn't have to be this way when I
was a kid scalping was illegal and there
was no online market so the way you get
to like go to Shady guys in raincoats
outside the stadium and like buy the
tickets from them okay that's the way it
used to work so really if you wanted
tickets there's no online Market what
did you do you waited
online so literally we'd stay up all
night if a big band was touring we'd
camp out the night before and stay up
all night waiting online to be able to
get a ticket the next day that's how
they were allocated there's no more
lines because now we do it by
Price which system is better well in
fact the system when I was a kid was
much less
efficient why because basically the
people the time we wasted online had a
high opportunity cost now we can just
pay in some sense essentially what the
secondary online Market does has
reintroduced efficiency to the
allocation of tickets now people pay
what they're
worth okay so in some sense the good
news is the market today is much more
efficient for allocating tickets than
was the market when I was a kid because
we don't waste time sleeping in the cold
waiting
online okay okay however it's not say as
Equitable because
now who gets the money well we when we
slept online who got the Surplus well
the consumer got the
Surplus presumably those of us who are
willing to sleep online could get
tickets for less than our Surplus if
than our I if if the value US of seeing
the show plus the disutility of sleeping
online
exceeded I'm sorry if the value seeing
the show minus the disutility of
sleeping online exceeded the ticket
price we wouldn't sleep
online so we got the Surplus now the
Surplus largely goes to secondary ticket
sellers it still goes to Consumers
people don't buy unless they get some
Surplus but who's not getting the
Surplus is
performers so even Taylor Swift is
making way even though she is now
setting the all-time record for a tour
the pr record was Elton John at1
billion Elton John to be clear has been
making music for 50 years Taylor Swift
is only 33 years old he now going to
break the record at $1.5 billion and
that is way under what her tour should
make okay way under what a tour should
make cuz she is not selling tickets the
price people willing to pay for
them okay so which system is better well
it's hard to
say on the one hand tickets today get
allocated to those who value them the
most according to
price on the other hand all that extra
money goes to
scalpers what could Adele or Taylor
Swift do to address this point
what could they do to at least make sure
that they got the money rather than
scalpers getting the money
yeah I'm
sorry well basically it's sort of hard
to know what the G price is but they
could for example set up an auction why
couldn't Taylor Swift say I'm playing
Boston I'm gonna put my tickets up for
auction people can
bid and it'll be like
eBay I'll just sell my tickets the
highest bidder you would end up with
exactly the same outcomes you get from
the secondary Market but all the money
would go to Taylor Swift instead of
going to these Shady StubHub
guys
okay why don't performers do
this the answer is I'm pretty sure
public relations there's no reason why
they couldn't Taylor Swift there's no
reason Taylor Swift couldn't hire an
infinite number of programmers set up an
online auction to make this work the
answer is essentially public relations
that basically artists feel they're
making plenty of money and they they
look pretty bad if they were charging
these incredible prices which is what
they get from these auctions which is
sort of too bad because people are
paying those prices anyway but sub sense
because they're hidden through paying at
StubHub Taylor Swift doesn't get as a
hard of time if she set up an auction
sold tickets for 2,000 or eight $1,000
each but that's sort of unfortunate
because it's really the same outcome
it's just who gets the money Taylor
Swift should get the money it's her show
she's the one adding value to society by
doing a three and a half our show not
these scalpers she should get the money
so the bottom line is there are ways the
bottom line lesson from this ticket
scalping example is
a we can see an example of shifting from
an inefficient allocation mechanism
which is waiting online to an efficient
allocation mechanism which is using
price but that shift did not necess
deliver the Surplus the folks we want to
deliver it to it delivered it to a third
set of actors who set up this Online
Marketplace
okay questions about
that okay now let's go to a much more
complicated example but one which really
lays out clearly how to think about
these tradeoffs which is the case of
taxi cab
medallions cast your mind back 20 years
ago okay notably before Uber and lft and
all these
things in that world if you wanted to
get from point A to point B and didn't
have a car you took a
taxi now taxis should be a textbook
example of a perfectly competitive
market right to be a tax driver you just
need a car and that's it pretty low
fixed cost when people have cars
anyway it should be a very very
perfectly competitive
market but in fact it was
not it was a market that was not
perfectly competitive because it was
heavily regulated by
cities and in particular what cities
did is they limited the amount of taxes
to those who held essentially
certificates that made them legal taxi
drivers they were called medallions
because they're originally medallions
but not a pieces of paper essentially
cities issued pieces of paper that said
you're an official taxi driver and only
if you had one of these could you drive
a
taxi okay what we want to do is analyze
what are the welfare implications of
these limited number of of taxi cab
medallions so let's go to figure 103
which is one of the more complicated
figures you'll see in this class okay
it's one of these back and forth figures
bear with me but please interrupt me if
there's
questions okay so imagine that
initially we had no taxi cab medallions
in a free taxi cab Market in such a
market let's start in the part diagram
on the left of figure 103 in such a
market price would equal marginal cost
would equal minimum average cost we' be
an equilibrium point little
E1 price would be P1 why we'd have
identical taxi cabs produce identical
Market it' be easily shopping be perfect
competition and weend up with price P1
at Price
P1 we would have at Price P1 each of the
identical cabs would produce little q1
rides okay because each cab and once
again let's assume to make life easy I'm
going to assume identical
cabs this is an assumption but not too
bad in this case much better assumption
than say assuming identical factories
the idea that cabs are kind of identical
is not implausible so assume identical
cabs they all have minimum average cost
at the point q1 little q1 on the le-
hand side diagram so a series of
identical cabs all of them have minimum
average cost at amount little q1 and
therefore set price equal to P1 now go
over to the right hand diagram we have a
demand curve there with a price of P1
that means that a total of big q1 rides
will be
demanded well if big q1 rides are
demanded and each firm is going to
produce little q1 rides that pins down
the number of
firms N1 okay once again go through the
logic and stop me if it's in clear we
know each FM will produce little
q1 we know at that price big q1 rise or
demanded therefore we could Define the
number of firms as big q1 over little q1
which is
N1 so there's N1 firms providing little
q1 rides each at a price of P1 in the
free market questions about
that once again as we learned a couple
lectures ago we know we end up there
because if there was less than little N1
firms the price would be higher there'd
be profits being made and new firms
would enter okay and you could just
should be able to show yourself that
they're less than the Len one firms you
could see the quantity be lower at a
lower quantity price would be higher
you'd move up the demand curve and
therefore profits would be being made
and therefore firms would enter and
there's not a lot of barriers to entry
here so this is not a bad example for a
competitive
market okay now let's say the government
comes in and says
um you know what we're only going to
allow there to
be we are only going to be allowed there
to be little end two numbers of cabs so
the government comes in the government
restriction here is in the form not of
price but of number of
firms the government says only N2 cabs
will be allowed this is a new kind of
restriction we haven't done this before
we talked about gas price
ceiling okay that was a price
restriction this is now a number of
firms
restriction government says only N2 Cals
will be
allowed okay now what happens there well
up to N2 if you look at the right hand
side
diagram up to the first dash line which
is little N2 little q1 nothing has
changed if the demain curve was such
that that big Q was less than little N2
little q1 nothing would have
changed but what happens once we get
past that first point little N2 little
q1 what happens is that now each cab has
to produce more rides because you can't
add new cab
companies each cab can no longer produce
at the efficient
Point each cab company can no longer
ride q1 rides why because it won't meet
demand and new firms can't enter so to
meet demand cabs need to drive more well
if they're going to drive more they're
no longer going to be efficient q1's the
efficient amount in other words think of
it this way q1 is the point in which
drivers are maximally efficient driving
once they have to drive more maybe
they're more tired maybe they have to
drive at hours that aren't as convenient
for them they're less efficient in
producing rides think of cab drivers
like a firm they have a perfectly
efficient amount of r to give once you
have them give more they're less
efficient maybe because they're more
tired well if they're less efficient
that means they are providing them at a
higher cost so the new supply curve is
flat until N2 q1 but the new supply
curve S2 is no longer a line S no longer
S1 which is a horizontal line the new
supply curve S2 is horizontal till that
first intersection and then becomes
upward sloping the new supply curve S2
has that horizontal segment that becomes
upward sloping and once again these kind
of Kink curves are hard let's explain
why the reason why it's flat is because
as long as there's less than q1 rides
per firm they produce at maximum
efficiency but once you ask any taxi
driver to work more than little q1
rides it's
inefficient okay you can see this by now
turning to the leftand side
diagram you see that to produce Q2
rides they do
so at a much
higher point at a much higher Point than
marginal cost
curve so if they're going to set
marginal cost equal to
price okay they are going to say so now
go back to the right hand side so with
this new supply curve okay question
about supply curve looks like it does
once again this is hard so please let me
know if there's questions about that
okay so with this new supply curve that
hits demand at a new higher price
P2
yeah
yeah it's flat to the left of that flat
part because as long if imagine demand
was shifted way inwards and demand was
less than little N2 little
q1 even if you restricted number of
firms each firm would still provide q1
rides the point is you're only allowing
up to n two firms let's say that demand
intersected that line so I I'm doing the
risky thing of drawing a diagram here
okay so you've got this demand curve
here right and you've got this supply
curve that looks like this and then
looks like this imag demand curve came
here and let's call this intersection
little N3 q1 well the these firm will
continue to prod that their efficient
level you just have a smaller number of
firms there'd be no reason to produce in
efficiently but the problem is once you
get past P this point more firms can't
enter what keeps this original supply
curve S1 flat is entry of firms but
firms can't enter past this point the
existing firms have to produce more and
they do so
inefficiently so this is the efficient
part of production for q1 firms for N1
firms I'm sorry the efficient production
for N2 firms but for N2 firms once you
get past here they have to be more tired
and produce less efficiently okay other
questions okay so the new price is P2
when now let's go back to the left at a
price P2 said equal the marginal cost
ignore the ac2 curve for a minute we'll
come back to that stay with
ac1 if we set that new price P2 equal
the marginal cost we get equilibrium E2
and a huge amount of profits the profits
at that new price P2 marginal cost is
well above average cost once again
ignore ac2 stay with ac1 okay at that
new price
P2 marginal cost is well above average
cost and you get a huge profit of the
amount
Pi okay so now they're making
profit now what's happened is by
limiting the number of cabs they are now
making profit what is this done to
social welfare well let's go back to the
right hand side what was the old
consumer
surplus what was the old consumer
surplus somebody tell me before we put
in this restriction what was the
consumer surplus raise your hand and
tell me
me you guys got this need a little more
confidence out of this class come on you
guys got an M you're Wicked smart go
ahead a plus b plus c c has two parts
it's sort of weird but a plus b plus C A
plus b plus C same person what's the old
producer
Surplus there's none
why in a perfectly competitive long run
equilibrium there's zero
profits okay we we so because of free
entry in a perfectly competitive log
equilibrium there's no profits so produ
Surplus is zero what is the new same
person what's the new consumer surplus
if we sell a price
P2 a what is the new producer
Surplus
B so what has happened we have
transferred
B from consumers to producers that's
their new
profits okay so be and aggregate would
be the sum of the little Pi triangles on
the left over all firms so we took the
profits made on the left multiplied by n
two firms that would give you
B okay B is the total aggate profits
that is so we've taken money for
consumers give to profits but we've
created a dead weight loss the dead
weight loss is
C so it's an inefficient
restriction okay it's an infinite
restriction now so so we have the
efficiency
loss we also have the allocation now
here we don't have an allocation loss
I'm sorry because we're in
equilibrium so the people willing to pay
for the rides still get the rides we
don't have the allocation issue here
because it's it's we have a new
equilibrium we're not out of equilibrium
in equilibrium which is in equilibrium
with fewer
rides what about Equity well that
depends on how you feel about cab Riders
versus drivers if you think in New York
City all the cab Riders are rich
investment bankers and the cab drivers
are poor immigrants then maybe it's a
good thing maybe it's good we've taken
area B away from the rich investment
bankers and given it to the cab drivers
if on the other hand you think a lot of
the cab Riders are also poor people need
to get to work it might not be such a
good
idea but guess what all that is
irrelevant
why because
actually there's a market for taxi cab
medallions they sell in the market
you can sell your taxic cam Medallion
can anyone tell me in this diagram what
the market price of a taxi cab medallion
should be if there a perfectly
competitive taxi cab medallion
Market what should the total cost of a
taxi cab medallion be can anyone take a
guess at
that the answer is is a letter is is a
letter Greek or Roman on this diagram
which tells you yeah Pi Pi
why that's
get yeah because if if I want to buy a
medallion I'll be willing to pay up to
Pi minus Epsilon to get it why because
as long as I pay Pi minus Epsilon I
still make
profit so perfect competition is not
driven profits to zero through firm
entry perfect competition driven profits
to Zero by selling the barrier to
entry there's a barrier to entry here
which is a government restriction that
covers the number of firms n two we're
now putting a market on that we're
letting firms buy their way in how much
will they pay they'll pay up to the
profits they'd make by buying their way
in so in
fact who is better off here it's not the
taxi cab
drivers they still make zero profit
who's better off it's The Medallion
owners and who are they a bunch of
randos who have happen to get issued the
medallions in 1930 whatever when the
government set up this
system taxing medallions are incredibly
valuable so for example um um in uh San
Francisco you have to pay 12,000 you had
to pay $122,000 a year to rent a taxi
cab
medallion in Boston it was
$400,000 to buy taxi money so those taxi
cab drivers who are not rich guys who
are driving you from place to place well
you were kids driving your parents from
place to place okay they're paying
$400,000 just for the right to drive you
around okay and the estimated lost
consumer surplus was about $2 billion
there was about $2 billion in Lost
consumer
surplus partly it was inefficiency and
partly was just going to these Medallion
owners okay now why do we have
restrictions like this well at one level
it makes sense you don't want any Schmo
d driving around giving people
rides it could be dangerous they could
be a bad driver they could be a criminal
so it makes sense to have some
regulations on this indeed this is an
example of something we call
occupational
licensing which is a set of restrictions
that government's put in place to make
sure people who say they're doing X can
legitimately do
X this makes a lot of sense for example
for
doctors we don't want a world of Dr
Nicks okay question how many of you are
well vered in The Simpsons
okay this is utterly
depressing okay that is the single most
important cultural accomplishment of the
America in the last 50 years as The
Simpsons you guys should absolutely be
watching and absorbing that for all the
lessons you need to know about life okay
Dr Nick is the terrible Nick doctor on
The Simpsons okay he's unqualified he
went to Hollywood upstairs medical
school okay he's to totally
unqualified um and uh that's what
happened we have some licensing saying
doctors have to meet certain conditions
have to get recertified we have to
license to drive a car that's not an
occupation Etc so the idea is
occupational licensing makes sense to
some
extent but having a random limit on the
number of cab drivers is not the way to
do it you should have some licensing
process okay so it's sort of makes
sense okay
now to have some licensing on the other
hand what you're doing is you're
essentially taking $2
billion and giving it to Rich Medallion
owners however we have good news bad
news for The Medallion King good news
for consumers which is
Uber Uber essentially turned the drive
Market into a perfectly competitive
market they said fine if you limit the
number of cabs to N2 we're going to have
a whole set of drivers do the same
things cabs can do with free
entry what happened well what happened
was taxi drivers and Uber drivers earned
a little bit less but Medallion owners
got smacked the value tax cap M fell by
90% why because profits went down
essentially with free entry we moved
from P2 back towards
P1 profits fell and therefore they
couldn't sell medallions for as much so
yes cab drivers lost a little bit and
they about Uber but the truth is
the big losers were Medallion owners who
were not a sympathetic crowd the big
winners were consumers you have no idea
how much life you guys are just spoiled
by life with Uber And We complain about
it it's got problems but you have no
idea how much better it is how much
cheaper is to get from place to place
how much easier is to get from place to
place than we had these limited numbers
of
taxis okay so this a classic example of
a market
Innovation increasing both Total Surplus
and consumer surplus total Surplus is
increased because we moved back towards
price P1 consumer surplus increased
because price has
fallen producer Surplus actually isn't
down that much because the producers the
cab drivers weren't actually making that
much money anyway the real losers of
Medallion
owners okay questions about
that so this is an example of how we use
the normative tools of
economics how we use the normative tools
of Economics to analy these kinds of
interventions let me end with one more
example which is a really fun one about
how we can actually use markets to help
the poor and the example comes from food
banks food banks organizations that give
away poor food to needy
people feeding America is one of the
largest food banks in the country has
food banks all over the country and they
were trying to decide how to send the
right food to the right
places well the market does this
naturally places where they want
hamburgers the price is high there
hamburgers there the price Falls places
where there's a lot of vegetarians price
hamburger isn't as high the market does
that naturally but feeding America it
wasn't a market-based organization the
whole idea was to get this food away
from free for free so they ended up
doing things like sending potatoes to
Idaho which is the home of potato
growing which was pretty
inefficient and they were trying to
think how can we more efficiently
allocate the food to the needy so what
they did is they made up a virtual
Market they said to each Food Bank we're
giving you a
budget and we're going to let there be a
market across all the food stuffs and
you guys can bid for what you want and
they'll be pric
but none of it's real it's not real
money okay it's all going to be free but
we are going to if if you're someone who
really wants potatoes you will bid the
most for potatoes and use up more of
your fake points to get potatoes and
that will allocate the potatoes the
folks who really needing the most so
essentially they created a scarcity
where there was none before there was no
scarcity you just said I want potatoes
you got potatoes until they ran out of
potatoes and didn't necessarily go to
the place that need potatoes the most
now the place that needs potatoes the
most will bid the most for potatoes and
the potatoes will be allocated there so
that's an example how you can use the
price mechanism while still helping the
poor you can use the price mechanism to
make sure the right Goods get allocated
to the right places but still have
things end up being
free okay so let me stop with that um
and we will come back next week and
we'll turn to the case of Monopoly