Hi everyone. Um it's so wonderful to be
here. As you know, my name is Jules. I
am a rising second year here at MIT
Sloan. Um just a little bit about
myself. Uh pre-loan I worked in the tech
industry um for about six years. And
then my summer internship uh that I just
finished up last Friday was um as a
product manager on the Adobe risk
platform team at Adobe. Um I'm really
excited to be here today to kind of
introduce our um our panelists. Um and
we have three panelists here tonight. Um
Dragana, Andres, and Janisha. So I will
allow them to introduce themselves um as
they please.
>> Great. I guess we can start with me.
Thank you, Jules. Um so my name is
Draana. Hi everyone. Really nice to to
meet you and to see um so many people.
Um I'm an MBA uh 2023 gradu. So, I
graduated in 2023, which is basically
the last generation of pre um large
large language models um in the
education
generation. So, jokes aside, yeah,
that's um that's me. I'm originally from
Bosnia. Um and after my MBA graduation,
I uh joined Amazon as a senior technical
product manager. I work on the Kindle
team or Kindle Direct Publishing team uh
more specifically. Um yeah, that's about
me. currently live in Seattle. So, yeah.
>> Cool. Uh, so I guess my turn. Uh, my
name is Andreas from Moropa. I MBA 2024,
so graduated last May, which is crazy to
think about that. A whole year just flew
by. Uh, and I'm currently working as a
development manager at Lynx Ventures in
Richmond, Virginia. Um I
have a background as an architectural
designer. So I did that in Mexico for
two years uh doing some groundup
developments industrial and uh multif
family stuff and then worked in New York
as a designer for more
uh for about three years before starting
at Sloan in 22.
>> Hi everyone, my name is Jennisha Cole.
Uh I graduated from the Sloan Fellows
program in 2023. I'm originally from
Singapore. Um and before Sloan I was I
spent about 10 years in the health tech
industry. Uh my background is in
engineering. So I I did you know the
gamut of things um from product
development all the way to
commercialization of new devices. And
right after Sloan I kind of switched my
role into a more commercial role leading
market expansion in the US. and more
recently I've joined the life insurance
industry as a program manager leading
digital transformation in marketing
analytics. Yeah, so very excited to be
here today. Thank you all.
Thank you to our panelists for
introducing themselves. So we'll just uh
jump right in and get started with some
highle questions first. Um and these
questions will just be open to all
panelists or any all of the questions
will be open to all panelists and um
they can choose to decide if they want
to share. So we'll kind of start off a
little bit easy um and ask our panelists
why did they choose uh MIT Sloan.
>> I can I can start with this one. Uh so I
it's funny because uh I think come
coming from an architecture background
it's not it's kind of like a
non-traditional
background to come into an MBA and I was
talking to people at my my previous job
and somebody recommended MIT as a place
that is kind of like very innovative and
diverse and uh just because of the the
amount of different programs and also
how it is housed in the larger MIT um
campus.
And that's kind of when I started uh
engaging with the program and and
talking to some people. So that's kind
of like what ultimately ended up driving
my decision to come to Sloan that uh met
so many people from different
backgrounds. It's a very welcoming
atmosphere and I think the work that I
was doing kind of was leaning on leaning
on a lot of the innovation uh work and
that found I found that very interesting
uh from the beginning at Sloan just
being at the cutting edge of of
technology and seeing that h kind of
happen all around me.
>> Thank you so much Andreas. Um does
anybody else want to kind of share their
experience on why we loan?
I'm happy to yeah share a little bit as
well. I think there's some similarities
with Andreas uh on this for me. Um so my
background is prior to Sloan I was
working in uh Kenya leading um like a
software uh sort of like platform
development uh for like a distributed
forestry company. Um so I was already in
kind of like tech tech and product
management and startup world and I was
kind of like self-taught on all of those
things. Um, and what I wanted out of a
business school I think were like a
strong community at the intersection of
sort of like technology both like in the
MBA program and also like outside
obviously which MIT is um essentially
that and then uh like a strong
entrepreneurship ecosystem and
entrepreneurship resources um and then
that that component of innovation as
well that that Andress was mentioning.
So that was the big reason why I
initially wanted to join MIT Sloan. And
then after I um got accepted and started
talking to students, I just really
thought that Sloanies were like really
just really friendly collaborative group
of people. Everyone I met was like so
nice to me and wanted to engage and so
that definitely also helped make that
choice or solidify that choice.
>> Yeah. So for me, I have a slightly
different perspective. So, by the time I
decided that I wanted to do my MBA, I've
already had almost a decade of work
experience my pocket. So, the the
thought about doing a two-year um MBA
program was a little intimidating given,
you know, my experience and also my age.
Um so, I was just looking at, you know,
programs out there that really could fit
my needs in terms of what I want to get
out of MBA program, which is to level up
my business skills, grow my career in
the health tech sector. And as I was
looking around, I wanted something that
is more is globally recognized and also
yet provided that immersive MBA
experience um that a regular to a
regular MBA student would go through. So
Sloan really fit that bucket with the
Sloan Fellows program and I'm happy to
chat more about that as well. It's it's
the perfect balance between an executive
MBA program and a regular MBA for those
with like 10 to 15 years of experience
just like what Terrell has mentioned.
Yeah.
Thanks everyone. Um the next question
we'll have here is kind of diving into
um how were you involved in the Sloan
community while you're at MIT? I think
like the first club that I joined at
Sloan um not that community is
necessarily only that but that was kind
of like the first thing was the first
generation low-income club. Um and um
there was kind of a like I'm also like a
first generation college graduate. So
that was kind of like um a community
that first really welcomed me and helped
me kind of like figure out okay so
here's how how everything works how you
know business school works how you pick
your classes which ones are good ones
how do you look for internships so like
just a lot of that support and also kind
of just like general social support so
that was the first kind of community
that I joined there's many others and um
I think following that first semester I
then joined the leadership um kind of uh
of of the of the first gen low-inccome
club and so on and so I was like pre
co-president um with some of my uh
colleagues and and good friends uh that
was one and also because I lived in
Kenya for um you know six years prior to
Sloan I also joined the Africa business
club and I was really excited just about
like all of the kind of students who
were in that club and all of the
experiences they were bringing from the
continent from all over many different
countries and organizing also the Africa
Innovate Conference which just like a
huge uh really like great event that
brings like so many kind of like
innovators, entrepreneurs, really great
people from the continent. So, it was
just really fun to help like organize
that and and and be part of it. Um those
were just like two kind of highlights.
Um there's many others, but yeah, I'll
let someone else chime in as well.
>> Yeah. So for myself um there like like
what Draana has mentioned there are so
many clubs you can choose from it's very
diverse um and there you know clubs that
cater to different interests so for me
myself uh coming from a health tech
background I also did immerse myself
more in the healthcare club as well as
um joining a hackathon called MIT
hacking medicine as a community member
so that's how um I got to you know
immerse myself more more with the
networks that are within MIT itself. Um
and at the same time there were also
class level communities. So there was a
culture club within um my program itself
where we actually had a cultural night
um to expose stu um classmates to
different cuisines and c traditions uh
from their home country. So that was a
really enjoyable experience for me.
Yeah.
Um, for for me, uh, I think I
I as as Draana Janisa mentioned already
that there's there's so many clubs,
there's so many groups and I I was one
of those that signed up to a lot of them
first semester and kind of started
getting more and more involved in some
of them as like as the time went by. But
so I kind of like was more active on the
Latin American business club, the
Hispanic Business Club, and the real
estate club. Um they
the real estate club primarily because
that's where my career interests were.
Uh and given and given my background in
architecture is also kind of it's a it's
an interesting club that it kind of like
lives within two house within two
different programs. lives under Sloan,
but there's also a lot of people that
you meet from outside uh across the
school, outside of the outside of the
Sloan group and got to meet a lot of uh
cool Sloan through that too and got
really close and also Lat Latin American
business club and Hispanic Business
Club. Uh I think that's where I met a
lot of a a lot of friends that I still
kept in touch with and
uh also
all the all the events that they plan. I
kind of become like a really really
great way to kind of build community and
as Braana mentioned it's kind of like
one of the most it's it's a really
welcoming community that I think uh
helped me pretty much through all all
anything that I would run into any
issues with recruiting or any issues
with classwork or just like personal
stuff. So I think those two affinity
clubs became really important to me. Uh
and I think the ocean the ocean
structure of the MBA program was also
very uh helpful. Uh I think was like a
great way to kind of start meeting a lot
of people and like helping helping
organize some of those community events
and those like Christmas uh social
gatherings and that kind of stuff was
like I think a great part of my
experience that I really enjoyed helping
out with.
>> Thanks everyone. Andres, I wanted to
kind of tap in what you said just to
share with our prospective students what
oceans are. Could you give um just a
highle overview of what an ocean is?
>> Yeah, of course. So, for the general MBA
program, uh the class size is about 4
and some change 440 420 not entirely
sure what the number is, but that's the
larger class. And then for the first
year, for the first semester,
you're you're you're in the you're
organized into subgroups called oceans
that are kind of like about maybe 60 70
people. And they kind of really become
like a really a really close-knit group
within the larger the larger 400 and
something uh people in the program that
you take every class together. uh you
you have like one elective that you can
do the first semester, but but you
really kind of share the classroom day
in day out and you're you have a bunch
of different events and you have your
and within the 60 people group, you also
have your core team. So it's it's kind
of like an a way to create community the
first semester especially for
uh
especially it was really
I guess it was I guess it was really
important for me because it coming into
such a large program with so many new
things it can it can be an overwhelming
place but the group of 70 pe 67 people
that I was with in day in day out in the
classes it became like a support group
for everybody. So, everybody was able to
kind of share experiences and and trade
notes and and kind of help each other
out in a very meaningful way just
because of the the size that we were at
and seeing each other so often.
>> And thank you so much for that. Um, so
we'll kind of dive into more specific
FGLI questions or first generation
lowincome questions um to give the
students uh or the perspective students
here a little bit more insight into what
it's like to be um a Fly student. So,
uh, we'll kind of start off with as a
first generation college graduate, are
there any specific, uh, scholarships or
support programs that they should know
of
and that you've utilized.
There were definitely like if I remember
correct so I I've forgotten a little bit
because it's been a while now since I
graduated. Well, a while three I guess
three years almost. Um there were
definitely like some smaller funds I
remember um available for students. I
think um for example like if you're
experiencing financial hardship there
were some some funds that you could tap
into. I think uh also some for sort of
like some of the events cuz some of the
events are kind of like paid events that
that um like as part of the MBA program
that you could like draw support from
for for that specifically. Um, yeah, I
think I would, yeah, I want to maybe
sort of like tag someone else who's been
there more recently to tell us about it,
but there's definitely been been um some
some kind of like sort of like smaller
funds and resources that that we've been
able to tap into during my time there.
uh well okay I don't know about the and
have used but piece of it but one that I
didn't use but I wish I would have used
and it's not a loan program but I know
that a lot of people did the to the togo
fellowships especi uh for people that
are kind of like um I think it's a
little more finance leaning uh people
with an interest in finance I didn't do
it but I know a lot of people that did
it and I know that it's a great resource
and and I didn't know and I didn't know
about it when I started the MBA. uh
within Sloan uh the I think the student
groups can actually become a really good
resource because the the
yeah I think I think this is the I'm
talking about what Terl is mentioning in
the comments that some of the some of
the activities that we would do uh this
with this with the Hispanic business
club or with the FLI group uh I remember
there's some there's some travel
opportunities ities. There's some uh um
some travel opportunities that
student life office or the student
groups can kind of like apply for. And
in that way, I participated in some of
those activities that are off campus or
that might that I know that that's kind
of like a big thing and can and can be a
financial hardship. Uh
but I think
I think one one thing that I that I that
I would like to mention though is that
it always felt like when there was any
kind of need uh the student the program
program managers and student life office
it's was always within reach and super
approachable. So any kind of uh
any kind of question would be would they
would always be open to kind of like
have like a very holistic and
comprehensive answer that
would pretty much solve what you're
looking for. And so I did reach out the
to the program manager a few times and
was able to kind of get some guidance
and find the support that I needed in or
the programs that I was looking for.
>> Yeah. So for um for me I did not um rely
a lot on like financial assistance or
maybe because like like what Andrea say
I haven't done much research on that but
I've heard about external funding
sources. Um so similar to go there's
also the forte women MBA fund that you
can look into. I I do know a couple of
classmates who actually got a small
fellowship out of that. Um so I believe
there are external um bodies that you
can actually refer to as well. Yeah. And
to echo what Andre um mentioned, you can
always reach out to the student life
office and they will offer you avenues
to look for um funds whenever you need
them.
>> Thank you, Janisha. Our next question
here is for students who come from
non-traditional or low-income
backgrounds, what specific resources or
networks at Sloan have been the most
impactful in building confidence and
access to leadership roles?
I think for me and I definitely come
from a little bit of a like
non-traditional background as in sort of
emerging markets startup um tech space
um coming into MBA and wanting to
transition into sort of like a big tech
product management uh and kind of
leadership. I think um I definitely did
rely on my sort of
colleagues and friends from the the fly
club. Um so a lot of them especially the
second years um as we came in
you'll always find people who are like
interested in the same things that
you're interested in. And that's the
thing with Sloan like you'll always find
people who have like made the pivot that
you're trying to make or have done
something that you're trying to do. And
so like what's great about that is you
just sort of like if you talk about like
what you want um then the people the
people and the help somehow finds you.
So definitely for me the fly club
members have been helpful for example
for things like interviewing when I was
like applying to Amazon like applying
for these uh big tech companies applying
for leadership roles um then in in in
other clubs as well like other business
clubs at Sloan. So those are very
helpful. And then also just like other
kind of like
like career focused clubs um where um
there will be a lot of different
programs that will help you like
especially not knowing like you want to
go into consulting you don't know how
that works like what is it that you need
to do you'll have career office that
helps you do that and then you'll have
like the consulting club for me it was
like the product management club I had
no idea what like product management
cases were and like how to do that so
there was a lot of folks who helped me
both from the fly club and the product
management club and the career office to
kind of like get there um and like get
my internship and get my full-time role
down the line. So definitely I think
just like broader Sloan community I
would say and then your specific
career interest and affinity groups are
definitely helpful with that navigating
that process.
So I just want to add that um because
Sloan is so diverse
what I what my personally what I feel
social economic status is just one part
of it there. So what really helped me is
taking up some of the leadership classes
where you get to understand yourself
better, understand your strength,
understand the value that you can convey
um whenever you you come to a group. And
I think MIT Sloan just has a neck for
choosing people. I would say at least
80% of the people um who are humbed
and willing to learn from people from
various backgrounds. So I never felt
like coming from a you know fli was a
was something that I had to constantly
remind myself about. Um and there were
and like Jordan say there are avenues to
build confidence by taking up leadership
positions in clubs and definitely fli is
not a qualifying factor in that. It's
more like what value you want to bring
to the table and what you want to learn
out of the experience. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I I agree with what Denisha and
Draa have said for sure. I think the
diverse the diverse community and
uh
being able to being able to talk to
anybody about what you want and then if
you don't know the if you don't know the
person across the room then that person
that you just talked to will introduce
you and they'll be able to guide you
better into what you're into what you're
starting to explore if you're actually
interested in. I I think it just becomes
I think the community, the people that
are in the room with you, it's like such
an open place that you can ask questions
that you might not be able to ask
anywhere else. And them those answers
being so readily available. Maybe
somebody maybe the person that's sitting
next to you but just didn't know, you
just didn't happen to talk to them, but
somebody else makes that introduction. I
think those social connections are
are extremely uh valuable in empowering
you and trying to in make
sure that you're getting to the place
that you that you want to be. Uh whether
that is uh something in leadership in a
club or or looking for or talking to the
right person at at some com at some
company that you're interested in in
recruiting for. Uh, and also I think the
the question is uh maybe what's on
campus and like what's in Sloan, but I
think when you're when you're Sloan and
you're a student, being able to talk to
the alumni, it's a great resource. I
think I I talked to a lot of alumni just
trying to also figure out what is it
that I wanted to do and all these
different avenues that I never heard of
before. uh and that and just having
those informal conversations with any
with people that people that are open to
talk to you because you're a student was
extremely valuable and really helpful
for me with some as for as somebody that
uh from a nontraditional background and
also uh first generation college grad
and also grad grad. So I think
everybody's being so open and talking
and and willing to help you. I think
it's extremely valuable.
Thank you everyone. Um so the next
question I'm going to ask is more about
uh the financial trade-offs. Um
specifically for fly students uh an MBA
can be really costly and so uh what
financial trade-offs did you face during
the program and how did you navigate
them without compromising your
experience or contributions or rather
ambitions?
I can talk, but I also feel like I
always talk first. I don't know. Do I
That's fine. Yeah. Cool. Um, I think
like, yeah, I think that it is for
coming from like a firstgen low-inccome
background, it's almost like when you
look at that, like when you're on the
outside and you're applying and you're
like looking at that price tag and
you're figuring out like how do I even
do this, right? Um, it is a serious
investment. Um, and that's just
something to acknowledge, right? It is a
serious. So like I'll just talk a little
bit about like the way I did it, right?
So like one thing that I did even as I
was sort of like applying I was
literally putting in the spreadsheet.
All right, like what is this investment
that I would have to make like maybe
what's the expected scholarship that I
could get, right? Like that could be a
range. So you kind of like apply you
apply and then you may get a merit-based
scholarship. I got some but not all of
it of course. Maybe there's some
external scholarships. maybe there's
some personal savings, right? And then
maybe there's some financing and loans
that you're gonna like take out um to be
able to like make this work for you. So,
I literally made a spreadsheet with all
of this information and then kind of
like put all right like leaving business
school and this was one of the
tradeoffs, right? Like leaving business
school is like for me to like make sure
I can like pay back for this for like
this education and everything like what
do I have to do? And I was like all
right well I don't think I can
temporarily go back to like you know my
social impact work that I did in in
Kenya at this rate but then again and so
that is a tradeoff right but then again
I can you know like the job that I would
be getting in product in the states
would definitely like according to my
spreadsheet within the next five years
like help me get where I want to get
right so it's a little bit and I'm not
saying like everyone needs to do this
kind of like long-term planning right
but it is a little bit understanding
like all right so maybe with this
investment I am going to have c certain
potential short-term career tradeoffs
but also potential like long-term career
gains so I think that's kind of like my
personal experience at the moment I'm
having like a I was having a short-term
potential tradeoff but then kind of a
long-term gain of like the experience
that I'm getting um and kind of like
where I'm on track to like sort of like
meet some of my other financial goals
and yeah and I think also during the MBA
program like budgeting is the thing,
right? So, like there's going to be a
lot of things that you want to do. Like
there's going to be a lot of like trips
and events and things. So, some of the
trade-offs is like, well, you have to
pick and choose, right? If you can't
like, you know, afford all of them or
pay for all of them, like you pick the
ones that you want to do most, you pick
the ones that have some like financial
assistance that comes with it, you pick.
So, it is you can still have like a very
good experience and very full experience
with some of this sort of like careful
budgeting and short and long-term
trade-offs that you make and still get
to your goals. Uh, it's just kind of
being aware that that it is a big
investment and it requires some kind of
like um I guess more careful planning.
>> Yeah. So for myself, I did take a loan
and very much like what Draguna said, I
also did a spreadsheet to measure what's
the the MPV of the education, right? Uh
and I have to say it's it's kind of hard
to quantify, especially in uncertain
economic times, but one thing I know for
sure is the intrinsic value of the MBA
is going to take me further in my career
and even even my life experiences. So I
constantly kept that in mind. And just
to add on um to like you know looking
for funds um when you are in school um
besides like external scholarships um
you know financial aids there are also
ways you can earn money while you're on
campus for instance doing an internship
you can be a teaching assistant you can
be a research assistant and those do
cover some of your tuition as well um if
you can and if if those fit into your
schedule it can be a pretty fulfilling
experience when where you get to work
with like the professors and students at
the same time. Yeah. So, that's
something to to consider as well, like
the flexibility of getting your um
studies funded while still having their
full-time experience. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I'll say that uh maybe my
approach wasn't as structured as Doranas
or Denisia.
Uh but I
I mean I think that's well that was one
of the takeaways from being in so that I
can actually be more structured about
those things now. Uh I think for sure
though I I there there was
it was a mix a mix of different sources
that that kind of allowed me to do this.
And I also definitely saw it as a
long-term investment in in myself and my
growth and my and my financial goals for
the long term. uh just because of the
place that I went to before uh it was it
was it was clearly not heading in the
direction that I wanted to be uh in the
long term. So I think it was a
combination of a combination of scholars
from from Sloan that uh allowed me to
allowed me to have a little bit of a
little bit of to make the decision to
begin with and also a little bit of
loans but also being a little bit
strategic on the types of things that I
wanted to do while in loan like it like
Draana mentioned there is there is a lot
of trips there is a lot of events there
is a lot of these things but
uh there's
Not
there's there's things that are
definitely that you can participate and
see them as kind of like helping helping
you get the full experience when
I get I guess like maybe like the way
that I was strategic about picking the
things that I was doing is just having
kind of like a well diversified
uh things list of things that I was
doing when you can just kind of you can
go to certain certain events, you can
go, you can do certain trips, but uh at
least being able to say that that I was
that I did certain amount of things once
and and fully being present and and
being able to engage with the with the
people that were there or with the or
with the professionals from outside of
Zone that I was speaking to for a
certain event outside of the city or
stuff like that. Uh, I think I I was I
feel like I was able to get a a full
experience by just
picking from a wide range of different
opportunities instead of uh repeating
them over and over. Um, so and I I think
I think that kind of like that's the
perspective that I took more than
anything.
Okay, we'll have our last question um
from me as moderator and then we'll dive
into the Q&A uh open Q&A from the
audience. Um so the last question here
um is how does Sloan intentionally build
a sense of belonging and community among
students from different backgrounds?
Uh, I can jump in on this one. Um, I
think I I don't know if I did a great
job earlier about explaining what the
oceans are, but I think the oceans was
kind of like the high one of the
highlights for me from the beginning
because like it was such a it was such
an impactful way of building community
from the get-go that you have this team
of 60 people where you have an offsite
the first week of the of the year where
you get to meet them and have like very
you get to you get to know them very
personally and you're kind of encouraged
to be vulnerable with them and have kind
of meaningful conversations that I think
that was my my first uh aha moment of
being like okay everybody everybody here
is interested in in seeing you grow and
that you can actually have very
meaningful interactions and have very
um you can create kind of very
meaningful communities as long as you're
as long as you're engaging and you want
and you and you want to build the same
community. I think the the the first
touch point of the oceans was like what
really impactful for me and then that
kind of set the tone for everything else
afterwards. Uh being able to also carry
that kind of sense of community and
openness and willingness to willingness
to share what you what you know to the
people around you and also uh being able
to remain open and vulnerable and ask
the questions that you that you want to
that you want to hear people's
experiences of. Um so that's that's kind
of like what I what impacted me the
most.
I can speak to the Sloan Fellows
program. So the Sloan Fellows program
typically has about like hundred um to
120 students. So it's a good size where
you get to know everyone and I think
Sloan has the Sloan um program office
has done a great job in ensuring that um
every one or two months there are
bonding you know events u activities
that happen. So for instance in fall you
have like apple picking because it's app
apple season. Um towards the end of the
year we have like a trip to like you
know somewhere nearby. So for my year we
did get caught. Um so depending on on
what the program offices plan out and at
the same time I did mention throughout
the year as well that there are
different um committees that were formed
within the program itself. So I did
mention one about the cultural community
uh committee where we had a night where
you know we had different cultures and
um an event where we we brought food and
you know we share different cultures and
traditions. That's just one example. We
also have another event where we
actually get together every week to
share our life stories in a very
intimate setting. So that's how we kind
of build bond with each other and it
doesn't matter like where you're from,
what what have you experienc what kind
of experiences you you've been through
because you will realize that everyone
brings um you know their own unique set
of lens and experiences to the table.
Yeah,
>> thank you um for answering these
questions. We're going to transition
into the live Q&A uh portion of this
session. So I'm just going to very
similarly I'm going to ask the question
and then our panelists can um answer
them as they choose. So the first
question here um is as a first
generation student I find myself coming
across a lot of surprises. What would
you recommend I do before starting an
MBA program to limit the untold
distractions when starting my program?
It's it's a it's a good question. I
think it's it's difficult and I say this
because I was definitely the person in
the MBA program who kind of came in and
came in without doing much preparation
and then was in at the same time was
interested in everything and wanted to
try like all the different kinds of
classes ranging from you know like what
we talked about before like I want to do
entrepreneurship but also I'm interested
in some of this like enterprise
management stuff and I'm interested in
you know all kinds of different things
that I wanted to try. Um, so there was
definitely a lot of like I don't want to
say not necessarily distractions but
just a lot of different interests. What
I think does help maybe and what I would
do differently coming in is
maybe like thinking ahead every
semester. Okay, so what are like my top
three to four kind of goals for this
semester, right? And that could be
something like you know I want to build
like community in this type of way or I
really want to like land this internship
or I really want to learn about this
specific area or like this specific kind
of thing that fascinates me or I want to
you know so setting some goals is good
and helpful and I think that gives you
some direction because you come into the
program and there's a million things
that are happening right from the
classes that you can choose the people
that you can meet the clubs that you can
participate in the events there's so
much, right? So, trying to figure out
like how you navigate that, it helps to
to set some personal goals. But I think
it also helps to be a little bit like
open-minded in a sense of like, okay,
not just like I'm going to follow these
goals and that's it. Like leave a little
bit of space for exploration of like
things that may surprise you and that
you may find. So like I think I think
that that combination of mostly goals
and some openness for new things would
have helped me maybe come in a little
bit more focused.
Yeah.
Um just to get through a few more of
these questions. how we're going to move
forward is I'll ask uh one of the
questions and then we'll have one of the
panelists answer and then we'll just
jump into the next question just so we
can um get more of the questions going.
Um so this next question here is um
Olivia a guest can um is asking can you
talk about the specific opportunities
that you had to gain exposure to for
tech careers and opportunities on
campus?
I guess this should be me. I don't know
if um Andreas or Yeah, I guess. Um I
think for specifically for tech careers,
it's pretty great honestly. Um product
management club and technology club were
really helpful. Um I think also um
career office um at Sloan does help. So
like meeting with them early, talking
about your goals and and things you want
to do and them directing you to the
right resources that helps a lot.
There's a lot of I think alumni and
secondyear students that have already
for example you know maybe landed
internships or jobs at the places where
you want to go. Um so talking to them
helps um as well and uh and there's also
just like recruiting events on campus
there at least used to be in 2023 I
think probably still now. So, um there's
kind of like these like organized like
recruiting events, info sessions, um in
sort of like one-on-one or interviews or
group chats with different alumni. Uh
these companies do want to recruit Sloan
students. So, that definitely does help.
So, you can just kind of like plug
yourself into some of those systems. Um
just making sure that you do it early
on. And I think that's like like sort of
big tech especially uh comes in pretty
early like first semester and like early
second semester and then some of the
more kind of like startup stuff is like
throughout throughout the first and
second year. Um so yeah,
>> thank you Dana. Um so I'm actually going
to mash these next two questions because
I think they're very similar. Um but
the MBA involves quite a lot of travel
networking networking. Um, and so when
you think about how to budget or
finance, how do you structure your
financing plan? Um, and how does it um
how does this impact or come from what
is it like coming from a lowinccome
background financing these sort of
things?
Um, I think kind of like similar to what
I was um alluding to earlier that
like my like the budget plan that that I
did was kind of being a little strategic
and knowing from the get-go that I would
have I would allocate from the beginning
like a set amount for all these trips
and like all these uh events and kind of
like that's that's my budget And
really, I kind of frontloaded it because
I knew that just kind of coming in the
into the first year, get get as many of
these experiences in to like meet as
many people as possible and kind of and
the second year spending it a little
more kind of in the in the Cambridge
area events and that kind of stuff. and
and I think that's that's kind of like
the approach that I took uh with like
with the resources that I had at the
moment, the loans and scholarship and
savings combination of all the all the
above. And I think it's
it's uh it's a relatively common
approach. I'd say I found that a lot of
people I found that a lot of people in
my year kind of were feeling the same
way that I did and that there's a lot of
there's a lot of things happening and
you want to do all and you want to do
all of it and ends up being that the
first year you end up doing as much as
you can and and then second year kind of
becomes like this uh fostering
relationship relationship that you've
found and people that you met over the
first year and I think that's kind of
how I handled it just kind of very being
a little bit strict on like what my
spending would be for the first year and
then setting that that budget up front
and trying my best to manage that, I
guess. But being I guess like being
clear and honest with what you are
actually willing to to do and take and
and what you will be getting out of the
events.
>> Thank you, Andres. Um this second
question I do want to bounce to um
Janisha and also one other MBA student.
Um so this question is um if at all how
does the overall MBA or SFMBA experience
differ as a FGLI student um for those
compared to for those who do notident
compared to those who do not identify as
a FGLI student and does our background
affect much when socializing in general?
So Janisha, I'll have you start.
>> So um I think this goes back to one of
the questions you've asked earlier about
con building confidence. Um so I I'd
like to iterate again that you know it's
always good to understand the value that
you're bringing to the table. It's not
always measured in like economic terms.
So I think uh for me what helped was um
to start with leadership classes earlier
in the program. So for the Stone Fellows
program, you actually do get um I would
say a full term of leadership classes
paired with an executive coach. So this
is where you can work through some of
your li self-limiting beliefs about you
know being um you know FGLI
um and and basically seeing the world
differently as the what you can bring
from your unique experiences. Um and I
think the second point about you know
what Andrea's actually Andreas actually
mentioned again um there are certainly
some events where you might feel
excluded from just because of the cost
of the event right like for instance if
you're going skiing in Colorado you
might not want to sp like splurge
splurge on that trip alone. So that's
where you can you you can actually ask
yourself like do you want really want to
go on that trip or can you actually
organize somewhere that's nearer for
instance uh with a smaller group of
friends you see. So you can always it's
instead of like following what others
are doing you can always initiate your
own events as well. So I would say but
the biggest part for me again I think
back to what I just mentioned earlier on
is working through the self-limiting
beliefs right and understanding the
value that you're bringing to the table.
Yeah.
>> Thank you, Janisha.
Anyone else like to answer this question
as an MBA student full-time?
>> Uh, I can I can talk a little bit about
uh that. I mean, I think I think for for
me, um, the education aspect of it was
kind of like
it was tough at times to deal with that.
Um, it, if I'm being honest, it did feel
it did feel at times that that there
there was a lot of people that had all
this knowledge and kind of like had all
these this certain kind of like
understanding of how industries work. or
how like certain recruiting practices
work. And I and I came in pretty I guess
unprepared for that. Uh and
and uh it was kind of like tough to me
not to not kind of go to go to my get
into my head and be like, oh because
these are things that people like would
normally talk about during a dinner
dinner dinner dinner time conversation
and I never have those conversations.
But but going back to like what I was
saying that everybody But everybody is
very open about their experiences. So
it's uh kind of acknowledging that these
different experiences that everybody has
and and and
some of the leadership classes
definitely like help on like building
the confidence to ask the right
questions and and everybody and nobody
will I will tell tell you no in that
regard that everybody's open and will
kind of like talk talk to you and teach
you and and knowledge share in a way
that is uh that is honest and and
humble. Um, but it but kind of like
getting over that hump of of like we're
all here to learn. We're all here in a
community to support each other and we
all bring different values. I think that
was like something that I struggled with
at the beginning, but over time kind of
got better at at at acknowledging that
that we do all bring different values to
the table and that sure I might not know
I I might not know how different uh
corners of the financial industry work
over or have evolved over time, but uh
but there's other things that I bring to
and we can talk about those things and
the community itself, I think it's what
like helped me get over up.
>> Thank you, Andres. And so this last
question here I will have open um to all
of our panelists. Um and we will be um
this is our last question. So um the
question is what are some examples of
activities organized by the fly club and
how does it differ from other clubs
given that that many of them seem to
have very similar events and activities?
I'll talk quickly about just like um in
my experience I think in like yeah when
when we were um like 2022 2023 I think
the biggest differentiator of fly club
events versus like other events that I
had I think were that fly club or FGLI I
think now um they're more focused I
think on building community I think you
will have a a lot of like different
types of events for example um during
the MBA. So you'll have more like career
focused events. You'll have just like
fun party stuff that like friends do
which is also like totally fine and
totally great to do but I think the fly
events were more kind of like bringing
us all together kind of acknowledging
some of these things that I think both
Andreas and Janisha were talking about
earlier that we do have different
experience that often times we come in
and we are like what is going on? I did
not know what an MBA is before I started
thinking about applying for an MBA,
right? And some of our, you know,
colleagues or some of our like
classmates that are also like just
really awesome, they knew that they were
going to do an MBA like 5 years ago,
right? And were fully prepared. And
that's awesome to have someone who's had
that experience, right? Like I think
bringing us together, acknowledging that
like yeah, we maybe face a particular
experience and we all share that
experience and like how can we help each
other like navigate through that. That
was kind of the cornerstone of a lot of
these events um that we did like kind of
coming together maybe going to like a
trip in New England somewhere together
or like you know having like a Christmas
dinner party or a Thanksgiving dinner
party because like nobody's traveling
outside um of like Boston that year or
whatever. So I think that was that and
honestly many of my close friendships
came out of that group too. Um so that's
that's one big thing and then really
helping you like navigate that MBA
experience from from that FGLI point of
view has been really helpful.
>> Does anybody else want to share?
Yeah, I I mean I guess I guess just like
I would like to emphasize Draana's point
that like yeah I think it became a it
became a community where there's like
the mutual understanding of a shared
background and and that it is
acknowledged. It kind of it did it did
feel like it was a place I guess or a
safe safe space in that way that it's
easy to acknowledge and have tougher
conversations
uh because of a shared experience in a
way. Uh and and same thing like from
FGLI I I there's friends that I still
keep in touch with and like that I kind
of became friends with like through the
program and like became
uh great people to bounce off ideas and
just kind of
put my perspect put my experience into a
larger perspective of like what what's
going on around me because it is a