uh welcome everyone and thank you for
coming we have a great turnout today for
the first Rene Salazar speaker series
from the Bro Institute for January
2025 and the Rene Salazar speaker series
is from the latinx group and part of
Shades abroad so the latinx at Broad has
a mission of building Community among
latinx brodies and empowering members of
the latinx community and building a
community Network and allies for people
from Latin America and the Caribbean
so the r solar speaker series program
wants to highlight latinx and diverse
researchers within and outside the broad
Institute Foster collaboration allow
visibility and role models for diverse
individuals and opportunities to network
and promote their research as well as
highlighting members who are currently
on the job market or trying to um create
new areas of research or try and like
integrate into other countries or
promote their research in other
countries and Foster the collaboration
once again from these Avenues today's
speaker is Dr Julian MOA abalenda so Dr
Julian Mora abalenda was born in bota
Columbia his fascination with the world
around him led to the study of biology
and later biotechnology I feel that
integrates diverse areas such as
molecular biology agriculture Commerce
and intellectual property here in a
Bachelor of Science in biology and
recently completed his PhD in
biotechnology at University D Nas
Colombia in bota he's a member of the
research group in plan genetic
engineering for his institution and
additionally he holds a master's in
biotechnology and a master's degree in
Commerce from Macar
University Julian is also an amateur
nature photographer and collaborates on
Publications and artwork with his wife
he also has a personal passion for
culinary fermentation exploring it
purely for fun curiosity and his love
for food rather than for an academic
perspective so take it away Julian um
good afternoon everybody I would like to
thank you for the invitation for the
chance to be here sharing some of my
life and and my work and I would like to
thank forina and marar for making this
possible
and and I'm really pleased to to be here
and really really honored um I'm going
to talk mainly about um the work that we
do at the plan genetic engineering group
in in un National Colombia in
botam but I would also like to take the
chance to talk about the path that took
me there and sort of the experience of
working in this area of research and um
the career path that that I have
followed so in order to make the talk a
little bit more more personal and not
strictly technical
um seeing that people who attend this
these talks may be coming from different
areas of research and and could be more
interested in the personal aspect or in
the in the human aspect of of the career
path
and so I'm going to be talking about how
we we're trying to adapt and adopt
generic agricultural bi technology and
making it possible to to bring some of
this technology to to Colombian Farmers
to to the field and to the
consumer later on in this talk I will
be going deeper into what was my PhD
research and the research that the group
does but um I I'd like to start by
recognizing some of the people who who
have been together with me during this
path and that have been my mentors and
that have made it possible for me to to
grow as a professional and as a human
being and that uh sort of showed me a
path and helped awaken the interest the
academic interest U that have been with
me during different stages of my life uh
I I did um bachelor in sci biology in
University National Colombia in bot and
probably the first teacher that um that
awakened an interest a real academic
interest in me was professor eleno and
pis with whom we started the theoretical
biology group in in in the University um
it was a great group of students and and
Professor Andra where we we studied
evolution Ary biology from a theoretical
perspective we delved into the
philosophy and History of Science and he
opened our eyes to seeing biology as
more than uh a collection of species and
lab work uh but how it talk to other
disciplines like philosophy
thermodynamics physics uh seeing biology
as the interaction of complex systems
and um well it was really Awakening for
me to to be part of this and ever since
then I I feel that I have
a a view of biology that
integrate all these different aspects
that are not just Natural Sciences but
also human sciences and and seeing
biology as a whole body of knowledge
that interacts and talks to other
disciplines I did my my bachelor's
thesis research thesis in the genetics
Institute of the University team
supervised by Professor Jova
K and accompanied by by Rita
badri and that's where I I started
working with molecular biology and
learning some of the lab techniques that
that would be really helpful throughout
all my my
career I then several years after this I
I went to Australia to do my master's
degree in mcari University
there I met um Professor Paul Haynes who
was very strict but at the same time was
very passionate for for the work he he
he taught he taught proteomics at the
time and he really got the best out of
of his
students while I was doing that master's
degree which combined biotechnology and
commerce
and I I was able to to see how how well
coming from a relatively theoretical
background try to find
how the the knowledge in biology could
be applied and could be used uh
for for products to improve people's
life quality uh to see something coming
out of the lab coming out of University
and actually reaching reaching people I
did an internship at appli systems which
was a
startup from AAR University and the
supervision of Dr Junior
teal working with the development of a
fusion protein expression system in a
filamentous
fungus and well this University offered
this double degree in biotechnology and
commerce and and gave me the chance to
to actually work at a at a company while
I was still studying my my Master's
Degree seeing how there was this
communication between University and and
the
industry after the the Masters I came
back to Colombia with this vision of
actually applying this theoretical and
practical knowledge in biology H for the
development of of products I wanted to
see things happen and that's where I
talked to to Professor Alejandro chaparo
hiraldo who who was a teacher at the
department of biology University
National Colombia and he invited me to
join the plant genetic engineering group
um this was a long time before I started
my PhD I started collaborating with him
and then under his supervision I started
my
PhD
research Professor chaparro he had a
vision and the aim of the of the
research group uh has always been to
bring together uh different areas of
knowledge different disciplines H for in
order with a big aim of bringing crop
technology to the field and making it as
real as as it can get so not only being
strict from a research and a theoretical
perspective but um actually seeing the
products of biotechnology used by the by
the
agriculture producers and the and the
[Music]
consumers unfortunately Professor
chaparo died in
2020 but he left ER with a great
community of his students who still are
part of the research group and and and
are trying to continue with with this
Vision so he brought together H
knowledge in molecular biology tissue
culture and Agronomy he was an
agronomist integrating these fields as a
necessary elements for the development
of biotechnology in Colombia from a
public
university seeing what had been done in
Colombia and the work the group had done
until maybe 10 years ago maybe 12 years
ago and no no nationally developed
biotechnology product had reached the
field you know talking about crop biot
technology and part of this was due to
the difficulty of overcoming regulations
and the protection of several of these
products by intellectual uh
property things such as
patents so the group also started
researching in the IP Pro uh
aspects of crop biotechnology making
this a central part of the research that
that was done and making it evident that
this was something that had to be taken
into account since the very beginning of
any research project if it was going to
reach the field if the seeds were going
to be planted in real life conditions
there were some experiences uh by other
researchers in the country where
products were developed that were proved
to work but never ER reached a producer
or a consumer
because the the IP restrictions did not
make it possible it was impossible to
license impossible to to
overcome so we started taking this into
account and and exploring which crops
and which traits could be implemented
through this through this um point of
view
so
biotechnological crops have been around
have been in the market for more than 25
years close to 30 years now um and they
have always been surrounded by a
different kinds of protection such as
patent plant variety protection material
transfer agreements Etc and for the
development of a of a biotechnological
crop a genetically modified crop there
are lots of aspects that can be
protected by by patterns for example
such as Gene constructs um Gene
sequences protein sequences
transformation vectors molecular
biology techniques such as those for the
detection of of specific transic
events bacterial
strains plant tissue uh
protocols in some countries plant
varieties and seeds are protected by
patents in Colombia they are protected
by by a different kind kind of
of of Ip protection which is the
Breeders
rights and all these made it expensive
and in some cases impossible for
developments to be
um actually done with a commercial
purpose in in the
country they were either too expensive
or they were just not
available
however IP protection expires after a
certain time most cases it's 20
years and patents are only applicable
for a given territory or country or for
the European Union so if there is a
development of technology that is
patented in one country but not in
another that technology can freely be
used in in another country will have
after certain amount of time if it's
never protected so when a patent expires
or when a technology is not patented in
a country it is in the public domain
that means that it can be freely used um
without infringing third rights um third
party rights and that's where we started
um looking
into Technologies related to
agricultureal biot technology that were
in the public domain in
Colombia this is a topic that has been
mentioned in the scientific literature
since 2012 as far as we as we have
seen where um grusin noted that h the
first biotechnological crops were going
to have been in the market for 20 years
in in
2014 2014 so most of those Technologies
would go into the public domain
Jefferson coined the term act
biogenerics for this these crops and
specifically looked at the case of the
glyphosate tolerant soyan which was one
of these first crops to ever come into
into the market
[Music]
and there have been some mentions to
this aspect of of different crops and
different Technologies coming into the
public domain for the past
decade and we we have been one of the
groups uh that have adopted
this this
model there are two
different types of generic crops if you
want to call them like this and they're
clearly differentiated as how they are
are produced so first there are
off-patent
crops in order to produce an off patent
prop a genetically modified parent say a
corn plant that has a transgenic
event which has entered the public
domain either because it was never
patented or the patent has expired can
be crossed with a conventional parent
say from a from a variety or genotype
that is adapted to a specific climate or
specific region say the corn producing a
corn producing region in
Colombia a hybrid is produced and then
those hybrids are back crossed with a
conventional parent always selecting for
the transgenic trade for the
event and after four or five rounds of
of back cross and selection the
original conventional genotype is more
than 90 99% recovered but as it was
selected keeping in mind that the
the the it still had the transgenic
event we are talking about a new cultiv
which has mostly conventional parents
genotype but the transgenic event but
please bear in mind that this is exactly
the same transgenic event that was in
the original J parented it's in the same
part of the Corn genome in in this case
so the the transfer of the transic event
is done from a GM parent to a
conventional um genotype together with
the flanking regions of the genome so
it's the same transgenic event which is
off patent and therefore can be used uh
from the public domain this work was
done by some members of the research
group led by Jenny gimenez baretto
together with fenal which is the The
Guild of corn producers in Colombia so
this was a a very a fruitful
collaboration between a public
university and the corn producers in the
country and were able to develop a new
corn hybrid called fenel Tech
22 which is actually the first and up
until up until now the only genetically
modified crop developed in Colombia that
is planted that actually reached the
market that reached the field and that
it was ever consumed in the
country this is the the work that was
published which summarizes the process
of developing that off patent
event now the second model is the
strictly AC biogeneric a model AC
biogeneric crop and there are some
slight differences we also start with a
commercial gen crop say in this case the
Roundup Ready soyan which was the first
um glyphosate tolerance soy me to be
developed and we look at the expression
cassette that was introduced into that
first event to see what elements it's
composed of so there's a promoter uh
Transit peptide for the chloroplast the
coding region for the gene cp4 epsps
which is the one that confers glyphosate
tolerance and and a
Terminator however a similar construct
can be built
maybe changing the promoter maybe
changing the coding sequence but that
produces the same protein and therefore
this confers the same characteristic to
transform plants so it's a newly
designed expression cassette based on a
technology that is well known and that
is in the public domain so maybe there's
a patent that expired for this coding
region uh so it can be freely used in
other different kinds of constructs
maybe a promoter that is better suited
for for the model plant for soyan in
this
case this new genetic construct can be
inserted into a
transformation plasmid that is also in
the in the public domain and used to
transform um soyan plants so the main
difference between an off patent event
or an off patent model and an AC generic
model is that here there is formation of
plants there is not a transfer by sexual
reproduction from one parental to
another but there is actually new
transformation and therefore new H
transgenic events are produced but using
a technology that is in the public
domain and this is the model that we
have implemented for soin and that that
I will talk about more during this
presentation and that is still
ongoing other than intellectual property
restrictions or aspects that need to be
taken into account in the development of
a of a transgenic crop in Colombia
they're the regulatory aspects which
also it can be very costly can make it
Al also impossible for some small seed
producing companies or for universities
to be able to pay for the regulatory
process to obtain the permissions for
the planting and consumption of
transgenic events seeing that we were
dealing with mature technologies that
have been proven safe and for which
there is a lot of information available
um we
we were
able to talk to the
regulatory Authority in Colombia which
is the
Colombian agary Institute IC or
EA which in
2021 um updated the regulations for all
aspect related to the research and
production of genetically modified
organisms in the country and thanks to
the participation of the group of the
our research Group H we were able to
include a simplified process for events
and
technologies that are in the public
domain and have been approved and tested
in the country so uh sorry that I put
this in in Spanish but it's a legal
document so I thought I wouldn't
translate it just explain it during the
presentation so there's an a a paragraph
here that talks about authorized events
that can be transferred to new varieties
in the country but those authorized
events are events that have been
authorized for their use in the country
which have been proven safe and for
which there is information that is
available and that can in and what this
resolution does is that it makes it
possible to use that information and to
have a simplified process for
technologies that are we already know
which protein it is we just have to
prove that it's the same protein
and something similar happens for what
um here they call similar genetic
constructs which is the same as I just
explain for an AC biogeneric um crop it
talks about using a crop with similar
genetic construct to one that has
already been approved and tested in the
country
so if we start with a looking at the IP
landscape of of a of a crop and we also
taking account the regulatory aspects
there's a lot of items and a lot of
information that is already there and
that makes it a theory a lot easier and
less costly uh for for a development to
be
actually produced successfully and this
was proved for off for the off-patent
Corin so adopting the AC biogeneric
model for for Colombia that there's a
workflow
which starts with a freedom to operate
analysis and this is probably ER the
most important aspect and is from the
very beginning of our research project
every single aspect has to be taken into
account H to make sure you're working
from the public domain so that you are
not going to have IP barriers anywhere
along the development and eventual
commercialization of a product and we
adopted this model for herbicide
tolerant um specific specifically for
glyphosate soybean using Colombian
varieties and this is some of the work
that has been done by different members
of the research group the freedom
operation analysis freedom to operate
analysis was performed by Arana roas and
Jenny gimenez and they were able to
identify all elements of the technology
that could be used and that were in the
public domain in the country mostly
because they were never patented here
and some because the had already
expired anyhow all
the all the analysis included looking at
um world databases us databases to make
sure that nothing would be left out of
sight J men designed a series of of
vectors and and Gene constructs using an
optimized a codon optimized version of
the gene cp4 EPS PS so it was not the
exact sequence of the original um
Roundup Ready so soin but one that was
optimized for codon usage in soyan that
still produced the same cp4
epsps
protein this was included in a pcambia
1301 plasmid for
transformation and Ariana roas did the
first ever transformation assays in the
in the group using Colombian varieties
Colombian seeds and was able to obtain
in vitro uh PCR
positive soybean
plants then I I started my my research
work my thesis uh which aimed at
characterizing selecting and taking
those plants to the field in order to
evaluate their agronomic performance
under bio safety however not everything
went as planned as we will see in in a
moment so we have to revise and adapt
this model um because although we had
some inv vitro plans
we eventually have to do a lot more work
into the transformation regeneration and
characterization of those plants so we
have to sort of iterate the process in
order to have more more working material
so that's how we had to adapt the
model so this was uh the first hardening
assays that we did taking the the plants
from inv vitro conditions to X vitro
having plants in in in
pots here don't don't have I don't want
to go into two technical details that
are may be interesting for Colombian um
agriculture but these are the varieties
and we were able to harden 11 different
transgenic events which are not many and
the process of taking them from invital
conditions to X vure conditions it was
really a very difficult process many
plant died many events were lost and
unfortunately well we only managed to
harden 11 but potential events then take
them to the first ever field tests in
the soybean producing region of the
country under contained
conditions and what we had to experience
there and for those of you who who know
colia well I work in bota University in
bota our lab is in bota but the soybean
producing region is far east in the
Flatlands in in at least five six hours
away by car so we were not really close
to the field lots of the work had to be
remote and so this was also uh a process
of adapting how to to do that transition
from lab work to field
[Music]
work sorry I heard a a
bell I don't know what it
means okay
and um some events were lost during the
process however we did manage
to identify a few PCR positive plants in
the second generation showing that uh
the presence of a trans Gene was there
and to test some plants in the field uh
with the application of the of the
herbicide very few plants
were were actually tolerant in the field
and unfortunately that assay stopped
there and no no seats were were
recovered but we did manage to H get to
a point where we saw plants that
tolerated the herbicide in the
field however
this this um bottleneck where at each
stage lots of plant or lots of events
were lost showed the need to have a lot
more events in order to be able to
select those that could produce the seed
and that could H tolerate the herbicide
in field conditions so many members of
the group um J Rodriguez M Galindo ju
Romero and myself it went back to doing
transformation assays trying to optimize
the transformation process looking at
the interaction between agrobacterium
strains and different soybean varieties
we introduced new Colombian varieties um
to see which ones could perform a bit
better uh optimizing different aspects
of the tissue culture these are the
different stages because at each stage
well there's a selection using the the
herbicide but there is also a bottleneck
due to tissue culture conditions soybean
is a recalcitrant species so it's not
the most um optimal species to work in
tissue culture and transformation but we
were able to obtain several PCR positive
plants in the field so A New Hope is
born molecular hope of seeing actually
PCR positive this was uh work that took
a lot longer than was initially
expected so we went back to the field
with these plants from new
varieties but we also went back to
reality and here is the well the results
that were never expected were in the
first and second generation we were not
able to identify tolerant plants and we
were not able to identify PCR positive
plant we did not see the inheritance of
the trade we did not see the inheritance
of the gene or the inheritance of the
phenotype characteristic so all the
material that we were taking to the
field unfortunately was not viable for
to continue in in a commercial process
however we did manage to improve the
transformation protocol the hardening
protocol all and all different aspects
of of the tissue culture in the
different conditions and to uh devise a
model to take the plants from the field
from the lab to the field without losing
material and without having
to to travel back and forth all the
time however when these um experiments
were being performed the
pandemic H that we probably all remember
um reached us this made it very
difficult for lab work to be continued
for field work to be continued as I was
saying well it was very difficult to
travel to this region of the country so
there was a lot of remote work and most
of all we had the death of Professor
Alejandra chaparo who was the director
of the group who was the director of my
thesis and this changed absolutely
everything most of us at the group both
were
basically in the air we didn't know what
to do the results were not good and we
we were suffering from this terrible
loss I was not seeing a thesis anywhere
I didn't see how that could be a thesis
uh time was of the essence because I had
been working on my PhD for for too long
now doing repeating experiments that
were not working when they seem to work
they didn't and there was the
pandemic and I was very fortunate to
find in my life professor professor
Camilo Lopez gasal from a research group
that works closely to two hours for
manot biotech he works in in manot
biotechnology and he saw potential in
these results he saw potential in me and
he actually was the one who convinced me
that there was a feis and there was
something to be put together there in
order to to finish at least the the the
PHD process so I can't be ever thankful
enough to to Camilo for for actually
pushing me
and making me see that this was a
possibility although the results were
not ideal there was a lot of work there
were a lot of results that that told the
story told the story of how a model
could be not only adopted but needed to
be adapted um in order to to find those
bottlenecks and to see those those
elements that until you're actually
getting your hands uh in the in the lab
getting your feet in the field you don't
see what those problems are and that ER
will need to be need to be tackled um so
we revised the and we Revisited the the
ACT biogeneric model and we we produce
this figure which summarizes it uh these
are all the aspects of Designing a gene
transforming bacterial strains plant
varieties
selecting those events that have
potential characterizing them eventually
taking to the field and doing all the
analysis that are needed for regulatory
aspects the the generic model requires
that intellectual property is taken into
account all throughout the
process from the gene sequences up to
the molecular techniques the information
that is available
about the protein sequences the protein
safety probable allergens
[Music]
Etc and each country has its own
regulatory U landscape for genetically
modified crops we working in Colombia
this is not a crop that is
exported soybean so we deal with
Colombian regulatory requirements and we
were actually able to to have these
requirements um updated taking into
account the fact that most of the first
generation GN crops are in the public
domain and are well known and have been
approved in the country and um have been
proven safe
so taking into account these regulatory
requirements we were able
to
um influence or or yeah influence the
the updating of of Colombia's regulation
in this aspect
to to take into account generic by biot
technology here it's worth noting that
we have to work most of the time in the
optimization of the transformation
protocol and the inv vitro aspects of
this technology uh taking into account
that each element the interaction
between plant variety and bacterial
strain and the different steps in tissue
culture are genotype dependent each
plant variety um reacts and operates in
a different way so they need to be
constantly updated and
analyzed and um well this model has also
been expanding
and this is a work done by danela
portella who who's graduated from her
PhD in the group working with toac
repurposing tobacco for the production
of bioplastics but also under an AC
biogeneric
model we also explored how this model
could be applied for the development of
late light resistant potatoes in the
country seeing that the genes for this
resistance are well known have been
proven to work and are in the public
domain in the country so there is an
opportunity for the production of late
light resistant potato in the country
using a generic
model
and genes have also been identified for
the draw draw tolerance in in
Maze and well this is a field that needs
to be updated constantly as new genes
new technologies will be entering the
public domain every year as patent
expired or as the window for for
patenting also also closes for for seed
producers
so as you can see well the the journey
wasn't easy but I was very lucky to be
surrounded by wonderful people
especially
my my colleagues from the group jir mik
Juan David Jenny Daniela Lisa
danela who who contributed to this work
contributed to the model uh either with
moral support with
results and everyday
collaboration the research group is now
directed by Felipe
sento who who has taken over
uh and is well now leading the work in
soyan in Corin and also other projects
in in other species and other
aspects all this work
was possible thanks to University
National the Colombia The Guild of corn
soybean producers in the country fenal
and I was partly funded by
um a loan SL scholarship from the
ministry of Science in in
Colombia please feel free to contact
me if you want to collaborate if you
have questions if you would like me to
share some of the papers of the research
that we have done and if you have any
questions please do feel free to to
asking thank you very much thank you
very much Julian so I want to open the
floor to questions and there's going to
be a short survey that we're going to
put into the link uh into the chat and
so please fill out the survey because
you know our your feedback is very
important for us and please feel free to
ask any questions in the
chat okay so we have F uh one question
from Elanor young thank you for your
excellent talk do you foresee using the
method you developed to do something
similar with pest disease
resistance yeah thank you for for the
question um well yes this this
model can be applied to any crop or any
technology that is in the public domain
so either because it's a well-known
technology that enter the public domain
for because patents expired or they were
never patented um and as I mentioned for
the for potato we already did the
freedom to operate analysis for late
light resistance and it is in the public
domain in Colombia and probably in many
other countries as
well so yes um that's one specific
example the resistance in potato the the
off-patent corn that I mentioned
before that that specific event H is a
double event which has glufosinate
tolerance a herbicide tolerance but it
also has resistance to
lepidopteran um pests
which are genes many of the cry genes
have also entered the public domain so
they they can be used in in a generic
model so insect resistance fungal
resistance and probably other other
genes as
well just as a followup what do you
think would be most
beneficial uh in Colombia for this
application like is is there a specific
disease pathogen that you might want to
Target or do you think it's better to
improve agriculture using this these
Technologies okay so that would depend
on the crop that we looking at for some
crops maybe the limitation is production
costs where herbicide tolerance can be
very valuable but in other cases
uh insect control can be very important
in the case of of Corin so maybe using
other insect resistant genes can be very
interesting for corn uh for soyan
specifically uh rust is a is also a
significant pest so it could be
implemented and for
potatoes um late light resistance is of
economic significance in in the country
um in Colombia there's also corn sorry
um cotton GM cotton that that is planted
although the area is not very big it is
an important crop in the country and
insect resistance in Cotton um is of is
of importance and there are events that
are in the public domain well a thorough
freedom to analysis would need to be
done but I'm pretty sure that there are
insect resistance genes for cotton that
are in the public domain in Colombia so
those are basically the ones that that
could be used bear in mind
that part of this model uh is based on
the fact that they are mature
technologies that means technologies
that have been well proven so it's not
about making new technologies but using
mature Technologies technologies that
are well known and putting them in a new
context so
maybe well Colombia depends on the
import of GM seeds but the technology
itself can be moved from the from these
imported seeds into seeds that are
specifically adapted for Colombian
conditions and that maybe have a better
resistance to local pests and and they
need a an extra resistance coming from
from the GM technology or that are very
adapted to the weather conditions or to
the type of soils that we have in the
country and the GM characteristic is the
A Plus that makes it easier for the for
the producer or cheaper for the producer
better for the consumer but it's Al
always based on mature technologies that
are put in a new context the context of
a locally developed uh variety a locally
developed
genotype that's specifically adapted to
the growing conditions in the
country yes so we have quite a few
questions actually we have five
questions active so how difficult is it
to develop and bring a to Market a
transgenic product in Colombia with
respect to the USA or Europe from a
regulatory
perspective okay thank you for your
question ju
um Colombia has a very
sound regulatory system it's very clear
and um what it's what was one of the
first countries to actually develop it
its own regulatory aspect for GM crops
um so the regulatory aspects are not the
the obstacle I would say and from an IP
perspective probably it's easier in
Colombia to implement this model than in
in Europe or the us because companies
usually patent where the market is very
big and for many crops Colombia's Market
is not not very big and many
Technologies are never patented in
Colombia so they are in the public
domain and we don't have to wait for
patents to expire the limitations in a
country like like Colombia come from
other aspects as I mentioned in during
the talk geography is a is um an aspect
that needs to be taken into account
because the the most
developed cities and the the lab
Laboratories and the universities that
have more resources are in cities that
are maybe not close to the regions of
the country where the crops are grown to
agricultural parts of the country so so
there's sort of a miscommunication or or
a difficult communication geographically
speaking between laboratory and the
field uh there is a very
important hub investigation Hub in in
Palm which is cat Alliance for
biodiversity cat which have excellent
labs and excellent Fields adjacent to
one another but that's probably the
exception in the country and another
aspect is of course the the resources
available for or research there is not a
big culture of producers to invest in
development because it's a risk and they
have preferred in in many crops to
import seeds
rather than develop their own seeds so
there is not a lot of resources for the
development of local biotechnology and
locally produced seeds because it's a
risk and it's a lengthy process and
sometimes producers want immediate
results and they would rather just
import seeds than to make them together
collaborating with universities and
risking those
resources what are the prospects of Ip
and patent development in Colombia do
you think patenting will become more
feasible in near
future well there's sort of
um
attention between different groups in
the country on
how how flexible should patents be and
or how many patents should be
granted
um
so part of that comes from the the the
free trade agreement with the US and and
trade agreements with other countries
which
require more patents to be granted in
the country but there are groups in
Colombia that are advocating for more
public domain and for a more strict
requirements for things to be patented
for
example Professor osar laraso from
University naal De Colombia he works in
the faculty of Law and he has opposed
patents and and he advocates for
[Music]
um opening more aspects to the public
domain not only in agricultural
biotechnology but also in pharmaceutical
biotechnology advocating for more
Technologies to be available for
Colombian developers and Colombian
researchers uh so yeah there's a
tension I don't know where where it's
going
[Music]
um sometimes it seems that more things
are are being p it but there's always um
new technologies coming into the public
domain just because of of time and and
expiration so um this is going to be a
decade where each year many genes many
technologies that were ever patented or
patents that were requested will come
into the public
domain so we're coming up uh to the I
will stay on as long as we have
questions please feel free to stay
congrats as an alumni from the biology
program at the University at NAS
Columbia it's excellent to see of your
achievements um see thank you very much
uh do you see any institutional interest
from Colombian governmental or private
sector agencies to use this kind of
Technology towards improving food
production and quality in
Colombia okay thank you Juan for your
question um well sometimes the the
message is a bit
contradictory because this is a
technology that has a certain opposition
in in the country and I guess in every
single country but that producers
actually asked for it and and and look
forward to to having it h but
specifically we have collaborated with
um
depart the national planning department
uh that is working on a policy Bri on
the use of public domain
Technologies for um for the development
of of biotechnology in the country and
they are using our research as one of
the examples of how the public domain is
a source and is something that can be
mined that can be exploited because
there's a lot of information there that
that maybe is not used enough so yes
there is an interest we have been
contacted by the by the national
planning department and well they they
work in different aspects pharmaceutical
biotechnology engineering but also
agricultural biotechnology and they use
our work as an example of
this okay next question what do you
think about the barriers related to
intellectual property and crisper
technology particularly for developing
countries well this is an issue thank
you for for that question that we have H
delved over quite a few times asking
ourselves if we should be working with
crisper and and Gene editing genome
editing in general and Professor chaparo
asked this question almost every meeting
every group meeting that we had and
um well I think it's a technology that
we should be aware of that we should
learn how to use and that many
researchers in the country are are using
or several researchers in the country
are using with with great
advancements but that is not going to
reach the field anytime soon probably
because of Ip barriers ER in Colombia
you can use the crisper technology for
research purposes only but if you want
to develop a commercial product you need
to license the technology and sometimes
that is just not
possible or too
expensive before starting with the ACT
biog generic model we tried to contact
some companies to see if they would were
would be open to license not Gene
editing technology but transgenic
technology and we didn't receive answers
so it's not that they didn't refuse to
license or it was too expensive they
just didn't reply the
email so something similar might happen
with with chrisper technology where
where developments don't come out of the
lab and if they
are um eventually profitable will the
the prices or licensing would be quite
steep your next question what would you
say to Young researchers who want to
dedicate their careers to investigations
like this for example regarding the
challenges and opportunities thanks for
the
talk thank you for your
question I would
say go
ahead surround yourself very well with
great people people that you trust
people that are there for you that's
more important than the the plants the
genes the lab the machines because you
will eventually need a lot of help and
that can only be given by by by good
people around
you any other problem can be
solved uh there so there's yeah three
more questions right now so what are the
advantages of this public domain based
model compared to chrisper cast Gene EDI
thanks great
work thank you
Oscar well the main advantage is that
it's free to use that it's in the public
domain and therefore doesn't need to be
licensed in order to be used so it can
from the beginning have a commercial uh
commercial aim um not just for
research if you're working with crisper
and you want to eventually have a
commercial product you you need to bear
that in mind from the very beginning
that you will need a license and that um
probably as a as a researcher in a
Colombian University you're not the one
who's going to be H putting the
conditions for that license so you
you're going to have to accept what the
owners of the technology are going to to
demand of you um so if you want a
commercial product which was the aim of
the groups since the very beginning for
the seats to actually reach the field uh
working from from a generic perspective
using elements from the public domain
that's a great advantage and uh at least
in in theory it reduces costs greatly
because you don't have to assume the
costs of binding the genes discovering
the genes proving that they work pro
proving the concept the the proof of
concept has been done um because these
are mature Technologies and you can also
um use some of the regulatory
information
that has been produced about the safety
and efficacy of of these Technologies so
so you would be cutting down costs and
time uh using all the information that's
already
available all right so uh for the just
another reminder uh please fill out the
survey link I fixed it so that you don't
have to request so it should be freely
accessible and available to everyone uh
next question is is from an anonymous
attendee to what extent has the off
patent corn develop by you been adopted
by farmers in Colombia and how has it
been
accepted okay thank
you the off patent development was done
together with um with a guild of corent
producers which is fenal
which are actually the farmers
themselves which are in in a guild that
that uh dedicate some of their profits
to research and development of coren
seeds so it
was they themselves who promoted this
this use of the
technology they are importers of seats
biotechnological seats and they wanted
this technology to be available in the
seats that were developed by them it was
introduced into a genotype that was
developed by the producers themselves
because it's adapted to
Colombian conditions so so the interest
actually not it didn't come only from
the University looking for someone to
finance the project but the producers
themselves looking for researchers who
could bring biotechnological
developments to their varieties and
their genotypes I however do not have
the information of the
extension the area that has been planted
or the or the
the
production that has been done using this
specific um hybrid feltech 22 but I do
know that it has been planted and is
planted in Colombia because um the city
is available for sale and it has all the
all the approvals from the national
authorities for for their use uh both in
the field and for its consumption
okay last question Anonymous attendee do
you think public sentiment towards GM
technology has changed do you think that
there are effective ways to improve
perception um yes I do think it has
changed the
focus of the opposition to GM technology
I think has changed from from a safety
point of view which used to be the the
original concern to to put in in a
certain way I think GM crops the GM
crops that are in the market have been
proven safe once and again and that I
don't think is the main concern I think
the concern among consumers
and um general public is more about the
whole industrial agricultural model um
monocrops um the use of herbicides
pesticides
um agricultural biodiversity what
happens with the seats that
are local varieties things like this and
how how how can they live together with
GM crops uh not from the the
biosafety perspective and I think these
are very valid questions that need to be
addressed in any type of Agriculture um
and that are not necessarily related to
to a cro being GM but maybe to an
industrial
um agricultural model that needs to to
be complemented by non-industrial
Agriculture and I think researchers are
more aware of of of this and the way in
which perception can be improved is
precisely by breaking the link between a
certain type of Agriculture and GM
technology these are two different
things GM technology as it as it says
it's a technology it's how a gene is
introduced into a crop and it has been
associated with certain crops and
certain models but it doesn't have to be
that way um I think there is a
compatibility between organic
Agriculture and GM technology for
example um and another aspect that I
think could help to improve public
perception in a country like Colombia is
precisely by having GM crops that have
been developed in the country H by local
producers with local varieties by a
public university and that is not
necessarily associated with import Ed
seats at technology coming from from
outside all right thank you again uh
please fill out the survey you'll also
get an email link um thank you again to
our speaker Julian that was a fantastic
talk it was actually the biggest group
we've ever had for the speaker series um
and you know starting the new year
strong uh we are overtime and I'm being
kicked out of the room so I will have to
end the meeting if you any other
questions please contact us or Dr Julian
Mora
Ober uh whenever you see fit um thank
you once again