So, thank you for having us today. Um,
my name is Sasha. I'm from Ver. Our
founder and CEO, Tim Hidel, is an MIT
alum and we're a proud part of the
engine community. At VER, we're
addressing one of the most urgent
challenges in the data center industry.
We're overcoming p power delivery
bottlenecks that limit speed and scale.
The growth of AI is powered by
electricity and the demand for
electrical power is soaring. But today's
conventional technologies such as copper
cables and bus bars can't support the
megawatt class racks already on the
horizon seen here from the Nvidia road
map. The infrastructure required to
distribute that power can't accommodate
the volume of cabling, the oversized
heavy bus bars and additional cooling
equipment requirements in the facility.
This is making many current facility
designs obsolete before they're even
being built. So the challenge is clear.
How do we deliver much higher power
quickly, compactly, and efficiently so
that AI can continue scaling.
Ver provides a superconducting power
cable solution to meet this challenge. a
compact modular high-capacity design to
transfer power in and around the the AI
campus or the data center campus
directly into server racks.
Superconducting power cables replace
conventional power distribution options
carrying 10 times more power than copper
with near zero losses enabling densities
conventional conductors just can't
support.
Here you see the components of the VER
product including the superconnecting
cable assembly, cooling infrastructure,
controls, electrical protection and
cable terminations that interface with
standard equipment.
These components form an integrated but
flexible platform. For example, one
cooling system supports multiple cables
across the campus.
Various products can be applied
throughout the campus from the grid
interconnection to building to building
distribution across the campus and into
the white spaces feeding the IT racks.
Compared to conventional feeders, there
reduces congestion and footprint
resulting in denser layouts, simpler
construction, faster energization. By
shrinking the power delivery
infrastructure, VE frees up space for
compute and extends the campus facil
campus capacity.
Multiple real use case analyses have
been have demonstrated the advantages of
applying superconductivity across the
campuses. The value proposition
propositions of our technology are
highlighted here. Inside the buildings,
we enable smaller, lighter, power dense
distribution, reducing copper,
supporting higher density clusters and
future proof proofing facilities.
With the longer reach, lower voltage
drop and smaller footprint, clients can
reduce construction times and use their
sites more efficiently. We've seen
optimized layouts for higher capacity
within the same land area, creating
direct economic value.
To show what this looks like in
practice, we created the STAR demo. STAR
is an abbreviation for superconducting
technology for AI racks, demonstrating
safe, compact, multi-megawatt power
delivery inside the building.
What you're seeing here is a fully
integrated 3 megawatt superconducting
power delivery system.
We're delivering 3 megawatt through a
single low voltage cable in a simulated
data center environment using the same
architecture as a live facility. Every
component is engineered for real world
deployment.
This milestone shows that
superconductors can deliver
multimegawatt power with far less space
and heat. And this technology is ready
now. If you're stuck trying to get
megawatt power across your data center
campus and into the IT racks, I'd love
to connect with you. Thank you.
>> Thank you Sasha so much. So um again a
reminder to pose your questions either
to the Q&A tab or the chat. Um let me
start with one. So what are the biggest
value drivers to leveraging
superconducting cables and why would you
say that? Um, superconductors deliver
five far higher power densities and a
much smaller footprint with almost no
electrical losses. And so that means
there are fewer conductors across the
campus. There's less heating, less
cooling, um, less less heating,
dramatically simplified installations.
So we've shown, for example, in some
installations that we can reduce the
construction by 40%, construction costs
by 40% and increase the time by 3 to 6
months. Um in some other cases also the
really the compactness if I had to pick
out one particular thing the compactness
of our solution and how that drives
value is um evidence in some of the
other use cases that we've seen in a 200
megawatt facility we were able to
increase the IT capacity inside of the
building by 12 megaww which resulted in
a revenue generation of 100 million. So
that was a very clear economic driver
due to the compact um footprints of our
cables.
>> Yes, good comparisons and good benefits.
Um and also what is your go to market
strategy at the moment?
>> So we're doing a few things. Um we're
partnering um across the board with uh
with many many people in stakeholders in
the data center industry. Um we're
working with them to develop early
partnerships. So as I showed the road
map for Nvidia, we're closely aligned
with that road map. So we're really
trying to be wrapped and not wrapped,
sorry, we're really trying to engage
early so that we can be ready for the
2029 deployment of mega megawws. Uh and
we want to do that even earlier. We're
speeding that up. So we want to actually
be ready in 2028, 27,28.
>> Okay. And uh one more question. Um is
the entire cable and cooling system
self-contained or what else of an
infrastructure is needed?
>> Yeah, so the entire uh the cable is
actually cooled using a cryogen liquid
nitrogen and so that liquid nitrogen um
is modular. It's a infrastructure that
it can be on a skid and we can multiply
that as needed for the cooling
requirements across the campus.
>> Okay, thanks so much Sasha.
>> Thank you.