Hello and welcome to the uh MIT ethics
of computing research symposium. Um so
you're about to see a bunch of talks
today. The sort of um smallest thing
they have in common is that they're all
reporting on research funded by CIRC,
the social ethical responsibilities for
computing initiative within the college.
um uh what what there's something large
they have in common um uh at CIRC what
happened is last year we had a call
initiated by Georgia Parakus then
associate dean of the college who um uh
we called out for across MIT for
researchers we could support who were
doing work in this area the social and
ethical responsibilities of computing
and we had 67 applications and uh we
from every school at the institute and
we convened a committee
um of reviewers with representatives
from every school at the institute to
select the best ones. So what you're
seeing here is kind of a collective
community judgment about what the most
exciting work in when it comes to
research in the social and ethical
responsibilities of computing being done
at MIT is so um I hope that you'll be as
excited about it all as we are. Uh so
thanks for coming and uh yeah so the
talks are going to be 15 minutes
followed by nine minutes of questions
and so uh during the talks the 15-minute
talks please store up your questions and
we'll try to run them as efficiently as
possible.