um good morning good evening good
afternoon depending on where you're
joining us in the world today we're
broadcasting live at MIT Nano uh in
particular we're in the immersion lab
the immersion lab is a central facility
engaged with helping you MIT users
off-campus users leverage the powers of
immersion the the powers and tools of
gaming to advance science to Advance
Engineering to advance education so I
invite you we're here today virtually
and physically some of us but I invite
you to come knock on our doors send us
an email reach out to understand how we
can help you apply the the tools and the
language of gaming ambient physiological
monitoring novel displays novel
Technologies to really think about the
new ways that we can move the needle
forward together so today um we're here
to celebrate how we can think about the
novel ways of using augmented reality to
manage and explore infrastructure we we
know how to use the wheel um we're still
developing the ways that we're going to
use augmented reality so Arman today is
going to share with you some very
Innovative and novel approaches to
thinking about how we see Behind the
Walls how we engage with our our
physical through the virtual again um
enjoy ask questions and I'll I'll turn
it over to Arman and um take it away
all right uh so yeah my name is Arman
and I'm graduate student second year
Masters in system design and management
program um and I'm also working on
Research how can we use augmented
reality to uh improve operational and um
maintenance tasks and uh just a little
bit about my background and how it um
motivated me on working on this project
and
exploring oh louder okay sorry can you
hear me um
is good okay right so uh I was working
in oil and gas before coming to MIT and
uh so the way that my work was involved
is around developing and building models
how can we represent the systems that we
were're dealing with like uh hydrocarbon
reservoirs uh subsurface systems uh and
how can we use those models to maximize
and optimize production uh that was uh
my main work involvement around the um
building and um optimizing the
infrastructure of the system and the one
of the interesting things that were I
encountered when we were dealing with
different um aspects of our work was
when we were um uh dealing with our
system we were modeling the like complex
uh U like reservoirs and we uh most of
them are you cannot really see them um
physically because they are located uh
like thousand meters under the ground uh
and um we had different groups were that
were dealing with the same type of
system but from the surface level so we
had different uh viewpoints on how we
were applying our uh um approaches on
how we can um uh yeah use our techniques
to to operate that system so I've seen
when we were doing the field visits to
to one of those uh like Wells sites uh
I've seen the issue that there was some
level of differences when we were
talking about uh how can we operate
system and we were speaking with field
operator and engineering department for
example and we we had different mental
model how we think about the system so
when we thinking about the model so we
would see on the right side uh that this
is how we um view the uh this
representation of the field or or the
Gathering system or the wellsite the
flow lines that's how we would be
operating um the field and when we are
talking to the field operator for from
their point of view they don't have that
understanding
was under the surface so they their only
focus was really is about uh looking at
the the like the number of valves number
of pipes which pipe should be uh
switched on and off and which Val should
be turned uh and that's where you had
that difference so when it was uh that's
where I was thinking about how can we
link that gap between communication of
having the virtual and Digital model be
uh integrated with the physical systems
and that's how I uh started to explore
how can we use augmented reality as a
tool to link that that Gap in the
communication and in the representation
of physical and and virtual systems so
now um that's where I started working on
developing a concept for around the MIT
Nano so what is a nano AR um Nano AR is
a digital representation of the system
of the Nano Nano facility uh and for
those who are not familiar um on the
call maybe uh Nano M Nano is a research
facility that's focused on on a research
around advanced technology and advanced
uh materials and nanot
Technologies uh and it has multiple uh
facilities inside that building that we
can uh take uh as our potential concept
to develop um the model that we can
operate and test and and um uh and see
and get gather the feedback and and
learn something from it um for example
it has U on a sub uh subfab area there's
a COR characterization room
um there are clean rooms on the um on
the multiple floors there's a fan deck
that provides the uh equipment to filter
uh uh and remove the particles from the
air in the clean rooms uh and also
there's a a prototyping room so we have
a lot of material to to to play around
with and we had a really good amount of
data uh that we could collect and build
a model um around the around the
facility uh that's where it led us to
think about okay so what so we have this
data we have the models uh like building
information model of the of of the
system of M Nano how can we use this
model and uh develop a concept that we
can test around and and build an
experience that user can interact with
through augmented reality um and that
concept uh the first concept that led to
us to explore okay let's focus on
operational and maintenance tasks so
that let's think about what could be an
interesting approach how um uh operator
who would be um managing and uh um
operating the certain U aspects of the
building with certain like facilities of
the building like fandc for example to
operate the uh Val and switches to to
support the environment in the clean
rooms uh what would be useful for them
to have in the AR uh application uh or
in in that ER experience uh so we
started focusing and Nar Nar in it down
to augmenting the uh engineering
infrastructure uh and that's where uh we
started uh uh looking for the data or
the assets that we can collect from
those B models to only represent
filtration system um like fire safety it
could be piping um and uh yeah and
plumbing or ducts so things that usually
you wouldn't see uh around the space
when you were inside the room so when
you're in the room you you definitely
you you see walls and uh Furniture but
uh things that are behind the scenes
like Behind the Walls uh ceilings and uh
you wouldn't notice them so that's where
we thought okay maybe that would be
useful to test and see how can we
augment that and overlay uh on top of
the the physical uh systems here so
that's where we proceeded that's how I
uh proceeded further with development
but
before uh building the um the actual uh
scene
I just wanted to highlight some of the
constraints that we had in developing uh
this experience so the constraints that
we uh should keep in mind of When
developing um AR experience or any game
development uh application uh any any
gameing development has this constraints
that are like two opposing forces that
are pulling the um the performance of
the game or the performance of the AR or
VR uh simulation into different sides so
you have Graphics quality you have the
like the textures and the
um the materials so how realistic all
the objects look in in that uh in that
game or in that simulation uh that's
like one side of the of of this boundary
of this envelope and the other side of
the of that uh constraint is the game
performance so how smooth you want the
system to operate when you um when you
interact with the simulation so those
are two things that you need to keep in
mind you need to find the balance really
uh by applying certain features by
changing the texture by removing uh
number of polygons so that's where it's
more Arts and Science really when you TR
when you find this that balance because
it could be different Case by case so
that's where uh that's where it it
requires several iterations to find that
uh The Sweet Spot between these two um
constraints uh for the applications that
we will apply for development so we are
uh have
dependent on the unity so we'll be using
Unity for our most of our uh feature uh
adjustments and how we set up the
interaction uh between the uh the user
the AR player and and the uh and the
actual system so in our case MIT Nano
augmented overlay that's where we would
be developing and adding
interactions we we would be using also
blender for um changing the textures and
the materials and removing the U that
level of detail that will hinder our
performance so that's where we want to
play around a little bit with the
quality of of our objects and assets uh
Autodesk is something that we use to
just to grab our uh initial source file
so Autodesk or any other any any outat
design uh platforms we can use uh it's
really for us it wasn't um a big
difference uh which source file we could
use but we we we need this 3D designs to
start with because we're using building
information model so uh that's where
that's how the um the MIT build so we
use that as as an initial first step and
we are also relying on meta quest uh
headsets and met Quest met sdks to
develop um interactions and um and Quest
Pro and Quest 3 was our choice for the
hardware for the headset um the reason
is because we want to have the pass
through uh feature the pass through just
for those who are not familiar uh in the
head in the VR and are you have uh the
this capability to see like to see
what's what around uh what surrounds you
in the space so you can walk in the
headset without taking them off uh
that's the pass through or see through
you can choose either one but the
difference between those two is that see
through is essentially it's a glass and
you can through look through the glass
and see the Holograms that are displayed
through the wave guides uh versus the
pass throughs where you just look at the
display and the headset using the camera
to to um to show you the visual of of
what you're seeing around you so it's
you're not really looking through the
headset is just looking at the display
inside the headset that's the main
difference um
yeah so first start with the data
collection uh so we had this massive
file for MIT
U bin file in um Autodesk navis works
and that's where we wanted to First
think about so if you think about the
concept you want to know okay where do
how do you want to uh organize uh how do
you want to start building this project
uh how you want to split the the
facility do you want to do this by by
room or by by a floor level uh there are
many different ways so this where you
need to be uh uh decomposing the uh this
large piece into smaller uh parts and
smaller sections that's where will be
much easier for your further development
so you need to think about these things
uh one step ahead and um but really it
also might require some iterations uh
but this is where we would start um
collecting our data you can also import
additional assets um if you need
something that's is not being built you
can develop yourself and uh you can
introduced to the uh to the AutoCAD uh
design or you can just import them into
the blender or Unity um it's really it's
it's a matter of what uh assets do you
need uh or what objects do you need
inside that build inside that experience
um so that was our first initial step um
yeah it's pretty much saying uh same
same thing uh except that if you think
about the what do you do you need
everything in that model uh probably not
if you look at one of the examples down
there um like you wouldn't need to
import walls for example that's where
we're not interested in displaying
everything that's visual so you don't
you you don't want to see um uh uh yeah
the actual like Furniture right for
example we want to only um focus on the
engineering infrastructure behind uh the
walls and the facilities uh so that's
where our Focus mainly um led to to to
take those
objects now the next step for in this
process is pre-processing of the
original files so that's once you import
the files from the from Autodesk or from
AutoCAD um that's how you you would see
them in in um in the blender uh in our
case and definitely this this is a lot
of material that you wouldn't need uh in
your in your design in in your AR um
simulation so you would want to start
thinking about how can you make this uh
Model A simpler um there are several
things you can do and U there are many
other sources that you can uh search for
how can you U remove number of Poes how
can you make the model um um yeah much
simpler um in our case this is what you
probably would be looking for this how
this how we represent our system so it's
mostly pipes and and and
infrastructure um and so first of all
once you import your U objects from
AutoCat you will see a lot of uh
different small pieces uh um bundled
together so you want to uh first thing
you you would want to do is to Cluster
all of those small smaller objects into
bigger components uh because that's that
way you can save uh computational
resources U because it's much easier to
process less number of components versus
the uh large number of components and
that's where you would want to kind of
group them and cluster um and also the
next step would be to remove number of
Poes um um do some um decimate um
function like there's some uh techniques
that you can do in blender to uh to
remove that extra level of detail that
you would wouldn't need really uh for
your uh for your AR experience um so so
the main thing that really helped us to
to move faster is just to focus on um
clustering objects removing some number
of poly polygons and um and also uh
material yeah you wouldn't need to to
have the material that are imported from
AutoCAD you can add the materials that
are much simpler uh from unity and
that's uh that's was our approach that
helped us down the
road uh now for the development part
this is the fun part uh this is where
you introduce all the features this is
where you decide pretty much this this
where you you can design your
interaction how you or are AR player is
interacting with the system and unit is
a very useful tool uh it has a lot of
Open Source packages that you can apply
um and uh even with low low level of uh
like or low skills um I mean
inexperience uh programmer can learn
this really fast there's many resources
and right now especially with Gen tools
you can uh script um any functionality
uh relatively easy and fast uh because
there are many things that are not
independent so once you create a script
you can just drag and drop uh that
component into the uh into into the
object and it should do the work and uh
yeah so the first when you start the
unity project you want to make sure you
you're setting up it in the right way
you have the right platform in our case
it was Android for meta quests um
devices uh headsets um yeah so we were
focusing on Quest 3 and Quest Pro mostly
pass through on uh we needed some hand
tracking so we want to make sure that
the the experience was as
uh as natural as possible so there
wouldn't be a need to to carry the
controllers uh in the hand so you you
would have to just use your hands to
navigate or uh switch the uh do some uh
buttons control or um yeah do like basic
stuff with your own hands and that's
that's where these headset have the
function to track your hands um and also
think about the setup for the uh camera
so the level setup is it eye level is it
floor level um for floor level you it's
when it's grounded to the to the um to
the level of your um of the floor or
your feet that's where you probably
would think about having Furniture uh uh
designed to that to that level but in
our case everything was actually
overlaid on top of us so it's mostly um
we're at the at the eye level of the
elevation so we wouldn't need to have
floor level U but things like that you
just want to think about when you set up
the project and there's uh multiple sdks
from meta XR that we also introduced to
have that interaction uh with hand
tracking and um other components as well
um I just want to go through like some
Basics things that we need to have as a
minimum uh to have that smooth
interaction is first one is is rigid
body so this is you where you want to
think about the physics of the objects
and rigid body is the physics component
of unity um where you can uh remove
gravity or you can add gravity you can
make the um objects static so they can
freeze in the in the location and in our
case that was essential because we
wouldn't want to have any facility we
wanted them to be anchored to a certain
uh spot to a certain location and that's
where uh we would have those um
components introduced uh and yeah
wouldn't need the gravity so the main uh
I guess feature that we
had to have from the rigid bodies the
Collision effect so if we're grabbing
some objects that's where you need to
have that Collision um detection and
collision detection is actually in
triggered by box collider I'll explain
it later um but this is things that you
were also would need to have for most of
your builds if you're developing AR
experience um yeah the Box collider is
actually showing the shape of that or
dimensions of the of the object uh yeah
in our case I had to
put like box collider around each room
so if you walk around the building you
would see um like it will have to have
some sort of a indicator or the area
where uh once you once you enter that
area or that box collider it will
trigger an event so that event could be
anything could be um activation of the
assets so you can make them visible or
invisible Once you walk between in the
room so that's that's just this this
basic stuff that uh help you down the
road when you're scripting and when
you're adding additional
functionalities
um yeah and then that's where you toggle
those like put all those together the
Box collider uh and the player so the
player essentially is your camera of
your Center eye anchor that you could um
you could assign as as a moving uh
collider so once your collider which is
around your headset is enter another box
collider of this room for example it
will activate everything around you and
then it will de activate everything
that's in in other colliders that's
that's like just basic stuff that you
you would have to um script and uh add
those components in the unit as separate
uh
component and then we also um like I
thought what if we just add some um
controls to the user uh if um if an
operator walks around the facility in a
AR headset maybe there was a need for
him to have some some level of control
what he wants to see what uh here or she
doesn't want to see in in the view uh so
introducing buttons to switch on and off
things would would probably make sense
in in this simulation uh and um and good
for us there was already a built-in
functions from meta XR sdks that we can
just grab one of those buttons and
introduce and in our case we we attach
those buttons to the to the hand to the
Palm so when you look like we have to
like uh uh stare at your at your problem
and it will show the buttons and you can
uh interact with that um menu I'll say
uh and it will it wouldn't show up all
the time in front of you so that's
another feature that another
functionality that you can U play around
with um
yeah and also you also need to script
the um what it does what what each
button actually activates when you press
uh when you press on that button like on
click uh you have to put a tag for a
certain asset uh and that's like when
you when you put the button um when you
press a button that's will it it will
activate those tags with those uh assets
that are assigned to the stack um it's
just some basic stuff and uh certainly
uh feel free to use the benefits of
having uh gen tools like GPT to help you
down the road with the scripting uh it
makes you uh it makes things much faster
now uh and yeah one of the last steps to
uh make sure that the simulation is as
natural as as possible is the the
calibration and scaling uh once you put
the headset you want to make sure that
uh the dimensions are in place and um
for example the in our case we wanted to
to match the um like the virtual uh
points of the like the far sprinklers uh
uh that are matched with the actual ones
in the in the space so um those
reference points as I would call them
are critical in in making sure that your
physical and virtual Alliance uh U
physically so that's where that's that's
the what could be the tricky part
because in our case the uh it just
turned down that the the actual model
was not up to date so it was hard to
match and then we realize that we
probably shouldn't be spending time on
matching the not up toate model so you
want to make sure that the model is up
to date um and it should follow and that
be that way it will be much easier to
match the virtual model with with the
actual asset um and
facility so it it could require some
back and forth uh um between calibration
and
testing yeah let's just see some demos
so this one it will show you how the
interaction will actually activate once
you the player in the AR headset will
walk around the
room and
yeah so this is how the field of view uh
looks and how the um so actually this
one uh has a built-in function in unity
that helps activate those assets uh not
by the Box collider that I was
describing but actually automatically
setting up the distance if you if you
want to have a certain distance where uh
the object would be activating uh that's
how it will look in the simulation
oh yeah s sorry so on in this space we
uh uh in in this view we have two types
of assets so we have the red ones the
red pipes are the fire safety system so
all the yeah the fire splinters that's
where the water would come to the uh for
that that's yeah basically it's a uh it
will be like Behind These Walls yeah on
on the up and and the the uh green ones
are the the ventilation systems the HVAC
so that's where the filtration and the
fans are uh located so I'll show you in
the next video that we can actually
we're going to do the walk around and
with the headset and it uh it should
show the uh how it looks beyond this
room yeah just also testing some other
small features like we can add some
distance like we can add the target for
example if we want to have uh uh
operator know where he needs to go uh
for a certain task we will add the like
a Target object and then we we can add
some simple navigation like you would
see in the game um like this navigation
Arrow uh which is very simpler approach
but there are many other ways that you
can go around this you can you can be
creative when you design uh these uh
features um yeah and
then and then we justed some buttons
control we introduced um things that we
can add some components for example we
were thinking about some troubleshooting
uh exercise if if an operator went to a
facility and he needed some um do some
um potential uh troubleshooting with
additional tools that he doesn't have or
he needs to match some certain design or
dimensions of of the tool with the
facility so he would press a button and
he would uh try them out at the at the
location this just ver the simple things
that you can also try but we're just
this is just a testing of how buttons
would interact and the last one yeah
this one is the uh the walk around uh
around the corner of the of this floor
so
yeah so you would want so that's
where yeah so this is now it's
overlaying at larger
distance everything that you would see
um that you would actually you would not
see but you would see this through the
AR headset so it's kind of like having
this X-ray vision
of the building um and this is just also
one of the testing it was in the process
of the testing so um some of the
elevation might be not up to the right
uh elevation but it was just like just
to show um how the process of
calibration and testing looks when we're
developing this type of simulation
right so now we went back to the to the
initial Point um and everything stayed
in the same place so it's anchored but
sometimes when you go around the corner
you might see some um misline that
that's the the thing about having making
sure that the scaling is is right and U
and it requires several iteration and
testing um yeah so but overall the
scaling uh in unity the one unit measure
is equal to 1 meter but could be off
sometime so you want to maybe add
additional multiplication to uh to
adjust for that factor um so there could
be some inconsistencies between the
model so now we have this concept so now
in we develop this workflow so how can
we do how can we uh investigate and
answer the research question does the AR
actually help us improve the task uh on
the on the job uh and things that we
want to measure are uh task completion
times uh number of errors or number of
mistakes uh and if there's any reduction
in the cognitive load uh these types of
uh uh measurements or metrics and
figures of Merit are are typical for uh
running a study with uh with a task
completion uh and also based on the
literature review uh it's a it's a it's
it's a typical type that you would
measure uh during the like experiment or
a study so we would be using the same
headset um the hardware of met Quest Pro
Quest three and we have several Concepts
to choose from um and the thing that we
would want to choose the the concept
that would require you to also compare
the uh the like a treatment group for
the uh for using the headset and the
conventional way of of doing some some
task without the headset and that's
where the key difference would would
show up um and yeah so I'll explain what
how we chose the uh our concept for the
AR study so this is the workflow that I
just uh went through uh yeah so now we
can choose this workflow is pretty
robust you can choose any uh facility
equipment you can overlay and run the
experiment with different objects now
and uh it it worked actually pretty well
um with the
um um so we had uh a file that we weed
from one of the companies that did the
scanning of this building so there was a
third party contractor who did the
scanning and we we're able to take those
files of the of the new uh I guess of
the area that's in the basement of
subfab area and we're able to run
through through all these steps and test
relative I mean within the couple of
days or or even weeks um just to show
that this uh process pretty is is pretty
um I guess it works well with any types
of complexity or any types of uh objects
that you can introduce in addition to
what we uh explored for the Nano AR so
uh that's where we proceeded to work on
the next uh object which is the the Fret
device which is fiber Extrusion uh
device it's a desktop uh um tool to
learn and teach how the fiber Extrusion
uh system works and to uh help uh
educate and teach how the U um
principles of manufacturing and advanced
controls uh and also uh data acquisition
so we took this we had this aat design
uh which was really good for us and
actually in this case we didn't have the
Autodesk AutoCAD files we just had the
on shape now which is the cloud-based uh
platform for AutoCat designs and we can
you could see that uh the files are
pretty high in in level of detail which
we might not need to have for the study
and once we uh start uh working on that
on the pre-processing part uh definitely
we want to have them uh these objects uh
in a much simpler
uh detail less detail level than we
would have them in in AutoCAD design uh
so this one yeah comparing to the
AutoCAD uh now it's it looks uh as a
more simpler version that should be fit
for purpose for us in our case uh for
the study uh it it should have more or
less same representation nothing is
really is is much different
um and yeah then you add it to the unit
to development engine and uh add the
features add the buttons interactions
and uh then you go and test uh and
calibrate same way that we did with uh
with a nano AR so this right now we're
just doing the calibration manually just
aligning uh how it how the object will
um will fit the the physical one and and
virtual one um but we're also testing
some other techniques like anchoring and
um that's where we we're still kind to
in learn in learning process proc of
doing this in a in a more precise way
but for us it it worked well just to
because since it's a is a very simple uh
tool and it's it's relatively easy just
to do it manually and much faster um but
for a complex system you might need to
have some some level of U automated
approach or uh or some control to to
apply anchors and um uh
rescaling uh techniques yeah this one is
just testing the
interaction with sub components so we we
had the we tested the guide system to
show to guide the operator to show where
to put the object uh or how to
assemble um uh this this device so
that's that that was part of our another
testing um Step
and then now that we have this
interaction in in operation we can go
run and run the study and collect more
data so in this
case we are showing the
virtual um components overlay on the on
the real uh thread device and we're
measuring how fast can we assemble
compared to the groups that are not
using the AR headset so this is the uh
just example of how can be it can be
used for for your
study
yeah and with that I think that's uh
that should be all for for my part
and we just started the study so we're
running this this is is the actually the
pilot uh and we we're testing how um how
human subjects are interacting with a
system and with a physical and if
there's any obstruction that we need to
keep in mind of but um so yeah we just
the first step was just to to make sure
that it's uh the AR uh model is working
and is functioning but based on the
research that we did on the literature
review um yeah it it shows that could be
promising uh for in like in General on
average um AR can help reduce the task
completion time uh in some papers it
shows that it could be by half like 50%
of the time and uh for number of Errors
it also helped reduce number of errors
that are made during the job and the
cognitive load which is the assessment
done by the NASA TLX assessment and that
also uh showed that the results can show
that it will help reduce that cognitive
load and we want to prove that if if we
have the same same results in our case
all right arm on thank you so much um
and so we're gonna take some questions
we're GNA leave a little bit of time uh
Kelly went ahead and submitted that in
chat so if any of you guys online have
any questions or comments feel free to
uh put that in chat or if anyone here um
yeah feel
free yeah so um he said given the
complexity of all the steps within this
system is there any automation that we
can do um to kind of expedite maybe
changes that happen uh in the future
yeah that's a good question actually I
was I've been looking at at this process
first by establishing what steps are
required to do manually so then we can
at least find the I guess the bottleneck
of in this workflow uh at this point um
if the design changes um I mean the
fastest way is is really is importing
objects into the I I mean any change
that that is made uh we just grab those
change and bring it to the uh blender
and that's where we will add that prefab
that only that section to our uh
simulation but how to make it automated
that's a good question I don't have an
answer on automation part right now but
I think it's something to to explore and
improve on the making it more
efficient uh and we have a question here
regarding the second project to the the
Fred project is it easy to understand
the system with many components
removed
um uh I wonder what kind of components
they're referring to in that
question uh yeah I mean if we remove
walls and things like that um yeah I
feel
like um when you're walking around the
facility uh you have general idea um if
the object object that are overlay they
are that's the where the calibration is
the key uh you want to make sure that
the dimension and the scaling is up to
as precise as possible because once you
remove them that's where it can get U it
can get distorted and if it's distorted
then that's it doesn't make uh sense to
to look at the object that are like
standing somewhere in the in the wrong
spot so if you that's if if you have a
calibration done right uh it should
intuitively tell your like tell your
brain I guess process that information
as naturally as possible that okay if
there there's a wall and behind the wall
there's a certain piping that's what you
would expect to see if you uh te that
wall apart right and that's uh that's
how like our understanding was that we
only need the features that are not
really visible uh to our eye so uh and
calibration would would help us avoid
any uh inconsistencies and yeah so
that's that's how our approach yeah and
that actually does allude to this this
next question how did you ensure the
correct placement of the AR component in
the real world so kind of that overlay
and I know we kind of talked about
strategies on how to go about doing
this uh yeah the um like finding the
right spot right yeah so this would be
kind of the calibrating yeah like the
reference point so anything that you
would see in in the virtual object that
are kind of sticking out of the walls
like one of the example was far as
Sprinklers and or or the the uh HVAC um
like the fans and the something that you
would you would see physically and you
would want to Anchor those objects
around around those reference points
that that was our strategy that we uh
that we chose but definitely we can
introduce additional things that we uh
because it's really sour design right so
we can add things that are actually in
the room and we can anchor uh how we can
initiate the the simulation around that
uh like the virtual space like for
example if we standing here uh we can
overlay uh like one of these cameras
right and we want to have to to initiate
the game when we are standing in in this
in the middle of this room and that's
how we can introduce that anchoring
effect and we can match the dimensions
of of this like for example of these
cameras around here so that's kind of
just example how can you go around this
uh uh on finding the right spot and
finding the right placement of virtual
objects compared to the physical ones
yeah
thanks uh great question question keep
them coming uh is that Poss is it
possible to combine the physical
property other than shape of an object
into the AR system um so perhaps
material or
Texture
um might be so I think you might be
referring to haptics in
that
prop um physical properties
um yeah sure
[Music]
MH yeah for that we we'll need more data
and uh if there's a real time uh yeah
for the question uh can we actually see
if there's any like a pressure or
temperature or or some sort of a uh like
measurement behind the actual uh behind
the virtual uh representation of the
system so yeah for uh for that we'll
definitely need more data we'll need
more um data acquisition linked to the
to the actual system but right now it's
all um I'll say not live it's it's more
static so once we build it it's the file
just U being sent to the headset uh and
we don't have that feedback like
real-time feedback loop that you would
call that you would expect from the
digital twin right so that's where
digital twin kind of comes into into
play so we we want to have that real
time interaction and that will be uh a
little bit heavier uh to process that
information because you need to have uh
some some level of control and uh we
need to connect the headset to to a
cloud and then where we can build those
uh like me take the measurements uh
acquire the data and and also overlay in
real time that I think that's
interesting uh thing to test but at this
moment we only have a static version of
of the of the building
it'd be a great use case though seeing
some real time real time data coming
through definitely
yeah um all right and anybody else I
know we we Arman kind of threw threw a
lot at you guys you know talking
everything about the development and
jumping into unity and have you used
Unity before jumping into the project
yeah that's the the thing that we I
haven't used Unity uh in my in my life
before uh and this is where um I felt
that the learning this process from
scratch was helped me find the I guess
the the bottlenecks or things in the
process where we can help improve and
focus on the on the on the right steps
to uh to get the model built uh as as
like fit for purpose right so we don't
spend too much time on developing things
that we don't we don't need for the
experience uh yeah but for and actually
we tested on L students that we just
joined this semester so we have this
workflow and we uh intr them to this uh
to this new uh like way of building this
experience and we were they were able to
catch this really fast so I think now
it's becoming a really powerful tool to
introduce this to new students uh and
they can learn and and develop this in
in uh in a much faster and efficient way
yeah and it's just working with VR and
AR as a headset and all of you know with
all of the complications and limitations
that you have on that because I like
what you mentioned early on kind of
balancing both the techn techical and
and how we can get kind of utility out
of this but also you know the artistic
side so figuring out what kind of
changes you need to do with the assets
but still being able to convey that
information and sustain the performance
on the headset because this has this has
to be Standalone right you do have to
walk around um so I just thought that
was incredible journey that you kind of
took us on and then you're asking is
this useful right jumping into that that
research side of thing so definitely
stay tuned uh everybody else to to see
what the outcomes on that uh project is
but in the meantime um I think that does
bring us down to our hour um so if
anybody does have any kind of continued
questions uh you can shoot us an email
at immersion at mit.edu that comes right
right to us but we will be back in 2025
um we don't have anything anticipated
for the December for our imers Series so
stay tuned for early January and um
thank you all for joining us today
thanks Armon thank you