Coastal climate science activities and
experiments is an educational tool that
helps kids learn and feel how we are
going from elevated levels of carbon
dioxide in the atmosphere to harm to
human beings to marine life and to the
ecosystems on Earth. It starts with the
greenhouse effect. The air gets warmer.
Warmer air leads to warmer water. The
water vapor is feeding into storms and
that's causing more hurricanes. When
students do this, they do a series of
experiments to get a sense of this
mechanism. The mechanism is physical or
chemical or biological. They're going to
see what it feels like to do that and
then say, where does this fit into the
overall cause and effect chain of how
increased carbon dioxide in the
atmosphere is leading to climate change
that's causing harm to marine life and
to human life. For more MIT moments from
MIT Open Learning, like, subscribe, or