I've been very fortunate to spend um
most of my career in two institutions
Berkeley and MIT that are very um I'd
say porous and collaborative towards um
towards industry I think in um uh at
Berkeley uh I directed something called
the Berkeley Center for New Media which
is a small uh interdisiplinary campus
center but we worked a lot with
different um um uh organizations in the
Bay Area technological and otherwise is
and um right before I left um Berkeley I
was uh uh the recipient of the
Craigslist chair in new media and we
collaborated with them around um
technology and questions and uh
questions of of media and they funded
this chair. So I think um uh you know as
I came to MIT uh it was particularly
interesting to me to see how well
integrated kind of uh MIT's innovation
engine was with the larger um uh
innovation engine of uh uh uh of not
only Cambridge but the the world at
large. So yeah, some of our most
interesting collaborations um uh have uh
being with partners around the future of
building the future of concrete
construction uh in the department is
very important. Uh just this last
semester I started a a kind of um a
research program uh here in the
department. I've I've kind of uh uh
worked to better integrate uh or even
better integrate the kind of work and
design and research that we do in the
department. Um and so we just started a
three-year cycle of um uh research about
uh the architecture of extreme
environments, not only outer space but
increasingly extreme environments here
on Earth, but that's involved a lot of
interesting industry collaborations as
well. And so I don't think um uh you
know one of the great parts about an
institution like MIT is you you have an
incredible world of ideas but you're
always asking how can these be in
service to the world in service to
society uh and not necessarily
instantly. That's you know it doesn't
work if you're always looking for the
kind of instant fix. Um because uh just
like in nature, things need to be
useless before they're useful uh and
evolved to become really important. The
space architecture studio is a
collaboration between ERA Astro and um
uh and the media labs space exploration
program. And so um uh but we have other
um uh another you know another huge um
uh part of what uh project in the
department in the last couple of years
has been um a series of climate research
studios um funded by a donation from um
uh Allan and Terry Spoon but also
involving partnerships with um in uh
recently the uh masonry industry and
local unions in um uh in Brooklyn here
in uh uh Massachusetts and New England
to really think about how we can um uh
reuse and remake buildings using um a
more circular approach to materials. And
so these are just some of the examples
of the kind of uh direct impact we have
with our design work here. So the you
know the architecture department one of
the most interesting things about
architecture a bit um you know my own
career encapsulates part of it but our
department is everything from historians
to engineers to practicing architects
and uh we we work with collaborators all
across the university from
nanotechnology to arastro to material
science. um uh this department is the um
is both the oldest um uh professional
department of architecture in North
America but also probably um the most
out there in terms of the extent to
which we're pushing the limits of
research and design and building. So
that's why it's an exciting place to be.
One of the um beyond my you know work in
the university and the research work uh
a big part of um my uh creative life is
uh my practice modem with my partner
Katherine Maul and you know that work
which can range from proposals for
massive urban sites to very specific uh
installations in galleries
collaborations with artists is really um
uh looks at questions of place um and
really looks at how we can create
singular objects and experiences which
both convey and at their best even
catalyze change in um uh the
intersection between a very local place
and an experience of a single body and
the largest possible systems that that
place is connected to.