Matthew, founder of Baymax.
>> Hi everyone, my name is Clara.
[cheering]
>> And today we are your host for this RPD
>> 422 AAA
[cheering]
5.
Got me
burning up.
Ready
[cheering]
[music]
go.
[cheering]
>> [cheering]
[screaming]
[cheering]
>> You feel
>> [cheering]
>> Let us start. [screaming]
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [cheering]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
with
>> [music]
>> is my dream, [music]
baby.
I'm [music]
so [music]
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> I think I can do this.
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> I know.
I know.
[music]
You don't care.
>> [music and singing]
>> 4 3 2 1
[music]
staring at the
only [music]
[music]
5 4 3 2
>> [music]
>> Everybody
[music] drama
my girls in the girls in the back
on [music] my drama.
My world in the back
[music] of my mind.
When my girls in the back in the
[music]
world in the back.
5 4 3 2
>> 1
[music]
5 4 3
How are you?
>> Your hat is so cute.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Are you recording?
[music]
4 3 2 1
>> get it. [music]
Hey,
help.
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
LA [music and singing]
we [music]
don't
[music]
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> Baby
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
I
>> [music]
>> Wait, I know. [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> It's so bad. It's good.
[music] My
king
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
My second
[music]
I feel
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> more than
the [music]
crazy
[music]
>> [music]
>> Everybody. [music]
broken.
[music]
Hey
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
>> like
[music]
for real
came out. I was like 5 4 3 2 1
Sweet days
and [music and singing] sweet
[music]
now that I'm without [music] you.
5 4 3 2 1
>> Baby
5 4 3 2
Yeah.
[music]
Where we go. [music]
Here
[music]
we go.
2 1
[music]
I want you [music]
to
[music]
super
>> [music]
>> Don't say no.
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> No. No. I mean, kind of.
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
No way you can make us.
We are about to paint [music] the town.
[music]
I can't stop us.
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
They moving back. [music]
4 3 2 1
[music]
I'm the only one. Oh my Oh my god. I got
a [music] good dream. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. You
make me feel like a [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2
>> crazy.
No doubt. [music]
[music]
in my head. [music]
Baby
[music]
5 4 3 2 1 [music]
I bring the pain
[music]
that
you wrapp
[music]
5 4 3 2
thinking
[music]
I'm
true.
>> [music]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
by
Got it. [music]
Don't care about [music]
5 4 3 2 1
crazy
just like crazy.
crazy. [music]
>> [music]
>> All the girls are both
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2
>> [music]
[music]
>> La
5 4 3 2 1
>> It's okay.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> until we have not
[music]
Super highlight.
4 3 2 1 [music]
I'm all going [music]
[music]
[singing]
2 1
g.
[screaming]
>> [music]
>> Sorry.
>> It's a good song. I think I've heard
nine coverage for no
reason.
I can't even imagine like I know the
difference
>> [music]
[music]
>> She got it.
3 2 1
[music]
birthday.
[singing]
[music]
I think I think [music] I think the
message
>> really
[music]
got all I need.
Hey. Yes. Let me see some action.
[music]
All
>> [music]
[music]
>> right, everyone. Here's a little tiny
break just cuz I want to make sure
people step back. I need
>> I need everyone on
I need everyone on this side to step to
your right. We cannot have people pass
this white line here. I'm so sorry. Even
if you're a performer. Performers, I
need you to leave your belongings and
then not be in this area. We have a lot
of expensive equipment. You cannot pack
this.
>> One more time. Need a lot over you guys.
Step couple more that way, please. A
couple more. People who are not
pedestrians who are just passing by,
please do not push our dancers and
please do not push towards us. Can you
guys move over to the couple?
>> Thank you so much. Look, we have so much
space. Yes. Thank you so much. Let us
continue.
>> Too far. Too wide.
[music]
and down up [music]
>> [music]
>> only
[music]
for some
My way.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> Um, everyone.
Super supernova. [music]
I'll put it back.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
5 4 3 2 1.
I'm so prick. I'm so prick.
Wake up. [music]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> Well, there goes my
4 3 2 1
I know [music]
I was a queen that I'm meant to be. I
live [music] to try to pay for something
[music]
to
[music] get
ster
Someone
[music]
5 4 3 2
>> [music]
[singing]
>> to walk.
>> [music]
>> Take
[music]
my
love.
Let's go.
>> [music]
>> Let me see. [music]
Me
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
She [music]
got me. [singing]
[music]
Okay. [music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Make that money.
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
This is my attitude.
5 4 3 2 1
[singing and music]
language
>> [music]
>> 5.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 practice
that [music]
we practice that
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
[music] over.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> together.
D
[music]
4.
Mr.
Shin
[music]
got [music]
fun.
We got fun. [music]
We got fun.
Open up.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
[singing]
My way
[music] better.
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
all day.
Baby,
it
back
cool.
5 4 3 2 1.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
2 1 Python. [music]
[music]
Heat. Heat.
5 4 3 2 1
[cheering]
[music]
>> You're about to
[music] Okay, everyone.
It's a moment.
[music]
Trying to guess.
>> [music]
>> You're the dead.
[music]
Hey. Hey. Hey.
4 3 2 1
[music]
Heat. Heat. Heat.
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> Let's go.
Okay, Kayla. You got it.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
4 3 2 1 [music]
[music]
until [music] we got your mind
out of control.
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
Laura next.
[music]
They were ready with their hands.
online.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1 [music]
All
right.
[music]
But I
won't let anything 5
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> really
[music]
excuse me
around
>> [music]
>> to this song with someone like a really
intense [music]
Three, two, one.
>> [music]
>> My baby
[music]
show
5.
[music]
[music] Look at me. Look at me.
Look at me. Look at me.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Show me baby.
[cheering]
[music]
I better [music]
break.
[music]
>> [screaming and cheering]
[screaming]
>> Yes.
>> 3 2 1.
[music]
>> I would I would
>> when they say high five This is what I
[music]
>> know. I got that that you like.
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> 13.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5
[music]
>> [music]
>> Do it like you.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
[music]
>> What in the world is 4
1?
[music]
>> [music]
>> Oh my god.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5
4 3 2 1
[music]
Oh my god.
me [music]
about
[music]
5 4 3 2
My ladies [music] don't get you know if
you
sad
[music]
>> [music]
>> Are you thinking about I'm thinking
about you? [music]
I should do
[music]
thinking about you.
I should
4 3 2 1
[music]
You got me.
>> 4 3 2 1 [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> this morning
3 2 1
[music]
Yeah,
5 4 3 2 1 [music]
Left, right, left, right.
[music]
If you know
this
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> popular
that retro soundtrack. You're like,
"Yes, this is 4 years ago. [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
Born [music] to be
born to
>> [music]
>> I can say
[music]
3 2 1
me.
Yeah.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
Let's [music] see.
[music]
2 1 [music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
Come on. Come on.
You should
say
that we needed earlier.
[music]
Look at that.
I just feel the older I get more.
[music]
>> Oh, I love the top.
3 2 1
[music]
story
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Everybody [music]
tell me
[music]
a little
more.
Hello. Hello.
>> Guys, all performers out of here.
>> Performers out of here.
[music]
>> If you are not back, please leave.
I wish
[music]
I
3 2 1
Baby. [music]
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
and I'm the [music]
killer
and I'm the
killer.
>> [music]
>> 5
4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> That's crazy. [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1 [music]
>> [music]
>> Oh Jesus Christ.
>> Wow. [music]
[music]
5 4 3 2
>> [music]
>> Can [music] I [singing] even give me all
[music]
the
Yeah.
[music]
[music] Now
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> I [music]
5 4 3 2 1
I just want you right now. I just want
you
[music]
know what I want.
Your mind
[music]
[singing]
and we can go high.
[music]
You know I can go my
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Wow.
>> Don't worry about it. [music]
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
[music]
>> I want
you to [music]
strangers
[music]
strangers.
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> Yeah.
Now you
[music]
4 3 2
>> [music]
>> down.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Everybody
[music]
5 4 3 2
Oh my god.
Wow.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> Look how
quiet.
>> I think it's just [music]
>> Wow, y'all keep looking.
Now look at me. Look at you. Now look at
me.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Tell me
baby
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
outside.
I forgot. [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
I feel okay. No pain [music]
tonight
because
[music]
I
Don't [music] you
always
2 1
[music]
[music and singing]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
D.
[singing]
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
[cheering]
[music]
>> 4 3 2 1
check those [music]
Check
down check.
[music]
4 3 2
We're going to play
[music and singing]
[music]
say about
5 4 3 2 1
Girls, [music] we don't shake.
[music]
Come on. Come on. Come on.
>> [cheering]
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
>> [cheering]
[music]
[singing]
>> Can you come back
[music]
here?
It's all about
5 4 3 2 1
E.
[music]
>> [music]
[cheering]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Hands up.
>> [music]
[music]
>> without
you. [music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Show me
>> [music]
>> this way. [music]
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Let's
get this
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Forever. [music]
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Maniac.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
Do
I do [music]
yeah
[music]
go [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2
>> [music]
>> fresh.
[music]
Everybody [music]
Only [music]
only real.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2
someone [music]
who you [music] are with
[music]
I need you
to [music]
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
[singing]
fire [music]
shing shining.
So [music]
my head
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
Two, two, one. Two. Two. [music] One.
Two. Two. One.
4 3 2 1 [music]
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> I'm on the last [music]
level. No more. You're the next
[music]
level.
[music] They got you next level. Take it
down. Take it down.
La.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> Take it up.
Let the sky up.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
Heat. Heat.
[music]
Let
go.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
sing [singing]
[music]
it down. I want you. I want you.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
together
with you. With you [music]
forget
[music]
[cheering]
Heat. Heat. Heat. [music]
2 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
I just got to get
you
5 4 3 2 1
>> Oh my god.
>> [cheering]
>> Hey,
dance.
[cheering]
Let's go. Okay. [music]
Be careful.
Yeah. [music]
Okay.
[music]
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
[music]
>> I saw you from
December.
Oh my god.
>> 5 4 3 2 1
No.
Hallelujah. [music]
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
The lights [music]
[music]
again. [music]
Yeah. Yeah.
[music]
>> [cheering]
>> Hey,
[music]
4 3 2 1.
>> I was like [music] Yes.
4 3 2 1 [music]
Too much.
[music]
>> [music]
>> I'm going.
[music]
[music] Oh my god.
>> [cheering]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> you
[music]
make it.
Come on.
>> [music]
>> Me
[music]
what you want to
>> [music]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
I
Okay.
Back back.
[cheering]
4 3 2 1.
>> [music]
>> So good.
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> Down.
[music]
4 3 2 1. Hallelujah. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
right now.
[music]
Hallelujah.
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> I can do this all day.
Back it up. Back it up.
>> [music]
>> 5
[music] minutes.
We're not going to [music]
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> Everybody
[music]
broken fire.
We go. We go.
I was like, "Boy,
[music]
>> I thought
I like that.
Don't wait.
This is very [music]
[music]
excuse
somebody
[music]
2 1
me.
play [music]
first.
[music]
Who's mad as me?
>> 5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> going to make you
happy.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1.
[music]
Hey,
>> first [music]
[music]
do it. [music]
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Let you know
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
[screaming]
[music]
5.
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
again.
Make you
[music]
make you
5 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> 5
4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[singing]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
[cheering]
>> 4 3 2 1
[music]
Good.
I'm I'm a man.
All right, everybody. We got a little
break again.
And
>> we're
>> we're going to have we're going to have
our two uh additional Tik Tok challenges
at this moment. The second
>> So the first one we're going to be doing
by Cordice. If you have a chance, please
come up to the front. Try to condense as
close as possible.
>> Step up and show your best wish to go.
>> Also will be sent to
Try to open up.
Try to open up and give windows open so
everyone can be seen. Okay.
married.
>> All right.
Oh my god.
[music]
>> Hey
I just
[music]
got my new
Hey,
I'm a new
[music]
shoo.
>> [cheering]
>> Good job.
>> All right, we got
>> We got our second Tik Tok challenge.
It's going to be
>> Golden
Eddie K-pop man. Come on.
We're looking for dancers who can shine
a gold.
A come on up up.
Where was that? She went
to her. Where she at?
[music]
>> [music]
>> to believe I was a queen.
I live
[music]
on [singing] my own.
Now that's how I'm getting.
[music]
[cheering]
>> Thank you so much for joining us on our
true Tik Tok challenge.
>> I feel like we sealed the home today.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Oh, I don't think anyone else. Did
we seal the home today? All
right.
>> Um, at this moment we're going to take
some pictures. We're going to take a
huge
>> group picture
everyone can just come to the center. If
you're taller, please stand up in the
back. If you're shorter, please pass
down in the front.
We want to highlight your lovely outfits
and costumes.
Please come in all the way.
>> I see I see you guys over there. Come
on. Join the picture.
>> Come on over. Join the
join the join the picture.
Join. You guys want
>> All righty.
Any other staff? Come on in. You're
good. Okay.
>> Who are we looking at?
>> Look at this one. Look at this one. Look
at this one.
>> Let's get to the sun.
>> 3 2 1
>> Can we do a cute pose? Maybe do some
carts.
>> Three, two, one.
What? One more picture. One more. No,
no, no. Okay, we're all set.
>> All righty.
So
>> before we wrap, we want to say a huge
thank you to Media Live NYC, our
sponsors, our performers, and all of you
guys for bringing your energy to Times
Square. Give it up for yourself.
[cheering]
Let's do a big round of applause and
cheer for Media Lab.
>> And thank you so much to all of our
performers and sponsors.
Hey guys, I'll make a little uh thank
you. Okay, so hey everyone. First and
foremost, I want I just want to thank
you all so much for being here today at
this huge beauty event. It really truly
means the world seeing so many people
come together for something we all love.
A massive thank you to our sponsors and
to all the incredible groups supporting
us today. And of course, thank you to
Media Lab. Lu are you?
>> Oh, hi. Thank you. [cheering] Thank you
so much for giving us the chance to
collaborate and bring this team in Time
Square. So, amazing Clara, my Clara,
thank you for doing this with me. And to
our [cheering] staff member, you know,
thank you for always helping and always
being here for us. I also want to thank
take a moment to thank every single
performer who took their time and effort
and energy to be here. You guys bring so
much life, talent, and heart to this
community. And to my friends and to my
friends, thank you for always supporting
me through everything. And thank you
believing in my passion, ambitions. I
always support you the same way you
support me. Okay.
>> Lastly, I want to leave you all with
this. In our generation, we see so much
hate and judgment and criticism,
especially online. But today reminds us
something bigger that we can create
spaces for of love, support, and
respect. So, let's make this community a
place where everyone feels safe to
express themselves and enjoy K-pop for
what for what it's meant to be. kind,
inspiring, and unifying.
>> Let's continue this
[cheering and applause] fight kindness,
lift each other up, and stand for what's
right always. And thank you everyone.
And let's keep dancing. And I want to
use this moment to say eyes and
[cheering]
>> All right. So, this has been your MC
Clara and MC Matthew. [cheering]
>> Thank you so much for joining us. And we
actually have a little encore RPD
session. So if you'd like to finish it
off, we got around 15 minutes or so. 15
to 20 more minutes of RGB. Let's
[laughter]
slow it down.
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
[music]
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
>> Hey, hey, hey.
4.
[music]
Baby, I'll make you
>> [music]
>> Disney
[music]
>> [music]
>> Why don't you know? Don't you know?
Don't you know?
[music]
I feel
I
suck.
[music] Let's
go.
[cheering]
[music]
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
[cheering]
>> 4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> 2. [music]
[music]
4.
>> [music]
>> 5 4 3 2 1
>> to me.
I love [music]
I want to [music]
[music]
know. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> 4.
Yeah.
I am
[music]
praying tonight.
I don't know.
[music]
team shot.
>> So he like can't go anymore
and they want to use a camera.
>> Can I
No, no, no, no. [music]
looking for
[music]
like
1.
[music] Baby
girl
1191. [music] My life.
[music]
I'm feeling
4 3 2 1
Happy birthday.
[music]
3.
Oh my god.
[music]
4 3 2 1
>> [music]
>> No, no, no, no, no.
[music]
>> I don't know if they want to.
They might have
the camera. [music]
like [music]
[music]
pretty
high.
>> [cheering]
[music]
>> 5 4 3 2
>> [music]
[music]
>> Baby
Christmas. [music]
Are they here?
[cheering]
>> 4 3 2 1 [music]
My
[music]
feeling.
>> [music]
>> 4 3 2
>> better [music]
[music]
through the solar system.
Yeah. Heat. Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> How you see
[singing]
[cheering]
2 1
[music]
Let a little
Cheeto. [music]
[music]
>> What is this?
5 4 3 2 1
[music]
I want nobody nobody [music] but you.
Nobody nobody
[music]
nobody
nobody nobody
[music] nobody but you
nobody
[music]
5 4 3
You got [music]
my hand
[music]
2 1
2 3
[music]
>> [music]
>> That was so
[music]
like it doesn't end up
>> [music]
>> 3 2
>> Come on. Come on.
[music]
5 4 3 2 1
I'm not [music] girl. I'm at home. I'm
not
I'm [music]
[music]
5 4 3 2 1 2 [music]
again. [music]
[music]
>> 3 2 1 I check my calendar [music] later.
already.
>> What? You didn't listen to it yet?
>> It's so good. [music]
>> I listened so bad. I have five.
>> [music]
>> You're going to do this.
>> Really?
Wow.
[cheering]
>> Wait, wait, wait a second. Can everyone
here win all the people inside the
video?