Our first session is about data
analytics and digital twins to realtime
control by Dr. Brian Anthony, principal
research scientist at MI at MIT's
department of mechanical engineering and
associate director of MIT Nano. Please
post your questions into the Q&A tab.
Dr. Anthony, welcome. The floor is
yours.
>> Very good, Eduardo. Uh, thank you. And
good morning, good evening, good
afternoon, everybody. I know some people
we have live and some people will be
watching this after the fact. So um what
I want to do today in the next say 30
minutes is uh teach you a little bit uh
and inspire you a little bit around the
the art of possible and as Eduardo said
sort of the intersection of of data
science and operations uh but sort of
digital twins machine learning all these
concepts do come together in an
interesting way. So the agenda some
opportunities and needs I think they
abound in mining. Why isn't mining fully
data enhanced already? Question. Um
share a little bit of the the art of the
possible that are tools that you should
be using already. Code automation as a
sort of a a level setting of what you
can do now. um sort of some motivation
for how to take how to how to approach
designing [snorts] in a ecosystem such
as mining or manufacturing where you
need to have both domain knowledge and
take advantage of modern instrumentation
tools whether it be data science or
sensors and then close with some rapid
dive examples. So we like to say
education at MIT is like drinking from a
fire hose. So I'm going to turn the the
fire hose on uh and do please chat with
questions. Um so there are many valuable
data science digital twin which is a
digital twin just a model that's updated
over time but valuable opportunities in
mining. So it's resource intelligence
mind-to-mill optimization integrated
autonomous operations overall improved
reliability safety geotechnical risk and
certainly energy and sustainability. So
there's a lot of opportunities and you
could ask well why why are we having
this webinar? Why aren't mining
operations smart and automated already?
If you ask a chat GPT that question and
tell it to generate an image, well,
these are the two images that it'll
generate for you. So, why aren't mining
operations smart already? Um there's a
nice survey put out by mining magazine a
year ago um that emphasizes that very
there aren't a large number of companies
far less than majority of companies that
are actually reporting machine learning
AI deployments in the mining space and
the biggest barrier reported in that
survey to entry is the the lack of
knowledge in the workforce to how to
deploy skill how to deploy different
technologies whether it be novel sensors
or analytics and then certainly the
availability of of sensors and and
interoperability of of technologies that
you can deploy into the harsh harsh
environments of of mining and mining
operations.
So part of today is is making sure that
you're aware of of what the new tools
that are available can possibly do to
help at least reduce some of the skills
challenges. It hasn't solved the skills
challenges, but um and then we'll take
it from there.
So I I know I imagine that all of you
and if you have not had the chance to
have a uh an interaction with with
Gemini with chat GPT um um please do. So
let me just level set everybody with
what are the the new tools that are
possible. So I wanted to start from
scratch in in preparing my these slides
for you. I wanted to say, well, how how
fast could somebody that knows
at least a little bit of the data that
they have, how could you use machine
learning tools, things like chat GPT and
Gemini to augment
your understanding of how to analyze
data. So what do I mean mean by that? I
I found this in in one day. Let me share
with you what I did in one day in
preparation at least this section of my
talk. I found this open data set um data
mining challenge from 2016 predicting
dangerous seismic event events in active
coal mines. So in this data set there
are almost 80,000 records um with data
on seismic activity different um sort of
measurements of accelerometry
of of
number of different temperature sensors
different site information and the data
is labeled and in that it has a labeling
as whether or not in the subsequent day
it was a normal day of operation or
there was actually seismic activity. Um
so the data is labeled well and the
prior day
are we able to predict you know the the
labeling of the data was the following
day was a normal day or there was a
heavy seismic activity that maybe we
could have been alerted to. So we have
80,000 data records and the question
posed by this challenge and and the the
question that you would often want to
ask in a in a data science application
of data is I have some historical data
some observations that I have labelings
for. You know I have the last three
years of of data where I have seismic
activity and I and I know whether the
following day whether there was an
active seismic event or not. So we would
like to take that historical data, learn
the mapping between an input and an
output. The input in this case would be
the seismic activity, different
temperature sensors, sort of
environmental conditions and then to
predict whether the following day is
going to be a normal day or there's
going to be seismic activity. Right? So
we want to learn a classifier. We want
to learn a machine learning tool back in
in the future. Observe what's happening
today and predict what's going to happen
tomorrow. Are we going to have a seismic
event based on all the sensory data?
Right? So this is a a classical very
sort of classical machine learning
problem where we have some some
observations here. I've oversimplified.
We have some observations, some
historical observations that we have
some labeling. We know that one side is
normal, one side is warning. And we want
to be able to learn what that boundary
is. And that's what that's a it's a good
machine learning problem. And we're
doing this on seismic data. So So what
did I do? I downloaded the data and I
loaded it to big tables and I loaded
that into uh Google cloud and then I
spent two minutes typing the bold lines
that you see here into chat GBT said
well I'm I've loaded this data I have
training data that's the t I had the
labeling whether or not it was normal or
warning the following day and then I
have some validation data that I'm not
going to use in the training and I also
have labels associated with that. So I'm
I'm I what I would like to do is is
train a particular type of classifier.
In this case, a random forest
classifier. It's a it's a classifier
that's a game of 20 questions, if you
will. And that's not the important
thing. I I know this thing. I've heard
of this thing called a a random forest
classifier. So I want to train a
classifier that's going to be able to
predict warning versus normal on the
training data. And I would like to
validate its performance on the
validation data. So this is the coding
that I'm going to tell you that I this
is all that I did. I loaded the data and
I typed this. I said improve I gave the
instructions to chat GPT improve this
coding prompt.
Well, what did chat GPT give to me? Chat
GPT improved my prompt. So I first like
that's what I want to do. And chat GPT
said, well, okay, well here's a a more
expansive. I thought for 30 seconds and
it gave me a little bit more nuance of
the things that I might be wanting to
think about. I didn't generate this. All
I generated was the five lines of human
text and it said, "Well, here's some
inputs. Here's some more clarity on what
we think are the tasks." So, I did not
edit this at all. I took that and then I
swapped over to a a different machine
learning tool. I jump jumped over to
Collab which is uh Google's online uh
Python environment um that has its
companion language model interpreter
called Gemini and I dumped that prompt
the prompt here that was generated by
chat GPT I dumped that into Gemini and
say hey create the code that will do
this and run it.
So this all that you're seeing on these
following slides are code that was
created by Gemini in response to that
request. It's Python code. It's five
slides of code that would have taken me,
you know, a a day of solid day to make
sure I debugged it. Um, it sort of looks
at the data, make sure there's no
missing data, make sure that it it
converts text data uh to numeric data in
a in a creative way called one hot
encoding. that's not important. Um, and
then it trained the model. This model
training, well, there was about an hour
of me debugging because Gemini didn't do
a perfect thing. So, I did a little bit
of debugging. Um, but it generated the
after I did that debugging, the model
took about two hours to train and and
then it ran this code to well, how how
well does it work on the on the
validation set? And it has a really high
accuracy, a really high precision. um
generates some plots automatically and
these are the plots of the final result.
It it identified automatically for me
the features in my data that were
important. It gives me an ROC curve that
tells me how well the classifier works.
How often is it predicting the right
thing? How is it predicting the wrong
thing? And it's not perfect, but I I
took two minutes to type and in a little
bit of time to debug, two hours of the
computer in the background running
itself to develop one type of
classifier. It's this the the the model
here is a a decision tree which takes as
input all this seismic data, tremors,
energy, and it's now has a way to
predict whether or not tomorrow is going
to be a normal day uh or a warning day.
So, this is truly amazing, right? These
tools are amazing and I and I say this,
I'm sure some of you are familiar with
that. But I did so very very little. I
wrote these five lines of text. I loaded
the data. I knew the right things to ask
for it. I I did have to do the
debugging. So these new tools are going
to help, right? They don't they don't
solve all the world's problems, right?
We're not replacing humans. We're going
to need to do different things. We're
going to need to be managers of these
tools and know how to use them
appropriately. The new tools are going
to help with some of the training
problem. There needs there remains a
strong need for sensors. There remains a
strong need for the context of how we
collect data. And indeed, there's much
to learn from manufacturing. And when
we're designing ways to be smart, to be
automated, we need to take into account
both the physical context, domain
knowledge, and what sensors can give us,
the data, the information-rich data can
tell us. And we don't want to put too
much burden on our our algorithms. We
would like to be as intelligent as
possible in the deployment of our
sensors.
So, first, um, here are just five slides
that I'm going to show up real quick.
And there's you you'll there's some
literature references on the bottom that
you can go to, but I I show these these
are areas now that are that are being
addressed that are bringing to bear this
concept of data science and automation.
These are both academic and industry
literature uh in the mining space,
right? Just to motivate the deep dives
that I'm going to tell you. So or body
modeling and resource estimation under
uncertainty you know you can sort of see
why and like the references here are at
the bottom and things like you know
real-time control of machinery and
operations and creating digital twins. A
digital twin is a is a model that's
updated with some data can be physics
informed and data informed but allows us
to predict the future. How do we choose
to dispatch our trucks and do um the
logistics of operations? How do we
maintain our equipment? How do we
monitor when machinery is starting to
break down? Whether it be uh trucks out
in the field or the maintenance
equipments that is doing the sort of the
separation and and and uh combination uh
and then being able to control
processes.
So these are just sort of a laundry list
of things that are you you're seeing in
the academic and industry literature,
but now we need to figure out how to
bring these things to bear. So the key
ideas that I want to make sure that you
have is in in the mining space in the
manufacturing space that I'm going to
draw some analoges from you you want to
take a a bilingual or a two axis
approach right we're able to be
successful because we have new AI tools
better sensors but we can only be
successful if we bring our domain
knowledge to bear the physics the types
of questions that we should ask and
answer in the mining industry as domain
experts, you know, the processes and the
machines, what are the questions to ask,
what the what information would you like
to get out of your data and and data
science experts can help us understand
the the types of algorithms and how to
use these tools and actually you don't
need to be a data scientist anymore to
do basic level of of coding as I tried
to highlight at the beginning.
So what I want to do now um in the next
say 15 minutes is show you now some
personal examples things that are
happening at MIT uh that are in the
space of of both manufacturing
uh and automation and operations and in
novel sensors that are applicable both
in manufacturing and in healthcare and
in mining as it turns out. Um but
putting it into sort of two two
contexts. So twins, digital twins are
just models and they're we can have
twins of many sorts. We can have um
physics based twins, data twins, and we
can have twins of an individual process
or a machine. And we can develop twins
of an entire operation. So I'll tell you
a story about a twin of a machine. And
then I'll tell you about tools of how
you twin and model a complete operation,
whether it be a factory or a mine, for
example. And then don't forget that all
of our data come from sensors. And so
I'll tell you both about a a physical
sensor um that is built on a new
technology called integrated photonics.
It's the miniaturization same way that
we make micro electronics. We can now
that miniaturaturize optical systems and
make optical systems on in the form
factor that fit onto sort of phone like
devices um that allow us for example to
do non-cont measurements in the field.
And then talking a little bit about how
machine learning tools can help us
improve our our soft sensors, our
virtual sensors and and being able to
for example accelerate how we solve
inverse problems and meaning how do we
take our seismic data and and rapidly
estimate well what is the domain what is
the geography what is the landscape
below the land that explains those
seismic observations that we had. Okay.
So first um first deep dive you know
here is a an example just to motivate it
um that we've done with a manufacturing
company and they they have this this um
machine and you know think of this
machine as as as a as a vehicle as a
mill as a in this case a packaging
machine and we collect data from this
machine. In this case, what this machine
does is wraps packages. And there's a
mech there's mechanical wear on this
machine. And that mechanical wear is
associated with the bearings. It's also
associated with the the blade that's
used to cut the plastic wrap that wraps
around this package. And so the question
is, well, how can we use the data? Take
the data that we're already collecting
for free in some sense and and monitor
the health of the machine. This
machine's doing a task. It's wrapping
packages. But can we also extract
additional information about from these
data from these data? This is the data
associated with one package coming
through this machine. It's torque versus
time. It's position of the blade that's
cutting the plastic wrap. It's the
velocity of the package. It's all the
time series control system data that's
dealing with one package as it passes
through this machine. And the question
is well can we can we extract not just
well we're doing our job packaging but
can we say something about well are the
bearings wearing is the blade wearing so
that was the question and the answer is
indeed yes and the tool that we're going
to use is this thing called a decision
tree this thing that I sort of
introduced at the very beginning with
what GPT uh coded for me or Gemini coded
for me um but we have this this this
historical data for every package and
then we also um have as our labeling,
right? In in machine learning, we need
to have historical data that has both an
input output relationship where in the
future we have an input, we're trying to
predict the output. Here we're trying to
predict the health of the machine. In
this case, the health of the machine,
we're going to use as a surrogate for
health, the age of the machine since it
was last maintained. So, the time since
the last maintenance when we lubricated
it, sharpened the blade, etc.
I'm going to spare the details because
that's not important for today. But the
this decision trees and their sort of
their collection of trees which is
called a random forest is really just a
series of questions that we ask on our
data. And in this case here we're asking
questions on the on the chat GPT example
we were asking questions about seismic
energy to detect whether or not there
was going to be a seismic activity
tomorrow. Here we're taking all this
sensory data, the speeds, the positions,
the torqus of this machine, and we
predict the health, the age of the
blade. Yeah. And we can have different
different labeling in our historic data.
We chose in this case to use the as a
surrogate for where the age the time
since it was last maintained. But we we
have now a very easy tool that is taking
as inputs this these data we're
collecting for free and predicts well
how healthy is the machine so that we
can do condition monitoring and
prediction well what we need to do is
well how well does this model work and
here what I'm plotting is comparing now
we we use some of our historical data to
train and then we're going to use some
of our historical data to ask the
question how well did the the training
work how well is the model behaving what
you would want in In a perfect model
that would trained well on historic data
that we use to do the training and
generalizes well to our validation data,
you would expect you want zero error
between what the model predicts and what
the truth is. So we split our data use
some of it to train and here on the
validation data we want to be able to
predict what is the reality. And so what
we would want on this plot is a bunch of
zeros. we would want the error between
the predicted age and the actual age to
be zero. But we see here there's it's
not we have a lot of zeros, but for each
package that goes through sometimes
we're we're 10 months off in the
apparent age, the apparent wear, and
we're eight months off in the other
direction. But what do you do with a
noisy sensor? Right? So I I I show this
because I want to emphasize here is a
great example where if you were just a
machine learning expert, say I look at
this and this is not a great model.
Maybe I need to use a a neural net or
support vector machine. But here I've
I've made a a a decision tree which is a
noisy sensor that takes as input the
data I have and predicts a noisy output.
And what do I do with noisy sensors? I
filter them. I apply moving average. I
use the things that I classically know
how to do in analyzing data. And then
doing that using that physical context
now I can actually use this in a way
that makes sense.
So I guess my message there is sort of
even bad models or sort of bad from a m
purely machine learning perspective uh
when used correctly uh can be very very
very good. Okay, so that's what example
one. So how do we use data in monitoring
the health of the machine? So now this
this next sort of example is um I know
I'm sure some of you are using um what
is called discrete event or discrete
time simulation in the simulation of
operations. But in my experience, I've
found that many organizations both in
the manufacturing domain and in the
mining domain are not. So how do you
model operations at at an appropriate
level? I can drill down into individual
machines, but how do I how do I model,
for example, this factory or how do I
model the flow of machines when machines
can sometimes break down and sometimes
they can be they take some time when
they're broken down to be maintained and
be repaired. At some aggregate level, we
can think of every piece of equipment as
being modeled as um how often when it's
up, how long is it up? And when it's
down, how long is it down? So to first
order, I can look at my maintenance
logs, understand the meanantime to
repair, the meantime to fail, and
mathematically I can think of a a a
piece of equipment or a road as having
as being in one of several states. It
can be in an upstate or a down state. At
any instance in time is informed by
historical data of how often when
something's operational, it stays
operational or when it's down, how long
it stays down. I can think of a machine
as being up or down, healthy or good.
And at any next interval in time
tomorrow, if it's up, what's the
likelihood of it still staying up, of it
staying in a good state, or what's the
likelihood of it transitioning? So, the
data we collect, the the big data that
we want to collect to model operations
are are um things like this, the
maintenance logs, how long is something
up and down? Now, how do I then use that
observational data to then create a
model to create a twin that allows me to
predict the future or to decide for
example
what would be the benefit of doubling my
maintenance staff so that my the the
likelihood the rate with which I came
back from a a sick state a down state to
a a healthy state was twice as fast. So,
how do I play some what if scenarios in
investing in different machinery or or
or hiring more people? So, the modeling
tool is nothing more than to
oversimplify flipping a biased coin. So,
I can use a biased coin if I if I know
my machine is going to be up 90% of the
time. Well, I can, you know,
algorithmically, you know, here's
graphically, but algorithmically, I can
I can generate a random number that is
not that's 90% that's that's heads 90%
of the time. And so I can model all the
all the equipment that has different
healthy states. I can model capture the
historical data when things are up, when
things are down, and I can model that up
down time by just flipping a bunch of
random coins. Now, that is a notion.
It's oversimplified, but that as a
notion is what tools such as any logic
or plant sim
um use to monitor many types of domains.
Here I I'll show you some results from a
tool called any logic. And what any
logic does is is allow you to simulate
operations at the level of machines are
up, machines are down, roads are
blocked, roads are down. And it has
under the hood basically this simple
logic where I assign probabilities of
things being up or down and and then
letting my let my virtual world operate.
Now the reason you will pay some dollars
for a tool like this um if for this
video play uh this is the the 3D
rendering of a copper ore mine um where
we have some trucks going around and
they're they're sort of you know doing
both inspection and sort of routing out
and we have different camera views. So
this gives you a nice graphical way to
see sort of physically to map have a
mental image of what's going on. But the
reality is well under the hood it's
actually I can look at it from 2D and
understand what how in my simulation how
things are moving around but then I can
actually you see how resources are being
used and I can play some scenarios well
how do how do operations improve if I
change the number of trucks or if I I
change the number of resources available
and so this gives me now a tool to then
play what if like how does my throughput
how does my utilization change um and to
then be able to use this to take simple
data of general availability of
equipment, general flow, and be able to
then ask what if questions. Um, and
ultimately under the hood, what we're
really doing is flipping some bias coins
that allow us to simulate material flow,
people flow through a complex operation.
Now, I'm I'm dramatically simplifying
and going very fast on that, but I I
highlight it because as a tool, in my
experience, it's an underutilized way to
be able to represent physical operations
both in in manufacturing and in mining.
Okay. So, I think um we're getting a
little bit close to time here, but let
me let me show you um sort of two quick
examples just to inspire you in the the
art of what's possible. So um
there is a um what's called the photo
acoustic effect. If I take a laser beam
and I shine it a pulse laser beam and I
shine it on material whether that be
rock, dirt, steel, aluminum or tissue at
the right wavelength for that material.
If I take a pulsed laser, the light will
be absorbed by the material and it will
slightly heat up and that heat up causes
an expansion and that expansion
dissipates as sound. And that sound will
then propagate and I that sound will
then propagate through a medium and and
then I can also use another laser by
want so I can use light to generate
sound in a non-cont way. I can then use
another laser acting as an
interferometer
monitoring at some point on the surface
of the earth or of steel or of a person
and monitor the sound wave as it goes
by. So in this way I can use two light
sources, two lasers, a pulse laser and a
continuous wave laser to both generate
sound in a medium from a distance and to
detect and to detect sound.
And I and I I highlight this more
because I have a hypothesis. Um we're
developing this technology. This is this
image here is showing something that we
developed 30 years ago and using fully
non-cont measurement of silicon wafers
undergoing rapid thermal processing.
More recently, we've done that same type
of phenomena on people where we can now
at 2 meters away, shining two laser
beams on a person, generate an
ultrasound image of the sort that you
would acquire at if you were putting a
contact probe in in contact with the
person. Um and again it's relying on
sort of pulse lasers to generate sound
and a continuous wave laser to detect
the vibration of the surface scan that
over the material surface to see
subsurface to see in this case what a
slice into the the human body would look
like. Now this is the the macro scale
optics that we used. I mentioned just
briefly integrated photonix is a
technology
that is allowing us to miniaturaturize
optical systems. So all of this sort of
tabletop meter scale of technology now
fits through the benefit of what is
called integrated photonics. It's
basically making small optical fibers on
a substrate the same way that we can
make small wires on a substrate. All of
that technology is now on a chip that
fits into a box. And my you can see my
hand here. I know it's my hand because
it has one of my rings on it, but is
sort of a little bit bigger than an
iPhone, but now this is now a system, a
sensor that allows us to do non-cont
ultrasound using light to generate sound
and using light to detect sound. And I I
I have to believe and this is more on
the research side of things. I have a
hypothesis but I I have to believe that
there are some mining opportunities and
would love to chat with folks on this.
Now going back to sort of things that
are are deployed already. So one one
last case example I'll share with you.
Um and this is more on the soft sensor
side of the world and when you're trying
to make sense of data and you'll hear
more about this from the talks after
mine um from the the different
companies. Uh one of the problems, one
of the common needs in in the mining
world and seismic world is solving
inverse problems. Meaning taking my
observational data and figuring out well
what was the world that explains that
observational data. So if I had for
example a domain on a seafloor and I I
could I can write down physics and tell
you if I if I generate a pulse of
acoustic energy how that energy is going
to propagate. That's the forward
problem. But what I'm what I'm presented
with the data that I collect this is the
data that I collect and I need to solve
the inverse problem. I need to collect
that data say well what was the domain
that explained that observation I'm
trying to do imaging I'm trying to
collect all this data and the way that
we typically do that is by iteratively
solving a forward problem but solving
the inverse problem says okay I'm going
to keep solving the forward problem
changing the physical parameters of my
world changing the the dimensions the
elastic properties until I've over hours
and hours and hours of iteration have
figured out well what are the parameters
what is the domain what is the layers
what's the speed of sound in the layers
that allows me to say hey yeah given
those observations this is what my
domain this is what my speed of sound
map look like so what I want to um
excite you about is something that we've
done to accelerate that inverse model so
what do we do we we take we we rely on
the fact that physics we have really
good physics that allow us to predict
the forward problem. So let's instead of
using the forward problem iteratively in
an inverse solution, let's pre-generate
synthetic data. Let's generate a bunch
of domains,
let's use the the wave equation to
predict what our sensor input would be.
So instead of doing this every time
we're trying to solve an inverse
problem, do it once. generate a massive
quantity of inverse data and then train
a network train a network on how to
solve that inverse problem
and I let's see there it goes so we
train a network to take as as input you
know we take our historical data our
synthetic data pass all the time series
data and say hey we want to learn how to
directly map from that raw data to what
the domain is
and and so Here this is just uh some
experimental results of showing all
these different individual blocks or the
different domains that we simulated and
then um the reconstructed on synthetic
data. But what we're able to do now is
real time inversion.
Real time where we pass the raw data and
instead of iteratively running a physics
informed loop at the time when we solve
the problem, we generate our or we
pre-generate that synthetic data and
directly in real time can ingest the
input and predict what is the domain,
what's the speed of sound, what are the
structures uh that we're seeing in that
domain.
Okay, so I know that was a lot. Um, what
I really wanted to cover is is sort of
it's critical. You know, the machine
learning tools that are available are
going to accelerate the way that we can
collect and analyze data. It doesn't
change the fact that we need sensors. We
need our physical context when designing
the systems that allow us to be
impactful in this space. Um, and so with
that, um, if we have time for questions,
I'll I'll take one. Um, but also happy
to follow up, uh, online.
Yeah, we have time for a couple of quick
uh answers to questions. One question
from the audience is a hurdle is uh that
the this
keep facing is the lack of data or
rather sparely a populated data and
handling them especially labeled ones
like description or type of failure
observed in an equipment. Any particular
helpful ways you have implemented to
deal with this from a data science
perspective?
Right. So I mean if we we we need data
um and
but at the same time you know the being
strategic I guess that it's not a data
science solution. It's it's more of a a
system solution. How do you how are you
strategic in investing in the right
places to get the targeted data? So
that's where the domain knowledge comes
in. That's sort of one part of the
answer. And the other one is um in this
era of soft sensors, well what what are
the what are the data that we could
collect that are correlated with
something that we would like to measure
and having physics informed and data
enhanced ways to sort of predict the the
the the
hidden property that's not directly
measured but it's correlated with thing
that we can measure. So it's it's yeah
it's it's a to to make sense of data.
Yes, we need the data. But I I think
where you're going to be most successful
though is not re relying purely on the
data. Sort of relying on what's called
the sort of the gray box model where we
have some physical knowledge that
informs what type of sensors to
strategically deploy and then how to
make the most extract the most
information out of the data as informed
by physics as opposed to relying on just
big data uh and not bringing any
physical context.
And Brian, the last question. How
photonic sensors reacts to dust and fog
and humidity often present in mines?
>> No. Awesome question. I mean, like any
any um we've not put a photonic sensor
in a mine yet. So, just in full
disclosure, um but like any electronic
device, yes, you have to deal with the
environmental issues. So, here the
device that we're I showed you briefly,
uh we're putting that into some clinical
medical environments that are that are
moist and and and need to be cleaned and
sanitized. Um, but the any electronic
device or optical device is going to
have sort of ranges of both temperature
and humidity and to make the r a rugged
device. Yes, there's still work to be
done on on that. Um, and we've not done
that. Um, but I I would be very again,
this is more of the I'm I'm being a
little bit selfish here. I would love to
talk with people that can tell me more
about how to what might be the
appropriate opportunities to deploy
those types of sensors in the mining
environment and would welcome the
opportunity to sort of further the
activities on our commercialization side
that are getting those out into medical
and manufacturing domains to understand
well maybe we can also do this in the
mining domain.