okay uh let me go ahead and get started
um so you know today I'm starting my uh
uh week on uh static competition so um
you know think about what's going on
here you know I so so far the first two
weeks have mostly been Monopoly models
obviously you know most comp most
Industries or most things have interest
have multiple firms in it so you know
I'm going to now start you know every
lecture for the rest of the term it's
going to be multiple firms competing um
you know and terroll goes through his
book he does sort of this long run to
Short Run chart where he sort of talks
about you know in the short run firms
can basically do nothing in competing
with each other other than setting
prices and then you get this sequence of
variables that take longer and longer to
adjust and I think the way his book is
written is is in some sense the you know
the way we solve models is always by
backward like multi-stage games by
backward induction you solve the last
stage and the next to last stage and the
next to last stage and so you know his
book is sort of written this way where
you go backward from here and that's you
know kind of how my course is written
although these days it's really going to
be an awful lot of discussion of this
and then other things just as individual
topics okay um but so the next few weeks
it's going to be short-run things um you
know when we're discussing short-run
competition what we talk about one of
the things big things we talk about is
is um uh markups we talk about markups a
lot because markups lead to dead weight
loss that's a major welfare concern um
but they're also going to be you know
just like in price discrimination you
got that sort of second welfare concern
of the you know misallocation of the
goods that are being sold will also get
sort of you know Mis purchased sing of
goods that becomes another consideration
here as well okay so what I'm going to
do in this lecture is I'm going to start
with all of the classic stuff in I/O
that people don't do anymore but sort of
do that as I think background for things
that you know is how modern sort of
studies of competition are done uh so
anyway I start and I you know I'm
talking about old historical stuff and
you know put up I added some pictures of
the old old dead white guys who sort of
developed these things so there's Corno
uh uh Coro compet
1838 so you know obviously Kono was
thinking about a world that's very
different from ours a world in which
many of the things that people bought
were like completely undifferentiated
Goods like wheat and corn and wool or
whatever where it just sort of a product
is a product and there's sort of a
universal market for it so Coro thought
about a model where you had n firms
there was some homogeneous good that
they were all producing that had inverse
demand P ofx the producers have cost
functions CI of XI that depend on what
is the quantity produced by firm uh
I Coro you in some sense Coro invented
Nash equilibrium so Coro thought of the
model he had this sort of timing where
the firms are simultaneously choosing
outputs X1 through
xn when they choose those outputs
they're sort of going to all bring their
goods to the market there's going to be
a market determined
price and all the firms are choosing
their quantity assuming that the
quantities chosen by the other firms are
all held fixed and that's going to be
the optimality
condition
um okay what happens in chono
competition so you know in chono
competition right the firm is maximizing
over
XI um
XI
times P of x i plus sum over J different
from I
XJ minus CI of
XI okay so that's every firm's
maximization problem is maximize
quantity times the market price minus
the cost your quantity affects how much
you produce it ends up affecting the
market price through its impact on the
aggregate on the aggregate supply and it
obviously affects our cost of
production you know so what do we get
well you know if a profile is an ash
equilibrium it's got to
satisfy um first order condition for
this for each ey what does the first
order condition look like
um you know so first it's you know this
times the derivative of this gives you
you get a p of the sum of the XIs minus
derivative of this is marginal cost the
third term in the in the thing is um uh
XI times the derivative of that so we
get
Pi Prime Time XI star equals z okay so
this is sort of what the classic Corno
first order condition looks
like what are some implications so first
of all um price exceeds price ends up
greater than marginal cost right this is
price minus marginal cost is the first
term XI is a if XI is a positive number
P Prime is a negative number so this is
price minus marginal cost equals minus
Pi Prime XI is a positive
number um production in a Corno so we
get a second welfare loss in a Corno
oligopoly so first welfare loss is
there's dead weight loss second is
production is inefficient in a cornal
oligopoly production is inefficient in
an asymmetric oligopoly because if in if
the firms are asymmetric in equilibrium
x1's going to be different from X2 if
x1's different from X2 and P Prime is
the same for everyone because it's
evaluated at the aggregate demand then
that means and the p is the same for
everyone that means the C primes have to
be
different um so in an asymmetric
corop um the realized marginal costs are
different so the quantity that's being
produced is being produced
inefficiently um okay you know example
to think about this is you know for
um uh you know if you think about model
for producing oil in the world today is
something like a Corno oligopoly there's
a set of countries every country you
know the ones we're centrally producing
or choosing how much to cons how much to
produce if each country is sort of
maximizing its production then you know
you're going to have countries like
Saudi Arabia has oil that they could
pump out of the ground for $5 a barrel
or $10 a barrel they're not pumping it
out of the ground Canada is getting oil
out of tarand for $50 a barrel and you
know there's sort an inefficiency there
from lowc cost producers not producing
while high cost producers are producing
holding the quantity
fixed okay um firm outputs are usually
strategic substitutes so if you look at
a Coro model if I put q1 on this axis
and do what's the best response for firm
2 to an output of q1 uh you get this
downward sloping uh line and you know
the equilibrium looks like this if I put
Q2 on this axis and graph
br1
Q2 you know Coro equilibrium is
typically this sort of intersection of
two downward sloping
lines okay that's what it normally looks
like uh it doesn't have to look like
that and the Kono equilibrium is not
always unique you could imagine if you
could sort of somehow draw these things
with Wiggles in them that they intersect
multiple
times um okay uh fourth result of this
you know take this uh expression price
Minus cost is minus XI star P
Prime uh and then divide both sides by
Price uh I get an expression that looks
very much like the Monopoly pricing
expression except it has an XI star on
the right hand side instead of having an
X star on the right side but it's some
sense this is the Monopoly first store
condition so because this is the
Monopoly for store condition except with
an XI here instead of a capital X here
uh I get this expression price minus
marginal cost over price is minus XI
over xar time 1 over Epsilon so if we
think about how does competition reduce
markups in the Coro
model obviously you know elasticities if
you don't have a constant elasticity
demand curve elasticities also change as
output changes because you know the
elasticity is non constant but if you
think about the rough constant
elasticity intuition this is going to
say that you know with n for molopoly
prices are going to go down roughly like
one over n um and you know this is sort
of one of the features that made Coro
popular is that people have this
intuition with Monopoly prices are high
as you get more competition in prices
ought to decline and they ought to
decline you know in some decreasing
returns to competition way and they
ought to ASM toote to perfect
competition as the number of firms goes
to Infinity uh and Coro has those
properties and and that's you know one
of the reasons why it became a popular
model to use
um okay notice that you know like
marginal costs are different with
asymmetric firms learner indexes are
different with asymmetric firms because
each firm's markup is uh XI over xar and
so the XIs are not all one over n in
equilibrium the markups are different
but so we can think about sort of like
what is the average markup in an
industry across firms so let's define
the industry wide learner index to be
price minus average marginal cost over
price where we take a weighted average
of the marginal costs giving weight you
know XI over xar so we give more weight
to the firms that are producing more so
this is sort of price minus average
marginal cost over price uh theorem is
that you know and you can just this is
just basically taking a weighted average
of these weighting them by XI so the
theorem is that
um average IND the industry average
learner index is um negative H over
Epsilon where H is the sum of XI over
xstar
squared okay so it's this H is the sum
of the squared market shares and so you
know the Coro model predicts that um you
know the Coro model predicts that the
markup in an
industry um depends on
sum of squared market shares and some of
squared markup shares is a sort of
summary statistic for how large markups
are and you know this was sufficiently
uh influential that if you go back and
read like how us merger guidelines were
designed in the
1950s they explicitly refer to herend
doll indexes and they're explicitly
referring to herand doll indexes in the
sense of like you know
if I even forget what these numbers are
but there's something like this you know
if the herend doll index in an industry
is less than .18 then we will allow
mergers and if the per dollar Index is
between .18 and. 28 and the Delta
H you know then what we'll do is look at
whether Delta H is less than or greater
than
0.01 and they will tend to sort of
consider mergers as questionable or not
depending on whether the change in the
herand index is bigger or smaller than
0.001 and then for Industries where the
herel is already above 0. 28 then
they're going to be sort of uh you know
then they're then mergers are typically
not going to be allowed but this is just
the you know because the herend doll
index had this role in the theorem that
it was a measure of how competitive an
industry was it took this very Central
role in in in competition and if you
also if you look at the you know I
discussed the sort of cross industry
cross-section IO uh from the 1960s
constant regressions of markups on Hind
doll indexes because herend index was
supposed to be the correct measure of
how concentrated an industry was um one
thing to note though you know you
definitely should not be thinking of the
her andal index as a welfare proxy
because you know you think about it it
it's measuring markups relative to the
cost they're there but so for instance
you know if you have two firms that are
perfectly symmetric the herel index is
05 uh it's 1 half squared plus 1 half
squared is 0.5 suppose one of those
firms gets more efficient and lowers its
cost when it lowers its cost everyone is
better off
you know social welfare goes up but the
hind doll index also goes up because the
firm with a lower cost now starts uh
producing a higher share of the
output
okay okay um you know in the old days uh
one could you know and I I let me say I
think big mistakes students still make
today is trying to be too original I
mean I think almost the best way to do
research especially when you're starting
out is always to take some existing
paper and improve on it because if you
take an existing paper you improve on it
you've got something better than an
existing published paper whereas you
know you start from scratch with some
creative idea you spend years on it and
then you realize two years later that
we've done is created a worse version of
something that already exists whereas if
you know you start with the existing
Frontier paper you know where the
frontier is you improve on it you've got
a frontier New Frontier paper okay but
anyway back in the day um you know Kau
was
1838 uh berran 45 years later picks up
coro's paper and say I can come up with
an interesting comment on Corno so his
comment on Corno was that you know many
firms don't choose the quantity that
they're going to produce what they do is
instead set a price for their product
and then sell however much at that price
as people are willing to buy um so he
just sort of flipped around this
discussion from firms choosing
quantities treating everyone's quantity
is fixed to firms choosing prices and
his comment is basically that
predictions of corob model change
dramatically if you make that simple
flip from firms are choosing quantities
assuming quantities are fixed the firms
are choosing prices assuming prices are
fixed um so anyway brr model you know
let X be a market demand function assume
that X is weekly decreasing and that P *
X of p is
bounded uh assume that all firms have
Market have unit cost C firms
simultaneous announce prices all demand
goes to the low price firms uh then uh
we don't get this sort of Coro
continuity we get a immediate
discontinuity which is two firms is
enough for perfect competition so the
unique equilibrium of this model is P1
star equals P2 star equals
c and you know this is what you know
Frank fiser is sort of writing about
economic theory would sort of say this
is an exemplifying Theory you know you
sort of make these somewhat extreme
assumptions that is you know firms
announce prices and all demand goes to
the lowest price firm even if it's one
penny less than the other firm but what
you show is that with these assumptions
you get this sort of extreme outcome
which is competition Works different for
Le from kruno when it's a discontinuous
thing and any number of firms is enough
to have perfect competition okay um you
know one version of this model that
still does get used is if you think
about firms that have asymmetric costs
you have two firms with cost C1 star and
C2 star
what's the
equilibrium uh the equilibrium is the
firms end up both pricing at C2 star
with all of the demand going to firm the
firm with a lower cost um if you want
you can think of it as firm one as
charging C2 minus Epsilon and getting
all the demand um but sort of when you
have asymmetric
Corno uh prices are determined by the
second lowest cost in a market and I
think that's the important intuition
that's sort of like the second lowest
cost determines what happens in markets
that are you with this very int intense
price competition or on differentiated
products does this change have
information on the cost
um yeah so let me see so if you did this
model where you had um private you don't
have knowledge on their
distribution yeah so in some sense if
you have um private information on costs
um this is some sense that that's that's
what we normally refer to as an auction
model you know right like it's an
auction I don't know what the of the
painting is to you you don't know the
value of the painting is to me so I bid
something giving myself some expected
markup because you know if I bid cost
then if I win or If I Lose I'm I'm
unhappy both ways and so I bid something
in between well in the buying something
I bid something in between you know my
value and zero and you do the same thing
and we get some and we get positive
markups for that reason yeah so that
that becomes a you know like in the uh
you know values uniform 01 model you bid
v over2 as the equilibrium so it's some
sense that that is a
model you end up reconstructing
something kind of like Coro that you get
positive markups and as the number of
firms goes to Infinity the markups go to
zero so that would be another way to get
a Coro like
prediction um anyway I I do talk about
I'll I'll do auctions in in like week
eight or whatever but we actually get
that um you know the place where that
analogy is more direct is like
procurement auctions you have auctions
for contracts to pave a road in the city
of Cambridge uh and those are allocated
by auction and exactly you don't know
what the rivals costs are going to be
for that Paving job so both of you bid
some mark up hoping to win
yeah um okay um you know comment on
again go forward another 46 years um
comment on uh uh Kau compet comment on
berran competition by Harold hotelling
uh and I I wanted to put him here
because um Harold hotelling is my great
great grand adviser um so you know
hotelling was Arrow's adviser Arrow was
mask's advisor masin was feenberg's
adviser Drew was my adviser um so anyway
some fondness for Harold hotelling um he
actually and you know you know he was
actually um so if you go look at my
advisor family tree um they're all
mathematicians Beyond some point like so
you get to all those friend
mathematicians you know whose names you
hear in probability Theory whatever
because hotelling has PhD in math rather
than uh in economics so like my family
tree goes back sort of you know three
branches in economics and then
everyone's a mathematician from that
point forward like for hoteling advisers
um but anyway you know hotelling through
Mo well mostly through having advised
can Arrow hoteling does have like a
thousand over a thousand descendants um
you know brand advises or whatever um so
anyway so hoteling and and I actually
you know I love Hotel tellings writing
also you sort of get him to sort of you
know he's got this sort of very you know
in some sense self-confident but trying
to be understated style of this of sort
of um you know after the work of the
late professor edworth one may doubt
that anything further can be said on the
theory of competition however one
important feature seems to have escaped
scrutiny this is the fact that uh of all
the purchasers of commodity some buy
from one some from another in spite of
the moderate differences in price and
that say that price reaction should be
ous rather than non-differentiable as
they are in beran's model and then
working out the friction so anyway um
you know hoteling's
model is and in some sense hoteling is
open the path that everyone has followed
since which is thinking about
competition in terms of heterogeneous
consumer populations and some underlying
type space of consumer of heterogeneous
consumers um so he had this sort of line
uh where he had consumers arranged on uh
01 um and actually you know hoteling
spent a lot of his career at UCLA and I
think was thinking about this as a beach
uh in Southern California um you know
and so hotelling did have the sort of
model you can think of is you've got
sort of the two you know uh two two
stands on the beach each one selling
drinks and hot dogs and ice cream or
whatever and then you have all the
customers who are lying on blankets
somewhere along the beach and then when
they want to get something to drink they
pick up and they walk to the nearest
stand and then they buy something and
then they walk back to where they were
sitting on the beach okay so his model
is we have these consumers and there
utilities um so I put fet on this
axis so then if I graph the utility that
you get buying uh
consumer of type Theta buying from firm
one I get utility that looks like this V
minus t * Theta minus
P1 so that would be my utility of buying
from firm
one and then uh consumers also have a
utility of buying from firm two uh so
let me on this axis put uh V this is V
minus T1 minus Theta minus
P2 so you know the argument is that you
know T is
my dis utility per unit of distance
walking and so my utility from buying
the product from firm 1 is V minus t *
Theta because Theta captures my distance
minus P1 and if I buy from firm two it's
V minus t * 1us Theta minus
P2 and so uh you know he did this in a
one diim this one-dimensional type space
captures your preference for both Goods
and so he assumed there's a constant
marginal cost C he considered again you
know the Nash equilibrium before Nash of
firms simultaneously announce prices P1
and P2 and then firms announce those
prices it's a simultaneous move game and
then consumers decide who to buy from
and then the firms earn their profits
and it we just look for the static Nash
equilibrium okay um you know the
standard case we discuss in this model
is if V is large
then there's some consumer Theta hat
who's indifferent between buying the two
products so this consumer Theta hat has
v minus t Theta hat minus
P1 equal V minus t 1 minus Theta hat
minus
P2 so at those prices that consumer is
indifferent between the two
products you solve that equation and it
tells you that the indifferent consumer
Theta hat
is uh 12 + P2 minus P1 over
2T with that in consumer do I have on
the next slide or not um so with that
indifferent consumer then you get you
know X1 of P1
P2 is 12 plus P2 minus P1 /
2T and X2 of P1 1
P2 is 12 minus P2 - P1 over
2T okay the demands add up to one if as
long as this consumer is willing to As
Long As V is large enough this consumer
is willing to buy so everyone buys from
one firm or the other so there's no dead
weight loss in this model everything you
know demands end up being independent of
V so this is if uh whatever um
V minus t
* 12 + P2 minus P1 over
[Music]
2T uh minus P1 greater than equal to
zero so as long as
this indifferent consumer is willing to
buy demands are completely independent
of v and just are these linear you know
these are linear demand curves so what
he's done is he's just sort of proposed
this model of heterogeneous consumer
populations and said with that het
heterogeneous consumer population model
we just get price
competition with these particular linear
demand
curves and what happens when you have
those linear demand curves
well you know firm I is just maximizing
price Minus cost time 12 plus um PJ
minus p over 2T so if it sets a higher
price it gets a higher markup per
consumer but the number of consumers go
down uh with one over two t being the
slope of the downward sloping individual
demand you know demand curve facing
it uh I take the first order conditions
for this it's just algebra and given
that it's a linear demand curve we get a
quadratic objective function it has an
interior maximum uh and what we get is
the best response for firm I to a price
PJ
is 12 of C + t plus
so if I try to graph What's Happening
Here P1
P2 so if P1 is zero the best response
for firm 2 is 1 12 C plus T is
positive and then it's a line that's
upward sloping so this is the best
response for firm two
to a price of
P1 okay and this is uh 12 C plus
T and then similarly the best response
for firm
uh one to a price of P2 is going to look
like
this so I'm graphing firm One's best
response you know I'm graphing this
thing backwards as you do in Game Theory
where sort of as P2 is higher I'm
graphing P1 is higher but this line has
slope 1/2 relative to this this one has
slope 1/2 if you view it as a function
of this line so we get these two upward
sloping lines they
intersect that's the equilibrium and we
get P1 staral P2 staral C plus
T um so what are the sort of economic
imple implications here one is that you
know markups are proportional to the
product differentiation parameter T so
it's the amount of product
differentiation in a market that ends up
determining how large are the how large
are the
markups okay um you know the hotter it
is and the more unpleasant it is to walk
across the sand the higher will be the
prices um and you know people today I
think use this model you know not just
for differentiation in physical space
driving but like differentiation in
taste space as well so if you think
about competition between Coke and Pepsi
how much do you like Coke how much do
you like Pepsi there are some people who
are love Coke and and dislike Pepsi
there are some who love Pepsi and
dislike Coke there are some who are
completely indifferent between the two
the amount of taste
heterogeneity is what determines the
markups and numerically with these
linear demand curves it's the amount by
which people at one end of the line
versus the other it's the relative
preference of people at one end of the
line versus the other this person thinks
Pepsi is tea better than Coke that
person thinks Coke is tea better than
Pepsi tea is the equilibrium mark
up okay um you can do an nirm circular
version of this like so imagine that you
have obviously you know there are lots
of parts of the United State well you
know obviously you'd have to all go all
the way down to South America and some
parts no one's going to be the beach but
you could imagine giant Beach that's
just you know we have an resort island
where the beaches just circle around the
whole thing um if you put n firms around
this it's as if the competition between
any of these two firms is now going to
be like T * 1 over n is going to be the
effective distance between them and so
if T * 1 over n becomes the effective
distance between them you're going to
get you know P star
= C + T * 1 n so this is a model where
it can be like Coro and as you put more
and more firms into the same finite
dimensional product space markups to
Kine and are continuous with perfect
competition as n goes to
Infinity
um anyway I'll just say later actions
are strategic complements just means
that it the reaction curves look
different from how they looked in Coro
here it's an intersection of upward
sloping lines Coro is an intersection of
downward sloping lines uh that's going
to understanding sort of some of the
implications of the model that's going
to matter
later okay um okay any questions on uh
hoteling's
model okay
um okay so vertical
differentiation you know final thing we
think of is that you know there's many
examples like Coke and Pepsi there's
clearly one is the better product and
one is the sorry there two products are
just a matter of taste whether you like
a versus B there are other examples we
think of where differentiation consists
of one product is better and one is
worse um you know so if you think about
you
know do people want to buy the you know
do people want to buy the sort of BMW or
do they want the Toyota yarus or
something like everybody would rather
have the BMW um like everyone admits
that this product a is better than
product B but the question is how much
are you willing to pay for product a
versus product B okay you could have
again you know this sort of you know
maybe some people still like flip phones
but you know you have the sort of modern
phone competing against the old flip
phone you know with just a keypad and a
little screen like this everyone agrees
that the sort of modern phone is the
better phone but people just differ in
how much they're willing to pay for the
better product not ter so the differ the
the consumer preferences here are going
to be vertical rather than hor what call
vertical rather than horizontal so
do this example I've got two firms um
they have Goods of quality SL is my flip
phone sh is my
iPhone uh and the lowquality phone
everyone would agree is worse than the
high quality
phone uh we have consumers have types
again distributed on a on a unit
interval or sorry non-unit interval now
Theta lower bar Theta upper bar uh and
the utility functions are going to be
the consumer utility of a consumer of
type Theta buying product I is Theta SI
minus Pi so the Theta is your marginal
value of a unit of quality you could
also just think of this as a model where
consumers are differentiated by income
and have a mar different marginal value
of of uh income and therefore you know
they have all the same utility that they
get from higher quality but just some
people have more money than others they
have a greater disutility of spending
money okay
um okay and so consumers have this
utility if they buy from firm I they get
zero utility if they buy from neither
firm at
all uh I'm going to for Simplicity
assume a unit mass of consumers uh unit
density of consumers on interal Theta
lower bar Theta upper
bar okay so what's going on here is um
you know here I'm typically going to
have my Theta space you know often we
have our Theta space start start at zero
but here everybody in my model is going
to light quality so I'm going to sort of
think of a model we have this sort of
interval Theta lower
bar Theta upper bar and so
consumers you know consumers are rate on
this interval of positive
values okay so again consider the same
game that um you know Bertrand and
hotelling considered firm simultaneously
choose prices PL and pH taking the other
firm's prices fixed consumers decide who
to buy from from and then firms earn
profits that's the end of the
game what do the utilities look like you
know here
um dra first draw a line like
this this is the line Theta SL minus
PL so it starts at negative
PL and then it goes up with a slope of
SL this is the utility that you get
you know this is UL L of theta that's
utility you get buying from firm
lals UL L of
theta okay then other line I'm going to
draw is firm H has the higher quality
product um so if you had type zero which
nobody does you'd get utility Negative
PH from buying that product uh but but
then I'm going to assume that's a
steeper sloping line like this Theta sh
minus pH it's a steeper sloping line
because uh sh is bigger than SL and the
slope is s the slope is s
okay so what happens in this model again
there's sort of some in equilibrium
there's be some indifferent consumer of
type Theta
hat consumers with types above Theta
hat uh so these guys all buy um the high
quality
good these consumers upper envelope is
these guys
by uh the lowquality
good uh as I've drawn it there's another
Point that's of importance called Theta
Prime I'll call Theta Prime I named
Theta Prime in the
slides anyone with a type below Theta
Prime uh is going to buy
nothing because neither good is worth
paying what's being charged
okay you know I've drawn this in the
case where Theta Prime is below Theta
lower bar and Theta hat is between Theta
lower bar and Theta upper bar and in
that case what are the demands um the
demand for the high quality product is
just Theta upper bar minus Theta hat and
the demand for the lowquality product is
Theta hat minus Theta lower
bar if Theta Prime were to the right of
this the demand for the lowquality
product would be Theta hat minus Theta
Prime um but anyway I drew it like this
so this becomes the
equations and then again this Theta hat
satisfies
um Theta hat sh minus
pH equals Theta hat SL minus
PL so that tells you that Theta Hat Time
sh minus SL
equals pH minus
PL you know that gives you this
expression
here uh for what the demand is for
product
H
okay so again it's it's a story um but
it's a and it's a story that just
basically what has done is it's just
given us again two linear demand curves
you know these are both you know they're
they've got other parameters in them and
it's not so obvious but you just look at
it's like oh yeah that's just it's a
linear fun function of PL and pH it's a
linear function of PL and pH
uh uh hotelling was a symmetric linear
model at you know the two demand curves
looked exactly the same here the demand
curves look different um in particular
you know
the firm if the if the prices were equal
everyone would buy from firm H so in
some sense firm H's demand is higher
than firm L's holding the prices fixed
um but that's what the equations look
like
but they are you know the it's it's just
a shift of demand curves one demand
curve is higher but the the demand
curves are both linear with the same
slope in the two
variables okay any any question on that
getting from the equations to the
slopes so that's what our demand model
looks like and then again the question
is like what happens in this
competition and again it's just
uh you know it's it's solving a um uh
it's just solving two equations and two
unknowns to find what the demand curves
are it really is Not So Different Here
from uh what hotelling did um so if I
plot P1 and P2
again so the best response resp to firm
h of a price PL turns out to be if you
remember the other one was 1 12 P plus C
plus T so it turns out to be 1 half P
plus C plus um instead of T we get Theta
upper bar minus sh minus SL which is
like the amount of differentiation that
there is between the two products from
the perspective of the Theta upper bar
consumer so it's a lot like P plus C
plus T but just with the amount of
difference between the products here
being From perspective of of the um High
Theta
consumer and so what that looks like is
uh you know we start again here if um so
we put PL here pH here um so uh it
starts at 1 12 PL plus C plus something
or other so it starts at some positive
thing and it goes up with a slope of a
half so this is the best response for
firm H to a price of PL
okay and this is
uh 12 of C plus Theta upper bar * shus
SL now firm L's best response is 12 of
p+ C minus something and so the minus
something is again related to how much
differentiation there is um notice
because like when pH is zero this
becomes 12 of C minus something this
thing could even be negative or it it's
c below C and it could even be negative
number if um differentiate depending on
how big different how big
differentiation is um but so I'll draw
it as like starting as a positive number
but it starts from some smaller amount
and then it also goes up at a slope of a
half so we get
BR
h brl of pH looks like
that so this starts from 12 of C minus
Theta lower bar time shus
SL okay and given the things both have
slope a half again there's a unique
intersection and it's right there and
you can think of this as PL star comma
pH
star okay and what we get is this
asymmetric equilibrium you know the
formulas look the same but this one's
got twice the bigger number minus the
smaller number and this one has one *
the bigger number minus twice the
smaller number so this is a bigger
number than this
one uh and so what we get is you know
again you know vertical differentiation
just like horizontal differentiation it
creates finite uh demand elasticities it
creates positive markups if you put
uniform distributions on the vertical
tastes it can be linear demand curves
just like the horizontal model is um in
equilibrium those different the
differentiation again leads to positive
markups uh it leads to positive markups
but it leads to positive markups where
firm H is favored firm L is
disfavored um notice also that if Theta
upper bar and Theta lower bar are too
close together uh this doesn't work and
firm L just has to drop out of the
market you know because right the
equilibrium looks like Theta upper bar
minus 2 Theta lower bar over three as
Theta lower bar approaches half of theta
upper bar firm two is just pricing at
cost if firm Theta lower bar was even
closer to Theta upper
bar what you'd get in equilibrium is FML
would just be shut out it would get be
driven down to pricing you know to play
best response would have be pricing
below cost it eventually doesn't price
below cost it can't compete in the
market okay so vertical differentiation
like horizontal
differentiation produces finite demand
elasticities it can it can sort of give
plus uh again um you know sort of
standard Coro like markups it doesn't
give us a model where Coro is um it's
like you know Coro have that continuity
end goes to Infinity price heads to cost
here this doesn't happen because there's
only room for a finite number of firms
you get the you know like you start
taking this space you tried to have
three or four or five or 10 different
firms selling to this at some point the
firms get too close together the firms
that are are below just get shut out of
the market and can't compete and so it's
only the high quality firms that are
making any sales and so there's some you
know some minimum level of markups
you're going to have to get there um
although obviously with um you know as
firms crowd the space the difference
between the sh firm and the sh minus
Epsilon firm you're only going to get
Epsilon profits but you're still just
you're going to get it with just a few
firms
active
Okay okay and obviously I I think you
know modern IO reality we think that
vertical differentiation and horizontal
differentiation are present in most
markets we think most Pro most products
there's sort of some compon extent to
which we think product a is better than
product B that everyone would agree on
or almost everyone would agree on and
then there's other horizontal aspect you
know like everyone wants a phone that
has better battery life and a better
screen resolution and a better camera
but then there are other things of
people like the look and feel of a
versus B and are going to have you know
know the operate like the operating
system of a versus B and are going to
have horizontal and vertical
tastes okay um so let me go back to
horizontal differentiation now and this
is sort of motivated by how the
empirical literature and iio has
developed
so generally like you know the standard
you know hoteling is a very nice model
um of competition on a line hotelling is
not as good a model once you have three
firms instead of two firms because you
have three firms you have to think about
where do we put the three firms in
product space you know one thing you
could do is um what I do with my Eraser
um there it is um you know you could uh
if you're someone who likes high school
geometry you know you could go back to
your Youth and say okay here's what I'm
going to do I'm going to have the three
firm hoteling model and I have firm one
here firm two here firm three three here
uh and you know there's going to be a
set of consumers who are indifferent
between firm one and firm two based on
their prices and a set of firms
indifferent between firm one and three
based on their prices and a set of firms
indifferent between
firm uh one and two based on their
prices uh I think that has to go through
the same point um and so we're going to
get these sort of three different
regions
so you know an equilibrium these guys
buy from one these guys buy from
two uh and these guys buy from firm
three I'm going to sort of use
everything I remember from high school
geometry to figure out the areas of
those things how the areas of those
things are functions of P1 and P2 and P3
and then you know when I get to four I'm
going to make it a tetrahedron and I'm
going to draw all the volumes of those
things but it's it quickly becomes just
sort of a intractable mess with lots of
corners and you also sort of think why
were we doing this in the first place it
wasn't like we felt that people were
uniformally like uniformally distributed
on the beach seemed okay once you get
between you know competition between you
know Google and Samsung and Apple to
sell Modern phones is it really uniform
on a triangle why do we believe that
anyway um so what people do instead is
they've switched to this kind of um
utility Spectrum where you know in some
sense what hoteling was trying to do was
switch fit two firms into a one one
dimensional space and fitting two firms
into a one-dimensional space was a great
idea to make it more tractable fitting
three firms into a two-dimensional
space you know it just gets awkward and
so the qu observation is why not just
stick with an end dimensional space for
n firms instead of an N minus uh
onedimensional space for n firms and so
what people do is assume the utility
that firm I gets from buy utility that
consumer I gets buying from firm J is PJ
which is like the vertical quality of
product
J minus Alpha * PJ the price of firm J
plus Epsilon i j that's my uniform taste
for how much I like iPhones or how much
I like Samsung phones or how much I like
Google pixel phones okay so we get this
sort of uh and then people typically
also actually with n firms will now
typically go to n plus one dimensional
uncertainty and they'll add Epsilon i z
which is how much do I the outside good
of not purchasing anything so that could
be you know how much s sentimental value
do I have for my current phone um which
is often the outside good is just not
buying anything and keeping the phone
that I've already got okay and you know
people can have different so in some
sense I've got in that phone example
I've got a four-dimensional preference
space how much do I like new iPhones how
much I like new Samsung phones how much
do I like new pixel phones and how much
do I like the old phone that's already
in my pocket okay and you know the
people can have different views about
these things both for Taste based
reasons and like the one my pocket is
broken or not broken or whatever
Condition it's
in okay you know demand in this model in
general case it's just an N plus
onedimensional integral to figure out
the demand for product J when these are
the prices I just integrate over that n
plus one dimensional space it's just the
integral over the subset of that space
where product J gives higher utility
than product k for all K different from
J and I'm just integrating the density
of the joint distribution of types over
that region so you know it's like here
I'm integrating the density of types to
find demand for good one in this
two-dimensional space I just integrate
the density over this particular region
of space and so I'm still integrating
over these regions of space that look
kind of like that um actually you know
like right the two-dimensional model
here let me do two products and no
outside good would just be like I've got
uh Epsilon i1 on this axis Epsilon I2 on
this axis um and I would just be you
know this region so these people buy
from good one these people buy good two
it's just entirely as Epsilon I2 greater
than Epsilon i1 so it's an easier
integral to do typically than those ones
with the things stuck into a lower
dimensional space because you're just
integrating over quadrants uh or half
spaces
[Music]
um
um you know sometimes in empirical
papers if people want to do this they're
just sort of simulating a bunch of
drawing a bunch of epsilons at random
figuring out how many of those consumers
buy each product that's how you sort of
do this practically speaking um you know
this model is sort of tractable in the
special case when there's no outside
Goods uh the v's are all equal and the
epsilons are IID with some density F you
know in general
um right you know you're trying to solve
a game an N player game you have to
solve an n n equations and N unknowns
problem but if you have looking for a
symmetric
equilibrium then you're back to sort of
a one equation in one unknown problem
because you have a one unknown equation
in one unknown problem I'm just trying
to Max you know I'm so fact that um you
know when is there an equilibrium of a
symmetric model where all the firms set
price P
star you know that's going to be if P
star belongs to the
argmax over P of profit of firm uh
J uh when it sets price
PJ and the other firm set price P
Star right so sorry if I make it
symmetric so this profit it doesn't
depend on J this is just one equation in
one unknown that lets me find P star
it's just each firm is maximizing its
profit holding everybody else's profits
at P star and so you know where
asymmetric models are an N equation
problem one equation symmetric
equilibria you can often find by just
solving one equation and one unknown and
so people often do that to give
insights um so let's look at what is the
you know and obviously the pi
J Pi of PJ comma P star is going to be
XJ
of uh PJ comma P
star uh
times PJ minus C right so your demand is
just price Minus cost times demand like
it was in all the other
models uh what is demand look like
um okay um so if I'm thinking about
every other firm is charging Price p or
P star and I'm considering charging my
price
PJ when when is someone going to buy
from
me um they're going to buy from me if um
their preference for me so they're going
to buy from me if Epsilon i
j is at
least the maximum
um K different from J Epsilon i
k
plus PJ minus P
Star right if everyone else is charging
P star and I charge PJ which is greater
than P star I have to be that much they
have to have that much higher
idiosyncratic preference for me than
they have for anybody else and if I
charge a lower price they can be this
much lower than their best preference
for everybody else and still buy from me
so what you get is the demand for me is
this is let's suppose that their you
know suppose that this I'm going to call
Theta their greatest utility they get
from buying from any other firm or
greatest idiosyncratic taste for any
other
firm then they're going to buy from me
this is the probability that their type
is bigger than theta plus PJ minus p so
that's a probability that you know this
is the probability that Epsilon i j is
bigger than theta plus this and then
this is the density of this is the
density of
theta right so if you're
choosing um you know if you're thinking
of that there are n other draws or n
minus one other draws their n minus one
draws from some distribution f what's
the probability that the largest of n
minus1 draws from f is in some tiny
interval theta plus d
Theta and the probability that this is
it's an order statistic calculation I
don't know if the order statistics have
disappeared from 380 um but so you know
the density of the highest of n draws so
the probability that someone is in this
the highest of n minus one draws in that
interval is you pick some firm to be the
highest their value your the Epsilon for
them has to be in this interval which
happens with probability F of theta and
all other epsilons have to be less than
that Theta which happens with
probability capital F of theta the N
minus 2 so this is the density for the
highest of the N minus one rival draws
but so anyway this is what that's what
my demand looks
like you know if this is what my demand
looks like then again I'm just going to
have the first order condition that I'm
going to have to have you know PJ you
know P star satisfies the first order
condition uh D Pi J
dpj evaluated PJ equals P
star equals zero and so I'm going to get
a first order condition the first order
condition is just going to look like PJ
minus C * dxj dpj plus XJ equals z
um and so it turns out you can just you
know if I I should do that right again
so I have this first order Condition
it's going to look
like um P star minus
C time
dxj
dpj evaluated at P
Star Plus XJ of P
star equals
zero so that's what the first order
condition is going to look like as it
has always looked in this class and then
the XJ of P star is going to be 1 over n
in equilibrium with n symmetric
firms so you just get P star minus
C is just equal to minus1 over n dxj
dpj one other thing I meant to mention
before is um
you know look at this utility function V
minus alpha x p plus Epsilon utilities
are only defined up to a uh Aline
transformation I think probably hear
that 121 a lot so you can also think of
this as like V over Alpha minus p + 1/
Alpha * Epsilon i
j so this model when people put in a
price coefficient Alpha is a lot like
the hotelling model where one puts a one
over Alpha where the T used to
be because one over Alpha is like the
size of the transportation cost size of
the heterogeneity relative to having a
unit coefficient on the price so people
you know when people do empirical iio
they always put an alpha here but you
can think of it as fixing this as one
and putting a one over Alpha in front of
the
epsilons okay so anyway so what do you
get us the mark up when you do this uh
would you get to markup is price so this
is price equals
Cost Plus uh -1 over n one over dxj
dpj so anyway the equilibrium formula is
price equals C + T *
something so it's c plus T * 1 M of N
and one over M of n is just what you get
differentiating
you know it's it's the M of n is like
what you get differentiating this thing
with respect to
PJ and you can see it's got things like
f to the N minus 2 and F and n's in it
and stuff but anyway if you do the
calculation you differentiate on the
integral
sign this is what you get so price
equals C + 1 M of n * 1 over
Alpha where M of n depends on the
assumed density
of theeta of the distribution of the
epsilons so some
cories
um suppose f is uniform 01 so you know
like uh certainly hoteling could have
done instead of the beach you could have
done the sort of people living on a
square where this was utility Epsilon i1
this is Epsilon I2
okay turns out that if hotelling had
done his model on a square he would have
found the neat result that uh price
equals c plus 12T he would have gotten
exactly the same thing except with 1/2
in it um but so with the linear model
you can extend this to you know people
living on a hyper Cube or cube or a
hyper Cube or whatever and the formula
is exactly correct that price equals C+
1/ n * T so the thing that everyone
loved about Corno is true of this
hypercube model of product
differentiation
price is just C plus T where T is sort
of the length of a side of the cube how
how intense is your preference for Coke
versus non Coke or whatever and uh
things decre decline like one over n if
they're n firms in the
model um what can we say more generally
going outside the uniform distribution
um suppose that you know uniform
distribution is bounded above suppose
that the Epsilon is bounded above or
that the tails are thin tails are thin
like the normal distribution in this
sense of limit as Epsilon goes to
Infinity F Prime over F goes to negative
Infinity um then as the number of firms
goes up prices drop to cost so if we
take bounded distributions or we take
distributions that are not bounded but
have very thin Tails then you do get the
result that competition drives prices to
zero um does that happen for all
distributions the answer is no most
important example where that doesn't
happen is the logid error distribution
which people often assume because it
makes algebra easier but it turns out
for the logit model so the lit this is
the logit CDF where you know gamma's the
oiler mascheroni constant like
0577 so in the lit model what you
actually get is price equals constant
Cost Plus some constant Time 1 + 1 nus1
* 1 Alpha so as n goes to
Infinity you know P star is going to C +
one over
Alpha so in the lent model uh prices
what K Alpha oh yes K Over Alpha thank
you um
uh where K is some K it's it's just some
constant I forget exactly you know like
you you can think of it's like 2378 I I
forget what the number is but it's just
it's just a
number so in in the logit model prices
you can compute what it is you know
prices are just like a C+ you know
prices as number of firms goes to
Infinity competition doesn't eliminate
markups um and you know how is this
possible you know the idea is that these
models have a
somewhat unreasonable assumption that I
I snuck over on you which was that you
know as I said like in two Dimensions
it's like you know how much do I like
iPhones versus do I like Samsung phones
it seems like okay it's reasonable to
assume there people those two separate
differ or preferences but what I snuck
over on you is that um here I said it
epsilons are IID independent and
identically distributed okay the more
products you have it gets harder and
harder to say it's really plausible that
my taste for a BMW and a Mercedes and a
whatever are all completely independent
of each other you know as the number of
firms gets large the products get
awfully similar to each other so if
you're a person who likes Mercedes
styling you probably also like BMW
styling and if you're one who likes
Toyota you know Lexus styling maybe you
also like you know Acura styling or
whatever so you know in some sense what
the lent model is assuming if you assume
we keep having this every new product
has this completely new idiosyncratic
reaction to it you know Suppose there
are a million products out there and you
tell me okay yeah they're you're one of
a million products in the market but
this person likes your product better
than every other product well you know
to think about you know right the
markups depend on what this dxj dpj what
do I conclude
when I've just been told they like my
product more than everybody else's
product I'm like wow they like my
product a lot okay now in
the hyper Cube model if you know like if
the Epsilon i j is you know is is
distributed uniform
01 I'm like they like me best out of a
million things it must be my utility for
me is like
999999 something or other or they
wouldn't have been buying from me but if
while they like me this much there's
also somebody else who they like
999998 or something and so I I think the
amount by which they like my product
over anybody else's product is Tiny
therefore I'm going to have my demand is
very price sensitive and if I don't
price really low they're going to switch
so I have this incredibly price
sensitive demand but if you have like a
you know maybe you know this if you have
an exponential
distribution and you're told that you're
the largest of n exponentials how far
are you above the next highest draw um
the answer is one that's sort of a
property of the exponential distribution
that if you're the highest of n draws
from the EXP un standard exponential
expect your your posterior for their
value for youu is n and your posterior
for their product their value for the
next highest one is is has high
expectation n minus one so you think you
have like one of of uh you know space to
price relative to your rival and so like
with an exponential distribution we
actually get the you know you get
exponential distribution you're going to
get like you know P star equals c plus T
doesn't depend on N at all the the more
exponential draws there are out there
they're just Yep they're probably like
me a lot more than somebody else you
know they like me they like me a million
they like the next guy 999,999
lit isn't quite like the exponential but
it turns out to be just very similar to
the exponential and that
approximately um it ends up with an
approximately constant
markup and that markup depends on what
weight you stick in front of the Epsilon
i j in the in the logit model the one
over Alpha okay um and you know there
are distributions for which if you take
a really fat tailed distribution one
that's fatter tailed than the
exponential prices can go up as n goes
to
infinity and again you know I don't I
don't know that we think that's often
realistic like where do these you keep
getting these independent taste from but
you know it's you know in these models
it's there you should be aware of
it questions on that so okay I think
that's what I had to say oh yeah I so I
think I'm going to skip this slide um
the one thing I wanted to say in this
slide is you know suppose you know
student comes to me and says I want to
write a paper about mergers and the
effect of Mer mergers are having on
markups in Industry X um this is sort of
a you know know your theory cautionary
tale if you know student says okay I'm
going to estimate demand logit demand in
this model and see what's happened when
you merge from five firms down to four
firms if you know phone maker a buys
phone maker b or whatever and you know
you know so you can sort of estimate
your loin model and say I'm going to
allow the price sensitivity to vary and
have it be you know V us uh V minus
Alpha P plus Epsilon utility and I'm
going to estimate the alpha and see how
price sensitive things are and then when
I found out how price ensor things are
see what the merger is going to do you
know what if you then use that model
let's say when you go from five to four
firms how do markups go up me the answer
is markups go up by 1.06 7 you know with
five symmetric firms the markup is C
plus k thing times 54s when you go to
four firms it's c plus K Over Alpha time
4/3 so on the question of how to markups
change when you go from four firms to
three fir five firms to four firms um
you know the answer is the that question
has an answer that's independent of the
all the parameters you estimate in the
model and the answer is just this and so
you know if you do want
to estimate how mergers would affect
markups in models with horizontal
differentiation you know you have to
make sure sure you're correctly
estimating you know this object dxj dxj
DPI versus dxi DPI um and the sort of
you know the models like the logit model
kind of built in assumptions about what
those things are and you know if these
things both just have an alpha in them
and those Alphas
cancel you you're not actually
estimating what you think you're
estimating but I didn't want to take
time on that okay so um uh
going to more modern pictures I Stu
jong's picture on this slide so um
discuss you know recent
paper um discussing the effects of uh
bundling on competition um so the
motivation for this paper is
[Music]
um you know there are many firms where
there is sort of this antitrust concern
about firms bundling and selling their
products together instead of selling
their product separately um so you know
firms for instance if you're U maybe you
think they don't really matter but like
you know apple is selling phones and
they're selling
earbuds uh and you can sort of think of
like I can design the phones and the
earbuds so they only work together and
have to be bought as a bundle or I can
design the phones and earbuds so they
work separately and I can be competing
with Samsung separately in the phone
market and separately in the earbud
Market um you know with operating
systems this often comes up is like what
features do I build into an operating
system so that people have to buy the
bundle of the operating system
containing these 37 different components
all from me or do I allow sort of
plug-and-play compatibility so we have
separate competition product by product
okay okay and so you know um this is a
potential antitrust remedy in for in
Industries with large Market power is
forcing them to be compatible uh you
know and not use proprietary connectors
or whatever um to extend their
monopolies and so
you know Joe's papers about this
question of will when will markups you
know will bundling products together
make markups higher will it make it
markups lower how will it affect
consumer
utility so in his
model um you have these uh n firms and
the N firms all sell M distinct
products and he looks at utilities of
the following form you get utility V
minus pjm plus Epsilon J M if you buy um
product J uh if you buy sorry product M
from firm
J and he Compares two separate models uh
one model is
where the firms compete separately in
this whole Matrix of prices so you know
firm one sets prices P11 p12 up to
p1m and then firm two sets prices p21 up
to
p2m and then firm three I'll just have
three firms Post Its bundle of prices
p3m he Compares that to a bundled system
where the firms just design their
products to be all mutually incompatible
so firm one just sets a price uh Capital
P1 firm two sets price Capital P2 and
firm three sets a price Capital P3 for
the bundle so this is the bundle of
getting all of these goods from me this
is the bundle of getting all these
things from firm two and this is the
bundle of getting all these things from
firm three and he thinks about which
results in Greater consumer welfare in
Greater profits having unbundled pricing
uh or having bundled
pricing okay first observation is you
know when do consumers prefer buying
bundle one from bundle two well that's
if M * V minus the price of the bundle
plus the sum across all products within
the bundle of
epsilonm is better than buying MV minus
the price of bundle K times the sum
overall things in the bundle of Epsilon
I
km and again normalizing this by
dividing by the number of firms so if I
convert this to like a you know this is
M products so P1 over M I'm going to
think of as the per product price
you know this is what's sort of going to
be equivalent to sort of P11 or
something it's you know how much are I
charging per product in the
bundle so I like this one better if and
only if um V
minus V minus one over M PJ plus 1 / M
the sum of Epsilon I JM is bigger than
this so basically bundling is like
converting the model where you have
utilities Epsilon i1 up to
Epsilon N1 into a model where you
have 1 over M sum of Epsilon i1 and 1
over M sum of Epsilon I IM right you're
just basically converting comparing the
model with utilities from the original
draw random draws from the original
distribution to the model with utilities
that are random draws from this
distribution so that's what I do when I
bundle is I just change the distri of in
sycratic consumer preferences and make
it an average of these okay and
obviously right the um uh Central limit
theorem is going to tell us that as M
goes to Infinity you know these things
are going to be have smaller this is
going to have smaller variance than that
and it's going to look approximately
normal as M goes to Infinity but normal
with a smaller variance than the first
one had
um okay so let's think about whether
prices are higher again same price first
order condition I've done over and over
again so first order condition for for
uh price competition is PJ minus C *
minus dxj dpj equals
XJ and again if I'm looking for a
symmetric equilibrium of this model this
is going to be P star minus C time minus
dxj dpj equal 1/
n and what is dxj dpj going to be
dxj dpj is just the density of consumers
who have utility for me equal to the
maximum of their utility their
idiosyncratic reaction to me equal to
the maximum of their idiosyncratic
reaction to everybody
else and so
um you know so fixing n right this first
order condition right we I don't have it
written down anymore um so right my
first sort of condition
was uh you know P star = c - 1 / n * 1 /
dxj
dpj or actually I do this
okay that's sort of what my first order
conditions always keep looking like so
equilibrium prices are low if this
density is high and equilibrium prices
are high if this density is low so in
this you know dxj dpj is the density of
the
set of consumers who have my Epsilon
just about everybody else's
Epsilon um notice that right the
distribution of the sort of sum of the
epsilons it's more concentrated about
its mean it's thinner in the
Tails okay so consumer surplus in this
model depends on there sort of two main
welfare effects for consumers one is
price levels consumers like low prices
um and and there's less dead weight loss
when prices are low um the other thing
that welfare depends on is match quality
consumers are better if they're getting
their favorite phone and their favorite
earbuds and their favorite charger than
if they're getting their favored of one
and their second favor of the other and
their third favored of another so the
match quality is our consumers getting
what's the best product for them on on
every
subcomponent uh and then there's the
price level thing that they care about
okay so uh what's the result so first
result on the paper is that bundling
reduces per good prices when an equals
two so if you you have a firm if you
have two firms um and they bundle their
goods together equilibrium price per
product prices go
down
um noting you know prices go down mean
that the firms make less
profit
um and why is that you know the answer
answer is
that you know that density of 1 over M
Epsilon becomes more
concentrated when n equals 2 what we
have is just what's the probability that
ui1 minus ui2 is less than Delta and
that's just the probability that we're
close to the 45 degree line that is that
my my Epsilon for firm one is close to
my is within Epsilon of my sorry within
let's say this is you know small Delta
what's the probability that my
preference for firm one my preference
for firm two are within Delta well if
you take the distribution of tastes that
used to be like uniform and you sort of
you know like in the uniform
distribution this thing is not all that
big but then like you sort of add end
Goods you make this thing distribution
look like this almost everybody has a
preference of exactly a half for both
products then once they have utility of
exactly a half for both products they
have a huge probability they're within
some tiny Delta of each other therefore
price competition becomes very intense
so when n equals 2 it turns out that you
know whatever m is bundling just always
makes the prices
lower so you know some sense firms
should not want to bundle uh in in a two
firm model okay um what's noteworthy
though is while the firms don't want to
bundle the consumers also don't want the
firms to bundle so the prices go down
but the consumers are worse off and
that's because the
worse match quality overwhelms the price
drop so there's a price drop uh but it
also makes the consumers worse off
because they get worse match quality and
it doesn't compensate the and the price
drop isn't big enough to compensate them
for the drop and match quality
um
now when n equals 2 that's true when n
is large when n is above some
threshold um bundling starts to increase
profits and why is that well you know
again the sort of value this sort of sum
of epsilonm starts getting to be a very
tight
distribution and so what's the density
of consumers who have very close values
for the best and second best thing
that's a density measured out here you
know if you like me best what's the
probably you like someone else what's
the sort of probably the other person as
close to you um as
when n gets large you know holding n
yeah holding M fixed letting n Go Large
looking further out in that distribution
it gets thinner tailed and the dxj dpj
is small and therefore the P star is
high so bundling is good when the number
of firms is
large um and a third result is when you
fix the number of firms and the number
of goods goes to Infinity then you know
increasing then bundling eventually you
know bundling drives prices to zero as m
is going to
Infinity so I think it's just it's a
some ways that I wanted to do it because
I want to sort of cover some reent paper
and it's a nice example of
how that basic Pearl off salop intuition
of price is about differentiation and
it's about dxj
dpj is a very good way to think about a
lot it's a good way to think about a lot
of issues sort of bundling included
I don't understand why four like is a
result so because we're just
like putting Infinity in the
denominator would they ever charge like
an INF price sorry um oh I should have
said sorry I should have said uh this is
um that's with C C equals zero so it's
going to be that um I I think I had a C
equals z assumption so it's the yeah
limit is it probably should have written
limit as M goes to
Infinity uh
PB over M minus C goes to
zero I think maybe I had C equals z
throughout the paper
um
yeah okay okay uh let me end there then
I have uh I didn't think I would get to
these last slides but um so anyway on
Monday what I'm going to do is um
discuss oligopoly price
discrimination um where you know you
have oligopolies who are competing to
sell multiple products and therefore are
going to be price discriminating in
selling multip products and then I'm
going to do two empirical papers uh
breast andan and Miller Weinberg uh
breast andan you know I took the star
off it this year because you know breast
andan is it's the original it's a real
classic you know it really looks 50
years 40 years old when you read it and
you're like wow I can't believe you do
things that way but it's so I'll just
I'll discuss the ideas in breast and
hand not going into the details which
now look very oldfashioned and then I'll
sort of discuss Miller Weinberg and I'm
part I'm doing less empirical work here
because tobas is talking about demand
estimation here and an awful lot of
demand estimation is really about
estimating static models of product
competition with those Epsilon i j kinds
of models that uh I talked about
okay e