okay so wel come back from uh spring
break
oh we're still talking about mixtures
we spoke about mixing and uh separation
and uh we are going to talk today about
stratification but uh I want to spend
the first uh few minutes uh answering a
question that I had from a colleague who
is following the lectures online and
uh um asked me a nice question
about uh how can how can we do um
separation at constant temperature and
pressure you remember that we did the
the entropy of mixing by mixing gases
and we we obtain this formula for the
entropy of mixing then we also uh spoke
about the fact that uh we could have
done the mixing in a better way in terms
of U thermodynamics I could we could
have done it
reversibly and therefore extract the
adiabatic availability of this situation
or this state with respect to this mixed
state we also spoke about uh computed
the minimum work of complete separation
of a mixture when in mutual equilibrium
with a reservoir which keeps it at the
same
tnp and we found that the minimum work
is equal to the difference in the Gibs
free energy of the separated final
State uh from the uh initial mixture uh
state so this
diagram uh
shows graphically what what the problem
is so we have a
mixture and we want to separate
it and if the mixture is uh in um and we
want to separate it at at fixed the
temperature and pressure so that uh in
the end it will remain in mutual
equilibrium with the thermal Reservoir
which is at this same
temperature now if uh the mixture is an
ideal mixture of Ideal gases we have
found that the initial State and the
final State they have the same
temperature and also they have the same
energy
but of course they don't have the same
entropy so the separated State we call
it B
here uh has lesser entropy than the
mixed state so in order to separate we
have to remove at constant energy this
entropy to go from here to
here so removing entropy from a system
requires another system that picks up
that entropy
and that's why we need the reservoir but
the reservoir which starts at this state
here cannot just pick up the entropy in
order to pick up some entropy it also we
need to give it also some
energy and so to pick up this amount of
entropy this is the amount TR times that
entropy is the amount of energy that we
must give to the reservoir
of course these are minimal amounts uh
because we we considering the reversible
process which is the
optimal so the question is how can we go
can we can we do this okay one
possibility it's on the next slide so I
I'll I'll switch back and forth between
this and the
next uh is to make a a process like this
we we take first the mixture
and cool it down to this state
C of course we have to do it reversibly
so we will use a Machinery to do that
and uh so in order to cool it down we
change the
state we need the Machinery to
consume some work which is equal to the
available
energy of this state C which is colder
than the reservoir but as you remember
the graphic representation of available
energy is given by this segment from
here to here with respect to this
Reservoir so even if it is colder than
the reservoir it has a positive
available
energy and uh finally then we will do a
an adiabatic a
work only so a weight process that takes
us from here to here and this is the
sequence so here is the
is a
Machinery which cools down the mixture
from the initial temperature to that
temperature T
TC and in order to do that a Machinery
needs to consume work which is equal to
the available energy of State C and
while doing that it will
transfer that an amount of heat to the
thermal Reservoir which is equal to this
work because the mixt no sorry uh take
it back which uh is going to be
different uh to be given by this much so
it's not equal to that work
sorry and once we have the mixture
prepared in that state then we can
perform our uh workon
process like weight process using semi-
perable
membranes that will uh
for example this membrane which is
perable only to particles to the black
particles is initially uh here then uh
by it's pulled down by the weight so it
compresses the gray particles to their
say half of the of the
volume and then also this other membrane
which is perable to the uh gray uh
particles only it's on this uh side here
and then the weight going down here so
consuming work will push the black uh
particles to their half so it will do
sort of a partial compression of those
in doing that we go from here to here so
we spend the the weight the sum of the
weights uh uh energies of the weights is
the adiabatic availability of these
State here so this is a possibility to
perform of course it requires membranes
it requires uh reversible processes so
it's not very
practical uh so uh many times in
practice when you need to really
separate things you can also use um
chemistry so chemical engineering in uh
solvents that would extract this sub
you're interested in from your mixture
and then uh once it has been
separated then you have to recover your
solvent so that it it's not consuming
the solvent
or
uh which could be a a physical solvent
so or but could also be a chemical
solvent maybe not it's not a proper word
but to give to give the idea something
that would prefer
entially
um interact and um react chemically with
one of the components and then you have
to uh reverse that reaction in order to
recover your solvent after you're
separated okay but even if you do it uh
chemically uh and if the final states
are these ones and your solvent is a is
a dummy variable so to speak of the
process in the sense that you it's a Cy
it goes back to its initial State uh and
and and remains therefore pure at the
end uh then this still represents the
minimum work of
separation and so it is refer reference
also in order to compute the uh second
low efficiency of that separ actual
separation
process
okay so let's go now to this uh problem
of stratification
and we are interested for example in the
stratification of gases in the
atmosphere like oxygen nitrogen
CO2 so remember that we started by
saying that uh for this kind of uh of of
problems uh we model uh like in the bulk
flow uh
State um model we we model the the
energy of the substance as given
by uh the energy which is proper of uh
the stable equilibrium State for the
given entropy volume and amounts of the
substance plus a potential energy which
in the case of gravitational uh uniform
gravitational field is uh as we all know
uh
mgz okay
and the mass of course depends on the
composition so the the local mass of the
uh fluid
Parcels uh changes with elevation due to
changes in
composition the chem the the chemical
Potentials in this situation are
substituted by the role of the chemical
potential is played by the total
potentials which is still the derivative
of the energy with respect to the
amounts but now the amounts appear not
only here but also in the in the
mass and that gives rise to a contribut
additional contribution to the potential
so we have the chemical potential plus
the gravitational
potential and so we have the sum of the
two is the total potential that is what
enters in the conditions for Mutual
stable equilibrium between uh fluid
parcels and therefore also between uh
layers of fluids Parcels of fluids that
find themselves at different elevation
in the gravity
field so in order to
impose uh Mutual stable equilibrium we
will impose equality of chemical
potential I'm sorry total potentials
between two layers at different
elevation we will assume instead as an
approx ination that uh although we not
going to assume that the temperature is
is completely uh um uniform so we're not
uh we want to go beyond the model of a
of an isothermal atmosphere we we will
assume that the temperature changes but
that the local changes are
irrelevant or can be say neglected for
this
uh computation of the chemical
equilibrium
so in order to apply this we have to
write this chemical these total
potentials and the total potentials are
written one at elevation Z Plus DZ and
the other times at elevation
Z and uh of course we need to use this
double contribution chemical plus
gravitational for the chemical part we
will assume ideal mixture Behavior so
the chemical potential is given by the
pure component uh chemical potential at
the same temperature and pressure plus
RT log of the mole fraction of that
component and then here we have the
gravitational
contribution and the line above has the
Z Plus DZ
contribution
so in order since these two must be
equal
you do some uh manipulation you also
remember that uh since here we have the
difference between the chemical
potential at Z Plus DZ at the
pressure that belongs at at Z Plus DZ
and
that at elevation Z here enters the D
the partial derivative of mu with
respect to the pressure which is the
specific volume and that's why in the in
the end
this is what we are left is the specific
volume
DP plus RT uh the derivative of the
logarithm of the mole fraction plus the
Mi gdz and Mi of course as the are the
molecular uh masses of the various
components so we have one equation like
this for each component because all
components can be exchanged
between
layers and
uh this is actually true also for the
pure substance so if you have a pure
substance so just one component this
equation becomes this
one and if you recognize that the
specific that the molar mass divided the
spe specific volume and remember this is
specific volume uh molar uh so m / V is
the uh
density so this equation becomes
dpals minus the density time G * DZ
which is which leads when you integrate
to the uh verul equation of static fluid
mechanics but you can also apply it for
example for a gas so for a gas
specifically volume is not constant so
you shouldn't put the you should
remember that V is RT over
p and therefore you can
integrate uh you can integrate you can
RT over P so you get DP over p on this
side and you have uh mg over RT on the
other side you can integrate so this
becomes the derivative of the logarithm
that's why the exponential here and on
the right hand side depending on whether
your temperature is fixed or not if it
is not fixed you have to integrate in DZ
the inverse of the
temperature so this is the equivalent of
of of the berulia equation for for a gas
which gives you uh the the the the the
exponential pressure uh uh Decay with
height uh for an ideal gas in the
gravity field if you have a mixture
instead and the mixture is of gases
we can play the same uh and here is a
similar expression but it's um it is you
get one expression like
this uh for every
constituent and uh this is the partial
pressure so you compute these partial
pressures which also go down
exponentially with
Z but there is a coefficient icient of
the exponential that depends on that
depends on the uh molar masses so the
heavier uh particles the heavier
molecules go down faster than the the
lighter
molecules and so their partial pressures
go down
faster for
example oxygen is molecular weight
32 molecular oxygen and
nitrogen molecular nitrogen is 28 so
that difference 28 versus 32 makes it
makes it so that the partial pressure of
oxygen goes down more rapidly than that
of
uh nitrogen with elevation and
therefore as you go
high the
percentage mole I mean the mole fraction
of of oxygen uh
diminishes from the about 21% at the sea
level to uh to lower levels uh at higher
elevations we'll we'll see a graph in a
moment once you have the partial
pressures of course since this is a
mixture of Ideal gases we can use
Dalton's law and by adding them you get
the total pressure so you see how also
the total you can compute also how the
total pressure goes down in the
atmosphere you can also uh like uh here
we did it for a liquid uh for a pure
liquid you could also do it for a uh for
a mixture of
liquids it's the same you start from the
same equation only that now for the
liquid the specific volume is
constant if if you can apply the
incompressible fluid
model and so
you uh this is the equation to be
integrated and you can combine these two
because you have to one equation for
each uh constituent you can combine them
into this equation here and integrate
and here's the result of the
integral this is a mole
fraction of constituent
one at elevation
Z of course the other constituent as a
mo fraction one minus
y1 this is the ratio of the specific
volumes of the pure
components these are the difference in
the densities in the pure components
this is molecular weight of one
component and this
again is Z over the temperature or or or
if the temperature is
varying it's the it's the contribution
of the bearing temperature
now in the in canvas you will find a an
Excel file that I am sharing where I do
this
calculation where I made uh these
prots so I'm considering
air and I'm
using uh an air made of only four
constituents nitrogen oxygen argon and
CO2 and I assume that at the elevation
of the MAA laa laboratory which is at
MERS
uh this is the composition I express
them in ppms parts per
Millions so today uh the PPM of CO2 is
420 ft 25 up
there okay using of course the the the
the mole fractions are 32 and so on 44
for
CO2 and um this is the expression that
we use in order to compute the partial
pressures and this CZ is that
integral or actually actually it is a
non-dimensional
non-dimensionalized integral of the
temperature and for the temperature I am
assuming the
actual
uh measure temp there is something fishy
here because it should be 1 minus a z
here uh so there is something wrong in
this denominator in the integral but
that's the that's the
um The Temper the the temperature
distribution that I'm assuming which is
the average measured temperature uh that
is find is found in the books of uh the
handbooks of chemical physics people
have have measured the average
temperature in the atmosphere it goes
down uh about six and half degrees
Kelvin per kilometer of elevation
people have also measured the uh
pressure as a function of elevation and
this is the correlation p p not is the C
Level
pressure and Z is the elevation in
kilometers and that's we are not using
this we just use it as a check for our
calculation so this formula here is
these triangles on the spot
here which as you already see match
pretty well almost
exactly our uh estimate based on this
calculation here so uh by substituting
that by doing this integral which can be
done and then Computing the function CZ
and using the mole fraction I mean the
mole molecular weights you find the
partial pressures for example uh8 this
is the partial pressure of
nitrogen
zero elevation is a sea
level uh 3.4 is
manua and this is the top of Mount
Everest 8 point
uh uh forget now uh 8500 something uh uh
meters
so you see the pressure the partial
pressure of nitrogen goes down this is
oxygen it also goes
down and of course the sum of the two
plus the sum also of the others the
others argon and co2 have such low
partial pressures that they might in
order to visualize them I multiply them
by 60 for a factor of 60 for argon and a
factor of a th000 for
CO2 so this one is
CO2 the green no I'm sorry this is the
green is
argon and the blue one is the uh is
CO2 this is the
value uh measured at U
manua but as you see at sea level the
value is much higher and that Mount
Everest is much lower these is these are
the mole
fractions but before we go to the mole
fractions you sum up the partial
pressures and you get the total pressure
which is this other
curve so the reason why at the top of
Mount Everest the air is
thin is twofold one is that U the main
one is that the pressure is about uh
um
three
32 so it's 32% so every time you breathe
you you take in only uh in the volume of
of the lungs are more or less the same
so you take in one3 of the
air
plus there is this the second order
effect which is has to do with the
molecular uh the the composition that is
you see the mole fraction of nitrogen
goes uh up and that of oxygen goes down
but see it goes down very
slightly and uh so you get instead of
21% you get maybe 20 or 19%
the effect is more important for CO2 the
mole fraction changes quite a bit with
elevation so if you measure
425 ppms at
manua at sea level it's over
okay now this uh
is just the beginning of course of
things that you can calculate along
these lines and so I wanted to point to
you this website which is called climate
for you which contains a lot of um
measurements historical measurements of
CO2
temperatures uh all sorts of uh
comparisons so I'm not going to deta
dets of these plots only to show you
that I'm sure you've you've seen this
many times this is the CO2 going up
along the years this is from
55 to to the last month this is what
January and uh this is the uh various
ways to measure the the average
temperature
many Labs many universities have their
own ways of a averaging over six months
one one one month one year and so on so
you get uh smoothed lines or peaks in
any way this gives the the idea that the
temperature is indeed uh going
up
uh and of course uh um
not only the atmospheric temperature but
also this is the temperature of the
upper layers say the first 100 m of uh
the
oceans which is the layer in which there
is a lot of mixing due to
turbulence so it's an average um L where
where of course
the reason I'm bringing this up is that
um between that layer and the
atmosphere there is a tendency to reach
Mutual
equilibrium for the various gases
including CO2 because
CO2 uh gets um dissolved in
water and
uh and then also CO2 being a higher
molecular weight molecule
has the tendency to go down so once it
uh reaches
uh the first the modeling of the first
layers are are are sort of Complicated
by the by the chemistry because CO2
gets gets um
ionized uh solvated in
into bicarbonates and then carbonates
and so you you also need a chemical
equilibrium which is something that we
have not done yet uh um but eventually
when you go at about 450 M of
depth
um CO2 becomes um Al liquid also so you
get a liquid liquid mixture and from
that point
on that uh
stratification uh formula that we
derived for liquids could be applied in
order to see how this the the CO2 uh
concentrates in the bottom layers of the
oceans where in fact there are literally
uh Lakes of U of super critical
CO2 uh and it's actually a major place
where a lot of of the carbon in the in
the planet is
stored these other
uh plots represent U
compare uh this CO2
oscillations uh with temperature of the
oceans and of the
atmosphere they also tend to um
show a sort of a
delay from the peaks in the uh
temperatures of the uh ocean and
atmosphere and the peaks in the CO2 so
many people are speculating about the
origin of this uh
um because as you know we of course by
burning uh fossil fuels we produce uh um
CO2 that goes into the atmosphere and a
good part of that maybe half or almost I
let's say 40% of it goes uh into the
ocean through this
equilibrium
uh but of course we are concerned about
the amount that stays uh because it's a
greenhouse
gas actually just to mention that just
the other day there was a an article on
MIT u tech talk
or about
people concerned about this
new uh or or little mentioned gas which
is
24,000 uh times uh more powerful than
CO2 in terms of greenhouse gases which
is uh I think some sulfur as a fluoride
okay uh now that molecule though I I I
tried to to read quickly through that
article I couldn't find
uh they mention how much it's produced
by the various countries but it doesn't
mention um the the concentrations how
many ppms we have in the
atmosphere uh they also say that it is
very stable in the atmosphere I'm sure
uh they have U the reasons to to say
that on the other hand a heavy
molecule by gravity tends to go down so
so I haven't found yet I don't think
these people of the um the climate for
you website have already uh done
collected data about that particular
molecule but I'm sure that soon they
will because they're very they are very
keen at uh keeping updated with all the
various
news and
also this graph or reports the uh solar
activity is measured by the sun spots
solar spots and
um uh there is a cyclic activity and uh
uh this activity is related to some
effects on the cosmic rays and the
formation of clouds so this also um a
lot of people
who uh study uh climate change
uh are are studing the connection
between
this kind of solar activity and uh the
clouds because the clouds as you know
are uh this the the source for cooling
in the of of the planet via the albo
because they reflect some of the light
away so by controlling
clouds uh cloud formation you could also
uh
control uh
global warming okay so enough for the
advertisement of this website which of
course it's not an advertisement but
it's simply uh mentioning because it's a
good source of uh uh scientific
data back to
stratification uh here's another problem
which is very similar to the one that
we've done with with
gravity which is uh centrifugal force
so if you have a fluid which is uh
static with respect to a rotating
reference
frame H you know that uh uh there is a a
force like gravity that uh that pushes
you uh pushes uh the heavy particles
towards the the exterior
no and
U well it turns out that you can model
the this kind of U it's not really a
force it's it's a it is a
fictitious uh an apparent Force so
apparent force can be represented by a
negative potential
energy so if we assume an energy like
this and instead of mgz we use
um the mass
times the angular velocity times the r
squar this is the negative potential
energy we get a total potential which is
this negative
contribution and
then if we consider the uh Mutual
equilibrium between two layers at
different uh uh distance from the center
of uh the the axis of
rotation so you impose that the chemical
potential here and there are equal again
we assume
um the mild effect of temperature but
not completely U uniform
temperature uh okay so we
do yeah we you go over the same
steps and here there's an error
definitely here because there should be
like
a 12 M Omega squar the RDR here I
think so I need to correct that yeah
it's something like
this uh so this is the the general one
that applies for all substance for all
for each substance of the mixture if you
don't have a mixture but a pure
substance you get an equivalent of the
beroni equation for the Statics for the
fluid Statics
here so here the pressure
goes again
exponentially as you go um down the
centrifugal
force there is no minus sign here so the
pressure goes
up it's opposite than the gravity
field for a gas and for a
liquid it goes up exponentially for the
gas and uh parabolically uh for a
liquid and then again you can apply the
same formula to find the partial
pressures in gas mixtures or the or the
mole fractions in liquid mixtures I skip
the details because they are exactly
parallel and uh with with the case of
gravity I mention this because it's it
is an in energy uh in the energy
um uh business uh
um
centrifuge are important um because they
are used for example to separate to
enrich uh the uranium from the natural
concentration in the isotop
233 which is the
file
nucleus which is 7 71 uh% you need to
take it up to three or three and a half%
depending on the reactors and uh and in
order to do
that you make this uh react with an exal
fluoride
um and then you you put them into these
U
centrifuges which separate the small
difference between the molecular weight
of the 238 and the 238 35 and 38
isotopes that minute difference is
enough to separate the gas so you'll
find more of the 238 towards the uh
outside and uh and then uh of course
this is not completely static otherwise
uh you wouldn't have any you wouldn't
have any yield in the in the process so
you need to do the extraction and the
extraction ction complicates things
because of secondary flows and so on so
these are just details but there is this
nice uh article in Scientific American
if you're interested that does all that
very well
explained and then you of course so you
have to
run one centrifug from one you get
slightly enriched you put it in the next
uh uh uh stage and so on and this is how
many stages you need in order to OB
obtain a correct uh Cascade so that you
get 3% uranium uh 235 up here you can
you get depleted uranium just 2% from a
feed which is the natural uh
composition and then of course you'll
read about the fact that also these
depleted uranium uh as is problematic
because it's uh kept in some cylinders
somewhere near nearby this uh these uh
separation plans and uh they sometimes
there are accidents also there because
uh uh because these contain the steel
containers get rusted and so there is a
lot
of cost associated with uh not only the
separation which is energy consuming
but also the keeping the sites
safe in spite of all these costs uh uh
the costs of nuclear energy is still
competitive very competitive and so many
countries are uh using it and uh and of
course a good part of the investment is
also into
uh doing some kind of control of the
management of the waste and the
byproducts and so
on uh and this cost can be huge just
mentioned for example that in in in
Italy uh we had a referendum in
1989 that banned all the nuclear power
plants we had a few and one was already
uh what just built and that one in order
to keep it uh
closed you it's cannot just close and
get
away it it still has after 40 years no
years it I think it is has about 200
people working there just to keep it
uh how do you say stopped I mean not
working okay
offline
okay yeah there is
another very
similar uh problem that can be can then
be done with exactly the same logic that
we've done for gravity and uh um and
centrifugal uh field now this is for an
electric field so and this is also gives
us the a a chance to introduce the
electrochemical potential
electrochemical potential is one in
which you have that
your uh fluid
Parcels uh also contain charged
particles so if we denote the partic the
charge by
Q okay the the Q the charge is given
by how many particles of you have
times the charge per particle so Z is in
terms of the charge of the electron so
for example
uh sodium plus is an ion that
has Z equal to + one because it has the
charge of an electron but of the
opposite sign so it's a plus one the the
an electron as a
charge uh minus
one Z is minus one for the electron and
F this
F is called the farad
constant and it is the
charge of a mole of electrons so each
electron has a charge which is given by
this Ive reported the all these digits
because um
uh uh a couple of years ago it has been
decided by the International System of
Units I I think by somebody uh that um
these are the digits to be used so there
is no uh Dots Dots Dots as they used to
be so and also for the avocados number
that's the number you should
use and this is also for for a Bossman
constant all right so if you take uh an
Avogadro number of so multiply this
times this you get the farad constant
and the product is something like um
500 kums per mole something like
that uh
okay whereas of course you know that
remember that if you multiply avad
number times boltzman constant you get
the uh the gas
constant so it it should be it shouldn't
be it shouldn't be confused by the fact
that we call it the gas constant and
then then you apply it to liquids and
solids because after all it's just the
boltman
constant uh it also happens to play an
important role in gases but not only in
gases
so so quity calling it the gas constant
is a bit misleading and perhaps
confusing anyway so this is the
charge of uh a
mixture with these many with these many
constituents and each one of them having
a certain uh
um uh partial char
charge okay and the energy that you have
to
add to the energy proper of the stable
equilibrium state of the uh non charged
components is equal to the charge times
the value of the
electrostatic field so Fe is the
field and as you remember from your
physics once you have a field
conservative Fields you take the
gradient minus the gradient of the field
it gives you a vector because the
gradient is a vector operator and uh so
you apply it on on a field which varies
with with
position and minus the gradient is
called the electric field it's
Vector so the Bold uh X is here so X
bold means XYZ it's a location in
space and and the Bold in these symbols
means that they are
vectors it's true that also these ns are
also vectors but they are not vectors in
XYZ but it's simply a list of numbers so
yeah but I hope you not get confused by
these uh
details okay
so when you do when you compute
conditions for Mutual
equilibrium as usual we have this
derivative of energy with respect to the
amounts but also here the amounts now
are not only in this stable equilibrium
State
non-charged part of the energy
of of your of your fluid Parcels but
it's also on this side and the charge
depends on the ends
so that's when you do the partial
derivative with respect to n you pick up
from
here as Z and
F which is then multiplied by the value
of the electrostatic
field and so this is the electrostatic
contribution and this is the chemical
contribution and that's the total which
is in this business called Electro
chemical
potential all right so the an the the
analog of the problem that we've
considered so is that now you have an
electric
field so suppose you have some charges
or charged um a mixture of
charges or charged
particles for example a solution in
which you have electrolytes
or and U in an electric field
okay so the electric field is directed I
made it for analogy like like a gravity
like the same direction of gravity so
that this is
X all right same logic apply the
equality of chemical potential between
these two
layers using now this formula for the uh
total potentials sorry I said chemical
but it should be total
potentials and um after the details this
is what you obtain this is the
expression specific volume DP RT times
the derivative of the logarithm of the
mole fraction and here's a uh
contribution of
the uh gradient of the electrostatic
field so this is uh minus the electric
field uh dotted into
DX this is true also for the pure
substance so you could you
have if you have a pure substance or
just one uh
say charge in some electric field a
charge charge particles in electric
field uh you get a equations which are
similar to the ones we obtain for
Gravity but of course typically you
don't have only charges of one kind uh
you have mixtures of charges and uh so
this is the expression for the partial
pressures if they are in the uh gas uh
phase or if you are in
solution so if your charges are in in an
electro chemical
solution and you want to compute how the
uh concentration
changes uh as you move along the
electric the direction of the electric
field uh this is the how this formula
integrates you can also do it for a
variable
temperature okay for the simplest
example here U suppose you have uh the
plates of
condenser or say an anode and a cathode
and you
have some charge carriers so particles
with charge that
are uh between these two so if the
plates of the condenser are close enough
the electric field varies linearly from
the values of the field in one plate and
the values on the other plate so you get
a linear uh Fe so the electric field
which is the derivative the gradient is
the the X direction is the derivative
with respect to
X is
constant
okay and uh and if you apply those
formulas for for the liquid
case um the mole
fraction comes out to be
exponential so the the plus the positive
charges we have a concentration that
decays as you get uh far from the
negative uh
electrode because they like to stay near
the negative and and the negative
charges
Decay uh exponentially as you go far
from the positive
electron okay all
right so now we can move
to another interesting topic that is the
one
of uh what happens when
mixtures of various
components uh boil or
condense or
freeze
so we first going to do something with a
ideal
uh models and then we'll say something
about um non ideal
models you remember we talked about the
lonard Jones potential I'm not spending
much time on this again
uh this can
be through molecular Dynamics or Monte
Carlo uh numerical simulations
a way to
model
substances in
fact you can model a pure
substance with those just those
parameters uh there are uh I
think if not thousands of maybe hundreds
of articles that have played this
game in recent years because of of the
advances in molecular Dynamics
uh and um
so you people have developed uh um this
pseudo substance that is called lard
jum okay so so it's the Leonard Jon's
pure
substance where you you play with
non-dimensionalized um
properties for example this is the
non-dimensionalized
density uh it's number density so
particles um per unit
volume this is the
non-dimensionalized uh
temperature
and there has been a dispute for a while
about what this
um for example with the critical point
is characterized but now if there is a
very nice article in Wikipedia under
this title so that's where I also took
these plots because they're very nice
um which uh summarizes and
explains uh the details of these
calculations so the critical
point uh of this fluid is given by it's
like a Universal fluid no so it's given
by this U um these
values so once you fix you take your
substance and you think that your
substance is correctly described by a
value of Epsilon and the value of
Sigma
then uh you know that that substance
will have this critical temperature this
critical pressure this critical volume
so that means also that this is an a a
way in which you can infer the
values of those epsilons and sigma for a
given
substance if you know the
substance and uh
you therefore know because people have
measured the critical pressure and
critical
temperature you can make a system of
these two equations and obtain uh the
Epsilon and the sigma that properly
correct
the
properly get you to the critical values
of t&p unfortunately these these there
are only two
parameters the Epsilon and sigma in this
model so
um they are not enough to make the model
Universal
because the most difficult one to to to
model is the is the volume the critical
volume so if you match temperature and
pressure then you're going to be likely
of the critical volume in
fact
uh for example if
you if you
compute PV over RT like the ratio the
ideal gas
ratio uh at the critical
point since these values are
fixed uh you take this ratio it becomes
dimensionless this is called the
compressibility uh
Factor typically denoted by
z uh and
um for the lerum uh it's this is the
number
if this model was Universal it all
substances would have this
number for the critical uh this critical
ratio that's not really true because for
example if you go uh water it's pretty
off it's it's .23 instead of
31 helium 4 it's 31 so it's pretty good
argon
also CO2 is
off okay so there is missing it this
says that uh the Leonard Jones uh model
is incomplete it's a very good uh
starting uh place but it's
incomplete uh possibly due to the fact
that especially when you get to the
liquid phase the lard Jones considers
only pairwise interactions and uh
instead when the molecules get close to
one another also three body interactions
may become may may have a role and
they're not accounted for in this
model but you can predict uh uh
condensation and boiling You can predict
the fact that the the substance below
the
critical temperature doesn't like to
stay in certain uh in certain uh regions
so it it prefers to separate
into a liquid and the and a vapor
phase and also it
predicts pretty
well
uh the surface tension so you can
measure the surface
tension for example here as a it shows
it as a function of temperature this is
the interfacial
energy uh of the molecules that live in
between uh the liquid and the vapor on
the other side so they are in a they in
order to stay there which is a more
uncomfortable location to be uh they
have more energy so this is surface
energy can be interpreted as the extra
energy that the molecule needs to stay
in on the uh
interface and which uh
therefore um
okay uh also the triple
point the triple point can be uh
computed and uh you um you can compute
the volumes at the triple point is you
get the solid the liquid and the vapor
coexisting so you can compute at what
what is the specific volume that they
have
is the volume of the
solid you can compare the volume of the
solid because these are after all it's a
model
of some kind of soft
spheres and you want to compare how they
fill uh the volume you know if you take
spheres and you try to pack them in a
given
volume you're not going to fill the
entire volume because of course there is
a the void between one and the other so
you can you can do um perfect
packing uh and the perfect packing has
uh let's see where is
that I didn't write it
here yeah here the the volume of a
completely packed sphere spheres is this
one is 1/ the < TK of two time the
volume of the
particles so it means that the other 30%
of the volume is is the empty space
between the various spheres
okay so here the triple
point the model predicts that the
solid has is not completely packed is
1.5 the completely packed volume the
liquid is
1.7 is better packed than the uh than
the uh than the solid and of course in
the
vapor the vapor
is as much higher volume per
particle
800 okay
here if you
compute uh the compressibility
factor for the vapor at the triple point
you find that it is approximately one
very close to one that means that
already there that there uh the the the
the vapor behaves pretty much as a as a
an ideal gas because you see PV equals
RT
okay and then by
um these are plots that show uh
what what other parameters you can play
with in order to adjust but also to make
the numerical calculation let less uh
heavy for example by uh
truncating uh the
um the potential and saying well beyond
a certain distance instead of having
small digits I just put it zero okay
that that makes that induces some errors
and this kind of er maybe errors but may
also be
uh considered as
a as an additional tool with which you
you can have you can gain that extra
parameters to play so as to fit also the
volume okay all right so this is one um
this is the numerical uh
world in
the in the old time
uh
the
physics U couldn't enjoy these numerical
possibilities and so there was a lot of
uh of physical thinking and wonderer
WS in his PhD
thesis for which he got the Nobel Prize
in
1910 uh developed this simple model with
again two
parameters only two parameters like lner
Jones
B is the co volume so it's related to
Sigma
say and uh a is related to the force of
attraction so it's related to the
Epsilon
of the Leonard
jnes and this is the two ways of writing
the Vander vals equation of state which
is a an improvement with respect to uh
the ideal gas law if you set a equals z
and b equals z you get PV equals
RT which accounts also for the
attractive forces and for the fact that
the volume of available to the molecules
and is not the entire volume because
especially in the liquid phase uh the
volumes them themselves I mean the
particles themselves U occupy some
volume and so that's not volume
available for the other
particles so that's the physical
intuition behind this once you have an
an expression like this which is an
equation of state so we have a function
of volume between volume pressure and
temperature as you remember from the
pre-initial lectures you can compute the
compressibilities
uh the coefficient of the this is
isothermal compressibility the isobaric
expansion uh you which enter also in the
Meer relation which gives you the
difference between the spec specific
heat at constant pressure and constant
volume so by doing those
derivatives with this equation of
State here is what you
get for example in a limit uh for Vapor
states in the limit not the ideal gas
limit Min the limit of
uh
vapor in such a way that um the the co
volume is the so the volume available to
the particles is much greater than the
co volume and also the particles
leave far away from from each other so
that the attraction is also
small
then
this
approximate you get an ideal equation of
State you get CP minus CV equals R so
that's the Maya relation for ideal gases
uh you don't get exactly zero for these
things so you get
Corrections which are useful to to
represent non ideal gas
behavior for
example this is the jewel Thompson
coefficient which is the derivative of
temperature with respect to pressure at
constant enthalpy which is useful when
you expand a gas in a throttle to
compute whether it is going to heat up
or cool
down well or you can
also
compute um the critical
point because as I will show in a moment
or actually let me show it now if you
draw the
isoterm for example at constant temps
this is a pressure versus volume diagram
and these are the
isoterm so in the ideal gas uh uh State
PV equals RT so if T is constant PV
equals constant so this is would be an
equation of a
hyperbola okay as you see as you go uh
lower in in temperature and also in
pressure these isotherms get
distorted and uh at one stage there is
one isoterm which we call the critical
isotherm in which there is a
um in which the the first order
derivative goes to zero and you have a a
flex but you can apply the model also
below that so this is what theand Val
isotherms would would look like okay it
goes up and
down now if you remember when we did the
the chatelier brown
principle we found that
the compressibility one of the one of
the stability conditions
were uh that the his compressibility is
greater than zero and therefore the the
derivative the first derivative along an
isoterm so constant
T the derivative of p with respect to V
which is the slope of these
curves should be
negative so here yeah it goes down it's
negative here it goes down it's negative
negative here it goes to
zero and then the derivative goes up
positive positive positive until here
and then it keeps going down so the this
region here where the
derivative of the isoterm is where the
slope is negative does not satisfy this
uh stability Condition it's an unstable
situation that's the situation in which
your particles don't like to stay and
they prefer to separate into a dense
phase and
into a non-dense phase which is the
vapor
Now using going back to the previous
slide using
the
uh the model we can also compute the
chemical
potential chemical potential is
important
because for example when we have uh
Mutual equilibrium between
phases we need the quality of chemical
potential so even for the pure substance
if you have the liquid and the vapor in
mutual equilibrium they have to have the
the chemical potential equality of
chemical potential not only temperature
pressure so you can compute the chemical
potential with the Vander vales
model by
integrating the usual derivative that we
use often the derivative of mu to P is
equal to the specific
volume so mu is equal to you integrate
over over um over pressure
so you have an integration constant
which depends on temperature only and
then an
integral from uh of of V uh in
DP then you can inte do this integral by
part so this could be also PV minus
integral of p in
DV and since
p is given here by the V vales equation
you can do that
integral and the result is that the
chemical potential is a constant of
integration times a function of T and
V this function of tnv
we don't know that
constant C of T but we can reason even
without knowing knowing it
uh
by using the fact that we know that when
you have liquid and Vapor in equilibrium
the chemical potentials of the two
phases must be
equal not only but also the pressure and
the temperature so if I have a uh so I
have two conditions equality of
pressure so PF is equal to
PG and that's the saturation pressure
that's what we call the saturation
pressure when we have a liquid and a
vapor in
equilibrium so that gives us by
substituting here PD p vdv v with w
means substituting this expression here
for the
pressure uh so we get one
equation where the unknowns are two uh
it's the volume of the uh liquid phase
and the volume of the vapor
phase the temperature is a
given okay so that's condition one
equation that derives from the condition
of equality of
pressures then equality of chemical
potentials says that the chemical
potential at of the liquid is equal to
that of the vapor so you see the the
constant of
integration uh goes away and you have
this
equality where the function f is this
function here so now I have a system of
two equations for a given temperature
from which we can solve for the specific
volumes of the two phases in mutual
equilibrium and so once I have uh
computed that volume either VG or VF I
can you I can compute this function f
and I can express the chemical
potential or actually the difference
between the chemical potential and the
chemical potential at
saturation as F minus so in other words
I'm using I'm using the chemical
potential as saturation to express this
integration Conant constant see so this
is what is done on this other
graph we plot mu minus
muat so essentially that it is that
function f TV minus F at T
VG okay it is a
function of
temperature and
uh and volume and so on so for an
isoterm here's how they
look if I am above uh the critical
point it's uh it's a continuous uh
monotone
function but when we get to the critical
point we get to uh the beginning of
something that is uh uh kind of a
discontinuity let's look at it
uh far away from the from the critical
point so let's look at it for this
isotherm this
one okay so the chemical
potential goes like that it gets to this
point where it crosses the chemical
potential for the vapor so it's the one
computed from the other side
at this point here the two chemical
potentials are equal the pressures are
equal the temperature are equal so that
is the stable equilibrium
State and it corresponds to having vapor
in these conditions with this specific
volume and liquid in that condition
that's the saturated
liquid okay that's how the mixture likes
to separate this is the stable situation
our however you see that this Vander
vales curve
curves
continue
down continue
down without violating the stability
condition the derivative this derivative
here is still
negative so these are
still somewhat stable they're not fully
stable but they are somewhat stable
they're
stable and also on this other side here
the derivative is negative and they
corresponds to this branch of the
chemical potentials that goes up
there
then you get a switch in which the uh
the derivatives of the pressure the
stability condition gets violated and it
corresponds to this
this is what happens to the chemical
potentials so for example if I wanted to
if I plot that um the thing a bit
enlarged
here
okay and let me
consider this value of pressure I have
three three chemical three values of the
chemical po potential so the chemical
potential for the Vander vales has three
uh has three
values and uh notice that
we here we're plotting mu minus mu
sat and remember that for a pure
substance the chemical potential is the
Gibs free
energy
so uh this one is of the three uh points
is the one that has the minimum GS free
energy that
corresponds to the stable equilibrium
State and the stability condition is met
by first of all having that the the
derivative of thep DV constant T is
uh
negative and second the condition of
equality
of mutual equilibrium between the two
phases this other one the intermediate
stage State uh is a metast
stable it satisfy is only the condition
that the
pdv is less than zero but not the
equality of chemical
potentials and this one this other one
is
unstable because it doesn't satisfy
that so what's the what's the meta
stable what what's the meta stable
situation somewhere here
if I'm somewhere
here I have a
liquid
that
uh doesn't real doesn't realize yet that
it would be more stable by
evaporating or maybe a liquid
that in order to
evaporate needs to form the first little
bubble and forming a
bubble in a
liquid requires energy because you
require the surface energy the
interfacial energy so you need you need
energy to do
that uh and that is why
these meta stable states are feasible in
practicing
experimentally if you manage to
U for example here you you have a liquid
which is
um in stable conditions at the given
temperature and then you lower the
pressure so you decrease the
pressure uh suddenly uh then you your
liquid finds itself at the lower
pressure the same temperature down
here it it is super heated with respect
to that uh
pressure and uh therefore its stable
situation would be to uh U to become to
evaporate but in order to evaporate it
needs some some energy to form that
interfacial that that that initial uh
bubble
ER and in fact the moment it uh it gets
that energy maybe from some noise from
some vibration from some uh cosmic ray
or or particle that uh uh provides that
uh energy to to form that
surface what happens you
see consider it again a a a plot having
to do with
uh gives free energy this state here
with respect to the stable state has
this much
extra free
energy because because uh that's uh
that's the metastable state so this
extra free
energy is there
uh the moment you have provided the
initial trigger to nuclear the first
bubble then uh it becomes an explosive
uh process the the the collapse
from uh from the liquid to the vapor
because uh all this free energy is there
available is made available to form
additional uh surface additional Bubbles
and and all that so you only need to
tell the the the the liquid that it is
in in that metastable state and it will
start uh and burst into so and the same
is on the other
side on the other side if you are
here okay so this because this was a
liquid and this is the
vapor the same
here here is the metast stable this is
the unstable and this is the
stable see you get this
much free energy as soon as you have uh
uh actually I think I I
misspoke you have to to turn around all
what I said because when I'm here
this was the
vapor this is the vapor up to here so
this is the metastable vapor and the
what I said before had to do with the
liquid so the liquid is here so this is
the metastable
liquid let me write the metastable
paper and this is instead
metastable uh liquid
also here so this is the unstable also
here you get um so so for the vapor you
get again
the now uh for the vapor of course the
energy is not needed to form the the
first bubble but the first
drop and as soon as you form the first
one and the the the the system realizes
that there is a a more stable state it
will use all the free energy to
redistribute fast the the the that free
energy in order to form the the surface
that is needed to form those uh um those
um those drops in order to
condense now
this phenomena
have been worth uh another two Nobel
prizes so one is the the one by Wilson
who
invented this method it's called the
cloud chamber and the other two Glazer
the bubble chamber these are
both um ways
to uh
detect uh
Elementary
particles these were the initial ways in
which you could I think also somehow
similar um ideas are used today in more
modern
um detectors but uh uh see what what
happens is that you in the cloud
chamber
you you form a
subcooled metast stable Vaper so you you
form something like
that and in
the um bubble chamber instead you form a
a superheated uh liquid so they are sort
of
symmetrical
um uh
devices and then you
wait for the
particles that uh um you want to measure
you want to
visualize these particles deposit energy
typically they
ionize uh the the liquid or the vapor in
which they they they travel and that
ionization energy is what triggers the
formation of either the uh
um the the the bubbles or the the um of
the vapor um or the
drops so in this case you form little
drops uh like the drops that you see in
in the clouds in fact this is the the
same
phenomenon whereby Cloud some part of
cloud formation is triggered by cosmic
rays we are as you know the Earth is
continuously uh
hit
by flux of cosmic rays these are Char
particles with a lot of energy that come
and when they hit the atmosphere they
provide the atmosphere is has some water
vapor in
it but that water vapor didn't have
enough uh um energy to um form uh the
the droplets that
to the cosmic race provide the that uh
uh energy and that triggers the
formation of of of the clouds in that
neighborhoods and here it is the same
then
after of course this um you then you
have to to light to put the light in a
in particular way so that you you you
visualize these traces these um uh
trains of uh uh uh
of droplets that have formed
okay
okay so
the the last thing on the Vander valves
uh is well okay then what happens if we
instead
are in the unstable
so suppose you
start from an unstable suppose you you
manage to uh so how can you how can
you do this
U
prepare a sample in a state which is
unstable well you have to do it
quickly for example
uh you remember this is the pressure so
you can go uh very quickly down in
pressure and therefore you're uh so from
Super critical or from above the
saturation curve you just uh
quench or you cool down quickly although
cooling is more difficult because
cooling requires uh extracting uh heat
and heat uh it's kind of a slow thing to
to do in in experimentally
so but uh you can do it in in thin uh
samples like between two
um two glasses two small glasses like
the chemistry labs and therefore by uh
by cooling that the the by by cooling
that somehow it cools in mediately the
entire surface of the fluid it doesn't
require too much time because it's a
thin layer of fluid in any case suppose
you have these are
numerical uh
simulations uh very nice
uh and there are three cases one is uh
the middle one is when you you drop into
this region here the unstable region
uh with the
critical with the critical specific
volume so you this is the critical point
you you cross the critical
point and then you have a s development
of uh of
um how do you say a
pattern first
initially uh the
the mixture I mean not the mixture the
your substance is homogeneous then it
begins to
separate the
separation is in terms of a b continuous
so you see the blue particles are all
connected to the blue particles the red
part the red particles and the red
regions whereas if you are off
critical you form either um bubbles
the red things are
bubbles or
drops okay but what is most important is
that this phenomenon occurs very quickly
because again of this uh important free
energy that is there uh in order and is
available to form all these
interfacial regions in initially small
and then after a while uh uh once you
have formed all that then um the system
will try to coales in order to uh reduce
the surface
tension reduce the surface area uh and
so you the two bubbles will form a
bigger bubble so that the the surface
area goes down and that is a way to uh
go down in in free uh in free
energy and yeah time is up I think I
forgot to say but the word
spinodal appears all over that this
curve here that is the locus of the
points inside that separate the region
between oops between unstable and stable
is called a
spinodal curve SP noal curve and for
Vander vales you can even compute its
equation which is this
one okay yeah enough for today