John Lou asks, "How do we understand the
roles that can best support advanced
manufacturing? A new program from MIT
aims to give shopf flooror workers a
ladder to become shopf flooror leaders,
technologists who bridge the gap between
technicians and engineers. Please
welcome John Lou.
[Music]
[Applause]
Good afternoon everyone. Again, my name
is John Leu and it's such a pleasure to
be here in Vienna, Austria. It's my
first time in Austria and I have to say
I've never been offered chocolates more
frequently in the past 20 12 hours in my
life. So, it's a a beautiful place to
be. I teach in the mechanical
engineering department at MIT and uh I'm
really fascinated by how we learn or
should learn STEM skills uh to prepare
for the future of industries. And I
think about that on the level of systems
all the way down to individual
experiences for the learner. Today, what
I'd like to do is I'd like to spend the
next 20 or so minutes challenging uh
perhaps conventional or current
perspectives towards worker training and
worker roles. And I'd like to do that by
proposing a new worker class called the
technologist, a technician and engineer
hybrid that really bridges the gap
between these traditional worker roles.
So let's start from the top here. Uh
this is US- ccentric data, but perhaps
you might see kind of data very similar
to this in Europe as well. uh the these
are quarterly surveys uh across uh the
nation uh that are basically asking uh
US manufacturing firms what is the
largest pain point that you're
experiencing in that particular quarter
and so you'll see uh normal challenges
like business conditions or domestic uh
economy and scales what you're seeing in
the gray however you'll see in the past
15 years the gray has been climbing and
climbing and climbing and the gray uh
save for a small gap uh around COVID has
really been the prevailing challenge uh
that companies in the US anyway are
reporting what what is the gray
attracting and retaining a quality
workforce and so that's a that's a
challenge that I think really excites or
concerns uh many folks at MIT and
certainly myself now it's easy to focus
on the numbers of course the the
millions of people that we have to be
able to obtain what I'm really
interested in is let's not forget about
that quality issue that uh is part of
the survey itself. A key challenge is
quality. How do we retain? How do we
attract a quality workforce? And so it
turns out in surveys, many interviews,
employers often say, "Yeah, I wish I had
more skilled technicians or more quality
workers." And and yet they're offering
wages that perhaps are lower than the
local Costco. Uh and uh why can't they
offer more wages? Well, many of these
especially small to medium-sized
enterprises are stuck in what we might
call at MIT a low wage, low technology,
low productivity equilibrium. Uh on the
other hand, we have uh companies also
complaining that you know what the
community college uh really is not a
very relevant solution for us anymore.
When I need a new worker, I really don't
go there. Uh I have to kind of go out
and maybe I'm working with talent firms
and I'm spending $40,000 $50,000 per
hire. And so, and then on the community
college side, they're complaining that
we can't even fill our cohorts or our
seats. Uh, you know, young people don't
want to come to our community colleges
anymore. And so, there's really a gap, I
think, between the current demand and
industry perspectives on workforce and
then the current workforce development
system itself. Uh, and then this really
matches with uh kind of historical
trends. In the past two, three decades,
we're seeing a decrease in general of
middle-skilled roles. This is true for
manufacturing but also broadly in other
industries as well. And then finally uh
I think our labor economists will also
remind us that uh just because there's a
demand for something it doesn't
automatically generate uh the supply for
it. So what does this mean for the
average small to medium-sized enterprise
or even a large company? What it really
means is firms, what they do is they
will hire really anyone who will show up
at 8 am and continue to stick at a job
for, you know, three months, six months,
hopefully three years or five years. And
we might call that, we might use a
phrase calling that hire for will and
train for skills. Now, that's a deeply
uh problematic
approach. And there's something that
makes it more complex uh which is
advanced manufacturing. When we're
talking about technologies that all of
our firms, many of you in the room want
to be able to adopt and deploy onto the
factory floor, AI, robotics, digital
production, many what is a central theme
that connects many of these technologies
is that these technologies are
connected. So no longer is it a single
process acting on its own. It needs to
be able to to to be able to successfully
integrate. You have to understand how
this technology impacts downstream flow
or upstream flow or how it connects the
entire system. And then what that means
is it certainly raises the question well
who then should be integrating and
optimizing uh these shop floor
technologies. Now uh if you in in many
of my conversations with companies this
is leading to almost a recurring mantra.
Ah we wish engineers had hands-on
skills. Oh we wish technicians had
analytical skills. And there seems to be
a gap in roles and competencies between
these traditional uh worker roles. And
so really I started a few years ago to
start to ask the question well you know
are we actually asking perhaps the the
wrong question. Perhaps there could be
another type of worker role not just to
run the machine on the shop floor but to
think about how do we integrate the
systems and adopt new technologies. And
so that brings me uh to this concept of
this potential, this technician engineer
hybrid who could be able to bridge the
gap between these two traditional roles
and to be able to address many of the
challenges that I just posed
earlier. So we sought to uh test this uh
question. We interviewed scores of
manufacturing firms in New England and
we asked them, hey, do you see this gap?
And if so, you know, imagine a worker
who could plug in this gap. You know,
what would you imagine this person do?
And to do that, we we we sourced from
task descriptions from our Bureau of
Labor Statistics. We called this BLS.
And we asked them, hey, what kinds of
engineering tasks might you want to
delegate to this kind of hypothetical
technologist role? And what you're
seeing here on the right uh on the on
the left of this graph, analyze
performance of systems or equipment. Uh
on the third one here, not carrying out
SOPs, uh but determining operational
methods or procedures. And then the
second one here coordinating right with
others to resolve problems. Uh perhaps
you know to summarize this I might say
strong analytical skills identifying
areas to increase efficiency and
communicating both vertically up down
and and laterally. Now these descriptors
uh might not seem surprising to us
because we often work with engineers but
remember this is what manufacturing
firms are saying they need as a delta on
the shop floor worker where maintaining
or running equipment uh has been
critical so far. And so a a conclusion
that we've made and that I would suggest
to you today is that advanced
manufacturing it really requires workers
with both that technician's practical
knowhow that they understand the process
or the understanding of particular
equipment and combining it with an
engineers's understanding of processes
and
systems. Well, that sounds all fine and
dandy. Uh but the question is, you know,
can we actually develop this kind of
workforce? And if you want to be uh
practical or realistic about developing
this workforce, I think you actually
have to be also think about the
implications of developing workers in
advanced manufacturing and namely that
uh if you really are in the space, these
technologies will also do is they'll
also reduce the shelf life of your
technical skills. And so this is where I
uh want to make a comment about
conventional manufacturing training. I
think this is a good uh pa capture or
representation of how we think about
current manufacturing training. I could
use the old adage, give a man a fish,
feed him for a day, teach a man to fish,
feed him for a lifetime. I'm sure we've
all heard that adage before. But in a
situation like advanced manufacturing,
if we were to extend that analogy, it
might be like this person has to fish
this year, hunt deer in two, trap
lobster in five years. And the question
is if we knew that a priority for the
firms who actually want to adopt
advanced technologies that are evolving
at a more and more rapid pace do we
really want to stick to the left-hand
side the conventional paradigm of
manufacturing training now in the left
hand side if we know that someone has a
skill set in welding he can carry that
for 50 years I think it makes sense
let's give them that skill set let's
teach them how to fish but in the
right-hand case when you know that the
game is changing. You might not exactly
know what the game will be in five, 10
years, 15 years, but you know it will
change. Perhaps it makes sense to take a
step back and think about why the why of
the game in this case. In this case, for
animals, maybe we're taking a step back
and we're thinking about the animal
senses. How do I my understanding of
animal senses enable me to bait
effectively or to hide from the game
effectively? And it turns out in
manufacturing there is an analog. In
fact, in the past two decades, we've
distilled what we believe are the
principles of manufacturing that do not
change uh no matter how the game
changes. And that is no matter if you
are 1800's printing press uh to 2025
so-called industry 5.0 or 4.0 to 5.0 uh
you always have to understand flow and
variation along four levels. The
manufacturing process, the manufacturing
system, the supply and the people. And
in fact, this is how we teach our
master's students in advanced
manufacturing and design. We give them a
core set of understanding of the
principles that make manufacturing
manufacturing. It's not necessarily
additive manu additive manufacturing is
going to be different in five years. Was
it still manufacturing? Yes. These
technologies that we're so concerned
about and we spend so much time
discussing, they will change. But these
principles, these activities, they do
not change.
And so what we uh do at MIT for a master
student and what we'd like to do uh in
this project is really uh uh this kind
of curriculum model shall we say we have
in the hub of a hub and spoke model all
of these principles in manufacturing
that don't change no matter uh again
they're timeless and if timeless they're
also equally applicable uh to a mom and
pop machine shop uh to a semiconductor
fab and then what we do is we surround
them uh with what I call the spokes,
right? These technologies that are
industry specific or are specific to
2025. And so what do we do? We try to
empower the workforce by educating on
the critical thinking why and then
linking that to the cutting edge
how. Okay. And my claim here is that if
you have a workforce, again, not just
the engineers, those without university
degrees, if they truly understand the
why of manufacturing, here's my claim
that workers will be nimble. If they're
not tied to a piece of technology or
equipment, when something comes in next
and they understand the why, they can
pivot. If they understand the why,
they're not tied to one way of doing
things. They might be able to question,
they might be able to propose a
different an alternative approach and
think about trade-offs. And if you have
a workforce that understands the why,
you're not just tied to doing what
someone tells you to do. uh you might be
able to think through and add
recommendations or suggest make
suggestions and so you know of course
there's a there's a very large list of
what we think a technologist could do
but I'll just highlight a few you know
perhaps one could apply uh process
control techniques to be able to analyze
and optimize processes or work with
engineers to employ efficient design of
experiments and so on and so forth along
the levels of systems and operations and
processes
Now I showed uh industry mapping before
and now I've shown the hub and spoke
curriculum model and it turns out that
many of the ways that industry is saying
hey we really need more skills we need a
more quality workforce it really maps
very well uh to our hub and spoke
model okay so I've spent some time
talking about the gap of roles
skills and turns out there's a few other
gaps I think I'm very interested in one
other gap uh on our end is the educ
education gap. And so if you have an
associates degree from a community
college and somehow you end up wanting
to earn a four-year engineering degree,
essentially you have to start over
unless you have an articulation
agreement. And so we have to be able to
handle the education gap as well. Why?
Because what what is a really promising
or really exciting possibility is
perhaps you have someone who starts as
an assembler or an operator, right? and
they take a program, they become a
technologist and then in that role they
see, hey, there's a junior engineer that
I'd love to be in five years. And so
then they go and get more education and
they become an engineer. And I would
love for this program to be a connector
of education and also career pathways.
Imagine what that could do uh both to
excite young people, entry- level
workers about starting an assembler or
operator positions. Also imagine what
that might do to the engineering
workforce if you have folks coming in
with years or decades of experience as
an operator or as a
machinist. And so this is uh as you
might imagine a very broad effort. It's
actually not something that one group uh
in MIT or even MIT can pull off. What
we're doing here is we're broadly
collaborating uh with education sites
across New England, two in Rhode Island,
three in Massachusetts, uh three uh two
in Connecticut. So these are our
education sites. Uh we work with
industry. I'm sure you recognize many of
these logos like Seammens or Autodesk.
And then finally, we work with a number
of different education institutions uh
to develop simulations and develop
assessments and develop labs as well.
Uh now this of course it's too small to
see. We are just starting to pilot
actually this fall and the cohorts that
we're after are small. There may be
cohorts of 15 across six education
sites. That's you know not even 200 uh
technologists uh that we could produce
in the next two years. So not very large
uh numbers as a pilot. And yet these
letters here there are letters of five
US senators and seven US house
representatives. The reason why is not
because we're claiming uh that we will
produce you know 1 million workers but I
think there is an understanding of the
potential impact on firms and economic
development. Uh there's always ways to
uh continue uh learning about this
project and you know our perspective on
how we believe workforce development uh
can improve or evolve. Uh next uh
tomorrow's kind of workshop I'll
probably spend more time less on the
systems level uh work that we do. I'll
probably dig more into the experience
level or on the learner side of things.
But again, happy to share more. Here are
a couple papers. One in a a policy
facing one that we published in the
National Academyy's journal. And then on
the right hand side, it's the MIT News
Press on the project itself. Thank you
so
much. Hey, I think we have time for a
few questions.
Okay. What are the benefits of
introducing the new role technologists
instead of upskilling and raising
requirements for today's technicians?
Great question. So, one thing I I want
to highlight is I was very careful to
call this a worker role, not necessarily
a new worker. We're not necessarily
bringing in a new person into the
company. In fact, this program that
we're working with, companies are are
committing to sending their star
incumbent workers. So, if there's a
technician or a machinist that has been
at the job for 5 years, 10 years, it's a
star. You know, you you as a company,
you believe in that person and that
person has an appetite for more
development. Send that person to us and
we will use the technologist program to
make him or her a leader.
Okay. What cultural shifts need to
happen on the shop floor to support the
emergence of this hybrid technologist
role? This is a great question. Uh
culture is definitely both an
opportunity and a challenge. We have a
number of even our partners who are
working with us on developing the
content. Some of them will often you
know say offhand like oh why do we even
need to develop this content? They're
never going to have the you know they're
not going to have a leadership role or
they won't have an opportunity to
influence uh decision- making. And so it
will be I think a tussle I would say
with uh small to medium-sized even
larger companies um on what kinds of
opportunities can we actually give these
technologists in order to succeed. But
what I think uh this program can do is
perhaps be a Trojan horse. You know we
send someone who is empowered and
enlightened and then all of a sudden
employers their boss and other folks see
uh the kind of value that they can bring
onto the shop floor and now we're in a
larger conversation with MIT.
Okay. And I think we have time for maybe
one more
question. Let's see. How do uh how to
persuade manufacturing engineering
technologist
uh to apply for the new cu apply new
culture?
So this one I think was partially uh I
partially addressed in the my my
previous response. Um I would also say
that as we have more use cases, as this
program starts to deploy, uh there will
be I think a number of different
successful uh stories. And in fact,
turns out as we did industry mapping, we
already see what I might call quasi
technologists or technologists in the
wild. uh companies who are deeply
invested in their workforce wanted to
empower them and over the course of five
ten 15 years somehow managed to bring
someone from an entry level uh to some
technical leadership on the floor
eventually perhaps even to an
engineering uh role. And so one example
is again a probably a 30 person company
in electropolishing in northeast
Massachusetts. you know, he took someone
who was a young lady who was an entry-
level technician, I think earning about
$18 per hour and in about 10 years, uh,
at the end of it was the head of quality
and and to do so, we had a number of
conversations. Uh, what did you have to
do in the past 10 years? Obviously, a
lot of investment from engineers and the
owner, but also sending them kind of
jerryrigging different trainings across
the state. Now if companies who are so
committed take 10 years to do so
couldn't we formalize that uh and be
able to produce kind of formal pathways
to that kind of role in leadership.
Another anecdote actually one of my one
of the stories that inspired me uh was
the story of Niha Dave. She's a a
graduate or alumni from the MENGEN
program, the masters of engineering
program. And she told me essentially two
years after she graduated from the
master's program, she was uh the the
plant manager. Uh and there are a number
of different processes that were out of
control. And to succeed at her job, she
needed to uh basically release a
plantwide pretty complex design of
experiment. And she could not get her
shop floor workers to really have buyin
or understand what was the DOE that she
wanted to And what did she do? She took
coffee breaks. She entered the coffee
room and took coffee breaks to introduce
these concepts that I've been talking
about run charts and SPC and CP CPK. And
then she said as a result of that over
the next six months she was able uh then
to launch a plantwide design of
experiments because she had the buyin
and the understanding of her shopf
flooror workers. And so that keyed me in
early on as we were trying to develop
this understanding that hey if this is
what our MIT graduates are already doing
and they're doing in an ad hoc way like
obviously I cannot expect every MIT
alumni to be able to win over the entire
plant uh to get control you know to to
bring the factory back into control then
wouldn't shouldn't there be a formal
process for that well thank you John Lou
thank