(regal music)
(upbeat music)
(Professor Wallace laughing)
(upbeat music continues)
(wheels squeaking)
(upbeat music ends)
(cheerful music)
(students chatting)
- When we feel valued,
we do our best work.
When we feel supported, we
have the courage to take risks.
And when we empower
others, we unlock potential
that they may not have even
realized they possessed.
Hello, I'm a professor in
mechanical engineering design.
A teacher.
And more than anything, my
goal is to inspire students
with the confidence to dream big,
to be good, and to feel good.
I want to help students be better than me.
(cheerful music intensifies)
(audience cheering)
(cheerful music continues)
(audience continues cheering)
I want to make students' stars shine.
(playful music)
(students conversing)
At MIT in my design
class, our number one job
is to provide opportunities
for each student's star to shine bright.
So in the class we do that, of course,
at our final prototype launch,
our presentations.
Where each team of students
will present their ideas on stage
in front of thousands of people.
(audience cheering)
(playful music continues)
It's the culmination
of everything they've worked towards
throughout the entire course.
And that's no small undertaking.
- [Student] Yeah, you can.
- So how do we adequately equip them
for such a pivotal moment?
(groovy music)
(students conversing)
Leading up to launch day,
there's been a consistent and
steady stream of encouragement
and support every step of the way.
And that's just the bare minimum.
(groovy music continues)
In the Pappalardo Lab,
where most of their physical work
and prototyping takes place,
we ensure that each student
has all the materials,
machinery, and tools that
they could possibly need
right at their fingertips
in order to explore and follow ideas.
(groovy music continues)
We provide a framework for the
product development journey.
We provide resources for
students to develop skills.
We provide students with
ways to make decisions
and develop consensus.
We help students learn
to prepare and practice.
(groovy music continues)
We critique, and many
times we support in ways
that students may never even realize.
Things just appear.
(groovy music continues)
- Let me make this change real quick.
- For example, in 2023,
Red Team worked on a robot
that drove on train rails
and washed the rails so the
trains don't lose traction.
So we're thinking, "Well,
how are we gonna test that?
How are they gonna do it for real?"
(upbeat music)
So even while they were
just thinking about
their early stage design,
we were sourcing train tracks
and building a miniature
but full scale railroad so
they could test their device
and learn.
For Green Team,
we installed a wave pool
so they could test their
water safety product for real,
on balmy winter days.
(upbeat music continues)
(water splashes)
We do this for all of our students.
There are countless examples like these,
big and small, throughout
the journey of the semester.
But in no uncertain manner,
the students own their own journey.
Teams make their own decisions.
They decide and are
responsible for what they do.
(upbeat music ends)
(engine rumbling)
(students conversing)
(gentle music)
We want to make a student's star shine
because ultimately it's going
to be them out there on stage
presenting the products they've designed,
and it will be them
out there in the world,
in their careers far beyond the classroom.
(gentle music continues)
So in order to do that, we
give them the opportunity
to own their journeys.
We empower them to make
the decisions themselves.
We try to instill in them
a sense of confidence
and self-worth by letting
them take the lead
and drive their paths forward.
That way, when they get
to the end of our course
and ultimately get out into the world,
they'll have all the tools
and skills needed to
confidently make a difference.
(gentle music continues)
So how do we apply this? How
do we make others' stars shine?
Well, in a sense, it's
really about being generous,
about giving opportunity and support,
and letting people grow
and make their own choices to have control
of what they're doing.
So feel the warmth of
making others' stars shine.
A team of us is stronger
than any one of us.
Until then, keep playing seriously.
(gentle music continues)
(audience cheering)
(audience continues cheering)