Morning
everyone. My name is Batis Puvier,
founder and CEO of Diplo AAI.
I'm here today to tell you about what we
do, which in a nutshell is to take a
product that you are building and to
identify and track every single
regulation, law, and standard that
applies to that product. So you can
imagine this is a task that takes hours,
weeks, months to do, and it's errorprone
and so forth. Um we're very very proud
across the last three years to be
supporting some of the largest
manufacturers in the world that trust us
to be embedded in their product
development process. You see some of
those that are listed uh on this slide
here. We have a few case studies towards
the end as well. In a nutshell, I'm sure
this is probably not a huge surprise,
but regulations are going out of
control. There are objectively more
regulations published every single day
across many more jurisdictions, a
fragmentation, lack of harmonization
across countries. And then of course you
have all the software horizontal
regulations things like PAS materials
data privacy AI cyber security recycling
EPR all those topics that are coming out
that honestly didn't exist before. So
what this does is it really slows down
development time and leads to risk for
business launch. Um, of course, what
happens is you have really, really bad
visibility in terms of what is tracking.
Potentially, you are operating in over a
hundred countries around the world and
you need to know for every single
country what are all the requirements
you have to follow. You want to know as
soon as they change so that if you're
building something which honestly may
take 5 years, let's say, you need to
know as soon as something changes so
that you don't come to launch realize
you're not compliant in China for
example, then not able to launch as
well. Now, in a nutshell, the system
does three things. Uh the first part is
tracking, right? So pretty simply, the
system will look at every single update
that happens around the world. So to
give you a sense of scale, there are
4,000 regulatory and legal updates every
day just in the United States alone at
the federal and state level. And that's
really any regulation, any law, any
meeting, any press release, any speech,
any hint of a regulation that might come
up. The fact is for any of you, you
know, out of those 4,000, probably 99.9%
don't apply to you.
But the fact is 0.01% do. And the
question is how do you get the guarantee
that you are finding every single
requirement for your product without
having to look at those thousands that
apply. And so the tracking says we're
going to look at maybe like 20,000
updates around the entire world find the
10 things that apply to the company. And
that's where the second part comes in.
So then engineers and R&D folks are
using the platform to say great we found
these 10 things that potentially affect
our product today. The real question is
what do you do as a result? What is the
impact? Is it a design change, which is
maybe the worst case? Is it a compliance
change? Is it a reporting change? What
do you have to do? Again, we may we may
have found these 10 things for you,
which is great, but each of those 10
things could be 200 pages long. And
again, this is where engineering and and
and R&D teams are reading one by one to
figure out the requirements. So really,
this is where that, you know, AI can
support and jump in for you. And
finally, the distribute is about getting
that information out to the engineering
and R&D teams, right? Imagine you've
you've tracked something, you found some
change that's really critical to some
system that you're building. You've done
the analysis, you know what to do. Now
that the most important thing arguably
is to get the word out and tell people
about it and and give the engineers the
tools to understand exactly what they
have to follow, what are the nuances,
what are the gray areas, etc. Um, give
you a bit of a case study. We are uh
live uh with one of the largest OEMs
around the world, you know, more than
100 billions in revenue and they trust
us to work with them from the initial
product development phase all the way
through to launch. Um the way that they
evaluate it, which is honestly the way
that happens most times, is you do a bit
of an AB test. And from their
perspective, the first thing that
mattered was efficiency. So how long do
they spend today manually going to
websites finding those thousands and
thousands every single day across many
teams decentralized around the world and
finding all the government updates every
single day. So they reporting spending
around 480 minutes or hours and hours
essentially every single day and with
the system they find 10 minutes uh to
look at those relevant alerts. At the
end day this is not that surprising
humans are not built to look at
thousands and thousands of things as
this is where AI can jump in as well. So
obviously a huge huge time saving which
is where a lot of the business case was
built but arguably more important is
what are the net new requirements that
they found that they would not have
found otherwise. So this was a
three-month P side by side. They had
their regulatory teams by the way there
are around 50 people that are doing this
full-time finding everything across all
the countries and yet around 30% of what
the system recommended they had reported
to have not found and were critical. Of
course these are not your standard
regulations. These are all the newer
ones around data privacy, AI, especially
in different parts of the world and and
globally too. And so, as you can see,
there's lots and lots of different ones.
The key ones that I've talked about are
around robust tracking, what does it
mean for you to not miss a single
requirement, the efficiency you can have
and minimizing all those redevelopments
as well. So, very happy we have a booth
in the other room. Very happy to talk
again, and thank you all very much for
your time.