thank you again for joining and welcome
to a new installment of MIT startup
exchange demo day I'm Marat rodenstein
program manager with MIT startup
exchange and shortly you will hear from
eight exciting startups all members of
startup exchange but first i'm going to
give a brief overview of our program and
I hope you find it all
useful so MIT startup exchange was
created about close to 10 years ago now
within the office of MIT corporate
relations to support MIT connected
startups as they grow expand and help
solve some of the world's greatest
challenges and we do this by fostering
Partnerships and collaborations between
the startups and Industry primarily
members of the MIT industrial Ison
program or ILP represented by so many of
you here today and also the MIT
Innovation ecosystem and Beyond the
startups in our program have a very um
strong connection to the Institute and
they can be based on MIT licens
technology or founded by MIT faculty
staff or alumni and they can also be
vetted by some of our MIT peers
including the engine start Nano and Cale
startup connect
plus we have around a thousand startups
in the program and they usually join at
Pilot stage or Beyond and they can cover
any sector and any geography here you
can see some of the trending
Technologies of MIT startups and I've
noted in bold those represented by those
presenting to you today of course
starting with AI ml
also big data and analytics energy
storage and sustainability Robotics and
Healthcare and life
science so when it comes to Value
everything that we do is to support the
startups present opportunities where
they can share their Technologies and
solutions and connect with industry and
so the Partnerships that can develop out
of that or collaborations ultimately
result in success cases like the one
highlighted here and we do this in a
variety of ways it's a very customized
and curated approach and I hope that
everyone can be taking advantage of all
of these benefits so for example we
launch calls for startups we call these
opportunities and they're based on
corporate's priorities and internal
challenges and startups can apply on our
website and if selected they can work
with you as an ILP member to help you
solve a problem that you may be may be
facing in your industry we also have
oneone meetings and events including
demo days like today or other webinars
or conferences where there startup
linning talks and Exhibits or many
opportunities for engagement we also
host workshops and trainings sometimes
in connection with our MIT
peers and so what is demo day it's a
virtual Forum that we host every couple
of months now to facilitate interactions
between the startups and Industry and we
hope that this can happen sooner rather
than later so it's sort of a short and
sweet forum
and we actually hosted our first live
demo day in Silicon Valley in June of
2023 and are looking to host our next
live one on April 2nd in Cambridge and
then on June 11th we'll have the next
virtual one so please check out the ILP
and startup exchange sites so you can
join us register and take advantage of
all our upcoming events the format to
today is going to consist of eight
startups presenting for four minutes
then we'll have two minutes of Q&A and
it'll be followed right on by uh
breakout rooms for the Q&A portions I
ask that you please use the Q&A tab at
the bottom of your screen and indicate
which startup the question is for and
throughout the event please um engage
with the startups via the chat we want
to make this as Dynamic and interactive
as possible and as always reach out to
us if you need help connecting with the
startups at any point so a couple of
final
reminders um the startup presentations
are being recorded
and at the end of the event you'll see a
brief survey pop up on your screen if
you could please help us by filling it
out and sharing your feedback so with
that let's just hear from the startups
now