So uh the uh what I I'll talk mostly
about u riskneutral pricing and uh black
shows will be more of uh uh of an
illustration to to to the method to more
general method which I think is very
important and very important for pricing
derivatives. uh and many many a few of
you uh did uh look into black shells. Uh
so my hope is to to give some a little
bit more depth and a little bit more
perspective on uh how what is the bigger
picture of derivative pricing uh through
through risk neutral valuation. But as
promised uh before let's start from uh
from the interest rates from from the
slide which similar slide which I showed
you on the first class and Andrew
Gensson already talked about yield curve
construction and everything but yeah so
that's how what happened since since we
started uh that's the yield curve
or it's just as planning as it was in in
September just before beginning of the
class and that's where we are now. So uh
quite predictable in a sense because fed
moved the the rates for by 75 basis
points and that's uh that's exactly uh
what what uh what happened uh here uh uh
the uh uh
the uh the the parallel shift is only uh
at 70 base points. here but more of a
50 here.
Uh what uh now a little bit of
huristics. How does it look like? Well,
right now it looks like we are very
similar to to this shape, right?
Which was
uh 19,
right? On the other hand, this shape
is is almost exactly the same, right?
Which was in fact just before the
crisis. So, uh in both cases a recession
fall I mean in both in both cases there
the curves are inverted and in both
cases the recession followed shortly
after. I certainly think hope that it is
closer to this because just this is
basically the next snapshot in uh in 21
and the curve is completely normal shape
and and the economy was uh the recession
was very very short and the economy was
on a very solid track by then but and
hopefully we are not in this situation
because this is just before the crisis.
It's before before bare turns collapse
before lemon collapse. So a lot of bad
things happened after that. uh uh in any
case uh this is all non non-scientific
prediction and the the real question
here would be to to to do some soral
data analysis something like Stefan
Stefan Andre talked about about
analyzing the shape of the curves and
bond markets using uh
uh PCA principal component analysis but
always fascinating to look at the data
and always fascinating to look at the
curves which in my opinion are in the
middle in the center of finance.
Okay, let's move on to uh
to the
uh topic of our class. And the idea is
to to see
uh how replicating the payoff can help
us to price derivatives.
uh and how to learn that actually if we
can follow market market dynamics
uh that how it can help us to price
derivatives and actually that the real
world dynamics is not that important
it's it's what market implies uh that's
what important and how it is connected
to morting gales and to mathematical
apparatus to to stocastic calculus
connecting that. So, but yeah, here is a
simple example uh horse betting, right?
So, uh let's
assume
clear that we have two horses, horse one
and horse two.
And we I mean you're a bookie and you
know the horses well. you know that this
horse has 20% to uh chance to win and
this horse has 80% chance to win,
right? But people bet uh bet on the
market and uh uh 10,000
is bad on this horse. People don't know
exactly these probabilities. They know
that this this horse is better than
this. So they they bet rather
the public bets
50,000 on this and 10,000 on on this,
right?
Um and then what you do, you just take a
commission, right?
Uh say 1%
and you you have
6,000 in your uh uh 600 in your pocket
of the commission. So now the question
is you need to set the odds for for this
race right. So well one way to set the
odds is knowing the real exact
probabilities. One it's reasonable to
say let's make it four to one.
So what what outcomes are possible
right? Then horse starts horses race.
So
H1 wins H2 wins.
So if a uh horse uh the first horse
wins, you will get
50,000,
right? This this amount and you will pay
out four times this amount because you
set uh you set the odds four to one.
So
this will mean that you will be left
with 10,000 profit.
This is low probability outcome. You
know that second horse is better. So
what happens is second horse win uh
second horse wins. Well, you will keep
this money. So it will be
10,000
and you will pay a quarter of this,
right?
And this will be
on my books minus
2,500
at the end, right? So you you will lose,
you will have to pay, right? Of course,
if you compute expected value, if horses
run along many many times, it will be
zero, right? Uh 10 *
2 plus minus 2 2 and a half time.8
is zero, right? But for this on average
it the horses have to run a lot. Right?
Now let's consider a different way of
setting uh setting odds.
You forget about the these numbers. You
just look at at at what was bad, right?
And you rather set the odds five to one.
Okay, let's see what happens.
Well, if the first horse wins, you will
get 500
50,000
and you'll pay 50,000, right?
Well, if second horse uh wins, you'll
get uh you'll get 10,000
and 1/5 of this. So you'll pay out
10,000.
So no matter which horse wins wins, you
are you break even for sure in in this
particular outcome, right? So and if you
were collecting some fee, you just keep
the feed. You'll do it next time.
So
basically what you did by setting the uh
the uh the odds according to the market
you hedged yourself. You you eliminated
every uncertainty
which is probably
the the outcome which you want.
All right. So this is all about betting
and we are not betting people.
In fact, we are scientists.
So, and
we'll uh we'll be talking today about
pricing derivatives. Uh again, some
simple examples and derivatives which
we'll be looking at uh will be uh call
put options and and forward contracts
just to refresh. So, what are those? So
the the simplest possible
derivative is a forward contract which
is an agreement
to buy a security in our case a stock in
the future for for a price which is set
today.
Uh generally speaking uh so uh the the
payout of of a forward is just the
difference
of
uh of the strike and the uh the
price at the expiration right at the
expiry.
So the payout is s uh uh s minus k where
k is a strike agreed price right and uh
for forwards the agreement uh is that
the strike is set in such a way that it
costs you nothing to enter it today
you basically say we agree with you
today for a zero price that
I'll buy the stock at the price K,
right?
Uh so uh quite useful diagram is the the
payout that's uh that's sorry that's a
blue line. So it's in our case it's S
minus K. So that's forward.
Uh now call option.
Call option is an option to buy
a stock at price K. Right? So basically
at expiry
you will decide are you buying the stock
at price K
or if it's if you don't want to you you
won't. And generally speaking, if the
stock ends at the money higher than the
strike, you will buy it, right? Because
it will be cheaper. And if uh if the
stock uh uh ends uh below the strike
price, it you will say thank you very
much. And the contract will expire
worthless. So this is the payout at the
end. And this is the price of the call
option today, right? Obviously it is not
zero price contract. It is you you will
pay some money to enter into this
contract. Right?
Uh
another
usual and simple contract would be a put
option
uh which is an agreement to to sell
uh the uh it's kind of opposite right
it's uh it basically prevents if if the
uh the option uh the uh stock is too
high you won't sell it. If if the stock
ends low, you will sell it for a higher
price. So it is basically
insurance kind of insurance of uh uh of
against stock falling below uh below the
the strike price. And here is the the
current price. And what we'll be doing
today is deriving these curves, deriving
the current price of price today for the
options and the forwards.
And what we'll see
is
a few observations that
uh
the only uh what will matter it is
assumptions on uh on the dynamics of the
stock price. Some assumptions on how the
stock behaves, some assumptions on
interest rates.
uh and and uh given given that there
will be no uncertainty in in the price
of the derivative and this was believe
me this wasn't clear to market
participants before black and shows
uh
u and uh the u
the Another
important observation which we'll see
that the uh the preferences of market
participants will not matter. It's you
know similarly in to our horse racing
example we'll be able to to uh to find
the riskless ways to replicate replicate
the price the price of the option.
All right. So
let's start
with uh with a simple example of the
forward
and uh let's start from from a discrete
uh uh time and and and stock prices and
uh because it's it's simple simpler to
understand
and uh so what does it mean is that
right now we
uh have
some price of our stock s0.
Uh we have price of our contract f0
in in the case of uh of the forward. We
assume that it's zero, right? Because we
we assume that we uh the we are entering
at the forward contract at zero price,
right? And there are two outcomes that
we are only one step away. So some time
dt to the future. And uh at the outcome
the the outcomes either s1 or s_ub_2. So
the stock can go either here and here.
And our derivative
according to our formula will be will go
to
s1 minus k
or
s2 - k
right
so again from naive perspective one can
say well there is some probability for
stock to go to go up to to s1 one and
some probability 1 minus P for stock to
go down.
And one would say that we can assume
that our price now
is actually expected value
with this probability of
uh of the value of our derivative at the
end.
Right. And so it will be
P * F_sub_1 -
1 - P * F_sub_2
U
and well
P * S1 - K
plus 1 - P *
That's 2 minus k
and from uh from here we can actually
well what we what we are looking for is
the agreed price on our forward right so
we can say that our strike price should
be PS1
uh plus
1 minus p
* s2
But we don't know the the probability
and in fact that's as we'll see in a
second that's not a good way to approach
it.
And why? Here is why
because here is a suggestion what we
should do. Here is a suggestion how we
we can construct
a riskneutral portfolio here. So
that's what we are going to do.
So at time zero
we enter into uh into forward contract
with strike K and we'll in a second
we'll see what this strike K will be at
zero at zero cost cost right
enter
forward
at at zero cost
and we will borrow
money to buy to buy the stock. So we are
borrow
as zero. So we'll buy we borrow money in
a bank and uh and buy a stock
for a minute. Let's assume that our
interest rates are zero for for
simplicity. Okay. So what happens at
expiry? What happens? It's time time
equals zero time equal dt.
So at at at expiry what we'll do
we will deliver the stock right because
we have it deliver s
and we'll receive our strike guys
and repays the loan.
So basically what happens here we we we
borrow here we had a stock we came here
we delivered the stock this cost nothing
so we receive K that's a grid a grid
strike and we repay the loan which we
started here it because interest rate is
zero we it didn't change right if it
changed it will be discount some e to
the minus e to the rt t times s0.
So
now that's what we'll get here. And here
we started with zero, right? Because it
was we paid zero to enter. What can we
say about this?
Well, if this was greater than zero, we
we for sure receive money, right? There
is no other outcome.
If it's less than zero, we for sure lost
money.
No arbitrage assume will tell us that
neither is possible.
So because the price was initial price
was zero, this has to be zero
because this replicates our payoff.
So our strike
has to be as zero, right?
So if there are no interest rates, the
forward contract would just we we we
would agree to buy or sell the the the
price in the the stock in the future at
the current price if interest rates are
zero.
So no no no choice and we don't care
about real world probabilities
and we don't care about uh
about what what how the stock behaves in
in real uh in real life. We just
replicated everything. What's
interesting though? What interesting
though we can find a probability
which will give us our uh our strike or
which will give us this formula. Right?
So what what will it be? Well, well, K
is is equal as zero
and uh so our P and I'll call it
neutral uh risk neutral prob probability
S1
uh plus
1 minus P N
S2
Right.
And that's uh and we we can find our uh
PN from here.
S0 - S2
divided by S1 - S2.
Uh
what's interesting observation here?
First of all, that we can find this rift
neutral probabilities
and we uh we actually could price our uh
our forward contract using this
probabilities using this expected
expected payoff. The interesting the
most interesting part is that our
current stock price our underlying
under this riskneutral prob probability
is expected value of the future move of
the stock and that's what we will see.
So that that's basically our riskneutral
measure. Then that's how we will be
looking for our risk neutral measure
because
we can always find a measure which
implies that our our current underlying
value asset value is expected value of
the future payoff and that's a measure
which we can use to price the
derivatives.
Okay. So, let's move to something more
interesting
and let's
do
and
call option but still in in discrete
time, right?
So
our call option payoff would be maximum
of the the value at expiration minus k
and zero. Right?
Right. That's is here. That's that's our
payoff. That's the hockey stick.
We still assume for for this exercise,
let's still assume interest rates uh
zero. So uh our diagram will be our
value of call option which we will be
looking for uh at time zero. Our stock
is zero. Uh S0 stock goes to S1 or to
S2.
Uh and our value of our call
will go
uh we we assume that s_ub_1 is greater
than s0, s_ub_2 is less than uh zero. So
here uh value of uh of our option will
be what?
S t minus k, right?
And
value of our call option here will be
>> zero right because it will be this this
thing.
Okay good. So now
what we want to do
we want to to find a replicating
portfolio.
Uh and here is suggestion how so
replicating portfolio in the case of
forward was stock itself right it it it
was rep replicating the the payout. Now
my suggestion is to do the following.
Our replicating portfolio would be some
amount of cash and some amount of stock,
right?
And
we we want to find these values of of
cash and how much stock we need such
that our
our option payoff is replicated here,
right?
Well, we we certainly can can do it uh
in in this simple case, right? Because
well, in the beginning
our our portfolio will be B 0 plus A S0.
At the end it will be B1
plus S1
or B2 plus A S2.
Right? And our condition of replication
is that in this state it should be equal
to this. Right?
And in this state it should be equal to
this because we are replicating our
payoff.
And let's notice
that because our interest rate is zero
again, this thing doesn't doesn't change
because it's just cash, right?
Well,
nice nice and easy. uh from here we can
find that our a well if we subtract this
equation from this equation I mean we
have two equations with two unknowns so
b 0 is one unknown and the second
unknown is a so from here we can easily
find that a is equal s1 minus k
divided by s1 minus s2
right
and uh b 0
B 0
is equal
S2 * K - S1
/ S1 - S_UB_2
and
knowing that if we replicate it the same
as before if we replicate it the port we
have a replication portfolio that's what
uh uh where it should be uh uh here and
this is our C 0 and that's what we are
looking right we are looking for the
value of our option at time zero
so
our C 0
is equal to a
S0 minus S2
or
it is
uh
s1 - k
divided by s_ub_1 - s_ub_2
* s0 minus s_ub_2.
Okay. So basically by the same
replication argument we were able to to
find uh uh to find uh our value. Now
coming back to our risk neutral.
Sure enough, if we use this this same
probability
which is derived from from expected
value of of the stock, the price of our
C 0
is actually
P neutral
times ST minus K
plus 1 - P neutral
time zero.
Right? So if we know this probability
and we can derive it from here instead
of doing all this difficult machinery,
we can just take the payoff and take
expected value of our payoff using this
probability and get the value of our uh
our derivative. Now
all right.
So that's discrete world.
Uh and yeah so
they just for your reference here it is
the same set of formulas for for any
for any payout.
Uh and it one other interesting
uh useful
uh comment here is that we started with
replicating for portfolio. So we we
started with some cash and some stock in
order to replicate the uh the the value
of our option in on the next step.
Right? On the other hand, one can
rewrite it and say that this portfolio
is because this is just cash. This is
riskless portfolio
and we we will see that just in a second
that sometimes it's more convenient
instead of talking about replicating
portfolios about talking the portfolios
without risk. So we basically form a
portfolio of option of full value of
option and some stock such the
combination is riskless.
Okay. So that's our discrete world.
With that, let's move on to continuous
world.
So and in continuous world for today
we'll be looking we we'll be working
with
logn normal dynamics
but we'll see that it's not absolutely
crucial is just nice example once again
and logn normal dynamic is basically
a dynamic which implies ize that there
is some
some growth and there is some random
component.
Well, one can also write
uh it in this form
and let's talk a little bit about DW
what what it is. Uh so uh DW is uh
random walk inner process. So expected
value of DW
is equal to to zero and standard
deviation
of DW
is equal to square root of DT
and that's what always
bothers me. Why standard deviation has
to be square root of DT? Why why do we
know that? Well, and here is a handwavy
reason without any measure theory or
anything else is the following that so
our
suppose we have n
dt steps right our random walk had nine
n steps
right so
the collection of those will be DW0 DW1
so on and dw
and the uh no not equal. So our dwn the
final value after n steps it will be sum
of all the smaller steps.
Right? So what's expected value of
WN?
Well, it is sum of the expected values
of all DWS
and each of them is zero. So it is zero.
It's in fact Martin Gale, right? It
stays zero. Well, and what is the
standard deviation
or variance
uh of our DWN?
Well, it will be sum of squared
of each step.
Uh
yeah, and what I forgot to say to tell
here
Is that
probability
of us going
up? Uh
we we we are going by one either up or
down.
And on each step
uh it is 1/2 with probability 1/2 we go
up or or down. And correlation
our our steps
uh
are not correlated. Right? That's
important. So then the the variance
uh here will be
sum of expected values of t wi
squared
each of them will be one with
probability with probability 12.
So uh it will be
it will be n right so with probability
1/2 it is one with probability 1/2 it's
minus one so sum of squares will be all
ones so n after n steps it will be n
okay fine now let's uh put our n steps
on a on a finite period of time, right?
Let's
assume
uh le let's uh let's assume that
we have a final period of time and we
split it and uh and n equal
periods of delta t of small delta
And we also let let's assume that
instead of doing the steps of one uh and
minus one uh
let's assume that
they are some number D right
plus or minus D right with probability
uh
h Sorry.
Okay. So, expected value of of our
random walk still stays zero and our
variance now becomes uh becomes what?
sum of 12 d^2
+ 12
d^2
right
so n d^2
and our n we we assume that it is just
split
uh period of time. So
t d ^2 divided by delta t. Right? So
basically what what I'm trying to say
that if we put our steps on a on a
period of time that's what's our
variance. And now if we make the steps
smaller the the time steps smaller and
the space steps smaller as well right
we're kind of taking intofinity. We we
make we are taking a limit over the
finite period of time
and the only way for this to stay finite
or n zero is for this to be of order of
magnitude of square root of t.
So a long winded
uh question
uh long winded answer is for
for why
standard deviation of our brownian
motion has to be square root of t
because otherwise we either will have
zero zero variance or exploding process.
So for this process not to explode
this has to be true.
All right. Uh
now another observation before we go to
uh to option pricing
uh is to
to talk about Taylor formula and eto
formula as
at a followup to it. Right.
So if if if our life
uh was deterministic and there was a a
function of two uh two variables
and s and s and t
then our tailor formula to the first
degree or to the second degree let's
let's write it
right? We'll take the partial
derivatives
with all with both respect of both and
then we'll have second derivatives,
right? So 12 of
d2f by dt squared
dt^ 2 + 12
d2 f by d s 2 d s 2
uh plus
mix derivative
right? So this is to second degree plus
plus delta. Right? Uh this is to the
second degree. Now in our uh in our
stochastic world these two terms have
kind of different magnitude right. So
this the deterministic term is of
magnitude dt and uh and stochastic term
is of of mag magnitude of square root
right. So if we go back to our
uh our tailor formula and still and and
would like to to have expansion to the
first to the first degree what what
we'll have to do
so in our stochcastic world.
So this is the first degree right? So
this we keep
this is first degree or
le at least less uh first degree or less
right because our ds is dt plus this is
of order of magnitude of square root dt
right so this will keep
completely
and now if we Go to mixed terms. This is
second degree squarely.
Get rid of it. Now uh this is certainly
more than first degree. So get rid of
it. But here something is left and what
is left is is square of this roughly
speaking. Right? So we'll have to have a
term which is coming from uh from ds
squared.
So which will be
12 of d2 f by ds^ 2
and from uh from d s 2 the first term
will be dt ^ 2 not not interesting the
mixed term will be dt * dw will be uh
more less than dt but uh the square of
dw will be exactly on the of the order
magnitude of dt. Right? So here will be
sigma squar s^ 2 dt
uh ds^ squ sorry
right and so the and this is called
etheros's formula very important uh for
stoastic calculus and this is quick and
dirty derivation
of it.
Okay. Now,
uh let's move on
uh to our
to our
No, this this will leave probably.
So, we'll need this this
but this we don't need.
So let's move to pricing.
So we still want to price
a
some claim derivative claim
and we'll call it f in our case and
we'll form a replicating portfolio.
And as before, our replicating portfolio
will consist of some stock,
some cash.
And what we want to do is to replicate
our uh value of our claim on each step
on each step dt. Right?
Now
let's do the trick which we did before
which let's rearrange this. Right? So
let's notice that
a s t
minus f of t. So the combination
or f minus a sorry more
that this combination of uh of our
derivative and stock is riskless.
And what does it mean that uh well now
we are we'll assume the uh
that interest rates are not zero. What
does it mean? It means that
this thing if it's riskless it has to
grow with time as e to the e to the rt
right
by definition. So
BT
is equal e to the RT
times B 0. Right? So we started our
strategy at time zero and since then our
cash is growing with interest rate T.
And what does this mean? Well, this
means that
our DB is deterministic function. No, no
need for e or anything like this.
And we all can differentiate,
exponentials.
So, trivial mass. That's how RB works.
So now that's so let's try to
differentiate the whole thing. We we
know the right side because it's
deterministic it will be this.
So the derivative
of our riskless portfolio
will be r times
uh our riskless portfolio
times dt.
Good. Now
we'll keep it as a right hand side and
for this we'll use our our
uh uh eido eidto's formula right
well let's do that so we continue to
differentiate that and we get
df minus a
ds s
and our f is stochastic. We use our
ether's formula will be
d of dt
* dt
plus
df
ds
* ds
plus our stochastic term plus 12
D2F by D S^ 2
D S^2
and we don't forget to subtract this
and if we just continue continue further
and start collecting terms.
So we we'll expand our uh ds according
to our formula right and we'll collect
terms with the certain terms with dt and
uncertain terms with our dw right so if
we're collecting our terms with dt here
it will be df by dt
plus
12 uh uh 12 coming from ds^ squ and ds^2
remember it will be
sigma^ 2 s^ 2 dt it comes from from this
only right so it will be
oh so sorry sorry well yeah not okay
that's fine plus 12
d2f f
by d s 2 sigma squ s 2 and I missed this
one and if we are collecting the dt
terms it it has to be that right
uh plus df by ds
times mu s
right
and we should not forget dt term from
here minus
a
mu s
and that's completes our dt term. Right?
Now let's see what happens
with our dw term.
Uh well dw term will be partially from
here right?
DF by DS
sigma S
from here right
minus
part part from here a sigma
S
and this is equal DW
uh times DW right and what it is equal
to well it is equal to this right yeah
>> um how come we can say that dw equals dt
because I thought we just knew the
standard deviation was the square root
of dt but like
>> so dw^ squared is dt
>> but like I thought w was random. I
thought dw was random. So how can you
say that when you square it you get
something deterministic?
Uh well that that this is more of a
notation
but uh but yeah we we kind of yeah it is
not very uh very rigorous notation
but that's basically
what uh what uh what it's formula tells
you.
>> Okay.
>> Right. So if you go into uh the strict
proof that that's what you'll get
basically for for the second for the
square term right but yet
>> add to that when we talked about brownie
motion the quadratic variation of
brownian motion is constant
over time intervals.
>> I see. Okay.
>> And so over the infinite intervals.
>> Okay. That makes sense.
>> Yeah. It's combination of infinite
decimal and the fact that the the yeah
the that the standard deviation is of
order of magnitude but yes you are right
it is uh it is kind of slope annotation
uh okay so and this is equal to
RF
right uh minus R S R A S
uh DT T
and because we we knew that this this
part is deterministic, right? So there
are no DW terms on on this side.
So what does it mean? That this has to
be equal to this,
right? And this has to be equal to zero
because right right hand side here
is completely deterministic.
So uncertainty has to disappear. Why it
disappears by construction because we
from the very beginning we said that we
want to find such an A and that's what
we'll get just in a second that this
portfolio is riskless
or another another way that we can
replicate our uh our our derivative. So
if this is equal to zero
then our a is equal to uh df by ds
right
and we are done right so what we are
done in a sense
that we arrive at the following equation
basically. Uh where should I write? How
about this?
So our main equation will be this equal
to this. But we'll substitute a
and let me write it here. The equation
which we arrive at
df by
dt + 12
the second
f by d s^ 2
sigma^ 2 s^ 2 is equal to rf
right
minus r
df by ds * s
And this is the black shells equation
right. So that's what we are looking for
and that's what we will be solving.
So just
to give
yeah so in the slides there are nicer
and more cleaner write up. Um
yeah. So the basically what what we
found out that any
derivative claim any pay payoff has to
satisfy this this this equation.
Well under assumptions of our log normal
mo motion. If if we assume some other
dynamics of the stock, the equation will
be different but we still can derive it
in in in a similar manner. Right?
And but but the beauty of it that any
derivative claim uh any uh payout at any
time uh time before expiry has to
satisfy the this this equation. More
moreover this equation doesn't depend on
our drift
on our real world drift
and we we'll come back to this uh come
back to this shortly. Uh so so it
doesn't matter what what matters is
volatility right uh and uh that we we'll
touch upon hopefully we'll have time to
touch upon it further in black shaw
theory it is assumed constant but it
doesn't have to be it it you can assume
some function or you can assume this to
be stochastic itself which will make the
uh the equations more complicated and
more complicated to solve But but once
again
uh so and that's uh that's what uh
Fisher Black Martin Scholes and Robert
Merton discovered or published in their
1973 paper. Believe it or not, it was
quite controversial because uh and
actually wasn't very much applauded at
this time, but was recognized by a Nobel
Prize in 97.
Uh and they always fun fact to to say
that all three of them are associated
with MIT. uh um um Bob Mertin is still I
think a professor at at MIT which is
obviously
quite quite nice to to talk about it in
these walls.
So uh now uh coming uh well maybe a
couple of remarks
uh yeah uh yeah so v said that so any
derivative satisfy this equation it
doesn't depend on real world uh drift we
obtained it this equation by by
replicating strategy and that's the most
important uh the the
other beauty of it. It's not only
replicating strategy, it's also a
hedging strategy. Right? So if we know
our A which is actually derivative of
our current price with respect to stock,
we can hedge out all the risk. Right? So
basically by holding option and some
amount of stock this this amount of
stock our portfolio becomes riskless
which is very important practical
conclusion. Uh the more mathematical or
technical uh observations are that this
is actually a form of heat equation and
a a good technical exercise would be to
uh to uh to figure out what what change
of variables uh gives you uh the heat
equation and this is a very wellstudied
and solved problem even though it will
be it has to be numerical. Um so as any
partial differential equation to solve
it uh it will require uh it will require
the uh initial or actually in this case
final conditions and boundary
conditions. And what is our final
condition? Well our final condition is
actually our final payoff
which will be this. This is our final
condition. This we know right. And what
will be our boundary condition for for
call will be that at zero uh the value
of the call is zero.
And the other B boundary condition would
be uh would be that at infinity it is
actually uh the approaches S as S as S
as S as S as S as S as S as S as S as S
s
minus K right
uh and if we imply
uh this
boundary
uh conditions and uh finite conditions
and this is the conditions for for put
we can uh derive uh the arrive to
analytical or semianalytical formulas
for for the prices. Of course it's
expressed in the terms of uh uh error
function which has to be tbulated. Um
uh yeah uh in in more complicated cases
in in the cases of more complicated
dynamics uh of course the the formulas
are not so nice and most probably it
will require some numerical numerical
integration and numerical uh procedures
which is a big part of numerical
finance. In fact, what I wanted to talk
about is uh coming back to uh
riskneutral pricing and let me
uh
uh let me
do it here.
Uh basically how how do we find our
riskneutral measure and how do we find
our riskneutral PDF?
Well actually
fine
in the case of log normal it is pretty
simple because
well our ds
is equal to
mu s dt
plus sigma s dw. W.
So here is a nice trick. If we take
expectation value of both sides,
then we'll get a differential equation
for
well uh for
expected value of this is zero, right?
Because expected value of DW is is is
equal is equal zero. So an expected
value uh of this will be
mud dt right.
So nice differential equation for our
expected value. So
our expected the the expected value of
of the stock
should be equal to initial value of the
stock
time e to the mu t right but for our
riskneutral assumptions
remember so we said that in discrete
case the whole point of uh
riskneutral probability was that
expected value of our stock
should be
our stock may be compounded by by
interest rate right well when interest
rate was zero it was constant
it was so uh
in in logn normal uh uh dynamics ds over
s will be martingale martingale So this
has to be equal to s e to the rt because
in under risk neutral dynamics our stock
has to be has to grow with r. So
basically it tells us that mu has to be
equal to r
under our risk neutral measure.
Right? So now okay mu is equal to r but
uh but we can easily find a pdf
of of this process at time t and that's
what it is of log normal process
basically right
with uh with mu sub substituted by r.
So
yeah so
mu substituted by r and what what I'm
saying that now instead of solving
our black shs equation for any claim our
under uh logn normal dynamics we we
could just take the our payoff and
integrate it against this pd PDF the
final PDF and get the value of the
function now as is expected
expected payoff under risk neutral
measure
and that's our risk neutral measure
right so that's a nice benefit of course
it is easier for log normal for other uh
for other processes uh it is not that
easy
um but uh it's certainly an added
benefit.
Another
uh another example which I want to give
you in the past in the last 10 minutes
is another replication example.
Uh
so
let's form such a portfolio.
Let's buy a call and sell a put.
So what what what is it? Well, let's
draw a diagram.
And let's draw a diagram at time
maturity t. Right? So we long a call.
So with some strike K, right? So this is
our strike K. So our call is looks like
this.
We short a put, right? So put would be
like this. And short put it will flip
it, right? So it's like this.
How does it look?
It looks like just like a forward,
right?
So
at maturity
by this portfolio has zero uncertainty.
It's forward,
right? So at any time before maturity,
it has to be value the the forward value
of the stock,
right? So it it always has to be so at
at maturity it is S t minus K.
So uh well
at maturity
so at any point of time
the difference
of call and put
has to be
the difference of
value of the current value of the stock
and to tell the truth discounted value
of of the strike. Right?
T minus T
and the beauty of it that we we made
zero assumptions about dynamics of the
of the stock here.
This has to be true always. It's just
how the payoffs look look like
because we always know forward. It is
only dependent on uh on uh interest
rate. it doesn't depend on uh on
dynamics of the stock and this portfolio
doesn't depend on dynamics of the stock
and it's quite powerful because it
basically tells you that if this is
different at any point of time you have
an arbitrage
and to illustrate that I actually
uh
went oh sorry uh went to Bloomberg
took real prices of calls and puts. This
is Apple stock a while ago admittedly.
uh and uh here I I literally plotted the
data from here for call and for for put
and literally summed it up and you see
that it it is a straight line and no
surprise because if if it w wouldn't be
it would be an arbitrage people will
jump on it immediately people check for
it all the time the beauty of it that
the the dynamics of The stock is not log
normal and how can we see it? Well, I
also plotted here implied volatility for
I think I did it for call here and if it
would be log normal the volatility
should be straight line and it is not
right. That's why we need more
complicated models for for stock
dynamics. that why black trolls is a
nice example but but we need stocastic
relativity
uh or or others jump diffusion is by the
way uh if tricky thing because the
Martin gales with jumps don't really
work so the the life becomes becomes uh
more complicated so um yeah so that
that's a nice another nice example of
replication, right? So, and in general,
that's how a lot of things function. You
what you try to do, you look at the
payout of a portfolio and you try to
replicate the payout with the
instruments which you have at hand or at
least approximate the payout because if
you did it, you know the price now
or you know arbitrage. The the other way
to do it is for some form some
complicated portfolio
and find misplacement right and that
then it becomes arbitrage. Nowadays it's
practically impossible but but
people did a lot of things with more
complicated options even 15 20 years a
well 25 years ago I think Jake uh has a
good story about that how he was
starting in effect options. Yeah the
just in another illustration I did the
same for IBM stock and yeah sure enough
it's the same straight line. I didn't
plot the implied wall, but it's probably
even uglier here.
Um, yeah, we're about at time. Uh, but I
would leave you uh with a little bit
food for thought here. Uh, so this is
called digital option. The payout payout
of digital option or all or nothing
option, right? It's basically either
pays you zero if you end up uh out of
the money or it pays you one if you end
up in the money. Right?
Uh
the uh this is how black shs would price
it that this is actually uh how coal
spread looks from uh uh from the data
which I just showed you uh pretty close
to this. So my challenge to you is find
a replicating portfolio
which which prices it digital because I
claim that you don't need to have a
dynamic of the stock or do any
complicated things here. You can
replicate this uh this payout
uh practically exactly actually
approximate the the payout uh and uh
that's how actually how people hedge
digital options.
Um yeah so think about it. Um for with
this let me stop stop stop stop stop
stop stop stop stop stop stop stop stop
stop stop stop stop stop stop here and
any questions happy to answer
looking forward a little bit so we have
two uh classes the two two invited
lectures
um
uh and one of them the the sec the the
one in in a week time will be by John
Hull. It will be by by uh by Zoom and he
will be uh talking about uh machine
learning. Uh and I think it will be an
interesting lecture well at least
interesting because for me John Hull is
an icon. He I mean not only he wrote the
most famous derivatives pricing book uh
he also uh created halw white formulas
and made a lot of contribution to
quantitative finance. So and I I we we
are working on on a couple of
collaboration projects. He's in
University of Toronto. He's a professor
of University of Toronto. So yeah a
little bit of advertisement.
All right. Thank you very much.