the MIT energy initiative presents
unpacking us climate and infrastructure
laws MIT energy initiative deputy
director Robert Stoner takes stock of
the bipartisan infrastructure act and
inflation reduction act and their
potential impacts on the energy
transition written by Tom
Melville this November the 2022 United
Nations climate change conference cop 27
will take place in charmal Chic Egypt
bringing together governments experts
journalists industry and Civil Society
to discuss climate action to enable
countries to collectively sharply limit
anthropogenic climate change as MIT
energy initiative deputy director for
Science and Technology Robert Stoner
prepares to attend the conference he
takes a moment to speak with us about
the climate and infrastructure laws
enacted in the last year in the United
States and about the impact these laws
can have in the global energy
transition question as we speak you're
getting ready to go to cop 27 can you
set the
scene
answer there's a lot of interest among
vulnerable countries about compensation
for the impacts climate change has had
on them or loss and damage a topic that
the United States refused to address
last year at cop 26 for fear of opening
up a Floodgate and leaving us taxpayers
exposed to unlimited liability for our
past and future emissions this is a
crucial issue of fairness for developed
countries and well of acknowledging our
common Humanity but in a sense it's also
a sideshow and addressing it won't
prevent a climate catastrophe we really
need to focus on mitigation with the
passage of the bipartisan infrastructure
investment and jobs act in the inflation
reduction act Ira the United States is
now in a strong position to twist some
arms these laws are largely about
subsidizing the deployment of low carbon
Technologies pretty much all of them
we're going to do a lot in the United
States in the next decade that will lead
to dramatic cost reductions for these
Technologies and enable other countries
with fewer resources to adopt them as
well it's exactly the leadership role
the United States has needed to assume
now we have the opportunity to Rally the
rest of the world and get other
countries to commit to more ambitious
decarbonization goals and to build
practical programs that take advantage
of the investable pathways we going to
for public and private actors but that
alone won't get us there money is still
a huge problem especially in emerging
markets and developing countries and I
don't think the institutions we rely on
to help these countries fund
infrastructure energy and everything
else are adequately funded nor do these
institutions have the right structures
incentives and Staffing to fund low
carbon development in these countries
rapidly enough or on the necessary scale
I'm talking about the World Bank for
instance but the other multilateral or
organizations have similar issues I
frankly don't think the multilaterals
can be reformed or sufficiently
redirected on a short enough time frame
we definitely need new leadership for
these
organizations and I think we probably
need to quickly establish new
multilaterals with new people more money
and a Clarity of purpose that is likely
beyond what can be achieved
incrementally I don't know if this is
going to be an active public discussion
at cop 27 but I hope it takes place
somewhere soon give the strong role our
government plays in financing and
selecting the leadership of these
institutions perhaps this is another
opportunity for the United States to
demonstrate courage and
Leadership question what investable
pathways are you talking about answer
well the pathways we're implicitly
trying to pursue with the infrastructure
act and Ira are pretty clear and I'll
come back to them but first let me
describe the landscape there are three
main sources of demand for energy in the
economy industry meaning chemical
production fuel for electricity
generation cement production materials
and Manufacturing and so on
Transportation cars trucks ships planes
and trains and buildings for heating and
cooling mostly that's about it and these
three sectors account for 75% of our
total greenhouse gas emissions so the
pathways are all about how to
decarbonize these three end use sectors
there are a lot of Technologies some
some that exist some that don't that
will have to be brought to bear and so
it can be a little overwhelming to try
to imagine how it will all transpire but
it's pretty clear at a high level what
our options are first generate a lot of
low carbon electricity and Electrify as
many industrial processes vehicles and
building heating systems as we can
second develop and deploy at massive
scale technologies that can capture
carbon dioxide from Smoke Stacks or the
air and put it somewhere that it can
never escape from in other words carbon
capture and sequestration or
CCS third for end uses like Aviation
that really need to use fuels because
they're extraordinary energy density
develop lowcar carbon alternatives to
fossil fuels and fourth is Energy
Efficiency across the board but I don't
really count that as a separate pathway
per se so by investable Pathways I mean
specific ways to pursue these options
that will attract investors what the
infrastructure Act and the IRA do is
deploy carrots in the form of subsidies
in a variety of ways to close the gap
between what it costs to deploy
Technologies like CCS that aren't yet at
a commercial stage because they're
immature and what energy markets will
tolerate a similar situation occurs for
lowcar carbon production of hydrogen one
of the leading low carbon fuel
candidates we can make it by splitting
water with electricity electrolysis but
that costs too much with present day
technology or we can make it more
cheaply by separating it from methane
which is what natural gas mainly is but
that creates carbon dioxide that has to
be transported and sequestered somewhere
and then we have to store the hydrogen
until we're ready to use it and
transport it by pipeline to the
industrial facilities where it will be
used that requires infrastructure that
doesn't exist pipelines compression
stations big tanks come to think of it
the demand for all that hydrogen doesn't
exist either at least not if industry
has to pay what it actually costs so one
very important thing these new acts do
is subsidize production of hydrogen in
various ways and subsidize the creation
of a CCS industry the other thing they
do is subsidize the deployment at
enormous scale of lowcar carbon Energy
Technologies some of them are already
pretty cheap like solar and wind but
they need to be supported by a lot of
storage on the grid which we don't yet
have and by other sorts of grid
infrastructure that again don't exist so
they now get subsidized too along with
other carbon- free and low carbon
generation Technologies basically all of
them the idea is that by stimulating ATS
scale deployment of all these
established and emerging Technologies
and funding demonstrations of Novel
infrastructure effectively lowering the
cost of supply of low carbon energy in
the form of electricity and fuels we
will draw out the private sector to
build out much more of the connective
infrastructure and invest in New indust
processes new home heating systems and
low carbon
Transportation this subsidized buildout
will take place over a decade and then
phase out as cost fall hopefully leaving
the foundation for a thriving low carbon
energy economy in its wake along with
crucial Technologies and knowledge that
will benefit the whole
world question is all of the federal
investment in energy infrastructure in
the United States relevant to the energy
crisis in Europe right now answer not in
a direct way Europe is a near-term
catastrophe with a long-term challenge
that is in many ways more difficult than
ours because Europe doesn't have the
level of primary energy resources like
oil and gas that we have in abundance
energy costs more in Europe especially
absent Russian pipelines in a way the
narrowing of Europe's options creates an
impetus to invest in low carbon
Technologies sooner than otherwise the
result either way will be expensive
energy and quite a lot of economic
suffering for years the near-term
challenge all is to protect people from
high energy prices the big spikes in
electricity prices we see now are driven
by the natural gas market disruption
which will eventually dissipate as new
sources of electricity come online
Sweden for example just announced a plan
to develop new nuclear and we're seeing
other countries like Germany soften
their stance on nuclear and gas markets
will sort themselves out meanwhile
governments are trying to Shield their
people with electricity price gaps and
other subsidies but that's enormously
burdensome
the EU recently announced gas price caps
for imported gas to try to eliminate
price gouging by importers and reduce
the subsidy burden that may help to
lower Downstream prices or it may make
matters worse by reducing the flow of
gas into the EU and fueling scarcity
pricing and ultimately adding to the
subsidy burden a lot of people are quite
reasonably suggesting that if
electricity prices are subject to crazy
behavior in gas markets then why not
disconnect from the grid and
self-generate when that also help reduce
demand for gas overall and also reduce
carbon dioxide emissions it would but
it's expensive to put solar panels on
your roof and batteries in your basement
so for those Rich enough to do this it
would lead to higher average electricity
costs that would live on far into the
future even when grid prices eventually
come down so an interesting idea is
taking hold with considerable
encouragement from National governments
the idea of energy communities basically
towns or cities that encourage local
firms and homeowners to install solar
and batteries and make some sort of
business arrangement with the local
utility to allow the community to
disconnect from the National Grid at
times of high prices and self-supply in
other words use the utility's wires to
sell locally generated power locally
it's interesting to think about it takes
less battery storage to handle the
intermittency of solar when you have a
lot of generators and consumers so
forming a community helps lower costs
and with a good deal from the utility
for using their wires it might not be
that much more expensive and of course
when the National Grid is working well
and prices are normal the community
would reconnect and buy Power cheaply
while selling back its self-generated
power to the grid there are also
potentially important social benefits
that might acre in these energy
communities too it's not a dumb idea and
we'll see some interesting
experimentation in this area in the
coming years as usual the Germans are
enthusiastic