so we're going to make a good part of
today about talking about some of the
other people who have thought about
music representation or or talking about
other people's thoughts and whether we
agree with them or not specifically to
Giants of the field uh elanar suffrage
field um her article on um music
representation and uh Nicholas cook on
what's comparative musicology and what's
computational musicology and what they
might have to do with each other if
anything so let's um let's start by by
talking uh a little bit about the Elanor
self field article um she's a before
getting into computers and continuing
afterwards she's a specialist in broke
music which is sort of uh Western
European musical era from a lot of
people say 1600 to 17750 roughly 1580 to
1770 but with the previous areas
overlapping and previous and next ones
for a bit
um and so she talks about uh about some
some things in her article um anyone
remember anything about um the article
that has this diagram what's what's she
kind of showing
here we
call I know you do you're just
shy a note has a lot of parameters note
has a lot of parameters yes no has a lot
of parameters what kind of relationship
are we talking about has a
means what word pops into your head when
you think of Haas
so into your ontologies that forgotten
what are the two
choices yeah go ahead morom tonomy and
morony Hann did you have your hand for
which one of those two that would be is
it morom moromi yes yes yes because the
taxonomy is the one that we use for uh
Kingdom film you know what what kind of
thing is something yeah so note has a
lot of um different
different parameters and it's made up of
a lot of different parameters I think
it's it's something that maybe just
sounds so obvious but but this was you
know a really revolutionary way of
thinking about some of these things and
this diagram has become sort of the one
of the legendary diagrams in the field
every field has these legendary diagrams
and I know um that Dr suff field would
have drawn that flat a little bit better
uh if she had known that this was going
to become so famous but yeah this is
this is the one that we oh yeah we're
talking about components of a note and
we're going to argue about certain
things um and we can see that some of
these things are
um what kind of a thing is duration she
talks about is it a graphical thing can
you see
duration it's interesting that's that's
good that's good that you're you're
puzzling over it
there's well let's um let's try to
figure out the context that I'm talking
about when we talk about duration she
talks about three contexts that musical
representation happens in if you
remember them three
contexts it's a big part
of one of the early parts of our
article give the first letter
of each of
them that trigger anything what what is
some ways music's represented
yeah the graphical yep the graphical how
it looks
right great let's let's fill out the
other two before getting back to the
question I was talking about yeah go
ahead what's that the sound
sound good and then the other one she
uses kind of um
two words at different
points or the graph the sound
graphical uh is that semantical semantic
yep and semantic or semantical I like
semantical um and um what would the L be
it's a in this case for her logical
logical yeah so the semantic yeah you're
right it should be sort of alls
logical great so what's duration in this
which context are we talking about
we in this
diagram what's that I just can't hear
Graal graphic and or logical graphical
or logical great so definitely not sound
right are we all in agreement with Jake
that uh that that that this doesn't
sound very good unless you have a good
internal imagination right this is we're
not hearing anything good
so what's and who you got to take a
stand on this if even if you're wrong
who who wants to say that that this
duration here is more in the graphical
domain I mean we're seeing a picture
here good and who thinks is more in The
Logical domain great great super so we
have have a little bit of disagreement
more people on the graphical side what
what would be the argument that um that
it's a graphical duration somebody who
who went for the graphical yeah Vanessa
it's a visual representation there are a
bunch of different visual
representations that represent how long
a note is supposed to be so you can like
look at it and'll make sense what it's
supposed to be great super so we can
look at it and we can see what's going
to be we a graphic and we see the
graphic and go there who wants to make
an argument for The Logical on
this three people yeah um I guess like
even just seeing this it's all relative
to other parts of the like you need the
conly the sycal context of like beats
per minute or like yeah um and the times
are sharing right so so we're we're
going quite a bit further and saying
yeah the duration only makes sense in a
larger context of things super um let me
come up with two ways that you might uh
describe something we'll stop
there describe what I did what I have on
the board in the most purely graphical
description possible
take yeah
John three notes ofal with have three
notes of equal duration
great dur um dur yeah not
dur anyone want to see if we can go even
more graphically yes go ahead Jason uh
two vertical lines with three three
filled in circles with sticks attached
two vertical lines with three filled in
circles with sticks attached I like
everything about that except the word
that came before attached why don't I
like
sticks I like stems even
less lines yeah what what don't I like
about stems if we're going for
sticks yeah Adam they already give a
contextualization for an abstract symbol
yes we're already abstracting something
Jason that was
fantastic and and and Adam great to the
yeah so so we can go we're already
making assumptions that well you know a
line could represent a stick so um it
was uh John's thing that two notes of
equal durations is a great description
but which one um but three filled in
circles and by the way we're already um
we're already doing some sort of uh
we're already interpreting a little bit
that u a bunch of continuous lines that
um are kind of oline and stick out we
think oh that kind of represents a
circle but yeah but we'll go with that
three build in circles
between two
lines with more lines okay something
like like that
which one of these does suffrage field
consider to be on the graphical domain
and which one to be on The
Logical too
obvious shout it out which graphical or
logical
logical Des describe the thing that it's
pointing to you in the most graphical
form you
can so you want to take a shot at this
Matthew do you want to take a shot what
it's pointing to in the most
graphical it's a flag hanging off the
end of the stem it's a flag hanging off
the end of the stem who who wants to uh
go even even further back this corner
take a shot
I mean a strip that like decreases in
width in a curled a strip that decreases
in width in a curled uh manner yeah so I
think we can go further even than a flag
but we can but we sort of have curled
strip thing your interpretation says oh
that's a flag and then there sort of a
Next Level Up says Flags represent
duration so we can go in all these world
and what um why I love this article even
though it's you know now over 20 years
old is that nobody puts out so clearly
to me to um to think about what all
these things actually mean so we have
three domains that she's talking about
the sound a context she says ter she
uses uh I call them domains in my head
we'll use her term uh context sound
graphical or she most uses the word
logical um but um
semantic or semantical could also be uh
is also a you term that's use and that
one is coming up a lot
more together these last two parts and
and we're pretty good at distinguishing
between sound and either of these other
ones right yeah
um together these last two will
sometimes put them together as
symbolic that these are things that deal
with symbols on a page or conceptually
on a page or conceptually written
written or conceptually written um great
now uh she says in her article which one
of these holds the most
interest BL
remember this it's okay it's a longish
article but yeah it's a graphical
graphical unfortunately not but thanks
thanks for taking a bold stand stuff's
good we've eliminated graphical which
one want I take a
guess um I'm I'm gonna say sound you
would say sound and you would
be with most human beings because most
people buy uh many more CDs than they
buy abstract musical scores encoded in
computers but she's really on The
Logical so it's good um so sound yeah
sound is is what most of us work with
the music but for for her purposes for
the purposes of representation she
especially she was really interested in
logical things thanks uh right everybody
who didn't speak was thinking of logical
and and think no thank you um bold
people for for taking a stab at this
um great
so one of the things that she talks
about um later on do you remember that
she talks about musical scores and
anyone remember any sorts of musical
scores she brings
in some funny ones and some pretty
normal
ones we had a lot more fun on our on our
problem set this weekend than read time
I can tell went in but not in the depth
that second Trio from the Mozart Claret
quintet was the first one she also thank
you thank you Jake I was uh you know
you're allowed to have computers open so
you can also uh look at these if you
want yeah uh she also talks oops sorry
thank you somebody I'm going to going to
assign tasks for each person to fix VAR
stupid CU prisms so I'm going to want
one person to be the um we can't see
anything task and one person for the um
the the thing is rolled up okay yeah so
this particular one she also does some
other things including Gregorian chant
um a lot of things representing sort of
a music historical perspective um and
each one chosen uh many of the later
ones chosen because they have a
particular interest and difficulty in
representing part of your problem set
too is to make a contribution to that
set of
Repertory that um when you say and you
will hear software people and coming up
with things who haven't been taking you
the full liberal arts education and
music you know oh I have a system that
can represent all music I want to be
like great here's DDR show me how your
system represents here's here's um South
Indian music how does it so these are
are all challenges and there'll never be
a system that can represent all of them
but
um hence why most of us will avoid the
all music
things this particular score has had a
um about as much impact from the article
as this diagram had um it's sort of
become the Hol world a little bit more
complex than Holo world of Music in
representation encoding I want know
computers explain what a h world
is yeah the basic file that everyone
writes at the beginning as a sample yep
and what do you do with hello world you
you print it out print it out somewhere
great and um some languages you put that
back slash n otherwise nothing prints
yep great so it's how do you get how do
you do something very simple in a
programming language this piece piece or
at least the clarinet part the top part
of the five has become that um that
piece so um at least one of it so I
think we should at least hear it once so
we can get it in our head oh and uh just
just so you just so I can kind of hear
kind of go when um you might do it
involuntarily when something happens
that's not in the score from this
recording
[Music]
I didn't
hear
repeat now Adam on it anybody
else yeah what
was uh they kind of glazed over the
triplet at glazed over the triplet yeah
great which is uh which is kind of a
problematic per uh performance for this
particular one because one of the
reasons why this is almost certainly
chosen was can your system represent
triplets um the performers playing on a
clarinet that uh we hypothesized mozar
originally wrote this for that could go
two notes lower than this and so played
those low notes instead of um instead of
starting high and going down good so
this is um the hello world piece that
you'll be getting uh any other thoughts
about uh Elena suffrage Fields work will
come back to her more as the semester
comes
on well um just a just a reminder uh
there's one um exam in this class and
it's um sort of the midterm but it's
about two-thirds of the way through the
semester and it's the one uh the only
one that's not based at all on
programming but based on readings and um
and the big thoughts I put it that way
so that you have these readings and big
thoughts going through your head as you
start working on your final projects um
I think this is I think you can pretty
much count um that some thoughts this
and some of these questions might be on
there so give it another read when you
get a chance and let's move on to
um Nicholas Cook's uh comparative versus
computational musicology article and
here I've given you the questions I'm
going to be asking uh written down on
the outline today um and I and so take a
second to um you jot down some some of
the notes so you probably already have
them because I gave you these also on
the um on the canvas s right
thinking about um take a second while I
play uh a little example from the first
piece that
um that he discusses
[Music]
would know 2001 Space Odyssey this one
of the
pieces okay so
um we'll get back to this and you what
he uses this piece for in a little bit
but first thing is kind of the
fundamental question one of the a couple
of the fundamental questions about CL
what um what does he mean there's no
such thing as a good or bad
representation of Music per se yeah
Vanessa like just of the point is that
like it's all that's particularly good
or bad about it it's like depending on
what you're attempting to use it for
there are different situations where
like certain characteristics might be
more beneficial than others and in that
scenario you can make a good or a bad
choice but it doesn't mean it's all
around great so so fantastic I think
that really captures a lot of what cook
saying it all depends on what you're
trying to get out of it what are you
trying to do so U some of your own
representations um are going to be
really bad representations even if you
get an A+ for certain things
but um o did I like have the whole
recording going um but they could be
great representations for some other
things um somebody want to give an
example either from the reading or um or
from your own thoughts but maybe
preferably from the reading if you have
it of of what one representation that
would be uh bad in a specific case and a
rep and the same representation how it
could be really good for something
else yeah go ahead
um I guess the is more detailed but like
at the beginning they had a lot of um
charts that represented pieces and they
mentioned that this would be really good
for like comparing the formats of
different pieces to each other or like
finding similarities between repertoire
but for example like a performer
wouldn't be able to use this
representation fantastic so cook begins
uh his article by showing certain charts
that might uh help compare similarities
across pieces but not not be very good
for a performer so this is
um from the same piece from Luke's
etterna one of the parts showing at any
given moment what the full range of the
piece is um what's the um what can you
say about what happens to the range of
the piece around measure 60
65 I want to take it
yeah go
ahead like the average pitch just
increases overall the average pitch what
frequency frequency the average
frequency increases quite a bit there
right anything else you could say about
it it's going more specific even that
that the average pitch because that
that's also a very good representation
average pitch yeah Adam there's a
descending sequence that goes throughout
the can there's there's a yeah there's a
descending uh line sequence something
like that that's continuing on and then
it continues but what else
happens yeah Jason a bunch of voices
appear in the top great yeah a bunch of
voices comeing in the
top and the top most ones maybe also
have a descending sequence that's it's
great now I mean you can get all of this
from a musical score but we'll go back
here where's the first um first point
that there's two different
notes this measure here
here you could do it you can do it but
that is what this is not a very good
representation of on the other hand it's
a very good representation for seeing Oh
my gosh I'm going to have to count
really hard if I want to get in exactly
at that right moment right but um second
representation showing the number of
different notes pitch count graph how
many different notes are being sung is a
very good representation if you just
wanted to um now now you're doing your
uh next horror film or something and
you're a big Stanley Kubrick fan so
you're going to rip off uh what he did
in 2001 uh but you just need a 5-second
clip for your scariest part where are
you going to choose give me a measure
number that give me a shot 52 53 52 53
yeah right we have a whole bunch of
different pitches all sounding at the
same time that could be really tense I
think this is talking about um pitches
without octave pitch classes you all
know that term now um so yeah a lot of
things happening very easy to do in this
graph but very hard to do in
others so
um goes through some of the different
things now
oh this gra sorry I just forgot on this
this one per can you perform from this
one from this
graph see a lot of I see some up I I see
I see some yeah it's not the
best thing for being able to perform
that piece probably not the best thing
but you can almost perform from it from
the range graph thing so there's some
things that are in between um better the
pitch count graph can you perform from
this no though you could I mean thinking
about in the future you could take a
piece's pitch count graph and uh use a
computer to write a different piece that
had the same pitch count profile um and
it might be an interesting type of thing
um but yeah you couldn't perform this
the same piece for some ontological
definition of the same piece right good
we can skip the entrance graph uh second
piece talks about um oh this is the B
talk string quartet number four oops
we'll get a tiny if it's working a few
seconds that if it doesn't give me a
YouTube
ad no okay
um B talk similar uh similar era a
little bit earlier uh composer also
Hungarian um so this is
showing what is this showing I remember
somebody who I haven't heard from
yet Jonathan do you remember
this soundes sound waves what particular
parts of it
anybody
that not sure you're not sure okay good
good not not sure saves the whole class
great super harmonics harmonics no not
exactly this yeah def amplitude how loud
each part is what does it mean when the
V is really really really really
quiet it's not playing yep so you can
quickly see which parts are playing
where and then somehow make a composite
that is more like the um the uh what do
you call it the amplitude wave type the
um the sound wave um of of the piece as
a whole so yeah um I don't this is this
is one of the ones in that article that
one of the most so I'm always like eh
doesn't get so much out of it but um but
because this is the type of thing
computational people do wrote my own
program to generate the same thing um
this is a piece by hien's uh uh by uh
yoseph Heiden uh around I guess 1790 uh
called the surprise symy uh anyone know
where the surprise happens from looking
at this yeah so sometimes these things
can be uh very great I didn't even
realize though that the Dynamics were
kind of thinning out leading up to it I
always knew that there was one gigantic
cord right about here um go on and you
can see the various other places that
these things happen so so these can be
good representations for some
things so what's this hum drum that he's
talking about anybody
remember this part yeah
a to manipulate
dat great so it's a I think I heard it's
a framework that's used to manipulate
musical data uh in the Unix uh terminal
great um it's written by um it was
originally uh written by um music cogn
cognition perception and Theory
specialist uh David hiron and um who
we're going to read a lot about what he
used hum drum to kind of demonstrate new
about music but right now we're mostly
you know we're looking at oh what he did
um humdrum is uh in many ways the pred
the predecessor to music 21 and a
lecture that David hon the inventor gave
when I was uh I think I was a first year
grad student to like change my life I'm
like oh my gosh I want to do this but uh
your system the system was already 10 15
years old by then 20 years old maybe and
um like we have these things called
objects now so but um so it's a non-ob
oriented it's shell shell scripting
things which is pretty cool if anybody
anyone ever pipe a script from one thing
to the next you yeah youve input send it
to a program uh input text usually or or
bytes and then it sends something out
and you can send it to the next program
so you could have one program that just
goes through and strips all the ties
from notes and then you have another
program that you know labels the pitch
classes of everything um very very cool
very um new things and so hum drum had
its own format which was called um
actually I'm going to jump through some
some of these questions don't don't seem
as relevant for class discussion called
Kern which was basically a musical score
turned sideways so first part going
vertically here second part vertically
here third part and so on
um and um and so this was a way that
meant that looking horizontally you
could see anything that was happening at
the same time and very useful back
before graphical editors where you can
uh tab among
them oops contrasting um uh in the
article was this particular um
format ESS code and this is um one of
ones how do we read
this some people Adam great but I want
to want to get some more reluctant
participants and we'll come
back anyone want to take a guess what
anything means um yeah John like some
sort of figured base some sort of
figured base yeah does totally look like
that not exactly what what it actually
is but great great first first guess
what what numbers do you see that um
that that make you think it's like
figured base so scale degrees scale
degrees Yeah so something maybe to do
with scale degrees do we see eights and
nines are zeros no no so so that can be
a good good thing what so great great
guess that moved us into toward the
right direction um these are scale
degrees what's all this other stuff
might
be yeah Hannah is like the sharps and
the dashes represent like The Accidental
so Sharps probably a good one do um with
this part so this piece would have a lot
of accidentals if the underscore did and
might like the shorter Dash oh the
shorter Dash can you tell me where one
is uh I guess like in the first line the
one before the seven yeah I should be
like can somebody point out one that I
can reach yeah this one or this one good
good yeah so um minus signs you've I
think we've already seen that as a way
of representing um maybe Flats flats and
Shar shs I mean when we say there is no
such thing as a good representation or
bad representation per se I will say it
is a bad representation If this means
flat and that means sharp but if we
reverse them so I'll assume that good uh
What are some of the other symbols we
see yeah Adam then symbols in the melody
or any what's some other things you see
up here top is the composer top is the
composer maybe
boam it's not actually but but good
guess good guess that's great
um yeah Vincent sorry sorry V and then I
I don't think he's going to fire
everything yep the underscores represent
duration and then like the 16y
represents like the lowest okay okay
good good good so we'll start we'll
start with one thing the underscores
might represent duration so what does
that what's that mean think think about
that for a second we'll come back that's
totally what I say okay well then fill
it out a little bit um well I was going
to guess that like one underscore would
be some standard like maybe a coordinate
or something like that and then two is
more yep and then two is more how it's
it's a fixed width font but it's
stilling hard to see do we what are the
lengths that we see the
most
one two do we see three a
lot not too many no end of the line end
of the line line yeah so there's some
places where you see through good good
so that might have something to do with
things
um any places where there's two that are
uh numbers that
are without uh separating
underscore John where do you see one
bottom left bottom left good thanks for
finding one I can point to you yep so
and what's right proceeding it
period period what period might
represent rest might represent a rest
what else might it represent
yeah good a DOT a DOT so it could be one
of those
things quite often after let's see so
one of the ways we can figure out is if
we get a particular length and then does
everything else work what do you think
the space
means measure separation measure
separation some measures seem to be a
lot shorter than others but yeah it
could be a measure separation could also
be as a lot of these formats are just to
make it easier for us to read that
there's a certain readability that's
built into some good good um and uh
Vincent you were starting to say
something about the 16 up there having
something to do with the uh so like how
the UND duration how some have like one
or two um but those would all be
multiples of like whatever is best right
there would be the 16 so like the first
one would be like two 16 notes or an E
note so this would be two 16th notes or
uhuh oh so like got that five where
there's one one be one 16th note and
then the six great so let's see what do
you think 44 means everybody 44 right
good M do you want to say something on
that um yeah yeah um basically along
these lines and yeah I think the thing
that we're probably trying to get to now
is that like it doesn't quite seem to
add up if it's 44 on each one with one
um is uh 16th so like there are a lot of
measures with three and I believe it's
two underscores like the the the I'm
sorry to make you point super high maybe
there's an example lower but the the Top
Line the the first one it seems like the
full um measure yeah yep so it's two
underscores yeah two two which would
imply that they're all quarter nodes if
it's in four4 which means that like and
then the one right below it has the
exact same but like in the last
um with the duration of the coord note
splits it up so those seem like eth
notes rather than 16th notes great super
awesome great let's let's do a tiny bit
of the metadata um you can take a guess
what language is the
metadata anybody
know see just yeah Jason I this is the
code from the reading Yep this isak code
and what what's the uh isach or Essen is
the the two ways of putting it yep and
um anyone know where Essen is yeah
Germany Germany do we see some German
things good so this is a a very famous
piece and I want to say um as you're
choosing things to represent and
choosing things in it um and Nicholas
cook is amazing I think Nicholas CH
chose the absolute worst piece he
possibly could have chosen to be the
demonstration this and I've thought of
switching out
um cut might be it's not sent for cuer
it's the something about the title
Germany Germany anyone El
overall it's the Nazi national
anthem so I I wish that he had chosen
better but fortunately if we crop off
the top um it is also the pre-nazi
National Anthem with different words and
the current national anthem and a piece
composed by yoseph Heiden so the
Surprise Symphony composer and I wanted
to um put it up it's rather small might
need to zoom in or or get up but see or
you can look at the article see if you
can re Now read the notation from
hearing this assuming YouTube's going to
work this time and this is the modern
word
word second
line 31 1
5 1 2 3 2 4 3
2 oh was that a
[Music]
flat might be an otive
sign you can hear the sharps are
definitely Sharps those who can hear
secondary
[Music]
dominance anyhow we don't have to hear
the
[Music]
rest yeah yeah yeah you win the World
Cup more than us we know
um okay um
so two more two more questions one I
didn't put on here before we move on to
another topic
um what does comparative
musicology mean and how's it have
anything to do with computational
musicology and that's the main title of
the piece the
article anyone let's take stand take the
first one what is
comparative
musicology we can probably figure it out
from the words so yep I believe it was
like just that concept of comparing
music to each other regardless of where
necessarily far yeah uh so it's it's
comparing pieces of music to each other
but not necessarily you know close
things not oh let's look at the first
movement and compare it to the second
movement but let's look at oh um let's
look at a nationalist song from Germany
and let's look at a nationalist song
from Kenya and see if they have any
connection let's look at um oh shoot I
forgot to put it into into the slides um
the person uh I BL on her name not
checking my email I I have the picture
to put into the slide and I didn't get
uh her name is uh trout uh sorry uh yeah
trob um big New York Times obituary and
I have a notification that won't Sandra
CH the Pioneer one of the Pioneers in
the psychology of comp comparative music
uh mus musicology died very recently and
she was the one who famously did
experiments to show that people could
identify here or two songs from the same
culture which one's the lullabi and
which one is not all throughout the
world and this experiment's been um
replicated with other uh musics uh quite
a lot uh recently um over in the lab at
at Harvard but she was a big one so this
notion of looking across
cultures uh anybody take um in class I
think a couple people have uh intro to
um to Global Music or World music yeah
so great so um did did the word
comparative musicology come up much in
your class not really not really good
the paper it says that that was what
used to be that's what used to be
ethnomusicology the study of music and
cultures and it yeah did you you also
didn't see in your classes yeah so
comparativist approaches is of looking
at things um from here and you know
there and saying what's similar to them
got a um so gave way to Modern
ethnomusicology which is the study of
Music in its culture and so the notion
that um that you go to a culture you get
to know the culture very well um and
then learn from how the culture itself
is describing its music in order to um
say something uh valuable and and that
the more you get to know one culture and
the less you spend time comparing you
know this culture in Paraguay to that
culture in lap land uh the the more that
you just F focus on one place the more
depth of knowledge you'll get and in
part because uh the early negative
history of comparative um musicology uh
deserves its very bad rap and we have to
still be really careful for it because
we're always going to be comparing you
know what what are the countries I keep
you know Paraguay and Lapland and uh and
you know Kenya and uh okanawa and Japan
and all these things together and then
we're also going to compare with bein's
Ninth Symphony in order to demonstrate
uh what if you're a German around 1914
or a German around 1933 what is the
conclusion you will always come after
comparing all these
things someone take a guess give a
hypothal mind what's that is the best
the who's is the best your whoever like
you identify with yeah and the people
doing this were mostly white
Europeans so uh the comparativist
project while it gathered a lot of data
um we would now say it was embodied in
the uh Narrative of of white supremacy
oh now this class can't be shown in in
Florida um uh but uh you know it and and
that really really happened and the
issue is um and so ethnomusicology this
Focus tried to to say let's stop making
this comparative um type of project so
that um so that we can actually
understand
why individual pieces of music are great
and interesting and valuable and
meaningful and touching to people all
over the world and a lot of people even
in Germany don't like Bean's Ninth
Symphony um so working as particular
things and then the irony that comes out
is that the comparativists were still
you know looking at a small number of
pieces to compare I mean quite often
look at comparative uh musicology uh
also called systematic at that time um
systematic musicological Works we're
talking about one piece from here one
piece from here because that's all that
people had um and so this go out a style
right
when this thing comes
along and suddenly I mean not not this
particular uh lightweight thing but the
gigantic you know hunking ones that you
can still see in the computer museums
and stuff uh that were able to compare
large numbers of information and at
least encode their
biases if not you know at least you
could see what had been encoded into it
so this is where the comparativist
project comes together with the uh
computational
project but as you can see I mean the
danger is that by using a computer we
can still be replicating the kinds of
mistakes that were made quite a bit
ago so we're going to have to be hyper
Vigilant the more
more hyper Vigilant against
that we're going to be hypervigilant and
it probably means that some sometimes uh
if for that we shouldn't be focusing on
um on musical um things for our major
projects that we don't know anything
about so I'm very glad um that the
encoding of of South Indian music that
we have somebody in the group who is a
of expert can can I call you an expert
on on a a very very strong um
understanding this and that we want to
get to know our repertories before we
work too much on them and I think it
kind of comes back to um to this anyhow
even for repertories that um might be
more conventionally studied so we're
going to look at some pieces in a bit um
and uh we're going to start by jumping
into a particular Buck Coral um and I
want everybody to at some point to do
all the things of trying to get into the
style of that piece by hand because we
don't want we want to be able to at
least be a little expert ourselves on a
particular Repertory before we turn it
over to the computer helps to avoid the
gigo or goo problem anyone know what
that is
Gio know Garing garbage out garbage in
equals garbage out so we want to make
sure that we're not um putting garbage
in
great I think I'm going to skip number
three for now we'll do it um the sign
score to sound because that one's a
little bit me talking more and let's
jump to a little bit of programming
because we haven't done that in class um
in a while so go ahead and take take a
second or two and um grab a Jupiter
notebook while I try to get my screen
set up to have two things at once how
about that um great you've already we're
going to do some unlocking as know that
this means that um from here on out
unless you're told otherwise you may use
um these materials in any problem Set uh
going forward so you've already unlocked
the pitch module lowercase p meaning
it's a module and we'll also unlock the
Note and the duration modules right
now and we don't even we're not even
really going to need the pitch or the
duration module so let's start with
everything on the Note let's um okay I'm
going to need to get this later
um
let's start with one of my favorite
notes I don't know why C five became one
of my favorite notes I think it just
demonstrates something and it's right in
the middle screen good and
um always remember that you can get a
list of um of what any object can do and
by the way you all got its upper and um
the class rule is I go too fast you say
slow down okay everybody practice that
say It Out Slow Down slow down good you
don't want me to slow down right now but
at some point you will and just shout it
out great so you can always get this uh
python unhelpfully uh gives it an
alphabetical order which means the
things you don't want to know about the
private things come first but um you can
see some of the things are happening
here and very nicely uh you'll see that
duration is one of the attributes or
Properties or something of of a note
and Pitch is also a property of a note
so that's pretty good
yep so we can get that pitch from the
note object and it's
looks pretty similar to um the other
note
things so can we get the Octave of a
note yes we can can we get the name of
the note yes we can what are some other
things we did with pitch can we get the
accidental from a pitch yep can we get
the
accidental of note no we cannot so one
of the things you'll find in the music
21 and again music 21 is just one
framework you can use hum drum you can
use build your own um but one of the
things is it started with uh this that
there's some things about a pitch that
seemed like you're going to use so often
that we might as well put it on the Note
make it a um a shortcut and then a lot
of things just too complicated so you'll
if you want something deeper go grab it
from The
Accidental or to grab it from the pitch
object
um notes also have a
duration note. pitch and pitches do not
have a duration so this is sort of going
into the logical representation mode um
that some things have durations and some
things
don't let's see what we can um do with
this let's let's look at the duration
since we haven't looked at the duration
module
yet or the duration
class okay so we have a duration and we
can see some of the things um duration.
almond unfortunately I did not go with
that great idea uh what anyone remember
what I said I went with boring term
type so everything starts off as a
quarter note but we can make it
half
and remember early on in the semester we
talked about representations a duration
uh before it was a duration of one now
it's some sort of a duration of two two
whats could be a lot of things could be
2 seconds with a tempo of 60 could be
two beats two ticks
um music 21 has chosen to represent
everything in numbers of quarter
notes so duration is one um duration of
two is a half
note
let's have dots zero so let's add some
dots and now we added six dots to the
notes um and we get something
like like this um my favorite random MIT
thing that you all can figure out based
on that uh thing
what what is the limit of half note as
the dots approaches Infinity
sorry whole note good good yall can play
with the Easter egg and set the um dots
to Infinity later and see what happens
um okay
so we have some of these things let's
put the dots back down to I don't know
something
manageable and quarter
length each of these things affects each
other and they're almost all setable so
that can be helpful in your programming
like
3.5 and now we get that it's a double
dotted and um probably a mistake on my
original part but everything U most of
these objects are are mutable so if we
go back to the original and duration
it's still now has the quarter length so
you can change the duration on the side
similarly with pitch do
um pitch.
Step it's already C we'll make it a
d and now we've changed the step of the
pitch to D but not change it's
accidental and now this is still on here
give everyone a second or two to catch
up I'll make it a little small smaller
so that any parts that people have
missed you don't have to you don't have
to write down everything that I write
down uh only write things down as
they're helpful for you to finger memory
remember
it okay um that's all I'm going to talk
about with unlocking notes and durations
at this point um I'll don't think I've
put a per a prominent enough link but
you can Google it music 21 has a users
guide and so you've kind of gone through
chapters one through two um in this
class so far but let's let's unlock some
other
things uh
unlocking
scores so we're going to give you your
first larger representation things and
to do this we're going to um from music
import something called stream and
something called
Corpus oops no
trailing um I was putting that there
because you can also invert import sign
called converter I'm not going to talk
about it um but converter is a way of
loading things from your hard drive
Corpus uses um a batteries included set
of about 8,000 pieces that comes that
come with music 21 so there's about
8,000 pieces in there and and we'll grab
one of them and when I'm not um thinking
very much I apologize I go to this Bo so
we'll load from the Corpus we're going
to parse meaning make sense of the of
the um representation Bach bwv
66.6 bwv means the
Bess the box work um uh index and by Bo
in this case um I mean Johan Sebastian
Bach daddy Bach there's some other boxs
in there and this is um the work number
66 6 movement um it's the one that we're
going to use quite a bit because it's
the smallest uh shortest Corral he
wrote and um what I'm going to ask you
to
do over the next couple classes as part
of the avoiding garbage in garbage out
want you to learn to sing Your Part from
this
Coral can you can you do that can you go
to the piano and match pitch on one of
the parts if you're really not um you
feeling very confident you're singing
you can do the soprano part at whatever
um octave is most comfortable but it
would be nice to be able to sing this as
a group and we'll come back to this one
um next class so you now have sorry
should have slowed down I was like
talking about something else B we're
going to store this piece as a variable
and one of the things you're going to
find very helpful is do show um can you
raise your hand if you have gotten
everything installed so that you can see
uh scores when you call show on things
anybody anybody still having some
difficulty that on okay great super
we'll make sure that we can uh get that
up and um and and see if we can uh get
that straightened out there were some
some helpful hints put onto one of the
discussion points about um dealing with
M score 4 but want to get that yeah when
we get this um this a notebook chance
yeah I can make sure to do that just if
there's something that I create in the
middle of class and it's not a one
button thing and you don't see it by uh
9:00 a.m. the next day just drop me a
line but I'll try to do that and
sometimes I'll give you the cleaned up
one I should have a script on my other
monitor but I'm not uh getting it now
great so let's look at that boach thing
it is
something in the project is music 21
stream is a what is it Shout It
Out module and score is a class class
class good so this is an object of class
score in the Stream module in the music
21 package project whatever you call it
and this is the particular memory
location that you can hack on my
computer to uh to deal with the stream
we can change we'll just make this
change its ID to BU short something like
that and then we'll see something nicer
than just a memory location that's
sometimes helpful okay
so this we call at the beginning of the
uh semester we have how many things are
in bck this was a trick question on the
first day you all stuck around well a
lot of trick questions and
um there are six things in the bo what
what's what are two basic answers that
you thought might be the um a good
answer to how many things there are in
the Box ballpark
figures 100 100 yep why maybe about 100
what's notes notes good what's another
number that you might have thought could
be there four four why number of parts
of parts good so let's see what those
things are um well one of the things
streams um scores are a type of stream
everything in there's a type of stream
can be treated like um like lists so you
can index them get what zeroth object is
get the first
object ah there's our part second
and so
on so what's that last object everyone
remember python give negative one
indexing uh we have something that says
all of these soprano Alto tenor base are
all have these what do you call it this
pretty
little thing around them so that's how
we get six things we have metadata which
is data about data that is usually
having the title of it so and things
like that we'll get to met dat later but
I know you want to get so let's see
what's what's an index I can use to get
something that might have notes in it
zero probably not negative one which one
do we want to look
at give me a number to put in here two
two okay so two is in this case the Alto
part and you would think if you don't
get that metadata as zero that this
would be um this might be uh you know
that one indexed or something right one
is soprano 2 but no it's zero index but
the zero is metadata um there might be
multiple things at the beginning not
just one metadata there could be more
could be metadata lists so it's you
might not always get this so you could
do something like like this for B for
thing I always use thing in b um because
I don't know what it is if is instance
thing music21 Dost
stream.
part print
thing oops what did I do um I
didn't sorry streamed up part because I
imported that um I imported stream into
it so that can be one way to get this
I'm going to tell you all of the most
General ways of doing things now so that
it sort of forms a mental habit but um
but we want to um but just just to know
you will learn some shortcuts so you
won't need to have to code all this uh
later great so now we have all the parts
what do you um let's do this we we got
the bach two let's see four thing in
Bach two that's let just call that Alto
let's call that Alto right Alto equals
Bach two for thing in Alto I always like
good naming see I'm calling it thing
thing's the best naming when you don't
know what something is yet suppose you
could call it L for element or something
print thing and what and when we call
from the very fast thing for stay what
it's going to
be so it's a bunch of measures but also
an
instrument I think that that's been
fixed in the latest version and it looks
like everything else but yeah so we have
an instrument there so we can do this
again I'm going to copy I just copied
here I'm going to go here and paste um
and we'll again do that is instance
checking if is instance that means is a
member of this class thing um stream.
measure
print thing okay now we've gotten just
the measures and
and we can get um oh I don't know
measure 2 equals Alto three I think we
got that is that I guess right okay and
we can keep writing the same type of
thing for thing
in in
M2 we don't need that because we're
already in a measure and finally we get
to
notes finally we get to notes
so that's where I'm going to end um this
part now um that I've given you a very
tedious way to get two notes from a
score that you go through all the
parts um you go through everything
that's in the score find the things that
are parts and then you could do a next
iteration on here another uh for Loop
another if go through each of the parts
and figure out everything that's a
measure and what oh sorry everything
that's a measure and go through each of
the measures and do this a for Loop
within a for Loop within a for Loop um
but we're going to learn some better
ways to do this later but I want to
leave you at least two days with trying
to do everything the hard way before we
start to get to the easier ways um so
you can do this so that's that your only
assign assignments continue working with
um your um on your problem sets and to
learn to sing your little part of bwv
66.6