so it's going to take a couple of
minutes just a couple of seconds just
for us to bring everybody together into
the panel session so I really just
wanted to say thank you to all the
speakers so far for some fantastic
forward-looking very Broad and very
challenging presentations touching on
everything from jobs and skills and
economics to biotech and synthetic
biology and AI uh it's obviously clear
that Manu Advanced design and
Manufacturing are going to be you know
kind of key foundational capabilities
for the future of our economies and for
tackling some of our our hardest
problems including things like climate
change and for the development of new
Innovative products and services but
also for like National competitiveness
and Regional
competitiveness so now everybody's back
in I wanted to kind assert the
moderator's privilege to maybe ask the
first question while we uh um get other
people's questions I really encourage
Their audience to um add uh new
questions to Q&A but a certain am amount
of moderator privilege um you know one
of the things I'd like to encourage the
speakers we're not really aiming for
consensus but you know the things we we
don't agree on may be as interesting and
and important as the ones that we the
ones that we do um so you know given
that we have an audience that's kind of
drawn from multiple industries from
multiple regions from government from
industry um from non from nonprofits and
from Civil Society you what would be the
the you the one uh key action or Insight
that you would each kind of really you
suggest that people take away from our
you know the discussion this morning and
then we'll move into questions from the
audience so I don't know Ben do you want
to kick off on
that sure uh I've been really I think so
I hear the two clusters of
presentations um talking about Workforce
issues so how we develop new skills and
how we learn to perform in a more
digital manufacturing environment and
then also there are these presentations
about exciting new technological
possibilities new products that we can
produce new ways of producing them and
then part of me thinks about
organizational behavior and how um
organizations you know both employers
but also maybe regulatory organizations
or government organizations that provide
incentives can can um adapt to the these
new technologies and new skill
requirements and one of the pieces that
I find so interesting is that
organizations just like people aren't
always rational they make decisions in
the short term that are going to hurt
them in the long term and in some cas
they're predictably irrational so one of
the uh areas that I emphasized that I
want to bring back up is is risk is that
we've evolved in the United States and
to some extent in certain Western
European markets to be extremely risk
averse when it comes to manufacturing
only to produce the things we know how
to produce well where we have an
existing comparative advantage and not
to take chances to produce new things
where essenti these organizations might
fail at producing it competitively but
still might learn something along the
way way and I think the example from F's
presentation earlier was you know this
is for for employers to use or develop
new designs um right now or to implement
them in manufacturing it's highly costly
and risky but new technologies can help
drisk that experimentation and drisk
exploration um of new possibilities so I
think um the role for for government
nonprofits is in many ways to to drisk
experimentation and Innovation um and do
manufacturing but it's also for
technologists to help drisk that process
as well um so I I I'd like to emphasize
that thank you and that I think that's
that's very incisive Bruce do you have
any any thoughts on that I'm sorry could
you repeat the question oh yeah so
basically you know from the the range of
of conversations we've been having is
what would be the you know the one kind
of action that you'd recommend for
either leaders from industry or from
kind of you know government or nonprofit
they're engaged in the manufacturing
space you know
yeah so I I think that if you look at
what we're doing at at rebuild um
certainly implementing lean um so
simplify and standardize really look at
that hard before you do any automation
so that's the first thing U second thing
is just training your people I know you
ask me for one thing but um training
your people in datadriven decision
making um that is machine learning AI is
all about about learning from data and
if we don't collect data uh store it and
trust it none of this technology matters
on top of it so if we we don't do the
basics to make processes as simple as
possible um and then if we don't do the
basics of collecting and making
decisions with data just with dashboards
some basic analytics just some charts uh
to start with statistical process
control as an example um
it that's the foundation for all of this
and if we can't do those things for at
least AI we if we don't do those things
the rest of it it it won't it won't work
so and I think people jump right over
that they want to go to the latest model
or the coolest thing and they forget
those foundational elements of
training and uh
simplification no I think I think that's
fantastic because that really does point
to the kind of the the heavy lifting
that's required in sustaining sustaining
innovation within ex established
Industries and those sorts things so so
just move to Chris so Chris you're very
much
representing kind of an emerging new
manufacturing field a whole new set of
products a whole new set of processes
you know you like your perspective other
things that either reflected particular
of the The Bu manufacturing space but
more generally in terms of how we
approach moving into these these nent
spaces where there's as as Ben mentioned
high risk um you know new Workforce
challenges new technology challenges
regulatory challenges you know what's
the big moving question you know
principle question that you would you'd
recommend in that kind of
space yeah I think kind of like to me
how do we as the various stakeholders
around these questions whether you're in
BIO or traditional manufacturing is how
do we make manufacturing cool again
right people love to make things and
they want to be able to make them for a
variety of different
purposes how do we embed the complexity
of Technologies and all of the tools
we've talked about here into the
Manufacturing Systems such that people
are free to do the things that they want
to do with them and I think in some ways
this is actually a little counter in
maybe the lean ideas right lean lean
doesn't like Innovation it only
innovates through the practices of what
it's already done but it doesn't leave
room for truly transformative new ideas
and so as we kind of think about how do
we train workforces how do we bring new
technologies online we have to kind of
build a society where we embrace the
manufacturing is going to look different
given that we now have different
Technologies right I mean why do we
continue to make things the way that we
did 50 years ago this is true and bio
it's true and in mechanical systems when
we have all of these new things that are
advancing I appreciate it they're not
fully advantaged yet to be able to roll
out but that's where the kind of messy
part comes in and I think where the
opportunity lies how do we train
students to be excited to work in these
spaces how do we show them that it's
going to be possible and how do we sort
of as companies bring the parts together
to show how it's going to be possible
and really Dr risk as Ben was saying
some of these newer
ideas no I think that's fantastic I
think that that kind of uh Echoes off
this sense of this side of this lump
labor fallacy there's only a certain
amount of work to be done it's almost as
if there's like there's not only a
certain number of things to make there's
always new things that we would you know
we can imagine and we can make and so
that that expanding Frontier I think
that that brings us really to to fire
it's like you how how do you think about
this kind of not just the optimization
of things we do at the moment but you
know bring these sorts of approaches to
the new things that we can create and
the new ways that we can use them and
the new ways that we can organize around
kind of fabrication and use and those
sorts things using techniques like
gen yeah so I think um overall I've been
very excited about the new possibilities
that have opened up and a key thing that
has changed is we have we have been
looking at Ai and I think aiid driven
Solutions but now what we are looking at
is the start of the idea of General AI
which is that the AI model is not just
trained to do one thing but it can
actually help with many different things
and chat GPT type models are one example
of it but this is the direction that I
think is definitely the one of the key
things that will drive um the many of
the design and Manufacturing AED AI AED
design and Manufacturing advances and um
yeah yeah I I I think from from my
perspective I always like to think how
can we leverage all this amazing
knowledge of optimization and
simulations to help the AI models rather
than just say we'll start from scratch
because there is so much knowledge that
has already been built and how can you
create and combine these two to come up
with better
Solutions and so far we have seen a lot
of promising
results that sounds fantastic so just I
want to give one example kind of to uh
Chris's point on lean and Innovation and
so what we've seen is we did a a project
where uh we we bring the incoming part
so we're not trying to design the final
thing we're trying to design all the
derivative works so we bring an incoming
part we automatically generate the mold
that makes the part and then we Auto and
the the fixtures that are used to trim
it these are actually Theros set
composits and then we automatically
generate the CNC cutter paths to cut
that so we can bring the part in and do
that whole workflow and it it's in a
fairly constrained environment of a
certain types of parts so it actually
you know the generative AI Works quite
well but one in order to do the tool
paths we had to make some assumptions
that essentially we're going to fill the
tool holder with five tools and with
those five tools we can machine
anything we couldn't get the operators
on the floor to put the five tools in
the tool holder even though they could
do everything with those five tools they
had their own tools that they liked so
we're actually in the process now of
running a lean transformation of
bringing everybody on board looking at
the whole process and helping them to
understand how this does change their
job so this is where all this great Cool
Tech kind of meets reality and we find
that lean is a way to bring those two
worlds together we call it you know
digital lean how do we bring the Two
Worlds together with the and it's the
continuous Improvement respect for
people kind of
construct that's fantastic I just wanted
to follow up one of the questions that's
come in from from the audience on on
lean U and it was a question Bruce the
um said when working on lean
implementations in small scale
businesses and I know we had a lot of
focus in the conversation around this
kind of the the large bulk of us
manufacturing being in smaller
organizations so we often see businesses
that have a relatively High degree of
customization uh High mix low volume
High
customization um you know it's kind of
an under researched area in how do you
help these small organizations sustain
lean in this kind of low volume custom
small small manufacturer kind of
environments uh it's it's really got to
be driven by the top it has to be part
of the the
culture um and it it it takes a lot of
work like for example at rebuild we have
a chief a chief lean officer so a chief
executive and the
CEO pushes this as a concept the entire
senior leadership team participates in
lean events so it happens at all levels
of the organization uh there are monthly
goals for lean Improvement so it's it's
a significant effort um but it has
significant payoff so it's it's not a
set of tools that you use it's not a 5S
chart that you put up on the wall it
really is in in order for it to be
effective a cultural
transformation and that's not 6 months
and it didn't work it's multiple years
of getting better better better and and
Bruce if I could just follow up from
some of what I've learned is that it it
also seems to go into your hiring where
I think some organizations use lean and
they're essentially oh we'll hire people
and they you know maybe we'll we'll
teach them they'll go through a lean
training with a third party but I think
that the what a cultural transformation
means is like you also hire people who
are bought in that they're going to be
responsible for making improvements in
their own um station in the company and
it's also higher skill expectations that
I think you have for workers that you
bring in do you think that's fair yes
and
specialized lean Engineers lean managers
lean transformation coaches throughout
the organization on site that is what
they do so their additional staff 1 to
3% of
of people so it's actually adding people
but you get more than that Improvement
back no I think that that seems to play
to one of the things that seem to be
coming out around this kind of idea that
the the knowledge environment that the
uh all the people involved in
manufacturing kind of are working in is
is changing dramatically it's you know
the with the kind of the ability to
understand more about what's going on in
the plant about the design about having
much softer equipment that can be retas
as you say five machines in a box kind
of thing um you and one of the question
that came in F was related to that and
it's in terms of says um do you see the
potential for using geni design
co-pilots the means of generating
Dynamic assembly methods for lean
Fabrication in custom environments and I
think it' be to give you all to comment
on this question about you as we move
forward into this environment where the
production plants are more flexible the
products are more varied the skills are
at a higher level and we've got the AI
tools to help us interpret that how does
that all kind of play out so F do you
want to you kick off on that sure yeah I
think um the answer is I do definitely
see a possibility of that happening
there is uh thinking about the assembly
methods U there are some early works
that we have seen which uh which look
promising having said that a like like a
lot of other things that I mentioned in
my I talk the key thing or kind of the
top three things for the same problem is
data data and data so if we can get data
the generative AI models can solve much
complex problems than Dynamic assembly
and if you can collect data for it or if
we can use Le leverage existing data I
think this is U not a very complex
problem from that perspective um but the
quality of the data the bias in the data
the extent of the data the modality of
the data all of those things are things
to think about when when looking at new
applications so Ben I you you've been
right in the middle of this kind of uh
debate about how this kind of new new
forms of knowledge is affecting the um
you know the use of AI within
organizations so I don't you any
thoughts on this space well maybe if I
could follow up what I find so
interesting about your work as is the um
a democratization of design and I think
you're able to point out clear
limitations in high stakes environments
that these tools you need kind of an
expert interpreter to know whether these
designs are ready for prime time in
manufacturing or what to what to be
useful and what not to be useful and you
see this in other manifestations with
like GitHub co-pilot for coding for
example that really you know excellent
programmers who know what they want and
can interpret code can use it to really
you know become a superstar programmer
highly improve their productivity but
someone in the hands of someone who
doesn't quite know what good programming
looks like it could be maybe a dangerous
tool or a tool that leads them astray
and some of the researches has I think
confirmed that for those interested you
might look at this study of BCG
Consultants that shows on on some tasks
all the Consultants improve their
performance when they use generative a
but in other tasks you have Consultants
that are persuaded to uh to you know
essentially pick the wrong answer um
when they're using generative AI but
they get the right answer without that
sort of assistance so I wonder when we
talk about democratizing design are
these tools only going to be useful for
designers who already know how to design
for manufacturing because they're able
to point out they're able to pick out
the designs that are already um
applicable or is it really going to uh
lower the barrier to entry for for
design so I do wonder if if you know
like what expertise is still required
here I think and it depends on what
stage of the new tool that we are in I
want to kind of draw a a similarity to
when finite element analysis software or
cfd software came up initially people
were hesitant to use them then people
started using them but always verified
it and at this point most of our
students just use it blindly right but
the expert students really know when the
Tool gives a wrong answer or when it can
have convergence issues similar to this
I think there is the aspect of with any
new tool there is a learning curve and
there is a tech development curve the
second part of your question is really
interesting because I think the key
value that we get with these type of
tools is for a
nonexpert and as the tools develop right
right now we have some prototypes where
you can go and ask it to generate a cad
model in simple text language and it can
generate simple CAD models now if you
look at the current learning curve of C
CAD software students have to come up in
an engineering school learn how to do
Cad and then they learn one software and
they never switch because the cost of
switching is very high right so there
this is where I see there is
democratization where you're not
necessarily becoming experts in tools
but you're thinking more around your
ideas but you will of course learn to
use the AI as a tool because AI is also
a tool in
itself D if I can jump in a little bit I
think AI is kind of a huge wild card in
the biotech space and I'm sure everyone
saw yesterday the Nobel Prize was
awarded for the ideation of proteins
using AI tools it's now possible to
think of entirely new proteins that
didn't exist before the problem that
still exists now is to how do you take
those proteins that have been designed
and actually manufacture them right the
the models aren't good enough to account
for all of the natural elements required
to produce them at scale uh it seems to
me right this is really how
democratization might play in where
biology because we can start to generate
larger data sets and we need to do so in
the manufacturing space you you could
actually imagine design tools for
biology now that don't really know
anything about the underlying biology
but say say I want to make this protein
I need a host to do it and I need a
process that will accommodate it you
know I think this is really where the
potential is at the intersection there
that hasn't really been realized yet but
uh you know I think like we've seen in
these other fields will be quite
exciting so Chris you want just to W the
other side of that which is obviously
the um biology is slightly different to
many other manufacturing spaces in that
we are biology um and the the idea that
you know um we got used to the idea that
everyone can write software and
manufactur software that everybody can
uh design screws and manufacture screws
um but the idea that everybody can
manufacture biology is kind of a um a
fairly new idea and the implications
that at scale and what kind of models we
need to do to understand how the
molecules we produce will actually
impact on the human systems diversity of
those
so have you sense of how that may break
open that manufacturing space yeah I
mean I think if we already look at
what's happening in you know a lot of
large companies that have gotten spun up
in the synthetic biology space we could
look at genko or amoris or some of these
others that have really automated much
of the front end of I have a gene I want
to be able to put in an organism I can
make an organism that now does that so
the front end is starting to show that
it's going to be feasible to start and
you start to layer in some of these AI
tools I think it's going to become you
know even more facile you know where the
the challenges sort of as you pointed
out which is thinking about how do we go
from I built a strain that performs a
task to that strain now has to operate
in an environment that I've defined it
in this could be a bioreactor in the
context what we've talked about or it
could be you know some type of harsh
environment you know if we're thinking
about terraforming or things like this
and then of course what's the impact of
the interaction of that system with that
environment and ecosystem I think we can
kind of break it into these three parts
that we have to think a lot more about
the front end I think is relatively
straightforward today work to be done
but it's a time and money question the
other two I think really still require a
lot of fundamental research one just in
the manufacturing s sence itself and you
know what's that relationship how do we
start to build the data sets to support
that and then on the back hand I think
it's it's sort of the societal and and
ethical questions of where should we be
leveraging biology to do this it's very
possible to do a wide number of things
today should we is I think a very fair
question that I think we all have to
Grapple
with that's great so we had a couple of
questions coming in that kind of bridge
two areas so one area is very much this
kind of um kind of cultural aspects you
basically the you know the management
management culture and change inside of
organizations manufacturing
organizations that going through these
Transitions and then the other one is
around this question of kind of um
ecosystems so these kind of broader like
skills
Workforce um technology development
ecosystem so I don't know whether you um
you know people had had thoughts on
either those in those like internal
cultural aspects and change methods and
Bruce obvious V to lean but um and also
these questions about kind of taking
those outside into these broader system
systems like Regional Workforce
ecosystems how do we manage things like
poaching and those sorts of half-life of
skills and things like that so I know
Ben don't whether you want to to kick
off in that kind of space sure and I'll
go back to one of the specific questions
which Drew on some of Bruce's data about
unfilled positions in in manufacturing
how there is a higher demand for job
than there is a supply of of skilled
workers in manufacturing and that's been
growing uh as a problem since 2018
certainly acceler during the pandemic or
sorry really since the early 2010s not
and and then has been accelerating since
the
pandemic you know I I think there are a
few Dimensions to this problem one is
Cle clearly wages that companies that
that we work with that pay high wages to
their production Workforce have far less
problem uh you know far reduced problem
in recruiting that their workers more
excited to to go to those firms I mean
that's that's pretty straightforward how
do you offer how do you justify offering
higher wages well you become more
productive you you know you adopt more
Advanced Technologies and the practices
like but Bruce was talking about so
there is this really you know positive
feedback loop I think between adopting
really Advanced production practices and
being able to recruit workers um one of
the things that we've seen and this
relates a bit to the culture question is
that we've seen multiple very distinct
models of organizing work so if you just
think about how do you design a job so
in manufacturing there's a lot of
attention to designing processes on a
factory floor there's attention to
designing products but there's not
really as much attention to designing
individual jobs what workers do um the
Japanese in in the introduction of cross
training at companies like Toyota and
Honda Nissan were were Pioneers in
thinking about ergonomics and how do you
you know not overwork people in in
certain tasks but there what I mean by a
job design is is a little different I
would you know think about Job design
similarly how do you design anything
else you think about your your customer
you think about what motivates them what
they want and rarely do we really ask
those questions about workers and
particularly the workers that would
thrive in a manufacturing environment
instead we think okay well what is the
process demand and I'm going to stick a
person here so so one of the things that
I see from the highest performing
organizations we study is a much flatter
organization of work and what I mean by
that is traditionally you'll have kind
of um what I hear from the community
college folks is like they talk about
721 how they train people SE seven folks
on the front lines and kind of operator
roles to two people in let's say setup
or managerial roles to one engineer and
that's very traditional you it varies a
ton by industry but what It ultimately
it is is it's pyramidal that you have uh
a lot of people in these lower skill
lower wage jobs and then fewer people in
the higher skilled jobs and and what I I
think you know at at rebuild they do
this to some extent and and at other uh
high-tech factories they do this where
it's you expect every Frontline worker
to have technical skills uh Bruce talked
about this expectation at North American
stainless where it it's not that you you
just have the two people who do setup
everyone is capable of doing setup and
they can rotate through those positions
everyone has the ability to
troubleshoot uh machine programming
issues or troubleshoot any issues with
with robots um everyone has the
opportunity you know everyone has the
knowledge to run a CMM and and do kind
of uh quality control so so that type of
flattening of the manufacturing
Workforce and designing jobs to require
multiple different skills so people can
slot in different parts and also can
participate more in continuous
Improvement I think is a big part of of
a culture shift and like what John said
at the beginning it's just you know you
can expect more of people on the factory
floor and I think they can they they
rise to the occasion in these
firms no I think that's I think that go
back to I think some of the conclusions
of the MIT uh work of the future report
and I think there's this idea that the
workforce has become by very bifurcated
and the future has to be much more where
there's no we don't have that Gap in the
middle of the workforce um so I know
we're coming close to time we had one
last question come in um which is around
this question really how do we get
started on this AI stuff um so somebody
was asking a question about are people
using their own um AI models and tuning
them are they you I guess that goes both
to both the the general uh language
processing for we doing textual stuff
but also to manufacturing processes so
you know how do you recommend that
people kind of get started with this in
terms of either using existing llms
commercial ones or building Their Own
Foundation models in some of these kind
of spaces um I don't know who wants to
who wants to take that well I can talk
in general I won't go in necessarily to
training Your Own Foundation models I
would say most people should not try
that in fact people who have have found
that the the actual large line
large language models works better but
um than custom trained ones but um just
because they train a much larger data
set but in general the the whole reason
we created the study the M the study
that we collaborate with McKenzie on is
to EXA answer that exact question first
of all um think of it like Google Maps
so first of all what we do is we lay out
a map of of the different stages the the
different routes you can go through um
then we position you on that map we
essentially Benchmark you show you where
you fit and then we help you understand
how do you go to the next level and so I
will just tell you kind of the the
general starting point is pick a problem
that really matters to your business not
one that's cool one that really matters
to your business and that if you move
the needle on it it will have a material
bottom line impact to the business so
that's the first thing makes it a whole
lot EAS you to do your
Roi collect data on it so put sensors in
so you know I talked about we we had a
situation where our scrap rate was
really high on a very important part so
we collected data on it now in our case
we had enough skills that we did our own
analytics but largely a lot of them can
be done in powerbi but the the third
step I would recommend is find a vendor
who can solve that problem and help you
do it because it's going to be very hard
to typically for you to hire the data
science skills that you need especially
if you're smaller so um if these
problems are in solution spaces where
they exist you can get someone like a
falconry or someone like an augury to do
predictive maintenance they're they're
out there and we're what we're even
found in the last study is manufacturers
and Rebuilders doing this as well are
creating micr vertical Solutions so
Titan cement is making AI for cement
manufacturers they're Greek company so
they know they're only going to operate
in Greece but they can sell their
software to cement manufacturers
globally um so Cooper standard is doing
that with H belts and hoses they're
making
a uh kind of a real-time process control
using generative AI tool that they
Market kind of live works so uh take
advantage of those kinds of solutions so
that's and I'll let FES or someone else
answer to the really give a better
answer to the Jered AI
question great so uh I think I would uh
like to start with first thing yes we do
we do train our own generative llm
models and BLM models having said that
that's not something I would recommend
to people who are starting it requires a
lot of compute and a lot of data I would
definitely I think the lucky thing right
now is it's a problem of plenty if you
go to any online resources is just like
uh
huge set of learning resources that are
available on all of these topics for
what I recommend to my students so I
teach a AI for engineering design class
and many of the students from mechi but
other schools also like Sloan and
architecture and other schools
they one of the key things that students
learn the most is by picking a project
that they're excited about which is I
think what Bruce was also mentioning is
pick a project which may be relative
simple and you can get access to data
and try to go through that entire
pipeline of how does it work and I think
that really helps you incrementally
build on more and more complex things as
you learn about the process and yeah uh
that's it's a fun
Journey well thank you very much and I
know we're at time so I'm I'm GNA draw
to conclude so first I want to say thank
you to to all of our speakers for some
really fantastic questions and some
fantastic interaction over over the over
the panel um and then I wanted to you to
thank the audience really and thank you
for joining us I hope you enjoyed the
presentations and the conversation I
found it challenging and and useful um
I'd also like to to thank the
communications team here the help to
organize the event and obviously a a
special thank to our our speakers
including my co conspirator on setting
this up Ben um in a few days the
recording of the uh the webinar will be
available to our members on the website
which is ILP mit.edu and I also want to
just take a couple of seconds just to
highlight a fewer upcoming events uh we
have three upcoming uh oncampus events
uh here at MIT we should also be
streamed to members we have a
sustainability conference coming up on
the 22nd of October a nano Summit on the
23rd of October and our Capstone R&D
conference on the 19th and 20th of
November which is a kind of a big
multirack conference all those will be
streamed uh We've also got Regional
member conference in Paris on October
the 17th Madrid on nov the 14th and
Houston on December the 3D and we have
two more webinars scheduled
decarbonization on the 7th of November
and a startup exchange demo day on the
11th of December registation for all
these events on our website uh the team
here at MIT looks very much looks
forward to seeing you all on on campus
again or at some of our regional events
or even online so thank you very much to
both to our speakers and to all our
attendees um and have a enjoyable rest
of your days thank you right