[Music]
welcome to the Leading Edge an MIT
webinar series focused on the latest in
Technology Innovation and Industry
brought to you by mit's industrial L on
program today's event is on Advanced
design and Manufacturing
[Music]
featuring Ben
Armstrong John
Lou Bruce
Lawler J Christopher
love and fiz Ahmed
and now for our host Steve
Whitaker hello everyone uh good morning
good evening good and good afternoon
depending where in the world you're
joining us from and welcome to First in
our full series of Leading Edge webinars
uh my name is Steve wher and I'm a
program director here at mit's corporate
relations and the MIT industrial liaison
program more than 75 years our mission
has been to connect hundreds of
organizations from around the world with
mit's research and Innovation ecosystem
which includes worldclass faculty
students and more than a thousand MIT
connected startups uh if you're already
a member and would like to connect with
any of today's speakers please reach out
to your program director if you're
interested in becoming a member please
check out more information at our
website ip. mit.edu today's topic
Advanced manufacturing and design is a
timely one around the world
manufacturing designer want some more
growing economic social competitive
Innovation and National Security
priorities well at the same time new
technologies such as additive
manufacturing generative Ai and
biofabrication are transforming the
competitive landscape and pushing the
boundaries of what can be made and how
it's made so today we have five
fantastic speakers who will each examine
some of the key moving pieces in this
puzzle and then we reconvene for panel
conversation before we start just a few
quick housekeeping items you can submit
questions during the presentations
please use the Q&A button use a chat tab
for technical questions we'll be saving
most of the questions for the panel but
depending on how things go we may also
answer some of them along the way the
webinar is being recorded and we made
available exclusively for ILP members
later for on demand viewing at our
website ip. mit.edu so now I'm going to
hand over to my colleague Ben Ben
Armstrong he'll moderate the speaker
presentations and engage in a brief
follow-up conversation with each of
speakers as time permits he'll also
present on his own research uh Ben
Armstrong is the executive director and
a research scientist in mit's industrial
Performance Center Center where he
colees the work of the future initiative
has research and teaching examines how
workers firms and regions adapt to
technological change and his current
projects include the working group on
gender Ai and its impact on jobs as well
as a book on American manufacturing
competitiveness his research has been
published and featured in academic and
popular Outlets from The New York Times
uh to the har Business Review so Ben
over to you thanks so much Steve you
know uh welcome everyone I'm really
excited about this morning's program um
Steve mentioned we had five speakers
including myself and uh what's nice
about today's program is that all the
speakers really fit together with one
another we have a a growing community of
uh faculty and researchers and students
at MIT interested in um the issues of
the moment in in manufacturing in the
United States and around the world and
today I think we're going to be able to
dig into some of that research and
understand how not only does it uh
thrive in the lab but also it has real
impli ations in the real world so we'll
start in a few moments with John Lou uh
my my terrific colleague who is working
on a very exciting program to support
the training of a new type of
manufacturing technician and he's going
to go over some of the workforce
challenges in the current manufacturing
ecosystem and how his research and and
work as an educator responds to those
challenges and then I'll speak a little
bit um about the connection between
John's work um focused on uh Talent in
the workforce and then the the later uh
speaker so I'll try to act as a bridge
um in in talking about the state of
manufacturing globally issues of
competitiveness and and what really the
the competitive game of manufacturing
looks like today then we'll transition
to three presentations about Advanced
Technologies in manufacturing and how
they're being used we'll start with
Bruce Lawler who is not only an MIT
colleague working on uh machine
intelligence and Manufacturing
operations the application practical
applications of AI in Manu manfacturing
but he's also a practitioner he's the
president of digital for rebuild
manufacturing which is a very exciting
uh new type of manufacturing company in
the United States and then we'll hear
from from Chris Love who's um an active
researcher in biotechnology and
biomanufacturing and he'll talk about
how Innovations in the biow world um
highlight some of the manufactur the
importance of manufacturing new types of
products and how manufacturers can stay
on the Leading Edge in terms of uh uh
being flexible enough to produce new new
types of things and then finally um
we'll turn to FZ Ahmed who um is really
a Pioneer in the study of generative AI
applications for manufacturing
particularly in design and then we'll
we'll convene and we'll try to answer
some of your questions that have come
through the chat um in a final panel
discussion so with that overview of the
day um we're going to start with
Workforce we'll then Bridge into more
advanced applications of technology and
we'll try to have a framework to see how
these pieces fit together but without
further Ado I'd love to introduce um
John Lou from mit's leap group who today
is out in the field uh working with some
um educational institutions and and has
been very gracious to make time um to be
with all of us so John thank you so much
and I'm excited to hear what you have to
say