Hi everyone. Uh my name is Punar. I'm a
postto here at the Shiman Center and I
will um talk about our efforts to use
deep learning to identify um regulatory
interactions that are driving solid
state transitions um across the
different um regions of the uh
trajectories different um
differentiation trajectories and so on.
So many of the biological systems that
um a lot of us are interested in uh and
many of the biological systems that we
see in nature are characterized by
dynamic cell state transitions. uh where
cells move between different functional
identities like um embryionic stem cell
differentiation and development or the
opposite of it where with cellular
reprogramming we have the somatic cells
being reprogrammed into stemlike state
or it also happens daily in our bodies
with T- cell maturation and aging and so
on. So of course um the the there is an
underlying dynamical process that uh
governs all of these cellate transitions
and these are um driven by uh gene
negligatory interactions. Um so these
are non-static uh they're contextual and
they also operate at different scales.
For some interactions effects may be
instantaneous and for others there are
delays.
So some of the questions of interest
when studying these dynamical systems is
uh why do cells that look initially
pretty similar uh in terms of their
genomic profiles end up um going into
different uh sulfates and what are the
regulatory interactions that are driving
these uh across different scales of
biological time. And once we have uh
insights into these we could get an idea
about uh how to intervene in these
systems so that we can reroute the
trajectories. So of course the fact that
single cell sequencing is destructive
makes this challenging because uh we
can't track the cells across time. What
we have usually is just snapshots uh
from subsets of the population at
different time points. Uh but since the
sampling is random uh we could actually
very likely um match cells across time
points because um with random sampling
we can assume that it's going to be a
pretty good representation of the uh
population at that time point. Um but
now comes the challenge that
um at any given experimental time point
we have a heterogeneous mix of cell
states because cell state transitions
are asynchronous. Uh they don't happen
at the same time. Um so we get these uh
cells across different um regions of the
landscape. This is actually both a
blessing and a curse. Um it's a blessing
because that means that with a limited
number of or with just a few snapshots
it's possible to cover a um large part
of the data manifold. Um so that makes
the um computational methods to infer
trajectories possible. Um but it's also
a curse because that means experimental
time is not the same as biological time
and also because the uh progression
speed changes along trajectories.
So there are a lot of different
approaches to uh understand drivers
because this is a very popular uh
problem in computational biology since a
lot of uh systems are um characterized
by these dynamical uh changes. But a
common theme is that a lot of them are
identifying individual genes and uh some
of them are identifying drivers per
trajectory and not the uh progression
along the trajectory. um but then the
same transcription factors for example
end up coming up multiple times in
different processes or in different
trajectories within the same population.
So the question is are they uh leading
to different trajectories because of
their uh different regulatory
interactions and can we capture that
from uh the uh snapshots by
understanding the dynamical process
behind these
cells. Um so our approach is to first
learn a continuous time dynamics of
these systems. um we're going to use uh
some flow-based uh models in order to
parameterize the um velocity fields and
that's going to allow us to learn a time
dependent evolution of the um of
individual cells. And given these uh
we're going to first of all from the
velocity field we're actually going to
try to infer a biological notion of uh
time and then along that time we're
going to uh use graph neural ods in
order to understand gene regulatory
dynamics. Um and the way we're defining
um a driver for interactions is that the
interaction should both be uh strong. um
it could be negative or positive but the
strength should be high and also the
effect of the interaction. So the
um so if you perturb the target uh gene
that's being upregulated for example if
that makes a big difference uh in the
velocity landscape um
then combining these two together
defines a notion of a driver for a um
interaction. So of course ideally we
would um have multiomic data since that
gives a lot more information into cell
states and also the regulatory
interactions but we're going to start
with transcrytoic
data right so what we have is um samples
from different time points right and
what we're going to try to learn is a
flow over these um samples and the data
distribution that the samples define um
this is similar to the diffusion um
model that a previous speaker described.
But in our case, we don't we're not
starting from a noise distribution uh
because we already have data at t equals
z. So we're going to define mixture of
gaussians over our uh data points um at
multiple different time points and we're
also ignoring stoasticity for now.
So given this the velocity field that we
learn um basically defines a flow that
takes a cell that's at a specific
location at time zero to a different uh
location in the gene expression space at
a later time point. And you want to
learn these velocity fields such that it
can explain the data that we see.
And these velocity fields over in
individual um samples also define a flaw
over the probability distributions. So
but we don't assume that this um change
in the gene expression is the only
reason the gene expression will change.
We'll also incorporate a growth term. So
um you could compute these growth terms
from um prior data as in um annotations
of apoptosis and proliferation uh genes
and that actually helps with
convergence. But we're going to uh we're
not going to keep it uh static and we're
going to um learn it in the model as
well. There's no unique solution to this
uh setup because the continuity equation
could be satisfied with multiple
different velocity fields. So that
requires us to make some assumptions on
the velocity field and we're going to
basically penalize uh long paths and uh
unnecessary mass destruction. So
basically trying not to make any changes
to gene expression or the u density uh
distribution unless we need to in order
to explain the data and this basically
defines a uh optimal transport distance
in the dynamic setting.
Um, and we also want to make sure that
while we're trying to anchor a shortest
pass, the data flow actually happens on
the manifold. And we're are uh going to
pre-train a a VAE that basically uses a
triplet uh loss to make sure relative
distances in the um neighborhood graph
based um distances in the PCA space um
is also preserved in the
VAE, right? Um we continue to actually
learn uh update the VAE uh after the
pre-training while jointly learning the
velocity field because we found that
this really helps with reconstruction uh
and simulation of new data and also the
sharpness of the um partial derivatives
that we're going to compute later on. Um
and that's with both matching densities
and also matching uh predictions
observed to the observed data after uh
reconstructing with VAES. And there's
just a word of caution um because
there's no correspondence between the
predictions that we make and the cells
that we see um we're going to use a
Waserstein distance but was distance is
actually biased in the sense that your
probability the entropy of your
marginalss will influence the uh scale
of the distance. So we use the biased
version in order to u make sure every
batch has the same amount of influence
over
training. Right? So before moving
forward, I just want to show you that um
using linear tracing data set where we
have barcoded cells that encode clonal
relationships um we can actually check
how well the uh trajectory inference
happens and if you look at all of the
data sets so what we have here is um
hematopotic stem cells differentiating
into neutrfils and monocytes. So we
don't know which cell at the initial
time point um the late final cell from a
final uh faith came from uh but we do
know that the progenitors um we can
calculate basically the uh faith
probability of progenitors using the
clonal
barcodes. Um oh this did not update. All
right. Um my bad.
If you look at the whole uh data uh if
you look at the whole data set actually
I think it should be because this
was if you look at the whole data set we
get about n close to 99% accuracy but
the thing is of course making
predictions along yeah of course making
predictions along the um differentiated
like the final fates u will be very easy
so that's not really a good notion of uh
um accuracy the more difficult task is
trying to figure out what the
progenerous from the initial time point
is for uh each of the cells at the um at
the end and for that we get close to um
89 uh%
accuracy right so this learns the
generative model over the um cell state
transitions but one thing that we
mentioned is that u we want to learn
these um interactions over a notion of
biological time and not uh not
experiment experimental time but right
now the velocity field is taken in
experimental time and is generating uh
samples at a given experimental time. So
in order to convert this into a bi
biologically meaningful notion of time
we're going to decompose it into three
components uh gradient uh flow
rotational flow and harmonic
flow. The gradient flow has no curl
curls at all. So this is basically
solving attracted to a specific point
and uh that describes the Wington
landscape if you're familiar with the uh
notion of marbles rolling down a hill to
reach a final state um along a along a
potential landscape of uh
differentiation. A rotational flow
captures local cycle. So it's more
related to cell cycle and stuff. uh for
our questions because we're interested
in uh initial cells ending up in final
phase, we're going to use the gradient
flow decomposition. And what we do is uh
basically order the cells on this
landscape and the landscape is not going
to be um a straight line. Uh but this
ordering is going to give us a notion of
yeah
stse. So then what we can do is create
these trajectory specific time series
data um order them based on the
landscape
um and then learn uh train a graph
neural OD in the biological time such
that
the changes in the gene expression of
your um regulators um of the regulator
regulators of a target will try to
predict the uh change in the gene
expression of the target gene at that
time point. Uh for this what we found is
looking at expression itself is not very
useful but looking at the velocities uh
ended up being more useful and we were
able to capture
um biologically meaningful um
relationships and we add a time delay in
order to um also preserve
interpretability. um we are we're using
assigned and linearized attention uh
mechanism. I'm going to just highlight a
few um results and I move on. So first
of all
uh in IPS-C trajectory early on in the
um differentiation uh we or I I guess I
should say reprogramming trajectory uh
we found that um there's an interaction
between poxd and foxo and foxd was uh
previously um validated experimentally
to increase um potent reprogramming
efficiency. Um on top of that we also
see
some interactions that come up for
multiple different trajectories like u
make and kf4 interaction. But what we
see is the dynamic of um when they
influence the trajectory and how much
they influence the trajectory actually
changes for iPSC trajectory. it becomes
uh a highly influential interaction
early on goes down but then comes up
again uh during the IPS-C when the cells
reach the uh pur potency um states but
we don't see that in the neural
trajectory and stromal trajectory it
goes down and stays low uh relatively
low and um importance of make for
stemlike pur potent cells were also
experimental
validated right so when we look at the
top 20 interactions of the very early
day one um or actually day day two is
when they start to um sequence. Uh what
we see is the enhancement of uh
enrichment in pathways related to pure
potency and also down reggulation of
epithelial messenymal transitions which
is the opposite of meenymal epithelial
transition that cells are required to go
through for pur potency. Um so this also
um validates our um insights. Uh we look
at a very small part of the regulatory
network and also see that sou and nano
uh their influence and their
interactions with other um uh
transcription factors go up as we
approach the pur potency stage in the uh
um transitions.
Lastly, we capture similar um insights
for mouse hematopois where we see that
sp1 is a driver that comes up for both
the CMP and LMPP trajectories. Um but um
when we look at the when we don't rank
trae when we don't rank drivers just
based on the gene itself but look at the
interactions as well the uh speed one
gata one becomes the top one the top uh
um interaction for the CMP trajectory uh
whereas gata 3 doesn't appear in it uh
top 10 at
all lastly the gold standard for
basically um understanding that we
learned A good gene regulatory model is
to test out uh perturbations. We there
is a published paper that uh performed
um gene accounts for hundreds of uh
genes in hematopois. So we look at the
um difference in how the relative
population sizes change with knockouts
um and we compare it to our results in a
different data set. um because of the
growth term we can also um now learn
whether the uh changes in the gene
expression leads to a apoptosis. So be
in uh incorporated as well. And we see
that while the numbers aren't exactly
super correlated, the directions are
very very well
correlated. Right? Limitations. Um of
course the transcrytoic data only
provides uh um one view of the uh cell
state. So extending this to multiomic
data would actually be very informative
not just only for regulatory
interactions but also um when we look at
um tracing data sets with multi ohm data
we see that using both of the data uh um
data resources actually increases the um
predictive power of our progenitors by
um quite a lot. Um and we could also
generate hypotheses on accessibility
gene expression relationships by looking
at the delay jacobian. So the partial
derivative of the um OD after
integrating it for a while. And that
could uh give us now insights into
potentially new interactions that we may
not have uh in uh curated data sets.
I'm excited about uh the potential of
using this for understanding um a cell's
environment on its spatial temporal
trajectory uh as we have um spatial
temporal data sets now as
well. Uh I'd like to thank Caroline and
uh Shiva for being supportive during
this project. Um I also like to thank
the members of Shimiss Center and Ulab
uh especially Dora who um we I had very
useful discussions with on trajectory
inference early on and uh GTN for
discussions on graph neural
networks. Uh we have time for one
question.
All right, thanks for the great talk. Um
my question is you know um in in in the
underlying physics that uh it's chemical
reaction dealing with all these like um
interactions, right? Um so that
basically means it's always um
stochastic and I to my understanding
that um you're using an OD model which
all stoasticity is in the initial state
um and I do understand that um yeah
indeed even if you use an SD you will
still have a proalistic flow OD but I
guess like once you start to use OD and
you admit that there well I admit there
is stoasticity like how do you interpret
like the interaction because you got the
stoasticity absorbed into your into your
um velocity. Yeah. So we actually don't
know the shape of the noise in single
cells, right? So with stochastic models,
people make the assumption that um there
is gaussian noise uh in all cells and
they place a gaussian noise over the
gene expression data of all cells. But
um that's probably not very
um biologically
um that's probably not biologically
accurate. Um I would expect it to be
more uh cell states uh dependent um in
early u versions not for the trajectory
inference uh part but for the gene
regulatory inference part I did consider
using SDS I don't see a accuracy
increase I see thank you