good to see you everyone so um in this
second talk I will talk about um
generative modeling so first question um
who has used chb or anything like that
maybe everyone right but who have heard
the term of generative model before you
got to know CH
GPT well still quite a lot yeah so um in
this talk I will give um very high level
overview of um what generative modeling
is and how it's impacting um our life
and and our future
research so there is no doubt that we
are in the so-called gen AI area so um
for public audience perhaps this moment
happens when chbt or or many other chat
BS were introduced so you can
communicate with um the computer in
natural languages you can talk you can
ask the computer whatever problems and
um it's it's just like an agent that can
help you to solve um many issues so this
is not the only um generative AI model
so another very popular and very
powerful tool is the so-called text to
image generation so for example um the
users can give um the computer some text
which is usually called a prompt and
then the computer can generate an image
so um for example change the adap
let me remove
this okay I hope it
works okay sorry about that so for
example um in in this case the promp
would be um a Teddy be teaching a course
with generative model written on
blackbot so it is very likely that um
the computer hasn't the computer
algorithms hasn't seen this exact image
before um but this is how it can produce
from the given text
prompt so um we can even go one step
further we can ask the computer
algorithm to generate a video and this
is um what is generated by Sora um one
year ago so um this is just really
impressive so I believe perhaps um no
producers have ever um um kept um take a
video in this wave um having so many um
um paper planes flying on top of trees
or or or Forest so this is completely
generated by kind of the imagination of
the computer
algorithms so um actually generative
models could be very powerful um
productive um tools um in our daily life
for example um it's still kind of a trap
B but it is a TR bot that can help us to
write code so um this is kind of an AI
assistant so it um um it can read your
code it can try to fix the issue of your
code and you can directly communicate
with the agent using natural language
and the agent will turn it into um code
so in some sense um perhaps the previous
um programming language is C++ python or
Java the next level of programming
language would just be English or human
language so um it's more than that it's
more than just computer science actually
gen models has been used in many
scientific uh problems so this is um uh
an application which is called protein
design and generation so the ultimate
goal is to design or generate some type
of proteins that can solve um some
problems um um that we we care about
let's say uh are some um very um um
dangerous uh very fatal diseases so this
work is called um RF diffusion um it is
it's actually part of the uh um the work
of the Nobel Prize winner um this
year and there are many other scientific
problem that can benefit from Al
generative modeling so um this is a work
from Deep mine a few years ago so um
they can use this model to predict um
the the the weather change um over the
um next several hours or or next several
days so this would be a very difficult
problem um for um classical algorithms
because as we may know um the change of
weather or the change of climate is
chaotic so it is very difficult to
predict it precisely so we may not want
to have the exact physical um state of
that moment what we want is some
qualitative behavior let's say whether
it's raining or whether it is windy at
that moment and in this sense G models
of deep learning could provide a very
good um solution to this
problem so actually um before the reason
emergence of um gen models uh in in in
um in our daily life um actually genive
models have been used or developed um
for decades so um this is a tool which
is called patch match or um that's
called as um content aware field in the
software Photoshop so it was a very
impressive tool um when I was um PhD
students and at that time I work exactly
on the same problem so the problem here
is that you will be given a photo and
the user can specify some area or some
um structures in the photo and their
computer algorithm is trying to fix the
photo or edit the photo based on their
uh um user um um instructions so
actually at that time there is no deep
learning and to be H for this
application or for this um algorithm
there is even no machine learning so it
is a very classical computer vision
algorithm but conceptually this is also
a kind of generative
modeling so the technique behind this
generative model actually can Dat Back
even um another 10 years ago so this is
an algorithm that is called um texture
synthesiz the goal here is that you will
be given an example texture and you want
to extend the texture to um to to a
bigger image or or or you want to past
the uh the texture to some 3D objects
that um that you care about so the idea
here is is just very simple you just try
to synthesize um the texture pixel pixel
by pixel based on what um has been
synthesized so in today's word this is
actually an autor regressive
model okay so um then this is basically
what I'm going to talk about in in in
this talk I will very quickly um go
through uh the concept of what is a
generative model and then I will
introduce some approaches some Modern
approaches um to how we can build
generative models using today's um deep
neural networks and then I will also
talk about um how we can um formulate um
real world problems into kind of
generative modeling
okay so first what are generative models
so um it turns out this is a very
difficult question because when the
gentic models becomes more powerful and
and more and more powerful the scope of
the gentic models keep changing so even
though I will talk about um some
classical definitions of gentic model I
just want to say perhaps today every
single problem could be formulated as a
kind of gen
models so now let's look at the
applications or scenarios we have just
introduced so what do these scenarios
have in common so for example on image
generation or video generation or and
text generation actually there are
multiple predictions or or or actually
conceptually infinite predictions just
to one input let's say if you want the
computer to generate an image of cat so
you will tell the computer this is a cat
I want a cat and conceptually there is
an infinite number of possible C so
another property of generative model is
that so some predictions are more
plausible than some others so for
example um if you want um let's say a
cat and then um their computer May
generate a lion or it can also generate
a a dog and then perhaps for um in
common sense a lion is more plausible
than a dog in this scenario um of course
a cat is more plausible than a
lion and another very intriguing
property of gentic modeling is that your
training data may not contain the exact
solution so as we have seen I believe
the computer has never seen a teddy bear
standing in front of a blackb and and
teaching um generative models and
similarly the computer may not um must
have not seen these um paper planes
flying on top of forest so this is kind
of an outof distribution generation so
the computer algorithms were trained on
some data but what they are generating
is some distribution that could be
outside of uh um the training data so um
in addition most of the time the
predictions of generative models could
be more complex and and more informative
and conceptually it is higher
dimensional um than their input so for
example in text to image generation if
you want a computer to generate a cat
which is just a very short word and
their output image would would have um
um millions of pixels or maybe even more
so um all these properties make J model
um way more difficult than some of the
classical um deep learning or
recognition
problems so um in a textbook this is
kind of um formal definition of what
would be um gentic model um usually when
gentic model is introduced it people
would compare it with a so-called
discriminative model so what is a
discriminative model so typically um as
you have seen in Philip talk if we care
about image an image classification
problem you will be given an image then
you are going to train a model for
example a neuron Network then you want
the neuron Network to Output a label
let's say a doc and conceptually in this
very simple scenario we can just imagine
um generative model as reversing this
process so in this case you would be
given a dog and then you would like to
train a model again which could be a
neuron Network and then you want to
Output the image which is X so in this
case there would be many possible output
many possible docks the output will be
higher dimensional and the output the
output would be another dock that you
haven't seen
before then un conceptually this is kind
of a
probabilistic um visualization of what
would be a discriminative model and what
would be a generative model so
um so on the on the left um on the left
hand side um is a discriminative model
you have you have some um Green Dot
which is one class and some orange dot
which is another class so the goal of a
discriminate model is just to find a
boundary that can separate these two
classes which seems easier then
conceptually the task is try to find out
this conditional probability
distribution which means you will be
given X such as an image then you want
to estimate the probability of Y such as
um it is a label zero or label one then
as a comparison in the context of a
generative model you would still be
given the same data the same the same
dots but the goal here is to estimate
the probability uh the probability
distribution of this dots let's say in
the case of um this class which
corresponds to yals to 1 you want to
estimate what is the um conditional
probability distribution of um this
class so conceptually in alernative
model we care about probabilistic
modeling so that is the key problem
alernative model want to address and
that is also the key
challenge so you may wonder why why
there is probability and why we care
about um probabilistic modeling and
actually in many of the real world
problems we can assume there are some
underlying distributions and you can
also assume your data is actually
generated by some very complicated um
word models so for example um if we care
about a human face images um we can
formulate the problem as there would be
some um latent factors such as the poe
the lighting um the scale and as
actually the identity of the face so
this would be the latent factors and
then you assume there will be some
distributions about these latent factors
and these latent factors would be
rendered by a word model so that is for
example how you can um project a 3D
object onto a a 2d GD of pixels and then
this um um this latent um factors will
be rendered by this word model and what
you can actually observe is just a 2d GD
so that is the observation X
then your 2D GD would follow some very
complicated distributions that cannot
simply be described by some um um
underlying distributions so this is um
why we care about um probalistic
modeling and a generative model is
trying to to uncover these um underlying
factors or or to to reverse this
process now so for example let's say we
have some data let's say I have a data
set of docs which means I have many data
points um and every single data point
would correspond to one image of a doc
then conceptually we imagine there is
some underlying distribution that can
model the distribution of all docs so um
it's worth noticing that this is already
part of your modeling um because you can
model the underlying word generator uh
in many different ways so even though we
often assume there is this underlying
distribution
this distribution is a part of the
modeling and then the goal of generative
modeling is to learn a neuron Network or
perhaps another model to approximate
this distribution let's say um this this
this red distribution is what we can
learn um from a neuron Network and the
goal here is to minimize um the distance
between the data distribution and the
distribution you estimate
this is still a very difficult problem
there are many solution to this problem
but conceptually almost all um existing
generative models could be um um
formulated in this way and they are just
trying to address the challenge um
exposed by this
problem then conceptually assuming um
your model has done a good job of this
then you can start to sample from the um
distribution you estimated so um if your
model is doing a good work that means
when you sample from distribution this
distribution you would you you will be
doing something that is conceptually
similar to um sampling from the original
data distribution that in this case
hopefully it will produce another doc
that um your algorithm haven't
seen then um it is um also possible to
do the probability estimation so that is
your model would be given another image
let's say a cat and then you can ask the
model um How likely this image um is
under the original data distribution
then in this case um if the original
data distribution are about dogs and the
input image is a cat then hopefully it
will produce a low estimation of the
probability density so um this is kind
of um how we can um use probability
modeling to uh um formulate the
generative modeling
problem um then as you can imagine the
most powerful tool today for us to
address generative modeling is deep
learning so um Philip has given a very
excellent and very quick um um
introduction of what deep learning is so
conceptually in a in a nutshell um deep
learning is representation learning so
what Philip has introduced is a process
of learning to represent the data or
conceptually the data instances that
means you will be given the data let's
say the images and then you want to map
the images to labels so um this is one
way of using deep new networks for
representation
learning then in the case of um
generative modeling actually there is
another way of using deep learning but
still for the goal of representation
learning so that is we don't just want
to learn the representation of one
single data instances
so we want to learn the representation
of a probability distribution so that is
a more complicated problem and
conceptually it can be viewed as
learning the mapping the other way let's
say um here the output would be the
labels let's say um on the um the label
of cats or the label of dogs and then
you want to m m map it back to the pxel
space so um then as you can imagine deep
learning or deep uh networks is a very
powerful tool for generative modeling
and conceptually when you use this tool
for this problem the models are actually
simultaneously playing these two roles
so first learning to represent data
instances and second learning to
represent probability
distributions then this is conceptually
what a model would be look like so um
your model will be given a very simple
distribution for example um it could be
a gaan distribution or it could be a
uniform distribution it doesn't matter
so in the case of an image this would
look like just a a completely noisy
image then the goal is to learn a neural
network such that it can map a noisy
image to just another image um in in in
in the output space then conceptually if
your model can do a good work hopefully
the output would be a visually
reasonable image such as a doc in this
case then um you can just keep sampling
um noise from the input distribution and
hopefully the neuron network will turn
everything into some meaningful images
in the output then conceptually when you
do this actually your neuron network is
trying to map a simple distribution
let's say um gaussin distribution here
to another distribution which
conceptually is to approximate the
underlying data distribution then in
this sense a generative model is a
mapping between distributions it is not
just a mapping between a pair of data
points and and and a label it is it goes
from one distribution to another
distribution um the next slid would be a
little bit technical perhaps and I can
go very quickly so these are some of the
um um fundamental elements of a
deorative model so first of all you may
need to formulate a real world problem
um as a probabilistic model or or
um ative model this is kind of one of
the most critical Parts um for us to to
to design an algorithm and after you can
do that you need some representations
and today um usually this is a neural
network so you want to represent the
data and their distribution and then um
you need to introduce some objective
functions to measure the difference
between two distributions and then you
need an Optimizer that can solve the
very difficult optimization problem and
then you also need an inference
algorithm which is conceptually a
sampler that can sample from the
underlying distribution um so um today
many of the uh um mathematical or
theoretical um research would be about
um one or many element in in this list
um so I'm not going to um delve into the
details but next I'm going to give a
very high level and very quick overview
of um what are some of the modern
approaches and popular approaches um to
generative models and and I'm also going
to explain why a generative model is a
hard problem so this is the figure you
have just seen so um as as you can see
the problem here is that if your model
will be given one noisy uh image or
noise input you you you want it to map
it um to to map the noise to an output
image so why this is hard so um recall
that in Philip's talk he has talked
about the problem of supervise learning
so in that case you will be given one
image and also a label of that image so
you have a pair of input and output so
that is a very well formulated problem
of supervise learning and that problem
is easy for modern um neuron networks to
solve but in the case of gentic modeling
conceptually it is an unsupervised
learning problem so that is you will be
given an image but then conceptually you
have no idea what
and input noise would corresponds to
that image then this correspondence or
this pairing problem is also what your
underlying algorithm should try to
figure out so then in this sense
conceptually it is not just about
mapping pairs um of images or pairs of
data it's about mapping two
distributions so you want to map a
simple gaussian distribution to a very
complicated data distribution and this
is is why gentic modeling is
hard so there are many um effective and
very smart algorithm to address this
problem so I will start from some um
very fundamental and and and and very
elegant algorithm and then um I will
start to talk about um some of the state
ofth Arts algorithm today so um first I
will talk about um variational
autoencoders of vae so conceptually in
generative model as we have introduced
you want to map an input distribution to
an output distribution then we can
formulate this as an autoencoding
problem that means if you will have the
distribution of the data then you can
train another neuron Network to map the
data distribution to the the
distribution you like let's say a gon
distribution then you can then then
after you have this distribution you can
learn the generator to to um transform
it back then conceptually you compute
the distance between the inputs and and
the output so this is a the very
classical idea of Auto encoding in deep
learning but uh In classical algorithms
usually conceptually this would be
applied to the concept of U um data
instances that is you apply this to
every single images so in the case of
variational autoencoder conceptually the
concept of autoencoding is applied on
the distribution so you can just imagine
this distribution is is just one object
it's just one entity that you want to
you you you you want to uh process so
you transform this object into this
simpler object and then you transform it
back so then this is um the autoencoding
idea the another very popular solution
um that is kind of the beginning of um
um research in generative modeling 10
years ago um is called the generative
aers real networks or in short G and or
again um concept
again also just want to learn a
generator that goes from a simple
distribution to the data distribution
but instead of introducing another
Network before the data uh before the
simple distribution in the case of again
it it introduced the extion network
after um you you you have obtained the U
um estimate distribution so um this
extra neur uh neuron Network would be
called a discriminator the goal of the
discriminator is to tell whether your
sample is from the predicted
distribution or is from the real
distribution then if discriminator
cannot tell which distribution it is
from then that then it means this these
two distributions would be very similar
so um gen is kind of the most uh um
popular and most powerful generative
models um over the last um decades until
um um the there are some very powerful
tools um came out over the last um three
or four
years so um another very powerful
generative modeling tool is called Auto
regressive models and in the context of
um natural language processing this is
usually known as next token prediction
um but concep the idea of Auto
regressive or Auto regression is more
than just in the next token so um
basically if we care about um
probability that involve many um
elements or many variables then um
following the very basic principle of um
probability Theory we can always
decompose this joint probability into a
train of many conditional probabilities
so the key idea of autor regressive
modeling is
to um model every single conditional
property
individually um rather than modeling the
the entire joint probability so if you
do this decomposition following the
order of the sequence let's say in this
case you want to predict X1 first and
then you predict X2 um conditional on X1
and so and so forth if you follow this
sequential order then you can turn your
problem into next token prediction so um
this idea of um Auto regressive model is
to break a very complicated problem into
a bunch of simpler and smaller
problems so for example um in this case
um in in the first output you you will
estimate a very simple and lower
dimensional um distribution um in this
illustration for example it would be a
one-dimensional distribution and then in
the second note it will predict um the
next dimension of the variable that it
will be a two-dimensional uh
distribution and so and so forth uh it
will be difficult to to visualize a
higher dimensional distribution but
conceptually when you do this um it
would be a distribution in a high
dimensional space so this is the the key
idea of autor regressive
modeling then um over the last three or
four years there is a very powerful
model emerging especially in the context
of image generation and in computer
vision so this model was motivated by um
thermodynamics in physics so um the idea
is that um you can you can um formulate
the problem
as um repeatedly corrupting the clean
data or input image by adding gaussian
noise and then you can progressively
turn it into a fully noise image and
then the learning the goal of learning
is to reverse this process and if you
can do that then you can progressively
go from a noisy input back to the clean
image and this this idea is called a
diffusion or it is often Al also called
denoising
diffusion so conceptually um using the
terminology of um probability or
probability distribution this means you
will have an input data distribution
hopefully uh it will be about clean
images and then you just repeat
repeatedly adding noise on top of it
then conceptually this is just like
running a convolutional kernel on top of
the distribution space and by doing it
many times ultimately you will turn the
data distribution into a gan
distribution so then your model is just
trying to to to learn to reverse this
process
so this is what a diffusion model um may
look like um at inference time it will
start from a very um simple distribution
say a gin and then it will progressively
reverse the process and go back to the
data
distribution so actually this visual uh
this visualization is very similar to
many of the concepts um that are popular
in graphics so for example you can
imagine the starting points of this
process is some colonal shape let's say
um it would be a sphere or it would be a
cylinder then you want to progressively
morph or warp this object this shape
into another shape that you like let's
say um this could be for example just a
mountain or um a bunny so you want to
progressively walk
the input sphere to a bunny and this is
a very well studied problem so inic case
of distribution modeling we can imagine
this
distribution literally as a geometric
entity and then you can formulate a
process to do this transformation and
actually what I have just described is
kind of an emerging idea with which is
called flow matching so you want to flow
from a very simple object or very simple
shape such as a sphere to another more
complicated shape such as a bunny and if
you have this algorithm and then if you
formulate your underlying shape as some
probability distributions and then you
can use this idea to do a um probability
modeling that is um generative modeling
so here conceptually this is just
another visualization of the same thing
you will be starting from some
um simple distribution let's say a gaan
and this would be your data distribution
that you want to model the goal here is
to progressively change your input
distribution to the output
distribution then um there are many
excellent Solutions in computer Graphics
to this problem so one idea here is to
learn a flow field
so you can imagine if this is literally
a 3D object then you will have some um
3D vertexes or 3D surfaces so you want
to gradually move these three uh uh the
these 3D surfaces um from the sphere to
some 3D surfaces um in in in your in
your bunny so um then if you do that
then there will be a flow field that can
be constructed um um via this process so
um there there will be a lot of
mathematic details behind F and of
course I'm not going to delve into it um
but this is kind of the high level idea
of um the latest progress in um um
generative modeling that is um flow
matching so U conceptually these are
some of the popular approaches um today
um to gentic models um I I haven't
covered any of the mathematical details
um but it is kind of fun to walk through
all these methods um the point I'm going
to to make is that in all of these
generative models there would be some
deep neuron networks as the building
block and conceptually this is just like
in deep neuron networks there would be
some layers as the building block so the
layers are those uh um modules that um
Philip have just introduced so they
could be a linear layer they could be a
Ru um they could be a normalization
layer or a soft Max layer so neuron
networks
are some entities that thata is built by
so-called layers and today these gen
genitive models are some entities that
are built by Deep neuron networks so in
this sense the gentic models are the
next level of um
abstractions okay um then next I will
talk about how we can use this
mathematical models or this uh um
theoretical models of of generative
modeling um in the context of solving a
real world
problems so as we have um introduce the
the key problem in generative model is
about this conditional distribution so
you you you want to model a distribution
that conceptually um you will be given
the condition why and um it is about the
distribution of your data X but then
reality what what is y and what is x in
in common
terminology Y is called the conditions
let's say you want to generate a cat um
it could also be some constraints let's
say um you you you you don't want to uh
generate um some type of output images
it could also be labels or text labels
or or maybe some other labels and it
could also be um attribute let's say you
want to generate a big object or a small
object so in most of the case the label
um the condition y would be more
abstract and it will be less
informative and as a comparison the
output X is usually called the data or
it would be the observations or or
measurements um of the
um of the samples that you can that you
can see in the real world problems so in
the case of of image generation then
usually X is just the image so usually X
would be more concrete than the
condition Y and it would be more
informative it would be more um higher
dimensional um now let's go through the
um applications we have just introduced
and and let's discuss what would be X
and what would be y um in the case of uh
in in in the context of a natural
language conversation or chatbot the
condition y would be the so-called
prompt that is given by the user um and
the output X would be the response of
the chatbot so usually the output is
higher dimensional and there would be
many um plausible outputs that can
correspond to the same
prompt and similarly in the context of
um text to image generation or text to
video Generation Um the condition would
be the text prompt um it could be a
sentence it could be a class label it
could be some attribute and the output
would be the generated visual content
such as an image and video and the
output is higher dimensional it is more
complicated so these are kind of typical
use cases and of course this is also the
case uh in terms of um 3D generation in
this case the condition would still be a
text prompt and the output would be um
the 3D text structures um in this um
computer vision of Graphics application
the the 3D text structure would be the
shapes um textures or or maybe even
illuminations of the underlying
object and then we can move one step
further um um then we can generalize the
scenario to to the problem of let's say
protain generation in this case um the
input condition could still be some
prompt it could still be some text let's
say you can you can try to tell the
computer that I want to generate a
protein that can cure cancer so that is
valid but the problem here is that
there's no way for the computer to
understand what does it mean by cure
cancer or or what it can do to cure
cancer so in in this case there would be
a lot of research in how you can
represent the underlying condition that
you care about so you want your output
protein to have some properties and you
hope that those property would be
related to let's say cure cancer or
curing some U um special diseases so in
this case there uh um the condition
would be more abstract it could also be
a higher dimensional because it is the
abstraction of some behaviors let's say
cure cancer and the
output would be another representation
that is um also higher dimensional you
know let's say the protein structure in
3D it would just be like another kind of
um um 3D
object um then let's talk about some
other scenarios that typically people
won't think of as a generative model
let's say this is a very classical case
that people will regard as
discriminative models we have introduced
so this is um oh oh sorry about that not
not not this one so this is um the the
the typical case of um image generation
as well so you will you will be given a
class label and then your algorithm will
be asked to generate the output image so
this is the so-called class conditional
case which means um your y would be very
specific about one label but then there
is another scenario where you can
imagine you won't you won't be given any
uh uh conditions so that means you want
to generate the data output that will
follow the entire distribution of the
data that in this case um you you can
imagine the underlying condition as an
implicit condition which means you want
the image to follow the distribution of
your underlying data sets
and if um if your if your model can do a
good job in in in this regard so it will
try try to distinguish the distribution
of this data set with the distribution
of um any other data
set okay then this is um the case I have
um just confused with so this is the
idea that we can um apply a generative
modeling to the scenario of um um
discriminative modeling so here is a
very typical case um of supervised
learning or of um um discriminative
learning that is image classification so
you will be given an image and then you
want to estimate the label of that image
and if we want to formulate this as
ative model then in this case actually
Y which was a label in almost all our
previous
examples would be the image in this case
so the image is your condition in this
case and then the class label X would be
um the
um predicted output so you want to model
the probability distribution of your
output so um just because this model um
this problem is is too simple and too
trial and usually people won't think
about it as a generative model um but it
can
be so then what is the point here so if
you can model image classification as a
generative model then actually you can
can extend the scenario from um close
vocabulary classification which means
you will be given a predefined set um of
class labels to the scenario of open
vocabulary recognition that means you
won't be given a predefined set of class
labels so that means there could be many
plausible answers to the same image that
in this case you will still be given one
image but then your output is no longer
one unique correct answer there could be
many different possible answers that can
describe this image for example in this
case these are all reasonable answers to
say this is a bird or a flamingo this is
a red color or perhaps orange color so
as you can see even for this very
classical um image classification
problem if we try to formulate it as a
generative model the it could also opens
up new opportunities and it will enable
new applications um that is um that that
that is nontypical for um classical
discriminative
models and we can even move one step
forward so you can you can imagine the
input condition Y is still an image and
you want the output not just be a label
or or or or shocked um description it
can be an entire sentence or it can even
be some paragraphs that can describe
this image so actually this is also a
classical problem in competivision which
is known as um image captioning so you
want the computer to write a caption
about this
image and then with this context we can
even move one step forward so then this
image could just be part of the input in
your conversation in your natural
language conversation with your chat
booot then in this scenario the
condition would be the input image and
some other text that is some other text
prompt that is given by the user and the
output would be the response of the
chatbot based on this image and the text
prompt let's say in this scenario um
given this image the user could ask what
is UN user about this image and the
tboard can try to come up with some um
answers about this problem and it says
um it is just unusual to um Iron close
um on ironing part attached to to the
roof of a moving taxi so
um um in many other real world problems
such as robotics we can also formulate
the problem of policy learning um as a
generative model so for example um if in
in in robotics control there could be
many
plausible um trajectories many plausible
policies um that can fulfill the same
task so in this case for example um you
want the robot to move this t-shaped
objects into the Target location so um
the robot could either move from the
right hand side or it could move from
the uh the left hand side so both
trajectories are plausible so there is
no single unique answer so then this is
why this Al this also where we can use
objective models um to model this um
policy learning
problem so in general this is what what
we have just seen so a generative model
conceptually just care about this
conditional distribution so in my
opinion actually there is no any
constraints or or or um or requirements
about what can be X or what can be y so
they conceptually they can be anything
so that
means we can use generative models to
solve many kinds of real world problems
we can just try to formulate all these
real world problems as kind of
conditional um distribution problem and
then we can try to apply the latest uh
um advance in generative models um as a
tool for this problem so this is also
partially why gentic models is becoming
more and more common today um for people
to solve real world
problems so um this will be the last
slides of this talk um but I just want
to um give some of the high level idea
um and convey some of the most important
messages in my mind so as we have seen
uh um generative models have some deep
neuron networks as they are building
block so this is just like deep neuronet
will have some layers as they are
building blocks so 10 years ago the
research in deep learning has been
mainly about these layers so let's say
convolutions activation functions
normalizations self attention layers Etc
so that is the research about one decade
ago
and then we have generative models and
generative models becomes the next level
of
abstractions um all previous research on
deep neuron network still applied but
there is a new level of research that
would be built around generative
models then moving forward when people
use these generative models to do more
amazing stuff let's say large language
models reasoning and agentic machine
learning which we will cover in in the
remaining parts of this
talk in this case these existing
generative models will become another
level of building blocks so as we can
see and as you have seen from um Philips
uh introduction slides we are building a
a stack of many different levels of
models so these are different levels of
abstractions so the abstractions could
be layers could be deep neural networks
they could be generative models and they
could be um reasoning agents so this is
just like how computer science has has
progressed over um um the last century
or also so people are building different
levels of abstractions and then we can
unlock different levels of new opport uh
opportunities so in this sense I would
say so um dtive model is the next level
of De learning and it's also the next
level of obstruction and building blocks
and with that that um is the end of my
talk
[Applause]
mapping distribs which is much
higher that mean they are inferior in
that simp you mean uh gentic models is
inere in the simple Tas of um supervised
learning yes
[Music]
um I think there is no um
certain answer yet because in some sense
I think it is is it is not yet a common
understanding that you can address a
discriminative problem using generative
models so if it is a very easy let's say
close vocabulary classification task if
you very clearly know that you have 10
10 possible labels or or 1,000 possible
labels then um usually a simple solution
is sufficient but even in the case of
the so-called open vocabulary
recognition let's say you will be given
one image you still want one label let's
say a hashtag then you you can still
have a vocabulary but that vocabulary is
just the English vocabulary the human
vocabulary it could be very long and
even in that case I think a generative
model is is a good idea then if you want
to move move one step further you want
to have a sentence as a description or
if you want to start have some
conversations that is based on this
image then agative model is perhaps the
only solution that that you you you you
should
use great presentation two questions we
talking is it we
MH a good question so the first question
is is it possible to um go the other way
so um I think it depends on what is the
method so I think recently the answer is
yes so the flow maturing algorithm can
can enable us to do that so as you can
imagine in my in my analogy if you
imagine flow matching as as moving from
a sphere to a rabbit then conceptually
it doesn't need to be a sphere it could
be a cat you can move from a cat to a
rabbit then in this enery that means you
can transform from one arbitrary
distribution to another arbitr
distribution and then they are they are
their position is just symmetric so then
conceptually you can swap them right so
so that's the first question the second
question is about um if I recall
correctly is about um the robotic
scenario so is there um a clear
objective
function yeah
that's yeah that's a good question I
think um it is more like a distinction
between reinforcement learning and
imitation learning or basically just
supervised learning so I think
conceptually we can always formulate the
problem as reinforcement learning that
is you just want to uh uh approach the
goal so let's say if the goal is to move
the t-shape object to the Target
location and then if you can do that you
have the reward if you can't do that you
you have nothing or your reward is zero
that that that's possible then imitation
learning or um supervised learning is
the other way so you you you try to give
some examples of what would be the
possible trajectory and then I try to
make make the
behavior um yeah I think I can take
questions offline um because I'm
overtime and let's move on to the next
talk
[Applause]