So, good morning. I'm Daniel Hastings,
uh, the current head of the MIT
Aereroastro department. Uh, today we
celebrate the, uh, 64th anniversary of
the first Lester Gardner lecture given
in 1959. The gardener lecture is made
possible by the request of the ma the
late major Lester Gardner a member of
the MIT class of 1898
to sponsor annual presentations on
aeronautical history. So we've broadened
it to aerospace.
Over the years we've been honored by
luminaries such as Igor Sikosski, Jimmy
Doolittle, Ivon Bril, Neil Armstrong to
name a few.
A remarkable individual, Major Gardner
played several critical roles in the
advancement of aviation in the early
years of the 20th century. Uh he
actually actually with the encouragement
of Grover uh loaning and Hunac and Glenn
Martin he uh organized the gardener
publishing company which published
aviation who's who which later became
aviation week which some of us read
every week.
In addition, he was the founder of the
Institute of Aeronautical Sciences,
which later became the Institute of
Aerospace Sciences, which became the
AIAA.
So, he had he had his hand in two very
big things. Uh, he was an air officer in
World War I, uh, the recipient of
numerous aeronautical awards, including
the Daniel Guggenheim Medal in 1947.
He was always interested in MIT wi which
continued throughout his life and he
helped establish this garden
lecturesship as well as the hunaca
professorship.
Uh with that as background I want to
turn our attention to our our speaker
today um colonel retired uh Pam Melroy
who is the NASA uh deputy administrator.
Now she Pam asked that I keep her her CV
very short. Okay. So, what can I say
about Pam? Um, she's uh flown uh many
aircraft uh in in the Air Force. As
deputy administrator, she performs the
duties and exercise the powers delegated
by the administrator.
Uh assist the administrator in making
final agency decisions, acts for the
administrator in his absence. Um she's
also responsible for laying out the AY's
vision and representing NASA to the
executive office of the president and
Congress, you know, and so on. She's
been an astronaut, has flown in space uh
three times, right? Three times, right?
Flew the shuttle up up in space, helped
assemble space station
uh and has worked with a DARPA, Loheed
Martin, a number of other places. But
most important, she's a graduate of MIT.
and we're very proud of her. So with
that, Pam, up to you.
>> Thank you so much. Uh it's really
wonderful to be back at MIT and uh I
really appreciate that brief
introduction. Uh Dan who is a treasure.
You are a treasure. I've enjoyed so much
working with you uh in the private
sector as well and uh thank you for your
leadership of the aereroastro
department. I do have to let everybody
know that I actually got my degree in
earth and planetary science here, not in
aereroastro. Uh but um I think uh you
know most of my career was spent doing
essentially aereroastro engineering. Uh
so I'm really happy in the position that
I'm in now that I have the opportunity
to have the science background to work
with the science mission directorate at
NASA as well as feeling very comfortable
with both aeronautics and space
technology. Um, so I've really been able
to achieve a lot of my dreams as a
result of the work, uh, that I was able
to do here at MIT. And so, um, you know,
extraordinarily impressive department,
uh, and activities going on. Loved the
pitchfest we just heard. It was, uh, it
was very impressive, actually, having
heard a lot of those things. There are
so many things I could talk to you about
today. Um, but I decided to pick
something that I think is extremely
important and perhaps provide a little
bit of context around that. And that is
our moon to Mars strategy. Uh I'm hoping
to talk for a little while, but uh I'd
also like to have a dialogue. I want to
take your questions because we have so
much stuff going on at NASA right now. I
won't come even close to discussing uh a
tenth of it, but uh to me, this is uh
very important. It's a critical aspect
of what we're doing.
So I do want to give a shout out uh to
MIT. Many of you maybe have seen this
picture of Margaret Hamilton who was the
lead for the guidance system development
uh software for Apollo uh and she was
right here at MIT and in fact it's just
fascinating as we go forward with
Artemis to realize essentially software
engineering was invented by Margaret and
her team just didn't exist as a
discipline before Apollo. Uh we needed
that. It's a great example of how the
technology investments that we make when
we do hard things actually spill off
into other areas. I think everyone's
familiar with Buzz Aldrin's thesis and
the work that he did as well, but I just
want to make a a special shout out to
Margaret because she's near and dear to
my heart. The fault detection,
isolation, and recovery algorithms were
absolutely critical. Um, you all
probably heard the, you know, we're all
turning blue down here, you know, kind
of thing. the overflight uh for Neil
Armstrong. But in fact, what was
happening was that the nav system was um
you know had a massive stack overflow.
Uh but Margaret's algorithm enabled the
flight to keep going because essentially
it dumped the stuff it didn't need. It
had a list of the things that it
absolutely had to have and then every
time the computer reset it carried over
the critical data to the next level
which allowed that that flight to
continue. So really truly extraordinary
work there.
Uh so I I hope you had the opportunity
to uh watch the Aremis launch either
real time and live or uh after the fact.
It was really impressive to be there. Um
one of the things that's interesting
about launching a rocket for the first
time, it's not just about the
technology, it's about the operations as
well. And so for us to figure out
signatures that we were seeing as we got
close to launch countdown, making sure
that we understood what was happening to
the vehicle, it took us a couple tries,
but we were thrilled. And the
performance of the rocket was absolutely
incredible. And uh one of my favorite
pictures uh in the upper right corner, I
think we're all used to seeing digital
images where people stack, you know,
several complicated things together.
That is actually not stacked. That is a
selfie uh in the upper right corner from
the solar array of Orion. So at the tip
of the solar array was a camera and
pointing back. Yes, that is the moon and
beyond it the earth. And that is a
real-time photo that was taken. Uh that
was just um I think phenomenally
inspiring for all of us to see real live
photos from the moon for the first time
in uh more than 50 years. So really
really phenomenal. So we're at a very
very special place in time. We've spent
the last decade of investments to get to
this point in having the transportation
system that will enable human beings to
go to deep space. Um I'm I'm going to be
very, you know, straightforward about
this. It has been a tough decade for
NASA. It's very hard to go into tech
development uh because you're not flying
hardware. So people are like where are
we? What's happening? There's nothing
happening. And uh in fact uh you know
space the investment takes a long time
to get to this point and uh the first
test flight was absolutely phenomenal.
Uh as a result of that there's been
changes in space policy and discussions
about what our destination was going to
be uh that have had an impact I think on
all of us. So NASA took an approach
which um I really was very supportive of
which is capabilities-based approach.
We're going to build the capability to
send humans into deep space and then
wherever anybody decides to send us, we
will be ready to do it. But I think
we're at a different place right now and
um especially with the uh announcement
that we made on Monday of the Artemis 2
crew. So the first crew uh that will go
into deep space in more than 50 years.
Uh really extraordinary. It's getting
real. It's getting very real. So we hope
to fly that mission by the end of 2024.
Uh right now the long pole in the tent
is actually a refurbishment of
electronics uh between Orion 1 and Orion
2. So uh that all those electronics were
pulled a few days ahead of schedule
actually and they are now at the vendor
uh for evaluation and understanding. But
some basic things like the fact that we
didn't get saltwater intrusion inside
the vehicle and things like that give us
hope that that we'll be able to to stick
to that schedule. Uh the next long pole
in the tent, there's a couple pieces of
the SLS uh manufacturer, but I was just
there last week at Mashe and saw uh the
Artemis 2 vehicle uh getting very very
close. So I think I think we're, you
know, in pretty good shape. Uh just like
in Apollo, we've got thousands of people
involved in this and thousands of people
invested in it. One of the things that
is uh unusual is uh and very different
from Apollo is that we were very focused
on going together internationally. So um
Jeremy Hansen, one of the crew members
is from Canada. Uh this is there could
be no more visible representation of the
difference between Artemis and Apollo
than this crew. Uh first of all, we have
a woman, we have a person of color, we
have a person from uh an international
partner. So it's it's very different,
but it's highly appropriate because
Apollo the after all the mission was to
send a man to the moon and return him
safely. That was it. What we found when
we got there was there was all kinds of
really interesting science and other
technology spin-offs as a result of
that. But really in the eyes of the
public and the stakeholders that was the
mission. We've got a different mission
now. Artemis is a very very different
purpose. It's actually about going out
into deep space with humans to stay. And
uh so I I love this picture just because
I think it's it's a critical part of the
story.
So uh and we're starting this year.
We're not waiting. Um, Capstone is uh in
the near rectal linear halo orbit that
we plan to put gateway which is our
orbiting logistics cache and uh
technology demonstrator and potentially
a jump off uh point for Mars that will
be uh put into orbit around the moon.
The problem is it's a very complicated
orbit. It's really interesting being an
astronaut because I have a strong
intuitive sense of low earth orbit
mechanics. I mean I just lived it. had
to fly three rendevous and dockings and
undockings with the space station. So,
it's just something that I really really
understand. I'll tell you what, I have
been struggling with the astronamics
around the moon because it's really a
three-body problem. Uh so much
influenced by the gravity of the earth,
but also much more influenced by the
gravity of the sun. So, um fantastically
challenging, especially as you look at
our destination, uh for Artemis is the
South Pole. much more difficult uh than
getting to the equator. Uh one of the
benefits of the NRO orbit is that it
will ensure that we have 100% comm uh at
all times for the crew, which I think is
really important. Um, one of the things
that was very interesting about Apollo,
if you go back and talk to those folks,
how they sweated it when the crew was on
the far side of the moon and how little,
you know, information there was no
information, especially when you're
making critical burns like a, you know,
uh, uh, the burn to get back into the
trajectory back to Earth. Um, all
happened on the far side of the moon.
So, Capstone is providing us really
critical information about that orbit
right now to really understand the
dynamics better. I mean we certainly got
the theory. Um we know a lot about the
earth's gravitational field from all the
satellites that have been operating
here. It's a lot more complex with the
moon and in particular that threebody
dynamics. So that data is going to be
critical because it will help us operate
gateway more efficiently.
And then this year we'll be landing
through the commercial lunar payload
services multiple science and technology
payloads on the surface of the moon.
many of them to support uh important
decal recommendations around science but
many also to pave the way for Aremis and
for crude missions uh because we really
want to be doing science and technology
with our astronauts on the surface of
the moon that's what they do best so um
this is uh you know very exciting I
think from my standpoint see the more
hardware we can see on the moon as early
as possible that is actually also very
helpful for all of
First of all, it paves the way and helps
us understand what we're going to do.
But I think we can also send a very
different message to all of our
stakeholders, which is we're here to
stay. This isn't just a camping trip,
boots on the moon, and return home.
So, I'd like to talk about the moon for
a moment. One of the things that we like
to say is 50 years ago, we went to the
moon. So, what's different? Well, first
of all, the moon is different. I talked
about going to the south pole of the
moon. So the previous exploration of the
moon was all in the equatorial region
and of course the south pole of the moon
is a very interesting place. Uh the
technology and the science
demonstrations uh that finding out that
in the deeply shadowed regions of the
south pole we have the potential to find
water. We still don't know how much
exactly or where the optimum places are.
So we really have a lot of work to do
there. But uh it's it's very different
geologically uh and it's a very
different place from any place that
we've ever explored before. Then you add
on to it that we're different. Our
technical capabilities, the things that
we know how to do, the science that we
know how to do and the exploration is
completely different. We have learned so
much. I mean, if you look back at the
history of the space shuttle, um, we had
the opportunity to fly an orbiting
laboratory and also manufacture a space
station, repair the Hubble and deploy
it, of course. Uh, but we learned a lot,
but it was a tantalizing amount of
science that we got out of the space
shuttle. And if you're going to operate
a national lab only about six times a
year for about 10 days to two weeks at a
time, sooner or later you're going to
decide you need more more science, more
data. And that's why we built the
International Space Station, so that we
could do science 365 days a year. But in
addition to that, we learned how to
sustain and support humans and the
science that they are doing for much
longer periods of time. And that is
absolutely critical as we go out into
the solar system. So our capabilities
are not the same. What we have learned
is not the same. It is in fact a new
moon.
One of the things that I get asked uh a
lot is please help those of us who
intuitively know why space is important
and why space exploration is important.
How do we explain that? How do we
explain that to the average American or
or indeed the average citizen of Earth?
So um together with our senior leaders
at the agency, we put together this why
chart and it's the the uh the structure
is around explaining some of that. So
I'll start with science front and center
and I think that's critically important.
Science is the seed corn for our
technical capabilities of the future. We
all understand that the scientific
research that we do today leads to
technological breakthroughs in 10, 20 or
even 50 years and that's very very
important. So it is the seed corn
we can get unique science from space
that cannot be done anywhere else. One
example of that for great example is the
James Webb Space Telescope operating in
frequencies and at levels of sensitivity
not achievable here on earth. Uh there
is no way that we could look back in
time to just a few hundred million years
after the big bang and really understand
the formation of the universe without
going to space. But in addition to that,
especially as we've seen on the shuttle
and station is the microgravity uh
science that we do gives us amazing
insights into biological and physical
sciences. It's extraordinary when you
take gravity out of the equation. The
second and third order effects that we
have learned that will enable us to do
things like have more efficient fluid
flow and combustion here on the earth.
the insights into the human body. Uh why
is it that our astronauts are dehydrated
but they are not subject uh to
substantial higher percentages of kidney
stones is a great example of the kind of
critical research that we can only do in
microgravity. And of course there's no
way to look at the earth as a system
except from space. You simply cannot get
enough terrestrial sensors to understand
what is happening to our climate. And in
fact 80% of the data that we use to
understand uh climate change and what's
happening to the climate comes from
space. If we're going to have a prayer
of measuring the impacts of the things
we hope to do, we have to do it from
space. Science is front and center.
Second, national posture. That's uh a
big umbrella. uh it can talk about
things like uh uh national geopolitical
posture but I think more importantly
it's the capabilities of a country to do
science and technology. So I mentioned
Margaret Hamilton and software
engineering. There's multiple other
examples. I think most people are
familiar with at least one spin-off uh
from NASA the uh the camera in your cell
phone which was developed uh to put a
camera on a chip for earth sensing. Um,
there are so many examples. There are
countless examples. But the point being,
as President Kennedy said so many years
ago, the point is to do it because it's
hard. And so when we do hard things, we
lift the technical and scientific
capability of our country to attack
multiple problems. And increasingly with
a growing commercial space industry, the
economic impact is significant. This is
a high-tech, high- growth industry. And
all around the world, countries are
starting space agencies because they
don't want to get left behind on the
impact of space. And in fact, space is
impacting so many other industries now.
Agriculture, maritime, homeland
security.
I often speculate that uh 35 years ago
there were a lot of people saying, well,
what is this internet thing and will it
really have an impact on my industry? Uh
I think in 30 years we we will not be
asking a question about what the
relevance of space is to other
industries.
And finally inspiration. It's the way
you feel when you see that picture from
the James Webb Space Telescope or the
Hubble Space Telescope. But importantly
this is attacking the other issue our
other seed corn issue which is the
pipeline of STEM students for the
future. Space really plays a unique role
in inspiring people, making them think
about their place in the universe, but
also providing excitement and relevance
for problems of the future that focus
students on investing in STEM. So these
are the three buckets, if you will, that
I think are absolutely critical. So uh
when administrator Nelson and I came to
the agency, I was spending a lot of time
thinking about our moon to Mars
strategy. And maybe it's because I was a
physics major, but to me, these are our
first principles. Anything we build in a
strategy has to address all three of
these areas. And the reason is that as I
go around the world, I often meet people
who only care about one or two of those
buckets. They don't care about all
three. Some do. Uh what that means
though is that if we don't have a
strategy that addresses all three areas,
we are missing key stakeholders. And if
you want a politically resilient
approach to human space flight and
exploration for the future, you're going
to have to hit all three of these things
and stay laser focused on it.
So, uh you may have heard a lot of
arguments, maybe you've uh proposed them
and I'm happy to discuss them and um
that has to do with uh you know what are
we doing? So there's um you hear all
kinds of things like well we should be
just doing science and we should be
doing it all robotically that that's you
know more cost-effective. Uh I've also
heard you know why do we need gateway?
Uh why are why don't we just go to Mars
first etc etc. Well, um, we don't have a
decal survey for human space flight the
way science does where you gather input
from the broadest set of communities
about what what it is that needs what
are the critical science questions that
need to be resolved. So when I came to
the agency, I brought us all together.
Um, I found an organization that was
made up of the highest technical leaders
called the federated board and said,
"Okay, we've done a lot of work on this.
we we actually know what we need to do
to get to Mars. Um let's talk about it.
What capabilities do we actually need to
develop? And by the way, what are we
actually trying to do? So um this is the
challenge that I gave the team. I said,
I want us to create a blueprint for
sustained human presence and exploration
throughout the solar system.
It's really important. I think if you
ask the average American, what is the
job of NASA? That would be it. This is
what we've all been waiting for, right?
We've got to figure this out and we need
to develop that blueprint by practicing
it on the moon so that we can then go
demonstrated on Mars and then go on to
the next destination after that. So
every single word in that statement
means something very important. Uh I'll
start out with talking about science. So
sustained human presence, why is that
important? Well, as we uh have learned
from the space station, having science
247 is actually the best way to get your
return on investment.
So, it's okay if we're going to go to
the moon, it's a three-day trip or so,
maybe maybe a week, spend 30 days doing
science, and then three days coming
home. That's actually not a bad return
on investment. Anywhere else in the
solar system, the numbers get really bad
really fast. So, even Mars, at the best
that we can hope for, six months there,
30-day stay, probably about a nine month
trip home, you're kind of looking at a
two-year trip for 30 days of science.
Now, that's okay for a test flight, but
that's not actually how we are going to
get the maximum science return. So we
really need to think about how to get a
sustained presence and we need to be
incorporating science from the very
beginning. The extraordinary knowledge
that we gained from the samples of the
moon uh that our Apollo astronauts
returned that was not the original
purpose of that program. It was just to
go and come back. But it was incredible.
I mean, those those samples are
unbelievable in what they've taught us
about the history of the Earth, the
history of the moon, and the history of
the solar system. So, we really need to
be incorporating science front and
center. And I'm really excited to say
that everyone is on board with that, and
we're making significant progress in
that area.
Transportation and habitation, that's
the one we've made all that progress on
in the last 10 years. Uh, but we have a
lot more to go. We need to be looking at
transportation systems on the surface of
the moon. Uh when I talk about
maximizing science return, one of my
favorite statistics is actually not that
long ago, I think it was about four or
five months ago, the the all of the the
sum total of the distance traveled by
all the rovers on Mars finally exceeded
the last four missions of Apollo. So
finally after 25 years and those those
four short missions to the moon when you
send humans they bring transportation
they bring a lot of power and they bring
this your brain. So we can get a lot
more science by using human machine
teameming but they have to have the
ability to get there and to stay alive
and to be uh transported around
infrastructure. So my point about humans
doing science in space long term, we
have to develop the human infrastructure
to support humans to stay for longer
durations in deep space. NASA needs
that. If we're going to get the science
return on investment, we have to have
the communications backbone. We have to
have the power. We have to have landing
sites. We have to have all of the things
that support humans for a long period of
time. But excitingly here on Earth,
infrastructure enables new business
models. We see that every day. It's not
just roads, our aircraft system. Uh in
addition to that, of course, the
internet is a key piece of
infrastructure, our power grids, all of
those things enable the business models
around us. So if we make the investments
in demonstrating scalable and
cost-effective infrastructure to support
humans, we know the economic business
will follow us.
And finally, operations. Greatly
overlooked, not by me as an operator. I
lived through the transition between uh
operating the space shuttle for short
duration missions and the transition to
long duration missions on the
international space station. Very very
very different. We had a lot of things
to learn about human health and
performance and how to optimize our
operations. We're going to have to start
all over from scratch doing science on
the on the surface of another celestial
body. We have much to learn in
operations.
So when I challenged the federated
board, they brought together a set of
objectives in these four different
buckets. They said, "What do we need to
learn, understand, and prove to be ready
to go to Mars?" So, I think it's really
important to see that this actually
transcends a lot of the arguments in a
lot of ways. We can show that we have a
very clear path from the moon to Mars as
a result of these objectives.
Just like to talk for a moment about
science and human machine teameing. Um
to me this is actually uh a very very
exciting new technology area. I've been
interested in it since I worked at DARPA
and even before uh the concept that we
are actually going to maximize the
capability of our to do exploration but
also to do science by the right
optimization
and uh you know we all know what
machines are good at and we also know
what humans are good at. Probably the
toughest technical problem of all is
figuring out how to partner them and how
to create an architecture that actually
leverages the capabilities. I think we
just barely scratched the surface, but
it was very exciting for me in the last
planetary decal where they proposed a
mission with a a little rover on the
surface of the moon going around uh
crater a crater on the south pole and
picking up geological samples from
multiple areas that we know from uh from
remote sensing um have very interesting
geological properties and then
delivering them to the crew for return.
Now, the astronaut crew said, "Wait,
we're scientists, too." So, uh, one of
the things that I think we need to look
at is how to maximize the human element
as well. I mean, it's great. Let's get
10 times as many samples as we actually
have room to come home and then give our
astronauts handheld tools. Um, maybe
they'll be using a helmet visor uh
eventually on Mars, maybe with operating
a helicopter for remote sensing as well.
But the idea being that uh we can use
humans to select the right sample. So I
have this dream that there's a scientist
uh looking through the helmet visor uh
looking at the samples with handheld uh
uh you know mass spectrograph and etc.
And then everybody in the back room
jumping up and down and saying bring
home number seven. That's the sample we
want. So I really think we can we can
learn how to maximize science by
efficiently understanding how to do
human machine teameing.
So I want to make the point that it's to
me that's very important which is that
uh this moon to strategy that we've been
working on is really really aimed at
trying to figure out how to maximize the
crossover. Now it is true that Mars is a
very different destination but I think
my point is everywhere is going to be a
unique destination in the solar system.
Instead we need to develop a framework
this blueprint for how do we do this?
What order do we do things in? How do we
efficiently figure out how to operate
those things? We can work the technical
differences between the moon and Mars.
that's perfectly okay because we're
going to have to do that at every
destination we go to. It's having this
overarching framework that is so
important. So this moon to Mars strategy
has been done in consultation with
industry uh with our international
partners. We held workshops last year.
Uh we had a public comment period. I
hope some of you contributed to that.
Um, and I'm excited that um, at the
National Space Symposium, we will be
rolling out the results of our first
architecture concept review. Now, I'm
going to set expectations here with
regards to that. A lot of this was
actually a bringing about the whole
agency together, all of the mission
directorates to talk about this moon to
strategy and what we what needs to be in
the architecture.
We think that the objectives will be
enduring. We will certainly review them
as we learn new things. But what won't
be enduring is the state of the
architecture. The architecture will have
to evolve as we have new technologies
and new learning. We know that some
technology will not work as well as we
hope that it did. There will be new
capabilities that come online. And so
every year we plan to have an
architecture concept review and then we
will have a public consultation period
to go through and have inputs. In
particular, one of the ways that we're
communicating is there will be a series
of white papers that talk about the
trades because I hear this all the time.
Well, I did the math and the delta V for
this and so forth. This is a systems
engineering problem. So every single
element of the architecture has massive
trades involved in behind it. But we
need to do a better job about
communicating that especially with our
technical community who can identify the
flaws in our trades or remind us about
new technologies, show us new ways of
doing business. So I think that's the
critical difference. We we have been
talking about this technical um
activities trying to get to Mars for a
very very long time. I think what's
really different about the moon tomorrow
strategy that we have now is uh that
it's trying to bring across all of our
stakeholders. We're trying to focus on
science, national technical capability
and of course inspiration which the
great thing is that that comes with that
especially when you're sending humans
but also when you're doing worldclass
amazing science as we have seen with all
the things that we're doing.
So, we um don't know and we won't know
if this is a politically resilient
approach. Uh but I think it's really
important to bring the whole community
along to make sure that all stakeholders
are consulted. It's really important
that you participate and uh keep track
of this. I want to hear your good ideas.
Uh we will be rolling out what that
consultation process looks like. I'll
let you know this one is going to be
really tight this year. And the reason
why is we made the decision uh to try to
work on a process for this architecture
concept review and then rolling out the
the stakeholder reviews uh discuss the
architecture and then start into the
next rev. We need to get it aligned with
the budget cycle. So our next ACR is
going to be in November so that it will
inform the ne the following budget cycle
which is really helpful but there's not
a lot of time till November because it
took us a lot of time to get to this
first uh architecture. So um I think I
think we'll see a better cadence going
forward. Uh but I just want you to keep
your eyes open for that because we
really care and we want you to
participate in it. Uh I think uh we have
to find a way to bring new ideas in
faster.
So with that uh that was what I wanted
to focus on today was to talk about our
moon tomorrow strategy. Uh but I'm very
happy to take your questions on anything
you want to ask.
So we have a microphone that will move
around here with for questions from the
audience and there are also people
online who are asking questions. So
great. So, okay. So, let's start. Does
have anybody here who has any questions?
>> Hey, Pam. Uh, excellent talk. Uh, so my
name is Eric and I work in the
mechanical engineering department and
I'm sure a lot of us here are working on
really exciting, you know, new projects
that are hopefully aligned with Artemis
and some of these future missions.
>> And one of the questions I had had to do
with um, a lot of our technologies are
probably like low TRL. Um, and you just
talked about how we're trying to
accelerate or bring, you know,
technologies quicker into these space
missions. Could you go into a little bit
more detail about what NASA is trying to
plan to do in order to, I guess you
could say, alleviate some of the red
tape from a technology perspective?
>> Yeah. Oh, it's worse than red tape, my
friend. Um
so it was very instructive for me to
work at DARPA for four years because uh
we used to say technology transition is
a combat sport and it is indeed there's
huge barriers to technology transition
and often they are not actually about
the technology. Uh we I think I'm really
glad that uh the space technology
mission directorate was formed um in the
uh Obama administration. Actually, Dava,
where is Dava? Yeah, there she is. Thank
you, Dava.
Um because having our own technology
development organization inside NASA
theoretically makes tech transfer
easier. theoretically uh even even in
the science mission directorate which
does tech development for science
missions it is still incredibly
challenging so uh for for me a key part
was actually to bring the agency
technical leadership together to have
that discussion you can understand the
operational perspective of don't don't
don't give me that right I'm trying to
keep my astronauts alive so uh I think
uh we are just in the first stages of
really trying to figure out and get
people used to the idea we need to do a
lot more techdev and um you know I
really really interesting discussions
actually with some of the stakeholders
for example around nuclear propulsion in
space well you don't need a Mars
transport vehicle until the next decade
why are you doing that now well because
we have to do the development
demonstration programs so that we can do
an analysis of alternatives and have
enough information this is something
that DoD does really well they they
really understand that that pipeline has
to exist I think because especially in
human space flight the scale uh is so
long that I don't think this is a part
of our DNA yet. Um, so the, you know, I
think the big, uh, area that the
administrator and I feel very strongly
about is to grow STMD's budget because
they are where all of that tech
development needs to be. And I'm pushing
them to make sure that at least 10% of
their portfolio is very low TRL. So
that's just kind of a best practice
across the federal government that you
have to have the uh tech investments in
the very low TRL things and about 10% is
about right because they tend to be lab
demonstrations and then you need to have
uh the money to take it to a TRL6
demonstration. So I don't know if that
helps answer your question about what is
that strategy.
>> Great. Thank you. So do we have any
online questions?
>> No. Okay,
over there.
>> Hi Pam, nice to speak to you again. Uh,
for those who don't know, my name is
Justin Chio. I am a uh aereroastro
undergraduate senior. Uh, and what I
want to know is has NASA taken into
consideration um what they are going to
do and how we're going to have an
improve a better architecture given the
limiting factors of the launch rate of
SLS
>> given that we're can only send four
astronauts per year. Yeah, thanks
Justin. I think one of the things that's
really interesting about um coming into
the agency is realizing that um we
actually are have almost no capability
to change anything in the next three
years. What you're really doing is
you're setting yourself up for the next
decade. And so I hopefully you saw that
out of the moon to Mars strategy. And
the same thing is true of the budget
cycle. I mean, we just, you know, got
our 2024 budget um that is not even
approved yet. It's just the president's
budget out on the street. So, uh you
know, we have the vehicle. We're focused
right now on getting the flight rate up
uh to a cadence of once a year. We think
that's absolutely critical uh both for
technical u making technical progress,
but also for political resiliency as
well. So, that's our the focus of our
area. We're restructuring the contract
for SLS right now. Um, interestingly,
uh, we do think that there are other
customers. DoD wanted no part of SLS
because they were afraid they were going
to get asked for, um, money.
>> Yeah. So, you know that, right? On the
other hand, they're quite interested in
having access to the capability once
developed. So uh what we are hoping is
that that will enable us to make some
investments in infrastructure and
potentially theoretically it's possible
to launch three a year theoretically. Uh
it could it will take a while to get
there and we'll need the the customer
additional customers to make sure that
that happens but we uh are working right
now with industry to hand over SLS to
become a service. Right now there is no
mechanism for DoD to use SLS because
it's 100% NASA owned in the way it's
structured. So having it spun off as a
commercial service capability we hope
will enable us to to do that more cost-e
effectively. And of course I think um
you know new technologies uh are
certainly out there. I personally don't
think there's anything that well I mean
it's ridiculous. We put a huge amount of
investment in it and we've proven that
it's capable and we're going to launch a
crew on it. Nothing else close to that
yet. So I think uh but you know as it
happens we'll have a concept review once
a year and hopefully new ideas will come
forward.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, there was a question back there.
>> Uh thank you. Um my name is Dan and I'm
a a graduate researcher at astroy and I
wanted to thank you first of all for
this um inspiring lecture. My question
relates to your chart on the why and
benefits to humanity, which is a
question I often ask myself. I'm curious
how you see the exploitation of space
research and microgravity research over
the coming decade considering that by
2030 the ISS is meant to be
decommissioned and Lunar Gateway is
going to be significantly smaller. So I
wonder how you see that sort of
industrial exploitation of microgravity
manufacturing and research.
I really didn't pay him to ask that
question, but I'm super glad you asked.
Um, that's one of the other things that
we're spending a lot of our energy on
right now. Um, so this is something that
just isn't widely known. So, thank you
for the opportunity to talk about it. We
are in the second decal research uh
effort or decal uh study program for
biological and physical sciences in
microgravity. So that kind of comes as a
surprise to a lot of people um how how
really focused we are on that science.
We are actually just really hitting our
stride in the science on ISS and what's
coming from it and some of the
industrial research that's going on as
well which you don't hear as much about
because it's proprietary and trade
secret. Um but extraordinary work. So,
we're very confident uh that
microgravity research has a long place
that there's a lot more work to be done
and we're just really beginning to to
get a hold of that. So, ISS has been
extended through 2030, but we're working
with four companies right now for a
commercial LEO destination. So, I have
to say ISS was amazing. I mean, I helped
build it, but we didn't know what we
were doing. We took our best guess and
it was a prototype space station and a
lot of the technical capabilities on
station are amazing and we use them over
and over and wish we'd done like 10
times more of it. And then there are
things that just didn't work the way we
thought they were going to. So, we've
learned a lot and I think our focus
right now is working with those four
companies to transition that knowledge
and they're out there trying to raise
capital and we're raising some in uh
we're getting some investment money as
well uh to put into their activities to
help them prepare for commercial LEO
destinations.
I personally think that Gateway is not
an ideal place for microgravity
research. It's a deep space research
location, right? things beyond low Earth
orbit. So microgravity you can get
pretty close to home. Uh the deep space
is is much harder to get. We should
really be focused on the kind of
research that can only be done in deep
space and supports us going to Mars with
humans uh forward in the future on
gateway and that's why it's going to be
much smaller.
>> Yeah, a question here.
>> Hi Pam, thank you for the talk. My name
is Evan Kramer. I'm a third-year
graduate student in the department
astro. My question is uh in terms of
Mars sample return. Um I'm curious about
your perspective of the importance of
simultaneously developing Mars
technology TRLs while also trying to
focus on lunar exploration and what
efforts are happening to make sure that
TRL development for Mars exploration is
feeding into TRL development for moon
exploration.
>> Yeah, that's a complicated question. as
I pointed out you know that the previous
chart that I had uh there are there are
differences and there are strong
similarities uh particularly around
infrastructure
uh I think you know the ISRU is going to
be its own thing uh having said that
there's you know the foundations of ISRU
is actually power I mean it is
staggering how much power is needed for
ISRU so when I look at as a a techdev
effort I mean humans you know we're
operating space station on 110 kilowatt
uh ISRU 2 to 5 megaww. So a very very
very challenging problem uh by
comparison. So uh a lot of that
foundational work is going to apply in
both cases. Um and you know I I look at
it and say without the power we're not
going to get any of those tech
demonstrations done or have any of those
those capabilities. So for for the near
term anyway, especially with our limited
budget, we're focused on those really
big rocks, which most of them you see
here. Without those things, uh we won't
have the other capabilities that we
need. It is very interesting. You may
have seen that um the science mission
directorate recently released a draft
strategy for Mars exploration. So we
went through a very interesting
discussion about their Mars uh strategy
and the moon to Mars strategy and how
they feed together. The linkage is
really around the decal survey which
really drives the science mission
directorate. Um moon to Mars is very
challenging because it's beyond a decade
and so that was actually part of what
motivated them to look beyond a decade
for their strategy. So we really see
these two streams converging. Uh I think
the Mars sample return is critical to us
because it will guide where we plan to
send humans I think on Mars. So there
there is a lot of discussion in the
agency about how to converge our science
strategy with the human spaceflight
strategy. I hope that helps.
>> We have any online questions?
>> Yes, I was just going to say we have an
online question who's wondering if the
architecture review process will
eventually be applied to other aspects
of NASA. Um, for example, aviation
concepts that may benefit from further
transparency and development.
>> Boy, if I had a nickel for every time
somebody said, "We love your moon to Mar
strategy. Do it for everything." And uh,
all I can say is that it took like a
100% of my time and energy over the last
two years to get here. It's exciting to
have the validation of the process. I
think the key elements to it are around
communications
uh around bringing um unity of purpose
inside the agency but also in the
broader uh tech community and um you
know strategy development is uh a unique
thing um there's a lot of actually great
if there's anybody who also has a
business degree you you you know that um
I see many strategies quote unquote
strategies that are lists of good things
to do that is not a strategy. That's not
how it works. So, um I do think that
that uh strategic thinking approach is
critically important. I have to say I am
pretty happy uh and I'm very picky about
this with our tech strategy and both
STMD and aeronautics. What I'm not as
happy about I think that got brought out
is how well we communicate about it. So,
one of the things that aeronautics is
doing that I really like is building a
community of practice around advanced
air mobility and uh through the
workshops, the roundts and that kind of
consultation. I think um we're beginning
to see a lot more of that transparency,
we're going to extend that out for all
the tremendous work that we're doing
around decarbonizing aviation in
aeronautics as well. But it is
interesting. Um, for those of you who
are engineers, talking about
communications is usually not the top of
their list, but it's actually really,
really important.
>> Actually, you know, we do have a
communications requirement for
undergraduates.
>> Glad to hear it.
>> Precisely so they can communicate.
>> Well, your your pitchfest showed that
it's working. So,
>> any other questions?
>> We have a cover.
Can you raise your number? All the way
over there.
>> Thank you so much for your talk. Uh my
name is Clara and I'm an exchange
student from Imperial College London.
And so you touched upon a lot of
interesting topics. Uh my question
pertains to the fact that there's a
growing competition of a what I would
say is like a dwidening set of mineral
resources out there. I mean I think uh
the semiconductor industry is pretty
symptomatic of that and all of this is
happening against an increasingly
unfavorable political backdrop. And so
what I wanted to know is how is that
impacting design decisions considering
that pretty much every single space
project is really a long-term project.
You talked that you said that moon to
Mars was basically beyond a decade. So a
lot happens in 10 years and yeah
basically how is that getting factored
into I guess the strategy overall? Yeah,
I think the short answer is that it's
not. Um, I would say, you know, my sense
of the aerrow uh aerospace industry
large
uh as you know, electronics in
particular are an area that is typically
four generations behind what we use
terrestrially uh because of the
requirements for uh radiation
uh tolerance and exposure and uh
qualification. So I think um the way
we're addressing this issue inside NASA
is really driven more by uh I would say
the larger issue of global supply chain.
So um you know what I discovered when I
came to NASA is that we had different
people thinking about supply chain. So
we had the engineering organization
looking at from a like a quality risk
standpoint. Safety had their own lens.
uh the same thing around counterfeit
parts and things like that. Um I don't
think we had a very consistent approach
from a procurement standpoint. So uh we
formed uh an informal supply chain
working group just to enable awareness
of all the different things that were
happening at NASA around this and we're
also strengthening our relationships
with DoD. Uh interestingly DoD has
different supply chain issues than we
do. they tend to buy at much larger
scale than we do. Uh we have we have
more one-offs. So we're thinking about
that. Uh we can often plan ahead more.
Uh what we have learned is we've been
doing a good job inside the agency.
Okay, this mission got delayed. We need
this this part that was purchased for
that program, but they're delayed.
Somebody else needs it now. We're going
to do a swap across programs. The next
step is to start do that doing that with
DoD where we're actually broadening that
pool and that approach to it. We're also
really finding out that a lot of the
data is anecdotal. So, uh, we're
building a single tool that will bring
all of the information about the, you
know, critical risk and so forth and
have that actually at the front end of
procurement planning. So, this is the
dream. We're not there yet, but the
dream is that we can actually project
out our procurements over the next 10
years and say maybe it would be better
to do a bulk buy in a certain area for
certain type of technologies and um you
know get consistency for industry which
is really good for them uh but also
better planning for ourselves. Critical
minerals is going to be really
interesting long term. I think it's a
great point. I think it'll take a while
before it hits the space industry really
hard.
Okay, final question.
>> Oh, Jeff gets the last word.
>> Is it an astronaut question?
>> Well, no.
>> He's not going to ask me about flying in
space.
>> Although I mentioned some people I was
on the selection committee when when we
picked you.
>> Were you? I don't think I remember.
>> And I'm glad we we made a good decision.
But look, this has to a lot a lot of
people ask me about, you know, what are
the Chinese doing? Does it have an
impact on NASA? I know there's political
sensitivities, but I'm I'm sure a lot of
people here would love to hear your
thoughts on that.
>> Yeah, I think um you know uh so for
those of you who are not aware, there is
something called the Wolf Amendment.
It's a a law that was passed that said
that NASA can't work bilaterally with
China except under certain conditions.
And in fact, we are working bilaterally
on a very few small number of things. Uh
one example of that is we are exchanging
in ephemeris data on our spacecraft
around Mars uh to make sure that we are
deconlicting um activities around Mars.
That's a great example. We just there's
a barrier and a threshold that you have
to prove uh that critical technology is
not being transferred. Um but it does
make it a lot harder for us to work with
China. Um obviously we have a great and
long-standing relationship with Russia
and have since 1975 and that's a in a
very different place. Um I think there
there are challenges in that area. Uh
the the difficult part for us is a an
extreme lack of transparency around what
is exactly happening in the Chinese
space program. Um I mean you know NASA
you can go online and get information
about anything. There's a lot of
information out there about each one of
our missions and uh and then we also
have a commitment to open science and
publishing our results and and sharing
them publicly uh and sharing the data
publicly. Um which is also uh we don't
find very many international partners
that have quite the open science
standards that we do. um there's
typically a period of time at least
where it's protected and only the
researchers from the country uh of
origin get access to that data and uh we
feel particularly in climate science
this is so critical we need to get that
data out to anybody who can find a good
use for it. So that's probably one of
the biggest barriers for us in in
working with there's some really key
philosophical differences on the happy
side. We have so many part we've got
partnerships
um I think we have agreements with like
63 countries around the world. So that's
an amazing number if you think about it
and most of them are in science. Uh but
it is it is really phenomenal and I
think um that that is just critical to
us going forward. If we're going to go
out into the solar system, we're going
to go as humanity. We're going to go as
partners. We're going to go as
representatives of Earth, not of any one
country.
All right. Thank you very much for such
a great talk.