welcome to the afternoon session we have
three wonderful Talks by three wonderful
students uh Noah is a student of Anor
and C uh you tell us about start telling
us about
watermarks great thanks um and thanks
for the invitation um so I'm going to be
talking about edit distance robust
watermarks um and this is Joint work
with
Anker okay so in recent years there's
been a lot of uh significant increase in
AI generated content there's been
studies which show that it takes up say
you know maybe half the internet and
there's been various problems or
potential problems associated with this
so for instance um there's potentially
issues in terms of say people editing
Wikipedia
um there's also evidence that it
training Ai and AI generated content is
potentially worse than generating
unnatural content and finally there's
concerns about
misinformation so in light of all this
um there's uh been a lot of anxiety both
in the media and in the government and a
few years ago the White House released
an executive order on trustworthy
development and use of AI and this
executive order outlined numerous
potential mitigations for some of this
increase in AI generated content and one
of them was ways of labeling synthetic
content such as using water
marking and that's going to be the
subject of this
talk okay so in particular I'm going to
talk about what are marking language
models and let me first tell you what a
language model is it's defin over
vocabulary which I'll call Sigma which
is a set of possible tokens a token in
general is a subword unit or some unit
of a word but for this talk just think
of token as being synonymous with
word and a language model specifies the
probability distribution of the I token
in a
sequence given preceding tokens I'll
call T1 through tius one and so in
particular we'll call the probability
that the I token TI is equal to any
value x given the preceding tokens T1
through TI minus1 model of TI equal x
given T1 through IUS one and so as one
example we can look at uh say gpt2 if we
feed the sequence of tokens about DNA on
the left hand side
here the to the model gpt2 will output
the distribution over tokens which is
shown on the right so DNA is the most
likely next token in some of the other
ones are
shown now to any language model is a
canonical generation procedure which
samples the tokens in sequence as
follows so at each step I I'm going to
sample token Ti from the model's next
token distribution given the preceding
ones that have already sampled and I'll
do this for a total of capital L steps
so in particular L will denote the
length of the model output and I'm going
to assume for Simplicity that it's
fixed this is roughly speaking how you
know Chach BT works
now the goal is to come up with water
marking schemes for language
models and roughly speaking a water
marking scheme is a way of embedding a
subtle pattern in the language model's
output so that a few properties
hold the first property formalizes the
idea that we don't want the watermark to
significantly degrade the quality of the
language
model and so in particular we're going
to aim for this property known as
undetectability
which means that roughly speaking the
output of the watermarked language model
looks like the output of the true
language model and I'll be more formal
about this in a few
minutes the second property is
robustness which means that the water
marking scheme should work namely that
it allows us to detect that the output
was
watermarked even after an adversary
comes along and makes some perturbations
to the language model output so if we
ask chat GPT for an essay and then we
come along maybe add some words delete
some sentences you name it then as long
as we don't make too many perturbations
we should still be able to detect this
edited essay as being
watermarked the third property is
soundness which means that if we were to
write the essay on our
own namly not use this language model to
generated then it should not be detected
as watermarked in other words we're not
falsely accusing anyone of producing
output uh from this watermarked model
they didn't
okay so that's the rough idea of how a
water marking scheme works now let me
give you a little bit more of a formal
definition so formally speaking a water
marking scheme consists of three
algorithms a key generation algorithm a
water marking Al algorithm and a
detection
algorithm so the key generation
algorithm outputs a secret key at random
which you can just think of as a
sequence of
bits the watermarking algorithm takes as
input the secret
key as as well as a prompt such as the
question what is DNA and it outputs a
sequence of tokens or text and this
sequence of tokens will have some
pattern embedded within which should um
allow us to detect later on that it's
actually
watermarked now how do we actually
detect this well there's a detection
algorithm which takes as input some
sequence of tokens such as that output
by the language model as well as the
secret key that we generated and it
outputs a single bit denoting whether or
not we detect that this sequence has
been watermarked
okay so now let me formally Define these
three criteria I um discussed earlier on
so the first criteria is undetectability
and formally speaking what we want is
that if we were to fix a prompt and ask
the language model for multiple samples
of the output of the watermark algorithm
multiple independent samples then no
polinomial time distinguishing algorithm
should be able to distinguish this group
of multiple samples from multiple
samples from the true language
model in other words these two
distributions are computationally
indistinguishable and a Cory of this
requirement is that if we have any
quality metric which is computable by a
polinomial Time algorithm then the
quality metric will be the same for our
watermarked algorithm and for the true
language model so this establishes that
we're not degrading the quality of the
language model
now how do we formally Define
robustness well what we want is that if
we take any prompt as well as a secret
key generated at
random ask our water marking algorithm
for a sample of text and then pass this
through some noisy an adversarial noisy
Channel which introduces a constant
fraction of edits namely insertions
deletions or substitutions at each
position then as long as this constant
fraction isn't that large the detection
algorithm should still output water with
high
probability the final property is
soundness which means that if we fix any
sequence of tokens independent of the
secret key distribution and we pass this
sequence of tokens to the detection
algorithm then it should output not
water marked with high
probability and so together these three
properties of undetectability edit
robustness and soundness constitute uh
what I'll call a water marking scheme in
this
talk and there's been a decent amount of
work in recent years um both in theory
and in practice on getting water marking
schemes which satisfy some combination
of these properties and I'll highlight a
few examples on this
slide so one line of work that started
with some uh paper by Chris gon and
zamir a few years ago was also um follow
up by zamir and few other papers as
well show that there's water marking
schemes which satisfy undetectability
and
soundness but not quite edit robustness
their water marking schemes are only
robust to a subc constant fraction of
edits namely a fraction of edits which
decays as the length of the text goes to
infinity and really we want to get
waterm Maring schemes which are more
robust say to a constant fraction edit
so uh basically we're modifying you know
some fixed fraction of the language
model text like
5% and there subsequent Works which did
get stronger robustness properties for
instance a paper by Ki padal showed a
water marking scheme that's edit robust
um and sound but it did not
satisfy as strong undetectability
guarantees it only satisfied a weaker
property known as Distortion freeness
which roughly speaking states that the
distribution of a single sample output
from the language model is
indistinguishable from a single sample
output from The Watermark model the
problem with Distortion free watermark
is that they might suffer from
diversities you could have a watermark
which always outputs the same response
to a certain prompt this will be
Distortion free but it's maybe not very
useful because we often want more
diversity in the language model
outputs yep I understand that your
undetectability is a very strong notion
that implies a bunch of but a weaker
notion might suffice right and and is
the is the weaker notion these people
look at sort of how should I say it's
meaningful um it's it's meaningful for
like maybe certain tasks like if you
kind of have like a maybe like a factual
question you're asking and uh you know
if if you wanted to describe some some
fact maybe there's only you really only
care about like a single sample from
this but maybe imagine you wanted to
kind of be more creative like you wanted
to write a story then you often for
these maybe creative tasks you want like
you want you want to be able to generate
multiple independent stories and
Distortion freeness is not sufficient
for that so there's maybe some depends a
little more on the task and like it is
interesting to relax on itability in
other
ways can yeah so the con you said
constant but the Conant should depend on
something so like you say it achieves
constant at it robustness what's the
Conant uh so for for our for your for
our thing it will depend on actually
I'll introduce this later but it will
depend on the entropy so it will depend
on something
yeah but yeah good
question uh so one last paper by Kristen
gun established tected by water marking
schemes that are sound but only robust
to a constant fraction of
substitutions and it turns out that
going from substitutions to edits in
general will require new techniques in
particular because edits includes
insertions and deletions which can cause
offsets and these are actually pretty
challenging to deal with so our water
marking scheme is the first that gets
all three of these properties um and I'm
going to to tell you more about this um
in the next few
slides there a question
uh can you clarify a little bit more on
why we want detectability I would think
just intuitively that you would want
like people to easily recognize
something uh okay so why do we want uh
detectability I guess it depends on the
application if you like want to be able
to kind of if you want some public
attribution for your water marking
scheme then yes you want there to be
like some this is more like a signature
scheme you want there to be some kind of
way of seeing you know easily that the
text was generated by a language model
but uh I I think that you know there's
some applications where you really like
don't you want to basically kind of
pretend that this is generated from the
two language model
and you maybe only care about detecting
whether it was actually you know a
language model or you know something
else for some Downstream
applications that you will want to use
your secret key for for detection and so
there it depends a lot on the
application uh
um but I thinkability provides you the
guarantee that it doesn't degrade
quality in any way yes that's that
that's that's the main that's one main
motivation yeah exactly how else would
you guarantee that it doesn't degrade
property quality you know it's a way to
there's maybe other ways but this is the
kind of the cleanest like strongest
possible
way uh yes there are um and I I won't
discuss those that much in this talk
about there
are uh
[Music]
yeah like yes yes there are um yeah uh I
won't say that much about it but I I'll
touch on it briefly I
think okay great so um now I guess there
are a few questions about why
undetectability let me just motivate
edit robustness quickly um so why not
just substitutions well there's a lot of
applications of editing sequences which
involve insertions or deletions
and um so in addition to uh text a lot
of sequence data say you know another
application of sequence modeling
sequences is DNA and in DNA mutation we
often consider insertions or deletions
as well and one other interesting fact
is that the process of tokenization
itself even if there's not an explicit
adversary can insert or delete
tokens so let me give you an example
language models actually don't output
words per se they actually output tokens
or token IDs which are just numbers in
order to convert a sequence of tokens
into human readable text we actually
have to apply what's known as a
tokenizer in particular a decoding
algorithm the tokenizer which takes as
input a sequence of token IDs and
outputs uh text this particular sequence
of tokens will correspond to the text
DNA a
molecule now to actually apply a a
watermarking detection algorithm we have
to go back from text to tokens
and if you take this sequence of text
imply the encoding algorithm for the
tokenizer you end up with a different
sequence of tokens than the one you
started out with in particular the first
three tokens were deleted and we
inserted one new
token so the problem here is that the
mapping between tokens and text
sequences is actually not one to
one and due to this fact even without an
explicit adversary there may be edits
that are introduced um when going from
tokens to text and back to tokens
and why do we want a constant fraction
of edits well I think the best
motivation is say in related areas like
coding Theory getting robustness to a
constant fraction of of modifications
like substitutions or edits is a gold
standard okay so now I can move on to
say what our main result is um and
before stating our main result I need to
introduce one more notion which is out
of
entropy it's motivated by the following
observation which is that if I ask a
language model say a good language model
to Output the Declaration of
Independence there's really only one
answer to this question it's the
Declaration of Independence and you
can't really Watermark this it was
written several hundred years
ago and more generally we can only hope
to Watermark language models with
sufficient
entropy so I'll measure entropy using
what's known as the entropy rate and
it's defined as
follows so it's the average over all L
tokens from ials 1 to capital L of the
entropy of the I token TI given the
preceding tokens T1 through
ius1 with respect to the language model
and this is divided by the maximum
possible enty of a token which is simply
the log of the alphabet
size so because we're using this
normalization the entropy rate will
always be be a real number between zero
and
one now here's what we
show under an appropriate cryptographic
assumption for security parameter Lambda
which parameterizes things such as the
running time of the
adversary there's a watermarking scheme
for language models over alphabets of
size that's a polinomial one and
Lambda which satisfies the three desired
properties so first of all it's
undetectable to all polinomial time
algorithms and here I mean polinomial in
Lambda it's sound which means that it
detects any fixed sequence as
watermarked with probability that's
negligible in Lambda so smaller than any
polinomial function in Lambda
and finally it's robust to a constant
fraction of
edits as long as the entropy rate of the
model is
Alpha and a few things I'll remark here
are that the entry rate of the uh
language model actually shows up in the
alphabet size we need the alphabet size
to be Lambda to the one over the enty
rate the second thing I'll note here is
that the constant fraction of edit
robust to also depends on Lambda so for
our scheme we showed something like
Alpha squared although it you know I
think that can may maybe be improved
yep tokens yeah exactly
y uh sorry I can't hear what if the
entrop is really high in some places but
really low in other places during
generation uh good questions what if the
entrop is high in some places and low in
others um so it basically what we need
is like kind of a a mean uh we're going
to be averaging over many positions and
so as long as the mean entropy is high
there's enough positions where it's high
enough that you'll be good so this
allows it to be low in some
positions okay so let me say a few words
about this alphabet size um one thing
you might ask is is is this
practical um you can actually look at
the values of Sigma and Alpha for for
say gpt2 so for gpt2 there's about
50,000 tokens
and you can compute that the entry rate
of gpt2 is something like 0. 28 at least
for kind of Tex that lies in its
training data
set unfortunately these values are not
quite good enough for our theorem to
apply um for gpt2 we would need to take
the security parameter Lambda very small
it close to
one the good news is that there is kind
of some empirical ad hoc techniques
which actually can be applied to make
this practical and you can actually
implement this roughly speaking the idea
is to group a constant number of tokens
together
so suppose we group um we group
sequences of three consecutive tokens
together as a kind of given an example
here by doing this we increase the
effective alphabet size from Sigma to
Sigma
cubed however we don't change the
entropy
rate because the entropy per token is
increasing by a factor of three on
average and also the log of the alphabet
size is increasing by a factor of three
so by doing this we can boost the
alphabet size keep this Lambda to the
one over Alpha the same and get in a
more favorable regime for the
parameters something bothers me here so
why can't you arbitrarily increase the
alphabet something grows with the
alphabet size right is the runtime of
the algorithm
perhaps arbitr increase I mean the run
time definitely goes the alphabet size
yeah so so I can't I can't let the whole
sequence the sentence be the uh you know
the so I guess okay one other thing I
haven't mentioned here is that your
robustness also decreases by this
constant Factor because now like I only
have to change one of those tokens and
so like I really want this to be a
constant um and also when you're kind of
doing these empirical things what is a
constant and what is like Lambda it
becomes a little bit um trickier to kind
of think about what is constant because
changes and the one time also increases
you look at
exactly okay so in the last uh 10 or so
minutes I'm going to overview the proof
of the theorem and tell you about some
kind of
related results which I think are kind
of maybe of interest in their own right
and in particular I'm going to discuss
how we can construct edit robust pseudo
random codes which is essentially a
combination of an error correcting code
and um um a secret key scheme um and
then I'll show how edit robust through
to random codes imply edit robust
watermarking um that's what we show um
I'm actually only going to focus on the
first
point so let me first what a pseudo
random code
is um a pseudo random code or a PRC can
be most simply defined as a water
marking scheme for the uniform language
model Now by uniform language model I
simply mean the model which does not
take as input a prompt and just outputs
distribu uh the uniform distribution
over sequences of L
tokens now to be to be clear let me just
remind you what the three properties are
so undetectability for the case the
uniform language model tells us that no
poly time algorithm can distinguish
between the output of quark and the and
multiple independent samples from the
uniform
distribution we also want robustness so
edit robustness means that our water
marking scheme's detection algorithm is
robust to a constant fraction of edits
I'll also um discuss substitution
robustness where we want robust a
constant fraction of
substitutions and finally we want
soundness which means that independent
text is not recognized as
watermarked so in this talk I'm going to
discuss how to construct these pseudo
random codes the proof that edit robust
pseudo random codes imply edit robust
watermarking follows from similar
techniques from a paper by Kristen um
gun uh last year so I won't discuss that
in in uh during this
talk okay so to construct edit robust
through random codes the way we do this
is we actually first show a construction
of substitution robust through random
codes so then show how to upgrade this
to edit
robustness so what we show is that under
an appropriate cryptographic assumption
there's a binary alphabet pseudo random
code which is robust to any constant
fraction of substitutions bounded above
by a
half now what is this cryptographic
assumption it's somewhat standard um and
one thing that works is assuming that
log Lambda hunas in the binary hyper Cub
Dimension Lambda form a weak pseudo
random function family so let me unpack
that a log Lambda hun is a function that
only depends on log Lambda
coordinates and the fact they form a
weak stud random function family
basically means that you cannot learn
this in polinomial time with respect to
the uniform Distribution on the hyper
Cube now I want to compare our result to
one result by prior work by Christen gun
which showed the same conclusion as us
namely a binary alphabet
PRC but they had a different assumption
and to compare these assumptions it can
be useful to look at ugo's five worlds
so the assumptions of Christ and gun uh
are known to imply public key
cryptography and so in this sense they
lie in
cryptomania in contrast our cryptic
Africa assumption this this one by
bkfl um is not known to apply publicy
cryptography so in this sense it lies in
minic Crypt which is weaker you know um
which means that our assumption the
senses is weaker than those of um
Christen gun I will say however and this
there's a question about this earlier
that the um so random codes that
crypting uh that Chris and gun are able
to show as a result of their assumption
have a stronger guarantee in the sense
that they're actually public key pseudo
vom
codes so they're actually getting
something more for their assumption as
well so they also get us public key
watermarking scheme is a result yeah
public keybard marking scheme
yeah okay now let me move on to the
second part of the proof um the idea
here is to go from substitution robust
prc's to edit robust
pies so what we show is that given a
binary alphabet pseud random code on
length L strings which is robust to a 1
half minus Epsilon fraction of
substitutions then in a blackbox manner
we can construct a pseudo random code
which is um an alphabets of size order L
which is robust to a one minus order
Epsilon fraction of edits so we're
getting edit robustness but we're paying
in the size of the
alphabet and one thing I'll not is that
the edit robust PRC that we get is
actually robust to an arbitrary
permutation on the string not just um
some adversarial edits so it has this
stronger property the same holds for a
watermarking scheme but not if you
combine it with some of these you know
empirical um kind of ad hoc things which
group a constant number of consecutive
tokens
together so in the last minute or two
let me give you a sketch of how our edit
robust sud random code
works so let's start with a substitution
robust do a random code which I'll call
Key gen Watermark detect with the
subscript of
s I'm going to construct an edit
robustum codes now I'm using subscrip of
e and the rough idea is to write down
the indices and ones of the output of
the substitution robust Toom
code let me tell you a little bit more
detail about what I mean by that so the
key generation algorithm for edit robust
scheme is the same as that for the
substitution robust scheme which just
outputs a secret
key now how does the watermarking method
work I'm going to first call the
substitution Rob Boss Water marking
function which gives me a binary string
X of length
L I'm going to then let script I denote
the set of indices I little I where x i
is equal to
one then roughly speaking I'm just going
to Output a uniform permutation on the
elements of this this indexing
set i'm eliminating few kind of bells
and whistles and I'll maybe get to some
why we need some of these in a few
moments but this gives me a sequence of
tokens which are now just integers from
one to L and the length of the sequence
is roughly order
L now how does the uh detection
algorithm work I'm just going to take as
input a sequence of tokens which may or
may not have been outputed by the
watermarking algorithm I'm going to
essentially try to reconstruct X so I'm
going to let x i Prime be the indicator
that token is equal to I in the
sequence and then I'm going to feed the
string X1 Prime the the string of x i
primes to the detection algorithm for
the substitution robust pseudo ROM code
which is going to Output either
watermarked or not
watermarked so why does this
work well the main idea is that
insertions or deletions from the
sequence of tokens t
correspond to substitutions in the
binary string
X so let me just kind of illustrate
this if you have the binary string X
which is 0 1 1 0 01 this corresponds to
the sequence of tokens T which is
236 we have a noisy Channel which
inserts say a four into the sequence
that corresponds to changing the fourth
bit of x from zero to a one and
similarly a deletion from T will
correspond to changing a bit of x from a
one to a zero and so in this way we can
use the substitution robustness of the
original watermarking scheme to get edit
robustness for the new
one now there's a fair number of of
details here which I have omitted and in
fact the scheme that I've uh kind of
sketched on this slide is actually not
undetectable there's there's some things
you have to add as one example of some
technical difficulty that comes up is
the scheme as I've um showed it here
gives edit robustness for only a smaller
than one minus order Epsilon constant
fraction edits it's more like a one
quarter fraction of constant edits and
this is actually not good enough for
applications to watermarking we actually
need the constant fraction of edits Z
robust two to be very close to one and
so in light of this we actually have to
add some additional components to our
watermarking scheme which will force the
alphabet size to blow up by constant
Factor um
yeah I add tokens
uh you mean just like add a bunch
more um so uh How would how would you
want to add them I'm not like oh oh just
like oh like if you're an adversary who
inserts tokens at the end uh yeah that
that's fine like um it's like as long as
the number of tokens that you add isn't
that big you'll still get edit
robustness because this is all kind of
permutation and variant on on T so it
doesn't really matter if it's to the end
or other
parts yep here that we're like
representing tokens like in or like
we're representing output in
unary um I wouldn't think of it as un
it's more similar to like there's maybe
the simplest way to get like um edit
robust error correcting codes is via
this indexing trick and there's there's
actually you know better ways of doing
it but this is maybe analogous to like
the simplest way of getting edit robust
um error correcting
codes like what would happen here if I
had a duplicate token like I had 2362
um so if you have the duplicate tokens
don't affect anything like I only look
at the existence of whether or not there
is some token that's equal to two so
yeah I can actually add as many twos as
I want nothing's going to change as long
as there already two in the
sequence
yep misspell
token Oh you mean like misspell a word
okay so so actually like for misspelled
words the way that language models
actually deal with these is that the
kind of the tokenizer will break that up
into smaller subwords maybe able to
break it up into letters or something
else like sub units and so that will
actually correspond to like deleting the
original token and inserting maybe two
new tokens so actually like misspelling
the way that you can kind of get these
edits these insertions and
deletions um into the into the token
sequence Okay so uh I guess this is my
last slide so uh we have the first edit
undetectable edit robust water marking
scheme um I didn't talk about how do we
go from edit robust prcs to edit robust
watermarks um Sor there's many open
questions so maybe the biggest open
questions to come up with edit robust
prcs under reasonable assumptions um
that have constant alphabet
size it also be interesting to improve
the Practical implementation or to
figure out if there's properties of
natural language models that actually
can be exploited to get U mod marking
schemes that work better in practice and
there's lots of other uh open questions
as well so I'll stop there thank you for
listening
[Applause]