wow that was inspiring wasn't it we we
solve big problems right um welcome to
the 2024 MIT sustainability conference
for those of you who don't know me I'm
gatri shasan executive director MIT
corporate relations I'm about 8 and a
half months Ro old in this role so I'm
still learning so you have a lot to
teach me um today you're going to hear
from Professor Richard Lester who's the
interim vice president for MIT climate
um five climate project Mission
directors you're going to hear from
eight startups in the sustainability um
space and you're going to hear from
several MIT faculty researchers and
Industry
collaborators I just wanted to start
with what is MIT I know you heard you
saw the video but what is MIT MIT is
comprised of
17,1 180 employees employes I'm one of
them uh about 1100 professors and like
faculty out of which 28% are women 4500
undergraduates and 7,300 graduate
students a total of uh almost 12,000
graduate student uh so students at MIT
and 29% are
international what else we have five
schools and we have one college schools
are more defined based on the home of
the faculty member or the research
whereas the College comprises of
interdisciplinary interaction between
the different schools and making it more
uh impactful in terms of research that
touches different a uh areas of
access in addition to the schools we
have 65 plus dlc's is what we call
research lab centers and programs and we
have about $840 million on campus that
comes through sponsored research 20% of
that is industry sponsored research and
half of the industry sponsored research
is through industry uh liazon ILP
members we have 592 patents um filed in
fi23 um 362 patent issued we have $40
million in revenues through licensing of
MIT uh Innovation inventions and about
23 startup companies that were spun off
in FY
23 we are all about Innovation you talk
you hear about Innovation Innovation
Innovation ecosystem that drives
Innovation here at MIT but what exactly
is innovation at M we think of
innovation as the process of taking an
idea through impact right so that's what
we strive for and that's what we make
happen our research priorities as you
heard president conlu talk about we have
three areas that we want to focus on as
institutional priority we have climate
and sustainability we have life science
and we have ai and we want to solve big
problems we don't want to small solve
small problems we want to talk talk
about what is the global Challenge and
we want to address
it and again we want to address it in a
very evidence-based manner the climate
project I don't want to talk any further
about it because you're going to hear
all about it today through the climate
Mission directors and through uh
Professor Richard Lester and others but
what is industry leaz on program some of
you are members and have benefited from
it some of you are not members and may
benefit from it and so who are we we are
all about looking at what we have at The
Institute to offer research Innovation
students and education right that's what
as an Institute we have to offer and
that's what I feel as industry Partners
you may want to leverage and engage with
us on and you can leverage and engage
with us from learning and understanding
through webinars through conferences
like these through workshops and through
you know programs like professional aded
exec Ed and other such learning
opportunities for your you and your
employees we can you can learn um uh
discover and solve problems you can meet
with faculty members program leaders to
share with them what your problem
problems are and then perhaps figure out
a solution to those problems problems
and then of course Network right network
not only through uh colleagues in
Industry through to faculty uh and
researchers through students that are
engaged and also in terms of startups
right and we talk about startup exchange
you will hear from uh eight different
startups but what is startup exchange
it's a way for us to connect startups
within the MIT ecosystem to the industry
Partners across and make those fit
happen with that I want to thank you but
I want to give a huge shout out to three
different uh entities one is Rebecca
Miller and Yuri Ramos who actually
helped make
this uh a vision of the sustainability
conference into actual action here so
thank you you'll hear from them over
time
um I wanted to also thank the
communications and events team sitting
across the uh behind us working behind
the scene tirelessly
to make this actually possible and make
us all look good right and then lastly I
wanted to St thank the startup exchange
team you know working with and
identifying the right startups for a
pitching and bringing to your Forefront
so that you can see and hear from them
so thank you to all and thank you uh
audience to be here and contribute to
making this a success
[Applause]
thank you gatri U what a warm welcome uh
we're already feeling the love from our
audience so thank you for that and thank
you for joining us today I just wanted
to say good morning good afternoon good
evening to all of our wonderful
in-person attendees um as well as the
hundreds of people joining um our live
stream feed today so um we're we're
thrilled you can join and contribute uh
to today's uh interaction and
exploration of this critical space so
we've already heard from president MIT
president Sally corn Bluth on mit's
commitment to this crucial area of
sustainability and we'll continue
exploring throughout the day mit's
actions in this area ranging from um the
launching of the six uh climate missions
through mit's climate project you'll
hear from a panel of the the climate
Mission directors how we're leveraging
AI to tackle challenges in the climate
space but ALS also the flip side this
extreme demand energy demand from uh
these data centers and the the AI boom
we'll be uh and talking about a number
of strategies uh for enabling
decarbonization of Industry ranging from
Aviation construction chemical
manufacturing and Mobility among others
and we'll hear from a lot um we'll also
this will be this message we'll hear
from expert faculty cuttingedge startup
companies leading Global corporations
such as uh your ourselves and the
government stakeholders um that enable
these breakthrough Technologies new
business models and policy incentives um
but first let me allow my allow me to
introduce my colleague Yuri Ras uh
program director with mit's Corp office
of corporate relations good morning
thank you Rebecca let me introduce you
to my colleague Rebecca Miller or Dr
Rebecca Miller also a program director
we had the challenge we shared the
challenge of you know putting this
conference together we do hope you folks
enjoy as much as we did planning it for
the companies in this Dynamic space the
message is very very clear investors are
seeking green opportunities customers
are prefering environmentally
responsible businesses and organizations
sustainability reputation is
increasingly vital for attracting Talent
on the one hand we're seeing urgent
concern for business resilience and
competitiveness including from facility
damage supply chain disruptions and
service outages on the other hand as you
hear in our afternoon panel the business
of sustainability and also by our
keynote speaker Brian we see significant
opportunities that will unlock billions
in Market potential create new jobs and
strengthen economies while advancing
sustainability want to show you a chart
by Bloomberg according to Bloomberg you
can see behind us pay special attention
in the last four years Global investment
in the low carbon energy transition
reached a record of
1.8 trillion dollar last year reflecting
the resilience of clean energy despite
geopolitical challenges High interest
rates and inflation tough days together
with your fellow attendees representing
over 100 major corporations today either
here at marot or online you can explore
collaboration
networking idea sharing and engagement
we truly hope that you as I said in the
beginning that you enjoy this event the
exchange of ideas as much as Rebecca and
I did enjoyed planning this day for you
thank you so to help enable this idea
sharing and engagement that Yuri just
mentioned uh we'd like to invite you to
use the pigeon hole tool you can see on
the the screens at the right and at the
um and left of the room uh this allows
you to submit questions to the speakers
and also to upvote questions if you
think uh you see one that you're really
interested in the speaker answering so
you can access the site just using the
QR codes and also through the pigeon
hole website using the passcode
sustainability 24