(buoyant music)
- My name is Mina Konakovic Lukovic
and I'm an assistant
professor at EECS at MIT,
and I'm also part of CSAIL
I lead a group called
Algorithmic Design Group
and this is my second
year as a professor here.
When I was thinking about what
I want to do for my studies,
I was actually deciding
between architecture,
mathematics, and medicine
and in the end, I chose
mathematics and computer science
because that lets me touch
upon all of these areas in some sense.
Before coming to MIT,
I was a PhD student at EPFL
in Lausanne in Switzerland,
where I was working mostly
on geometry processing
and I wasn't doing any
of the machine learning
or robotics things before.
And I was fortunate enough
to get a postdoctoral fellowship
called Schmidt Science Fellowship,
where they offer you to go and study
wherever you want in the world,
but also pivot the area
that you are working on.
That's what led me to MIT,
because MIT is the best place
that does those kinds of applications
and is one of the rare places
where you can actually do
this kind of exotic research,
but also be on top of the game.
So I was fortunate enough to come here
before the faculty job as postdoc,
'cause that let me also
get familiar with MIT,
with this environment,
it's a special kind of environment
that you don't see in most places.
My mentor was Wojciech Matusik,
a very well known established researcher
in the field of computer graphics,
but also known for exploring
very risky and novel directions
that are not typical
for computer graphics.
He was one of the pioneers
and one of the researchers
who started exploring
this computational design
and fabrication direction,
and robotics within computer graphics,
which led me to join his group.
In my group, we work mostly
on developing new algorithms
that help you design or fabricate things
in a more efficient way
or a more optimal way
than what you can do manually.
We do a less traditional
kind of research here
where we do play with 3D models,
so we do have to leverage
some of the famous algorithms
that we're developing with
the computer graphics,
but we do use them in applications,
such as robotics, such as material design,
such as designing transformable
structures and so on.
I really like the environment
that we created here.
People are complimenting
each other's skills
in a way that it does not create
a competitive environment,
which I find very important,
that they're actually friends
and they feel open
coming and talking to me
any day if leave my office door open.
I think that's the kind of environment
that I would also like to
keep throughout my career
because I feel
that they're really enjoying
their time together,
that also helps them move
further in their research
and in their careers in
a more healthier way.
- Working with Mina is great,
like Mina gives us a proper balance
of like independence and also
how much guidance we require
and also she maintains a proper lab vibe.
- We get a lot of intellectual freedom.
We work on everything from
like geometry to biology,
to machine learning, to
robotics, it's amazing.
- My favorite thing about
MIT is definitely people,
the people that you meet here
and that you have an opportunity
to interact with here,
you don't see that elsewhere,
it's really amazing.