um and also welcome to those of you who
are online um this is a you know this is
a busy time of the semester and we know
that uh many people will appreciate the
recording um as a chance to to uh return
to this um I'm looking forward um to a
very interesting conversation um in both
this session and then right U following
it after a brief Break um another
session with our our other guest uh this
afternoon around this the question uh
that generative AI poses um for the uh
for the legal structures um and and
rights and practices of copyright in the
United States and and in fact around the
world um and I think this will this
conversation is designed to be
informative um so there will be a little
bit of just basic uh kind of you know
getting the community up to speed about
the terms of the law uh it's also
designed to be thought-provoking um and
we've invited uh you know one of our
speakers to kind of provoke us into some
thinking about what's at stake um for
authors and creatives um as generative
AI emerges as a technology um and then
it's also designed to be specifically
reflective um for the MIT Community um
and and others who are interested um in
what's at stake at the interface of
technology and Society um so I will
introduce our our uh main speaker for
this uh first session in a moment and uh
before I turn it over to him I'm gonna
to um Kazi who's the director of policy
and advocacy at the author's Guild I'll
give a longer introduction in a few
minutes um I'll just say a little bit
more about myself uh about about cir um
and then give you kind of maybe about 5
10 uh minute overview of uh the history
um and current status of copyright um in
20th in 21st century United States um so
uh as Nico said I'm uh I'm a professor
of History here at MIT um where I teach
and publish in the field of 20th century
US legal history one of the courses I
teach at MIT um is called the history of
the US Supreme Court um uh although I am
not a lawyer um I am a legal historian
um and also serve as one of the advisers
for mit's has concentration in legal
studies um and uh you know I should just
sort of say given everything that's
going on in the world um you know in my
teaching I I do teach about the rule of
law the separational powers the
administrative procedures act the
empowerment Control Act of 1974 other
things that I hadn't had on my syllabus
um last year but we'll be adding to them
um very very quickly um you know and
it's really designed to be a space for
MIT students to to Grapple with issues
um uh from the past as they as they uh
connect with the present um and in the
last year or so I've had a chance of
doing this in conjunction sometimes with
with c um with social ethical and
responsibilities of computing initiative
of the college which is as it described
itself is facilitating the development
of responsible habits of mind and action
and I love that phrase
for those who create and deploy
Computing Technologies and fostering the
creation of Technologies in the public
interest and and so I think it it was a
logical connection um for us to think
about generative Ai and copyright as
crucial issues um both for uh fostering
the creation of Technologies um thinking
about about the public interest and also
developing responsible habits of mind
and action for technologists at MIT and
Beyond uh so let's get into the kind of
you know the nitty-gritty of it um and
uh I'm H I'm going to sort of run
through some history for you here for a
few minutes um I don't I don't have
slides but I'm happy to provide
citations or other information in the
Q&A if people would like to know more um
and you know we certainly know from our
founding documents um some of the key
phrases um that we know pretty well uh
we know all about the pursuit of life
liberty uh or we know about life liberty
and the pursuit of happiness we know
from the Constitution and the Bill of
Rights uh that property uh is protected
from without due process of law um but
one of the phrases that does not appear
in the constitution is the phrase
intellectual property and the
Constitution says that it uses this
nowhere but nevertheless the
Constitution is what protects
intellectual property um as a form of
property in general um and where we can
find this most clearly is in Article 1
Section 8 uh this is part article one
gives Congress the power to do the
following quote to promote promote the
progress of Science and useful Arts by
securing for limited times to authors
and inventors the exclusive right to
their respective writings and
discoveries right so this is the kind of
key phrase that in order to promote the
progress of Science and useful Arts uh
by that Congress gives us the power to
secure for limited times to authors and
inventors the exclusive right to their
respective writings and discoveries
that brief phrase structures all of
intellectual property law in the United
States it emerges from an anglo-american
tradition there are of course versions
in the EU and in other jurisdictions
which I do not have the expertise to
talk about today now this breaks down
into two parts right so for inventors uh
there are patents and again this is not
something that we'll be addressing today
but of course intellectual property
certainly extends to patent law and
other fields uh but for authors uh there
is something called copyright
and we'll focus on the latter here now
copyright um to give a basic definition
and I'm borrowing here from the US
copyright office which is an entity of
the Library of Congress um uh copyright
protects original works of authorship as
soon as a human author fixes the work in
tangible form of expression so you can't
just have the idea you have to fix the
idea in a tangible form of expression
now this could in this takes many forms
this could include a book uh but it
could also include computational code
paintings and photographs musical
compositions uh and the list goes on now
as we think about the implications of
generative AI um it's worth considering
uh maybe three more terms that you might
want to have at your fingertips or that
you might come across as uh you're
reading in this
area but copyright law also spends a
great deal of time uh considering the
the definition and the boundaries of
what is called called derivative Works
um such as translations musical
Arrangements movie adaptations right new
things that come from old things right
that are derived from existing things
and derivative Works can be
copyrighted but they can only be
copyrighted if they are substantially
transformed and if they bear the
personality of the creator of that
derivative work um so you know a
translation of a of a book from from
Japanese into English um can be
copyrighted um if it is if it Bears the
personality of the creator of that
derivative work how I might uh translate
a work is different from you or you or
you right and that's in part what makes
it uh derivative and also therefore uh
copyrightable copyright also extends uh
to the production of or the second term
here transformative work right and to
understand what that means uh courts
have generally seen this as one that
adds new expression meaning or message
to the original work right so so it's
not just a copy right but it is a
transformation um transformative work
also uh does not substitute for the
original use of the work you can't use
the one instead of the other as
equivalence then it's not hasn't been
transformed um and third that it does
not harm the market for the original
work right so if there's something that
claims to be a transformative work but
it essentially puts the the original out
of business and then the the Creator
author of that first work might have a
copyright claim to
make all right third time um and then we
will uh dig into the specifics is the
term fair use that the protections of
copyright do allow for the fair use of
copyrighted Works um and this happens at
MIT every day as MIT faculty you may use
copy wred images in class or share short
readings for educational purposes to a
limited group of students right and this
is you know and there are General
guidelines for fair use that courts have
adjudicated when they do um they use
four uh principles to figure out whether
something is a fair or an unfair use of
a copyrighted work first the purpose of
the use right is there you know is there
purpose to you know to transform or or
duplicate something they would consider
they would look at the nature of the
copyrighted work uh the initial
copyrighted work and whether it is
highly creative or or not third and the
amount of the taking right did you copy
a portion of a book or photocopy the
entire thing right the courts will
consider that something like that and
fourth what is the effect on the market
for the original right does uh you know
does a a fair use of copyrighted
material put the original out of
business
so these are some terms um um is going
to talk about in his presentation about
how this uh affects authors that that he
works with cl Schneider after this is
going to talk about you know some of the
implications of those for the MIT
Community let me just say one more thing
which is this question what is copyright
for U you know what were the founders
aiming to do um in the constitution in
1787 and certainly they they said very
explicitly what they wanted to do they
wanted to promote the progress of
Science and useful Arts right and that
remains I think very important today um
you know almost two Century or more than
two centuries later um they the solution
that they that they hit on in 1787 was
the second part of that Clause right to
secure for limited times to authors and
inventors the exclusive right to their
respective writings and discoveries and
it is not uh immediately clear um that
the solution that was offered in 1787
still works in an age of generative AI
right um and I think that the the
founders would have you know really
thought that fostering intervention inov
sorry fostering Innovation and rewarding
creators were two sides of the same coin
right um and that that balancing test
certainly remains uh important today
some uh now feel that this that the
claims of how that this is at stake have
changed from two directions first from
Publishers who see a threat to their
business model um and who are asserting
copyright claims against generative AI
companies um you may have seen this line
of argument in cases brought by for
example the New York Times um and second
from authors uh who object that large
language models are profiting from their
work and are concerned that llm outputs
May threaten their professional
livelihood now over the course of the
day and of course in other programming
we may do uh at at uh at the college
over the course of the semester we'll
explore these issues and some of the
implications that are at stake but now
what I'm going to do is turn things over
to our guest um um Kazi as I said is the
director of policy and advocacy at the
author's Guild uh this is a professional
organization of over 15,000 writers um
and in his capacity he oversees the
Guild's policy portfolio including
positions on copyright collective
bargaining antitrust and artificial
intelligence so he's a great person to
talk with us today uh he has previously
served as the guild staff attorney uh
and holds a JD from the University of
Iowa col College of Law and also uh
importantly for the author's Guild an
MFA in creative writing from Columbia
University uh and translates poetry from
uru uh with work published in several
literary journals um and has contributed
a chapter on Digital Book piracy um in
the first edition of the rutage
companion to copyright and creativity in
the 21st century um so um uh the the
floor is
yours um thanks thanks everybody thanks
Chris for that wonderful um introduction
and really really great um background on
copyright law it's a I um I kind of fell
into copyright sort of by happen stance
I didn't study copyright when I was in
law school I was going to go into
Finance uh law and then the financial
crisis happened but when I was doing my
MFA I had the opportunity to um start
working for the guild who were looking
for a lawyer at the time and uh it's
it's really one of the most fascinating
areas of the law I think it gets closest
to philosophy at times and um the
questions that we grapple with are are
are so rich and and just have deep
implications for um for for for the way
we you know interact the way we
communicate uh what we read um how we
browse the web uh Etc so um I'll just
start by giving kind of a beef brief
background of the guild and what it is
is what it does and how um we got
involved in generative Ai and in that
process I will um touch on some of the
uh Concepts that Chris introduced uh
fair use uh transform transformative
work uh drift Works Etc so um the
author's Guild is uh the oldest and
largest Professional Organization of uh
writers in the US it has been around
since 1912 um right now we have 15,000
members uh all working authors and we
really focus on this idea of the
professional author which which goes to
our mission of uh providing and creating
fostering an environment where anyone
who wants to write can earn a
sustainable living from their writing
and that's that's a big part of our
mission um we're active um we we are
active in DC as a lobbying group we
Lobby in behalf of authors um a lot of
our work has you know has been in
copyright but we also um given the way
uh the publishing industry has changed
and and and and the the income um
potential for authors has declined uh
We've sort of uh moved into other areas
of the law including antitrust uh one of
the initiatives that we uh have been
working on is to give authors collective
bargaining rights Collective action
rights um because they're independent
contractors under current labor laws
they can't work together which means
that one author cannot talk to another
author about what they're getting in
their contracts and and they can't all
go to the publisher together and say hey
this is unfair these are these are the
kind of terms that we want so that's one
of the things that we've been working on
but um uh pretty much since um late
2022 um uh AI has kind of like been a
daily presence in my
life um not a day goes by I mean it's
just uh you know endless calls on AI
lots of we've done a lot of work on AI
in the last uh now almost two years um
and uh what happened in late ch late
2022 was Chad GPT came online and um we
very quickly just to pause there for a
second and we we we actually were aware
of uh implications of Co of um AI or
copyright um for like a few years before
that because um we had seen prototypes
like I don't know if people have heard
of the next rembrand it sounds like now
it sounds like Atari but um you know I
think in 20 20 18 or so it was uh kind
of like the state-of-the-art AI model
and it was a um AI that could developed
by Microsoft that could uh generate
images in the style of rbrand um and um
so we were aware of the questions that
AI raised for copyright um one of the
questions I'm I'm glad you mentioned
that in your um in in your definition of
copyright you mentioned human author and
um there that was actually a huge
question uh at the time um it has to a a
large degree been resolved but the
question was what happens when uh a
machine creates um uh a work of uh you
know a work of art a work of literature
writing do we does does the machine own
copyright who owns copyright in that
creation um and there is a long
tradition in copyright law of of um
recognizing that it is that copyright
only belongs to the human author um
there are there's a long line of cases
um the the the the idea started really
kind of becoming um um or or getting
fleshed out in the early 20th century
with the Advent of uh of
Photography um where courts grappled
with uh the question of whether or not
there was any um um originality of
expression in in the work and so the the
the the question of what is human
authorship is it the machine that's
creating or is it the author that's or
is it the human that's creating really
became a focal point of uh of uh early
sort of uh copyright um um uh
discussions around AI um in
2023 the copyright office uh came out
with a guidance document that U
essentially um uh talked about how it
would register works that were created
using Ai and and they following the long
line of cases they said that they would
not register works that or they would
not not that they would not register
works that they would that the author or
anyone claiming registration in the work
uh that had some AI um use would have to
disclaim the parts that they did not
themselves create that were not created
by a human
author um so that's where we're at right
now if you use table diffusion or um any
number of image generating AI to make an
image um unless you modify it in a
certain way that's not copyrightable and
even then only the parts that are um
that have uh human authorship and
original expression only those parts are
copyrightable so um for example you
could have um um there was one
interesting example that I heard
recently where someone had created an
artwork but only used like a dog that
was generated by AI and they were
thinking about copyrighting it and you
know the answer is well yeah the
copyright office will register the
artwork but you have to disclaim the dog
and the dog will not be so anything that
is generated by a machine is actually uh
is not protected so anyone else can use
it um without any any need for any
authorization so um that was one of the
questions um that we were grappling with
uh at the time we weren't really aware
of there wasn't a whole lot that we were
aware of as far as how training is done
and since then the primary focus for us
has been the ingestion of um books and
other copyrighted materials when it
comes to training um you know when you
train in llm you um you you need all
kinds of data right you know you know in
computer science parland you just say
data but like this data also includes in
some cases hundreds of thousands of
books and uh um we know in some cases we
know the models and the books that they
were trained on uh in other cases we
don't um some of the models out there
some of the large language models are
blackbox models like
anthropic um and uh the GPT models after
3.5 so we don't really know the data
composition the training data
composition in those cases um but we do
know by analogy from what developers
have told us um for for instance uh
llama um used a data set called um the
pile which uh includes a subd DAT set
called books three which which is
comprised of 200,000 books that were
downloaded from a pirate site so and um
oddly enough This was um this was uh
this was revealed by the the developers
of meta in a paper they put out um where
they got the data set and so for us that
is a huge concern you know I mean if
developers are going out there and
instead of Licensing the books they are
downloading pirated copies and then
training large language models on them
um that's that's ultimately uh one it's
unethical because uh you know as in in
the definition that that Chris mentioned
of copyright there's a key term called
exclusive so the exclusive right means
that you as the in ventor you know in
the patent um uh scenario or you as the
author or the or the Artist as the
creator of that work you uh you can
exclude anyone else from using that work
you decide who gets to use that work on
what terms uh Etc and it's a limited
Monopoly that that Congress created
precisely to encourage Innovation um so
um so so yes so uh you know when you
download a book or download 200,000
books books to train a model uh you are
infringing on the exclusive rights of
the author now um there are legal
nuances that um I'll go into a little
bit uh Chris also mentioned this uh this
the the the the notion of fair use which
is a very key Concept in copyright law
and that basically allows um it's it's
not um it's it's not a suspension of
copyright but it's it's essentially an
excuse um because uh courts understand
and that the the copyright Clause begins
with the preface for the advancement of
Arts and Sciences so there is a public
uh kind of good element in the copyright
clause and fair use facilitates that
fair use says if there is something that
is being something being innovated then
you can use a copyrighted work without
permission now there are the four
factors um the amount and substantiality
of the use the nature of the copyrighted
work um the um I always blank on the
third Factor the the effect on the
potential Market of the work
um what is the third Factor R the yes
yes so the amount of the taking so so
it's it's like it's a it's it's
essentially a balancing test and not and
and courts when they look at these
questions they can they can give they're
not supposed to give equal weight to any
of the factors so in some cases the
court might say um you know because okay
so one example the from a recent case uh
Supreme Court case was um um uh Andy
warhall did a screen print based on the
photograph that was taken by a
photographer now the LI the photo of
Prince um the artist formerly known as
Prince uh now the photographer licensed
uh the prince images on her own and then
Andy Warhol silk screen Prince were
competing in the same Market as the um
as as the photographers uh the Court
Supreme Court when it looked at the four
factors it it it it gave more weight
even though it found that the work was
what is called transformative that it
added a new medium meaning or message to
the original photo of Prince it did so
in a way that had a profound impact on
the market for the work so in that case
the court weighed the fourth factor a
little heavily and came out and said
this is actually not fair use uh and
this was actually infringement so it's
it's you know fair use is interesting
I'm not a litigator but I've been around
litigators who litigate fair use and um
it's it's you never know you never know
how it's going to come out you can be
sure of your arguments and when you get
go in the courts looking at it in a
certain way but um the the the what's
and this in the ongoing litigations now
there are several ongoing litigations um
over AI generative AI there litigations
in image um against able diffusion
against meta pretty much any com any
company that develops AI is facing a
lawsuit right now uh there's also
several um I believe by last count there
were uh
13 lawsuits against large language
models that were just brought by authors
and Publishers uh they're all class
action most of them are class action
lawsuits um so that means that if and
when the lawsuits progress they could
cover
you know thousands of people but uh the
the key question that will come up in
this lawsuits and it hasn't come up yet
because the defendants the AI companies
hasn't haven't asserted a defense yet is
that they will say
that um I'm just trying to be mindful of
time too so okay um they will they will
say that our use is actually fair use
because we are transforming the work we
are transforming the work into something
new a new technology now the problem
with that uh argument that we see a big
problem is that these Technologies are
capable of uh in you know in many cases
actually reproducing the work you know
you can we have filters now in in in in
in a lot of the public facing AIS but um
you know we know from experimentation
that um in many cases the AI can
reproduce verbatim the the contents of
what it has ingested um they've been
experiments to show that people are
working on on on on these Solutions all
the time um there's also in other in in
other situations the AI can be prompted
to produce a derivative work for
instance um Chris mentioned derivative
Works uh one example of a derivative
work is a very common example of a
derivative work is a is a film
adaptation or a screenplay based on a
book and you can easily use an AI to do
that so what I'm trying to get at is
that the technology even though there is
is something that's new happening to the
work conceivably it is also a technology
that is has um that that can
completely EV eviscerate the market for
The Works uh not not just the works but
eviscerate the market for the rights in
those works so uh you know uh if if you
can use AI to uh create a screenplay
that will diminish the value of the film
rights in a book uh if you can use uh AI
to in in some cases you know when we
were in in when we were experimenting
with GPT and trying to figure out what
it could do from the perspective of um
an author or a published work one of the
things that it it can very easily do is
uh or other AIS can do is create a um a
hypothetical SQL to the work which again
is a d d an exclusive derivative right
that um every author has under copyright
I'll just um I I I I don't think you
mentioned this but basically copyright
itself is a bundle of six exclusive
rights um the right to reproduce the
work the right to publicly perform the
work the right to um uh uh create
derivative works of the work which is
you know you can you can use your work
to create a new work or license it to
somebody else uh the light the right to
distribute copies of the work and there
is one that's called that's a specific
mechanical right uh for um media the
right to publicly display the work and
then the sixth right is a specific
mechanical right
um so so these six rights together are
what enable any um publishing contract
to come into existence they enable any
film rights deal to come into existence
the film rights deal is premised on the
right to create a derivative work a
translation contract is premised on the
right to create a derivative work uh
publishing contract incorporates the
right to display the work the right to
reproduce copies and distribute copies
of the work so um so the value of all of
those rights it's not just that the
value of like a book will go down that
people will stop buying a book but what
will happen is that there will be the
the transactions that happen right now
for authors and Publishers the value of
those rights will go down so that's a
that's a big concern for us um let's see
um there's so much that I can I can I
can talk about I don't want to go over
time
um um
um just looking at my notes um because I
know that we will have things to talk
about during the Q&A as
well
um yeah um the so maybe I can mention
some of the other things that we're
doing uh because we see this challenge
the the the the uh and we really want to
preserve this the human right writing
profession because um there is no
underestimating it AI is is is posing a
pretty existential threat to this
profession um and I'll talk a little bit
more about in our Q&A um but um so we
are active on several fronts we are
working with um members of Congress to
introduce uh legislation and uh
regulations that will protect human
authorship the way we're trying to do it
is um one is that we need to know what
is being ingested by the models I mean I
think there's an interest in this this
policy from a a lot of different uh
groups you know privacy groups are
interested in that you know we should be
able to as consumers we should be able
to know what's being what's being put
into the large language models or like
other other AI the the second thing that
we are concerned about is the market
harm to human created Works which is why
we've been supportive of and pushing for
um uh disclosure requirements on AI
generated um images um text and other
types of content and again you know like
the we can come at it from copyright but
the thing is the the the ramifications
of AI you know they really radiate into
other uh spheres of our life so for
instance disclosure you know we are
interested in it from the point of
preserving a market but there are other
um um policy reasons for for requiring
disclosures uh non-consensual
pornography is one of the ones that is
often very often cited as the biggest
reason for um you know there being a
disclosure requirement so people know
that something is AI generated versus um
you know quote unquote real um we're
also involved in a in a lawsuit right
now against open Ai and Microsoft that
that is a class action lawsuit uh with
uh 13 bestselling authors as the class
plaintiffs um and all of the lawsuits
including ours are simply are premised
on the the the the the the simple
allegation that in the course of
creating large language models
developers uh made illegal copies of the
works full copies because as we know um
you know the the training data set it's
um in in self-supervised training uh you
you don't really break it down or or
annotate or anything you just kind of
throw all of the text that you can find
in a large in a large f and run
algorithms on it so and that actually is
a violation of one of the exclusive
rights which is the right to reprod the
exclusive right to reproduce the work so
by making a copy to train a large
language model you're actually uh
committing a copyright infringement
violation against the author so that's
that's what the lawsuit is premised on
um it's it's it's still in its early
stages um uh in fact like our CEO was in
a deposition yesterday so we'll see
we'll see how things uh things go from
here um and but the likely scenario is
that fair use is going to play a pretty
big role um in the coming months uh
especially in this landscape so I think
I'll stop there and maybe we can
continue to q&as because I'm sure the
audience might have
some thank you um
so I think these are on yep they on um
so before we get to the the public Q now
I'm going to just kick off with one or
two questions for um for some things
that we had been emailing about in the
last few days and and weeks and kind of
leading up to this um and one is um I
wanted to just talk a little bit about
what it what it would mean to the
author's Guild uh to win a case like
this and let me say more about what you
know what I mean that the legal system
is designed to produce sort of winners
and losers right um but uh is there is
there a win-win scenario right one that
both protects author's rights and
fosters Innovation um at the kind of
scale that that the the for-profit um
and non-for-profit AI providers have
been have been accomplishing in the last
couple years y thanks that's actually a
really good question um you know we are
not uh winning for us does not mean
destroying AI That's not something that
we are interested in I think the the and
and some in some days it seems hard to
even imagine what winning looks like
given the kind of insurmountable
disruptions at times that we're seeing
but we do have some very strong Notions
as to as to how we can come out of this
um while preserving you know um not just
the writing profession but this uh
really special kind of place for human
creativity um and uh the the the it
really does come down to licensing I
think you know as long as AI companies
and developers are um being ethical and
legal really about their acquisition of
the works that they're trained on then
we can start sort of moving moving
towards a um a responsible uh future for
the development of generative AI but if
you're uh you know if the developers are
going out there and downloading uh
caches of of books from Pirate sites um
then we're already sort of starting off
from a from a very wrong point of view
in in one of the documents from the
author's Guild um it has this sort of
three-part principle of uh consent
credit and compensation um so maybe just
talk a little bit more about that yeah
absolutely so um you know the consent is
a way to sort of reinforce the idea that
authors um and
and uh can you guys hear me okay yeah uh
consent is sorry consent just to
reinforce the idea that authors and
creators uh have the exclusive right you
know they they they they deserve this um
limited Monopoly that's in the
Constitution because that's what they
rely on to make a living and um you know
their work should not be used without
consent so and it's it's it's it's
another way to say uh you know we need
licensing because in a licensing what's
going on is that the the the author is
saying yes I I will allow you to use my
work for AI training and I think there
is a lot of interest um um you know
among authors to sort of allow their
Works to be used for training um and
other authors who are you know uh
principally against AI can say I do not
consent to you using my Works uh for
training I also want to make a quick
distinction because you know uh
especially early on in the um in the
conversations around generative AI um
you know when authors and other creators
started talking about well where's our
where's our right to consent you guys
are just you know taking everything that
we've created and putting it in uh some
of the AI and and and proponents of AI
and AI developers would come out and say
hey we actually cannot like you know
apportion consent because we're taking
you know like this huge like like masses
of data we're just scrapping you know we
we we're using uh uh scrapes of U of
several tens of millions of weap
websites we cannot do that and there
there needs to be a distinction made
between professional human creators and
their lives versus like anything that's
on Reddit or a message board I think and
and you can actually make that
distinction also from a copyright frame
because you know as we talked about fair
use one of the factors is the the the
impact on the market or the potential
market for the work now as far as I
understand there's not a there's not a
big market for like you know Reddit post
or I don't know there might be but uh
that's how you that's one of the ways to
differentiate professional creators
professional creators rely on
established copyright markets to earn a
living you know to raise families to do
you know all of the things that we do uh
our members unfortunately they're not
the earnings just every time we do an
income survey the earnings just keep
going down uh according to our last
survey um um the median uh income for a
full-time author which is someone that's
devoted entirely to their writing career
and not doing anything else was $220,000
a year and only 10,000 of those dollars
actually came from selling books so you
know it was already a precarious
situation that got even more precarious
as we started dealing with AI I don't
know if I answered that question yeah no
ABS absolutely and I think you know part
of what we're you know I think people
think about these issues is is trying to
find that path to to a win-win situation
y right um that is that Fosters
Innovation and creativity um and
protects uh protects creators and I
think that's that's you know an ultimate
Challenge let me ask a second question
um which is uh a broader one maybe uh
maybe even a little bit autobiographical
for you um uh you know you're you're not
a large language model developer right
you're not a computer scientist right um
and so what's it like to to work at this
intersection of technology and policy
how do we ensure that policy makers
policy Advocates like you have the best
technological expertise like how do you
you know how how do you uh sort of come
upon the technological knowledge that
you need to do your legal and policy
advocacy work and vice versa you know
how do how would you Advocate that
technologist get their hands on on
policy questions and the policy
implications of their work again thanks
that's that's also such a such a great
question and I thought about this one
quite a bit because you know when you
when you just kind of dive into the work
you kind of forget how you're working or
why you're you're doing what you're
doing and in in sort of thinking about
this question I found it really
thrilling
because I remember like early early days
when we were talking about like what it
means for Law and what it means for
policies that no one really had any you
know everyone just had these kind of
rough metaphors for what was going on at
least on the law and policy side of
things you know people might say the AI
the machine is eating up stuff or you
know uh it's like uh or like it's
hoovering up stuff and regurgitating it
and to me because no one really knew
what was going on under the hood
technologically I think the lawyers did
not have that facility so even if you
see the the the the initial complaints
that were filed in some of the lawsuits
not not in our lawsuit but in in uh in
some of the other lawsuits against openi
and meta um the complaints were very
rough and it wasn't quite clear what the
allegations were and that's partly
because the translation hasn't hadn't
happened you know um I I as as someone
who you know in my copious uh spare time
I I try to translate I I I think that a
lot of it is is translating what the
technologists are telling us about what
they're doing into a language that you
know is is is that that that lay people
that are not Tech Tech ologist can
understand and then being able to put it
in a thoughtful uh kind of policy
framework because as long as there's no
you know no translation happening then
you might have policy Frameworks that
are anti-in Innovation or they might be
too strict or they might be too LAX
because there's a fundamental
misunderstanding of of what is going on
so for me it was uh really a you know
vital that I I actually went and you
know I mean I have I just I just have
such a like congenital like non- stem
brain you know I I can't remember the
last time I took a math class but um I
forced myself to learn to read the Cs
papers about uh you know llm development
and AI in general like going back to the
first uh um it was uh I think it was
it's it's Kiros at all I don't remember
but it was the it was an experiment to
match um screen screen caps movie screen
caps with the descriptions and that was
one of the first uh I guess like um
large language model experiments that
was used uh it was it used about um a
cashier of 11,000 unpublished books and
to me that was fascinating to like see
how the technologists were approaching
um you know what they were doing you
know uh to to as a writer to see them
kind of hearing just to read them
talking about how important books were
or fictions in particular was and in in
in uh in in in reifying certain Concepts
um you know and and so I yeah and and so
that's that's how I really I think it's
really vital I think for my advice to
technologist would be um
I you know it's hard when you're in kind
of in your narrow channel of work like
it's the same in law right you know when
we're doing law we're just like there's
there's there's like an internal kind of
grammar that we use there's an internal
language we don't think about what's
going on outside of it so we but I think
what's important are these cross
functional dialogues so you know you
know what
people you know so you might not go out
and say uh download 11,000 books for
your experiment you might you know seek
out a license or you might like actually
seek out people who can help you seek
out those licenses um it's it's also
just a risk mitigation you know
especially now you know you might face
the risk of lawsuits ET but um it's just
it's just good to be mindful of like
what's going on outside of your box I
guess all right yeah and I think you're
right I think both that uh the
hesitation that technologist may have
about come about understanding copyright
law is as high as the as what copyright
lawyers have about how large language
aots work they're both they're both very
you know daunting learning absolutely
all right well let's um let's take a a
turn gears here and and open things up
for for Q&A um maybe Casper if you you
can kick it off if you speak loudly I
might repeat your question into the
microphone I have a question about what
the Practical threat
actually you if you don't mind I I guess
I have a question about what the um
additional threat the publishing
industry um posed by Ai and large
language models is um beyond the
existing the internet you know um so so
for example I can imagine a scenario in
which um uh you've written a novel and I
say um uh I asked chat GPT to give me um
a uh word forword quote of the whole
novel and it comes back with 150,000
word answer and then I read that instead
of buying the book and then imagine that
lots of lots of people do this so we
have uh all the people who would
otherwise have bought the book are in
fact just um getting chat GPT to
effectively give them the book but
that's not happening yet and presumably
it's a pretty remote possibility so is
it that you're worried that that may
happen or is it something else is it
something short of that that you feel
like poses a threat to the publishing
industry yeah that's a really that's a
really good question too I mean
um you're right that that's a remote
possibility it it could be there was uh
um computer scientist at the University
of Chicago benha I I I I think it's his
name but he was able to get uh chat GPT
to like give him each successive line
from Harry Potter and he kept going on
so but then open AI put in filters that
now you know now the response is due to
copyright restrictions we can't do that
so um so that's not actually the threat
I think that the the ultimate threat is
devaluing uh you know human authorship
uh when you have so I'll give you
examples of what what we see that we are
concerned about um one one thing is
especially with the internet a lot of
the publishing industry and how people
read has moved to uh you know it's it's
sort of controlled by a few big you
know olop any I'm I'm not going to say
that word but you know like uh like
Amazon um Amazon controls so much of
distribution and consumption of books
and they thrive on volume so
self-publishing is a huge thing now what
happens with AI is that it's so easy to
write a book write a book or like put a
book on Amazon and kind of game their
system to like earn Revenue so we we see
examples of this all the time one of the
one of the examples that we've we've
seen is uh someone will take someone
else's memoir and run it through Ai and
create an unauthorized biography based
on the Memoir and you know it's shorter
it's more consumable you know it might
it you might be like I don't really want
to read the Memoir I'm going to go for
this um that's that's one of the that's
one of the threats that we see but like
just on a much bigger scale where AI
generated books will just you know will
will essentially replace human authored
Works which take much longer ER to write
and then there's kind of this like
scenario where people get even more
acclimated to sort of like thinking of
books as it's like there's you know
there might not even be a human author
in question people are just consuming
text um and so for us like as a advocacy
Organization for authors it's very
important to make sure that those
economic channels remain viable for for
use by human authors um I don't know if
that's that was a very good question
that's I don't think if that's a good
good good enough answer but ultimately
like we are you know
um in infringement it's it's the the
second thing that I do want to mention
is that it's like it's it's not
necessarily about the the harm of uh a a
a a chatbot reproducing your entire
novel but the harm to the principle of
copyright um you know the idea of
consent uh that's that's ultimately what
we're trying to vindicate both through
the LW suits and through our
advocacy I might add another perspective
of this from you know many sort of
academic authors um for whom
compensation is minimal or of or
sometimes you know
non-existent um are those other two
letters the consent and credit right and
so there are you know there are many
academic authors who would who right now
would recognize you know yes people in
the world are turning to
um you know commercial generative AI
tools to ask and answer questions about
how the world works right and we have an
interest as scientists or others in
making sure that the outputs are you
know have good science in them in so
ways they want to be in the model right
um but um you know they they operated
under a previous sort of publishing
regime in which they put the articles in
you know PubMed or they put them in you
know publish them in under an open
license
um and you know suddenly that you know
lends itself to to ingestion without the
kind of consent and and credit issues
even if comp you know compensation may
be more of mine for professional authors
but for academic authors you know those
other two C's can can be really
important as well that's really good and
and maybe because you know you you're
involved in the open source um aspect of
things I I was really interested in the
the new preference signaling uh
methodology that that the uh the the
creative comments put out I mean I think
so for instance even if you publish
something under an open source license
you might not have given a license for
it to be ingested for AI in which case
you know the consent thing still comes
into place but um yeah now we're moving
towards a more robust sort of speak like
yeah I think though yeah that is a
that's where I think will the you know
authors and and and scientists inventors
other kinds of people will will
ultimately need need to be heading yeah
and again like going back to the the
market part right you know I mean the
market for academic work is very
different than the market for a trade
book or for a romance novel you know or
or um or a detective
story
yeah come on down I have a very basic
question so forgive me question it seems
to me that a lot of what makes copyright
enforcable is whether or not someone is
infringing on the market value the
ability to make money and people's
ability to fight being unfairly ingested
without their consent um seems to be
increased if there is an organization
that they work for like the New York
Times that can say Hey you are in ping
on my future profits um whereas
individuals like
screenwriters right if their um
subtitles are uploaded into an open
database and that gets ingested it's
harder to make that argument that a
screenwriter that you're hurting their
future proceeds because they're not part
of this larger organization so my bigger
question is what are the failings of the
copyright law as it is currently written
and because so much of it seems to be
framed in terms of making money what is
that leaving
out I mean just so many so many amazing
questions I I I should should have
should have I should have known I'm an
MIT um so a a couple of comments on on
that actually it is interesting you
would think that working for an
organization like the New York Times uh
as a writer would kind of give you a
little bit more you know uh well would
would give you leverage for enforcing
your rights but what happens is that you
know when you're a staff writer for the
New York Times the entire copyright
belongs to the New York Times so or even
if you're a contributor a lot of times
the New York Times will take all right
in the work which means that you
actually don't have any rights left to
enforce so all of the enforcement that
is going on from a copyright point of
view is New York Times kind of enforcing
its own property interest in in you know
things that like authors have written so
but it is a very good question because
uh with screenwriters for instance there
are unions now unions are playing a very
important and interesting role right now
because one of the threats to the
profession comes from say Studios not
high ing screenwriters uh but you know
using Ai and last year um there were
some very intense negotiations between
sag aftera cuz it's also affecting
actors you know I've heard like just
very strange stories of like if you have
a tiny role for like $50 a day you show
up on set someone takes you aside gets
you to step in like a booth and they
they do a 3D print scan of your body and
then that's used for like so so there
are things like that that are happening
so unions are playing a very important
role right now in enforcing rights you
the the the difference between us and a
union is that unions unions also like
the the the way entertainment unions
work and this is just by way of
background in case you're interested and
I'm I'm going to get to your ultimate
question um the the way the unions exist
in the entertainment industry we're not
a union but in in screenwriting and
acting they exist because there is an
arrangement between Studios and the
talent that um that that the Talent is
actually considered an employee of the
production which is why they're able to
get health insurance and residuals so it
it it fundamentally always comes down to
health
insurance unfortunately you know so even
in that case the screenwriters don't
actually have any copyright in the work
because they are considered employees of
the studio for that but because they
have the union they can they can they
can push back against the um but they
don't have the same rights Visa V AI
companies now copyright law a lot of it
is about making money because um
copyright but it's you know it's it's
about making money but there are other
parts to copyright law that I'll mention
it's a really good question actually um
it's uh for our members they pretty much
only rely on copyright because they're
tradebook authors you know the the their
books the way they're sold is that a
publisher is interested in a book
there's like you know there could be an
auction for the rights the publisher
then rep packages those rights and sells
it to a film company if it's a big book
so like it's it's the value is it every
every stage of the supply chain for
those rights like has a value to that so
it's all driven by copyright for our
members um what copyright the other
things that copyright really it's been
called the engine of free expression by
the Supreme Court and it's not something
that we really focused on today but um
you know I I think that with with how
easy it is to kind of generate
misinformation using Ai and uh if you
know it's that signal noise kind of
question that comes of like the signal
gets buried when there's too much noise
which is one of the reasons why we need
to sort of you know have regulations
around like what is AI generated you
know what what the customers are
consumers are
encountering
um the copyright also leaves out other
areas you know because copyright is
limited to the protection of uh
expression copyright does not protect
ideas so there's a very often times
authors will come to me and they'll say
someone plagiarized my work and I'm just
like well did they actually copy your
expression and they'll say no but they
take took my idea well that's not really
actionable copyright so but there are
these other attributes of the work like
an author's voice for instance you know
you can we're seeing this now in in in
in in analogous areas you know like
voice actors for instance have been able
to make a really good case for like the
the the they're having they call it like
biometric ownership of like their their
voice attributes but authors have an
authorial voice like Hemingway has a
very recognizable voice that's not
really protected by copyright you know
um so so there are things like that that
you know that that ideas are not
protected if you have a very unique idea
for something that's not really
protected by copyright so there's still
things that fall kind of outside of the
fall out of the copyright seve so to
speak yeah thank you
first of all thank you very much for the
talks and also the discussions L I feel
it's very insightful and meaningful to
all of us uh the question I have
actually we had a a chance to briefly
talk about this before the session but I
think probably will benefit everybody in
the audience is that in MIT you have
many many events like this and it's
usually recorded and uh usually when
recorded this and if if if you put this
on website we ask speak sign consent so
that's the
normal situation or process everybody is
familiar with but with generative AI you
can add some more generate more valuable
uh results from it B you can easily
summarize a person's presentation or
panel
discussion and generate that into a
summary
and uh I know you told me you need to a
separate resent recent form for that
report and signed by all the speakers or
participants I wonder if we can uh may
you can describe a little more detail uh
how we should approach this or can they
sign the same like yeah two items in the
same consent sure sure absolutely with
video recording
the rest yeah I know what kind of
potential risks could be if if we don't
do this properly thank you sure
absolutely absolutely so uh you're
you're looking at a few different things
one is the actual copyright right so um
if I come you know if for instance I
came here with a speech that I had
written and I go to the podium and I
read that speech and you recorded that
speech I Have a copyright interest in
that recording because that is a
recording of my you know Express
so when you do a release form a lot of
times like the release form will contain
an intellectual property release where
you say I actually like give you
permission to use any intellectual
property that might have come out of my
talk in a way that you you want to and
if you have that intellectual property
released then you're fine then you can
run it in a you know in an AI because
you have a broad release I guess like it
just it comes down to how broad or
narrow the language of your release is
um and then the second thing that you're
looking at is also rights of publicity
and personality especially if you have a
celebrity celebrities often times have
what are called rights of publicity
where they own um almost like a
trademark type interest in the way they
look or their particular style so you
want to make sure that your release
contains uh you know that you all that
they allow you to use it in that
wayk a follow as an audience I'm sit
here and listen to and I uh sub write a
kind of like a uh understanding or
summary about what I learn and do I need
to get permission from you no no no not
in that not as an audience okay got you
thank
you all right thank you uh my question
is about uh is there
a is there a difference between
potential infringement versus actual
instan it infringement because I I no
right you know having a model itself but
not using it to do X yeah versus the
actual X just wanted to get a better
understanding of that thank you
absolutely no there is no there is no
there is no such thing as like
infringement in the future the
infringement either occurs or not now
but you raise a very interesting point
because infringement when in the context
of AI happens the way I understand it
the way I explain it it happens at it
can happen at two different stages right
so you have a model but you're not
prompting it to do anything infringing
so you're not committing any
infringement however when the model was
trained there were copies made of works
during the training process and the
algorithm was run on so there is
infringement that has already occurred
at that point now as a user it doesn't
concern you but you know I just wanted
to be clear there's we say infringement
in the output versus infringement in the
input so let me take a you know kind of
Devil's Advocate position here here
right which um I think we have heard
from some of the large language model
developers but in the story goes
something like this um if I walk into a
li you know if I go into a library and I
read every book on the shelf and I walk
out and I write the Great American
novel I don't know anything to the
people in the library right um is that
what Lang large language models are or
what's different setting aside uh the
specific case of when we know that they
are trained on specifically pirated
information right but if uh but is is
that is that specifically the issue yeah
so that's you know I mean so my my kind
of I get asked this question a lot and
my my usual flippant answer is like are
you worth 1.3 million 1.3 trillion
dollar because that's what you know
that's what the the value of a sort of a
technology like that is but I mean it is
a very like good question because What's
um there are two things that I want to
say about that one is you know goes back
to your earlier question about
translating sort of between technology
and uh policy and language how important
language is so you know a lot of the
language that we use around AI has come
from people that have a very large
commercial interest in AI so you know
the the reading analogy is is is done
precisely in some ways it does obfuscate
what happens in a kind of on at the
technical level when you train a large
language model um which you know as I've
said a few times like it actually makes
a copy even the probabilistic
representation in the model is a
representation of that expression now
you know you can make that argument well
you know when you're reading something
or memorizing something your brain is
doing the same thing and is that like
copyright infringement because your
brain is doing that
um I mean this can get philosophical
like I guess my brain is a tangible
medium of expression you know to use uh
the definition but the the the the short
answer is that you know this the the
difference is between scale you know
it's like and and copyright Fosters like
it also goes back to this idea of human
authorship so copyright is in precisely
interested in humans innovating you know
based on the work of other humans but
copyright is not going to protect like a
mechanical or like an algorithmic like
process that can be um that can be used
on a very massive scale you know to do
the same thing okay um Let me let maybe
we'll have one more question um Casper I
would just be curious about what what
your idea about the long-term future
would would be in 15 years time yeah um
H how would you um how would you hope
that what sort of arrangement between
authors and AI companies would you like
to be in place can I just give a
tangible example um it suppose I I wrote
Harry Potter books um you suppose I I
allow I license I say it's okay for um
AI to be large language models to like
take my books and read my books is it
that I get paid a flat fee for that or
is it that when um when the AI is then
used to generate a um fantasy children's
book I get some portion yeah but would
that work because um how would you be
able to trace like how how big an
influence my books were on the output
versus other books that it may have read
like so how are you thinking I mean I've
I've got a clear sense of like you don't
want them to be trained on pired
versions of my books now but what is the
15-year like IDE good solution that we
could find to this that's uh you know
we've spent months talking about this it
is like it believe it or not like uh it
is the as they say the million-dollar
question in all of the specialized
copyright law panels that I have
attended in the last like few months
licensing um so one thing that I will
say is that uh licensing is already kind
of mushrooming because I think the the
the the presence of large language
models created a need and then there
were tons and tons of startups that are
like filling that need right now so um
you know almost on like a semi weekly
basis I get uh an email from a startup
saying hey we're building like a
licensing model for like content are you
guys interested in talking to us uh we
uh the author's Guild actually has one
partnership right now and we will have
other Partnerships uh non-exclusive
partnership with a uh company called
created by humans which um facilitates
uh licensing to AI companies so uh 15
years down the line it might happen like
in the next year that like we have all
AI uses are are are s of license now the
question that you ask is a very
interesting one because the value of the
market has not been established yet so
you know the few examples that we have
seen so for instance Harper Collins the
big publisher they entered into a AI
licensing deal and they set the value of
each work at
$5,000 um for a three-year license uh
lump sum you know the work can be
prompted as many times used as many
times so so that's one that that's one
way people are looking at it do we go
for a lumpsum there are technological
ways that I understand are you know I'm
at MIT so I I someone here should should
tell me if this is true or not but uh
there are the technological means that
are coming around where you can kind of
calculate a base value for how many
tokens were used you know and and and
and align it to the particular work so
it's not even that like you know someone
generating a fantasy novel it's like
whether or not Harry Potter that the
token attributed to Harry Potter in the
large language model were were used in
generating a response about Wizardry for
instance so those things are coming but
but I I imagine that the income from
that is going to be minimal now we're
also seeing all kinds of interesting
Downstream uses starting to come online
like chat Bots based on authors uh one
of the things that uh early on came
online was something called The Dan
Brown chat bot where you can kind of
talk to Dan Brown about his books and it
was basically they had ingested the
books um so but the licensing question
is a very interesting one for me because
I'm I'm in like in in in in discussions
around that a lot uh right now people
are starting with lumpsum but I think
there's going to be a more a finer
economic value that we will eventually
ascertain for these
rights all right uh and I'll just say
one final thing that longterm in the
field of generative AI is 15 months
months but we do need to be thinking
about about 15 years deep seek came
online so now we don't um yeah so uh
right now we're going to take a brief
Break um and there there may still be
some snacks outside restrooms down the
hall um and our um will be uh in
attendance at the next panel our next
speaker will come a few minutes after
that and we'll start up again soon so
thank thanks very much
[Applause]