I liked making things in Algeria.
We had a mechanic next door, so I would
go and tinker and work with him.
So that hands-on
experience came from there.
That's what MIT is about.
So somehow I arrived to MIT later,
and I find that this place emphasizes the
hand and the mind together.
I was born and raised in Algeria.
In a small town at that
time called Qasl al-Bukhari,
it's actually a beautiful still today,
with the mountains and the plains.
My father was killed.
I was maybe about three years old.
My elder brother at that time who was, I
would say, 12 or 13 years old,
so he became the head of the family.
We did not have many
books or access to books.
Sometimes a person can get a book maybe
from France or from someplace,
and then the book is passed around, a
book on math or physics.
I was very, very weak in math.
My brother, Mahfoud
one summer, took me aside.
Till today, I don't know what he did,
but he kind of
got the right trigger.
I sat down with him and
he was teaching me math.
So then I went from below zero to
getting the first prize in
mathematics that next year.
I wanted to go abroad,
but not any other place.
It was the United States of America.
So when I came to Boston, I was at BU.
One time, the instructor took me and a
couple of other students
by the Charles River on the Boston side.
So then she says, "Do you
know what those buildings are?"
That is MIT.
And I say to myself, "I
have to be with those people."
So the work that I do is in design,
modeling, dynamic
systems, control systems.
And also you could say maybe adding
intelligence to systems.
And all of this applied
to robotics, automation.
With a place like MIT, you get all these
opportunities to work with
among the most intelligent people.
You can just pick up the phone and maybe
you're speaking directly
to one of the world experts
in nanomaterials or what have you.
And with that, you
can do maybe big things.
And so when you work in these kinds of
activities or programs,
then you can see the
impact at a large scale.
We don't have to wait maybe many years,
but you can see that in
a short amount of time,
the impact that they are doing.
And that is, I think, very rewarding.