Um today we're going to talk about the
sum trotder theorem. I mentioned the sum
trotder theorem on the first day and it
could think of as a fundamental theorem
in projection theory. It's um the the
one of the rare theorems that is
completely sharp. is just the right
answer for a natural question in
projection theory. Um and um and yeah,
so we're gonna talk about it. Um and see
yeah, so so there's some interesting
techniques involved in it. Um and yeah.
Okay. So so that there so that so that's
what we'll do. Um all right. So let me
remind you what it says.
[Applause]
So what we talked about on the first day
I called it the sum troder projection
theorem.
So the setup was that you have a finite
set in the plane and you have a set of
directions
and then s= s of xd is the largest
projection of x in any of these
directions.
So that's that's the if and then the
conclusion is that the number of
directions is bounded by s2 overx + 1
which we saw in the first.
Okay. Um so this theorem is really a
correlary of the theorem that they
proved that is more general that I'll
that I'll state now. Um, and the more
general theorem is a theorem about how
points and lines intersect in the plane.
Okay. So let's say X is a set of points
in the plane
and L is a set of lines in the plane.
The number of incidences between X and L
is the number of pairs. So take a point
and a line so that the point is in the
line
and we make a picture.
So suppose those are our lines and these
are our points. Um, how many incidences
are there?
This line has two points in it. So that
counts two. And that line has one point
and that line has one point. So that's
four instances.
You can also think of this as the sum
over all the lines in the set of lines
of the number of points on that line.
This is a way of measuring sort of how
how much the points and lines are
intersecting with each other.
Okay.
So the the general summarity troder
theorem says that um
you have some points and some lines. The
number of incidences between them is
bounded by the number of points plus the
number of lines plus
points to the 2/3 lines to the 2/3.
Okay, let's look at some examples to see
where this stuff comes from. Um, and the
examples will also remind us of the
connection with projection theory.
[Applause]
Okay. So, how could we have x
incidences? Um, that's not too hard to
do. If you have one line and you put all
the points on it,
then the number of incidences is around
x.
How could you have l incences? That's
not too hard to do either. If you have
one point and you have all the lines
passing through it. Um then the number
of incidences is around the number of
lines.
Okay. Now how can you get this? This is
the most the most interesting and it's
you know it's it's a fundamentally
trickier example than the first.
So the third example is one that we have
discussed. It's based on an integer
grid.
So let's say x is an n byn
integer grid.
Okay. And then we're going to try to
draw some lines that each hit many
points. And we observed in class on the
first day that if you have a line at a
rational slope then it will go through
many points. So those are our lines.
So let's say um so we have to make this
a little more precise. So first I'll
describe the rational slopes. So q subm
is defined to be the fractions a over b
where a and b are integers
and the a and b have size at most n.
Okay. Now our set of lines
is a set of lines with slope in qm.
Um and they pass through a point of x.
Okay.
Oh, this is a good day for colored
chalk. So, here is a typical line from
our set of lines. I pick a rational
slope and then I start at any of the
points and I draw a line at that slope.
Okay.
All right. So now let's try to compute
um how many points and how many lines
and how many incidences this has.
Um all right. So the size of x is n^2.
It's easy to see. How many different
slopes are we talking about? Well the
number of fractions is around m^2. Some
of those are reducible. Um but it turns
out that the number of distinct
fractions is still around m^ squ.
So this is uh
not trivial but not difficult.
Maybe I'll put a little something about
it on the homework.
Okay. So now
uh how many incidences do we have? And
we can say that
well each point is in a line of every
one of these slopes. So the number of
incidences is number of points times
number of slopes. So that's n^2 * m^2.
Okay. Now
how many different lines do we have?
Well we we have m² direction. We have to
think about how many lines are in each
direction. And actually thinking about
the number of lines in each direction,
you really you can think of it in terms
of projection theory.
So suppose S is one of our directions.
Let's say pi subs the projection at
slope s of x1 and x2 is um x2 - sx1. I
guess the the projection whose fibers
are lines of slowbass.
All right. And um so the number of lines
in direction S is exactly
the size of this projection.
Okay. And how big is the projection?
Well, so let's make a little lema. Um,
so
s is in qm and x is as above. Then the
size of this projection
is bounded by m * n.
So proof. Um,
okay. So we have x1 and x2 are integers
between 1 and n
and s is a over b.
So if I take ps of the point x1 x2 I
have uh what is it? x2 - a over b x1
which I'll put over a common
denominator. So it's b x2 minus a x1
over b.
And this here is an integer
of size at most like m * n
m * n.
So there are at most m * n choices for
for what this could be up to a constant.
Okay. So therefore the number of lines
is smaller than um the number of slopes
times m * n lines per slope. So that's
like m cubed n.
Okay.
These are written as upper bounds. There
are also matching lower bounds. Um so
the so that those upper bounds are
actually tight and if you do a little
algebra you will see that the incidences
between x and l is at least l to the 2/3
x^ 2/3
just by plugging in that this is l
that's the number of incidences and
that's x.
So that's where this thing comes from.
Okay.
Um
so the the two main ingredients we're
checking how many directions there are
that are have slope. how many rational
numbers are there with height up to m
and how big is each of these
projections? And you can take those same
computations and feed it into the
projection theory set up here. Um and
you you would get you would get theorem
one.
You you would get that this is a sharp
example for theorem one.
Okay.
Uh little pause for questions and
comments.
Okay. So this example you can kind of
see from it that theorem one and theorem
two are related to each other and
theorem two is more general because this
could be any set of lines. Whereas in
theorem one in the projection theory
setup, we would have a set of directions
D and the set of lines would be all the
lines in direction D that go through a
point of X. So that's a somewhat
specific set of lines. And this one is
more general.
Um,
so it's not very difficult to get from
here to here and it's not that
interesting. So I got to leave it as an
exercise on the homework. Um
okay. Now another question that came up
on the first day is um are there other
examples in projection theory besides
this square grid that also are uh that
also are sharp for somebody trotder and
there are very few that are known but
since we just did this I can tell you um
a bit the other ones and uh it's
conceivable that that the list I'll show
you is is everything
Okay.
So, what are the sharp examples for
submar?
Okay. So we've just seen the
historically first example which is a
square
integer grid
and that goes back to air in the 60s. I
think there's a second example which is
a rather small variation on it but we
have we know so few examples that it's
worth mentioning. It is a rectangular
integer grid
and that was done by ele.
So instead of n byn just put n1 by n2
and then do a similar analysis.
Okay.
And then there is a third thing that we
can do which is to replace the integers
by integers in some other number field.
So for example
uh integers adjoin the square root of
two
um or perhaps another or perhaps other
neighborhoods.
Okay. So this is in a paper by Olivine
Silier and and and myself and it's
actually only currently worked out for
some special number fields, but I
suspect it works for any number field.
If anybody knows more about number
fields than me, this could be a nice
little project to work it out correctly.
Yeah.
>> One question about the rectang
>> um yeah, there probably is. So um
yeah so it you know it takes a little
writing and whatever you see what
happens for each one and each n1 and n2
um but there yeah but there are sharp
examples that involve not grids that are
not square
um okay so let me say a little more
precisely what this means here
so we would have a set
in our ring of things of height up to
So that would be the set a1 +
square of 2 a2 and with the
property that with so with a1 and a2
integers and of size up to n
and our our new qm
um
maybe qrm. So quotients in this ring
size n this would be quotients of the
form a1 + 2 a2
over b1 + 2 b2
where the a i and b i are integers
and they have norm.
Okay. And now we can do the same thing.
So L is the set of lines
um with slope in
QRM
and they go through
a point of of X.
Oh sorry X. So X is just Rn by Rn.
Okay, so that's the example and then if
you compute a little bit you'll see that
everything goes in a way that's
analogous to the first example.
Um and um I guess I erased the key
points which was unwise but uh but if
you think through the first example you
know we used an integer grid. What did
we use about integers? Basically we just
used that integers are are closed under
taking products and taking sums. That
was what we used in our proof. And you
know this is a ring. This is a ring. So
these guys are also in a similar way
closed under taking products and taking
sums. So it works the same way.
U
okay. So it's a big mystery in the field
to have to have what's called an inverse
theorem for severity troder. An inverse
theorem would say that uh if you had a
set X and L that where this was tight
and where especially where this
dominated then what could you say about
X and L? Or as a special case if you had
a set X and a set of directions D where
this is tight what could you say about X
and D?
So we have uh on the one hand we have a
handful of examples where they're tight
and they're based on a lot of algebraic
structure. They're based on the ring of
integers in some number field. Um and on
the other hand we have very little in
the way of theorems that's about what
you know what what we can definitely say
about x and l if this is tight.
>> Yeah.
from kind of the quadratic number field
examples. Is it important for it to be
like a unique factoriization domain?
Seems like if that fails then you get
extra collapsing along.
>> Yeah. So the question is um is it
important whether whether our ring has
unique factorization?
Um I don't think it's I don't think it's
too important. Um we in our proof over
the integers I don't think we used
unique factoriization of integers
um
uh but you there are there are some
things we would have to check about each
number field like we'd have to check
that there are you know how many
quotients are there in this thing of
quotients um and um yeah so anyway so
there's there's I'll I'll put something
about it on the problem set as an
optional project for people who want to
explore
Yeah,
>> like for the for the original integer
brick case, we sort of reported nice to
have different slopes here. Do we have
some like requirements on our choice of
a I b I
>> um so okay so I think the comment is
that in the original case I said that
the a over b should be a reduced
fraction.
>> Yeah.
>> And do we have an analog of that? Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um yeah, we do. Um so you know so
this right so this is a set of all the
fractions A over B and if if a given
real number if a given fra rational
number can be represented in two
different ways it still only counts once
in Q and the same thing is true here. So
that you know the the same number here
might have more than one representation
of this flavor which makes it not
trivial to count the cardality of this
set.
Um and we and we do need to know the
cardality of this set to correctly
analyze things.
Um I guess something like unique
factoriization could come in there so
that there's you know before I said put
it at put it in lowest terms which is
maybe not quite as clear what that means
if you don't have unique factoriization.
>> Yeah. So say in the regime
x is greater than square.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um let me say the question
back and then I'll make sure I
understand. Okay. So if you look at this
right hand side, different terms will
dominate depending upon the relative
sizes of X and L. And there so there's
sort of different regimes. Um
so one regime is that X could be bigger
than L squ. So they have just a ton of
points and not very many lines. And in
that situation, this term is bigger than
that term and that term. So in in this
situation the x dominates.
Okay. So I think the question was um can
we describe some structure theorem in
this case? Yeah. So I think we can. So
in that case the example
is example one here. Um and so the
structure theorem would say that um you
really have to have well
you know there there may not you know
let me take let me say that so in this
regime I don't think there's that much
structure so I have some lines not very
many and then I have a ton of points and
I want to have x incidences that means I
had better put each of my points on a
line so I put each point wherever I like
but not not off in the middle of space
but on one of these lines and then I get
this many incences
so there's not that much of a structure
theorem we could ask for here and there
and and there's not that much of a
structure theory we could ask for when
this dominates but here if that one
dominates um there are very few examples
and there could be a structure theory
>> sharp example in the two um has to be
sharp example in the projection
>> yeah so the question is how how do sharp
examples in the two things compare
Um so if you start with a sharp example
in the projection theorem um then you
can make a set of lines that's the set
of lines that go through X and have
directions in D and that will become a
sharp example in the in the general
theorem.
Now if you start with a sharp example in
the general theorem it may not have the
special form that makes it relevant for
the projection theorem. So you can't go
the other way.
always have to read that. But like the
sharp example, they are like the the
rectangle with the square grid and the
one
all of them they are sharp for both
cases.
>> Yeah. So all the sharp examples we
mentioned are sharp examples for both
cases.
Um that's right. I guess there's one
more comment about it that um this setup
is invariant under projective
transformations.
Projective transformations take lines to
lines and of course take points to
points. And so if you start with a sharp
example maybe coming from a grid, you
can apply a projective transformation to
it and get a new sharp example for this
theorem,
but it won't any longer correspond to
the projection set.
Um so okay so the full list of sharp
examples for this theorem that we know
about is the ones I just wrote on the
board plus you can apply projective
transformations.
Um and yeah, in terms of proving an
inverse theorem, which is a big open
problem, proving an inverse theorem for
this would be harder and more general
than proving an inverse theorem for the
projections.
But we don't but that that the one for
projections, we don't know either. And
that would be a good starting point and
it might be a little more accessible.
Okay, let's keep going. Um so the goal
for the class is to describe how to
prove this thing, right? Um so the first
thing I'd like the first estimate I'd
like to show you is a double counting
estimate for the incidences which is in
a similar flavor to the double counting
estimates we've done earlier in the
class. But let's just see how much
double counting tells us about this
problem.
All
right.
So, double counter
All right. So by double counting we will
prove the following estimate. I'll call
it lema one. The incidences between x
and l are bounded by x * l to the 12
plus l.
All right.
So here's the proof. Um okay. So the
incidences
are the sum over the lines and I count
how many points are on each line.
And now I'm going to Koshy Schwarz that
so it's less than
Okay. So, what do I gain by Koshi
Schwarzing it? Well,
you think about the number of points on
this line squared.
It's very similar to counting the number
of pairs of points on the line.
And then we can make use of the fact
that for any pair of points, it only
lies on one line.
All right. So I'm going to bound this by
um here. So okay, so it's not quite
true.
Let me say all right, let me say
something in parenthesis. It is not
quite true that the number of points on
the line squared is smaller than
the number of points on the line choose
two.
That would be true if the number of
points on the line is pretty large. But
if there's only one point on the line,
then this is one and this is zero. So I
have to add here um I guess I can just
add one.
Okay. So now I get two terms. So this
one contributes
[Applause]
number of points on the line choose two.
So I all I'm doing is changing this to
this. Um and then I still have my L to
the 1/2.
Um and then um if I put in one here,
this gives me the number of lines to the
1/2 which groups with that. I get the
number of lines and this matches that.
Okay. So this here represents lines that
contain at least two points and this
represents lines that contain only one
point.
All right. And now the key point is that
that is smaller than
that.
Right? So what are we counting here? For
each line, we're considering pairs of
points on that line.
But you could also think you could sum
over all the pairs of points and then
ask how many lines go through that pair.
And there are at most this many pairs of
points and for each one of them there's
only one line. So that's the double
count.
So this here is the number of x1, x2 and
l. So that x1 and x2 are on l.
If you count the lines first and then
add up over the lines, you get this
expression. But if you fix x1 and x2
first, there'll only be one line. And so
you get this.
All right? and and now this is that. So
that's the end of the proof.
Okay.
So let's make some remarks about this
simple proof.
What double counting tells us and what
double counting doesn't tell us.
All right. So,
first we only used
that two points determine a line.
[Applause]
The only fact we used is that through
two points there's only one line.
So that means that it works in some more
general cases. So for instance it works
uh for points and lines over finite
fields
[Applause]
because over finite fields it's still
true that through any two points there's
only one line.
Okay. And generality is good but this
sort of a blessing and a curse in this
case um because the whole sorre troder
theorem is not true over finite fields.
I'll show you an example in a second.
And that means that this proof which
only uses this fact cannot really be
proving the whole summary troder
theorem. So that's remark B. So the
summarity troder theorem
is false
over FQ2.
U here's the example.
X is uh the entire plane, all the points
at Q2.
And L is all of the lines.
You could take literally all the lines.
Uh or you could take all of the lines y
= mx + b where n and b are in fq. Uh it
doesn't matter very much which one.
Uh okay. So size of x is q ^2. The size
of L is Q ^2.
And how many incidences do we have?
Well, each line has Q points. So
incidences between X and L is uh Q * L
which is Q cubed.
Okay. So this example is sharp for lammo
1. is that's equal to x L to the 12. It
matches that term up there and it's much
bigger than the right hand side of
summarity trotter,
right? Okay. Yeah. So, let's do a little
algebra. So, we have here an x * l to
the half and semi troder. We have an x
to the 2/3 l to the 2/3. Um, so there
are different regimes about who who who
dominates there. Um but this thing is
always bigger than this thing and it's
usually much bigger. Um so
and so here x * l is q cubed x to the
2/3 l 2/3
would be q 8/3 which is much less than
the number of instances. So the the sum
troder bound does not hold in this
example.
Okay. So um
okay so that shows something important
about the semary troder theorem that we
cannot prove it just by using the fact
that two points determine a line and
doing our double counting in a very
clever complicated way. we generally
need another input
and all of the proofs of summarity
troder theorem use somehow the topology
of the plane. Um so see
all proofs of similar trout
use the topology
of the of the plane in some way and the
topology of R2 is kind of different from
the topology of FQ2 whatever that might
mean.
Okay cool.
Um, so I know four different proofs of
I've seen four different proofs of the
Seady Troder theorem and they use
topology in some different ways. I'll
show you just one. I think it's probably
the one. I don't think it the proofs are
not that different from each other and I
uh I think this probably is the one that
um would is the most convenient for
thinking about projection theory for
balls in R2. Yeah,
>> you're saying Troder, but you always
mean this one on the lower board, not
the
>> Yeah, that's right. That's right. Yeah.
So, we'll prove this theorem and it's
not very it's not too hard to see that
this theorem implies the one on the top.
Yeah.
Okay.
Um, cool. So the proof I'm going to show
you is based on uh cutting the plane
into pieces
and it goes back to work of Clarkson,
Griebus,
um Edles, Briner, Shereir, and Welzel.
Um it's not it's not the very first
proof, but I think it's a very nice
proof. Um and then it's a slightly
revised version of that that that
Netscats and I worked on. Um, okay. So,
it's based on cutting the plane into
pieces. So, let me say what I mean by
that by stating a lema.
All right.
So, cell decomposition lab.
says that if x is a finite subset of the
plane and s is a natural number
um then there's a way to cut up the
plane.
So it's um I think of it as a cell wall
and then a bunch of cells. So each one
of these is open and I'll call it a
cell.
and the set W is closed
and I'll call it the wall between the
cells. So the image here is that I have
some points.
So that's X and then um
have something like this. That's W and
this is 01, O2, 03 and 04.
Okay.
Um
Okay. Okay, so it has some properties.
Number one,
each line
intersects
at most around S cells.
And also the line can intersect the wall
but in at most around S points.
Okay. And then um
each cell in the cell decomposition
has at most x over s2 uh points.
Okay. Now um it's not very obvious yet
where all this where all these formulas
came from. And it's definitely not
obvious how to prove this. Um, but it's
it's pretty easy to prove this in the
example that X is uh approximately like
a square grid. So, let me just show you
that as a motivation for where this
might come from
and to help digest what the what the
lema says.
>> Ah, yeah. So right
so the comment is I didn't say anything
about a set of lines. Um
so so
what what this means is uh for every
line L and here this is for every line.
Um now if we had a set of lines all we
would really need is to have this for
the lines from our set of lines. But in
practice it's actually just true for
every line.
Okay.
All right. So, the cell decomposition
lama in general is some somewhat
difficult. We'll talk about the proof,
but let me show you an easy case that I
hope will motivate the statement.
>> Yeah,
>> we want X to not intersect the wall.
Looks like you just put X in the wall.
It looks like we could just put X in the
wall. Um, let's see here.
Yeah. So, another comment is that X is
allowed to be a subset of the wall. And
that sounds a little suspicious.
Um, but um, we do get something from
that because every line only hits the
wall in S points. So if X were a subset
of the wall, then every line would only
hit X in S points. And that would be a
useful tool for us, right? Also remember
that S is a parameter. So for each S,
there's a way of doing this. And we're
going to eventually, you know, we'll
look at our set of points and our set of
lines and then we'll pick an S that's
strategic. So if S is small, this is
really quite quite strong.
Okay.
So here's an example
is that x is uh is roughly
a square grid.
So let me make that more precise. Let's
say x is contained in 0 to n^2
and x intersected with a unit ball
around any center is small
and let's say that there are around n^2
x.
So what does this x look like?
have an n byn box
and um yeah, let me imagine cutting it
like a checkerboard into unit squares
and um this tells me that I have on the
order of one point of x in each unit
square.
Okay, but this is a class of sets that
so I call this this is like roughly a
square grid.
Okay, so now how would we cut it up?
I cut it up
like this
and over s. So the wall is S vertical
lines
union with S horizontal lines.
Okay,
so the wall cuts it into S squared
pieces. And because my set is
distributed so evenly, each of these
pieces has about the same size. So that
gives me the third bullet.
And if we were to make a line in this
picture, well, it can only cross each of
these other lines once. So a line will
intersect the wall at most 2s times.
And it to go from one cell to another
cell, it has to cross the wall. So we'll
only enter about two S cells.
Okay. So the
the bullets are not hard to check.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay. Um
so
so this um de decomposition method based
on the key observation that it's
actually helpful to cut up our problem
like this. Cut up our space like this
and then count the incidences in each
cell separately and the incidences on
the wall. Um and in each of those pieces
we can use our double counting argument.
But when we add it up at the end, we may
get something better than using the
double counting argument globally.
Okay.
All right. So, proof of theorem two
assuming this lema.
All right. So, we're given uh x and l
and s is going to be tb
and we can apply this uh thing.
Okay. So let's say that x i is x
intersected with oi
and we can say that x i is less than or
equal to less than x / s^2 that was
given to us as a bullet point and the
sum over i of x i is at most x because
these are disjoint sets. Okay. Um now
let's say that li is the set of lines
that intersect the cell oi.
Okay. Now these are disjoint. Each point
is only in one cell. These are not
disjoint. Um because a line goes through
many cells. So this blue line belongs to
LI for this I and this I and this I but
not for this I or this eye or that I.
Okay. So if you add up over I the size
of L I that is bounded by S times the
size of L because each line in L belongs
to at most S cells.
All right. So now let's count our
incidences.
So
there are incidences from each cell
and the incidences related to the E cell
have points from the E cell and they
have lines that enter the E cell.
There also are incidences involving the
wall. So add the incidences from X
intersected with the wall at L.
Okay. Now we apply our double counting
LMA to estimate each of these things. So
that's less than um the sum on I
X I L I to the 12 plus LI.
And for the wall, well, each line only
hits the wall s times. So we have s
times the number of lines.
Okay. Now from this point on, we just do
a little bit of algebra. We just have an
expression involving these numbers x i
and li. And we know a few inequalities
about x i and li. and we'll just put
them together.
Um
here, uh it's reasonable to Koshy
Schwarz because I know information about
Xi and Li separately. So that will
disentangle this sum on i Xi 2 to the 12
sum on i li to the 12. This sum on li I
just read that off and that can be
grouped with that.
Okay. Um, and now what do I do with this
sum of squares? Well, I know that each x
i is bounded by something. So, I can
pull that out.
So, I'll have x over s^2. And I'll have
left the sum of x i.
This sum of li is just here. So it's S L
to the 12 and I copy this.
Okay, this sum of X I is bounded by X.
And so then I'll do a little algebra
here. This is the important term. I'll
have an X^
squared to the 12.
So X and X. I'll have an L to the 12.
And I'll have some powers of S. There'll
be a 1 over s coming from here and an s
to the 1/2 coming from there. So al
together I have an s to the negative
one2 and this I'll copy over.
Okay, let's pause there for a second
after the algebra.
Okay. So let's take stock of the bound
that we got and how it compares to the
double counting argument.
If you compare this to the double
counting argument, the terms sort of
match up. So in the double counting we
have x l to the 1/2 and that first term
gets decreased by s to the minus a half
when we when we uh introduce our cutting
and then the second term of l gets in
increased by a factor of s.
So if originally the first term
dominated then life will get better when
we uh do this decomposition
and if originally the L dominated then
life will not get better when we do this
decomposition.
Okay. So at the at the end here we just
choose S greater than or equal to one to
minimize the right hand side.
Um, and if you do a little bit of
algebra, you'll get out the summary
trout bound.
Okay.
Um,
so I remember spending some time trying
to digest why things were getting better
when we subdivided.
And here was one thought I had about it.
If you look at the double counting
bound, there are these different
regimes. So there's a regime where the
left term dominates and in that regime
the double counting bound is bigger than
the truth
and there's a regime where the right
term dominates
and you can always have L incidences so
that's not that when the right term
dominates it's the truth
okay and so what are the regimes the the
right term that the L dominates if L is
bigger than X square.
So we have a lot of lines compared to
the number of points then um then double
counting already gives a sharp bound.
Okay. So suppose originally that L is
not bigger than X squ. So if I just
apply double counting out of the box the
the X L to the half would dominate which
I'm not so happy with.
Then I try cutting things up into cells.
I count the incidences in each cell.
Is life any better?
Well, I have S squared cells. So, if I
if I look and and the points are kind of
evenly distributed. So, if I look inside
one cell, the number of points goes down
by S^ squ, which is quite a lot.
How about lines? Well, not every line
goes through this cell. So, the number
of lines also goes down.
But because each line goes through many
cells, each line goes through S cells,
the fraction of lines that I would
expect to go through this cell is 1 / s
of all the lines.
So the number of points goes down a lot
and the number of lines only goes down a
little.
By doing that, I'm tilting things
towards having a lot of lines and few
points. And if you think about if you if
you track you know what is the best
value of this S. What happens is the S
is best when we cut it in such a way
that inside of each cell the number of
lines is the number of points squared.
And that means the double counting is
giving the correct bound inside of each
cell.
Okay. Uh, questions or comments.
Okay. So, let's talk about how to prove
the cell decomposition LMA, which uses a
little bit of topology.
Um so in our cell decomposition lema we
want to take our points and kind of cut
them up in evenly in some way and that
is reminiscent of a classical thing in
topology called the ham sandwich theorem
and the cell decomposition lama is like
a like a cause a variant of the ham
sandwich theorem. So I will first recall
the ham sandwich theorem and how to
prove that and then we'll we'll uh work
up to this.
All right. So our our starting point in
topology is going to be the Borsuk ulong
theorem.
So I'll I'll recall that. I'll state
that and then we'll try to prove
everything else from from Borsukan.
All right.
So the borsak gulam theorem says that if
you have a function from the n sphere to
rn which is continuous
and it's antipodal. So that means f of
negative theta is negative f of theta
for every theta in the sphere. Um then
the conclusion is that 0 is in the image
of f. There is some some point in the
sphere that got mapped to zero.
Okay.
Um,
so as a correlary of that, we're gonna
do the ham sandwich theorem.
So one version of the ham sandwich
theorem says that if 01 up to O N
contained in Rn are bounded open sets
um
then there exists a hyper plane H that
bisects the
So for instance, if I had two bounded
open sets in the plane, there would be a
line somewhere that bisects both of
these sets.
Okay, so proof. Um, so first we need to
sort of parameterize our choice of all
the hyperplanes.
And a good way to think about that is
that a hyper plane is related to a
linear function.
So this is a hyper plane. I also I'm
going to have one a hyper plane and one
side of it. or pay attention to which
side is which. So this shaded region
would be the region um
a1 x1 plus a n xn is bigger than b. So
one side of a hyper plane can always be
described that way and we have the
freedom to scale a. Um so let's say that
theta is a1 up to a n comma b that could
be in the n sphere by scaling theta
which doesn't change the hyper plane.
Okay,
so those are my hyperplanes. And now f
of theta
um
let me say
here let me say it this way. This guy
plus b is bigger than zero.
And uh this thing here I will call l sub
theta of x.
Okay. So f of theta is f subi of theta
is the volume of oi intersect l theta is
bigger than zero. That's the volume of
oi on this side
minus the volume of oi and l l sub theta
is smaller than zero.
So f_subi of theta is the volume of this
part of oi minus the volume of that part
of oi.
Okay. So notice that fi of theta is zero
if and only if the hyper plane
associated to theta
biseects oi.
Okay. Um also
f_si is antipotal
f_subi of minus theta is negative f_subi
of theta
because if I replace theta by minus
theta I take the minus of all these
coefficients and I'm replacing l of
theta by negative l of theta and so that
switches
uh who so I so I'll have the same zero
set the same hyper plane but now this
one will be positive and that one will
be negative.
So I'll switch these two things which
reverses the sign of fi of theta.
Okay.
Um
f_subi is also continuous.
So if I adjust theta then I'll make a
small motion of this plane and that will
change these volumes but only
continuously because the sets are
bounded and open.
Okay, so finally I'll make f by just
putting together all these fns. And so f
is a function from the n sphere to rn
and it's continuous and it's antipodal.
So the conclusion is
so then Borsagulam tells me that there
exists some theta. So that f of theta is
zero and that means that h theta bisects
all these sets.
Okay.
Um
all right. Now this by itself is not
going to be super helpful for us. Um we
have a set that lives in the plane. So
the theorem says you know I can find a
line that bisects any two things. Um I'm
hoping to take a complicated set and cut
it into many even pieces. And so a more
relevant warm-up is some way of bicting
many sets not just two.
Um okay. So if I put more open sets here
then there will not be a hyper plane
that bisects all of them but I could be
more flexible about what sort of cut I
would allow. So it can't be a hyper
plane. It has to be a little bit more
complicated. And it turns out to be a
reasonable idea to consider cuts by
polomials of some degree. And there's a
so there's a natural generalization of
this.
Uh you could do really any class of
functions but but for this application
polomials are useful and it's called the
polomial ham sandwich theorem.
All right.
All right. So here's
here's a more general version polomial
hand sandwich.
Okay. So let's say polomials of degree D
in Rn
that is the set of polomials so
polomials
in n variables over R so that the degree
is at most D
and so this is a vector space
and it has dimension approximately d to
the n. If you if if the dimension n is
fixed and the degree is going to
infinity
u the dimension is not hard to figure
out. You count how many monomials are
there of degree at most d.
Okay.
Um so the proposition says
that if capital n is strictly less than
the dimension
of this space
then
there exists a polomial p the space of
polomials
which is non zero
and the polomial bisects each of the
open sets. So let's say
fi of p is defined to be um
the volume of oi intersect p is positive
minus the volume of oi intersect p is
negative
and uh fi of p equals zero for all i
from one up to Okay,
so that's the statement of the
proposition. Instead of using a hyper
plane, we use a degree D the zero set of
a degree D polinomial to bisect our
sets. And then we can bict many more
sets. And this is exactly how many. As D
increases, we have more uh degrees of
freedom, bigger dimension, and we can
bisect more things.
Um so at the level of intuition you can
think of this in terms of degrees of
freedom.
Um
so
the dimension of this space tells us
sort of how many degrees of freedom we
have to play with. Each one of these is
a constraint. And if the number of
degrees of freedom is at least the
number of constraints then the then the
theorem says we can actually find a
solution.
Okay.
Um, the proof is essentially the same as
this. So, proof, what do I need to
check? Um, well, fi.
So I I've
so I just need to check
that fi are continuous
and fi of negative theta is negative fi
of theta.
Okay. So why is it continuous? I won't
do a full proof but if you adjust the
coefficients of this polomial a little
bit then the set where it's positive
changes but only a little bit and so
this volume should only change a little
bit that's continuity
and why is it antipotal well if I switch
P to negative P um actually yeah let me
put P's here
if I switch P to negative P then it
interchanges these two sets and so it
swi switches the sign of fi of p.
Okay,
cool.
All right. And now f is going to be
f_sub_1 up to fn.
Now f is a map from where to where. F is
a map from polomials of degree D on Rn
take away zero
to RN.
Why is that?
Okay,
I was waving my hands a little bit when
I said that f is fi is continuous.
um and uh fi is is not continuous at
zero.
If you know if the polinomial is zero
then both of these sets are empty. So I
guess by the definition fi of zero would
be zero. Um but um uh then if I move p a
tiny bit so it's not zero then these
sets are these sets will appear and
they're they take up most of space. So
there would be sort of a jump
discontinuity in those sets. Um so the
reason we had to do this is that fi is
only continuous on the space of
polinomials without zero. So if I take a
nonzero polinomial and I change the
coefficients a little bit then this set
will only change a little bit.
Okay.
that. So actually I should say that
that's not completely trivial that fact.
Um it takes a little a little proving
um
it's related to the fact that if you
have a nonzero polomial then any of its
level sets like cannot have positive
volume.
If you have like polomial equals 3 that
defines a hypersurface and it cannot
happen that that hypersurface has
positive volume and that's basically
what you need to check that this is
continuous.
Okay. So this is a space from here to
here and to apply borsk ulam I need to
have a sphere for my domain. So this
sphere is sitting in here as long as n
is strictly less than the dimension of
this space. So this is this is where we
use this hypothesis.
Okay. And then Borsulam says that zero
is in the image of f which is what we're
trying to prove.
Okay,
cool.
All right, so we're getting close to
having a tool that we can use to do this
decomposition. And now we have a little
technical issue or a little mismatch
because in what we want is to start with
a finite set and have a cell
decomposition that kind of cuts it into
into even pieces.
And um this proposition is about open
sets. If we have a bunch of open sets,
we can simultaneously cut them each in
half. So we need a version where the
open sets are replaced by finite sets.
And that's not difficult to do. It's
just a technical thing. Oh, that's how
it works.
[Applause]
Okay. So proposition
um if SI contained in R2 or Rn I guess
is okay are finite sets
I = 1 up to N and N is less than the
dimension of poly D of Rn
um then
there exists a nonzero polomial poly D
of Rn
So that
um what does it mean? So in some sense
we'd like this polomial to bisect these
sets. Um but we have to say something
slightly weaker and I'll explain why. So
that SI intersect
P positive is less than or equal to SI /
2 and SI intersect
P negative is less than SI / 2,
right? Okay. So you know this set could
be a set of three points. So it's not
possible that half of them will be
positive and half of them will be
negative. So the best we could hope to
is that one would be positive, one would
be negative and one would be zero.
Okay.
Um Okay. So proof
for any epsilon bigger than zero, let's
say O epsilon I is the epsilon
neighborhood of SI.
So that's an open set. And so we can
apply our proposition to that set.
apply polomial ham sandwich
to O epsilon I and we output a polomial
pepsilon which is in the unit sphere in
the space of polomials
[Applause]
uh and it bisects them. So we know that
the volume
of oepsilon I intersect P bigger than
zero is half of the volume of oepilon I
okay so we have this for every epsilon
and now we want to take some kind of
limit as epsilon goes to zero and the
sphere is compact so the sphere sn is
compact.
So we have a subsequence
uh pepsilon
some subsequence of them converges to a
limit p which is a polomial in sn
okay and the claim is that the p does
the job.
So
let's say this is the zero set of P.
Over here P is positive and down here P
is negative. And suppose a particular SI
was not split up evenly like this. It's
more than half of that on that side.
Um here let me do that
yellow.
There's SI. So why can't that happen?
Well, think about what
the eps pepsilon would be doing.
So oepsilon i would look like this.
And what would pepsilon look like? Well,
it's a little perturbation of p. We take
uh you know we have some convergence. So
so that would be the zero set of
pepsilon here's pepsilon is positive
here is pepsilon is negative
and that violates this.
So
if SI intersect
P is positive was strictly greater than
12 of SI um then we'd have O epsilon I
intersect Pepsilon positive would be
strictly greater than 12 of OI epsilon I
contradiction
Okay.
Okay. So now let's prove the cell
decomposition lema.
So we improve the cell decomposition
lama by using the polomial by using this
proposition many times.
Okay. So we have some set of points
x
and first we use our uh proposition with
um n equals 1 and so d equals 1.
So we're only so actually easy case of
our proposition we're only bicting this
one set of points. So here's p1 equals
z.
So the output is a polomial P1 of degree
D1 = 1 and it bisects the set.
So we have X plus is the set of X and X
where P1 of X is positive etc.
Okay. Then we use our proposition with
n= 2 and we get a polomial P2 of degree
D2. D2 would probably also be one, but
it let me just put sort of the general
thing. So it would be less than our N2
uh to the 12.
Um okay. And P2 P2 bisects X plus and X
minus.
So here's the zero set of P2
[Applause]
and it bisects each half. So now I've
divided X into quarters.
Okay. And we keep going. So at step K,
I use my proposition and I have N K
which is 2 K and DK which is less than N
K to the 12. So that's like 2 to the k
over two
and uh and I I output a polinomial pk
and it bisects
the 2 to the k minus one previous guys
or two to the k previous guys.
So I'll draw one more. I have four
pieces and I find a new polomial and I
bict all four.
Okay. So now uh when do I stop? I choose
the final K.
So 2 to the K is S squared.
And that means the final DK around 2 the
K / two is around S.
Okay. So since I bisect at every stage
um I get x intersect o y smaller than x
/ 2 k which is like x s^2. So that's my
third bullet.
So I'm trying to prove
each cell has only a 1 over s^ squ
fraction of the original points. We have
that. And then I'm trying to think about
uh how each how the lines intersect the
cells and how the line intersects the
walls.
So these are the different cells and the
red stuff is the walls. So if I draw a
line here,
um
the line intersected with the wall
is smaller than d1 + dot dot dot plus dk
because you know how how many times does
a line intersect the zero set of a
polomial?
It's at most the degree.
Okay,
so these degrees are bounded by 2 to the
2 to the k / 2. So this this is a
geometric series.
It's bounded by its last term 2 the k /
2 which is around s.
So that's the second bullet.
Okay. And every time this pol this line
moves from one cell to another, it has
to cross the wall. So that also bounds
the number of cells that the line
intersects.
Okay. So that ends this the proof or
proof sketch of the cell decomposition
lema.
Um any questions or comments?