uh hello everyone my name is George vski
I'm former MIT Lin canab researcher and
now CEO of alata and our mission is
securing data collaboration and AI
supply chain so this is how AIML Works
companies in different industry develop
applications they deploy them into data
analytic
platforms and at a badrock they use
clout storage so they want to have data
daming decision making in real time and
respect data privacy and
Trust uh it turns out that in 82% of the
breaches involved Cloud story data so
this is vulnerable point of this
ecosystem and the data security software
Market is
skyrocketing uh according to Google
research if attacker has access to
0.01% of the data set he can completely
destroy the trained model so garbage in
garbage
out the solution is
alata alata provide the tool kit for
human users devices and
AIML uh analytical
platforms that enables to provide data
privacy and Trust by Design and our
product is fortified data Lake can be
implemented in hours in
multioud it provides intuitive user
experience and it can be seamlessly
integrated with AI platforms like data
brick
snowflake uh IBM Watson AWS maker and
others so let's look at the example the
client calls to the customer service and
all a your call will be transcribed to
the text and this text will be sent to a
application as a prompt a application
creates the personalized offer and this
offer will be provided to the client in
real
time so this data is very
sensitive and AI Mo and LM model is also
very sensitive so it's it's it's trained
on real financial transaction and real
credit history so alata can help here to
secure audio calls transcriptions
personalized offers models and also the
data set for
training so existing encryption
Solutions fall in two
categories some provide data privacy by
Design at cost of integration with AI
platforms and sums are opposite so
autostat can do both we provide zero
trust security and this is applicable
for a
IML uh additional autostat even can
boost the cloud the speed of the
operations because they also compress
the data for example loading the 1 gab
of encrypted data using zata can be
three times faster than just using the
same data in in the same cloud and also
data compression can help to lower the
cloud storage cost also up to
60% so we are
MIT based team we have US Patent for
this method and we've done pilots and we
have letter of support by loet Martin
and British
Telecom so
uh we were looking
for uh strategic partners and if you
share our vision we would love to
continue this conversation thank you