It is my pleasure uh to introduce not
one but two research scientists from
Kristen Ardley's lab. It's Amriita Soule
um and Amy Gulamett. Uh Amriita holds a
bachelor in science and a master of
science and life sciences from the
University of Mumbai and earned her PhD
in molecular biology and biochemistry
from Virginia Commonwealth University
where she studied DNA damage response
mechanisms in Christopher Valerie's lab.
Amriita completed her post-doal training
at Yale University in Ranjet Bindra's
lab focusing on combination therapies
targeting DNA repair pathways in solid
tumors. She'll be talking first and then
following her will be Amy who obtained
her PhD in the autonomous University of
Barcelona Spain where she focused on
epigenetic de deregulation in
hematological malignancies. In 2014, she
started her first pd-al position in
Hulgar Hines lab focusing on uh single
cell sequencing technologies. In 2017,
she joined uh Burget Kokals lab at Dana
Farber Cancer Institute to study
resistance and T- cell acute
lymphoblastic leukemia and cartis cell
therapies. um applying the knowledge she
has gained and developed in Hular Haynes
lab.
Okay, so let's get started. Please again
ask questions throughout with the
microphones and thank you. Uh thank you
Michelle and thank you for having us
here today. This is our very first time
at the MPG primer and we are very
excited to tell you guys all about the
developmental GTEx project. Uh before I
move on, I just want to thank um all the
donor families who have generously
gifted uh us such precious gifts to
support the important work. And just a
note that uh some of the slides will
have histology and tissue images.
Okay. So um before I move on to
developmental GTEx project, I'm just
going to give you a quick overview of
the GTEx project which probably most of
you are aware of. So the GTEx project
which was launched in 2010 aimed to map
the effects of genetic variation on gene
expression uh on a broad a broad range
of tissues. The primary goal was to
improve the understanding of regulatory
mechanisms in complex traits and
diseases. GTEx collected over 50
different type of tissues in around
thousand postmortem adult donors and uh
they also developed protocols which were
um very standard operating protocols for
tissue collection processing as well as
facilitated uh open data sharing via the
GTEX portal. The gene expression and the
splicing data was mostly generated using
bulk RNA sequencing. Through this tools
we also identified uh cis and trans
eqtlers altogether geek has been pretty
instrumental in linking genetic
variation to regulatory function and
thus helping researchers in um uh to
connect non-coding variants which make
up most of the G-W was heads and this
helps us to understand biological
mechanisms and disease pathways.
So all of the GTE work for most part um
generated whole genome sequencing data
and bulk RNA sequencing data. However,
with recent advances we have tools like
single cell RNA sequencing available to
us now. Uh technologies like these have
enabled profiling gene expression at a
resolution of individual cells offering
much deeper insights uh compared to the
bulkard seek. Um majority of efforts
like human cell atlas uh psych code hub
map ban and more are leveraging these
tools to systematically map transcrytoic
profiles across human tissues at
cellular level. Single cell seek as we
all know allows us to resolve cell tide
states and even differentiation
trajectories within tissues. These
efforts by these consortiums however are
very important. However, most of these
focus on adult tissues and most do not
capture developmental trajectories.
There has been some effort uh by the
human developmental cell atlas uh to
which is beginning to fill these gaps.
Uh they focus only mainly on prenatal
tissues. However, these studies are
generally focused on sampling the same
tissue across multiple individuals as
opposed to multiple tissues from the
same donor which hampers hampers cross
tissue comparisons and investigations
into um effects of genetic variation on
gene expression.
So
there is a need for pediatric normal
reference data. As we know a
comprehensive understanding of normal
human development is critical for uh
uncovering origins of many diseases. A
number of inherited disorders from
congenital mal forations, heart defects,
neurodedevelopmental
disorders originate during gestation.
Additionally, there are pediatric
cancers which are believed to arise from
uh transient development cell types that
are not captured in adult data sets. Um
also both genetic and environmental
influences during early development can
predispose individuals to diseases that
manifest later in life.
All this underscores the need for
pediatric specific reference data sets
to accurately study disease mechanisms
and identify their developmental
origins.
So here I would like to introduce the
developmental GTEx project which was
designed to extend the foundational GTEx
resource by incorporating a
developmental dimension. While GTEx
focused on adult tissues, DGEX aims to
profile gene expression across key
stages of early human development. This
project will collect tissues from 120
postmot donors stratified into four
developmental age groups, infancy, early
childhood, pre-pubertal, and
post-pubertal. Each group will include
approximately 30 donors, enabling
cross-sectional analysis of gene
expression changes across developmental
stages and across tissues. This data
this data will support investigation
into eight specific gene regulation
developmental trajectories as well as
early origins of disease.
Now in par to the human collection, DGEX
includes a non-human primate arm to
enable cross species comparison of
development developmental gene
expression. We are sampling 126 reesus
macaks 72 marmicetses across a range of
developmental stages covering both
prenatal and postnatal periods. The
postnatal time points are aligned across
species between humans uh humans
marmicets and macaks
uh which allows comparative
developmental analysis. Importantly, the
prenatal non-human primate samples
provide rare and ethically feasibly
feasible access to developmental time
points which are not accessible easily
in humans. This design enables to better
understand conserved and species
specific aspects of primate development
especially during uh early life stages.
Now there is still a limited
understanding of how well regulatory
networks and developmental programs are
conserved between humans and non-human
parents. Most of what we know about
human biology both in normal and disease
state has been studied in model
organisms uh like rodins especially
mice. However, mice are evolutionary
distant from uh humans especially they
exhibit key developmental differences
during uh uh during early postnatal
stages. These these differences limit
their translational relevance of
findings. Um as we have seen in that in
some of the clinical trials which failed
despite having strong pre preclinical
data in rodent models. In contrast, NHP
share more similar developmental
trajectories in humans making them
critical reference for understanding
early human development and improving
disease modeling. Therefore,
establishing normal reference data in
NHPS will enhance our ability to
interpret human developmental data and
bridge gaps between model systems and
clinical research.
The NHP component of the DJEX project
includes two key primate models. The
Reus Macak which is also known as the
old world monkey and the common marmicet
which is known as the new world monkey.
Marmicetss have been widely used in
biomedical research due to their small
size um high reproductive reproductive
efficiency and their tendency to produce
dzygotic twins sharing a placenta a
feature valuable for developmental
studies. Recess macaks are the most
extensively used NHP u are most
extensively used in NHPS in research and
are phogetically very close to humans
especially uh comparable uterine and
placental structures. Together, these
two species offer complimentary
perspectives on primate development and
help model the conserved and divergent
aspects of human paragy.
Taken together to summarize uh the DGEX
project aims to build a comprehensive
reference atlas of normal tissues uh
across three species. Uh here we are
again uh just to recapture we are
profiling uh variety of tissues from 120
pediatric donors across four age groups
and um also recess makers and common
monets. The ultimate goal is to define
developmental and tissue specific
molecular patterns across these three
species for integrative analysis using u
a number of sophisticated tools like
bulk RNA seek single RNA seek whole
genome sequencing to help characterize
gene expression chromatin accessibility
and gene variation. I'll let Amy
continue.
Yes, thank you so much Amita for the
wonderful introduction to the
developmental GTEx project. Building
upon that, I'm going to dive into how we
actually acquire the critical human
samples for the project. Our human
sample collection relies on the network
of the organ procurement organizations
or OPOS's across the United States. We
part we partner with six of them
including connect life and life gift
amongst others. These OPOS's provide us
with significant amount of volume of
pediatric donors referrals to screen for
allegible donors.
Now once a potential donor is identified
by an OPO. The next critical step is to
determine donor allegibility. This
process is very rigorous and relies on
specific criteria. We don't reinvent the
wheel here. We actually leverage the
existing organ and tissue transplant
donor screening processes that the
OPOS's already have in place. This is
this structure approach provides donor
families the opportunity to consider
donation for the developmental GTEx
project. As you can see on the box on
the right, this outlines some of the key
inclusion and exclusion criteria that
guide our selection. Donors have to be
18 or younger. They have not received
blood transfusion within the 48 hours
amongst others. We also are collecting a
large amount of donor meta data. This
builds directly of best practices from
the original GTEx project. The
deidentified donor level data includes
credformation sex, demographic details,
comprehensive medical history, birth
circumstances, environmental exposure
amongst others.
So now once a donor is allegible and
media data is collected the crucial step
is the tissue sampling itself. First the
develment geek tissue sampling utilizes
common coordinate framework. This is
critical because enables reproducible
sampling across diverse sites diver
different donors and even different
species. This ensures that a sample
taken from say a spe a specific region
of the lung in one donor is comparable
to a sample from the same region in
another developmental stage of another
donor. Secondly, the collected tissue
sites and all the metadata gathered are
aligned with other consortiums as
Amarita mentioned before. Um so sampling
is performed by highly trained recovery
teams with introduction of diagrams and
images of as visual guides for tissue
procurement process to ensure the
highest quality on-site instruction by
dedicated pediatric pathologists is
consistently available at the OPOS's
throughout the project.
Now let's look at the s this the
specific SC sampling schema itself and
how it varies is based on the unique
size and structure. So in general most
tissue sites we aim to collect a small
standardized samples. For solid organs
as you uh we collect a 2x5 by 1x1 cube
and for mucosa organs we'll collect a
2x5x1 subitted in it full thickness of
the organ. Each of these samples is
divided into three alocors as you can
see in the image. Two of them will be
frozen for molecular analysis and one
will be fixed for hystopathological
evaluation. One key important aspect and
beauty of this project is that we will
maintain spatial orientation of these
tissues. So the frozen part is adjacent
to the fixed part and the fixed part is
adjacent to the other frozen part. So we
uh know specifically the orientation of
these tissues.
Okay. So however studying developmental
introduces a unique challenge. Organ
size changes significantly during
development. As you can see here on the
left, heart sampling schema changes from
birth to to adulthood where we'll be
collecting whole hearts and non-human
primates. And then for younger donors,
we'll be collecting sections and then
for older donors will be we'll be doing
subsections. Again, this is another
example of a testy sample uh where
younger donors will be collecting the
whole organ but as uh but it will
collect young donors will collect the
full organ but older donors the samples
will be sections.
Understanding and adapting to these
demental changes in organ size and
structure is vital to ensure that our
samples are truly comparable across the
entire fidactic age range allowing us to
accurately track developmental and gene
expression patterns.
While we cover the human side of
collection in detail, it's crucial to
also highlight the tissue sampling in
our non-human primate collection. Tissue
sampling for the non-human uh human
primate is designed to map the human
tissue sampling as much as possible
without with modifications from species
specific anatomical and developmental
differences. The human the non-human
primate won't be affected by donation.
So we'll have additional tissues. tissue
eskeemia is minimal because as soon as
uh as soon as sample collection begins
immediately uh from ethanasia we also
have uh as a marina mentioned before we
also be collecting prenatal samples
okay so now having discussed eligibility
and sampling protocols I want to
highlight the impressive scale and death
of tissues that were actually collected
in the developmental GTEx project for
the human donors on average we're
collecting 20 different different
tissues directly on site and then there
will have there will be secondary
dissection dissections up to 72
different tissue from a single donor. So
similar for the non-human primates we're
recovering up to 50 to 60 tissues and
then we'll have secondary dissections
that will go up to 80 distinct tissues
per animal.
As you can see here, we'll be collecting
the skin. Uh there's a comprehensive
list um uh the brain, the thyroid, the
pancreas. Um
so yes, so to maximize uh certain organs
will be recovered and whole like the
hearts, the lungs and the brains and
these will be sent out to specific
places where the heart will be sent out
to the children's to chop where it'll be
further subdissected. The lungs will be
sent to the University of Rochester for
sub dissection followed by the lung map
protocols and the brain will be sent to
the University of Maryland and then uh
further sub dissection to the University
of Yale.
Okay. So I want to take a step back and
provide a highle overview of the entire
developmental GTEx workflow. This
schematic details the comprehensive
journey of our samples from donor to
data to ultimate to discovery. As you
can see here, the workflow presented in
two parallel streams. The left side
outlines the process for human postmortm
donors where you can see we'll be
collecting 120 donors. All of our
samples will have pathology review. Then
uh then the the whole food organs will
be sent to us uh to the broader will be
bio banks and on the other on this on
the other side we'll have the non-human
primates the marmiss collection from MIT
and the makox from Oregon will be sent
to us at the broad where we'll bioank
them.
So yes I'm
thanks Amy. Can I ask a quick question?
Yes. Um we have anonymous attendee
online asking about if the cause of
death like kidney failure or cancer the
person um will this affect the results
or are they excluded
from from donate for donation? Yeah,
there's a whole list of eligibility
criteria. Yeah,
thank you. Yes. So as uh Amy described
the workflow spinner brother is
authorized and uh what kind of samples
are collected? There are some samples
which are uh collected fresh and they
have to be processed uh as soon as
possible. One of them is blood. Uh till
date we have collected around 44 disease
pediatric donors and for each donor we
obtained two types of blood samples.
Frozen blood which is frozen on site and
is usually primarily used for DNA
extraction which the downstream can be
used for whole genome sequence. We also
collect fresh blood. This blood is
shipped to abroad for downstream
processing. From this we isolate
luccoytes which are then used for single
cell RNA sequencing the profile gene
expression. Now it's very important to
evaluate sample quality uh or we need to
consider uh the sample quality and this
is dependent on three uh key time
points. Uh one of them being u when is
the blood collect what is the time from
the passing of the donor to the start of
the collection that has passed. uh then
time from sample collection to ship uh
to shipment initiation and time from
shipment to receipt and processing of
the blood. All these time variables are
crucial because delay in any of this can
actually hamper downstream RNA integrity
and does affect downstream uh data
quality. Faster turnaround helps
preserve uh transcript transcrytoic data
fidelity as well. Um this is at the
bottom an example of a donor. Here you
can see that uh 0 hour marks the time of
passing. Then after 20 hours uh the
blood was collected. 7 hours after that
the shipment was set up. And by the time
the blood reached broad 35 hours 47
minutes had shots. This changes from
donor to donor but this is just an
average uh time what it can take. Um we
receive blood at broad after hours on
weekends and the broad security assess
us. we can track the shipment and then
somebody from the lab uh retrieves the
blood and process it processes it u so
that we can uh make sure we take care of
it as soon as possible.
Now um when we actually so our goal uh
is that from the fresh blood we can
isolate uh white blood cells which are
also known as luccoytes. These are
critical component of the immune system
and help body basically fight
infections, inflammation and disease.
Although they make a small fraction of
the whole blood, they do have distinct
cell types like T- cells, B cells,
monocytes, um, NK cells and all your
granular sites. Um, they provide
basically a snapshot of the immune
activity in the body of the donor at the
time of sampling. In pediatric donors
especially, it can help us to understand
how immune system develops, responds to
stimuli or maybe um or how it may be
altered in a disease. Now after we
receive fresh blood samples in the lab,
our first step is to get rid of all the
red blood cells, we do this by a
magnetic separation. Um this helps us to
enrich WBC's and also um get rid of all
the noise that could uh come from RBC's.
Once RBC's are depleted, the enriched
WBC suspension is processed through this
honeycomb hive capture assembly. These
are basically these uh contraptions you
see on the left bottom corner where each
of these contraptions has wells in which
individual white blood cells are
captured and then uh and they each
receive a unique unique molecular bar.
Once the cells are captured they can be
stored for a long time in in the
negative AT and um we can then basically
process them in batches. We don't have
to process the downstream single cell
RNA sequencing per per donor. we can
have them as a batch and then process
them. Um, one good thing about this uh
hive assay is that it also helps us
preserve granular sites which are often
lost by uh uh other traditional methods.
We also do uh uh PBMC isolation and
storage for the non-human private
species um which are done um so the
marmicets are done at broad and the
macak blood is processed in um Oregon
another in addition to blood we are also
collecting uh skin tissue samples from
donors to isolate fibroblast. So when we
receive a skin sample we basically and
this also is received at the same time
as blood. So once we receive the skin we
start by carefully trimming the skin
sample, reming the fat and then this
tissue is then cut into small pieces and
allowed to adhere on a petri dish on a
gel matrix. Um you do a regular cell
culture change media do like a single
passage so that you obtain primary
culture and once at uh a correct
confluency uh we can cryopreserve these
fibroblasts and these are biog.
Now these fiber was cultures basically
allow us to use in downstream functional
assays. We can reprogram them to uh
IPSC's. Um also these are uh important
resources that reflect the living cells.
They basically reflect donor's genetic
and environmental history in form of
living cells.
Um another thing Amy mentioned is that
all the tissues what we collect um are
they undergo pathological review. So we
collect a frozen tissue and then we have
a fixed tissue another frozen one. So
the fixed tissue all the fixed tissue
samples undergo detailed review by a
pathologist. The review serves um
multiple critical functions from initial
quality control, tissue identity as well
as quality assessment. So in the initial
quality control, the pathologist
verifies that the label tissue matches
what's actually on the slide.
Misidentification can compromise
downstream data analysis. So the tissue
mismatch is verified. They also check
for orientation issues if the tissue was
embedded or sectioned in a way that
might limit interpretability.
Uh then it's a technical uh slide
quality issues just to over overall look
at the quality of histologology slide
including staining quality, tissue
folding, section thickness etc. Once the
initial QC is complete, the pathologist
evaluates the biological quality of the
tissue. Each tissue gets an atysis
score. This indicates how much
postmortem degradation has occurred.
Highlyssis can obscure tissue
architecture and limited TP. Adolysis
score is usually given from a scale of 0
to three. Zero being good and three
being bad. The pathologist also looks
for the presence of target versus
non-target tissues to make sure that uh
the slide actually has the intended
organ or a structure. um and sometimes
an un unintended occur due to collection
error or an or anatomic uh proximity.
We also look for signs of any diseases,
inflammation or abnormal development
which was not uh known prior to
collection. And last but not the least,
maturation assessment for pediatric
samples in particular. Evaluating
developmental stages can provide
important context for interpretation.
After all these assessment the
pathological final review determination
is performed and then we decide if this
tissue is suitable for downstream
applications.
Now um the different tissues are um
reviewed by pathologists at different
centers. The University of Maryland
brain bank tissue review scans from uh
NHP and non-human brains. uh all the
non-brain human tissues are uh reviewed
at CHOP and the non-brain uh uh NHP
tissues are reviewed at NPRC Oregon.
I'm just going to uh show you this one
example as to uh what information we can
gather from uh histology slides across
development. So in the top panel you can
see that um the slide show the
development uh developmental progression
of globilli in kidney in maca kidney
spanning from gestational age 50 to an
adult in GD50. Um you can see that the
kidney is in early developmental stage.
There are no mature gli yet but renal
vesicles and chromma shaped bodies are
starting to form.
At GD00 uh gladilogenesis is actively
underway. we can identify some S-shaped
bodies. GD50 which is um a late
gestational stage for Macak glumberi
become more defined and as we move from
neonate infant juvenile to adult we can
see that glumberi are fully mature and
functionally stable. These slides will
help us visualize um and understand
developing organs and their highly
organized and fully functional uh
aspects across ages. Um so we are
basically cataloging this uh across a
range of tissues in NHPS and humans and
this is going to be a very important um
uh aspect of information which will
eventually be available to the
community.
So building upon that we're now going to
transition to the diverse uh types of
data that will be generated from the
developmental GTEx project. As mentioned
earlier, all tissues are biobback and
every collected tissue under goes a
detailed hisystologology imaging. So we
will be generating whole genome
sequencing, bulk RNA sequencing, long
read sequencing, single cell technology
such as the multi where you obtain the
gene expression attack as well as
methylation uh assays and various
special single cell sequencing
techniques.
So all of our donors will receive a
whole genome sequencing to provide a
complete genetic blueprints. This will
allow to identify inherit genetic
variation, improve genome and isopform
structure annotation and enable genetic
demultiplexing if samples are batched
together.
So we will also be performing bulk RNA
seek on the majorities of tissues
collected. So so far we have sequenced
to date 264 samples from 31 donors and
46 different tissues in humans. 262
samples from 27 donors and 61 tissues in
Makox. and 237 samples from 18 donors
and 59 tissues in marmma sets. So just
uh an a quick overview of the PCA plot
and plot where we obtain a separation of
the different tissues indicating the
high quality across the data in the
species.
So another assay that we're going to
perform it will be fulllength RNA
sequencing using mass iso seek to
enhance our understanding of isoforms
throughout uh developments. This method
was developed here at the broad by Aziz
and we've already performed a pilot
study where we uh where we took 12
humans six marmicets in Makox uh
different tissues in different age
ranges and as you can see in the heat
map we already have um tissue type that
drives primary clustering and a
secondary clustering driving by species.
So there's a lot of biology to be
discovered here.
So another core assay that we'll be
doing is single cell sequencing where
we'll be profiling from the same single
cell the gene expression and the
chromatin accessibility using 10x
genomics. So other assays u gene
expression and attack the 10x uh multi
will be our core assay but we will also
be doing single cell methylation and
spatial transcript on some on some on on
some of them. So these powerful
technologies move us beyond bold
averages providing unprecedented
position to map development at the
cellular level.
So just to elaborate on our core high
resolution assay. This slide provides a
brief overview of the 10x genomics
motion a technology a technology central
to the developmental geeks where we'll
be linking gene expression and chromatin
accessibility from the same nuclei. So
briefly for those who don't know the
technology, you take frozen tissue, you
isolate the nuclei. Each tissue requires
a specific protocol u for isolation. Um
once you obtain the nuclei, you perform
the 10x multiome which is by doing
droplets of single cell. You will then
perform the libraries attack gene
expression and you will obtain the gene
expression and the chromatin
accessibility of that nuclei.
So as mentioned earlier so this will be
our main core production but uh we are
in parallel uh doing the same
experiments at Yale University.
So as Amita mentioned before the tissue
that we will be doing performing single
cell sequencing has to be of high
quality uh high quality data. So um we
will select tissues that have a high RQS
score and that have a good autosis
score. And then on the lab side
validation of uh for good data will be
intact nuclei and the traces we obtain
from those libraries.
So we will be generating a beautiful
multi-home data sets where we'll be
create we will we'll be having the three
species we'll select two age ranges the
young and the older side and where we
have matched the tissue types. So we
will be generating 10x motion data on
all of these brain regions amydala
talamus hypothalamus cerebellum and
kidney pituitary muscle quadriceps lung
liver thyroid muscle and adrenal gland.
This is going to be a beautiful data set
where we'll see a lot of biology within
tissues and within species.
Here's just a glimpse of a data set that
we've generated. So this is a kidney
sample where we did 10x motiome where
you get the gene expression and the
attack. Here you can see uh beautiful
clustering both in the gene expression
and the attack where we get high number
of genes per cell high number of high
number of of of cells. Uh and for the
attack metrics we get good good TSS uh
score. So this is human kidney uh and
high frag uh fragmentation high quality
uh overlapping peaks. So this is just a
glimpse of the kind of data we'll be
getting from the from the 10x genomics
multihome.
So as mentioned before another workflow
that we'll we'll be performing will be
methylation profiling at the single cell
level using skil skill biotechnologies.
So again briefly you isolate the nuclei
you fix them then you perform
combinatorial indexing isopy sequencing
again you barcode them you sequence them
and then you analyze them. So we
performed a pilot data set on kidney
where we got two younger donors and two
older donors and we performed this assay
and we're still looking into the data
but you can already see beautiful
biology where there's a specific infant
cluster that uh that is specific only to
the younger donors. So there's a lot to
be discovered in these data sets. We're
really looking forward to it.
And lastly, we'll be performing spatial
assays to understand tissue organization
and cell interactions. For the spatial
assays, we have tried slide tags on
kidney again on the same uh on human
kidney. So, briefly with this
technology, you place a section of
tissue on the sequence spatial barcoded
array. You tag your nuclei uh with photo
cleave spatial barcodes. You isolate the
nuclei and you perform 10x genomics
where you'll capture the mRNA and the
special barcodes.
Um with this BA with this pilot as we
took the kidney we placed one of these
arrays on the medulla and on the cortex
and as you can see here we have a Disney
plot on the medulla and on the cortex
where you can see the specific uh
different subtypes from the different
anatomical region. Again a lot of
biology to be discovered.
So what are the outcomes of this big
project? So tissue collection and data
generation are currently ongoing. Um
data and pipelines will be available on
the GTEx portal. On the portal, you'll
be able to select the data uh for
interactive visualizations and all
tissues will be biobanked for future
reference
for future research purposes.
And um
to conclude to bring it all together,
the Derto GTEx projects represents an
unparalleled effort to transform our
understanding of pediatric development
and its evolutionary foundations. It is
crucial to remember that pediatric
tissues are fundamentally different from
adult tissues. They have uniquely cell
type compos compositions and distinct
physiology to study the evolutionary
conservation and differences of
developmental programs between humans
and non-human primates. And the
developmental geoteex project will prov
will provide a groundwork and
infrastructure for many research studies
for example hallucinating the origins of
pediatric diseases, childhood cancers to
developmental disorders. Everything that
we presented here today um is uh we we
wrote a marker paper that describes all
of the project. If you're interested in
learning more about it, what tissues
will be subsampling, the exclusion and
exclusion criteria that was asked
before, that's also in the paper um that
you can find online.
So the most important I want to uh
acknowledge and we're extremely grateful
to the dilemma GTEx donor's families who
have generously provided such precious
gifts to support our research work uh as
well as all of the non-human primate
collection
and uh the develment gist consortium. It
is amazing to work with such a a big
team and all of our broad colleagues
here at the uh at the at the broad and
our industry collaborators. So yes,
thank you very much any
questions.
Um two questions. one before I'm curious
about how the proof is going. Um, is
that being a bottleneck and are you
getting to be picky about maybe like
having some other dimensions of
diversity on stage in your data set? And
the other is I'm just feeling so aware
that this is 120 dead children, many of
you. Yeah. And and those families and
I'm wondering is there a plan for kind
of ongoing relationships with those
families giving you updates about the
project?
Yeah, there is a thank you for the
question. So, uh I'll answer the second
question first. So, we actually have an
LC initiative where basically they
connect back to the families and they
are informing them how their gifts are,
what are we trying to do with them. So,
there's a constant communication aspect.
So, there's actually also LC paper which
they're going to publish soon which
talks about these efforts and uh your
first question was how is the
recruitment going? So I think uh it's
very difficult because also getting
consent because of the age of donors
it's not very easy. So uh sometimes for
a couple of months there is a quiet but
sometimes we do see a lot of donors in a
month. So it's up and down. Yeah. And uh
as you said it's 120 donors pediatric
it's it's hard. Yeah. But it's very
precious and we do appreciate everything
we get.
Uh, we have a question online from Ben
Weisberg. Um, I'll ask them one at a
time because I know it's hard to deal
when there's multi-part questions. Um,
will the DNA be sequenced with long
reads?
You know,
but uh I think it all depends on and
what biological interest. As we get more
data, I think we'll have more questions.
self. And then another question uh Ben
asks is when do you anticipate the first
release of data to the portal?
I it still do you know I mean because
it's when the 10x single cell data and
then we have the RNA ready to release.
So I think the plan is so right is going
through thorough QC. We have generated a
lot of data. uh a bunch of our
computational people in the team are
doing thorough QC and then the hope is
to generate uh release it uh sometime
this year I don't want to say next month
but it's it's this year and then the
last uh question from Ben is if they
already have their own access to GTE to
just GTEX will they automatically have
access to DGEX
um or is there a separate application
process to access the data we'll defer
that to our PI question.
Um, are there any other questions? We
don't have any other ones online yet.
Come to the mic.
So um I was wondering you know how you
said that you have fresh blood too and
we also say that similar to a small and
digitex I think these ones they don't
have pre-existing um disease mostly so
and the time like to get the sample in
30 hours to broad so I think I know it's
a very hard situation when that thing
happen I was wondering if the families
they register even at the time that the
kid is born like how can they say that
this is going to happen if there is no
pre-existing issue to deliver the sample
that quickly.
So you're saying that how do we know if
there are any pre-existing conditions in
the blood? I'm not Yeah, because I think
I saw in one of the slides that it takes
about 30 hours to get the sample and
then so we do look at viability and of
the blood and then there are certain
like for example the hive assays they
recommend oh the viability should be say
75 to 80%. Sometimes it's 60. We'll
still proceed because it's such a
precious sample and uh a whole range of
cerology is done to all these samples.
So we know if there are any like they're
screened for infectious diseases and
everything. So but we we have some
information on that when we see samples.
Does that somehow answer? Yeah. And the
second do we have any other question or
should I so um so the frozen tissues
they're going to degrade right? And I
think they they create it or no?
So no, there's a process put in place
when when there's the the donation um
tissue is collected and it's they follow
everything is like on frozen trays that
you don't lose a chain of cold. So
everything is like when they send them
there's in dry ice when they come here
to pro they're put in minus 80. So
there's no degradation.
I mean you do have a lie between
starting collection but uh that's why
we're doing all of the pathology to make
sure that the essays assay that we do is
highly good quality data. So there is a
control and and the eskeemic time is set
to be not to not exceed 24 hours. Yeah.
So that is already in place and only the
fresh blood is shipped on ice. The the
the tissues get frozen right there. So
they so you can hope that the RNA
degradation stops there. Great. Thank
you. Impressive work. Thank you.
I've got a question. Um, thinking about
denovo mutations and sematic mutations.
Uh, do you have the ability to genotype
the parents of the child? I might have
missed it in the beginning. That's a
that's a great question. Uh,
yeah, not no plans yet, but to be seen.
Yeah,
I can ask another question then. then
people probably want to get back to
their stuff. I was really impressed
about the multiome being the core assay
rather than just single nucleus RNA
seek. Um is there plans to I guess I was
wondering also about the the idea to do
both bulk and single cell? How did you
pick how much you're going to spend to
bulk versus single cell or why not just
put every all your money in the single
cell pot? Very you need a lot of money.
the it's expensive assay. So bulk is is
affordable. So they want to do on all
the tissues the bulk and then we'll
focus on we'll do this pilot and then
we'll focus on biological questions to
continue on with the single cell assets.
But yes, if we could do all the tissues
and all that would be amazing to do
single cell but we're doing quite a bit
now. Yeah. Yeah. It's a balance between
a good design versus how much the
expenses. Yeah. And just out of
curiosity, what is the total budget? I
might have missed it at the beginning.
What is the total budget? I think you
can get on the NIH. It's public. It's
publicly available. Yeah, because it
involves a whole range of things from
donor like authorization collection. So,
it's in the NIH website.
I see. So, you don't know what it is.
Did I know? No, I don't. Yeah. Yeah. I
can look it up later, but I don't know.
I don't know.
Any other remaining questions? We do
have a little bit of time, but I know
people like to enjoy their breakfast.
Um,
all right. I just want to say thank you
to Rachel who's in the audience because
she showed us the fiberglass culture and
yeah, so thank you. I just
Yeah. So, I mean, it's been great
collaborating with everybody at Broad
because when we started the project,
there was a lot of things which we were
learning. So, people have been extremely
helpful.
The broad community is amazing. So,
thank you for everybody. Yeah. Yes.
Wonderful. And on that very high note,
let's thank our speakers again.