hello everyone thank you so much for
having me today um so profit is has its
roots in MIT my uh partner and founder
co-founder Jonathan Burns taught at MIT
for about 30 years and uh I'm also a
graduate a lot of businesses right now
are at an inflection point on AI where
the amount of data that they can get out
of the public domain is pretty much
reach
saturation and the real uh Frontier is
how to use Enterprise data or uh unique
data to just the Enterprise itself that
private data uh this is a huge
opportunity comes up in the Google
conferences and um this is one of the
things that was written about here in
fortune or Fast Company this is exactly
where profit is um exists in the use of
uh converting uh proprietary data to a
usable data set so that corporations can
use this information and ground
themselves um in their own
operations in particular um one of the
major limitations to AI right now is the
ability to use the proprietary
Enterprise data to actually drive AI
models and also uh data governance trust
and the ability to validate and not get
lost in hallucinations on their own data
so all of these things are challenges
that uh profiti
addresses so um what's really exciting
is it turns turn out that we do exactly
what uh the keynote speaker talked about
um we are creating synthetic data and
we're doing it through the lens of the
profit and loss statement that tried and
true core of any Corporation um we show
up with a corporation that might be
using three or four profit and loss
statements to run their whole business
and uh will create in some instances
over a billion profit and loss
statements we create a full p&l for
every invoice line of every transaction
and we use their Enterprise data to do
that and that
transformation is a critical component
of how we can actually use large
language models to generate huge value
for
corporations and the way we do that is
we can absorb all of the companies data
uh transform it into a value added p&l
for every invoice line and because of
that the grammar of our data set when
it's output is in the language of the
income statement so it's easily absorbed
as any other language would be in a
large language
model what we do is we've identified
over the years um 26 distinct data sets
that are generated by corporations uh we
have a very clear way to absorb those
into the profit and loss statement so
for example let's say that you're using
GPS data to track your deliveries we'll
take that data and we will then
calculate the exact cost of every
delivery on Tuesday you got stuck in
traffic on Wednesday it took took you 15
extra minutes to deliver all that is
included in the data sets that we absorb
and creating that kind of visibility
into what's really happening in the
corporation we do that across all the
line items on a general ledger and we
take all the data that's listed here
which is very
extensive that First Transformation is
one of the things that creates all these
pnls and this is what you I now will
call uh basically generative data uh or
and the other thing that we do is we
create segmentation data which again
augments the data creates even more
value uh the 8020 rule is Alive and Well
in every corporation that we've worked
with by the way we're approaching $600
billion doll of Revenue through our
model so it's well vetted across
multiple Industries AC around the
world in one instance we're working with
a 1010 billion retailer uh for them
we've created over a billion pnls we've
taken in 13 data groups across one ERT
system
and they're using it to monitor their
promotional spending understanding
exactly which customers are profitable
versus not as well as what channels are
profitable versus not um we're using it
to help them with store labor planning
uh with over 2,000 stores uh there are
2,000 people making decisions about one
of the largest expenses in a retailer
and that variability is something that
AI can help with dramatically and
finally uh we help them understand the
profitability of every product every
supplier every plan anagram in every
store so that's an example of where
we're using this transform transform
data um then we also have a global
distributor again uh lots of data groups
three RP systems across multiple
countries here we're helping them see
private label pricing customer contracts
and product mix
optimization and we also work with
global manufacturers here we're looking
at multiple Erp systems across multiple
countries um and we're helping them
understand the actual impact of supply
chain disruptions variability and
inbound uh raw materials as well as
customer negotiations so our ask is that
uh we'd love to work with some of you uh
in the audience um we work generally
with very large multinational companies
um and overall we uh would love the
opportunity to work with you if uh you
think this is an opportunity for you
thank you