Okay, everyone, let's get started.
We have an exciting day ahead of us with
an enormously fantastic lineup of
speakers and um poster presenters. So,
good morning everyone and welcome to the
third variant of function symposium here
at the broad um institute. I'm really
excited to see so many familiar faces.
How many hugs this morning were already
given? It's incredible. It's lovely to
see that um we have such a strong V2F
community and also lovely to see so many
new faces for everyone here in the
auditorium in person. We have multiple
overflow rooms at the broad for inerson
attendance and we have over 500
attendees um joining us virtually today.
So we are um a thousand attendees this
year which is just along the track
record of previous variant to function
symposia um joining from all over the
world spanning academia industry venture
capitalism and beyond and that kind of
scale and reach and diversity um is
really what makes our community powerful
I think and I'm um filled with joy and
pride and excitement about um about
that. So this symposium as the previous
um symposia um of V2F here at the broad
is hosted by the Nova Norris Foundation
Center for Genomic Mechanisms of Disease
which is a bridgeet center focused on
bridging science and innovation for
translation in the metabolic disease
space and really for connecting Danish
science with scientists here at the
Broad Institute and as a matter of fact
we had 45 Danish collaborators flying in
over the last two days here to join us
for our variant to function symposium
and the annual NNF center symposium and
I just want to say the warmest welcome
to those I haven't given a hug yet and
I'm so excited that you are here um and
for the coming days ahead
I will just say Bridget Center or bridge
building um I'm going to pause and say
as an academic in the United States
where science and so much more is under
attack bridge building I'm very fond of
bridge building I've always been fond of
bridge buildingilding But I'm
particularly fond of bridge building um
these days and I think bridge building
across institutions um across the globe
really between academia and industry
this um between science and the public
for increased science communication
towards the public and bridge building
across scientific disciplines has become
so important and the bridging of
scientific disciplines. I think the V2F
um field really is a stellar example
that has showcased over and over again
that the bridging of different
expertises, clinicians, biologists,
mathematicians, computer scientists,
geneticists, patients, and so forth make
the difference and can have an enormous
impact.
So, let's think today as an as a day of
bridge building. Reach out to somebody
um with expertise outside of your
comfort zone. Don't lay back but e
engage actively in the discussion. I
think Eric Lander and Mark Bailey have
done a great job last year with their
keynote discussion rather than a keynote
lecture in the sense of this isn't a
dialogue. We have to advance the field
um together um as we are moving forward.
also post on social media so we can
engage in discussion with the outside
world even beyond the attendees of this
symposium and actively contribute to
science communication towards the
public. Um great we have more people
trickling in which is lovely. I have the
great honor now to thank the most um
important contributors for today and I'm
going to start with Kasper Le who's here
right in in the front seat. Kasper has
been co-chairing the varant to function
symposium with me from the get-go which
has been an enormous pleasure. Kasper is
man the man managing director of the
noonautus foundation center of genomic
medicines here at the broad um and I
think I speak on behalf of the
leadership that we are very care um
grateful for your careful shephering and
I'm also really grateful for your faith
and the support in continuing to embark
on variant to function as one of the
guiding principles for our center. So
let's give an appro
and I and I will say that the welcome
remarks are on behalf of both of us as
we want to thank particularly so our
generous host the Nova Nordis Foundation
and particularly so Tanya Peterson. Oh
there there you are lovely. Um and
Christina Williamson our contact persons
at the um at the foundation. It's so
lovely to see you as usual. An enormous
pleasure to interact with you and I'm
very much looking forward to collecting
this week and to discussing science and
beyond. And this here's actually a
picture from your last visit at the
broad in the genomics platform. Um,
arguably most importantly, a huge thank
you and shout out to the cent's admin
and operations team led by Anika Vimma
and multiple other attendees, but
particularly so Carly Croano, who has
tirelessly worked on organizing and
preparing for this event, the symposia,
they don't just happen. There's a lot of
unseen work in the background. I would
love us to um clap and give a huge
applause to both Christina, Tanya and as
well as Scarlet and Anica.
We are very grateful. So, um I'm also
going to give a a shout out to Todd
Golat, the BRS director, and thank him
for his strong support and guidance
along the way. and to Eric Lander who
cannot join today because he's
celebrating with um the family um the
Jewish New Year. Happy Jewish New Year
to all of those who are celebrating um
um and and your families. Of course,
Eric has been arguably so one of the
earliest advocates and supporters for
variant to function and the variant to
function initiative um here at the broad
institute as he has asked me along with
Jesse Angright's Navi Frag initially to
launch a broad internal variant to
function initiative in 2017 which has
been an enormous pleasure and I'm really
um excited that Jesse is not only here
in person today but he's also going to
share his continuing amazing work in the
V2F space later today in this symposium.
The V2F story for me um is a personal
one. Growing up in the Alps, I really
have never imagined I actually grew up
on a farm that I would spend my career
connecting genetic varants to disease
biology in the context of cardioabolic
disease. But in back in 2007 when the
first you know waves of jas just hit us
as a community, I attended a symposium
in Munich and Thomas El was there and
Thomas is one of the or was one of the
um senior um authors on the diagram
consortium investigators who was part of
the 2007 um um largest genomide
association study back then for or first
genome association study for type 2
diabetes um published in Nature. and he
described the challenge. He said what's
expected is that these JVA signals for
diabetes they appear they come in LD
blocks because of the HL type structure
of the human genome. But what probably
not everyone has expected is that the
largest chunk of these signals is in the
non-coding part of the genome. That
problem in 2007 hooked me. I took on a
PhD project with Thomas and Hansa at the
Helmhold Center and develop a
computational and experimental strategy
um for my PhD thesis in the variant to
function um context to predict which
regulatory varants would be um
functional and and related to type two
diabetes progression and manifestation.
So I'm I'm saying this it actually took
seven years um until this work got
published in in cell which is just an
indication of um how long variant of
function studies particularly in the
past have taken um and that is being
changed drastically now.
The point I wanted to make is that at
the time I could hardly imagine that we
would be at one point able to trace the
full path from genetic maps through
mechanisms through um to medicines and
yet that's exactly what the field has
embarked on and making possible and I
think speakers today like the tray bas
George Church VJ Sankaran with his um as
one of our variant to function pioneers
um seeing his um V2F target moving all
the way into the clinic Ben Kleinstever
and others others are um definitely
examples of the success that genetic
information can be moved through the
angle of mechanisms all the way down um
to medicines to to treat patients and
with that other than in the previous two
years we launched the um um V2F
symposium open to the public in 2023
where we focused on genetic discovery
and gene regulation and cellular
phenotyping. In 2024, we then doubled
down on technology development for
scaling variant interpretations.
Um that was last year along with a
fantastic keynote um shared between Mark
Daly and Eric Lander on where human
genetics um future um or where they are
seeing the the future of human genetics.
This year we are um our focus is
twofold. On the one side, we will
continue and double down on scaling
variant interpretation on the along the
axis of biology being gene regulation
and cellular programs and on the other
time on the other side for the first
time we're going to reach towards
translation and connecting these
insights to therapeutic um hypothesis
and speakers like um Robert Plench I'm
so excited that you are with us here
today. VJ Sankaran and Blank Kleinstea
are light, you know, northern lights in
this path to literally leveraging
genetics to actually um translate um
information into the clinic.
Now, since this year's theme is very
much about reaching towards translation,
it's worth pausing and asking what
actually makes a good drug. And I
borrowed here an analogy from Matt
Nelson, the CEO of Jensenians, who has
given a fantastic keynote lecture at our
MPG seminar at the Broad earlier this
year. Um I'm actually coming this to um
um to this in a moment. Sorry. For now,
I'm just going to um make the point that
at the basic level, what makes a good
drug? We can say it makes um it's
important that it actually works in
humans, ideally, not only in mice. For
the intended disease indication, it
needs to be safe. Of course it has to
reach the right place and the right dose
and it needs to be selective targeting
the right mechanism with not too many
offtarget effects right and for the
future. So um the the notion is
definitely that it has to be
mechanistically anchored in human
genetics and biology so we have causal
evidence in hand for a given target and
differentiate and ideally tailor to
patient subgroups. And here's where I'm
going to borrow Matt Nelson's analogy um
that he presented at the MPG retreat
earlier this year. He compares it to
space exploration which itself is
ambitious, risky, expensive and has a
high failure rate. But he makes the
point um a very valid one that there's
an estimated more than two um2 billion
US dollars per commercial launch which
means as he calculated that we can fund
roughly 25 Falcon Heavy space launches
for the cost of launching just a single
successful drug. That's I mean we just
have to pause and realize that bringing
a given target to the market and
treating patients is an enormous
expensive effort. Now what's the problem
here? The high failure rate um I just
discussed this this morning with church
together too is on the one side the
problem of innovation in that many of
these medicines they fail to major
improvements above the standard of care
since they are often targeting similar
pathways. On the other side, and I'm
sure Robert will talk about this later
um this afternoon, it's a problem of
attrition and the attrition problem
particularly factors in in late stages
of clinical trials in phases two and
three which drive the high ro costs in
drug development.
That being said, I love this um recent
um um you know work that um Matt Nelson
and Eric Minl published in Nature last
year where they basically looked at the
estimated relative success for a given
for for a set of targets supported by
genetics compared to controls across the
different phases of clinical translation
and across a whole number of different
disease indications. And what we can
draw from here which this community is
very well aware of is that genetics
absolutely matter. Genetic support
increases the likelihood for a given
target to end up in the clinic by two to
eightfold. But the particularly
important point here is that the p um
that the most um critical impact is
actually in the late stages of clinical
trials in phase two and three where
exactly this attrition problem of
failure at the level of efficacy and
safety kicks in. So you know thinking
about genetics as the foundation is a
very meaningful concept. Now we have
talked about this iteratively over the
last two years. Human genetics has been
incredibly successful to identifying
hundreds of thousands of genetic regions
in the human genome that associate with
the whole um series of different traits
and diseases relevant um to humanity. Um
not only diseases and traits but also we
can start mapping disease progression.
we can start parsing individual like
large clusters of disease into subtypes
and endoypes of disease. It's an
incredibly exciting space and
particularly so with um increasing cross
bioank analyses as for example the Bravo
consortium is undertaking in the rare
variant space. I think Ben Neil is here
and we'll um chair a session later. Hi,
lovely to see you and the global bio
bank meter analysis are spearheading
examples of exactly what has to happen
right now which is the meta analysis of
large large bio banks across the globe
such as the GBMI undertakes and meta
analysis 24 biioanks across more than
two million individuals to come up with
robust signals and really drive us
towards saturation and lay out the map
of genetic associations with disease. We
can say that genetic discovery itself
from first principles is a solved
problem. It still has we have to double
down on it and we have to reach
saturation but we know how to do it very
very well and we have an enormous amount
of um genetic signals to work with. The
challenge is a different one that's the
reason that we are coming here together
every year where you know we are looking
at these robust maps between genetic
variation and disease and traits in
humans. And I like to say, you have
heard me saying this um for those who
have um um um you know been at um some
of my previous talks that this is to me
the foundation for targets and
mechanisms of actions that are
actionable towards therapeutic
translation. This middle the mechanisms
um that enable the translation. But
that's exactly this prosecution of
genetic signals to disease driving or
disease modifying biology is what's
lagging behind. the biological interpret
um interpretation is drastically lagging
behind. So one could argue that one of
the grandest challenges in human health
is the scalable mechanistic
interpretation of genetic data to lay
the foundation for rationally designed
um medicines. And I thought I'm going to
quickly walk you through a few of the
challenges that continue to exist in the
community and that we have to continue
work on and that are being touched on
throughout the diverse talks we have um
in this day and also an enormously um
exciting poster session at the end of
the day.
One of the challenges has always been
and still is I shared with you my story
how I started my PhD is the fact that
the majority of these um common genetic
signals are located in the non-coding um
genome in the form of um LD blocks that
have fine map to some extent but still
in many cases we are not sure what the
causal disease driving varants are which
target genes they are and which pathways
they implicate we will have a lot of
talks focused on this today bridging
this gap requires And that's a challenge
in itself to work with disease truceful
cellular models that respond in disease
relevant ways. So we have to turn oursel
and really critically evaluate actually
are we actually working with the right
cellar model systems. Are we working
with a set of stimulations or are we
assessing invivo physiology in a way
that is recapulating at least a large
fraction of disease pathophysiological
processes.
We also need which is rarely existing in
the community matched multimodal data
sets across truth uh these kind of
truthful disease cellar model systems
that let us um that let us
systematically interrogate disease
biology as it progresses over um over
the pathophysiological events of a given
disease.
We also need um
sorry I've been tested negative for
COVID and flu but I've been down sick
for a couple of um over the weekend and
I'm have finally recovered for
fortunately.
So a challenge also is we need scalable
highdimensional readouts that capture
both regulatory and phenotypic effects
across across all of these different
phenotypic modalities that um are in
coordinated ways impacting biology
related to disease. And and this is an
incredibly exciting space to watch. We
need and there's an enormous involvement
of these data that are currently being
developed to fuel the next generation of
statistical models. You hear Beu today
to talk about her Sage QTL dynamic um
modeling framework at single cell
resolution um only possible because of
data that are currently being developed
in the community. We we are looking at
every day a new um phenomenal
sequence-based model hitting um hitting
the rubber and and being available to
the community. We have Johannes Lintner
today um presenting on the Bourzo um
model. There are many many more that are
currently being trained on a diversity
of different data sets which is an
exciting space. I'll also say that um
Eric and Mark in in their keynote um
discussion last year, they have called
for the importance of com um
comprehensively cataloging effects of
effective gene modulation through a
large set of ptopsic experiments across
a wide range of primary disease models
and Elisa Donard a phenomenal group
leader here at the broad in in the
Lander lab has taken on that challenge
to wrangle the groups. Um we are lucky
enough to be part of that um effort to
um get together the community in the
disease space and really think about how
can we systematically perturb thousands
of targets in a harmonized manner um
with readouts that not only stop at um
the at um at the RNA level but also fold
in multiplex site seek readouts and and
optical information through high content
imaging that many of you know we are
really fond of to develop data sets that
enable us to um develop um the next
generation of computational models that
would be able to identify you know sets
of GBA hits that converge on the on the
same functional pathways for for
example. And finally I think a space
that is incredibly exciting to think
about is ways um that are often called
or the strategy is often called jvas
nadish where we are looking at
systematically mapping genetic variation
to disease-driving biology in these
truthful patient models. The idea was
incubated as part of the international
common disease alliance um together with
Gha Trinka at the Sanger and and many
others in the community um and called
the cell map framework where the idea
here I'm going to just include two
slides of results on our end in in my
lab where we are you know have these
truthful primary patient samples we are
pulling them together and then reading
out across multiple diff different um
phenotypic modalities to capture the
full pro um um propagation of biological
information in the cell as it is as the
cell is exposed to disease relevant
stimulatory conditions. The reason I
wanted to include this slide is to show
you um two nuggets of what we can start
drawing from it which I think is
exciting in just um a sample size of 118
donors of subcutaneous primary
adiposytes exposed to a series of
different stimulatory condition and
reading out with 10x multi ohm the
single nuclei chromatin accessibility as
well as RNA and using our im metabolic
disease oriented highdimensional
imagebased profiling liposy profiler, we
can start seeing LOSI through a
stringent collocicalization framework
like this one here that um robustly
associates with fat distribution and you
can start tracking the full um the full
path of how genetic variation acts on
chromatin accessibility connects it to a
collocicalized expression QTL and to an
image QTL to you know um make the path
and the connection of genetic variation
impact not only on gene regulation but
also downstream pheno types that relate
to disease biology. When we look to
nomite um in these 118 donors across the
different disease relevant stimul um
stimulatory condition and adopocytes we
can then ask for the collocicalization
rate across metabolic disease traits. I
have a set of examples here like fat
distribution, insulin sensitive um um
insulin resistance and glucose meastas
and lipid hemasis and you can
acknowledge that roughly 10% for LDL
where subcutaneous codiposytes are not
expected to play a major role um but up
to 80% of these ja signal appear to
collocicalize with any of these
molecular QTLs coming from um um attack
RNA or image space profiling. Huge shout
out here to Hzam Dashki and Yu um um
Wang in my lab um fantastic scientists
and and he is a postoc who have put
together these very recent data sets um
on a short notice. I also want to shout
out to Sophia Mets a great postoc in the
center um co-advised by Camila Sheila
and myself and and previously with
Thomas Kilpen um if you are interested
in reading a really good variant of
function review in the adopite space
please um look at this one. It's a it's
a great one. Okay. So, what's new and
coming in vibrarian to functional
research? Just quick notes on the one
side context. We learned that um Thank
you. We learned that context really
matters enormously enormously disease
stimulation context. Particularly
whether it's nutrient signaling,
inflammatory cures or hypoxia, the
cellar environment matters to unfold and
manifest variant effects. That's what
the community over and over finds these
days and it's is important to factor in.
We need to read out biology across
multiple phenotypic scales. We are also
and that's the second point here. We are
entering a bioank scale era of molecular
phenotypes where the 10k 10k um
consortium for example but also the UK
bio bank and finen are now ramping up um
to basically map 10xmotium for example
along with metabolomics and proteomics
in tens of thousands of individuals that
will um you know that will be available
to the community and make a huge
different in interpretation.
I also think that this point here from
gene centric to program centric view um
which my lab is embarking on a lot
currently is is an important one where
we are moving beyond linear gas um
variant to gene um kind of translation
and going more and more along the notion
that a lot of these lossi they act
through coordinated polygenic cellar
programs and mapping these cellar
programs um paves the way to um identify
patient subgroups towards therapies and
then there's of course AI I that's two
that's a bucket that is exploding at the
moment. I just saw from Jong Soo earlier
yesterday their new GPN model which is
seems to be at least from the first
glance phenomenal in terms of enrichment
of sniper heritability. There's one
model after the other being developed
and trained by increasingly you know
better um data in the sense that they
capture disease biology better and
better which is an exciting space. I'm
very fond of the iterative lab in the
loop model where we are working with
challenges in machine learning and
thinking about how do we have to design
an experiment to then um um develop a
model and go back to improve and refine
the model itself in order um by by
designing an experiment that is um
ideally suited for addressing exactly
that problem. And then finally uh um the
translation piece where of course the
patient specific invivo gene editing
through base editors earlier this year
has um is one of the examples that is
just so incredibly exciting to witness
in our field and we have Ben Kleinstea
who has has been involved in this study
and in this work in this space with such
an enormous track record today um
speaking to us. Okay. So the sessions um
um very quickly going through them
addressing multiple of these challenge
that I laid out. We are going to start
with scaling variant interpretation
shared by diet de Montes and have
exciting talks from Ruth Los um Jason
Flanick and Bezu focus on the question
how do we move from millions of variants
to interpretable maps and disease endo
types at scale. We are then moving on to
the gene regulation session chair Pred
Bernstein um along with exciting talk
from Yesper Martin and Jesse Angrites in
in our center um focused on decoding the
regulatory architecture that connects
variance to a factor genes and then I
think after lunch we are decoding
variant effect through cellar models
shared by two pairs with exciting talks
from Khloe Vani who is co-leading the
human cell atlas um and Johannes Lindner
um who is um um or has been in David
Kelly's that and develop Boroy, a really
um intriguing machine learning model.
And finally, the last session is
translating variance into therapeutic
int um um insights shared by our very
own Ben Neil and the speakers. And I'm
so excited, VJ, that you could make it
this year. I don't know where you're
sitting right now, but I'm I'm really
looking forward to hearing you as as one
of the V2F pioneers and seeing through
all the way to clinical implementation
of your um of your work as well as blank
bl Ben blank client steiver who I've
praised earlier. Casper I know will do a
phenomenal job at introducing Robert. So
I'm leaving that um to Casper very much
looking forward to um um to the talk. So
this is kind of the full arc that we are
spending today. Um, I'm not going to
repeat all of the different parts, but
we'll just say the whole is greater than
the sum of its parts. I'm just including
here a few icons. I was sick when I made
this, so there's a lot of um gaps in
this in this slide. I apologize for it.
The point I wanted to make is this needs
um this needs bridge building. The V2F
field continues to need bridge building.
This is why we are so strong. along with
our B2F symposium hosted by the NNF
center. I also want to shout out in the
spirit of um bridge building that the
welcome connecting science is launching
the biology of um of scale conference
series next year at the welcomecom
compass. That's a um symposia that um
Gosha Trinka, Craig Lassenbury, Jonathan
Pritchard and myself have put together
focused on developing and thinking how
we can measure and model biology at
scale through new tools and technologies
ma um combined with um um with
computational strategies.