great hi everyone uh I'm Stuart uh MIT
PhD I actually just graduated in March
and I'll be showing capsa our technology
to make AI reliable uh but first a bit
about uh Themis so we're an MIT spin-off
uh from seale our founding team includes
Professor Danielle Rose who's the
director of Cale as well as Dr Alexander
Amia and Alay miti uh we're post seed
we're currently about eight employees uh
one of our beta customers is one of the
largest oil and gas companies in the
world uh we've been using our product
for about a year uh and they've been
thrilled with it uh and so our product
capsa helps you to know what your model
does not know and I'm going to explain
why that matters and how you can benefit
so globally what motivates us AI has a
trust problem uh we've seen a number of
public uh failures or embarrassments of
AI systems making mistakes uh we know AI
models can be more reliable and should
be more reliable and so we've developed
capsa as a way to take any AI model and
help you to know when you can trust it
so we can give you the uncertainty or
the confidence of every single output
generated by any model uh and using
these we can help you to reduce time to
Market reduce development costs uh We've
designed it to be as easy to integrate
into your existing workflows as
possible uh so first just backing up a
moment what is uncertainty and why
should you care about it uh so here we
took a example data set so this is from
Vision we have a multimodal solution uh
and so we took a obstacle detection
Network used for self-driving vehicles
uh and this was trained on Urban driving
data so on the left there's an example
of an image from a data set that this
was trained on and the middle is an
example of an output from this model
that's designed to look for obstacles in
those images and so it picked up here on
the cars because it was trained to do
that uh but we injected this uh deer
into the image which doesn't appear
anywhere else in the training data
because it's only Urban scenarios we can
see that the model does not pick up on
that as an obstacle now with capsa you
get this confidence for every single
output generated by your model so we can
see in that highlighted region uh
there's burst because capsa knows your
model has never seen anything like that
before and so you can't rely on your
model's outputs uh in that reason of the
image and so in this case we can tell
you maybe don't go there anyway there
might be an obstacle
there now this is a multimodal solution
I can also show you an example with llms
uh so I'm sure you're all very familiar
with hallucinations uh we can try to
prompt hallucinations by asking
misleading questions so here we asked NM
what is the average size of tiger eggs
and for each token in the response capsa
tells us the confidence or the
Insurgency so here we're highlighting in
uh different shades of red or heat uh
the risk or uncertainty in those tokens
and so as we generate the response we
can check the risk or uncertainty level
of that response and use that to detect
hallucinations or unreliable outputs and
if it exceeds some kind of maximum risk
level we can use this to say block the
answer before it ever goes to a user if
you're in like a chatbot scenario for
example now here's another example with
llms uh this was actually llama 3 and we
asked it for a book with characters from
it so base llama 3 you just get this
answer you probably don't know if you
haven't read the book recently under's
game uh that there's no characters from
MIT in it but with capsa when we get
these uh confidence values in every
token here we're averaging over phrases
you can see that the LM is very
confident in its description of the book
but it's not at all confident in its uh
answer to the question or that passage
at the end about characters from MIT uh
so we can not only help you to recognize
hallucinations uh but also even where in
the outputs the hallucinations are most
likely to appear and so we believe that
these capabilities should be standard in
all AI systems and so that's exactly
what capsa
does uh so yeah these examples I've been
going over uh are primarily in quality
control we're helping you to
uh reduce hallucinations ensure the
accuracy of your AI models uh but this
uncertainty quantification has a number
of other applications uh for example
data cleaning and data curation we can
help you find mislabeled data U that
tends to uh highlight uncert or
uncertainty tends to highlight those
examples uh we can help you select new
data to improve your models uh to help
you find valuable training data uh we
can also help to eliminate bias we
actually have some published works on
debiasing AI models uh using this
capability and then anomaly detection so
when your systems are in production uh
we can help you to find uh potential
errors and avoid them uh mitigate
failures in real
time so we're here to look for
Partnerships and more proof of uh
Concepts so please reach out to us uh if
you'd like to see either more specific
use case demos we have some for medical
insurance I'd like to highlight it works
for any architecture any model any
industry uh please do reach out with us
uh we're happy to work with you if
you're interested as a question customer
partner distributor so on and so forth
so great and we'll be in the Next Room
thanks