Uh yeah, thank you so much. So I um was
assigned the task of like giving a
primer just like by myself basically to
uh set the scene and talk about the
sequence to function models uh with some
u historical context and a little bit of
a language modeling tool and this is all
just to set the scene for the next talk
which is I think way more exciting uh
than this one. So stay for the next one
as well. Um so let me introduce the
group first. Uh so sur so the right half
of the team is basically here today and
the left half is in South San Francisco
at Genantic. Uh we are basically a group
of people uh interested in regulatory
genomics at Genantic.
Um developing and applying AML methods,
most sequence uh models, DNA and RNA
sequence models uh to understand rules
of gene regulation um and to support
nucleus based medicine or therapeutics
like cell and gene therapy for example
and also to analyze um disease
associated variants with these models to
have um basically more like mechanistic
insights into um diseases.
Um so we are in in Janentech and Jed is
the R&D part of Genantech led by Aviv uh
and GCS is the computational sciences or
the computational branch of Jed uh led
by John Marioni and Braid is the the
biology research and AI development
department uh where we are in. Um so
let's start with the the fundamental
question uh of uh regulatory genomics
which is basically all cells have like
mostly the same genome but they
interpret it very differently. Um
so can we understand this code or how
cells interpret these code differently
so that they can function differently.
Uh let me introduce some maybe basic
concepts just so that we are all like on
the same page. Uh so genes have proximal
regulatory elements driving expression
called promoters. um transcription
factors are the proteins binding to
regulatory elements uh and more dist
elements and typically more cell type
specific dist elements are called
enhancers where TFS also bind um and
cells basically express different uh
repar of transcription factors to um
modulate their gene expression profiles.
And the second mechanism is also to make
um the chromatin where these regulator
elements are like physically accessible
or inaccessible uh to regulate the the
gene expression. So in this case for
example the enhancer is accessible and
here is not accessible and so on and so
forth. So the two main mechanisms of uh
gene regulation but these are really
super high level principles. So uh we
are interested in how exactly this works
for like each gene in each cell type uh
where these regulatory elements are and
how exactly they are driving expression
in different context. So this is kind of
the fundamental uh question. Uh maybe
let me introduce also some essays as
well. Maybe all of you are already
familiar but um just for the sake of
completeness. Uh so chipsseek is the
essay where we um profile binding site
of proteins for example like
transcription factors or histones and
attackic and DNA seek um measure the
accessibility of chromatin um and cage
and RNA seek are the transcription level
uh essays. So cage for the transcription
initiation and RNA core the entire
process of initiation and elongation
which we can use as a proxy of steady
state um mRNA concentrations
um and we have these experimental
methods basically to profile um these
molecular events like genomite for
example for the RNA seek what we end up
with is a a huge one-dimensional vector
of counts um showing where exactly the
um expression or transcription happens
And and similarly for a taxic and
chipsseek we have these genomide um
profiles of count. Um and because of the
the sequence preference or sequence
specific of the TFS uh we see strong
association between some sequence
features and and these uh dysfunctional
tracks let's call it uh for chips for
example it's maybe a simpler rule. So
wherever the TF binds there's a specific
motive for example underlying the the
binding sites or these chips peaks for
attack it's like a bit more complex
because we have the combinator
combinatorial rules of or combin
combination of motifs basically driving
the the accessibility and for RNA seek
it's basically more advanced because or
like more complex because of the distal
regulators. So it's not uh maybe from
like bottom up um the signal and rules
get more complex and also more like
distal uh from more local to more like
global dist signal. Um so in addition to
experimental methods we have basically u
in silicon or like computational methods
to study these associations of sequence
features to functional tracks. Uh and
the main method that I will talk about
here is sequence to function models. Um
so this is a super brief and very
non-comprehensive
u list of uh models that maybe initiated
this whole uh research.
Um so the machine learning formulation
of the problem I just described. So
which is um associating these sequences
with the functional uh genomic signal is
uh basically training a convolutional
neural net with the with the DNA
sequences.
So if for example we have an attackic or
DNA or chips crack um or the binding
sites um where the um the the binary
labels indicate whether there's a
binding or like accessibility or or not.
Uh this is kind of the label that the
neural network is predicting and the um
the surrounding sequence is basically
the input of the the neural neural
network. So as I described for the
attack DNAs and and cheap cases uh this
is relatively local. So a relatively
small model typically explains the
signal really well. Uh question
these are quantitative values. These are
not categorical labels that you're
predicting, right? So the original
tracks are counts because we basically
count like how many reads are mapped to
this specific position for like each
base. Uh but we can transform or um
normalize them in different ways but the
original signal is basically count.
Yeah. So the first generation or first
wave of methods basically simplified the
question. So they binarize the signal.
So whether there's a binding event or
not for example uh sorry the prediction
is maybe easier and the the loss
function is like very typical binary
cross entropy. Um and it was a the first
generation of these models used a
multitask setting. So from one um from
the same input DNA you basically predict
like multiple um binary events. Um
then the second generation or like
second kind of wave of models is the
profile models. So instead of binarizing
and losing some information for the
functional tracks people switched I
think JA initiated it in the BPET paper
in uh uh 2021 instead of binarizing the
event basically take the whole shape and
magnitude of the the signal into account
uh by just modeling the profile exactly.
uh and there are many interesting
features of the the profiles and the
shape of the profiles especially the
attack signal is like really interesting
and swag will also mention some
interesting properties of it um it
started with the chip nexus or like
chips seek tracks uh and now there's a
recent prep from Kaja lab um extending
this to a taxi uh with lots of
interesting analysis uh check it out um
but the models are still local right
because we are still predicting like
accessibility for example or like um TFC
uh which is a local signal. Uh so the
models are still taking 1 to 2 KB input
window and then predicting also like 1
KB output for example in the base pair
resolution. So for each base uh there's
a prediction made. Um but this changed a
few things in the uh in in modeling
basically one is like the loss function
for example like how what is the right
way of uh modeling the profile itself.
Should we take the count structure into
account for example like using a a poson
or like a multinnomial loss for example
within this window window. Um and the
receptive field is more important here
as well because in the binary you
basically use the entire sequence but in
this case we need to think about what
the right receptive field of an
individual base like on the output side
should be on the input side. Um so these
are the new challenges that emerge in
the profile modeling.
And third and maybe the last kind of
wave of or like group of methods uh is
basically larger models. Um so imagine
instead of like looking at individual
binding sites or um attackic peaks you
just tile the entire genome and for each
tile you just stack all the functional
data you have including chipsseek attack
DNA seek um
and like cage for example KC like the
transcription initiation uh and these
types are really really large like 200
to 500 KB
um and this this is how you train the
model basically without selecting any
specific by positive and negative
regions. You tile the entire genome,
stack all the functional tracks you have
as a as a profile uh and and you make a
prediction. Uh scaling becomes an issue.
Um there are some tricks for example
like bin the output uh like eight or 32
base pair bin output is like one simple
trick uh to reduce the dimensionality of
the output. But the the idea is to
basically treat all of them uh the same
and make all the predictions all at
once. So these are extremely large
models um both in terms of the input
length but also in terms of the the
number of things that they predict um so
7 8,000 tracks are from multiple
organisms like from human and mouse um
predicted by this the same model.
Um
yeah, this is for example like one nice
example from the Bourzo paper uh uh from
from Kico where they added the RNAC
profiles which I think changed the um
sequence to function modeling quite a
lot. So initially like people interested
in like regulatory genomics were using
these models for different downstream
tasks that I will also mention in the
next slides. uh but with the uh gene
expression modeling I think it opens up
like new avenues and basically new types
of analysis that one can do with these
profiles. So the training didn't change
much. Uh still there are large like
tiles of uh windows. It's RN seek is
just like added as a new modality and
the training is is basically the same.
Um but models learned like started
learning basically lots of new things
right for example if you add an track
the we are basically guiding the model
to learn about like splicing uh splicing
to or like alternative polination and uh
basically new information about
regulatory genomics. So in this case we
see the EGFR gene and all the peaks
basically represent the reads mapped to
the exonic regions. Um and and the
prediction looks looks really good. Um
but there are a few issues. So um issue
number one is basically this is limited
to um GTEX and encode balic tracks. Um
and there is lots of cool biology
happening in single cell for example uh
which is not really modeled in in this
case. And the second one is basically um
people with like more focusing on
expression in in many cases they don't
really care much about profiles. They
care about the expression levels across
conditions across tissues or different
regulators of different genes in
different contexts. Um so although the
profile modeling of RNA seek enables
different types of analysis for many
people um there are different questions
that we ask about like the the what are
the regulators of a specific gene in
different contexts.
Um and if you basically keep adding the
single and another another issue is that
the single cell arc profiles are not
super trivial to to um preprocess in in
many cases we don't even have access to
it. people simply use like the counts.
Uh so count is kind of the main
representation of the data in single
seric. So it doesn't fully fit in this
paradigm that is now a basically a
continuation of the uh previous
iterations of these models. Question
uh when you just referred to the counts
are you talking about uh gene by count?
Yes. Okay. Thank you. And by gene
matrices
coms represent the expression levels.
So the last um model I will talk about
is like our work decima basically where
we um did this. Um so the the visual
representation is different but the idea
is to have the sequences around the
genes like a pretty large window same as
as the war model like half megabase
window and predicting expression of
genes in different context. So this is a
busy slide but let me walk you through
it. Uh so the sequence window is same as
the Bzo model and the model is already
uh pre-trained. So we are find
technically fine-tuning Borso model. Um
and we show them and and this is a gene
level model. So the observations are
genes but the model is pre-trained on
the entire genome with different
modalities like chipsseek attack and RNA
and and DNA. Uh and for each gene we
have um thousands of different contexts
where this gene is is expressed. Right?
So these are the columns uh that are
shown here. uh and rows are different
pseudo box. So instead of using the
single cell data really at the single
cell level uh we collapse single cells
to like pseudo box representing
different cell types in different
studies, conditions and tissues. Uh so
this basically uh gives us thousands of
pseudobach profiles. Uh now that we have
many atlases uh that are already syped
and nicely annotated um we can simply
access these uh annotated atlas data
sets and prepare the pseudo box and
fine-tune the model on these pseudo box.
Uh so let's say you look at EGFR but in
this case you look at it in the healthy
fibroblast context let's say Crohn's
disease fibroblast context macrofage
context and and so on and so forth. So
each row in this case is is one suitable
Um and this solves some of the issues
that I mentioned. So we don't really
care much about profiles. We are
interested in different sets of
questions like the um context specific
regulators of these genes. Um and we
also want to scale it up in terms of uh
samples and studies and single cell data
sets. Um and this is led by Avantic and
and Alex. Um
so how do we use these models? what what
are they useful uh or what what do
people use it uh for in general and I
will exemplify uh major some major
common downstream tasks using the
decimal model one question um how much
did using Boroy for like the
pre-training help versus just training a
model from scratch and I'm just curious
because like the human cell atlas right
it's human data and everybody has
different snips and whatever and then
Borzo is trained on I think like cell
lines and it's just very different
genetic background. So I'm just kind of
curious if Borzoy helped a lot or just
just because of that kind of issue.
Yeah, it it helps really a lot. I mean
this is the the short answer. you don't
have the full ablations uh because one
can technically do also boro like models
but also leaving out or like holding out
some modalities entirely uh like an
attack only boro for example or like the
the full model or also decima from
scratch instead of pre-training uh but
overall it helps a lot um and one simple
way to see it is basically if you look
at the gradients of the model it nicely
overlaps with the attackic signal so the
taxic is one of the main um modality
ities that model is still kind of
remembering and and using for expression
prediction. Um but yeah, it helps really
a lot.
Um
yeah, so common downstream tasks. So
this I think most of these tasks were
already in the deepc paper in 2015 and
we still keep um using or basically
exploring these models uh uh using like
in the context of these uh downstream
tasks. One is basically interpretation.
So the models are relatively
interpretable. Um when we make the
prediction, we can simply take like the
gradients or interpret the model in
different ways to find uh the sequence
elements that are really driving the
prediction. Um which is kind of the main
methodology to understand the regulatory
rules uh that we are interested in. Uh
synthetic sequence design is is another
interesting direction uh that is getting
more popular these days. um uh basically
designing promoters and enhancers for
like therapeutic applications with
desired properties which is typically
cell type specific uh expression uh but
I will show some um
basically generalizations or like
different kind of flavors of it uh in in
the next slides as well. So var effect
prediction is another common task. So
basically querying the model with some
counterfactual counterfactuals which is
like what if I had the reference al in
this case and how would it change the
the predictions. So this gives us um
a method to quantify the predicted
effect of a of a variant for example uh
so that we have a more mechanistic
understanding of the variant. uh this
might link for example the TF uh that is
affected by the variant uh in a in the
context of a specific uh regulatory
element in in a um linked to a specific
gene in the context of a specific cell
type for example and there are some nice
papers using these models as oracles and
they basically come come up with really
interesting creative insilica
experiments um like given that the model
takes a really large like the large most
of these apply to large models uh the
the third category basically especially
the last one because you can come up
with some creative ways of um quering
these models uh like in the cream paper
for example Shush Shushan um came up
with like interesting ways for example
if you move the a specific regulator
element around like closer to TSS or
like farther from TSS how would it
change the expression or if you shuffle
a specific enhancer sequence what is the
impact of it in in a specific gene and
so on and so forth. Um and in our
examples for example we are using these
large models to um score shorter
sequences
um where we use um basically we use like
shorter regulatory elements in the
context of um uh yeah I will I will show
basically how we how we use it in this
context. So the first example is about
the interpretability like as I mentioned
the decimal model is making predictions
uh of gene expression in thousands of
contexts. uh one thing for example to
look at I mean the first thing to look
at for example in the context of one
specific gene is whether the predictions
make sense or um it basically accurately
predicts the um the gene expression. So
this is a test set gene a gene that I
like um because the some of the genes
expressed in a few very different cell
types but not markers of these cell
types and also not the housekeeping
genes I think are really interesting. Uh
so in this case we see that the
expression is uh highly correlated uh
the predicted expression is highly
correlated with the measured expression.
Um and there are some tricks in the
model to um force the model to capture
like cell type specificity uh more
accurately and which is what we see in
this panel here. So this gene is
expressed in some brain cell types and
some lung epithelial cells um which is
what we are showing on the right side.
uh and we see a similar pattern for the
predictions as well. So the predictions
look good. Uh then we can start looking
at the regulators of this gene. Um which
is what we see here. So basically we
look at the gradients. Um
so yeah this this part is really
critical I think because we look at the
gradients of a specific output uh with
respect to input and we basically show
the uh input sequence regions driving
the predictions uh of this gene in the
context of a spec one specific cell type
because it will get more complicated in
the next slides. And in this case we
basically look around the the TSS region
and we see the regulators of the um
regulators of the of the gene for
example the RFIX uh motifs around the
TSS. Um
but since the uh the input window is
basically half megabase you see
different patterns throughout the the
entire window. Uh question
input to output are those integrated
gradients from input to output that
we're talking about. Yes, the input uh
input times gradient.
Um so another thing for example we can
look look at is not the the proximal
elements but also the um the distal
ones. So in this case we are looking at
um again the attributions
um of the expression of the fab fab P1
team and this is uh the Tata box nicely
captured by the model around the TSS. So
the model recognizes it as a as a
promoter. I think this is also one of
the um features that are learned during
the pre-training. So the model is not
maybe learning what a promoter looks
like because it probably knows it really
well already from the pre-training. uh
and the cool thing about this gene is
also it's expressed in two very
different cell types like entites
and now we can look at the attributions
uh of the entite signal and hpocy signal
separately and then see basically if the
model is capturing any sype specificity
and in the proximal case or in the
promoter case you basically don't see a
big difference so it just sees a
promoter
but if you look at a dist element which
is the enhancer of potentially the
enhancer reputative enhancer of FAP P1
gene uh the attributions look different
because the model interprets the the
enhancer differently. So uh we see three
transcription factors in the entite case
the SEP CDX and RX. Uh and only two of
them light up in the height case. Uh so
this is basically what we mean by the
regulatory grammar or or the regulatory
code that drives expression. Um so
although the cells are looking at the
the same genome they basically interpret
it differently because the they express
different transcription factors which is
uh what I show here. So uh CBP a
transcription factor across different
cell types. Uh we see high expression
both entites
uh and the model picks it up um in the
sequence but not using the expression of
these transcription factors. uh and CDX
is a more enter specific transcription
factor uh which basically aligns really
well with uh this finding because we see
the the motif of CDX uh in the enhancer
of P1 gene in anes
you're attributing the motif to the TF
based on prior knowledge right not okay
yes yes exactly um so basically we look
at the attributions and then um there
are like simple ways of using cataloges
like Jasper or Hokamoko for example to
like scan and then associate the known
motifs to the uh small regions of
attributions.
Um do you hold out the prediction like
these genes are they held out during
training or does the model have access
to the fact that these actually are
expressed in the yeah all of the genes
uh that are in the paper and also in the
stock are basically tested genes. So the
genes that are not seen during training
including fat P1. No, no. I mean like
CVPA, CDX2 and the transcription factors
are they does the model have are they
included in the they may or may not be
in the training set but the model
doesn't really know that this the motif
of this gene is basically the CDX2 gene
that it already saw in the training. So
it's purely sequence model. It might
know some of the motives regulating CDX
but not there is no explicit link
between the CDX gene and the motifs of
the CDX gene in the model. Yeah. But
implicitly there would be that with the
fact that that like if you know every
cell type that's expressing CDX2 is also
expressing
one.
Um
I mean when they look at when the model
looks at the enhancer of the FAP P1 gene
there is like no explicit signal saying
that CDX2 gene itself is also expressed
in this cell type right because like
each gene is a different observation and
it might have seen it during training or
maybe it's in the test set I don't know
exactly uh but these are kind of
different observations from the model's
point of view
but there are different models that also
condition the sequence uh on the
expression of specific transcription
factors that make the model more aware
of it explicitly.
Yeah. Um I have a question which is uh
do you have an intuition on why the sign
of this input times gradient is positive
for DFS but it felt like it was negative
in the DSS uh in the case before. Okay.
Yeah. negative attribution basically
means so um
there are I think two potential
mechanisms like one is maybe more
biological uh version is a repressor for
example if there's always the model sees
a motif and the expression is always low
and whenever the model doesn't see the
motif then expression is high so
biologically it might be a repressor so
the model can pick it up and this is
what we see in different cases like in
neuronal cells and non-neuronal cells
for example there are like really strong
repressors but in some cases it might be
an artifact too uh which is potentially
because of the multitasking. So imagine
a scenario for example um you have bunch
of neuron subtypes and then microia for
example and then you are making a and
the model saw lots of neuron specific
motifs for example in the neuron
regions. So when the model looks at the
microia uh enhancer let's say the lack
of a a neuronal motif is already a good
it might be a good predictor of the
presence of a microbia specific signal.
So you can see an upside down neuron
motif picked up by the model. But in
this case there's a really strong
contrast between all the neuron subtypes
and microia right like if this is how
you form formulated the whole uh the
problem. But if you have like thousands
of things I think this signal will be
like diluted and be less of an issue. Uh
but still there is no clear or like we
cannot say certainly that it's always a
repressor when we see it in in these
cases. Uh but if there's like prior
biology known about specific repressors
then uh yeah like you feel more
confident about the thing question.
Did you say that repressors would be
positive and activators would be
negative.
So depends on where you look at um if
it's a a repressor in in neurons let's
say
um then whenever the model sees a
repressor then there is like no neuronal
expression right so whenever there is
like no motive there is let's say a high
neuronal expression I'm just like making
it up if you look at the attributions in
the scope of neuron expression then you
will see an upside down because it's
negatively impacting the expression
right whenever you see it there is no
expression but if you look at it in
another cell type you might see it
basically the the other way around. So
it might still it may not repress the
expression. So it might cause or it
doesn't really repress any expression.
So you you see it the other way around.
So depends on
um yeah what part of the output you are
looking at.
Okay. So now let's make it basically
more complicated. Uh now that we have uh
the expression of these genes in many
different contexts, we can ask like more
complex questions too. Like initially um
it was all about like cell type
specificity, right? Different comparing
different cell types or um finding
regulators of cell type specific signal.
Um but this is basically a generic
concept, right? So we just select an
output or we select two groups of uh
pseudo box like a positive group, let's
say, and a negative group. Um then we
look at the local change which is
basically the we subtract like positive
and and negative um and calculate the
gradients with respect to this
differential signal. So instead of
looking at an attributions of an an
specific output we look at the the
attributions in a differential way. Um
so the model then we try we ask the
question that like what are the the
sequence drivers of this differential
signal. So if you uh define positive as
one cell type and negative as the rest
for example you do like the typical cell
type specificity type of analysis. U but
we can also define it in in different
ways right because now we have basically
more flexibility or like broader
coverage of biology with single science.
Uh and once we have the differential
signal uh we do the same thing. We look
at these regions of high attribution and
and through a method called TF modiscoco
um we cluster all these regions and
assign them to like non motives which is
like in this case for example gtt gct a
driver motif so um this then
um it doesn't give you a specific gene
so you kind of marginalize the gene but
it gives you a specific TF explaining
differences between the positives and
negatives that you define and we can
define in many arbitrary ways. So for
example, instead of looking at like
entite versus hpetite in the previous
case, we can look at the T-Rex um but
more like subtle changes in T-Rex, for
example, cycling and non- cycling T-Rex
and ask the model what are the
regulators of these two cell states in
this case. Uh and we see some usual
suspects like the E2F for example. Um
but in this case we are basically
looking at the logage correlation. So we
are not looking at the correlation
between predicted and measured
expression but we are looking at the
predicted and measured lo changes
between these two groups
and uh like another contrast that we can
create also is the cross tissue
analysis. So we can look at the cardiac
fibroblast versus non-cardiac
fibroblast. Um so a bit also similar to
cell type analysis but not exactly the
same. So we are looking at the same set
type but across uh different context
like in in different tissues for example
heart versus uh other tissues and also
they asked the model what are the the
regulator drivers of this specific
differential attribution. So um this is
kind of the sequence to function way of
like pitching the model right because it
feels like a uh like an extension of the
existing models. But if you think as as
a single sinic person um it basically
it's very similar to differentially
expression analysis where you just
compare different groups of cells but
instead of getting like bunch of genes
that are differentially expressed you
get an additional information about what
TFS are regulating or driving this
differentiation. So I think in a way it
basically adds like another layer of
information on top of the regular
differential expression as if that we
typically do. Question. So you're saying
that um these motifs that are being
picked up here uh might drive multiple
genes in this differential expression
scenario.
Yeah. Basically
uh what we do is we have some genes that
we want to target, right? For example,
differential express genes between these
two states. let's say the cycling T-Rex
and the non-cycling T-Rex. Then um for
each each of these genes, we run the
same query. So we look at the
differential attributions and cluster
the motifs that we see. And when you do
it across genes that are informative in
the context of the specific question, we
end up with like bunch of motifs. So
these are the ones that are over
represented
across genes that are differentially
expressed between these two groups in
the differential attributions.
So I think I mean same as this but just
imagine you do it like with multiple
relevant genes and you kind of
marginalize the gene dimension so that
you end up with um the contrast that you
have and then the TFS driving it. And
the third example is uh maybe a bit more
complex uh but we look at the again the
same cell type but across conditions. So
this is maybe a more familiar
differential expression analysis like
healthy uh uh like an healthy individual
and a chron uh patient and we see like
similar patterns basically uh motifs
driving this uh these differences. So in
this cases we are not expecting to see
motives driving um the fibroblast
expression itself but only the
differences between a healthy fiber
blast and a diseased fiber blast.
Um another example um is sequence
design. Like as I mentioned um synthetic
sequence design is is one of the u cool
directions um that these models are
really useful for. Um and the way we
formulated here is uh is slightly
different because in the sequence design
typically we design like smaller
sequences like 200 500 base pair
sequences but these are like super large
models. So how do we like reconcile
these two? So Laura um uh in my team
basically formulated it as a as a nice
incilica experiment where we have a a
short random sequence and and some cargo
and then we kind of implant it in a in a
scoring locus in a safe locus where kind
of nothing happens. Uh and if the model
responds to this sequence then we just
assume that there is uh expression there
are patterns that are driving the
expression. So almost as if like we are
doing the experiment where we integrate
a reporter essay uh like a reporter
construct and then running a reporter
essay which kind of lights up the EDFP
even the cargo gene is uh is this the
standard reporter SA genes uh then one
can start with a random gene uh and this
is kind of the scoring function it
scores like this short regulatory
element um and model again makes like
8,000 9,000 different predictions right
so if this uh fake cargo gene would
light up in these different context
Um so then we can basically start with a
random sequence and in a in a very
simple directed evolution kind of method
we can keep mutating it until we are
happy with the from the design objective
point of view and in this case uh so
self type specific regulator design is a
very standard task. So you have for
example a fiber specific element or a
microfase specific element and so on.
But in this case since we have lots of
different condition and context we tried
something a bit more difficult. Um so
initially we basically start with a
random sequence and we make a fiber
blast specific element right so the
contrast here is fiberblast versus rest.
Uh so the model basically makes like 50
edits to come up with a fibroblast
specific element and then we basically
continue with a slightly different
objective which is higher expression in
an inron fibroblast and a lower
expression in the other fibroblast. So
in a way it's a a very simplified
version of a multi- uh objective
optimization uh but we are not doing it
jointly. We just do it uh sequentially
like fibroblast specific first and then
disease fibroblast specific then this we
can also interpret because basically we
know where the model edits which motifs
um exist in the sequence and and so on
and most of the motives basically make
sense. Um
yeah and the the last case I think is
variant effect prediction. This is also
are you sorry are you gonna I I don't
know if this is possible but can you
test this in fiber I mean it's kind of I
imagine hard to get fiberglass out of
Crohn's and edit them but like is there
some sort of idea that you want to at
least put some fibroblast in some sort
of inflammatory condition in a cell
culture and see if you can get whatever
cargo this is to be expressed
specifically. Yeah, I think it's really
interesting. It would be really
interesting to test it um like with an
experiment um if it's doable. Yeah.
Yeah. So the variant effect prediction
um example again with with the with the
same model um so we again follow the the
standard formulation of the web task
which is to query the model with two
different of a a specific variant that
we're interested in and look at the
differences between the expression
um expression profiles. Um and if there
is like a um significantly high um
differential signal between these two
cases, basically we can nominate um a
cell type and a gene um as a mechanistic
explanation of the uh of of this
variant. Um
and for this uh we basically picked the
the biggest um available single cell QTL
data set like 1K 1K. I think there's a
follow-up now uh a larger uh data set
but in uh this one they have I think 900
or 1,000 individuals um profiled with
single sac and and the the um immune
cell types are profiled and they have
the genotypes of the individuals. So
they just call the uh they find the
variants that are uh driving the uh the
expression in these individuals. Um so
this is a a reprocessed version of the
1K 1K single set EQL study from EQR
catalog. Um and there are a few ways of
doing it. So you can look look up like
specific variants and then uh nominate a
specific regulatory mechanism or uh you
can do it kind of more um broadly where
we formulate the question as a
classification whether a variant is a
cell type specific um EQ for example
single cell EQL or not. So in this case
we have the fine map variance um
analyzed by the EQI catalog with the
posterior inclusion probability like
higher than 0.9 for example the the more
confidently fine mapped variances are
positives and uh the gene match 20
negatives for um for each positive
variant that we have and then this is
basically a binary classification
problem whether this variant is a single
cell eql in different cell types. So we
do it like different for each different
different cell type. Then for each cell
type this is a different classification
problem and we have the the AUPRC's of
the classification results. Um and in in
many cases the model is doing a really
good job uh distinguishing these uh the
variants that are um increasing or
decreasing expression uh in the context
of different specific cell types. Uh but
the cool thing is now we can do it for
like remaining 8,000 um conditions or
like different cell types right so this
is a nice validation that the model
picks up uh the variant signal and this
is another way to look at it so for like
each uh sorry coach on the previous plot
um so what do you think is driving like
performance is it the number of cells in
these data sets like platelets for
instance are not often been found in a
single cell data. I mean or what do you
think is kind of differentiating the
cell types here? I think this we haven't
checked it but this should be correlated
with uh maybe the the size of the of
these populations
um and maybe the data quality as well.
Um but it's a function of multiple
things like if
um
if variants are affecting a gene that is
not really well captured by the model
maybe the the dist elements are maybe
like really far away or the model is
having issues basically understanding
the regulatory rules of a specific gene.
Uh yeah if there are more variance for
example impacting this gene this might
affect it too. uh so at the gene level
or at the cell type level model has
uh different like levels of performance
right so based on these combinations
model can perform poorly too but one I
think really interesting thing is that
if you look at the variants that are
flagged by these models it's often a
combination of common eqtls and also the
rare variance so model doesn't really
have an explicit notion of uh frequency
right the a frequency so I think the
right way would be to basically look at
all the functional variance without I
mean if we have such data without
thinking too much about the frequencies
and the combination of it will be
probably more captured because otherwise
the model will flag more rare variants
as well which might show up as the false
positives in the EQL context although
they might have an impact but not u
captured in EQL simply because they're
not common enough question
are those cell type labels taken from
the cell ontology ology.
Uh these are the author provided cell
types. I think author provided cell
types. So the the authors annotated the
paper. But we have to match the cell
types that we have in our model and then
the uh cell types that the model uh the
authors provided in this paper.
So I need to speed up. Um then we can
look at the fine map variance and their
effect sizes uh and correlate it with
the uh lock fold changes which is kind
of the main score that the desma
produces. Uh and it looks reasonable
basically. Uh this I will skip
uh yeah maybe like some some notes and
or conclusion about the the this
section. I think the major trend as you
see um is concepts like emerge in the
machine learning field and it's applied
maybe unsurprisingly in in regulatory
genomics lots of like architecture
decisions loss functions and and machine
learning concepts are uh really quickly
adapted uh and applied to regulatory
genomics related questions. Uh and there
are like many different ways of uh
designing these models. Different loss
functions, how to structure the output
for example. So um like in in terms of
like these components there there are
really big differences. Although models
might look similar basically sequence to
function is the main kind of principle
uh there are still lots of hidden
challenges within each of these these
directions. Uh but two major groups like
if you basically really construct this
space and cluster these groups like you
will see a models that are really small
and efficient and single task uh and the
models that are really large and
multitask. Uh and there are like pros
and cons. Uh multitask models are more
convenient if you don't want to load
like hundreds or thousands of of models.
Um and in some cases there are questions
where we don't really know where to look
at. Uh so if you have single task
models, you load the model that you have
in mind and basically query the model.
But if there is like a big multitask
model, it might guide you basically uh
about like where to where to look at
like in which context uh that you need
to look at. Um and so um so are these
models foundational? So it depends on
what the the definition is. Uh but if
you remember the definition from the
original Stanford report, it's basically
any model trained on large data sets
that can be adapted to a wide range of
downstream tasks. It it seems like
pretty foundational to me. Although they
mention this svision in the report, um
it's basically not a a requirement. But
um if people can come up with
applications that you didn't even think
about when you train the model I think
it's foundation enough
um and some open problems um
so as you imagine like one of the trends
is like just having more and more tracks
right like the models are predicting
like the large the third category is
predicting more and more tracks um but
there is some kind of structure between
these between these modalities so the
attack chipsseek are related or histo
modifications and attack are related or
attack and expression are related. Uh
but these these are not really used
because we just like stack everything
and predict all at once. Um so there are
some attempts to basically move things
around. So instead of having the
sequence as input and everything as the
output, you can move some of the things
from output to input. For example, his
modifications or attack and sequence can
be your input and then you can predict
kind of the rest. Uh but this is this
feels a bit arbitrary. we have some some
notion of uh causality or like
associations between the tracks. Uh but
there is no principled approach I think
to um fully exploit this. Uh and the
second one I want to mention is like the
design is more like a byproduct or like
it's an auxiliary function. The model
doesn't really know about design but we
kind of force the model to design things
typically with like directed evolution.
So it's not a fundamental part of the
training. uh and you can use language
models basically to uh especially the
auto reggressive language models to
design sequences when you prompt them
with uh different functional uh prompts.
Interpretation I think is limited um
there are lots of interpretivity methods
that I also show showed in the previous
slides but if you think about the
counterfactuals we are limited to the
counterfactuals of the sequence. So we
since the sequence is the only input the
only cool uh creative experiments we can
do is to perturb the the sequence and
then see what happens in the output. But
if the sequence remains the same but we
can change the functional tracks uh that
would be a really cool way of perturbing
uh um biology too. But these models
don't really allow it since everything
is like on the output side. Um and
uncertainty and like whether the when we
have these like cool creative
experiments whether we are going out of
distribution or not is something we also
don't often check. uh or if uh the
sequences that they're requiring the
model with are they like human like or
is the model really confident about
these answers is not uh fully
established. I think another hot topic
is like predicting gene expression
variation across individuals. Uh there
are many groups now studying this. It's
it's really exciting. uh although we
have um the power to understand
mechanism of individual variants when we
use them jointly to predict expression
of a specific individual these models
often fail because they are trained uh
on the reference genome so they're not
really aware of the um genetic variation
in human populations. Uh but there are
some uh some cool attempts there as well
and the the software is often
fragmented. there are like people just
like implement things in in arbitrary
frameworks and this makes it difficult
to like put them um in the same context
and use them jointly. Uh so we have a
paper that I will show in the next slide
too but um
uh like basically check out the the
preprint too. Um so what we did is
basically we fixed the framework to like
pietorch um either reimplemented or uh
deployed the implementations of these
models implemented in PyTorch. Uh so
this is a model zoo but also like after
you load the model some uh standard sets
of uh downstream tasks are like simple
functions to design sequences uh predict
variant effects or like interpret the
models and so on. So simply um check out
the the QR code and can see the code as
well. So briefly about language
modeling. This is not really something
that I am really uh expert on. Uh but
just to set the scene and um give it to
to Sur I will briefly mention um what
genomic language models capture.
Um so one major category in genomics is
mass language models. Uh
where we basically mask like individual
base pairs and predict the uh predict
these bases from the context. Right? So
uh for example these bases are are
masked and predicted uh from the context
and these are basically practices
adopted um from NLP like many things
that I listed on the earlier slides
architecture decisions and loss
functions and so on. uh mass language
modeling also emerged in NLP and then it
kind of changed the the AI landscape
completely in NLP context and people
naturally asked like if we can simply
apply it to genomics or not or can we
basically build foundation models using
uh these the same principles that um
enable people to build foundation models
in other fields. Um
so there are like many models now there
there is also maybe not fully complete
list uh but many different uh mass
language models like GPN GPN MSA from
Yunong's lab and DNA bird and others uh
kodicious is one model that I think Sag
will mention as well uh and there are
some auto reggressive language models as
well basically where we yes
is the single base pair uh masking is a
single base masking the common practice
right now or are they experimenting with
are people experimenting with different
sizes of masks and do they see that it
matters? Uh yeah do you know? Um yeah so
there are people encode the input
differently in some cases there is also
like camera encodings or like the the
bite pair encodings as well. Uh some of
the models are like really so for if you
really want to mask a single base pair
then um it it makes a lot of sense to
basically encode the input as single
nucleotides. Uh but what they do is like
in training not really one base pair at
a time but like some fraction of bases
randomly like 15% for example are
randomly mass and some bases are also
like randomly um mutated as well to make
the model like more robust. Okay. But
when you say 15% it's like single bases
at 15 b 15% of the um right? Yeah. Mhm.
Not so much like a region of five bases
right next to no not continuous like
segments of the input but like random
bases. Um yeah and these are like
relatively simple or like smaller models
uh in terms of like context length um
and training strategies differ as well.
Some are human specific which is
extremely challenging I think and some
like simply augment these models with
the genomes of other species hundreds or
even thousands of species species LM is
is a nice one but it's now adopted in
many different language models I think
uh I will highlight GKMSA because it's a
it's a cool model and I like Gonzalo and
Yunong um it's one of the earliest
models it's a small uh context model
where the input is basically not just
the human sequence but like a multiple
sequence alignment of the uh the DNA
sequence and the masking is done for
like a human for example. So the model
is in this case. So there are some nice
uh creative ways of injecting inductive
bias, right? So this in this case the
model so the authors basically know very
well that uh conservation is really the
main source of um information for this.
It should be the main source of
information. So they inject it
explicitly. Um then this is the input.
Um the output is basically the
probability of each base for the mas u
positions and as I mentioned in this
case like 15% of positions are masked
um
yeah so this is one of the earlier
models I think GPN was an an arabidopsis
model without multiple sequence
alignment uh but
without multiple sequence alignment I
think if you apply it to human genome
directly the signal is really really
difficult to pick it up uh so then They
basically augmented the model with um
aligned sequences from from many other
species as well. And also how these
models use genomes of other species. The
way they use it is also different.
Sometimes they just pull all the
sequences and train one model on the
pulled um sequence. Sometimes they use
the multiple sequence alignment. And in
some cases they also have a an
additional token uh encoding the
species. So you really condition the
model on the species and then this the
sequence from this species and the model
learns more explicitly about um the
features of the sequence condition on
the species token. Um in this case 100
vertebrate species um leveraging
conservation and the genomic context in
this case and variant effect predictions
or like pathogenicity of the variance is
the main application downstream
application in this case. Uh so the way
it works is basically you compare the
probabilities of like a and c for
example. If your reference al is a and
the alternative al is c. Uh then the the
local change of of this gives you a
score of how um severely this variant
might be breaking things in the genomes
that you are looking at which is more or
less a proxy of um ptoenity of the
variant. Uh and there are comparisons to
like CAD which is um more like a feature
engineered version of the um of of
variance and variance scoring and
protein language models or like Philop
question. Can I ask you a question about
the masking actually? Yes. kind of
related to the question just now is like
what is your opinion on masking
individual bases randomly versus masking
like curs because for example you might
assume that DNA regulatory elements are
like you know have they have motifs
right so so what is your opinion on that
yeah I think they will serve different
purposes like if you mask the entire
motif then the question you're asking is
like is there anything else in the
context like other motifs for example
that are predictive of this specific
motif that you are masking but if you
mask individual bases it's different
then
maybe across but also within the motif
as well. So if you see the entire motif
but only one basis must the model will
have like lots of power to understand
what this motif is because it kind of
reoccurs in many different contexts. Uh
but then maybe your power to detect the
interactions between motives will be
limited um because you are basically
superimposing two two questions at the
same time. So you look share information
across motifs but also within motif as
well. But camera encoding I think is a
really really strong prior that we don't
entirely need is my very personal
opinion because we force the model in a
um in a very specific direction. Um yeah
so the var effect prediction is
basically um looking at the differences
of the probabilities of two different
alles which is kind of the main score
that the model generates and it's
comparable or in some cases superior uh
than CAD and ESM or phop which are also
other approaches exploiting
conservation. uh there are multiple
evaluations um I will highlight two so
one is from Anu's lab um
they design different uh tasks basically
different like levels of in in in the
order of increasing order of
difficulties so for example whether a
given sequence is an enhancer or not for
example like one regular terminal
classification where the language models
perform really well too uh but this is a
relatively easy question uh but as you
go basically more to more difficult
tasks
which typically involve more like cell
type specific signal then the model
starts failing. So um because it's not
basically the model really sees right.
So the model is u learning more like
rules of conser uh biology but not
exactly the cell type specific elements
and the regulatory gram grammar. uh so
in cases like the accessibility QTS or
accessibility prediction itself the
models uh don't really work well but in
so there are sets of questions that
these models should be used for and some
other questions that the models maybe
shouldn't use for and trade team is a
recent preent so the second evaluation
where we work together um so Gonzalo
basically um structured two variant data
sets one is non-coding variants from OMI
so one group just went through all data
set and flag the non-coding ones um the
non-coding rare variants linked to
mandelian traits and this is like one
data set basically you have some causal
non-coding rare variants and a match
negative set from nomad um and for the
complex traits we have UK bio bank
finite UK bio banks variance basically
from from Hillary's lab um and also a
negative set basically with the very low
um fine mapping kind of score and then
there different criteria to to match
these positives and negatives like as
challenging as as we can and then we
asked if the models can classify or like
succeed in this like classification
task. Uh and the results um this is like
super busy and I won't really go through
we can spend an hour I think looking at
this figure and try to make sense of it
but there are different ways of looking
at it the zero shot or like the probing
based um ways of like scoring it. uh but
the TLDDR I think is like CAD is
performing really well. This is the last
version of CAD uh which includes some
machine learning as well. Uh and models
um sequence to function models perform
better
at complex traits. Um and the GP and MSA
or like the language some of the
language models perform better in in in
mand mandelian traits. um basically is
the is the TLDDR and lots of large
extremely big uh language models also
fail uh in in both of these tasks
interestingly. Uh so my very personal
kind of opinion about language modeling
uh maybe the last um yeah I think the
last slide. So um most of these
practices that we copied from NLP uh
they are not I think really applicable
um because if you think about NLP uh the
one thing is the language is like very
much structured. We don't have like
simply random words or like things that
are shuffled or not informative. And the
second thing is uh in addition to this
very structured language the the ratio
of labeled and unlabeled data sets is
like hugely different. Uh a vast
majority of it is like unlabelled data
and we have very small labelled data. So
this ratio is different. But if you look
at the the genome basically the the
structure is loser especially in the
non-coding regions. Um and also the um
the label data is like really abundant
and by labeling it's kind of nature's
way of labeling it which is basically an
experiment. So if you think about all
the experimental data um and how loose
the structured the language itself is
it's a really bad combination when you
simply apply the uh the principles from
language modeling. So this is like one
kind of interesting way of like
visualizing it that I came up with
yesterday. Um basically so if the models
if there's like one specific signal that
a specific cell type is paying attention
to um the the the genome is basically a
superimposition of all the cell type
specific elements. So there are
different regions that are active in a
specific context but when the language
model looks at it bas it basically looks
at the genome without any functional
data and it won't really be able to
delineate all these uh segments that are
functional in different context. So uh
if you really want to the model to pick
up the the context or cell type have
specific effects then the functional
data is really useful. But I think still
seeing these models as a datadriven and
more like modernized version of
conservation models or like modeling
conservation is is a better way to see
it rather than uh foundational models of
of the genome. Uh so yes that I would
like to conclude. Um so sequence to
function models it's a very well
established framework. Uh but there are
still some really cool um challenges
like open problems to take on. Um
language model is a really great tool I
uh as you will see in the next slide
too. Uh if you use it in in different
ways I think it will be really useful
and functional data is like abundant and
essential. Uh inductive bias is
basically where the the creativity plays
plays a huge role. In some cases it's
maybe simple just like switching from
convolution to dilated convolution for
example. But in some cases it's um for
example avoiding the repetitive regions
um in the language model training is a
nice inductive bias. So it doesn't have
to be a fancy modeling decision but also
simple decisions about preprocessing or
um structuring your input uh as some
room to inject in inductive bias. And
for whatever reason these two
communities are like relatively
distinct. Um although they are modeling
like very similar things still like some
sequence features of the of the genome
from different perspectives both the
models and the communities are are
distinct um something to think about and
also new frameworks I think can really
bridge this uh but how so I will leave
you with this cliffhanger so that you
can stay for for the second talk with
this I would like to thank all the uh
collaborators the team members and also
uh my son which is like the last name
without whom I think I could have slept
better and I would have had a better
memory as well. So, thank you so much
for your attention.