Hi. Uh my name is Johannes. I'm the CEO
and co-founder of Defraction. Um and at
Defraction we do two things that will uh
guide you through it. One, we see
further and two we think faster.
So the problem when you look at visual
AI today um and you have a camera plus a
sensor behind an processor is that um
you have a couple limitations which um
are necessary for things like if you
operate in space or a high frequency
manufacturing line. So one you have a
limited resolution of your image which
comes from the fact um that you lose
information every time you process that
information and secondly um you lose
also time as you go from your camera
sensor afterwards to your processor and
then having to output some sort of
intelligence for example what kind of
bubble am I seeing or is this a
satellite that I'm seeing up there or
not. Our inspiration was the eye. So, if
you've seen a sparrow catching a bug
midair in flight, um it's a very
impressive thing to do. And I was taught
in high school that uh the eye actually
is just a camera. But that's not true.
An eye has some intelligence and can
detect shapes and fastm moving things,
trajectories, and that actually
intelligence in the eye allows the
sparrow to catch that fly moving very
fast.
Now taking this um we applied it to our
visual sensing and processing unit and
we built a better eye. Um now this one
replaces the camera and a GPU. It's two
in one. You can see further 20 times
further than the defraction limit which
I always explain with the last letter
that you can see when you go to the
optometrist like when it gets blurry.
That's your defraction limit. We give
you a 20 times better defraction limit
than any camera can do today. And we can
also think faster because the processor
inside is photonic. We can think up to a
thousand times faster and understand
what we're looking at at a thousand
times faster with a thousand times lower
energy consumption. Why it works is that
we developed this technology with my
co-founder Sikad Kua. He's a professor
at university at MIT and University of
Maryland. He also did his PhD at MIT. Um
I'm also an MIT grad and uh he in the
last 10 years developed this TRL4
exclusive use patent and tech uh with
NASA and DARPA and the idea is that the
scene coming through a lens is being
defracted by different plates that are
optimized based on our algorithm that we
patented and gives us the maximum
resolution by quantum mechanics. So on
the right you can see a recent paper
published where uh we reached this
defraction limit which is the last
letter you could see in this case on the
left is a star on the right we could see
actually that those were two stars and
one was hiding 25 times further behind
the other one. Um we also have a project
with DARPA uh that an SBI director phase
2 of $ 1.5 million um that we have uh
already been working on. So if you see
about here in in our against our
competitors both on GPUs but also on
SMOS cameras we can see 20 times
further. So if you can see something at
130 m we can see it at 2.4 km. And if
you can react to something in 100
milliseconds or so we can do it in
microsconds.
So our camera has a very broad
potential. Um we are starting in space
awareness um and the air defense golden
dome and earth observation. Uh but then
we are also expanding to drones and
detection systems but very importantly
also to quality control. So fastm moving
conveyor belts uh for quality control of
bottles, electronics, semiconductors and
of course robotics and autonomous
driving.
So for the ask uh to all the members
here, we would love to partner and find
use cases where you require an very high
speed, very high resolution, very low
energy consumption by processor. Um and
it can be both in defense and space. So
in drone, earth imaging, space domain in
quality control like food beverage,
semiconductors, batteries, visual
inspections of utilities and agriculture
from space or if you're purchasing data
today from satellite imaging um or
inspections from drones, then uh this is
something where this technology would
also excel. So yeah, thank you very much
and I'll move on to questions.