thank you thank you very much for for
your very kind introduction it's a a
tremendous pleasure to to be here today
to tell you a little bit more about what
we do at the Microsystems technology
Laboratories and how we collaborate not
only with lots of people on campus but
with hundreds of of different companies
worldwide to to make an impact in Micro
Systems and micro Electronics because
that that's our our mission Mt for short
is the home of Microsystems research and
education at MIT and our definition of
of Microsystems is very broad going all
the way from Innovations in materials to
to systems microelectronics
nanotechnology electronic and photonic
devices sensors bioms integrated
circuits all the way to system level
prototyping so very very Broad very
broad mission for a a very important
impact that we think we we are playing
because we all know that
microelectronics has enabled many
different revolutions o over the last 75
years it's because of micro electronics
that the computer Revolution happened
it's because of micro electronics that
the communication Revolution happened it
is because of microelectronics that the
internet and the AI Revolution
are happening today but even though
microelectronics and semiconductors and
new materials and technologies have been
transforming our society for the last
few decades I would like to to argue
that we are just starting to scratch the
surface of the true potential of
Microsystems and that's exactly where
MTL comes into
place so we are just starting the the
scratch the surface how how can that be
I mean we are already making an impact
in in in Computing we are making an
impact in Communications we are making a
the internet and AI possible but at the
same
time microelectronics I I would argue it
is the absolutely critical missing piece
today to enable personalize affordable
health care that can provide better
outcomes if we are able to bring more
sense
more intelligence to the devices around
us I have no
idea I I have no doubt
that we are going to start a revolution
in healthcare not not only
there microelectronics is also key for
feeding the wall again if we are able to
bring more intelligence to agriculture
more intelligence for the to the food
production ER Network in in our world I
have no doubt that we will be able to
increase efficiency and really
significantly transform our society yes
in the same way we have transformed
Society for the last 75 years through
Computing communication the internet AI
Etc also there is no green energy
without micro Electronics without
semiconductors and without chips there
are no electric vehicles there are no
renewable energy resources that there is
in summary no no green
energy and when we look at the AI
Revolution and what is enabling the AI
Revolution it's all the the AI data
centers that
are coming up all throughout our
geography and AI it's right in the way
of the exponential Improvement in
performance that microelectronics
semiconductors and materials have
enabled for many many
decades so microelectronics has
transformed our world and it's in a path
to continue to create new new
revolutions at the same time I would
argue that microelectronics also
represents one of the most important
risks for our society and and that that
is highlighted in in this plot here
which shows energy consumption as well
as energy production as a a function of
time ER in green we we
have the the energy consumption by micro
electronics and semiconductors as a
function of of time while in Orange we
we have the walls energy production and
as we see it the amount of energy that
goes into Electronics is increasing
exponentially and if the current trains
continue roughly by
2035 or 2040 my micro electronics and AI
data centers and semiconductor based
communication systems are going to be
using 100% of all the energy being
produced in the world no energy for food
production no energy for transportation
no energy for anything else than
microelectronics and that's of course a
problem and that that's also a huge
opportunity for all of us so that's
where
MTL is playing a very important role in
the MIT ecosystem our mission is really
to develop the next generation of
materials devices systems and
microelectronic prototypes in very close
collaboration with our industry industry
colleagues we are an inter departmental
Laboratory spanning more than seven
different departments and approximately
70 different research groups across
MIT and when I think when I step back
and think okay what what are the the key
the key enablers that have made MTL
successful I I I would summarize them as
follows first of all the very very
strong Community if you ask anyone a at
MIT about the different communities that
the different labs and initiatives have
everyone will highlight MTL as one of
the strongest communities on campus and
again the community is not only the
professors and the students it's also
the staff and
especially our industry industry
Partners we have a full commitment to
Excellence like everyone else a ad MIT
and all the different departments that
are essential for the future of
Microsystems are very well ranked
internationally and we take full
advantage of
that we also thrive in inter
disciplinary research and because we are
a fairly large Department touching lots
of things all the way from sensors for
food production to health care and the
future of compute we divide ourselves in
smaller interdisciplinary research
communities and here we have a few of
them such as the the center for
integrated circuits and systems doing
everything related to chips and chiplets
or on medical electronic devices and
realization Center the
medc AI the AI is Transforming Our wall
at many different levels and MTL faculty
members are working together in the MIT
AI Hardware program to make that happen
for Power Electronics white bang of
semiconductors are extremely important
components and again there is a a an
initiative on that as there is one on 2D
materials as applied to energy Ai and
compute and we are not stopping there
there are new programs being started all
the time and right now we are working
with with our community to get two
additional initiatives started
one on the future of display technology
both large area displays as well as AR
VR displays and there is another
initiative being started as we speak
right now
today at MTL on the use of
semiconductors to revolutionize
Healthcare we are also very fortunate to
have access to to worldclass
experimental facil facilities such as
MIT Nano the Lisa tissue building here
at MIT which is the the State ofthe art
probably the world best microelectronics
prototyping facility and if you haven't
had a chance to to visit it h please do
because it's a really really impressive
place where you can see a research
happening 24/7 and I believe there are
tours organized for for this after
for those
interested we thrive in Innovation and
we thrive on entrepreneurship and new
startups in in this field come out of
MTL all the time and here we have a a a
few of the ones who have come out of MTL
in in the last few
years and last but not least we are
extremely proud of our very vibrant
industrial consorti or or me the
Microsystems industrial group that is
made of 16 amazing companies that are
supporting our work ER throughout many
many decades I'm
sorry and this work as I mentioned spans
all the way from basic material ER
research a AI driven material Discovery
all the way to new semiconductor devices
and sensors putting them together into
more complex chips changing the factor
of electronics Electronics doesn't have
to be rigid like today's computers
Electronics is going to be flexible it's
going to be transparent it's going to be
invisible and we spend a lot of time
prototyping actual systems all the way
from Smart fabrics and textiles
to insect scale micro robots new
biomedical H devices and systems etc
etc and we don't stop at the prototyping
we also spend a lot of time thinking
very carefully
about entrepreneurship and the supply
chain that is necessary to take all
these Innovations from the lab to the
market and I would love to work with
with with all of you on
this so we organize lots of different
events and activities throughout the
year and I I don't have a a time today
to to go through through all of them but
I I do want to highlight a a couple of
of initiatives such as our annual
conference the Microsystems annual
research conference or or mark this is
the the
largest university organized micro
electronics and micro systems conference
anywhere in the world it happens EV
every every January in a a wonderful ski
resort a couple of hours North of Boston
I I invite all of you to to
attend we also have a a a a a very
Lively career fair happening every every
September where hundreds of of of
students and companies take take part
a a a very Dynamic and active resume
site and also I I do want to spend a a
minute or so on this a program which
goes beyond M micro micro Electronics
you know a a few years ago I I asked MIT
students hey we all know that Hardware
is the future we all enjoy playing with
hardware and with the breakthroughs that
Hardware enables but if that if that is
the case how is that many of you are are
actually going into software and what
the MIT students told me freshman and
sophomore was you know what when we
first joined MIT we were super excited
about Hardware everything from
microelectronics to robots to everything
in between but then as first year and
sophomore we appli to summer internships
to Hardware focused companies
and we got rejected from every single
hardware company while we were getting
amazing internships in
software companies and that is a problem
we are closing the pipeline right at the
beginning and we started this program
the Northeast micro Electronics
internship program to to change that to
provide summer internships to first year
and second year students throughout the
Northeast in Hardware Focus companies
this year we have more than 450 students
interested in Hardware focused jobs in
industry and I need your help I need you
to reach out to us and provide
opportunities for for for the next
generation of Technology
leaders and I'm running out of time but
I I do want to to finish by by
highlighting that this year we celebrate
the 40th anniversary of the Microsystems
technology laboratory and for many
decades we have had a very close
partnership with I
LP in everything related to hardware and
microelectronics and we are exercising
this partnership this year by organizing
our 40th anniversary celebration at the
same time as this Flagship ILP R&D
conference so tomorrow November 20th in
this room we will highlight lots of
innovations that have come out of MTL
the Microsystems technology Laboratory
uh over the decades I'm looking into the
future the future of healthcare the
future of quantum the future of energy
and I'm very much looking forward to
seeing you all tomorrow at this
event thank you thank you so much for
your attention