[Music]
the idea is to take some hypothetical
situations that you've either seen in
the movies read about or been in
depending on your experience in the
public sector ask you at tables to think
of your best advice to the people in the
situation in each hypothetical effective
leadership in the public sector we are
asserting requires different strategies
behaviors and
qualifications than effective leadership
in the private sector the key difference
is being able to facilitate consensus
building decisions made by all not just
by the leader they know how to provide
Direction without taking control
empowering others to make decisions and
helping to resolve conflict among
stakeholders and interest groups and we
talked about doing those things as a
form of service we alluded to but didn't
get into much
detail about
facilitation RIS responsibilities both
at the
table where you're trying to work with a
group and away from the table on behalf
of the group before the group comes
together there are things that the
facilitative leader can do must do to
make the chances of succeeding when they
are together at the table
increase at the table and away from the
table we'll be using that
phraseology the next several sessions
and we talked about facilitative leaders
who both encourage
advocacy on the part of the people
they're working with and
inquiry on the part of
participants and that's not easy to do
some
people find that their advocacy impedes
their
capacity to inquire enabling discussion
of undiscussable issues you want to
provide leadership in the public Arena
and you're assisting a group there are
things that they really need to talk
about if they're going to reach any kind
of informed agreement when a
facilitative leaders seeks to bring a
group into a conversation about things
which for some of the people very
uncomfortable how do they do it it's
part of the facilitative service that
they provide they have to know how to
make the undiscussable discussable any
hope of working through and resolving
their
disagreements hinges on moving all of
the participants in a public
dialogue from positions to interest
not a guarantee that that's going to get
you to
agreement but if all people are doing is
repeating their
demands you're not going to get anywhere
a facilitative leader seeks unanimity
but settles for overwhelming agreement
you don't vote you're not interested in
what the majority wants and the reason
if you say unanimity is the measure of
the decision you invite black
you have some actors in the group whose
primary objective is to sabotage the
group and they're happy with that in
many quarters of the world people think
of this as the UN
problem you're saying we can't do
anything unless everybody agrees and
some oh good we're still on that that's
great that'll mean nothing or bad will
happen that I don't
like so here's the first scenario the
mayor has appointed a blue ribbon
committee to advise her on a new process
of public budgeting one that will ensure
greater public
engagement the mayor named a leading
corporate figure in the community the
CEO of the largest employer in the city
to chair or lead this advisory committee
there's an immediate back clash in the
press the community is convinced there's
no way this person should have been
named to be the leader of this group
question to you what's your advice to
the
CEO regarding a how to introduce himself
to the rest of the committee and the
public secondly how do you think the CEO
should prepare for the first meeting of
this committee and third how can the CEO
establish credibility with the other
members of the committee let alone the
community at large so we're looking for
your table's best advice to this CEO how
could this person Be an Effective
leader is it inappropriate to suggest
that he resign as that's what I was
thinking and not necessarily from the
whole committee like
but then like are they still a leader
after that I feel like that could be
contentious it kind of like you know
like it feels like a little bit of a
slap in the face of the mayor I mean it
is a budgetary committee and I do think
there's like a lot that the public
sector learn in some ways from the
private sector what is his commitment to
the community how is his business give
it back to the community maybe taking a
back seat on like the next couple
meetings kind of just saying like I'm
here everyone layer ideas out the table
so maybe have dominating meetings as
much as could or they could but
eventually he's the chair I agree like
he cannot dominate but he will be asked
to intervene at some point if his role
is a facilitator like at the end of the
meeting like giving giving that like
unbiased summary of like what's
happening it's not skewing anything or
only pulling out the opinions he he
agrees with but really like giving a
summary of like everything that was
covered at this table um we threw out a
couple of um sort of different options
kind of mostly centered on the question
of how does how does this person
establish credibility right off the bat
in the first meeting what can be done
and then will here had a great idea
which was what if the person sets up
meetings beforehand with a
representative sample from this
committee so that when everyone does
show up to this first initial meeting
those people can see that the CEO person
has taken their advice on board and has
listened to their their concerns and
their thoughts we were discussing and
biani spearheaded the idea of
recognizing the backlash that is
preceding this CEO trying to not subvert
the backlash but address it headon in a
one-on-one setting that allows someone
in a structured format to air their
grievances but also their interests so
that you aren't entering into the first
committee meeting in sort of like a a
cacophonous room full of maybe miscon
ception stereotypes not only in a sense
of like establishing credibility but
also from a purely like facilitative
standpoint I don't want to say control
the narrative but maybe set the record
straight from where they intend to come
in we were talking along kind of similar
lines about this role of transparency
specifically in the first meeting for
the CEO to go in and very clearly
delineate what their expertise is within
this setting and what their expertise is
not and so in that sense open in up
space for the other members of the
committee to take on leadership roles in
sharing their own expertise and also
creates an opportunity as well for the
CEO to express his own interest and true
desire to learn from the other members
of the council and from the community as
a whole one of the things we were
talking about not necessarily hearing
from folks before the first meeting but
really using that first meeting to kind
of establish guidelines checks and
balances systems and the process that's
going to come about um to really kind of
focus around trust building and
Coalition building during that first
meeting or first several meetings like
really taking an unbiased view of like
taking notes and listening to all of the
different people who are in that room
and then giving a very unbiased feedback
or like recap of that um and so then
people begin to understand that they can
you know voice their opinions voice
their thoughts without anything being
kind of overlooked or brushed over
because they're not in agreement with
this leader identifying himself as a
human being and not just this kind of
powerful figure and then being really
clear about you know how he will be held
accountable and how you know this
process will work I'm curious to hear
thoughts on this whether it would be
appropriate given how
poorly uh the process started for this
CEO in the first meeting to offer
voluntarily to resign as chair I don't
know off like say anyone else in the
room we can come up with a new process
for finding a new chair but then we also
talked about maybe that would be
insulting to the mayor in this context
resigning you know and leaving that just
confirms the fact this was the wrong
person to take on a leadership role in
the public sector but
possibility is
changed if they recognize the danger of
proceeding in the way the people are
immediately upset about and they say not
an assistant a
co-chair and they have to make sure
before they put the mayor in the
position of announcing that that the
coaches will be able to work together so
then they're delivering to the mayor a
proposal that's already been worked out
that that's how I would respond to the
resigning
idea it's interesting that it becomes
about who the CEO is and why they were
appointed rather than who the mayor is
and why they appointed that way and I
think it it's more reflective of
actually what the mayor wants and how
they wish to lead if they're going to
appoint a CEO theoretically based on the
fact that they think this person can
operate this steering committee from a
hierarchical point of view how is it
reflective of the mayor and what they
want and how they wish to lead and what
sort of leadership stance they
prioritize actually makes me want to put
the attention on that person versus like
the person who's appointed and how they
need to then figure out what to do in
order to to deal with someone else's
decision about
them if you ask ask what's it take to Be
an Effective leader in the public sector
I would argue more than whatever the
skill is and the experience is that work
for you in the private sector some other
additional ways of building trust as a
way of establishing credibility and not
assuming you can count on your title and
your history as a source of credibility
I had imagined we would be through
several scenarios by now and I don't
want to keep you from dinner while
you're having dinner I will ask you to
talk about a second
scenario so I'm going to uh switch the
context in this
scenario scenario takes place in a
different city different metropolitan
area in one of the inner suburbs
the school
committee being attacked from all sides
the teachers have voted no confidence in
the superintendent the teachers union is
demanding that the superintendent resign
the elected school committee is
divided some backing the
superintendent and some supporting the
teachers union there are a whole raft of
policies behind this that are dividing
the
community when whether current efforts
to ensure student safety in the
buildings are adequate who's to blame
for the very low scores on Statewide
exams in this city as compared to other
schools in nearby cities the need for
either more or less parental control
over the content of the K through six
curriculum whether or not more
investment should be made in advanced
courses for the most gifted students the
desirability of mainstreaming versus or
rather than separating special needs
students all these issues this division
sharp
division between teachers and the
superintendent between and amongst
teachers
amongst family members what's your best
advice to this
superintendent under this
circumstance given all of this all of
this hostility all all of this
difficulty how would you help this
person get things back on a useful track
as the leader in the schools and
education area in this community so the
idea is to have table discussion and
then we'll see where you come out and
see if we get any differences in my
previous job we talked a lot about
making sure that like we come in with a
clear goal and like like what is
actionable from like this feedback like
not just going in general get feedback
but like coming in with concrete ways
that the feedback can actually be used
setting expectations like this is what
we can change this is what we can't side
the conversation could impact that
probably better to just be un FR with
like what's in our realm as right now
and even like short-term long what could
we change this year what would we need
to work on that will probably take 10
your own workers who are not believing
in you like their trust is completely
lost in you and it depends on them for
your whatever plan you have to be
successful they're not feeling hurt or
they're not having you know vested trust
in their their quote unquote leader that
you know creating mechanisms for um kind
of Distributing that that leadership
amongst the teachers you know I would
first see what the problem I would after
that I'm going to be like okay now let
me get a team of experts all the issues
that were highlighted to be I would try
to solve the
issues and like give that confidence to
whoever cares about it I'm going to use
say the next 6 months to remedy this and
you will see this kind of change and
like make these kind of short-term goals
for people to gain confidence in them
account I think the makeup of those
boards doesn't have to be like the
people who brought it up at the you
know whoever is most qualified to be
yeah like what are the
pivotable are plac like where change
could be made are they the right person
to do it so like what does res me like
it doesn't even have to necessarily be
immediate what is a succession thing
look like how can I come someone else to
be able to take this on or point out who
I think should be able to see me if it's
clear that like I suspect that it might
not happen through like a presentation
or you telling people that but you
actually need to get people in the room
and then start guiding the conversation
towards this common realization we're
all here for the same thing right we all
want the same thing right the one thing
you could actually do is to get
representatives from this room um from
these different subcommittees in one
room and then you start to get them to
think together about Solutions it's like
oh if we mainstream these kids what's
going happen with these other resources
that are going to come from
mainstreaming them you know can we do
something with that just like collab get
them to collaborate with each other
interesting idea maybe having like
representatives of each interest part of
the committee like it's not
siloed by interest but it's like like a
representative Committee of all the
interests yeah that's they're forc to
talk with each other and that there
isn't this like arm wrestling between
the silos they would probably choose the
one who has the largest voice who's kind
of a fighter but but these kind of
people may not be good to putting a
negotiation uh process I think part of
being a facilitative leader is also
preparing each of these folks to be able
to best advocate for themselves so then
you go back to that oneon-one
relationship again so before you have
that meeting where you start to do the
collaboration you need to do
preparations with them but it's also
kind of difficult because they have
you're not biased towards any specific
concern so let's say safety of the
students in schools um k to6 curricula
um the mainstreaming of the special
needs students like you have to sure
you're not biased or every single one
that's the hard part yeah I think that
would also support the uh problem that
you're bringing up that you don't want
to just bring the guy the loudest voice
to the table you kind of want to give
others a chance that's part of
facilitating the process cuz you're
helping everyone improve the mindset of
being ready to
collaborate essentially a decision needs
to be made that's like in favor of one
party instead of the other I think
that's the part about pairing them and
then letting them do the negotiation
amongst themselves at the table kind of
builds that trust that you're not biased
because people are putting their own
skin in the game you're
not they sort of like bring order to the
space enforce rules bring things to yes
this
hypothetical is uh what the vast number
of people who see themselves as leaders
in the public sector are dealing with
daytoday these are the circumstances
that people are being prepared to work
in and when
conflict has overwhelmed whatever
forward movement somebody who thinks
their the leader has they have to have
some idea some strategy what do you do
when all this conflict has wrapped
itself around whatever the functional
responsibilities are were you trying to
think of ways of
resolving the conflict telling the
superintendent you can do this this this
and this to resolve the conflict were
you mostly thinking about talking to the
superintendent about how to proceed with
the work that needs to be done in spite
of the conflict you think that a leader
in this position can do something to
wipe the conflict away to resolve it if
not what are they supposed to do about
the work that's supposed to get done
it's completely
Frozen because everybody's at everybody
else's throat are they supposed to
mediate this all these different
disputes that they're the focus of I
know they can
resign it's not you don't have to
I number of years people are in
positions is getting shorter and shorter
in the public sector in the United
States and in other countries conflict
is om thepresent people either don't
know of a way to proceed in a leadership
role and trying to resolve the conflict
so they walk away or they're thrown
out because they don't appear to be able
to solve the conflict whether they leave
voluntar or not their term is short
because the
conflict is
overwhelming so our group um held that
you know there's accountability to
improving the system um and
accountability by the superintendent to
either acknowledge you know their role
in it um also to um either facilitate or
be adjacent to an ad hoc committee that
can facilitate a
Discovery process or audit of what
exactly has been going wrong within the
school system um even making
considerations for conducting uh like
investigations and interviewing with
other parts of the school system and key
stakeholders to um help facilitate a
transition process and um inheritance of
a new a better system that where we
understand the challenges that are going
on um and ways that can adjust moving
forward the superintendent still would
probably be recommended to to leave um
at that point um however I do think that
their institutional knowledge of the
issue is relevant to identifying the key
issues of the system do you believe that
if they could just solve one of these
conflicts and have it clear that it was
their doing that resolved it and they'd
be accepted in that role of trying to
resolve them because they resolve one
thing first yeah I mean I think it seems
to be a complex issue where there is um
pivot Points where there is the most uh
upside if it is resolved um so
potentially solving one and finding out
the the positive impact from that might
give a vote of confidence so you would
entertain that proposition that if they
can do something and actually take one
of these clear conflicts in the
community and get the people who are
primarily the key actors and secret them
away somewhere and help them work that
out and then come out together with them
and announce look we've solved this and
if we can solve this we can solve all of
our conflicts trust me not exactly
one I think it requires a more
comprehensive strategic approach but
solving a big issue first might be a
first pillar of or milestone for that
what about setting a lot of different
people in motion with responsibility for
trying to resolve or mediate different
disputes now there is not being the one
to resolve these
disputes but saying I have this person I
don't I don't know if they're loyal to
me or not but maybe they would say they
would accept responsibility over the
next six weeks for this particular
conflict between this group and this
group because they're close to both
sides and I'm asking them to see what
progress they can make and I'm giving
them authority to act on that and then
you've set a lot of different people
carefully chosen on the grounds that
there's no chance the superintendent can
solve all these problems they're the
source of most of them or at least the
symbolic source of most of them what I'm
asking is as you think about your
personal theory of practice and you have
one whether you confront it regularly
and build it or not you have one what do
you assume about the management of
conflict and the role of leadership
there are sides the union this and the
people who are managing the union I
found in real life as a person assigned
as a mediator from outside they don't
even know what they're fighting about
they're really really angry they'll tell
me a topic I'll sit with everybody
privately confidentially I'm just an
outsider I'm just asked to see if
there's any way to help there's no way
will accept the Librarians not having
the final control of which books go in
the library for K through six that's it
no chance no
way okay why what do you mean
why well couldn't there be an occasion
in which the Librarians mostly do this
but if somebody has a concern that the
Librarians and some other people have a
conversation about it and you can asked
for a chance to discuss this without
saying the only ones who make the
decision of the
Librarians we never did it that way I
know that but I'm trying to see whether
it's possible to invent a way forward
that meets your underlying interests
differently from what's been done in the
past well I don't know if my people will
accept it if I were to be in a
conversation where that was being
discussed well could we try it and see
right getting people to discuss the
undis what they think is
undiscussable how do you how can you
facilitate that we shifted to a
different um Direction and thought about
hiring experts or a technical Advisory
Group of sorts to work alongside the
superintendent on the issues that were
identified uh because
it's not that the superintendent can
solve it all I don't think the Advisory
Group or the experts can solve it all as
well what we discussed was to have
people who were more knowledgeable of
those particular issues and could have a
better understanding of how to solve
them and then we also talked about
releasing a memo of sorts which outlines
the plan of how the superintendent and
his team can tackle these issues uh
because what you were saying about oh if
the super intendant solves one issue
will that be enough for him to start
working on others and I think in a lot
of cases that is true uh because to gain
the trust back of these different
stakeholders even saying that okay I'm
starting to solve this one issue I mean
not one in like one issue but like
starting small I think is important to
gain the trust back of these
stakeholders so I think even starting
small definitely helps gain trusts of
communities and other like union leaders
and people yeah it's a highrisk strategy
to assume that if I could just find the
Lynch pin solve this one quickly then
everything's going to fit together my
hunch is in this particular kind of
story where the superintendent is
supposedly the administrative leader but
also is the object of the conflict for
many of the parties that waiting for
them to pick one of these disputes and
resolve it through their intervention so
they can wave a flag and say you can all
have confidence in me look I solve this
probably a losing strategy
whereas if the
superintendent could have private
conversations with a lot of the folks
who are complaining about something that
the superintendent's doing and say well
would you be willing to take
responsibility for the next period of
time of getting this this this and this
together and coming up with your
suggestion of what should be done
together I don't want to hear a summary
of what you disagree about I'm looking
for you to produce positive proposals
and nobody's tried to convene these
folks and I think they would trust you
to do that they're not making final
decisions they're making
suggestions together for ways are
resolving issues and if we could get a
half dozen different people if the
leader can
facilitate the engagement of other
participants and help build their role
in
leadership I'm arguing that the leaders
role is enhanced I think a lot of times
this strategy is used the one you're
describing but my problem with this is
that you're asking those people to do
more labor who are already experiencing
these problems and in a lot of cases
when I worked with uh communities
especially is that they do not want to
take responsibility because they're
already frustrated all these
stakeholders and then me going in as a
superintendent for example and saying oh
maybe you can help me solve this and
it's like but that's your job do do you
understand so I feel like it sometimes
puts a lot of blame and a lot of work
and a lot of labor on these different
stakeholders and my question is how to
address that how to approach this in a
way that it doesn't look like that
instead it looks like we are trying to
uh co-create Solutions so how do you
approach
that next time I'm going to give you a
list of a dozen what I called my micro
skills of facilitative leadership one is
how do you convince someone to take
responsibility for helping to solve up
the problem that they think you're the
part of you can either do that or you
can it's not about how sweetly you talk
it's not about being smarter than the
there's a set of principles for how you
get someone who's opposed to you to
agree to help solve the problem with you
what does it take to develop Your
Capacity to facilitate to turn around a
conflict situation to set an agenda for
a group that's Has No Agenda to set
ground rules to how people in a rockus
meeting are dealing with each other the
final session I really want to ask you
to assess your sense of yourself Your
Capacity to become or to be a
facilitative leader or to say I don't
see it that's not my role I don't see
myself in that capacity I really want to
get you to take the micro skills to take
the things that we talked about last
time and this time and say do I see
myself functioning in this kind of
situation if you were in the
like the superintendent with lots of
people mad at you partly because of the
symbolic positions you have partly
because of the things you've said and
done partly because they just believe
different things from
you can you see yourself going to
work or not can you deal with
conflict my sense is if you don't have a
pathway in your mind for transforming
those conflict situations into more
workable forms of
collaboration then you you're not going
to be able to keep it up it's too hard
you need to Envision some path you need
to imagine that you have a half a dozen
micro skills that it takes to work
effectively in that situation so we will
come to that before we stop I want to
come to the the the gender and race
questions that people raised last time
in the case you were just looking at
were you imagining the
superintendent male
female One race another race does it
matter to your analysis of the situation
how should we see how do we see gender
and
race
intersecting with questions of
leadership now that we've talking about
facilitative leadership uh in the public
Arena I mean if you question yourself do
you imagine you were seeing things in a
certain way because you were presuming
the superintendent was male or female
and because it was female you imagined
there were certain options open to her
male no we constantly say we should
consider gender and race and a variety
of other other attributes as independent
variables are they in fact relevant
variables in any of the conversations
that we've had
I have personally witnessed women of
color and positions of power and I think
if they were in this hypothetical
situation they would be forced to resign
or there would be this almost like Witch
Hunt happening and I think I mean I'm
coming from a field of architecture but
I've seen it happen with leadersh ship
within that realm faculty or like deans
of colleges in that same realm and it
happens very often so I think I mean
like in my mind I was just imagining a
male in this situation I didn't imagine
like a race but I think that when
it's specifically I'll only speak to
like a person of color um I I think the
repercussions and the processes there
are a lot different often
times because of the expectations of the
community around them or because of
their own sense of themselves I think
it's because the
expectations are
higher from the community around them
and
then even if they're meeting the same
kind of threshold as potentially like a
a a white male um the expectations are
so much higher of them that it's almost
impossible for them to succeed in that
capacity
because there's it's just someone's only
human so can you think of a pathway or a
set of steps that would make that
diagnosis less likely to be the case I
have a question where is these scenarios
are located in the US and where exactly
because I mean we keep referring about
those cases in the previous session and
in this session is are they Global
because the MS like the values the the
are completely different from country to
Country and within a country are
completely different from region to
region or from Urban to
rural uh you mentioned in your case
before in the first scenario that's why
you ask that questions why you choose a
CEO of a
company that perhaps here in the US with
you know the values in certain parts of
this country the values of a a
competition or the values Trace from a
meritocratic system or capital
system makes that that person is a
person that eventually could be admired
by the society and perhaps the mayor we
don't know the hidden agenda of the
major choose that person to represent
that committee but in other parts of the
world people do not have that values of
whether is a a razor company or computer
company or hiding people or lead people
because leadership is about completely
different value that making money or
having a big Corporation I'm not saying
that those are the values here in the US
please don't take me wrong but
I or take me wrong but but the question
I'm saying is very important that we
have a very specific context where this
scenario happen in order to respond
those questions and if be aware as well
that we have to understand the scenario
before we take a decision because one
decision in one country could be
completely the opposite in another one
if you understand the scenario perfectly
are you empowered
differently I I'm accepting the premise
you would be more informed in what ways
are you empowered by being more informed
what does it make you more um optimistic
about the moves you're making and that
likely to likely increase your
Effectiveness from a deontological
perspective I think that I will be more
legitimate to provide advice your
legitimacy because of the mov you an
advisor I'm talking about
yeah I'm I'm trying to convince
myself that there's a way to talk about
race and gender in the context of
leadership that has nothing to do with
personality and that has something to do
with being able to use the same skills
of facilitative leadership that another
facilitative leader has in a
situation because there's either a match
or a mismatch I don't know which between
the race and gender of the person who
wants to act as a leader and the
constituency or the context in which
they're working either that or it
doesn't matter I'm too old to believe it
doesn't matter I've lived through too
many things where race and gender have
mattered to think that there could be a
way that they don't matter so now I'm
trying to figure out well how do they
matter and how can instruction build on
what it takes given that they matter but
I I don't see it yet clearly what
instruction differently not differently
to females that want to take on a
facilitative leadership role do they
have to learn different things do they
have to learn it with more confidence do
they have to learn how they're seen they
learn the same thing but they learn how
what they've learned is seen by others
and so they can make adjustments before
it's even necessary because of how
others are viewing them not teaching
anything different I'm not assuming that
anything different will play out in
terms of the logic of
leadership but I I believe this makes
some difference in terms of the
perceptions you talked
about um women of color in positions of
responsibility who expect they're going
to be judged more
harshly than a a a a white male
counterpart would be in the exact same
situation and if I assume that's true
therefore what can we do to help bolster
the person maybe I can't do anything
about bolstering the person maybe it's
the context and if I have no power to
change the context doing something
different for with the person won't add
up to a different outcome I don't know
which I believe it is think about the
questions that came up about the
scenarios I will focus on micro skills
that I think an effective facilitative
leader has to have I will enumerate them
I will probably use a screen and talk
about what those skills are and when I
think they come into play and how uh you
can learn them perfect them develop them
that's going to be the focus next time I
want to talk about those micro skills of
facilitating and empowering and turning
a conflict situation into a joint
problem solving situation and shifting
people from positions to interests which
I think is as I said essential as a step
in the process of trying to be effective
as a leader I'll see you again next week
[Music]