(graphics whooshing)
So, let's look at the next question.
"Large language models often
generate code that looks right,
but fails in practice.
So, how do we make this
systems more reliable?"
So, this is actually
a really good question
because this is a question
that the programming systems
community has been working on
actually with a fair bit of success
over the last two decades.
You know, I remember when
I had my first laptop,
I could never run it
probably for more than a day
without the machine crashing, right?
And compared to that,
the level of reliability
that we have today
in our computer systems is
actually quite remarkable.
And a lot of it is due to techniques
that we have developed over the years
to analyze programs, to
help find bugs and software,
to help even identify
certain kinds of security vulnerabilities.
Now, the tools are not perfect,
which is why we still have
lots of buggy software.
And they do have one major shortcoming,
which is that they tend
to be pretty hard to use
and require a very high level of expertise
in order to use them,
which is why you really
only see them used at,
you know, some of the largest companies
like Amazon, or Microsoft, or Google,
and mostly, for those places
where the stakes are very high, right?
Where you have the core
infrastructure software,
where the cost of an error is very high.
I do think that one of the
big open areas for research
is how do we bring the
benefits of many of these tools
and many of these techniques
that today are mostly
restricted to the lab
and to some of the largest companies,
and how do we put them at the fingertips
of everyday developers?
I think that's going to be
one of the really interesting
stories in the next few years.
And it could potentially lead
to very dramatic improvements
in software quality
if we do it right.
Let's go on to our next question.
This is again, a question
about some research
that my group has done in
the last couple of years.
So the question says, "Your LINC framework
combines LLMs with symbolic reasoning.
Is this hybrid path the key to safer,
more trustworthy AI in programming?"
Yes. So, a little bit of context.
What is LINC?
In collaboration with several
of our colleagues here at MIT,
I had a privilege of
participating in this LINC project
a couple of years ago where we explored,
what happens if when a language model
is dealing with a question that involves
some detailed logical reasoning?
Instead of just outputting the question,
it translates the question
to a formal notation
that can be given to an
automated reasoning engine,
that can then come back and
produce a reliable answer
and produce that answer.
And this is part of a broader agenda
that we have been pushing for some time
around neuro-symbolic techniques
that combine a lot of the
very important benefits
of neural networks
with the kind of very
precise symbolic reasoning
that machines are very good at.
In the context of programming,
this is especially important
because some of the properties of software
that we really, really care about,
such as the lack of
security vulnerabilities,
such as having very precise control
over the behavior of the software,
a lot of those things really require
very detailed, logical reasoning.
And so, I think a lot of the energy
that we're going to see in the near future
is going to be into how do
we get these language models
and these AI tools that we have today
to make better use of logic
and symbolic reasoning
in those cases where precision
really, really matters.
Let's take another question.
"You've said that the
core ethical challenge
is ensuring machines do what
we want and only what we want.
How does that principle shape
the future of AI programming?"
I think this actually very tied
to the question we had
before around verification.
I do think that we have a
responsibility to make sure
that the software that we
put out there in the world,
that we actually have some confidence
that it's going to do
what we expect it to do.
That it's not going to have
these gaping security vulnerabilities
that today leave a lot
of people vulnerable
to cyber criminals,
to loss of their private data,
and leave our whole infrastructure
potentially vulnerable.
And so, this is directly
tied to this question
of how do we make sure
that the software we put out there
is actually going to behave
as we expect it to behave?
The big thing about software
is that we do have a lot
of tools to help us ensure
that software does what
we expect it to do.
And so I think it is
going to be, in many ways,
society-wide choice that we have to make,
to push for software
quality to be a priority.
To make sure that the software
that is put out there in the world,
actually is fit for purpose
and it's going to do
what we want it to do.
So the next question is one
that I actually get asked a lot.
"Should students still learn
programming the hard way
or should education shift
toward human-AI collaboration?"
So I think there's a couple
of layers to this question.
So there's no question that
learning to program early on
is hard, right?
For many people,
this is the first time
they are encountering
this need to describe something
at this level of precision,
and with the level of
care that is required
in order to get a program
that actually works.
To some extent,
LLMs are going to be very helpful
in helping students get
through that early phase
where nothing they program works
and where it's very
easy to get frustrated.
However, once you get
past that initial stage
and once you're more
proficient in the tools,
I think a lot of the
things that we teach today
are things that are still going to be
very, very important in the future.
How do you take a big, hard
problem and decompose it
in a way that allows you to
solve every piece one at a time?
How do you actually think through
all the different contingencies
and all the different
things that can go wrong
as users are using your software?
How do you think about the
software not just as an artifact
that is trying to solve a problem now,
but as an artifact that is
going to have to survive
potentially over decades
and evolve as requirements?
All of those are things
that are still going to
be very, very important
for students to learn.
That said, of course it's
going to be very important
that students know how to
think through this question
using the most advanced tools
and the tools that they
are going to be using
in their professional life.
I don't think there is a tension,
at least in the case of programming,
between students learning
how to use these tools
but also learning the fundamentals.
Next question.
"What is your preferred
programming language?"
Oh, this is actually a hard question.
I think it really depends
on what you are trying
to accomplish, right?
So for example, there are
research languages like Haskell,
created by academics for researchers
that are just beautiful in
terms of the abstractions
and the power that they provide.
But I probably wouldn't use them
to create a new website, for example.
People in the programming
languages community
tend to look down on
JavaScript, for example,
as a language that is full
of holes and inconsistencies,
and problems that programmers
are constantly tripping over.
And it is true, it has
lots and lots of warts,.
But it's also a really expressive language
with remarkable infrastructure
that actually allows you to
build things very, very quickly
and deploy them without a lot of hassle.
So I think the right
language for your problem
is going to depend on what
you're trying to accomplish.
I think the most important thing
is for everybody to have
a broad set of languages
that they are familiar
with and proficient with
so that they can actually pick
the best tool for the job.
And now we have our last question.
"What are some AI-assisted
software engineering tools
you use to enhance productivity?
And what are the optimal ways to use them
without compromising your own learning?"
So that's a really good question.
Most of the programming that
I do on a regular basis,
I use Cursor.
I also use ChatGPT.
Both of them are very
useful in their own way,
and I find they are especially useful
for some of the aspect of programming
that I don't particularly like.
For example, once you
put all the functionality
into a function,
writing all the little checks to say,
"Oh, make sure the input is correct
and make sure you're throwing
the right error message
when this happens," right?
These tools are actually
amazing for things like that.
They're also really, really good,
for example, when running experiments,
in helping you build a
lot of the scaffolding
that is required to run
experiments, and collect data,
and even plot that data.
So I do think that one of
the things that is important
as you work with these tools
more on a regular basis
is building that intuition
about what are the kind of problems
that you can easily delegate to the tool
and will usually do a good job at,
and what are the things where
you shouldn't even bother, right?
Where you're just better off focusing
and taking out your pencil and paper
and thinking clearly through
what you're trying to do,
and then just writing the code yourself.
And that intuition is not
going to be set in stone.
The tools are evolving quite rapidly.
But I do think that maintaining
that internal mental model
of what you can delegate
and what you have to do for yourself
is really important in using
these tools productively.
And so these are all the
questions that I have today.
I hope you had a good time.
I certainly enjoyed
answering all your questions,
and I look forward to being here again.