startup exchange uh discussion as I said
earlier at the beginning uh at MIT we uh
you know we we we don't just do research
uh we do produce companies companies
that will take the research bond
findings to their uh prototype to the
market and to make an impact so that's
why we have the next session about the
startup exchange and and my my colleague
uh Katarina will moderate the session
and uh I'll just let her take over. Uh
Katarina,
thank you CJ for the kind introduction.
Hello everyone. I'm delighted to be here
with you today to present the startup
lightning talks. We've invited two
startups for you to meet. Each one will
present for 10 minutes followed by five
minutes of Q&A. So, please keep sending
your questions through the Q&A feature.
But first, I'd like to take a couple of
minutes to tell you about our
program. So, Startup Exchange was
created within MIT corporate relations
to support MIT connected startups to
grow, expand, and solve the world's
great challenges. And uh we do that by
fostering collaboration and partnerships
between uh startups and industry such as
um corporate members of the industrializ
program as many of you are and the MIT
innovation
ecosystem. So the startups we support
all of them must have a strong
connection with the institute. This
connection might come through the
founding team, the technology and some
um are also affiliated to uh our MIT
peers who vet and support the startups
throughout the year. Um today our
program has a network of close to a
thousand startups virtually working in
any sector. They also may be located in
any country and we typically start
working with them when um they have a
technology or a product that is ready to
be tested or used in real
environment. So everything we do at
startup exchange is to expose and
connect startups with industry in a
highly curative way and we also provide
learning opportunities to both parties.
This includes launching calls for
startups based on corporate's own
challenges and strategic priorities,
facilitating one-on-one meetings between
them, and hosting different kinds of
events such as demo days, um speed
networking events, speech sessions, and
the learning opportunities typically
come through via workshops that we uh
co-organize with our MIT peers. So at
the end of the day the goal um of all
these activities is to fold. Um on the
one hand help startups uh scale pivot
expand your customer base and in case of
corporates help them learn as well about
the most recent technologies
um help them uh expand your portfolio or
even create new business lines. And um
this slide features a very small sample
of the success cases we had to date uh
that usually uh include proof of concept
pilots um joint uh RD R&D and even
acquisitions. Um this is startup
exchange in a nutshell. If you'd like to
learn more about our program, please do
reach out. I'd be happy to answer any of
your questions.