it's a pleasure to be here with all of
you
today thank you thank you very very much
I'm just going to reset that timer
there there we
are so I recognize that most of you are
probably not neuroscientists and I want
to try to orient you a little bit about
the general approach that we're taking
in the field of Neuroscience before I
dive into a specific story I'd like to
tell you
about so here's generally how I think
about what we're trying to do or
accomplish as
neuroscientists we're first of all
trying to understand the human condition
what is it that makes us human and why
do we do what we do peripherally or
relatedly we're trying to understand
other species they do amazing things
that we can't do in really fantastic
ways and understanding things about our
place in the world is really informative
obviously we want to kind of Leverage
these pieces of information we glean
from these investigations to treat brain
disease and I ideally improve artificial
neural systems as
well I think about two kinds of ways of
thinking generally in the field for how
to approach these goals most people
subscribe to maybe one or the other the
first is brains biological brains do all
this amazing incredible stuff they make
us human they're what they're why we are
what we are but it is really complicated
and really messy and the past 140 years
or so of Neuroscience has really dived
into this sort of diverse glory of the
brain but it's been hard to get to
general principles and really deep
understanding now an alternative
approach has sort of focused on the
engineering aspects of things can we
distill a few principles out of
neurobiology and build artificial
systems and use those to a help us
understand how brains do things but also
build things that have broad impact in
the world of course that's been
fantastically successful over the past
10 years but it took an enormous amount
of effort over the past 50 before that
to see that come to fruition and it
wasn't clear that it
would so I want to spend a few minutes
and talk about how artificial neural
networks came to work so well and be so
powerful because the interplay between
the study of the biology of the brain
and building artificial systems is where
my lab lives and where I think a lot of
future impact is going to be made in the
field of Neuroscience so this is your
just General cartoon of a neural network
there's inputs there's a hidden layer
and there's some outputs but in order to
make them work and build them this way
and figure out how to make them work so
well we needed to take some important
abstracted ideas away from decades and
decades worth of
biology one of the principles that seems
to be necessary to make these kinds of
systems work well is they have to be
formed of discret units like this one
right here right each of these things
they're discreet units they have some
kind of threshold or nonlinearity
associated with them about how they
integrate their inputs Ru is the really
common one that lots of folks use in
their Anns but there's lots of others
they're connected by lots and lots and
lots of synapses individual synapses and
those synapses have specific weights and
those weights are
modifiable those principles weren't just
invented by Engineers these things came
from Neuroscience so how did we get to
this point I'm going to give you the
history of all of neurophysiology in one
slide are you ready so we started with
kahal at the turn of the previous
Century defining the neuron Doctrine
neurons are in fact independent units
it's not some kind of cium like blood
vessels they're independent cells doing
their own kind of independent thing but
they're connected to one another and
they signal through Action potentials
the mechanisms of the action potentials
were defined Eckles hodkin and Huxley
many others around the 1940s or so
the evidence for synaptic connections
between neurons was a prolonged uh
period span of decades but it really
solidified in the 50s uh with the
quantal hypothesis from Bernard cats
subsequently it was shown about two
decades three decades later that those
synapses could be modified dramatically
by the activity in the network this was
the work of bliss and Lomo in 73 the
work of Eric kandell and many many
others over the subsequent decades so
together that formed the basis for how
to build these neural networks but if we
put these principles into neural
networks as many many people did over
the past you know 50 years or so they
tend not to learn very well it's really
difficult to make them do what you want
them to do in any kind of efficient way
something was missing and something that
something was not something we could get
from the biology instead it took
engineering Insight from Jeff Hinton
hopfield who just won the Nobel Prize
and many many others you need control
systems for learning these networks just
wander off into weird local Minima they
never converge takes forever Etc until
you start to put control systems in
there what do I mean by Control Systems
well one of the things one of the
control systems you've probably heard of
is credit assignment that's the main
thing that seems to run back propagation
which is behind pretty much all of the
advances Inns over the past you know
decade or two so what's the credit
assignment problem if we put some input
into a network like a bunch of images
and we ask the network is that image a
dog it gets it right or it gets it wrong
we want to use that outcome to train the
network and make it better how do we go
about doing that there's all these
synapses all these units are connected
to one another with all these synapses
how do we know which synapses to turn up
and turn down how much do we turn them
up and turn them down in order to get
the network to get
better so one way to do that is to look
at the output
compare that to your target create an
error signal and feed it back into the
network the original ways we thought
about doing this were really simple and
kind of global or scalar it's the way we
think about neuromodulation in the brain
happening A big flood of dopamine says
something good happened but it doesn't
contain specific information about which
synapses or which cells drove the good
outcome so learning from that really
broad signal is pretty difficult the
thing that really changed the game was
figuring out how to vectorize the error
signals and provide specific information
back to individual synapses to say you
were really involved in making that
error I need to turn you down you were
really involved in making the right
thing I need to turn you up so that's
what runs basically the machine learning
Revolution uh that so changed our lives
in our
world but it's not clear that this is
how brains learn it's a super powerful
algorithm neuroscientists like me have
gotten more and more and more interested
in it as a model for potentially how
brains learn it obviously works super
well for machine learning and
Engineering but is it how the biology
implements learning there isn't an
alternative really at this point
learning in biological systems is really
poorly understood so we set out to look
for evidence of this kind of system in
the Mamon brain there isn't any so
far back propagation or vectorized error
signaling has generally been thought to
be implausible or biologically
infeasible for a couple of reasons one
is if you have a feedback kind of input
that contains error and a regular input
the feed forward input they interact
with one another and interfere you can't
have them going on at the same time even
if you do this in regular neural
networks they don't it doesn't work so
the way this is solved in normal neural
networks is temporal separation you have
a feed forward pass then you have a
feedback pass and they don't interfere
with one another because you've
separated them in time the brain does
not work like this the brain is
continuous it's possible that there is a
separation hiding somewhere in one of
the rhythms of the brain but so far at
least to my knowledge it hasn't been
found there's an alternative idea though
that potentially you could
separate feed forward and feedback
passes
spatially in the dendrites of neurons
individual brain cells have these really
complicated processes that look like
branches of trees that are called
dendrites and so this idea has been
around computationally for quite some
time but has never been experimentally
tested so here's an example of one of
these neurons this is a layer five
paramal neuron this is from a mouse but
you have basically the same neurons in
your cortex you have lots and lots and
lots of them a lot more than this mouse
does but this is what they look like
they're the sort of heavy lifters
computationally for the cortex and
generally speaking bottom up kind of
feed forward information comes in down
here around where the cell body is in
the nucleus and this is where the output
of the cell is as well
but more complex higher order kinds of
inputs arrive out here in this really
distal extended process that looks more
like the extended sort of crown uh of a
tree and it's thought that maybe air
signals or Target signals might be
present out there and so we wanted to
test that this idea that dendrites could
maybe mediate some kind of vectorized
error signaling in the brain now there's
a big problem with doing this there's a
reason no one's done this before for is
how do you identify error signals in for
example a mouse doing a task in a neural
network we have access to every single
cell synapse whatever possible
measurement we could want we just get in
there and look at it we built the thing
right the mouse we do not it's very much
through a scanner darkly we can put some
electrodes in and maybe sample a few
cells we can turn on a microscope and
Sample a few cells but we cannot record
from the millions and millions and
millions of cells that are probably
involved in this task
so how could you possibly identify error
signals in the neurons that are actually
involved in the task that has thus far
stymy the field my amazing postto
Valerio frion came to my lab to do
something completely different and when
he arrived here quarantine happened and
he was locked in his apartment for six
months pretty much he couldn't come to
my lab he couldn't do anything while he
was in his room for six months he
thought of this great idea to use a
brain computer interface to Short
circuit the rest of the brain and make
just the neurons he was interested in be
the ones driving the task and so here's
the task design he's got a microscope
that peers into the head of a mouse the
Mouse is awake and behaving he's just
sort of bolted down to the microscope
there's a glass window in his skull and
we're going to image the activity of
some
neurons the activity of one population
of neurons that we've defined we're
going to call it p+ it's literally four
neurons
rotates a visual stimulus and if the
animal rotates it Far Enough by
activating those P positive neurons the
animal will get a
reward that's counterbalanced by the
activity of this other population the
blue ones P minus the more the blue ones
get activated the visual stimulus
rotates counterclockwise and the animal
gets farther and farther from getting a
reward the mice learn to do this really
very effectively they can basically just
sit there and think real hard activate
p+ activate p+ and the visual stim
rotates and they get rewards they get
very very good at doing this and now the
entire task is just dependent on these
four neurons that we are
watching actually it's the two
populations actually eight neurons that
we're watching there's a bunch of other
neurons that we're recording that are
involved in the task but they're not the
ones that actually drive the task so
this is what these neurons look like in
the brain this is a sort of sideon view
that's the surface of the brain all the
way at the top that'd be down deep in
the the brain this is similar to what I
showed you for that layer five paramal
neuron here's the cell bodies and
there's there dendrites going up to the
top where we think that air signal is
present so we don't see it like this
when we're doing the experiment we see
it from the top down because we're
looking down through the window and the
surface of the brain so it looks like
that so all of that blinking is the
mouse thinking that's neural activity
distributed across lots and lots of
neurons flashing so those are the action
potentials and the nerve impulses
recorded microscopically
so what we're going to do is rather than
just look at those were the Somas we're
going to compare Somas with dendrites in
an attempt to see the feed forward and
the feed back kinds of error signals one
of the things we observed right away was
that individual responses just randomly
selected in any given neuron were really
different in terms of their relative
ratio amplitude so sometimes a dendrit
is bigger sometimes the S is bigger and
sometimes it's really dramatically
bigger so here's just a plot of that for
a bunch of samples from this one neuron
and you can see that there's a huge
amount of variance so we called that the
somad dendrite residual it's basically
saying when is the dendrite very active
when is the Soma very active right that
in the interest of time I'm not going to
go into the details is actually
predicted reasonably well by the
activity of the whole neural network
around uh that neuron so that seemed to
us to be like oh maybe this is a
potential you know window into these air
signals is this something we could
perturb so we expressed an optogenetic
actuator in a set of inhibitory neurons
to try to turn these dendrites off while
leaving the Somas intact that's what
this is showing you the inhibitory
neurons are up here in the Sur at the
surface of the brain and there's the
ones we're going to record and so you
can see under control conditions just
like what I showed you before there's
lots of activity there's some
differences in the amplitudes of the
signals but when we turn these neurons
on they inhibit these dendrites and you
can see that the dendritic signals go
down really
dramatically there's just averages from
that cell there's examples from almost
2,000 cells it's a super robust super
powerful effect so we can preferentially
influence the activity of these dorites
and just as a side note anesthesia does
basically the same thing when we lightly
anesthetize the mice which is congruent
with how we think about anesthesia
operating on top down things that
connect different parts of the
brain so these dendritic signals contain
reward related information about the
task we just broke up the task into
different epochs before the outcome that
would be like oh I got the reward okay
great uh oh sorry after the outcome I
got the reward okay great or I think I'm
about to get the reward I'm not really
sure and what you can see between these
two populations this is just the data
and then that's just the shuffle to do
the statistics is there's a really
robust representation in the dendrites
of outcomes so the dendrites are very
effectively predicting I got a reward or
I didn't get a reward but what's
incredible is the dendrites also are
highly correlated with right before the
animal gets the outcome it hasn't
explicitly been told you did it right or
you did it wrong the neural activity is
predictive of
that can we perturb these behaviorally
relevant signals by perturbing the
dendrites like I just showed you we do
exactly the same experiment but while
the mice are running the task right and
you can see that these differences
between here and here go away
right for I don't know how many neurons
it is 50 50ish neurons it's very
robust so now this all looks like it's
going in the right direction we see
these dendritic signals they're
behaviorally relevant they're related to
reward we can perturb them can we see
evidence as far as I know the first
evidence for vectorized signals so we
compare the p+ neurons the ones that
decrease error with the p minus neurons
the ones that increase
air the hypothesis is that if vectorized
signaling is happening we'll see
differential signals depending on the
causal contribution of the neural
populations to the task but it's
possible we won't it's possible we'll
see sort of scaler things where air just
goes up or goes down the same way in all
the neurons or we won't see any real air
representations those are our three
Alternatives I obviously wouldn't be
setting it up this way if I saw these
two things because they're not as
interesting right we do see evidence for
vectorized error signaling and here it
is here's an example neuron that when
it's active when when it's dendrite is
active error goes down you can see it
right here for it decreases in errors
versus increase in errors that neuron is
causally contributing to the animal
being able to do the task more
effectively and you see exactly what you
would expect the inverse in the P minus
neurons and that happens across the
population for lots and lots and lots of
neurons additionally now can we perturb
those signals and actually degrade the
learning are these signals that we're
seeing actually produc ucing the changes
in the animal's behavior that's never
been shown before and so we turn to
exactly that same experiment we activate
these layer one inter neurons to
selectively inhibit the den rites and
now these differences here go away
there's no longer a nice vectorized
representation of different kinds of
air and now the animals don't learn
either so we were really really pleased
when we saw this result this is a I I
know most of you don't don't know this
but this is a hor heroically difficult
experiment that Valerio conducted that
took him many many many months and we
weren't sure it would work and there it
is it's very robust so what I've shown
you today is one attempt that we've made
to kind of work at the interface here
about all of the diversity and messiness
and biology and and beauty of the brain
but thinking about it from a slightly
more a&n perspective we do this a lot
now this has proved to be a really
really fruitful way of doing things we
have a bunch of experiments and papers
and things in progress now looking at
stability versus flexibility looking at
catastrophic forgetting how to build
models about that and how to actually
improve performance in Anns most of you
know that catastrophic forgetting really
plagues most artificial neural networks
we think we have some clever ideas along
these kinds of lines about how to
potentially solve some of those issues
before I go I just want to thank all the
wonderful people that I get the
privilege to work with uh in the
laboratory I highlighted aro's work
today but all these other people are
doing amazing stuff all of the funders
that help keep the lab running we really
appreciate all of their support uh this
is not a drunk member of my lab passed
out it's my son it's past his bedtime
thank you all so much I'd be happy to
take
[Applause]
questions thank you Mark for sharing
these fascinating results um
questions have you guys LP if they
actually modulate the
voriz VOR or in the of not only learning
but also
unlearning sorry you're asking about the
lfp yeah so now for a lot of the neur
mod around looking
at
mod of learning learning so the lfp if
you could briefly repeat question oh
sure so the the first part of the
question was uh is the lfp modulated by
these vectorized eror signals did I
capture that yeah so the lfp uh is a
local field potential it's an electrical
measurement that's very fast much faster
than our calcium signals uh but it's an
average activity of a lot of different
things and actually people don't
entirely understand what the lfp really
reflects because it's a spatial average
of a lot of different stuff I would not
expect us to be able to see these very
specific Iz signals and in fact if we
just average across the neurons blind
that with our data blind to p+ P minus
or not participating you know in the
task it just smears out you just don't
see it there are definitely task related
signals you definitely see task related
signals in the averages and I would
predict you would see them in the lfp
but the vectorized signals are very
specific and just get swamped by
everything that the actual experiment is
really hard to do you can't image and
lfp at the same time the electrodes kind
of in the way but I think the spatial
average of these signals gets you
basically the same
answer hi thanks yeah so uh Sam gersman
gave a a talk at MIT uh maybe in the
last year or so uh and uh and he
mentioned uh this work and that it was
an instance of uh work in technology
that helped us better understand uh how
brains work right that back propagation
uh is uh is something that also happens
in biological systems but I wouldn't go
quite that far the reviewers at nature
really have pushed back when we tried to
say that for good reason so I don't want
to get caught out saying like this isn't
evidence for back propop this is
evidence for vectorized signals it's at
the level of cells not at synapses we're
trying to figure out how to do it at
synapses but just just want to caveat
that a tiny bit no problem yeah in any
case it's a learning from technology
going back to uh you know create a
hypothesis to test in neuroscience and
so uh but his belief seems to be that
it's very difficult uh that there have
not been big breakthroughs really that
go the other way around you seem to be
more optimistic about that can you say a
few words about uh you know looking at
Neuroscience to do biologically inspired
compute or biologically inspired
learning with technology totally totally
I so that's a great question I was going
to try to stick more of that in here but
in the interest of time I kind of took
it out I think we are definitely at the
point where we can start to do that I
think Sam's absolutely right that has
been a problem is trying to take really
you know specific biological discoveries
and Implement them in silico or in
hardware and see some dramatic gains one
of my PhD student projects is to try to
get dendritic nonlinearities a bunch of
other things into networks in a
trainable way which he's accomplished
for the first time which is super cool
using gradient descent but they don't
just somehow magically work better than
just boring Point neurons with raus or
something in them instead you have to
operate them under really severe
constraints then the dendrites start to
get you the magic and so I think
reframing how we think about performance
and efficiency not from just you know
what can I do with a gigantic cluster of
you know infinite neurons right that's
obviously not how brains evolve to solve
problems and that eventually is going to
be how we have to evolve to solve
problems we can't just keep making these
things bigger and more energetically
expensive and I think brains hold the
secret for how to do that in the best
way that's my personal feeling thank you
again that's a great
question okay great thank you very much
Mark let's give him over hand