Let me see if I can Okay. Um, hello
everybody. My name is Shar. Uh, I got my
masters in PhD from MIT a long time ago
and now I am the founder and CEO of
Notch where we develop smart
metamaterials for nextgen wireless
comms.
Um so last year the Russians in the
Russian Ukrainian war uh ditched all
their sophisticated wireless
communication equipment and uh for for
controlling their drones and started
using this uh this is a drone um it's
got a fiber optic reel and it gets its
entire C2 and GPS link through that
fiber optic reel. It's essentially
unjammable. Um, and this this sort of uh
I mean this is a still a current problem
for the Ukrainians. Um, but it
highlights a problem with wireless,
right? Wireless technologies. You got
radio and then you have antenna. And uh
the focus has always been on the radio.
Um because the antenna is kind of, you
know, this weird rod-like device,
uninteresting, unintelligent,
uh no directionality. it it uh
susceptible to interference. Um and the
current state-of-the-art when it comes
to antenna technologies are phased
arrays which are you know militaryra N
squared antenna elements um a lot of
power you got parabolic dish which is
large slow uh heavy um and at what we
are doing at notch is we're putting the
antenna first so that's what we believe
the future of comms is going to be um
and the way to do it is with something
that we invented called a metamaterial.
Now this is an engineered material. It
acts like a filter. It uh is you know
electronically controllable to be
transparent or reflective. Um and then
you can use it as a building block and
you can take your unintelligent antenna
and you can create a new kind of antenna
system by you know surrounding it with
these meta materials and then you can
block against jammers in any direction.
You can block against multiple jammers.
You can then use it to steer a beam,
concentrate energy in one direction or
multiple directions um 360 degrees. You
can tilt up and down.
And we have developed something called
the magic series of antennas. You can
see over here this is the wizard and
it's you know you can get 9 dBi of gain
fully steerable 360°.
You can form two beams, you can form
three beams. Um you can form six beams.
You can form any antenna pattern. Uh we
have a butterfly here. Uh this is all
just a reminder like one antenna
element. You cannot no phase array here.
So and we use AI to develop all these
antenna patterns.
Uh we've tested this. So we have the
magic wizard on a car over here. This is
in Alaska because you can't test
anywhere else anymore. Um, so this is in
a denied environment and it's used to uh
track our freefly astro carrying the
elf. The wizard can double the range
compared to an omni in any direction and
the elf can get you know eight times
closer to a jammer. Um so we believe
like I said antennas first that's the
future. Uh we can make now with
metamaterials uh 360 degrees steerable
phased array tilt up and down double
your range interference proof. Uh it can
reconfigure its antenna patterns 100
times faster than a blink of an eye. Um
it's lighter than your phone. It uses uh
less power than your smartwatch. It's
fully software defined so you can add
any other functionality to it. And um
you know like most technologies they
start new technologies they start in
defense. So we're seeking partnerships
with defense companies but also we are
because it's an antenna system um we're
seeking early customers with anyone
making radios or onman systems or
communication equipment. Um I will say
that this technology started like metam
materials is about 50 years old. If it
existed back then, all antennas would be
built like this. So, I'll end with that
[applause]
>> questions. Anyone?
[clears throat] Well, I've got some
questions. Um, sorry. Uh, can you, uh,
can your antennas also do elevating
steering?
>> Yeah, we can do elevation and, uh,
elevation steering as well. Yeah. And
and as a model,
>> thank you. And to follow up, can your
antennas tune across different bands?
How would how would they work with a
softwaredefined radio?
>> Yeah. So the metamaterial that forms the
building block is um tunable across
multiple frequencies. So then uh you can
use it with uh software defined radio
that can hop along with the
metamaterial.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you. Anyone else in the audience?
question.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh,
>> sure.
>> Have you set up any tools so that an end
user can uh
set up the patterns and the frequency
ranges that they need on their own.
um the patterns are derived through very
you know intensive um
machine learning and then uh but you can
then access them. So we have an API you
can call up a pattern you can point
wherever you want. So we have an API to
do that but doing it by yourself is
something that we would not like to a
customer we would not do.
>> Okay. So a customer would come to you
and you could you could fine tune
something.
>> Yeah. they can come and ask us what
pattern they want and we can develop for
that.
>> Okay. Awesome. I by the way I love it.
>> Yeah. Great. [snorts]
>> Yeah.
>> Great.
>> Thank you Shakriar. Uh I want to remind
there will be an exhibit after this
these presentation. So if you didn't
have a chance to ask more question or
you like to see some demos please see
after this presentation. Thank you. I
>> have one of the antennas out there so
you can
>> Excellent.