Well, I have the absolute privilege of
welcoming you to the last session of uh
2025 uh Nanosummit. Um indeed uh this
session is very special to me, very
special to all of us here at MIT Nano.
Um it is a session uh we called honoring
visionaries in nanocience and
nanotechnology.
So uh this afternoon we celebrate
vision leadership
qualities that have shaped MIT's role in
advancing nanocience and nanotechnology
for years and years and that vision and
leadership indeed continues uh through
what we are doing at MIT nano. You have
just seen the leaders of tomorrow
present many great advancements and
indeed just 0.5% of what actually is
happening inside our facility.
So a visionary who has been central to
the story of MIT is MIT's 17th president
Rafael Refe and I have a distinct honor
of welcoming him to stage in a moment. I
just want to say a couple of words
before I do so because I believe last
time he introduced me he said a couple
of words as well and I tremendously
appreciated it. Um over the course of
his career at MIT Rafael's impact on
both MIT and the field of science
technology and in particular nanocience
has been profound. um as a faculty
member he saw the importance of creating
shared facilities that could bring
researchers together. And of course the
very next thing he did is he became the
director of micros systemystems
technology labs the predecessor to the
present MIT Nano an organization that
defined the path that we are now
following. He worked to expand those
shared fabrication spaces and build
communities because indeed it's those
communities that build tomorrow that
human friction of interaction that
places like the fab like
characterization like the immersion lab
of nano can indeed enable.
As president of MIT, he championed bold
investments in research infrastructure
uh by making MIT Nano possible, ensuring
MIT could remain at the forefront of
nanocience discovery.
Nationally, President Reefe extended
Vene Bush's vision for the endless
frontier advanced through academic
discovery. His tireless efforts shape
the continued national commitment to
science and technology advancements and
indeed for years to come. We are changed
because of what President Reefe has done
for all of us.
Because of his leadership here on campus
and his belief in a power of shared
discovery, MIT Nano, the innovation
powerhouse that he stood up, now
supports more than 1,500 users across
more than 50 departments. I mentioned
this at the beginning. That's at this
point after seven years of existence, tw
over 20% of MIT research groups touch
MIT Nano to accomplish their needs. So I
cannot think of a better messenger to
tell us about the legacies that he built
upon shaped by Vanver Bush and then by a
remarkable MIT alum Robert Bob Noise
whose story you're about to hear.
President Reefe, please join me on
stage.
[Music]
[Applause]
Vladimir, thank you for such a very
generous introduction. I guess um if I
want you to tone it down, I'll take care
of it at my next introduction of you.
You have heard uh today mostly about the
future and the future you're building.
My few minutes of remarks is about the
past and where we come from at least at
MIT. So I'm extremely honored and
delighted truly to join you at this Nano
Summit. Uh but also importantly to
announce that we are dedicating the
clean room at MIT Nano in honor of
Robert Noise of the MIT class of 1953.
As most of you know, I'm sure Bob is the
person who put the silicon in Silicon
Valley by inventing the first monolithic
integrated circuit based on Silicon.
In fact, for many years during his
lifetime, he was referred to as the
mayor of Silicon Valley.
More than anyone else, it was Bob Noise
who sparked the micro electronics
revolution.
His legacy, however, is about much more
than technological brilliance, which he
certainly was in leaps and bounds. He
co-founded virtual semiconductor and
then Intel where he served as its first
CEO and where he oversaw the invention
and commercialization of the micro
processor.
Bob noise set new standards for
entrepreneurship
uh and entrepreneurial leadership in
tech and in the valley as well and it
was a template for generations to follow
including that of many MIT alumni.
He was a leading legend.
One day shortly after I became MTL
director, I was informed that Bob Noise
was visiting MIT that day and had
requested to meet with me.
I was wearing my regular professorial
outfit, an open color shirt and a
sweater.
I decided that I could not meet such a
living legend dressed so casually.
So, I asked my assistant to run to the
MIT coupe to find me a tie. Any tie
ASAP.
I was desperate not to appear
disrespectful.
She came back right on time. And then
Bob Noise showed up my office
without a tie. Of course he did because
another of his innovations was an
unpretentious informal management style
that has characterized tech ever since.
In fact, in his honor, I'm not wearing a
tie today.
I also want to take this unique
opportunity to thank Ray Sta of the
classes of 1957 and 1958
whose generosity has allowed MIT to
honor Bob Noise in such a fitting way.
Ray, do you mind raising your hand?
[Applause]
Rey again I told you that my remarks
were about history. Rey was a peer of
Bob Noise in co-ounding analog devices
in Cambridge in 1965 and growing it into
a global leader in signal processing
and processing devices.
Ray's data was for the east coast while
Bob Noise was for the west coast.
Ray also was and is the driving force
behind nanoscale research at MIT.
The whole idea of what eventually became
the micro systems technology
laboratories at MIT and MIT's first
classroom facilities in building 39 was
pushed by Rey.
In order to wheel MTL into being, he had
numerous meetings with the MIT
administration at the time to convince
them to make such a bold step. And of
course, Analog Devices was the first
company to commit financial support to
MTL.
Race data also deserves credit for
physically bringing together electrical
engineering and computer science at MIT
which were on opposite sides of the
street until he gave us building 12 the
Ray and Maria Stata Center for Computer
Information and Intelligent Sciences.
Moreover, Ray Stata gave MIT the first
gift that allowed us to launch MIT Nano
and Ray has been a driving force in my
own career.
When I joined MIT in 1980, it was as the
first holder of the analog devices
career development professorship which
Ry established in 2022. I had the great
honor of receiving an award named for
him from the Massachusetts High
Technology Council. And today I'm the
Ray and Maria STA professor of
electrical engineering and computer
science.
When Rey pushes something good always
happens.
So I want to also thank him for
insisting over decades that MIT remain
at the leading edge in the semiconductor
space
even when
even when the country itself thought it
had left advanced chief fabrication far
behind.
When MTL was conceived just as I was
arriving at MIT, it was seen as utterly
necessary.
The US still manufactured over half over
half of the world's semiconductors and
MIT needed to educate experts for that
industry.
The challenge of course was that
semiconductor laboratories were and
still are extremely expensive.
So it could only make sense in a
university if it was going to be used by
a large number of faculty research
groups.
MTL's pioneering faculty solved that
challenge in part by creating a
tremendously attractive collaborative
and collegial culture which included
weekly microlunches that still exist
today that faculty wanted to join and be
part of.
In 1990, I became the second director of
MTL and had the privilege of serving in
that role for nine years.
But
as the new millennium began, MI MTL
facilities were becoming outdated in
equipment, in space, and some would
argue in concept.
In 1985, Japan had surpassed the US in
global semiconductor market share.
In 1987,
another contemporary of race data and
Bob Noise, Moraurice Chang of the MIT
class of 1952 and 53 had established
Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing
Company or TSMC, reshaping the industry
with a foundry model that separate the
manufacturing and design.
And by the year 2000, US Fabs were
producing less than 20% of the world's
semiconductor chips.
Chip manufacturing had become very
capital intensive. The thinking in
industry at that time was that if Asia
wanted to do chip manufacturing, let
Asia do it. The US would concentrate on
where the real value added was on cheap
design.
The US also largely stopped investing in
educating students in the semiconductor
space. This included even universities
such as UC Berkeley and Stanford at the
heart of Silicon Valley. In that era, I
would regularly hear in Silicon Valley
that software eats hardware for lunch.
I did not subscribe to that claim.
Of course, software and digital
technologies were are and will continue
to be critical to the economy locally
and globally, but software runs on
hardware.
Advances in one enable and stimulate
advances in the other. Advances in chip
technology and cheap manufacturing make
possible advances in chip design which
in turn make possible advances in
artificial intelligence and vice versa.
And I knew that the emphasizing hardware
was going to come back to haunt the
United States.
So when I became provos at MIT in 2005,
I had the opportunity to do something
about it. Fortunately, the deans of
engineering and science at MIT were in
agreement and with their support, MIT
made the bold decision to double down on
semiconductor research and education by
creating MIT Nano just as everyone else
was moving away.
Then came the supply chain shortages of
the pandemic and the US government
suddenly realized that it was a national
security issue when virtually all of the
world's most advanced chips are
manufactured in Asia.
When then Secretary of Commerce Jenna
Ryondo came to tour MIT Nano into in
2022,
right before the Chiefs and Science Act
passed, she said to me, referring to MIT
Nano, the country needs 10 of this.
Clearly, the future will rely on both
algorithms and semiconductor chips. I
believe that MIT needed to be at the
leading edge of algorithms as well,
which is how the Schwarzman College of
Computing, this building came into
being.
And with MIT Nano, MIT now has vastly
improved facilities and equipment for
the hardware end of the spectrum.
Moreover, MIT Nano expanded the welcome
offered by what was always a supremely
welcoming community. It has allowed even
more faculty, students and entrepreneurs
across the institute as well as industry
leaders and government entities to solve
major research challenges in MIT Nano.
In 2022,
it was a distinct pleasure to name the
home of MIT Nano after Lisa Sue, CEO and
chair of AMD.
Another semiconductor industry leader
educated at MIT.
Lisa, by the way, is MIT through and
through. She has not one but three
degrees from MIT, a bachelor's, a
master's, and a PhD.
Finally, I want to finish by thanking
all of you for being so patient to
listen to so much ancient history.
However, MIT
at the nano scale is a story of
leadership that continues to this day.
From Bob Noise to race data to Morris
Chang in the early days of the industry
to Lisa Sue today, MIT has educated a
large number of remarkable leaders in
the semiconductor space.
Now with the Robert Noise clean room,
this remarkable MIT community is ready
to continue to shape the future
with the next generation of nano
discoveries. You heard many of those
today and the next generation of nano
leaders who themselves will become
living legends in their future.
Thank you so much for including me in
such an important day and thank you for
allowing me to listen to your
spectacular presentations today. Thank
you.
[Applause]