welcome everyone good morning we're so
pleased that uh you're joining us here
today for our MIT um Health Science
Forum um on the topic of speed and
foresight and Drug Discovery
accelerating and drisking innovation in
healthc care and I think um you're going
to hear about a lot of exciting
Technologies today but also not just the
the what but the how and the who how we
can work together there's um In This
Crowd uh representatives from uh MIT of
of course but also corporations from um
around the world leading in in the
pharmaceutical areas and neighboring
Industries so I think a really wonderful
combination of um people and uh to
network with as well as startups and
students and um those from the broad and
other of our neighboring institutes um
so welcome um i' i' just like to say a
few remarks before handing it off to um
our first speaker um firstly this is a
intimate event
um you can see we're we've got a full
house but I'd really encourage you to
participate ask questions um we're going
to have a panel where there's going to
be time for discussion and we'd like to
hear from you so um please don't be shy
and um I I thought I'd set a little of
the context um so by sharing some of the
remarks from some of our leaders in this
um this area that we call Kindle square
and the Greater Boston Healthcare
ecosystem so um MIT president Sally
cornbluth made the comment that her
mission was to make sure Kendall Square
becomes an infinitely self-renewing
source of biomedical process progress a
limitless creative pool perpetually
refreshed by a stream of new ideas from
every corner of life science and
engineering to unlock solutions to the
most important problems of our time so
this is a big challenge to be
limitlessly creative perpetually
refreshed um but we're all of us seeing
that there's a great deal of
transformation um throughout drug
development whether it's in Target
identification screening preclinical
clinical trials and these are due to
developments in high 3ut screening in
Automation and Advanced Imaging in
Cutting Edge new approaches for using
artificial intelligence and M machine
learning and model organized
Technologies among others these are the
ones we will focus on for our um our
event today um and the our focus is on
how these tools can be employed to
accelerate and improve drisk the drug
development process but alongside of
this we want to talk about this
important topic of how so um recently
you may be aware the The reun Institute
opened a new facility and there were
some remarks um by Mass General um CEO
Ann kaansky that I'd like to share
exactly on this topic so um they're just
I think so so well phrased so she said
cross-disciplinary collaboration is a
Hallmark it's it's really how you do
transformational research and
breakthrough science at scale everyone
talks about this but few actually
achieve it Partnerships between
Healthcare and Academia accelerate these
breakthroughs and Foster Innovation that
is the model of scientific discovery
this whole area represents that Boston
and Massachusetts represent so we'll be
addressing this important topic also
today alongside all of these uh exciting
Technologies