welcome to the second part of the deep
learning uh day and this second part is
going to focus more on you know given
all the tools that you have seen this
morning how do we build systems around
them and the type of things that you can
do and in this particular hour well 45
minutes so that I will be talking I'm
going to focus on agents which is a kind
of Il defined concept so you know at the
end of these 45 minutes you will be
equally confused don't worry about that
um and and I wanted to just give you a
couple of examples of agents that I find
interesting so the first thing is that
you know when when some of us started
working on the field in particular when
I started around the decade of you know
the year 2000 and so on it was what we
call the Benchmark Golden Era we have a
images for instance if you were building
a computer vision system we had
databases where every single object was
annotated we knew exactly what the
ground truth was we knew what had to be
done there were data sets with lots of
images all annotated According to some
criteria and that allow us to evaluate
algorithms and you could rank them which
one was better which one was worse you
know things were very easy you know you
could take a picture like this one here
run the state-of-the-art computer vision
algorithm at the time ask what is the
content of this picture and the output
was this and you knew this was wrong
everybody will agree with that and you
know minus one point for this detector
and everything everything was very very
clear we are not we are not living in
that time anymore we have models that
can do all kinds of very sophisticated
things and it is really hard to valuate
how they how good they are in fact it's
an open area of research to try to find
ways of evaluating these systems to tell
which one is better than which one and
you know as Philip was showing this
morning there's been a revolution on the
speed of how advances are happening from
the 60s to the year 2000 basically we
went from very simple neural networks to
the first pH detection systems that
actually kind of worked but in the last
decade we had like an acceleration of
all kinds of systems converging to the
large language models that we have today
and they can do all kinds of things know
you can use chpt for many many things
that are really interesting here is an
example of asking chip to solve a high
school math problem where you say well
there is a treasure hunter found a a a
chest filled up with gems there are 175
diamonds and so on and so on how many
gems are in the chest and CH GPT gives
you just an answer with your beautiful
reasoning explaining all the different
equations that you need to think about
where the unknowns are and at the end it
tells you there are the total number of
gems are
225 which is wrong but who cares you
know it's so beautifully written you
it's better written than the question
itself so it's just amazing what the
systems can
do so the ne the the thing that is
happening now that everybody is very
excited about at least for the last two
years now is AI agents and I think this
will remain a very hot topic for the
future and by the future I means the
next six months more or
less so what is that has enabled agents
to appear I think there are a number of
different aspects that uh build what is
the infrastructure of an agent one is
the fact that these models like chpt and
so on they are not unimodel anymore they
are not models that only deal with
language you can actually mix different
modalities for instance you can input
text and a picture like in this case and
you can ask GPT this is gptv what
happened here and you know this is an NE
Network that will take everything as
input images and text everything gets
translated into tokens at the end
everything is kind of the same and it
will just generate an answer and this is
the answer that it gave which is a
pretty good description of what makes
this picture interesting and it could
have been describing what is happening
on the background of the picture but no
it did focus on the object that is
actually interesting for us humans when
you look at this picture you know the
interesting thing is this car in the
swimming pool and that's what chipit is
talking
about there is this you know I was
showing also this example where you know
you have this high high school math
problem and CHP is wrong but there are
also a number of other things that
people have been discovering that you
can do with these models to make them
better besides just training them more
and making them you bigger there are
other things that you can do so for
instance one thing that to students here
at might did was to you know one thing
that happens every time that you ask
your GPT the same question it will
always give you different answers
because it's just sampling from the
probability distribution of different
words and will generate something
different it might actually mean the
same thing but it will have different
wording in this particular case if you
ask to solve this math problem to CH GPT
the first time it gives you the answer
that I showed you before which was wrong
but the second time with a different
instance the same model it just gives
some something different and it actually
happens to be right in this case you as
a user you don't know which one is wrong
or which one is right you just know that
there are two different answers so one
thing that you can have is to you can do
is to have these two agents these two
different language models debate between
themselves so you can now take the
second answer and just copy paste that
text into the dialogue window of the
first llm and tell the LM a different
version of you say something different
here it is and just copy pay the answer
what do you think now so if you do that
it changes its answer it Revis the
answer and in this case agrees that the
right one is the first is the one given
by the second one because you don't know
which one is right you just do the same
thing with the second one with the
second llm you do the same thing you
copy paste the answer given by the first
one and in this case it just still
sticks to its answer so what they found
is that when you have these interactions
between agents they converge more likely
than not to the correct
answer so you can do this with all kinds
of things here is you know trying to
answer you know a question about
uh some mathematical calculation and you
know if you ask this to two different
agents both get it wrong the first time
but once you copy the answer to one
between themselves they realize that
there are other possible answers and
they just start keeping keep revising
their answers so in the second round the
second one got it right and the first
one still got it wrong you can do this
again and again and eventually both of
them converge to the right answer
this is not always the case as you can
imagine this is not always going to be
working but what they showed is that the
more agents you put together the more
rounds there are performance seems to be
improving and you know we haven't really
seen a plateau here you keeps doing
better and better but of course this is
going to Plateau there is so much more
you can do but this is an example of
where creating a society where you have
a few different language models
interacting with each other you can
build something that works better than
each of them in is
ation we have seen also that you can use
these language models to do to write
code and this is another very important
piece that will allow systems to become
agents where you can give an instruction
you give an a specification of something
you want to do and the llm IT outputs
code that you know if you run it
supposedly it will actually do what you
know what you ask it to so this coding
capability is actually a very powerful
way of then having this llm to be able
to actually interact with the world
because once you write code you can
execute that code and that code can
perform operations in the physical
world so you know these language models
are very powerful you know for instance
in coding they are amazing you can go
just the chpt you ask it to you know
write a Matlab script that draws a
bouncing ball inside a square which is a
very typical problem that you know you
do when you are trying to learn coding
and you know this is what the output is
supposed to be just a ball bouncing on
inside a square if you ask this chpt
gives you a script that you know it
looks pretty good with comments and
everything and if you take this and copy
paste it on the M lab window and you run
it indeed this is you know the result it
works really well so you know one can
think these language models are amazing
how they do this well another very
important thing not to forget about is
that these models are trained with a lot
of data and sometimes the power of these
models is not really the model itself
it's the data so in fact you go to
Google and you ask for you know examples
of mlap scripts of bouncing balls inside
the squares you get tons of different
examples and you know CH GPT has learned
from all of those so it's the web
contains a lot of information these
models have been trained with an amount
of data that is just so much bigger than
the amount of data that you have seen in
your life that it's just hard for us to
write our hands our heads around you
know how much data they have
seen these models have all kinds of
really interesting properties for
instance the generative models that K
was describing they show some
interesting uh compositional
capabilities for instance if you ask a
image generative model like Del to draw
an image of a cup of coffee you know it
draws a picture that looks like a cup of
coffee very realistic H if you ask a
picture of a cat you know it generates a
picture that looks like a cat and if you
ask for a cup of cat it gives you this
which is quite amazing now you think oh
wow you know it really understood these
visual concepts and it understood what
will me what will be a coherent
composition between these two concepts
despite that this is something like you
can you cannot have seen this in the
real world well you think you cannot see
this in the real world because if you go
to Google and you query for a cap of cat
then you realize that people are putting
Cuts in sides of Cups very often and
taking pictures of them and putting them
on the web so sometimes some of the
capabilities that we see of these models
they are really a reflection of how rich
is the training data that has been used
to train
them that doesn't mean that they don't
exhibit some of these compositional
capabilities that go beyond what the
training data contains but it's just
hard to know exactly you know what is in
the training data and what is
not so a lot of the power of these
models is coming from the training data
that they
have we have also said that these models
hallucinate if you talk with a with a
chat GPT and you ask for things that you
know might contain some factual
information then they will hallucinate
the stuff so you ask where did I
graduate it from it says you know it's
something it looks nice it's written in
English it looks beautiful the first
piece is true but the second one is not
true
it could have been true but it wasn't
okay so CH is not actually trying to
tell you what is true it's just trying
to tell you something that could be know
it's just sampling from those
probabilities saying oh this is a
sequence of words that could be true
because it has high probability and this
you know it had high probability because
I actually once was I was offer that
possibility so there is some alternative
world where this is true and it just
judge it but it doesn't know in which
one it
is so you know now also I wanted to to
tell you another thing is that you know
these models look very surprising a lot
of the power is coming from the data but
there is another thing that is very
important also is that you know a lot of
complex problems might not be as complex
as they seem for instance let me do a
quiz uh you all know what a linear
function is a linear function is a
function that if you take two inputs the
output is equal to the sum of the
outputs you know if each input is
processed individually
that's one condition the second
condition is that you take an input and
you multiply it by a
scalar the function that applies to that
scale input is equal to the output times
the scalar okay these are the conditions
for a linear function in fact it means
that you know as Philip was showing
before you know a typical neural network
layer is a linear layer where is just a
set of weights and the input and the
output are related by the multiplication
by a matrix so in this particular case
you know this is the drawing that Philip
was showing this morning so I'm going to
do a
quiz I'm going to show you a few
Transformations and I want you to tell
me which ones are linear linear and
which ones are not so here there are
four Transformations the first one is
taking a picture of a picture as input
and then you have to rotate it the
second one is a scaling of the image the
third one is to transform a color
picture into a grayer scale and the
final one is to Def focus a picture so
think about it for 5
seconds okay raise your
hands uh for all of you that think that
number a that a is a linear
function okay let's say there is a 15
people
B no
B okay 30 C
H okay 10 10 again maybe and
D okay and how many people did not raise
their hands at all because they just
didn't
care okay so there are a few okay good
good just to calibrate the the answer
okay they are all linear all of these
functions are linear you can find a
linear implementation for all of
those you know if you take a rotation if
you take two images you sum them and you
rotate it's the same thing that rotating
them and then suming the rotated results
or scaling is the same thing you take
two images you sum them up and then you
do the scaling it's the same thing that
taking the images scaling them and then
summing the result the same thing for
gray scale and the same thing for blur
they are all they can all be implemented
with linear functions what this means is
that a linear layer in a neural network
can do a lot of
things and sometimes a lot of the
operation that we feel oh wow what
amazing is this thing that has happened
here well you know a linear function
could have done it it's not true always
of course not is why neuron networks
have nonlinearities and lots of layers
but linear layers can do a lot of stuff
and sometimes it's also hard to
appreciate how strong can these models
be and the power for from even simple
models like linear
functions okay so now you know this is
you know all the things that are going
into the mix of what is happening now is
in in AI on one side is you know some
problems look complicated but they
actually simple and you know there are
advances in a number of different
directions that are all happening
together and in language models this is
a typical conversation that an agent
that a language model and a human can
have you know where in this case let's
say a human is is a doctor and is
sending some patient reports to the
language model and the language model
that's been trained know with data that
knows a lot about medical uh diagnosis
and so on is just outputting possible
diagnosis and there is a conversation
this is the typical conversation one can
expect with chpt this is not exactly an
agent what an agent is is when you start
incorporating more stuff to it so the
first thing is that the human will not
just provide information with language
it might actually provide information
with different modalities it could use
images Voice Text all of this is going
to enrich the interaction with the
language with the language model the
second thing is that the language model
itself which is at the core of an agent
it also has coding capabilities which
means that it can take some of the
instructions that the human is providing
and translate those instructions into
code that will get executed in order to
use a set of tools for instance the
agent could perform a search on a
database maybe the database contains
electronic health records and the first
thing that it realizes is that given a
question it requires actually to access
the database will write code that will
access the database it will get the
results and it will perform an operation
and then there are also planning tools
that can be attached to this agent one
on thing could be you know debates it
could be interaction with other agents
Chain of Thought which is another tool
for reasoning and Philip will be talking
more about those things the composing a
task into sub goals and then
accomplishing its sub goal independently
and so on and so
on so in that case a conversation could
go this way when you have an agent the
human sends to the agent some patient
reports the agent um sends some possible
diagnosis but it doesn't send this
diagnosis to the doctor it sends the
diagnosis to another agent that it will
disagree or agree with those diagnosis
and it will say in this case okay I
disagree request an x-ray the first
Agent H will interact with the human and
will ask for an x-ray the human gives
the X-ray the agent run some code access
the database to get some health records
from the patient to get more context and
then eventually provides a
recommendation and the human performs
the final diagnosis so this will be an
interaction with an agent where now you
have a system built around llm so in
general an agent is going to be
something that is is a system which
could be an llm at this scoree that is
going to perform actions in the real
world the real world in this case could
be a database or so on it could perform
actions and it will change its Behavior
based on the results of those actions
so for instance when we were talking
about that models hallucinate facts like
here when I was asking where I did
graduate from if you do the same thing
ER in being then what you have is that
you actually get a slightly different
Behavior if you ask the same
question the agent actually realizes
that this question is better answered by
first doing a web search so it will
perform the appropriate it will write
the appropriate code that will be hidden
to you you will not see the code you
will not see the the execution because
there is a parture that all the time the
outputs of the llm and whenever it is
code the only thing that it does is run
it it doesn't show it on the screen so
in this case it will perform a search on
the database and in fact you can see
that sometimes you know there is this
message that appears searching it's just
executing that piece of code and then it
provides an output and the output is a
paraphrasing of the content that is on
those web pages that doesn't mean that
the system will not
hallucinate but it's less likely because
it's going to be used it's going to to
be using information that only needs to
be paraphrased so it doesn't have to
create as much content as if it's just
creating the answer by itself from the
weights store in the neural network so
it's less likely to hallucinate but it's
still possible this not prevents does
not prevent hallucinations 100% but it
can provide for instance Links at the
end that tell you what the sources are
so you click there it opens the web
pages that were used to generate this
answer but this particular text is not
in those web pages as is so it's been
Rewritten so I wanted to show you just a
couple of examples of agentic systems uh
just to go into a little bit more
details of how they actually work and
the type of things that you can do so
the first one is going to be bper GPT
which is a is a vision system and that
was developed uh by researchers at
Columbia University and the second one
is uh an agent for interpreting neural
networks which is something that we've
done here at it but the idea here is you
know these agents are going to be
combining the power of language models
with this coding abilities in order to
solve tasks by also using tools that you
have to provide provide them with so let
me talk first about Viper GPT so this is
a pretty interesting system that tries
to answer questions about the content of
images and the idea the basic idea
consists on the following you have a
picture and you have a question that you
want to have answer and the the system
what is going to do is going to write
code that once it's executed it will
answer your question and I'll explain
now I'll go into the details of how that
works and what I mean by you know
running code and answering
questions so here is an example of how a
conversation with a with a base a vision
based agent can go uh when it doesn't
have this when you don't use this kind
of agentic system agentic structure with
tools and so on this is just uh of the
shelf language model with vision that
runs on the image so if you ask you know
here in this picture what are the boys
eating it just says the right answer
muffins if you say what are the what are
the muffins it says on the table so you
know here is getting things right you
know how many muffins are there it says
two how many kids are there too many So
eventually gets confused and you know
you have these conversations that can
derail very
rapidly so what they proposed was
building an agent that will answer these
questions and the idea will you know is
the following one so you have this image
you want to answer your quer how many
how many muffins can each kid have for
it to be fair so this is a sophisticated
question that requires not just counting
how many kids there are but actually
also accessing some common sense
knowledge about what do you mean by
being fair ER and so on so you know this
is a sophisticated question that will
require reasoning a lot about the
question in order to find the answer and
the propose The Proposal is that then
what you have is a system that will
first write
code so that if you execute this code it
will answer your question so here is the
piece of the code that was generated
after that and I'll explain later how
that works and what is interesting is
that interesting is that if you execute
this
code so the first line will just find
the muffins we'll count them you know
you have a line that counts muffins you
say eight then you look for how many
kits there are the patches that contain
kits then you count them you know there
are two patches and then you you comput
the division of 8 divided by two that
gives you four so the answer to this
question is
four so it's just a much interesting
usage of how you know different tools
that you can run on images will allow
you to answer this question so let me go
in detail now on how all this works so
the first thing is this is not a system
that is trained this is just using a
system that is already pre-trained a
language model that is already
pre-trained that has coding capabilities
like chpt and just as uh Kim was Jun was
showing before what you have is a prompt
that will tell the agent in this
case what kinds of functions it can use
and how it has to call them so there is
a long prompt so here is the beginning
of the prompt and the prom is just the
type of prompt the description that you
will provide that you will write if you
you were writing a python Library where
you have lots of functions and you have
comments and you have examples and you
put all this as text and you just put it
as part of your
prompt and then after this prompt you
attach the question that you have so now
chpt will understand that you know there
are all these functions I can use in
order to answer this question and it
will just write code to answer the
question so what is in this prompt well
there are all kinds of functions for
instance there is going to be a function
that is called fine
that input is a string with the name of
an object that you care and it will
output a an array of patches containing
the objects that you care about so it
will return just small images each one
being a crop containing the object that
you care
about so for instance if you're finding
muffins the result will be these eight
patches there are many other functions
for instance you know anything that has
been built by computer vision scientists
so here you know there's another
function that will compute the depth of
the image this means that it will tell
for each pixel how far away is from the
camera so this is the picture it just
outputs a depth map indicating in this
case it's a colorcoded depth map
indicating which things are nearby the
camera and which things are far away and
there are lots and lots of functions of
this
kind there are going to be functions
that are application specific and these
are the tools that you are providing the
agent with and then the there is just
the generic programming knowledge that
the llm has that it knows how to write
Python scripts and then I can
combine conditions loops and so on with
the tools that you are provided to
create programs that are relatively
complex so and now you also have the
benefit that you have all the common
sense knowledge that the language model
has so when you ask for questions the
language model will use it source of
your it base of Common Sense knowledge
to answer those questions for instance
here if the question is is the animal
that is not gray a dog so that's you
know a sophisticated question this is
actually quite difficult to answer for a
language model directly on the image
because negations get complicated but
here the model just translates this
image into code and then it executes so
the first line finds the images with
cats and dogs then it looks at one is
this gray true is not gray not is this
patch gray false so you this is not
great so it returns
yes so here is you know the answer to
that particular
question here is another example you
know Computing math that is quite
complicated with depreciation of this
car what will be worth in five years so
that requires understanding the make of
the car and then understanding what
depreciation means and so on a lot of
knowledge that the language model has so
it will just look at the code you it
will write the code and and then it
looks at the detects the
car it looks for what is the make of the
car so that gives you access to the
depreciation
rate and then now it has also to the
current access to the current value and
just multiplies those two numbers and it
gets the depreciation so it just gives
you a number which you know might be
right or not but it gives you a sense of
the fact that this system can perform
actually complicated
queries you can actually use it also on
video for instance here there's a movie
and you want to know you know return the
two kids that are farthest from the
woman right before she hacks the girl so
here is the hugging okay so that's the
question and you know just using the pr
that I show before the output is this
piece of code that execute it it
actually looks at you know it passes the
video into segments and it starts you
know looking for when a hack
appears so just executing each looping
over all the frames
until it detects the
hug keeps
executing until it returns
the two patches with the kids so it's a
pretty sophisticated reasoning the
systems are not of course it can fail in
many different ways there are many
different types of failure mod that you
can imagine but this is a sophisticated
question that require like a interesting
processing of the video and it's through
this combination of the power of the llm
is reasoning capabilities and all the
tools that get added to
it so you know this systems have code
available this is the way that you build
the systems basically by engineering The
Prompt working having the right prompt
is actually relatively easy to get it
working it's difficult to get it working
really well so you really need to do
things properly it's very important that
the library is written in a way that
will look like as professionally written
as possible because that's how these
things has been trained it's trained by
looking at code on the web is really
good if things use a standardized
language like if you start changing the
rules of python on the Fly it's just not
going to perform very well so you want
to make sure that you respect you know
as closely as possible all the
conventions that are being used and you
write your functions in ways that are
very you know very familiar to what a
programmer will
be and then it's just a set of API calls
that you do with the language model it
could be an open source model or a close
or a close model that has an API and
it's just a set of API
calls so that was for Viper GPT and the
next one is this multimodal
interpretability agent that we've been
working at MIT in my group so here is is
a similar idea in the construction so
you have a language model that will be
augmented with tools and it will perform
a question you have a question but in
this particular case instead of just
giving the output once and you're done
you have a system that will you know it
will execute some code that will be
based on the question that you have it
will run it on images it will see
results and it will keep writing its
code until it gives you the answer that
you want so it's it's like one degree
more sophistication in how it actually
interacts with the world outside so how
does what is that we are trying to do
here so one of the
challenges H when you build neural
networks is that it's unclear what is
that they are doing now you once you
have trained you have all these weights
and all these neurons and yeah the input
and the output look good but we have no
idea of what is going on inside how is
that this output came about or when is
wrong why is wrong can I predict what it
will be wrong so you want to really
understand what are the different things
that allow the system to work so there
are a lot of different ER directions of
research that try to answer this
question and most of them are based on
very specific ways of analyzing the
content on of a neural network there are
methods that are based on sancy methods
that are B Bas on probing single units
and there are you know a number a
collection of ways every every each of
those very specific on how they analyze
a neural network and they provide one
type of
answer so what we want to do is once you
have a neural network that is capable of
Performing some action like for instance
maybe it's a discrimination where you
know you have a picture and it
classifies this image as being among you
know among a thousand possible classes
so in this case you know it says this is
an airplane but maybe I want to know
what is that unit in the middle there
doing okay so I know what the output
units are doing because they are giving
me my outputs but what is happening in
the middle I want to know what that unit
marketing red is actually
doing so when you are trying to
understand what a neural network is
doing there are many questions that you
might want to ask you might want to know
what is you need 45 in layer 4 doing or
what are the biases in the output class
for the dog class or how many units
inside the neural network actually
detect cars or you know so on and so on
and so on so you really want to have
like the flexibility for understanding
the content of an neuron Network that is
similar to the flexibility that you have
to interact when you interact with a
language model where you can POS any
question so really what you would like
to have is some agent that helps you
understand what another what a neural
network is doing so that you can ask
questions and the this system will
interact with Network and it will answer
your questions so that's what we try to
do what we try to do is to build an
agent that is enhanced with a set of
tools so that it can actually interact
with a neural network that has already
been trained to answer questions about
the mechanism that the neural network
has
learned so let me show you an example of
once this system is built how it works
and then I'll explain what are the
different pieces that make it possible
so let's say that you have a user you
have this agent that will interpret that
we call Maya and at the end at the
bottom you have the neural network that
you want to understand so the user asks
what is the role of unit 122 in layer
four and in this case the neural network
is a rest net uh neural network you know
given with with something that kin
discovered um and is trained to do image
net classification so you want you want
to know What that particular unit is
doing why who cares that's the unit that
you care that I have the sample for so
so here is what Maya will do so the
first thing that it will do is will
translate that question into a code that
it will run in order to experiment on
the neural network and the first thing
that it does it runs a particular tool
that what it does it takes the entire
image net it passes image net through
the entire neural network all of the
images and it records what are the
images that most strongly activated that
particular unit so every unit will react
to different inputs in different way
ways and in general if you have relus
strong activations are considered to be
meaningful so if something activates
very strongly that particular unit then
one could conclude that maybe that's the
particular concept that is driving that
unit so here is the three images that
most strongly activated that particular
unit the numbers in this case is just
the activation score and these units are
convolutions so they react to different
pieces of the image and highlighted
region is the region of the image that
is responsible of that high
Activation so no Maya looks at these
images Maya is based on in this case on
gptv so it can take images as inputs and
it will analyze the output of those
images and it concludes that the highest
activations seem to show B eyes and
indeed if you look at this images you
pay attention you will see that all of
them had a b eye so it's seems to be
high five near the neck and these three
images just by chance happen to have a b
eye so now he wants to be sure that this
is a b tie detector so it does the
following thing it calls a different
tool that now it will generate an image
so this will not be an image that comes
from imag net instead it will be an
image that is just
generated and it generates a phas and it
sees that that does not drive the unit
the activation is very very
low so now it says well now let's edit
this picture and add a b eye to it and
just by doing that change suddenly the
activation goes up again and this image
the only difference with the previous
one is that it contains a b TI all the
rest of the pixels are more or less
identical this is another tool that I
describe later that is capable of taking
an instruction and changing the content
of a picture so now it concludes well
this neuron seems to select to be
selected for both eyes particularly in
the context of formal attire because it
performs more experiments what I'm
showing here it's just a selection just
to give you a hint you know some idea of
what is actually what it's going to do
so this is the full picture of the agent
you have a language model a multimodal
language model in the middle that can
take us input text and images and then
you have a set of tools that it can call
the tools are going to be a set of
functions that I'll describe in a second
and then it has also has functions to
generate data to send data to the neural
network and functions to read the
behavior of the neural network
so for instance one of the tools that it
has is the capability of sending an
image through the neural network and
recording the activations and maps and
activity maps of a particular unit so
you take a picture you indicate a neural
net a unit inside the neural network and
it outputs a number and a selected
area this is one tool another tool is
going to be this data set exampl which
is just it takes a data set of images in
this case let's say imag net again a
unit that you care about and it outputs
the top end images that must strongly
activate that particular unit with their
scores so it's an array you know of T
PS you can have also a image generative
models that's another tool so in this
case is stable diffusion where you take
as input text and it outputs a picture
that corresponds to that particular
caption so that allows the system to
create images that might have might have
properties that he wants to test that
might not be available on the original
data set that you provided with because
maybe you want to test something that is
very fine grain and you really need to
synthesize
it and finally so there are tools to
edit images where the input is one
image then you have an instruction of
what you want to do with that picture
and it outputs just that the image with
that transformation some other things
might have changed on the picture
because this is a generating model that
is doing the operation but most of the
changes are going to be the ones that
you care about but you know other things
could
happen so this particular tool is based
on instruct PS to PS which is a is a
model that allows to take a picture an
instruction and transform it into
another picture this is another I want
to open a parenthesis here because this
is another very important aspect of
modern generative models is many times
you have a model you want to build
something that solves a particular task
and we know that you need to have a lot
of data to train these models but in
many cases you don't have data like here
what we need is data that will you know
this is what we want to build we want to
build a Neal Network that will take
these two inputs and output you know the
transform
images and you need to have data that
has this form that are triplets of an
input image an instruction for the
change and the output and this is work
that was done by Tim Brooks and and
alosa EOS and collaborators at berlay
so the challenge here is that you need
to have a lot of data and this data is
not available out there so one of the
things that is happening now in the
field is to use all the
different tools that we have nowadays
built know language models generative
models of different kinds and so on in
order to generate synthetic data that
you can use to train new models so for
instance here this model was trained
using synthetic data so the way that the
synthetic data is is generated is quite
creative and I think that a lot of the
research now comes into how do you
figure out ways of generating synthetic
data that has the conditions that you
care about so here is how what the
process was so the creation of the
training data started by just asking GPT
to start with a caption of an image and
propose a sentence that will be an
instruction for an edit and then another
sentence that will be the final
description of the image after that edit
it so you don't need you know this is
something that you have you just you can
take chpt and you can ask it to do this
and it will create these triplets where
you know you in this case you say
photograph of a girl riding a horse and
then the instruction can be have her
riding ride a dragon and then you know
the output should be a photograph of a
girl riding a dragon so you give one or
two examples of what you want chpt can
just generate more of those the only
thing that you need to start with then
is a collection of image captions and
there are lots of databases out there
that contains a lot of image captions
that you can use to then ask chpt to
create Triplets of this kind so this is
one piece of what you need the second
thing that you need now is to generate
also pairs of images of before and after
and in particular there is a a
particular approach that is called
prompt to prompt that allows you to do
that so if you have two prompts each one
with a slight variation of the other one
they can generate two images where the
only change is whatever changes between
the two PRS but once you have that
that's it you're done now you have
oops now you have pairs of images and
the instruction you just need to reorder
you know the order in which inputs and
outputs are defined and that's it you
train your model so that's a very
creative way of creating your training
data is fully synthetic there there are
no real examples in this training
data so this is you know once you have
defined all these tools this is how the
Maya pron will look like where you have
you it's again a bunch of code that will
look like a python library that is just
part of what you input in the text
command and then you ask okay now tell
me what unit X is doing in this neural
network and it will just use the code to
write the script that is necessary to
understand what the neural network is
doing what is interesting is that it
actually will not just run the code and
give you a straight answer right away it
will actually keep
refining creating hypothesis and running
experiments until it reaches a
particular answer so it will not stop by
just running the code once so here is
what happens in one interaction with
with Maya so you start saying okay what
is that particular red unit there doing
in a particular pre-train model so the
first thing that it does it creates it
runs this code that throws all the
entire image net through the Nal Network
to see what most strongly activates that
unit and we don't tell the agent to
actually start experiments this way it
decides by itself that does an
interesting way of starting because it
will narrow down the number of
hypothesis so here there are no it
returns five images and the they are the
five that it returns so you can see the
activations in this case goes from zero
to one so these are strong activations
and it's highlighting this spherical
object but in fact you know Maya looks
at the images and he concludes that
oops that these images seem to be
showing a spherical objects interacting
with hands
which if you pay attention to the images
you will see that there is a hand always
over there not in the selected area but
just nearby so then it says well let's
actually check if this is true so let's
perform some editing experiments to test
this hypothesis so it runs the following
experiment it creates it uses two
prompts to create two images a person
holding a banana and a person holding a
cube so these are the two images that
Reg generate that are not a spherical
objects it's hand interacting with an
object but not an spherical object and
now it runs this through the the neural
network it has to write code to do that
too and these are the returns very low
activations the unit doesn't seem to
care about this images and now it says
well now let's uh edit this image from
non-spherical to aspherical and let's
analyze again the neuron Activation so
it runs it runs the tool that transform
images with an instruction in this case
there are these are the two commands
that is sense replace the cube with a
red ball replace the banana with a ball
so just to remind these are the two
input images and after these
Transformations the first one becomes a
hand holding a a ball you can see that
the hand is not perfect this you know
these models are not perfect so there
will be a lot of issues there and then
the banana gets transformed into this
which is pretty interesting not to see
the this is a pretty cute uh
transformation so it runs these images
through the neural network and it sees
that now the neural network gets
activated with these images and in fact
if you compare it with with the previous
activations you can see that there's a
big jump in the in the activations so it
concludes that yeah indeed this neuron
seems to be selective for hands
interacting with physical objects and
now you can say thank you and because
it's an llm it will tell you you're are
welcome and you know just to remind you
that at the end you're interacting with
an llm and things can get off hand you
know quickly depending on what you talk
about so we know this is correct because
we actually synthesize this unit is this
is not real unit inside an neural
network this is something that we have
created synthetically so that we can
evaluate performances in this case we
are using some which is a segmentation
algorithm that is driven by text and we
use that to create a model that will
actually be selected for balls when
hands are interacting with them so this
output was generated by this model that
we created so we knew exactly what the
ground truth was so we use that in order
to evaluate the model we have lots and
lots of different units that we that are
fake are not real unit that we use to
evaluate this model but we find similar
behaviors on real units so here is
another one this is a real unit inside a
neural network this one is selected for
tennis balls so it runs all these
experiments it formulates a number of
hypothesis so it's behaving like a
scientist and it's running you know it's
creating prompts that will test each
single hypothesis then it runs all this
on the neural network it sees it's
testing different context whether the
ball it can be any ball like if it's a
soccer ball does it work or if it's a
yellow feeli like maybe it's just the
color that is selected for and it
concludes that not this seems to be
really you know selective for tennis BS
so at the end it performs a number of
experiments until it reaches that
conclusion it's actually quite creative
these models can get quite creative in
the experiments they run so here is an
example where a is run a series of
experiments and he found a neuron that
is selective for facial features on
animals particular selective four eyes
and noses so then it decides to create a
picture that will contain a cut face
with clear eyes and nose and it runs
this through the neural network here is
the image and here is the activation so
effectively it seems to be reactive to
the nose and a leave it to the eyes and
it gives some a score and now it says
well let let's transfer the cat's eyes
and nose onto coffee cups this is very
creative like this is a very creative
experiment and you know run the edit
tool and it gives you this
picture which is you know very
interesting and it runs this and it does
not activate the unit so this is an
example of how creative this can get
this is another example where is detect
is SE realized that some unit seems to
be selective for birds and it's focusing
on the heads so it creates two images of
birds sitting on a branch and you see
the times two is using like python
tricks in order to do these things he
creates these two images and now he says
well let's replace the head of the bird
with a cat head and the head of the bird
on the second image with a dog head
which is crazy and then you here are the
original images these are the transform
images and let me zoom in you know these
are the heads that they put there so
it's really does look like a cat and a
dog and yeah the activations just go
down quite substantially
so it just just concludes his
experiments and continues doing and then
of course it has failures for instance
here it concludes that there is some
unit after some experiments that seems
to be Rel reacted to faces so it creates
an image with a family
picture the unit seems to actually not
care about faces but that doesn't seem
to bother the model and it says well you
know let's flip the family picture
upside down just to test if this is
really selective and flipping an image
upside down is a very simple task no
just you can actually write in Python
the code that will do this is very
simple but instead of that it uses the
tool to transform an image which is just
the wrong tool to use and it gives this
output which is crazy and it just you
know it says that it does not activate
the unit and still it concludes that
yeah this is you know selective for
parts of people and so on like this is
an example of a failure of reasoning
like the tools did not work the images
are not supporting the evidence and the
model still just happily goes and says
whatever it can whatever it wants to so
there's some confirmation bias going on
here so this with this I will conclude
so you can see agents are just this way
of creating tools that solve tasks so an
agent is really an llm at its core in
general enhanced with tools so that it
can interact with a world outside
perform actions get out outputs and
change its Behavior based on those
outputs so with that I will conclude I
can take a couple of questions while
Philip comes to the podium thank
[Applause]
you so the question is what are the most
promising
uses what do I think are the most
promising us uses of Agents well I think
that agents are there are lots of
promising uses I think that anything
that has to do with tool use so I think
that for instance is they are very
exciting in in the UC in the education
domain where you can actually have
agents per you know helping teach
material where they will ask questions
to a student get the results and and
refine the type of interactions that you
want to have so that the student
actually learns some Concepts so that's
a very interesting area of research uh
of course in healthcare there are lots
of potential uses and people are already
using them in different ways there are
lots of challenges also with the use so
you know there has to be an study of
their failure modes and how to better
use them and so on but these are like
some example of interesting areas but I
think that in scientific discovery there
are going to be very exciting so let me
take some more questions over there
so so the question is some of these
experiments as is performing experiments
they seem a bit random and you know is
there any guidance on how it should
perform the experiments so that it does
it's not so Random in this particular
set of experiments we did not provide
any guidance uh besides what appears on
the library with examples but there are
no examples of how to
actually we don't guide it on which
order on what type of experiments you
should be running first but that's
something that you can do you can
incorporate into the library a
description of what are common uses and
you know in particular scenarios how it
should be used to answer particular
questions that are pretty fine if then
if the question goes outside of that
then you know it's left to its own
devices to figure out some other random
process but if you have a set of
interactions that you know are very
commonly going to happen you could
provide guidance on how to do that just
like in the same way that you know
humans as humans we know exactly which
steps to follow when we solve tasks for
which we know there is a procedure that
normally works so here you can think of
something similar as how you will you
know train humans to solve
tasks so we'll have more time for
questions after but