Um these are fairly challenging topics
because you know we're really just going
to be proving one theorem today. But
this theorem which is called Shannon's
noiseless coding theorem will involve a
lot of the probabilistic tools that
we've developed earlier in the class.
Uh, so I'll give you an introduction to
what data compression is and really how
Shannon's work put this on a rigorous
mathematical foundation. One of the cool
historical facts about what I'm going to
be teaching you about today is that it
literally happened in this building, you
know, pre the renovation, but the
theorems I'm going to tell you were all
laid out, you know, right here, not down
the hall in a different building,
literally right here in building two. So
this will be cool. So, let me start off
by giving you some historical context
for the leadin for this, right? Um, so
how many people here use text messages?
Okay, should be everyone. You're all
paying attention. That's good. Um, you
know, of course, when we're texting each
other, we use short forms like, you
know, BRB, right? Uh, in fact, every
once in a while, I'll see a crazy, you
know, acronym that I don't know, but
maybe you guys know, right? And so you
can think uh that the acronyms, you
know, especially as you get older and
you stop being as plugged into it, at
some point they're just, you know, you
have no idea what people are talking
about anymore. But, you know, this isn't
even a new phenomena. So, let me give
you some historical context.
Back in the day, long long time ago, you
know, the way that people used to send
messages was through telegrams.
And the problem with telegrams was that
they cost a lot of money. So we're
talking about they cost a dollar per
word. So people wanted to send each
other telegrams. But you know the same
way that when we have text messages we
have you know common phrases and strings
that we say over and over again. So we
figure out the short form. Well here you
know they would create some sort of code
book to compress communication.
And some of these things were pretty
obscure things. You can go back through
and look at the telegram books from way
back in the day and you can find lots of
gems in these code books. Like if you
send someone a telegram that had this
word which I can't pronounce, uh what it
meant was it translated to the phrase
has not been
reinsured.
That's a pretty technical concept.
Uh they also had another one you know a
z kh e. This word if you sent it through
a telegram back in the day this would
get translated to clean bill of health.
So all of these phrases are saving you
money because you know instead of
sending uh this many words in this
phrase I'm getting away with sending
just a single word for a single dollar.
Uh some of these really you know go off
the rails. So, this is my favorite one
when I look through these Telegram
books.
Uh, NBET. So, what did this mean? This
meant captain is insane.
Hopefully, that one doesn't come up that
often, but uh that really was one of the
phrases in these code books from way
back when. So, we're going to talk about
today is really the mathematical
foundation of what it means to compress
data. And even better, we're going to
talk about what it means to find the
best compression for data. So, I'm going
to give you some examples. I'll give you
some definitions, and we'll think
intuitively about what a good
compression ought to look like. And
we're going to be working up to this
beautiful theorem, which is called
Shannon's noless coding theorem. That's
going to tell us the best possible way
to do data compression.
So let's start off with um you know the
key definition
at least that kicks it off and as I
mentioned you know this happened all in
this building. So in 1948 in this
building Claude Shannon
founded the field of information theory
and this field you can take whole
graduate seminars on it. It's a
beautiful, rich, thriving field.
He's really one of the mathematical
heroes of this entire area of modern
research.
And we're going to tell you about his
first beautiful theorem
uh in the lecture on Tuesday. I'm going
to tell you about an amazing result that
was proved by a graduate student here on
an exam. So you guys all took an exam on
Thursday. And it turns out that uh the
theorem I'm going to tell you about on
Tuesday was proved by a graduate student
who was given a question for his uh
project and he invented you know
something that we still teach to this
day. It's amazing and beautiful. And
then in the third lecture we're going to
talk about Shannon's second main
theorem. So first let's define what we
mean by our data source.
You know this is the source of what we
want to compress. And you can consider
much more complicated sources you know
um but let's keep it simple for today.
So a first order source is described by
the following things. So first of all
there's an alphabet
which is just a set of all possible
symbols and we'll denote that by capital
a and the individual symbols are a1 a2
all the way up to a k. Okay.
And then the other component we have is
that we have a distribution
which is going to be a distribution P on
the alphabet. So it'll tell you the
probability of the first symbol. It'll
tell you the probability of the second
symbol all the way up to the kth symbol.
So all this first order source is is
it's a ksided unfair die. you roll the
dieice and whatever symbol from your
alphabet comes up on top, that's your
next symbol in your message. So what
happens is that the first order source
is going to define a long string that we
just take by taking iid samples. And so
the way that this works is it's going to
generate
length n strings
where each symbol
is iid from this associated
distribution. So the way that I'm
constructing a long phrase is I take my
k-sided die that's unfair. I roll it n
times and then I just concatenate all of
those letters in my alphabet together
keeping track the order in which I
rolled them. Now you can think about the
alphabet as being composed of letters.
But really you could think about it as
being composed of words too, right?
Maybe the way that I create a sentence
is by creating, you know, rolling my
dieice and getting my first word,
rolling my die and getting my second
word. This would be a terrible model for
English language. And there are a lot
richer models you can do, things like
Markov chains where a lot of this theory
is going to carry over, but we're going
to keep it simple and just talk about
this as our data source. So, I'm trying
to send a message through a telegram to
someone else. And the way I decide on
what message I want to send is I use my
first order source to generate it. And
then I care about how short I can make
my communication be to transmit that
message from my source. So are there any
questions about the setup? Do people
understand what a first order source is
and what the communication problem is?
Okay.
So you know as I mentioned there are
more complex sources like Markoff
chains. But now let me define precisely
what I mean by a code book and a coding
scheme. So what is a strategy for
compressing communication? This will be
our second key definition. So we'll say
that a coding function
fi it's a function that maps
symbols of length n from my alphabet,
right? which are just things generated
from my first order source. Two 01
strings.
Now, if you haven't seen this notation
before, this notation star here means
that I can take any length I want. So,
I'm mapping anything that my first order
source generates to a string of a
variable length, but it's composed of
zeros and ones. So, maybe one of my
message gets mapped to the 00 string.
Maybe one of my messages gets mapped the
111 string. So in fact, the length of
the output doesn't need to be fixed
across the different messages. And
that's exactly where we're going to win
because somehow the intuition is that
more frequent messages should be mapped
to shorter strings. Now, first of all, I
need not just that, you know, this
coding function maps uh every message to
an output string because that wouldn't
help me. Like what if I mapped
everything to the string zero or
everything to the string the empty set?
That wouldn't help me decode and figure
out what the original message is. So we
need the property
that we can successfully decode. In
particular, what we want is that for any
pair of different messages that are
generated by my first order source, we
want that their image under this mapping
is not the same.
So that's the key property because what
this really means is just that we can
decode.
Okay,
so this part is a little bit subtle,
right? Um, you know, later on when we
talk about, you know, Huffman codes on
Tuesday next week, we're going to have
some constraints which are called prefix
free constraints that we're really going
to talk about, you know, a coding
function that maps, you know, symbol to
symbol, right? But, uh, symbol to
sequence. But here the way we're
thinking about it is n is gigantic and
it's fixed and then what happens is I
decide on my coding function fi and I'm
just going to oneshot transmit some
variable length message and at the end
of the message we say end termination
over and then the key point is just that
um you know things which are different
get mapped to different outputs and we
see where the actual thing ends and then
we want that we can recover X and Y from
this. So, are there any questions about
what a first order source is or what a
coding function is? Does this make
sense?
Yeah. Okay. All right. So, let's do an
example, right? And really our main
question is going to be this question
we're going to address at the end with
Shannon's theorem. So what is the best
coding function?
And I even have to define what I mean by
best here. But let's do an example to
make all of this explicit. Let's say
that our first order source has two
letters. So our alphabet is of size two.
And these two letters are A1 and A2. and
we're going to have P1 is equal to 7/8
and P2 is equal to 1/8. So already here
there's a huge asymmetry because the
first letter in my alphabet is way more
likely than my second letter, right? And
you know I'm going to set n equals 2.
So, I'm looking at, you know, length two
messages from my first order source. And
what are all of the messages that I
could want to transmit to someone? I
could want to transmit A1 A1, A1 A2, A2
A1, and A2 A2.
Each of these messages has a different
probability. Like A1 A1 is much more
likely than the others. It has
probability 49 over 64. This is 7 over
64,
7 over 64 and finally 1 over 64. So the
chance that I get a2 A2 is very
unlikely, right? And now what we can do
is we can think about candidate code
books and coding functions. So let's do
the naive thing first and see how good
the naive thing is. So the naive thing
is just to map the symbol a1 to zero and
a2 to one. So in this case when I get my
code it's just going to output 0 0
because I literally do it just you know
symbol by symbol. A1 gets replaced with
zero. A2 gets replaced with one. My code
would be 0 one here one zero here and
one one. And now I should define what I
mean by the best coding scheme. What we
care about is how much money I pay on
average with this coding scheme and the
cost of you know uh my transmission the
same way it is you know for things like
telegrams it'll be some amount you know
per symbol in this case not per word. So
we can compute the expected length
of this particular encoding. Notice that
the expected length is a property of the
first order source and the choice of the
coding function. Right? So what is the
expected length? Well, we can do this.
This is a very easy computation. What's
the probability I output the first
symbol and then I output, you know, a
length two message? What's the
probability I have the second message
and again I output a length two message?
What's the probability I output the
third message from my first order
source? and so on.
So this is a very easy computation to do
because it's just two. No matter you
know what my first order source outputs,
I always pay two symbols.
Okay.
So I claim this is not optimal.
So you know can we do better?
Anyone have any intuition for how I
could design a better codebook for this
particular sequence?
This one's not too bad because there's
really one dominant event, right? Which
is the event that my first order source
outputs A1 A1.
So originally when that happened, I
output I outputed a length to code.
I want to do better. So any ideas?
>> Yeah. output one.
>> Yeah, like zero for example. Right. So
in this case, for example, my new code
book.
Well, I'll have my message, you know, A1
A1 A1 A2 A2 A1 A2 A2. In this case, I
could output zero, right?
But now uh you know what I need is I
need to I could do let's just do
something else for this, right? I could
do 1 0 1 1 0 and then 1 one. I'm not
trying to get optimality yet. I'm just
trying to get an improvement and we can
calculate the new expected length.
And now with this, you know, very large
probability that I output the first
message. Well, I'm only paying one with
this, I can add up, you know, 7 over 64,
I'm still paying two. And then on these
other messages, I'm losing, right?
Because now this third message, A2 A1,
instead of its length being two, its
length is three. And on this last
message, I'm losing again because it
used to be two and now it's three. But
if you work it out, what this works out
to be is 87 over 64, which indeed is
less than two. Right? So this was an
example where the naive encoding we
could improve upon.
And we showed that we could do better.
But really the question now is what's
the best that we can do?
So it turns out that there's a very
clean and elegant answer to what's the
best we can do and it's related to you
know really the first key notion from
information theory which is called the
entropy. So let me just define what this
is and then we'll talk about
Shannon's theorem that we're going to
prove. So the binary entropy
of a distribution
in our case P which is given by
probabilities P1 P2 up to PK well we
write it as H of P1 up to PK and it's
the following expression it's the
negative sum from I= 1 to K
of PI log PI. Okay.
So in particular, you know, you have to
be careful with the negative signs here.
So this log is base 2. This pi is less
than one. So this term inside here is
negative, but we're fixing it with the
negative outside. So the entropy is
something that's non- negative. Okay?
And what I claim is that this simple
definition right here is the key to
understanding what is possible in terms
of data compression and what the optimal
scheme is. And we're going to unravel
that as we prove Shannon's theorem. So
let me now tell you Shannon's theorem.
It comes in two parts.
So we fix a first order source
exactly as we've been doing.
And let's say that this first order
source has entropy
H. We just plug in whatever our
probabilities are that define the first
order source into this binary entropy
function that I defined right here. And
let's say that the result we get is this
numerical value H. That's some constant,
right? And what I claim is that for any
coding function, no matter how clever
you try to be,
any valid coding function fi, we have
the property that the expected length.
And what I mean by this is this is the
length
of phi of x1 up to xn where this x1 up
to xn comes from our first order source.
I claim that this is at least the
entropy h * n minus little o of n. So
just to make sure you guys may not have
all seen asmtoic notation before. What
this expression means right here, little
O of N, just means that it's a function
that grows smaller than N. So you should
think about like N over log N or root N.
So the main point is that as n becomes
large, this is the term that dominates
and h is the answer to what the per
symbol length is that we pay in our
encoding function. So this bound only
kicks in when n is large because when n
is small this term might actually be you
know more significant than this right
here. But what we're saying is that at
least in the limit we can understand
what is the best possible coding scheme.
Okay. So this is one part of Shannon's
uh noiseless coding theorem. Let me
state the other part which is just the
natural converse that you can actually
achieve it. So moreover
this really is the answer. So there is a
coding function
phi with the property that its expected
length L is defined the same way as at
most the entropy time N plus little O of
N. So up to this plus minus little O of
N. we've resolved what the right answer
is for the best possible coding scheme
and amazingly this kind of mysterious
function called the entropy pops out and
that's really the thing that governs
what the best you can do is. So are
there any questions about the definition
so far? Um you know we've talked about
coding functions, we've talked about the
binary entropy function and now we have
this key theorem that we're going to
prove today.
Does this make sense?
Yeah. Okay. Good.
All right. Uh, and just to be clear, I
said this in words, but you know what
Shannon's theorem is telling us is that
H is the best
per symbol
from our alphabet length that you can do
for a coding scheme.
So you know before we prove this theorem
let's work up to it with some intuition
first.
So, let me ask you to test your
intuition
now that we have now that we know what
target we're shooting for.
[clears throat]
So, what distribution
P on K symbols. We're still fixing our
alphabet size
requires the longest encoding.
This just for intuition sake, right?
because we already know what the answer
is for the best possible per symbol
length. We know it's the entropy
function. So you can think about this
question mathematically. If I have, you
know, any distribution P on K things,
what distribution on K things is going
to maximize that binary entropy
function. That's one way to think about
mathematically what I'm asking here. But
maybe the better way to think about it
is to go back to your intuition. So if I
just started off with this, right, and I
told you that there were first order
sources and that we're looking at coding
functions, intuitively, what kind of
first order source would be the hardest
to compress?
If you think back to this example we had
right here, you know, how were we able
to win over the naive coding scheme? was
we exploited the fact that you know the
probabilities were very different
because there was this uh message A1 a1
which was so much more likely so we
could encode that very frequent outcome
with a very short string but maybe
that's not always possible so you can
think about this thing mathematically in
terms of the binary entropy function or
you can think about it from first
principles just from your guess instead
of doing the calculus
Yeah,
>> like all all PS are uniform
distribution.
>> That's exactly right. That is completely
correct. So in fact the answer to this
question is what you'd expect what you
could have guessed even before class
started the uniform distribution.
So the uniform distribution P1 equals P2
all the way up to PK is all equal to 1
over K. In this case, what does the
entropy look like? Well, it's minus the
sum of i = 1 to k of pi log pi, which is
the same thing as
log k, right? And what this corresponds
to is this corresponds to the naive
encoding
at least if k is a power of two because
one of the things I can do is I can just
take my first
uh you know symbol let's say it's uh ai
and I can encode this using log k bits
because you can tell me which of the k
symbols it is and I take the second
symbol and encode it using log k bits.
So in fact this is an example the
uniform distribution where the naive
encoding cannot be beaten. One of the
ways you can prove that this really is
the answer at least once we have
Shannon's theorem is you can solve the
calculus problem you know which pi which
is a distribution and has non- negative
entries that sum to one has the property
that it maximize the entropy function.
you'll find out that this is the answer.
But it really corresponds to this
intuitive fact that you know when
there's no discrepancy in the
probabilities you can't have any win in
terms of making uh more common things
shorter code words.
Okay, good.
So uh we have our intuition. Uh let's
work towards proving the first part of
Shannon's theorem.
So let me state one of the key lemas
which really corresponds to this uh
thing that you have intuition for. Now,
so what I claim is that any coding
function
for the uniform distribution
on k symbols.
It has the expected length
being at least
log k minus some constant. So o of one
is some constant. You'll see in the
proof why this constant shows up. It
really comes from the fact that you know
for my coding function I still can
encode you know some of my symbols using
very short strings and then I can fill
out things with longer strings too. So
there is some you know slight
improvement you can get but for reasons
that we'll get into that'll come out in
the wash. So you know the sketch for
this
is the following. You know all of these
symbols are interchangeable right? So we
can look at um you know we can think of
fi as mapping symbols
each of these k symbols
to nodes
in a binary tree.
So in particular, I can start with this
binary tree where the root is the empty
set because I output nothing. There are
no zeros and ones. My message just says
end. And then maybe down here I output
the symbol zero. Down here I output the
symbol one. Down here I output the code
0 0 1 and so on. Right?
So my constraint that fi is a code is a
valid code is just the constraint that I
map each of my symbols to distinct nodes
in this binary tree. I can't have any
collisions.
As long as there are no collisions and I
meet the definition of being a valid
coding function. And now the intuition
is you know you want to minimize the
expected length for you know what the
depth is of the symbol you're searching
for wherever you map it in the street.
So what should you do for your first
symbol? Maybe you would map it to the
empty set because you know that's pretty
shallow. Maybe your next symbol you
would map somewhere here and then you'd
map here and you'd map here. And
basically you'd fill out the levels of
this tree in order. you'd fill out all
previous things uh because all these
symbols are all equivalent, right? And
this will minimize the expected length.
And you can check that you know most of
the symbols are going to get mapped down
here where their length of the message
will be log K. And maybe you're off by
some constant factor that you know
depends on the fact that there are
symbols before it. But if you work out
the details, this is you know what you
can show explicitly. It's just this lema
that for the uniform distribution for a
coding function, you can't do better
than log K minus some constant. Okay,
but now we're going to use this simple
lema and we're going to appeal to it in
powerful ways. So let's do a thought
experiment before we get to the first
part of Shannon's theorem.
And let me ask a sort of simpler
sounding question which is going to be
the heart of the lower bound.
So what if I made your life easier?
You know, you're trying to encode a
general message from this first order
source, but what if I made your life
easier by promising you something
structurally about the message you're
encoding that gave you more information?
So, what if
you know
there are
N1 occurrences
of the symbol a1
n2
occurrences
of a2 and so on. Okay, so I'm making
your life easier because instead of
having to worry about a general message
from your first order source, what if I
told you something about that message
and promised you? I'm not going to tell
you where these symbols of A1 appear,
but I'm telling you they're exactly N1
of them. I'm not going to tell you where
these symbols A2 occur, but they're
exactly N2 of them. What if I told you
for this for each different symbol type?
I told you exactly what their count was.
So now you know what we can do is we can
ask first of all how many
such sequences are there?
If I promise you that this condition
holds, then I can ask a counting
question, which is how many possible
messages could there be under this
promise that I'm giving you. You can see
now this will connect back to a lot of
the topics we did earlier in the class.
So the key is really the multinnomial,
right? If we had only two symbols and I
told you how many ones there are. I told
you there were kes out of n things, the
answer for how many strings there could
be would be n choose k. But in general,
if I have k larger than two, when I tell
you all of those types, what you're
going to get is you're going to get this
multinnomial
which is called n choose n1, n2 all the
way up to n k. And it's defined, we've
seen it before, it's just n factorial
over n1 factorial, n2 factorial all the
way up to n k factorial. That just
counts the number of ways of, you know,
coloring a set of integers from 1 to n
with k different colors once. I promise
you that there are n1 reds, n2 blues,
and so on. Okay? So let's just denote
this quantity as M because this will be
important for us. And now we can get to
a key observation. Right? So it sounds
like so far in proving Shannon's
theorem, we've only thought about
special cases. We talked about the case
where we had the uniform distribution on
K symbols. But what I claim here is that
now we're back to the case of the
uniform distribution. So we know how
many sequences there are. And moreover,
each of these sequences
has the same probability.
So the probability that they have is P1
N to the N1 P2 to the N2
times PK to the NK. So there are a ton
of possible sequences, but each
particular sequence you give me. Well,
every time I see a symbol of, you know,
A1, the probability that happened was
P1. So I multiply by P1. Every time I
see a symbol of type A2, I multiply by
P2. So what this means is we're back in
the uniform distribution setting because
when I made you this promise
about the number of counts of each type
of symbol, well, I know how many
messages there are and I know that it's
the uniform distribution on those
possible messages.
So the intuition behind the first part
of Shannon's theorem really comes from,
you know, two parts, right? We're going
to expand what's happening with this
expression. We're going to use
Sterling's approximation and the binary
entropy function will pop out, right?
But then it'll turn out that we can
remove this assumption because when we
think back to tail bounds, right? You
know, if I had a first order source
where the probability was P1 for the
first symbol and P2 for the second
symbol and really that's a coin that has
bias P1 and I flip it n times, what we
know is that the empirical number of
times we see heads is going to converge
very quickly to P1 as a fraction. So in
fact this assumption that you know what
n1, n2 and all the way up to nk are is
not really such a big assumption just
because of large deviation principles I
should approximately know the number of
symbols of each type anyways and that's
the way that we're going to piece this
all together. So that's the preview of
the argument but let's do it. Okay
so now what we can do is you know from
lema one
We know that the expected length of my
encoding even if I condition on telling
you the information that there are n1
occurrences
of a1 n2 occurrences of a2 and so on. We
know by the first lema that the expected
length must be log m minus maybe some
constant. So here this constant isn't so
bad right because you know log m is a
really gigantic thing. You should think
of it as being like exponential in n and
this other o of one is just a constant.
So now the entire name of the game is
just to figure out what log m is. And
this is where the binary entropy
function is going to pop out.
So let's do that.
So we can just plug in for our
expression for m this multinnomial
uh expression we wrote down. And then
we're going to use Sterling's formula to
group together terms and simplify.
So plugging in the multinnomial we get
that log m is equal to log of n
factorial minus the sum from i = 1 to k
of log n i factorial and then I have my
constant sitting right here uh which is
the slack in this expression.
So this is just using the multinnomial
expression and using properties of the
log.
And now what I can do is I can use
sterling.
So sterling's formula gives us an
expression
that n factorial behaves like
square of 2 n * n e to the n.
Okay. And really this part isn't going
to matter because I'm taking the log of
all of these expressions. That's just
going to get thrown into the constant.
The important thing is this n over e to
the n. So when we plug that in, we're
going to get a very nice expression. So
let's use sterling. Well, we'll get that
the expected length is at least
uh
n log n minus the sum i= 1 to k n i log
n i and I'll have some more expressions
right here. All I'm doing is I'm pulling
out this n the n term. So when I have
you know n factorial behaves like n the
n I get n log n. This behaves like ni to
the ni. So I get n i log ni. But now I
have to deal with all of these e to the
n correction terms. So I'm going to have
a minus n log of e and then a plus sum
from i= 1 to k of n i log e. And then
I'll have my o of uh one sitting in
here. Right? So this is my expression.
But now life is good because I claim
that this expression just goes away,
right? So this is n log e and this is
the sum over i from 1 to k of n i log e.
So what is the sum of all of the n i's?
N. Why?
>> Because like that's the total number of
each I guess. Perfect. So the important
point is just to not forget what the
NI's are. They count the symbols of type
I. And the total number of symbols of
you know type I when we sum over I is
just the total number of symbols which
is N. So this part completely goes away.
And now we're in good shape because we
can start to see where the entropy
function comes in. Right? So you know
how can we think about this in terms of
the entropy function? Well, we can
rewrite this expression right here as
the sum from i= 1 to k of n i log n,
right? Because then it's just the ni
that's varying. I'm just splitting n up
into the sum of the ni's. And then when
I you know uh arrange these expressions
what I'm going to get so this part right
here is you know the sum from i = 1 to k
of n i and then I have uh
log
n over n i right
and when I put a minus in front of this
I can switch these 2
and then I'll have my minus O of 1
sitting here. Right? So in fact now what
I can do is I can divide through by N.
Right? And what I'll get is N I over N.
That looks like you know a probability.
So it'll be equal this expression right
here to the binary entropy function of
n1 overn
n2 over n all the way up to n k overn
and I still now I have my um uh little o
of actually n term here.
So I'm in good shape right? So you can
see that when I expect each of these
ni's, you know, the ni overn to behave
like pi, that I'm pulling out this
binary entropy function. And this is the
first part of Shannon's theorem. Right?
This gives us our valid lower bound.
It's actually almost there. Let me just
clean up the proof. Right? So you know
what this tells us really is that even
if you were given the promise that there
are NI symbols of type I then you can't
do better than this expression. But in
principle the thing you might be worried
about is you know maybe every
configuration of the NI symbols is very
unlikely. Right? So now let's turn this
lower bound into an actual lower bound
for Shannon's theorem.
Uh, let's see. I can do it over here.
So, let me just reiterate, you know, why
I'm not quite done yet, right? So, I
claim that, you know, what we've done so
far doesn't quite prove what we're
after.
Because you know the thing we could be
worried about
is that
there might not be
any choice
of Ni's
that's very common.
So let's pop up a level. Right? So what
I'm saying here in this proof, you know,
the way the proof is structured is I'm
saying, aha, even if I told you that,
you know, NI is the number of
occurrences of symbol type I. Well, in
that case, you can't beat the binary
entropy function. The trouble is that it
might be very unlikely that that
configuration of Ni's is really what
happens. So you might tell me, all
right, when that happens, I'm dead.
You're right. I have to pay the binary
entropy function. But maybe I just never
have to that situation never arises. So
that's the last part of the proof that
we have to worry about is we have to
argue why these NI at least some
suitable choice of them is actually
quite likely, right? And so the key for
this is you know the following
definition and then we'll connect it to
our earlier discussions of tail bounds.
So we'll say that a string
is epsilon typical
if we have the following property
for all i you know for all of the
symbols uh in our alphabet. Well we take
that string and we look at what its ni
is. So what is its count of symbol type
I? We divide it by N. And I want this to
be very close to PI. In fact, I want it
to be epsilon close. So this is what I
was alluding to before was that this is
the type of thing we proved for tail
bounds. You know, when K equals 2, when
we just have heads or tails, we want the
empirical number of heads in our string
to be very close to the true bias of my
coin. I want it to be close up to an
additive epsilon. And this is the same
thing. It's just saying that the
empirical average of the number of times
we actually roll a particular side for
our die is epsilon close to the true
probability. So we'll say that a string
from our first order source is epsilon
typical if this condition holds for all
i.
And now you know the main part is really
that we can come back to chbashev.
Remember that we used tools like
chebbesev churnoff inequality and so on
to [clears throat] prove that the
empirical number of heads converges very
quickly to the expected number of heads
and this works you know even when we
have a ksided die instead. So what I
claim is really the consequence of what
we proved by Chebesev's inequality quite
a few lectures ago at this point is that
the probability that a random string
from our first order source is epsilon
typical is actually quite large. It's
like one minus maybe k over epsilon^ 2n.
So the point was that when we had
chbachev, we could argue that as n was
going to infinity, you know, because the
variances behaved nicely for the sum of
independent random variables that the
probability being far away from our
expectation was going down rapidly with
n at a one overn kind of rate. And then
maybe I have to do some kind of union
bound over each of these different k
sides for the die. You know, any one of
those goes wrong, I fail typicality. But
at the end of the day, the point is, you
know, when you look at this expression,
K and epsilon are fixed, right? So K is
fixed by our first order source. And you
should think of epsilon as being your
target accuracy in Shannon's theorem.
Maybe I want to get up to optimality up
to a 0.01 or a 0.001.
The point is just that if you take n
large enough, then this term is still
going to zero. So you're almost always
typical. So one of the hard parts about
you know the results we're doing in
coding theory is keeping all the
parameters straight in your head in
terms of what's the order in which
things go to infinity. So k is some
fixed thing epsilon is merely tiny and
then n can be gigantic in relation to
things like one over epsilon.
Any questions about this statement that
I'm asserting right here? This makes
sense and it seems to jive with the
things we covered for tail bounds. Yeah.
Okay. So now uh let's put this all
together, right? So uh putting this all
together.
Let's see what we have.
So you give me some coding function and
I want to argue that that coding
function cannot do super duper well. I
care about the expected length of your
coding function. And we can break this
up into two parts using the law of total
expectation. Right? We can look at the
expected length given that the string is
epsilon typical times the probability
that it's epsilon typical.
And we can add in the expected length
given that it's not epsilon typical
times the probability that it's not
epsilon typical. So all I'm doing is I'm
using the law of total expectation to
break up my computation because what we
know how to reason about is really this
part right here. Right? when we have a
typical sequence, we can reason through
like this log of the multinnomial what
the expected length must be. So what I
can do is I can just, you know, I'm
interested in a lower bound. So I can
just drop this term. So this entire
thing is at least, you know, 1 minus k
over epsilon^ 2 n because that's my
probability of being typical. And then
I'm going to use this fact that I had
about how it relates to the binary
entropy function. So I'll put in you
know minus n sum from i = 1 to k of p i
plus or minus epsilon
log of p i plus or minus epsilon
and then the entire thing will be you
know minus some little o of n. So here
I'm being slightly sloppy because you
know the way that I reasoned about here
was I gave you what n1 n2 all the way up
to n k were and then I talked about log
of capital m being the lower bound. So
here really epsilon typicality is not
any one configuration of the ni's. a
range of configurations for those ni.
But I know that each of those ni are
equal to, you know, ni over n is equal
to pi plus or minus epsilon because
that's the thing we plug into the binary
entropy function. But the point is that
this expression right here, it doesn't
actually vary that much as you range
epsilon over some tiny, you know,
subconstant. So in particular if I take
this expression and I look at epsilon
which is little o of one. So it's
something that's actually going to zero
as the length of my code increases the
length of my message. Then what I'm
going to get here is that this behaves
basically like the entropy function at
pi up to some small slack. So what this
will give me is what I was after that
this is equal to N * entropy minus
little O of N. Okay. So really this
proof, you know, putting it all
together, it mimics what I did in the
special case where I promised you what
the NI's are, but it just uses the fact
that maybe I don't want to tell you the
NI's. I just want to tell you it's
epsilon typical. And then I want to use
the fact that the binary entropy
function doesn't vary much as long as
the pis are, you know, what they're
supposed to be plus or minus some little
O of one. So these are all computations
you can do, but this is just the
intuition for where it is. And this
gives us the first part of Shannon's
theorem. We have our bonafiday lower
bound on the best possible coding
function. So are there any questions
about the proof of the first part of
Shannon's theorem?
This was a lot of ingredients.
Yeah.
>> But can you explain again why we don't
need the why we don't need to consider
the root n
>> the the square root 2 pi n? Yeah. Well,
okay. So here what's going to happen is
that uh
all of these things I'm really plugging
sterling in into this expression. So
when I take log of this expression, you
know, I'm going to have these giant
terms in here. You know, log of n to the
n looks like n login. I'm going to add
in some other terms. You're right. I
could worry about what happens here and
that would be a login term, right? But
the point is that at the end of the day
the thing that I want is this little O
of N. So all of those login are just
tiny by comparison. So even though by
this vantage point that looks like a
serious term. It's a root end sitting in
there. But after I take the logs really
the action is all happening in this part
right here. But good question. So that's
what makes some of these you know coding
theorems a bit tricky is that you know I
promised you when we did things like
probability and counting that we would
see ways that these tools would come up
in very complicated things. This uses a
lot of material from earlier in the
class, right? If you just think about
what all has happened, we used tail
bounds to argue about typicality. We
used combinotaurics to understand what
exactly this multinnomial works out to
be. And then we used Sterling's formula
in order to massage it into something
which has the binary entropy function.
And all of these things required a lot
of estimates about what the error terms
are and how they add up. But the
intuition at its core really comes down
to this idea that you're encoding um if
it works you know I mean typicality is a
common thing that happens and in that
case the probabilities of the different
outcomes are very close to each other so
then you can't really beat log of the
number of strings so at the core this
lower bound in Shannon first part of
Shannon's theorem is exactly this kind
of statement that we all had intuition
for that you can't beat the naive
encoding for the uniform distribution
and we're just reasoning about why this
holds even when it's merely close to the
uniform distribution. All right, so this
was a challenging proof. Uh, you know,
Tuesday's lecture will be an easier
proof. Thursday's lecture will make this
look like a cakewalk. I'm sorry, but
it's true. So, let me pause. Any other
questions about this? Does this make
sense? You guys all comfortable with it?
Yeah. All right. So the good news is
that uh now we're in a position where we
can prove the other side of Shannon's
theorem very easily. So the second part
actually follows from roughly the same
kind of argument. In fact, the way that
I'm going to write it is really as a
block diagram for this what this
encoding function looks like.
So let's prove the second part
of Shannon's theorem.
So let me ask a question first which
will get us started.
Okay. How many
epsilon typical
sequences are there?
Well, let's just work it out. Let's do
the combinatorics.
So, what I claim is that the answer is a
sum over signatures. you know all of
these n1 n2 up to n k that are epsilon
typical
right
and uh we have this multinnomial here n
choose n1 n2 all the way up to n k so
this is just by definition the answer I
sum over all of the signatures that meet
my definition of epsilon typicality and
I count the number things that meet that
signature.
Okay,
but let's get an upper bound on what
this is.
So, you know, first of all, I can think
about this expression. I'll still be a
bit sloppy here. the same way I was last
time where I'm going to think about this
multinnomial as really being you know p
i uh p1 plus or minus epsilon * n p 2
plus or minus epsilon * n and so on. So
I don't know what these [clears throat]
n1 n2s are but certainly I could choose
whatever choices that are close to pi
that maximize this expression and I
could use it as an upper bound for every
term that shows up in the sum. So the
same way I used my uh used this notation
earlier just to think about all possible
values that meet this condition of being
close to the pis I'm doing the same
thing here. But now I have to worry
about how many terms there are in the
sum. And this is where we get a huge
win. So you know what how many how many
uh times does the sum execute? You know
how many things are we summing over for
this multinnomial? It's actually not
exponential in n. That's the key point,
right?
So in fact, you know, how many different
signatures meet the condition of being
epsilon typical? Well, I could just
ignore the constraint that it's epsilon
typical. And just look at all of the
possible signatures. You know, how many
choices are there for n1? There's n
possibilities. How many choices are
there for n2? There's n possibilities.
And so on. So I get n to the k. So this
term right here, remember that we're
going to be taking the log of all of
these expressions. So this term right
here has the same property that it's not
exponentially large in n. And that's a
huge win for reasons we'll see.
So I'm going to call this term right
here m prime even though it's really a
function of you know whatever I jitter
these pis to be. But now I promised you
that really our proof is in essence
going to be a block diagram.
So let's prove it.
Let's explicitly come up with a good
coding scheme
uh for this first order source.
So we start off with our message, right?
And then in my block diagram, I'm first
going to ask is the message epsilon
typical.
Okay,
you give me the message. Uh I can
certainly compute what all the ni are
and I can plug it into the expression
and decide whether it meets my
definition for some value of epsilon.
Now in the case where the answer is yes,
how am I going to encode this message?
The first thing that I'm going to do is
I'm going to ask you what is n1 up to n
k. Right? And then I can ask you what
string is it.
Let's worry about the no branch later.
But let's compute the number of bits
that this coding scheme uses. Right? So
how long is my transmission? Well, I
have to tell you whether the answer is
yes or no. That's one bit. I tell you
yes or no.
What about you know telling you what the
signature n1 up to nk is? How many bits
is that?
At most.
>> Yeah. K login.
>> Perfect. k log n because I only pay
the log of the number of possibilities.
I just have to write out a binary string
that tells me which of the possibilities
it is. So this is a huge win because all
of these questions the answer to them is
really hidden in this little o of n term
because it's not linear in n. The only p
place where I'm going to pay linear in n
is this last part right here which is
what is the string? This right here will
get me log of you know m prime and what
we just argued was that you know log of
m prime even when I maximize over you
know what p prime i to put in here
that's epsilon close to pi I'm going to
get something you know the log of m i is
going to behave like the binary entropy
function time n up to some lower order
terms. So now down this entire branch
I'm only paying exactly what Shannon
wants me to pay. I'm paying up to
leading order the binary entropy times
n.
Now you guys can help me out with you
know what happens in the rest of the
way. So you know here I could pay plus
one bit because I have to tell you no
it's not epsilon typical right. Uh and
here what I can do as it turns out any
guesses what I can do down this no
branch
anyone have any intuition
so let me ask a leading question
you know see uh Shannon's theorem I have
the slack built in little O of N right
uh what's the probability ability that I
go down this branch at least if I set
parameters correctly. What do I want it
to be? Do I want it to be a half
probability? Something closer to one,
something tiny,
maybe little O of one.
So if I set these parameters the right
way, the probability that I fail and the
thing is not epsilon typical is little O
of one because remember it was this K
over epsilon^ 2 N for my chbash bound.
So if I set the parameters right, that's
tiny. And if this is little of one, the
probability I go down this branch, I can
actually afford to do something really
dumb here. So what could I do is I could
just output
the trivial encoding.
So how much does this trivial encoding
pay? it pays a constant x n maybe a 100
x n but so what it only happens with
probability 1 over login that we go down
this branch so it doesn't actually
prevent me from proving Shannon's second
theorem so this is very unlikely so I
can just give up whenever that happens
and do the naive thing so you know let's
analyze this and just write down what
the expression is even though this block
diagram really uh does the trick right
so let's compute the expected length.
So the expected length I always have to
tell you the answer to the question
that's yes or no. Is it epsilon typical?
If it's epsilon typical which happens
with you know 1 minus little o of one
probability because this n is gigantic
compared to k and 1 over epsilon squar
in that case I pay this k log n plus
this log m prime
and otherwise I pay this k over epsilon^
2 n all times
maybe log K * N because this is my
trivial encoding is that for each symbol
I just tell you which particular symbol
it is but the point is that you know
once I tell you what K is maybe it's 10
once I fix my target accuracy maybe it's
0.001 O1
n can be large enough so that this term
becomes arbitrarily small
and then it's multiplied by something
linear in n but then it becomes much
much smaller you know any constant times
n I can make it as small as I want so
this is the proof of uh Shannon's uh
second main theorem
any questions
you guys should have some questions.
So you know just to summarize really you
know the way that all of this fit
together was a bit magical but it's
really based on this block diagram is
that even though appriori we were
worried about how do I encode an
arbitrary thing that could come out of
my first order source. The point is that
there's this event that happens that
makes it a lot easier to reason about.
This event almost always happens and
once it's epsilon typical then the
problem behaves like the uniform
distribution on some universe and we
just care about how big is that universe
m prime that's a multinnomial and when
we use sterling's approximation the
binary entropy pops out but this block
diagram is really how the proof goes
both for the upper and the lower bounds.
Okay, so we're probably going to finish
a couple minutes early, but let me tell
you where uh we're headed for this. So,
you know, this theorem looks amazing,
right? We started off with this, you
know, question about what is the best
encoding. We saw that there were naive
encodings that we could improve upon and
then we figured out what is the natural
limit in terms of what's the best that
we could ever hope for at least in the
asmtoic regime where n is going to
infinity. But this coding scheme would
actually be pretty terrible from a
practical standpoint
if this were all there would be. So if
you think about it, right, you know,
when I defined what a coding function
was, a coding function is just a mapping
from a possible message to what I'm
going to encode it as the code book. But
in principle, you know, as n becomes
gigantic, you know, how large is that
codebook? it's becoming exponentially
large in n because there are all kinds
of messages. So, this would be terrible
if I had to do this because I would have
to preg
anyone would ever want to send and fix
what is I'm going to transmit along the
channel. That would be a really bad way
to do things because it's not an
efficient way to do the encoding, let
alone the decoding. you know, if I
actually receive some message, then how
in the world am I going to figure out
what was the original thing you started
from other than looking at everything
and figuring out what its image was?
So, what we're going to cover on Tuesday
is a really amazing scheme which is
going to give us a different way to
think about compression. And it's a
scheme that has a lot of beautiful
cominatorics. It's called the Huffman
code. And what'll be great about the
Huffman code is that it'll naturally
give us efficient encodings and
decodings. So that'll be the Tuesday
lecture and then on Thursday what we're
going to talk about is you know the
other big uh result of Shannon was you
know it's not just about data
compression but when you're transmitting
messages you know at long distances
inevitably there are errors in your
transmission. So what happens you know
when some of the symbols that you're
sending along the telephone wire get
corrupted? Is there a way to recover and
decode what was the original thing you'd
meant to send? It'll turn out that you
can do amazing things. These are really
the building blocks of, you know, the
starting point of what's called coding
theory. That has a lot of applications
in other areas of computer science. And
in fact, you know, one of the biggest
challenges for things like quantum
computation is really how do we do these
schemes in quantum computers too. So,
we'll stop early and uh you know, as I
told you in the beginning, come to
office hours, ask questions. We're here.
Don't take your foot off the gas pedal
quite yet because there's still a lot of
course work to go. But otherwise, I'll
see you next week where we'll continue
our coding theory and information theory
units. So, see you then.