Well, welcome everyone back after the
lunch break uh for the session number
three um towards clinical application.
My name is Magdalina Religara. I'm a
physician scientist and a postto in Ana
Grea's lab. So this session is very near
and dear to my heart. Um so let me
introduce you the first speaker. Um his
name is Dr. Holtz Sakai and he's a
post-docctoral fellow in chemistry and
chemical biology at Harvard Medical
School in the laboratory of Dr. David
Louu. He completed his PhD at Princeton
and the McMillan lab and in the LU lab
he works on prime editing approaches
which he's going to tell us all about
today in his talk in vivoprime editing
rescues alternating hemoplegia of
childhood in mice.
Okay. Can I stand
here? Okay. Uh thank you for the
introduction. Uh today I'm excited uh to
share with you some unpublished work on
prime editing to rescue a rare
neurological condition uh called
alternating hemoplegia of childhood. And
so this is a rare disease and I hope
that some of the metal lessons that
we're able to extract from this work uh
could be applicable to your rare
monogenic disease of interest.
And so alternating hemoplegia of
childhood is a debilitating neurological
conditions where patients suffer from a
number of symptoms including paralysis
typically on one side of their body.
They also have a number of other
symptoms including involuntary distonic
contractions and generally can suffer
from poor coordination as well.
symptoms appear within the first few
months after birth uh and can lead to
developmental delays and patients are
ultimately in many cases unable to live
independently. So mutations in the ATP
1A3 gene cause HC and specifically in
the alpha 3 subunit of the catalytic uh
uh trimer. Mutations occur throughout
the protein coding sequence of uh ATP
1A3 but primarily cluster within the uh
central transmembrane region. Mutations
are hetererozygous, denovo and usually
autotosomal
dominant. And quite interestingly the
vast majority of AHC cases in fact
twothirds of them can be accounted for
by just these three mutations alone.
Aspartate 801, glycine 947 and glutamate
815.
So for patients with AHC uh there are
currently no disease modifying
treatments available. Uh they typically
rely on symptomatic care. They are
highly dependent on caregivers given
that at any moment they can suffer uh
one of these debilitating attacks and uh
in some cases in the most severe cases
patients can regress and um really is a
quite serious
disease. So to address the underlying
therapy, uh researchers at Duke uh
developed a mouse model of the disease
that recapitulates some of the the key
hallmarks of this disease. And when they
deliver into this mouse model uh the
humanized uh ATP-p13 trans gene under
control of a uh neuron specific promoter
while they do observe some benefit uh
according to certain metrics they
ultimately aren't able to find any uh
durable rescue out to 70 days of these
clinically relevant phenotypes.
One reason why transgene complementation
might have been unsuccessful in this
case is that actually in vitro studies
in xenopus oites have shown that
relative to wild type healthy alals uh
inclusion of dominant uh negative human
alles exert this uh dominant negative
effect uh on uh current in this
particular patchclamp
experiment. And so given the sort of
challenges associated with trans gene
complementation uh given this putitudive
uh mechanism, we asked the question of
whether precision genome editing might
be able to directly address uh the root
cause of AHC by reverting some of these
mutations uh and potentially overcome uh
these uh cellular mechanisms providing a
proof of concept uh permanent
intervention for this uh debilitating
neurological condition.
And so among precision genome editing
technologies of course uh crisper cast 9
nucleuses uh are an immensely powerful
approach for precisely introducing uh
gene disruption as we heard this morning
uh in the case of cast jevy. The LU
group has also pioneered uh sort of more
precise technologies uh such as base
editors which by fusion of a diaminise
allow us to very precisely install uh
transition mutations uh in the genome uh
as well as prime editors which by fusion
of reverse transcriptase allow for
what's effectively search and replace uh
genome editing and through a prime
editing guide RNA which specifies both
the target locus uh as well as in a
threep prime extension the replacement
nucleotide
sequence. And so we identified B and
prime editing as a potential strategy to
directly correct pathogenic alals
without requiring uh doublestranded
breaks that might uh lead to undesirable
outcomes. And so uh from the outset we
recognize that particularly uh for prime
editing there would be a number of
challenges that we would need to
address. The first is that uh while
Xvivo prime editing uh is underway in
the clinic uh invivo prime editing
particularly in the central nervous
system uh does remain
challenging. Second, ATP3 actually has a
critical role in prenatal uh cortical
development and so it was unclear from
the outset whether we could actually
intervene postnatally.
Third, in order to address a majority of
HC genotypes, we would need to develop
scalable and parallel approaches to
target multiple alals in parallel. Uh,
and finally, and perhaps most notably,
there had been prior to this work no
previous reports of prime editing uh
rescuing a behavioral phenotype in a
neurological uh disorder in an animal.
And so a really gratifying and exciting
component of this work um for me as a
lab scientist was getting to interact uh
with you know some of these patients and
community leaders who are on the front
lines. And so I really uh am gratified
to work with them. And you know you
can't ask for more uh motivated people
to work
with. And so uh to answer this question
we teamed up with a number of scientists
across a series of institutions. I have
to highlight Alex Souza uh my co-lead at
the Broad as well as Marcus Terry at the
Jackson Labs and here are fantastic uh
patient collaborators uh Natalia, Nina
and
Simon. And so we set out to target uh in
this work a majority of AHC mutations
collectively targeting 65% of of AHC
cases.
uh to correct these mutations. First uh
in human cells, we thought that in
principle we could apply base editing to
correct uh three or four of these
mutations. Uh but actually as it turns
out uh proximal bystander nucleotides
that would undergo uh competitive
damination actually prevented base
editing from being applied in these
cases. But we were able to achieve uh
for a well isolated adinine efficient
reversion to the wild type sequence. For
the remaining mutations we turned to
prime editing and from the outset we
included uh benign silent mutations
shown in green. Uh that was because
previous work had shown only reverting
the pathogenic mutation would result in
uh heteroduplex intermediates that would
be efficient substrates for cellular
mismatch repair. And so by incorporating
uh benign and co-installing silent
mutations uh we might be able to bias
repair pathways toward productive
editing. I'm showing just a brief uh
subset of the optimization experiments
that we performed to correct these
mutations. But suffice it to say that
after a substantial amount of work, uh
we were able to uh efficiently correct
five of these mutations uh across a
number of different strategies in our
cellular models uh of these
mutations. To actually translate these
conditions into a more disease relevant
uh cell type, we collaborated uh with
Christine and Al at Northwestern
uh to who had access to uh patient
IPS-C's.
when we initially tried to translate our
optimized uh correction for example for
this particular mutation uh we only saw
7% correction in IPS-C's and so this is
starting from uh a a genetic baseline of
50% these patients are hetererozygous
and so we're trying to make this bar go
bar go to
100 however by incorporating sort of now
uh routine enhancements to the prime
editor system including more active
prime editor variants uh engineered PEG
RNAs that enhance cellular stability as
well as including an additional guide
RNA that through uh proximal binding
here uh puditively uh increases the
chromatin accessibility of the target
site. We're able to restore uh editing
up to 70% in patient cells.
Applying these strategies across the
remaining mutations again we can
efficiently now in patientder derived
iPS-C's efficiently correct these
mutations back to wild type. Uh we also
assess the precision of our uh editing
strategy applying a genomewide
nomination pipeline called circle seek
uh to assess and nominate uh 450 sites
genomewide. uh actually looking at the
editing there we observe no offtarget
editing of anticipated biological
significance. So in this in vitro
portion of the work, I hope I've been
able to show you how by using precision
genome editing, uh we can uh make these
cell lines, something I did not discuss
today, uh actually optimize and refine
correction strategies for these
mutations first in in our hex cell
models before finally advancing them uh
into more advanced cell
types. Moving forward, we're really
excited about further scaling this uh
technology uh through machine learning
models which allow us to nominate uh PEG
RNAs for consideration and actually
evaluating them experimentally using
high throughput lentiviral
screens. And we hope that these
approaches or other more recent alil
agnostic technologies might allow us to
address a broader range of these
mutations. All right. So with uh
correction of these mutations in human
cells in hand, we next ask the question
of whether we might be able to intervene
uh in disease
biology. And so uh in the absence of
humanized animal models uh we considered
the the orthologus mouse gene. And while
this is over 99% identical at the
protein level, uh the coding sequence
actually differs by about 10%. And so we
actually reoptimized prime editing uh
strategies to correct these mouse
mutations with the enhancements uh
discussed previously. And we can achieve
correction in uh hetererozygous mouse
primary fiber blasts uh derived from the
animal models with those
mutations. And so this is the sort of
gory details of our optimized prime
editing system. But suffice it to say
that we can then package those into a
dual AV9 vector system wherein the prime
editor is split across two vector halves
N and C terminal that will uh upon
successful co- uh corransduction
reconstitute uh by protein trans
splicing and so along with a GFP marker
uh for
biodistribution uh we deliver these into
these animal models uh by intra cerebro
ventricular administration at P 0 and uh
subject these animals to a barrage of uh
phenotyping phenotypic assays including
at the molecular behavioral uh and
biometric levels. These experiments were
done in collaboration with scientists at
the Jackson Labs uh specifically Marcus
Terry, Laura Anderson and Kat Lutz at
the rare disease translational center.
And so when we first assess editing at
the genomic level, here is the
hetererozygous uh baseline of untreated
animals. And upon prime editing, we can
achieve uh up to 50% pathogenic alil
correction in bulk uh cortex samples. Uh
but actually looking at GFP positive
nuclei. So these are cells that are very
highly uh transduced. uh we can observe
you know up to 90% or higher pathogenic
alil correction in certain brain regions
suggesting that uh in some in some cases
uh were more limited by vector
transduction than by the prime editing
system
itself. Uh we also assessed uh in
addition to uh genomic correction uh
transcriptional uh rescue of ATP 1A3 in
bulk. And uh this enrichment that we
observe relative to DNA is consistent uh
and consistent with the fact that AV9 is
expected to uh selectively target these
neurons where ATP-1 A3 is being
expressed as opposed to for example GAL
cells.
Uh in addition to uh DNA and RNA, we
collaborated with Kathy Swedner and
Elena at Mass General Bighgam to assess
the functional rescue of uh ATPAS
activity in our treated animals. And
relative to HC mice which display an
enzyatic defect, we can significantly
restore uh enzyatic activity back toward
wild type
levels. In addition to molecular
readouts, we also assessed a number of
critical behavioral uh phenotypes uh
most notably this hypothermia induction
assay. So here mice are exposed to a
cold water bath uh to induce uh episodes
of donia, hemoplegia, and other
seizure-like events that's typically
observed in patients. And so uh mice are
assigned a qualitative score ranging
from normal behavior all the way to uh
severe uh cases where the mouse is
unable to write itself. We also quantify
the number of seizure-like events and
measure the amount of time it takes for
these mice to first uh regain writing
and then subsequent uh normal voluntary
movement. And again, patients also
experience uh these types of symptoms
and so in response to harsh stimuli and
and those types of uh
triggers. So uh relative to HC mice
which score very highly on the scale, we
can significantly reduce uh the
qualitative severity of these episodes.
But more excitingly and quantitatively,
we can measure the most severe events,
specifically these tonic clonic-l like
seizures. And relative to HC mice, we
can essentially restore the number of
those events back down to
baseline. Uh measuring the amount of
recovery time for writing and also
subsequent uh mobility, we see that uh
these AHC mice have a sort of uh shifted
recovery time where they take much
longer uh to recover from these
hypothermic events and prime editor
treatment shifts that back toward wild
type.
Beyond uh these types of induced
phenotypes, we also measured
coordination using the roto rod assay
and we can restore uh coordination in
prime editor treated animals uh up to or
almost back to wild type
levels. Most notably, HC mice like some
patients can display a survival deficit
due to spontaneous uh episodes and HC
mice uh do not survive out to the study
end point of 52 weeks. By contrast,
prime editor treated animals uh we can
significantly enhance survival and
reduced instances of spontaneous
death. So I hope I've been able to show
you uh across the central dogma and also
at the level uh of uh behavioral and
survival readouts we've been able to uh
intervene in HC disease biology. A sort
of key missing link that we're excited
about exploring further is uh using
invivo electrphysiology to actually uh
assess uh to what extent prime editing
might be able to intervene and partially
rescue uh this type of circuit or higher
level uh complexity and this is in
collaboration with R Georgie and Elsa at
Leiden
University and uh sort of going to the
ladders to cur's idea of identifying
notable biological mechanisms
I think in the case of therapeutic
genome editing, maybe the biological
hypothesis is is often quite simple. But
I think now that we have these tools, uh
we can actually use them to study uh
biological questions related to disease
and its progression. For example, uh you
know, at what level does uh correction
at the protein level uh translate into
organ or behavioral level
phenotypes? As we advance toward the
clinic, we're also thinking about a
number of other studies related uh to
dosing uh more relevant routes of
administration uh in the clinic as well
as later ages of
intervention. And so that's all uh I'll
share today. Um but I hope uh you know
moving forward that we'll be able to
accelerate progress uh through the
approaches mentioned previously and that
this work will inspire the creation uh
of humanized models or alo agnostic
methods that will allow us to target an
even broader range of these mutations
moving forward. And so with that uh I
have to thank uh David of course uh I
mentioned co-leads Alex Souza and Marcus
Terry uh these sources for funding and
I'll be happy to take any questions
during the Q&A.
Well, thank you Holt. That was a great
talk and very very exciting data. Um, as
with the previous sessions, we're going
to do questions after the the next
speaker. We'll do it all together. Um,
so let me introduce you the next
speaker. It's a pleasure to introduce
Dr. Rashad Gupta. Raj Gupta is an
assistant professor of medicine at
Harvard Medical School with a research
lab um in the division of cardiovascular
medicine and genetics at Birkham Women's
Hospital and also here at the Broad
Institute and as a physician scientist
he is interested in how genetic
mutations affect vascular function
especially um to find uh new treatment
targets uh and that's what he's going to
talk uh about today um and a talk titled
toward a cure for several cavernous
malfformations genetic insight and
perturb seek in action. I'm very excited
about the inaction part, right? Yeah.
Thanks. Thanks so much for that
introduction. Um, is my mic on? Can you
hear me? Okay, perfect. Um, well,
wonderful. So I did my posttock here at
the broad institute uh many moons ago uh
with David Alt Schuler and the goal was
to identify the genetic drivers of
common diseases like coronary artery
disease and hypertension and that's what
I started my lab to study but by you
know sort of uh curiositydriven research
as Anna likes to say a lot um we
identified that there were these nodal
pathways shared between common vascular
diseases and rare vascular diseases and
so this community of ladders to cure has
sort of helped us hone in on is there
some therapeutic potential for insights
made from common vascular diseases on a
rare disease and that's the story I'm
going to share today. Okay. So the
disease that I'm going to uh talk to
everyone about uh is cerebral cavernous
malfforms. There's been a big uh um
focus on neuro degenerative disease
neuromuscular disease and this is a
neurovvascular disease and so it's
extremely rare. It's c there's a
mandelian form which is one in 5,000
people and then there's a sporadic form
which is one in 200 people. So more
common. The mandelian form is driven by
three mutations all named for the
disease they cause CCM1, CCM2 and
CCM3. And what you see in these
pictures, it's almost like a blood
blister of the brain. It's like a
enlargement of the venus uh structures
that results in these enlarged uh blood
vessels that can burst at any time. On
the right you see an MRI and each one of
those black dots shouldn't be there.
They can burst unpredictably and result
in uh hemoplegia, stroke and death. And
the only real proven therapy is
neurosurgery and it's a very painstaking
neurosurgery. Only the sort of most
skilled neurosurgeons the chief of
neurosurgery at children's hospital here
is one of the worldleading experts and
they have to sort of individually excise
each of these lesions and they don't
know which lesions are going to burst.
Many of the lesions form in inoperable
regions of the brain like the brain stem
which they can't go after surgically and
there's no therapies that delay or
reverse the
disease and so you know I got super
interested in this disease because of
our perturb seek work that I'm going to
share with you and so I asked every
neurologist in the city to send me their
CCM patients and somewhat embarrassed me
every time a patient comes sees me they
say so you're a neurosurgeon right and I
sort of have to say well no I'm actually
a cardiologist ologist. I'm just really
interested in this disease. I think we
could cure it one day. And so, you know,
some of my u you know, patients will
even say, "But you're still a
neurosurgeon, right?" Because they they
they, you know, believe that that's
really the only way to treat the
disease. And but the but the exciting
part that I like to explain to the
patients that I talk to is that their
rare disease is teaching us about the
common diseases of the blood vessels and
the other way around, right? And the
reason for this is the common diseases
that we study, right? like coronary
disease and hypertension. They're driven
by these small effects size variants
where we don't know the causal genes. We
often are assuming that like we know the
causal genes but are often wrong.
Whereas rare diseases like cerebral
cavernous malfforms or thoracic aortic
aneurysms are driven by rare variants
identified in familial studies and are
linked to severe phenotypes but they
both converge on the same nodal pathways
and in endothelial cells that's been
increasingly apparent from our perturbed
seek work. And what I'm excited about
and it's something that you know I think
is is you know we haven't talked about
it today but this sort of virtuous cycle
between rare and common disease right uh
when we did perturbse seek we only knew
the biology of the genes we were
identifying because of prior work in
rare disease and I think the rare
disease work is informing the common
disease work and hopefully the other way
around and so the outline of what I'll
present today are that um you know from
perturbse we have identified central
nodes for vascular disease risk and the
node that I'm going to talk about is the
regulation of KLF2 and 4 transcription
factors that are very involved in sheer
stress response the response of
endothelial cells to blood flow but you
know there's this opposite direction of
effect between CCM and CAD genetics and
so what are the insights we can make in
that um so finally the the work that was
funded by this latter secure seed
project was to define the causal pathway
for CCM better and that was to look for
cellular phenotypes with cell painting
you know work that JT Neil beautifully
presented today. And then finally, we've
sort of begun the effort to develop
therapies in this space. And so the work
that you know sort of motivated our our
entry into CCM was an endothelial cell
perturb screen that was done by Gavin
Schnitzer and Helen Kang in our lab in
close collaboration with Jesse Enrightes
who's now at Stanford. And we were
trying to study the
228 non- lipid associated CAD genes that
were identified from GIWA studies. We
wondered if we could study all of the
possible causal genes in endothelial
cells at the same time. And so the the
project that we embarked on was
perturbing every possible causal gene.
So in a poolled format, use crisper eye
to knock down expression of of each one
of the possible causal genes within a
megabase of each of the G-W was variants
and then perform single cell RNA
sequencing to look for the
transcriptional effects of each of these
perturbations. So in the middle panel
you'll see that we were able to
successfully sequence 215,000 single
cells with 37,000 different guide RNAs
and 90 cells per target gene. And then
we then use methods that were developed
in
particulated gene networks from this
analysis. So you find like denovo which
genes have effects on which genetic
programs in in vitro. And you know
here's like sort of what we call the
wiring diagram of the endothelial cell
that's sort of denovo analyzed from our
perturb data right no assumptions are
made these are just the the genes that
travel together you know in our
experiment and you'll see that there's
50 co-regulated gene programs 37 of
which you would have found in any cell
type u they affect like common processes
like cell cycle or ribosomal biology but
13 of the programs are endothelial cell
specific and they are in the sort of
pathways that you would expect to be
associated with vascular diseases. And
the one one of these programs topic 8 or
program 8 from our analysis was enriched
for CAD genetic risk. So 41 of the 241
CAD risk variants all converged on this
pathway. And the pathway is sort of
shown here in this
cartoon. Genes that were upstream of KF2
and 4, which is sort of the nodal piece
of the pathway. um they're in a a
pathway called the CCM pathway. And that
that's that's sort of depicted in the
middle of the of the diagram, but genes
upstream and downstream of KF2 sort of
unite to show genetic enrichment for all
of these uh variants. And so uh one of
these genes is CCM2 itself. And we had
never heard of CCM2. We' never sort of
heard about the disease itself. But what
we were seeing is that loss of function
of C CCM2 and other genes in that
complex were protective for coronary
artery disease. So now we sort of after
reading the literature we had this sort
of dilemma. The literature is telling us
that large rare deletions in CCM2 were
causing this severe neurovvascular
disorder. But then when you look at a
common misssense mutation in that same
gene, it's protective for coronary
disease. And so our ladder secure
project was to really confirm these
opposite directionalities, really see if
that's true and to better define these
phenotypes. And so to begin with, why is
there opposite directionality? So on on
the right you see work done by Mark
Khan's lab at the University of
Pennsylvania where they made the CCM
knockout mouse model and they made it
for a crit one knockout which is also
CCM1 which you see in the top right and
then in the bottom left is the CCM2
knockout. You see these brain lesions
that are forming in the cerebellum. When
they knock out mech 3, which is just up
downstream of the CCM pathway, it's the
sort of kinace cascade regulated by this
complex. They rescue it. So they cure it
in mice by knockout of mech 3. So they
say that the pathogenesis of the brain
disease is high KF2. And we also think
that's the protective effect in CAD. So
why could this be? Why are there these
opposite directionalities? It could be
that there's specific biology at that
misssense mutation. It could be that
there's a difference between complete
and partial loss of function, sort of a
do dosage effect. It could be because
arterial and venus ECs respond
differently to mutations. And it could
be because there's a difference between
developmental effects and adult effects.
These are the kind of questions that
will probably take my lab the next 10
years to study. But I think they're
really important and exciting. And so
just to begin with what have we done
like with with the broad community and
the ladders to cure community is that
you know we found that the the coding
mutation that's associated with
decreased CAD risk is at this one spot
in the CCM protein and you know its
minor alo frequency is 8%. So it
probably doesn't affect risk of a rare
disease but the CCM causing mutations
are all sort of on the C terminus end
they affect maybe other properties and
so what are those other properties? Are
there different proteins that bind at
each site? And one of the things that
binds on that C terminus end is a new
protein that had never been linked to
this complex. It's an orange hair. It's
called Q1RD1. Um so our hypothesis was
that different cellular mechanisms may
respond may be responsible for CAD or
CCM. And so to sort of unlock this, we
use the cell painting or variant editing
approach that JT Neil nicely introduced,
right? They use machine learning of of
microscopy images to identify the
effects of different mutations and they
have standard cell painting and then
variant cell painting which you heard
about earlier today. So we kind of ran
through a lot of mutant alals in CCM and
what you see is the reference al for CCM
at the bottom. The wild type AL results
in cytoplasmic localization of CCM.
Right? All the green all the GFP tag CCM
is all in the cytoplasm. But a specific
variant al at the C terminus end of the
protein this isolucine 432 to thrienine
changes the localization completely.
It's sort of one of the examples JT
talked about that now it's more nuclear
localization. A different amino acid
change at that same residue has no
effect. It's still cytoplasmically
located. And so you know now we want to
expand that. So we finding specific
phenotypes for disease associated
mutations for the rare disease that
aren't seen with the common disease and
now we want to see if like all the
mutation all the genes in this pathway
have similar morphologic effects. So uh
GIA a new post document in my lab has
sort of run this analysis and this is uh
you know work we did you know with the
imaging platform here to knock out all
of the sort of topic eight genes that
were enriched for CAD and all of the CCM
genes and they don't all cluster
together in perturbse seek they all show
the same transcriptional phenotype but
morphologically they cluster separately
and so finally I want to just spend the
last few minutes talking about you know
is there an opportunity for therapies
that target what we've learned and so we
we want to make the case that we could
repurpose a drug that was actually
developed by Nat Gray when he was here
at the Broad and Dana Farber. It's an
IRK 5 inhibitor. It's part of this
pathway. And so uh the cartoon here are
all the sort of functions of the CCM
complex. Uh you see CCM 1, CCM2, and
CCM3. They bind each other. They bind
mech 3. They affect KF2 and 4. Our data
suggests that's the mechanism of
disease. But the current therapies in
development are targeting peripheral
mechanisms. There's a clinical trial in
in progress to target uh to use statins
which target HMG co-red reductase sort
of not a central member of this
complex recursion with work that was
actually done here at the broad with an
carpenter is using templ which re which
uh targets reactive oxygen species and
then other companies are making rock
inhibitors for this disease and like I
said those are sort of in that dotted
circle they affect stress fiber
formation that's an important mechanism
of disease but we don't think that's the
central mechanism. That's not the node
that keeps showing up in all of our
experiments. The node is really the
genes that are driving disease risk. And
so if we wanted to target that, we found
in the literature that um Nat Gray, a
great chemist who had made protac
molecules for uh KK one and two for
cancer had made an IRK 5 Proac. And Nat
Gray is so famous that even if he shows
his compound does nothing, he can
publish it in cell chemical biology,
which he did very nicely. Right? So this
is a uh they made the compound. It was
extremely specific um as you see in the
bottom right RNA seek and it was uh a
very potent inhibitor of ver 5 and
downstream signaling but it had no
effect on cancer. So then they stopped
working on it. Um but we think that you
know we have knockout cells CCM2 and
T1rd1 knockout cells that are resistant
to sheer stress. They they demonstrate
some of the phenotypes that you'd
expect. And so at the bottom kind of the
most striking phenotype is that the CCM2
and TRD1 cells have like stronger stress
fibers and uh right above that you see
that even with flow the wild type cells
will all align but the knockout cells
sort of retain this disorganized
pattern. And so we tested their five
protac and you know there is a
therapeutic range where you could take
the CKO or CCM2 knockout cells and they
will normalize KF2 expression whereas
wild type cells will have like a minimal
response to KF2 expression. So we found
this to sort of be a a possible targeted
therapy to the central mechanism that
that might be promising for CCM and we'd
like to expand that work. And so I'll
end by saying our you know we're just
kind of scratching the surface of how
nodal biology could affect one rare
disease and one common and multiple
common diseases but to go forward we
want to develop invivo perturbse seek
methods to identify the co-regulated
networks in a disease context um and
we're starting along those lines you
know uh with aavs that target
endothelial cells that were actually
made by the deman lab here we've been
able to get pretty good expression in a
crisper eye mouse we want to determine
the different invivo effects of CAD and
CCM associated mutations. We want to
test the efficacy of this first compound
for you know possible um lesion uh uh
resolution in mice that get CCM disease.
And then finally I didn't have time to
talk about this but we've we've
partnered with the foundation. So
there's a alliance to cure cavernous
malf formations that kind of enrolls all
the patients who have this disease and
we want to now that we have perturbed
seek data we could take all the genotype
negative families and see if they have
mutations in in related genes to this
this pathway and so with that I'll thank
the people who did the work Gavin
Schnitzer Helen Kang led the perturbse
and multiple members of our lab Jesse
Angry's lab u has been really
instrumental in almost all the work and
we uh always thank the families that
have contributed samples and their time
to this research. Thanks.
[Applause]
Thank you so much for this talk. I want
the two speakers maybe to join me up
here. Uh and we'll starting our Q&A
session. Just go and grab a microphone
if there's any
questions. If there's none for now, I'll
start. Um hold I have a question for
you. Um you kind of in the beginning
kind of presented that you know you have
a disease you have a gene you have the
mutations and then you tried with base
editing but they were offt targets
effect and then one maybe works the
other one didn't and then you went to
prime editing. Do you think that would
kind of be the pathway forward for you
know if I have a gene of interest then
that would be kind of the pathway that u
that everybody has to go through. Yeah,
I would say um and this happens quite
often in our lab where people will you
know see a mutation
and at least try base editing. It's
possible that you know even if it's like
two nucleotides away if the window is
just right you can get just on target
without any bystander. Um and that
sometimes surprises us too like
sometimes we'll make calls like oh
there's no way base editing will work
but let's just try it anyway. And
surprisingly it does. Um but yeah, I
would say given the additional maybe
experimental requirements and throughput
for prime editing, we usually put that
as a a second second choice. But let's
say prime editing will get more and more
efficient. Uh would that maybe overtake
the base editing? Yeah, that's that's a
that's an interesting question and we
certainly hope it will get there. I
think um now we're starting to see where
our most optimized uh prime edits can
start to hit the levels of like some of
the earlier base editors. We're still
the base editors are still just like
monsters at daminating DNA and actually
for those actually offtargets become
much more of a problem. Uh so prime
editing is much better uh due to sort of
the three successive DNA hybridization
events that have to happen in the
mechanism for offtarget limitations.
Yeah.
I had a question for Raj. I was
wondering if whether in the CCM patients
or the mice if you studied the arterial
endothelial cells, what phenotypes would
you see? Yeah, that's a great question.
So, um the the we're studying that in
the lab because that's like sort of the
best evidence that there's a different
protective effect and the short answer
is we see a protective effect in the CCM
hetererozygous mice. Homozygous CCM2
knockout mice don't survive in germline.
Uh inducible CCM2 knockout mice exist
and they can survive. We haven't studied
them, but we thought a hetererozygous
mice mimic the effect of like a modest
germline uh common mutation. And she
fang in my lab is is got really nice
data that they get less a less vascular
inflammation. Um so you do see that loss
of function, you know, modest loss of
function is having a protective effect.
Yeah.
Hi. Uh, I'm Ashley Connor at Microsoft
in the Broad. I really appreciated both
of your talks. I had a question about
the relationship that you drew between
identifying mechanisms that allow you to
draw parallels between rare and common
disease. Mhm. Have you thought about
ways or have you identified any patterns
that will allow us to help making those
relationships as we think about
therapeutic strategies that might allow
us to kind of shift between applications
in rare and common disease space? Yeah,
that's a that's a great question and
Anna Anna has like great experience with
this as well and I think we're all
trying to do this to some extent. Um,
our approach was like cellular genetics.
So perturb seek um identify pathways and
nodes you know using perturbation in a
relevant cell type and then you'll see
this convergence of genetic risk on
certain pathways and then the pathways
are probably already described from rare
disease. So that's like a more laborious
way of doing things. I think it requires
this sort of you know high throughput
cellular phenotyping. Um but we're just
talking about transcriptional pathways
there. What about like morphologic
pathways? Well, maybe like variant cell
editing and and microscopy could do
that. Um, and then uh you know, I think
you could harness the pleotropy of
varants, right? So, um, as more
sequencing becomes available, maybe you
could just find it from like lots of
sequencing of biioanks. UK bio bank's
not really powered yet for something
like CCM but we would expect that there
should be like convergence of certain
mutations on like hemorrhagic stroke and
CAD risk but it's just not powered yet
with only 500,000 but maybe at like a
million two million it would be. Thank
you.
Hi. So, I had a question about the
efficacy between the um the hacksaw
models that you were using and the mouse
models. And I thought it was I mean I
thought it was super exciting that the
efficacy was so high in the mouse
models. And I was wondering
um I mean I was wondering what
challenges there are like going forward
with efficacy like on the mouse model
side compared to the yeah compared to in
in vitro. Yeah that's a that's a good
question. It's always um you know a
little bit disappointing when we do all
this work in the hexel and then it just
doesn't translate always. Um,
fortunately we do have some approaches
now that allow us to to elevate
efficiency in more primary types. Um,
but yeah, your your question about I
guess translating from in vitro to
invivo editing is is is a hard one and I
would say that um for us we typically
try to assess
um in the most advanced system possible
and as early as possible just to get a
sense of what those challenges might be.
Um and and whether um I guess there
there are alternative editing strategies
that you might want to pursue or
prioritize. Yeah.
Question. Um so regarding the the prime
editing um in vivo introduction of uh
indelss even though it's a a fairly low
number is this something that you're
concerned with and is there anything um
in the mechanism of how they get
introduced that you could try to
leverage as a way to minimize them?
Yeah, that's a that's a a good question.
So I think
um so for one of the mouse models we had
um I don't want to go too much into the
detail about the the specific
complexities of the prime editing system
but um one of the mouse models had what
we call like a PE3B nicking. So we have
a second guide RNA that nicks the
opposite strand to bias DNA repair. And
in some cases that nick can be
selectively introduced only after the
edit has been introduced. And so when we
use that type of strategy we typically
see very low induls in vivo. Um but for
the other mouse model where we didn't
have you know that requirement that the
mutation already be corrected followed
by nicking and it just nicked elsewhere
we actually observed much higher indul.
So something that we're following up on
that to to reduce uh the number uh that
percentage is to you know modify the
strategy to to have that second nick uh
be concurrent. Um I will say that uh I
guess it you know will certainly depend
on your particular disease of interest
whether uh I guess indel mediated say
nonsense mediated decay might you know
be relevant for your your particular um
protein. Um, but at least I think as
long as it's leading to
non-functional variants that are just I
guess truncated um that don't compete
then that that might be okay depending
on the disease as well.
Okay. Well, I wanted to thank the
speakers for two excellent talks and for
all the work they do. Thanks for the
discussion and we can move on.