My name is Angela Kohler and I have the
priv privilege and pleasure of chairing
the future of uh health and life
sciences. I do not have the pleasure of
following Sally Cornbluth because it's
always a challenge to follow Sally. But
luckily you gave the vision statement
for heels. So yeah, it's great.
Uh yes. So I will have the pleasure of
introducing three speakers who are
thinking about the the interface of
health and life sciences and
nanotechnology. And so um I think there
will be a slide that will show their
faces but we have Anna Jaglennic who is
at the Koch Institute. We have Jag Shaw
who um is from Mariah Bio and Geot
Traverso just snuck in kind of he's a
professor in mechanical um engineering.
Let's see. So, uh, Sally mentioned the
vision for heels and, um, what we're
really doing as one of the presidential,
uh, strategic initiatives is trying to
think how we can build f build a
community with folks across campus,
including all five schools and the
college of computing to try to tackle
some of the most trans transformative
problems in human health. And that
includes artists, that includes uh
people who are thinking about ethics,
that includes our colleagues at Sloan,
but also engineers and scientists. Um uh
there's some guiding principles
associated with how the different
strategic initiatives that you're going
to hear about today. You're going to
hear about manufacturing, you're going
to again hear about life sciences,
you're going to hear about climate.
there's some guiding principles for us
and that is again trying to bring in
community trying to undertake um
open-source strategies there's sally I
won't repeat
um trying to be people focused as was
mentioned trying to develop trainees
across MIT we really want to build
communities um and I think also
important for this audience all the
strategic initiatives are thinking about
how do we engage our colleagues in
industry at the earliest stage stages
for partnership and collaboration. Um,
and then we have an institutional
commitment as these strategic
initiatives to work with you to try to
identify funding sources to actually
enable that research.
So on the heels side, here's sort of our
our pillars within heels. We're focused
on developing talent. So for us, that
means trying to develop um funding
sources for trainees across the board.
We care deeply about entrepreneurship
and trying to take our innovations from
within the institute to the wider world
often through new venture creation. So
we partner with the engine, we partner
with Martin Trust Center, we partner
with the Bandai Center. Um we're
particularly interested in catalyzing
discovery. I'll say more about this um
through seed grants. So we're often
providing seed grants to different
folks. I'll say more about nanocience,
but here are some of the topics that
have bubbled up across campus. The seeds
in our case really require
interdisciplinary teams, people from
different departments, different DLCIs.
And moving forward into year two, we're
working with industry partners to issue
grant challenges to the community. And
then from an impact perspective, we're
hoping that we can grow some of these
seeds that we're planting literally
today on October 1st. Our seed grants
start today um into strategic
initiatives. We have some that already
exist. I'll say a little bit about the
MIT MGB seed program and the MIT program
for um health sciences and
semiconductors.
So heels across uh MIT I was really
shocked when I learned that 75% of the
MIT community has already published a
paper in health and life sciences.
That's really remarkable. We're a very
large community spanning like I said all
the schools as of this weekend even I
should say heels launched on December
4th but we've really been ex in
existence for six months and as of this
weekend we uh reached the milestone of
having funded 140 different labs on
campus through a variety of mechanisms
including fellowships grants etc. And if
you're interested in the health and life
sciences, please mark your calendar.
We'll be holding an annual symposium in
March.
So, I figured I would say a little bit
about these seed grants that are
starting today. Um, I don't have cool
images yet because the research is
literally starting today, but of the 19
seed grants that we issued, 13 of them
self-identified as being in the
nanotechnology space. So just listing
some of these we have um just one on the
top is a a collaborative um project
thinking about mapping multi-body
multi-organ dynamics of the maternal
fetal system. Nanotechnology plays a
role in this and we have colleagues from
ECS material science BCS mechanical
engineering um and civil and
environmental engineering as part of
that team. There are a number of uh
projects that are associated with drug
delivery and sensing and imaging. Um so
we actually think within the se the
heels umbrella we can create a cohort of
teams that are thinking about
nanotechnology and work with nano.
Um I'll say something briefly about the
MIT MGB um seed program that's run by
Alex Jalick and Emory Brown. The goal of
this program is really to um plant seeds
with our colleagues at the local area
hospitals focusing on MGB. Um and uh
they issued a call thinking more about
uh a AI enabled diagnostics and digital
health solutions. They got 134
proposals. They've now narrowed it down
to 32 finalists. I got a peak at what
those who those finalists are and I
would say probably 75% of those
proposals relate to nanocience. So
that's really cool.
Um and then finally the MIT health
sciences and semiconductors program is
another program that I think people here
should know about. They uh ran their
first grant cycle over the summer. Their
strategic areas of focus are biosensing
imaging micro nanofluidics, magnetic
diagnostics and ultrasound technologies.
Um these projects uh require partnership
with IMC to actually move forward and
they were able to fund four grants in
this area over the summer and they'll
have future runs as well. Um and then in
the spirit of entrepreneurship I'll just
say there's an upcoming grant call um
which is called the momentum grant. This
is co-sponsored between MIT Heels at
Climate and the Desponde Center. Um, and
here what we're doing is giving a little
bit of money for people to sort of check
the boxes on internal academic work with
the idea that this would let you know if
there's a there there for commercial
translation downstream. So these
applications are due October 15th. Uh,
we have a heels leadership team. If you
have questions, thoughts, we would love
to hear from you. There's an email
address. If you send us a question, I
promise you I'll get I'll get the email
and I'm uh happy to answer.
Um, and with that, I'll transition to
the real show, which is the the amazing
science that our speakers are going to
talk about. Um, as as I said, we have
Anna Jenk from um, the Koch Institute,
and she's going to talk about next
generation mRNA delivery powered by um,
predictive AI. Then we'll uh, transition
to Geot Traverso who will talk about uh,
engineering for extremes, nano for
health. And then we'll close out with
Jigash Shaw who is at Marai Bio. He will
talk about targeted lipid nanoparticles
for extrahypatic delivery. Once we're
done with the talks, we'll uh basically
sit down for panel and um take questions
from the audience. So with that, I'll uh
bring in uh Anna.
Well, thank you so much, Angela, and
really a privilege to be here today and
talk um with all of you. Hopefully um my
slides will work um because I'm not sure
how to give a data talk slides. Um
excellent. Um
so I want to u talk a little bit about
um kind of our health care and medicine
how it's really changed over the last 30
plus years. I think we've really um
transitioned from treating illness when
it occurs um sort of when you're you
know bleeding you go to the hospital and
you get treatment to really thinking
about how can we prevent illness from
happening in the first place and I think
it it sort of started in the 90s and has
really I think expanded greatly in the
last 10 years or so and I think part of
the things that have made this possible
is not just advancements in
biotechnology and science um but also
personalized and digital health um that
allows and really information that
allows all of us to really understand
disease progression and understand
things that we can do to prevent it from
happening. Uh nutrition and microbiome
science also is a big part of that. So
there are many tools that we use for
this and I think we're all um familiar
with things like vaccines. I want to
highlight one thing and you know um work
at the cancer institute about 13% of
cancers are actually caused by
infectious disease and some of which can
be prevented with vaccines. HPV is a
great example and I'll talk about that a
little more in a in a second. HPV is a
virus that um uh infectious disease that
leads to cervical cancer in women. Um of
course early dete uh cancer interception
is very common. We all have screenings
um whether it's through imaging or other
um Gio may talk about um colonoscopies
later but but there's many different
ways to screen for that and of course
nutrition metabolic health is extremely
becoming extremely important and I think
we all understand why this is important
it can reduce health care costs but most
importantly we can have healthier better
lives and longer lives as well and so
just to go back quickly to the HPV
example um we know that um HPV causes
cervical cancer and we know that
vaccines now we have data from the CDC
that show that the vaccines that were
developed against HPV can help prevent
that cancer from occurring which I think
is really um a huge um finding but but
the issue still remains as you can see
in the graph here that um we're not
immunizing uh not everyone is getting
those immunizations um and there's still
quite a bit of people that might be not
protected against this disease. It's
actually if you're HIV positive, it can
be worse. Um so, so what I've spent my
effort really is trying to understand
what are um some of the challenges that
persist there and globally there's
estimates that go up to as high as 40%
of people who start multid-dosese
vaccinations don't complete them, which
means they're not protected. Um and even
in when we look at cancer therapeutic
vaccines which we all know might be the
next um great uh imunotherapy to treat
cancer um oncology patients also drop
out and as low as 50% um do not adhere
to their full dosing regimen. So there's
really a huge need to make these things
easier for people to get the therapies
that could really be lifechanging. Um,
and so I've devoted a big part of my
career in trying to address these
issues. Of course, there's societal
issues, but really from the technology
standpoint. Is there a way for us to
lower the bar for people to get these
therapies? Um, and I certainly do a lot
of work in the global health space and
collaborate with the Gates Foundation.
And um, in those cases, we're talking
about low to middle inome countries that
don't have the infrastructure we have
here. But also in the United States,
there are areas once you go outside of
Boston and big city centers that are
rural and that just don't have the same
infrastructure. I think sometimes we
take for granted that we live in an area
with some of the best um hospitals and
medical care in the world. And so those
people may not have access to many of
the therapies as well. So our group
really tries to develop um new
technologies and new manufacturing to
improve access and delivery of both
preventative and therapeutic medicines
for people across the globe including
here. Um we also do a lot of work um in
the area of microlastics
um and um micronutrients and nutrition.
But today I'm going to focus on um the
the two platforms that we developed um
for um one to um extend the efficacy and
durability of vaccines um or
therapeutics um and two to make the ease
of administration easier. So the first
quickly I just want to talk a briefly
about um how we developed what we called
our seal platform and really the idea
here was can we develop a single
injection formulation that uh for
vaccines that are self- boosting so you
don't need to have the repeated shots so
this can have improved efficacy and it
can be durable from that one single
injection and the idea is as you know
there's many different vaccines now we
have the mRNA LMP vaccines which I'll
get to in a minute But there's different
types of vaccines, different type of
molecules that need to deliver. And so
we decided um that we wanted a platform
solution, one that could be applied
across the different u modalities of
vaccines or molecules. Um and actually
as uh professor Bulovich um echoed to
sort of echo what professor Bulerich
said earlier um we ended up really
looking at the semiconductor uh industry
um and how they can package things in
tiny little things um because we wanted
to essentially build a tiny little cup
that could take any drug and could be
injected and delivered and then it
releases that drug at some point in time
after it's injected. Um the nano lab was
just um instrumental in helping us
develop this technology. There's
actually a dirty room where they let us
play around uh with various things to
make this work. We ended up publishing
this work um in in science. And really
what we did is until now until that
point, this was in 2017, the um pulse
the drug delivery field really with um
the drugs that were to be delivered were
usually for long-term delivery were um
placed in these matrices and the drug
was throughout the matrix that limited
the type of control you can have with
regard to drug kinetics. In the case of
vaccines, you need the vaccine to be um
stable and then released months after
you inject it. And so to really have
that kind of precision and control over
the kinetics, we went to a core shell
structure. We wanted to design a core
shell structure just like an egg um has
a shell on it and the egg is stable, but
once the shell breaks, it comes out very
quickly as we all know. So that was
really what we wanted to create but at a
scale so tiny that could be injected
with a regular needle and syringe. Um
and so it was very difficult to do this.
We failed for those students in the
audience. We failed many many many
times. Um but eventually we created this
new manufacturing process. It was almost
a new way of 3D printing where we can
make these bases um that are made out of
material medically approved material um
and then we use PZO electric nozzles
which are found in inkjet printers to
fill it with any drug or vaccine you can
imagine um and then we seal these
particles. So we created this core shell
structure where the drug is in the
center and it's stable until that shell
breaks just like an egg. Um and we were
able to achieve this using the MIT nano
facilities. Um, and today we have a
company that's now scaling this process.
And if you can see this little um, a
3-in wafer has about 7,000 of those
particles in it. So, we really took
something that you can do in micro
electronics and semiconductor industry
and brought it to the pharmaceutical
industry. And this allows you for these
very precise kinetics. Um, we and this
is just what the particles look like.
You have an SEM on the bottom. Um and
you can make these with high fidelity in
these large arrays. So it's really a
beautifully manufactured process just
like you have in the semiconductor
industry. Um and but most importantly
we're able to these each vertical line
here in this graph shows invivo release
of the drug inside or vaccine after it's
injected. And you can see we can not
only release days after injection but
months. That last one on the right is
six months out. And the way we can do
this is the material of the shell is
from PLGA polymer which is a polymer
used uh in the medical industry as
resorbable sutures as screws. It's used
in some drug formulations. So it's has a
huge record of safety. Um and we can so
we can tailor this release um to
whatever is needed and we can mix and
match these particles. Um, there's a lot
of data I could show, but I just want to
highlight that we've shown that we could
use these particles from a single
injection to deliver three doses of the
polio vaccine. We've shown that in
non-human private primates, you can get
protective titers. Um, and we've shown
we could do this for many different
types of vaccines. hepatitis B which is
a recombinant protein vaccine um
influenza and of course mRNA um COVID
vaccines and I'll get to that later but
hepatitis B and polio virus vaccines um
have completed non-human primate studies
we've also shown that you could use this
technology
to treat other diseases you could use
this for cancer immunotherapy drugs we
have um again all published data we
published in science translational
medicine um you can use it as photo and
chemotherapy drugs to treat metastatic
cancers. Um, and also you can also um
use it to leave drugs behind after open
heart surgery on the heart to help the
heart tissue uh regenerate. This was
just accepted to sell biomeaterials. Um,
and so we've shown that we can do all
these really beautiful things to extend
the durability from that single
injection, single time of contact with
the patient. The other thing that we're
really interested in um is really to
make the ease of administration of drugs
and vaccines easier. Um and for that we
went to micro needle technology. And I
don't know if those of you that are
familiar with micro needles are kind of
a bed of nails um a little band-aid that
you can pre uh press into the skin and
releases the drug in the tips. It's
actually made from sugars. Um, and as we
know during the the COVID pandemic,
there was really an issue with
delivering the vaccines, the storage and
so on. These little micro needles are in
solid format and they don't need to be
refrigerated. So, they're easy to um
handle and you know, here's one for
those you probably can't even see it.
And that could administer your dose of
vaccine or any other um drug if that's
the case. Uh, and you can just press it
onto your skin. Um, and so what we did
is we designed and built these three
three-dimensional printers that could be
shipped basically around the world to it
doesn't even have to be a pharmacy. So
it could be shipped around the world and
the ink contains the vaccine um as well
as the material to make the micro
needles and so they could be made on
demand. Um, for that we had to come up
with a new manufacturing process to fit
it into a box which you see there in the
center if you look there's a centurfuge
free mold filling. So we were able to
build that into these printers and you
can again build these arrays of these
micro needles that can be delivered. Um
we then I'm not going into all the
detail this was published in nature bio
technology for the sake of time but
we've shown that these are a lot more
stable at room temperature. Um they
contained mRNA L&P vaccines. We did this
work during COVID. Um and we showed that
much more stable at room temperature
than the conventional vaccines that are
in liquid format for in fact we had six
months stability at at room temperature
with these solid state formulations. Um
so to to just sort of the but the
challenge remained in for us to create
these we had to develop a new L&P a new
nanoparticle that was stable under these
conditions. there's a has to survive the
manufacturing process which involves
drying and then it has to be stable in
storage conditions and in the first
technologies has to be stable in the
body for a long time as well. So um my
students got a little frustrated in
posttos in trying to formulate some of
these things. Uh and like I said, we had
this really great formulation, but what
we what we wanted after all this work
was done, people called us and they want
us to work with some of the clinically
approved vaccines um and formulations
from uh companies like Madna and Fizer.
And what we found is that the Madna and
Fiser LMPS when they go through our
processes for these two technologies,
they don't survive. Um and so we had to
really think of this from a formulation
perspective. Um and so we developed in
collaboration with professor uh Mina
Konakovich um at the at uh the computer
science department. Um we created a a
machine learning accelerated um program
that allow us to really test all these
different formulations. Um and this is
an example what it what it did. It would
tell us what exipients to test. We had a
in a small 96 well plate. we would dry
the samples um and see which ones
survived and we'd feed that information
back into the algorithm um and this then
once we had the lead formulations we
would then test them in our devices and
eventually in animals and so very
quickly again we worked with Madna and
Fiser vaccines and this really shows you
the progress of our optimization
algorithm and the various rounds that we
tested at the top there shows you the
various round our target was to reach
100% stability compared to the liquid
formulation The bottom shows you the
various compositions that we tested. Um
and you can see after six rounds it's
not a linear process but we reached um
100%. Um again we characterized these
various aspects and I'm happy to I sake
of time I can't go into it but we can
talk afterwards. Um and then we tested
is in two models. one, we went to the
mouse model and we validated that in
fact the AI assisted formulation ended
up performing just as good as the um the
regular injectable vaccine. Um so it
really validated that this works in a
mouse and of course a lot of things work
in the mouse. So um and again just more
data reiterating that. So we then we
went to non-human primate model to see
if it works there which is closer to
human as we all know and again we had
these brilliant results that showed that
you get the exact same immune responses
whe if you use the solid state
formulations with the AI optimized um
formulation versus the liquid stuff that
you can get from Madna or Fizer. Um so
this was really thrilling but what I
wanted to end on here and highlight that
um the development timeline of AI
assisted uh map formulation was really
tremendously shorter than anything else
we've done. So first we started um doing
this process manually. It took over four
months. We explored a hundred different
exipients and no formulations matched.
So we failed after four months. We
failed and could not have uh formulation
that worked as well as it needed to. And
so um then we decided to try a different
approach and started using the AI um
implemented the AI model uh and within
less than a month we had our lead
formulation which I just showed data
for. Um and then after that we went into
rodents and finally NHPS. So um with
that I just want to emphasize how
powerful some of these tools are that we
have in accelerating our progress and
then I also want to highlight how great
MIT Nano has been to us. It's really
allowed us to innovate in so many
different spaces and really bring this
semiconductor micro electronics aspect
into the pharmaceutical um space and
really to advance uh health care for for
global health. And then most importantly
I want to thank our really terrific
terrific staff and of scientists in
particular the work I show today um Jimi
and Khan uh Jim is a graduate student
core six and Khan is a postoc in our lab
who really have been tremendous in in
doing a lot of this work and of course
all of our funding agencies as well
including the gates foundation in barta.
So with that, I thank you.
All right. Um, let me see if our slides
are
I see them on the screen.
All right. Well, uh, wonderful to meet
you. I'm Gio Traverso. As you heard
earlier, I'm in the department of
mechanical engineering. I'm also a
gastronurologist and I practice across
the river over at the Bighgam. And what
I'd like to do over the next 10 minutes
or so is share with you three recent
stories really speaking to the nano sort
of aspect and how it relates to health
but really across length scales. And so
with that uh let's dive right in and you
know we tend to focus on the GI tract um
and hence the the the picture of the uh
pill. So the first body of work is work
that was led by two incredible
post-docctoral scientists in our group
Alvin Chan and Amea Curtine who are now
faculty members at uh in Singapore at
NTU as well as in Minnesota respectively
and the challenge that they took on was
really thinking about how to accelerate
the development of nano particles for
delivery of nucleic acids including mRNA
and others. And this is work that has
been supported by several bodies
including art by age as well as the
marble center here um as well as uh the
Singaporean government. And the you know
how we refer to this system is as comet
and uh in that it is a transformer-based
model that really helps accelerate the
whole development process. But let me
just take a step back for a second and
remind you of the challenge that we have
in front of us. So mRNA is a nucleic
acid. If one injects nucleic this
nucleic acid into the body it is unable
to be taken up by cells usually andor
degrades fairly rapidly and so somehow
we need some help from a lipid nanop
particle and that carrier or vehicle is
what enables essentially entry into the
cell traditional L&PS are composed of a
set of ingredients and so here we have
some of the more common ingredients
there's an ionizable lipid a helper
lipid a pegbased lipid and cholesterol
and very fine sort of changes in the
ratios of each have incredible effects
on the ability of that nanop particle to
enter the cell or even to target
different parts of the body. And so
recognizing that you know there's this
tremendous sort of impact on both
delivery but also the site of delivery.
uh what uh Alvin and Amaya and the team
decided to do was initially build a very
large set of experimental formulations,
test them and then use that data to then
train a transformer-based model that
really could treat each individual
component on its own but then use that
framework to then help accelerate the
next step. And so uh they were
successful in doing this. This paper
just came out in nature nano just a few
months ago. And this is just to give you
a flavor of the kind of things that one
is able to achieve very quickly through
these encilicoerated kind of
formulations. So I include here data
from the rodent work and we have in
green the clinical benchmarks and then
in the light blue the level of
expression of the amount of protein that
is produced in vivo and what we're
seeing there are improvements that are
greater than five to 40fold above the
clinical benchmarks. But now we have the
ability to very quickly arrive
essentially at the answer by using that
framework. Now I'm going to shift gears
a little bit. I'm going to go now to the
macro, but you'll see how macro enables
and actually works together with a nano.
And this is work that we've been doing
now for about a decade. And we've had
collaboration with Novonortis, the NIH,
but also ARPH. There have been many
people involved and these are some of
our students and collaborators uh over
this journey. And the fundamental
challenge here that we were tackling is
the recognition that most people if they
have to take a drug would rather take it
through the root or the system that is
shown here on the right a capsule over
the injectable format here on the left.
Now the challenge of course is that many
drugs like insulin or humra or even mRNA
vaccines is that they are degraded in
the GI tract and that's because our GI
tract has evolved to degrade these
materials. Many of our foods are made of
proteins and nucleic acids and you know
we've evolved to degrade these but also
these molecules are so big that they're
unable to essentially transport or
travel across the GI mucosa. And so what
we um did really inspired by uh in this
case by sephalopod squid was think about
systems that could use jets to really
facilitate that injection. And we had
done a lot of early work using different
tiny little needles. But we said you
know maybe we can eliminate needles uh
from this process. And um someone can
click on the screen. Perfect. Thanks.
And so what we did was we developed a
family of devices that facilitated
delivery of these jets and these jets
essentially carry nano particles through
the tissue and then these are able to
distribute to generate the therapy that
is intended for the specific condition.
And so having developed a family of
devices uh let me just show you uh what
this looks like. So this is one of those
uh sets of devices. Uh essentially they
use a jet and what you'll see here is
essentially that jet sort of delivering
that stream of nanoparticles. In this
case this is on the bench but this also
happens in vivo. And to show you what
happens in vivo here we have
cross-sectional imaging of delivery in
different parts of the GI tract in this
case of a pig. But what we were able to
do was quantify the fundamental uh
pressures required to really inform the
optimal delivery parameters in different
parts of the GI tract. So having
established all of this, we looked at a
few different therapies that typically
are not administerable through the oral
route. We looked at for example GLP1
receptor analoges, but now we're
achieving bioavailabilities or levels
that are comparable to an injection. So
there is an oral semaglutide on the
market. that bioavailability is 1 to 2%
in that formulation. Here we're
achieving 50 to 90% bioavailabilities
that are comparable to subcutaneous
administration. We also demonstrated the
ability to deliver sirna using these
systems. So I'm going to transition I
should say that that body of work was
just published at the end of last year
in nature and then this uh body of work
that's been supported by our page and
the Gates Foundation and led by an
extremely talented uh scientist in our
group Troy Kang really set out to tackle
a fundamental challenge of initially
adhesion or engagement with wet
surfaces. So certainly I think we
recognize that on the wearable side, but
this is a big problem in the GI tract
where we have a wet moist system or
surface that is turning over on a
regular basis. And so we said, well,
maybe we can look at nature for
inspiration. And uh essentially what
Troy did together with our collaborators
was look at a fish or or a family of
fish called raora or sucker fish. And
these are fish that essentially are able
to adhere to many substrates. And so on
the right of the slide, you can see uh
the range of substrates, right, in the
form of whether it's a shark or a
turtle. And these fish have evolved to
adhere to these different surfaces. And
so we said, you know, maybe there are
some lessons that we can take from this
evolutionary experiment. And if I hope
you can appreciate there the sucker that
has been highlighted. Um essentially you
can see that there are a lot of
similarities even though the substrates
are actually quite different. And so uh
what Troy together with our
collaborators did, we were able to get
Raora and study essentially the sucker
system to really understand how this
system can integrate and facilitate that
engagement with the mucosa. Um we also
filmed them. So we collaborated with a
group at uh BC and we were able to film
the engagement with synthetic sort of
gastric tissue to really understand the
steps involved in how this sucker fish
can engage with the surface and studied
and really delineated all the individual
steps of that process and developed a
synthetic remora capsule that can do all
of this. And so uh we demonstrated that
not only could we do this but we could
recapitulate that adhesive system. And
this is of course at the macro uh scale.
And what this system allows is
essentially you can administer this and
the natural paristoic motion in the GI
tract essentially is acting really to
help with the engagement with the
mucosa. So you'll see here there's a
contraction in the esophagus and then
the system is adherent to the GI tract.
Now this is where nano comes into the uh
the conversation where now we have a
macro structure enabling that
juxtaposition of the device with the
tissue or the side of the delivery and
now we're able to load these devices
with nano formulations in this initial
example of an anti-retroviral for the
treatment of HIV where we're able to now
support treatment orally for once with a
once a week capsule and beyond that
we've also delivered mRNA using uh these
systems. So, similar to some of the
things you just heard from Anna, we've
developed some solid formulations that
we're able to immobilize on these
systems. And not only are we able to
immobilize them, but we're able to
achieve uh delivery and functional
expression in pigs using these systems.
So, hopefully it gives you a little bit
of the flavor of what we're doing in
nano and bridging some of the medical
device macro sort of aspects and how we
are at least reimagining what we can do
for patients. I want to thank the work
of many and these are some of the folks
and their families at our recent uh
celebration on one of the Boston
islands. And with that, uh in case I
don't get to your questions, uh here's
my email. I want to acknowledge all of
our incredible institutions, but of
course all of the funders and sponsors
that really enable and support our work.
So, thank you so much.
So uh while my slides are coming up uh I
put in the fact that I'm of you PhD 999.
So uh uh uh but uh spent some time at uh
institution up the way uh then
transitioned into industry. So, one of
the through lines that I'll take
advantage of of what Anna and and Gio um
uh talked about was the idea that we can
deliver mRNA, which is the language of
the cell to reprogram cells. We can get
them to make vaccines so that they can
present antigens so that we can generate
an immune response. But we can also get
them to reprogram in a variety of
different ways including if you're
familiar with cartis cells so that cell
the cart cells can go and kill uh uh
cancer. So I'm going to give you a
flavor for how we're trying to get to
these other cell other cell types using
lipid nanoparticle technology that was
leveraged during the uh uh pandemic. So
Marai is actually a flagship company and
I'll give you a bit of a flavor of our
business model first. We do not make our
own therapeutics. We are a foundry of
sorts. We generate targeted lipid nanop
particles that go to a variety of sites
that I'll describe and try to identify
partners that have therapeutic cargos or
therapeutic hypotheses that would then
leverage our ability to be able to get
to those sites. So our work is really
very broad in the context of trying to
get our nanoparticles to a variety of
different tissues and then enable uh
therapeutics for for the next stage. Our
model is really built on um another
through line here is AI and the use of
those tools. But lipid nanoparticles as
geo described is a chemistry game right
now. It's really understanding what kind
of ionizable lipids which are thought to
be the lynch pin of the um nanoparticle
but also other components that can be
put together and then screened at scale.
So how do we screen them at scale? So
part of what we've developed at um Marai
is a micrfluidic technology that allows
us to make large numbers of different
L&P formulations all at once and then be
able to put many of those into an animal
into a single animal and then deconvolve
and multiplex where each one of these
formulations has gone and it'll be a
technology that many of you be familiar
with a barcoding technology that allows
us to not understand just where the
nanoparticle went but as you saw in
Geo's uh animation where it actually
delivered to the cell. So where it
actually got out of the endoome which I
think of as the lipid nanoparticle gel
of the cell how can escape so that it
can have therapeutic effect.
One of the other when we carry out those
invivo multiplexing we generate a lot of
data that data allows us then to refine
where our nanoparticles can go and this
is where the active learning based
approaches based on this invivo data has
really um dramatically increased our uh
potential for getting to cells of
interest. We're a part of the flagship
ecosystem and leveraging that allows us
to also look at things like binders. So
once you can get a nanoparticle to go
there by chemistry, don't forget about
biology. Biology has binders and
antibodies that can actually even
increase the level of potency. So we're
bringing those two technologies together
to be able to get high potency delivery
to cell types of interest. And I think
we've heard a lot about scale here and
you know being able to do something at
the benchtop being able to do something
in mice really does ultimately is just
the aperture that you need to open up to
be able to get to pre-clinical studies
and monkeys but also into human beings.
So how do we make sure that we can scale
that material in the context of clinical
and commercial production GMP quality
and that's where we have some
partnerships with our industry partners
like thermo um there we've been able to
now take our partners all the way from
the discovery element all the way to
clinical evaluation and hopefully their
success that would result in
commercialization.
So I'm going to talk about the elements
of the platform that we've built and
then give you an example of how we've
built a particular uh targeted
nanoparticle uh for our our our goal. So
we have some chemistry. I think that
this is kind of the table stakes in L&P
biology is trying to understand kind of
what kinds of ionizable and other
components you can put together. We've
developed this high throughput
formulation platform internally a
proprietary system to be able to get you
know 96 nanoparticles of different
formulations simultaneously. We've also
developed a proprietary barcoding system
as I'll describe. It allows you to
distinguish from being just getting to
the organ of interest but actually
getting into the cell type of interest
and escaping the endoome and delivering
that therapeutic uh capability. And then
we, you know, machine learning for us is
a tool and we try to sprinkle it in
wherever we can and to give us the
advantage of being able to take large
scale data sets and turn them into new
learnings.
Another piece of uh the flagship
ecosystem that I just wanted to
highlight here is mRNA is just one
language that the cell speaks in. There
are a variety of different languages of
nucleic acids that uh the cell uses and
we've been able to work with a large
number of different kinds of nucleic
acids um mRNA transfer RNAs um small
interfering RNAs that you've just heard
that you've heard about as well as DNA
and gene editing and sample amplifying
RNAs that are quite large and still
remain to be are still are challenging
to uh um formulate but we've been able
to expose our lipid nanoparticles to
those as well to be able to understand
what else what other languages can we
deliver and what other therapeutic
hypotheses can we deliver to the cell.
So our pipeline looks quite broad but
really what we're trying to do is unlock
tissues so that we can enable these
therapeutic hypotheses to be developed.
So I'll talk a little bit about how we
have built out our first set of uh um
components. We usually start by
identifying a cell type of interest. The
base L&P is really where most of the
work needs to be done. Being able to
ensure that the particle gets to the
cells and tissues of interest and then
doesn't get into the cells where you
want to avoid offtarget toxicity.
Then additional as I'll show you there's
some benefit to adding um some
intelligence to the particle as it were
by adding in binders that then
selectively get to cell types of
interest. um and and revealing that. So
I'll just describe our barcoding
technology first. So we have a large
library of of uh proprietary lipids and
what we do is we formulate in this case
um example is 10 lipids. So this is real
data. So it's not even though it looks
all very colorful. It's actual data. Um
we took 10 ionizable lipids. Uh they are
now encoded by 10 different nucleic acid
barcodes. And what you see on the on the
far right uh your left is the dose. So
we're trying to dose in equal numbers of
these barcodes and different L&P uh
different lipid nano particles. What you
see in the middle is now we're very
interested in getting to immune cells
for this particular example. So we're
pulling out the spleen and then asking
how much how many of those barcoded
dosed barcodes actually ended up in the
spleen. So that allows you to look at
now the proportion in the stacked column
plot of all the different uh barcodes
that ended up there.
This is a technology that has been used
pretty widely. But one thing that um
kind of causes some constrnation at
least in uh in our in our experience is
that only about 1 to 2% of those L&PS
actually deliver their therapeutic uh
cargo into the cytoplasm. So many of
these barcodes are stuck inside the
cell. What we do in the last part is
that the nucleic acid that then gets
delivered into the cytoplasm under goes
a modification that changes its
sequence. So we now can distinguish
between the cytoplasmically delivered
material and the material that was dosed
into the animal. And that allows us to
look at different kinds of uh
phenotypes. So enrichment here we're
we're seeing that the um an LNP gets
well into the spleen and also seems to
get well into the splenic cell
cytoplasm. That's what the third column
would be. There's also some examples
where the reduction in the
biodistribution is actually turns out to
be very small in the in the dish in the
splen spleen itself but very large in
the cytoplasm. These are particles that
now we've um done a a good deal of
analysis on actually have increased
endooal escape. If you put them in the
endoome, they deliver their material
very well. So much so that they don't
even hang around in the endoome for a
long time and as a result have very good
delivery into the cell types of
interest. And then of course there are
nanoparticles that we can say we can
exclude. They don't they don't really go
to the spleen very well and they don't
really accumulate in the spleen. So this
allows us then to identify a set of
lipid nanoparticles that can go to in
this case um the spleen which is the
second column here. One critical piece
of the lipid nanoparticle field is how
do we dearget the liver? So those of you
that took your physiology you can't
dearget the liver. It takes 25% of of
the volume of the blood. So you can't
get particles not to go there but you
can get them not to go into hpatocytes.
And that's part of what we've developed
here is a number of lipid nanoparticles
that don't undergo delivery into the
liver so that then they can persist and
go to other sites in the in the body.
And what we've seen here is two
different nanoparticles here that have
modest levels of reduction in liver
delivery and some increased levels of
the spleen. And this is our base for our
ability to then do
um active learning based uh formulation
optimization. So what we do is we take
our formulation and luckily Gio
described what the four components are
that go into traditional nanoparticles.
They're put together in a particular
level of formulation components. We then
put those into animals at large numbers
and then identify all of that data to
try to understand how we can hill climb
and increase the level of ontarget
delivery in the spleen and reduce the
level of delivery in the liver. And what
you can see here is over the course of a
variety large number of invivo studies
we can on the left on the right hand
side sorry your left hand side
uh you can see that we're minimizing
liver delivery in this case almost two
orders of magnitude in the context of a
bioluminescent cargo and on the right
hand side we're being able to maintain
delivery to the extraatic site and so we
started with our barcoding allowed us to
identify a base LNP that was the
substrate for machine learning then
allowed us to then look at delivery. And
so what you can see on the um bar graph
here is delivery now to human cells in a
mouse where we've uh put in human uh tea
cells. And what you're looking at is
you're looking you see that um our
commercial lipid gets to about 30% of
those tea cells and we can increase the
level of delivery to about 60% in this
model. But perhaps more importantly,
the immunoistochemistry, which is a more
qualitative readout, shows you that the
commercial lipid gets avidly to the uh
liver. And this is me measured by the
brown staining, which is a uh readout
for the reporter that we've delivered to
these cells. And you can see that our
MRI lipids have remarkably lower levels
of delivery. So we've now created a
particle that when injected IV will go
to TE-C cells and not to the liver. That
wasn't good enough. We wanted to see if
we could do even better. So, we
identified a number of receptors on T-
cells. You're familiar, those of you
that are familiar with the alphabet soup
of T- cells will know CD3, CD8, CD4. But
more importantly, we have a number of
companies again within the flagship
ecosystem that we love to take advantage
of that are building many kinds of
binders. Traditional vaccination or
immunization based approaches, but also
ones that are based on viral proteins
that have been evolved over millions of
years and that have low immunogenicity
and high affinity on the order of
picomolder binding some of these viral
proteins. And then also uh you may be
familiar with Lio Laya Sciences recently
uh had a fairly significant A- round.
They are building machine learning
binders for us and they happen in a
month and you don't have to wait for any
mice to kind of develop antibodies for
for any of this for any of this work. So
we're very excited about the
opportunities to build these binders.
One of these binders against CD8 was
then added to the surface of our lipid
nanoparticle. And I'll just quickly walk
through the fact that what we can what
we've been able to do is take the base
L&P and now increase the level of
delivery dramatically inside these uh
mouse models and maintain the level of
offtarget uh delivery compared to our
commercial LMP and and this um this is
our base substrate for now doing some
clinical studies with some partners.
Those of you that are familiar with the
CARTT field will know that in vivo
reprogramming of te- cells to be able to
not have to take the tea cells out for
each patient and then put them back in
again but actually directly reprogram is
actually a particular uh case study here
and we hope to have some uh NHP data on
that very soon.
We've taken the same uh approach and now
we've been able to go after other immune
cells and hematopoetic cells stem cells
as well to be able to direct a lipid
nanoparticle with a base to a cell type
of interest using uh one of these uh
base LMPS as well as an a binder. So
we've developed a number of technologies
happy to discuss those with others. They
may be that may be of interest to you.
multiplex barcoding in vivo the machine
learning the active learning the immune
cell tropism as well as our modular
extrahypatic platform using a binder um
again our model is really co-creation
with a partner so we're currently look
we currently have a number of
partnerships where we're looking at a
variety of different therapeutic cargos
using these targeted L&PS and we're
we've opened up a number of these cell
types some of them may be of interest to
people in the audience happy to discuss
so thank you very much.
>> Can you hear me?
Um, that was great. Uh, and we're going
to have questions from the audience, but
before we do that, um, today has been an
interesting morning. We started the day
off with a government shutdown and this
is sort of illustrative of um the sort
of impacts that we're seeing across R&D.
I often like to tell people that the
model in this country for R&D is going
to change and evolve in many ways that
affects all the sectors. And given that
we have two academics and one former
academic who's made the jump into
industry, I'm curious to um hear your
perspectives about how this will impact
you in your respective sectors.
>> You want me to start? Um well, of
course, it's it's not good from um many
different um levels. I think it, you
know, it's really hard for us while we
are very good at controlling
experiments, it's really hard for us to
control the government and what's
happening around us. So, I think there's
really not much that um we can do
outside of just trying to manage um our
lab and our spending and sort of how we
think about
you know uh making sure that we continue
to innovate and continue to push the
work forward. I think actually at the
beginning in your talk really
illustrated that MIT given all the
uncertainty around funding not just due
to the shutdown but MIT has really uh
put forward a lot of different programs
to kind of help supplement maybe some of
the losses that we'll see um you know
and that we are seeing from from the
government funding you know the other
aspects are um looking at other ways to
receive funding and that's foundations
and myself and I know Gio we've been you
know fortunate to work with um the Gates
Foundation
um and and other foundations that I
think are not affected necessarily
though obviously they're being asked for
to fund more work so that's affecting
how much they can give right to some
extent um and then you know really being
creative and maybe um Jack can talk more
about that how uh we can partner um with
industry perhaps some sort of inind
things where there's an exchange change
of scientists or access to different
facilities. So really trying to make
things happen even though you don't have
that grant coming in, but maybe you can
have a a free person if you will and
free access to equipment or or something
um that can really help move the
research forward even though you don't
have the big grants coming in.
>> I mean Gio, you've talked a lot about um
ARPA. So do you expect any sort of
impacts on your group?
So with respect to RPH, I mean I
received our RPH grants. It's I don't
know if people are familiar with RPH,
but RPH sort of is a new entity
relatively new. That's sort of about
three years ago to basically support
high-risk uh potentially high reward
concepts and to try and nurture them,
you know, all the way through ideally
through early stage clinical trials. and
RH is one of the largest ones in the
country uh over $60 million aiming to
transform what we can deliver orally and
so far as can we deliver nucleic acids
and achieve high availability or can we
deliver electrocuts which wasn't
something I talked about today but a lot
of the work that we're doing now and so
I received a notice yesterday that our
funding happens to be managed by the
department of the interior that's just a
nuance of how the different funding
comes through but I received a notice
that we should continue so Our guidance
was continue and that that was the
guidance. I think just to add to what
Anna was just saying and I think whether
there is a shutdown or not, I think if
anything it just highlights what I think
increasingly we as an academic community
recognize is that we need to diversify
if we haven't done so already as far as
our funding streams, right? And so as
Anna said, we've been fortunate to work
with the Gates Foundation for over a
decade. And um you know, we I've worked
very closely with Nova Nordis for over a
decade as well. Um and a few others and
I think if anything whenever there are
shutdowns, it's not the first one at
least unfortunately uh in the last few
years. And I think it just again sort of
reemphasizes the need uh as an academic
to you know try and at least seek out
opportunities and partnerships. And I
mean that's my my tip.
>> And then how's this impacting industry?
And it's just like maybe it's the silver
lining that we may all play better
together.
>> Uh uh I think we play well pretty well
already. I think uh I I don't want to I
said it's been said many times but not
only does do the ideas the nent ideas
that are leveraged in the context of
industry whether by individual
entrepreneurship or you know by
licensing some of these ideas you guys
are generating the workforce. I love
hiring MIT students. Uh, you know,
they're fantastic. They are well
trained. So, I think that we just that
the it feels like there's no more
toothpaste in the tube at some point,
right? If we do not fill this uh
pipeline, we're not going to have those
kinds of people. But to your point, in
the near term, let's say that we can get
over this at some point, I do think that
there are some real opportunities for
really interfacing some of these things.
There's I'll be honest there's no chance
I'm going to be getting any raora fish
at Marai setting up some kind of lab
there to look at those. So there are
some really fantastic ideas that when
academics are ready we really would love
to partner. And what do we offer? We
offer some of the opportunities to take
things to scale perhaps that maybe are
not always available. The ability to be
able to scale out in some large sets of
experiments. So we do have capital
>> somewhat that I think could be deployed.
So everybody will have to give a little
bit on either side. It's not the same
kind of uh trench warfare that we we
might have uh experienced before, but
I'm very excited about what we can do.
>> And and you mentioned an interesting
model system. So we also know that the
federal government is changing how we
think about the use of animals within
research and trying to get us to think
about sort of alternatives to
traditional animal model animal models.
So um how are you all thinking about
that push?
Well, I think it'd be great if we didn't
have um didn't have to do all the animal
work and there was a very uh validated
way to evaluate things in a nonan animal
model. Um I think and and so if that um
you you know people some people are
working on this and lab on a chip and
and various um things we're doing some
stuff with uh women's health health in
that space trying to see how um you know
drugs and lactating mothers get into uh
the breast milk and um can we screen
which drugs do that um without you know
in in a dish rather than going to actual
experiments
in animals or or people and I think as
long is it's safe. It's actually a good
push, but there needs to be resources
and funding to really develop and
validate. That's really the key piece
here is validate that um we have a good
alternative that is predictive.
>> Um and I think once we have that, it
could be actually uh a you know,
helpful. But of course, we don't want to
um I certainly wouldn't want my child or
myself to receive something that hasn't
been tested in you, you know, an animal
just on a chip and but you know um
anyway you know in a few decades maybe
we'll have such strong validation that
we'll have confidence that that is safe
and you what what can we do at MIT along
these lines?
>> Yeah. No, I mean I think that it's
wonderful to see that sort of these
things are aligning and we've been
working on Xvivo and in vitro models of
the GI tract for example and deliver you
know for about a decade. I mean we
started a company that is based here and
in Switzerland that you know is doing
this for drug delivery science and also
we have some more recent data really
predicting toxicity in a dish that
translates really well to large animal
models. So I agree I think that it's
wise. I agree with Anna though. I think
that it's still early, right? So the
vision and dream of having these
encilico twins that are able to predict
the outcome of the experiment without
having done the experiment in vivo is
challenging with the current data set.
Can we get there? You know perhaps and
and I hope that that we do. You know I
think that would be incredible. I you
know I I just I don't think people want
to use animals and and I think that we
really try to do everything we can
before we get to that point but I think
it's more the burden of data to overcome
that hurdle to convince you know the
regulators and ourselves as the end
users or or loved ones etc to to use it
that
>> and is industry looking at MIT to sort
of help fill the critical path in some
way?
>> Absolutely. Hey, I I think that the you
know I'm not going to add to what an NGO
said. I think it's fantastic. I think
the regulators are also thinking about
the modularity of these things. So the
idea that
>> maybe for a single drug you'll have to
do certain kinds of animal studies, but
then if you just replace the mRNA, would
you have to do all of that work again?
And so this idea that we can then
version you know for the computer
scientists in the audience version
control these drugs and then take
advantage to reduce the burden of animal
models in the aggregate I think is
another area that uh where we we can
exploit and you know again uh MIT is not
just the tech part or the
entrepreneurship it's it has strong
binds into the regulatory agencies as
well because they all do work through
kind of the logic and education that we
all use. So, how can we make that
happen?
>> We we have more questions on the list,
but we have run out of time. So, I'm
sure our speakers would be happy to uh
address any questions that you have at
the break, but please join me in
thanking them again for a great panel.