Hi, my name is Jen Barbara. I'm a part
of the admissions team at MIT Sloan.
When candidates apply to the Master of
Business Analytics program, we're
looking through your applications to see
evidence not only of academic strength,
especially from relevant coursework like
linear algebra, mathematics, computer
programming classes, but we're also
looking for leadership skills and
ability to collaborate with others.
We're interested in seeing the things
that you get involved with while a
student during undergrad, this the
clubs, the organizations, the
competitions that you've been a part of.
We're also looking at your past work
experiences. If you've had internships
or have been working full-time, that's
really important for us to see that
you've been able to demonstrate success
in a professional capacity. We're
interested especially in experiences you
have that relate to data science,
analytics or you know business in
general. Some of the candidates that
come to our program are also involved in
research and research assistant
positions. Uh we're certainly interested
in hearing about how you've partnered
with faculty members to produce cutting
edge research related to the field as
well.
The business analytics program is
differentiated from some of the other
programs that exist because of the
12month nature of the experience. You
have nine months of traditional
coursework that couples with a
seven-month capstone project, giving you
also 10 weeks of full-time experience
with a partner company during that final
summer semester. Students join this
program to learn from industry-leading
experts in optimization techniques and
advanced analytics and different
opportunities to partner with real world
problems that companies like Microsoft,
Nordstrom, Macy's all are facing each
day.
[Music]