hello as the last element in our
discussion of musical representations I
want to talk about two different
fundamental ways that we can represent
musical
scores TimeWise and partwise and these
really matter in anything that has more
than one note or more than one independ
part going s once and I want to
acknowledge I'm going to be using slides
from a presentation called notation as
composition by William Andrew burnson
creator of the B bage notation
package one of the ways that we can look
at musical notes is as musical scores is
as a series of containers so that we can
think of uh and part based containers so
we have a score and within that score as
the first element we have two parts in
this case and within those parts we have
measures and we might even go further
and think that within those measures we
have voices but first when we think
about dividing a score into parts let's
say it's you know the score of um a
massive three-hour Opera well you start
with you whatever's at the top of the
piccolo or something like that and you
go with the piccolo part from measure
one all the way to the end of the three
hours then you go to the second part
probably the flute and you go all the
way from one to the end and so on and so
you have everything in one part from the
beginning to the end and it makes it
very easy to do the kinds of analysis
that look at what happens in the
part the other principal way of looking
at musical notation representation is
you have a score and within that you
have all the things that happen at a
certain moment so that be getting you
know you might say well there's all the
clubs and if it's a 10 bar score you
might have trouble trouble trouble
trouble trouble Alto base base Bas base
Bas so on and then you have all the time
signature key signatures all the time
signatures and then every note
everything that happens at the beginning
of the
piece and then you have everything that
happens at the next instant the next
time that something happens here
and in this particular case when we get
to the third instant um which is the E
quarter note in the base and then the c
u the C eighth note in the E there there
is something that's happening in the top
part that that g half note that is not
represented in that instant but is
thought to be continuing from before and
in the next instant the there was just a
an eighth note with nothing else
happening and so this makes it very nice
to see what's happening at every attack
and you might be able to
programmatically go back and see what's
happening at every instant but it makes
it very hard instead to figure out
what's happening from one uh beginning
of the score to the
End by the way we call these instance uh
instance or uh offset moments or you
know cuts through hierarchies generally
speaking but often we Cally call these
salami slices in the process of creating
these things salami
slicing it's just kind of something
that's come out in music 21 we call this
process codification and so you'll see
the cify happens a lot so which is
better part-based containers or time
based
containers each of these formats has
their own POS positive things and
drawbacks as I said part-based
containers make it very easy for us to
follow an entire part from beginning to
end an entire line from beginning to end
time based containers let us see what
chords are happening in a certain moment
but very hard to follow
Melody but each of them has certain uh
certain difficult to encode things for
instance in alia staff uh a staff where
something uh optional is happening or or
you can do this instead of something
else what part is that in how do you
encode that uh do you put a part with
hidden measures all the way up to this
moment and hidden measures all the way
to the end and how do we indicate that
the player could do this so this is
something that's very hard to encode
when we do part-based representations so
instead let's move to time based
representations because it doesn't have
this they don't have this problem but
instead they have other problems where
do we put these Grace notes uh in you
know in in encoding like this especially
when you know we know that not all five
of those Grace notes come after that
last let's assum it's trouble in base
Club after that last B of the sub tuplet
within the triplet you know where do we
go how do we encode Grace notes do they
attach to the note next to them or or
what and both of the representations
have maj problems when we want to look
at things that involve horizontal and
vertical at the same time things like
voice leading here's a common uh voice
leading error in uh in sort of very
strict traditional uh harmonic writing
where we have um and we have a overlap
where the low G crosses the boundary
established by the B before and goes up
to the C above it which form format
makes this possible to see if you're
just look at each part alone you see
okay there's a b going to an E then we
get to the next part there's a g going
to a c but you don't see that the G
Going to the C overlap the B going to an
e on the other hand if we look at it in
time based we have a g and a b and we
look at that then the next part we see
there's a c and an e but it's hard to
tell well did the G go to the C did the
G go to the E did the you what what
happened how's the voice leading happen
so these are the problems in musical
representations and we'll quite often
find that we have to convert from
part-based representation to time based
representation and back or in the case
of a voice leading moment we have to
keep both the part and the time based
representations in in our head in the
musical memory in the representation at
the same time in order to find these
things I find these problems really cool
and hope you guys do too and solving
them is is another one of the great
choice of this class