okay good
morning so we started talking about
systems with chemical
reactions and
we just go quickly over what we have
done so far
we set we consider the two uh uh most
representative setups the closed
system up here and the uh open system uh
uh
setup for which of course when we
analyze uh we have to make uh at least
the energy and the entropy balance and
sometimes also uh here also the volume
balance
and these balances take these
forms where these differences between
properties of the uh products and the
reactants energy entropy here the
enthalpies because we have bulk flow
interactions
are uh
important and they have U the
feature that we need
to um
we need to deal with the fact that the
composition changes now because uh as
the process proceeds we have a chemical
reaction in place one or more chemical
reactions in
place we introduced the notation for
stochiometry and the proportionality
relations and we defined the properties
of reaction as a way
to concentrate
the part of the change in the properties
that has to do with the change in
composition in this last term where we
um have the product of the reaction
coordinate and what we called uh the
property of reaction for example this is
the energy of reaction the enthalpy of
reaction but in the same way we can
Define also the entropy that gives free
energy and the volume of the
reaction and remember that if uh the not
here means standard pressure so one
atmosphere um the not here without the
temperature dependence means also
standard temperature so STP
means uh this a standard temperature 25
degre C and one
atmosphere it
may seem that we have to measure
properties of reaction for every
reaction that we have to deal with but
fortunately that's not necessary all we
need to do is to measure the properties
of reaction for what we will Define as
the
uh reactions of
formation these properties of reaction
for example this is a reaction of
formation from molecular hydrogen which
is the most stable uh species for
hydrogen in um at STP and uh it's the
formation from that to
Atomic hydrogen which is not which is
also an elemental species but it's not
uh the most stable and in order to go
from here to there we have to break this
hydrogen
bond and that requires energy and this
is why uh we the the curve that
represents the equilibrium state for
hydrogen even at zero
temperature uh is above the curve that
represents the um molecular hydrogen uh
States and at zero temperature this
difference is precisely what we call uh
the bond
energy instead what we call the property
of
reaction doesn't refer to zero
temperature it refers to standard
temperature T
not so it is the difference between that
property in this case the enthalpy if we
go vertical wise or the entropy if you
go horizontal Wise from the difference
in the uh enthalpy or entropy between
this state and that
state okay so this represents
graphically the enthalpy of reaction and
the entropy of
reaction we ended the last lecture by
with this graph that wants to point
out that even the bond energies can be
described somehow as by means of the
Leonard Jones potential that is a
possible reasonable uh model perhaps not
the best but uh it it is simple enough
that one can use
it
and the values those of the parameters
the lender John
parameters for U Atomic
bonds Bond
energies Bond energies are uh at least
three orders of magnet itude stronger
than the Vander vales forces they're all
electrostatic forces
but the ones that you need in order to
uh form this Bond uh are much stronger
not only they occur at closer
distances you see this is a point seven
Armstrong uh with respect to uh the
the bottom of the Vander
vals uh forces which is at about 3 point
something angstrom
for for the liquid um for example this
is liquid
water and also notice that yes I have
plotted this but in order to make it
visible I had to multiply it by a factor
of a thousand otherwise it would be
almost flat as compared to the strength
of the
uh Atomic bonds calent
bonds
okay
now the properties of
reaction as we have seen at zero
temperature are
um
related to the bond
energies so for example if I take this
is the reaction of
formation of water of two molecules of
water from two molecules of hydrogen of
molecular hydrogen and one molecule of
oxygen in order to go from this
configuration to this configuration you
have to
break these two hydrogen bonds and the
oxygen Bond and then reassemble in this
other way
at the end in this other way in the in
two water molecules you have four
times and oxygen hydrogen
bond okay four
times the strength of these bonds are
listed are plotted are measured you find
tables that provide uh this strength and
also the
typical distance between
atoms between the nuclei in these bonds
for example the blue one is the hydrogen
it's the closest it's
74 Peters that's 74
an
uh the oxygen is
here and in the middle we have the hydro
nen and oxygen
Bond and in fact in fact if you take the
uh the the the depth so the strength of
these
potentials so the epsilons for the
lender
jnes for these bonds and you do the
simple counting of what's the difference
between having four of these ones four
of these ones that are worth 459
as compared to two of these ones the
hydrogen that are uh 432 and one oxygen
495 uh you you find that um the differen
is is is in in favor of of these one so
these are more stable they are less
uh the strong erly bound
strong more strongly bound and um and
this number which is by the accounting
of the the bonds is very close to the
enthalpy of formation of two moles of
water the
difference stays mostly in the fact that
whereas the bonds are computed at zero
Kelvin the enthalpies of formation are
listed at standard temperature and
pressure so you have to correct in going
from here to
here for the specific Heats uh from zero
uh temperature to uh
298k and if you do that correction you
get closer to this
number so in a sense this is to say that
the Leonard Jones representation
is not bad for uh giving a first look at
what
uh this properties of formation and at
least the enthalpy of formation comes
comes in comes comes
from
now this slide wants
to describe what's behind the S relation
and these properties of uh formation so
it turns out that we um we don't need to
measure all the properties of of
reactions but only those of uh uh
formation from a set uh which is
complete enough that uh so we Define a a
complete set of
independent chemical species from which
uh you can construct any other molecule
so these are like the building blocks of
chemical compounds and uh typically they
are called the elemental
species in order to Define this set you
need to to to request two conditions the
first is that yes every
molecule uh must
be uh every so you you you you construct
any chemical species and you have to be
able to construct it from these
Elemental species according to a
chemical reaction of formation which is
this
one now in our
notation where we put um everything on
the left hand side with the plus
stochiometric coefficient for the
products and with a
negative stomri coefficient for the um
reactants this is the way uh we would uh
uh write our
reaction but you could also write it
this other
way and formally this will be useful in
one step below the other condition that
you want to impose is that they uh the
set of these species be independent from
one another so that uh it is impossible
to convert one into the other or several
into the other rather that condition is
written by saying that if it if you ever
write a chemical reaction that involves
only Elemental
species that reaction has to be
identically uh trivial so zero all the
tetric coefficients must be zero
otherwise it would be possible to
transform gold I mean lead in Gold not
like instead of chemistry you do alchemy
um so the Practical choice is to select
um practical and conventional choices to
select as Elemental the species that
have only one type of nucleos example
the oxygen Mo molecule has two nuclei
but they are of the same kind so only
one
kind and plus since you uh you know that
um for example oxygen you you you can
find in several uh uh molecular
configuration like Atomic
oxygen uh the ion uh or ozone O3 and O2
okay you pick the one that is more
stable at standard uh condition so uh
you so you so in this way case for
oxygen you take
O2 and that turn turns out that you have
to select one species for each atomic
number in the periodic table I'm sure
you remember the periodic table uh and Z
is the number of protons in the nucleus
of the
atom um the actual
um the
Isotopes which has to do with the number
of neutrons that are in the um um
nucleus of the atom don't count for
chemistry because chemistry is mostly uh
uh was responsible for chemical
reactions is is the Electrical
uh the electrons and the protons and not
the the weight of the uh of the
nucleus which is instead important for
nuclear
reactions and of course
I I think you can proceed in a similar
way also if you are interested in
nuclear reaction so you want to apply
this same kind of
reasoning uh to the properties of
formation of
nuclei you would have to Define um a set
of complete and
independent uh
nucleons and typically you would choose
the proton the the neutron and the
electron and uh what
else I don't know maybe quarks are
different
level uh anyway so
um so then for this reaction of form so
you select your um your compound and you
find the stochiometric coefficients in
terms of that are needed in order to
construct your compound from the
elemental species these are the alphas
and then you write down the uh according
to our rule so the summation of the
stochiometric coefficients
times
the properties of the pure components
that appear in the reaction at
STP and this gives you the rea the
property of reaction and this is that
since it's the reaction of formation we
call it the property of formation of
your compound
I okay now it turns out and this is the
the good
um practical aspect of this uh
Choice it turns out that you can
safely arbitrarily
select a reference
value for
the property ATP of the elemental
species and since it's arbitrary now in
other words it will not uh it will
cancel out your calculations in
chemistry you can set you can select any
number so the the simplest is to select
equal to
zero why
so well
because H in your chemical problems
you'll have to deal with chemical
reactions that have this generic form
equal to Z so 0 equals the stochiometric
coefficients times the chemical
compounds now each chemical compound
like here can be obtained from the
elemental species so we can formally
substitute this formula here for the
compound in here and we
get a chemical
reaction that
involves only the elemental
species by the condition of Independence
that requires that these
um set of stochiometric coefficients be
all identically equal to
zero this is more or less the formal
um expression of what you do when
you uh fix these tetric coefficients in
the
reaction you balance the reaction by
putting the proper stomri coefficient i
s all right that's what you're searching
for
[Music]
um the new sais that
satisfy that solve this
equation
okay so now if since we're interested in
general in this kind of
reaction the property of that reaction
for example the energy of of reaction
for that reaction is given is defined
this
way if you substitute this expression
here because you see here we
have
uh this pure component energies at
STP for your substances for your
substances that appear in your reaction
and you can write them in terms of the
properties of formation and these are
uh summation that you take on the other
side so this is the
substitution and then you bring the
summation in and you you find that this
second
contribution has uh as
coefficients that are identically zero
for the reason that we just mentioned
before so this
summation cancels the way and therefore
you find that the property of real
reaction is equal to the weighted sum on
the stric coefficients of your reaction
of the properties of formation of your
of the of the various components that
appear in your reaction this is called
the S
relation and the fact that these things
are multiplied by zero allows you to
select any their value
being not important so
so you con conventionally select those
equal to zero and
also you could safely select that
the STP value for the pure components
are equal to their uh properties of
formation like we do here setting this
equal to
zero there is another
minor uh but dangerous complication
dangerous if you forget about it in your
calculations that most of the tables of
uh since much of this has been developed
when people dealt with combustion
problems and the products of combustion
are in uh in the gous
phase in Practical
applications
um in
people are
listing the values of formation of the
species when they are in the gaseous
phase but many species for example
water at standard conditions is not in
the gas phase because at 25 degrees C
and one atmosphere water is liquid yet
in the table you find the property of
formation of water
in the fictitious gaseous state so
what's that okay that is an sort of an
extrapolation of water vapor from the
range of states in which it behaves as
an ideal gas for which you know uh the
properties for example the specific
Heats at constant uh pressure as a and
you know them as a function of
temperature you they are given by
correlations we'll see some in a moment
and and what you do is to
extrapolate those uh properties down to
standard conditions as if that substance
kept behaving as ideal gas down to those
STP and that's how you compute this
from this temperature T where it behaves
as an ideal
gas down to to here and also for entropy
you just apply the the laws of ideal gas
and extrapolate down to
STP okay so these are
details now when you
compute ah yeah these
tables give values for the enthalpies of
formation of number of
compounds from which you can cook up all
sorts of chemical
reactions uh
for example we we're interested in U
combustion of
methane or the combustion of iso
octane ISO octane is sort of close to
gasoline and methane is natural gas the
main component in natural gas so these
are important for energy
uh applications as you
know so in order to right this
uh this is the uh the representation of
the complete
combustion uh so the simplest model for
for oxidation of the fuel complete
oxidation of the
fuel and uh so the stochiometric
coefficients are minus one minus two +
one plus two then you pick from this
table the vales of values of the
enthalpies of of formation so for
example you look for CH4 which is
methane is some here minus
74.9 so that's where where you get this
number the uh ele the elemental
species have no Rea no value for the
property of formation zero for them so
you can recognize them here they these
are the elemental
species hydrogen nitrogen molecular
oxygen so so you get zero then you have
CO2 so you look for
CO2 which is uh here minus 390
393.7 and then you get water which is
here at the bottom
242 and you can
calculate
this these numbers are in mega per kilom
or you or say kilj per mole and if you
divide by the molecular
weight for methane is 16 you get U this
number negative 50 megga per
kilogram for
isotine it's a much higher molecular
weight so mole wise it's a much higher
um um
um enthalpy of
reaction uh that's because you have many
more bonds to break per
molecule but if you divide by the
molecular weight you get a number which
is of the same very close same order of
magnitude as this one and actually this
turns out to be true for all
hydrocarbons yeah I don't I thought I
had it in the next slide we don't just
will come up in a
moment okay
uh so
negative means that the reaction is
exothermic and we'll we will see now
what the sign of these properties imply
in
determining the
direction of
spontaneous uh evolution of the reaction
so let's
take the steady state reactor set
up and let's assume that we
want H the reaction to occur at constant
temperature and and pressure meaning
that the inlet uh flows and the outlet
flows are going to be kept at the same
temperature and pressure
and this is going to be done with the
heat
interaction at some temperature
TQ for this moment for this
slide this temperature of the reservoir
is not necessarily the same
temperature of the inlet and at which
you want the reactor to
operate okay we
do our energy balance and our entropy
balance
bance we combine them
by
eliminating uh Q
Dot and here's the outcome it gives the
entropy production by IR reversibility
multiplied by TQ the temperature of the
heat Source or say heat bath or heat
reservoir termal reservoir whatever you
want to call it uh is equal to
minus Epsilon dot which is the
reaction
rate the rate of the reaction
coordinate times this combination of the
enthalpy and the entropy of
reaction which looks like the same kind
of combination that we have
in uh available energy or actually
exergy if you look back into when we did
a review of exergies in bu flow uh the
difference in enthalpy minus the
temperature of the res times the
difference in uh the entropies between
Inlet and outlet that is the exergy of
your
flows so this is the
exergy related to the exergy difference
between the products and the
reactants with respect to that uh
Reservoir at temperature
TQ now when Epsilon
dot is
positive the reaction is forward it
means that uh
uh it it is it's proceeding into
producing products consuming
reactants
okay so this the fact that of course
entropy cannot
cannot be destroyed so uh that this has
to have a always positive sign if it has
to really
occur gives you a a Criterion to decide
whether the reaction will be forward or
backward at that temperature because you
want if you want it forward you you need
Epsilon dot to be
positive so in order if that that's
positive in order for this to be
positive you need that you need this
linear combination to be uh
negative so in this table you can
summarize the possibilities so if uh if
you want that to be
positive and you want it to be positive
at
all combinations you certainly make you
could make sure that this that the
enthalpy of reaction is negative so that
is an exothermic reaction
and
also that this term doesn't influence
the sign of the overall linear
combination so you want so certainly if
the entropy of reaction is positive
you're safe because this also gives a
negative contribution you're also safe
if it is negative but not too
negative okay because this will this
with the minor sign in front if it is
negative it would be positive it
eventually could um could cancel out the
negativeness of the enthalpy uh and so
you could you could reverse uh the fact
which happens uh if if this uh is not
satisfied or actually if this is
satisfied okay so you see these
properties of reaction gives you the key
to understand whether uh uh the reaction
will go in the direction you want
because typically
you you you bother uh constructing
reactors because you want to uh have a
consume some products in order some
reactants in order to produce some
products that you
want now
if we repeat the same
but with the same
temperature as uh so so the the heat
bath or the thermal Reservoir has the
same temperature at which the reaction
occurs so when you have your reaction
for example placed in a calorimeter or
in a
thermostat uh so it's a thermostated
reaction at constant pressure
again and this pressure is the the
atmospheric pressure again your balance
equations it's exactly like before only
the T Q now is becoming equal to T and
then this
makes this linear
combination is the Gibs free energy of
reaction because H minus
TS is the Gibs free
energy so this is uh
why we typically say that the reaction
occurs in the direction of of uh
negative uh gives free energy yes you
need uh the GES free energy of reaction
to be negative in order to the Epsilon
dot to be uh
positive
however this depends on temperature
because the GS free energy is a function
of
temperature and in actually uh in the
next slide we will prove this relation
here that the the way the gift free
energy changes in temperature is this
way is related to the enthalpy of the
reaction so the rate of uh change of the
G free energy divided by
RT with respect to temperature
is equal to the enthalpy of reaction
divided by RT
s this is the that
relation and that is the proof the proof
comes from an old friend of ours which
is this relation that gives the enthalpy
in terms of the chemical potential for
the pure substance the chemical
potential is gives free energy if you go
back in your notes you find this
relation and if you put it inside here
uh out
comes this
thing this
plot has here it plots
versus this is not temperature it's it's
one over T it's a 1/ t scale so actually
the scale is here is 10 4 over t
so it's a one / T
scale which is precisely the thing we
respect with doing the
derivative and uh this axis instead
shows Delta G over T over
RT
it's the yeah there is the the logarithm
of of 10 because this is done on
a this is the log of
nerian log instead of log of 10 but
apart from this
Factor
uh this shows the dependence of Delta G
/ T versus 1 /t it's almost
linear and the this these
slopes the slopes are represented by the
negative of the
um of
the enthalpy of
reaction so for the exothermic reaction
this is positive so you see these ones
ones that go up are the exothermic
reaction for example co+
one2 is CO2 or water is here H2 plus
half O2 is H2O and so on
and you see that uh so if this is
uh positive because the relation that we
proved the previous slide was that the
entropy produced by
reversibility uh divided by uh the
reaction
rate so if this is positive that is also
positive you need this number to be
positive so from here
up you have all uh product favored
reactions but for
each uh reaction for even the uh that of
formation of of water if you go
sufficiently high in
temperature and as I go down in high in
temperature means one overt goes down so
if I go down here eventually I will find
the temperature
for water is of the order of what maybe
5,000 uh
K it becomes negative so it becomes uh
reactant
favored so water dissociates instead of
okay and the same is for True for
CO2 CO2 also dissociates at higher
temperature high
temperatures
okay this of course is important because
if combustion we do uh it's true that
the oxidation of a fuel produces CO2 and
water but if you are very high in
temperature like in an adiabatic flame
setup like the one we will consider at
the moment uh the temperatures are so
high
that U the reaction that uh that CO2 and
even water a little part
dissociates and of course if it
dissociates it consumes some some energy
in order to break those bonds that are
particularly stable
another
setup that is important is precisely the
adiabatic setup in which we have a
reactor uh which is insulated so no heat
no work interaction just uh just the
reaction itself makes things
happen and this time of course you
cannot have the same uh temperature uh
of the outlet so in the outlet you'll
have a different temperature of the
products and we call it t add for
adiabatic of
course you have to write an energy
balance and the energy balance this time
will be simply that
the the net of the enthalpy coming
coming in with this bulk flow must be
equal to the enthalpy going out with the
Outlet bu
flow so this must be equal to so this
gives you one
relation that allows you to solve for
the diabatic
temperature ad diabatic product
temperature and once you solve for that
you go into the entropy
balance and that uh allows you to
compute this difference
and you can write this uh s do
irreversible one way
is to write it this uh
way
um I don't I yes here it is
um yeah you you essentially uh add a
zero you add the entropy balance I sorry
the energy balance which is zero so you
can add it it doesn't change the entropy
balance and you multiply the uh entropy
balance by T so that it becomes uh
dimensionally an
energy and then what what you get you
can split the outcome as two parts one
is our familiar Gibs free energy of
reaction term multiplied by the Epsilon
Dot
and these other uh terms are essentially
they're written here are essentially the
in the difference in the exergy of your
products at this
temperature from the reactant I'm sorry
sorry take it back uh it's the
difference between the exer that the
products have have at this
temperature you see this is still p
uh and the
um and that they have a temperature uh
of the
reactants so it's a difference between t
add and
T of
the xergy of your
products and so so you see if you
want the reaction to occur in that
direction you need Delta G to be
negative but it must be negative enough
to overcome this xergy
here and this
xergy is what will be uh you could um
deploy uh in application for example
in if this is high temperature you could
use it to
run the heat exchanger of of a thermal
cycle to produce electricity and so
on we will do the calculation for for
fuels
um again another setup is the exergy
kind of
discussion
here we still we use a TQ as a different
temperature as the temperature at which
you want your reaction to
occur and you assume also that this I
shouldn't really call it a reactor but
it's a reactor that is going to be part
of some more complex system that
contains also Machinery thermal Cycles
whatever you want in order to produce
some work so this is like a a box which
could be a power
plant that takes
in reactants produces your products it
could be a materials processing
plant that Tak in raw materials and
produces your uh material you you desire
to con
to to
manufacture okay now in some cases you
do right usual the energy and entropy
balance and you compute now the
work so the
work in some cases depending on the
conditions and the values of these
properties of
reaction sometimes you can do
work and the maximum work you can do is
given by
this and if you have entropy produced by
reversibility that will detract from the
maximum you can do so your actual work
will be less than the maximum because
there is a minus sign
here
sometimes you cannot extract work but
you actually need to spend work in order
to make that uh
occur this is the
minimum work you need to
spend and if you have irreversibility
that will detract and it will now this
sign becomes plus and it will add up to
the minimum so you will have you in
practice will you spend more work than
the minimum
requirement
okay so let's do something more specific
specific
about the oxidation of hydro
carbons In This Very
simplified view in which we consider the
overall basic uh reaction mechanism of
complete oxidation of the hydrocarbon as
if uh there were only that one which is
not
true but in this simplified view you
already can do a lot of uh interesting
uh considerations and
calculations first of
all you notice
that the mechanism involves involves the
fuel
hydrocarbon K is the number of
carbon nuclei in the molecule and L is
the number of
hydrogen uh nuclei in the
molecule you need oxygen
and the two main products of are CO2 and
water and that's the balanced
uh stochiometric
coefficients
typically when you burn a fuel like this
you don't do it in pure oxygen although
you could do oxy
combustion but you do it in you you use
air as an
oxidant and so um
oxygen is only one is going to be only
one of the uh components in the mixture
of your
oxidant the mole fraction of oxygen in
air is about
21% so if you want one mole of oxygen to
to to be available for your fuel you
need
um these divided by so one over these is
like
477 moles of
air and that therefore the
stochiometric amount that you need since
for one mole of of fuel you need K plus
L4 l l over four molecules of oxygen
that means 4.77 times this uh of air so
this gives the stochiometric
air fuel ratio the S stands for stoom
metric and if
you are more interested in weight uh
fractions this is the air to fuel
ratio Mass wise you have to multiply by
the molecular weight of air and divide
by the molecular weight of the fuel
also if you need to completely burn your
fuel you want to make sure that if you
have combustion
application uh
[Music]
the you don't leave unburned unburnt
hydrocarbons
around so for example you think of if
you think of a combustion chamber in the
internal combustion engine
yeah it's loaded with
fuel uh and you have the molecules of
fuel spread around in the combustion
chamber and if your air is just a sto
stochiometric
amount uh chances are that the last
molecule of fuel will be on one side and
last molecule of oxygen on the other
side and they will not encounter so you
you you miss that uh uh and So you
you're going to have some unburnt fuel
so for this reason you provide extra air
extra oxygen you provide some excess
air so the the actual fuel air ratio
that you use is U more than the
stochiometric amount and the ratio of
what you actually put over the stoom
matric is called equivalence
ratio we talked about the heating values
of fuels being in the range more or less
in the range and now hopefully yeah okay
here is the
list for the various
hydrocarbons
with um molecular weights that range
from two of hydrogen to 16 of uh methane
114 of iso Octane and
up and you see that the uh enthalpy of
reaction Except for hydrogen which is
much higher or for carbon which is lower
in terms of megga per kilogram the
others are all in the range between 40
this one but between 44 and 48 more or
less 50 for methane
and also you could compute the uh
entropies notice that the
entropy um of
reaction of
combustion uh is not does not
necessarily have to have a positive sign
some for some fuels it's
negative what's important for the
application and you have already used it
in in your homework is that the
difference
between the enthalpy and the Gibs free
energy is small percent wise percentage
wise in terms of the Gibs free
energy which is related to the exergy of
of the
fuel uh you see that this ratio is
between plus and
minus uh 2.4%
so this allows you for for for simple
calculations to neglect the difference
and say that the exergy of the fuel
which is the G three energy minus the G
three energy is uh almost equal to the
uh lower heating value of the fuel which
is the
enthalpy these other
table provides more specific uh values
for
uh heating
values and also the air fuel
stomatic uh ratios for some practical
fuels and introduces to the idea that uh
uh heating values with as you
know if you if you buy a a burner for
your house
you have to deal with
the salesperson that gives you
efficiencies and sometime most most of
the times the deficiencies are based on
the U lower heating
value but nowadays they are send they're
selling uh a lot of
condensing
burners where they exploit also uh the
uh heat of condensation of the water
that is in the products of
combustion and therefore the proper
reference for computing efficiencies
there would be like the higher heating
value sometimes they play with this
difference because that difference can
be large for example for natural
gas it's about
10% which is not an
unimportant
amount so
why where does that difference come from
so we have to distinguish between lower
and higher heating values and uh and we
have to therefore consider how much of
the water that is present in the
products of
combustion
uh condenses
now the setup here is the setup of
U Raul's
law we are at pressure
p we
have uh water vapor plus let's call it
uh two
um the other products of
combustion and water vapor is the one
that can condense that can that
condenses at least part of it at a given
temperature and of course we
have dealt with this problem and we uh
we Pro the routs law that the routs law
tells you what is the uh amount of water
vapor that is in the gases phase when
there is
equilibrium with a liquid phase
and there cannot be
more water vapor here so that amount
given by the RS law is the
maximum that can be uh dissolved or or
dissolved in the gaseous phase
uh if you have less in instead less that
than that amount then there is no
condensation it's like for a it's like
for today today we have rain so that
means that moist a has more water than
it can uh uh stay there and therefore we
got we get it drops condensates and then
we get
rain uh on a dry uh drier uh
day there is less water vapor and it's
below the threshold for
condensation so this is all in this
expression here where of course it's R's
law with uh the mole fraction in the
liquid phase equal to one because we
assume that this liquid phase is just
pure water not salt to dissolve the
other things
okay all right so ral's law gives us the
maximum so the actual amount is called
the relative the Rel I mean the the
actual amount divided by the maximum is
called the relative
humidity relative to the maximum that
you can uh
dissolve and the saturation uh pressure
is that of pure water and at the
standard temperature 25 C that pressure
is about 3 17
atmospheres so you see that uh you
by taking the pressure down here so you
can this is about three atmospheres
divided by
101 which is atmospheric pressure this
ratio is equal to the maximum so the
maximum this instead of Y 1 s should be
one
gmax uh
is uh
3% so out of out of 100 moles of stuff
in the product of combustion at most
three can be water
molecules if you have more your
combustion reaction produces more water
then the extra will uh condense
so if you do the inventory for
water this is the amount produced by the
your reaction in your reaction yeah so
in the products that's the
amount some of it remains in the gaseous
phase some of it goes into the liquid
phase it
condenses and the stochiometry tells you
that per unit amount of fuel the amount
of water produced is L over2 so this L
over2 will be split into partly
condensed and partly um water
vapor the mole
fraction in the water
vapor is defined as the amount of water
that is remained in the vapor phase
divided by the the overall amount in the
vapor phase and so the overall amount is
the overall products of
combustion minus the water that is
condensed so it went away from the the
gases phas so this is the m fraction and
the total amount is given by this sto
sto so if you combine all
that you get uh that the maximum amount
of uh water that uh can stay in the
gases phase is limited by this
combination of the Ln case that describe
how many carbons and hydrogens you have
in the fuel
molecule and when you have condensation
which happens when L over K is greater
than
04 this is the amount that
condenses okay so if that amount condens
it
releases the
enthalpy of vaporization of
water and that enters into your
balance
equation and so the the the
heat that you need to uh
when you compute when you compute uh the
the heating value at standard uh
temperature you're actually making a a
an experiment in which you have your
reactants
gone come in at the
STP produce your products and you need
to put some uh uh heat
out at temperature t no
so as to cool the products down again to
this temperature here so that's the
setup in which you measure this
value
and and this is the entropy balance I'm
sorry the energy balance that is that
defines per unit so the amount of heat
that you have to extract per unit of
amount of fuel that you have uh burnt in
that um experimental setup is the
heating the the actual heating
value and part of it is equal to the
negative of the enthalpy of
reaction and part of
it is due to the um condens
condensation um
enthalpy
okay so if you do the calculation for
example for
methane the value is in megga per
kilogram
54.7 if you neglect this
condensation it's only
50.1 and the Other Extreme is if you
want to have a even quicker calculation
and forget about
uh um the amount of water that remains
in the gaseous phase and assume that
everything every single molecule of
water that has been produced condenses
then you put l over2 here and you get
what is called the higher heating
volume uh it's
55.5 okay so there is heating value and
heating values and they actual the lower
if you neglect condensation and the
higher is you a bit overestimate
condensation
so this reactor that we uh just
considered it's represented again here
and in this
setup with this
setup we can consider
three possible cases the one is the
heating value the one that we just uh uh
did
in which there is no
work and you set the outlet temperature
of the few of the products uh to be uh
standard like the
inlet in this setup that
defines U the combination that um from
which you measure the heating
value the exergy setup the exergy of the
fuel is what one in which again you have
the products out at um atmospheric um
or standard
temperature but your reactor has some
system inside that allows you to extract
work and actually does it
reversibly okay so if you do it
reversibly so you set uh
[Music]
um you in order to obtain the maximum
work you set the entropy produced by
reversibility equal to zero in your
entropy balance and the outcome is this
one and the exergy of the
fuel turns out to be equal to the
negative of the Gibs free energy at
STP and notice that in this calculation
see while here you only have the
enthalpy difference and in the enthalpy
difference then you need to account for
condensation here you have the enthalpy
difference but also the entropy
difference and they are multiplied by
the temperature T not so one brings
in the enthalpy of vaporization the
other brings in the entropy vaporization
and they are related to one another
this uh for a pure substance you have
this identity that
hfg is equal to T
sfg at every temperature because of the
condition of mutual equilibrium between
the liquid and the vapor so these two
contributions cancel
out so this Delta G negative does not
have contributions from condensation
so ex the condensation doesn't play a
role in the exergy of the
fuel uh if you want what I'm neglecting
here uh
is the
mixing uh
entropy terms that are here depending on
how you put in your fuels certainly the
air has is a mixture of oxygen and
nitrogen sometimes you put in your fuel
like premixed so
you you mix the fuel with with with the
air so you have a mixture and in the
entropy balance you should consider the
mixing terms and then also the products
of combustion is a mixture and so you
have entropy term so somehow these are
approximations in which we are
neglecting mixing
entropies the final setup of this is one
in which you compute the adiabatic flame
temperature no heat no works just a
adiabatic insulated
reactor in which uh you just have this
combustion reaction occur
the energy
balance is this one now the enalia of
the products has to be computed at
temperature uh t t add T
adiabatic we can add and
subtract the enthalpy of the products
standard temperature so that this
difference here is the same that appears
here in this other setup and we have
already computed it it's the heating
value times Epsilon Dot and this is just
this sensible heat that is sensible yeah
heat that is required to heat up the
products uh from standard to adiabatic
flame temperature and you can compute
that by simply using the properties of
an ideal gas um you can actually start
even from
um standard temperature even if even for
water because because in the heating
value which is on that part you assume
that water is in the fictitious
gaseous state so you can use those
correlations for specific Heats and
integrate of course this gives you an
equation in which t u uh adiabatic is
the only unknown
and you can solve for
it once you find
it you can put it in the entropy balance
also in the entropy balance which is
this one entropy of the
outlet uh is greater than that of the
inlet and the difference is the entropy
produced by irreversibility you can add
and subtract the uh entropy of the
products at standard conditions and uh
and uh so this last difference is is
equal to the entropy of the
reaction times the reaction
coordinate and this initial difference
is the uh you can obtain by integrating
the formulas for an ideal gas
mixture when you do this kind of
calculations and least we have a couple
of tables that show these
numbers uh later
on you you compute the entropy of this
typical
values are in the range between 26 and
30% of the negative of the G en so of so
if you take T not and put it on the
other side T not Time s reversible is
the waste of
exergy destruction is the uh the source
of inefficiency of your system and that
is equal to uh is is equal to about 26
30% of the exergy of the fuel so that
means
that uh by burning your fuel in a steady
in a in a reactor like
this you
wasting about 25 to 30 % of the
availability of the fuel without having
consumed one
single unit of
energy okay and this is the if you
remember the reason why uh I told you
that U if we
ever will follow history and uh we'll
have power plants or production of
electricity that will exceed our current
65% of the best available
technology uh we will have to find
alternatives to burning fuels this way
in diabatic
Flames because we need to overcome this
25% loss
of
efficiency of potential
efficiency now have you seen in the
previous uh slide we need to do those
integrals to compute the enthalpy and
the U uh entropy the difference for the
product of combustion between the
standard and adiabatic flame
temperature one way to do that
calculation uh this is just a detail but
you can this you can find correlations
for the specific Heats of the various
substances and one
way one correlation that is given in in
the book and from which I
have extracted some of these
numbers uh this kind of correlation is
is is able to cover um with a single
correlation uh the range from standard
to
5,000k with very good approximation
otherwise uh in um typical software uh
they use uh they split the range with
a with a a correlation that holds
between standard that say 25 C and say a
10000 K and another correlation from a
th000 so you have to split the integral
into two
parts the the thing that was uh into
these integrals here you see it's the
summation of the specific Heats of the
various
products weighted on the their mole
fractions in the uh product uh stream
and also for the entropy is the same
thing only divided by T so you need to
compute this and with that kind of
correlation you can do it simply because
by using a correlation of a
similar um fractional powers of the
temperature with the coefficients that
awaited some of the individual
coefficients of the various molecules
which to take from this uh and then also
the integral of this fractional powers
of temperature can be
done explicitly so here's the result of
this integral that's the result of that
integral and so that is the actual
expression that then you will have to
solve
uh uh numerically in order to obtain the
diotic flame temperature from the energy
balance I am mentioning these details
because I'm not going to go uh over
other details but in the past I have
developed this Excel file that I
will share with you on the on canvas
just in case uh in the future you'll
have to maybe teach a course like this
and you may have your students play with
these equations this
a several sheets it allows you to
compute to use all the equations that we
have seen it allows you to compute for
example the enthalpies versus entropy
diagram uh
for reactant and
products it uh can allow you to ID
identify
uh uh for example in this case the
temperature I assume the reactants are
at
700k and to compute the adiabatic flame
temperature uh so the temperature of
this other state for the products so you
can play with this if you
like of
course we left it alone but uh
we are not always working with the
steady uh or steady state flow
reactors uh often like in an internal
combustion engine or in bombs uh not
necessarily used for Wars you use bombs
also to measure in the lab uh like the
heating power of fuels or the
um uh flame propagation rate
uh uh
so you have a close system set
up and you can perform exactly the same
uh reasoning that we have done so you
the only difference is that you have to
perform a volume
balance and if you can assume that both
the initial and
final states are in the gases phase the
ideal gas law gives you the volume
and then if the volume remains constant
like VP equals VR then you find that the
ratio of the final temperature over the
final pressure is equal to the
initial uh
ratio but there is also the ratio of NP
over
NR so for example for the heating value
you could measure a heating value at
constant volume
you would have no heat exchange you
would have a I'm sorry no work
exchange and you would have a heat
exchange enough to bring your products
down to the environmental temperature
but you have to accept that since it's a
closed volume setup the final pressure
will not go down to uh
um to atmospheric and it will be a
pressure
P that determined by the ideal gas law
is determined by this
thing okay so if you do
the the energy
balance you get the heating value and
the heating
value this time in this setup is equal
not to the enthalpy but the internal
energy of
combustion
plus uh the amount of uh energy that is
involved in condensation and I presume
that here I should change this into an A
U that's the internal energy of uh
condensation of of condensation and not
the enthalpy
or if you consider an adiabatic setup
like a a true bomb set up where there is
no work no
heat this is the final pressure in terms
of the final
temperature and you compute the the
final temperature by again the energy
balance these times the only difference
is that is instead of the uh specific
Heats at constant pressure since the
energy uh for a gas depends on the
specific Heats at constant volume it's
the CV that you have to integrate
here and uh you can then compute the
pressure once you have the temperature
you can compute the pressure from here
and then you can compute the entropy
produced by reversibility with the
entropy balance and you find that this
time the uh loss of
uh uh the exergy distruction so the loss
of efficiency is a bit
smaller well why well
because because you are left with
products that are in a container and are
a very high pressure and that high
pressure has some availability you could
use it to expand and therefore to make
work so that is a s of transformed
uh part of the exergy of the fuel into
that and that's
why these are the numbers so here are
numbers for a
closed combustion
chamber
temperatures are very
high and pressures of the order of 10
atmospheres
and here that ratio is indeed in the
range that I said for the steady state
uh flow
burner the ad batic flame temperatures
are
lower and the uh
irreversibility is
higher actually these calculations
are done not using simply the reaction
of oxidation of the
fuel but they're also using uh the other
two reactions that of dissociation of
CO2 and of H2O because those two react
are important at high temperatures and
are also energy uh intensive in the
sense that they consume up some of the
energy released by the combustion
ruction and therefore they
are important otherwise you if you
neglect those you would get uh even
higher values for the temperatures here
and in the Excel file you'll find uh
that some of the sheets you you you're
neglecting this uh uh dissoci this
dissociation of CO2 and H2O and some
other sheets you find them that those
are the ones what
that where you also compute the
equilibrium because we the moment we
haven't done yet the next time we'll
talk about chemical equilibrium and
those reactions are assumed to be in
chemical equilibrium at these
temperatures so let's uh
summarize for the
closed uh system set
up what we have seen
in this energy versus entropy uh
diagram uh this is the curve that
represents the stable equilibrium states
of the
reactants and this is the one that
represents those of the
products T not is this slope here which
touches the reactant at this point so
these are uh the reactant
mixture so it would be your
fuel including the air that you're using
to oxidize the fuel at 25 C1 atmosphere
it's in this state
here and these are the
products of
reaction after you cool them down at
standard condition
is
okay so the difference in
energy between this and that is this
blue
arrows that's the
energy of
reaction and the difference in the
entropies this Black Arrow here is the
entropy of the
reaction and
again some
sometimes this point will be to the left
of that one sometimes it for other fuels
it will be on the right there's no
fundamental reason why it should be left
or
right
okay we start with the products I mean
so with the reactants
at um
STP and we run
[Music]
our
adiabatic constant
energy
combustion adiabatic flame temperature
set up so the energy remains constant
and in the final State we end up
here with this state with the
temperature which is represented by this
slope Which is higher
okay now talking about exit I mean yes
available energies so let me call omega
as we did in the initial part of the
course Omega the available energy with
respect to a res so the not up there
means with respect to a reservoir at
standard
temperature so in any in any place of
this diagram which uh you remember any
point we can
compute uh the energy and the entropy uh
this
is
uh the expression for the available
energy energy minus the energy uh when
the system is in mutual equilibrium with
the
Reser but now we have two options
here one is with the off case
no
reactions so for no
reactions the composition cannot change
and so our reference State the the so
the the reactants are in mutual
equilibrium with our uh Reservoir at
this state
here so this is the state with energy u0
R and s0 R so it's here
If instead we allow the chemical
reactions then
our the mutual
equilibrium will with the reservoir uh
will be this one the most stable is when
the product when the the products uh
have
occurred the reactions are have allowed
to go to a more stable uh Mutual
equilibrium which is this one the state
at t0 of the products so I can
compute of course this state has zero
availability with respect to the off
situation but with respect to the to the
on situation so with the
reactions it has an availability which
is given by this blue uh line here so
that's the available energy of the uh
Inlet State we respect to the uh Outlet
state so to
speak when I do the the the flame the
diabatic combustion I end up with this
state
here and it's availability it's
available energy you remember the
construction you have to go down here
geometrically until you you reach the
line that has the slope of the temper
tempure of the reservoir so this is the
blue this is the U available energy it's
less than in initial and uh uh what's
what's
missing is the amount of is related to
the amount of entropy that you generated
by reversibility if you look at this
triangle this angle this tangent is
t0 and so this uh
side of the triangle is equal to t0
times this length which is s
irreversible
okay
okay now sometimes well first
observation here is that U these two
curves um approach each other as you go
ey in uh in
temperature so if we could have the
combustion occur
uh by preheating our U reactants at a
higher temperature for example T t1r
here when I do the
oxidation the adiabatic flame I produce
less entropy by reversibility and
therefore I consume less
exg that increases the efficiency so
preheating the reactants is a way to
improve the efficiency of course
preheating requires some some
availability some available energy this
much and this is the available energy of
the heated reactants with respect to the
reactants themselves we so this I'm
using the
off expression for the available
energy and then when I have obtained
these products
of course at a higher
temperature see T1
Prime uh they have this much uh uh
available
energy and even if I pay off what I
spent in order to do the
preheating I'm still gaining in terms of
the fact that if I of course if I do
things uh reversibly uh I have less
energy waste than exergy waste than in
the previous
case
and and the last observation is the
following that okay well could we keep
preheating and so get uh closer and
closer this
concept has been um so the question is
is it
possible to
go to an extreme in which the two to
where these two curves one of the
reactants and the one of the products uh
touch each
other and they do at a certain
temperature
provided you do what you have to mix
some of the products with your
reactants in fact this is also done in
internal combustion engines it's called
ex exhaust gas
recirculation so you take some of the
gases and mix them with the uh reactant
mixture that makes these curves get
closer to one another and therefore
reduces the
irreversibility and increases the
efficiency of course if you do too
much is this mixing involves an entropy
of mixing so what you get
by getting these two curves closed you
lose uh in uh in the mixing entropy and
that's also an
irreversible these concepts of very
theoretical of course then they you know
Kenan uh has brought up this question in
41 also so
alert 1948 and then also
1973 and later on every 10 years or so
people uh go back to this one I haven't
been following so I don't know if the U
frequency of 10 years is still respected
but uh at least we we are talking about
it now
so
um we ourselves
you can you
can go to this reference uh and we
worked on some calculation and we
computed the amount of u water that you
have to
dissolve uh in uh this was combustion of
hydrogen and we wanted to look at what
dilution you should put in dilute your
products of combustion uh
which in this case is just water uh in
order for the temperature at which they
touch not to be too high because if it
is too high uh you see the problem here
is that you you want to do the
preheating and while you're
preheating uh you should uh be able to
contain the the reaction it should you
should freeze the
reaction and allow the reaction only so
so to speak turn it on only when you are
here then uh you turn it on and nothing
happens because you the the reactants
and products are in equilibrium but then
as you cool down the products you you go
down this curve so you you obtain uh
more then uh you obtain the exergy
essentially of of the fuel with respect
to this
one so in the preheating you spend this
exergy and in the uh cooling down of the
products you obtain this energy and the
difference is the exergy of of the fuel
uh but the problem in practice is that
as you go above a certain temperature
any uh mixture will have a self
combustion and autocombustion limit and
it will burn by
itself uh that's why uh we were looking
for a way to dilute enough so by
diluting you reduce the temperature at
which this happens and therefore you
have to go below the uh
self self combustion temperature and
here is this so for
example we could find that uh I think we
did like 1500 or maybe thousand this is
the amount of water molecules that you
have to put in
I don't think anybody has ever done this
kind of a uh thing uh
practically but conceptually it's uh
it's something to be kept in mind so I
think yes we can stop here today and uh
next time we do uh chemical
equilibrium okay