good morning everybody I'm Sam Madden
I'm one of the co-organizers of this
event although I know very little about
security or cryptography it's like you
know the extent of it is you know use a
strong password and uh you know keep
your keep your Linux installation
patched so um there you go that's my
security crypto talk for the day uh
anyway I'm very happy to be here to
introduce this event thank you for
coming uh this is a thing we've been
doing for the last 2 years to sort of
highlight cool things happening in
computer science in the College of
computing so today is uh security and
crypto day or crypto and security day I
don't know what is it called something
like that um anyway um we have a really
awesome series of talks uh a mix of
people from MIT and uh from outside uh
and a mix of students and faculty uh and
we're going to it off with uh one of our
esteemed faculty from MIT sh dadas who's
going to talk about um some of his work
on secure hardware and uh cryptography
and Hardware so thanks sh all right
thanks Sam um so Sam's now my boss so uh
you know make sure you clap a lot after
the talk maybe during that's fine too uh
uh oh
see uh awesome um yeah really excited to
be here um I want to tell you about work
that's been going on in my group and
Daniel Sanchez's group Daniel S Sanchez
is a computer architect I pretend to be
one um and the two of us um about three
years ago uh started thinking about um
Hardware acceleration for cryptography
and uh there's been a a few Papers
written um I want to mention Nicholas
amaric who was really the prime mover of
most of the work that uh I'm going to be
talking about today he's graduated uh
but Simon langosi who's one of my
students is sitting over there so uh
find him or me during the break uh if
you're interested in learning more um so
um let me parse the title for you um
designing hardware for protography I
mean that's kind of Fairly obvious uh I
mentioned that we were interested in
Hardware exploration uh it turns out you
can get uh lots of speedups if you're
willing to build um build a chip a
custom chip uh so I'll tell you about
that that's uh about the first half of
the talk uh and then the second part
which is a little bit more wague but you
know vague and exciting are kind of uh
synonyms um cryptography for Hardware so
as we went through this process we
started looking a little more deeply
into uh fully homomorphic encryption uh
schemes of the specifics of those
schemes um zkps which I'll get to also
in the talk and I started thinking about
how we could kind of massage if you will
initially uh these uh algorithms uh to
better
uh fit Hardware implementation and then
we started thinking about code design
and so um that's really why I wanted to
give this talk here to cryptographers uh
the second part of this to get a sense
of whether there was a kind of a
cooperation and a Synergy that uh could
be created uh between the design of
Hardware that uh
is that's tailored to cryptography and
the cryptographic algorithms themselves
um so um I want to briefly tell you
about a success story um that uh is a
hardware for crypto for Hardware success
story um and then I tell you about um
some work we did uh it started a couple
years ago on accelerating fully
homeomorphic encryption and designing
custom hardware for that um and uh then
move on to the second part of the talk
which um it turned out um was is more
closely related to uh zero knowledge
proofs
zkps um and accelerating those and then
talk about what's next and uh hopefully
uh we can have a robust discussion over
the break I'm happy to answer questions
you know if you raise your hand I'll uh
I'll stop in the middle especially
clarification questions uh uh but like
deep questions about um the specific of
algorithms well I don't know the answers
to that so ask Simon um when when uh
when we're done so uh what is the
success story what motivated us right
and very simple AES right so what
happened was um AES was invented ranell
you know decades ago and um it stood the
test of time um and then uh Intel and
other um Hardware manufacturers decided
that U encryption was a good idea um
people wanted fast encryption of memory
of dis and so on and so forth and so AES
got into the hardware and um there were
obviously specialized implementations
circuit implementations and smart cards
and uh microcontrollers and a whole lot
of different um uh pieces of Hardware
but uh I think the big um Advance was um
getting into x86 processors AES and I
was put into x86 processors and suddenly
um AES encryption and decryption was
blazingly fast um and um it was
initially put in there because AES was
used in TLS for for example um then what
happened was the cryptographers
discovered that when they were writing
software in um uh x86 uh on to run on
x86 machines um and generally writing
software that AES was actually faster
than um specialized and arguably simpler
algorithms like uh sudam number
generators uh prfs and U more advanced
things like U verifiable secret sharing
and so on and so forth so I'm teaching
this class with the alkai this past
semester um and we split the lecture
since she was doing the crypto I was
doing the security um lectures but
during the crypto lectures should
constantly um say prf oh think of it as
AES right or prg think of it as AES so
it really was something where the
cryptographers it was crypto uh uh
hardware for crypto right as opposed to
um uh just accelerating crypto it it
made a it made a difference into the way
in in the way cryptographers thought
about um implementing cryptographic
Primitives um and the reason for this at
which um I'll repeat um which I think
you've guessed at this point um is that
um while the prg algorithm perhaps in uh
in a simple processor would be faster
than AES um written in software the AES
Hardware just beats it um and so it's
much better to use AES from a
performance standpoint and if the proofs
go through or based on your assumptions
sure go for it so the question is now
that we have all this High polluting
cryptography that's really out there and
it's been amazing over the past decade
all of these things have kind of made it
into the real world you know well partly
because of blockchain and
cryptocurrencies uh but because of other
things as well um just cloud computing
uh the question is you know can we do
something like AES for more advanced
Primitives which is actually
intellectually I'd say more exciting
because these algorithms are so
sophisticated and they have so many
parts you know moving parts to them but
then it's also more challenging because
we got to pull out a primitive and then
convince the hardware people um to go
build it right because if you want to
get the speed ups that I'm going to talk
about uh you got to put it into a
silicon right you know kind of directly
into silicon um so I want to tell you
about U accelerating fully homeomorphic
encryption um work um that that we did
which we don't quite work on anymore but
you know that's because we're doing
better things right um so um FHA I mean
I don't know how much you know about FHA
I'll tell you what you need to know to
understand the rest of um the material
I'm going to cover but fully homomorphic
encryption is crypto magic right it's
essentially says you don't need to know
what you're Computing on as an untrusted
device and you can still do the work and
you produce an encrypted result that's
basically gobble be um and you end up
sending it back and the person who sent
you this encrypted data uh now decodes
the result deciphers the result decrypts
it and uh they get what they wanted you
know they figure out how much money they
owe the IRS or they figure out you know
hopefully they don't have this horrible
disease or what have you um so um you
take X you encrypt it you send it over
to the server server runs for a while
actually a long time um and and then you
get back encrypted FFX and then when you
decrypt it you're often running right
and so the this is the Holy Grail of
secure Computing because the trusted
Computing base um at least from a
privacy standpoint is zero there there's
no trust and there's an Integrity issue
here which uh we probably won't get to
in this talk um but um that's something
that potentially could be fixed with
zkps um so that's perfect security so um
I want to tell you a little bit about
FHA because we're going to try to
accelerate it and um the current fhe
schemes um are based on the Assumption
of learning with errors and um lwe and
ring lwe uh and essentially what happens
is you have um a bunch of um PL Tex so
those are the M's and in order to get
efficiency you pack these um PL Texs and
they usually 8 bit value so you have
something large and you you break it up
and then you you you pack it up again um
and so n could be 16,000 okay so that's
a a good number to think about so you
have um essentially vectors of plain Tex
values you add a little bit of noise to
them um and so uh and then you uh
encrypt it using your secret key and
this part we're not actually going to
talk about because this is on the client
side and we're concerned with
accelerating the encrypted computation
right so so you end up getting this
cybertext polinomial um which um now is
is because of the encryption is the
giant polinomial where n is 16,000 and
then the coefficients are th bits right
so now you're multiplying these numbers
and you're going oh my God I mean this
you know what bit turned into into a
million bits and that's kind of the
downside of it I mean it's slow as a
snail right um it's uh it it's crypto
magic but it's it's super slow um now um
the operations that you perform um are
uh essentially things that would
obviously mimic and follow the plain
text world and um when you think about a
vector um uh addition and uh um and uh
Vector uh uh scalar multiplication
they're pretty straightforward right so
they kind of mimic the the plain text
world but when you actually want to
multiply to PL text um it's a much more
complicated algorithm and it's fairly
complex in terms of the cipher text
world so you end up doing things with
pairs of um cyberx polinomial and so you
have the cyberx polinomial which is a
pair for x and you have y and now in
let's say in the plain text world uh you
want to multiply X and Y right um and so
you end up having to do polinomial
multiplications uh many of them um and
um additions to get XY here and this
would in this is now in the encrypted
world and then on top of that you have
these key switch hints that are many
megabytes that uh give you efficiency so
these things you know were not uh what
Gentry U put up you know in 2009 when he
invented the first FHA algorithm over
the years these algorithms because of
efficiency they do the packing they do
the cipher Tex you know polinomial the
numbers are security parameters n has to
be large there's all these other
parameters uh that uh need to fit
exactly right and so we haven't really
done anything with that we just take
what uh cryptographers tell us to secure
um at this point at least in in in the
stock and we try to go and and uh build
hardware for it uh the point is um
there's a lot of data here Cipher Tex
are you know kind of a million times
larger than PL Tex and um you are
messing around around with these cext
not in sort of a linear streaming
fashion but you're doing convolutions on
them you're doing effectively the
equivalent of ffts on them NTTS number
theoretic transforms and this is
basically what the the most painful
operation would be uh this XY well it's
actually the second most painful
operation I'll get to the most painful
one uh a little bit later so you can do
X Plus Y and you can do XY therefore you
can do encrypted computation um and um
you uh can do additions fairly easily um
uh XY is much harder and then the other
bad thing about multiplication is this
noise thing that I talked about is going
to explode with multiplication and so uh
that's is another problem right so we'll
get to that so um as as you saw we often
need to multiply polinomial and um this
is kind of literally great school stuff
which is U for year transforms um the
number theory has the NTTS number
theoretic transforms uh similar than fft
and and um you can do it in N log n
versus n square right so I mean there's
no way you can handle n Square huge um
uh uh difference to n log n so everyone
uses
NTTS um so the other thing that um we
have to U exploit here is uh residue
number um systems in residue um
arithmetic um and that really comes down
to you have these coefficients that are
a thousand bits right no one builds
thousand bit multipliers right it's just
not tenable you know this hasn't been a
thousand bit multiplier parallel
multiplier built ever um so um RNs is
absolutely critical um in um being able
to do uh this arithmetic and so
essentially what happens is you have um
a bunch of um little um 32-bit primes
let's say um and there's L of these and
then you take these thousand bits and
you break them up into let's say 30
32-bit numbers and then you're running
all of these things in parallel right so
you got yet another um um uh uh
Dimension here um and so uh that's our
primitive data type and so you think
about this thousand bit number and for
from a cryptographic standpoint or from
an algorithmic standpoint you just say
oh there's
L there's an L Vector here or vector of
length L and all of that is happening of
course there's another Vector associated
with the polinomial uh y y y so all of
this stuff you now have to kind of
orchestrate and the biggest issue here
is data movement you got a th000 bits
you got 16,000 coefficients you got a
pairs of these polinomial you got to
move the stuff onto the chip these
things are megabytes uh you know if you
do it right you know it'd be fast if you
do it wrong takes forever right um so um
but the nice thing is that we can get
away with 32-bit multipliers okay which
is huge um so um I want to give you a
sense of um what we can exploit and
what's hard right and I gave you a
little bit of a sense of what's hard so
um I will say that what we want to build
here is an F interpreter right we're not
interested in doing you know machine
learning with FHA or or doing your taxes
with FHA we want to accelerate um
encrypted computation in broadly
speaking so the input is a circuit which
is what you want to compute in the
unencrypted world except of course now
everything is encrypted and you also
have the inputs uh that correspond to
the the input to the Circuit that uh you
wanted to compute and then you want to
get the output out so there's two things
going on so think of it as an
interpreter and we want to accelerate
The Interpreter right so um most
previous um FHA accelerators pick
something specific like a neural network
or something and accelerated that but
now if the circuit itself is is an input
um that's uh it's something where um you
have to obviously get a programmable
accelerator right um and so I mentioned
the big polinomial arithmetic I
mentioned the mega gabt so data movement
is is really where it's at right you
know computation sure I mean CPUs have
arithmetic units to gpus have arithm
units to what is that Asic going to do
for you what is the specialized ship
going to do for you well basically the
same thing but the movement that goes
into these um arithmetic units uh the
multipliers and so on that it could be
orders of magnitude multiple orders of
magnitude slower um on a CPU versus um
if you orchestrated it exactly right and
everything is static because I mean you
don't know squat of what you're doing
it's it's all encrypted so you don't
know what's underneath so therefore you
have to take the if Branch you got to
take the then Branch you got to have
fixed iteration Loops all of that so you
exploit that to the hilt um so the the
other part about FH which is kind of the
the last you know messy part of it um is
that this noise thing right you know
this you're going to keep adding noise
especially after you multiply and
essentially what this means is that
resolution goes down so you have th000
bits and it gets chopped down to 900
bits after to multiply you roughly
speaking um and then you know it goes
down and down and eventually you're
going to run out of bits which means
that you've lost functionality right um
and so um what happens when the
coefficient vid goes to zero well I mean
you know happens um you better not
go there so you got to stop um and um
one way which is you know what that FH
schemes got to um evolve initially there
were these schemes called leveled fhe
schemes right and leveled FHA schemes
essentially said um let's go ahead and
um when we're running out of room when
our coefficients are getting too small
let's bail uh let's essentially go you
know uh mommy you know let's go back to
the client um and then get them to um uh
essentially um decrypt and and
re-encrypt right so you go back and
forth back and forth because the only
person who knows the key is the client
right so that's those are these leveled
FHA schemes and um uh you know this
works um it's obviously many rounds of
communication and the larger the depth
of your circuit uh the more the rounds
of communication uh in terms of
multipliers uh the more the rounds right
so so we ended up saying let's do an
acceleration of a leveled FH scheme you
know back three years ago and um this
was an architecture specialized for fhe
and as I mentioned um this was a
programmable uh interpreted architecture
that could do um any computation as long
as the uh it was limited depth right um
and so you know I'm not going to bore
you with the details of this papers have
been written and you can read it uh you
can read them um if you want but
generally um we had Hardware tailored to
FHA operations and um the orchestration
of the data movement which I have a
compelling example of a little bit later
um was was really the the key with
respect to getting speedups and the
speedups were enormous now I will say um
this is a a a design that uh was built
as a hardware description language and
and um uh there are efforts by Intel for
example um to uh build silicon um uh
using roughly you know and I'm not
taking credit but roughly this type of
architecture uh and there startup
companies but and the reason they're um
actually building Hardware is because
you can get three four orders of
magnitude right I joke that we've taken
the snail and turned it into a tortoise
right you know it's not quite you know a
hair yet because you still have a few
more orders of magnitude to go um with
respect to the overhead of computation
but you know three orders of magnitude
uh you know ain't um
um well I mean it's it's not bad right
um it's it's it's pretty good um so you
can now do things that you could do
before if you had this Hardware um and
the big issue really um as we got
through the first part of the talk um or
the first part of this um this research
effort was uh you know this level f is
sort of not particularly satisfying um
and you had this communication cost and
um this large communication cost was
really going to slow things down if you
wanted to do interesting things right
like deep neural Nets um and um so
people invented bootstrapping um in the
F the FHA um researchers and it's an
expensive uh procedure to refresh Cipher
Tex and this is even more complicated
this procedure than multiplication
obviously or the the key switching and
uses that and the idea is that when
before you run out of room you
effectively do you have a uh you do a a
decryption and and re-encryption in the
in the encrypted world it's really you
know magical I don't understand it um
and you go back and forth you have the
saw to thing where you get down to let's
say 200 bits and then you rise rise up
again to 1,000 bits and uh so on and so
forth um and so um as uh we have to um
in the even in the level of H you do
have to U perform computation at
multiple bitwidth and you want to
exploit that so uh the nice thing is
that RNs allows you to exploit that
because you can have fewer 32bit um uh
multiplies you know when you have a
coefficient that's lay 500 bits versus
the th000 bits right so you want to
exploit that because there's there's a
large Factor there and you don't want to
leave um any speed up on the table so um
some observations um communication is
really hard to Accel because um the uh
network cards and the hardware for
switches and routers are very hard to
change you know they have to conform to
standards and uh the physical layer is
very hard to accelerate um you know it
still takes the same amount of time you
know to get across the internet from uh
here to
California than it did U as as it did um
you know 10 years ago obviously
computers have gotten more parallel and
faster um and the other part of it with
respect to computation which I want to
stress is is uh uh is om doll's law
that's Gene omdal um who uh you know
said something that's really you know
it's common sense and my interpretation
of it would be let's say that you had
you wanted to get
um a huge speed up of 100x well what
that means is you can't even ignore 1%
of the computation because if you didn't
speed up 1% of the computation then
you're limited to to to 100x if you
didn't speed up 2% of the computation
you're limited to a 50x speed up right
so um when uh you design Hardware
accelerators and you want a,x speed up
it basically says you got to accelerate
everything um you know you can't ignore
anything right there's no bottl LS I
mean everything is a bottl l okay um and
so if you look at bootstrap versus
leveled FH um and I'll tell you about
this second uh processor um uh at least
a little bit that that we designed um
you you compare them and you say with
bootstrap fhe it's very complicated
there's a lot of computation but very
little communication in leveled FH it's
it's it's the other way around so uh
Hardware acceleration can give you this
picture right it it basically crushes
the computation down through uh this
Asic design and doesn't touch the
communication and so if you had a deep
circuit you absolutely need to um
accelerate bootstrapping right so that
was kind of obvious to us as soon as
we've kind of finished the F1 project um
and and so then we move to um uh
thinking about how to accelerate
bootstrapping with which was um and then
re red I mean this was designed too so
we changed our minds about a bunch of
stuff and so this is a vector processor
that's a very wide Vector processor and
then uh in order to store everything uh
on the chip you know and this is a big
chip by the way it's it's think of it as
a multi-core processor um and uh but
these Cipher Tex and these polinomial
were all stored on the chip um and so um
they the scratch P single level register
file is 256 megabytes new functional
units and I want to tell you about this
data movement and give you a an
algorithmic um uh Innovation uh that was
due to Nicolas saric associated with
this the pipelining of all of these
operations that I've told you about
namely the polinomial multiplies and the
key switching and so on and so forth
right so um you have this Vector data
path that's 2048 I mean this is just 16
here of uh but um it gives you an idea
and you can chunk these things um uh so
if you have 16,000 remember and you only
have 20 48 you do have to chunk there
and so this is just a simpler example
where you have to do some chunking and
in Hardware um if you have a data path
data path that's 20 48 Lanes wide Vector
ads and multiplies that act coefficient
wise are easy because you can just sort
of pipe them across you can just sort of
have this Lane and you're just piping it
across right um so it's easy to pipeline
but NTS are convolutions and
automorphisms are transposes and
permutations so you're picking things
from all over the place right um and um
this is the reason why gpus and CPUs are
really slow right because they have to
do this one at a time right so there's
sort of this order end you know built in
to picking things out because not
because necessarily of you can you can
break that down with parallelism but the
movement that gets the data from the
output of one multiply to another um or
in these intermediate steps um is is
this uh
linear computation because you're doing
this you know pulling into the register
file going back and so on and so forth
um so um um you know it'd be it'd be
great if um you could do uh things a
little bit better and so here's a
pattern of uh data movement which is a
transpose and CPUs and gpus can do some
chunking but effectively think of it as
aoan it's the maybe the constant is is
is is is smaller than one uh but they're
not good at this right and here's
something that they're even worse at
right right so in FHA you have to do
something like for the exponents index *
3 more n okay and so now you have to do
that what I have here and this is aut n
on a CPU or a GPU right so um in CR Lake
um it turns out you can do this in
constant time right roughly constant
time and the reason for that is that um
is is Nicola's ideas on um you take uh
you want you have a two- dimensional
chip so you took that 16 vector and and
thought about it as a matrix um and now
now you U think of this as you want to
transpose this um or you want to do this
other automorphism on it and think of
this polinomial is spanning the whole
ship um and um basically there's a
two-level transpose operation which
corresponds to local transpose um and
then um um a a permutation and both of
these things are fixed permutations and
it turns out you can U take NTS or
automorphisms and decompose them
um into these transposes and each of
these transposes is two levels in the in
in the chip um and you with one per NTT
and two per automorphism you can
essentially do um the operations that
you need for the ckk scheme for example
right so suddenly now you went from um
order n to essentially order one for
this part of the computation right and
so you can imagine that uh and similar
things happened in F1 as well you can
imagine that that's where the speedups
came from right so it's not the
computation parallelism that that gave
you the speedups so that's really
essential because CPUs have that uh but
it's it's really the data movement that
gives you the the big wins um and so um
it's 5,000 times faster than a 32 core
uh processor so that's goes back to
saying that the parallelism W wasn't
where it was at with respect to the
speedups and you know does better than
F1 but here's the bad part of it you
know 20 million bucks anyone has 20
million bucks handy you know we'll build
it for you right but so Intel is
building one of these and there's a
startup company that uh in probably in
Shelt mode in in Europe that's that's
building one of these accelerators uh
but this is really kind of the rub of U
Hardware design which is great you know
you motivate people by getting these
large speedups no one's going to build
Hardware if you tell them that um it's
going to be five times 10 times faster
than uh the CPU it's just not worth it
but so you motivate them by getting
these types of speedups but then you got
to go build it and it takes years and
and so on and so forth right so but
that's life um so um that's the story so
you know this was about a year two years
ago and uh we don't work on this anymore
but uh it turns out uh you know the
people are continuing to work on it and
U Architects have follow-ups um uh on uh
on F1 and crat Lake and uh things are a
little bit better now uh with respect to
the size and um uh and the speed um but
I want to move to the second part of my
talk which is U really kind of looking
more closely I told you I didn't know
much about FHA we did this work anyway
we knew enough to do the work uh but you
know can we do better with in terms of
uh making this process um easier because
it's the hardware is easier to build uh
by tailoring algorithms themselves right
so uh um so verifiable computation kind
of the analog of U FHA I'm not going to
say very much um about um the spe the
specifics of this but the basic idea is
you want Integrity untrusted device um
you want to ensure that it's done the
computation correctly now zkps have this
additional privacy uh uh property that
says that um you have a witness and U
you you don't have to give that away um
um as U the the approver can um can keep
some secrets you know of from the from
the verifier um and so um but that's not
Central to anything that I'm going to
talk about right so think of this as the
Integrity analog of FH all right um and
so um same problem um super slow if you
run it um in uh uh on conventional
processors um and so Hardware
exploration would be nice right so
uh there's a whole bunch of VC schemes
right um there's a ton of them um and um
the basic idea is that um you want the
valuation of f to be um something that
you don't want to do for some reason uh
because it's going to get much slower
when you ask someone else to do it and
maybe it's because of the Privacy
requirement uh but it may be the case
that if the verification time is smaller
than the evaluation of F that you rather
someone else do it um and of course um
the the proving time is going to be uh
way um larger than the evaluation of f
itself and that's what we'd like to
address um I mentioned the zero
knowledge and so there's some scenarios
where the client can't execute F on its
own and so you want to be uh in that
situation because that motivates the
work right so there's a lot of
applications I don't want to get into
that uh the gro scheme is the most uh
popular and the most used scheme from
2016 um and um it's got tiny proof sizes
okay um it's basically three uh words or
Ian call it a kilobyte um it's a compute
bound algorithm um and and it uses
elliptic curves um and it turns out you
need
and this is something that you should
look at and go whoa whoa this is a
problem because I told you about
multipliers it needs 381 bit multipliers
nobody builds these right so um so there
was one uh piece of work U before um uh
the work I'm going to describe to you on
accelerating uh zkps and it was called
pipe ZK it published an architecture
conference and they got five to 10 times
speed up and I won't repeat what I said
about
um minuscule speedups you know not
motivating Hardware people uh I guess I
just repeated it but uh um but as you
can imagine you know this didn't go
anywhere uh because of U of of the the
small speed up you could use parallelism
and uh at maybe at higher level and get
this type of uh speed up um and so why
right and the main reason is this this
multiply and I'll tell you a little bit
more uh but um it turns out there's a
whole bunch of uh zkp um schemes out
there and and things growth is not kind
of could fit into this modular zkp
Paradigm but uh if you kind of jam it in
but in general if you look at the zkp
world there's iops and pcss uh so
interactive um um Oracle proofs and
polinomial commitment schemes and you
can kind of plug and play right you can
you can pick a an IOP and you can plug
it into this PCS or use a PCS for it and
and and and vice versa um and so
generally you you translate uh iops
translate things into polinomial
structure and then you commit to uh uh
to computation by committing to
polinomial um and so that's your zkp
right so the PCS Universe there curve
based things like Groth um hash based
things that uh that U have been around
for you know three or four years and
then there's Lattis based things that
are emerging so if we looked at all of
these things um and said okay from a
hardware standpoint you know what works
right you know what can we so some of it
is just choosing things right and then
there's actually you know massaging
things right so you'll see a little bit
of both of those um and so um I want to
contrast the uh the first two kinds the
curve-based PCS have downsides they have
tiny proof sizes uh but they have
complicated curve operations like in BLS
and um uh you end up having these large
multipliers and it turns out there's a
lot of data dependent control flow which
kind of goes against the grain with
respect to pipelining and not having uh
pipeline Bubbles and you know changing
your mind about what you want to do sort
of halfway through and which is a
problem in Hardware um hash based PCS is
take advantage of fast Hardware
operations I mean you know shot 3 right
you know have an array of shot 3s and
paraly to your heart's content um and um
you can also like play around with these
modulus moduli and and uh do things
right um You have tree and Matrix
structures that are easily paralyzable
but here's the downside proof sizes are
much larger we talking two three orders
of magnitude larger right but the nice
thing is that you go from kilobytes to
megabytes okay big difference from um
from going from megabytes to gigabytes
okay so constant factors this talk is a
lot about constant factors it out where
you are um uh in in terms of the kind of
the range of constant factors is a big
deal so kilobytes to megabytes is okay
megabytes to gigabytes is not okay okay
um so um so we looked at a bunch of
things and then we we zoomed in on
Spartan and Orion um and decided that
these map best to hardware and we've
kind of changed our minds about this but
this was about a year ago um and decided
to go go go with this right so um so now
let's look at um this it's a little bit
different from what I've showed you
before
but here we have Groth 16 and uh it
turns out Gro 16 is you know slightly
faster on a CPU than the spot in the ran
thing um and it also has less
communication right so you're kind of
going what um it's yeah but it turns out
uh because of what I told you about the
curves you can absolutely crush the spot
in Rion computation you know by 1,000x
if you did it right um and so in turns
out even from an end to end standpoint
uh even though you're paying more partly
because of the kilobytes megabytes and
and and existing networks which are you
know megabytes per second uh you can do
better right and I'll give you some
specific numbers but this is the basic
idea right so again a choice that's
perhaps counterintuitive because you
were worse in two fronts but when you
look at it in a different substrate uh
it it's actually the right thing to do
right um and so Spartan and Orion have a
a bunch of different things inside of
them uh sparse Matrix multiply some
check protocols polom arithmetic Merkle
trees reach solman codes and we got a
speed up all of them right uh because of
arm doll um and um it turns out um if
you um kind of look at a little bit you
know inside of it the Spartan IOP uses
essentially the spars sparse Matrix
vector and then Orion uses the other
ones the PCS scheme and um if you look
at um these low-level tasks uh there's U
basically a small number of functional
units which are listed here um that
correspond to running all of these
things and they're used in many
different uh task of Spartan and Orion
but that's kind of the mapping right um
and so now if you kind of look and you
say well you know these things take 2%
and you go oh you know in a different
world you 2% I don't care right you know
98 or 100 look looks pretty good but if
you want a,x well you got to speed up to
2% right there's there's no two things
about it um and so I just wanted to
point that out just more concretely than
I have uh previously um and so um so
this thing U no cap is a design of a
programmable acceler erator same thing
it you you have your circuit and the
circuit is an input and you also have
your inputs to your circuit um and it's
a a vector processor um that supports
Vector modular multiplication and
addition one of the things that's
interesting that I'll get back to is uh
in this hash based World it looks a lot
more like the fhe world not exactly than
the elliptic curve world would look like
the fhe world right so we were looking
at this and going oh we've kind of done
this before or something similar to this
before right um in uh looking at at our
thinking back on our work on F1 and Crea
Lake um it turns out for the tasks that
I mentioned the five tasks that The
Primitives that are underneath uh it
turns out uh you know they have
different uh requirements so uh uh you
end up you know wanting to have a very
wide Lane processor 2048 which is the
same as at cradle Lake um uh in when
when you want to do um um uh for example
Vector multiplication and addition but
when you do want to do hashing and NTS
uh you want something that's slightly uh
uh that's narrower um static control is
a big deal same thing I mean it's h you
you have to do things without
um knowing what you're working on it's
not quite the same as in the encrypted
world uh but um since you have to the
prover has to produce a proof it's
similar in that sense uh so you can do a
lot of pref freshing and scheduling um
data movement is important
so um these pictures are are pretty I
don't think they're going to um tell you
anything other than the fact that uh uh
you actually have two different modes of
operation um and the way you want to
think about this is that sometimes you
want to use 2048 parallelism and you
think about these things as all running
all these Square Banks uh uh and and U
processors running in parallel and
sometimes um you uh you're you're
running them in series in sort of you
know they go pipeline from left to right
uh in terms of 16 steps of computation
right so those are the kinds of things
that you'd have to do in order to uh uh
in order to Target the 2% and the 69% or
the 18% right so that's that's where
it's at so um I just want to give you a
sense of U you know one optimization
like I gave you for the U transpose unit
um that was important here uh let's take
a look at the sum check protocol which
is a large fraction of the time um it
turns out the things that you have to do
are you have an input n is large um and
it actually blows up to like something
like 20n or or whatever in this example
um I have 3n and so you're streaming
this input onto the Chip And this is not
going to fit in these register files and
as you're doing this you're Computing
you're reducing um this input and you're
Computing a hash for it right this is
kind of something that happens in the
sum check right you produce R1 you
reduce R1 then what you do is you're
going to try and uh this algorithm is
going to fold this so you actually have
to um uh um take this the 3n that you
computed and you got in the in the naive
algorithm um you're going to stream it
again um and now you're going to use R1
and you're going to fold this into
something that's 3 n / two by
multiplying the first half with R1 that
you computed in the first step and then
multiplying the second half by 1 minus
R1 and then you get an output that's 3n
/ two um and um you're going to reduce
as you're doing that you're going to
compute the R2 hash of the n over two
and then you're going to repeat this
process right so think of n as not
fitting on the chip but you know
something at half of n might fit on the
Chip And what you're working with
initially is maybe like 20 n or
something so you got many levels of this
right um and so um so now let's say um
you have R2 what happens now um well you
got to load um uh the 3 and over two
again because that doesn't fit on the
chip and you got to do this um folding
again and then you get down to 3 n over
four right so at some point you know
everything's going to work out because
everything fits on the chip but I want
to talk a little bit about um the
optimization that we made was that was
fairly important uh not you know super
dramatic that speeds up this part so
essentially it's recomputation it it's
like do the work
again uh uh uh because that allows you
to not store um uh more things right
because you can just generate on the fly
so not a obviously a paradigm that's
been used many times so assume you have
R1 and R2 then the idea is that once
you've gotten R1 and R2 in order to do
this previous thing which is getting the
3 and over four um you go back to the
original input stream that in expand it
on the Fly and then do this computation
right so essentially do pairs so nothing
uh profound here but important from a
data movement standpoint right so that's
why I wanted to point this out so
there's a whole bunch of things that I
won't Bor you with uh that correspond to
things like that I just wanted to give
you one evocative example example so um
in this simplified example you save
traffic you know maybe you get Factor
two um and recursively maybe it's more
right so this is super advantageous to
when the Su check size is large which is
usually the case so um this so we took
the oryan Spartan code Simon took this
code and sped It Up by water refractor
five so we're going to compare against
the sped up version on a CPU for
fairness and um uh you can get about
500x on the proof generation again if
you build this Hardware um but we've
been fairly careful about getting a
hardware description and and and doing
all of those things which are necessary
in the in the world of computer
architecture um I wanted to mention uh
this is just proof generation but um
going back to the trade-offs really it's
about sending the circuit over finding
the uh getting the prover to produce the
proof coming back verifying it well
there's Network Transit here right and
we can't ignore that right but if you
look at um the the proof sizes well it
turns out that you do pay sending a
kilobyte over the Internet is you know
it's not thousand times faster than
sending a megabyte over the Internet um
but you know maybe it's 10x faster right
um and so you you you call you assume
some Network link and um include that
ver uh latency in the verification time
and and you're still like you know 20
times faster so provided you had this
Hardware it's a good idea to go ahead
and go to larger proof sizes okay um and
so that's kind of uh the the the the
lesson we got we learn from it um still
it's a smaller ship than cred Lake but
hey someone has 10 million bucks right
lying around we'll build it for you
right um yeah go ahead
um the one time cost um so yes yes yes
uh so this is the capital cost I'm I'm
talking about the capital cost right um
after now if you now depending on volume
so you know that's a totally different
conversation it's a great question um I
I I I'll I'll give you a better answer
but the short answer um is what I'm
putting up is capital cost and then um
if you were going to sell a billion of
these you know there's a lot of people
who would give you that give you more
right in fact if you just yeah uh that's
right if you claimed you could sell a
billion of these you know um uh you
could do that right so I want to I want
to finish up telling you about um I
think a a level of co-design uh and and
hopefully Intrigue you with you know
thinking about these kinds of problems
uh that we're looking at that uh Simon
um myself Daniel and yupen Zang have
been looking at in terms of what's next
right um and I think uh ven's question
you know may get answered here a little
bit as well so um one of the things that
um helps with Hardware is uh number of
users who want to buy your chip as I
just mentioned to venod and um one of
the things that um that is nice about
the zkp accelerators and the FH
accelerators is this picture right um so
which is essentially that um You' got a
bunch of different schemes that kind of
have similar Primitives right and this
is kind of the game I mean AES Was A
Primitive right it's a very basic
primitive can we discover Primitives uh
that would be useful and then you get
the intels and the amds you go put these
Primitives in there and everyone's happy
right um so if you look at these
checkboxes um you they're well I mean
they're kind of uh similar in the first
three and and and um the the last one
which is the elliptic curves uh is is is
quite different right so this sort of
tells you that that maybe you know if
you want to go build a universal
cryptographic accelerator that you
should be thinking about hashes and and
maybe lates and not as much about
elliptic curves okay um so that's one
thought right you know which is you know
can we do something and we have some
thoughts on it um there's a distribut
distributed zkp world uh where you say
well let me build a chip to handle a
circuit of size s and that's a big chip
and therefore it's super expensive so
it's nonlinear if a chip is twice as
large it's going to cost you Capital
cost is going to cost you twice as much
right I mean even the volume cost would
be about twice as much but the capital
cost is really super linear um so um
pianist is a d zkp distributed zkp
placed on the plon IOP and it does
chunking to go take you know uh go run
stuff on Amazon clusters and so on and
so forth so this is just purely software
um uses a curve-based PCS so um Simon's
been looking at with upang looking at
replacing this U distributed zkp curve
based ZK
curve based PCS with hash based PCS and
it turns out um you um can imagine a
distributed architecture where you have
smaller chips but then you build a board
or a multi-chip module of these smaller
chips uh that may be a tenth of the size
and the big question is um when you go
off chip it's much slower so you don't
have that much bandwidth it also takes a
little bit longer so you have to
structure your algorithm such that the
communication across these things so
this is really going back and redesign
plonk a little bit with respect to the
chunking to essentially say things like
I'm only going to communicate hashes as
opposed to these NTS okay across these
uh chiplets which are much smaller and
so now you know it's much cheaper
because and maybe this is an academic
project where you build a little uh chip
um that is you know a tenth of the size
of this uh bigger one and then you build
a board uh you can get you know 10 of
these back obviously you need you need
10 of these and you build a board and it
only works if the algorithm is such is
structured in such a way that the
communication across these chiplets is
much smaller than the communication
that's required inside of the chiplet
right so that would be a codesign of the
algorithm which is you know kind of
ongoing and and we're happy to tell you
more um so yeah so that's it you know my
final thought is um is there you know
some notion of accelerat ability that
can guide cryptographers you know I've
given you a bunch of interesting you
know ideas hopefully intriguing ideas
but you know I haven't synthesized them
and and I did I promise to well maybe I
did but then I lied um but U um but I
haven't synthesized them into you know a
metric um that essentially takes in you
know the fact that you know going off
jip um uh uh is um is painful uh data
movement is where it's at you know
parallelism is easy uh pipelining is
easy but uh uh certain kinds of
pipelining are hard um and so you know
how would that change you know the way
if if a zkp expert you know uh and we
we're kind of trying to do that with
upang zkp expert you know went went up
from first principles and said I want to
build the optimal hardware and zkp
together right what would we come up
with right and so uh well hopefully U uh
you uh you're intrigued
thanks I had no idea a how long I
took okay right um awesome yeah happy to
take yeah
yeah forgive the 20 million or 10
million forgive okay that's a good word
for
yeah so so now how does how does um you
know how do the online cost ongoing cost
uh compared to doing this uh with an npg
for ah so yeah so
Daniel has um a a
board um that is looks like that um you
know and and each of those things are an
fpga the the the the little squares are
fpgas right he's got I I don't know what
it is so you're absolutely right um so
that's kind of so fbga have issues uh
you pay um a factor of 10 in speed
you're running at 100 mahz as opposed to
a gahz MH and um that that you
definitely pay um the other part that
you pay which is an additional factor is
the amount of stuff that you can put on
an fpga so in some sense you you got a
factor of 10 because of the circuit size
shrinking but you blew up by a factor of
10 because an fpga has lookup tables and
can't do it but that's okay because the
fpj has already been built right and so
you buy that but you know there are
thousands of dollars right so so you can
imagine building um you know big fbga
taking a big fbga and building a board
like this at a 3X3 board like this and
maybe doing this PL thing and now you
you're in good shape your Capital cost
is is in the thousands of doll I mean
tens of thousands of dollars as opposed
to the 20 million um there are some
challenges that are associated with you
know permutation networks um on fbga
unfortunately right so all the one
downside there probably other downsides
but the first thing that comes to mind
is you got these lookup tables and you
got you to structure this stuff um
exactly right right and um and and so
the permutation networks and all of
these things that I talked about they're
not that great on F fgas I mean you know
there's a lot of work that needs to be
done in order to make them um
competitive and you could I mean you
could imagine doing that work but it's a
it's a perfectly reasonable path to
follow and I think from an academic
standpoint I it's uh it's probably the
path to follow okay okay cool one more
question if I may so you know let's
again assume that the 20 million Is
Forgiven right what is the the marginal
cost of building each chip you know oh
um so um is it more like 10K I literally
what you do is you go to a tsmc and you
uh you you you say I want um you know a
billion of these or you want a million
of these MH and um depending on the
number you there's latency with respect
to when you actually get a run right so
that that might take you a while to get
the the chips back because you know they
have other customers and you know
they're filling their pipe too mhm and
um the other part of it is um is is the
is the cost uh and and so if you're
willing to commit you're probably you it
goes down for sure I mean it's I mean AR
AAL you know used to say you know a
million of of anything meaning a million
of any chip is a buck each right you
know that that's what he I mean he used
to say that right but I don't believe
him um but U but you know that's
reasonable I mean obviously I'm quoting
him so it but it's a Pity way of
describing that you know once you get to
volume the the actual ship cost it
really shrinks where you're not worried
about it y so I guess my question really
was about fpga versus A6
oh right so fpga the fpga they have it's
a little bit like gpus V know where you
know there's a there's a margin so if
you want to go buy a fga from xlinks or
gpus you're paying a lot so now if
you're willing to live with that you
know so there I think you know there's
an expansion Factor if you are the chip
designer you could get this Buck right
because you you you actually building it
now of course you're selling it for for
10 so there there's a markup there which
you know uh but I think that's certainly
not as bad as the capital cost okay
great thanks yeah go ahead um yeah
amazing talk so my question is about the
uh the hardware acceleration part so you
mentioned the main problem that is
arising it is because of the data
movement yes so if we were to design
some Hardware accelerators uh for some
uh for all these cryptographic
algorithms and we try to make sure that
this data movement is reduced by what I
mean that is like if you're feeding a
large bitstream into an accelerator I
would want that bitstream to be
processed within the accelerator without
sending it back and forth again and
again yes so can we think of like some
methods in which uh for example as you
mentioned like know like we cannot build
very large multipliers but like can we
think about like some Innovative schemes
in which we can do the multiplication
but without doing this back and forth
again and again I mean well you know
multiple are well researched right you
know so um so I can't imagine that that
well certainly I can't imagine myself
you know coming up with a with a with a
new multiply algorithm uh but I think
that at a level higher than that um is
where we're working right you know which
is which is sequences of multiple I and
um feeding the output of of one multiply
into another and and making sure that if
if it was on the chip and you're right
there you grab it and go right um but if
you needed to move it you know well even
uh to uh a different bank of registers
or a different scratch Pad uh you lost a
little bit and you the game is over um
and and you you you've lost if you have
to move it off chip right so um It's
Complicated enough um that you know I
don't have a handle on kind of this you
know this beautiful scheduling algorithm
um that would do it exactly right
because you know it's very constrained
and and the numbers are important
because you know how much you can store
spilling is bad as I mentioned um but
but that's kind of the the the Crux of
the matter I mean I think that you you
put your finger on exactly the um on
exactly the problem I I I don't a
general purpose algorithm to solve it I
think it's probably
you know feasible now the that algorithm
now is your cost model for this
accelerate ability metric that I
mentioned to you because you want to say
that assuming you had this beautiful
algorithm that would do the scheduling
properly um and then uh you know that
tells you what your cost of data
movement is and now your actual
cryptographic algorithm should use that
right you know as opposed to this order
and square it's like util a and square
it's going to come up with the wrong
thing you tell it that you give it a
better U uh uh metric it's going to come
up with the right actual overall design
right right that's a great Insight so
another related uh question to this is
why don't you go to Iran maybe yeah yeah
well venod got three questions you know
yeah but he's VOD yeah yeah right so
microphone
yeah right so and know some some
cryptographic
algorithms
um have a problem with side Channel
attacks yeah yeah and so are there any
issues with that and either the design
of the hardware or its use great great
question so in the FHA World um we
basically say you know side channels be
damned because um it's Cypher text and
you could you could see the cipher text
right so that's fine in the zkp world
it's it's nuanced because in on the
prover side you got to be a little bit
careful because there's a there's the ZK
part of it um which is the witness right
you know and so you you don't
necessarily want as you're doing it you
don't necessarily want to leak the
witness so um V honestly it's a great
question uh we kind of ignored it um we
and that's why I said don't worry about
the ZK part this is about the integrity
and so you have to kind of look at it a
little bit more carefully uh I think for
the designs that we have the fact that
it's static control the fact that
everything happens kind of the same
regardless of the bits is a huge help
right so that's pretty much all I have
for you right so yeah Iran had a
question yeah thank you well first uh uh
thank you for this talk clearly these
are exciting times for thep graphic
techniques for protecting General
computation and I think that this kind
of acceleration is essential for it to
have the uh to fulfill the Practical
promise um I have a question about um
handling uh faults um as as we know when
vsi design uh making sure that uh fals
fults have low enough probability is a
traditional uh design Criterion in Asic
design um but in some cases you may be
able to afford fults in which case you
can push your clock rate faster or have
more aggressive design roles and
potentially get a lot of
performance um now we know that in some
contexts uh when you have specific
algorithms like the ones for factoring
you can afford mistakes because you can
compensate for them at a higher
algorithmic level and I wonder if we are
looking at that pattern again here for
example in the case of U uh verifiable
computation you may be able to afford
occasional faults as long as you can
catch them through the very mechanism of
verifiable comp ation or in the case of
FH if defaults end up just increasing
the noise that you handle anyway they
may be absorbable have have you looked
at that no no we haven't looked at it
but I think I think um um I I want to
say that um aay josi has been looking at
things that maybe not exactly that but
you know you you you should check in
with
him um and he's he's written some nice
papers on U on um FH acceleration in
particular um um from he's at Buu for
those of you who who don't know him uh
but um yeah so um um I don't I I don't
think I have a great answer for you on
but I will say that um um in the in in
the context of um static control um it
is an exploitable uh mechanism to uh
fall tolerance is easier right in in
Fall tolerance is is really difficult
when particular faults um are much worse
than others um and but maybe they have
less lower probability and it's you know
kind of heterogeneous like that it it
becomes a much harder problem um in the
context of the designs that we have um
it's very homogeneous in the context in
in the sense of false right so it it's
going to be um well you know the
pipeline went through or not you know
and and um it's it's there's no data
dependent control flow um but um going I
think the other part that uh uh perhaps
uh um uh is the more more exciting is is
exploiting the uh well having F tolerant
algorithms themselves right you know
which is uh which I think is kind of a
little bit orthogonal to um to
accelerators in the sense that those
would be useful in the CPU as well uh
and the combination of that I'm hard to
think about but uh it's certainly
something that should be exploited for
sure right thanks all right time so
thanks for I think we have a bre now
thank you