And now let's talk about how is adipose
tissue [music] formed. Adapose tissue
contains progenitor cells or adipose
tissue stem cells that can differentiate
not only into adiposytes but also other
lineages including cartilage and bone. A
fraction of these cells then enter the
adypogenic commitment stage where it can
only become adiposytes and these are
what we call padiposytes.
Edipost tissue also contain other
precursor cells that can give rise
preferentially to beadosytes with
thermogenic capacity.
Finally, under the right conditions,
both white and beigosittes can convert
into each other.
Much of what we know about adiposite
differentiation and adipos tissue
formation comes from in vitro studies.
Here's an overview of these studies
where we start with a tissue biopsy
which is then digested to release
stromal progentor cells which we can
grow and expand in culture.
Over the years scientists have
identified the right conditions
which we can expose these cells that
will then lead to the progressive
differentiation into adiposytes.
At the mechanistic level, adipoy
differentiation is defined by key
transcription factors which will bind
DNA and drive gene expression programs
to support lipid storage and metabolism,
thermogenesis
and hormone synthesis and release.
While some of these have been studied in
great detail including master regulators
of adipocy differentiation which include
par gamma CBP alpha. Now modern biology
and updated pertubation methods suggests
that there's still much more to discover
and the right time to do it is now.
Now as we come to the conclusion of this
first lecture, it's important that we
discuss how can we harness adipos tissue
biology to improve metabolic disease
outcomes.
And the key overall idea is if we can
make more and healthier adiposytes, this
can have an enormously powerful effect
on metabolic health. So here are some
ideas of how we can think about uh uh
exploring adipos tissue biology to
improve metabolism. First we can think
of ways to promote healthy adipos tissue
expansion where we promote uh newer
adipocytes or uh hyperlasia versus
hypertrophy or making larger adiposytes
which as we discussed is linked to
metabolic diseases. We can also focus on
uh adipos tissue distribution by making
more subcutaneous adiposytes versus uh
abdominal or visceral adiposytes which
are also linked to metabolic problems.
We can think about uh ways to promote a
safe lipid storage where lipids are now
mainly uh contained in adipocytes to
prevent spill over to other tissues. And
finally, we can leverage thermogenic
properties of beige and brown adipocytes
to promote a state of positive energy
balance that will lead to higher uh
energy expenditure and metabolic
improvements. And here's how you can
contribute to this challenge. We'll take
a look at two key questions. What can
machine learn models learn from
perturbing adipocy transcription
factors? And can we get better at
predicting genetic perturbations that
will shift adiposytes into desired cell
states?
Well, hopefully this first lecture gave
you a great overview of the biology
needed to complete this challenge.
[music]
And next, we'll have Julie walk you
through the technology and the data
provided for this challenge.