Everyone, welcome. My name is Katherine
Ferrar and I'm have the privilege of
being on the admissions team here at
Sloan and oversee um our master business
analytics program, our master of
finance, and our MBA early offering in
addition to some of the other programs
that were touched on in that video. We
hope you enjoyed that. I think it's a
great way to share a little more about
the what you'll find here when you get
to Sloan and um the the community that
you'll find here as well. Um, but today
I'm going to be focusing um on our
Master Business Analytics program
specifically. Um, and as my colleague
shared in the chat, if you have
questions, please use the Q&A function
to submit those. We'll do our best to
try to get to all of them and we'll save
some time at the end to answer a few
live as well. Um, but with that, go on
to the next slide.
Um, so we first like to kick off uh
talking about our mission. Um, it's core
to everything we do here um at the Sloan
School. We are educating students to
fulfill this mission um which is to
develop principled innovative leaders
who improve the world and generate ideas
that advance management practice. Um
you'll find opportunities to build
skills within this um um within
aspirations of this mission through
different electives um that you take and
uh through different organizations and
student activities that you might become
a part of once you're a student here at
Sloan. And then um in addition, I like
to highlight too as you're thinking
about um you know this program and maybe
submitting an application, you know,
when you're writing uh your essays and
other pieces in the application, you
know, think about past experiences that
um you know, may have used pieces of
this mission um and how you've applied
it to what you've done to date um that
align with the goals of this mission.
So our portfolio programs, we also like
to share this slide too um to show that
you know you would be coming to the
master of business analytics program but
you're going to be exposed to students
in a variety of programs here at Sloan.
So we have um masters of finance as I
mentioned the MBA program, our leaders
of global operation program, our Sloan
fellows MBA, our executive MBA and our
master of science and management
studies. Um so you'll have an
opportunity to you know really build a
network and get exposure not just uh
folks who are going to be a part of the
masters of business analytics um but
take classes and um participate
extracurriculars with students across uh
the degree programs here at Sloan.
And so on this slide um I just like to
highlight this is a full-time program.
Um it's 12 months. Um it's a rigorous uh
um quantitative degree focused on
applying the tools of modern data
science to solve real world problems in
business and society. Um it's for
someone you know you don't necessarily
have to come from a STEM background, but
we do like to see that you have comfort
um with quantitative focuses. So have a
strong background in mathematics,
computer science, and statistics is
helpful. Um and I do um want to
highlight too that it's three semesters.
So you have fall, spring and summer uh
with this program.
So what is business analytics? Um for
those who are early in their research,
it's an approach to solving problems
that starts with data. You build models
and arrive at decisions that create
value for the organizations that you
will be in.
And again, um just highlighting it's a
full-time 12-month program. Um some ask
if it's part-time but at MIT we don't
offer part-time programs. Um so 12
months full-time and you again applying
uh tools of modern data science
optimization machine learning. Um this
program is also in close partnership
with MIT's operation research center um
which is a discipline of applying
advanced analytics methods such as
optimization, statistics, machine
learning and probability um to help make
better decisions that impact society and
the world positively. Again, tying back
to our mission. Um, and again, it's a
it's a rigorous curriculum in terms of
quantitative skills. Um, and so there's
a lot of different electives that you
can choose from that will spin out with
those and close ties to computer science
and electrical engineering at MIT as
well.
And I'll touch more on the capstone
action learning component here in a
little bit. But here is an overview of
uh the curriculum that you'll find over
these um three semesters. in you'll see
in the middle there winter semester
during January. Um it's called IEP
independent activities period. It's
MITwide. Um it's an opportunity to do um
different focuses outside of just a
regular coursework. Um but with uh the
business analytics program, you'll be
kicking off your capstone um review and
and putting together your team and
meeting with companies. Um again, I'll
go further into what capstone project
is. It is a highlight of the business
analytics program. Um, we added a couple
of new uh courses on here as well. Um,
but you can go on our website as well to
dive a little deeper into the curriculum
and learn specifics.
And I just like to highlight um the
analytics faculty. We're very lucky to
have some world-class uh faculty uh here
at Sloan. Um, and you will have an
opportunity to potentially do research
assistantships with these faculty
members. I'll touch on that more here in
just a minute as well.
So um inband students can apply to be a
research assistant with the MSE faculty
member of their interest um in the fall
or spring semesters. Um it is an
application through them. It's not
through the admissions office. So that's
something that you would do once you're
here and metriculated on campus. Um it's
a commitment about 10 hours per week and
it does help offset your tuition and you
get about uh 13,000 per semester.
And then here are um some examples of
research that students have done with
faculty.
I just we just like to share this if
you'd like to look at some of them. It
does uh go across a variety of focuses
in industries, sustainability,
healthcare and transportation.
And so the analytics capstone project um
it is again a a hallmark of uh the
business analytics program. Um it begins
in January and runs through August. It's
a 10-month project. uh it's 24 units. Um
you uh are in a team of two. Um you work
on a real life uh data science problem
with a company over a course of seven
months. Um and you have a dedicated team
of MIT faculty and PhD team to help
support you during this time. Um
basically you're kind of working with
this company in kind of a consulting
role helping them scope out and identify
issues. Um you meet with them at least
once a week. Um then you have u a
full-time summer work experience with
the company um over the summer in
person. Um and it's a $22,000 tuition
offset as well and you are provided a
small living expense during the
summertime and then at the end for this
program that students do graduate in
August each year. Um, so you come back
to campus, um, you complete a final
written report and as well as a
presentation, um, with the host company,
um, and you present this at what's
called the capstone showcase at the end
of August before your graduation.
This is a great opportunity to have an
immersive experience and and to work on
site. Um, you get real world experience
in the field of data analytics and data
science. It's a great resume builder as
well.
And here are some of the companies um
that students uh participated in last
year and this year. Um as you can see it
again is a lot of recognizable companies
that span a variety of industries. So
there's a lot of different areas of
interest that you could be um
participating in on these projects.
And then here are some sample capstone
topics as well.
And I will just give a little plug that
there is a component of the capstone
showcase that is live streamed each
year. Um we will be posting this on our
website. So just stay tuned to our
admissions events page. I think it's
going to be August 15th this year. So if
you'd like to see some of the
presentations live, you can join that.
So career support um when you come to
study with us we know it's um very
important not only to learn about a
specific industry but um you know also
find an interesting competitive job. So
our career development office really
partners with students um before they
even metriculate to help you kind of
develop a plan and better understand
what it means to work within data
science and or analytics or product
management or you know like whatever um
your interest might be for this program.
Um, you know, folks coming into this
program are early career. Um, we see
people coming in who have primarily just
internship experience. So, there's a lot
more structure into supporting students
in this program. Um, you'll receive a
dedicated career adviser who will work
closely with you throughout the program
and help you identify what you might
want to do and develop a plan for your
job search. Um, I will highlight that uh
we have a career core that's built into
the first semester and it's meant to
help prepare you for your job search as
well through workshop group sessions,
you know, building your LinkedIn resumes
um all the way through helping you um uh
negotiate your offer letters as well. Um
so there's a lot of support and
networking opportunities that the career
development office here at Sloan
provides for students within this
program.
And here's just an overview of some of
the comprehensive career services.
And we do have um industry speaker
nights um that are MIT and Sloan wide um
opportunities for students all around to
join. Um there's also opportunities to
connect with alumni as well and
different um industries and and connect
with them to help you in your job
search.
And so this is just to share um some
sample job titles. Some people earlier
on or you know what what does someone
with a business analytics degree go
into. So you can see that under the
sample job titles. Of course data
scientist is one of the most popular um
focuses to go into but there's a wide
range. Um machine learning engineer,
operations analyst, product analyst,
portfolio manager um and other titles
that you can see there. And then um
these are some of the companies that our
students have gone into after they
graduate. Um and again you can see it it
spans a wide variety of of industries
and focuses.
Um if you'd like to you can go online um
and look at our employment reports and
you can see greater detail and
breakdown. Um but this slide just
highlights um the average base salary
from our most recent employment report
um and some of the locations of where
students have accepted jobs within the
US. Um over around uh 90% 96.5
um or 95.6% excuse me have accepted jobs
here within the US. And then um 18.6% of
students um actually were able to secure
their job u through capstone companies.
And here's an overview of the MBAN class
profile um from 2025.
I like to share this just to highlight
some of the backgrounds that uh students
come from. Um you can see it's not just
STEM focuses. So again, it's not a
requirement to come from a STEM
background. Just be comfortable with
quantitative skills. Um 40% women. Um
the average GPA is 3.92. Um, we have the
average GRE on here because that's the
test that most students decide to submit
or applicants, excuse me. So, that's the
best data that we have, but we don't
have a preference between the GMAT GRE
or GMAT focus. Um, and then you'll also
see I like to highlight um the your time
of work experience is around eight or 15
months average work experience. That
does include internships.
Um I just like to highlight this uh
slide too with the various clubs that
some of our um students in the business
analytics program participate in because
you do have a wide variety of
extracurriculars open to you as a
student here in data science and
analytics and beyond. Um student clubs
are a really great tool to give you
exposure different types of industries.
Um build relationships with alumni. um
and also with potential companies. So I
would a lot of these clubs do secure
company um executives to come and speak
who might be looking to hire students.
Um so there's a lot of great um
opportunities to uh participate in once
you get here. There's some conferences
as well that can also help you get
industry exposure and partner with
industry practitioners coming to campus
and speak at these. So they're great to
get involved with and build
relationships and can certainly lead to
lead to employment opportunities.
So, moving on to our application, I will
highlight that we have not released um
the new application yet for this cycle,
but the deadline is set. So, it's going
to be January 5th and it will be coming
out very soon for business analytics.
So, please stay tuned. Um but we will do
have um some components here that I'll
review quickly. We have the onepage
resume. You should include, you know,
relevant awards, scholarships,
professional societies in addition to,
you know, extra community activities,
any research experience or maybe in, you
know, obviously internships or any
teaching assistantships are helpful to
share here as well.
And then we have our essay questions, a
500word limit um for this past year.
That could be changing, but um I'll
speak to what we had for this past
cycle, you know, and then within that,
why are you pursuing this program and
what you hope to gain um from joining um
the Master of Business Analytics
program. Um we have a short answer
question as well. um how the world uh
shaped you um and it's an opportunity to
expand on your background u um and how
that has uh helped you grow and develop.
We have three letters of recommendation
uh that are required. Um for those who
are current students, um we ask that you
submit three academic uh letters of
recommendation. One must come from
someone who can speak to your
quantitative abilities. Uh for those who
might be working full-time, um please
submit two letters of um academic uh
from academic sources, excuse me, and
one from a professional or a recent
employer. Um we don't accept letters of
recommendation from family members um so
just a note there um for those who might
be in family businesses. And then um
academic transcripts of course um two
video questions. So the first one is a
60-second um time frame. Um it's an
opportunity to introduce yourself uh to
future classmates. And the second
question is a randomly generated
open-ended question. Um you have 10
seconds to prepare and then a one minute
response for that. And they're very easy
questions. Um it's nothing you need to
worry about preparing for in advance.
It's just to kind of assess your
communicate communication ability.
And then of course relevant coursework
and professional certifications. You can
share those if you have them. um not
required um but if you do have if you
took any online course work or have a
CFA or something like that it's helpful
to share that there um and again as I
mentioned for test scores we accept the
GMAT GRE and GMAT focus and we really
don't have a preference between the
three
and interviews are required um they are
conducted um online uh so virtually
through Zoom um and you will have some
questions beforehand that we will submit
to you they change year to year um but
you will have time to prepare for those
before your interview.
All right. So, I know we went through
that quickly, so if there's any
questions, um, happy to try to answer.
Absolutely. All right. Uh, hi everyone.
My name is Steve. I'm also a part of the
admissions team here. Uh, Katherine,
thanks so much for going through a lot
of the information regarding the MBAM
program. I do have a few questions that
uh I wanted to run past you, but you
know what? I'll give you a quick break.
I know you just talked for a little bit,
so feel free to take a sip of water.
There were a few questions that came
through that were reoccurring, and I'm
happy to uh address those uh as well.
So, a couple of questions off the bat
that came in regarding the application
components. Uh, as Katherine mentioned,
we will have um more of an app tips
webinar coming up later regarding the um
the the program itself, but I'm happy to
touch on a few uh aspects as well. So,
first and foremost, there were a lot of
questions about if the GRE or the GMATs
are um mandatory for this program. The
answer is no, they are not. They are
optional and you can submit your scores
uh if you so choose. Uh then the next
question in your mind might be okay well
if it's optional what's the benefit of
submitting scores versus not well the
benefit andor um how that's calculated
is that if you have a a score that you
are proud of and you feel is a um a
strong representation of your analytic
skills then by all means we think that
that's a good opportunity to submit that
score. However, if you choose to not
submit a GRE or a GMAT score that will
not negatively impact your application.
What we will do instead is we will look
at the data points that you've submitted
with your application and make our
decision based off of those data points.
So by just uh not including a test score
that all that means is that we would
just have one less data point. But if
you still feel strongly about your
application with those other points
that's completely fine. Uh the other
question that came through was just in
regards to our deadlines themselves and
if there is any benefit to applying
early if we have a rolling status and
that the answer to that is no. we
actually uh do not look at applications
until after the deadline has passed. So
really utilize as much of the time as
you need to craft what you think is the
strongest application that you can
possibly make. Uh once you feel that
it's at its strongest, that's when I
recommend that you hit the send button
on that application. And then from
there, uh all of our applications are
are jumbled together. There is no
indicator of time. Those that applied
early don't get first preference in
terms of reading. everything is kind of
pulled together for our readers to um uh
to look at. But with that said, I do
have a couple of questions that did come
through. Uh Katherine, now that you've
had a little bit of a break to
>> Thank you, Steve.
>> Of course. Uh so one question that came
through is uh actually um centered
around the program. Somebody wanted to
know if um having in internship during
their undergraduate program is mandatory
to be admitted into the MBA program or
sorry the MBAN program.
>> Great question. Um it is not mandatory.
Uh actually no work experience is
required uh as part of your application
to to um be a candidate for this
program. However, we do like to see
leadership um experience. So but that
doesn't have necessarily have to be
through an internship or full-time work
experience. They can be through
extracurriculars if you were president
of club or you know you were a teaching
assistant or a research assistant in
your undergraduate studies as well. Um
those can be great ways to to showcase
that but again it's not required.
>> Excellent. Okay great. I know there are
a lot of questions regarding the
application components to the degree
itself. Um I will just say again that we
will have another session later on in
the fall that will go into a deeper dive
about the the components themselves. I
love that folks are uh thinking ahead in
regards to that. Uh although there is
this one question I think that folks do
have in mind is that um what if there
are in your experience Katherine
extracurricular activities that you have
seen or examples of that folks uh dive
into that are common occurrences on uh
applications.
>> Thanks. Yeah, another great question. Um
really like when you're looking at
choosing extracurriculars, choose
something that you're passionate about.
Because if you're just choosing it
because you think it'll help build your
resume or your your candidacy for the
program, you're not really interested in
it, that's really going to show um for
us um as we're looking through it. Um so
that's the that's the my biggest piece
of advice for that. Um but as I said,
you know, we are looking for um
leadership experience in in some ways an
example. So certainly participating in
extracurriculars and and and getting
those leadership roles um can be helpful
in in showcasing that in your
application,
but it doesn't necessarily have to be
data analytics focused.
>> Perfect.
All right. Excellent. Um now, uh some of
our folks in the audience uh and this is
definitely a hot button topic as we uh
talk about the the different types of um
curriculum that we offer here at Sloan.
Could you highlight if there are any
opportunities for our um MBAN students
to be get involved in the lovely world
of AI and any AI related courses?
>> Yes, definitely. Um I I I know we went
over it quickly um but one of the new
courses that's being offered for the
Ozen business analytics is a deep
learning course. Um and that's part of
your core uh courses in the fall. Um MIT
is very focused on AI. Um so you'll find
that built into a lot of uh the
coursework that we have here at Sloan
and MITwide. Um there's a lot of
initiatives around it too. So there's um
some extracurricular student clubs um
some research the faculty are working
on. There's a lot actually a lot of
research the faculty are working on
right now that's AI focused. Um so
there's definitely opportunities um to
build and hone the skills in that area
if that's what you're interested in.
>> Excellent.
Great. Thank you so much. Um, now in
terms of uh other questions that have
been coming through, sorry, as many
folks are starting to fly through. So,
one question that I think folks wanted,
this is a two-part question for you,
Katherine. For those that are coming
from a uh a non- STEM background for
this program, would that particularly
hinder one's application?
>> Definitely not. Um, it's again, it's not
a requirement to come from a STEM
background for this program. Um, you
know, we know when you get here, we're
we're here to teach you and train you
the foundations of data science and
analytics. Um, we are setting you up to
be successful um, leaving Sloan and and
going into the data science world. Um,
so we don't expect you to already have
all those things under your belt once
you arrive. However, um, we do want you
to be comfortable with quantitative work
because you will do um, computer
programming. um you will have you know
some you it's helpful to have some
background in mathematics and statistics
and calculus uh to do the coursework
once you arrive here. Um so we do like
to see that um you know either in your
undergraduate work or if you choose to
take some online coursework as well.
>> Excellent.
>> All right. Perfect. Um so let's dive
into kind of the second part of that
question is that for those that uh saw
in some of the requirements there are
required courses that we are looking for
within the the program itself. Is it
expected to have completed all of the
required courses that uh are listed on
the application?
>> Good question. It it is not. Um it's
certainly helpful to to share as many of
those as you can. Um but again we're not
looking for you to have the full list
completed. Um it is again I will
highlight the computer programming
piece. Obviously it's being data science
analytics you know having familiar
familiarity with Python or Julia is
definitely going to be helpful for you
um once you join the program.
>> Perfect.
Great. Uh there have been a few
questions that have been coming through
on the chat as well just regarding years
of experience and I'm happy to take this
to you Katherine. I just want to get
your two cents on it as well for folks
that I'd say uh that are on let's say
the higher side of looking at three
years worth of experience or beyond um
and how that kind of fits into this
particular program for the amount of the
profile that we normally see of folks
having zero to two years worth of
experience uh if that would negatively
impact their application. What I would
just say is that for this particular
program, we are norm we are looking for
those between zero to two years worth of
experience that if you have more uh
years worth of experience by the time of
metriculation or coming into the program
in August, we may have a conversation if
there is a different program within our
portfolio that might be uh a better fit
for you. For example, our MBA program or
some of our other uh offerings. Would
you agree with that uh statement,
Katherine?
>> Yeah, definitely. um you know as you
mentioned you know maybe the MBA program
might be better if you are looking to
hone your skills in data science we do
have a certificate that allows you to
focus and do a deeper dive within the
MBA program for business analytics um
but really you want to think about when
you're trying to decide the two programs
is you know the business analytics
masters uh is preparing you to go out
into the world of data science you're
going to be going into more of an entry-
level role um you're going to be
building your leadership um there might
be pieces that may not be applicable to
you if you have a greater than, you
know, 5 years of work experience or
more. Um, it may be redundant of what
you're learning. So, you want to think
about the cohort you're going to be
going into and what's going to be the
most beneficial for you um after you
graduate.
>> Perfect.
Excellent.
All right. Great. So, I'm scanning
through. I know we've got plenty of uh
questions that have still been coming
through, so please keep me honest uh in
regards to that. Um, one that is
actually uh something I want to touch on
is that for those that are, let's say,
doing a research opportunity with a
current professor, does that technically
count as full-time experience at this
point?
>> Um, if it would count as um part-time
experience or an internship. So, that
would be absolutely something to include
on um your resume and share with us. I
think it's if you're do four months or
or greater then it would count as
full-time work experience but if not if
it's less than that um or under you know
30 hours a week um that's part-time.
>> Perfect.
>> Katherine um in terms of uh numbers as
we kind of look at the the class
profile. So the first one I'll I'll
happily take for you. some there were
some questions regarding if someone
didn't fall into let's say the average
or the median range of things like their
test scores our GPA or anything along
those lines if they should hold off
applying until they meet those criteria
to that I would say no I would there's
the the median GPA that we have is not a
a beall end all that is just the the
median if we have folks that um fall
outside of that range that is completely
fine in doing so uh what I would just
recommend to you is making sure that you
feel or finding ways to um create a
strong application and submit that based
off of the experiences that you uh
personally have. But for you, Katherine,
I'm not sure if we have these statistics
on hand, but would you be able to
comment on the popularity of this
program, whether it be the amount of
applications we receive per seat or um
uh how many are accepted into the
program?
>> Yeah. um because it varies year to year.
Um we don't share how many are accepted,
you know, the percentage of acceptance
rate um because it does change. Um so we
don't want to set expectations or
disappoint. Um but as far as the
applications we receive each year for
the program, um it's generally, you
know, can range between 15 to 2,000
applications every year. Um and there's
80 seats that we usually try to stick
with for this program. So you can kind
of do the math on on that end.
>> Excellent.
Perfect. So, keep me honest, Katherine.
How many more uh how much time do we
have left for questions?
>> Uh we we have about 10 minutes, so we
have we have some time to cover a few.
>> Okay, perfect. Uh let me go through uh
some of the questions that we've had
coming through. Um
>> I can quickly while you're looking I I
saw someone asking about the RA
application process. Um again, that'll
be something that um is handled directly
through the professors you're looking to
do the rehip with. Um so once you are
metriculated and come on campus um you
generally will take your first course
semester and then look at um
participating in an RA ship with
professors. So it's something you would
do later um here once you're at Sloan.
>> Perfect. And actually, this is a good
one that um I think will a lot of folks
would like to know about is that the the
program itself can seem very STEM
focused and fast-paced program, but what
are some common characteristics that set
successful candidates apart in terms of
either mindset or just going beyond
their technical skills?
>> Yeah. No, great question. Um again, like
you know, this program is very
technical, but it's also um we're hoping
to build you as a a business leader,
too. We want you to be able to, you
know, have both sides of those skill
sets. Um, so someone who has, you know,
leadership experience, um, someone who
has an innovative mind thought, um, who
who enjoys the challenges of learning,
um, and going past the status quo is
important. Um, and then also having a
collaborative spirit though, you know,
um, I think maybe it was mentioned in
the video of the motto here of Sony's
helping Sloan is a very collaborative
environment. Um, every there's a lot of
teamwork focuses in the curriculum and
then the extracurriculars that you'll
see here.
you're broken down into teams, you're on
a team with the capstone project. So,
that's a huge component and we look for
that too in your application.
>> Great.
>> And Katherine, would you mind just
commenting on um any fellowship or
scholarship opportunities outside of the
capstone that might be associated with
this program?
>> Yeah, great question. Um so, every
student who submits an application is
automatically considered for merit-based
um fellowship funding. Um so, you don't
have to submit a different um
application. um you will uh know once
you receive your decision for the
program if you've been awarded any
fellowships. Um but again, you do have
that $22,000 offset from the capstone uh
company um time. Um and so that's that's
really a great benefit of the business
analytics program.
>> Perfect. And as I started to scroll back
through and look through some of our
other questions, I'll give you a quick
break as well. Um, one question that
came through was, is there a heavy focus
on health care in AI at MIT? While I say
that it's slightly niche that we
probably have a few classes that touch
on healthcare and also AI involved with
healthcare, what I will comment and I'll
also mention is that at MIT Sloan, we
have seven different certificates that
are available and open to folks across
all of our programs. So, one of those
seven certificates being uh in the space
of healthcare. What are certificates?
They're basically like what you could
consider a minor from an undergraduate
university or honestly a road map of uh
giving you an idea of how to take
specific electives uh to focus in on a
respective topic. So we have uh product
management, analytics, finance,
entrepreneurship as other examples of
certificates. So that could be a good
balance for you if you're really looking
to take your career in that that way and
focus in on the healthcare space to take
that uh particular um uh certificate. Uh
but going back to the question that I
had for you Katherine is someone was
curious how our MBAN program or MBAN
program differs from the masters of
finance or even the Sloan MBA in terms
of analytic intensity or career
flexibility.
>> Yeah. No. Um another great question. Um
so this program is for someone who's
looking to go solely into data analytics
and and um you know that's their
passion. That's what they're they're
looking to do long term for their
career. Um, you know, again, there
there's some of the leadership softer
skills that you'll learn here as well
for the program because we think that
that's very important for you to have as
you go out um into working for
organizations, but we want you to be um
you know at a at a prolevel skill set of
uh data science analytics. So, that's
the main focus of this program. The
masters of finance, similarly, the main
focus is going to be finance. Um it's
going to be for someone who knows that,
you know, finance is going to be their
career. Um, for the MBA program, I think
the difference is you the MBA you can
certainly focus and and specialize in
certain areas. As Steve mentioned,
there's those certificates that are
open. Um, but really it's more of a
generalized degree because you gain a
wide variety of skills when within that
program. Um, so if you're looking to,
you know, do uh maybe different career
pivots um during your time, an MBA can
help you with that because it's more of
a generalized degree.
>> Excellent. And this was a question that
I wasn't familiar uh with an answer, but
I'm just curious if you have any uh
insight into as well is that for folks
that have completed the um the MBAN
program, do you normally see students
that have a pathway into a PhD programs
within MI MIT?
>> Yeah. No, it's a good question. Um we do
see a handful every year. Um, usually
the students choose to do a thesis or
component and and certainly um
participate with the research
assistantships, but we do see a handful
each year um that are interested in the
PhD.
>> Excellent.
Uh going back to the background of of
candidates coming into the the program
itself, for uh candidates that are not
coming from a STEM background, are there
any courses, certificates, or skills you
recommend completing ahead of time to
make their applications seem a little
bit more complete?
>> Yeah. Um, you know, it's certainly up to
your your schedule and your capacity.
But again, if you don't have strong
comfort or familiarity with computer
programming languages, you know, Python
at a minimum, um, that might be a great
course to take online and and get and
brush your skills u up on that one. Um,
and then, you know, certain mathematics
courses, calculus, statistics certainly
would be helpful to um, take uh, for
this program as well.
>> Excellent.
Okay, perfect.
Let's see here. As I go through,
still have plenty of uh of questions
that have come through, but I'm trying
to find some that uh might attain or um
pertain to to all that are involved as
well. Um, oh actually could you give a
little bit of insight into after the
application component moving on to the
next part of our evaluation process uh
how that what those uh conversations are
structured as and what folks can expect
from the interview aspect.
>> Yeah. So it's a conversational
interview. So they're going to be um you
know reviewing your application and
their questions are going to come from
that. They may ask you to elaborate and
speak more to it. Um, so obviously being
prepared on what you submitted uh for
your interview and then um they do have
some u pre-in questions um that you'll
you will submit. Um they change year to
year. Um they're technical questions um
but that's something that you will have
advanced notice to prepare for um and be
ready for by the time you you get to
your interview.
>> Perfect. And is there any say like um
the questions themselves are they more
quantitative focused, behavioral focus,
a mixture of both?
>> Quantitative. Yes. So, the questions
themselves are going to be more
quantitative focused. The interview is
more conversational, behavioral.
>> Perfect. Excellent.
All right. Great. And I know that we're
we're coming up on time and I'm trying
to see if there are any final uh
questions that we have. Actually, uh one
I guess I'll go back to the the
application to kind of close us out. is
that uh if for those that are coming
from an undergraduate uh background, are
those folks allowed to have two academic
letters of recommendation and one
professional uh letter of recommendation
or should it be a different skew?
>> Yeah, so if you are currently a college
um senior and you're looking to apply to
this program or still in your studies,
um we do ask that you submit three
letters of um recommendation from
academic sources. Um, but if you are
someone who is working full-time at this
point, um, it's it's fine to submit one
professional letter of recommendation
and two academic letters of
recommendation.
>> Very good. All right, folks. I know that
we have a number of interviews or a
number of questions that have are still
out in the chat. We've tried to get to
as many as we could in our time, but I
also want to be respectful of everyone's
time as we kind of wind things down uh,
and talk about next steps. So,
Katherine, over to you. That is going to
be it for me for our Q&A portion.
>> Thanks, Steve. Thanks for helping
moderate. Great questions, everyone. As
Steve mentioned, I know there's a bunch
in here. Um, I think we answered a good
bit, too. But, um, the ones we didn't
get to, please email us. We we actively
monitor the email that you see up here
on the screen. Um, and we'll get back to
you quickly. Um, we do have a number of
events upcoming for this fall as well.
Um, some topical webinars, uh, going
over a variety of components for the
business analytics, um, capstone
curriculum, things like that. So stay
tuned to our admissions event site. Um
and we'd love to see you there as well.
And as Steve mentioned, um we will be
doing app tips webinar specifically for
the business analytics program later
this fall. The application should be
released later um in August. So it'll be
coming out shortly as well. So please
stay tuned. Thanks everyone for joining
and thanks for your time.
>> Thanks Stephen and Morgan. Appreciate
you.
>> We care.