(swooshing tune)
(electric tune)
- Hi, I'm Phillip Isola
and I'm a faculty member at MIT in EECS.
And I study computer vision
and machine learning in robotics,
and I'm happy to answer some questions
about those topics today.
So let's go to the first question.
Okay. What is embodied intelligence?
Embodied intelligence is
the study of AI systems
that have to interact in a physical world,
in the real world.
So think robotics.
But the study of embodied
intelligence is really,
encompasses a lot of different fields.
So we need to be able to
perceive the 3D world around us.
That's a vision problem.
We need to be able to take
actions and make decisions.
So these are problems in
decision making and robotics.
So embodied intelligence is
a very kind of holistic take
on the AI problem.
Let's go to the next question.
Can you tell me about your contributions
to the field of computer vision?
Specifically, could you detail
some of your key work in
applying machine learning
to image processing?
My work has been on a
few different topics,
but one of the central themes has been
on trying to understand
how should we represent
the world around us,
specifically how should we
represent the visual world
around us.
There's a lot of different
answers to that question.
And you know, one answer might be
you could have 3D models of objects,
and you could have the
geometry represented
and you could have like
the semantics represented.
For example, I would know
there's a cat in the photo
or a dog in the photo.
My work has been on a
slightly different direction,
which is, let's not kind of pre-specify
or hand engineer the way of
representing the visual world,
but let's let it emerge
from a learning algorithm.
And I've specifically worked
on using deep neural networks
to learn visual representations from data,
where the representation that's learned
is what's called a neural embedding.
It's what the neural net has come up with
as a way of organizing
the data that it sees.
And in particular, I've worked a lot,
my group has worked a lot on
an approach which is called
self supervised learning.
So in this approach, you
don't teach the neural network
from kind of human specified labels,
but instead you train the network
to try to predict properties
of the raw data itself.
So for example, you could take a image
and you could mask out half
of the pixels in the image
and try to predict the missing pixels
from the pixels that are observed.
So this is something that you can train
on just raw data
without having any labels
or humans specifying
what you know, the
representation should be.
But the neural net learns how
to make these predictions.
And by doing so, it comes
up with a representation
of the world, which knows
something about objects
and continuity.
Like it knows that if I have, you know,
the left half of the table here,
there's probably a right half of the table
on the other side.
This idea that just by
predicting missing data,
missing visual information,
you will get a representation
which knows how the world works.
And that's a representation
that can be used
to make meaningful
predictions about the future.
For example, what will
happen if I open this door?
What will I see?
Will I, what will happen
if I drive my car forward?
Will I go through a red light?
If I can make these predictions,
I can make good decisions.
And that's the type of
visual representation
that I've worked on.
Any advice on how to tell the difference
between AI generated
images and natural images?
Right, this is a hard one
because I can't tell anymore.
We're just at a point in history
where if I see a photo online,
I don't know if it's real or if it's fake.
And that wasn't true a few years ago.
This is very much a new thing.
The main way that I would try to assess
if an image or media
online is real or fake
is not gonna be by looking at artifacts
or the visual content.
It'll be, you know,
looking at the context.
If there is some kind of
crazy implausible photo
of some celebrity on Mars,
I'm gonna think it's probably fake.
If I don't trust this source,
if it's an anonymous source,
I might not trust it.
That's the state that we're in right now.
Luckily, there are some
technical tools that can help.
So there are AI systems
that have been trained
to detect if a photo
or some kind of content
is made by another AI or if
it's real authentic content.
And those sort of work.
We're in an arms race where
the generative AI methods
get better and better at making
realistic synthetic content.
And the detectors get better and better
at detecting any little artifact
that gives away that the image
or the content is not real
and it's gonna go back and forth.
That arms race is not gonna
have necessarily a clear winner,
but we'll see what happens
over the next few years.
Ultimately, I would say I trust media
when I trust its source.
I can't verify just with my eyes anymore
whether or not an image is real or fake.
Okay. Let's go to the next question.
Could you explain to me what deep nets are
and the kinds of
representations that they learn?
So deep nets are, you know, super cool.
They're the big thing in
AI that everyone uses now.
Deep nets are basically
just a class of functions
that can be used to make decisions
or learn representations of the world.
And there are class of
functions which are modeled
off of how the brain works to some degree.
So in our brain we have a neural network,
a real neural network, and a deep net
is kind of an approximation to that.
It turns out that deep nets
are really a simple class of
function, in a certain sense.
They're just a stack of layers
and every layer takes the input data
at the bottom of the stack
and it kind of transforms it.
And layer by layer the data gets processed
and transformed until at
the top of the network
you get a better kind of
representation of the data
that can be used to make
predictions or decisions.
And these layers are all
doing very simple operations.
They're just doing what's
called a linear operation.
And then a simple thing
called a point non-linearity.
It's just this linear,
point wise non-linear,
linear, point wise non-linear.
So these are very simple
mathematical objects,
but they can do amazing things
when they learn from data.
And what kinds of representations
do deep nets learn?
Well, they learn to
somehow organize the data
in a way that makes it easy
to solve the task of interest,
which might be to make a
prediction about the data,
to classify the data
or to make a decision on the basis of
what the network is seeing.
Okay. So let's go to the next question.
How did your research in
image to image translation
shape your current work?
Okay, this is taking
me back a little ways.
But back during my postdoc
about seven or eight years ago,
I worked on this problem called
image to image translation,
which is to try to take
an image that is presented
in one kind of style or
modality, like a color image,
and predict what it would look
like viewed a different way.
For example, translate
a photo into a sketch
or translate a sketch into a photo,
or maybe take a photo and try to say,
what would it look like
if some artist, Cison,
had painted that scene?
So you can kind of visualize
the world in different ways
and we called this a translation problem,
translating from one visual
format to another one.
So this project was really fun,
it was popular, and it
definitely affected my thinking
and my ongoing thinking about AI.
To take you back, in the
era before we did that work,
there were a lot of special purpose
ways of solving problems
in computer vision.
So if you wanted to solve a
problem, like object detection,
try to label all the objects in a photo,
you would use a fairly different method
than if you wanted to solve a problem,
like estimating the depth of
all the objects in the photo,
like predicting what's called a depth map.
So that didn't really satisfy me.
I really wanted something
that would be a more uniform,
unified solution to all those problems
because what we kind of realized is that
all of these different
computer vision problems
could be thought of as taking
some set of pixels as input
and predicting some other
set of pixels as output.
So the output pixels could
represent where the objects are,
or they could visualize
the depth map of the scene.
So these were all pixel to pixel problems
and that led to us calling
this project Pix to Pix.
That was the name we gave
it, Pixels to Pixels.
Essentially, we had a more
general purpose framework
for solving all of those problems,
rather than having specialized
solutions for each one.
And that made me realize essentially
how powerful a more general purpose
and unified solution can be.
And really the big trend
over the last, you know,
5 or 10 years of AI, has been toward these
general purpose solutions.
The biggest phase of that now is
with these large language models
where one big model is trained to do
a lot of different tasks.
So when you interact with a chat bot
or a language model, you can
ask it all kinds of questions.
You can even ask it to make an image
or to solve a math problem.
And it's one model that with
a kind of generic framework
is able to solve all those problems.
So I think that's an interesting trend
and that's what I'm always
kind of on the outlook
for right now.
Simple, unifying principles and methods
that can be applied to a
wide variety of problems.
Any recommendations for the
best AI image generation models?
Hmm, okay.
One I really like right now
is called Stable Diffusion.
I like this model
because it's open source,
so we get to use it and intervene on it
and really study it as scientist.
And it's one of the image
generation models that works well.
So my lab mostly uses Stable Diffusion
in our research as the current model.
Another one that I like a
lot is called Control Net.
Control Net is kind of the
current most popular iteration
of image to image translation.
We did, you know, old work like X Depicts
and now people have gone way beyond that
and Control Net is the latest.
So what it does is it allows you
to condition your
generative model on an image
and produce another image.
For example, you can take a sketch
and you can turn that sketch into a photo.
So Control Net, Stable Diffusion,
these are some of the fun ones
that I'm playing with now.