fairly broad title but I'm actually
going to work through several case
studies to try to uh give you a flavor
of the um the ideas that I would like to
convey so I don't need to introduce
distributed Cooperative Network control
I think most of the audience is familiar
with the variety of applications uh I
want to talk about uh underlying sort of
fundamental limitations in control
design so I'm going to have uh two
themes uh throughout the talk uh and the
First theme is going to be that uh I'm
going to think about spatially
distributed systems uh which involve uh
networked uh and Cooperative systems
over networks and I'm going to talk
about distributed parameter systems
which people normally think of as
control of pdes in the same breath and
the way I want to connect them is that I
want to think about these this problem
over Continuum space and problems over
graphs and networks as I think about the
graph as dist discretized space but
discretize in in terms of the graph
structure which can be fairly
complex um we're familiar with this sort
of maybe in uh when you do pdes and you
do numerical methods you get typically
differential equations over typically
regular graphs but if your meshes are
not regular then you get more General
graphs and when you have discrete
systems or sort of particle methods with
a large number of particles you often
look at the equivalent pdes that come
from Continuum models so this is not an
unusual point of view but I want to
adopt that for control design as well um
because space over arbitrary graphs can
actually be quite different from say
going between discrete time and
continuous time and time is a
one-dimensional ordered set while
discretized space can have a much richer
structure we'll see that there's much
richer phenomenology or differences
between the discrete and the Continuum
so that will be one theme the other
theme is going to be uh about
constrained uh control design over
networks uh where the constraints are
coming from the a priori uh restrictions
placed on the controller architecture
and those are really the important
questions I want to address
um so it is generally a very difficult
problem to do optimal con constraint
control design think about decentralized
control or various other uh restrictions
the problems are typically non-convex
non-scalable Etc um on the other hand if
you think about multi-agent systems uh
there are many effective algorithms
proposed for multi-agent systems that
are not necessarily optimal but they're
provably correct or have certain levels
of of performance by Design uh so why
worry about optimality at all since it's
so difficult and I want to argue is that
optimality really is kind of a way to
think about co-design of the plant and
the controller together it's about
understanding how controllable the plant
is rather than trying to just design an
optimal controller and I hope to make
that point uh with the following example
that may be uh familiar to some of you
so uh this is an unstable airplane and
this was made famous in the CDC body
lecture by Gunter Stein I want to talk
about another problem very briefly to
make the point out I want to make
throughout the talk so think about a
rear steering bike so that is a a bike
where the steering uh wheel is actually
in the rear and you're not trying to be
fooled so when you turn the handlebar
right eventually the bike will go right
and vice versa okay this is a
fundamentally difficult bike to control
in other words it's fundamentally
difficult to ride um and there's a very
nice paper that I recommend to all of
you uh by Carl asan company that
explains all the details I'm going to
just talk about one aspect of this very
quickly um so you can understand how
difficult this bike is to ride if you
look at the linearized Dynamics between
uh the actuation is The Handlebar angle
and the output is the Tilt angle of the
bike uh and so that these are the only
inputs and outputs uh considered here
and you can think about the fundamental
limitation on the sensitivity function
over all
controllers uh you can find a lower
bound on this in terms of a right half
plane and pole and a right half plane
zero that these Dynamics have okay so
this is a not only an unstable system
but it also is a non-minimum phase
system with a right half plane zero and
the sensitivity cannot be made any lower
than this quantity so in particular you
can see that the distance between the
right half flame pole and zero the
smaller it is the larger this quantity
is in fact when they're on top of each
other the system is not
stabilizable so but even when they're
not on top of each other but close the
system has very very high sensitivity
now you can relate in this paper that's
uh uh it's laid out in detail how the um
the right half plane pole doesn't depend
on velocity but the right half plane
zero depends on the velocity the Nom
remember this is linearized Dynamics
around a particular velocity so for High
Velocity it's uh it goes out further to
the to the right uh this is this is less
sensitivity than low velocity and in
fact this is the only way you could
write this bike the people who have been
able to ride this bike I tried but I
couldn't several times is you run along
with the bike at a certain velocity and
then you jump on it and you start
pedling like crazy and and you could if
you're if you're good enough you could
sort of maintain decent control but you
when you get to the end of the road you
have to slow down and you can see this
repeatedly when people trying to ride
this bike as the velocity decreases you
kind of lose control and you fall off so
in a way this tells you roughly the um
performance limitations now the
distances between the pole and the zero
and so on are related to the geometry of
the bike uh for example it is U so here
let me see so it is related to the fork
angle the center where the center of
gravity is and so on So based on those
relations which are fairly easy to
derive what you could do is you could
redesign rear steering work this is a
redesigned rear steering bike looks very
funny uh in fact the higher the center
of gravity the further are the distances
between the pole and zero uh and the
further to the front that center of
gravity is again the further the
distance between the pole and zero So
based on these
relations uh and the limitations on the
sensitivity you can actually redesign
the bike to be more easy easily
controllable so the optimal control
design or the limitations on performance
were useful not in designing the
controller but in redesigning the plant
so that it is more easy to control right
so now you don't have to be very skilled
to ride this bike okay so again so this
is you know this is well known to
overcome these limitations you can add
sensors and actuators but here this is
an example of actually redesigning the
plant
so uh so this is kind of a an
interesting point to ponder in the
current ERA of data driven control and
model predictive control reinforcement
learning Etc what seems to be happening
one way to understand it is that the
controller design itself you give me a
plant and then I design the controller
that process is being automated through
data driven techniques or model
predictive control and so on uh so what
is the utility of optimal or robust
control and you know this was a a point
that was kind of known in the 80s and
90s but seems to be not fully
appreciated in the in the networks
literature is that you really use
optimal control to characterize when is
a good what is a good plant easy to
control when is it easy to control once
you use those techniques to design a
good plant like I did with the uh like
like it was done with the bicycle
example then essentially any good
controller any well-designed controller
does not have to be optimal will work
well so optimal control really should
you should be thought of as a way to re
sort of doing co-design of the plant and
the controller but actually more
importantly the plant itself and then
any decent controller will work on a
well-designed plant all right so this
actually John Doyle used to say this all
the time uh B basically design use
optimal and robust control tools to
design a good plant and then a p ID say
controller will work well reasonably any
reasonably designed controller
so uh that's the point I would like to
make about these constrained distributed
optimal control problems which are hard
and and non-convex you use them to
characterize when is a network easy to
control so this is a question of network
controllability that may be addressable
by looking at constrained distributed
optimal control uh in engineered systems
it tells you how to design the network
structures and maybe in natural networks
it can tell you why the network evolved
to have that structure in the first
place so this is very ambitious I'm not
going to be able to answer this question
in general but I'm going to give you uh
three different manifestations of this
kind of thinking uh I'm going to talk
about architectural features and
distributed control that come for free
uh and then I'm going to talk about
constraints that can be tractivity
imposed meaning lead to convex problems
uh and those give some insights and then
I'm going to talk about large scale
networks and architectures that have
fragility which means you need to do
something about that architecture change
it to introduce easy of ease of
controlability okay so that's so these
are going to be particular case studies
not an overarching Theory but I think
kind of lead maybe to the directions
You' want to go if you want to form an
overarching Theory so let me go back to
theme one which is the analogies between
networks and pdes so this is the
standard consensus algorithm on a graph
I don't think I think I don't need to
describe that to this audience but this
is the laian uh Matrix of a network uh
that is the so here's an example of this
you start with a quantity at some node
and it diffuses over the network this is
effectively the network version of the
diffusion
equation um when you have consensus in
directed networks under some assumptions
no Cycles Etc you can think about this
as a combination of advection defusion
on a
network
um so you could also have which is some
people uh look at consensus with
additive
noise uh in you know that corresponds to
the diffusion equation with random
Fields time varying and spatially
varying random Fields uh in physics this
is called the Edwards Wilkinson equation
which in 1D describes the Dynamics of a
long polymer chain in sort of in L ofan
forces uh you can think of this as
additive uncertainty now you can think
about a uh consensus for example with
random link failures where the structure
of the network is changing
stochastically in time the counter part
of that would be uh diffusion in a
medium whose diffusion constant could be
time varying and spatially varying so in
physics this is called diffusion in
disordered
media um and you can
combine uh sort of media disorder
together with additive uncertainty uh
and you can think of it you know the
Continuum version of that is this uh
this kind of this kind of Dynamics even
though it looks uh a little bit looks
simple it's linear but with random
coefficients can actually have extremely
rich Behavior so nikolia and and Wang
and and others have shown that even when
this uncertainty is gaussian you can
have behavior that leads to heavy tals
and Levy flights and so on uh so it has
a very rich
phenomenology um another set of examples
this is the famous sort of V strings
otherwise people call them vular platoon
but since these days I'm allergic to all
military metaphors I'm going to call
them military strings instead uh so
sorry I mean vehicle strings uh so here
let's say you have a a string of
vehicles on a freeway the objective is
to go at a constant velocity trajectory
and you want to you say do velocity
position and velocity feedback and if
you close the loop on velocity and
position feedback you get a model that
looks like this where the matrices K and
F are the feedbacks on all velocities
and positions and they kind of look they
look like Lans and I'll talk about this
in a little bit more
detail you can also have the problem of
phas synchronization in transmission
networks and the model looks very Sim
similar like this this is the linearized
swing equations of power networks they
have a very similar structure to this
equation um the analogy here is with the
wave equation so here this is the wave
equation with what's called Kelvin V
damping and this is the uh for the case
we're here the damping term is constant
times the identity this is kind of
viscous damping uh but again these
Systems Support wav like phenomena and
so it's not surprising that they are
analogous to the wave equation all
right uh so let me talk about um uh
these three different different uh
aspects of the problem so I'll talk
about uh architecture features that come
for free and how you could use them
maybe to characterize limits of
performance so let's look at a very
simple
example uh I want to do distributed
control of diffusion so think about a
bar that is being where the temperature
is being controlled by a heat input
which is your control U of XT uh this is
an idealization of course just to
understand limits of performance often
you don't have that many
actuators um and the performance
objective may be something like lqr so
here you would integrate in both space
and time and you can think about this as
an inner product in the space L2 over
over space uh and then integral in time
0 to Infinity uh so one of the things
that are easy to show is that if in an
lqr problem you're a b q and r operators
are translation invariant here
translation invariant with respect to
space then necessarily the solutions of
the uh R operator radi equation for this
problem is will also inherit that
spatial
invariance um here's an example so so
then the optimal
control is an integral in space uh at
each time so it's memoryless in time and
in space it's given by say a a kernel
that represents the spatial action on
the state to produce the control by the
way in in throughout this talk the state
is denoted by sigh not x x is a
positioned coordinate so that's
important to keep in mind um so uh
transition invariance means that the
integral kernel of this operator is
toets so it has the structure that is
shown here um and
and so what that means is that the
control for this at this particular
location is given by a convolution
kernel because a toets operator acting
as an integral kernel is equivalent to a
convolution in space so the control at
this point takes the state everywhere
and convolves it the control over here
has the same convolution kernel acting
on a shifted version of the state so
that's the implication of the uh
translation in
variance uh you can this is quite
General so if you have a sort of a
homogeneous medium with an actuator
sensus array that's has some regular
pattern you can describe that as sort of
equivariance with respect to a group
action and then the first architectural
feature that you can show about this is
that the optimal controller will inherit
that spatial invariance or this the equ
facial equivariance more accurately and
so the controller can also have a very
special
structure and which is related to the
equivalent structure of the medium that
you're trying to control uh this is not
too difficult to show but um but the
point of this is let's forget about the
proof once you realize this then you
don't have to actually Implement an
optimal controller you can implement the
same sort of convolution structure with
pids for example okay and that is sort
of something that uh this sort of the
this architectural feature enables you
to do
right
uh so you can also do this in bonded
domains let me let me skip that because
I have a lot of material to get through
uh so this is not restricted to only
infinite domains over groups it's it's
it's a little more General but there's
another architectural feature with which
is very important and that's the uh
these the Decay properties of these
kernels so again uh let me tell you how
this is solved uh and it's very very
simple uh so because of the translation
in variance in space take a for
transform in space and now you have a
differential equation in time uh that is
algebraic in space Lambda is the spatial
wave number so that's spatial frequency
so this is a very simple parameterized
family of first order
equations uh you can do the same thing
with the performance objective and then
your ratti equation becomes a
parameterized family in this case of
scalar uh Rat equation which is a
quadratic equation which back in middle
school you all learned is solved by the
quadratic formula so that's quite easy
to do at every Lambda so you get a
parameterized family now in fua space of
the ratti equation solution as well as
the feedback back uh gain
now this the feedback gain in Fier space
spatial Fu space is an irrational
function so it doesn't correspond to a
PD operator but rather an convolution
operator and then the key question is
what is
that oh come on okay that's that's that
was an important uh figure that it's not
uh rendering but I'll try to describe it
um
so you could
um you could here um take this uh Fier
symbol and you can extend it into the
complex plane the over through a extend
it to a strip around the imaginary axis
and the extent of the strip tells you
the Decay rate in space of the
convolution kernel yes so if I
understand this correctly related to
what the with the topic was at the
beginning you're saying that the of
controlling this problem is related to
the spatial dependence that the system
has uh what I'm trying to say is that
the um if you think about this kernel
here right the the Decay rate away from
the diagonal uh determines how far you
should look for how far you should do
state feedback so if it's very small you
can kind of truncate it and and be local
so the Decay rate is a proxy for how
localized the optimal centralized
controller is that's something you get
for free right and I'm going to show you
the dependence on the various system
parameters of that right so that's why
characterizing the Decay rate is
important but in this particular case uh
again because of this analytic extension
idea the the Decay rate of course is
related to the abscissa of these Branch
Cuts related to the square root and so
you can characterize it in terms of the
system
parameters here because it's very easy
to find the branch cuts of this square
root uh so this is this is quite General
you don't need special invariance for
this uh this is a much more general
property about the natural decay of
centralized controllers but this kind of
characterization in terms of system
parameters is something that you only
get with spatially invariant and this F
technique Fu transform technique and I'm
this is an important point I want to
make so let's look at what happens to
the Decay rate uh for example it's
related to this quantity so if this goes
to Infinity uh you get very rapid Decay
and if it goes to zero you get a very
fat kernel so that requires information
from far away uh special cases uh if you
look at Q over R going to Infinity which
is the cheap control case it tells you
that your K is almost decentralized
so if you have cheap control which means
you can tolerate large control signals
you don't need to look far away but
alternatively if control is expensive uh
then the kernel is highly centralized
which means the optimal controller wants
to gather information from far away
that's how it compensates for the lack
of local actuator Authority
um so but you can actually uh look at do
a little bit further analysis and look
at the uh the role the plant plant
Dynamics also Play Because here I
assumed Alpha and beta be uh to be one
and let's just step back for a minute um
in other areas of engineering you use
these sort of non-dimensional Quant
numbers like the rolds number or you
look for various length scales in the
problem to give you insight for example
the rolds number allows you to
understand the phenomenology of a LGE
ship uh by doing a lab scale model that
are matched to the same renals number
and that's extremely useful uh so you
finding these non-dimensional numbers is
very important in addition you also look
for characteristic length and time
scales that characterize your problem so
we don't do that very much in controls
but I think it's very useful as I'll
show you in a in a second so for example
signal to noise ratio is one such
non-dimensional number that is extremely
useful right
uh so I'm going to do this very quickly
but you could do some sort of uh unit
analysis of the lqr problem and bring in
the roles of Alpha and B in this case
but basically it boils down to this your
uh controller's characteristic length
scale that is how far the kernel uh uh
is spread is actually depending on one
over this number which has to do with
the actuator of Authority rate divided
by the diffusion rate and so if
diffusion is fast and you also have high
actuator Authority that gives you the
sort of the same length scale so both
the speed of diffusion as well as the
actuator Authority both play a role in
determining the um the renal number the
not the renal number the length scale so
fast open loop diffusion gives you more
centralized kernel because the Dynamics
of the plant are spreading information
disturbances very quickly and so the
controller has to gather information
from far away and high actuator
Authority makes you more localized but
both of these have to be taken into
account and the length scale depends on
the ratio of both okay uh you could do
the same thing for the wave equation so
you might imagine that this is actually
quite useful for understanding how to
size your
actuators uh for a particular problem
like this there's another version of
this that was done by hunal arales who
was a student here two years ago uh of
Ali jbai and pekos soy and she looked at
the calman filter version of this
problem and the calman filter is
characterized by both the process noise
and the measurement noise and uh and
then you know you could do the same sort
of
analysis uh and you can find a a length
scale for the filter uh for example if
you have fast open loop diffusion you
have a more centralized skur this is the
this is the cman gain this is the kernel
of the cman gain in The Observer and so
that requ that tells you how far the
cman filter needs to gather information
to give you estimate of your local
state um and then if you distrust the
model for example large process noise
then your kernel gets localized it's not
useful to gather information from far
away because your model could actually
be quite wrong so your estimate of the
local state may not benefit from
information from far away since their
model is is quite different uh again you
could uh and you could sort of do a
branch Locus analysis similar to what I
showed you to determine analyticity
regions and determine the spread of the
cernal uh and in in that case uh you get
some interesting observations that Kunal
made uh so for example there's a
particular set of parameters where the
common filter is completely
decentralized its performance is
actually quite bad but the optimal thing
is completely decentralized in that case
the the measurement noise is spatially
correlated and it kind of conspires with
the pl Dynamics so that neighboring
measurements can only make your estimate
worse which is kind of an interesting
observation that we didn't really see
before doing this kind of non
dimensional
analysis all right so um again these are
very useful exercises in terms of
understanding the performance
limitations of your optimal centralized
estimator um so here are um so now the
second um and I'm going to this is okay
I'm going to try to skip through this
I'm just going to mention one important
aspect of
this uh so I want to do constrained
controller design so what I told you
before are the features that come from
free the centralized controller the
centralized estimator has these
properties what if I want to impose
properties now so I want the uh
estimator or the controller to have uh
constraints on the spatial information
of spatial spread of
information um so one thing that is
quite common to do is to look at a sort
of a standard problem of robust control
after the Ula parameterization becomes a
model matching problem and the question
would be now since the model matching
problem involves the Ula parameter Q you
can ask if I impose constraints on the
controller say controller only looks at
in a network problem only to the
neighbors uh does that correspond to
nice constraints on Q and the answer is
generally no but there are special cases
I want to talk about one of them because
that's kind of
insightful uh another area that's become
common today is related to what's called
what I would call closed loop synthesis
so it was known um you know since the
80s that if you look at the um input
output uh closed loop and you look at
stabilizing controllers then you get
these aine constraints the set of
stabilized closed Loops is an aine set
but the constraints the aine constraints
that describe it are really kind of
horrible they involve in the myo case
interpolation constraints with right
zero directions and left zero directions
and so on so recently a new framework
was proposed uh by nuc matney John Dole
and wank uh which they call system level
synthesis uh which is not in my opinion
a very descriptive name but really it's
a it's a variation on closed loop
synthesis where the rather than putting
the constraints on the full closed loop
put the constraints on a portion of it
and then the constraints become these
very nice sort of apine constraints that
don't involve right half plane PS in
zeros and zero directions so they're
much more simple to implement
numerically so that's one aspect of it
and there's another aspect in the two
are independent of each other even
though often they're discussed in tandem
is that the once you design the closed
loop that now satisfies the certain
structural constraints say again nearest
neighbor for the closed loop you can
then get a controller implementation
that also satisfies that same con uh
it's not optimal it's a relaxation in
general unless you look at certain
classes of problems but it is a way to
get you constrained controllers from uh
in a convex manner I'm not going to talk
about this I'm going to talk briefly
about uh this
problem so
so this actually uh goes back to the
work of petus
vulgaris who are the student at Lids
back back in the um in the 80s actually
uh and then the the idea is that if if
if I look at the set of constraints on
K and that set was closed under
additions compositions and
inversions uh then it's closed under
feedback and if you think about the ula
parameterization in the stable case that
means I can go back and forth between K
and Q and uh by in by additions and
inversions uh and products and so the
same set of constraints apply on K and Q
if and only if and so the problem
becomes uh uh in some sense if I have
convex constraints on K then I get
convex constraints on Q and then the
model matching problem is is linear iine
and so the problem is convex uh so for
example is lower triangular MOS systems
uh symmetric Etc but an important
counter example which you want is banded
a banded controller which for example in
a linear chain would be nearest neighbor
that's not closed under these
constraints so that doesn't uh it's not
in this class nonetheless uh this is
interesting then riten provided a
generalization of this where you don't
really need closure under products but
closure under this sort of quadratic uh
form and they called it quadratic
invariance uh you could do the unstable
case of course it follows uh but let me
show you what it means in for spatial
temporal systems because that gives you
a little bit of
insight so let's look at the wave
equation again with an input U and the
output is s the state and that's the
wave equation with wave speed C if you
look at its impulse response or this
spatial tempor impulse response you get
an input output description uh of the
system from U to Y and basically it's a
spatial tempor
convolution and if you think about the
spatial temporal impulse response H it
tells you something about how an input
will spread out in space and time and
the impulse response for the wave
equation looks like this looks like a
cone right and that tells you so
disturbance comes in it doesn't show up
in s until a certain time determined by
the wave speed
so an important quantity to look at is
the support set of this spatial temporal
impulse response and here you have uh
con causality for the wave equation and
then think about uh systems whose spal
temporal impulse response belong in a
funnel a funnel meaning that it's made
up of two functions both of which are
concave uh and then one can show that
this class is closed under compositions
inversions and feed compositions
feedback and additions and so we call
this funnel causality and what it really
means is the
following if you want to let's say
control a system where the plant the has
a certain support set for its spatial
temperary impulse response what that
means is that if a disturbance comes
into somewhere in the plant it takes a
certain speed before it gets to a
location another location in the plant
determined by that speed right um if the
controller funnel contains the plant
funnel so I use a controller that in
which the information within the
controller travels faster than the
disturbances travel in the plant then
that's a convex
problem okay so that tells you I mean it
it tells you that the problem is convex
maybe it's more tractable and so that
tells you kind of an architectural
limitation on the controller that you
need to have a tractable problem you
need the information passing within the
controller to be faster than the
disturbance propagation through through
the
plant uh you can you know there are
generalizations of this over graphs uh
that was a done by Randy kogal um but
it's not quite satisfactory right
because compared to the formulas I
showed you for the Decay rate which gave
you a lot of insight what I really would
like is an a formula for uh like the
controller speed divided by the pl plant
speed as a kind of a Reynolds number or
a non-dimensional number that
characterizes how difficult the problem
is and we don't really have an explicit
formula for that we just know that the
problem is convex when this ratio is
larger than one yeah okay so I'm going
to skip this because I'm running out of
time and I want to move to this uh the
third and last topic which I think is is
more recent and more
interesting and I want to look at the
scalability of
certain uh Network control problems over
larger
networks um so I'm going to talk briefly
about consensus and vular formations and
then some new work uh related to this
phenomenon called Anderson localization
um so I'm going to mention physics a lot
uh and so the subject of condensed
matter physics is really the study of
large systems of interacting atoms and
molecules um it is not that surprising
that this is related to large scale
Network control problems because there
we're studying large numbers of
interacting Dynamic systems they're not
molecules and atoms they're macro
systems but the certain mathematical
patterns are common between the two
Fields uh so here's one problem from
statistical mechanics that's that's
interesting and seems to be and it is
related to the vular strings problem as
I'll show you in a second uh so this is
called the problem of harmonic solids so
you you model Atomic luses uh as balls
and springs so this is a completely
classical model of the vibrations within
a an atomic uh an a crystal lce say
um the terms they used in physics as
short range interactions the atoms are
uh interacting with neighbors only uh if
you think about a network operative
control system think about that is only
local feedback okay so that's the
equivalent term uh the question that
arises is is uh when do you get long
range order so what does that mean in a
crystal
lce the position of an atom here is
correlated with the position of an atom
billions of SES away that's what it
means to have a solid Crystal otherwise
it's a fluid or a gas so uh in terms of
formation of vehicles or you know uh
schools of fish swimming or uh flocks of
birds this could be thought of as the
rigidity of the
formation and then the question in
physics is how come short range
interactions lead to Long long range
order okay in which structures does this
is this
possible so what is known is that if you
look at uh Crystal lates or regular lses
like basically uh Z to the D in
dimension one and two short range
interaction cannot lead to long range
order but in dimensions three and and
higher uh long range order is possible
and so as they like to say only solids
can only form in
3D um so similar things appear to hold
in control problems even though control
problems are not really about atoms and
and molecules but let let me show you
the the results for luses so you can
study consensus first order consensus in
this case in the presence of random
disturbances now you don't reach
consensus what you what the best you can
hope for is that all the St wobble
together around some Network mean and
then the variance of this wobble is kind
of the your proxy for rigidity and now
you can Define you know the details you
don't have to pass through this this is
basically average deviation from Network
average at a steady state uh you can
show that that's the 1/ N times the
trace of the pseudo inverse of this
lassan and so it's this quantity which
is one over the all the igen values of
the plin
reciprocals except for the one at zero
of course so it's kind of like the
center of mass of the reciprocal of the
igen values all right so that's easy to
show and then you can calculate them ASM
totically as n goes to Infinity for
luses and you see that they scale like
this so in dimension one it scales
unboundedly with the size of the network
in dimension two also unbounded but with
log of n much more slowly but in
dimension three and higher it is bounded
okay
so uh this is very much related to many
other well-known problems like effective
resistance in resistor lates uh random
walks the return uh possibility of a
random walk in D dimensional luses they
always involve calculating a quantity
like this and you can think about this
quantity as basically kind of the
density of igen values or the reciprocal
of the igen values near zero right
that's really what's important it's a in
the physics they call that the density
of States uh and you can calculate that
in D dimensional luses this uh quantity
ASM totically behaves like the uh the
total mass over a ball with density one
over r s so the density has a
singularity at zero but the total mass
is actually bounded in dimensions three
and higher but in dimension one and two
it is not and that's really the basic
all of the different mathematical
arguments boil down to this right so
that's why it's common in all all of
these other
areas you could do the same thing for uh
for platoon now this is second order
consensus and I'll just tell you quickly
what the answer is so what happens in
platoon is that if you only have local
uh measurements say you have ranging
devices measuring the distance and the
relative Rel distance a relative
velocity to the Vehicles near you uh but
you don't have any absolute measurements
then as you simulate a very large uh
well-designed controlled
formation subject to stochastic
disturbances it wobbles like an
accordion as it's moving down the
freeway and this is sort of a depiction
of that for a 100 vehicles and you can't
get rid of that unless you introduce
something like everybody knows their
distance to the leader some absolute uh
measurement and so you can you can
analyze this uh and there's a mechanical
model
equivalent and basically the problem
becomes this so here I have a an example
but this is it's more General than this
example where my feedback law at each
vehicle is related to the relative
distance and relative velocities ahead
and behind but if I have a speedometer
in this system then I can compare my
velocity to the agreed upon velocity and
I can use that for feedback if I know my
distance in an absolute frame of
reference uh then I can use that
feedback so I'm calling these absolute
measurements and these are relative
measurements and so it turns out that if
you add these in uh these green K andf
are standard llans that have an igen
value at zero and as n goes to Infinity
the igen values accumulate towards zero
but but the absolute measurements shift
that Spectrum away from zero and then it
gives you the scalings that you will see
here so if I have absolute position
absolute velocity that sort of accordian
motion goes away but if I only have
relative position absolute velocity then
the some proxy for that accordion motion
will scale as n
unboundedly and if I have a set a flying
formation for which getting absolute
velocity is not possible then the
scalings are much worse okay and so what
that means is that the the Splatoon
problem or the vehicle strings in 1D
vehicles on a highway is fundamentally
difficult because of the combination of
two things the 1D topology and this
relative
feedback the inability to have these
absolute measurements now this is useful
because it allows you to okay if this is
going to be the problem
okay you can't change the topology right
you're on a lane on a freeway there's
not much you can do about that right but
you can maybe do something about this
this is a thing you want to do something
about maybe Institute a communication
systems basically line of sight
Communications and Cascade the the the
measure distances to various Vehicles
there are many ways you can think about
ameliorating that but but that really is
what this analysis is useful for
okay um all right so uh let me skip
through all of this
um and I want to talk I want to end by
talking about uh this question where uh
I've discussed these additive
disturbances in harmonic solars and
vehicular
platoon uh I want to talk about the role
of multiplicative disturbances
multiplicative
stochasticity right um and this is
related to another physics problem uh
which goes by the name of Anderson
localization so let me describe the
problem of Anderson localization in the
simplest mathematical model this is an
experiment you can all do in mat laab in
uh with very little
effort so consider this Matrix which is
kind of the lassan of the 1D heat
equation if you do finite difference
discretization uh and consider
perturbing it with a diagonal Randomness
like this right and I want to think
about and these are IID random variables
and considering large matrices and I
must look at the effect of adding this
Randomness on the igen vectors of this
Matrix so and look at the igen vectors
of Matrix before the randomness and
after before the randomness the igen
vectors here this is a matrix of size
10,000 and I'm plotting the igen vectors
they are as you would expect the sign
dinos
SWS if I add a little bit of Randomness
this is what the igen vectors look
like this is on a standard scale and
this is on a semilog scale so they this
is the first five igen vectors so
they're Peak they Peak they're very
narrowly supported they're actually
supported everywhere as you can see here
they're very narrowly supported and they
occur at random locations
and if you look at a semilog scale you
see that they actually have this
characteristic exponential decay away
from the peak so they're highly what's
called
localized um almost surely as n goes to
Infinity uh localized and so for very
large matrices it takes almost no amount
of Randomness to change the nature of
the igen vectors from this to this so
the nature of the vectors is very
fragile so here they're delocalized as
they're called or they have white
support and here they're very localized
yes
um okay you're you're um uh I can answer
this because if you do the same thing in
3D and those matrices also have igen
values close to zero this doesn't
happen I'll explain this in a minute
yeah so it's it's really related to the
structure of the Matrix more so than its
igen values I can produce another Matrix
with the same igen values with a
different structure for which this
phenomenon does not
occur okay all right so so this is a
fragility phenomenon now uh the physics
interpretation of this just to give you
the historical context is as follows uh
so if you think about H not as the um
the hamiltonian of a of a say in the
shortener equation and then you add a
little bit of Randomness that's adding a
little bit of Randomness to the in the
potential so the think this is the uh
wave function of an electron in a medium
which has slight Randomness in the uh
potential so Randomness in the material
property and um what Anderson showed uh
in 19 58 is that in dimension one uh any
Randomness with arbitrarily small
variance will shift the wave function
from being delocalized meaning the
electron can be anywhere in the medium
to this localized which means the
electron is pinned and sometimes this is
called the metal insulator
transition however in dimensions three
and higher you need a certain threshold
of the randomness before you see this
phenomenon of
localization and so that is again a
manifestation of the role that the
dimension or the connectivity of the
network plays and this happens both in
discrete networks in Continuum space
that that's it happens in all of them
but this is a phenomena of the fragility
of the igen vectors of a large
Matrix okay um so so why is this
important for us uh well this is still
very active area of research to this day
because the the phenomenology here in
various Dimensions various types of uh
uh a um Pro potentials is actually quite
wide um in semiconductor physics this is
really a very important current research
problem um but more interestingly for us
recently it's been discovered that
localization happens without
Randomness and so uh so I've just
discussed random Ness in media um but
you can have Randomness due to Geometry
if you will complex geometry and I don't
like to use the word complex because it
just means that you don't really know
what's going on um but which is true in
this case and I you'll see in a minute
uh but for lack of a better name it's
it's uh it will happen over non-lattice
networks with no Randomness but it have
provided they have a sufficiently
complex geometry and I'll show you uh a
an example of this this is currently a
very active area of research there's a
Simon collaboration on localization of
waves people are discovering this in
Acoustics they're discovering it in in
various other areas I'm going to show
you a fascinating example uh in uh
molecular vibrations in enzymes and then
I'm going to relate that to uh something
like the swing equations for Power
Systems so so here's a model so this is
actually a very interesting paper from
2019 that describes this so you could
take a uh enzymes are catalysts and
they're these very large
biomolecules um they have a there many
of them have a known 3D structure
through x-ray crystallography and so the
exact 3D structure the positions of all
the atoms is well known uh you can have
a model for how this uh molecule
vibrates CL classical model we just
think of it again as balls and springs
and the strength of the Springs are
related to the interaction between
different uh atoms so what this work had
with this paper had done is to take this
model of a molecule as a as a collection
of masses and springs in
3D the uh an enzyme starts out as a
chain it's encoded in in DNA so it
started out as a chain of amino acids
and you can label each element of the
Chain by the original one-dimensional
order from which it arose before it
folds and based on that you can come up
with a lassan matrix depicted here
graphically which shows the so the
dimension here is the index along the
chain of the different amino acids and
blue dots means there's a spring of
substanti of sort of above a certain
Thresh strength and white means there's
no connection in this 3D structure so
this is the lassan Matrix of the
vibrations classical vibrations in 3D of
this large set of masses and
springs now you can look at the modes of
vibration both the igen values and the
igen vectors of this llan Matrix gives
you the vibrational modes and their
temporal frequencies and what you
discover is that what they have
discovered is that at the top of the
spectrum meaning at the very high
frequency of vibrations which in this
case are in the range of 2.8 to 3 terz
the um the this is a depiction of the
vibrational modes again along the chain
here you have about 600 elements you the
igen vectors have peaky locations they
have very large amplitudes of vibrations
here but this doesn't tell you very much
unless you until you look at the 3D
structure and what you see so these are
these are localized igen vectors because
they're peaked very sharply peaked at
different locations when you look at the
3D structure you discover that these all
of these Peaks are gathered together in
roughly a small location in this
molecule and remarkably what so what
that what does that mean that means at
the very high frequencies top of the
spectrum of
vibrations uh the only a certain portion
of this enzyme that one site
is vibrating with large amplitude and
the rest of the molecule is basically
not moving at that frequency so
remarkably those frequencies and those
locations are found to be responsible
for the rate promoting function of the
enzyme so this molecule was designed so
that only those sites which are rat
promoting when which which play the
catalytic function are the ones that
have the large uh amplitude oscillations
at the frequencies that are chemically
relevant for
catalysis and so here localization is
occurring not because of Randomness
there's no Randomness in the structure
right this is a fixed structure it's
happening because of a complex
geometry right and this and so they've
done this for a large number of enzymes
this is not as surprising here's a
mathematical sort of abstract
mathematical explanation for why this
might happen so if you take theasian
over a reg irregular domain with a very
irregular boundary that's my proxy for
uh complex
geometry but the Lain itself has no
Randomness in it it's just constant
coefficient you do a transformation a
domain transformation of this complex
geometry say to the unit
ball and then you look at the transform
PD operator the complexity of the
geometry is then reflected into the
complexity of the diffusion coefficient
so you end up with an equivalent problem
on a very nice symmetric region with no
complexity in its geometry but the
complexity is all in the diffusion
coefficient now so that's appr proxy for
the randomness of the media so that's
why complex geometry can be thought of
as actually a kind of a complexity in
the um or this Randomness in the medium
so we wanted to think about okay I just
need five more minutes and and I'll be
done so this is the the most important
part of the talk I think because this is
really current work uh we wanted to look
at simp what is the simplest example of
an nwork uh for which this localization
phenomena of igen vectors occurs and
does it have implications for
robustness okay so here's a simple
example this is an by the way this is
not a circle this is the the the those
two nodes are not connected uh but the
connectivity here is is increasing and
then it's constant and then decreasing
this is the what the laian Matrix looks
like very simple here are the igen
vectors plotted this is a network of
size 200 so I'm this is the igen vector
in increasing IG value so indexed by
increasing IG value this is this is
space so that's the site number and you
see the first 80 roughly the first 80
igen vectors are peaky they're localized
and the remainder are kind of not really
they're spread out over a certain
region uh here's uh here's what the igen
values uh look like and I've labeled
them by inspection of the ones that are
peaky versus the ones are not so here's
an example of a peaky igen vector it
Peaks very sharply this is IG Vector
number 20 here's a
semilog to show you the exponential
decay rate and here's an example of a
non Pagen Vector that has a mass that is
spread uh throughout the region of the
network so I labeled this with blue and
label the localized ones the red that we
have some understanding about why they
the difference because these have larger
gaps which are you can relate to the
Decay rate anyway uh here's another
example this is another
Network where now the localized igen
vectors are actually towards the top of
the spectrum rather than the bottom and
you can come up with many other
examples so our question is does this
localization of igen vectors have an
implication for robustness again
motivated by the Anderson localization
problem which is a fragility phenomenon
and so you can you know this I'm going
to uh try to look at this problem in
terms of the so-call pseudo Spectrum so
uh the standard Spectrum by the way this
is a very nice book by Lloyd trathan on
Spectra and P Spectra this is basically
robust control uh in the language of
numerical analysts and and physicists
where they study this thicken spectrum
of a matrix with the perturbation having
Norm less than Epsilon you can look they
don't really look at it this way but
here we're going to look at it this way
which is a kind of a compressed pudos
Spectrum uh this object should be very
familiar familar to those of you who uh
took do you do you teach robust control
still here so we submitted this paper
and two reviewers out of uh four uh did
not understand that this is the same as
the super level set of the res of the
transfer function uh
anyway do it's good to teach robust
control so we're going to look at this
thick and S Spectrum for for this
network which now
uh I'm going to put this Lan as the
lloan say of the Swing equations of a
power Network I'm going to perturb a
node with the Delta whose Norm is less
than Epsilon and I'm going to look at
the Spectrum of this uh operator so this
is a uh if you look at the Spectrum here
it's with a small beta it's sled up uh
along the very to the left of the
imaginary
axis if this EI is just the Vector with
just one in the I position and zero
everywhere if I place that in a for a
node in this region so I'm perturbing
the Dynamics of that generator in this
region in the localized region and I
look at the resulting Pudo Spectrum it's
uh here you see a zoomed area it in this
particular set of parameters it's
perturbed it goes into the right half
plane on the other hand if I perturb
with the same value of perturbation a
node in the delocalized region it barely
has any
effect so in this network oops in this
network a small perturbation in the
Dynamics of a node in this region has a
huge effect compared to perturbation of
a node in the delocalized region so
another manifestation of this fragility
phenomenon that's due to the
localization of the igen vectors of
aasum right there's no um in some sense
here the the disorder is not throughout
the domain the disorder really is
Randomness in the Dynamics and and
similar things can be shown I'm not
showing them here for Edge uh dynamical
Edge perturbation so I assume the link
between two nodes can have a dynamic
perturbation a Delta that is dynamic
with Norm less than Epsilon that link if
it's in the delocalized it's sorry if
it's in a localized region is has a much
bigger effect and those Effects by the
way the contrast between
uh the this perturbation this
perturbation increases as I increase the
network size so this is another
fragility phenomenon uh that is due to
something new not uh uh not really the
lattice structure because these are not
lce networks these are networks with in
quotes complex structure but as you can
see I don't have to make the structure
too
complex uh to to to begin to see this
phenomenon um so this is something we're
studying currently it has obvious
implications for Power Systems um
basically here the network topology
determines the limits of performance
again but now limits of performance is
in terms of fragility and robustness
okay so uh sorry I went over time but I
really wanted to get through that and uh
yeah I've I've said all that yes thank