yeah so I'm a professor in the chemistry
department at MIT I am also a member of
the Koch Institute and the broad
Institute I've also been involved over
the years at the center for
Environmental Health and Sciences
I came to MIT really excited about the
convergence of engineering and
Innovative science
and that's what really drew me I did my
postdoc at Harvard Meadows Medical
School across the river with professor
John collieres studying Anthrax toxin
trying to understand how infectious
agents such as Anthrax toxin or cholera
toxin botulinum neurotoxin actually
infects cells at the molecular level and
through those interactions I uh
certainly heard a lot about MIT and was
able to interact with people here and
it's always fascinating wanted to be a
member of the team here and so in many
ways I'm very fortunate to have had that
experience as a postdoc across the river
but super excited to start here as a
professor in 2011. before my postdoc I
actually did my PhD
in at the University of Chicago in
organic chemistry
investigating how we can actually use
chemistry to make peptides and proteins
and that's really these two areas
influenced me strongly in terms of my
efforts at MIT that are underway right
now yeah so I've since my early days in
my education I ultimately wanted to be
an organic chemist I actually wanted to
go in the laboratory use experiments to
actually build molecules at the
molecular level I found that fascinating
and through my journey at University of
Chicago I met a professor that said Brad
do you actually know proteins are
natural products and my laboratory
actually makes them and so immediately I
jumped in I said I want to actually make
proteins using chemistry I thought that
was fascinating proteins are the
molecular machines that allow us to live
and so I thought at some level if we
could understand them with molecules
then perhaps in the future we could
design them design them with computers
design them in the laboratory and that's
exactly what's going on now but through
those efforts at University Chicago I
learned a lot of chemistry but I didn't
learn about biology and so for me to
bring together my education I thought I
should go do a postdoc trying to
understand biology how is it that
infectious disease actually works how is
it Anthrax toxin for instance infects a
cell that really allowed me to connect
the dots between chemistry and biology
and so that's a big part of me and how I
actually built my research program at
MIT which is how do we think at the
molecular level how do we design and
understand molecules and then translate
that into some meaningful aspect
hopefully that would affect a human
being so a big part of my group has
always been to look at nature how does
nature actually solve a lot of the
problems that we think about in terms of
health issues and so we're always
learning from nature a big part of that
was to say okay we have this delivery
problem in biotechnology the delivery
problem refers to the fact that larger
molecules eopeptide a protein and
oligonucleotides simply cannot be
delivered effectively into cells it
can't be delivered across your
gastrointestinal tract and so can we
look to Nature to understand how nature
impacts delivers like a protein into the
cytoplasm and so that's where the
anthrax inspired me to understand what
is Nature's molecular machine for
delivery of large enzymes into cells and
so we simply ask questions about that
and we rendered Anthrax toxin non-toxic
of course and then asked that question
can we piggyback or hijack that delivery
system now to actually get proteins into
the cell and the answer is yes we can
and we've been doing that for the past
10 years and we continuously learn in
those efforts and in thinking through
how do we solve these big challenges
another issue is it just takes too long
to do experiments it takes a long time
to make the molecules prepare them and
then let alone go study them in an
animal or in tissue culture on cells and
so forth so in light of that in the
spirit of MIT we've been asking over and
over again how do we accelerate the pace
in which we actually do science a big
part of it in the chemistry department
is okay we need to make molecules and so
we've built robots that essentially are
at this stage of where you type in
molecules proteins that you would like
and you hit go on the machine and it
actually makes it and that's the basis
of what we call a rapid flow or
automated flow protein synthesis now
we're continuously expanding that
technology to the case in which it will
be next time hopefully in 10 years when
I'm giving an interaction or interview
we actually make a protein while we're
having the discussion