hello everybody we're to be talking
today about something that sounds really
esoteric really confusing vocabulary
reduction how do we go to vocabulary
reduction how do we reduce our
vocabulary are we talking about C Spot
Run what what does this mean it really
is about something that we do every time
we do analysis whether we do music
analysis or textual analysis or we're
trying to think about you know what
really happened um on that last phone
convers ation I had with u you know my
partner or friend or something like that
we're trying to reduce the number of
complexities down to something smaller
and more manageable and one of the
places where we do vocabulary reduction
quite a bit is in Roman numeral analysis
uh we don't label everything a Roman
numeral we tend to label the things
depending on who your teacher was maybe
she or he said we only label things that
are really chords what is that that mean
um when we're thinking about how we do
this as humans we don't really have to
think too much about how we do this we
just have to get better at doing this
but if we're going to train a computer
system to be able to tell us only the
things that are really there to reduce
the vocabulary of a score into something
more manageable then we're going to have
to understand this process quite a bit
better so that's what we're going to do
today I'm going to move over to the
Jupiter notebook and U today I didn't
have time to make every single thing a
little bit uh you know really polished
so you'll get kind of a sense of how I
how I program how I make up uh
assignments for us and how um some of
the wrong turns that happen along the
way maybe it'll be useful so let's go
over to
Jupiter okay we're going to start by
importing from music 21 the Corpus
method and let's load up a piece by
claraa Schuman her uh Piano Trio slow
movement one of my favorite pieces and
we've looked at this uh once in class
before and it's going to take a little
bit of time it's a little bit of a
slower thing you might need to wait
here okay it's a Piano Trio but it
begins with just the piano part it's
really lovely section let me find a
YouTube video and place that in here
and you can click on that or just Google
it find find it in there anyhow the next
uh eight measures we looked at once in
class and we can see it it's when the
violin and the cello enter and the piano
switches to something else the violin
playing the same Melody we looked at it
because of those um those Grace notes
sure if we can highlight that there
there we go um and they um
yeah and they were a problem for some of
our representations of been codings okay
so let's just extract the piano part
from here and you can see some of the
mistakes that I've made with my own uh
music 21 package that this happens I'm
like oh I want to extract two parts uh
first off that should be two to four
anyhow but in any case it's giving me a
list of um things so I've made two
mistakes uh that's not giving me a
stream it's giving me a list I'm going
to okay now I'm going to do this again
we're going to import the stream we're
going to um to create a new score not
part for putting things in and we're
going to put in gosh I cannot type piano
after all these uh we're going to put in
part two which is the piano right hand
and we're going to also put in part one
which is the piano left
hand and
in order to make this run faster we'll
just take the first 16 measures uh I put
measure zero just out of habit in case
there's a pickup measure there isn't in
this case so I could have really started
with one so now we're going to look at
just that little excerpt just the panel
part all that to get rid of some empty
rests but that's kind of okay
here okay so we're going to play um with
just creating the chords of this and
we'll remember the cify function which
is kind of a fun part of Music 21 and
we'll show it and because we're taking a
trouble cluff and a base cluff put
together in instruments this is always a
little bit wacky uh you kind of get used
to counting mcen numbers of uh Ledger
lines when you are playing with cify and
uh there were times in my life when I
could actually eyeball that first note
and say yep that's G I got it but those
times have have passed so instead we're
going to recurse go through every single
um element in every measure and
everything and get all the chords from
that c chords is now aart and we're
going to take every one of those chords
which we call C and put it into Clos
position and say that it's going to be
an octave four and uh in place equals
true we're going to replace the old
chord and now we're going to show that
uh the are the same thing and now things
look quite a bit better so um yep
there's a thing we can paare back up can
we kind of look at same page yeah a
little bit um yep that's a d down there
that's a g okay so so it worked worked
pretty well okay we'll Zoom back in
again so that we can see
great now what we're going to do is we
want to uh label everything that's
happening in this so first we're going
to add analyze the key what key are we
in we're in G major yep uh you'll see
that this is called The Piano Trio in G
minor but this movement is in G major
great so we're going to uh iterate over
every one of these chords again and
we're going to create a Roman numeral
for each of the chords actually we're
going to import the Roman package from
ran module from music 21 and there's
this cool thing that you wish you had
your last um time you were programming
your last problem set Roman numeral from
chord so we're going to take the chord
and uh say that we want the Roman
numeral in G we're actually going to
create an object uh called Gore major
which is a a variable which is the key
of G object and the reason for this is
otherwise we would have to create a new
key object for every chord and over time
that becomes slow so what we'll say is
for our original chords we'll give them
the lyrics which are equal to the figure
of the Roman numeral so whatever the
Roman numeral is will asside that to the
lyric you see it's not the fastest thing
in the world but now you can have it and
we can look at
um we can look at those odd chords in a
little bit you can go ahead and pause
the video if you want to look at them in
more detail have a nice
laugh but I'm just going to uh just get
a quick excerpt the first four measures
that first line there just so we can
compare without having to to move our
eyes up and down a lot
so now we'll compare this to the
original piano part uh with the left and
the right hands and just see do these
chords look about right okay yep see
there's that weird thing that that
second chord isn't really a six4 chord
it's really that that low G is still
sustaining and then uh is that a four
chord or is that a five 42 chord it's
going to be a little bit difficult
because we want to make sure is that a
patura or is that a chord tone it's a
little bit difficult in fact this would
be the challenge problem to be able to
take something where we have arpeggios
Melodies things and Do vocabulary
reduction on a piano part like this this
is still one of the big unsolved
problems in the field and make being
able to make progress on how do we
reduce the number number of You Know
chords of Roman numerals of analytical
things to only the quote unquote real
chords on a complex score on a
orchestral or a piano score is still one
thing that that you could get you know
an A++ you could get complete published
paper out of being able to do that for
now we're going to um and and there are
some great ways to do that we'll uh be
looking at a dissertation by a guy by
the name of Christopher William right uh
at some point for people who are very
interested in such
things we're going to be applying the
concepts of vocabulary reduction to box
four-part Corrals because these this is
music that tends to have all of the
harmonies changing very often and not
having a lot of the arpeggiation and
things that we were just
seeing you're going to be working in
groups and I'll talk about the problem
set later but I want to say that there's
two different approaches that you could
be using um and perhaps more to do this
kind of
assignment what I'll be doing in the
rest of the video is an approach where
you start by
labeling every vertical element and then
you start removing ones that don't seem
to actually be chords this is a great
way of working another way of working
that resembles perhaps a little bit more
closely how we as humans work is to
start by identifying non-harmonic tones
and putting them all out into various
places and then removing the vertical
chords that are not real
chords perhaps by also using the
various Roman numeral sections to give
you a sense I want to show a little bit
one particular B Coral we'll look at the
opening here of a four voice piece and
you can see moments that oh that looks
like a passing tone that looks like it's
going to be a little bit um yeah just on
its way someplace here it looks like a
neighbor
tone this might be a suspension to here
or or this might be a restruck
suspension and so on so we can do it uh
by hand but then how do we train the
computer to do it so that would be one
type of question and then once you've
trained a computer to identify these
tones you can create a version where you
remove them and
cified after this comes an essential
step of identifying where various key
changes might
be so regardless of whether you start
with looking at finding passing tones
neighbor tones and so on or start by
looking at every particular chord and
removing the end result ends up being
the same and your work can be judged by
how well each various part had been
identified through your
process I would suggest if you're
working and dividing up the tasks among
people in your group that you start with
the removal of various uh individual
non-harmonic
tones if on the other hand your group
chooses to uh work where everybody is
working together at each stage then
perhaps the technique I explained in the
rest of the video where you label chords
first will yield better
results but we can go and do something a
little bit easier if we stick to Corral
style compositions so we'll go back to
our favorite boach piece bwv 66.6 which
is going to have its own problem in a
little bit but we're going to cify it
I'm guess get cut and pasting up here
and we're going to again once we cify
everything put it into Clos position put
it into octave 4 and again replace all
the chords in place if you haven't seen
how this technique Works look at music
21 users guide chapter nine and chapter
10 we do that a lot there in fact with
this piece so you'll see um see some new
techniques and be able to do it a little
bit more slowly
so this piece has an interesting
characteristic that it ends in a
different key than where it begins so if
we look at the Key of measure 0 to2
using Carol Crum hansel's prob T key
analysis method which is built into
music 21 and we see that it's an a major
but then if we look at the last seven
measures 4 through 10 we see it's an F
minor so we're going to work on each to
the two parts separately so let's first
look at measures 0 to two and get this
excerpt as bords uncore excert should
probably called it excert one whatever
and we can look at those first two
measures and let's use the same
technique that we used with clar Schuman
um to go through each chord and get a
Roman numeral from it and then put the
lyrics in so we can see it we just have
to change G major to a major again you
can just put the string a there but I
kind of prefer to do this so we'll do a
major and a major and um kind of
change uh C chords to B chords excerpt
and of course uh a mage is not the same
as a major so we'll go ahead and fix
that put that in and now we'll take this
excerpt and show it
and we could see okay it's quite a bit
simpler we have the one 56
six yeah things like that um this is
actually a really good time to
remember uh think about references
because we haven't really talked about
this so this is just the excerpt of just
the two measures when we go back and
look at all of the chords one of the
things you can see is that the figures
do sustain back to the that part in
other words the chords in the excert are
the exact same objects as the chords in
the cify part so what you change on one
of them will change on the other but if
we go all the way back to the original
bu
part and we show it we'll see that hey
there's no lyrics anywhere anything
because there were no chords there and
we um just can't sort of get back to
that anyhow that was a little bit of a
digression while we uh look at the Roman
numerals here these look like the kinds
of Roman numerals I was taught uh so
there's not too much too much to do
there so let's go back to the second BL
excerpt the one that's in F minor and
measures 4 through 10 so we'll go ahead
and get measures 4 through 10 and we'll
call that b exer B chords excerpt
2 and measures 4 through 10 when we show
this part you're going to see that
there's one problem with uh all of our
um showing things and that is to say
that the the measuring numbers are not
going to be kept but whatever okay so
we're going to go ahead and create a key
of F minor and pause this for one second
in the video to see that when we make uh
a key. key object really important to
make a lowercase f if you want to show
that something's minor and I call it Fe
by the way because you can't obviously
put F number sign pound sign to mean a
sharp sign as a variable because it
would just be a common so we sometimes
use borrow things from other languages
and so FIS Fe is the geran for FSH okay
so getting back
here getting back here we're just doing
the same thing that we did before B
chords exerpt 2 we're getting each of
the chords changing them to ran numerals
taking that ran numerals figure and make
it into lyrics and now we're going to
show that section and uh these measuring
numbers are the thing I was talking
about that I guess we have to add three
to each one of them to get what it is
eventually you know we'll be able to
contribute back to open source projects
like mcore and be able to fix this
limitation uh haven't had time to do
that yet such a great project anyhow so
we can go look through and see that okay
this time there's a lot more interesting
chords and some things that definitely
we want to reduce the vocabulary of
because I don't think all of those
chords actually say let's just grab that
last measure of the second system here
which is measure uh eight and look into
that um over here yep so there 's an a
sharp and then a b and a C sharp in the
base yep that's definitely the right
measure and we can see that that that
chord quote unquote on the second eighth
note is almost certainly not a chord
that is a lead a passing tone right and
so that flat augmented chord um 66 or
something whatever that was that's
something we want to reduce in the
vocabulary
so how can we do this I'm going to give
you one quick way that we can do this
let's just excert um measure 8 call it
M8 and just get that one measure from
the this is from the cified version uh
measure eight and we can just show it
make sure we got the right one always do
this by the way the number of times that
somebody has worked hours and hours and
can't figure out the bug because it
turns out that wasn't the right bug that
wasn't the right measure so yeah I'm
going to pause the video for one second
and go through those uh chords in some
detail so sorry I've cut off the soprano
but it's just a whole bunch of FS so we
can see that the first chord six I mean
that's really from the base that's
that's the chord that's happening it's
either the chord on beat one or the
chord on beat two so the third beat the
Baseline looks like it's doing some kind
of passing tone and then it's moving up
to that uh C at the end so something is
is happening and
but well it's really unclear if anything
except the first beat is something that
we'd want to keep as an actual chord
especially looking at the alto line
looks like it's has both of those D's
might be passing tones and the tenor
also looks like it's passing toone so a
lot of these cordal motions are things
that are introducing interesting
elements but aren introducing new
chords so what we're going to do in the
next section is let's just get a way of
saying which chords do we
think have the enough stability for us
to label them so we're going to look
through each chord in measure eight uh
in this case I don't need to do recurse
because measure eight only has chords
and time signatures maybe or something
like that and I'm going to print whether
or not the chord is consonant uh that's
a routine a method that's on every chord
object and then print the chord object
itself we can see that only that first
one six chord is actually a consonant
chord everything else is dissonant
according to the rules of total Harmony
so what we could do is we could create a
new stream and start putting all of the
chords in and then let's replace that
back into our uh into our original or we
can start copying things and putting
them but after thinking alloud at the
keyboard for a little bit I decided I
was going to just go through and let's
just remove all the chords that are not
consonant so every stream has a nice uh
little remove uh function it from it uh
there there are some problems by the way
just like all Python and many other
languages uh lists and arrays and stuff
like that that if you remove things
while you're iterating over there could
be problems but here it's okay so we're
going to remove every chord that's not
consonant and then we're going to get
that first chord uh the one six chord
and we'll make the duration of that be a
whole note so now when we look at
measure 8 we see only that consonant
chord t
and that's one of the forms of
vocabulary reduction that's going to be
pretty
common so when we go back and look at
the excert here uh for the first part we
don't have nearly as much to remove so
maybe we want to do the same type of
thing well let's let's just look at that
first excerpt and see what things are
consonant what things are dissonant and
uh
here we do need the recurse so we're
going to look at this first excerpt and
see wow almost everything here is
consonant there's that one false which
one do it refer to what's it refer to oh
let's just replace it and print the
figure instead uh not the figure the
lyrics instead and see that that one
thing that is not
consonant is a 5 seven chord something
that we might want to keep whereas the
something else that is consonant is a 36
chord
which uh we might want to remove and say
well that's not a real chord in this
case it is because we're about to be
modulating into another
key so we're going to be thinking about
how can we do these things what are the
various criteria that we can find and
how do we do this