(Upbeat music)
- [Narrator] When you look at
this image, what do you see?
You may think it's a moving image,
but it's actually a
single continuous picture.
to spruce up things like
artwork, ads, and decor.
Barrier-grid animations
turn everyday objects
into visually engaging
displays without electronics,
but this galloping horse isn't your average animation.
It's a bold new design created
by MIT CSAIL researchers.
Your standard animation
overlay resembles a picket fence
with a straight line pattern.
This conventional design
has been much more
straightforward to produce
than say, zig-zag patterns.
That is, until FabObscura enabled users
to think outside the box.
Now, you can explore uncharted
barrier-grid animations.
The program allows you to create
a sheet called a barrier or a grid,
and the underlying image
you slide that grid across.
The picture is a mashup
of different frames
from an animation,
sliced and interwoven to
present different snapshots
depending on where you place the overlay.
From wavy designs to circular patterns,
the team's FabObscura
software turns unique concepts
helping users add dynamic animations
to things like pictures, toys, and decor.
To create a barrier-grid
display with FabObscura,
you first upload a series of images,
like a few frames of a car moving,
or choose a preset like
a blinking eyeball.
FabObscura splices these
frames into one image for you.
You then type in mathematical functions
that graph out the shape and
movement of a barrier pattern.
For example, a wavy
barrier is a sine function,
curving up and down like a
series of hills and valleys.
By boiling down overlay
designs to math equations,
FabObscura allows you to tinker
with a variety of creative animations.
You can preview your design,
then fabricate the barrier and picture
onto separate transparent sheets
or print the image on paper
Using a standard 2D printer.
Your image can then be placed
and secured on flat handheld items
typically found in
homes and office spaces,
such as clocks and jars.
Artists, including graphic
designers and printmakers,
could also use FabObscura
to make eye-catching animated displays
without needing to connect any wires.
The tool could also help
create adjustable signs
in places like zoos,
construction sites, or stores
where you may need a
display to notify visitors
about closed off areas or
machines that are under repair.
called nested animations.
Depending on how you move the barrier,
you'll see different scenes.
They're layered clever designs.
While innovative, the researchers caution
that users should upload fewer
frames for nested animations
to keep the interlaced image simple.
They also suggest using
high contrast images
for a crisper presentation.
In the future, users could
upload videos to FabObscura
instead of sending individual frames.
The system might also
step into the 3D world,
expanding beyond the 2D handheld surfaces
to create barrier-grid animations
on larger, more complex objects.
From simple printouts
to mesmerizing motion,
FabObscura proves that sometimes
the most captivating technology
doesn't need a single wire or battery.