And so next we have Susan. Um,
>> you need the clicker.
>> I do need the clicker. I don't need the
pen.
>> It's about the MIT project. Wow, that
was fantastic. Uh, I also want to add my
voice uh to this chorus, my voice and my
colleagues voice. And to start by
thanking uh Zenab and this incredible
group that's joined here today and to
say that you all are pioneers. You know,
we've been I've been so moved by so much
creative work by so many leaders in the
field that have been brought together.
It's truly remarkable. And so thank you.
Uh I'm going to introduce to you the MIT
thermal energy network or mitten plan
for rapid costeffective decarbonization
of MIT campus. Uh it is the work of MACA
MIT campus group. MAC stands for MIT
alumni for climate action in
collaboration with GIO at MIT which is
the student group that we've worked
with. Maka was founded in 2018. The idea
for a thermal energy network for MIT
campus uh uh goes to Rick Clemensy, a
colleague of uh uh Garen um Eubank, who
we heard from earlier. Uh Rick and Judy
uh won a climate collab competition uh
that MIT sponsored in 2016. Um but it
didn't go anywhere. MIT wasn't
interested at the time in listening to
that. Um we we picked that up at MIT. Uh
the Maka group picked up that idea and
have built on it for the past three
years and we just introduced it formally
in a class that I t taught um this past
week uh and in an hourong presentation
which has been reduced to 10 minutes for
today. So, moving along, MIT's
decarbonization challenge is that 97% of
MIT's greenhouse gas emissions are from
the operation of its buildings and 26%
of all of Cambridge's greenhouse gases
are from MIT.
Um, MIT has had two climate action plans
in 2016 and 2021 um which postponed
significant investment in direct campus
decarbonization until later. uh its
emphasis in the early years 2020 up to
2040 and going on is uh power purchase
agreements uh in the Midwest uh and um
and mainly the power purchase agreements
um but uh it it hopes for um some major
breakthroughs uh in the future um and is
going to put you know is is there there
are voices uh among this chorus at MIT
who would like to see um uh small
nuclear reactors or deep geothermal uh
at some future point when it becomes uh
a reality.
The MIT thermal energy decarbonization
plan is an all electric campus fueled by
carbon-f free power. It implements
energy conservation measures including
waste heat recovery from ventilation
systems to reduce heating and cooling.
We're installing high efficiency water
source heat pumps in each building
distributed
um for heating and cooling. It
repurposes the existing chiller loop to
an ambient loop circulating 45 to 85
degree water year round to water source
heat pumps in each building. It
repurposes the oil tanks at the CUP
central utilities plant for thermal
storage. And there are energy transfer
stations operated by the Cambridge Water
Department exchanging heat with the
ambient loop where possible and if not
then looking to the MWR and and the
wastewater sewage or drilling uh
geothermal bore holes.
The plan is the most cost-effective and
energyefficient way to decarbonize the
campus. It demonstrates MIT leadership.
It leverages MIT's investment in
existing infrastructure. It eliminates
the cost impact of maintaining separate
systems because the water source heat
pumps uh provide both heating and
cooling. It eliminates energy
transmission losses, enables the capture
of free energy where there is concurrent
heating and cooling on campus and
perhaps will tap into future um
subsidies. Uh the Met building already
demonstrates this uh and this that that
demonstration is underway.
How is the campus heated and cooled now?
It has a central utilities plant with
co-generation. It produces steam and hot
water. It operates on a steamdriven
chiller. It generates over 22 megawatts
of electric power connected to steam
distribution connected to chilled water
distribution to most buildings and the
cooling load is high and most affected
by global warming.
Decarbonization issues with the existing
plant. The the grid decarbonization is
rapidly reducing carbon once added for a
combined heat and power.
Fossil fuel backup is necessary.
Efficiency of 50 to 55% source to
output. Low turndown rate of about 30%.
High thermal losses in the seam
distribution system of 10 to 20%.
nonzero losses in the chilled water
system of 5 to 15% and also the hot
water district system have losses also
um and hot water is what MIT's
administration is currently uh seeming
to embrace for its uh favored uh
geothermal um pathway pathway option.
How would the mitten plan heat and cool
the campus? Uh, distributed heat pumps
connected to a network of sources and
sinks. No one solution since the
buildings range over a history of
hundred years. Use of building
tobuilding and building inbuilding
sources and sinks. Use of thermal energy
storage and ground coupling with as I've
said Cambridge water, sewer or uh ground
thermal exchanges.
We consider this a fifth or sixth
generation district HVAC decarbonization
transition with an ambient loop,
two-pipe system, exhaust recovery,
distributed water source heat pumps,
thermal storage, air source heat pumps
and ground heat exchange, municipal
water thermal and other
uh and the chiller loop to the ambient
loop conversion. uh we would use the
same two pipes that exist already. Uh
first of all the blue uh buildings have
currently chiller loop. Uh oh and I
didn't say we have um MIT administration
uh provided us with a memorandum of
understanding uh to test fit our idea to
six buildings and those six buildings
are uh here uh W20 is the student center
and the rest are the athletic complex
W31 to W35
and three of those buildings have the
blue buildings have the Chillerloop loop
uh but the other three do not. So our
plan would for the test fit would
require the chiller loop to be added to
these three excuse me the ambient loop
to be added to these three buildings as
represented by the green dots were our
our uh proposal for these buildings
expanded to the whole campus. It's we
would also need an ambient loop here. Uh
those are the only two places that we
would need to do work. And I meant to
say uh that here are the six buildings
um on a graph of the EUIs of a number of
the buildings, not all the buildings,
but most of the buildings. And MIT has
very high EUIs with the lab build oops
with the lab buildings being uh
backwards. Uh the
um the the worst the worst uh performing
buildings. Uh and what's interesting is
that these six buildings represent a
quite
uh the huge a huge span of uh the campus
uh current u EUIS.
So
uh this is where uh in W33 the ambient
loop would run
and this is uh the cluster from above um
uh on which uh the ambient loop that you
just saw would be running uh from the uh
chilled water loop uh connection through
uh what you just saw and through this
building and into this building and also
into W20. We would also put uh solar
collectors on these wonderful flat roofs
that are uh hidden from view. Uh and we
would
um put on the roof of W20, the student
center u multistack heat pump units
where there's already space for that. We
would put as one option multistacks in
W34 as well. Uh perhaps another option
would be the AON SA23 in W34.
And then uh to compare um a central
plant fourpipe distribution system as is
being proposed. You can see uh that
um MIT currently has uh installed hot
water pipes in the Sloan complex. It
represents about 15% of the campus. Um
and the consultants plan would require
hot water pipes uh with I believe 180 to
they call it low
temperature pipes but not so low. Um 180
to 240 I believe uh degrees Fahrenheit
hot water in these pipes and all of this
would need to be um uh installed. And of
course that would need need steel pipes
and insulated pipes uh as opposed to the
ambient loop uh small areas here.
The
central thermal plant has heat losses in
transmission. Uh it starts off with a
lower CO cop
uh and Mittens has uh limited um heat
losses because of each heat pump being
in the building itself.
So to sum up uh a kind of topline
comparison of approaches um both
approaches meet building HVAC specs.
Both approaches achieve zero emissions.
uh our approach achieves those emissions
by 2035 were we to start this year uh
with a pilot on the existing six
building complex.
Uh ours is minimally disruptive as you
saw with the ambient loop only needing
to be extended in a few places. Uh we
need a pilot to confirm our projections
and to learn as the heat ever source uh
demonstration has learned uh a
tremendous amount. We need to do that
learning on the MIT campus by a real
project. It's easy to upgrade over time.
It's fiscally responsible and it's unc
clear whether MIT will seriously
consider our our proposal.
Uh our proposal we call a thermal
transition um leapfrog and we'll take
would go from the existing chiller plant
to a distributed energy network. So
finally, at the end of the day, the
project is not just about public
relations, but it should result in real
progress. The central utility plant will
play an important role in the mitten
solution. Our plan is available now.
We're using off-the-shelf equipment.
It's cost-effective. It will eliminate
carbon emissions and be minimally
disruptive. We feel that we can show the
world and demonstrate to other campuses
not only in Boston area or across the
North America but around the world that
this is a an approach that is
cost-effective, rapid and doable. um
MIT's the world's leading research
institute and should do something that's
not just uh cut cookie cutter um that
other campuses have already done um like
Princeton or like Stanford um and um
that is a centralized approach um and we
need to do a pilot and advocate for that
um for 2020 2025 so that we can get to
net zero by 2035.
And I'll close with uh words of Sally
Cornblath at her inauguration. Climate
change and its mounting consequence is
the greatest scientific and societal
challenge of this or any age. We need
energy and expertise from every MIT
school and college and from every lab
and every center from every member of
the faculty and from every one of you.
Um so um thank you and uh I think I want
to end really with this slide. We want
to get there by 2035.
And uh we're asking MIT when can we
start