Morning
and welcome to the entrepreneurship in
action track. I'm Katrina Mera, the
director of MIT startup exchange. I hope
you all enjoyed yesterday uh a full day
about MIT's scout uh cutting edge
research from AI and robotics to supply
chain and healthcare innovation. We saw
firsthand the incredible technologies
emerging from MIT's labs and centers.
Learned about recent initiatives such as
manufacturing initiative and MIT Learn
and of course the 10 amazing startup
exchange portfolio companies.
Uh while yesterday we focused on what's
possible in research and how it is
translated from lab to market, today my
colleague Arena Gazva and I uh want to
take a step further by focusing on
startup creation and industry
collaborations with the latter being at
the core of MIT startup exchange
mission.
In this session, we'll explore how
research progresses from discovery to
the marketplace. how startups are
created, how investors support their
growth, and how collaborations between
academia and industry accelerate impact.
Over the next 90 minutes, you'll hear
from experts who are at the forefront of
creating and scaling ventures. Paul
Schik will talk about AIdriven
enterprises and how startups can
leverage technology to achieve
exponential growth. Then Michael Kierney
will share insights on investing in deep
tech ventures. And Ariel first and Keith
Honda will dive into research industry
partnerships showing how collaborations
turn ideas and prototypes into real
world products and economic impact. Our
goal today is to provide you with
frameworks and insights that connect
amazing research and startups like the
ones you saw yesterday with real world
mechanisms of building ventures, scaling
innovation, and creating economic value.
We also hope to inspire you to engage
even further with our programs ILP and
startup exchange and other initiatives
across campus. Before we get started,
I'd like to um thank my colleague Arena
Gazva for coorganizing the track with
me. Unfortunately, she's sick. She's not
able to be with us, but I think she's
watching us in the live stream. And uh
I'd also like to encourage you to ask
questions throughout the session. Today,
we won't be using pigeon hole, but we'll
save a few minutes after each talk uh
for um live audience Q&A.