All right. So today's topic is
stochcastic calculus.
And this uh topic is really an engaging
one in uh quantitative finance because
it extends
ordinary calculus with real variables to
calculus that depends upon stochastic
processes and in particular brownie and
motion processes. And so when we are
thinking about how to model the value of
a stock or of a derivative such as a
simple option or a more complex option,
um we can model the dynamics of these
assets or uh derivative contracts
as integrals of functions
with respect to Brownie and motion where
Brownie in motion characterizes the
underlying dynamics of the asset. And so
it's really neat to see how we can
develop stochastic calculus and relate
it to what's familiar to us with
ordinary real calculus, but see how
there are extensions of the uh formulas
that accommodate the randomness
in the uh increments with which we're uh
integrating. So let's consider uh just
reviewing first brownie in motion with
drift. Um we discussed this earlier in
our discussion of uh stochcastic
processes.
And a standard brownie in motion model
is one where we have our process X
depending upon the underlying brownie in
motion standardized Brownian motion B of
T
with a drift parameter mu
and a volatility parameter sigma or
variance parameter sigma squared.
And the key property of brownie in
motion
is includes independent increments
and the variation of increments of the
process being proportional to the length
of the increment.
So with standard branding motion where
we have a drift parameter of zero and a
sigma volatility of one um the extension
of these properties to have essentially
mean zero and standard deviation equal
to sigma time t is to have the mean
depend upon time with the drift
parameter and the volatility uh or
variance to be proportional to sigma
squared times the length of the
interval.
Now in terms of understanding
Brownian motion um it's going to be
useful for us to focus on the
conditional distribution
of
the value at time t plus delta
as a function of
the value at time x of t.
And so when we think of a graph of
brownie motion which is some
path,
if we fix at a given value t
the value
of x of t
uh or maybe I should write this as s
the value of x at time little t. Then if
we know the value at time little t, what
is the distribution the conditional
distribution into the future? Well, this
increment uh t plus delta t. Delta t in
red, we can just expand that out to mu t
plus delta t plus sigma b of t plus
deltat t. And then we can group
the known terms on the left hand side of
the or the left hand terms of the second
equation u t plus sigma b of t. Then we
have a term mu delta t which is a
constant not random. But then we have
the increment of the Brownian motion
process from time t to time uh delta t t
plus delta t. So actually there's a typo
here. That should be b of t plus delta t
minus b of t.
And so uh we have that our delta x
increment
is mu delta t plus sigma delta b of t.
Now this increment has mean mu delta t
variance sigma squar delta t. And for
brownie in motion with drift,
this
increment is exactly distributed as a
normal random variable with that mean
and variance.
And what's useful to uh think about is
what happens as the increment
deltat t gets infinitesismal.
And so if we look at the infiniteesimal
increment
for delta t, then the expected squared
value of the brownian motion increment
is equal to sigma^ 2 delta t plus mu
delta t ^ 2. This is actually an exact
formula. And but what's important for us
is that as delta t goes to zero as it
becomes infinite tesimal then
this squared
increment has expectation that's of
order deltat t and it actually equals
sigma square delta t plus little o of
delta t. So this little O notation means
that as delta t goes to zero this
remainder part goes to zero as well. And
if we consider
powers of our increment of delta x
where the power c is greater than two
then this will also be small o of delta
t. So expressions that depend upon
second or higher order uh will of delta
x will actually be u comparable to sigma
squar delta t.
So in with brownie in motion and drift
um
we have the notation for a stochcastic
differential equation
which is simply the increment of x is
equal to
mu deltat t or dt rather plus sigma db
of t.
And with this notation um
the uh solution
turns out to be x of t is equal to the
value of x at time z plus the integral
from 0 to t mu dt plus the integral from
0 to t of sigma dbs.
And um
this solution sort of seems obvious
when we think about what how we
understand sort of differential
equations or with real functions but it
does extend to this solution when we
have brownie in motion. And so as noted
there this is equal to x kn + uh t - 0 *
mu plus sigma * b of t minus b of 0.
So our sort of integration of functions
of brownie and motion sort of have this
nominal solution which seems very
reasonable and will in fact show that
this solution is useful and it actually
extends to uh more complex
equations. Now the more complex
differential equations are one where we
consider a drift term mu that's not a
constant. It may vary over time and it
may also vary depending upon the
magnitude of the process.
So this kind of an extension is quite
general
and we can think about the same
extension to the volatility
rather than being a constant. It might
vary with t and it might vary with xt.
And with derivative
contracts,
um, we have values of contracts
which at any given time
depend on time, maybe time to maturity
and the level of the process.
And apart from those two sort of
features or properties of the derivative
at time little t we have a valuation
model that applies according to some
function. So it'll be very useful to
have these generalized drift and
generalized volatility parameters. Yes.
>> How is the um second like defined
because like obviously the first like
the better reman integral. What about
the second one? Like is there like an
actual formal definition of I guess it's
integral,
>> right? And and we will get there uh in a
moment, but you know if we're
integrating from
well here it's from zero to t. Um if
we're integrating the process over
increments, we're basically going to be
summing over the increments. although
summing on the infinite decimal time
scale over the entire period between
zero and t. And so if we break that sum
of infiniteesimal increments, we
basically get the last value minus the
first. And so we we'll see that come
into play. So um what we will determine
with this general setup though is that
when we have extended drift and
volatility, we then will have a solution
to this uh brownie in motion with drift
with sort of generalized drift and
volatility
satisfying this equation. So, we're
going to want to be able to compute
these
integrals
in a consistent way and the eto calculus
provides us with that. So, we have to
define eto integrals.
Well,
in defining eto integrals,
um we have this notation that we need to
be comfortable with. Um we are going to
first of all consider a
probability
process
that
is defined by this triple.
Now let's see have anyone people here uh
taken sort of advanced probability
or measure theory? Um
well we basically have here sort of a
sample space
and here we have what's called a sigma
field
of sets
which are subset of omega. And then here
we have a probability model
where if we have
a a subset of omega
and it's an element of this sigma field
we have this probability of that set
is well defined.
So
this notation sort of encompasses the
generality of probability models that
are important to
uh specify and be comfortable with.
Well, with the omega set here, um
these are a collection of little omegas
which are possible sample paths
of this
uh brownie in motion.
And
we can think of
okay here's one path one possible path.
Um another possible path
actually matches
the first path up to time t but then
continues on somewhere else.
Another path
could be one that is sort of reflected
about a given level. We went through
this a bit in our discussion of brownie
emotion processes.
And so we can think of just the
collection of all possible paths. Now
the filtration ft
um we think of
script ft.
This is going to be the sigma field
of events
um
or paths
which are fixed
or known
uh at times
s less than or equal to t.
So
with script ft the information up to
time t if
sort of this is our path up to time t.
Um
the event of
following this path up to time t sort of
is deterministic.
If we look back
deterministic
for s less than t but then it's random
random for s greater than t.
So we have a
uh a value or in script ft. It basically
says okay we can work with
paths that are deterministic before time
t but then are random after time t. And
so that's
relates to the uh concept of being
measurable.
So we say that um events in ft are
measurable with respect to bs with the
information set up to time t. So if we
consider times before t um the path is
actually just a constant uh or as a as a
function a path valued function that
that's constant. Now um if we uh have
this probability measure on omega the
space of all possible paths
um if we consider the sort of
conditional distribution
given
x at time t. Then we're trying to
specify the model for all future paths
that start at the level x at time t. And
um
the uh sort of that probability measure
over the entire space of
paths
um can also be restricted to the paths
up to time little t. So we can um
basically uh focus on probability
measures that are unconditional but
restricted to the information set up to
time t. Now we'll want to refer to the
value of the bronian motion at time t.
And it's important to
know that often this notation BT is
implicitly the value of a specific path.
So to emphasize that we'll indicate that
it's uh the Brownian motion path indexed
by little omega.
And so
we then want to consider the eto
integrals with respect to brownie and
motion first where we consider simple
functions,
real functions
where f of bs is the value of little f
evaluated
at the position value of the brownie in
motion.
and we'll want to consider integrating
that function
from 0 to t.
Um, and so uh this is this is our
notation. So
with a uh
sort of companion
uh graph with the same x axis as our
brownie in motion. We could have f being
some function
which um varies and we want to basically
integrate
this function f evaluated at the brownie
in motion. So actually this is uh
this is actually a wrong graph. I
thought we had had the same same graph.
We basically want um for
sort of let's say x= bs
um of omega
um some function.
All right.
Well,
if we
consider this notation to represent our
eto integral, we're going to develop the
formulas for these eto integrals.
And
importantly,
this eto integral
is going to
have
basically a sort of deterministic simple
real integration term for each path.
But
the paths indexed by omega are random.
And so this eto integral is actually
going to be a random variable. And as a
random variable, if it exists, it'll
have an expectation and a variance.
So let's consider a number of special
cases that will define eto integrals.
Okay, the first
case is the simple one where f ofx is
equal to 1.
So
let me just erase this
and have the level one.
So we consider f ofx equaling one.
So if we
integrate the increments of brownie
motion over
from zero to capital t.
uh let's propose that that's equal to
the increment from zero to
uh from zero to t for each path. So the
right hand side
corresponds to the sort of simple
integral
of this
path BS of omega between
BT between time zero and capital T.
And um
I guess it's not in the notes, but if we
were to consider the integral of 0 to t
db s
of omega.
Um, we could think of this as the uh
sum from zero to n of uh i
t
over n
let's see
let me do this i = 1 to n i -1 t
over n the integral from i - 1 t / n to
i
* t over over n
dbs.
So here I'm thinking of busy dividing
this increment from zero to t into
different increments
of width capital t over n. And
if we approximate
or each of these integrals here are
basically looking at the integral of uh
or the change in b s from these lower
limits to the upper limits. And so
the integral of dbs of omega you know in
a consistent way or well- definfined way
is defined by this increment of the
whole process. Now if that's true then
the when we consider the randomness in
omega
the expectation of this integral is zero
where b is the standard brownie motion
and this variance is equal to the length
of the interval times the sigma of
standard brownie motion.
Well,
if we change our function f to be not
the constant one over the whole real
line, but just the indicator of an
interval, it's just one between a and b.
So, we have a and b here. And we have
basically zero up to a and then it
equals
one up to B and then it's zero beyond.
Um
then this eto integral
is essentially looking at the change in
brownian motion from time a to time b.
So
no surprise that that's a reasonable
definition.
Now from these reasonable definitions
we can consider
a second case where our function f
is again a function only of time
s but it's given by a step function over
time with steps
or levels given by the ais that are
constant. So we go from this single step
function here to considering
um
basically different step functions
for our function f. Now
these step functions could correspond to
like the number of shares held of an
asset. And so, you know, this integral
could correspond to the gain or loss um
if the underlying asset sort of followed
brownie in motion. Um but here with this
particular step function,
we can define the eto integral to just
be the sum
over the increments of the step levels
times the increment of the process. And
so, you know, that's a pretty sensible
uh definition of the integral and it
would apply um if we had assets
traveling uh values going by a brownie
in motion process and say shares given
by uh the a constants that were maybe uh
deterine deterministic.
Now at this point we're using functions
f which are deterministic functions of
time.
We can then extend
this to uh sort of random functions. And
actually before I do so just notice in
red the mean zero and the variance of
this
eto integral of the uh step function.
The variance is simply the sum of the
squares of the
levels times the length of the increment
over which that level applies.
So now case three things get more
interesting. We can allow our levels
AI to be random variables
and these variables random variables AI.
Um
so AI equal to AI of omega.
This is
a path and so we can have the levels
vary depending upon what the path value
is.
And so
we want the AI
to depend
on
uh
and I guess by depend I'll say be
deterministic
on script ft subi.
So if we define our levels to
be functions that are in this are
measurable in this information set then
um that's what we're doing here. Now
earlier uh we talked about
nonanticipatory
variables
and so this is a non-anticipatory
variable. It basically says that the
level from TI on
for whatever that increment is is going
to be a function of what's happened in
the past. So this is like a realizable
uh function f where when we apply the f
function to the uh brownie motion
increments we're applying known
increments at all times.
And so with this case, we actually want
to make an assumption of measurability
on that I uh information set and we want
a bounded squared expectation of the
level. So if we have those two
properties then we can write out the eto
integral
as this formula and it will have
expectation equal to zero and variance
equal to
the sum of the expected squared ais
times ti uh + 1 minus ti.
Okay.
So, um
I guess rather importantly
with um these developments so far, we're
thinking of
the time S ranging from zero up to time
capital T.
And we have increments ti
+ one
where this increment
is something. Um for simplicity we could
define this increment to have length say
t over n for n increments and have equal
increments.
Um
but this uh this formula for the eto
integral is considering integrating
the brownian motion over the interval
from 0 to t. So
so integral from 0 to t f of s bs dbs.
This is our integral our eto process I
of f
and um we can write
I of f
evaluated at a particular path given by
this formula.
All right. Um well an interesting
example just from a mathematician's
standpoint is what if we define our
levels to be equal to the value of the
brownian motion itself.
So we're integrating
B dB.
So we're thinking of this example. So
case three
special case three um integral from 0 to
t of b subs dbs.
Well,
if we consider sort of discretizing
this eto integral
um
with these random levels ai
um actually I'm getting ahead of myself.
This integral will be a limit of these
um
for any fixed set of increments
that we apply this
random level uh
given by the value of the brownie in
motion on those increments. Then for
each of these cases with n increments we
get that we have mean zero and the
variance is equal to the sum of the
variances of each of the terms. And that
turns out to be equal to the sum over
the increments of the time increment t
level uh ti times the increment to the
next
uh time value. And this sum of ti ti *
ti + 1 - ti is essentially
equal or close to the integral from zero
to capital t of s dds
which should be a half t ^2. Yeah.
>> Um how do you conclude that the
expectation is zero?
>> Okay. The expectation is uh zero
because
each of these increments here
have expectation zero. So we're assuming
B of zero is zero.
>> Yeah. But what if Oh yeah, but what if
AI is not independent? Like when you
take the expectations,
>> okay,
>> okay. Yep. Yep.
Let's see. Okay. Ai of omega is an
element of f subti.
So um it's uh
it's uh
constant
on uh f subti.
So um
let's see
so a i of omega
um
and b
t i + 1.
uh
this increment
into the future from time ti is
independent of the pa of the past
and so it's expectation
if we take the product of these two and
take expectations
um
we can take
the expectation
sort of um
given
uh or the expectation over TI times the
expectation
um sort of given
let's see
over TI + one given TI.
So we can break down this expectation
into
its decomposition and the expectation of
this factor conditionally will be zero.
>> Yeah, that makes sense.
>> So
yep.
All right. Um
well uh
this case four
is the case that essentially defines uh
EDO integrals in general which is if we
consider
taking the limit
of
integrals with respect to sort of step
functions with random levels AI.
But then allow the increments the time
steps to get closer and closer to each
other.
Then uh the limiting value of this
uh eto integral of the step functions is
equal to the eto integral of f.
So
we have um the uh in our special case
where f
ofx equals x um f of the brownian motion
is uh the brownian motion itself. we end
up getting this formula
and here we have basically the sort of
discretized value of the integral
and then what's of interest is to see
how the limit of that equals this
formula.
And so to prove this
there's a nice mathematical trick. Um
and so if we look at
this
term on the right hand side here which
is an element of the sum it turns out to
be equal to a half the difference in the
squared values at the end points of the
interval minus a half times the
difference
between ti and ti + 1 squared. So this
is simple to verify. It's trivial but
incredibly useful.
And so if we sum over all the time
points from 0 to n minus one, we get
the sum of the first terms
minus the sum of the second terms.
And so this first term
is actually a telescoping sum.
When you sum the terms, there's
cancellation
of a of the middle value in successive
terms. And so we're left at the end with
the
12 the square of the last term here
minus the square of the very first term
with i=
0 here which is zero. So this is a half
bt ^2 minus b 0^ 2 which is zero. That's
the first term. And then for the other
we have minus a half the sum of the
squared increments.
And so
if we
know sort of what the last
uh time interval term is tn that's
capital t. And then we have the same
terms on the right. And what's important
to know
is that the limit of the sums of these
increments
converges to t capital t and this was um
the property of the total variation of
brownie in motion over any increment. If
we look at the sum of squared values
of increments and take the limit as the
number of increments grows large and the
sort of partition gets um
uh finer and finer then the limiting
value of these sums of increments u is
equal to capital t. So this is our
formula now for the eto
integral of b dbs
and um
let's see so so what's really important
to highlight
is that
this is not equivalent to thinking of
the brownie in motion process like a
real function.
where we're integrating B dB or X dx
which is x^2 / 2
we actually have this drag on the
integral that's depends on the variation
of the process.
Okay. Now we want to generalize
um to the uh
general case of eto integrals.
And so what we do is
we
consider defining the eto integrals
from 0 to t f of omega s
dbs.
But then um
we want to
basically consider this to be a process
XT
of omega.
And we want to generalize this
to an xt of omega where we're
integrating just
up to time little t.
So
what we want to do is
once we have this definition for the eto
integral
over a fixed interval from 0 to t.
We want to be able to define
the eto integral where we're integrating
only up to time little t less than uh
capital t. And so um
in order for this
um
kind of uh function to be uh to be well
defined
it will turn out that we need some very
strong mathematical arguments and
there's a book by steel chapter six on
uh sort of quantitative finance where he
does go into all the details and I have
to admit it's not really a fun read.
It's sort of interesting to look and see
what's involved. So you know how
important it is to sort of be a good
mathematician if you want to prove
things. But fortunate for us they are
proven well and we can apply them. So
what do we need? We need that the uh
function little f needs to be
measurable.
Script fs, the information set up to
time s measurable for every time s.
And we want the
integral of the squared f
over time
where that's for each fixed omega. We
can integrate the square of f and then
take the expectation of that. We want
that to be finite.
So
this
term this term here this expectation is
taking the expectation over the
probability model given by capital p.
Um, and we're for each omega we're
integrating the squared f over time from
0 to t
and we want that to be finite.
So um with this notation
we basically are extending
our
eto integral over 0 to capital t with
the eo integral from zero to little t.
And um we can define this by just
replacing our f function in the
eto integral
i of f by simply the function f times
this indicator from zero to t. So that
step basically chops off the integration
at time little t
and gives us our definition. Now um
let's see okay the uh the definition of
this extension
of
our eto integral over z to t to
integrating it over zero to uh little
t's for any little t less than t. Um
that's relatively
straightforward and intuitively obvious.
What's not necessarily obvious though is
that our process
XT
is a martingale
with respect to this stochcastic process
model given by the Brownian motions. So
um if we look at what it means for
a process to be a martingale, if we look
at the conditional expectation
of the time t + k
value given time t,
then
it equals the value of the process at
time t, little t, plus
the integral of the process process from
time t to t + k
and we're taking expectations
conditional expectations of that given
xt.
And so the expectation of this future
sort of increment from t to t plus k is
basically integrating a function times
increments of the brownie emotion where
our function values depend on the past
and the increments are independent in in
the future with mean zero. So this
expectation turns out to be satisfied.
And if we look at the conditional
variance of the t plus k value given xt
then it's equal to the expected square
of this
uh f ds.
And so when you look at the variance of
the discretized sum of increments,
you get the discretized sum of variances
of those increments which are f2 and
then the dbs squared
are ddt.
So this simplifies uh for the variance
to that term.
And
okay, all of this is fairly uh
I know it's like mathematical results
and it's sort of like who cares. Um
well it turns out that um this
um variance
turns out to be a squared norm
of our function little f
on the space of the probability
space of paths cross the time
increments.
And so what's
well, okay, actually I'm going to get
ahead of myself. Uh but let me let me
get to the let me get ahead of myself
and
basically
comment that
this norm
of our function f
is going to be a squared norm on the
space of etorocess integrants
And
let's see those of you who have taken uh
I guess real analysis or metric spaces
you know what's what's an important
value of
norms
what what do we do with norms
or squared norms?
Well, with norms, we can talk about
limits
of elements of the space
and talk about whether limits exist.
And so with this setup we actually will
have
the space of eto processes
and we can calculate the squared norm
between different eto integrals.
And so we can characterize uh limits in
those spaces and be guaranteed that
those limits exist.
So
with this sort of motivation of defining
useful norms on different spaces, um we
have this eto isometry
which is if we look at the
variance of eto
integrals defined by integrant little f.
Then those
squared norms or the variances basically
of the eto processes is equal to the L2
norm of the integrant little f.
And
if we write out the definitions of these
sort of squared norms uh we get these
equations.
And what's um relevant here is
um being able to express
our variance of the eto integral as the
squared norm of the integrant f.
So we have limits and convergences of
sequences of eto integrals.
And
something that's important
mathematically is if we take the limits
of these eto uh integrals
over increments that are getting f a
grid of increments that's getting finer
and finer. Do we have a unique limit or
not?
And so that's what's
important and is um the squared norms
and convergence are uh properties are
used to prove that. So we basically can
talk about closed linear subspaces
with these uh norms on on the space.
So what this does is it allows us to
define sort of the distance between
different integrants f
and um
the the uh existence of a limiting uh in
uh eto integral um as we consider
increments getting uh infinite. Tesmal.
All right. Um well,
we can think of this eto integral as a
remon sum, a limiting remon sum.
And
if we have time
steps ti for simplicity equal to it t /n
um we can consider the limiting sum
of f of
the brownian motion times the increment
of the brownian motion.
And
this
sum actually converges in probability um
as n goes to infinity
um to the integral. So um so we have a
limiting
value that uh exists convergence and
probability and um if we consider uh I
guess the co-variances
of
the x process given by these eto
integrals
from zero to little t. Um then
these will or this XT will be a mean
zero Gaussian process with independent
increments and the co-variance between
the process at time s and time t will
simply be equal to the integral of the
squared f over the times where they both
are non zero.
So um
all right so we take a partition from 0
to t we get this result
um and we can prove that the limit
equals the uh this integral notation. So
basically there's a limit that exists
and this is a notation for that limit.
Um and steel goes into a lot of the
details for that.
Now um
now what's of interest is that we can
now consider sort of some general eto uh
cases which will be referred to as eto's
formula for different kinds of function
fs functions f and so if we consider
first the case where f little f is a a
real function
mapping reals to real. Then
if it has a continuous
uh second derivative
then we can express the function f of bt
in terms of its sort of tailor uh
approximation
um and we get this formula which is
eto's formula for f of bt and uh in
looking at this expression
what's relevant is that okay the first
term f0 is a constant the second term
is a Gaussian sort of process integral
is an integral of brownian motion and
then the third term is the integral of
the second derivative of f with
evaluated at the uh bs value and So we
have an adaptive sort of drift term
and we can prove this formula or outline
the proof by saying okay let's consider
the tailor approximation of f at x plus
delta x and expand it to second order
terms plus a remainder.
And then if we take
the difference of f at time
t with b minus f at time z with b. Then
we're looking at
the sum of the increments from time t1
to tn.
And
those increments are equal to the sums
of the derivative of f
times the increment of time plus a half
the second derivative of f times the
squared increment plus the remainder
terms. And if we take the limits of
those we get the integral of frime
dbs plus a half the second the integral
of the second derivative. So tailaylor
series gives us this formula
and um we can think of
you know developing a notation with eo
calculus which is that our sort of
differential of f at bs is equal to
fprime of bs dbs plus a half fp prime
times at bs times
the squared of
db which is equal to ds the increment of
time.
So this is our etos formula
shortorthhand
and uh this uh shortorthhand
corresponds in a similar way to
derivatives and anti-derivatives
where sort of here's the stochastic
differential equation and here's the
solution to that stochcastic
differential equation on the top.
Now um what's really
neat and very powerful is that
if we want to solve for the integral of
a function. So suppose our objective is
to solve for the integral from 0 to t f
of bs dbs.
Well,
if we have
the anti-derivative
of little f.
So that means that the first derivative
of capital f is
equal to
such that fprime
is equal to f.
Then
if we choose the anti-derivative
with f of 0 equal to zero
then we get
f of bt minus f of b 0 is equal to this
integral of the derivative of f
dbs plus a half the integral of the
second derivative of capital f which is
simply fprime.
So this formula
is what we just derived for
itto's formula.
And if we
solve for this first term on the right,
then that's equal to f of bt minus a
half the integral of the first
derivative of frime of bsds.
So what's what's neat as a sort of
technique in stochcastic calculus is
that if we want to
integrate
a function little f
of bs dbs
then we can just apply eto's formula
in reverse
and
characterize as the anti-derivative of
little f at bt minus a half that
defining the anti-derivative to have f
of 0 equal to zero.
Now let's apply this just for the case
where capital f of x= x capital f prime
the derivative is one and the second
derivative is zero.
Um then the integral of DBS
is equal to BT
and um
let's see so so basically um the
integral of
BS DBS is equal to capital F of BT which
is BT
and then plus minus a half the second
derivative
or the first deriv
the second derivative of f which is
zero. So this gives us this result.
Um and if we consider capital f equaling
a half x^2
then little f is equal to x
and little f prime is equal to 1. And so
we get the integral of bs dbs is f of bt
minus that which is a half bt ^2 minus a
half t. So this gives us sort of a a
verification of the limiting results we
went through before with these eto
integrals.
Okay. The next step is to extend eto's
formula to functions of more than one
variable.
So we basically want to go from sort of
f ofx.
So one variable
fs we want to go to two variables
functions f and we'll write the notation
of s comma x
um which maps basically
let's see
the time space cross
the or the time range r plus cross the
real line of x into the reals.
And we're going to consider functions
little f
that are continuous to different orders
in terms of the time variable and the
space variable.
So
we have um
this notation C super one comma 2
meaning that um it's continuous with uh
first order derivative existing and
continuous and second order derivative
with respect to x and continuous.
And so we have a tailaylor series for
increments of this function little f now
of two variables which has the
multi-dimensional
d= 2 tailaylor series formulation
and it equals
the f
without the increments on t and x plus
delta t * the partial of f with respect
respect to t plus delta x * the partial
of f with respect to x. And then we have
the part the second order partial
differential terms. And the only ones
that are going to be of interest are the
second order partial of f with respect
to x which be will be multiplied by
delta x^2. the other second order terms
will actually be of small order uh delta
t.
And um with this
second order tailor approximation,
we're able to derive that the function f
of tbt
is equal to the initial value plus an
integral with over time
of a function of the brownian motion ds
plus an integral over increments of the
brownian motion.
plus 12 this integral of the second
partial of f with respect to dx^2.
And this integral here ends up being
multiplied or being integrated with
respect to the increments of time
because the delta x squ terms are uh
infinitely
equivalent to increments ds.
So um so for this uh
formula um we have here if we look at
the difference in the little f function
from time zero to t it equals the right
hand side. So this top formula here is
simply taking this second order
tailaylor series and looking at the
increment from 0 to t and what that
equals.
And what we get is a sum of two terms.
an integral with respect to time of
the partial with respect to time plus
the half the second derivative of f with
respect to x.
And um with this notation
for
the value of little f
um what's important to notice is that if
the argument
in the time integral
if that's equal to zero
then
this will be a martingale.
because the second term is an integral
of
terms times increments of the brownie in
motion and the increments of the brownie
in motion all have expectation equal to
zero. So we'll have the possibility of
this function being a martingale if
that's true. And this
integrant equaling zero is equivalent to
this partial differential equation
on the little f. So there's this
connection between uh martingales
and partial uh differential equations
for f when we're thinking of a process f
of t. So if little f is a martingale
um it will turn out that the partial
of f with respect to t will equal minus
a half d^2 fdx^2 which is a pde
condition. Now the other thing we want
actually for this to exist is um that
the variance of the function
f of tbt
which is bounded by the squared
expectation
um is uh finite
and so
this will be finite.
the variance if that
second term has finite variance. And so
for that to have finite variance, it's
the variance is the integral of the
square of that argument dfdx
with respect to time.
And so
all right. Um now what's interesting
with this EDO formula is um
we can apply it to a function little f
which is the exponential
of sigma x minus sigma^ 2 t / 2.
And
importantly um well let's see this d
partial of f with respect to t does
equal minus a half sigma^ 2 f and so
this um is actually a partial
differential equation
uh for little f
and but df dx is equal to sigma f the
second partial of f respect to x is
sigma square f and itto's formula
if we expand it out gives us this
expression for little f
and um this
function little f is in fact a
martingale
if we look at the expected value of f
given f of 0 0 um it equals 1. Now f of
0 0 is the exponential of
uh basically zero which is one and but
this function f little f if we plug in
bt for x it's a scaled lognormal random
variable.
So this little f evaluated at x equal to
bt. So it's a transformation of the
brownian motion
process path bt by this uh function um
is actually a scaled lognormal random
variable.
And so e to the sigma bt minus sig half
sigma^ 2 t is a scaled logn normal. And
the expected value of this e to the
sigma bt is actually equal to e to the
1/2 sigma^ 2 t. We proved that I believe
in a problem set. And so the expectation
of f of tbt is going to actually equal
one for all t. So this little f is in
fact a uh martingale.
Now um let's see with Brownian motion uh
with drift the ruin problem we can
actually use some sort of eto I u
process ideas
uh to deal with this um with this
problem where we assume that xt is a
brownie in motion with drift mu and
variance parameter sigma squar. So
here's its formula
stochcastic differential equation for XT
and we're interested in what's the
probability of stopping at A before B
where the stopping time tow is the first
time T that hits A or minus B.
And
this
argument is one that's uh very typical
of
uh quantitative finance developments I
guess by mathematicians
um and uh I it's actually a very neat
argument where um I don't think I could
ever have derived this but uh the
derivation using martingale theory is
really very elegant and so let's
consider trying to solve for this
probability
by using martingale theory. So let's
consider
a martingale.
Let's try to define a martingale
with value h of xt
defining mt
where
the tow is the same stopping time
and the condition on h is going to be
that if
we sort of are at the value xt= A then
the probability is one and if we start
at minus B the probability is zero. So
this is fixing the sort of terminal
conditions of the function h when it
hits the uh limits a or minus b. Well,
we can if we have a martingale that
satisfies this
function h of xt
then the expectation of the stopped
martingale is simply equal to the
probability that x tow equals a.
And uh
by the martingale property
the value
of or the expectation of the stopped
time is equal to the m0 the initial
value of the uh h function. Now the
initial value is the value when x is
equal to zero. So we're starting at zero
with the x process and it either moves
uh and hits a or hits minus b. So in
order for this h function to be a
martingale
we have to have that the pd condition is
satisfied on h. So the partial of h with
respect to t is equal to minus a half
the second partial of h with respect to
dx.
And so if this h function which is the
probability of hitting a first
depends just on the value of
xt.
Then it equals h of mu t plus sigma bt
substituting in for what xt is. So we
can work with the function
little f equal to h of mu t plus sigma
x.
And if the partial of f with respect to
t
which is by chain rule mu h prime of mu
t plus sigma x if that equals the second
partial of f with respect to x. The
second partial derivative of h with
respect to x is sigma^ squ hp prime.
Then this pde condition says we have
this relationship this differential
equation for h although it's in the
first derivative of h.
But we can then
rewrite this as the second derivative of
h evaluated at argument y is minus a
constant times the first derivative of
h.
And so
we can solve that equation
by
noting that sort of hp prime over h
prime is equal to d by dx of
log of h prime.
So the derivative of the log of h prime
is a constant. The solution to that is a
linear function.
And so we then end up being able to
solve for little h of y equaling this
formula. So this is the solution to this
problem.
All right, let's see. We we're at the
end of our lecture today. So next next
time we'll finish up these notes uh
talking about
standard
uh processes
where our sort of a function for the
drift and our b function for the
volatilities have to satisfy certain
properties. And if you read ahead in
these notes, you'll see that we need the
probability of sort of integrating the
drift over time has to be finite and
absolute integral and the integral of
the squared b's
have to also be finite. If those were
not finite then you would say have sort
of explosive behavior of these integrals
which uh where they won't exist. So
these are reasonable properties to
assume for those and anyway we'll go
through some interesting results here
with this particular problem um and then
turn on to stochcastic differential
equations next time. All right.
Thank you.