and uh I'll try to uh leave you with uh
what ultimately is uh a simple
perspective but one that stuck with me
on how I think new technologies can be
inserted into manufacturing going
forward and hopefully make manufacturing
more productive more efficient more
sustainable uh in the context of
specific Industries and use cases which
I think it's always comes down to so the
title is very broad scaling digital
production and it'll be uh laced with
some examples from our work here at MIT
from entrepreneurial Ventures and from
as mentioned in the introduction our new
initiative focused on manufacturing
across MIT uh I'd like to begin uh with
a question uh and that is uh you know
imagine uh how you would describe the
manufacturing of something as simple as
a Lego brick I love Legos have small
kids there's Legos everywhere at home uh
and uh you know it's it's arguably the
simplest possible product a single
component a single process yet uh Legos
are extremely precise uh and my answer
to the question is that it's it's really
hard to explain how to make it right
it's not just about the design the
geometry right you could make the cad
model and transfer that to the uh
production house but it's about encoding
the information needed to achieve the
product's performance right the
dimensions and tolerances and surface
finish and so on uh and that's really
hard I will make several uh mentions of
various types of AI tools and how I
believe along with the theme of this uh
meeting they can be very powerful in
accelerating uh product Innovation and
the process from uh concept to finished
goods but it'll be a long time until we
have the full capability to automate the
description of making something even as
simple as a Lego brick and uh like uh
many of you I'm sure uh uh you know I I
feel that manufacturing has transformed
enormously over uh you know uh history
in over recent decades right in 100
years we've gone from making automobiles
like Henry Ford's uh assembly line did
in the 1920s uh to you know not not just
making more and more uh efficient
vehicles and electric vehicles but you
know making the incredibly sophisticated
products that keep us connected today so
you know imagine that Lego brick and and
now imagine this right how does a
company such as Apple or Google or you
name it uh organized all the information
needed to execute uh manufacturing of
one of its products that's a huge
competitive Advantage also is a huge
thing to manage uh and I feel that you
know to to a simplification one of the
tradeoffs that uh We've made as a world
uh in uh driving manufacturing forward
driving products forward has been the
decentralization of Knowledge from uh
more decades ago single firms where the
knowledge and the resources to design
develop the process and produce work
Under One Roof you know whether it be
one building or one company across to
more distributed understanding right
from small Supply chains to know simple
cartoon here but long gnarly distributed
fragile Supply chains and with that you
know you can imagine again all the
knowledge and complexity it takes to
basically get anything made right it's
one thing to say I can make this this
way but another thing entirely to Source
it and maintain reliability of sourcing
and so on and so forth so while this is
not a talk about Supply chains uh
hopefully that's a motivating Point as
to uh you know one of the big challenges
I see that you know the world needs to
address in improving the productivity
and efficiency and sustainability of
manufacturing but also one that is in
some ways I think starting to limit the
rate and Pace at which we can develop
new and better products and that is the
increasing complexity uh required to
execute manufacturing at scale so my uh
general question for the talk is how can
we think about collapsing this
complexity while continuing to uh
innovate as organizations innovate as
Nations innovate as a globe uh and the
uh end point uh or you could say
backbone of the talk is this three plane
chart uh and uh this is uh quite you
know a high level but my idea with this
chart is that we can think of the
relationship between the design of a
product and the end point of production
not just through a lengthy chain of
steps but through in the future
relationships between the inherent
capabilities of the production
infrastructure we have
the machines the people the capabilities
in our factories and our supply chains
uh arguably as as a foundation we can
think of the capabilities we have for
product and process design at a top
level right where the inputs and the
ideas and the constraints come and by
some important interaction we will be
able to develop new computational tools
including tools of multim modal
artificial intelligence working with
different types of data right
manufacturing involves multi- modes of
data that can help Stitch the two
together I'm not here to say like we're
on the verge of solving that problem I
said earlier it'll take a long time to
even explain uh uh how to make that Lego
brick but that there are some exciting
and important advances that I think can
be very meaningful at certain places
along that chain and that there's uh
examples at all levels of the chart that
I've woven in into the rest of the
presentation uh so beginning with this
ground floor uh I see first of all that
there's uh an increasing tool set of
capabilities that are bringing new
processes new configurations of
automation uh uh into manufacturing
operations or making these tools
available to manufacturers and again it
depends on the specific context the type
of product that your organization makes
or sources or whether you're software
company or a hardware Product Company or
something else but examples include for
instance ways to use robotics to uh form
sheet metal right Sheet Metal
Manufacturing at large volume uh AKA
stamping right is done using large you
know fixed tooling fixed dieses like how
you make hoods of cars and uh those
kinds of components at large volume it's
small volume sheet metal forming while
it's a vast industry uh is is uh
basically a craft an art of craft uh so
uh uh among others there's a company in
California called Machina Labs that's
developing robotic automation for doing
small volume sheet metal forming one of
these uh uh pieces uh on that
foundational base that I mentioned uh
there are many local companies uh in the
Boston area developing new kinds of 3D
printing Technologies I'll talk more
about 3D printing in a minute uh this
one which you may know is called inkbit
it's a spin out of mit's uh computer
science and AI lab Professor matus group
and it has a unique capability to print
uh multiple materials with very very
high resolution and so this is uh uh
literally a robotic hand with pneumatic
lines and with effectively uh rubbery
tendons printed in in one piece the
kinds of things that like we we we don't
even know how to design for yet uh but
that capability is one of these uh
foundational pieces that'll find its way
into into product
workflows another company close to MIT
is called tulip uh they build uh uh
software and and and digital interfaces
for production workers so production
supervisors can uh monitor data from the
factory floor can uh develop apps that
provide uh things like uh heads up work
instructions and also can identify how
to improve improve uh you know the
productivity of factory floor operations
and so on and so forth many examples
like this uh some years ago uh uh I had
the opportunity with a former student uh
of mine here uh in uh our master's
program in manufacturing to spin out a
company with interest in industrial
scale metal 3D printing uh AKA additive
manufacturing and we co-founded a
company called Vulcan forms that now has
uh 150,000 foot factory uh just west of
Boston doing metal 3D printing at
industrial scale uh and this has been
about a 10year journey to this point and
we're just getting into scaled
production but it's an example of uh uh
a idea to bring a new metal 3D printing
technology to a factory scale and do it
not in the way of selling 3D printers to
the marketplace but the company designs
and builds its own 3D printing equipment
like the machines you see here and then
does production as a service uh not
unlike a contract manufacturer but one
that is focused on producing high value
metal medic metal components for a
variety of large Industries and large
customers and I'm not here to
necessarily say uh here's the details of
the company but use an example of what
the company has developed as another one
of these foundational pieces where I
feel there's important attributes of how
this process operates that are key to
this kind of three-level uh vision of
digital production in the future so for
instance we can use metal 3D printing to
fabricate components of jet engines from
small to large uh you would normally be
uh uh casting a Billet of raw material
forging it perhaps multiple times and
then Machining the component often a
very uh uh expensive and hard to work
with material and here we can print the
finished component in one go this is
about uh 600 mm in diameter and
representative of the size of a small
format jet engine the uh printing
process uh like most 3D printing
capabilities has a build plate so you
print the part or you print multiple
parts and then you slice the part off
and you can do finished postprocessing
the power of this technology and you
know 3D printing is one of these uh the
these uh production processes overall is
its flexibility right to a limit if you
change the code for the uh machine you
can print something entirely different
so on the same printer uh you can create
uh arrays of components of medical
implants these are uh the cup component
of hip implants uh that are implanted in
the human body and the reason why these
are 3D printed is that you can create a
three-dimensional lattice structure on
the surface uh so there's some
applications of you could say 3D
printing or more automated digital
Manufacturing in general where you can
you you make what you make today but you
might make it uh you know uh more cost
effectively or in a smaller volume with
higher accuracy here's a case where you
making something that you cannot
otherwise make because of this unique
structure on the surface that improves
the rate of integration with the bone
and what's powerful about these emerging
uh uh types of 3D printers and and you
could say more automated equipment
overall is the ability to gather data
from the manufacturing process uh so
this is my own kind of you know picture
to cartoon but as the printing process
is happening the machines are able to
collect data uh uh from each layer
printing happens layer by layer and use
that to construct uh you know uh using
the broad term digital twin effectively
a digital twin of the component
representing the data from the printing
process and therefore you can train
these models to detect anomalies uh that
can then indicate whether you had a
component of of of suitable quality or
you have defects in your print uh and uh
in order to bring this process to scale
uh we not only had to develop the
machines uh uh and the inprocess sensing
but develop a whole Suite of software
that allows us to virtually plan the
printing process and we can go all the
way to Machining at the end but because
for most components uh if you're
familiar with 3D printing you not only
have to print it and remove it and clean
it up and heat treat it to get the right
properties and metallic micr structure
but you often want to do some finishing
operations such as Machining to clean up
certain surfaces so now a different
component an example of uh a watch
housing uh this is just a demonstration
geometry but representative of real
applications things like smart watches
that can be made at Large Scale uh you
print not not one or 100 but you print
about 600 at a time on a build plate uh
and to get to the point of the finished
parts that look like this the software
chain uh involves virtual planning of
the process simulation of the 3D print
that involves laser power and a lot of
heat and energy uh and then the
collection of data during the printing
process and the creation of that digital
twin that can be match to a 3D scan and
this is of course very far accelerated
but also shows the integration of
Downstream manufacturing planning uh
virtualizing the Machining process and
virtualizing the Metrology process and
that uh full kind of end to-end digital
threat is really critical to Bringing
these digitally digital first processes
to scale and uh uh also uh all of the
printers are uh controlled centrally
right uh you saw the picture of the
factory it looked pretty empty it's not
that there aren't humans in the in the
process it's not that it's completely
lights out you need people to uh to
interface with the machines load them
unload them maintain them but the
monitoring of the printing process once
the machines are running is entirely
centralized and this is very powerful
because we can use software that goes
alongside the printing process collects
that data to look for Flaws to look for
defects and therefore improve the
process over time so this is one example
of uh uh many applications of 3D
printing as an emerging production
technology from Aviation and space to
medical devices to consumer goods
including the shoes of the the the soles
of the shoes that I'm uh uh wearing
today made by Adidas uh but I don't mean
to imply that you know this is uh
anywhere near a significant fraction of
manufacturing in fact 3D printing as a
whole is like less than a drop in the
bucket right if you think of global
manufacturing as a big bucket of value
created right 15 or so trillion dollar
uh what what 3D printing can do as one
specific process which has many
challenges in cost and and scaling is
ultimately only one one one maybe maybe
much larger drop in that bucket but not
a significant fraction of it but I think
it's reflective of this digital first
mindset that we need when we think of
how to design processes design software
to interface with machines and
automation whether they be uh existing
Technologies of which there's a lot and
you know those technologies will survive
for a long time uh and the insertion of
these new emerging Technologies and
processes in my own research uh uh some
examples are one the development of new
Metals New Alloys uh for processes such
as metal 3D printing and also
conventional metal uh processes uh so a
former member of my research group mahad
who's now a faculty member at Carnegie
melan University developed a computation
pipeline uh to discover new aluminum
Alloys uh that can benefit from the
unique conditions that exist in 3D
printing when you're 3D printing with
Metals you typically use a laser to
rapidly heat and therefore rapidly cool
the metal and that imparts unique
conditions and also unique challenges
for the stability of the metal itself uh
to make the long story short she
developed a pipeline that could look at
hundreds of thousands of combinations of
different elements also look at the cost
C and the carbon footprint implied by
their use and then predict compositions
that would be uh able to be printed uh
to be 3D printed and uh uh that had
attractive properties and we came up
with a family of Alloys that have higher
uh strength uh than uh existing known
structural aluminum Alloys and also can
withstand higher temperatures in use and
we're exploring commercial avenues for
that uh another way that we can think of
bringing these Technologies to to scale
is that uh you
know manufacturing is not just something
that happens in a factory right
manufacturing can happen on site or
there's many applications where you
could say a mode of manufacturing could
be used for repair on site and we have a
very exciting ongoing project with
collaborators at the University of M
Massachusetts uh as well as support from
the Massachusetts Department of
Transportation to look at a kind of 3D
printing for Onsite repair of uh damaged
uh and corroded aging infrastructure so
I know we shouldn't take pictures while
we're driving but I must admit I took
this picture driving slowly on I95 going
north if you are from Boston you know
the 9590 intersection and if you've
driven by there recently you know that
they're replacing this bridge with a new
one because the bridge is so rusted and
corroded this is probably one of the
most uh uh corroded aged bridges in the
state of Massachusetts and you know we
don't want anything to happen to this
this this bridge and Service uh so the
motivation for our work is uh you know
our infrastructure needs help and uh uh
actually there's many opportunities not
just in bridges but you know ships and
other things for repair of uh physical
structures before it's too late before a
structure needs to be replaced so again
to make the long story short we're
developing a digital thread that allows
uh uh one to scan uh say Bridge beams
this is led by our collaborators at at
UMass uh uh predict uh to what extent
the strength the uh properties would be
improved if you added material in that
place using a simulation a computational
model and then develop the technology
that we're hoping to bring into the
field to do on-site repair and you know
it will take time to do that it will
require a a fairly intricate setup but
we believe it's way more efficient and
cost effective than replacing a whole
bridge but is also potentially more
efficient and cost-effective than
traditional methods of repair that
involve closing the road cutting out
beams bolting on plates and things like
that and I feel there's a large
opportunity in thinking about how these
new you could say manufacturing
processes can also be used on site uh
for repair uh there's probably also many
applications in a railway infrastructure
from repairing rails to repairing wheels
and so on and so
forth so now let me go back to the
highle picture and just jump through a
few other examples not from my own work
but from other work at MIT and from the
broader community of things that I find
exciting and uh of course the three-
plane chart here I talked about the
bottom the production infrastructure and
now I'll talk a bit about the top the uh
tools we have for product and process
design right of course like design is a
complex activity design means many
things uh uh there's different processes
for dining different types of products
uh and so on and so forth but another uh
uh capability that I believe is kind of
the fringes uh is you know if we have
more more computational tools at our
disposal uh more ability to scale the
information that we bring into the
design process right uh it's not
necessarily the case that products look
or behave like in the future the same
way they've come to look or behave
because you know it's the way we expect
them to look or that this door hook for
example a very simple product obviously
is made this way because it you know is
formed out of sheet metal uh and there's
you know that that's one of the big
reasons uh so uh among uh these emerging
tools are methods to take not uh a kind
of inductive design uh but take a design
problem and specify the constraints and
then allow the computer to develop a
geometry develop a design that fits
those constraints uh you may know
what uh has been long called topology
optimization this simulation even is
from 2013 so not showing a new
capability but shows the basic idea that
if I start with a virtual block of
material and I say here's where I want
the hook to attach it's got a hook on
the door here or and and hold the the
clothing here uh tell me what the
optimal use of material is and as
computing power becomes more available
we bring in more considerations like the
carbon footprint of the material the
cost of the material we can make more
sophisticated choices and apply these to
more sophisticated scenarios and certain
emergent examples from the marketplace
include taking similar approaches and
applying them to for example Hydraulics
uh this is an example hydraulic manifold
where the conduits for the uh fluid are
uh optimized to reduce the pressure drop
and maintain the routing traditionally
when you manufacture hydraulic manifolds
you take blocks of metal and you drill
orthogonal holes perpendicular holes and
and that's a constraint but to reduce
the pressure drop to improve the
performance you actually want a much
more kind of organic distribution and
this is enabled by those kinds of design
tools but adapted to uh uh routing fluid
flow and simulating fluid flow and
incidentally by 3D printing there will
be future applications in physical
infrastructure uh large beams concrete
trusses Etc and uh uh in in a large part
using these kinds of Technologies
several years ago GE uh decided they
would clean sheet the design of one of
their jet engines uh and they discovered
that they could design it such that if
they 3D printed large components of it
they could reduce the number of
components significantly and uh with one
particular part of the engine uh defined
here as the mid-frame structure
they could reduce 300 components to a
single component and imagine the
advantage right in in uh other aspects
of the complexity of manufacturing and
supply chain sourcing and so on so there
are examples where uh you could say
let's let's do a rethink we don't have
to commit to this new technology but
let's think of what would be possible if
we started from scratch and then think
of how your organization would get there
if you determine it's a good business
case and a good reason to bring it into
your into your
portfolio and our colleagues uh at MIT
this is Professor F ahed in mechanical
engineering are developing what I
believe arguably the next generation of
tools that connect more powerful Ai and
machine learning capabilities uh this is
a to me a really inspiring example uh of
how you could uh connect uh uh
generative
uh design approaches uh uh to
Performance models for say the design
and uh configuration of something uh of
widespread utility such as a bicycle the
idea is that by putting a few different
model capabilities together you can uh
specify I would like a road racing
bicycle that has this certain style you
could input your own right uh you know
height and you know maybe Poss
preferences or you could sit on an
example bicycle in a store uh and then
the uh uh software would come up with a
number of design Alternatives based on a
simulation of perhaps the aerodynamics
as you are writing and this is just one
example uh but I think it's indicative
of how we'll see an ability to close the
loop between design and some amount of
encoded uh performance uh going forward
in the future
and I'm also uh really intrigued uh
about a number of startup companies uh
that are developing uh tools to automate
uh the steps in the design to
manufacturing workflow that are
traditionally very labor intensive I'm
not talking yet about like Factory floor
operations but imagine coming up with
assembly instructions to put an assembly
of components together or checking that
uh uh you know engineering drawings if
not generating the drawings in the first
place uh follow certain standards uh
such as you know standards of the
maritime industry and one company I met
recently is called der they're on the
west coast there's another MIT uh spin
out called Foundation llm working on
automated work instructions uh also a
spin out of the uh uh Cale the Cs and AI
Lab at MIT and this is where we start to
get to this kind of connective tissue in
the middle I think we're starting to see
more exciting possibilities uh
emerge so uh now it's just two I didn't
cut out the middle one but just to say
that you know to kind of bring the
points together you know let's think
about how these new capabilities in
product and process design uh kind of uh
don't necessarily require but could be
enabled by or could enable new kinds of
uction capabilities right uh data being
a thread between the two and at the
bottom we have arguably digital first
process techn Technologies and ways that
we can combine human knowledge with
machine instructions uh and at the top
we have uh the opportunity for a new
generation of design tools that are
manufacturing aware not just able to
explore you know massive geometric or
configurational design spaces and in the
middle uh you know this idea of
uh ai ai models that combine uh
multimodal data right the this is a
broad area of development in in the
field of AI models not just for
manufacturing but for generating images
and working with video and uh training
robots and so on and so forth but I do
believe there's a big opportunity and
need to develop manufacturing tailored
uh AI models that can learn on you know
geometry look at representation of
component on and understand you know uh
how can you screen for manufacturability
or can you uh uh report within a certain
category of component whether a design
is manufacturable or not similarly uh
working through uh reduced order
simulations of certain manufacturing
processes to then feed back uh to the
design and then my second Point here uh
figuring out how we can securely
abstract data among stakeholders
uh and we're kicking off uh along with
our manufacturing at MIT effort that
I'll mention in a moment uh a project to
Think Through how we could develop a set
of distributed AI models to support
manufacturing uh you know take for
instance uh using uh AI tools to
optimize a wellestablished manufacturing
process if not one such as 3D printing
such as Machining or sheet metal forming
or think about you know optimizing the
safety of a manufacturing process
process in general it's clear that uh
such a uh model could benefit from a lot
of data and whether it's one company or
a large number of companies we need to
figure out how to bring that data
together in a way that can be informed
by global models but can be tailored to
specific needs of certain processes or
certain uh companies and so we're very
excited to bring some bright people some
faculty and students uh to uh bring more
detail to this picture going forward and
in a way this idea or uh what'll be my
next point was inspired uh by Morris
Chang so Morris Chang is the founder of
tsmc Taiwan semiconductor manufacturing
company and he came to MIT we uh were so
fortunate to host him uh uh just under a
year ago and he gave a wonderful talk
which you can you can find online uh on
YouTube and uh he talked about the
history of tsmc and the history of the
semiconductor industry right and how
tsmc has now become right in a way the
world semiconductor Foundry and uh one
thing he said uh stuck with me the most
and it was right at this moment where I
took this picture he he put up this
chart of uh it away the semiconductor
you know supply chain value chain right
from research and development to
fabrication to packaging Etc and he said
tsmc did just one thing obviously did a
lot of things but he said they added the
red line he said we added the red line
we figured out how you could
bring knowledge and physical capability
together in a way that it would be
offered to the world and it would enable
a next generation of product Innovation
and now we know many of the world's most
valuable companies that make products
that rely on semiconductors you know uh
rely on the foundaries tsmc included as
their production resource and uh that
you know leads me to kind of an open
question like as we think of
manufacturing being more flexible in the
future what are the ways in which in
different Industries for different
applications manufacturing might be more
distributed but connected and what are
the ways where we'll see new models of
vertical integration right perhaps new
foundaries
if you will that can uh with a deep
understanding of process technology and
automation provide new scalable
capabilities for designers innovators
you know firms from small to large that
uh design products to bring those
products to scale and that will
certainly have implications on you know
today's companies that do contract
manufacturing that manufacture products
but don't necessarily sell the product
so that was to me me a particularly
inspiring moment and I think one that
relates to the overall theme of of the
presentation so uh uh let me close uh
just with just two slides before uh we
take some some questions so the first is
uh you we at MIT have been thinking for
uh about a year now how we can bring
mit's expertise together around the
theme of manufacturing and we've a we we
brought a faculty group together for
that same amount of time and similar to
the idea that you know tsmc just put the
red line around all the boxes and
thought about how to reconfigure
capabilities uh I believe that a lot of
the the future of manufacturing for
individual companies is is based on
looking at how to insert different
Technologies with their existing
operations use data and think about
driving forces such as new Energy
Technologies and sustainability and so
we've coined for ourselves this term of
new manufacturing like what does the new
manufacturing look like here in the US
and around the world and when you think
of why is this moment very very
important one of the driving factors is
because so many companies around the
world for various reasons whether it be
Supply chaina fragility or geopolitics
or you know driving force of of of of
climate change are thinking of how to
reposition uh and also realizing that
they can do much better their operations
can be much better and just one example
in terms of the big shifts is data from
our colleagues here on the amount of
foreign direct investment in
manufacturing in the US it's literally
at a generational high so while I will
wrap up with this slide uh that's what
this new manufacturing initiative at MIT
is all about it's about studying the
Next Generation themes in manufacturing
working closely with industry including
through an industry Consortium that
we're putting together this fall and
reaching deeply into mit's expertise in
uh in in in particular areas of focus
Robotics and automation AI for
manufacturing
biomanufacturing uh the built
environment and so on and so forth and
I'd be happy to be in touch and tell you
more about it uh is feel free to send me
an email at the address here thank you
[Applause]
all
right how do I see Ai and gen
transforming PLM uh product life cycle
management and similar systems uh great
question I I think I don't have a great
answer I think there'll be a number of
ways uh one of the challenges that I I
think exists is that a lot of these
tools and the same thing exists in 3D
printing for instance are being
developed
by different companies and how they talk
to each other the interrup operability
is key so you know uh from the PLM
perspective I think it will come down to
the companies that uh uh develop the PLM
systems bringing those tools on board
and establishing interoperability but
you could imagine new ways that you
manage uh you know configurations of
products that you document variants of
designs that you document test data and
quality data and I think that will
influence uh p M systems in the future
for sure and and and open question being
you know how do suppliers tie in and how
how do they provide more data Upstream
as well as you know uh companies
sourcing products provide it
Downstream if starting with production
infrastructure as a base of
manufacturing is there risk of adding
extra constraints to product and process
design uh you good question I think
possibly I would say more generally the
question is how do you how do you
represent the constraints uh of of of of
process capabilities I I also would say
there's many examples where you know we
don't really know the true bounds of
manufacturing at the design stage and
that can have benefits right oh I can
think you know think more broadly and
then manufacturing narrows it down or it
can also have the opposite effect if I
don't know truly what are the bounds of
a of a production process may maybe the
design stage is
restricted if you use 3D printing for
spacecraft or aircraft how can you
validate the quality and safety of
maintaining the parts after some years
great question uh there's uh established
capabilities for qualifying the parts
it's uh quite uh involved to do that uh
but uh you need to do the material
testing that is effectively the same
testing that you use to prove out
conventional processes the good thing is
that uh with appropriate control you can
uh you know achieve 3D printed material
properties that are conventional if not
Superior to many uh conventional
processes and that will enable these
Technologies to be inserted in you know
things like next Generation jet engines
and medical implants at
scale all right should we wrap up or see
if there's one question from the
audience yes
please all right I don't see any hands
so thank you again thank you