Hi everyone, my name is Laura Lubbert
and I'm also a post-doctoral fellow at
the Eric and Vanishes Center and it's my
honor to present our next speaker,
Professor Patrick Shu. Professor Shu is
a co-founder and co-investigator at the
Ark Institute as well as an assistant
professor at Berkeley University. His
work has been pretty influential from
the get-go. During his PhD, he played a
pivotal role in developing crisper cast
9 technology. And since then, his lab
has led groundbreaking work in genome
editing. Amongst others, crisper
technology that targets RNA and the
recent discovery of a whole new class of
guide RNAs called bridge RNAs. Together
with Brian He, he also developed EVO 2,
one of the largest biological foundation
models. Uh unsurprisingly, his work has
been awarded several accolades,
including the NIH Early Independence
Award, the Rainwater Prize for
Innovative Early Career Scientists, and
Forbes 30 under 30. Please join me in
welcoming Professor Patrick Shu.
[Applause]
Awesome. Well, thanks so much uh
Caroline and the organizers for having
me and uh it's a real joy and privilege
to be here today and tell you about some
of uh our work and trying to bring
together the fields of uh genetics and
machine learning. Um as so so you know
as Laura kindly introduced you know I've
been thinking about ways that we can
manipulate uh you know biological
molecules directly inside of living
cells for a long time and over the last
few years we started to really turn our
attention to how we could actually model
uh these molecules as well. And so if we
you know go to the words of Francis
Arnold the uh original inventor of
directed evolution right she says you
know for today we can for all practical
purposes rewrite and edit any sequence
of DNA but we cannot compose it maybe we
can cut and paste these pieces from
nature's compositions but we don't know
how to write the bars for a single
enzyic passage. uh but she ends by
saying however evolution does know how
to do this and so we started thinking in
the lab how can we decipher the language
of evolution to try to compose genomic
information. So these advances in AI as
we all know offer this universal
framework that leverage data and compute
at scale to uncover higher order
patterns in diverse domains including
natural language uh vision or even
embodied intelligence. Right? And of
course we're trying to apply this
machine learning paradigm uh to
biological molecules. And over the past
few years, we've seen some really
incredible breakthroughs for protein
structure prediction, lian docking,
looking at the complex folds of RNA and
so on. And that's obviously been really
wonderful. But the problem is despite
the immense complexity of even these
molecules and these modeling paradigms
so far, right? The complexity of these
molecules is really dwarfed by the
overall complexity of an entire cell,
which is many orders of magnitude larger
and more complex. And so the cell's fun
uh structure and its function are really
built by the diverse interactions
between all these different molecules
which is a staggering number of
combinatorial possibilities um at
multiple levels of regulation. So in
short this is really really complicated.
The good news is that all of this
molecular logic fundamentally is encoded
within DNA. That's a single sequence
that contains all the information that
is needed arguably to create an entire
organism. So in fact the effects of
evolution are actually passed down
throughout generations of life via these
DNA mutations. So in principle you might
be able to learn something about
function right or the functional
adaptations to natural selection by
looking at DNA alone. And so we asked
this simple question. Can we create a
machine that tries to learn the
evolutionary distribution of these
sequences from whole genomes and learn
something about the interactions of all
these different molecules that creates
an entire
organism. One of the central challenges
in doing this is that biology uses a
different language. It's foreign and not
very human interpretable. So on the left
you can see this schematic of this
so-called central dogma of molecular
biology where DNA is transcribed to RNA
which is translated to proteins. Right?
But you'll immediately see two things on
the right. The first is that these
sequences are continuous and
directional. And the second from the
bottom moving upward there's a hierarchy
of information flow that's embedded
across the different modes of this
central dogma where they're predictably
transformed uh into you know different
types of uh sequences and codons. And so
to try to understand this molecular
language, you can try to, you know, port
over the sort of auto reggressor uh auto
reggressive uh paradigm from natural
language modeling here to DNA where you
know if you want to do next token
prediction for a famous passage from the
English literature to be or not to be,
we all intuitively know the next token.
We've pre-trained on talking to each
other, right? But if I asked you GTGC
catct, would you know what the next
nucleotide is? Right? And to give you an
intuition for why at massive scales of
text, this next token prediction
paradigm can lead to general reasoning
and intelligence, right? It's useful to
look at a few examples. So if you, you
know, if I said in my free time, I like
to code, right? Or banana. It's not
banana, right? I I'll learn something
about grammar or um or or even world
knowledge. The capital of Azerbaijan is
Baku and not London, right? Or I'm
standing in Cambridge and not in San
Francisco, right? But you know, you can
you can get more complex things even
like spatial reasoning, right? Iro went
into the kitchen to make tea, standing
next to Iro. Zuko pondered his destiny.
He probably then left the kitchen and
not the bathroom, right? And so, you
know, kind of at massive scales of text,
you can start to break
apart unstructured data to find
patterns. And this is effectively what
we try to do in biological research,
right? We know and learn in high school
that we have genotype that's linked or
underpins phenotype in some way and we
try to use that to
uh dulge mechanism and phenotype is in
turn selected in order to influence
genotype. Right? And so by looking at
the next base or the next something in a
biological sequence, you can start to
learn pretty interesting and diverse
things about complex biological
properties. So an example would be if
the next nucleotide in my genome is
going to be a healthy nucleotide or it's
going to give me a devastating genetic
disorder. At the abstraction level of
residues, is the next residue going to
be a functional catalytic residue or
it's going to be some catalytic null
that inactivates my molecular machine?
Or it might be if this next uh
nucleotide is going to disrupt a
hairpin, an RNA secondary structure that
no longer forms the abdimer shape that
is required to bring a co-actor in order
to do transcriptional regulation or even
at the abstraction level of genes. We
know in proaryotic genomes genes that
function together are clustered together
in functional operons and so mod a and
mod b is probably followed by mod c and
not the kind of unaffiliated uh you know
DNA repair enzyme wreck a right and so
we try to take these intuitions to train
initial model called evo1 this is a
close collaboration with my arc
colleague Brian he um where we've seen
so far in the field lots of effort on
creating tasks specific specific
specialized models like ESM for protein
language or models for regulatory DNA or
for RNA language in particular. However,
all of these different components
because they're fundamentally encoded
inside of the genome, right? By training
a genome foundation model at long
context, we might be able to learn all
of these different elements, but
importantly all of their combinatorial
interactions as well. So we train this
initial model at 7B 131K token context
and show that the model is both
multimodal because it can understand
these different modalities of central
dogma but that it's also multi-cale.
I'll give you a few examples. In
addition to designing proteins, right,
where you're simply autocompleting some
residue sequence, you can also design
things like crisper systems which
orchestrates a cast 9 protein a
molecular scissors with a non-oding
guide RNA. Right? Because these are
fundamentally encoded within the genome,
EVO understands the co-evolutionary
relationship between these two different
sequences and is able to make functional
EVO designed cast 9 that are able to cut
DNA in the test tube or inside of a
cell. Right? That's a generation task at
the not just molecular level, but at a
molecular systems level. But you can
also do predictions at the cellular or
organismal scale. So one thing that
we're able to do here is to efficiently
classify essential from non-essential
genes. Something that's the territory of
experimental gene essentiality crisper
screens that take months to years in the
lab. Here we can replace that with
forward passes of a neural network.
Right? Even at the genome scale we can
generate uh long sequences at a megabase
that looks kind of like a proarotic
genome. You'll see that there's dense
coding architecture in both strands.
There are genes that can be translated
into proteins embedded within these long
unconstrained generations. They contain
protein structures that map to the
distribution of naturally observed alpha
helyses or beta sheets and their
ontologies map to fundamental functional
ontologies.
They even we can even see in these
single generations all of the tRNAs that
you need to support protein translation
but unfortunately we see only some of
the rnas that you would need to make the
ribosomes that would then in turn make
those proteins right so we sort of think
of this as a blurry picture of life
right and so hopefully more scaling
could actually get us to sharper uh
understanding and reasoning about
genomic content so in training this
model we uh uncovered so-c calledled
scaling loss for DNA, which is something
that we've seen in the large language
modeling space, which is that there's a
very predictable improvement in model
performance as you pour in more compute,
more pre-training data or more
parameters into the model. We see that
type of pattern here implying that these
are similar strategies that can be used
to improve genomic model performance,
right? And so EVA1 was trained on 300
billion tokens tokenized a single
nucleotide resolution of proaryotic and
fagee genomes. So these are the small
sort of single cellar organisms. And in
the next study we wanted to move to
understand ukarotic genomes like ours
right which are of course much longer
contain introns and you know uh you know
kind of non-coding space and uh you know
are much longer and more complex. With
EVO 2, we scaled to over 9 trillion
tokens of DNA across all observable
evolution um including bacteria, archa,
and all ukaria. Um and um and asked uh
if we could extend from 131k context to
a million token context if we'd be able
to learn uh more about these sort of
kind of ukarotic scales of biology,
right? And so just to give you a sense
of this, right? Individual molecules are
of course quite small and with EVO1 we
can fit in things like functional
operons right in proarotic genomes where
you have multiple different elements
that are coded together in cy sequence
but as you extend to ukareotic genomes
the scale of entire yeast chromosomes
human tads or entire bacterial genomes
right you can actually fit all of this
information in context um at million uh
token context right scale this model to
uh over 40 billion parameters um using a
multiconvolutional hybrid architecture
known as striped hyena. In EVO 2, uh we
developed a new uh architecture known as
striped hyena 2 um that uh like EVO one
uses these uh kind of gated convolutions
striped with 10% attention that's able
to evaluate long context at nearlinear
uh time uh and with improvements in
throughput of training, right? And so,
you know, this is essentially how we can
try to crunch, you know, these massive
pre-training uh databases and data mixes
without the, you know, kind of massive
GPU farms that you have in uh you know,
industrial AI labs. So, you know, so
that this is cool. Um lots of
architecture stuff. What what does the
model learn about biology, right? And
so, you know, you can feed in uh
mutations into the model and ask the
model what's going on at that mutation,
right? This is an entire field of
computational biology known as variant
effect prediction. Right? And so I'll
give you a more concrete example.
There's an important gene in the genome
known as broco one. Right? It's known to
be able to cause some breast and ovarian
cancers. Right? If you have a causal
mutation, right? Many patients might
elect for a double mistctomy. If you
have a benign mutation, you might just
elect for an annual mammogram. The
problem though is most people have what
are known as variants of unknown
significance which is fancy you know
science jargon for we don't know what
the hell is going on. The good news is
again Evo has an opinion about your
mutation. And if you uh sort of uh feed
in all the different uh known broco one
mutations uh derived from ClinVar, a
gold standard NIH database, you can see
that EVO is state-of-the-art in
classifying non-coding mutations and
their effects on pathogenicity and it's
nearly state-of-the-art for coding
mutations as well. Intriguingly, EVO in
training has only ever seen a single
reference human genome whereas alpha
missense from deep mind was trained
explicitly on human genomic variation.
So it's very interesting that it's
actually able to learn to this degree of
performance by seeing primate genomes,
zebra fish, bacteria phage, sea elegance
and so on. Um, and you know, now we're
trying to inject the model with explicit
information on rare and common genetic
variation to see if we can make a single
generalist state-of-the-art model across
both coding and non-coding
mutations. These were all zeros
predictions, but it turns out the
embeddings of the model, it's learned
representations have actually deeper
information about biology. And in fact
by training a supervised classifier on
top of the EVO embeddings you can
actually bring it to state-of-the-art
performance implying that you know
simple kind of prompt engineering or
steering the model in token space is
only kind of one way to improve you know
the you know genomic language model
performance or insights.
One of the common criticisms of these
large language models is that they're
blackbox right you know the models are
learning something but what are we right
and so there's a sub field of ML called
meantinurp or mechanistic
interpretability where you can try to
break down neural circuits from these
large neural networks into observable
parts right and so there's a classic
example in the field from anthropic
which makes the claude series of models
where they've broken down um clawed into
these different semantic features. One
of which famously corresponds to the
concept the con semantic concept of a
Golden Gate Bridge, right? And you can
actually see across a whole bunch of
different languages, these semantic
features light up in the same
place. If you ask Claude, you know, what
is your physical form? It will sensibly
tell you it doesn't have one. It's
simply an AI. But if you clamped this
Golden Gate Bridge feature to 10x its
weight, it now becomes obsessed with the
idea of bridges. I'm a famous suspension
bridge. I'm the iconic bridge itself
with its beautiful orange color and
sweeping suspension cables. Right? If
you try to prompt it to ask it to do
math, uh to ask it, uh, you know, what
you should cook tonight for dinner, it
will tell you you should cook the Golden
Gate Bridge, right? And so you can try
to take this uh type of uh you know
paradigm of breaking down this model
into human observable parts which is uh
you know called sparse autoenccoders
where you can try to break down and
interpret the model activations onto any
language model um including EVO. I'll
I'll first sort of note that EVO has
never been trained with any explicit
biological information. It's not it's
unanotated. It's unsupervised. you've
only asked it to do next nucleotide
prediction. Intriguingly, when you lay
out the E.coli genome here, because it's
a circular genome, uh you can see a
bunch of different semantic features
lighting up at different locations
across the E.coli genome. And what we
found was that there was a a particular
uh feature semantic feature that
corresponds to the idea of proage
sequences, right? And in fact, it's
actually doing a really great job at
finding the boundaries of these proage
sequences, right? And so what the sort
of classic binatic way to do this is to
take all these different genes, blast
them and try to figure out which ones
match to a fage origin, right? Those
are, you know, tools like faster and
others where you try to, you know, call
the boundaries. But the model somehow
has just learned this bottoms up, right?
And in fact these same proage features
fire in the spacers of crisper repeat
arrays right where in the process of
crisper bacterial adaptive immunity
these fingerprints are captured from
invading bacteria phage into these
repeat arrays and the model again has
sort of managed to identify specifically
these spacers that's foreign. So if you
zoom in on a different part of the
genome um you can find features that
fire on other things like open reading
frames, intergenic regions, transfer
RNAs, ribosomal RNAs. Um but not just
coding and non-coding features but also
features like the secondary structure of
proteins because proteins are of course
embedded in the genome. And so you can
see features that fire selectively on
alpha helyses or beta sheets and uh you
know kind of even in the context of kind
of protein known protein protein
interactions uh embedded inside of these
functional operons. So that's all
proarotic genomes. But if you moved and
looked at ukareotic genomes, uh you can
actually see in the human genome that in
non-coding promoters upstream of a
transcriptional start site, you can see
that there are these motifs or semantic
features that fire on uh these sequence
motifs that correspond surprisingly to
known transcription factor binding
motifs, right? suggesting that the model
may have some inkling about gene
regulation or
binding. You can also find features that
correspond to ukareotic gene
architecture like uh coding sequences,
untransated regions, but not just the
concept of exxons, but also the leading
and lagging edge of exxons. So, it's
able to find those boundaries. This same
feature can be used to look at the human
genome but also the woolly mammoth
genome for example which was not seen in
pre-training showing some sense of
generality of of these types of coding
features.
Macintob can also be used to look at
computer code, right? And it can find
errors in computer code. Um, you know,
like mine is riddled with it, for
example. Uh, you know, you can also find
errors in the genetic code and there
there are features that seem to fight
preferentially on frame shift mutations
um and not on, for example, synonymous
mutations. Um and so you know we're very
intrigued by you know the um
opportunities here to try to understand
and you know mechanistically interpret
something about how these language
models are learning about biological
features not just for classic well-known
features like I've shown you so far but
potentially to discover here to for
unknown things about the genome in
addition to breaking down the model into
these human parts again you can try to
use it for generation And we tested EVO
in three different generation tasks to
try to make mitochondrial genomes, whole
bacterial genomes or entire ukareotic
chromosomes. So if you wanted to make a
mitochondrial genome, which you of
course we all have, right? You can see
our version lined up here in the middle
of the slide in a dashed box, right?
Here are six evoggenerated mitochondrial
genomes. And what you'll see is that
it's not simply memorizing and
regurgitating your mitochondrial genome.
In fact, sometimes it'll, you know, kind
of flip the orientation of genes or
shift them around slightly. But
importantly, it keeps all of the core
genes that are in the mitochondrial
genome and it preserves all of the key
protein protein interactions. for
example, the core subunits of complex
one of this uh encoded mitochondrial
electron transport chain.
You can also generate uh uh you know
things that look like entire bacterial
genomes like the minimal uh sort of
species myopplasma genitalium and so you
can see with EVO one right and so here
we're showing you in blue pam hits to
you know the known uh sort of database
and then you can see that you know EVO1
generations were you know missing a lot
of you know kind of these known proteins
but this actually you know kind of
significantly improves improves with EVO
2. And to me, this kind of recalls the
improvements in scaling of these image
generation models where if you're trying
to make this sort of this kangaroo in a
hoodie with a welcome friends sign, you
know, sort of the early version of the
MA model gives you something that looks
like something on the street of San
Francisco, right? The the the sign is
kind of unintelligible. It's not that
cool. It looks a little sad, right? And
you know the hope is right with EVO 3
and EVO 4 and so on right we'll be able
to go from these you know slightly
sharper understandings of the genome to
something that could potentially be
synthesized and tested directly inside
of living cells. I think you can already
do so in a few shot manner. The goal is
you know to one day be able to do this
uh more
zeroot. Um this extends to ukarotic
chromosomes as well. But you know, one
of the things that we're often asked
with genome language models is, hey,
this is cool. You can embed DNA, I
guess, but what about epigenetics and
what about RNA? And uh you know so so we
try to you know kind of answer some of
those questions where you can take this
generative model a DNA model like EVO
and try to actually score its
generations with a model like an
informer or boro which has been
explicitly trained on things like DHS or
chipsseek data and uh you can basically
score these EVO generations based on
predicted chromatin accessibility right
and so in this uh uh in a sort of design
task. You can try to ask the model to
conform to user specified peaks, wide
attack seek peaks or narrow attack seek
peaks for example and by adding more
compute into the model at uh generation
time. What you can see is that the model
over time with more thinking is able to
try to generate sequences that fit these
user design patterns with higher
fidelity. Right? The fun thing is that
you can encode information uh in these
attack peaks like dots and dashes and
write Morse code messages like ARC or
EVO 2. And now we're installing these uh
directly into the genomes of living
cells and doing real attack seek on them
to see if we're able to make those uh
you know actual uh
patterns. I'll sort of uh you know kind
of motivate that I think this is
actually very general and it's not just
uh you know an epigenome structure
scoring function but it could be you
know really any generic sequence to
function predictor that you hook on top
of a generative model in order to be
able to design you know more complex
representations of biology. We think of
this as a foundational model because it
enables this app store of
different applications across different
modalities of the central dogma all the
way up to entire seller and organismal
scale tasks. We've shown a few examples
of that in this study and we hope you
know the community will be able to kind
of build many more. Right? This is a
fully open source model and by by fully
open source I mean the pre-training data
the pre-training infra and all the model
weights are fully available the code is
on GitHub the models hosted on hugging
face um we have a front end called EVO
designer which you can use to prompt and
interpret model outputs blast sequences
do structure prediction of the embedded
proteins and so on and so you know we've
been really delighted by the initial
reception and lots of folks who are
building with and I hope you guys do
too. Um, I'll just sort of end by
saying, you know, uh, you know, the
these these models that learn, you know,
on massive scales of DNA are just the
beginning, right? And so, you know,
we're very excited about ways that you
can improve the quality of the model
predictions and generations by uh, you
know, kind of uh, doing lab in the loop
with experimental feedback. And our hope
is that by taking the ability to compose
DNA combined with the programmable
recominases that we reported from the
lab last year, we'll be able to install,
you know, kind of uh DNA directly inside
of living cells that's been programmed
at a higher level of abstraction than
the sort of uh few bases that we're able
to edit in the modern gene editing
paradigm. Something that we're we're
really thinking of as genome design.
Um, you know, so I I'll just sort of end
by saying, you know, I think scientific
discovery is often a search problem,
right? You know, as we all know, you
kind of have to kind of guess and check,
right? Where we have multiple scientific
hypotheses and you need to recursively
test them to see what's going on, right?
Um, and you know, the problem is that
this is very confusing, right? And it
kind of feels like when you're a kid and
you look at the night sky and you're
trying to find that constellation, uh,
where is the Big Dipper? And, you know,
you have no idea. And what you really
want is something that's much more like
a co-pilot like the night sky app that
could tell you where the constellations
are across space and also at different
points in time. Right? This is really,
you know, kind of how biology is
orchestrated across space and time. And
so one of the things that is a flagship
initiative of ours at ARC is to build
these virtual cells that are able to
model not just inputs of universal
genome representations like I showed you
today but also uh inputs from the
environment where genotype and the
environmental representations
collaborate to create uh you know better
predictions of phenotype. We're doing
this across a variety of different uh
tasks uh including uh curating public
data with AI agents where we recently uh
released the world's largest repository
of single cell data by actually creating
an agentic crawler over all of NCBI SR
and uh taking kind of unstructured data
sets being contributed across the
community uh to uh generate over 400
million cells. Um we're also uh you know
in house generating uh you know
perturbational data and then uh you know
setting up the eval benchmarks and uh
novel uh algorithms to try to you know
kind of understand these cell
representations.
So, you know, I I I though I'll sort of,
you know, just say I I hope I've
convinced you today that, you know, in
in the community, we we kind of have a
piece the pieces to try to close this
conceptual touring loop, right, which
was first proposed in 1936 by the, you
know, kind of, you know, Alan Turing,
the computer scientist, where, you know,
if you had a machine that can read, you
know, kind of compute and then write
back to tape, you could in principle
implement any computable algorithm. And
by digitizing biological states, you
know, thinking about it and writing it
back into cells, right, we can start to
close this analogous touring loop uh for
biology. Um, you know, this has been,
you know, really wonderful uh, you know,
series of collaborations um, across ARC
with Brian Heath, Evo 1 was led by Eric
Newan, Matt Durant, Brian Kang, Duva
Katrickar, David Lee, and Michael Pauly.
and uh you know uh many folks uh
contributed to uh EVO2 across ARC our
partner Nvidia uh university
collaborators uh and industry
collaborators like goodfire for our
mechanistic interpretability work so
yeah thanks so much I'm delighted to
take
[Applause]
questions thank you so much
questions thank you for a Great talk. So
I think a lot about uh what information
that might be spatially encoded in
biological system that might not be
encoded by sequence for example. So have
you encountered any tasks where your
model just cannot predict it and you
think that it's actually because you
don't have that three-dimensional
information of the the fold of the DNA
for example or do you have any such
examples where you think that you'd need
to encode spatial information better in
order to perform? I think a lot right uh
thank you for that question and I I
think you know embedded in your question
uh no pun intended is the question of
what is a virtual cell right and you
know I think it's the word that's in the
zeitgeist today and lots of folks are
talking about it but it's actually very
poorly defined right and I think uh with
with both EVO and EVO 2 we had to work
really hard to actually just invent eval
from scratch um that would be
quantitative for the ML and comp bio
community and also I think like
conceptually interesting to the wet lab
community in a way that folks would feel
that these are actually useful tasks
that I would actually care about if
there was no AI involved whatsoever
right and I think we'll we'll need to be
able to do that for these single cell
foundation models and also for the
spatial ones right so you know I mean
complex questions like you know
dendritic cell activation in the tumor
micro environment right or you know some
sort of quorum behavior are the kinds of
things that I think single cell models
alone are unlikely to capture accurately
and spatial data of course will be
important and I think you know um you
know like multi-scale models of biology
right um you know biological scale span
from atoms to ecosystems right and I
think we'll have different modeling
types or paradigms that will indep
independently get developed and get
unified over time we have these all atom
diffusion models today that are trying
to do structure and ligan docking we
have these sequence to function models
and then we have these ways of trying to
you know embed natural language and EHR
information and you know I think right
now they're being developed somewhat
independently I think with EVO what we
saw was that there were protein and RNA
and codon and whatsoever language models
we tried to collapse them into a single
uh paradigm by modeling genomes alone I
think conceptually analogous ways of
collapsing these other types of models
um over time will also be needed.
Thank you so much Patrick for the
amazing talk. We unfortunately have to
move on for the sake of time but thank
you. Let's thank Patrick again.