And with that, I would now um like to
invite Chancellor Nobles to the stage.
Uh we're going to have a quick um
fireside chat. Uh there's no fire here,
but uh we'll make do. Uh please let me
pull this slightly to the center so that
>> Oh boy.
>> Yep.
>> On the hot seat. hot seat. Yes.
>> Morning everyone.
>> So, um I thought or we thought that it
would be nice for uh Melissa to talk
about her um uh experience working with
students. Um she's been here doing this
for a while now. Um and so, you know,
all of us try to imagine what it is to
be a chancellor of a university, right?
So let's start with what does that job
actually entail at MIT because at every
university it may have a different
definition. Would love to understand
what it means at MIT.
>> Sure. Thank you. Good morning everyone.
So I've been at MIT for um over 30
years. I came as an assistant professor
in political science and um recently
within the past five years became
chancellor. Um so the chancellor is
responsible for all things connected to
students on both the living side meaning
uh the division of student life as well
as the academic side both graduate and
undergraduate studies and there is an
office of 60 beneath me um which work
with our students and of course with our
faculty um so the president the provos
deals with the faculty and I deal with
the students and the president deals
with everything.
Well, thank you. Uh 60 plus offices.
That's a that's a lot. Um but I did want
to ask about I'm sure you see MIT
students at their most vulnerable,
right? These are all smart students that
come to MIT. They have never failed in
their high school education. They've
been validictorians
and um yeah overachievers and then they
come to MIT and they fail for the first
time. Uh what how how do you deal with
that? I mean it's a small ego or a large
ego that gets pricricked.
>> Yes. Well, many of our students, it's
true. Absolutely. They've been high
achievers and they've been known to be
the best and then they come into a place
where everyone is doing well and and
because we don't grade, the faculty do
not grade on the curve. It it's quite
devastating for those who don't do as
well. Um, but we have a big support
system for them and let them know that
uh they were in, they're here for a
reason and we're going to make sure that
they get out and succeed. So, we provide
lots of services and we let them know
you're going to fail, you'll survive,
you you we'll provide you supports that
you need and you'll do better. So, that
that helps, right? um they're smart as
you said, but they're 18, you know,
they're 18 years old and so we we always
want to make sure that we're supporting
them in the ways that they think best,
but it's not always easy, I must say.
>> Um and it often takes a lot of high
touch, which is what we provide as well.
We provide a lot of high touch for our
students, meaning we have a fairly flat
organization. Students send emails to
the president, her name is Sally, and
they say, "Hi, Sally." So, we don't have
President Corn Bluth. I'm Melissa and
the rest. So we we try to allow uh there
to be as much um connection between us
but uh obviously the president or I
don't deal with every single issue the
students have. We have a very um
elaborate uh support teams which u reach
out to our students as needed.
>> Yeah. So that means like depending on
the problems that they're facing they'll
go to one of the six%.
>> Yeah.
>> Exactly. Right. Um what's the most human
moment you've experienced with a student
that reminded you that they're not an
academic machine?
>> Well, usually and sometimes that can be
difficult. you know when I was teaching
um uh I was I the am ambitions and the
passions was something that um uh I I uh
I was surprised by pleasantly surprised
by that uh motivation was not a question
and I didn't have to work to motivate
anyone often times I think all the
faculty say students keep us on our toes
so uh so sometimes you we you know you
kind of forget that about them but what
made them what I would Oh, after class
they come and speak to me. They ask me
very personal things or things about
their lives or what they should do,
asking for guidance and things that
remind you that of course they're trying
to find their way even as they are
usually quite focused academically.
They often times recognize as we would
expect that they have fuller lives
beyond what's in the classroom.
>> Of course. Of course. Um
and I've heard you say the whole
student, right? What does that mean?
like what do you mean that I mean of
course we talk about academics they're
coming to MIT for academics but what is
a whole student
>> well oftentimes uh there's you know if
you say MIT most people say nerd right
they're like ah right I mean that's kind
of what people think and um and there's
some truth in that um but it's an
interesting nerd and it's a nerd that
just isn't about science technology
although that's a big part of it I was
the dean of the school of humanities
arts and social sciences before becoming
chancellor
And in that school we have music and
theater arts which is hugely popular,
poetry, creative writing, all of those
things. I mean just the what would you
expect the wide range of interest that
makes us human. Our students are no
different. Even if the public perception
is that they are not that way. So the
whole student means attending to their
intellectual interest giving them space
to think about those things. But
secondly, it's and as more importantly
actually is thinking about their person,
physical health, the human relationships
that they create, how to live in
community and dorms, all the things that
students deal with when you come when
you're on a residential campus, a quite
diverse residential campus and every
dimension of diversity and you're coming
to live and grow. So the whole student
means taking care of yourself and taking
care of your person outside of your
intellectual life. In our current moment
as the uh Steve was mentioning about the
concerns about technology emphasis on
the human part is even more important.
Um increasingly our students are coming
in with much more digital native in a
way that many of us were not. So of my
generation the life that I imagine being
a graduate uh undergraduate is not the
lives of our students. Social media is
there from the beginning. Oftentimes
when I'm in a meeting with the students
there are three people in the meeting.
me, the student in the phone. And the
phone has power. It's they're texting.
You think you you know you you're
dealing with uh a a technology that's
changing the way in which they interact
with me, in which they interact with
each other and themselves, right?
There's a there's the person sitting in
front of you. Then there's their profile
on Instagram. And there might not be a
lot of resemblance between the two. So
that's changing
>> the the world in which we're living and
it creates uh a different kind of
meaning to the notion of the whole
student. No, that's a very interesting
thing, right? I mean, uh, the student as
a person versus their online persona.
>> Yes.
>> Makes it the whole as well.
>> I mean, it would seem obvious, but when
we've talked to students, if you're
having a disagreement with someone, you
can just talk to them. You don't have to
put it a post, a tweet or whatever they
call it now, right? Part of my challenge
is keeping up with the nomenclature. But
anyway, um, whatever it is, you put it
out there and it creates um, it it can
complicate Yeah. relationships as much
as it can um advance them and there is a
way in which these social media help to
build community but you have to think
about it in a way that um you have to be
quite intentional about it because the
the uh the the downsides can be quite
extreme.
>> Well, thank you. I mean I hadn't thought
about the com and now with AI it gets
even more complicated.
>> Absolutely.
>> Um
>> absolutely
>> tough job. Um students today face
pressures um that like you mentioned
that our generation did not face. So um
can you explain what keeps you up at
night when you think about those new
challenges that we may not have faced
when we were younger?
>> You know um it's a that's a complicated
question. Um on the one hand many of our
students are uh the ones I meet are
quite earnest and optimistic about their
own futures. Yeah,
>> even if they despair about the world.
And I'm sure it seems kind of
counterintuitive or at least um
inreconcilable how you have those two
things happening. But you can think I'm
doing well, but many are deeply
concerned about climate change. So, and
kind of an existential concern. Some are
concerned or confused about how to think
about these technologies.
Uh the third is though they have great
faith in the ability of science
technologies to make differences. So
there's a there is a uh conflict of
sorts of of which I think is a different
kind of burden. Uh when I think about my
own life for all of the issues in the
United States when I was coming up I
thought that there was a um the
escalator was always going up but there
was a there was a certain confidence and
optimism about progress.
>> Yeah. as being inevitable and
unquestioned.
I don't think students see that that
this way. So, it's a challenging time
for our students in that regard.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Uh that's that's
something for all of us to think about.
Um
during your toughest moment as
chancellor, um
how did you balance being a leader
and being a human?
So it's often times and I imagine many
of you face these kind of issues. You
have a a hard decision or something that
you have to make some bad news that you
have to deliver but you have to do it in
such a way that leaves the person um
whole but decision stands
>> correct. Um
so usually it's basically um being quite
direct
maybe soften delivery but no ambiguity
um because ambiguity just complicates
something you know only makes it it yeah
it doesn't help. So I just always say,
you know, think about how I want
something told to me. Say it straight.
>> Yeah.
>> Respect me. Acknowledge that it will be
difficult for me to hear it, but say it
and then give me something to, you know,
take away with it, some optimism or
direction. So I try to do the same. I
think about students as I would want to
be talked to when I was that age. um um
even when people had to deliver bad news
to me and as when I was in college I
heard a lot of bad news so it was good
that I did.
>> No, thank you. Uh I I personally prefer
direct messaging uh respect but direct.
Um before you became chancellor, what
aspect of student life did you think you
understood but you were completely wrong
about it
or slightly wrong about it or did not
completely understand?
>> Well, I think so. I would just see them
in the classroom. I come in and we
teach, you know, I teach and things and
enjoy those conversations, meet with
students doing office hours and things.
I had no sense of life after they left
the classroom. I mean, none. um you know
where students were living. I knew they
lived on campus and things um but I
didn't have any sense of the depth of
the of their relationships just the
complexity of their lives. Um and now as
chancellor I see it much more in the
ways in which the institute is helping
to shape that the institute right um the
way in which it's helping to shape their
lives in ways that as a faculty member I
hadn't appreciated but um it's their
home for the four years that they're
there and um and it and so we have a
responsibility to make to make it as um
a you know responsibly provide a place
where they can thrive and we're all
committed to to that. No, and that's
where the whole student also comes in
into play. Um,
and of course the other the flip side is
also when students saw you as a
professor was different and now they see
you as administration.
So
>> yeah,
>> how do you break through that?
>> Faculty are revered
>> administration. Administration or not?
Um, so I'm admin. You admin
this true. I am admin. Um, one thing
that I do, um, I I try to make myself
available as possible. Unannounced
visits to different things with being
careful about
student spaces though because they do,
you know, if I come to unannounced,
they're like, really? So, I I I try to
go in places where I'm unexpected, but
um, where my presence would be welcomed.
see observing something going to back to
games you know uh different kind of
events I'll just show up uh that's one
thing the other thing I do quite
deliberately um and this is back to my
earlier remarks about it being a fairly
flat organization is that I have direct
um relationships with the leadership of
the student body so the undergraduate
>> association and the graduate student
council and they have my cell number I
have theirs and I meet with them every
two weeks privately one-on-one with
leadership so they get to know me and I
do this over the summer and we do this
during the year. So when things happen
and over the past three years or four
years it's been quite active on many
campuses in the US. those kind of
connections have helped quite a bit in a
range of issues and it just sets up com
you know personal conversations um so
that the admin they see how I see things
and I see how they see things and so it
makes our conversations we don't always
agree but at least we um we have a
relationship that makes those
conversations easy
>> easier
>> and to your point I mean it's not about
agreeing it's about being direct and um
compassionate at the same time. Yeah.
>> Um
>> I mean we talked about it. MIT attracts
the smartest kinds of uh students uh and
people in the room. Um what happens when
they realize that uh they're not smart
anymore or they're not the only smart
person in the room.
>> They just they either say uh they learn
from each other. I mean we have some MIT
alums here. I'm sure they can tell you
that um getting through MIT and and as
you can imagine most things is a is is
collaborative. It it you know in certain
ways the MIT experience is the first
step in learning how to work in
collaboration prepares you for the uh
workforce. You're dealing in labs. Um
some of our students have cons uh want
to be entrepreneurs. We've got all kinds
of programs to support entrepreneurship.
We have something known as sandbox where
students along with alumni um they
students pitch their ideas. they work
with alumni. Some of those things
succeed, some of them don't. But all of
those efforts are so in other words to
get better, you get better by working
with others, right? Um rather than
running away from it, you join teams,
create teams, learn from your peers. And
nearly all the students say upon
graduation, what got them through MIT
was working, finding their teams and and
that means creating their teams. Yeah.
Support teams, which allows them to
succeed. And that seems to me to be a
life lesson that um is pretty important
and and serves many of our students well
once they graduate.
>> You talked about many initiatives. Uh we
have about 200 plus initiatives for
entrepreneurs for students.
Anything that they want they have it. Um
uh the other question is you report to
the president right you work with
provost coordinate with VPs but again
this is coming back to you admin
>> students don't care what the admin
organization structure is right
>> correct
>> um or the org chart um how do you how do
you cut through that because you may not
be able to tell them that this is the
decision and this is not mine. This is
somebody else that has made the
decision. But how do you how do you tra
travel through those?
>> Usually anyone the student comes we send
them to the office where they need to
come because if it's coming to me the
president is because no one else can
solve it. Right. So the point is to push
it down.
>> Okay.
>> Be polite about it but you but also
people who are closer to it can are are
much better. Right. Exactly. So the
point of having some organizations is
that people do their jobs at the level
they have to do them.
>> So I have a couple lightning round
questions for you.
>> Sure.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Um complete this. Uh MIT
students will surprise you by
>> um they'll surprise you uh by their I
know this is going to sound like a kind
of can, but it's true. their earnestness
and their creativity. I'm always I you
know just I remember being I was
teaching a class and uh afterwards young
student said I I said can you come to my
office hours? He's like no. I was like
why? He was like because um I have my
company. I was like company. He was
running a company out of his dorm room.
I was like I was like he was a first
year.
I've had more that was one in particular
because I was so you know shocked. I was
like this could be a senior right? He
was like a first year student. So what
surprises me though is that they, you
know, just they're just interesting. You
know, they have their own interest that
each one is their own. You know, I'm I
grew up in New York City, part of my
life in New York City. And um part of
New York is like you do your own thing.
And when people ask me when I think
about MIT, it kind of reminds me of New
York. It's like just do your thing. Do
it well, but do your thing.
>> That's that's fascinating. Um, so, okay,
if you could install one thing in every
MIT student's brain, what would it be?
Um,
this uh,
you don't have to optimize everything.
Like everything's optimized. Not all
students, but many. I'm shocked. I'm
like, really? You optimize that, too? I
mean it's it's it's a it's a feeling of
optimization. Yeah. Yeah. I would say on
some things um
um
yeah just
take a little time to think to to to to
go um yeah think about the complex just
don't think about optimizing. I mean I
can't I
I would that's what I would ask him to
do.
>> So that picks another question. Does
that mean that the kinds of students
that we get are
uh a particular kind that
>> of course they're smart but are they
also
>> there's attention to it's an attention
to this is not a bad thing of course a
certain attention to detail and
organizing
and that has its strengths of course and
it certainly um and why in in asking
people to think differently about things
you come up against the question well um
if it's not fit if it's not broken,
don't fix it. Right? I mean, that would
be the response. And that's I understand
that response, but I guess my I often
say not everything can be prepared.
There is a certain value in serendipity
in an accident.
>> Yes.
>> And you don't always know, you know, you
may think I, you know, I if I take this
class, I do this person, I do, it's all
going to work. And and sometimes it
doesn't. Often it doesn't. And and so be
prepared for that. So there is a certain
amount of we use this term a lot
resiliency and it's used in we're using
it in our lives that is all of our lives
in different kinds of ways thinking
about our um uh the human condition uh
but in a very particular sense in the on
the campus in particular with MIT
students the resiliency comes from I
think being willing to deal with the
uncertainty that comes when your plans
go ary.
>> Yeah. And
I've seen that happen more than once. I
thought this and it was very well
thought out. You know, it was optimiz
but why do people, you know, act like
this? I would often hear I would often
have this uh this would come up quite a
bit in political science classes and
classes where uh we go through what
would appear to be the logic. This is
what the politician should do and this
is what the public should think. And of
course, this is what actually happens.
And Sue was like what happened? It was
like
>> life.
>> Yes. Humans or other motivations which
don't fit into whatever it is that as
you've as your your model of
optimization. So um so a certain amount
of resiliency but that that notion of of
of approaches to intellectual issues
oftentimes um also ends up being a part
of how you organize how they organize
their lives. Not all students, but of
course I'm speaking in generalities.
>> No, that's that's fair. Um um another
question uh what's the most MIT thing a
student has ever done that made you
think that uh Yep. This can only happen
at MIT. Oh, there are things I could say
but I probably shouldn't.
Um yeah, that's too revealing. But um I
guess I I I I guess the thing I would
say is a certain um
uh a certain willingness to take on a
really hard problem. Like we can solve
that. There's a lot of that like we can
solve that. A certain confidence that
you can actually solve really hard
problems in a way that isn't um isn't
put on. It's like earnest. Um that
surprises me. Is it like a naive or is
it
>> It's not really naive. It's thinking
that you figure out the problem
>> like you know it's going to be a hard
problem to figure out but you will what
do you mean you can't
>> okay
>> that surprises me. So it pushes you know
you you know pushes you you're like okay
maybe you're right.
>> Yeah
>> I you know that's a skill that if
students if you come in you don't lose
that confidence. It may be tempered of
course by reality and it will be
tempered by disappointments in the
Reich. But if you're able to maintain
that attitude and over the course of
your education develop the skills to
make it real or at least to give others
confidence that you can follow through.
That's a leadership. That's
entrepreneurship. That's the kind of
character that you would want students
to have. particularly people who you are
putting in positions of creating
technologies that will shape humankind
which as you show that's the way it is.
So you definitely want that even if you
know jaded adults or you know people
like myself okay but you don't want to
temper that too much life will do the
tempering but you'd rather have someone
have the confidence.
>> No I like that. Um
I know you said some of them are too
revealing examples. Are there any
examples that you may want to share?
>> No.
>> Okay, I'm not going to push you on that.
Um, with that, I I'm done with the
lightning round questions, but I did
want to ask one real question like um
forget about your official job
description.
What does this role actually mean to
you?
>> Right. So, I've been at MIT for 33
years. I've been there for a reason. I
really um I really uh respect my
colleagues and students and it's a
privilege to be the chancellor. um in
part because uh what it means for me is
to think that um I'm at a place uh I
believe in you know obviously I believe
in education all education even as it's
being challenged in our country high
education is still
uh uh you know the best path I would
argue for human advancement and there's
nothing as noble I think as creating
knowledge
and uh finding and dedicating it to
bettering the human condition. And so
for me as chancellor, what it means is
to be a part of that process in the way
that I hope is meaningful and which
supports an institution which I believe
in a great deal. So it's a great
privilege and I'm um and I'm happy to do
it and uh and I and I hope to make some
important contributions as I'm when I'm
chancellor.
>> Well, that's beautiful. Um
one last thing do you have any call to
action for the audience here? Yeah. So
I've been talking a lot about the
students and the point was to kind of
give you all a sense of what it you know
the people that MIT you know it's this
great engine but at the end of the day
the faculty the students and researchers
um many of us are here for the students
first right the students and then of
course the faculty and everyone else and
all of us are a very important part of
the MIT ecosystem and our students um uh
we've got MIT Misti which is Misti UK
We've got actually we've got so Misti
this is the inter uh the uh
international scientific technology um
program initiative that we have to send
our students out into the world. We have
a pretty uh diverse student body both
internationally on both the
undergraduate especially on the graduate
level 40% of our graduate students are
um over 43% are international students
and our undergrads are similarly quite
diverse.
uh we want to send them out into the
world to get great experiences
um and a lot of them have uh internships
at different companies uh around the
world. Uh
encourage you to think about being a
part of Misti having our students come.
They mean the work. One thing about MIT,
we don't have very few a semester abroad
because the engineering and science and
all of our majors are such that you
can't really graduate in four years if
you take a semester off, right? And and
it's very difficult to get the credits
from other universities that the faculty
at MIT will accept. So typically
students are uh available in the summer
and during January.
They mean to work. They mean to learn.
They come to the to the the internships
are meant to be um educationally based.
Um and uh uh you know you get an early
look and a a chance to work with really
um interesting students, intelligent
students, motivated students and also
they get to learn. I mean so learning
goes in two directions. I've talked a
lot about what our students can do but
also they have a lot to learn and the
world has a lot to teach them. I'm sure
that uh your companies and such would be
great um uh uh laboratories for our
students. So, give us a look. Um you've
gotten the real deal. This is the
chancellor unplugged kind of. I didn't
tell you all everything because you know
this is being taped, but
but it's usually all all good.
Thank you. Um, with that, uh, the next
session, I don't know who's jumping on
stage, but thank you so much. Thank you.
Really appreciate it. Okay.