Good evening everybody. Uh my name is AJ
AJ Tornator. I work at MIT libraries.
Welcome. Welcome to the Nexus at MIT
libraries for the screening of Citizen
4, a 2014 documentary directed by Laura
Press. This screening is supported by
the SHA team's grant that provides the
funding for the license of the film and
also pizza in the back. So please help
yourselves to that one. Uh this
documentary will be introduced by two
MIT scholars and I have the honor of
introducing them to you. On my right
it's Maria Garcia Montes uh who is a PhD
candidate at the history anthropology
and science technology and society the
SDS program at MIT. Her dissertation
focuses on the 20th and 21st century
trajectories of surveillance
technologies in Mexico. She worked as a
digital security trainer with
journalists and activists in Mexico at
the time Snowden blew the whistle on the
NSA's prison program. On my left is
Michelle Spectre who is a post-doal
associate at the social and ethical
responsibilities of computing short uh
circ program uh at the college of
computing where she directs the new circ
learning lab program. Her research
focuses on the global history of
biometric surveillance and its social
and political implications.
At the time that Sneran blew the whistle
on the NSA prison program, Michelle
worked for the US government as a
researcher for a bioeththics advisory
commission. It's a complicated uh
documentary and the director is also
very much part of the director and we
appreciate both Marielle and Michelle to
do a little introduction for us here. So
welcome and thank you both.
>> Okay.
>> Um hi everybody. Uh thank you so much
for coming to see uh this important film
which came out just about a decade and a
a decade ago but remains important till
today. Um, and before we get started
with our introductory remarks and the
start of the film screening, just want
to see by uh maybe we can start with a
show of hands how many people in the
room have heard of Edward Snowden.
That's just about everybody, right?
which is very different from what we had
expected thinking of the MIT audience
that were maybe 5 years old or younger
>> when these you know whistleblowing
happened and we have seen in our
classrooms that for some people Snowden
is someone that they heard of in the
dining room in their home many years ago
but they don't quite know what was the
deal uh so something that was a very big
event in our lives for a lot of MIT
students is not um because they were
very very young when this will all
happened.
>> Yeah, that's right. Yeah. In fact, just
a bit earlier today, we uh were speaking
with some MIT first and second years who
uh had I think only one of them in the
room had heard of Edward Snowden. So, um
we're really pleased to be able to share
the documentary um with the community.
And one more question, who here has
watched Citizen 4 already?
just Eric who wants to rewatch it uh
because of its present day relevance but
okay so this is a new film to a lot of
people uh Citizen 4 is a documentary
about Edward Snowden's whistleblowing in
2013 and so the gist of it is that um he
discovered or he he was the one to blow
the whistle on the secret program of the
US government called well of especially
of the NSA that was called Prism And the
oversimplification of this program was
that the government had direct access to
company servers of big technology
companies. So uh Google, Yahoo, uh any
big provider of your email or any
communications channels that you might
use through your phone or your computer,
the NSA had a backdoor into it and had
privileged access to be able to run
searches on it. So um as as in a way to
enact its mass surveillance program at
the time there was a lot of controversy
around this because you know a lot of
people felt that this was a very uh you
know big breach in the relationship
between the government and the people
where uh and also a breach between the
service providers and the people where
people had a reasonable expectation of
privacy when they were sending an email
when they were sending a photograph. And
then the government in its turn decided
to create these back doors, this access
to data that people presumed to be
private. And so this had like a very big
impact in the public opinion at the
time. And as a result of the of the
Snowden revelations, a lot happened. A
lot of change happened in the tech
world. encryption, end-to-end encryption
became the standard for most private
communications in Google. Gmail got
almost immediately, I think within six
months of the revelations, uh, Google
finally implemented end to-end
encryption on its email services, which
advocates that the Electronic Frontier
Foundation had been demanding for years
and have been ghosted on by a lot of big
tech companies. And so these revelations
did catalyze a big wave of change for
privacy uh measures in the tech
companies but this impact was not felt
equally across the spectrum.
>> Right. Yeah. I definitely recall at the
time uh that there was a lot of
expectation that perhaps there would be
some kind of major policy change in the
US, that this policy change would be
imminent, that we would perhaps um see
the introduction and passage of
legislation that preserves uh rights to
privacy in the face of surveillance and
data collection. Um and in the end, that
didn't really end up happening. We've
seen it happen in other places, right?
We have GDPR in Europe. we don't have an
equivalent policy framework here in the
United States. And this kind of mapped
on to what also ended up happening with
public opinion. I mean, Marielle, you
probably also remember this, that um
there was quite a lot of hope among
civil liberties activists and privacy
activists that Edward Snowden's
whistleblowing uh would sort of mark a
sea change in public opinion that it
would really get members of the general
public to really care about issues of
government surveillance, data
collection, and then also protections
that may or may not be afforded to them
by the private companies that create the
technologies that they use every day.
Um, but this also didn't really happen
as well, right? Um,
uh, civil liberties organizations really
latched on to, uh, Edward Snowden and
the events that followed, but it didn't
really end up making as much of a splash
in public discourse, or at least not for
very long. And I think a refrain that we
often hear uh, today, or at least I do
in conversations with students, with
colleagues, um, and just sort of out and
about is that, you know, privacy is
dead. you know, everyone has my
information anyway. The government has
my information. The private companies
have my information. So, what does it
matter? I mean, there was a hope that,
you know, Edward Snowden's um
revelations about the prison program
would sort of change that. That was an
attitude you were already seeing in the
early 201s,
but from my estimation, it just it just
didn't. And as Michelle was saying, this
documentary was, you know, came out
about a decade ago. Uh and the reason we
proposed it for this series on AI uh
thanks to HA and and and Mark is that
even though this was not the moment when
we were talking necessarily about
surveillance and AI, this was one of
those moments in that trajectory of the
computational analysis of personal data.
And even though as you will see these
documentary or really this not in
revelations have to do perhaps mostly
with one of the problems of surveillance
where does the government get the data.
Um and in the present day we start to
see you know the other problem like how
does AI address the other the other need
which is who will look at this data? How
will this data be analyzed? And this not
in revelations gave us much more of a
poor view into the sources of data that
the government had. Um it is still we're
talking about computational analysis of
data and especially data that arises
from electronic communications. So it is
part of this continuum of AI
surveillance even if the term AI might
not feature as prominently in the film
itself because of the time that it came
out. We also proposed it because of its
link to um you know it's we see it as a
productive film to discuss engineering
ethics and professional ethics for for
engineers. Yes, that's right. I mean one
kind of fascinating aspect of this story
is that Edward Snowden himself wasn't
you know he didn't hold a high level
position. Um he was you know a
contractor essentially working on a
large government project. Um
and so you know his actions raise a lot
of questions I think both for engineers
and also for people doing government
work about what their moral and ethical
responsibilities are and then if there
is something that they're being asked to
do in the context of their work in the
context of their technical work uh that
seems to be wrong that seems to
contravene collectively held values or
even may you know be against the law in
some way. um what ought you to do? And I
certainly remember from my experience
working in government that, you know,
kind of quiet conversations outside the
office, you know, with with peers, with
colleagues, you know, DC is a big, you
know, lots of people who live in DC are
working in government. This was really
the talk of the town. And one of the
things that people were talking about
was sort of whether or not, you know,
going to the press and whistleblowing in
this way was the right thing to do,
whether it was an effective thing to do.
Um, people had a lot of opinions about
it and it really kind of speaks to some
of the everyday dilemmas that might come
up in, you know, engineering and
computer science work um about how how
one handles that. And in the
documentary, I mean, we actually will
get to see um how this process unfolded.
We'll get to learn what Edward Snowden's
kind of decision-making process was um
and what the consequences of uh his
decisions uh in terms of bringing this
information uh about an otherwise fully
veiled um government program to the
public.
And the very high price to pay when your
country is divided and you know part of
your country thinks that you acted out
of love for your people and in the
service of your people and the other
part of your country thinks that you're
a traitor and how that plays out in an
individual's life and also in the
technopolitics of surveillance in the US
and beyond. So with that we are ready to
watch some Citizen 4. Yeah.