[Music]
okay so now let's introduce the
experimental technology that we're using
to measure the effects of genetic
perturbations in single cells in the
last decade or so there's been this
really amazing technology uh for genetic
uh engineering and editing called
crisper cast 9 which you may have heard
about in the news and this is a gene
editing technology that allows us to
specifically knock out or reduce the
expression of a Target Gene
and how crisper C9 works is we have this
protein called the cine nucleus and this
is guided to a specific uh sequence in
your genome based on the sequence of a
specific single guide RNA and this guide
RNA can guide you to Any Given Gene such
as tcf7 or pdcd1 and it brings along the
cast nucleus and when the cast nucleus
binds that specific site it leads to a
double strand break in the genome and
this is a really bad thing for the
genome in general but it allows us to
actually uh reduce or eliminate the
expression of a Target Gene and so what
happens when you have this break is that
repair Machinery in our bodies gets
activated and while trying to repair
this break uh there are mutations that
are typically made and those mutations
that are now introduced into the gene
lead to reduction or complete loss of
that Gene's expression so this gives us
the ability to reduce or knock out the
expression of a gene like tcf7 or pdcd1
in a highly targeted and specific
way okay so now using the crisper cast 9
Gene editing technology we can take te-
cells and with for each te- cell knock
out a specific Gene of Interest so for
instance in this t- cell we might have
knocked out the Gene tcf7 and in this t-
cell we might have knocked out the Gene
pdcd1 and we can do these perturbations
in parallel and grow up these te- cells
and then now we've genetically added
these te- cells we can introduce them
into cancer and the te- cells will get
activated in the cancer environment and
eventually they'll become exhausted uh
and so after some time we can isolate
the te- cells from the cancer and carry
out the perturb seek experiment and
perturb seek will allow us to read out
for every individual t- cell both the
perturbation are received here A or B as
well as the gene expression within that
single cell and we're able to read out
the perturbation the cell Reed because
the crisper cast 9 uh leaves find a
specific sequence in the DNA that tells
us what genetic perturbation that cell
received so the outcome again is the
expression of every single Gene in the
Single Cell as well as the genetic
perturbation the cell received and we
know that perturbing one gene will have
effect on many other genes in the cell
so for instance this genetic
perturbation a is associated with the
affector t- cell state which we can read
out by looking at the gene expression
and this perturbation B is associated
with a terminal exhausted cell state
which again we can read out by looking
at the transcriptional information in
that single cell so the data that you'll
get will be structured as follows in the
challenge where you'll receive a gene
expression Matrix that again has the
expression of every single Gene in every
single cell and in addition you'll see
uh for every single cell what
perturbation that cell Reed so for
instance cell one received the
perturbation tox meaning the tox Gene
was knocked out the tox gene expression
should be reduced in that cell at zero
and remember you have that information
as well as the transcriptional
information so the advantages of perturb
seek are many this is a single cell
readout so we can read you know the
effects of perturbations in thousands
and thousands of cells so that's really
incredible we can test many individual
perturbations in parallel so you see
here you know there's many different
perturbations we're characterizing and
because we have the perturbation and the
resulting gene expression in the same
cell that allows us to think about
causality and inferring Gene regulation
now the disadvantage of Percy is that
it's really challenging to test all
possible 20,000 perturbations so in this
challenge uh we're looking at about 70
perturbations to characterize all 20,000
perturbations it would take one Mark
Schwarz which is the who is the really
you know talented physician scientist to
perform these experiments it would take
him about 50 years to collect all that
data and likewise if we looked at
combinations of perturbations for
instance we wanted to knock out toxin
tcf7 that would be you know that would
require hundreds and hundreds of
millions of cells to really characterize
so the the throughput of perur seek is
really good but it's not infinite there
are limitations and our hope is with the
data science challenge is that we can
computationally move past some of these
limitations and even though we're only
able to measure you know a relatively
small number of perturbations we believe
that we can learn uh the effects of
perturbations in genes that weren't
measured in the experiment so in the
third lecture we are going to go over
the actual experiment that Mark Schwarz
did to generate the perturb seek data
that will be used in the data science
Challenge and you will see uh how to
manipulate that data and analyze it and
work with it and this will get you ready
to do all three tasks uh in the
challenge
[Music]