I'm David Newman the director of the MIT
media lab and the Apollo professor of
astronautics also affiliated with our
Harvard MIT health science technology
program I've been at MIT for three
decades and it's really my home and
family here at the media lab we're all
about imagining and then
inventing a better future a more just
future a creative future it needs to be
by with and for all we're really an
amazing ecosystem uh kind of a micro
ecosystem of MIT where we have artists
and designers Engineers scientists and
guess what we're all within the same lab
and so it really is
transdisciplinary and really what we're
about is again imagining that that
future that better future for all needs
to be by with and for all how do we do
that through inventing actually new
fields
uh for example maybe computational
social science or affective Computing so
thinking about the Long Haul of a very
optimistic view for people and the
planet everything we do is human
centered
design so thinking about our
transformative Technologies but also
experiences and in the future these
systems that really help people maybe
reimagine and redesign their lives
we're really excited um about the future
uh we have that's our vision our mission
and then shared Valu so we work very
closely with industry and our members
and it's really important that uh we all
strive for excellence uh making sure
that our inventions and our ideas are
shared shared as widely as possible
that's when we know we've gotten it
right we do um we do bet on the future
so we bet on those moonshots and how can
maybe some of our transformative
Technologies really have the most
societal impact so recently we've gone
through your strategic foresighting to
really take a look 10 maybe 20 years out
what's potentially the most societal
impact given our strengths of the media
what can we help shape what can we work
together with our industry partners and
our philanthropists and Founders that
really have that view into this future
this inventing that future that we all
want to see so for example um terms of
looking at the future of AI for us it's
Ai and The Human Experience all of our
AI tools all of our generative tools
they necessarily need to be enhancing
The Human Experience whether it's
education whether it's Health Care this
is really foundational and fundamental
to who we are at the media lab always
designing to enhance that Human
Experience so Ai and The Human
Experience is really uh foundational for
the whole for the whole Lab we grew up
also Foundation educational but what
kind of education and creativ are we
talking about we're talking about making
and doing with your hands so we're
talking about cultivating creativity
bringing out the best in everyone and a
lot of times uh you need to play that's
by being in a maker space that's by
working across the table I'm a rocket
scientist I need to work with an artist
and a designer maybe a geneticist
because when we think about bringing out
the creativity and education that will
really stick constructionist education
we do a lot of that Hands-On we do a lot
of that uh by play we do a lot of that
in groups of course and PE instruction
kids te teaching each other and scratch
is one of our you know really famous
contributions and when we can scale that
to over a 100 million users then we know
we've gotten it right so coming out of
the pandemic we're really bold and
bullish let's say on let's cultivate
creativity we think there needs to be a
new Revolution of creativity for all and
so that really speaks to some of the
energy the passion we have in terms of
of education and creativity here at the
media lab working with others how can we
how can we spread
that we're thinking a lot about the
planet I call spaceship earth um how do
we think about climate sustainability
from the media lab's perspective we have
a really bold Vision it goes from oceans
to land or Urban cities all the way to
space because today more than 50% of all
the climate variables are measured from
space looking down on Earth and let's
start with the ocean such an important
subsystem we've invented Internet of
things for the oceans without batteries
so now sensors you can measure monitor
we still have 95% of our oceans to
measure and monitor it's really
important when we think of biodiversity
and the role that the oceans play in
climate and keeping us Humanity in
balance with nature then we go to our
cities uh we all want to thrive and
flourish we really have to take a look
at the urban cities how can we um
redesign how can we think about that
next uh potential disaster that's coming
whether it's flooding and fire and uh we
believe in um really bringing in all
constituents all stakeholders whether
it's the the mayor the teachers the
educator and working literally around
the table we show a lot of Digital Data
about the cities and City Planning but
we all would love to live probably
closer to where we work and have good
food and have social you know Green
spaces to to live and play in so our
City Science group really looks at these
uh simulates them we run a lot of
simulations test B we work with cities
all around the world because there's
Solutions there's different solutions
for any place you live