Okay, today is our second and probably
last day of homogeneous dynamics and
projection theory. Um, let's remember
where we are and then we're going to uh
try to use the the things we learned
about last time to say something about
dynamics.
Okay. Um, so we'll have a league group
G, which so far is SL2R, and we have a
discrete subgroup, which so far has been
SL2Z,
and we're interested in GOD gamma.
Um, we have a metric M, which is a right
invariant
metric
on G. and then
we get it leads to a metric that I also
call M and G mod gamma.
Okay. So now G also has a left action
on G mod gamma
and this left this left action does not
preserve the metric because the metric
is not left invariant. So this left
action distorts the metric and we
started to study that last time and it's
going to continue to be crucial how it
distorts the metric. Um but it preserves
the volume.
Okay.
Um
cool. Okay. Now uh inside of this group
we have the uh unitary group
uh sorry the unipotent group
let's say UT is one t and our goal is to
understand what how the unipotent orbits
in gamma look. So we're going to study
u dox
in gamma. So x is a gamma
and there's an an old theorem of
headland from the 30s
which is the the kind of thing about
about this orbit that we're interested
in that
u dox is either periodic
or dense.
We won't exactly prove that but we'll
prove some things that are a little bit
related.
Okay. Um, now the unipotent group is
special and the one way of getting our
hands on something special about it is
to see how it relates to diagonal
matrices. So let's say this
a sub is that matrix that diagonal
matrix in SL2R. And then acute
observation is that a subr u t a subr
inverse is u e to the 2r t.
Um it's just a computation with
matrices. Uh I've done it a couple times
and I start to sort of anyway doing it
in front of you I think is not very
useful but if you are interested in this
it's if you do it yourself it starts to
make sense. Uh okay.
So now let's say that u 0 t of x that
means the set of u t of x t is a zero t.
So if capital t is large this is a big
piece of an orbit and that's more or
less what we'd like to study. What is
the shape of a big piece of the orbit?
And this observation tells us that
um u0 t of x is a r
u01
a r inverse of x.
Okay. And this is helpful because this
this u01 is much less intimidating than
u t. So this here is just a little piece
of the orbit. Um and so to understand a
big orbit we have to understand how this
a sub rar acts on a little orbit.
Um okay and another simple observation
is that a r is like a
little r to the j. So if big R is big J
* little R then we have this. Oh and in
in this equation by the way um E to the
2 big R is T.
Okay. So this a a r we can think of it
as a little r applied many times. Okay.
So therefore it makes sense that we
could just try to understand
how a little r acts on unipotent orbits.
Okay.
So, we made a picture of this at the end
of class last time with models and props
and everything. And uh and this picture
is is is uh the the the main tool that
we're going to think about for
homogeneous dynamics. So, I'm going to
draw this picture again and then we're
going to talk about why it why it is the
way we drew it. Um okay. So,
over here something a shape that I'll
draw as being kind of a cylinder. And
this is a fundamental domain. Um so so
this is either the whole fundamental
domain or maybe a tube in
in f. So f is sitting in the group g and
it's a fundamental domain
for g mod gap.
Okay. And so this length scale is one.
And this length scale um is also one. Or
we could also make it smaller if we'd
like to have a thinner tube.
All right. And now inside of this tube
are a bunch of pieces of unipotent orbit
that I'll draw like this.
Okay. So each of those is a piece of
unipotent orbit.
Um here is t = 0 and here is t = 1.
Okay. And now understand what is going
to happen to this picture when we apply
a subr.
So what we're going we're going to apply
um I guess strictly speaking l the the
we're going to apply it on the left.
We're going to multiply by a subar on
the left.
Okay. So what's going to happen? Um
first of all the unipotent orbits are
going to stretch that way.
Then second of all, okay, so so so you
just think about what happens to the
cylinder. There's going to be a
direction where it stretches. There's
going to be a direction that compresses.
And there's going to be a direction that
stays the same. That will be true at
every point. Um, but what's important is
that the direction that compresses is
kind of not the same everywhere in this
picture. And so to illustrate that, I'm
going to draw what happens at at a
couple of different heights.
So at t = 1
this
um and there'll be some direction that
compresses maybe it's that direction and
so when we apply l a r inverse this disc
is going to be squished vertically
and when it's squished vertically
then we'll have a triangle that looks
sort of like so.
Okay. And also at t equals z we have the
same disc with the same triangle in it
but there's a compression direction
which is different. So maybe down here
it's this direction.
So when we apply
LA subar inverse um then we will get a
pancake who gets squished this way and
that will affect these points
differently.
This after squishing the green point and
the orange point will be quite close
together.
All right. So that's the picture that we
ended with last time.
And what is important here
key point
is that the compression direction
is twisting
relative to
the unipotent orbits.
Meaning that if at a given height two
unipotent orbits are being compressed
towards each other then at most other
heights uh they won't be.
All right. So this is where we left off
last time. Um are there questions or
comments about this picture?
Yeah.
>> So in the picture you had last week,
these after things are all kind of
stretched out and compressed, they're
then mapped back onto the fundamental
domain half. But if they've been twisted
around, like is there some are they kind
of mapped back onto F without twisting
in some way to make it all perfectly
line up or is there kind of some other
twisting that happens again as they get
back back on F?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay, that's a good
question. Let's So the question is about
um how this gets mapped back into the
fundamental domain. Let's try to draw
that also.
So here
here's our fundamental domain.
First we apply this map just in our
group and we get something which is tall
and flat
and perhaps it is twisted a little bit
between the bottom and the top. Um
um
okay anyway then that is going to get
mapped back into our domain. So pi is
the projection from g to gm mod gamma
and which gamma will identify with our
fundamental domain. So this thing is
going to get mapped back into the
fundamental domain. What does that look
like? Um, so the fundamental domain is
kind of sort of a unit cube,
but this thing is way taller than a unit
cube. So imagine cutting it into pieces
whose height is only around one.
Okay? And this was only ever around one.
So each of those pieces now is small
enough to fit in the fundamental domain.
Um, and um
um let me call it piece one, piece two,
piece three, and piece four.
All right. Now, those are going to sort
of fold back into the fundamental
domain.
And at least roughly, I think it's good
to imagine it like this.
So each one of of these guys is
corresponds to one of those guys,
right? Okay. But they are not in order.
So it's not like they go 1 2 3 4.
They're in some um they're in some
order. uh one two three um so uh I don't
know much about about this order. I
personally don't know anything about
this order.
[Applause]
Okay. So now I think the question was
how would this picture look if this
thing were twisted a little bit. Um so
first of all you know when we say that
this thing is twisted a little bit it's
a change sort something like a change of
90 degrees or 180 degrees between the
bottom and the top and there are many
steps between the bottom and the top. So
that means if you just look at one of
these guys you don't notice or barely
notice any twisting. This thing is
basically a planer slab. Um, and then
these planer slabs are at slightly
different angles, but this map pi, it it
doesn't it doesn't exactly preserve. I
mean, those angles aren't exactly well
defined because this this is not living
in R3. So, it's actually not it's not
clear exactly what we mean when we say
that this slab and this slab are they
parallel or are they twisted compared to
each other?
Anyway, when they get mapped back in,
it's not I
I think that imagining this is is
reasonable.
Okay.
Um,
okay. Now, that raises a bit of a
question coming back to this picture
that people that that that we we were
trying to digest last time, like what
exactly do we mean when we say that the
compression angle is twisting?
Because the compression angle here lives
at one height, it lives over here, and
the compression angle there lives over
there. How do we compare an angle over
here with an angle over here? Uh given
that this is not R3, this is living in a
curved thing. Right? So I actually
rethought how to state it and I added
some words that I don't think I
mentioned last time.
I think when we talk about this
twisting, we need to include these words
relative to the unipotent orbits.
Okay. So let me try to make a more
precise statement about what this
twisting means and then we'll see how we
can do some computations in the league
group with matrices and and see that it
happens
[Applause]
All right. So, um,
okay. So, precise
statement
about what is twisting.
What is twisting?
Okay. So suppose I have a piece of
unipotent orbit in my fundamental domain
starts at G knot that's over there some
group element in my fundamental domain
and then over here I have UT of G KN and
T goes say from 0 to one.
Okay. Now at each point here there's
going to be a vector that compresses
when I perform ar.
So let's say v compression of t. This is
a a vector uh and this is the direction
that compresses
when we apply
left arce.
So it's the um so it's a it's a vector.
It lives in the tangent space of our
group at the given point.
and it's the smallest singular vector
for the derivative of this map.
Okay, so that's what we mean by the
compression direction.
Now, what does it mean relative to the
unipotent orbits?
So suppose that over here I have another
unipotent orbit
and it's this is like a nearby unipotent
orbit.
Okay. So this might be g plus epsilon *
v kn. epsilon * v is a little vector
that goes between these
starting points of these two nearby
unipotent orbits.
And up here or maybe here is ut of g
plus epsilon v kn. And here there's a
vector that goes between them. I guess
epsilon times
v orbit of t. So V orbit of T is going
in the direction of the from the red
orbit to the orange orbit.
Okay. So
so the the thing that is twisting is V
compression of T relative to V orbit of
T is twisting. The angle between those
two vectors is changing. That's the
precise statement of what is twisting.
And we can we can check what it's
happening by computing these two
vectors. Yeah,
>> you're conjugating technically, right?
Not just applying action. You're
conjugating, but when you say twisting,
you need to compare that some
if you apply the
apply the the gemic
you end up somewhere else.
I'm not sure if I understand comparison
twist.
>> Well, are you also following the body
orbit too?
>> Um,
right. So, the question has to do with
keeping track of things given that they
live in different tangent spaces. So,
okay. So, the compression direction is a
vector in the tangent space at the given
point along the orbit. Does that is that
okay so far?
>> Uh
yeah yeah yeah.
>> Okay. Um but then the comment is
you know if if I have a family of
vectors in one vector space then I can
say that they're twisted. But here I
have a family of vectors in a family of
vector spaces. And so it's not so clear
what it means that they're twisted. Um,
so I need to I need one way to do it is
to pick a reference vector to compare
them with. And so that's the job of the
of this V orbit vector which goes from
the red vector to this from the red
orbit to this orange orbit. And that's
like a a reference vector.
Um and then we'll see that so at each t
there's there's a orbit vector and a
compression vector and um the angle
between them is changing.
Okay.
Um cool. So, so there was a question
last class that basically was like
how are we sure that this is happening
this picture and the one way to be sure
is to compute these two vectors and then
and see that that they're not the same.
Okay.
Okay. So, let's compute them.
actually one of them we can comput.
[Applause]
So
ut is a matrix. So when we can we can
just multiply this through. This is ut
plus epsilon ut of v kn. And if we
compare sides we see that v orbit of t
is u subt.
Okay. Now let's figure out what v
compression of t is.
[Applause]
Okay. Um,
cool. So say we have some G knot and um
we're going to apply the left action of
a R inverse and that will move us to to
um a subr G.
And we want to understand how this map
is distorting the geometry of G knot,
the geometry near GN, and in particular
figure out which direction is being
compressed.
Okay. Um, so I think the best the best
way I could figure out to understand
this is to put it in a picture uh with
connecting this thing that I don't
understand yet to some maps that are
easier to understand.
So here's the identity and from here to
here I could apply a right
multiplication by GMAT and right
multiplication is much easier to
understand because that's an isometry
and the identity also is kind of nicer
than other matrices.
Okay. And then I'm going to go back to
the identity.
So this is right multiplication by a r g
all inverse which is also an isometry.
So if you put this all together, I'm
going to have a map from the tangent
space of the identity to itself.
And that map is an isometry times the
map I want to understand times an
isometry. So that all of the metric
distortion is going to come from here.
Okay, now this map is not so hard to
understand. So if I apply what am I
doing? So I I start with some matrix H.
I right multiply by G knot. Then I left
multiply by A R then I right multiply by
the inverse of A R G KN. What do I get?
Well have h I might I multiply on the
right by G knot. Now I multiply on the
left by a r. Now I multiply on the right
by this.
[Applause]
Okay. When I invert this I switch those.
I get a g not inverse and they cancel.
So this operation is none other than
conjugating by a r. Right? So this is
the conjugation by ar.
Okay. So conjugation by a r is a map
from our new group to itself takes the
identity to the identity and therefore
this map or really its derivative takes
the tangent space of the identity to
itself.
All right and now you can write this
down. This a r is an explicit matrix uh
tangent a tangent vector here is a
matrix abcd.
So this is just a b c d goes to or d c a
r of this is
e r e minus r ab c d e minus r e
so this is a thing you can write down
it's not that scary and we worked out
last time uh what it does so recall from
last time
that we have first of all we have an
orthonormal basis of TE of G which are
there's a basis vector N 0 1 0 0. Last
time I called this U, but there were so
many U's on the blackboard that I was
worried it was not a great idea. So I'm
going to call it N. N for nil potent
which is also true.
Um there's N tilda which is 0 1 0 0. And
there's a diagonal guy which looks like
this.
Okay. So what we figured out is that
the conjugation
makes n way bigger.
It makes n tilda way smaller
and it leaves the diagonal fixed.
Okay. So if I start at the identity and
I go all the way around, I'm doing this
conjugation and n tilda is the vector
that's going to get compressed.
But now if I want to know what vector
over here is going to get compressed,
well I start with antilda. I map it over
here. It hasn't gotten any shorter yet
because this is an isometry. That's the
vector that's going to be compressed in
this set.
Okay.
So it's the
right action by g of n tilda. This is
the singular vector
of d l a r inverse
with singular value
e to the minus 2r.
Okay. So that's basically the answer to
our question. So the V compress the
compression vector at T
that's R at so now I'm not necessarily
at the point GN but I'm at the point ut
of N tilda.
So that's n tilda ut g.
Okay. So now if you compare how these
two things are changing with T, you see
it is not the same because our group is
not commutative
because when you changing the orbit of
T, you're multiplying by UT on the left.
But when you're changing the compression
direction, you're multiplying by UT over
here in the middle. And it's a
non-commutative group. So those two
operations are not the same as each
other.
Oh um so I don't necessarily
think it will be helpful to do more
computations but I did some at home to
be sure and you know if if you imagined
that at time zero
the these two directions coincided and
then you see what happens as t changes.
You'll see that they stop coinciding.
>> Yeah.
>> So picking the inner product of the
vectors it makes sense as an operation
to do it to compare the angles in the
tangent space.
>> Yeah. Um that's right. So these are
vectors in a Romanian
manifold. um and so they have a well-
definfined angle and we can compute it
by taking inner products and and then um
uh right so I guess I guess we could say
that the coine of
uh
of the angle
between v of t and w of t
would be um
V.W
over norm of V norm of W.
I used to teach this a lot in 1802. I
think that's right. Um so we have
formulas for V and W. So we can compute
this and um it'll be a little messy but
we'll see that it is not constant in T.
[Applause]
Other questions or comments?
Okay, so the first big goal that was the
first chunk of the class, the first big
goal of the class was to um check that
this picture happens
and then the second part of the class we
will uh discuss how to use this picture
to figure out stuff about a long
unipotent orbit.
Okay. So, let's switch gears.
Okay.
Okay. So, let's call this tracking
the spread
of an orbit.
All right. So remember that we had this
u 0 t of x is a r
u01
a r inverse x. Let's call this guy x
tilda.
Okay.
Um
now this uh there was a discussion last
time you know what happens if this orbit
here is periodic
if this orbit here is periodic the
special thing that happens is that this
point X tilda will be deep in the cusp
and the deep in the cusp is sort of a
special case because we were imagining
that this was like a regular nice orbit
of length one but if it's deep in the
cusp it's sort of different.
So let's assume that X tilda is not deep
in the custom
and that's equivalent to saying that UX
is not close to periodic.
[Applause]
Okay. And let's break up R as capital J
times little R.
And uh so then I'm going to say that U.j
J is a little R to the J of U01 of X to
Okay. And I want to track how this thing
is spreading out through my homogeneous
space GM mod gamma. And we'll we're
going to track it by noticing how many
delta balls it takes to cover it. So
recall that X delta
is the minimum number of delta balls
needed
to cover X.
So our goal is going to be to estimate
U.j J delta um
in terms of J
delta and R.
Okay. And for for context for reference
um the we have a three-dimensional
space. So for the whole space the number
of delta balls that we need to cover it
is delta to the minus 3.
Okay.
All right. So, next of all,
our U.J is like a bunch of these
unipotent orbits.
Looks like that. And so, you might
notice that
it only really matters what the top
cross-section looks like. All the other
cross-sections are similar. So let's
take that top part down. Inside of
there, we see this. So let's call that
XJ. That's the top cross-section
of U.J.
And um then it's not hard to check that
U.j delta is like delta inverse time XJ
delta.
have uh
cut it into slabs of thickness delta.
For each thickness, the number of delta
balls that we need to cover that slab is
xj delta. This is the number of slabs.
Okay. So, so basically we want to track
how xj delta depends on delta.
So,
so fully spread
or maybe I'll say very spread.
Um, that means that
u.j delta is like delta to the minus3.
That would be like saying xj delta is
like delta to the minus 2. That xj
really fills a lot of the disc.
Okay.
So now
how does this picture help us to study
XJ?
So using the key picture.
All right.
So um
so let me label these maps pi 1 and pi 0
and somewhere in the middle we would
have pi t. Pi t is what our map ar is
doing to the slice at height t.
Okay, using the key picture
have a lama.
So if
e to the minus 2r is delta
then
um
xj + 1 delta is around a sum over t of
pi t of xj delta.
And which t's do we sum over? The t's
are in delta z and t goes from zero to
one.
Um this is al we can also write this as
delta inverse times the average
t between zero and one
of pi t of xj delta.
Okay. So, proof sketch.
Um,
okay.
So, here is our fundamental domain. Cut
it into slices of thickness delta.
So here's a slice at height t with
thickness delta.
Okay. Now when we apply l, we uh stretch
it up vertically
and we compress it in some other
direction. We get something like this.
And then we divide this into pieces at
different heights.
And let me color this particular
slab in red.
So that red one is one of them over
here.
So this these are each of height one.
Okay. Um
right.
So in this new picture there will be so
in the in the old picture there were
some unipotent orbits
that went through our slab.
Um so x describes where the unipotent
orbits hit the top of our slab. And now
we apply this map and now there will be
some points over here in the top of this
slab. And who will they be? Those points
over there would be pi t of x.
Okay. Now we want to cover things with
delta balls. So this distance here is e
to the minus 2r. So that's delta. So we
want to know how many delta balls does
it take to cover
that.
So that number there is delta covering
number of pi t of xj.
Right?
So over over here we started with xj.
Now what happens when we apply pi?
Each of these slabs gets folded back in.
Okay. Um and um the red one went
somewhere. I don't really know where,
but maybe it went over here.
And here in the top of it is pi t of xj
and it's delta covering number.
So the number of delta balls
in this strip
that would be um pi t of xj.
Okay. And now the uh this thing these
dots up here are are xj + one. It's the
set of set of dots on the top face. And
so how many delta balls do we need to
cover them? Well, for these ones we
needed pixj delta covering number and
and these other guys those corresponded
to different um slabs here. So there are
different terms in this.
Okay.
Um so now
we can try to use projection theory to
study this thing and it will tell us how
the covering number XJ + 1 delta evolves
as we increase J.
[Applause]
Any
question? Yeah.
>> Why do
the delta balls start to overlap when J
is large enough and kind of the
compression is more than delta? Because
delta is kind of the size of one round
of compression. If you do multiple, why
would it be for that?
Um
so I think the question is suppose at
the beginning that there happened to be
two guys here in X whose distance was
less than delta which might happen
>> then um what would happen to them?
Um
>> well
>> not that they're less than delta
slightly more than delta
but less than
eus 2r or e to the 2 r delta so that in
the in f they're in the same delta b
then applying the transformation
diagonal transformation that they're
then then they become in a delta
But before they're not in before they're
in two separate delta balls after the
transformation of one delta ball.
>> Right. Right. Okay. So it could happen
that we have two guys like maybe these
two guys are pretty far apart but after
we perform um pi t they got squished
together and they're now in the same
delta ball over here. Yeah that could
that could happen. And the the main
thing we have to study is how often that
happens.
Um but um
this lema is still true. Um
this might be a lot smaller than xj
delta because many many uh points that
were far apart in xj may have gotten
squished together in pi t of xj.
But this is just the number of delta
balls that it takes to cover um
the the image there.
>> Does that answer your question?
>> Yeah. I guess also like in the third
image like why is each delta ball
contained in only the size of one of
those kind of strips?
>> Ah okay. So we we tuned delta and r to
play together so that we picked r so the
thickness of this strip is delta. I
thought if the transformation is applied
multiple times then you get multiple
like e to the minus 2 r j scaling.
>> Um that's not wrong but when we apply it
multiple times we're not changing little
r we're just applying a subr a sub
little r multiple times. So so this
picture is describing what happens in in
one time
>> and then you could use this in many
rounds. So you could use this lama over
and over again.
>> Okay,
>> which which is what we'll do.
Okay.
Um,
let me change my notation a little bit.
so I was using the letter pi for this
maybe a little bit prematurely. What's
clear so far is that this is a map. So
I'm going to call it f_sub_1, f_t, and
f0. And so then I'll change this.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay. So now the next remark is that
these maps look a lot like linear
projections. So remark
ft is kind of approximately an
orthogonal projection
um pi t. So let me make a picture. So ft
does something like this.
And this thickness is delta. This is
one. Um and then pi t would just be an
actual orthogonal projection.
Okay. Um
so
[Applause]
uh ft is not not perfectly linear
uh but it is smooth.
Okay.
So now here is a proposition or exercise
about projections
says that if x is in the unit ball in
the plane.
Then if you take the average overall
directions theta and s1
of um pi theta of x delta
is at least as big as x delta to the 12.
Here's an example that shows where the x
delta to the 1/2 comes from.
So here's the unit ball and then inside
of it I take a smaller ball and I call
that X.
So X is the ball of some small radius
row inside of the ball of radius one.
Um okay then when I perform an
orthogonal projection
there's pi theta of X in any direction
I'll get a line of length row.
So I see that x delta is like row over
delta squared
and pi theta of x delta covering up is
like row over delta. So this is the
square root of that.
Okay. And this is the best thing to do.
Um you could devise an example where in
one particular direction the compression
is much smaller than the square root.
Um, here's an example like that.
B1,
here's X,
here's theta. Okay, in this example, pi
theta of X delta is much smaller. I'll
call this theta KN much smaller than X
delta to the 12 for one theta KN.
But at least in this picture, the most
of the projections are way bigger.
Okay, so it's not not super difficult uh
to check this proposition. And I'm going
to make it an exercise. I think we're
out of problem sets, but if we weren't,
this is a a nice one to review the
class.
Okay. And another comment is even though
these FTs are not exactly linear maps so
that we cannot just literally apply this
proposition they're close enough that by
using the proof of this you you can get
it for FT2.
So remark
the proof applies
to FT also.
Okay.
So if we put together this lema and this
proposition, we'll get an estimate about
the delta covering number of XJ.
Okay. So correlary if we put these
together xj + 1 delta covering number is
at least around um delta inverse time xj
delta to the 12
um proof.
So xj + 1 delta is
uh is at least by our lema delta inverse
times the average over t of xj
of um ft of xj delta
and then by our proposition that's at
least delta inverse time xj delta to the
on half and that's the proof.
Okay. So then let's just track what this
means. So x0 delta would be one. Think
about what x0 delta means. It's one
unipotent orbit. There's okay. So
therefore
x1 delta would be at least around delta
inverse.
x2 delta would be at least around delta
to the minus3s.
X3 delta be at least around delta to the
minus1 and 3/4
and so on and you'd get pretty close to
delta to the minus2.
Okay. And delta to the minus2 would be
like a definite fraction of the whole
space.
All right. Um, so this proves that a
unipotent orbit that's not close to
periodic,
it proves that it fills up a lot of the
homogeneous space.
It's not Headland's theorem. Um, hold on
a second. So, we didn't prove yet that
the orbit is dense. The orbit could be
missing an entire ball that's like half
the size of the space, and this could
still be true, but we did prove that the
orbit goes a lot of places. Yeah. Um and
this proof like does apply since
applying it each time loses some sort of
implicit constant like how do we know
that it's not becoming dense and just
like kind of an infinite decimally small
region of this full space.
Um
right so I think the question is like we
we didn't actually get to a constant
times delta to the minus 2 and if I
tried to do this sort of infinitely many
times I would be losing a constant each
time. Yeah, that's right. So, you know,
imagine doing this 10 times and we get
delta to the minus 1.99
and and that's what the method uh proves
so far. So, stronger things are true,
but but this method doesn't prove them
yet.
Um
so remark
um this doesn't show
that the orbit is uh is actually dense
and so
uh so maybe a question you know could
the orbit
do this
so here's our homogeneous space there's
a cusp but it's not that important
and and the orbit like goes around a
good bit, but it only ever goes around
over here and it never goes over there.
So, this proof doesn't say anything
about that.
Um, okay. So, as far as I know, the to
finish Headland's theorem requires
another step uh that is based on
different ideas from these ideas. Um, so
there's more to homogeneous dynamics
than than this story. Uh but this we did
still learn something interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you know like how close it's possible
to get to the full theorem by trying to
optimize all the constants in this term?
>> Um okay. So there are two things that we
might like to improve here. So the
question is how how close can we get to
the full theorem by optimizing the
argument that we've been talking about.
So one thing that you might like is you
might like to actually get to delta to
the minus2.
Um that still wouldn't necessarily rule
out this possibility but it would be
interesting.
And um if you look
if you look at this proposition,
one thing that you you sort of notice
that this proposition is sharp in this
very clumped case. And if you remember
back to the early months of our class,
if X was not so compressed, then there
would be even better estimates. So if if
you knew as an input that X is not too
clustered, then you could get all the
way to delta to the minus 2 in one step
or or two steps or something. Um and so
you might try to track that. You might
try to track not just the delta covering
number but also the row covering number
for different delta and row. And then
you could take advantage of this
clustering. And um I am not positive but
I think it is a reasonable 18156 project
uh to you try to use that to get all the
way to delta to the minus 2.
[Applause]
Even if you got a constant times delta
to the minus 2, it would
still not be obvious to me that you
filled the entire manifold and that
you're not missing a ball. And um I I
thought about it yesterday and today and
I I don't have I don't have a good
understanding yet of what you need to to
to get everywhere. Um so I would be
interested to learn if people have
thoughts about it or know about it.
Okay,
cool. Um so I think that there actually
are a bunch of ways to prove Headlland's
theorem and this is not one that I have
seen in the literature. Um and
all all of these problems become more
difficult and maybe more interesting
when you go to higher dimensions. Um so
the projection theory also becomes more
difficult and more interesting in higher
dimensions. And I wanted in the last
part of the class to just show you what
happens. Um and in particular we will
see a new question about projection
theory that we haven't mentioned so far
in this class but which I think is a
really cool question.
Um,
okay.
[Applause]
Okay.
So that I'm going to put this way. What
about
SLNR?
Right.
Okay.
Um so I'm going to take a somewhat
specific example although I think most
of what we'll say then would work for
any N. So for example, we could have
SL3R
for our G. Gamma could be SL3 Z. And U
could be the unipotent group of matrices
that look like this.
So the so from what I understand there
are several different one parameter
unipotent subgroups of SL3R. They're
slightly different from each other. And
this one is sort of particularly well
studied in the homogeneous dynamics
community because it's the one that
comes up in the Oppenheim conjecture
about quadratic forms.
Um, okay. But anyway, so we have this
one parameter subgroup. And so let's
call this u subt.
Okay. So our basic setup with like
conjugating by a diagonal matrix that
works. And the relevant diagonal matrix
is this matrix.
Okay. And then you can check that a subr
u subt a sub r inverse is u sub e to the
rt turns out to be e to the rt not e to
the 2 rt but that's not too big a deal.
Okay.
So now um
we have a bunch of unipotent orbits like
before.
There's a bunch of unit potent orbits,
but um the dimension of our group is
eight instead of three. And so we have
the direction along the orbits t = 0 up
to t= 1. That's still onedimensional. So
this thing here is a seven-dimensional
ball instead of a disc.
Okay. So now we apply uh we study
the action
of L a r inverse and we'll have a
picture like this
f1
f0
um and okay something here will happen
and something different here will
Um okay. So you can study the singular
values
the singular values
of l a r inverse and those are equal to
of conjugation by a r. So conjugation by
a r is is a very nice operation on
matrices. You can write it down and see
what happens. And you can compute these
singular values and they are as follows.
Um eus 2r eus r eus r 1 1 e to the r e
to the r e 2 r.
I won't do it on the board but I promise
it's not hard.
Okay. Now one of these singular values
corresponds to the u direction.
So little n is the vector that's the
tangent vector
to the group u at the identity.
Um and so little n is it's not super
important what the formula is but if you
differentiate that you'll see that the
tangent vector is that and that's one of
these guys.
So as before the direction of the orbits
is expanding and then on the B7 we have
the other seven uh directions. So this
thing over here is an ellypoid
with axes eus 2 r eus r eus r 1 1 e to
the r e 2 r
okay
so as we go from here to here these fs
are not exactly linear but they're close
to linear they're close to linear maps
and they stretch some directions and
they compress other directions by these
amount
Okay.
So what is different from before?
Okay. One difference is that this thing
is not exactly a projection.
Um
um
but that's not the most important
difference.
Um so differences from last time
Right? So if we had like an approximate
projection
that went from the seven ball to some
vector space V of dimension three say so
four dimensions are getting squished and
three dimensions are staying as they
are. That would sort of be approximately
a linear map with singular values
e to the minus r e to the minus r eus r
e the minus r 1 one one right if I had a
linear map like that these guys are
almost zero so these are the four
directions that are being squished these
are the three directions that are
staying the same the sing list of
singular values here is not quite like
that some of them are bigger than one we
didn't have that before and the ones
that are some of them are equal to one
the ones that are smaller than one have
two different scales. So that's a little
bit more complicated but I don't want to
focus on it.
Um
so
our singular values are a little more
complicated.
[Applause]
Okay let's ignore that. Suppose each of
these linear maps actually had those
singular values. So it was more like
what we were used to in projection
theory. There would be a different there
would be another difference from before
which is more important.
So number one number two we still have
only a one parameter family
of linear maps.
All right. So before when we talked
about projections from B7 to V to
threedimensional vector space, we talked
about like all of them. If you look at
all of the projections from B7 to
threedimensional vector spaces, then
something nice happens most of the time.
But we don't have all of them. We just
have a very thin subf family.
So this is not all of the projections.
Cool.
Okay. So, um there's also a cosmetic
complication that seven is a lot of
dimensions and there are a lot of
numbers. Um that but that that's not
that important. It's just a pain. But
but but these are this to some extent
and this is a really fundamental
conceptual difference.
Um so I wanted to show you not this
problem but the simplest problem of this
type
which is called the restricted
projection problem.
[Applause]
All
right. So this question which I think is
is is a cool question was raised by Fler
Katrine Fler and Thomas Orpinan in 2013
and the question is like this. So here's
the two sphere.
So we're going to be doing projection
theory in three dimensions in R3. So the
different directions are parameterized
by the two sphere. But we're not going
to project in all of them. We're just
going to pick some curve gamma and
project in the directions of gamma. So
gamma contained in s2 is a curve.
Okay,
the question is like this. um if X is
contained in the unit three ball and
let's say X is a delta SC set we'll put
to make it interesting we put some kind
of non-conentration condition and this
is the one that they had in their paper
basically
okay then estimate
the average
over all the directions in gamma
of the of pi theta of x delta cover
remember okay so pi so theta is a
direction an element of s2 and pi theta
is the orthogonal projection from r3 to
theta per so from three dimensions to
two dimensions
so estimate the average of that
seeh
I erased the wrong thing okay on this
very boring. Not two minutes ago, there
was a proposition. It said if you had a
set in R2 and you projected it in all
the different angles, then on average
the delta covering number of the
projection was at least something or
another. So this is like an analog of
that in three dimensions for a set with
the spacing condition, but with the key
difference that we're not averaging over
all of them. We're only averaging over
the ones in a particular curve gamma.
Okay. Now an interesting thing about
this question is that it matters what
the curved gamma is. And in particular
there's a big difference between an
equator which is sort of like a straight
line on the sphere and a non- degenerate
or curved gamma.
So the answer
depends
on whether gamma gamma is the equator is
one extreme or gamma non- degenerate
is another extreme.
Um instead of writing the definition of
non- degenerate let me just give you one
example of a non- degenerate curve. So
an example of a non- degenerate curve is
gamma is equal to the set of theta in
s2. So that the third component of theta
is a half.
So it looks like a the boundary of a
spherical cap like that.
Okay. So let me show you how these are
different from each other.
[Applause]
Okay. So, example
say gamma is the equator and s is two.
So, we have a sort of a quote unquote
two-dimensional set a delta 2 set. Okay.
So, our set x is going to be a delta by
one by one slab.
So that looks
okay. And so imagine that the the um the
two big directions are in the plane of
the blackboard and the slab is sticking
out of the blackboard by a little bit
delta. Okay. Now there's an equator of
directions that we're going to project
in. And think of that as the equator
that's like uh the sphere was centered
at the blackboard. You intersected the
sphere with the blackboard you would get
a circle.
So
here's gamma. So now if theta is in
gamma
then the projection of x is a delta by
one rectangle.
So there's a circle of directions where
if you project this slab you just get a
delta by one rectangle.
Okay. So then we see that the average
uh pi theta of x delta is like delta
inverse.
Okay.
Okay. Now, there's no obvious version of
this example where where gamma is that
curve that's up nearer the top.
And the difference is so you know if
you're if you're projecting in in a
certain direction then the fibers are
like lines in that direction. And so
what's special here is that all of these
lines are co-planer. And so you could
have a kind of planer object that has a
lot that that p where these lines
intersected a lot. And instead, when we
have those directions, then all of our
lines make an angle of 45 degrees with
the horizontal. They're like light
cones.
And these just don't fit together in the
same nice way that co-planer lines fit
together. So, it makes a difference. And
Fler and and Orpin, they they proved
that it makes a difference. So, they
proved some bounds for that thing that
are strictly bigger than this thing. But
it took a while to figure out what is
the sharpest bound. Um and that was
figured out sometime later in a paper of
six authors. Um Shang Wang Gan Shia Guo
me Terrence Harris Dominique Mald and
Hang Wa many of whom were here working
on it at various times. Okay. And we
approved um I'll just do a special case.
So if uh x and b3 is a delta 2c set
um and gamma is non- degenerate like
this example above then the average
theta in gamma of pi theta of x delta
covering number is bigger than cepsilon
delta to the -2 plus epsilon
Okay. And the best thing you could hope
for here is delta to the minus2 because
x itself probably has delta covering
number delta to the minus 2. So up to
small issues that this is the sharp
theorem.
Okay. Um this proof is based on some
version of the fora analysis method. Uh
but it's a more difficult version that
involves decoupling.
Okay,
cool. So this connection between
projection theory and uh between
homogeneous dynamics and projection
theory was discovered by Alan Linden
Strauss and Amir Mohammadi who were
working on uh quantitative estimates for
how how unipotent orbits become dense in
this setup and they realized this
connection with projection theory and
they found the literature they found the
paper by Fler and Orpin and and all the
follow-up papers and they used those
tools to prove of quantitative estimates
about how these unipotent orbits mix.
>> Yeah.
>> The question of projection theory where
kind of each unipotent filament kind of
reduces a different projection. Is that
set of projections dense in kind of the
whole space of projections or is it some
non-dense subset?
>> No, it's some non-dense subset. Yeah. So
here t is going from zero to one. For
each t we have more or less a
projection. Um and so we have a smooth
curve of length length one in the space
of pro of not exactly projections but
the space of linear maps.
Um and so it it is not in any sense
becoming dense in the space of linear
maps. is really just a few special ones.
And um and this is a a reasonable model
to picture in your mind like that that
sphere is like all of the projections or
all of the linear maps and that orange
circle is the ones that come up in the
in homogeneous dynamics.
Yeah. Okay. So in the last two minutes I
will write down a theorem that they
proved.
uh at least approximately.
Okay. So this is Linton Strauss,
Mahmadi, Wang and Yang.
Um so setup is on that board. So if G is
SL3R,
gamma is S L
3 Z U as above.
Okay, we take X um and we suppose U dox
is not close
to a proper homogeneous subspace.
So it's some analog of being not close
to periodic.
Okay. Then the conclusion is that
u 0t of x is delta dense
in um in the homogeneous space. But so
the homogeneous space has infinite
diameter. So this can't quite be true.
But in the if you cut off the cusp.
So you cut off the cusp. So you have a
compact piece of this. Um and delta is t
to the minus c. C greater than zero is a
universal constant.
Okay. And a key step in the proof is to
first show an estimate of the kind that
we were talking about that the delta
covering number of this orbit is is
pretty big.
Right? So the biggest it could possibly
be would be delta to minus the dimension
of the group. That's the delta covering
number of the whole space. And it's
quite close to that. That's a key step.
It's analogous to the proof that we
sketched for the simpler SL2R case. Um,
and there is an additional argument, but
it seems like the most novel and
important part of of this paper was
using projection theory, using those
kind of theorems
plus some other smart stuff uh to show
that the orbit covers a lot of ground.
Okay. Um Okay. So homogeneous dynamics
is a big subject and there are different
techniques but in this course I wanted
to show that there's a connection to
projection theory which is one set of
techniques and which helps to say some
some interesting