hello everyone welcome to the MBA
admissions application tips webinar from
MIT SLO Admissions Office my name is
Alexis Marcus I am part of the
admissions team I'm joined by a number
of my colleagues in the background today
to help you walk through the MBA
application and learn all the tips and
tricks to applying to MIT Sloans MBA
program for fall 2025 entry really
excited to be here with you um we do
still have a number of folks getting in
from the waiting room um so just being
mindful of that and this session is
being recorded today so if you are
missing the beginning of it you will
always be able to kind of co go back on
and see our recording on our YouTube
channel within the next couple days
we'll have that up on the website um so
today's agenda for the next 45 minutes
we'll be talking today about first the
value of an MIT Sloan MBA second we'll
dive right into the application process
we'll talk about the different
components of the application things
that have changed this year that you
might not have seen in past years if
you've been kind of monitoring
application are thinking about this over
the last few years and then we'll be
doing Q&A I know a number of people
submitted q u their questions ahead of
time when they signed up and I did take
a look through that and hopefully I'll
answer many of those questions
throughout the PowerPoint and throughout
um the presentation and then also we
have the Q&A feature at the bottom of
your Zoom screen please go ahead and
utilize that and submit questions I do
hope again that many of them will be
answered throughout the presentation but
again our team is here to answer those
questions for you some of them will be
answered live towards the end of um the
session today and then some of them will
be answered in that Q&A chat um so
thanks to all of my teammates for
helping out with that
process all right the first thing I want
to start with is the mission of MIT
Sloan and the reason that it's really
important to start with this is because
I do think that you'll see that our
mission is built into every single thing
that we do at MIT Sloan um and
accomplishing this Mission starts with
the application right so the mission of
MIT Sloan principle of management is to
develop principled Innovative leaders
who improve the world and to generate
ideas that Advance management practice
and again the start of that is the
application we're looking for those Le
those Future Leaders who are going to
improve the world who are going to
generate those ideas and ultimately help
to advance management
practice so today our session is really
focused on the 2-year MBA but we do have
a number of Port of programs at MIT SLO
and this is an example of our portfolio
here so you can see that we have a
number of different specialized Master's
programs as well as MBA programs
depending on your years of experience um
so the MBA the 2-year MBA it's a
full-time program and on average folks
have about 3 to seven years of full-time
experience when they're going into the
program that means that people you know
finish up either their undergraduate or
any you know Master's programs that
they're doing they're working full-time
in Industry between on average again
it's on average about 5 years years but
the range is 3 to 7 and we definitely
have folks on the lower end of that as
well as folks on the higher end of that
then they take that kind of Hiatus to
come back join us for that two-year
fulltime MBA program and then um go into
their career their next career move as
part of the MBA program you do have the
opportunity to do some dual and Joint
degrees those are listed here lgo which
is our leaders in global operations is
an opportunity to get both an MBA at MIT
Sloan as well as an MS and one of our
engineering disciplines we also have a
dual degree with um dusp which is
Department of urban studies and planning
and then we also have a dual degree at
the Harvard Kennedy School so those are
opportunities that you might want to
look into a little bit more today's
session today is really just focused on
the MBA application U but if there are
any kind of questions that pop up I
we'll try to answer those with regards
to the Dual degree programs otherwise
you're welcome to email us at the
conclusion of this event and we'll be
happy to talk to you oneon-one
so I want to give a quick synopsis of
what does the MBA class look like at MIT
Sloan so first and foremost I just want
to point out that this is the class of
2025 so this is not the incoming class
this year the class that's coming in
this year is still being finalized and
those numbers should be available for
you on our website I would say by
mid-september or so so this is the class
that came in last end of last August
right in the class of 2025 and the class
size was around 409 it was 409 that
included both lgo and MBA um on average
again like I previously said the average
years of work experience was five we had
great Global representation with 60
countries represented I'm not going to
go through each of these here but I want
to kind of just showcase this class
profile so that you can see that there
is a place for every single person at
MIT Sloan and in the MBA program we have
people from all different backgrounds
all different undergraduate Majors all
different Industries prior to their MBA
and we encourage that iers of thought
within the classroom so we're looking
for people with different backgrounds to
join and and apply uh to our
program so a couple of reasons to pursue
an MIT Sloan MBA um really you know MIT
Sloan is uniquely situated as M as mit's
um business school and so we have a
really great intersection between that
business and technology throughout your
MBA program you will develop leadership
skills to really allow you to enhance
your career so many people coming into
an MBA are looking um either to get to
that next level within their career
within their industry or they're looking
to Pivot we have plenty of people that
come into Sloan um and think about you
know completely changing Industries and
that is welcomed at MIT Sloan um so if
you are looking to either grow within
your own your your organization or um
take a step in and leap in a different
direction the MBA is a really great way
and next step to do that also um
entrepreneurship is kind of built into
the ecosystem at MIT Sloan and so many
people choose to pursue an MBA in order
to pursue a startup idea I will say that
many um MBA students at MIT loan have
started an a a um have done a startup
prior to joining doing while they're at
loan or ultimately um are involved in
some way in in a startup later on in
their careers because of that kind of
entrepreneurial ecosystem we have an
incredible Network at MIT slan and
that's one reason why folks want to kind
of pursue an MBA in addition to kind of
enhancing their own skill sets um really
kind of building that network will allow
them to have something to tap into for
the rest of their career we also have a
number of offerings at MIT Sloan we are
an experiential learning um school we
have a one year or excuse me one
semester C uh one semester Core
Curriculum and then after that it's full
flexibility within um our curriculum to
take any classes that are interesting to
you
we have certificate opportunities um and
then also our action learning Labs um
which are an opportunity to work on real
world problems in different you know
Industries different Regional
opportunities and those are just some of
our academic offerings that people are
you know are attracted to MIT Salone for
those reasons today we are really
focusing in on the evaluation process as
well as the application process so I I'm
going to kind of pivot now and talk more
about that um so the MBA a evaluation
process just by some sheer numbers to
give you a sense of kind of where things
stand every year we get around 5,000
applications and that's across all three
rounds so we have three rounds in which
you can apply to the MBA program um this
one in SE the first one is in September
the second one is in January and the
third one is in April um and we get
around 5,000 applications every year for
across those three rounds all of the
applications are reviewed by the
admission committee and then from there
about 25% of of applicants are invited
to interview and from that about 16% are
actually admitted so 16% of the overall
5,000 application excuse me 16% of the
5,000 applications are actually admitted
to the program every
year so what are we evaluating when we
are when we get those applications so
after the deadline every single
application again is reviewed so you're
likely wondering if I submit my
application tomorrow is the admissions
committee looking at my application the
answer is no we do not start to look at
the applications until the day after the
deadline so there's not necessarily an
advantage to submitting it early you
just need to submit it by the deadline
date um so for this year you know the
deadline um for round one is sep uh
September 30th and so you will need to
submit it by 300 p.m. on that day and
then on October 1st bright and early the
admissions committee will get to work
and start reviewing those applications
uh so what are we looking for when we're
looking at the applications we're going
to go through all the components of the
application in just a minute but as
we're looking at the application overall
we're looking at the full application
not each component right so we are
looking for demonstrated success
throughout your application as well as
what we call leadership skills or
personal leadership attributes so a
couple examples of that is how well do
you work in a team how are you problem
solving how are you a how are you
communicating your thoughts and ideas
and how do you adapt to change we are
not necessarily looking for people that
have already had the opportunity to lead
right so we're looking for the ability
to like um we're looking for the ability
to want um to work in teams to
understand the perspectives that other
people bring to the table and so
throughout your application each of the
components you want to think how can I
showcase this how can I showcase the
successes that I've already had both you
know professionally and academically as
as well as you know my future successes
and so um within the application um we
are going to be looking at that and then
we're going to be kind of true MIT
fashion we're going to be plotting you
kind of on data right so we are not
evaluating each component to the
application but rather looking at the
entire application and looking for
certain competencies and those fall
within again demonstrated success so how
well did you do in your undergraduate
how well did you do on any test scores
that you're submitting how well did you
do in any m's programs how well did you
do um you know on on work place
evaluation so that letter of
recommendation hopefully it's coming
from someone in the professional setting
um and then on the the leadership
attributes that's looking again at you
know how well are you problem solving
how well are you working in teams and
from there we're plotting you kind of on
this chart and then we're looking at
those upper you know quadrant of folks
that are actually moving forward within
the process so if we think back to my
upside down triangle where I said about
25% of folks are invited to interview
they're all scoring mostly within this
upper um quadrant within this box this
is intended to just be um demonstrative
and I don't want anyone to kind of be
wondering what numbers and things of
that nature the idea is just that you're
putting together a complete uh picture
of your experiences within the written
application and so we're going to jump
into that now so here is the application
checklist um and this is all on our
website as well and again we we'll be
posting this recording as well um as the
you know you'll see be able to see the
slides throughout the recording but this
checklist and all of the components are
on the website under our how to apply
section so we have three rounds for MBA
September 30th is the most uh the one
that's coming up um and then we also
have our lgo dual degree program which
we mentioned earlier and there is only
one round for that and that's November
6th so if you are intending to apply to
lgo you must submit the lgo application
by that November 6th deadline um so here
are all of the different components on
the right hand side of the screen and
we're going to go through each one
individually and then we will talk a
little bit about interviews towards the
end which are require but they're By
Invitation Only um so your written
application is submitted reviewed by the
admissions committee the first you know
um round of reviews by the entire
committee come forward and about 25% of
the pool is invited to interview and
you'll do a virtual interview if you are
invited to interview um if you are not
invited to interview you can get one of
two decisions uh you will get a reject
decision or you will get a wait list
without interview decision if you are
weight listed without an interview that
means that your application will be
reconsidered in round two at the time
that interview invitations are sent out
and then so on and so forth so if you
apply in round two in your weight listed
without an interview you'll be evaluated
in round three by round three you we do
not have a wait list without an
interview so everyone um you know will
will reviewed and ultimately either
invited to interview or a final decision
will be rendered at that
point so let's start with the cover
letter so the first thing on the cover
letter is we're asking you to seek a
place in a f in in the MIT Sloan MBA
program and within that we're asking you
to share some of your professional um
successes that you've had we're looking
for specific examples here the cover
letter is intended to be 300 words or
fewer and we do ask that you stick to um
that length because you know we we want
you to be concise and we want you to
show us you know what are the what are
those examples of professional successes
that you want to highlight for the
admissions committee so um within the
cover letter you want to sell yourself
you want to make sure that you're
showing us what those successes are if
they're quantifiable that's great you
can absolutely include that if they're
not quantifiable tell us why is this
example important what does this mean to
you tell us why MIT Sloan why are we the
school that you're seeking to get your
MBA at and you know why are you a good
fit for our program um so again those
professional examples perhaps some
personal if they're relevant to
demonstrate why it's a good match um I
think one of the biggest pieces of
advice here is don't focus on future
goals your past performance is really
the in U an indicator of your future
success and so we're looking for those
past
examples the rume is the next component
um I'm going to go through the resume
then I'm going to kind of go back and
talk about the two together so the
resume is a one-page maximum so we're
looking for some specific um formatting
here that's recommended is Times New
Roman font size 10 um we're looking for
a word or PDF format and then again the
sections should be education work
experience and then any additional
information we're looking for something
that's easy to read so you know we don't
want you to go crazy with um any kind of
unique formatting here we really just
want simple bullets to be able to kind
of go through and understand what your
accomplishments have been you can
showcase any volunteer work that you may
have extracurriculars leadership
positions anything that you've earned
outside of the workplace or within the
workplace as well um it's also an
opportunity to tell us about some of
your personal interests I think that one
of the things that's really exciting
when when I get into an interview um I
love being able see what people's you
know uh hobbies are outside of um their
professional world so if you have the
space to do it definitely include a
little bit of information on on who you
are outside the workplace you know
whether you like skydiving or you know
eating cheese we've seen it all and I
would love um you know to learn a little
bit more about you from from that resume
so I want to pause here and go back to
both the cover letter and the resume and
often times one of the questions that I
get is well can I be duplicative I want
you to think of your application as a
whole thing that you're putting together
rather than these individual components
that we're going through so your resume
should showcase what like what your
accomplishments have been in the
professional setting we want to see
those quantifiable you know bullet
points um on the rume rather than your
daily tasks um underneath the different
jobs that you have held you may want to
pull some of those examples out and
showcase those and expand upon those in
the cover l letter but you're likely not
going to have room to expand upon all of
those examples right so you're picking
out the ones that are that mean the most
to you and talking about the more in the
cover letter putting more um color
around those examples and then perhaps
um that you know in the video which
we'll get to in a few minutes um you'll
be talking a little bit more about your
personal um experiences or your personal
um interests and what you want why why
you're pursuing an MBA right and so that
could be talked about a little bit more
in the cover or excuse me in the video
and so you want to use the real estate
within the application in a way that
allows you to expand on different things
um in different places you don't need to
say it all in all of the spots um so for
instance like again with the resume you
want to be putting those quantifiable
accomplishments into bullet points
within the resume and then maybe
expanding on two or three of those
examples within the cover letter to
really showcase why MIT Sloan and why
this is the right program for
you so talking about the video statement
I just mentioned it so again this is
that kind of third part and putting
together the complete picture of who you
are um and so the prompt for this is
introduce yourself to your future
classmates here's your chance to put a
face with a name let your personality
shine through and be conversational be
yourself we're excited to meet you um
the best piece of advice for the video
statement is keep it simple um you know
whatever is your comfort level is really
where you should be with the video and
so if that's sitting at your desk in
front of a webcam similar to what I'm
doing right now um absolutely do that if
that's um you know perhaps outside doing
something that's fine too the only thing
I would say is be mindful of your
surroundings um so oftentimes we have
seen videos that have incredible views
of incredible places on top of mountains
or um you know on hikes and while
they're incredible the wind is blowing
in the background and we can't hear what
the applicant is saying the most
important takeaway from the video is
what you're saying um so we really want
to be able to hear you clearly so play
the video back for yourself numerous
times to make sure that it's clear the
audio is good and there's no questions
there um you know we want to know a
little bit more about who you are things
that we don't see elsewhere in the
application this video will absolutely
not be shown to any of your future
classmates uh but it is going to be seen
by the admissions committee and we want
to know how are you going to be
introducing yourself to your future
classmates your future friends what are
you going to be um you know what what's
your elevator pitch to yourself when you
walk into the slone classroom for the
first time you know potentially in a
year so using your judgment think about
how you would answer that question um
and put put together the video statement
the video statement is 60 seconds so it
can be no more than one minute um and
it's there you know you can take do
multiple takes of it and and put and
upload that video but we don't want
editing meaning we don't want it pieced
together um absolutely no music in the
background so please don't put it to
music um please don't use Clos C you
know captions at the bottom we're
looking really just for you to be
speaking directly to the camera um and
and us being able to hear your
story all right the next part of the
application is video question two this
this is a new component for the 2024
2025 admission cycle so for entry um in
Fall 2025 you will need to submit video
question two as part of your application
um so video question two will pop up in
your application after about 80% of the
application is complete so it will be
automatically appear as a tab within the
application once that's once you've
completed enough of the application to
let it here there is a testing um you
know a testing window first so before
you start it you can kind of see what
what's going to happen and then you you
go through the process and it will it
will walk you through it it won't be
sudden um so it is a 60-second
open-ended randomly generated prompt
about your personal or professional
experiences because it is about your own
personal and professional experiences
there is no preparation needed and there
is no no right or wrong answer I think
that's the biggest takeaway from this um
there is absolutely no right or wrong
answer you will have 10 seconds to re
read the question that will appear which
again randomly generated so everyone's
going to get a different question and
you will have 60 seconds to record the
answer and then the it will turn off
after the 60 seconds um the admissions
committee will use this to assess your
competencies that we talked about before
as well as your communication skills so
again the question will pop up I can
give you know some examples I'll give a
couple examples you might not get these
questions um but tell us about a time
that you faced an ethical dilemma or
tell us about a time that you had to
work with a difficult teammate and so
you will see this question on the screen
and then you'll have 10 seconds and then
the the camera will turn on so before
that question appears you will again
have that testing phase to make sure
your camera is working your mic is
working everything is good to go um you
will see the video question to tab
appear on your application once about
80% or so of the application has been
completed um and then if you click on
the tab it it won't immediately start at
that time so you could go back to it so
if you see the tab appear it's okay um
to you know close out of your
application and say hey I'm going to do
video question two tomorrow um but again
all of these parts need to be completed
by the deadline date in order to be
considered for the round that you're
applying for so I'm I'm anticipating
there'll be a lot of questions about
this but I hope I answer answered as
many uh questions as
possible so the next part of the
application is the recommendation letter
MIT sles MBA program only requires one
letter of recommendation the question I
get most frequently is Can I submit
another letter of recommendation the
answer is no the the application asks
for one letter the admissions committee
wants to see one letter so we're looking
for you to use your best judgment on who
can write the best letter of
recommendation to Showcase your skill
set and your successes so on the right
hand side I have put together all of the
questions that we asked the recommender
and so you should read through these
questions and think who is best suited
to answer these questions for me um we
are looking for you know a more a mo
more recent example so to the extent
that you have told your employer that
you are applying to the MBA program um
and that you're looking to pursue an MBA
and they can respond to these questions
we would love it to see it from you know
your most recent supervisor of course we
also understand that a number of folks
do not tell their employers immediately
um perhaps in round one that they're
looking to leave you know the following
summer and so you might want to ask a a
previous supervisor or someone else that
you work with again this should be a
professional Source um a couple quick
things make sure that you ask your
recommender early giving them ample time
their recommendation letter needs to be
submitted Again by that deadline date so
for September or excuse me for round one
September 30th at 3: p.m. we need to
have their letter in order for your
application to be considered complete
you will get an email once they have
submitted their letter um but you will
not be receiving a copy of that letter
similarly we ask that you do not have
involvement with the writing of the
letter itself that really should be an
authentic letter that your recommender
is writing and uploading to our system
logistically in order to get the letter
of recommendation you need to go into
your application and input the
recommenders contact information into
the system that will prompt our system
to send them a link to send the letter
and that will automatically get attached
to your application once they submit it
um a couple quick things on to note on
the recommendation letter we do ask that
you use their um professional email
address so um you know avoiding personal
email addresses like Gmail or Yahoo or
anything of of that kind of nature
really using the organizations um even
if they're not at your current
organization anymore whatever their
professional email address is what we're
looking for
there we also ask for additional
references so we're just asking for two
additional names of professional
references um that can speak to your
abilities so this you can think of these
additional references as folks that you
would have asked for a letter of
recommendation from had there been the
opportunity to submit additional letters
of recommendation additional references
we could um contact at any point
throughout the admission cycle so we
might um we might have questions um
about your professional aptitude and
want to contact an additional reference
you know during the read phase or
potentially after an interview but
before a final decision uh we will never
reach out to an additional reference out
of the you know just out of the blue we
will always email them and try to set up
a mutually convenient time for a call if
they do not speak English we will pay
for the translator so you don't need to
worry about that um and again you know
we will be asking them very similar
questions uh to what you see on the
right hand side of the screen here that
we asked for the recommenders for within
the
letter okay the organizational chart the
organizational chart is intended to be a
visual depiction that you create um as
you know of where you fall within your
organization or within your department
depending on how how large your
organization is
so we want to understand who you're
working with on a day-to-day basis um
who you're reporting to who potentially
is reporting to you or has a dotted line
to you who are your peers um a lot of
people email and ask you know I this is
confidential I can't I can't give this
information we're not looking for names
we're not looking for confidential
information we're just looking to
understand how many people fall within
your department how many people are you
interacting with on a day or daily or
weekly basis and trying to understand
that that level of detail if you are
able to give us all of it great you can
put the people's names in there from
your department again it doesn't need to
go incredibly High maybe a couple levels
above you if you're able to do that
again for some folks that might be a lot
of people you have to use your best
judgment here to to kind of showcase um
what those interactions look like and
and who you report into we do ask that
you Circle yourself on the
organizational chart in Red so that we
are easily able to identify who you are
if any of your references or the folks
the person that writes your letter of
recommendation Falls within the
organizational chart we do ask that you
highlight them in some way so that we're
able to make that connection that hey
this is the person that wrote the letter
of
recommendation um the chart should match
your resume and your employment section
within the application I hopefully this
goes without saying but make sure that
you know when you're putting together
your organizational chart for your
primary job that's also the primary job
listed on your resume as well as your
primary job that you've listed in the
employment section on the
application um this last bullet point
here if it's possible to Showcase you
know your career growth within the
organization or within the department
you can absolutely do that um in this
space as well we've seen a number of
people use the organizational chart in
creative ways to Showcase their growth
um throughout their professional career
so that's completely up to you if you're
you are able to do that um again you
don't need to include names on the
organizational chart but you you know if
you are able to that's super helpful so
we can kind of match it up and also once
we get into an interview when you're
talking about specific examples it's
nice to for the interviewer to have that
up and be able to kind of see and
understand what who you're talking
about okay test scores so the test is a
required component to the MBA
application so we do accept the GMAT or
the GRE um for the MBA program the GMAT
we accept the focus Edition or the old
10th edition so if you have a 10th
edition score we're absolutely still
accepting that um and if you've taken
the focus exam that's fine too I know
that they're starting to call it just
GMAT um all of it so you will need to
differentiate when you submit your score
whether you took the focus or you took
the 10th edition um in the drop- down
menu or if you have a GRE score you can
submit that as well I did make a note
here starting this year there is the
GMAC business writing assessment score
um this is an optional test that
students are applicants are able to take
um and submit to show showcase their
writing abilities to um potential MBA
programs if you have this score and you
want to submit it there is an
opportunity for you to do that um on the
application it will just be considered
as an additional data point um I will
make a note that some applicants um may
be asked to take this later on in the
admissions process and you'll see this
noted in the application that we may ask
folks that have a GMAT Focus um score to
submit a GMAC business writing
assessment score at the interview fees
but we will contact you after interview
invites have gone out if we intend to
ask you to do this um so not nothing to
worry about right now but if you do want
to be proactive and go ahead and take
that you can submit that score um right
at the application fees and that is
available I believe starting in August
2024 so in a couple weeks um it should
be launched on the GMAC website so in
terms of what formats are acceptable for
GMAT and gr both the inperson and L
online are both acceptable we have no
preference um again for the GMAT it's
Focus or 10th edition in person or
online whichever you know you have or
whichever you did is totally fine with
us and there's no preference given there
test waivers so we get a lot of
questions are we having test waivers
this year are will you wave my test the
test waivers are granted on a limited
case by case basis only they are only
intended for those folks that are unable
to take a test because it is unavailable
in the place where they live within the
world we understand there are certain
places within the world that still are
not able to access the GMAT or the GRE
online or in person and for that reason
we will allow you to request a test
waiver the test waiver is not intended
to be a statement of academic Readiness
or that you have done additional things
within your career or within your
undergraduate or um what have you that
means that you don't need to take a test
that is not the intention of the test
waiver um so if you want to access the
test waiver you will go into the
application navigate to the test score
section of the application and there's
the W link to the waiver right in there
you can submit the waiver please give us
around you know three to five days um
time to respond to your request if the
admissions committee says um yes you can
have a test waver you'll get an email uh
and then you'll be able to submit your
application without the um without the
test if the admissions committee says no
you must submit a test you will not be
able to submit the application without a
test score and you will need to take
either the Gman or the GRE in order to
move forward with the application um so
I hope that answers all the questions
but test
scores all right academic records and
Rel coursework you will need to submit
your transcript as part of your
application to MIT Sloan um you need to
submit transcripts from all schools that
you've attended or that you're currently
attending um if you transferred you need
you need to submit the transcripts from
those transfer institutions as well it
is not enough that the transfer credits
appear on your final transcript um
within the transcripts we're looking for
academic aptitude we're looking for your
comfort level with quantitative work um
and we're looking for a sense of
intellectual curiosity so this you know
this kind of area is often where I get
so do I need to have a stem background
or do I need to you know have a Quant
background in order to come to MIT Sloan
the answer is no um so you'll see that
there is a page within the application
that's asking you um a number of
relevant courses and if you've taken any
of those not all of them are
quantitative but some of them are um
there are plenty of people that have
been admitted to our MBA program that
that page is completely blank for them
so if that's the case for you do not
panic that is really intended for us to
understand within the admissions
committee decision meetings you know
does this person maybe need a little bit
of extra preparation to make sure that
they're set up for Success within the
classroom space our goal on the
admissions team and um you know on the
committee is really to set you up for
success and so we would never want you
to you know come into a program that you
aren't prepared for so if you don't have
some of the background classes that we
think that might be helpful we may give
you a preparatory class um in order to
matriculate if we if we were to give you
admission um in the future so that's
just one kind of note there when you're
listing out relevant cours work that you
have taken
already all right short answer question
we this was previously an optional
question it is now mandatory for all
applicants to submit the answer to this
question it's 250 word um text box
within the actual application itself and
we're asking you how has the world you
come from shaped who you are today for
example your family culture Community
all help to shape aspects of your
identity please share more about your
background this is an opportunity for us
to learn more about you expanding on
your background where you come from um
we are limiting it only to words so no
external videos or links will be
reviewed as part of this but we really
want to know a little bit more about you
so again when you're thinking about kind
of all those different components
putting together you know um the color
the colorful picture of who you are as
an applicant hopefully this sheds a
little bit more light on who you are on
the personal
side all right so we went through all
the components of the application again
all of those components are going to be
reviewed by the admissions committee
then we're going to sit down and have
that holistic review of the application
we're not grading the components we're
looking for competencies within the
entire application what Have you shared
with us for example examples what has
your recommender said um you know what
have you said within your video once we
look at all those competencies we'll be
scoring on those demonstrated successes
as well as those personal attributes and
Leadership skills plotting it on
plotting all of the applicants on the
graph and inviting those that fall
within that upward quadrant to interview
which will end up being about 25% of the
pool if you're invited for an interview
you will get an email inviting you to
interview in in information about
responding to additional short answer
questions that you will have to do no
later than by 24 hours before your
scheduled interview you'll schedule a
virtual 30 minute interview with the
member of the admissions committee and
then within that um 30 minutes you'll be
doing behavioral based questions
answering behavioral based questions
about your professional
experiences um so again we be looking
for specific examples on how you felt
about something how you handled
something um who else was involved so
talking about some of your professional
experiences and maybe thinking about um
different examples that you'd want to
showcase with in an interview your
written application is intended to give
us a taste of what is to come right so
like we we've read your written
application we've seen all these
successes that you've showcased within
that written application and now within
the interview we want to hear more that
we're inviting you to tell us more and
you'll want to think about what kind of
examples you might want to include in
that so my top tip for admission to MIT
Sloan we're looking for reasons to admit
you we are here to you know help you
walk through this process we want to
help you you know put your best foot
forward so hopefully all of these tips
um will help you when you're thinking
about putting together your
application apply early and follow the
instructions I'm going to say both of
these kind of together um applying early
you know is a balancing act you want to
apply when the time is right for you so
don't do it if you're feeling feeling
rushed um hopefully many of you that are
logged in today feel as though you know
you're you're ready for round one you
still have a couple months um of time to
get everything put together but asking
your recommender now getting all of
those kinds of last minute things
buttoned up and starting to put those
final touches on your application over
the next two months to be ready to
submit in September but let's say
something in life happens as life does
and it prevents you from hitting the
submit button on September 30th does
that mean that you shouldn't apply this
year because you're going to apply in
round two absolutely not go ahead and
apply in round two and similarly if you
um you know aren't able to apply in
round two you can apply in round three
we have three rounds we admit people in
three rounds every year uh but the
reality is is that in round one the
whole class every seat is available
right and so as we admit folks it
throughout each round we've we have
seats that are taken up it's just basic
math um so that's why we encourage you
to apply early if you're ready you don't
want to wait till to the last round if
you have an application that's ready to
to be submitted um and follow the
instructions we have been so thoughtful
and put a lot of effort into kind of
going through the application and making
sure that all the instructions are
clearly articulated so please follow
them they are there for a reason um we
are looking to learn more about who you
are right so be yourself in the
application be yourself in the video be
yourself um you know in your cover
letter really showcase who you are and
help us again advocate for you give us
all that data that we need to admit
you all right that is the end of my
slides I want to just put this one up
here we have so many events coming up
this um this summer and through the fall
and so that QR code will bring you to
our website of all of our upcoming
events um we have a like will be at on
like GMAC Fair we'll be at Forte events
um but we also have a number of our MIT
slown on the roads that are happening
quite frankly globally over the next
couple um weeks and so I just showcased
a few of them here but you can RSVP to
any of any of our events by using that
QR code and I also put the email address
on the bottom so if there's questions
that didn't get answered today or just
general questions you can always reach
out to us uh at this time I'm going to
invite my colleague I think David's
going to join us um and kind of run
through of a Q&A that's been happening
in the
background hey Alexis hi thanks for
loing in a lot of lot of great questions
out there and so thank you for everybody
we got a few minutes left to answer them
and we're not going to answer all of
them so just to reiterate please email
us we will get to your questions um so
one of the big ones is where should
applicants talk about why they're
choosing MIT slan yeah good question in
the cover letter so the 300w cover
letter is intended for us to understand
why MIT Sloan is a good fit for you and
why you are a good fit for MIT Sloan so
it's kind of a two-way street there so
we're looking for you to show us you
know what about MIT Sloan kind of fits
you know with who you are as well as why
um you know you're a good fit like what
what what are your characteristics that
fit with who we are looking
for um okay uh let's see another one
that we have
is
um what can people expect in the video
questions in terms of of you know the
the preparation especially video
question too since it is new to the
application terms of the preparation the
type of question that is yep so video
question two again absolutely no
Advanced preparation is needed is about
your the questions are all about your
per your own personal and professional
experiences so a question an open ended
randomly generated question will pop up
on the screen and you'll have 10 seconds
to review it and think of response um
I've done it a few times now you know
personally testing it out and thinking
of examples from my own personal
professional experiences and it is
totally doable um and the idea is that
we're just learning to learn a looking
to learn a little bit more about you um
and on that kind of you know um popup
question versus something like the video
question one where you have you know all
the Time in the World to kind of prepare
for it and put forth what your your
presentation would be um I would say
don't start stress about it too much
again there is a test window so like
none of the logistics behind it will be
a surprise you'll be able to do the test
before you jump into the actual
question awesome um and then also here's
a really great question what are some
common mistakes that should be avoided
when completing the
application not following the
instructions I would say is the number
one um we have again been really
thoughtful about putting those together
so again we ask for one letter of
recommendation submit one letter of
recommendation um we ask for the cover
letter to be 300 Pages excuse me not 300
pages that is definitely I'm definitely
misspeaking there 300 words um not
including the you know introduction or
salutation limit it to 300 words the
resume is a one-page resume you know
don't go submitting a 10-page CV with
you know every single thing that you've
done since you know Elementary School we
are looking for you to be um efficient
and effective within your
application so we got a as always we get
a lot of questions about the or chart um
so should appli so should applicants
pick which organization that they work
for for their orig chart or should they
use their most relevant most recent uh
job good question all right so the or
chart is intended to be your current
role your most recent goal so I'm
goingon to talk about a couple question
common questions we get
Consultants that will be the first one
that will come up um if you are a
consultant you can do your most recent
project that you worked on rather than
the firm that you work for so I'll just
use McKenzie as an example if you work
for McKenzie I don't need to see where
you fall within McKenzie I want to see
kind of where you fall or who you were
working with on your most re recent
client project another common one that
we get is military folks should they
include their military or chart um or
should they include you know if they if
they held a civilian role or if they've
held like another previous role um you
can do both your civilian role and your
you know on if your active duty your
active duty um org chart as well again
going back to what I was saying about
the confidential information I'm not
looking for confidential information
within this so just giving us kind of a
general picture of of where you fall and
and who the folks are that you're
working with or reporting to is really
helpful um a lot of people will say hey
I just started a job um like a month ago
so I'm not really sure like the or chart
is going to Showcase that much about
where what I'm doing we are still
looking for it to be your current role
so even if you just started the job uh
when you submit the application please
go ahead and make sure that it's your
application reflects that and has the or
chart from your new role uh and then we
can talk about it more if you get to
that interview phase like to understand
a little bit more about the details
you'll hopefully have more information a
few months later about what your your
new role looks
like and I guess I'll sort of uh one
last question keeping an eye on time um
so this is more about sort of the test
scores should people take multiple tests
and and submit them yes um so if you
have multiple test scores absolutely go
ahead um and submit all of those scores
we will look um at all of the scores
that are submitted one thing that we do
we do ask that you do not do is make
like a super score so don't just take
your highest Quant and your highest
verbal and tell us those two things you
need to tell us the full real score from
all of the um tests that you took so
that way when we if you are admitted and
you ultimately come we verify all of
these things so we need to have an
accurate accounting of what your GMAT or
GRE test scores were um so if you have
multiple absolutely go ahead and submit
them it's totally up to
you you have time for one more yeah oh
yeah we could take a couple more all
right cool so here's a really good
question how does MIT slan evaluate
full-time work experience uh do we just
look at 40-hour weekly commitments or is
it more specific titles roles
positions oh great question um so
full-time work experiences I mean you
know plenty of people are working more
than 40 hours in a work week um and
plenty of people are holding more than
you know one role right now I know there
are plenty of applicants that are
holding a role within an organization
and then potentially pursuing um a
startup on the side so we can definitely
look at both those we do ask you to
qualify one organization as your primary
employer on the application
um and so that would be kind of
self-identified by you is to what that
full-time experience looks like
internships are not considered a
full-time experience so we are looking
for for your employed full-time um but I
would say on average folks are working
40 40 or more hours per week um in a
full-time
role great thank you and sort of keeping
in that evaluation strain of questions
uh how do we evaluate leadership
potential in
applicants yeah great question um again
so we're looking you know for leadership
potential but not necessarily having
leadership um experience already right
so the MBA a lot of the MBA is getting
leadership skills and understanding how
to become a leader within your
organization within your industry um or
again pivot and become a leader and so
we are looking for folks that are
open-minded that are excited about
working with others and that you know
have had that experience in the past of
working on teams that have had the
experience of problem solving and we're
looking at all of those kind of together
with um what your recommender has said
about you how how are you as a people
person how are you you know thinking
about problems that have you know you've
had a long time to think about or
problems that have just AR resen and and
you you had to react on your feed all of
those kinds of indications or indicators
within the application are giving us the
the the information that we need to
assess the competencies in particular
what your future leadership potential
awesome um and then a question sort of
about the recommender we've got a lot of
questions about the recommender and one
of the more interesting ones is uh is it
a plus if the recommender is a member of
the MIT Sloan Community um or does it
make a
difference it does not make a difference
if that person does not know you in the
professional setting and really can
speak to all of those qualities if your
direct supervisor can talk about all of
those questions I had listed out that
are you know within the application um
and and they're an MIT SL Alum fantastic
that seems like easy but you are not
getting extra points by having a letter
recommendation written by someone within
the Sloan Community U so again if it if
it happens to work out for you in that
way that's great absolutely go ahead but
that you are not getting anything extra
by having a recommendation from someone
within the SL Community we are looking
for thoughtful detailed letters of
recommendation so whomever that means
for you is who should write your of
recommendation and I think that same
thing that same answer goes to title
right I'm not necessarily looking for
someone to write your letter of
recommendation that's at the top of an
org and that has met you one time in the
cafeteria or on an elevator I am looking
for your direct supervisor who really
understands your work and your your
successes day in and day out those
letters of recommendation are so much
more thoughtful provide so much more
insight and really quite frankly are way
more helpful to your application than uh
you know a highle executive that really
can't speak to your
abilities okay uh let's see uh question
about sort of the testing again
especially the addition of the of the
GMAC business writing requirement like
aspect if someone took a gr do you think
it's Bene beneficial for them to take
the GMAC in the name of being proactive
the writing ass the writing assessment
or I am just telling people that it's an
opportunity to submit the score but
we're not encouraging it in any way if
if you want to submit it you absolutely
are welcome to um it's just another data
point so there's absolutely no negative
inferences if you do not submit it um
and if for those that do submit it it's
just an additional data point um we
again we may ask folks that took the G
Focus Edition that are being invited to
interview we may contact them um but
that will be decided later on within the
admissions process
um and then a question sort of about the
transcript especially from students who
went through undergraduate or graduate
programs during covid and their
institutions moveed to sort of a past
fail how do we um evaluate that and how
how do they sort of want to report their
GPA there yeah absolutely so your GPA
were really clear on the application
should be reported exactly as it says it
on the transcript um so you know read
the instructions of the application and
do exactly what it says we're not
looking for you to recalculate your GPA
the only person we're asking for a
calculated GPA is for someone that does
not have GPA on their transcript if your
if your school is giving that GPA on the
transcript regardless of what it's out
of you will put it exactly as it says on
the application um and so for folks that
do have those path fails we of course
have become very familiar with seeing
those over the last four super common
almost every applicant has um a pass
fail or multiple given the covid years
um so I wouldn't put too much stress on
that you know we we're looking to kind
of see you know what your overall um
performance was in your undergrad but
I'm not putting too much stress on a
past
fail um and here's a really interesting
one I haven't seen before about the
about the resume itself how does a good
MBA resume different from say a resume
you would use to apply for a
job oh that's a great question um so I
think
sometimes they're a little bit similar
in the sense that you're trying to
Showcase your skill set for a particular
role right and so for us we're really
looking for impact bullets impact
related bullets impact results um so
what have your successes again been
within your roles whether it's your
current role or your past roles within
the same organization or a different
organization um you are not necessarily
outlining what you're responsible for on
like a daily basis where that you might
be doing that for um for a job you are
really showcasing what the successes
have been if they're quantifiable
putting in those successes um depending
on what the job is you might not that
You' be applying for in the future you
might not have all of those details that
level of detail um but you'd be having
more about like what you actually
responsible for we're not looking for
like a list of your responsibilities or
um we're looking more on the
accomplishment
side awesome and then sort of uh there
are a few people who are reapplicants
who've asked questions um any general
advice for reapplicants yeah great great
I'm glad that you're here thank you so
much for logging in um the application
will look slightly different with the
new components that you haven't seen in
the past but you are uniquely um you're
in a unique position right as a
reapplicant the admissions committee
will look at your past application as
well as your current application so my
biggest piece of advice is use this to
your advantage you essentially get
double real estate right so you had your
application last year do not submit the
same components redo almost everything
get a different letter of recommendation
even if it's from the same person have
them updated with new examples that have
happened you know in the last year um
you don't want to use all of those same
components as last year because
obviously that didn't work last year so
we want to make sure that we're
showcasing more of those successes
giving us more data that we can pull
those competencies from to move you on
within the process um so I would say you
know just be mindful review your
application from last year um and update
all the components that you
can let's see um Can people send
additional uh letters of
recommendation so the application is one
of the instructions and one of my
biggest piece of pieces of advice is
follow the instructions the application
asks for one letter of
recommendation um so please do not
submit more than one letter of
recommendation um and then someone asked
a question so uh why do we ask for
salary
information so salary information is
really intended to kind of see your
potential growth um sometimes it
showcases that it does not always show
showcase that and I will be completely
clear that it is very different across
Industries so we're asking salary
information but we're not putting
significant weight on it nor are we um
you know showcasing that in any way as
part of our evaluation of your
application so we're looking to see like
if you started within an organization
and you've had significant salary growth
let's say over six months that potential
potentially is an indicator of success
potentially there's a lot more to it so
like that will kind of spark like oh
that's interesting and then go into
going into the letter of recommendation
to learn a little bit
more awesome um and then sort of uh
let's see oh very interesting question
the GPA um should if your GPA is not in
a
4.0 4.0 scale is it okay to use a
service like W uh Wes to convert your
GPA please do not convert your GPA it
says with in the application when you go
to apply do not convert your GPA we are
so familiar with a number of different
scales throughout the world and we ask
that you do not you know change that GPA
in any way so put it in exactly as it
appears on your transcript the only one
the only applicants that should be
calculating a GPA are the folks that um
actually don't have a GPA on their on
their transcript itself some people do
not have a GPA and therefore we give
instructions on you know calculating one
if you have a GPA out of any scale do
not recalculate it you just put it into
the application exactly as it appears on
your
transcript and sort of does having only
two years of experience reduce one's
chances at
admission so it doesn't off the bat
reduce your chances we are looking for
again those examples of um work
successes we really do believe that the
more work experience that you have that
average of five years um the better
prepared you will be for the MBA
classroom the you'll come with better
you know more robust examples um you'll
be able to be a more active contributor
within the classroom that being said we
do have people coming in with two years
of full-time work experience and so um
you I I don't want to give a blinket
answer to this it really depends on the
applicant you really need to kind of
look at your work experiences um in
particular if you're thinking about
applying um in round one at this point
you only worked for one year so you only
are pulling from one year's worth of
work experience um to Showcase within
that application so it ends up being um
a much shorter time frame than many
other applicants so it really just
depends on what your own experiences um
are