so my name is yonas I'm an associate
professor in the operations Management
Group I've taught uh
om uh introduction to operations
management for the in the MBA program as
well as a healthcare elective uh across
programs and my research is part or like
a big chunk of my research is in global
health so I'll talk a little bit about
that and why I think it's um an
interesting kind of field to be in and
then I'll give an example of something
we did and I should say just like Karen
I've had a bunch of NBA and Ras in the
past and they without exception been
fantastic I've had a really really
really good experience working with MBA
and students on all of the things that
Karen said and theyve often been very
kind of heavily involved in the sort of
scope being an an early stage idea
generation which has been fantastic so
uh I work in healthcare like I said uh
and I think uh I've done work on sort of
global Health uh on ambulance systems on
public health and so I think what makes
my profile a little bit different from
other people who work in health is that
I haven't been doing any Hospital
operations so I've been interested in
these sort of higher level systems that
contribute to health outside of the uh
outside of the buildings of Hospitals
and Clinics and so on um and I think
another thing that's maybe a little bit
unique is all of this effort on global
health so Global Health meaning um sort
of not the medicine not the technology
but like the operational and system
design of the systems we use to deliver
Health in very very resource limited
settings so these are settings that are
so resource constraints for example you
know in sub Africa like Ken mentioned uh
that their systems just look
fundamentally different from what we
used to uh at least in the US and in the
UK where I was before uh and so they
require kind of a different way of
thinking different typ set of tools uh
and so they make for very interesting
problems so let me talk a little bit
about why I like this as an area and
then give an example I think I can be
pretty quick but we'll see so uh I like
working on this because I think there's
potential for impact just like Karen
said like we I think we're all
interested in in having some impact on
the ground and you know if you just look
at basic basic statistics uh there's a
lot of work to be done for example in
Subs Africa like we're talking about
high prevalence of preventable death
which is by definition preventable
because we know how to deal with it
clinically and technologically we just
haven't put the proper systems in
place uh the next reason is or you know
for that reason because it's a systems
problem there's like an operational
botton neck operations research
operations management analytics are the
right tools to deal with it right so
it's not about fundamental biology or
medicine it's really about systems uh
and so I think the
expertise uh that we have in operations
and analytics is is actually the right
tool kit to now make a difference um
like I said before these systems are
very different from what we've been
doing like our field has been doing
Hospital operations for probably 20 25
years but it's not as if the insights
from those types of analysis would
transfer directly to Subs Africa just
because the infrastructure the systems
the challenges everything is different
even the kind of priorities in terms of
which clinical conditions we look at is
is different and so we need to do uh
kind of fundamental systems research to
be able to address big questions in this
in this field and finally uh and this is
relevant for an analytics crowd another
thing that's happened is with you know
the Clinton Foundation The Gates
Foundation and these types of
Institutions becoming involved with
global Health delivery on the ground is
that now we have access to data that
before we did not have right so it was
very different I was too young at the
time but I think it was very different
30 years ago trying to make an impact on
the field in global health because you
didn't have sort of routine operational
data being collected now we do have some
of that and so we can actually use
analytics um to try to make a difference
okay um this is really the key thing so
if people have questions about this I'd
love to talk about this but I'll also
give an example of a project that I
think kind of fits at this to some
extent all of these
so uh the background is is H HIV H right
uh as you probably know the prevalence
of AGS is predominantly focused on Subs
Africa so it's a big big challenge uh
and the global Community has made a ton
of uh progress in terms of diagnosing
AIDS right so we get people diagnosed
and get them on treatment the
interesting thing is then the focus of
uh of Public Health shifts kind of I
guess up or Downstream and the Cascade
in the sense that it's not enough to get
people on treatment you need to make
sure the treatment is working and that
adhering adhering to it right and so the
goals now are these 9090 90 90% of
people being aware of the status 90% of
those being on treatment and then 90% of
those having suppressed viral load and
we're nowhere near these targets
okay and what you need to make sure that
the person who's on anti-retroviral
therapy for HIV is uh the that the virus
is suppressed is uh PCR testing and a
few years ago no nobody about PCR but
now everyone does and so these this
require sort of heavy duty lab equipment
okay uh and in for example Mala the the
country we were working with you have
you know hundreds and hundreds of
clinics out in the communities some of
them very rural uh but only about 10
molecular Labs that have the capacity to
do this testing okay uh and so what you
need to do is to collect samples blood
samples from people out in the field
transport them to a district up and then
to a lab and then the results back to
the field so that they can be
communicated with the patients so this
an example where uh clearly the
operational system that's in place has a
lot to do with how effectively we can
you know try to achieve these uh goals
that I said
before uh we work with uh an NGO called
writers for health which is sort of
operates these motorcycle couriers who
do this Transportation they go collect
some bring them to the district and then
to the lab then pick up results and
bring them back to the
clinic and when we started engaging with
them we realized that basically what
they were doing is they were doing sort
of these fixed Postman RS so the
couriers would do the same schedule
every week okay this was just a way to
kind of guarantee a certain service
level when they negotiated with the
Ministry of Health to set this up the
issue with this is that there was a very
very high proportion of empty trips like
there would be visiting places driving
for hours and not having any samples to
pick up or any results to return and on
top of that you know because they were
doing this sort of inefficient
scheduling they were contributing to
delays uh and so which is bad for
patient
obviously and so we kind of thought of
this somewhat simple system but it
doesn't have uh uh any precedence in
sort of global Health which was a let's
design some sort of communication system
that allows people in the field to
communicate to us the NGO whether or not
there are samples to be picked up and
it's not obvious how to do this right um
because there's no it might not be
electricity there's no managerial uh
infrastructure and so on okay and we
didn't want to deploy new technology
because then we have to maintain it and
we didn't want to uh put valuable sort
of new technology in the field in case
uh it doesn't stay there very long so we
had to convince health workers to use
their own technology their own phones to
communicate with us okay the second part
was even if you have all this
information it's not obvious what to do
right on Nationwide even if you know
where there are samples it's not an easy
thing to do to route and schedule
Courier trips to make sure that you're
you have the most kind of efficient
system possible and so that's where
optimization came in and so the idea was
we'll sort of crowdsource the data from
the health workers they'll use their own
phones to tell us whether or not there
are samples to get picked up and then
we'll use optimization to schedule and
Route couriers on a day-to-day basic
basis so it will be much much more
Dynamic than the old kind of Postman
system that was in place
before three minutes okay so let me just
do this very very quickly so the the
system for crowdsourcing the data was uh
was this sort of ussd system that was
free of chars to all of the health
workers in the country and we only ask
them at the end of the day enter the
system use the code that corresponds to
your facility and tell us how many
samples are waiting okay so ideally very
little disruption to the day all they
needed was to have their phone charged
and we' already checked that most of
them have
phones
uh so that was sort of the main part of
the information system I'll skip very
quickly through the the transportation
optimization it's basically about using
this information and then
predicting uh the samples that will be
coming in in the next week and based on
this information try to come up with a
smart schedule and routes uh for the
couriers to to pick up samples and
deliver
results uh and then the interesting
thing was what we were able to implement
this so we implemented in these three
districts uh that were meant to be kind
of representative of the scope and scale
of the different or the characteristics
of the different uh districts in the
country uh I'll just I'll go very
quickly through the results but what I'm
proudest of is we did this in three
districts then completely handed off to
the field so the NGO in country now owns
the system and since then this has been
scaled up and it's now running in 11
districts and the Ministry of Health and
the CTC in the US who's the main funer
of this uh have committed funds and have
like a timeline for scaling this up
nationally so the hope is that you know
in a couple of years the system we
designed kind of doing desk research
that MIT will be used to Route uh and
sort crowdsource data all through the
country to try to make HIV diagnosis and
viral Lo monitoring uh more
efficient I'll do maybe one set of
results um so the first thing is we
actually got data from health workers
the second thing is the data was
reasonably accurate so this was an
empirical question we didn't know if
this was going to happen uh using this
data we were able to shorten the delays
associated with transportation and we
were basically able to eliminate these
empty trips this is obviously useful for
operations but it turned out to be
really really really valuable for the
NGO in country as well because they were
getting they were losing credibility
because people saw them as wasteful
because they had these empty trifts and
then using you know this it system and
an analytics we were able to kind of uh
help their status in country as well to
to sort of come across as a professional
partner to the Ministry of Health