I'm Caroline ooler a professor in the
department of electrical engineering and
computer science at MIT and a core
faculty member at the broad Institute
one of the world's leading biomedical
research centers at the broad I
co-direct the Eric and Wendy Schmidt
Center which seeks to create a two-way
street between machine learning and
biology and I'm near haken I'm the
director of the MGH Center for Cancer
immunology and the director of the cell
circuits here at the BR Institute and we
want to share with you today an exciting
challenge taking place this January the
Eric and Wendy Schmid Center is holding
the cancer immunotherapy data science
challenge through top coder in
collaboration with Harvard's laboratory
for Innovation science mit's department
of electrical engineering and computer
science gordian biotechnology and the
Mass General cancer center today we're
here to talk about why we're doing this
Challenge and also to discuss the
problems at hand we'll talk about cancer
immunotherapy using our own immune
system to combat tumors exciting new
biological data sets that could open
novel avenues for cancer imun therapy
and why we think machine learning is the
key to unlocking the power of these data
we'll also get into the challenge itself
can you design algorithms that identify
genetic modifications of tea cells that
make them effective at killing cancer
cells now for some of our viewers we
know it's been a while since biology
class in high school or college so near
let's talk about tea cells okay well te-
cells are the soldiers of the immune
system every time we're sick say with a
virus our immune system mounts a
response tea cells find attack and
destroy the cell that Harbors the virus
as a result we get better they also find
and destroy cancer cells at least some
of the time but one of the Hallmarks of
cancer that we Now understand that
cancer cells are very skilled at evading
detection by the immune system cancer
cells mimic our own health tea cells and
send signals that cause the tea cells to
malfunction right and when that happens
the cancer cells can start to multiply
out of control forming lumps called
tumors and these cancer cells can also
spread to other parts of the body
through a process called metastasis and
on top of that cancer is not just one
disease melanoma is very different from
leukemia which is very different from
breast cancer exactly what we know now
is that our genetic mutations actually
influence how well we respond to
particular kinds of treatment even for
the same cancer in other words one
treatment for one patient won't
necessarily work for everyone else but
there is hope we believe that the future
for Cancer Care is
immunotherapy cancer immunotherapy uses
our body's immune system to fight cancer
by boosting or changing how the immune
system works so that it can better find
and attack cancer cells yeah an
immunotherapy has already shown results
and holds even more promises if we can
make the te- cells attack tumors even
more potently than now then we can
eliminate any form of cancer and any
part of the body that would be an
enormous improvement over current
treatments but you might be thinking
this is Quite a feat where do we even
start how do we make immunotherapy
scalable and effective so this is where
large scale data sets and machine
learning really come in the Life
Sciences are in the midst of a data
Revolution where in expensive and
accurate DNA sequencing is a reality
Advanced molecular Imaging is becoming
routine and single cell genomics is
allowing us to profile millions of cells
in a single
experiment these Innovations and the
massive data sets they produce have
brought us really to a threshold of a
new era in biom medicine however with
this opportunity also comes a challenge
our ability to generate data is rapidly
outpacing our ability to analyze and
interpret it
to give you a better idea a single lab
can generate a data set that Rivals and
size the entire movie library of Netflix
here at the broad we have more than 100
pedabytes of data under management which
is 100 million gigabytes put simply we
have reached the limits of unaided human
comprehension but fortunately the last
two decades have witnessed not only a
transformation of the life sciences but
also the data science
as we all know we're living in the
Golden Age of AI and machine learning
but unlike in the more traditional
applications of machine learning and AI
like recommender systems or online
advertising in the biomedical Sciences
the ultimate goal is often to understand
the underlying mechanisms for example in
our cancer immunotherapy data science
challenge we need to understand the
underlying regulatory Circuit of te-
cells in order to identif ify
modifications that will make the cells
more effective at killing cancer cells
so the causal aspect is really important
for this application and we will talk
more about this later but before that
near let's talk a little bit more about
imuno theapy and also our heroes the tea
cells so the idea of cancer
immunotherapy has actually been around
since the late 1800s initial
immunotherapy efforts sought to use
bacteria or viruses to mount an immune
response against the cancer
today there are two main categories of
cancer immunotherapy treatment which
both involve te- cells checkpoint
therapy and KT therapy the checkpoint
proteins which are on the surface of te-
cells are one of the ways that our
immune system self-regulates when
checkpoint proteins bind to healthy
cells they send a signal to the te- cell
to turn off but they also switch off
when te- cells bind to cancer cells
checkpoint therapies like the therapy
developed for advanced melanoma
block the off signal for te- cells and
tumors allowing them to kill cancer
cells in car therapy on the otherand
researchers actually remove a cancer
patients te- cells from their body
re-engineer the cells to make them
Target cancer cells and put them back
into the patient car te therapy is only
approved for a limited number of cancers
like certain kinds of leukemia non-
Hotchkins Lymphoma and multiple Myoma to
better understand how immunotherapy
Works let's take a close look at te-
cells we're going to use these Poké
Balls to demonstrate the te- cells te-
cells start as what we call naive te-
cells who have not yet seen their target
each naive te- cell in your body has on
its surface a slightly different
recognition receptor which is created
through an amazing process of random
rearrangement of Gene sequences to make
the t- cell receptor or what we call the
TCR the TCR recognizes specific
molecules presented on the surface of
the cancer cell represented here in the
melanoma when the te- cell receptor
first sees its Target on a cancer cell
the te- cells become activated and move
through a series of Transformations so
from a naive t- cell the cell becomes
activated and forms what's called a
progenitor t- cell State this t- cell
state has the ability to produce many
more t- cells and more of itself so it's
self-renewing in the second stage it
becomes an affector t- cell and the
affector te- cell can divide fast and
kill tumor cells so so it recognizes the
tumor cells and kills them in the third
stage the t- cell enters what we call a
terminal exhausted State this state has
reduced functionality in proliferation
and a shorter lifetime so it can kill
the tumor a little bit but eventually it
dies in addition there's a fourth state
of cells that are currently in the
process of dividing these cells are
known as cycling cells and any of the
cell States we just talked about can be
in this uh proliferating state to make
more cells to kill the tumor now you may
be asking why do we even have terminal
exhausted States for te- cells it's
because we all have chronic viruses that
are controlled by our te- cells
throughout our life but these te- cells
cannot work at full force or they're
going to cause more damage to the bodies
and the viruses that they actually
protect against so at a high level
deactivated te- cells can be in four
different states a progenitor state
where they can proliferate a cycling
state of cells that are in the process
of of dividing an affector state where
they can kill tumor cells and an
exhausted state which is in fact the
dominant type in human cancers the goal
of this challenge is to identify genetic
modifications that increase the
probability of these tea cells going
into the progenitor cycling or affector
States but what defines a tea cell State
well humans in mice have about 20,000
genes and one way of characterizing the
state of a T cell or any cell is by
measuring the activity of each of these
genes in a cell with today's single cell
Technologies these measurements can be
done at a scale of hundreds of thousands
of cells per experiment so this means
that every cell is represented as a
20,000 dimensional vector and then by
performing clustering we can identify
the cells that are in each one of the
states so the progenitor State the
affector state the exhausted State and
the cycling state so let's now shift and
talk about how can we change the state
of the t- cell so the state of a t- cell
is defined by the underlying Gene
regulatory circuitry changing a single
Gene in this circuitry can dramatically
impact the expression of tens to
hundreds of genes and through that shift
the t- cell from one state into another
now Gene editing Technologies like
crisper allow us to actually go in and
for example remove a gene which is
called a knockout note that by changing
one Gene you may change the activity of
many other genes namely the ones that
are Downstream from the modified Gene in
the regulatory circuit so by cleverly
identifying which Gene to modify we
should be able to move te- cells from
one state to another and reduce the
probability of generating these
exhausted te- cells exactly but the
problem is for us is that there's
approximately 20,000 individual Gene
modifications or perturbations that we
could make to a single t cell and 400
million combinations of these
perturbations testing all these
possibilities would be unbelievably
timec consuming and expensive so the
question here is how can we narrow down
the 20,000 possibilities to just those
few perturbations that are most likely
to work to reach our goal so this is
where you and your algorithms come in to
our data science challenge to reprogram
T cells to combat cancer and to make
this happen we've collected a very large
single cell data set from tumors in mice
where we measured the activity of every
Gene in 100,000 t- cells we've also
knocked out 70 different genes one gene
knockout per cell so that means we can
see how removing one of those genes
affects the activity of all the other
genes and that can give us insights into
the underlying Gene regulatory Circuit
of a two Cel but of course we've only
performed 70 Knockouts out of all these
possible 20,000 Knockouts but now given
this training data set the challenge is
to design algorithms that can predict
the effect of all these other unseen
possible Knockouts and identify the ones
that would lead to a higher proportion
of cells in the progenitor State the
affector state and the cycling State and
less cells in this exhausted state so
here is the exact breakdown of the
challenge in part one you will predict
the effect of Knockouts that have
already been studied in the lab this
will allow you to see how well your
algorithms work
in part two you will propose new
Knockouts that based on your algorithms
could boost the cell's ability to
destroy the tumor and then finally in
part three you will come up with a
metric for ranking how well a particular
Gene knockout would shift t- cells to a
desired State and so we're really
excited to announce something unique to
this challenge the top scores from part
one will have their submissions
experimentally validated in the lab so
you can get to see how well your
algorithms actually perform in
controlling tumors and eliminating them
note that a biology background isn't
needed to participate the Eric and Wendy
Schmid Center will provide all challenge
participants with a short online crash
course and the broad Institute is a
global leader in biomedical research in
particular in genetic sequencing so this
is a unique opportunity to learn from
leading life science and computational
biology experts and the crash course
will take you to the biology of the
immune system explaining the function of
te- cells in a tumor you'll also learn
more about the technology that we use to
generate the single cell transcriptomics
and the perturb seek data sets that
you'll be working with and the Crash
Course will give you an introduction to
the biases of these type of data and how
to work with the data you'll be well
prepped for the challenge in hand the
challenge will run from January 9 to
February 3 2023 you can sign up as an
individual ual or a team and will be
giving out monetary prices to the
winners of each part of the challenge
totaling 50,000 US dollar and the top
participants will be invited to become
an author on the resulting
Publications another great product of
this challenge is that the resulting
data algorithms and code from The
Challenge will all be made open source
for the community to use and we will
also be adding to these perturbational
data sets as new experiments become
available and we would love for you to
remain engaged in this problem also
after the completion of this particular
challenge to achieve the goals that we
just talked about we're going to need
new ideas new ideas that break through
the bounds of the traditional approaches
that address the most pressing questions
and ultimately help us intersect machine
learning with Biology so not only will
you get to do something you love but
your algorithms could change the course
of how we treat cancer if if you haven't
already register now and we're very
excited to be working with you
[Music]