I first got a chance of taking video
tips of my undergraduate freshman class
to put on open courseware and in the
first minute so many people get to watch
the videos and you're like oh this is
great more people than I will ever teach
in person. When MITx came on and we
could use the same video to structure
something with deeper engagement, I was
even more excited by that because I felt
I can basically now almost teach the
same way. The MIT students that I teach
in person watch the same video as the
online people and basically take the
class and then they come to class and
they do something else with it. And the
people in the world, they watch this
video and presumably they also use it in
a part of their life that's a different
part. For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe or follow.