And now a big welcome to our next
presenting startup in Patatica with
their novel AI enabled wearables for
continuous health monitoring and
research. Welcome to stage David
Crowley. Uh before I start just hands up
has anyone got a wearable like a
smartwatch, a smart ring, anything to
collect data. Great. So what we do is we
have wearable devices that are used to
collect data but mainly for clinical
trials and clinical research. Um, and as
one of the last speakers before your
lunch, I very much understand my role
here, so I will keep this short and
sweet. So, I am David Crowley. Uh, I
work in the pharma partnerships team.
It's my job to help with a lot of our
industry partners to understand how to
use wearables and how to use digital
data uh from these wearables in how they
conduct clinical trials and clinical
research. So, Impatica as a company, we
were co-founded in 2014 by Professor
Rosen Buchard of MIT, who is still our
chief scientific officer today. Um, and
we are based just across the river in
Boston. So, we haven't moved too far,
but we also have locations in Milan,
Italy, and Soul in Korea. Um, we are a
fullstack company. So, everything that
we do from the wearable technology to
the different digital biomarkers and
algorithms are all developed inhouse. Um
and really you know our our focus is to
create uh specific digital biomarkers
and specific wearables to capture
different measures as you go through a
clinical trial. We primarily work in the
kind of clinical research and clinical
trial space. We work with a lot of top
20 pharma companies um supporting over
120 trials to date uh and over 100,000
people have worn different variations of
our products.
So when we talk about clinical trials
today there are obviously challenges
associated with clinical trials. Uh one
of the most ones that we talk about is
subjectiveness. Uh so a lot of clinical
trials are based on different patient
reported outcomes which can be hugely
beneficial in terms of getting a
patient's perception and a patient's um
kind of um measure of a disease state
but it does lack a certain
objectiveness. So these measures can be
subject to different recall bias. Uh how
a patient is feeling on a certain day.
You know intermittent monitoring comes
into place where you may be only seeing
a patient once a month. Um so depending
on how that week has gone for them that
can influence their um responses. Uh
it's obviously costly to bring
participants um patients into a clinical
trial site to monitor them and then you
know from the participant aspect it is
burdensome to to travel to different
places to travel on site and have
different tests uh in place.
So what we've designed is the emphatic
health monitoring platform. Um and
essentially that is there to remotely
monitor patients and capture this data
in a more objective manner in a
continuous fashion. So this is the uh
wearable itself that's part of this
platform. Anyone who's looking can see
I'm wearing one right here and we have a
few more outside. Um and essentially you
can capture over 300 different digital
measures using this uh quite neatly
designed um quite unobtrusive watch.
There are five different sensors on
board. Depending what a a company is
looking to measure, we do tend to tweak
those sensors in different frequencies.
Um we do have kind of accelerometer,
gyroscope, skin temperature, pretty
standard. As you go towards the bottom,
we have more customized sensors.
Vententral EDA, which I'll be talking
about in a minute, looks at electromal
activity. So that looks at your galvanic
skin response. Uh very good at detecting
kind of periods of excitation or stress.
Uh and then optical PPG is uh what you
may be familiar with in certain kind of
health monitoring uh devices that look
at pulse rate, pulse rate variability,
respiration rate, blood oction and
saturation. So this is the flow of data
again just to to show you how the whole
platform works. Obviously we start with
the wearable device but then it
transfers to an app and goes up into a
centralized location in the cloud. Uh
importantly a participant doesn't really
need to do anything on this which is
great. they just put it on and it
collects this data continuously uh and
researchers and sponsors are able to
capture this data centrally in one
location. So in terms of our use case
and how this can be used um there you
know we've done a lot of research in
clinical trials and clinical research
not all published but I have chosen one
that is publicly available and we're
currently working with the US Department
of Defense to look at post-traumatic
stress disorder monitoring. Um so I
think 7% of uh veterans will develop uh
PTSD in their lifetime. That percentage
goes even higher when you look at more
recent uh deployments and and combat
zones. So what we're working with the
DoD is is to have continuous monitoring
using our devices um and looking at
different measures to try and predict a
novel digital biomarker to either
monitor disease progression or predict
risk factors of developing PTSD uh in
these uh populations.
So last but not least, thank you very
much. Uh in terms of
partnership, as I said, we primarily
work in the clinical research and
clinical trial space. Uh so if you are
interested in incorporating wearables
into your trial, uh a lot of the
wearable use is in CNS disorders, but we
are uh therapeutic area agnostic. We
work across metabolic disorders across
cardiology, obesity, oncology. So if
you're ever interested in using this
technology, please do come and talk to
us. I'll be outside and yeah to meet you
all. Thank you.