(classical music)
(traffic rumbling)
(moves into lighthearted upbeat music)
(Professor Wallace laughing)
(wheels squeaking)
(crowd cheering)
- Hello.
(upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
- Wow, what a rush.
That's the final product launch
for our mechanical engineering
design students at MIT.
It really feels like being
on a world championship team.
- [Speaker] NOMI is a water bottle cleaner
that will save our target
users time in their busy lives.
- Students come out of it
flying high on the belief
that they can handle any challenge.
It's a high stakes, high reward game.
But let's just think
about that for a minute.
Where is that reward?
(crowd cheering)
Is it in the limelight?
Is it in receiving the
cheers of a packed stadium?
(upbeat music)
Is it in knowing that thousands
online are watching you,
feeling idolized?
I'd say it's all very nice.
It's, it's great.
It feels good.
But, that's probably not it.
It's really in the knowledge
that you earned it.
That's when we experienced
the euphoria of growth.
(upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
(people chattering)
(soft orchestral music)
(students speaking off mic)
Many students come to MIT,
into our mechanical engineering program,
anticipating that this
is what they want to do,
that this is gonna be the culmination
of their undergrad experience.
And so how does that happen?
Well, we have a production
which is really designed
to inspire the community
here in the auditorium,
but it's also online.
And so, people all across the world watch,
with children, parents, alumni,
and so many kids are watching this
and anticipating it
throughout high school.
There's viewers in 140 different
countries around the world.
(crowd cheering)
One of the things that
I, you know, often say,
and I really believe, is
that to be a designer,
you really do, you have to
be arrogant enough to believe
that no matter what it
is, you can figure it out,
but then at the same
time, have the humility
that it's gonna take everything
that you have to do it.
You're gonna need to work
and you're gonna need help.
(people chattering)
(funky upbeat music)
- Presenting the yellow team.
- It's not at all uncommon.
Everyone has things they
feel confident about,
or not so confident about.
And you know, there's many
students that will say,
"Well, no, I can't really present,"
or, you know, "I can't do
a particular thing well."
And one of the most rewarding
things is, you know,
people trying, seeing people
try, seeing people practice
and then realizing, "Wow,
I can actually really do this well."
(jazzy upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
- With Feed Back, we can put
the fish back in efficiency.
(upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
- And it can have such
a transformative effect
upon one's life, just realizing, "No,
I'm not gonna limit myself by perceptions
of what I can or can't do,
because I know if we essentially
train, we can get good."
This experience really is
unique to our class at MIT.
- Paige is a novice water
skier and she's pretty nervous,
so she's incredibly grateful.
She can tell Jonathan to slow down
with just the push of a button.
- I mean, we're all used to
doing final presentations.
But to do a final presentation
where it's treated just as seriously
and just as real as like
a major organization
launching a new product,
that's an experience you don't
really get anywhere else.
(crowd cheering)
(smoke blasting)
For the students that are
upstage, it's all business.
They're on and they're doing their thing,
and that's really all there is to it.
For the people that are on
the team behind the stage,
there's incredible riveting intensity.
They're watching everything.
They're hoping.
"Oh, let's have this happen."
When things go great, they
jump up and down with joy.
- With Contour, all you have to do
is sketch, scan, and create.
- So now,
let's check on Juliana's creation.
(light upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
- There's just this kind of
tension and anticipation.
So the experience, even for the people
that aren't on the stage,
is really powerful.
Our aim is to help students
come to the realization
that what they do matters,
that they can develop
technologies that matter,
that they can do cool stuff.
With grit, with determination,
thought, process, hard work,
commitment, humility, and some help,
we can make a difference.
(light upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
(moves into slow bluesy music)
So, how to experience
the euphoria of growth?
Challenge yourself.
Think about what you want to be.
Have a goal and a plan.
Take action.
Follow a process.
Do the work.
Be seriously lighthearted.
Put yourself in a position to know
that you have given what you could.
Each of us in our own
way can experience joy
in the pursuit of our own
version of personal excellence.
We can believe that we have the potential
to be better, to grow,
that way we can make a difference
and look back with a smile.
We can play seriously.
(light upbeat music)
(light upbeat music continues)
(light upbeat music fading)
(no audio)