Obesity is one of the most urgent health
challenges of our time affecting over
890 million people worldwide. It
dramatically increases the risk of type
2 diabetes, cardiovascular diseases and
certain cancers. Despite the recent
success of incrretinbased drugs like
ompic, there remains a large unmet
clinical need. Many patients do not
respond. There may be side effects and
long-term solutions are limited. At the
center of this problem are adiposytes,
specialized cells that store fat and
regulate metabolism, the process by
which our bodies convert food into
energy.
>> Most of our fat is white fat, which
stores calories for future use. When we
take in more calories than we burn,
white fat accumulates, which leads to
obesity.
In contrast, brown fat burns energy to
produce heat when we are cold. Under
certain conditions, such as cold
exposure or exercise, some white fat can
transform and take on brownlike
properties, a process called browning.
Triggering this shift could help the
body burn more energy and combat
obesity. But there's another side to the
story. When fat cells don't form or
differentiate properly, fat can spill
over into other tissues such as liver
and muscle. This is a dangerous process
known as ectopic fat deposition. This
contributes to metabolic diseases like
insulin resistance and lipodistrophe
where abnormal fat distribution itself
drives health problems.
In this sense, both the ability of cells
to store fat safely, the adopenic shift,
and to burn fat efficiently, the
thermogenic shift are crucial for
maintaining metabolic health.
Recent advances in single cell
transcripttoics have unexpectedly
revealed that fat cells exist in many
different states, but the factors that
determine whether they store energy or
burn it are still poorly understood. By
combining single cell data with gene
pertubation experiments, researchers can
begin to map the pathways that push fat
cells toward energy storing adipogenic
or energy burning termogenic roles. The
challenge is really scale. Thousands of
genes can be individually perturbed and
millions of possible multi-gene
combinations can be made. Far too many
to test one by one in the lab. That's
where machine learning and you can help.
>> The goal here is to predict how specific
gene perturbations influence the fate of
fat cells, whether they differentiate
into energy storing widerocytes or shift
toward energy expending states. By
identifying the most promising genetic
switches and combinations, your work
could accelerate the discovery of new
molecular pathways for treating obesity
and metabolic disease.
This is where you come in. We need
algorithms that can predict the effects
of single gene perturbations, predict
the effects of combinations of
perturbations, capturing how genes
interact with one another, and propose
new gene combinations that are most
likely to shift fat cells toward
adipogenic or termogenic states.
The top predictions will be tested in
the lab at the Broad Institute, meaning
that your algorithms could directly
guide biological discovery in obesity
research. The Eric and Wendy Schmidt
Center and the Broad Diabetes Initiative
along with Massachusetts General
Hospital, Beth Israel Diaoness Medical
Center, and Crunch DAO are proud to host
the obesity machine learning competition
tackling metabolic diseases. This is
part of our annual series of machine
learning challenges that unite the
global community to address urgent
biomedical problems. The beauty of
machine learning challenges is the
collective intelligence they inspire by
bringing together experts with different
backgrounds from academia, industry, and
beyond. We accelerate scientific
progress far beyond what any single lab
could achieve.
Last year, nearly 1,000 participants
from over 60 countries joined our
autoimmune disease challenge. This year,
we invite you to take part in a
challenge that tackles one of the
world's fastest growing health concerns,
obesity and metabolic disease.
>> What makes this challenge unique is that
the winning models won't stop at
prediction. Top submissions will be
experimentally validated in the lab,
which means that your algorithms could
directly guide biological discovery,
opening the door to new strategies for
tackling obesity and metabolic disease.
Do you need a biology background? Not at
all. We'll provide a crash course in the
relevant biology along with all the data
sets you need. All that's missing is
really you and your algorithms.
>> The competition launches in December
2025. Monetary prizes will be awarded
and all code, data, and algorithms will
be made open- source for community use.
Our annual machine learning challenges
have already brought together a vibrant
global community of problem solvers, and
we hope you will be part of this next
breakthrough. Join us for the obesity
machine learning competition tackling
metabolic diseases. Your ideas could
help uncover new strategies to combat
one of the greatest health challenges of
our time. Visit the Eric and Wendy
Schmidt Center website today to
register.