So thank you. My name is Zishan. I'm the
director of partnerships at Encountable.
Um a unified laboratory informatics
platform that accelerates R&D for data
first approach. Um little bit connection
to MIT here. Um our out of the two found
three founders we have two went to MIT
null and will um but we also have Jason
who is was at Stanford and two are
computer scientists and one is a
material scientist. So what's going on
in our industry? The innovation gap is
about to explode. Around 45 million
technical workers will retire or leave
the industry by 2030, creating a huge
brain drain. On the other hand, AI
native R&D organizations that adopt AI
will cut development timelines by up to
50% by 2030.
Companies however that do not uh uh uh
do that investment and delay the data
infrastructure investment risk uh uh
lower innovation output by 20 to 30%.
So what is actually broken in the in in
this whole product development cycle and
the R&D data is decentralized,
unstructured and fragmented. Probably
some of you still might use notebooks,
Excel sheets or um different systems
that do not connect together are siloed
um and do not have any context end to
end and provide any value from the work
you do. they solve a certain uh uh uh uh
solution but the enterprises never get
to see the end-to-end value of the data
and that is why we created uncountable
uh as a platform to centralize connect
and structure all types of R&D data with
our structured experiment and property
database that sits at the core of our
platform and lets a user and a scientist
um add information at the point of entry
in a structured format.
without making them uh um sacrifice the
flexibility they need in their
innovation. So we have a limbs
capability, an ELN capability, uh
product life cycle management system
within our solution as well as QM and
most importantly what is used is we make
data actionable uh through reports that
uh and visualizations
and analytics and the holy grail that
everybody talks about today um AI and ML
specifically formulation predictions,
design of experiments and uh other AI
and ML ML tools based on the R&D data
that you have.
So what does good look like? So in our
world the the future of R&D is digital
and uh data is structured and
actionable. It lets the users and the
organization search, filter and track
experiments across projects and capture
data connected to instruments, equipment
and different data sources. Then you get
to leverage all your rich and clean data
to actually do machine learning and AI.
And accountable has developed some
proprietary AI and machine learning
models allowing um organizations to do
certain uh uh um um
capabilities that then they could make
their products go to market faster and
that they could reduce their innovation
cycles. So this is just one example of
of something you can do within the
system once you have this the data
transferred to your system to our system
and it it really shows a lot of value to
end users. Let me talk a little bit
about that. One of the examples we use
we have done in the past is Blue Nalu.
It's a company out of San Diego working
on cultured meat or cultured fish. Um
and before uncountable they were um
doing a lot of time consuming
uh data recording. They had limited
coordination. The consistency there was
inconsistencies in in in in in the
system. So they had a lot of rework. Um
it was hard to retrieve and track u uh
um audit findings u um when regulators
came over and traceability was was
basically restricted. With Uncountable,
they were um able to have everything in
one place, create an overview of all
their experiments so that when the new
person came in, they could get started
right away and knew what they've done in
the past. Um they were able to
seamlessly track along the R&D process
and most importantly improve their R&D
efficiency by 25%. So all of this helped
them also in the end when they go for
regulatory compliance uh um get to
market faster. So what are we looking
for today? Um we're looking for any door
openers, organizations, new customers,
pilots and partnerships where we can
present our solution and enable them to
improve and centralize their R&D
capabilities. Um connect with corporates
to also support our regional and global
expansion and also do code development
to gain insights to develop our own tech
but and customize for customers. The
areas that we uh look at here are very
broad. So advanced materials, chemicals,
farm, biotech. And what we really want
to do here is co-create value for R&D
and enable digital transformation teams
to generate new opportunities for the
organization. Thank you very much.