Hello everyone and welcome to today's CSAIL Forum
my name is Daniela Rus and I'm the Director of the
Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory at MIT and today I am delighted to
host a forum with professor Armando Solar-Lezama
uh Armando is a pioneer in programming languages
especially in probabilistic languages and the
use of AI uh for programming and Armando is also
the Associate Director of CSAIL so I have had the
pleasure of working with him for several years now
and uh you are in for a treat but before I pass
it over to Armando I would like to ask all of you
to please be an engaged audience Please start by
putting your name and your location in the chat
and then please contribute at least one comment
and one question uh throughout the talk at the end
of the talk we will have a chance to do Q&A with
Armando and uh with that Armando please take it
away thank you thank you very much i'm very happy
to be here and uh thanks to all of you for joining
us here on our uh uh webcast so today I want to
talk about this very fundamental question of how
do we tell machines what we want them to do this
is a question that goes back to the very earliest
days of computing there is this very interesting
text from Alan Turing that goes back to 1945 where
he's pondering how people are going to program
these new computing machines that are all the
rage at uh at this point and he talks about how uh
you know there's going to be this class of people
he thinks of them as mathematicians who have
certain puzzle solving ability and they're the
ones who are going to be telling these machines
what to do and he talks about how this process of
constructing instruction tables is never really
going to be boring because anytime any part of
this process becomes boring then we're just going
to automate that so that people are going to be
able to go back and focus on the stuff that's not
boring on the fun and exciting and novel things
and so you know this uh this was many many years
ago and you could say that we've done pretty well
by um Alan Touring's uh idea here right today we
have these wonderful technologies that actually
have people wondering like are we actually
going to still need to learn how to program are
programmers going to be obsolete um I think as as
time goes by we're starting to see that uh these
tools are going to play a very important role even
if they don't uh replace uh programmers but we are
seeing this explosion in the number of tools that
are available to help people create programs write
code and so programming is doing pretty well uh
and there's all these different ways in which we
can get help in telling the machine what we want
to do but today programming is not the only way
we tell machines what to do right and and in fact
you could say that the reason why we have all of
these amazing tools is because of a revolution in
machine learning that has been happening over the
last uh uh decade or so that has made it so that
we can teach machines how to do things purely by
examples right so for example if we have you know
some little uh robot critter we want to train it
to navigate some kind of environment we don't
actually have to go and write the code that is
going to tell us exactly how to move each leg one
step at a time we can use datadriven techniques
to learn how to do this from scratch and that's
part of the reason why we've been able to build
these amazing programming tools because we didn't
have to teach them explicitly were able to have
them learn by example however there's a lot to be
said for the traditional way of writing programs
that these more data-driven approaches fail to
capture right for example generalization uh when
we write code we might test it on uh you know
large set of examples but we expect it to work
on much beyond just the things that we tested it
uh you know people kind of make fun of engineers
induction where you say well you know I tested
it for n equals 1 and I tested it for n equals 2
and n equals 3 therefore it works for all n but
the fact of the matter is a lot of our software
generalizes really well despite the fact that it
wasn't uh proven to to do so another thing that
we really like about programming is modularity
and encapsulation this ability to take pieces
of functionality that are very uh that are very
complex and hide them under simple interfaces such
that we don't need to master all the complexity
of the underlying piece of code to be able to
use it in different contexts and what this also
means is that different parts of the code have
well-defined responsibilities if something fails
we know roughly where in the code to look for that
failure and to fix it we can localize these
behaviors to individual parts of the code and
this also means that we can develop functionality
incrementally uh software uh gains functionality
becomes more complex over time and we can have a
certain amount of confidence that when we add some
functionality that other pieces of functionality
are going to be okay they're not going to just
uh uh catastrophically forget how to do uh some
particular functionality and so all of these are
things that we like about programming that when we
are in this fully datadriven mode where we're just
letting the data um tell the system how we want it
to behave we might not get all of these features
on the other hand uh deep learning for example
has this amazing property that it's able to just
turn data into functions completely automatically
without the need for prior knowledge uh there's
this phrase that you see and you hear often in the
machine learning community let the data speak for
itself let's not try to go in with all our biases
and all our wrong ideas about how to do things
let's just gather lots of data and let the data
speak for itself so both of these worlds have
their advantages and one of the big questions that
we've been asking in the past few years is how can
we bring both of them together to get a lot of the
benefits from the datadriven approach but also get
a lot of the benefits of traditional software
and it turns out that these capability to have
machines write code for us uh this capability
of program synthesis can actually be a really
important uh step in that direction so how might
that look like so in my group we've done a lot of
work precisely on this problem how do we actually
leverage the ability of machines to write code in
order to attack problems that in principle
are learning problems and in principle they
are problems where you're trying to turn data
into functions but where you want to get many
of the benefits of traditional software so how
might that look like let me give you an example
this is from a paper that was led by uh my former
student uh Kevin Ellis who was co-advised by Joshu
Tennenbound this is a paper where uh it's as far
from software engineering as you might imagine
right in this case the idea was that we want to
build a tool to help linguists better understand
language and in particular they want to be able
to better understand language uh morphology for
example these are the kind of rules that tell you
that if you want the past tense of the word open
then you put a d at the end so that you get opened
as well as phology rules for example these are the
rules that tell you that when you want to get the
past tense of walk it's not just walked with a d
sound at the end but you have more of a t sound
at the end right walked and it turns out there
are rules in the uh the language that tell you
when you do these kind of conversions and being
able to take a language and extracting from it
those rules that tell you about the mechanics
of how this language works can enable lots of
really interesting linguistic work for example
if you want to uh study a particular dialect and
study what changed between that dialect and the
original source uh language if you have this kind
of representation uh you can actually uh explain
those differences in a very systematic way so this
is a uh this is a very important capability and
the way linguists traditionally have created those
rules is just by hand right some linguist goes and
listens to the language over uh the course of many
months tries to extract these rules that explain
how the language work well it turns out you can
actually frame this as a program synthesis problem
the idea here is that what you have is this set of
rules that you can think of them as a program that
given the stem of some word it's going to give
you as output the new form of the word uh together
with its meaning for example knowing that it's
the past tense or knowings that it's the future
tense and it turns out that all of these rules
you can think of them as a little program that
is transforming these syntactic form representing
these words and the sounds behind those words into
these new uh forms that is a program synthesis
problem for which as it turns out the program
synthesis tools that we have available to us can
allow us to actually solve this problem even for
uh real languages that people speak across
the world now I'm personally not a linguist
my expertise is in the area of program synthesis
um so I have to trust my linguist colleagues that
this is actually a uh description about some
of the rules behind Somali and how different
um stems are transformed into the different forms
of these words but what's exciting is that by
framing this as a program synthesis problem we
don't just learn from the data but we're able to
capture those formalisms that linguists know and
understand and are familiar with and we're able
to generate this very clear clean representations
of the knowledge that we're extracting from these
corpus of words so this is an example of the
kind of benefits that you can get when you
treat what in principle is just a uh problem of
learning from data as a program synthesis problem
but there's a broader class of techniques that
you can bring to the table to really get this
full combination between the kind of symbolic
reasoning that is embodied in something like the
example that I just showed and the deep learning
that makes many of these things possible and in
fact even in tasks where your final goal is simply
to learn some neural network to perform a task
bringing in some of these insights from how we
create software bringing in this insights from
the programming world can actually allow you to
do some really interesting things so let me show
you a couple of examples of how this can look like
and I'm going to be focusing in particular on this
problem of modularity how do we learn models
that have modular structure and why might you
actually want to do this so I'm going to start by
this uh work this is uh and this was led by uh my
graduate student uh Megan uh co-advised in in this
case with my colleague and collaborator Vochic uh
Matusk so the idea here was that we were taking
as the starting point these um actually really
cool uh uh paper that u um uh Voyek uh had uh had
been working on from before of these uh rubber and
being able to learn these little uh uh modular
robots that are built from uh different parts to
accomplish simple tasks and so one of the problems
that you have is let's say that you have here this
uh this little four-legged robot and you've
learned using reinforcement learning a controller
for this robot but then you decide that for the
task that you're trying to accomplish two legs are
not enough right you actually uh four legs are not
enough you need six legs and the problem is that
this controller was specifically made for this
four-legged robot right if you try to use it for
the six-legged robot it doesn't even type check
it doesn't even have outputs for all the legs
on the other hand if we could break down this
controller into these modular controllers that
can control each of these robot segments
and then have simply this higher level
uh control that coordinates the behavior of these
two modules then expanding to these new robots
would be relatively simple we would be able to
reuse the learned controllers that we have for
each of these assemblies we would now have three
copies instead of two and the only thing we would
have to learn is the new coordination mechanism
for these three set of legs right and the idea
is that by reducing this functionality we can
train this new version of the robot with a lot
less effort than what it would take to train from
scratch what's the challenge well the challenge
is that deep learning and deep neural networks
don't really like to be told what to do what do
I mean by that i can decide that I want each of
these uh modules to take care of the behavior of
the legs and that this controller is going to
be uh only doing very high level orchestration
of the motion and coordination between these two
modules and the sensors but in reality if I don't
have any control over the learning process then
there's no guarantee that that's actually what
I'm going to learn and in particular there's going
to be two important failure modes here maybe I end
up with a global controller that does too much
right maybe these control all it's doing is just
passing the signal through that this controller
had to figure out completely from scratch and not
doing anything actually useful that would be
kind of a problem because the whole scheme is
based on the fact that learning only the global
coordination should be easier than learning the
whole thing from scratch but if these modules
are not actually doing anything useful then
this is just going to be learning everything from
scratch with extra steps it's not what we want uh
on the other hand we could also be in a situation
where these modules are so over specialized for
this particular configuration that they're not
even listening to anything that this module says
they're just each doing their thing and happens to
work for this particular situation but it doesn't
generalize when we try to port it to a different
geometry or even to a different task turns out
that this second problem is a little bit easier
to address by controlling how much visibility
each one of these mod modules has to um sensors
that are controlling the the robot but the real
issue that we have to contend with is this first
issue right how do we enforce a good partition
so that these modules are actually forced to do
something and the idea here is that by enforcing
that we want the signal to effectively be a
lowdimensional signal we force these modules to
actually be uh taking responsibility for a lot of
the complexity in the behavior of these assembly
and so one way to think about this is that there
is this interface between these two modules where
you have some latent space some set of vectors
that are um that represent the different uh
configurations and then you have the action space
where the that actually captures the signals that
are being given to each of the actuators in the
robot right and so what you want is that this
latent space which has to be highdimensional uh in
order to get good training efficiency nevertheless
should have the property that it only maps to a
very lowdimensional manifold in the action space
uh because what we want is the that module that
is doing the mapping from this latent space to the
action space to actually learn how to constrain
the behavior of those um of those legs or of those
uh robot parts right so uh to view it a different
way suppose that you have this little uh robot arm
with lots of segments and so you want a mapping
from these latent space to the uh space uh of each
one of these actuators you want this mapping to be
such that if I move these uh these points a little
bit I'm going to get you know a slightly different
position for these actuators but it's not going to
do something completely crazy right it's not
going to just give me completely different
um uh behavior for for the arm because we want to
force we want this module to actually learn how to
keep the behavior within the space of reasonable
behaviors for those legs and it turns out that
the way we can do that is by directly enforcing
this property that small perturvations are going
to have a small effect on the behavior of uh of
this robot and it turns out that if we look at the
effect that that has on learning it's actually
quite uh quite substantial so here for example
we see some transfer experiments where in this
case we go from um six legs to 12 legs in this
case we go from uh six legs to 10 legs we even
have an experiment with a claw where we go from
four fingers to five fingers and we can see that
the red line here shows the performance if you're
just trying to train a controller from scratch
compared to the purple line using our approach
where you're seeing the effect of relying on these
model on these modules that have been pre-trained
in this way and so just like in software we can
take our reusable modules in in a program and
use them in a new context and expect them to uh
work we see that by doing this we can actually
train these modules in order to do uh good job
when they get transferred to a new situation
what is really exciting though to me is that the
same idea that you can use to you know get some
training efficiency when you're transferring
from one robot to another can also help us
actually understand how cells process RNA this
is uh this is really exciting and uh this is a
joint project with our collaborators uh at uh the
biology department here at MIT chris Burge and
uh Phil uh Sharp are the faculty members and
they uh we started collaborating with them
because they were very interested in this problem
of how RNA splicing works so basically in your in
every single cell in your body you have your DNA
that then gets copied into a sequence of RNA and
but before that sequence of RNA goes and leaves
the nucleus and it's used to uh produce a protein
there are these segments of the RNA sequence that
are called introns that are just removed so the
RNA sequence is divided into this parts of the
RNA sequence called exxons that are maintained and
these parts of the sequence that are removed and
this is a process that is common to all ukarots
to all u cells that have uh nuclei and it's really
important helping cells produce the wide variety
of proteins that they need in order to live but
one of the big questions in biology is exactly
how does the mechanism work the mechanism that
identifies the exact points where this sequence
has to be cut and where the pieces that have to
be removed in order to construct a new sequence
so back in 2019 there was a big breakthrough when
uh there was this uh paper published in uh cell
that showed that you could train a uh a deep uh
convolutional neural network to predict with over
90% accuracy just given a sequence of DNA or uh
given a sequence of RNA all the places where these
sequence was going to be uh spliced and um
you know this uh this was a pretty significant
uh breakthrough but it came with a little
bit of a caveat right and the caveat is that
uh the model is making these predictions but
we don't actually know what it is that it's
looking at in making the predictions so maybe
the neural network has figured out splicing but
we have not figured out splicing right and you
might say well who cares right if the model is
really good at making these predictions who cares
that it can't explain it to us right we know that
biology is very complicated anyway so maybe even
if it tried to explain it we couldn't understand
it so why bother with explanability but it
turns out that in this domain explanability
is actually really important and to understand why
we need to understand a little bit about how this
process works right so you have this sequence
of RNA and you have these two locations where
it has to be spliced where it has to be uh cut
and so it turns out that there are these very
distinctive motifs these very distinctive little
sequences of RNA that are identified by these um
molecular machinery that binds to those locations
and helps cut the RNA the problem though is that
these sequences are a little bit distinctive
but not fully distinctive and so in particular
you have lots of other locations where the exact
same sequences show up but they are not actually
splice sites right people call them cryptic sply
sites so how does the cell know which ones are the
real ones where those u molecules are supposed
to attach and which ones are the fake ones that
simply have to be ignored and the answer is that
there is this whole molecular machinery of other
RNA binding proteins that either uh prevent
splicing to happen at these locations or help
splicing happening at other locations and so
by the interaction of all of these proteins the
cell is able to decide where to splice and so this
brings us back to the question of interpretability
right why do we care about interpretability
well the problem is that this pure deep learning
model knows nothing about these proteins it knows
nothing about what's special about these different
uh sites it knows nothing about all the uh
uh decades of painstaking work in biology to
characterize all those different proteins and the
regions where they bind and having a model that
explains splicing in terms of these proteins would
be extremely useful because it would give us for
example targets for therapeutics right um it would
be able to explain not just that a particular
mutation is going to cause problems with splicing
but it will explain why and in explaining why it
will uh open the door potentially to therapeutics
to help uh mitigate the effects of that mutation
so we want explanability and a pure deep learning
model is not going to give it to us right and
so this is where once again we go back to the
whole motif of this talk and the whole idea of
modularity as a tool that is very important in
the context of programs and that we would like
to have in the context of this deep learning model
approach so in this case what we want is something
actually very simple we want to have instead of
just one monolithic model we want two models one
model that takes care of motif identification
of labeling the sequence with all the different
places where these RNA binding proteins are
going to attach and then a separate model that
is able to predict how these different RNA binding
proteins are going to interact with each other and
how they're going to lead to finally giving us our
splicing locations now given that biologists have
spent decades characterizing these RNA binding
proteins you would imagine that what we could
do is just take those motifs that have already
been characterized through uh these existing
um uh these existing data sets and simply plug
them in treat the output of those models that
tell you where different proteins are going to
bind as the input to the actual learned model
so in this case we don't really need modularity
we just need to train one model that instead of
taking as input the original sequence only takes
as input this information about what binds where
it turns out though that if you do that instead
of getting the over 90% accuracy that the pure
neural model gets you you only get 67% accuracy
so that tells us that there's something missing
here in the information about where these proteins
bind right and after some experimentation we found
that part of the problem is that these models have
a lot of room for improvement right and that if we
can replace them by modules that are anchored by
that original knowledge but that have the ability
to learn and to improve based on the data we can
improve that performance from uh the middle 60%
to 79% accuracy it's not quite at the level of the
90% although we have some evidence that that 90%
is partly due to the model using information that
is not actually costly related to uh splicing but
79% is still much better than the models that
are being used before but this raises a really
important question which is okay so we allowed
learning to improve each one of these individual
uh models of protein uh binding but how do we
know that we've actually learned something real
how do we know that uh our improvement in this
model reflect a real uh biology and not simply
these now learned modules figuring out how to
sneak information down to this model in a way
that is not really uh biologically uh feasible
well it turns out that uh that we can actually
do that and um and we actually have a series of
experiments where we were able to show um that uh
that indeed these models are doing better not just
at giving us that end to-end performance but at
predicting other kinds of experimental data about
the binding properties of these molecules right so
just to summarize there are these big data sets
uh for these RNA bind and seek experiments that
capture a lot of information about the specific
sequences that each one of these uh proteins
binds to and so we have this initial set of raw
data from which these motifs were trained and now
the way our approach works is that it starts it
takes this as a starting point combines them with
end to end data about the splicing mechanism and
from that you get this adjusted motifs that then
um when the output of these is passed to this uh
aggregator that computes the interactions between
these molecules we get a prediction about those
splicing locations so one of the questions to ask
is what if we now compare these adjusted models
against the original models on these initial
data the data that was used to train this initial
set of models and what we find is that there is
essentially no impact on how well these models
match these data relative to these in other
words what we're seeing here is that just this
data was not rich enough to fully pin down the
binding behavior of these models because what we
have here is two different models that match these
data equally well and yet one of them is giving us
significantly better endtoend performance than the
other but the real test is what happens when we
take data from a very different set of experiments
collected with completely different experimental
methodology that still aims to capture the binding
behavior of these molecules and suddenly what we
see is that the models that were adjusted with the
end-to-end splicing data actually perform um uh
significantly better on these particular set of
experimental data compared to the original motifs
right so this gives us stronger evidence that the
improvements that we're seeing here are really due
to better characterizing the binding behavior of
these molecules relative to the original models
that um that were used by uh by the biologist
so this is an example of how by bringing in some
of these insights that started out from how do we
make learning a little bit more like programming
uh can actually help us in identifying some of
these places where uh by learning a model that
has some of these modularity properties we can
get some of these benefits of interpretability
for example in this case that in turn can help
us gain a better understanding of a biological uh
system and so what we see here is really just the
beginning of how we might uh walk towards these
uh synergy between traditional programming and
the kind of ideas and techniques that we have
uh built up through traditional programming that
enable us to build uh complex programs and complex
uh applications and how we can apply them to these
broader class of problems where our interest
is not necessarily on software engineering our
interest is on getting a robot um to do a task
our interest is in understanding these mechanisms
inside each of our uh cells so you know going back
to the very beginning of uh of the talk automation
has really gone a very long way from where it was
at the time when Alan Turing gave uh his quote and
yet we can see the spirit of his quote very much
alive here lots of aspects of programming that
over the years have been very very uh tedious have
been automated away and we're seeing yet another
iteration of this big wave of automation coming
our uh way and yet um the challenge of for example
deciding what our software will do is not going
to go away right and what we'll see is programming
will evolve But it won't be eliminated and in
fact many of the ideas and many of the concepts
that make our uh software engineering world uh
work can actually find interesting and powerful
uses in other domains and in other settings where
the goal is very far from software engineering
and so with that I want to u open up to
uh answer questions from the audience
armando thank you so much that was really um
a tool the force um so let me start by asking
um let me start by asking uh some um some broad
questions so how is the programming paradigm
changing so can you can you summarize for us so
we've seen a very interesting example in robotics
we saw a very interesting example um in um biology
how should we think about this changing paradigm
of uh programming if I I'm in a different field
or even if I'm in computer science and I want to
uh I want to write a program for my class or for
a for for the so for a software engineering task
what yeah so so that's a very good question I
think one of the things that is going to one of
the things that is going to happen and and we're
already seeing uh some of these is we have these
huge variety of tools that we can bring to bear
for these uh for these programming problems and
each of these tools has different strengths they
have different uh weaknesses there's going to be
a lot of programming that we do today that is
fairly uh tedious and fairly routine and that
can be pretty easily automated away with a lot of
these uh a lot of these uh uh very powerful models
that we have available to us there's also going
to be the kind of programming that is very unique
and very specialized and that looks very different
from anything that anybody has done uh before and
where you're solving challenging programming tasks
that potentially people might not even be able
to solve manually uh themselves and I think for
those kinds of problems programming is now going
to be about how do we orchestrate these enormous
amount of computing power that we have available
to us right how do we set things up so that the
machines can actually help us um uh brute force
our way through the parts of the problem that are
aminable to brute force but also leveraging higher
level insights about what's automatable what's
not automatable and where um we need to uh come in
there's also going to be and there already
is a lot of uh teaching by example right
where a big part of it is less about how do we um
deal with the low-level nuts and bolts of of what
we're trying to do and more about how do we get
all the right uh data but also how do we set up
the training process so that we can learn what we
need to learn efficiently and um without wasting
enormous amounts of um of resources so I think
what we're going to see is uh many different forms
of programming that are all at their core going to
h rely on very much the same foundational computer
science skills that um we rely on today but that
are going to be able to take much better advantage
of vast amounts of of computing power and of these
very powerful models that we have available to
So um following in this um in this line I wonder
if we if we go back to the robotics example so
in the robotics example what you have argued
is that um now if we understand what uh what
some of the primitives for the robot might be
then we can kind of train those primitives and
then we can compose them to create a higher level
uh program correct um yeah so um and and so you
have shown a very interesting example for legged
locomotion but how should I think about that if
I want locomotion but my robot doesn't have legs
if my robot has is a snake or is um so should we
think about it um according to architectural
templates or according to tasks so that's a
really good question and I think the answer is uh
you know just like in software engineering a core
aspect of software engineering is how do I uh what
is the right level of modularity for my task right
and what are the right reusable abstractions that
I should build my um system around I think we're
going to want to start thinking about some of
these learning tasks in similar ways um what are
the right uh reusable components and and reusable
abstractions i want to go back to this uh video
that I had in the beginning that I didn't really
have a chance to um talk very much about this is a
um this is from a different project but with
similar goals where what we're trying to learn in
this case are actually modular environment models
that allow you to uh train this little robot in
this hybrid environment that combines in this
case water and land and have the model uh have
the system learn a model of the environ ment that
is explicitly modular that explicitly separates
the water model from the land model without having
to teach it oh this is water this is land simply
by having it explore the environment and so it
turns out that in uh in a context like this having
those modular environment models can help you
uh very easily adapt to to different environment
configurations because you don't have to learn um
the environment uh from scratch you can uh you can
actually rely on these pre-learned uh models very
very um efficiently so I think there's still a lot
to explore and a lot to learn about exactly how we
leverage these ability to learn uh in a modular uh
way what I've shown here are just some examples
of how you might be able to uh leverage that so
the human is the designer is still in charge of
um of specifying the uh the abstractions and the
modular the modules and then the idea is for um
for the system to take each of those abstractions
and map it onto some solution that could then be
um could then be generalized to slightly different
geometry but also with some limits um to how much
generalization there can be correct yes exactly so
um okay well everyone please put your questions in
the chat or raise your um uh your virtual hand and
uh let's see we have some questions from the
audience how does this relate to neuroeolution
to the neuroeolution algorithm so uh Bavesh
Nikra is asking this question so there has
been a lot of work over the years on uh
using evolutionary algorithms to evolve
um to evolve neural networks in in some ways the
the idea there is that the evolutionary algorithm
is just another optimization algorithm that has
different performance characteristics relative to
the standard um relative to the standard uh deep
learning uh uh toolkit um in this case though what
we have here is um a little bit different
from that in that we are uh we are actually
doing for the optimization just very standard uh
gradientbased um optimization but we're finding
other ways of introducing structure into the
uh into the process um you could argue that uh
evolutionary algorithms for example could play an
important uh role given also their their ability
to deal with these combinations of uh continuous
and discrete um uh optimization for example but
I think it's orthogonal to the idea of introducing
modularity and structure into the learning process
okay uh Daniel Windam is asking "As
AI capabilities progress what kinds
of design decisions do you predict will
be effectively deferred to AI versus
uh will rely on human engineering collaborators
and why?" So that's a very good question um one
of the things that at least uh at the moment
seems to be a uh pretty significant difference
between AI models and humans is the way in
which they can take in brand new knowledge
and incorporate that brand new knowledge into
um into what uh what they're doing right so the
models right now are very very good at the sorts
of tasks that come straight from their training
corpus right and for which they have enormous
amounts of training data in their corpus the
moment you leave the bounds of the kinds of tasks
that they've been trained very extensively on
uh now you're having to rely on in context
learning you're having to rely on uh you know
uh uh prompting and suddenly their ability to
incorporate that new knowledge that comes from
uh the prompt is severely diminished compared to
um compared to what people uh can do so in general
tasks that rely on assembling lots of different
knowledge that is not publicly available and that
was not uh present when when the models were
trained I think are less likely to be easily
uh and taken over by um taken over by by the
models that's that's just one uh dimension right
now on the other hand some of the things that
they bring to the table is lots of knowledge about
um the world right and lots of knowledge
about the um uh literature for example in
uh in a wide variety of uh of tasks and I think
finding ways to leverage that knowledge deal with
some of the uh flakiness that uh with which
they're sometimes um uh coming i think this
is a really important uh area in terms of uh
really getting the most out of these models
uh Armando while uh while our audience
uh is thinking about more questions uh
I'm also wondering how does this how
should we tie this into vibe coding
so I think again if if you're dealing with the
kind of task that is very easy to check with
the kind of task that is very um um routine uh
that looks a lot like things that other people
have done uh before then you can get a very high
degree of automation and um you can actually do uh
do pretty well right it's it's when you're dealing
with the tasks where for example establishing the
uh the correctness requires more than simple
uh test suites for example the kind of tasks
that require uh uh specialized uh knowledge
and especially the kind of tasks that require
knowledge that is not publicly available
out on the uh the internet that's where
you really have to uh that's where the
models uh really uh stop being as useful
we actually have um we actually have a new
survey that we just put out uh last month
uh where we discuss the broad landscape
of AI tools for software engineering and
identify some of the remaining gaps around some
of the things that uh are still very much open
questions in terms of really fulfilling the
promise of automation that uh we think these
uh these tools can can eventually fulfill
thank you Armando so Bob Blazer asks um the
chart showing reduced training considered examples
from four or more components to larger numbers but
to have reached four coordinated components the
controller must have already been well modularized
does the same technique work in generalizing from
one or two controllers to three or four that's a
very good question so the the smaller the number
of controllers that you initially start with the
harder it's going to be for these uh these to
generalize right and and I should emphasize there
has been prior work around learning uh modular
uh control that has achieved this by training
these models on many different contexts and with
many different configurations with uh very large
uh numbers of copies of these components the
more you have uh the more context where you
use these components the easier it's going to be
to generalize and one of the challenges that we
uh tackle in this particular paper is to see how
far can we push in terms of starting from very
very from essentially a single example of a single
robot with very small number of instances of these
uh of these controllers right because this is
the kind of task that you're going to run into if
you know you don't have a whole stable of robots
that that you've trained on but you just finished
building and training your robot and you just want
to make the small adjustments to them amazing um
well uh Armando with these words of wisdom uh I
just want to ask you one more question should we
still learn how to program yes in fact um one of
the things you could argue is that programming
is going to become significantly more useful in
in the future right um you know in the past one
of the things uh we've told people uh as to
why they should learn to program is not just
the fact that you know there's plenty of software
engineering jobs out there but also the fact that
anytime you're interacting with a computer right
knowing how to program gives you the possibility
of automating things that you would otherwise have
to do by hand now in practice that hasn't been so
true all along right the pain of writing code and
debugging it and getting it right it's often such
that for many things for which you could write the
program you just don't it's too painful it's too
hard but now suddenly that the barrier has lowered
um it uh that possibility becomes significantly
more useful however uh programming languages are
going to remain the most precise way that we have
for describing computation and so any time that
we have to have precision we're going to have
to have a programming language somewhere in there
in the middle and whether it's written by a human
or whether it's written in collaboration with a
machine that skill of being able to reason about
uh code is going to and to be able to think
in terms of code is going to remain essential
okay everyone so uh let's go back to our our
coding lessons um what uh what languages should
we learn or like what what do you think um
we we need to know at this point in time
i think the language the specific language is
a lot less uh a lot less essential than uh you
know just having a language that that you know so
well that you can think in terms of this language
and where you can internalize some of those
abstractions and you can and you don't uh you
don't have to translate in your head between your
thoughts and uh and the programming language in
fact one of the one of the things that for which
I think these models are probably going to get
much better in the near future is actually going
to be translating from one language to u uh to the
other so the notion of writing a prototype in one
language and then uh scaling it up in in another
one is probably going to become much more uh
feasible in uh in the near uh future so I I can't
let this go i'm sorry i um I'm having too much
fun we It used to be that uh the early programmers
learned machine language and then we went to
assembly and then we went to um what we used
to call as highle programming languages and now we
have all the AI languages and ultimately we want
to speak with a machine in natural language so um
so where's the so so how do you see this path how
do you see the gap from being able to um talk to
our machines in natural language um as a way of
um of sketching the um the outline of the program
and and really getting the program then we can do
some of that with vibe coding but uh in a kind
of a limited way right well so one of the things
about natural language is that it's actually
very ills suited for thinking at scale right
uh natural language is great when we're having
a conversation and we want to uh you know convey
some ideas quickly uh between us but uh you know
if you think about for example law is a pretty
good example of a setting where you have to do
language at scale and it really breaks down right
uh legal ease is uh uh you know it kind of looks
like English but it's not really English right and
it's uh it's its own different language because
you have this such uh extreme uh precision that is
required and even that is pretty awful compared to
the programming languages that uh that we have now
one of the ways in which programming languages
have gotten very good over the years is their
ability to build reusable uh abstractions right
and their ability to take uh functionality and
package it up and uh deploy it in uh in ways that
basically mean that you only have to write things
once uh that is already something that makes uh
modern programming very uh very powerful now the
question one of the things that is challenging
about existing programming languages and where
I think the models can really help is that before
uh we had this models programming languages had to
serve two purposes right they had to help you
write but they also had to help you read and
these two had very uh uh different uh constraints
right when you're writing you want something that
is brief and succinct and um that um you know you
can get through lots of code very very quickly um
by contrast when you're reading you want to have
all the information uh there and you don't want
to have to jump around all over the place in order
to understand how a piece of code uh works i think
with these models we have an opportunity to break
the connection between these uh these two things
right to to write in ways that are quick and dirty
and simple and then have the model help us expand
and make that thing readable and uh and make it
so that five years down the road when somebody
else is trying to understand what this code
is doing it's actually uh understandable so
I think there's there's a lot that the models
can do uh for us without necessarily having to
uh change the the underlying um uh representation
that uh that we rely on today in terms of of code
thank you so much Armando uh we will keep
this wisdom in the back of our minds uh I
will still aspire to be able to speak
in natural language to my computer and
um and uh I want to talk with you more
about that with that let's thank Armando and
um see you at the next CSAIL Forum have a great
afternoon everyone bye-bye thank you everyone bye