Thank you Jo for the invitation. It's
really a pleasure to be here. I know
many people in the audience interacted
with many people over the years and it's
fun to be here and talk about these
subjects something near and dear to my
heart heart uh safe autonomy and in the
intro I I like the the the the ratio of
demos to theorems. So you can count in
this there are theorems and there are
demos. So we'll see what the ratio ends
up being. But that's kind of the goal is
how do we formally approach robotics and
and before I begin any talk I really
need to point out my students and
posttos uh they're the instrumental
element of this entire presentation. The
videos wouldn't exist without them. The
theorems by and large wouldn't exist
without them. So they really make
everything go. All right. So I don't
think I need to say that we're in the
moment of the humanoids, right? Everyone
knows this. Everyone sees every other
day. I at first I used to update the
videos and then I just stopped because
if I tried to grab the video of the
moment of the dancing robot of the
moment, I just couldn't keep up. But
it's really incredible what's happened
in the last like, you know, year or two
in terms of humanoid robots and the way
they're being deployed and the behaviors
we're seeing. It's honestly mind-blowing
from someone who back in the day I did
like little simple planer walking robots
and it actually would go viral, right?
And now we're in a we're in a different
era. Uh and so of course this extends to
my lab. I have a humanoid, a G1 like
many people have now. This was back in
January and I like showing this video
because this was just a couple days
after we got the robot in our lab and we
I was doing a demo here and there's a
bunch of people standing off camera and
the robot was walking and my student
Gary told me during the demo that he was
running our locomotion policy in this
case an RL policy and I was shocked that
he got it working in like two days and
it was demo worthy. So this translation
of getting things to actually go on
hardware nowadays is incredibly fast. Of
course, in my lab, we're really
interested in where our heritage is. And
what you'll see in this talk is
modelbased control methods. So, we've
been playing with this idea of
understanding pure modelbased control.
So, this is just MPC for humanoid
locomotion. Zero learning involved. And
this is an RL policy, sort of the
standard RL policy. None of this was
sort of published, but and you can see
that we're trying to understand kind of
how do these two things relate to one
another uh in the lab. And that's really
been what this talk is about now is kind
of the last sort of year of
soulsearching, let's say, together with
some historic context in in where
control methods can actually fit in
this. Because the reality is is when you
combine modelbased with learning based
methods, you get some really special
things. I have to admit as a modelbased
person, as a as a someone that loves
math, you cannot deny the power of
injecting math into reinforcement
learning. This is an example which I'm
going to talk about later in the talk
but this is running what we call CLF RL.
Uh so it's an example of really this
fusion and what we're able to achieve
with it. But with the injection of
learning based methods comes this sort
of
distribution shift failure mode right
that's really catastrophic. So what
happens in this video is this the robot
as you'll see in the in the next bit
when it plays in slow motion is it was
walking just fine. This is just a pure
RL policy in this case. And the the
ankles strike. So it just starts with a
self collision. That self collision
knocks the robot into a domain it wasn't
trained for. Right? You're out of
distribution and all of a sudden it just
goes crazy and it actually broke the
ankles. It was it was a mess. And if
you've ever played with robots and if
you look on the internet, you see all
these examples of robots going crazy.
It's because they're you know when you
train things on data and you deploy
things based on that trained data, you
don't really know what's going to
happen, right? Right? So the fundamental
question becomes how do we do things
like guarantee safety in this context
right what's the paradigm to guarantee
safety and how do we certify it so
that's really what this talk is about
and I'm going to make the strong
statement here that I hope to defend
throughout the presentation which is
that safety is the key bottleneck to the
deployment of AI that if we don't solve
this safety problem all the cool dancing
videos you see online of humanoid robots
will never be realized in any like real
world application domain.
So to add to this, let me sort of say
this one more way. There's two axes that
you look at with robots. There's
performance and there's safety,
robustness, reliability. Right now,
everyone is pushing the performance
axis. That's great, but it results in
very brittle behaviors that again once
you take them out of where they're
trained, they can go crazy. So we need
to enable those behaviors to be
deployed. We need to we need to remove
the friction that safety will give
ultimately in these ideas being deployed
in the real world. And my second claim
is that control theory is the way to
remove this blocker.
So this is also a strong statement and
incredibly biased from my perspective to
be very clear um because I'm a control
theorist. So of course I'm going to say
control theory is going to be the you
know enable this deployment. But I can
think I can back it up with some
evidence. In particular, this is an
example of where control theory can play
a role in what I'm going to talk about
in this talk a bit. Things like a safety
filter. You take an RL policy which you
might be able to command to do bad
things like knock over this box. You
have a safety filter which is based on
control theoretic methods. In this case,
it's a CBFQP. And this safety filter
modulates the RL algorithm to guarantee
safety without knowing what the RL
algorithm is or how it operates except
that it takes a reference signal and
tracks it. So we need to be able to deal
with control with learning in a way that
we have elements we might not be able to
fully understand that is like blackbox
elements and we need to have formal
guarantees associated with that
deployment and this will enable things
to be actually deployed in practice. So
before I go into that, I want to step
back for a second again on my history of
where I come from. I'm a modelbased
control person, right? I love Leoponov.
I love barrier. I love dynamical
systems. I love nonlinear dynamical
systems in particular. I love hybrid
system models. And this is actually now
a decade old video. So 10 years ago, and
it's still pretty good. I got to say,
sometimes we forget that good things
were done before like a year ago. And uh
this is this is full multi-dommain locom
motion on a full-scale humanoid robot
using just pure modelbased control
methods CLFS where we actually have
springs in the ankles. So we have
compliant elements at the base and we're
able to get very natural and efficient
walking. This at the time was the most
efficient locomotion ever realized on a
humanoid type robot. We've taken these
ideas and because they're they're model
based, we can extend them to other
robots. Of course, this is Cassie, which
was for a while really the only biped
robot you could buy built by Agility
Robotics, uh, who is now deploying
Digit. Uh, and we're able to apply a
very similar paradigm in that case. So,
let me kind of talk about what that is.
So, let me do like a brief fiveminute
primer or less two-minute primer on
nonlinear control because most of
nonlinear control can be really be
broken down to everything on the the
right side of this slide in a nutshell.
Right? So, you have a nonlinear system
just general nonlinear typically a fine.
And if you want to do something like
stabilize the system, what you do is
find a certificate for that stability.
In this case, the the certificate will
be something like a leoponol function or
a control leoponov function. Here I'm
using leoponov with exponential decay.
So you make sure that function satisfies
a property you want. In this case,
positive definite and that its
derivative condition with respect to
flows of the system satisfy a decay rate
that guarantees the type of stability
you want. And what this does by the
comparison lema says that this thing
decays like this. the scalar dynamical
system which is clearly stable and that
implies that that this V will actually
exponentially stabilize because it's
positive definite you know that X will
ultimately drive to your goal state or
wherever that function V is zero right
and so you have this theorem that if
there exists a CLF meaning if you have
inputs that satisfy this derivative
condition you exponentially stabilize to
the zero level set of V in this case
this is like a periodic orbit on your
walking robot right so there's this
right nice connection that if you can
find this V you get this now of course
there's great work out of MIT SOS on how
you can find V's in the case of robotic
systems you can actually use feedback
linearization to find these leoponol
functions sort of uh algorithmically
formulaically and the end result of this
process is an entire class of
controllers that stabilize a system for
which this is an example implemented on
on Cassie clean meaning this is CLF now
this works I mean this really does work
in practice Of course, there's a lot of
caveats that I don't show in these
videos. Things like state estimation
took 9 months to really pin down
properly. It's a big problem in in
realizing this stuff on robots.
Something that RL actually helps a lot
with. Um, so the question is how do we
take these ideas now and how do we
extend them or or inform learning with
the the methods for modelbased control
that prove so effective. And so this is
one example now that I showed earlier
but I want to uh focus on it's a very
recent result where we can take what we
did with CLF QPS and instead of
generating a quadratic program
controller that we put online and have
to worry about things like state
estimation like I mentioned you take
these nonlinear controllers and you use
it to generate the reward function for
RL. In this case, our reward function is
a really clean four terms basically
requiring that this is a CLF and that it
decays as a CLF should decay.
You use this in training and then you
get to use all the benefits that RL
gives you which modelbased methods sort
of don't. You can GPU parallelize and
then domain randomize. And so you can do
this massive simulation to train up the
R RL policy to basically emulate the
modelbased controller. Of course, the
advantage here is we're not emulating
human data. something that might only be
true on one trajectory, but we're
emulating this this rich dynamics that's
present in the real nonlinear dynamics
of the system itself. And when we do
this, we're actually able to deploy this
in zerootshot, meaning once we train
this up, it actually really does work
off the shelf. I'm not I'm not being
sort of facitious here. We're able to
lay this out. And not only are we going
to we're able to do things like put this
on the robot and make it walk really
cleanly all over Caltech. It never fell
once in this whole filming. It walked
all over Caltech, but we're able to
extend it to other behaviors because the
advantage of modelbased methods is they
essentially have an infinite amount of
data in them if you'd like. Right? If
data is a bottleneck for for collecting
human data from video demonstration,
etc. Modelbased methods have an infinite
amount of data. For every initial
condition, you get a trajectory. Right?
For every controller, you get a
trajectory. Right? Now, you have to find
them. That's the difference. But once
you find them, you can do lots of really
cool things. So, this is a recent result
we had with CLFRL. now for running. So
we generate same process. We generate
from a hybrid system model. We generate
a CLF. That CLF is used as the reward
function in RL. We train this up and
then deploy it. And we did this in about
two weeks from start to finish. Um and
it turns out the hardest part was
actually the fact that we have visual
odometry on the robot as well to get it
to run straight. And that visual
odometry with onboard compute and
everything was kind of the trickiest
part of this. Making a robot run is one
thing. Making it run in a straight line
is is another one. And it's actually
pretty challenging. We took it outside.
It worked the first time we took it
outside, meaning off the bat. And we
threw a bunch of stuff at it because
that's what you do with robots, right?
Disturbance testing. The point is these
modelbased methods do fuse with RL.
Well, in my opinion, and this is just
one example of sort of the the kind of
things I think we can do going forward
to take away some of the hackery of
reward shaping, right? To to bring some
formal principles. There's of course a
wealth of examples outside of my lab on
people doing principled RL including
many people here at at MIT. So,
so that's the story. Of course, with
this story comes a caveat. I started the
the the talk talking about safety being
a blocker and I haven't addressed this
at all yet. Right? So, this is the robot
now running outside doing pretty well
and then of course
we get a collision. Right? Thankfully,
it was the the the the stick holding the
camera. It wasn't a person, but this
does not have barrier functions on it.
Does not have collision avoidance,
right? And this is what I mean by safety
as a blocker, right? When when you hit
scenarios you didn't expect, you're
going to have really bad things happen.
And the problem is if this happens in
this scenario outside, it's it's kind of
okay. If this happens in your house and
your dog's around or, you know, you
don't want these kind of behaviors. This
is these these robots are actually
really scary and and it's also painful.
I don't know if you can see my face up
there, but I'm kind of cringing. I I
thought we killed the robot there. I
really did. Um, so again, I go back to
this question. How do we guarantee
safety for these systems? Right. So, I
want to step back for a second now and
and do a little history because I think
history is important. I think especially
in this day and age when there's so much
stuff on the archive every day. We
forget sometimes that no one lives in
isolation. No idea comes from nothing.
Um, there's a great quote from asthma
there on exactly this topic. And so
people have studied safety for a long
time and it goes back to actually
earlier than 1942. But Numu's theorem in
1942 is really the de facto standard on
safety. And what it says is that if you
frame safety as forward set invariance,
which is what I'm going to do throughout
this talk. We can talk about that.
There's lots of other interesting
notions of safety uh safety on latent
variables, semantic safety. There's a
whole bunch of things you can think
about. But in this case, starting
simple, we want to make sure we don't go
to bad states and we want to stay in
good states. And in that case, it turns
out that back in 1942,
Nugumu figured out necessary and
sufficient conditions for forward set
invariance. And it's a very simple
condition. If your function, if you have
a function h that defines your safe set,
it's positive on your safe set and
negative outside, then the condition is
simply that h dot must be greater than
or equal to zero on the boundary of your
safe set, right? Which makes total
sense. meaning h dot the derivative
along flows of your system, right? Which
says if you're on the boundary and if h
needs to be positive to stay in the set,
your rate of change better be positive
or at worst zero or it will go negative
and you will leave your set, right? So
it's very intuitive. Of course, proving
it requires a little bit more, but it's
very intuitive. People have used this
conditions many many times in the last
sort of you know 80 years, right? and
it's actually been rediscovered on many
occasions um including I won't say
rediscovered recently but used recently
in things like barrier certificates etc
right so this was the state-of-the-art
when I approached safety in 2014 of
course there's something fundamentally
missing about this picture if you want
to do controller synthesis
what do you do with a condition that's
only true on the boundary of your set
right
Well, yeah. So, the the answer is if I
have this condition on the boundary, I'm
going to wait until I hit the boundary.
Then I'm going to see if that condition
is satisfied or not. And if not, I'm
going to switch to another controller,
right? But the question is when do you
switch? And when you switch, is it
continuous? Is it smooth? Do you do you
maybe add some buffers in here so that
you start switching a little early? Then
how early do you switch? How does that
matter? Right? You can see how you get
to a rabbit hole very quickly. So, I
wanted to ask the simple question, well,
we shouldn't do that. we should just
have a condition that's true at every
point in the set then we don't have to
worry about waiting to get to the
boundary right so how do we find that
condition and it turns out that the
ginshin is very so again what control
option we take the condition is actually
very intuitive so the generalization is
quite simple we take numu's condition
and we just replace zero with minus
alpha class k function but think about
it as a as a as a constant if you want
of h right then of course on the
boundary you recover nuru theorem,
right? When h is zero, this says h dot
has to be greater than or equal to zero.
But inside the set, what does it say? It
says that h dot when you're inside the
set, h can be positive. So this whole
thing becomes negative. So h dot can
decrease. So you can decrease h dot away
and as you get closer, you have to sort
of slow down. Now the question is does
that give you the right behavior?
Meaning do you slow down enough? Do you
slow down too much? Right? It turns out
that you slow down just the right amount
meaning that this is necessary and
sufficient for forward set invariance as
laid out by these papers with me and
Paulo Tabatada Jesse Grizzle etc. So
this is what is now called modern-day
control barrier functions, right? And
they're surprisingly only about a decade
old now. So what do we do with this? So
once we have these conditions, we can
use them for controller synthesis. But I
want to note one thing going back to
leaponov. It turns out that barrier
functions actually generalize leoponov.
If you take your set and you contract it
to a point, you end up with a leoponov
function. But in general, barrier
functions are cover a bigger class of
behaviors because they don't have to
actually be positive definite
themselves. They only sort of have to be
positive definite with respect to the
set outside the set. So that opens up
additional behaviors meaning inside the
set you can move around freely. So again
once we have these CBFS what do we do
with them? And then the answer I think
the second sort of big thing that
happened in the last decade was this
idea of a safety filter. And this idea
came about because
actually we're given these challenge
problems where we were told actively we
could not modify the nominal controller
on the system which as a control
theorist is like the hardest thing in
the world to hear. So we were sitting at
a table with Ford and Toyota and we're
presenting a bunch of CLF work and we're
like we'd love to get these CLFs cuz I
love CLFs on a car and they looked at me
and they said that will never happen
right? Why? Well, because we know what
works on the car right now and we don't
want to change something that works,
right? If it ain't broke, don't fix it,
as they say. So, but they said, if you
can come up with a control method that
lives outside of our current
infrastructure, we'd be interested. And
that's exactly what these safety filters
do. They take any nominal controller,
find the minimal modification
subject to the safety constraint. So, of
course, this gives you kind of a switch
controller in essence. It's it's lip
shit's continuous and smooth in some
scenarios that says that if your
controller is safe, you let it pass
through and if it's not safe, you need
to minimally modify it projected to the
safe set, right? And this is an example
of that in action. So on the left you
have the nominal controller, which is
actually a really well-tuned segway
controller. And then of course my
student in this im in this video is just
joysticking it, trying to mess it up,
and he can both make it go outside of
that yellow region and knock the whole
thing over. Right. Of course. Now on the
right, you pass that exact same signal
through a safety filter and no matter
what he does, he can't knock it over get
or leave the set. Of course, we've
deployed this in lots of scenarios.
We've done obstacle avoidance. So, in
this case, you have a human pilot who's
trying to crash the drone into into
walls and they can't do it. Um, I should
also note this generalizes potential
fields, meaning you you actually get
some improved behavior over potential
fields. Uh, we've done it for multi-root
systems. This was with Magnus Aggerstat.
Um, this was actually some of the first
experiments with CBFS ever. I was at
Georgia Tech at the time and we put it
on multi-root systems for collision
avoidance. Uh, so in this case, the grad
student again is flying this drone and
trying to crash it through this this
swarm of robots and you get this kind of
virtual force field type behavior from
the CBFS.
So that's fun. And then we also put it
on really compute inensive uh scenarios.
So in this case, we have a high-speed
racing drone and we're we're doing CBFS
only on a very small bit of compute on
this with onboard uh onboard sensing. So
everything is self-contained and we're
doing geoences. So in this case, you
have these regions in space you can't
leave and the the the student in this
case is flying this thing as quick as it
can towards these geoences and the the
CBF prevents them from leaving the the
the area. Right?
this same math. And the reason I'm
showing all these videos is once you
have the math, everything just kind of
follows, right? It's like a cascade
effect. It's a waterfall effect because
this same exact method we used on this
we put on an actual jet aircraft. So,
this is an F-16. This is the Vista uh
F-16. And here we're doing geo fencing.
So, there's a region in space you don't
want to go. And at this moment in time
right here, CBFs are actually flying the
plane. So we're we're doing safety
filtering of the pilot commands to
guarantee that we don't leave the region
and we're satisfying altitude floors and
ceilings simultaneously and we're we're
satisfying um G limit constraints among
other things. So making sure we don't
have too much uh force on the pilot. So
we do can do all that together uh with a
single actually in this case a single
CBF that filters the pilot inputs. So
there's no doubt that these things apply
really generally. Um this led us to a
lot of questions though. For example,
one question that we started getting
asked a lot was what about uncertainty,
right? What do you do? Well, we have a
whole set of results on input to state
stability and input to state safety with
respect to CBFS meaning if you have some
bounded uncertainty, you can actually
still guarantee safety. But we we
realized very quickly that boundary
uncertainty is fantastic, but we can
actually extend this to unbounded
disturbances if they're stochastic
uh using stochastic CBFS. So in this
case, we we switch to discrete time
dynamical systems for which there's a
discrete time CBF condition and we have
a theorem that says that if you satisfy
this condition in expectation, you're
guaranteed to be safety uh to be
guaranteed to be safe in probability.
Meaning you can know that you have some
probability of staying within your safe
set for a finite number of steps and we
can get an upper bound to that. Uh and
we can use that to explicitly calculate
the sa the safety filter in a stochastic
setting. We can collect data. We can
sort of learn the distribution and then
from that get conditions we can actually
implement in the safety filter. And so
we do this in particular in the context
of a drone with an unknown hanging mass.
And if you've ever flown a drone and put
a hanging mass, you know it's a very
hard problem to keep that drone flying.
And we did it in the context of
geofencing. So in this case, the
students trying to fl uh to slam the the
drone into the ground. And the
stochastic uh safety filter is making
sure that that doesn't happen based on
the data we collected. And the in this
case in particular we updated the
reduced order model to account for that
learned
uh element. So we can extend it to these
uncertainty situations. Um this is one
where we then take that idea and fold it
into perception in the loop. So now
we're doing onboard perception. So you
can see the viewpoint of the drone and
there's balls coming at it and it has to
avoid it. Again, same framework as I
implemented before or I discussed before
but now we're doing this with perception
in the loop.
And here's another example with
perception in the loop, but now we do it
to a quadriped. So the lesson here again
is we first had CBFS and now we have CBS
with stochastic uncertainty for example
due to model uncertainty, perception
uncertainty and we can fold all that
together in a stochastic framework. So
in doing this we realized a couple
things. First, we realized if we just do
a safety filter like I talked about
before, it's not as expressive as you
might hope because there are because
remember safety filters are sort of
pointwise optimal, but they're not
globally optimal, right? So, if you if
you do MPC without a safety filter, you
find kind of the inverse. It's
expressive. So in this case the the
quadriped tries to avoid the ball but
because you're doing just a state
constraint you don't have enough
predictive power at that state
constraint level. So doing a bunch of
experiments in this space we discovered
that MPC plus CBFS is a really powerful
paradigm.
So everything I presented previously was
if you have this one layer control
architecture and now we're going to
bring multiple layers together. Okay. So
let's see how that kind of works. So, by
the way, this is a video I just took in
my lab the other day. I went down to the
lab and the robot was on. This was not
pre-planned. We're not trying to do
anything fancy here. And I think
sometimes just showing the raw
experiments really give you a sense of
what these algorithms actually look
like. So, it's
by putting all these pieces together,
doing MPC plus CBFS, we're we're
starting to get into a very strange
uncanny valley now, right?
It starts to like pe now when we do lab
tours, people actually start to feel
sorry for the robot. They think it's
it's getting its feelings hurt and they
want to pet it. I'm not kidding you.
Which is weird because previously they
would always be scared of the robot,
right? And if you can make people feel
sorry for a robot, you're actually, I
think, doing your job well because
they're no longer scary, right? Uh so
we're starting to see this real
improvement. And this this actually
hurts back to work that we did a long
time ago. So we've been doing this for
many years where we saw that when we
layer these things together, we get
better behavior, we get improved
performance. So this goes to the second
thread that I've sort of been on in the
last 5 years in my lab, which is this
notion of layered control architectures.
So Giola and me both have done many
workshops now on this, talking about how
this is a really important secret sauce
um to making robots work, and it really
is. I want to show an example of this.
There's no barrier functions here. This
is an MPC together with a really good
controller. And to me, this is this is
one of my students, null, did this. This
is just really good control.
I mean, this is he's doing a geometric
NPC layer on top of it. But this is my
favorite video. One of my favorite
videos of all time from the lab. This is
a custom hopping robot that he makes hop
literally across this plank.
That is precise control to hop along a
plank that's this big. Right? And again,
what enabled this precise control?
layered control architectures, right? So
understanding, so I started with CBFS
and then we started doing this and
realizing that there's something really
special here because once you have these
layered architectures, they they're
actually really robust. You can take the
robot outside, can hop in lots of
scenarios. Um, this is the cannon you
guys stole. I put this video in because
anybody know the story. MIT stole that
cannon from Caltech. They dressed up as
security guards and then they came on
Caltech campus, stole the cannon and
they reassembled it on top of one of the
buildings here. Yeah. Okay. So, that was
the cannon. We got it back though. I
don't know how, but we got it back. So,
it's still there. All right. And so, we
can also start to do some interesting
things like add safety layers back in.
But now, we can do safety not at this
low-level control, but actually at a
higher level using simple reduced order
mocks. Right? So what I mean is we can
start with really good controllers and
in this case we're doing a safety layer
on top of them because this is a
complicated controller that has multiple
agent interaction with a fixed thing. So
it's a really hard control problem but
we can just add the safety layer on top
of it and get the whole thing to be safe
kind of out of the box.
So So what's happening here? Well, I'm
going to give you guys the secret sauce
to implementing CBFS on hardware if
you're interested. And it's it's exactly
this layered control. So I showed you
nonlinear dynamics earlier and that's a
lot of fun. But let's step back for a
second and just say let's suppose we
have some reduced order model and then
we want to put a safety filter on that
reduced order model and that's going to
feed into some full order dynamics. This
full order dynamic model is being run by
some controller that tracks that
reference. We don't care what this is.
This can be a policy, an RL policy. This
can be a VA. I don't really care. All I
know is that whatever it is, I needs to
take velocity as a reference. That's it.
And then I'm going to have my own
controller sitting up there, my own
internal reduced order model that I'm
going to use for the safety filter. So
think about it like this. Every element
of an autonomy stack has its own model.
If it's RL, that model was a simulator.
If it's a safety filter, you're probably
going to have some simple sort of maybe
kinematic model. And in this scenario,
you can formally guarantee safety
without knowing what's happening down
here.
What I mean and this is the theorem is
that if you have sufficiently good
tracking, so that's what's up here. If
you have in this case exponential
tracking
uh of this reduced order of this full
order model, oops, too many slides. If
you have sufficiently fast exponential
tracking, then you're guaranteed that
your system is safe. Meaning the full
order dynamics of your system is safe
buffered a little bit by this tracking
error. Even if all you have is a reduced
order model generating reference
signals. Okay, make sense? And how does
this work? I mean, this this kind of
blows my mind the first time we figured
this out, which was about 2022. Take
your reduced order model to be the
single integrator, simplest system
imaginable, right? Take your barrier
function to be don't hit obstacles in
the environment. Then your CBF becomes
this. And this is your safety filter,
which is literally like I'm writing it
down. It's like two lines of code. Put
that safety filter on a quadriped and
just modulate the joystick command, you
get collision avoidance. Right?
Take that exact same controller, put it
on a drone as a reference command, you
get collision avoidance,
right? So understanding these layers
mean you can really rapidly develop
things. And of course, you can change
the reduced order model. you can put
like a unicycle model on the on the
quadriped and do the same sort of you're
going to get a more complicated safety
filter, but the same thing applies.
So, of course, there's trade-offs here.
I mean, if you use a simple reduced
order model, you're going to get fairly
conservative behavior. It'll guarantee
safety, but it will be kind of
conservative. The better reduced order
model, the less conservative the
behavior will be, right? But this works
in a lot of scenarios. So, we did this
on a manipulator. So in this case our
barrier function is actually assigned
distance function with every point in
the environment for which we generate
our we have a simple just single
integrator reduced order model which we
pass as a reference velocity to the
low-level control on the manipulator.
And the one thing the one caveat here is
because the sign distance function is
not smooth. We had to find a smooth
approximation which gave you a small gap
that you had to account for in the CBF
condition as a delta. I say this because
it turns out that my my final sort of
theory piece on this is you have to pay
attention to the deltas here. These
matter a lot. What I mean is if you try
to do a reduced order model without a
delta on really complicated systems, you
actually can get safety violations.
And the reason why you can get safety
violations even though it's it doesn't
look minor is because exactly this the
tracking controller sort of we prove
that you get sta stability of a slightly
enlarged safe set when you have a
tracking controller. If you don't
account for that enlarged safe set
you're going to get slight violations.
So if you want to make things better you
got a buffer with a delta. So this
actually leads to input to state safety
and a whole bunch of beautiful math that
was in a bunch of papers if you're
interested on how you can robustify the
implementation of reduced order models
in this way by picking better deltas.
And in fact there's a theorem that says
this works. So I want to be sort of
explicit what what it fundamentally
means is before without a delta if you
have this tracking okay you need to have
exponential tracking all the way down to
zero to guarantee safety which is never
in practice true. What the delta gives
you is the ability to replace this
condition with bounded tracking which
any real system you'll have bounded
tracking. Right? So then you can recover
this this theorem that the full order
dynamics is safe even if you only have
these reduced order dynamics as long as
you add a delta accordingly in essence.
And that delta led to a lot of
interesting things like collision
avoidance locomotion this hopping robot
doing collision avoidance. So we've been
able to really study this in a lot of
different contexts. what the role of
delta is. Okay. So, so that's the story.
So, that's the layered architecture
story.
So, what do we do with all of this stuff
I presented to you so far, right? How do
we handle all of these pieces? So, let
me sort of recalibrate for one second
because I know I can kind of it's always
hard for me to give talks because I love
all the work we did in the lab so much.
I want to tell you about all of it and I
have to kind of like step back and only
tell you pieces and and and so I already
told you a bunch of pieces but why does
this matter to the original problem I
posed? So let's go back to humanoid
robots now. Now the videos I showed at
the beginning of the talk they had a
bunch of subtext in them that I didn't
that at the time you probably didn't
catch or maybe you did. First what model
were we using for the safety filter?
Right? Was I doing a forward or dynamic
model with all the joints like nonlinear
model for the safety filter? No. What
model was I using? The answer is
actually on the slide.
Single integrator. There it is. Single
integrator safety filter on the humanoid
robot. And this is the behavior you get.
It looks super dynamic, right? To
imagine a single integrator gives that
kind of behavior. Why? Because you
actually have really good controllers
below the surface. In this case, this is
actually um Unit's uh RL walking
controller, which is actually pretty
good, of course, as you know. So, the
better the controller gets down below,
the better our safety filters get, even
with reduced order models. And now we of
course know from the second part of the
talk that we actually get a formal
guarantee of safety on this full order
system even though we're only using a
single integrator reduced order model.
So, we have a theorem that says this
thing will actually be safe, right?
There's one other piece I didn't talk
about though yet that we have to fold
into the picture.
Anybody have any idea what that is?
What's the missing piece?
I talked about the models. I talked
about how I'm implementing. So you could
should get a pretty good sense. It's
actually the clue's on there.
>> No, the learning is sitting here. I'll
talk again about learning and we can do
this with CLFRL2. That's you know we're
sort of platform agnostic. It's sitting
on the board right and sitting on the TV
right there. Perception. How do we
handle the perception component? So
that's the last bit that's made a huge
difference. In fact, I'm going to make a
statement here that's pretty strong.
Perception is in many ways and how you
handle perception in many ways much more
important than the model you use for a
safety filter.
Single integrator model with really good
perception handling makes all the
difference. What do I mean by this?
What's happening here? So this is
actually a recent result that was at RSS
this year, but I I really like it a lot.
It's really beautiful. What we can do is
take perception data whether it's liar
or camera it doesn't matter we can solve
and this was this was a result of my
students and posttos where they came up
with this idea of solving pson's
equation a PTE and they can do this in
real time at faster than a kilo hertz
super fast to build a single functional
representation of the environment that's
smooth for any number of obstacles so
much better than sign distance function
and the end result this is where a
single obstacle You can do it with many.
This is your sign. This is your pos
safety function as we call it. Of
course, positive means you're safe. And
as the ball rolls through the scene, you
get this negative bit which is unsafe.
And then of course, we're also have a a
safety constraint that we don't leave
this set here. So, we get zero along the
boundary.
And this determines H. And that's what
I'm really pointing out is that if you
look at a safety filter, what matters?
You have your model and you have your
barrier function H. And you have the
gradients of that H. All of those pieces
are as important as one another, right?
And this is addressing the H. The model
itself in this case is very simple. So
this is a method. This is just the same
thing. But now if you watch the screen
back here, I think you'll appreciate
much more what's happening, right? It's
real time synthesizing the barrier
function solving pan's equation. And
again, this is just unitry's offtheshelf
RO and my student just interacting with
it, which is I I like this video. By the
way, this also worked in one day. And I
only say that because to me a sign of
the like the math being right is you put
it on hardware and it kind of works out
of the box. If you have to force it
uphill, you're you're probably not
you're missing something.
Here's another example where we actually
added a couple pieces. First, we had a
geometric representation of the robot in
the posance equation. And second, we
were actually doing this predictive
safety filter, which is a CBF condition
in an MPC problem. And that gives us
this predictive behavior. So as the ball
comes, we don't just go out of the way,
but we actually turn and rotate to avoid
the collision. You can actually see on
the screen the trajectory from the
predictive safety filter together with
the geometric representation all being
done in this pan safety function. Right?
So
that's the perception part. Again, going
back to this, we can close the loop on
some of the other stuff we did as well
though, right? So I talked about
stochastic CBFS earlier. That was a
leadin to this. Again, I told you we're
doing single integrator reduced order
models and they work really well. True.
But we can also make them better. How do
we make them better? We can collect some
data from the deployment of the single
integrator CBF on the hardware. We take
this data and we can learn the
distribution and then get a stochastic
guarantee on safety and we can learn a
better reduced order model that we can
then use for the safety filter. And this
better reduced order model, this D here
that we're learning includes in it, I
keep hitting too many buttons, includes
in it sort of contains the the the RL
policy that was under the surface here,
right? And so this is what happens when
you do this. Our learned reduce order
model has much better tracking than the
original one. Better tracking means
smaller safe set expansion, which means
tighter performance. Right? So that's
where all these pieces start to come
together. Again, I'm trying to really
demonstrate the interplay. And once we
do that, we can get really cool
deployments. So, this is now this safety
filter, but using this learned reduced
order model together with stoastic CBFS
outdoors. So, we're doing obviously
onboard compute, onboard perception.
This is actually the perception in this
case. So, these are the obstacles the
robot's sensing in real time. That's my
student Gary who it's avoiding.
And this one's kind of cool. Again,
anytime you take a robot outside in the
real world, the humanoid, first, it's
super cool, and second, you get really
big crowds. I don't if you've noticed
this. This was just us taking this out.
We didn't tell people this was going to
happen, and pretty soon we had like 50
people watching watching the robot and
wanting to interact with it. There is a
very visceral uh connection with
humanoid robots. So, anyways, this was
this is cool though because now we have
really closed the loop.
So there's one element though we haven't
like fully closed though between all the
things I talked about so far and it was
said earlier now you can say it again
what do we need to bring it back to
learning okay so is there a will for
learning so everything I did yeah we
learned the reduced order model but
that's really like learning for control
which is very important learning the
reduced order model but can we take
these ideas and actually bring it to the
learning community and so this is a
recent result that is sort of in that
light where we actually do CBFS in
training to inherently learn safety
filters using all of the tricks that
we've assembled so far if you'd like.
Right? So what happens here? We have
some RL policy and we want to roll out
this RL policy together with this safety
constraint. So in this case the safety
constraint I'm showing here is the
stairs. We don't want the feet to hit
the stairs ever, right? Because we want
to walk walk up and down stairs. We can
also do it for collision avoidance and
other things, whatever you want, right?
So how do you do this? Well, you're
going to roll out your policy, but as
you roll out, you're going to safety
filter. How are you going to safety
filter? Well, I showed you earlier the
rollouts themselves. So, our actual
model in this case is a simulator. We
don't know the model, right? But for the
rollouts, we can use a reduced order
model. I showed you how good an
integrator works, right? So, let's use a
single integrator reduced order model,
but now discretetized.
And then for this, we need we would have
a discrete time CBF condition, which I
talked about earlier. I keep hitting the
wrong buttons. There we go. a discrete
time CBF condition. Well, it turns out
you're able to prove that you can
enforce the continuous time CBF
condition and that implies that the
discrete time condition is satisfied
which means your rollouts will be safe.
So we can go from continuous to discrete
and from the rollouts and reduced order
model to actual safety on the full order
dynamics which in this case is just the
simulator. Why does that matter? Because
once we have the continuous time
condition this is fine in your input.
Hence you get an explicit solution. You
have an explicit solution. You can do
what? Why do we need an explicit
solution in this case?
Anybody?
We can GPU paralyze, right? We can't yet
GPUs paralyze QP solves. Not
effectively. There's people working on
it. But explicit solutions mean it's
like two lines of code you add to your
rollup procedure as you're doing the RL.
Meaning there's no real computational
overhead. Which means now you can chain
at the rollouts. And then the final step
is you bring all that back. You take
this whe if safety is violated, you take
the correction term, you fold it back in
and you take your nominal reward and
modulate by this CBF. So the the reward
has some knowledge that you're
modulating this output and you put all
those pieces together and this is
actually now you deploy that on hardware
straight up and you can do stairs. In
fact, let me show you the outdoor
montage. So this is now CBFRL with CBFS
in training. There's actually no online
safety filter here. we sort of learned
the behavior. Now, in practice, I would
do an online filter as well, just to be
very clear. We're just showing that this
works without one and we're able to
handle pretty dramatic stairs. I mean,
we have a ways to go to make this super
smooth and fluid. To be clear, this is a
very recent result, but I'm kind of
showing where things can go when you
start to inject now control into
learning, right? Meaning, what we know
about control into the learning based
procedures, right? One more time because
it's pretty
I love watching robots, right? So, so
that's kind of bringing everything
really back full circle, right? Make
sense? See all those pieces? So, in the
end, you have this repertoire of things
that we've developed.
So, in particular,
I'm going to go back to this statement
of why learning needs control and
control theory. And I will say the
converse is also true. It's not in this
slide, but I want to really clearly
emphatically say that control also needs
learning. We need each other, right? We
need each other and we need to find
these common intersection points. Okay,
so on one level, why does again, why
does learning need control? Because
control can can help address the
bottlenecks that learning inherently
has. Learning does great at performance.
It is not great at robust certifiable
safety critical behaviors. Right?
Control theory has a century of making
sure that airplanes fly with 10 theus 9
safety right we need to take those
principles things like safety filters I
mean here we have a certification that
our system is safe that we can use to
verify and certify the system in many
contexts and we put this in independent
of your RL algorithm to guarantee safe
behaviors on the system right so that's
what it can do on that end and then
coming back again control guided
learning can help to unlock performance
So I actually think going beyond just
safety filtering control can genuinely
help learning be better, right? And and
these are two examples from my lab. I
mean again I I say in in in all
humbleness, I mean these are a couple
grad students, incredible grad students
that did this, right? But I don't have a
hundred people in my in a company like
pushing forward the latest like reward
function shaping and and and that's the
beauty of math is just a couple grad
students really smart really smart grad
students I don't want to downplay this
enough these guys are brilliant but we
can get really good running I'll put
this up against any of the
state-of-the-art running I'm seeing
right now right and it's all based on
just clean CLS and two weeks of
deployment of course the stair climbing
too which is which is very cool so we
can use these controlbased principles to
inform reinforcement learning and other
methods. This talk, so my final piece is
this talk really focused on RL
specifically. There's of course a lot of
other ways you can do learning VAS etc.
uh large language models and I think in
all those cases again similar messages
could be made. I'm just not an expert in
those domains and I don't want to talk
outside my box. But in this case I think
I hope at least I made a reasonably
compelling case as to how we can work
together in this front. And so why do we
want to do this? So, I'm just going to
close with two fun videos. Uh, first,
the CLFRL was actually invented out of
necessity, right? A great quote,
necessity is the mother invention,
right? So, we had to do this demo and we
had to get the robot to walk really well
in a lot of different scenarios with
different loads on its back. And I
couldn't imagine the reward like shaping
and tuning we would have to do to make
that all work in a month. So, I so I
worked with my students. I'm like, we
have to find a principal way to generate
different walking behaviors. In
particular, we rolled out CLFRL for the
first time in this scenario.
This was literally 2 weeks after we
invented the idea. Um, and why again
this humanoid robot, the G, this is the
the G1 is carrying this drone. It's more
than just a drone. It's actually called
M4. So, we had to walk with it and
that's CLFRL. Then, we had to do this
behavior of bending over. Why? Because
you don't want to carry a drone unless
it's going to go somewhere. So then the
drone takes off,
flies away. So what you're trying to do
here is leverage the locomotion
modalities of each of each platform to
its its greatest benefit. So then it can
transition into a a driving robot and
back to a flying robot, right? And it
can take off. So it's able to explore a
lot of spaces that might be hard for a
humanoid, right? It can get a lot of
places. Like here, it's flying over the
turtle pond at Caltech. And while it's
doing that, the humanoid can walk around
sort of the long way. So outdoors, the
drone and and the M4 in particular can
really move around quickly. Of course,
inside you probably don't want that
drone flying around the hallway and the
wheeled robot certainly can't go
upstairs, right? So that's where the
humanoid can really flourish. In fact,
the stair climbing again was invented
out of necessity. This was the first
time we ever implemented that stair
climbing idea and we did it pretty
successfully.
So So this is this is this is actually
what what led to a lot of these
inventions. It started at math and a
month later we were doing these things
and this is where you'd really like to
take humanoids really outdoors doing
real world things right and of course
ultimately my interest is humanoids
around people these are just students
around Caltech that stop to watch the
humanoid and we're running here we're
running a safety filter uh using the LAR
from the the one I showed you earlier
called shield and my student here is
just kind of there's this is an autonomy
he's driving the robot around but we
know and feel confident that it won't
run into the people because it's got a
safety filter on it. Right? So again,
this is the final bit which is we'd like
to deploy these robots in places around
people and to that we need to have real
confidence that it will really work uh
in real world scenarios. Right? And
underlying all of that and I'll go back
to my origins is math, right? I mean
math is the great unifier. Uh math is
what makes it all work. And one simple
equation
can go a really long way. So with that,
thank you very much.