the economics of demand and Supply if it
was that easy everybody would be doing
it it needs education it needs passion
it needs commitment not just motivation
you know you need to be motivated
internally you need to be curious about
the thing that you're learning if you're
doing it just to get rich you're going
to get way bored way before you know you
ever actually get the opportunity to get
your first
[Music]
paycheck welcome to open liners a
podcast that tells the story of Learners
all over the world who use mit's open
courseware I'm Emanuel Li kasigi an open
learner myself from campella Uganda in
East Africa and I'm Michael Jordan
Pilgreen an open learner from Memphis
Tennessee hey Emanuel hi Michael it's
good to be back this is our third
episode I'm very excited Emanuel you
know today's learner is Nadar alawi
Nadar is from Jordan and is currently
living in
oh nice and Michael Nadar is actually
someone you've had the opportunity to
work with outside of ocw can you tell us
more about that sure I met Nadar through
the micr Masters and finance program and
I stayed in touch with him throughout
that process once he graduated undergrad
I knew we needed someone with his
quantitative skills at Bon click so I
recruited him to come work for me at Bon
click amazing amazing uh cuz one of the
reasons we wanted to start this podcast
was to Showcase that ocw has the
potential to be more than just an online
learning platform it is a tool to build
Global communities and Nadal story is a
perfect example to include in our first
season because it does exactly that
exactly I think the power of the
internet and MIT open courseware is that
superpower of networking to connect with
people all over the world unlike you and
before you getting his current
internship Nadar was already following a
really inspiring path he's been
passionate about Finance since he was a
teenager but some life circumstances
prevented him from really diving into
his studies before he discovered mit's
open learning resources he started open
courseware in 2020 at home in Jordan
while he was struggling to B balance
high school with 19 hour shifts at a
Falafel restaurant that's dedication in
the four years since his St his open
Learners Journey NAD has completed a
micro Masters in finance he has taken a
number of ocw courses in topics like
statistics coding programming calculus I
mean it's just amazing mitw and MIT
micromasters are both open learning
programs from MIT but they're quite
different and complimentary to each
other so with ocwa a learner has access
to materials from thousands and
thousands of MIT courses for self-paced
learning across just about any
discipline all free all online I've used
some of these resources myself they're
amazing so when a learner wants to focus
specifically on getting a professional
and academic credential in a h topic
that they like say Finance say Tech say
you know then there you can take a
sequence of online courses through the
mitx micr Masters program to get that
credential that you're looking for yeah
Nadar is super impressive I'll let Nadar
tell the rest of his story himself but I
will say finds himself in a completely
different place from where he started so
let's get into it here is our
conversation with Nadar alwi from
Jordan so I'm NAD I'm from Jordan I'm 23
years old I started my education journey
and passion for for my career which is
finance when I was about 15 I used to
watch you know like random Youtube
videos about Warren Buffett and how he
invests and and stuff like that and then
when I was going through High School
I just had a a bit of trouble finishing
it due to you know circumstances at home
and financial issues so I was actually
working a couple of uh you know
different jobs minimum W jobs Feld
restaurant you know stuff like that then
as soon as I finished high school while
I was working those jobs I got into
University and as soon as I got into
University I started discovering the
various platforms that MIT has to
endorse open and free education across
the globe so that would be in I think
September of 2020 during the
pandemic and I found first MIT on edex I
found the micromasters program in
finance and I found you know
ocw MIT open course whereare and I
started building into very know a lot of
various topics calculus statistics
Finance the most special thing for me
about um the MIT micromasters program
and the community that MIT Fosters
online is that you get to meet um
students from all around the world um
who have the same passion as you who's
trying to learn the same essential skill
that you are trying to learn every week
I would you know meet someone we chat up
online and you know my the friend list
that I made throughout that uh program
continued to grow and I some of them I
met in person some of them I me to meet
in person like you Mike and Emanuel and
after I finished the program I became a
teaching assistant and interacted more
with a lot of the students at MIT
Community teaching assistant for the
microm Masters
program and you know that's when
opportunities started coming in all
right let me let me ask one question
just to get us contextualized within
your journey so you know you said you
started finding these resources around
September
2020 that year during the pandemic where
were you what were you thinking about
what was your daily life like at that
point in time you know I would wake up
at like 5:00 a.m. go to my job in the
fla restaurant at 6 and you know work
for 9 10 hours a day and I was slowly
doing high school at the time and once I
finished I had a bit of free time I quit
my job and I decided that I want to
focus on my education so I was free I
had a couple of months before my
bachelor started in September around the
same time that the or October around the
same time that I started the microman
program it felt advanced you know it's
graduate level and I didn't even enter
my bachelor's and I had problems you
know with my high school so I wasn't
confident that I would be able to finish
the program but thankfully you know
after 10 20 30 hours a week of studying
for a
mighty exams I I was lucky enough to
finish the program and you know that you
know really helped me gain a lot of
confidence in my skills and
abilities and it helped me you know in
my undergraduate studies and helped me
in other you know Finance specific
programs such as CFA and the FM going
from just graduating high school to
tackling graduate level work is like no
small fee if you feel comfortable
sharing what were some of the
obstacles or problems you were having
during your high school education that
you were over able to overcome yeah it
it definitely was and you know at the
time my confidence was you know as I
said was too low and the biggest problem
I had was was just a lot of it was you
know family issues uh my dad had lost
his business we had to sell our house
and find a new one he went bankrupt
unfortunately and that just caused a lot
of stress and sort of havoc in my
personal life so I became just a little
bit isolated trying to you know work so
I can be able to support myself and my
family and I didn't have the mental
capacity to to focus on high school plus
you know like when when you put it in
the you know normal context of yeah like
this is high school this is you know you
got to finish this you know topics and
pass those courses it was pretty boring
you know I wasn't interested in it
really but when I started studying for
MIT you know it seemed like this out of
world you know higher class education
worldwide graduate level course it's
really intensive and really hard it it
aligned with you know my passion my
curiosity and I was able to push through
that hard work you know all this
happened September 2020 with the
lockdown I would like to touch a bit
about that I guess what I want to know
is how are you as a human being and your
interactions and the people around you
changed when your life before you met
ocw and the resources and then your life
after how you used to interact with the
environment the people around you your
family close friends you know throughout
my whole life I had just you know a lot
of free time that I would waste on
average stuff Netflix shows movies you
know playing games
and and and stuff like that but when
when I started the MIT program I was
like whoa wait wait a minute like this
is this material is very hard this
material is very
engaging and it was during lockdown so
everyone was you know already staying
home there's there was not much to do
outside of home which was you know a
blessing honestly my case all of that
time home and sort of isolation from my
my environment and and friends and
family that that was already happening
in place I I put that time and
dedication into right just just
finishing that program and uh because of
how hard it the program was and how
challenging it was and the the reward
once once you finish you know a quiz or
a problems set and you hit that check
button and you get the green mark it was
very gratifying it was very
rewarding and that became you know like
seeking knowledge and just the the
gratification of learning new things
became an essential core part of my
personality where now all I want to do
is just you know stay in home stay stay
home stay on my laptop continue learning
stuff online and gain new skills and
gain new so you know maybe there was
already a lot of isolation going on in
the world and that has you know helped
me gain discipline to my career to my
education and to the things I want to
accomplish did that discipline that you
cultivated over this Learning Journey
you know translate into other aspects of
your life did it Inspire others in your
Clos Circle did you even talk about it
with people in your closed Circle or was
it more just a online thing oh yeah now
now like my friends you know can't can
hear enough about you know they they'
had enough about my MIT passion and
story and journey I don't shut up about
it that there was a lot of people um
that I've talked to on the program some
people you know that that reached out to
me randomly on on LinkedIn on the
internet after seeing you know these
certificates and they would have a bunch
of questions and we'd hop on a call and
we' talk about the program and a lot of
my personal friends as well and people I
met in uni started taking the microm
Masters in the finances specifically and
like they would go through the courses
and you know they' admit me on their
progress and it changed me changed a lot
of people around me who are interested
in finance was there any instructors
that really inspired you in the
programming and if they did why you know
who who were the professors and why did
they inspire you um you know all of the
professors on on that program were great
and and they were all inspiring and they
all had their own unique way of teaching
but you know you know what my my
favorite was Eiger Professor Eiger medv
it was the first course I I was starting
it even started a little bit before my
bachelor's and was graduate level and I
would do the lectures and they would
seem very very very hard but then you
know there's like a recitation section
after each week and chapter where
Professor IG would start from the very
basic you know blocks of of math and and
the equations and finance and you know
we would build up more complex exercises
as as we go in the journey so just those
three citations you know I probably
wouldn't have passed you know
first few few courses without them and
how simple he made them seem did you
ever imagine that you would get this
type of educational experience from your
I'm presuming like your living room I
don't know where you studied um but like
how did how did uh open educational
resources you know not only change your
trajectory but like how you think about
access and opportunity globally and like
where do you see it going in the future
yep well it it really it really critized
education just from me from you know
Jordan working a minimum W job in in a
country that that is you know not doing
great economically I had access to the
best education in the whole world and
that education that I got manifested in
me getting jobs and and working remotely
with with companies in New York or
Arizona or in Jordan or in Dubai um so
now we're in a much more Global
atmosphere where after also Co happened
and work started being remote and you
know people started being more
collaborative online um so I think you
know anyone with with a phone and
internet connection and a passion now
can can you know just pick up the
resources that MIT has and the plenty of
available online education in general
resources that are free on the internet
and you know learn any scale you
want you mentioned Finance alot do you
you have a love for finance like
naturally or it's just something you
know it's where the money is it's what
I'm going to do it's definitely where
the money is yeah um but my passion for
finance started when I was 15 I was I
was just like always curious
about how um you know financial markets
function how the global economy can
function you know when when I was six or
whatever I whenever I would get like a
huge bag of sh ships I would sell it to
my friends um it's school or siblings I
was always just interested in you know
business in general especially finance
and learning about the global economy
yeah that's a nice one I I was like that
too I also used to sell sweets to my
classmates
yeah so I understand so you are
specifically looking for finance things
when you founded ocw yep and ever since
then have you taken anything out of your
circles maybe something outside Finance
yeah definitely um I did a lot of
calculus I did a lot of probability and
statistics programming Python and just
other skills so because I want to become
like a Quant I had to learn everything
about technology learn everything about
finance and sort of mix them together
and MIT was the perfect place to do that
because no other university in my
country had you know that kind of wide
range of you know offerings where you
can choose in one degree for the all the
assistant topics that I wanted to study
nice so of all the things you've studed
I know I personally have studed a lot I
would take the most impactful for me I
think were the AI lectures I've watched
why would you say first of all was the
most impactful and then the one that
kind of had the most impact in the real
life like when I took this course called
disqualification is when I like went
down the path I'm on now I think the
course is named modern Financial Theory
by uh Professor Andrew l i enrolled in
the micromanage program but just before
it had started I thought I would prepare
myself with that course during that
course during the time that they were
fing those lectures the big financial
crisis was happening in real time so
we'd see a lot of you know meaningful
interactions from the the MBA students
that were taking the course and
Professor Andrew Lou and all of the
specific questions they would ask during
that period it was such a coincidence
very you know maybe happy or lucky
coincidence that they started following
the course just when the financial
crisis was happening so how did you how
did you end up in the finance internship
so the first job I got as a quantitative
analyst was with a startup in Jordan and
it was actually in my second year of
Bachelors just when I finished the MIT
program and after a bit of time of being
a community teaching assistant I worked
with them for around six months you know
building models for crypto trading and
after that I I met Mike and he
introduced me to an opportunity
uh with with a company you know that
works in in New York and on Wall Street
and in the bond
market and you know it took a couple of
months of preparation and courses and
education uh that that Mike suggested
and after I finished those that's how I
landed my current
internship yeah and that that was that
was a lot Kinder than the actual
Journey so so you ended up graduating
during that time from your undergrad and
you know so my previous role was at a
financial technology startup primarily
focused on you know consolidating
corporate bond information uh Nadar had
been a standout student and teacher
associate is that what they called it
teaching assistant yeah teaching
assistant teaching assistant and the
microm Masters program we both started I
think at the same time both September
2020 so we were the same cohort of
microm
students and um as some of you may know
I that's when I got my job at uh the
financial technology
startup so my cours workk sort of fell
off because it became real life work for
me you know I didn't end up passing a
single course I don't think in that micr
Masters meanwhile Nadar had been killing
every single one uh
you know we would touch face every 3
months for a little while there and then
once he graduated that was kind of when
the program really opened up for him
when he started working for us and
solving some of these hard problems nice
ad you mentioned something about people
and how among the best things that
ocw enabled you to access or to do was
connect with all these people from
around the world and for you you have an
actual testimony you connected with
someone a fellow learner who
that led to an internship I would like
you to touch a bit about you know you've
met all these great people you've gotten
part of it you're in Dubai but I want
you to use your own words and paint for
us your life after ocw a huge portion of
my life is is owed to ocw as well I did
a lot of programs not just the microm
Masters and finance I I did a forarm
part one I did the CFA level one and I
did all of those with my bachelor
sometime while working as a Quant and
one time in real estate even under three
years I I didn't even know about frmr
CFA right I I didn't even know like what
skills I need to to learn I didn't know
about you know big data and and how to
do data analytics and data engineering
and and py Spark and all of these things
so the people that I met had all kind of
different careers some of them were
biologists some of them were physicists
some of them were senior vice president
residents at Major insurance companies
in Quant and some of them had already
had phds and just meeting those people
and having those conversation is what
you know broadened my my vision I
learned what I need to learn through the
conversations I've had through the
people that I connected with at MIT it
wasn't just about you know the material
is all there you can learn anything
online but you need to know what to
learn in order to be successful and you
know it wasn't just like you know
someone telling me that this program is
great and I would go to it I have a
friend for example his name is Deon uh
we we studied together frm and CFA like
every single chapter like we would hop
on a zoom call uh and you know we would
spend six hours together solving
questions and you know learning stuff uh
we did that for the microm Masters we
did that for CFA we did that for frm and
I had a lot of you know many more
friends that I you know had you know the
pleasure of studying with and
collaborating with so I I wouldn't have
done it alone without you know the
people and the community and the
friendships that I have made that
allowed me to survive right this this
very you know challenging program and
education Journey that's that's really
beautiful to think about that not only
were you getting open educational
Resources by coursework material but you
were getting access to a social capital
that you could tap in that you could
leverage you could leverage an
Executives experience you you know just
because he's your classmate or she's
your classmate right that that that
really is a beautiful thing you know and
just just we asked this question of
everyone that comes on the podcast and
it was uh a question from Kurt Newton
the director of open course sare if you
had a magic
wand what would you add to open course
sare what would you add to the micr
masters programs any open educational
resources well I would the whole degree
of Finance you know all of the C putting
it online I do it there is some
applications in the program where you
actually apply the theory and do
regression and and do what you learned
in the class more applied courses would
be um would be more you know appreciated
and specifically courses that are
centered around collaboration uh I've
met a lot of students um that you know
went through six or nine months of the
program and you know they've never been
on a zoom call with with another student
with a peer student like they didn't net
work so just maybe designing a program
centered around
collaboration would be a huge plus
because you know I I had an amazing
experience at uh MIT I think I made the
most out of it there's still more to
learn and make more out of it but a lot
of students just you know didn't focus
on socializing or you know didn't get
the social experience that I've had just
went in opened the course understood the
material did the and exams and you know
they they left out it's not bad to do
that but I think it's more valuable to
just you know increase the human touch
the human connection element that's
that's really beautiful um do you have
anything any message that you would want
to share with your friends your family
the world around you if you have a dream
you know just give it time stay
dedicated stay passionate stay don't
don't let your passion die out don't get
turned down uh you know you know don't
don't be too hard on yourself don't get
turned down don't have doubts over the
long run if if you really just put the
time put the effort in um you will make
your dreams come true and you just need
to you know get out there and show up
every day um if you show up every day
and like if you do a little bit of work
in your dream with enough time it's you
know it's it's more than just a
possibility to to make it true that
that's what happened with me here I
remember having having dreaming of
becoming a quantitative analyst on my
LinkedIn bio when I just started out
University three four years ago and I
thought it's a silly dream that that
would never achieve it but you know here
I am being a Quant in the finance
industry wow that was a full circle
conversation uh we followed Nadal from
the start of his ocw journey as a
struggling high school student deep into
his career as a Quant analyst pretty
amazing if you ask me from all this
what's your biggest takeaway from this
conversation I think my biggest takeaway
is exactly what nadara said in the last
um answer to the question was if you
have a dream give it time stay dedicated
stay passionate don't let your passion
die out and just keep pursuing it until
you achieve it I conquer I conquer my
biggest take out from all this is anyone
can achieve this we're hearing a story
of someone who started out all the way
from Jordan didn't have much going for
them but they stay dedicated putting in
hours working insane hours at a
restaurant but still having time to come
back and do all these resources put in
the time put in the work and it lat a
paid off you have someone from Across
the Nation ending up working for a
company that is across the seas in
another continent and is now living in a
different place that is the power of
what ocw gives you that's the power of
the community and the internet to know
that you can do it no matter where
you're from no matter where you start
you can access anyone on this planet
from any corner of it and it's possible
and ocw is giving everyone that power
and that opportunity and I want to say
thanks to everyone for tuning into our
conversation with Nadar we will be back
in two weeks with another story from a
different Learner in the global open
course for Community see you then
[Music]
open lers is produced by Alexis hot
special thanks to the supporters and
donors who make ocw possible to learn
more about mit's Open course rare and to
check out the courses mentioned in this
episode visit the open coreware website
at ocw.mit.edu
[Music]
a