To participate in this next exercise,
you'll have to grab um one of these uh
uh index cards that are on the table
that correspond to a particular
technology. It looks like film, radio,
and television are amongst the remaining
ones. Um and you'll get in small groups
um and uh work on those. Here's what I'd
like you to do. Find the other people
who have the same card as you. Um, uh,
discuss what you learned from the
readings, anything that sort of stands
out to you, comes to your mind. But then
I want you to make a chart, which you
can do on the whiteboard or on our um,
blue pieces of paper there. Um, that uh,
that capture sort of three key ideas.
First of all, who are all of the
stakeholders who are involved in the
implementation of this technology? One
of the things that I think Larry Cubin
is particularly wonderful at um is
giving you a sense of all of the
different hands that touch a technology
making its way into a school and all the
when it's in the school. This is
incredibly important for understanding
how technologies actually get used um in
in sort of a lot of times in like
canonical design. And I think this comes
up in sort of software engineering
classes and things like this idea that
like there's a programmer and a user and
the user is like one person who's
sitting at a keyboard with their fingers
on the keyboard and like that's the
person you need to pay attention to. And
that like two-part model of like
designer and user totally breaks down in
schools. Um there are lots of people who
are very different who could be
considered users of technology in
schools. Um, another thing that's that
Larry Cubin does really well is he he he
helps us pay attention to how these
people have what I'll call different
interests. By interests, I don't mean
curiosities. I mean like incentives,
stakes, sort of how a political
scientist might use the word interest.
Um, all of these different stakeholders
are rewarded for different kinds of
things. Um, they also have what we'll
call disinterests or disincentives. they
are also trying to avoid or will be
punished for different kinds of things.
Um so for the technology that you that
you picked a card of and are talking
with your colleagues about think of all
of the different people who you think
could be considered stakeholders in the
implementation of this thing. What and
then for each of those stakeholders come
up with like a couple of their interests
and a couple of their disinterests or
disincentives or things that punish them
or those kinds of things. Does that as a
general exercise make sense? Um, and the
thing that we're trying to do together
is around we want to we want to try to
recreate the world around these
technologies. That's what I think Larry
Cuban is so fabulous at, um, is saying
like, yep, a television set is going to
roll into a but it's going to roll into
a classroom and into a school and into a
community and there's all these people
who are part of that. Um, that's what we
really need to get out here. I'll tell
the last thing I'll tell you before I
cut you loose um, is Larry Cuban has a
totally fascinating history himself. He
was a social studies teacher in the 50s
and 60s. Then he was a school principal.
Then he was a superintendent. He was
actually the superintendent in
Arlington, Virginia. Um which is where
my wife went to school. So when my wife
was an elementary school student, um uh
her her superintendent at the time was
Larry Cuban. Um and are Arlington,
Virginia. Fairfax. Close enough. Yeah.
Yeah. Um and it was only after he had
like a pretty distinguished career as a
teacher, a principal, a superintendent
that he went to Stanford. Um got his
dissertation. um became a historian of
education and then eventually a a
history of education professor out
there. Um so he's someone who's like
extremely well read as I'm sure you got
a sense of and things like that, but he
also just deeply understands the kinds
of things that make schools tick and
make the people inside schools tick.
Does this exercise make sense? Find the
people with your cards. Move yourselves
around. Make this little chart either on
the board or on these blue pieces of
paper. Ready? Go.
That's a little bit th those things are
those things are hugely important you
know like like what like where does
teaching actually happen like there's
some human being you know who like needs
to go to the bathroom and needs to eat
and I mean he has that great quote in
there it's not about film but television
that they found that they're more likely
to use television in the afternoon than
in the mornings. Um and it and it all
it's all like biology and culture like
our brains work better in the morning.
We're all a little flagging by the
afternoon. Those kinds of things. Um,
and so yeah, I think that like anybody
who's building a technology has to think
to themselves like, you know, what are
you? Yeah. Yeah. What like what are the
variations in a teacher's day? Like when
do they have more energy or less energy?
How does it fit into those kinds of
cycles and things like that? Like those
are every bit as real as you know the
test score goals that we have or
anything else.
This is really good. This is really
good. Take a few more minutes. Take a
few more minutes.
We're trying to think about interest for
schools for producers. Sure. So, if
you're a school, so if you're a school,
what would make you go, h I'm not sure I
want to do anything with films. It's so
it's 1913. Um, silent films, you know,
started coming out in earnest around the
turn of the century. There's a handful
of people um one, you know, the most
prominent of them is Thomas Edison. You
know, a guy invents a light bulb. Um and
he gets in front of Congress and he
says, you know, he's first in 1913, he
says, I mean, I'll read the other quote,
but he says, um, in a decade, textbooks
will be replaced by film strips. That's
how powerful this new technology is
going to be. Um, if you're a school
principal, what would be some things
that make you go, you're pretty smart,
Thomas, but I'm not so sure about this
one?
Maybe if they just put a bunch of money
into textbooks. Sure. So yeah, they have
an entire infrastructure built around
the existing technologies. They h they
have shelves on the wall. They have
libraries full of books. Every one of
their teachers has been trained to teach
with textbooks. And not a single one of
their teachers in you know when these
things are first introduced has ever
been in a class as a student learning
from a film. So you have this huge
inherent conservatism in the system. So
that could be one. What would be what
would be some others?
I mean, yeah. I mean, I I guess it's
kind of adding on to that, but like
integrating it into like a classroom
setting, like how how would they even
like
uh integrate into like even even if
they're like completely on board like
like what how would they even integrate
it into a classroom? What for films?
What would be what would be some of the
challenges of integration?
Um like
the technology that you would need to
like uh put into a classroom or like to
a school. Say tell me specifically for
films what some of that technology might
be. Um I mean like isn't I I don't think
like the the projectors in like back
then could like fit into like a
classroom. Oh, they so they could I mean
you know like they're they're portable
enough but they're big. They're these
like big lumbering machines for which
the rooms are like if you have if you
have a classroom like let's say you have
a big population growth and so you're
you're you built you you know someone in
the 1850s built a school and it was 12
kids per classroom and now you're
putting 18 kids per classroom in there.
Like a totally legitimate reason would
be there is not space in this room to
physically move this machine. Like what
are some other sort of what else do you
need for films as a technology to be
able to be implemented? Do you need a
giant projector? You're going to put
thing on wheels. What else do you need?
A place to actually project it onto.
Okay, good. You're going to have to go
to all your classrooms and you're going
to have to install screens at the front
of the room. Like not the hugest
challenge, but also not free, you know,
not like like so who's going to do these
things? Um, you know, the uh the films
also came on these like huge reels. Um,
you know, it wasn't just like, you know,
pick your YouTube channel and play like
where in your building are you going to
keep a library of film reels? Who's
going to organize those libraries of
film reels? Like um you know if you have
four elementary schools in an or four
elementary classroom like let's say have
four first grades, are you going to buy
four copies of this film so that
everyone can watch it at the same time?
If not, how are you going to like
physically organize and move like this
giant reel from one space to another?
Those are all those are all you know you
could imagine the principal being like
but how are we but how are we but how
are we but how are we and all this stuff
costs money. Um, so those are all kinds
of, you know, like like, you know,
Thomas Edison is here telling you that
you're going to get 100% efficient
learning through this thing, which is
the potential gains, which you no one
has any evidence for because it hasn't
happened yet. But you've got to think to
yourself like like what are all these
costs? What are all these material
changes? Yeah. So think about how you
can articulate some of those things. But
good like when you really get like, you
know, for to to do this exercise, well,
you have to like what exactly is this
technology? Like like even physically,
what does it require? How many of these
things do you need to buy? How much do
they cost? All that kind of stuff. How
reusable are they? Um,
okay. This is really good. Why don't we
take a break here? Um, go ahead and you
can sit back down to the seats that you
were at. Um, I think everyone's written
kind of broadly enough um that we'll be
able to see from a
distance. But yeah, really good. Really
good. Now I need to find a little spot
for me to um
everyone's last minute notes. Every
Yeah. Yeah. Now is your chance to put
the final the final few things up there.
Um good. So every What was the minimum
number of stakeholders people came up
with? Um these guys are the winners with
the longest list. Let's just read it out
loud. Co. Oh no. The state admin,
parents, teachers, students,
corporations, manufacturers, edtech
investors, developers, policy makers.
Great. So, just as a starting point, I
mean, there are some other ones that
showed up around here, studios,
broadcasters, the FCC, um, that sort of
different psychologists. Yeah, there are
a lot of people who have something at
stake in these decisions. They're
complex, multihuman kinds of decisions.
So, that's a good start. Um, let me just
read. Um, so given how complex these
things are, why are folks so
enthusiastic about it? Let's ask Thomas
Edison. Um, what does Thomas Edison
think about this? I believe that the
motion picture is destined to
revolutionize our educational system and
that in a few years it will supplant
largely if not entirely the use of
textbooks. I should say that on the
average we get about 2% efficiency out
of school books as they are written
today. You're laughing. Why are you
laughing? Thomas Edison is just here
making up. He doesn't 2% that
doesn't mean a thing. He was good at
light bulbs. He wasn't maybe as good at
this. Um, the education of the future as
I see it will be conducted through the
medium of the motion picture where it
should be possible to obtain 100%
efficiency. Thomas Edison 1922. Um,
you'll read a couple of other quotes
that I have from Thomas Edison. One of
them is in here in in failure to disrupt
when you read that. But in 1913, he went
in front of Congress and said in 10
years the textbook will entire will be
entirely replaced by um film strips. And
then he went back 10 years later in 1923
and he said in 20 years textbooks will
be entirely replaced by film strips. Um
I think you can find many similar kinds
of arguments that are made today. Um I
think you will not have a hard time um
finding people who tell you that the
oldfashioned techniques are only 2%
efficient but the new ones will be 100%
efficient. Um so that's the promise. the
promise is that we could do
substantially better than we're doing
right now if we if we think about
implementing all of these uh different
kinds of technologies. Um so an
intuition that you can develop um is
that this is this is a century old
enterprise. Um for the last 100 110
years people have thought how can we
take analog technologies and eventually
digital technologies bring them into
schools to improve learning. Um there
are millions of people who work on
education. Many of them are very very
smart. Um from the earliest, you know,
you read a little bit about um uh
personal computers kind of from the 70s
and 80s, the Apple 2 plus kind of the
generation of computers that I grew up
with, but that's actually like 20 years
into the game. Um from the moment people
built computers the size of this room,
um computer scientists, educators,
learning scientists partnered together
to try to figure out if there's some way
to use computers to teach people. So, so
just compute, you know, not even all
these other radio, film, other things.
Computing alone is like a 70-year
enterprise of trying to improve schools.
There are lots of things that we've
tried and learned in 70 years. So, one
intuition that I hope you will take away
from this class is that when you're
thinking about an education technology
problem of any form or type, about a
design problem, an implementation
problem, a policy problem, you should
think to yourself, we probably have done
something like this before. Um there is
nothing that is so new, so utterly
different that there aren't like cognate
examples that could help us think
through whatever these challenges are.
Um let's think about a couple of these
stakeholders. Which stakeholders seem to
appear pretty much in all of them?
What's who's who seem to be sort of
universal stakeholders?
Teachers. Teachers. Let's start with
them because they're the best. Um I I
love teachers. I would I mean definitely
one of the reasons why I do what I do is
I just think teachers are great.
Um what what kinds of things get
teachers excited? What what what if if
you're if you're if you want to get a
teacher using education technology, what
are the what are the felt needs that
they have that are going to be really
important to them? This is one that I
think will be pretty consistent across a
bunch of these, but we can see if there
are differences, too. Reducing their
workload. Okay, good. I love it.
reducing
workload. Why is that so important to
teachers?
It's because they have so much they have
so much to do. These are not people who
spend a bunch of time like sitting
around waiting for the phone to ring or
something like that. Um teacher workload
in the United States is actually in
certain ways like much higher than other
comparable OECD countries. So O is the
organization of economic cooperative
development something like that. It's
like rich countries 30 or 40 rich
countries. Um, American teachers
compared to our colleagues in other
countries spend more time in front of
students actually directly teaching than
in many other places. Um, so many other
countries in the world like a full-time
licensed teacher would have more
collaborative planning time, more
grading time, other kinds of things like
that. So, US teachers compared to their
colleagues around the world are like
behind the ball on having time anyway.
Um, reducing workload is something they
care about. What else do they care
about? Like it has to spark the students
interest. Good. So, they don't want kids
to be bored.
um that one of their one of their core
interests is how am I going to keep
these folks motivated? How am I going to
keep them learning? What else do they
care about? They care about it being of
actually good quality. Okay, good. So,
like it's really important that learning
goes up, that quality is high, um that
that you know that that uh teachers take
their professionalism very very
seriously and that you know and and
they're held accountable in various
kinds of ways. Um, and this could be
different across different kinds of
teachers. Um, so in the United States,
we primaril we we we test in in certain
kinds of ways. We test like way more
than every other country does. There's
no country that tests all of their
students every year, third to eighth
grade, in both reading and math. Most
other countries are like if you test
them in the third grade, you probably
wait a couple years to like, you know, I
mean, you give them like but you give
them assessments or exams or whatever,
but you don't give them like big
national tests. Um and so if you are a
teacher of reading or of math, um your
test scores are scrutinized in a way
that a science teacher, art teacher, a
health teacher, other kinds of teachers
are not similarly scrutinized. Um so
within the you know there could be
different kinds of incentives. One of
the things I always enjoyed about being
a history teacher is that there there
were never really tests that I were
preparing my students for. um in the
same way I taught in private school, but
even my math teacher colleagues like
felt like they were preparing students
for the SAT, for the APs, things like
that. That was never really my concern.
Um as a result, like I had to spend less
time thinking to myself, this new thing
I'm bringing in this classroom, is this
going to prepare people for some kind of
nearly universal testing experiences?
Like my math teacher colleagues always
had to be thinking about that. I could
be like, well, you know, Tibetan
Buddhism isn't on the test, but it's
awesome. Let's study it. Um you know, so
so that's different. Good. other kinds
of things. Yeah. Tai and then Sabrina.
Um accessibility and like inclusion. So
making sure that like no one's left out
from your diverse group of learners from
any technology.
Yeah. Um and that would not be a
universal concern across these decades.
um that you know um uh it would it would
have been considered much more common to
say like certain people have totally
unsolvable learning disabilities and
society should tend to their welfare in
some other kind of way in the 30s and
40s and 50s and then somewhere in the
middle of the 20th century we passed um
the Americans with Disabilities Act um
which which totally transformed our
thoughts and in fact you know created a
federal right for people to have um you
know a a way of being a fair and
appropriate public education Um, and I
would also just say educa, like as
society has gotten more interested in
values of inclusion generally, um, what
people would have worried about with
inclusion with personal computers in the
1980s is very different for what they
would be worried about with the
computers that are getting in front of
their students right now. That's a great
one. I'm going to say being able to
track student progress.
Track
progress
assessment. Good. Yeah. I mean, actually
interesting over this uh century, you
know, um some of the earliest
technologies had nothing to do with
that, radio and film, but one of the
very earliest ones you read about um
physical teaching machines. Um uh and
hopefully you got I mean you saw some
pictures um I was just actually looking
today there was a Sydney Pressie is one
of the people who Audrey Waters writes
about. Um and there's somebody on
YouTube who had posted this like
fabulous two-minute clip of him
demonstrating one of his teacher
machines and unfortunately that account
was deleted before this year's class. Um
may maybe I'll send you a version of it
later. The only version of the video
still exists is one in which a nand
augur wall's voice is superimposed of
it. Um, so somebody took an audio clip
of Anand Agarwal talking about the
capacities of Edex. Um, and played the
audio over Sydney Pressy demonstrating
the teaching machine. Um, and uh, it's a
little too close for comfort even though
it's a century apart. Um, but teaching
machines, they were kind of like
typewriters. Um, they had these four
keys that were on them and so they would
display one question at a time. Um, it
was like pre-cantron technology, you
know, and then there would be one of
four possible answers. Um, in one of the
earliest versions, it had a little like
bank of mints in the back of them and so
when you press the right button, like a
little candy or something would roll out
and give you like a little behaviorist
positive, um, reinforcement kinds of
things. Um, but one, you know, one of
the main virtues of it was like, oh man,
if we could get enough people these
things, um, then we could like assess
their progress almost constantly. We'd
know exactly where they are. So, so this
idea of track, you
know, tracking student progress is
something that's like particularly
urgently concerned in our datadriven
world, but was still something that
people were interested in a century ago.
Um, what are what are some of the I'll
just put them under here. What are some
of the the the would be disincentives
for teachers? What are some things that
if you were trying to get teachers to
adopt new technologies would be the
sorts of things that would be barriers
for them? Complexity. Why complexity? A
lot of there's there's uh some teachers
who are more able to adapt to new
technologies and some teachers who just
cannot understand how certain
technologies might work. Yeah. So I so I
think I think that aptitude is right. I
also many like if you go into teaching
there probably probably two things that
really drive you. One is you love the
content that you teach. That's more true
for secondary educators than for early
elementary educators but probably true
for them. And you probably love people.
um very difficult to be a teacher if you
don't find people especially young
people pretty engaging. the kinds of
folks who find people engaging, they
might just find tech, it's not 100%
overlap, but there just technology is
less engaging. Like they didn't want to
spend their life sitting in front of a
computer typing itself. They wanted to
be interacting with people.
Um, but the other thing I would say is
that there are many educators who spend
a lot of time polishing their craft and
are good at teaching the way they're
teaching right now and have been
teaching for the last decade. And so
when they see a new piece of technology
come in, they're thinking to themselves,
is this thing really going to be better
than the thing that I've been doing and
got good at for a while, um, you know,
what am I g what am I I'm going to have
to lose something when I integrate this
new thing? Like like any technology
adoption involves loss. Any change
involves loss. You got to give something
up. Um, I think giving up it may be
pretty good. Um, a lot I think a lot of
people think that older teachers because
are are less likely to adopt
technologies because they're not
technology fluent. But having worked
with many many teachers, I'm really
convinced that there's no relationship
between age and technology adoption.
There are young teachers that are super
interested and there are young teachers
who hate it. There are old teachers who
are like, I'm pretty good at what I do.
And there are old teachers who are old
teachers because they've spent the last
20 years going, it's really fun to try
new things. It's really fun to try to
get better. What was one of your
disincentives, Sabrina? uh student
distraction.
Great. And obviously some of these
technologies are more akin to that than
others. Like if you're playing a film
strip or something like that, like you
probably have kids attention or things
like that. Um but uh certainly as we get
into computers, any anything in which
you know the the attention is where
where each student is responsible for
their own attention um is something that
that uh can can raise concerns for
teachers because kids like to be attend
to all kinds of things. What what other
things would be disincentives like
teacher displacement like they feel like
they're being replaced? Yep. Um so
teachers are a profession um you know
that that protects their job security
with a license and things like that like
lots of other professions do like
doctors and pharmacists and lawyers and
all kinds of people. Um and uh yeah and
yeah but most professionals are not
super enthusiastic about technology that
has the capacity to replace the
functions that they're doing.
Um, good. Let's think about some of
these other um, so, so this is a good
one. So, so again, we could think about
anytime a new technology is being
introduced, is it going to reduce
workload? Is it going to spark interest?
Will it spark interest in the first
three weeks of this new technology being
here, will it spark interest two years
after the technology has been
introduced? Is it going to be of high
quality? Do I have control over the
quality? Um, accessible inclusion, is it
going to improve learning? Will it be
able to track assessment? Is it too
complex? Will it like distract my
students? Is it going to displace
essential functions that I perform? Um,
those are like that is a good set of
questions that you could ask, you know,
that Cuban does ask in some ways of
radio and film and television and
teaching machines and computers. Um, and
you could ask them of AI and Khan
Academy and I civics and anything else
that comes along. Like these are all
still good questions to ask. Um, let's
try to hit now a bunch of these other
stakeholders. Um, who are who are some
of the stakeholders that surprised you?
Who are the ones that you were like,
"Whoa, I wouldn't have thought of this
in terms of education
technology, weird ones or unique ones."
I mean, I thought like my group was the
teacher machines and it was like the
psychologists that like come up with the
ideas um that go into how these
technologies are or what they're based
on. Um like I guess I never just never
really thought like oh like you know it
is the people who like thought of
constructivism and like situated
learning that has then sparked this
interest in everything else. Um and so
it's like people have ideas but all of
that initially stemmed from these like
two thoughts of learning. Good. Yeah. So
so so people have ideas about what good
teaching and learning should be like.
Those ideas are in some ways they seem
pretty universal because we can find
them going back through history but
they're als they're always being
reinterpreted updated things like that.
Um Sydney Pressie is in this moment
where behaviorism is an incredibly
prominent set of you know set of ideas.
This behaviorism you're probably all
familiar with of you know you uh punish
people when they do things wrong and you
reward them when you do things right and
you condition their behavior that way.
Um and so he creates a physical machine
that embodies those ideas. Um there you
know and then you know Seymour Papert
will come along um and be like oh man
why can't we learn math the way that
like kids who go to visit France learn
French? um why can't we make a thing
which is math land? I bet logo could be
like math land. He has a set he have a
set of ideas about what good teaching
and learning looks like and he
incorporates those ideas. Um and they
and people become partisans of these
ideas. Um you know probably the most
prominent partisan of education
technology in the United States today is
Salon. Um who's someone who like had a
very particular idea like a like clear
vision of what personalized learning
would look like. you know, he had he had
I don't know if you know about his his
personal experience, but he was like a
hedge fund person or something like that
and his uh um niece was having trouble
with math and he started tutoring his
niece in math and he put like did it
over videos and so he put the videos
online, people started watching them. He
go, "Wow, what if every person could
have this little like personalized
tutor?" Um what if each person could
sort of study math at their own
individual pace? Um, and then he built
this whole enterprise and continues to,
you know, he he's incredibly
enthusiastic about AI right now because
like, oh man, instead of just having me
record um a tutor for each person, like
what if the GPT can like generate
personalized text related to each
individual person or something like
that. Um, and those ideas, you know,
they're it's it's not like they're just
dropped in the world. They're advocated
for. Um, did you all see the New York
Time was it New York Times or Washington
Post? Somebody wrote an op-ed about um
about Salon and AI. It was either in the
Washington Post or the New York Times,
but it was basically something like this
is the first AI that your kid will love
or something like that. And it's
basically just a sort of celebratory
piece of of Kot MIGO. Um good. So, so
that's an unusual group, you know, and
and those groups um they I mean today
they like, you know, like Saw Khan goes
on the Today Show and tells people what
he thinks. He goes to investor
conferences and tells people what he
thinks. He goes to schools, you know,
Harvard and MIT bringing him in every
couple years and things like that. So
these folks advocate for their ideas. Um
they're not, you know, the ideas the
ideas don't fall from the sky. There's a
stakeholder who is advancing those
ideas. Who are some who are some other
stakeholders that seem important? Um, I
thought it was weird that you could
think about like manufacturers and I
mean like like the people who produce
transistors which is like TSMC and ASML
because if a bunch of schools across
America all of a sudden need like
thousands and thousands of iPads and you
have like this big backlog request on
like M2 chips or whatever is in them
right now and then someone like TSMC the
only people who really produce
transistors has this huge float and they
make a lot of money. Yeah. Yeah. that
that that that people become, you know,
that those folks then organize
themselves into trade groups um and they
go to, you know, they they how do they
how do they advance their interests?
They do things like um give some of
their materials away for schools,
demonstration, they create training
programs for their materials and share
them. Um they have sales and marketing
people that go around and get people
advanced about that. Um they like
sponsor conferences. they, you know,
what maybe that they're not even
directly advertising for. They're
they're just, you know, their presence
to try to encourage teachers and other
sorts of groups to to be behind it. Um,
you know, uh, we spend an enormous
amount of money on education every year
in the United States and lot, you know,
the the biggest chunk of that money goes
to pay the salaries of the people who do
stuff and another big chunk of that
money goes to heating and air
conditioning, you know, for which there
are people who are selling those things.
Um but you know basically the third
biggest bucket after those two is the
stuff we buy in schools to help people
learn. Um and so um uh yeah there there
are advocates who are you know the folks
who are not neutral in these things. Um
there are ways you know Apple computer
has been particularly prominent over the
last bunch of years and trying to craft
a vision of itself as a company um that
has a particular role inside colleges,
universities, schools those kinds of
things.
I think something that surprised me, but
maybe it's not that surprising, was like
government government as a whole and
like eludism between governments because
uh in the class we took last semester
like in education. We talked a lot about
like Americanism and how like it's so
linked with education and I know it's
such a big thing to be like oh like this
country has like the biggest amount like
the highest SAT score on average or like
this many people academy or something
like that. So sometimes it really is
just like governments competing against
each other and trying to see like who's
the best of the best. Great. And in the
United States when we talk about
government actors, what are all the
different possible government actors we
might be thinking about?
Education. So there's a US Department of
Education. Who else is there?
So local boards of education. So there's
local boards of education. So a very un
unusual thing about the United States
Department of Education is it is or the
United States education system is it's
extremely decentralized. There are
130,000 schools and there are 13,000
school districts. The modal elected
official in the United States is a
schoolboard member. There are more if if
you are if you're an elected official in
the United States, the thing you are
most likely to be is a schoolboard
member. Um and you know um schoolboard
members are interesting stakeholders.
They are um well and they range from
community to communities. In lots of
communities, they're just like a
community member who's particularly
interested in education. Um but there
are also um people who are looking to um
you know, it's an entry point for people
who are interested in political careers.
Lots of people who you are schoolboard
members go to be on state reps and other
kinds of things like that. This is a
particularly um sort of fakened moment
for people who are politically who are
who are politically ambitious to pursue
those ambitious uh through the school
system. Um especially uh in the American
right um where where reform of schools
has become like a way to get kind of
attention within the political party and
things like that. Um, and uh, and yeah,
there's all there's all kinds of towns
across the country where, you know, and
I think you get some of this is like
some school board is like, you know,
what would be really great is film
strips. Like, let's go big on film
strips. Um, you know, what would be
really great is like closed circuit
television. Um, wouldn't that be a
useful thing to have? You know, and so
it's it's not even like it's not the
teachers, it's not the superintendent,
it's not the people who are sort of in
the schools, it's like some community
members who are like, "Let's do it."
um uh you know I in uh in the United
States today there probably two versions
of that is there are definitely school
boards whose identity is sort of shaped
around like being a cutting edge school
like in a bunch of the affluent suburban
towns around Boston you know like Wells
Lee Newton like they want to be thought
of as having like really great cutting
edge forward thinking schools you know
Newton spent $200 million or something
like that on the last high school that
they built um and so it can be you know
a way they become a schoolboard member
is like I'm going to help the school
system modernize and embrace technology
and things like that. There can also be
the opposite. There can also be people
who come in um the most common is like
people who work for the technology
industry who are like you have no idea
how much surveillance is built into this
technology. Um all the time when I talk
to you know principles or
superintendents who are being like we're
kind of having a hard time you know
helping parents understand why these
things would be useful. It's like
someone who works for Google or
Microsoft or something like that, you
know, who like who knows the
surveillance capacity of these tools and
is concerned about it. Um, yeah, I just
kind of like an anecdote that I used to
work in edtech and educational
publishing and I worked on mostly
products for the state of Florida and
like really showed how much power some
of these districts have like the because
the school board would make a decision
like every several times or one or two
districts in Florida would some say they
need something and that would change the
entire road map for a product that's
used nationally. So it's like you have a
couple people in Florida who are like we
really need this thing and suddenly it's
like kids in Arkansas are also are
learning differently. So I would this is
in this is definitely still true. It's
breaking down a little bit because of
the capacity for sort of a web
publishing and custom publication but
for a big chunk of what you might I
don't know the latter third of the 20th
century the first 10 years of the 21st
century um basic you know like somebody
publishers would publish a US history
book um how do they decide what to make
of a US history book um you say well
like what are the most important states
to sell this history book
in Florida is one of them what are the
other ones You can name them.
California,
Texas, New York, California, Texas, New
York, Florida. Um those are like four of
the most important states just by
population. Um so now you got to think
about like the the standards of th like
the his every state has standards. The
history standards of those four states
are more important than the history
standards of Maine and North Dakota. Um
and as like political things come up
around you know history is where this
happens pretty frequently but it happens
in math and reading and other things
too. Um yeah actually I I used to do
consulting for uh um uh history for
publishers of history textbooks and once
I saw the sort of matrix where it was
like it was like all the possible topics
along the the columns and all of the
states along the rows and like x's of
like where all the topics get t you know
the I mean the other thing is for like
there'll be a huge you know group of
Polish immigrants that come to some
state and like they won't see Polish
people represented in their textbooks
and so they'll be like we're, you know,
we're only going to adopt books that
like talk about the importance of Polish
Americans in the history. You the
publishing companies are like, "All
right, add the Polish and then, you
know, but then the Italians do it and
the Cambodian do everybody else do it
and the textbooks get, you know, that's
why when you picked up your 800 pound um
history textbook, it was full of like
all these like weird little um bits and
pieces and things like that. So yeah,
these these state level I mean here's
another like tiny feature of this but
ends up being important. Um there are
some states mostly in the south where
material adoptions happen centrally or
have some kind of centralized function.
Um so Texas, Florida, they have state
level boards that say you can only adopt
books that pass these boards.
Massachusetts is a huge local control
state. Um the school districts in
Massachusetts will go bonkers if the
state tried to tell them which textbooks
they could or could not use. You know,
there'd be like another revolution. you
know, one if buy land, two if buy um you
know, C-class Mercedes or whatever it
is. Um and uh they they just wouldn't
allow it. But it means that those states
that have this sort of centralized
function actually end up having more
influence over the publishers because
they say, "Look, you want to sell a book
here?" You know, and now it's not just a
book, now it's a web program or things
like that. Now, the thing that sort of
like is breaking away some of that
monopoly, although also causing kind of
problems is, you know, states can say
like, okay, we want to, you know, we're
going to pass all these laws that b that
have the effect of like way ramping down
the teaching of black history. Um, and
you know, publishers can be like, all
right, well, your web version of that
will delete this and this and this and
this, but you know, over in New York or
California and liberal states, you can
have all that kind of stuff in there.
Yeah. Khil. Yeah. And kind of like uh uh
going off of that like the political
platforms play a like a large role in
most of these places in the US that's
very like very much there but as an
example from my own country like there
at every public school they have like a
speaker system like at the start of the
school specifically because they want to
play the national anthem. That's
something they did really early. The
kids have to uh to do it and to like oh
there's so much like technology that
just one thing why is this the only
piece of there is like some kind of
incentive they want to build with like
you know kind of political motive. And
then does does the does that broadcast
system be used at other parts of the day
as well or this only gets used at the
start of the school where the national
anthem have like some like some kids uh
every like classroom does like a session
where they just like do like some
religious stuff uh some like Arabic
poems some like fun facts and then just
that but that's mostly just I I love
that. I think that's a fabulous example.
So, so the the whatever the state
government is like the state is in the
nation the nation state government um
says every school must broadcast the
national anthem every day. Um every
single school in the country then has to
build a technology infrastructure that
allows that to happen and then once that
technology infrastructure is there it
can be used in other kinds of ways as
well or not used or other kinds of
things like that. Um you can find
national examples of this in other kinds
of ways. You know, one of the most
interesting countries right now um for
education policy makers to watch is
Estonia. Um about every decade, like
some country that people aren't really
paying attention to um gets really good
international test scores. Um so
Singapore was it for a while, Finland
was it for a while, people are obsessed
with Finland for a while, and Estonia is
kind of last like who are you people and
why like why are you so good at reading?
Um and uh Estonia is very famous for it
sometimes it's called Estonia. um their
government has really embraced the
internet um in a very centralized kind
of way. And so people are trying looking
at and thinking about how education
technologies are adopted in Estonia and
other kinds of ways. But it but it
wasn't a policy that was just for the
schools. They were like we're going to
put Estonia on the map by having really
good digital government services. And
that national policy decision ends up
affecting the learning experiences of
kids in schools in all kinds of places.
Yeah, that's a great example.
um students what are what are what are
the interests and and and disincentives
of students.
It's cool. It's a new piece of
technology. Okay. So, almost all of us
like novelty. Um that is one of the
advantages that technology has. One of
the um uh although an amazing thing
about novelty is how shockingly quickly
it wears off. Um actually I was reading
this on Reddit the other day. someone a
teacher was being like like I don't like
I brought a Nintendo Switch into class
so we could play these mathematical
logic games and my students were like oh
please miss can we just do worksheets
and I was like fine do worksheets then
um but you know they're like oh man you
want you play some online game I don't
want to play you know now there would
have been some moment that this class
would be like what we could play a
computer game in class this is amazing
um but that is you know um it's a sort
of it's a it's an interesting feature of
education technology adoption that like
novelty can be extremely compelling for
a short period of time and then wear off
pretty quickly. Do you have any comment
on like why students default is now back
to that pen and paper like the way like
because I mean people are always like
education has been the same for decades
and why does it always look this way
even after we've reformed it like why is
the default that pen and paper? Good. So
what well let's just highlight an
important thing that you observed um
which we we were talking about over here
too which is just schools are incredibly
conservative institutions. Um why why
why would that cons small C conser not
rightwing some of them are but um small
C conservative they do things the same
way over and over again. Um what are
some possible reasons for that? One is
if you went and interviewed parents and
said who are another stakeholder that a
bunch of people brought up um how much
do you want us experimenting with your
children? Um the answer to that is going
to be pretty low. Like the enthusiasm
that people have for experimenting on
children is low. Um second um everyone
in the educational system who's an adult
has what's been sometimes called the
apprenticeship of observation. Um you
all have been in school somewhere
between like 13 and 18 years. Um and
that shapes your experience. And so
people who have roughly the same
education level as you go into schools
and become teachers and they bring that
13, 18, 20 years of educational
experience with them. Um, and that
shapes the way you think schools should
unfold. Um, parents can bring those
expectations in. I was I will never
forget this. I was once working I was
conversing with a school in Utah that
was trying to switch to openly licensed
materials. It was pretty I don't know 15
years ago, 18 years ago or something
like that. They were trying to get away
from textbooks and to have people use
digital materials, particularly digital
materials that their teachers could edit
um so that they could make them, you
know, tailor to their students and
things like that. And they said and they
said, "But they still kept textbooks in
classroom." And you know, I can't tell
you whether or not that's true, but he
says, "The reason why we keep textbooks
in classrooms is if there aren't
textbooks in classrooms, parents will be
upset." Um that like parent like parents
when they go into a classroom expect to
see textbooks there. Basically, it was
cheaper to keep buying enough textbooks
to be in all of the classrooms than it
was to like hire administrators to
explain to parents why there weren't
textbooks in the classroom anymore. Um
so all of these different stakeholders
um this sort of conservative vision of
education is kind of part of that. Um
one possibility is that that's really
bad. Um that there actually like way
better ways of doing things that are out
there and it's a bummer that we're so
conservative and that's really holding
us back. Um, another possibility is that
the practices that exist in schools have
been refined over decades and centuries
and they are the way they are because
they're pretty darn good. Um, that they
that that we keep doing certain kinds of
things because they work. Um, so you'll
have to figure out for yourself as you
know if you hear examples of students
kind of adopting old practices, are they
adopting old practices because they work
really well and because they like them,
because they're comfortable and
familiar? Um there's an argument that
particularly in our age where students
are sort of fixated on grades and
performance in a way that they might
have not been in decades past because
you know not not because kids are like
more materialistic or something. It's
because of economic uncertainty. Um
because as the gap between wealthy and
poor people widens and the stakes of
education become higher people become
more fixated on it. Um and so those kids
who are sort of adopting familiar
matters like do they really like the
familiarity or do they know how to do
well in the familiarity and things like
that. But again, like all the, you know,
keep tying all the things we were
talking about back to the decision of
educators trying to implement new
technologies.
Um, everyone in your system is going to
have some kind of conservative impulse
all the way down to students. That
conservative impulse might be balanced
by the uh novelty effect that we're
talking about, but it's in there. So if
you want a new technology to really be
adapted in some kind of meaningful way,
one strategy you can have is to have it
align with existing practices. You could
say let's take technologies that do the
kinds of things that are already
happening in schools. Like that will be
less upsetting. That'll require less
training. That'll require less upset. It
probably also won't help that much. Um I
mean the people selling the technologies
won't say that. But if you're just like
digitizing existing practices, how how
likely are you to have substantial gains
from digitizing existing practices? Or
maybe you're like a big ambitious
reformer. You say, "No, no, no. We could
be doing so much better. We could go
from 2% to 100% efficiency in schools.
We just have to make big changes in our
practice." Well, making big changes in
practice requires convincing people to
change all of these things. Um there was
a I you know, I've read this book a
zillion times now, but I was just
revisiting um a line in here that I
loved. Um it was uh he says something
towards the end that were like
um settings have plans for their
inhabitants. Anybody remember that? He
was he was talking about the physical
layout of a classroom but but he was
using a broader sociological principle.
Settings have plans for their
inhabitants. Um people interact in a
space in a certain way because the
physical space is laid out and built in
that way. So I was talking with these
guys about one of the problems that film
strips have. To have a film strip in
your classroom, you have to take a giant
projector on wheels and you have to roll
it into the space. There would have been
some classrooms, you know, filled with,
you know, early 20th century, you know,
urban schools with tons of immigrants
who are pouring in on America's shores
that don't have room in their classroom
for a big thing. Um, the other thing
that film strips had that was a huge
pain is these giant film reels. You
know, the early film reels were really,
really big. Where are you going to put
these things? You know, your town did
not build a building um that that had
like, you know, an archival film studio
storage unit attached to it. Um let's
say you have a big school and there are
four first grade classes and you want to
buy a film strip for all four of those
first like are you going to build are
you going to buy four copies of the same
film strip? Like is each classroom going
to have its own film library? If it has
some centralized library, you have to
have some way of like tagging,
archiving, maintaining those things,
bringing into classrooms. I mean, there
are contemporary versions of all of
these things. Um, oh, you want to give
every kid a device? Um, how is that
kid's device going to get on the
network? How is they going to be able to
log in? Who's going to deal when they
lose their password? What's going to
happen when their devices break? Are you
going to make a Are you going to make
families pay for the devices they break?
Your kids are super poor. They can't
afford that. So, you're going to
contract with insurance company. who on
your staff has experience contracting
with insurance companies to ensure um uh
you know uh uh computing devices like
you didn't learn that at your I mean
we'll talk with the education school
deans on Wednesday but I'm pretty sure
they're not teaching their um their
their their students how to manage
insurance contracts and things like
that. Um all of those things become you
know um if if well they you know they
have a combination of incentives and
disincentives that are associated with
them. Um, good. Any any of these other
people that it seems like is important
for us to touch on before we um come to
conclusion. We talked about parents. Um,
you know, I I mean I don't know that how
much we talked maybe here's one last
thing that we could sort of talk about.
We talked a little bit about school
administrators. Um, but like a a thing
to be particularly attentive to um in uh
um in schools is just how many different
kinds of adults with different roles
there are. So, we talked about teachers.
Um, there are people who are school
principles. Like, if you're a school
principal, what are what are the most
urgent concerns that you have on any
given day? Um, what what like what are
what are the main incentives you have as
a school principal? Your budget. Yep.
You got to make sure you can pay for
everything. A teacher's not worried
about that. Teacher will buy as much,
you know, if a school pay for it,
they'll take as much technology as they
want. you know, some of them, but
principles have to balance a budget or
or, you know, I mean, the weird thing is
in the United States, it may not at all
be a principal's role to balance a
budget. It may be entirely a district
role. So, there are some school
districts where the district will make
all the purchasing decisions. There are
other districts where the districts will
take big chunks of money, send it down
to schools, and say, "Schools, make all
the purchasing decisions."
Um, what what else is super important
for principles? I was going to say like
just like maintaining the school
building itself for like student safety.
Yeah. Yep. student safety, maintaining
the physical school building, making,
you know, making sure things are running
and operating and stuff like that. Are
they also managing the relationships
with like the district and also parents
like all these outside? Yep. Yep. So,
so, so, um, they and they are, you know,
principles are sort of quintessential
organizational behavior, middle
managers. Um, they're like empowered to
do some things but not others. They're
accountable to lots of different kinds
of stakeholders. There's all kind of
complexity in what they're doing. Um uh
a lot of them are pretty keyed evaluated
based on test scores like especially in
places where people are at where
students are at risk of not passing
tests. Um and depending upon the policy
infrastructure test scores really matter
to them. Um safety and the orderly
operation of schools man like you know
in in like every person in a building
wants schools to be orderly but when
schools are disorderly the person who
has to deal with it the most is like an
assistant principal or the principal.
It's just more work for them. um you
know you know um you like let all the
kids have phones and you know fights
break out and all kinds of things happen
like it's the you know teachers have to
deal with it but the principles really
have to deal with it. I just like really
short comment just when you asked us
like what does a principal do? I've been
around them my entire life and I was
like I can only think of like two or
three things that I know a principal
actually does and I just think it's
really strange that like most people
aren't sitting you down being like this
is the person you go to for x y and z
things
around these organizations good good so
there there are I think there are a few
things that you can grasp from that
insight is first of all schools are just
unbelievably complicated um I've spent
the last 20 years basically doing
nothing but thinking about schools and I
still don't understand all the things
that are going on in there. They are
like if you want like just as an
ecosystem, they're unbelievably complex
and fascinating. Um the second is as you
transition if you decide to work be
involved in education, you sort you kind
of have to like relearn all this stuff
going from a student to being someone
who's working in education. Like there's
all kinds of things that were hidden
from you, masked from you, or just sort
of weren't important to you. You know,
like the odds that any of you were like
real troublemakers is pretty low given
that you're at MIT. Um but you know
there you know there's a classroom full
of people sitting somewhere um that like
knew principles pretty intimately
because they spent a bunch of time in
their office um because you know because
of things that they did and so forth. So
good. Yeah. If if if part of what
happens to you in this class is uh a lot
of times in social science we talk about
making the familiar unfamiliar. Um a
thing that you've looked at your whole
life and being like whoa look at all
these things there that I wasn't sort of
paying attention to or you know wasn't
made aware to me and those kinds of
things. Um maybe here's here's one very
concrete thing. Um uh let's think of
something like uh um a student
information system. Um or Canvas. Let's
think of something like a learning
management system. Who spends the most
time using
Canvas? Tell me about the people who use
Canvas.
Students. Students spend a lot of hours
logged in looking at stuff on Canvas.
Who else looks at Canvas? Teachers.
Teachers. Who buys Canvas? this true not
students and teachers in in in uh um in
business school I think they would call
this a third party payer problem. Um so
if you are a company that's making a
learning management
system who's like of your
stakeholders who has the most power to
determine whether or not your thing gets
purchased like some director of
education technology or something like
that some IT person. So, if you ever if
you've ever wondered like why is this so
terrible? Um, it wasn't built for you.
Like in some in some important ways, it
was literally not built for you. It was
built to solve the problems of some
middle level information technology
manager. Who's going to buy one of those
things? Um, so third-party payer
problems are rife across. I mean, the
problem with third-party payer problems
from like a classical economics point of
view is you just have misaligned
incentives. um you know um in in some
respects you could say that improving
the teaching and learning experience on
canvas is a cost um it's something that
like reduces your pro profit obviously
you have to make it good enough so that
you know if like enough teachers and
stuff are rolled I once anyone ever have
to use blackboard
okay good um I once met the I once met
the guy who made blackboard and I was
just standing there in line behind him
or something like that being like what
would it be like to have made a piece of
software that millions of people hate
like what like what would it have been
like to like introduce so much
unhappiness in the world with what
you've built like and I it was it would
have been rude I think in the buffet
line to to to ask him to ask him that
question. Um here's another thing that I
want to say about who buys these things
and this is really um important too
especially to any of you who are
interested in either an education like
starting an education startup or other
kinds of things. Um uh who in a school
can buy technology? What are some
possible titles of people who buy
technology?
We've mentioned a few. Librarians, a
librarian could buy technology.
Department chair. A department chair
could buy technology.
Teacher. A teacher. They're amongst the
least likely. Actually, one of the
sometimes people have made the argument
that a that a problem in the education
system is it's very it's very difficult
to have a real sort of bottomup
marketplace kind of effect. Um like
teachers have in most places teachers
have very few discretionary dollars um
to the I mean that's why they're like
holding big sales and asking like you
know when you become parents like your
teachers will ask you to bring in boxes
of tissues and things like that and
you'll be like what what broken failed
country do we live in where you cannot
simply buy all the tissues that you need
for the children um or paper two reams
two yeah two yeah two reams of paper a
semester for all your students you know
all right so the teachers don't have in
some cases they do, but in a lot of
cases you don't know what I mean.
Principles can buy things, directors of
instructional technology can buy things,
assistant superintendents can buy
things, superintendents can buy things,
school boards in some places can
directly authorize kinds of things,
although that's probably more rare, but
they can push for it. Um, but the point
is across the 13,000 school districts
and 130,000 schools in this country, the
answer to the question, who can buy
something is different in all of those
contexts. Um, that makes starting an
education technology company very very
difficult.
Um, when you go somewhere, you don't
even know who can buy the thing. Um,
like you don't even know who you're
selling it to. Now, there are people who
do know who buys all these things. The
only people in the United States who
know for every school in every district
who has the power to buy stuff are giant
publishers. Um, Pearson, Hotton,
Mifflin, what was the company you work
for? McGraill. McGraill. Perfect. They
have an army of salespeople. this army
of salespeople have fanned out across
the 13,000 school districts and once a
month, once a quarter, all the people
who I just listed who can actually buy
things, they take them out to lunch.
They bring them free supplies. They do
all that stuff. They, you know, like
they probably don't have a master list
somewhere. Instead, they have all these
sales people who know the answers to
these questions. Um, so if you're a
Silicon Valley startup and you're like,
"Oh, I know I've got this new like AI
thing I'm building. It's super cool." Da
da da. You don't have this massive
network of sales connections to help you
figure this out. Um, one my one of my
favorite illustrations of this is at a
bunch of education technology
conferences. Um, how many of you ever
have been to a conference where they
have like you have you have a badge,
right? And you can put stickers on your
badges or other things like this.
Basically, like one of the stickers you
can put on your badge. You can put like
your pronouns. You can put some other
things like that. You can put um buyer.
You can basically like signal to people
like I actually have the power to
purchase things. Um and then when you w
you know um uh if you know when you walk
through the exhibit hall they will pay
more attention to the people who have
the little buyer things on them than
they will to like you know critical
social science researcher badge um is
put on your thing or something like
that. So that is an incred so um here
are some things that you should take
away. These these systems are incredibly
complicated. There are all kinds of
stakeholders in them but they're they're
not so infinite. they're not so complex
that we can't like make a chart that
sort of manages and starts to understand
all these things. Um but as we move
forward and as we um look at more sort
of you know a thing that a thing that
you can do in any kind of education
technology problem any educational
setting be like all right who are going
to be the stakeholders for this problem
this thing and what are going to be
their interests. Um the more you know
and not you know again not just like
their official interest their official
like state policy interest is to raise
test scores or something like that. Um
but one of my favorite examples um that
we're talking about is uh televisions
were more likely to be used at the end
of the day because people were tired. Um
like your body's circadian rhythm um
indicates how technologies be used in
classroom. And that is just as real is
just as real as the policy mandate to
raise test scores um or the school
board's enthusiasm for technology or
whatever it is. Um and so we we can in
any kind of system we can figure out who
are the stakeholders in the system. What
are the interests of those things? What
are the disinterests? A thing is more
likely to work if it attends to those
real meaningful felt interests and if it
avoids those real meaningful felt
disinterests. And of course we're doing
this like in a very detailed way in
education. But if you were to let leave
education and you were to go into
healthcare, if you were to go into legal
technology, if you were going to retail,
you can do the exact same exercise. um
the technology that you're building for
a hospital, like it has to work for a
doctor, but it has to work for a nurse
and an orderly and a patient and the
patient's representative and the
hospital's lawyers and all these
different kinds of people. Um and so,
you know, on the one hand, especially
when people are designers of software,
we can have this sense of like, oh, I'm
building things for a user. I'm building
things for like this individual user
who's got their fingers on their
keyboard or their thumb on the screen or
something like that. Um, but I would
encourage you as we're thinking through
all these things to to think about these
networks of interests and stakeholders
much more broadly. Okay. Um, we'll talk
to some education school deans on
Wednesday. We'll learn a little bit
about uh implementation, how you
overcome some of these kinds of
challenges from me. We'll hear a little
bit about the National Education
Technology Plan. Um, and I will pair you
up with each other um to be able to do
some peer editing of your essays and
that will get us through the week. Sound
good? Bueno, let me know if I can help
you with anything. Otherwise, have a
wonderful rest of your afternoon.