good morning good afternoon welcome to
lecture
six um today we will be um finishing up
our discussion of summations that
binmore started for us last time and
then moving on to uh asymptotic notation
which is one of the bread and butter
topics of algorithm analysis it's a
really useful uh language and
terminology that we can use to talk
about algorithms and compare algorithms
without getting bogged down in all the
details but before we do that let's talk
about sums and before we do that let's
play with
blocks um so here is a very cool
question I have a stack of blocks you
could imagine it's even taller than this
I just grabbed six for now um and what I
want to do is sort of lean them out over
the table and well okay don't want them
to fall that's that's Criterion one what
I'm hoping for is to get this top block
all the way off of this table um so none
of the block is over the table so
currently I'm not quite there we can see
there's like an inch half an inch left
um so seems possible maybe um so the
rules are we can only have one block per
layer we can't double up we can't do
weird angles and whatnot it's just slide
these left and right until you're happy
and hopefully it doesn't fall um are we
clear on the game nice who thinks it's
possible raise your hand who thinks it's
not
possible all right well let's try
hopefully I don't hurt myself um all
right so I'm going to follow a nice
greedy strategy so I'm going to start
from the top and then I'm just going to
keep sliding left as much as I can until
it's about to fall over so if I go past
the center of mass it's going to fall
over so I'm going to go right up until
that edge and stop and don't worry about
the physics we're not here to talk about
physics um but I'm going to do the same
so let's freeze the top two layers and
try again let's slide this over until
it's just about to fall it feels right
around there all right let's keep
going all
right yep okay it leaned a little bit
I'm getting worried but we'll make it
work let's see uh
yeah okay and I think I might already be
off the table which was my goal but
let's let's go a little further why not
uh yes okay and
finally right around okay that's as far
as I'm willing to go I
think that is off the
table it's possible yes thank you
I cheated I put little marks on the back
so I knew how far to
go um but it is possible and now we can
raise the question how far can we go can
we get two lengths out here's what that
would look like two lengths out can we
get five lengths out 10 lengths out
let's stop at 10 who thinks we can get
10 lengths out over the table who thinks
10 is possible who thinks 10 is not
possible all right you're both right
um I'll explain why in a second uh let's
not have an accident during lecture
there we go so turns out I'm not going
to prove this now but turns out that
greedy strategy I just used is the best
you can do uh it's not too hard to prove
it's in the textbook if you're curious
um but let me tell you what that greedy
strategy ends up looking like um if I
have some chalk here we
go so as you might imagine this first
block sticks out half a unit over the
next block so its Center of mass is
right here on the edge um by the way I'm
I'm imagining these blocks are one unit
wide um the next one right here that's a
quarter unit because that's what it
takes to put the center of mass of these
two blocks combined right over the edge
of the third block turns out this right
here is a sixth this right here is an
eighth and all the way down until the
very n until the the it is the the very
n the nth
block has a gap of 1 over 2 N so this is
block 1 2 3 four five all the way to n
turns out this is the best you can do
which means the distance you can get
with n
blocks is 12 plus a 4 plus a 6 up to 1
over 2
N which let's factor out the 1/2 just
because that's cleaner that's the sum K
= 1 to n of 1 over
K this is also known as 1 12
time the N harmonic
number
harmonic
number this is a standard name for this
sum 1 plus a half plus a thir plus a 4th
up to 1/
n um and half of that is exactly as far
as we can get with n
blocks right so now the question is how
how big does this get if I have a
thousand blocks how far can I get if I
have a million blocks if I have an
unlimited number of blocks how far can I
get which means we're asking about this
sum this harmonic number I want to know
about that sum do we have a closed form
for it no not
really but as we saw last time we don't
especially need a closed form if all we
care about is approximation so let's
approximate that sum
so we have our sum hn which is defined
as the sum of the first n
reciprocals and we want to approximate
it and can someone remind me what tool
we have to approximate sums like
this yes the integral method absolutely
so this function 1/x is a decreasing
function and so we have our integral
method our integral bound that says that
sum
hn is between the
integral plus the last term in this case
the last term is sorry plus the first
term
one and the integral 1 to n of 1x DX
plus the last term which is 1
n so this bound is integral plus F of n
less equal to the sum is less equal to
the integral plus F of
one and I claim this bound is really
easy to remember um like I plus FN I
plus F1 are pretty simple things and
also if you if if you're dealing with an
increasing function instead of a
decreasing function it's the same two
bounds but they're on the other side
just because if it's increasing then FN
is going to be bigger than F1 so
certainly FN should be on the bigger
side but this is a really clean bound um
and and we can write out what this what
this says integral from one of 1 /x DX
from 1 to n that's Ln of n let's assume
we can do that um without writing it
down I you don't want to see me
integrate live that will go
poorly um but what this says is that um
Ln of n + 1 n is less equal to hn is
less equal to Ln of
n + one
all
right which is a pretty nice
bound um but we're really interested
in well first let's answer our question
um if we want to get 10 blocks out then
we're asking for hn to be about
20 which means we're asking for these
bounds these bounds are kind of
basically Ln of n right the one over n
and and the one don't affect things all
that much so really hn is basically Ln
of
n yeah this is I'm being imprecise here
but we'll be more precise about it in a
bit but for now it's about Ln of n which
means to get 10 blocks
out we need hn equals 20 because the
distance was half hn uh which means we
need n is approximately e to the
20 we need that many
blocks uh we need about four 400 billion
blocks to get 10 blocks away from the
table um each one is about an inch and a
half thick so that gets us to carry the
one 40 times the distance to the
Moon um probably going to run into some
other issues before you're able to stack
something that tall um so mathematically
yes we can get 10 blocks over the table
physically not so much that's why you're
both right
um but all of this was really an excuse
to get us here hn is approximately Ln of
n plus some smaller
terms um and let's try to make that a
little more precise what do we mean by
that what do we mean by hn is
approximately Ln of n well let me give
us a definition
[Applause]
let's write that F of n that's a Tilda F
of n is Tia of G of n so this
is
asymptotically
equivalent so f and g are ASM totically
equivalent if and only if the
limit of FN over G of n as n goes to
Infinity
is
one if you divide them and get a limit
of one then these functions are ASM
totically
equivalent and in this case well we have
these nice bounds on
hn well let's take that inequality let's
divide all three sides U by Ln of n what
are we going to get we're going to get 1
+ 1 over n Ln of n is less equal to hn
over Ln of n is less equal to 1 + 1 / Ln
of
N and as we take the limit as n goes to
Infinity the left side looks like one
this thing in the denominator gets big
so one over that gets small the left
side goes to
one limb n goes to Infinity of hn over
Ln of N and on the right side we have
one plus something that goes to zero cuz
that denominator gets arbitrarily
big so the limit equals
one I learned this in high school as the
squeeze theorem if you can bound your
limit between two things that are the
same then the limit is that thing um but
what we've concluded here is that hn
ided Ln of n limits to one as n goes to
infinity and
therefore uh sorry hn over Ln of n
equals 1 which implies that hn is ASM
totically
equivalent to Ln of
n so when I wrote approximately Ln of n
up there probably what I meant was this
much more precise thing that these are
approximately equal in the sense that
their ratio limits to one does that make
sense
nice all
right um
now before moving on to ASM totic fully
uh there's one other topic in summations
that I want to talk about which is not
summations at all but
products um and really what I want to
say about products is that often you can
analyze products as if they were
sums turn into
sums for example if we care about n
factorial
which is uh here 1 * 2 * 3 all the way
up to
n who can tell me how to turn this into
a
sum it's something written on this
board
yes yeah take logs perfect what happens
if we take the log of both
sides so log of n factorial uh here
let's let's be precise we'll call it Ln
of n factorial the natural log so log
base
e well remember when you take logs
products turn to sums in this sense this
becomes Ln of one plus Ln of 2 plus Ln
of 3 plus Ln of
n so if we want to understand n
factorial we could just as well
understand its log and its log is the
sum of a bunch of other logs and now we
have a sum and we can use all of our
summation uh tools on this sum to get
information about n
factorial for example we could use the
integral bound Ln of X is an increasing
function this time so we use the
increasing version of the
bound uh which says
that uh here we go so Ln of one plus the
integral from 1 to n of Ln of X DX is
less equal to the sum of Ln of K
K = 1 to n Which is less equal to Ln of
n plus the same
integral and if we do out that integral
like I said you don't want to see me
integrate live I will get it wrong um
but if we trust my notes this integral
comes out to um n Ln of
n um minus n +
1 Ln of one is zero thankfully keeps
things simple and so what we end up
finding is that n Ln of nus n + 1 is
less equal to this sum which as we know
is Ln of n factorial Which is less equal
to this same integral plus another Ln of
n n + one Ln of nus n +
1 so we were able to translate this
product into a sum and then use our
summation tool um to get get us a bound
on Ln of N and if we want to bound on N
factor sorry Ln of n factorial I
misspoke if we want to bound on Ln I
misspoke again apologies if we want to
bound on N factorial itself we can just
undo the log by exponentiating all three
of these take e to this e to this e to
this that preserves our
inequalities and what we'll end up
getting after we simplify it a bit is
that n the N over e to the N minus1 is
less equ to n factorial is less equal to
n n
+1 over e
nus1 so same denominator on both sides
we have n the N versus n the N plus one
on the two sides so the two bounds are
off by a factor of n not as good as we
had last time we are off by an additive
one less than that even but a factor of
n isn't bad for a number as big as n
factorial this isn't a bad
bound um is everyone clear on how we got
to this
bound wonderful it's not the best bound
we have
ow um let me tell you uh two better ones
oh sorry before that is this bound
enough to say that n factorial is ASM
totically equivalent to one side or the
other I see some head shakes can someone
tell me why
that's all right I'm tired
too um these two bounds are too far
apart from each other they're a factor
of n apart and so we can't say that this
divided by this limits to one or this
divided by this limits to one because we
have an N range in there to account for
and N grows to Infinity so we don't know
where in this range and factorial lies
and so we can't pin down that limit
going to a specific value so this isn't
tight enough to say that n factorial is
ASM totically equivalent to
something um but that's where Sterling's
approximation comes
in um Sterling's approximation says that
n factorial is ASM totically equivalent
to theun of 2 piun n * n e to the
end we're not going to prove that but
it's really useful you should write it
down you might end up using it in the
problem set hint
hint um extremely
useful um but remember this is this is
just saying that n factorial divided by
this limits to one so when n is really
really big the quotient of these two
things is close to one
what it doesn't tell us is what happens
for smaller values of n what if n is
just 10 can we use this to approximate
factorial how about 100 how about a
thousand I don't know this doesn't
really tell us it doesn't tell us how
good an approximation this is all it
says is that it's good in the
limit um so let me tell you an even
stronger
bound uh I don't know who to credit this
bound to but it's even more precise than
this one
uh it says that n factorial divided by
this
Thing 2 pi n n / e to the N so this is a
thing that Sterling tells us limits to
one and now we have some bounds on how
quickly it does that e to 1 over
12n e to 1 over 12n +
1 so not only does this limit to one it
does so very very fast exponentially
fast
and this we can plug in specific values
of N and see okay how close is this
approximation to n factorial this is an
effective bound one we can get actual
approximations out of this is just a
limiting bound but of course this is a
lot more complicated sometimes we don't
want to deal with all these details and
this is enough sometimes even that's too
much and that's enough so pick your
level of granularity as you need
it we're also not going to prove this
bound um that's even harder than
Sterling um but it's true and useful
questions on
that all right so that's everything I
wanted to say about summations and now
let's jump back to astics we already
started talking about astics with um ASM
totic
equivalents um and let's do an
experiment uh let's do an exercise um
we've already seen a sorting algorithm
we saw swap sort um in lecture four
where you you have a you want to put it
in sorted order and you do that by
finding a pair that's out of order and
next to each other and changing their
order and you keep doing that keep
finding pairs that are next to each
other and out of order until the whole
thing is
sorted uh and we saw so I'm going to
call that swap
sort we saw that the the number of swaps
that you'll need to make is exactly
equal
to number of
swaps is exactly equal to the number of
inverted
pairs so the number of pairs of two
numbers in our list where the big one is
somewhere to the left of the small one
so they're in the wrong order and we'll
eventually need to change
order um and well how many inverted
pairs could there be in the worst case
well in the worst case every pair is
inverted one the number one is is
inverted with 2 through n
and two is inverted well it's already
inverted through one we already counted
that but two would be inverted with
three through
n those are new in inversions that we
haven't counted yet uh three is inverted
with everything after
it plus one so this is the worst case
number of swaps we'll have to make um
and as we as we've seen we know how to
compute this sum this is n minus one * n
/ two also known as n ^2 over 2us n
/2 and this I'm going to
call S of n we have our function s of n
s being reminiscent of swap sort it's a
function describing the worst case
number of swaps we'll need to make in
swap
sort on Thursday we're going to see
another sorting algorithm called merge
sort uh I'll describe it then I'm not
not going to describe it now that's we
don't need to know what it does or how
uh we just need to know how fast it runs
how many comparisons does it have to
make um so let's
define M of n this is going to be n log
2 of n minus n + one uh and on Thursday
we'll see that uh that merge sort takes
at most this many steps to
complete and now I want to know between
these two function
between these two algorithms which one
is a better choice for sorting lots of
numbers if these are the two algorithms
I have to pick from and I know their run
times they're n^2 / 2 - n / 2 versus n
log 2 N - n +
1 this is s this is
M which one's the better
choice um and sorry that was rhetorical
um let's talk through it um let's do
sort of an eye tracker to see which
parts of the various formulas we look at
when making this comparison uh and just
to emphasize I'm I'm most worried about
what happens with lots and lots and lots
of numbers I'm trying to sort a million
a billion a trillion numbers um so I'm
interested in what happens in the limit
as n gets really really big if we're
trying to sort 10 numbers well I don't
care that's what however you want to do
it is fine 10 is small um but with big
data no one uses that term anymore I
don't know why um with lots and lots of
data these these differences matter so
let's see how we make this comparison
what are we going to look at well the
first thing my eye goes
to is this right here which is to say
that's the last place my eye goes I
don't care about that term the n^2 over
two is much more important
um by the time we're up into the N squar
it's an a little measly n / two doesn't
really make much of a difference right
intuitively anyway I haven't made this
precise but the first thing that I do
when looking at this is I just
completely ignore that N /2 I don't care
likewise I don't care about this n minus
one that we're subtracting the N log n
grows faster than that uh so with big n
this is going to dominate and this is
just going to be a rounding eror
so that's the first thing I do ignore
the lower
terms now I'm just comparing n^2 2
versus n log
n the next thing I
ignore is this over
two I don't really
care I don't care that we're dividing by
two if this had been n^2 divided a th if
this had been a million time n log n is
that really going to change my
determination
for small n values yeah those constants
matter those lower terms matter for that
matter when n is small but in the limit
as n gets bigger and
bigger that that extra factor of n is
going to overtake that extra factor of
log n no matter what constants we throw
in there
right so I don't really care about those
as well really all I'm focusing on is
the
N2 versus the N log n does that make
sense um every everything I just did was
completely informal I haven't Justified
any of that but we will um but first we
need to motivate it and there's one
other reason uh one other motivation for
not really caring about this constant
Factor uh with swap sort we were
counting what were we counting the
number of actual swaps we
make um we didn't say how you're finding
those swaps but there are there are
clean ways to do it so that the number
of steps you take um in the whole
algorithm is about n^2 over
two um but wait we have to do more steps
than just the swaps right we have to
like read numbers from memory we have to
um compare them we have to write numbers
to memory we have to increment our index
we have lots and lots of instructions
that we have to do during this algorithm
so maybe it's just those four
instructions every time we make a swap
so it's really four times n^2 over two
instructions
right instead of counting swaps we're
now counting instructions and I'm being
very loose about that but doesn't matter
um okay well not all instructions are
are created equal um every instruction
on your CPU happens on a a fixed regular
clock um and maybe ads
take when we have to increment our index
maybe that takes I don't know five
Cycles uh and
comparisons take 15 cycles and
read and write to memory take I don't
know 200 Cycles because memory is a lot
slower than arithmetic I made up these
numbers by the way these aren't real
don't trust me on that um but in this
fiction if we're counting Cycles instead
of instructions we're doing like one of
each of these per per round or something
um so really we're doing if I did my
math right about 210 *
n^2
Cycles okay so we're changing our unit
we're measuring different things um
let's measure something else say we're
on a 2.4 gigahertz processor 2.4
gigahertz processor how long does this
take in in real life time well it takes
about 210 divided 2.4
billion seconds uh sorry times n^ 2
seconds right so if we change what we're
measuring if we change our units
instructions Cycles
seconds the thing that stays is the N
squared the constant
changes but it's always proportional to
n^2 get a better um CPU um higher
throughput your time decreases but only
by a constant factor it's still
proportional to
n^2 this is another reason that it's
useful to be able to just ignore that
constant I don't care what it is because
I don't really care specifically what
units we're
measuring um I just care that it's
proportional to the right
answer does that kind of make sense why
we might want to throw away information
like this because it's easier to think
about n squ is easier to think about
than all this other junk cluttering it
up
um one more one more motivating example
what's the population of the
US does anyone know just off the top
yes about 330 million
absolutely about
335 um what is it um I wrote it down
893,00
is that more useful than what your
colleague said 330
million I don't get any more information
out of that in in my measly little brain
330 is I already have trouble conceiving
of a number that large I don't need all
the extra detail
right same for algorithm analysis I want
to be able to just focus in on the parts
that matter and have the option to strip
off the parts that don't so that's our
motivation we want to be able to to
communicate less information about the
run times of our algorithms or about
other
functions while still being
mathematically precise about it and
making sure we know what what was lost
what information are we retaining and
what information are we losing never to
to get again because
sometimes you need that extra
information throwing away all this stuff
is a great like broad Strokes way to
compare um certain algorithms but if we
have two algorithms that are both
proportional to n log n oh well now that
constant Factor really matters and we
better go and figure out what it is
likewise if we're comparing the US
population between this year and last
year well last year it was also about
330 million in change so if all we know
is 330 330 we can't compare them we
don't know if it went up or down or by
how much um turns out last year it was
about
334 um2 million
um
million so now we had a reason that we
wanted more information wanted more
precise measurements of the population
than just 330
million um but wait until you have that
reason let's let's do the broad stroke
stuff first and often that'll be
enough does that make sense as a
motivation for why we want to throw away
information about our functions
nice so
let's talk about how to do
that uh and the the main one we're going
to talk about is called Big O
notation the idea this is not yet a
definition still an idea uh we're going
to say that F of n belongs to Big O of G
of
n weird notation but you'll get used to
it um
when well roughly
F of n is less equal to G of
n roughly if we say f is Big O of G what
we're saying is that an algorithm with
runtime f ofn is at least as fast maybe
maybe much faster than an algorithm with
runtime G of
n with some
caveats with
caveats first of all let's throw away
constant factors
if we have to scale G up by 10 and now G
is bigger that's fine that's still Big O
uh and likewise we're going to ignore I
don't care what happens for small
numbers
ignoring small n don't need them I care
about what happens in the limit what are
the trends when n gets bigger and bigger
so these are my intuitions um
also
ignoring lower order
terms I still haven't defined that
either by the way but we talked about
them over here like the N /2 was a lower
order term compared to n^2 over two I
want to be able to ignore things like
that so this is still not precise let's
finally finally make it precise after
this question
yes oh no I want to give the definition
thank
you uh okay so our definition our actual
final definition of Big O is the
following um f of n is in Big O of G of
N
means
okay there exists a number greater than
zero and there exists a natural number
and not
such that for all n greater or equal to
n f of n is less equal to C
* G of
n um and if we're not being if we're not
restricting to positive functions
sometimes we put an absolute value in
there that's less important the other
parts of the formula are the more
important parts there exists a constant
factor C so that f is less equal to C *
G that's this ignoring constant
factors um there exists an N so that all
n greater than n greater than or equal
to n so there's some starting point so
that after that starting point this this
inequality is always true and I don't
care what happens before n
knot
um so that's this point here ignoring
small n small n are the ones smaller
than n then n not um n Subzero is
sometimes pronounced n not n a u g
HT uh
question oh gosh yes thank
you uh G of
n not the line I wanted to mess up today
thank you so much yes F of n is in bigo
of G of N means roughly that g is bigger
if you're allowed to scale it by a
constant and throw away small
values all right
yes yeah um
so
um FN is in bigo of g ofn means that
there's some positive value C and some
starting point n KN so that for all
input values that are bigger than n not
or equal FN is less or equal to C * G of
n uh so this is extending our intuition
that FN is small that f is smaller than
G but you're allowed to put in a
constant Factor if you need to before
that's true
yes um yeah so why are the question was
why are we putting in a constant Factor
when the whole point was to ignore the
constant Factor we ignore it by saying
that there exists a constant factor and
I don't care what it is as long as some
constant exists that makes this formula
true then f is Big O of
G um so we put it in so that we can not
care what its value is um yes can the
Conant between Z and one can the
constant be between zero and one good
question sure why not um if you want to
make G smaller and it's still bigger
than F go for
it no problems there all right let's do
some examples hopefully some concrete
examples will make this a bit
clearer um let's
say F of n is n g of n is n
2 is f of n in Big O of G of
n so is n in Big O of n
squ well if this is supposed to say that
the thing on the right is bigger then
hopefully we would want n squ to be
bigger than n and thankfully it is um in
this case we don't need the C to help us
f is already smaller than g n is already
smaller than
n^2 n is less equal to 1 * n^
2 for all n for all natural numbers n so
this would be our n value of zero and
this would be our C value of one all we
have to do is show that some not exists
and some C
exists to make this statement true and
then we're able to conclude that n is
Big O of n^ s
question um ah good question um don't we
need n not to be one because this
inequality is false when n is between
zero and one um excellent point um
I'm going to give two fixes for that
first of all we could change this to one
absolutely that's fine um the other
change is that let's go ahead and assume
that f and g are mapping the natural
numbers to the real
numbers so the inputs are just 0 1 2 3
and not all the real numbers in between
often that's what we use when we're
analyzing algorithms because we don't
have fractional inputs to to algorithms
um you could absolutely do all of this
analysis and all these definitions if
your domain was the reals
instead um but let's let's deal with
Naturals great uh great point also in
fact why don't we go ahead and assume
that all our functions are positive
valued um then we won't need that weird
absolute value you can still do a lot of
this um if you allow some of your
functions to be zero or negative but but
let's not clutter our minds with that
today let's go ahead and assume that all
of our functions map the natural numbers
to positive real values
yes um the question was is this
statement equivalent to saying that f is
ASM totically equivalent to some
constant multiple of G that's a great
question the answer is no uh and I'll
challenge you to think about why
um let's do a few more examples uh
actually I want to come back over
here all right F of n is n
s g of n is n F of n in Big O of G of
n is n s smaller than n if you're
allowed to scale by a
constant and this time the answer is
no um an algorithm that takes n s time
certainly wants to look slower take
longer than an algorithm that takes n
time so if Big O is going to be useful
for algorithm
comparison we hope that this would be f
and thankfully it is and let's talk
about
why um so if n s were in Big O of n we
would
need there exists a c and there exists
an
N so that for all n greater equal to n
KN uh let's see n^2 is less equal to C *
n right I just wrote out the
definition so we would need to be able
to pick some constant and some starting
point so that after that starting point
n^2 is always less equal to that fixed
constant times n but no matter what
constant we
pick when n gets big enough this
inequality is always
false we can't pick a constant big
enough so that this remains true for all
n for all big n if we pick C is a th
then from a th and one on this
inequality is going to be be false if C
is a million then from a million and one
on this inequality is false no matter
what C we pick the left side will
overtake the right
side right and increasing n not doesn't
help with
that even if we ignore more small values
all the big values fail you can't ignore
all the values
so
um can't
choose c big enough
all right so thankfully n^2 is not Big O
of n uh let's do another example uh is
n^2 + 3 n + 7 is that Big O of
n^2 we said we wanted to be able to
ignore lower order terms ignore things
that look
smaller um
well this one ends up being true and
let's see why well we can write right
there are lots of ways to prove this um
I'm going to be extremely wasteful and
do the following n^2 + 3 n + 7 is less
equal to n^2 + 3 n^ 2 + 7 n^
2 all I'm doing is saying this n is less
equal to n s this
seven uh this seven is less equal to 7 n
2 right and this
equals 11 N2
and so we've we were able to show that
this function is less equal to 11 * this
function for all
n so we can take n equals z and C is 11
and we're
done so lower order terms like this at
most Force us to pick a bigger C if we
want but again we don't care about the
specific value of C as long as such a
value exists so we can always swallow up
these these smaller terms just absorb
them into that c constant
yes good question what if we didn't know
whether one function is bigger than
another function just by looking at it
um well that is that is our task um
we're trying to compare these functions
and if we don't know which one's bigger
then we better figure figure that out
before we get our
answer so I don't have a general way to
do that um I'm I can just say that it's
necessary um let's do another example 3
n is that Big O of n minus 4 we were
also saying we'd like to be able to
ignore lower order terms on the right
hand side and intuitively that n minus 4
that minus 4 term doesn't really change
anything
this should still look like Big O of
n right and we can make that precise um
nus 4 is greater than or equal to n
minus well n
/2 when n is at least
eight all we're saying is that the N
function overtakes the four
function excuse me so this four we can
pretend it's a
n/2 we've lost a lot but it doesn't
matter because this is still a
constant time
n so this
function is bigger than a constant time
n and we can use that to do our proof um
3n let's see 3 n is less equal to 6 * 12
n Which is less equal to 6
* um that's that so nus 4
when n is at least
eight and so now we have our
C and we have our
n 3n is less equal to a constant times n
minus 4 which is the function we care
about so in the same way we can ignore
lower order terms on the right again by
just swallowing them into the constant C
at the cost of a slightly higher
constant C does that make
sense nice now some of you might
recognize the definition of Big O is
looking a lot like Epsilon Delta
definitions of limits and you if you
haven't seen those that's fine don't
worry it doesn't matter but um they are
similar Concepts and we have a useful
fact that um compares the two that I
will write down now
theorem so we're assuming that f and g
are functions from
n to r+ to the positive
reals
if the limit of f of n over G of n as n
goes to
Infinity
exists and equals
infinity so if F over G gets arbitrarily
big then there's no constant you can
choose to bring G back up to F because F
gets um bigger and bigger compared to
G then f is not
in Big O of
G
likewise if the limit
exists and is less than
infinity then f is
in Big O of
G and
finally if the limit does not
exist inconclusive F might be Big O of g
f might not be Big O of G if the limit
doesn't exist the limit doesn't help us
get an
answer but if the limit does exist it
tells us the answer if the limit exists
it tells us yes in this case no in that
case so this is a one-sided test if the
limit exists you're golden if the limit
doesn't exist you have to fall back to
the more complicated
definition all right uh I'm not going to
prove that it's uh not difficult to
prove it's in the notes if you want to
read about it but let's use it uh let's
see is n^2 in Big O of a million
n well how do we test that let let's use
this limit test we can look at the limit
of f over G of n^2 over a million n as n
goes to Infinity n^2 over a constant
time n that's
infinity and so the limit exists it
equals infinity and that tells us that f
is not Big O of
so very often if you're working with
actual functions and you can actually
take the limit and the limit actually
exists you get your answer much faster
than if you were trying to think through
the C's and the nend knots and
whatnot um another example is a thousand
in Big O of
n^2 what the heck do I even mean by that
a thousand isn't a function of N I
thought we were talking about functions
of
n
right well it is a function of n if you
want to think of it that way let me plot
it for
you let let me plot the N
SAR this is uh n s and let me plot the
function that takes every n and sends it
to the value a
th right right so this is f of n which
is defined as no matter what your input
is ignore it and spit out a thousand
it's the constant function that spits
out a thousand so when you see something
like this when you see a constant in one
of these ASM totic uh notations it's
really talking about the constant
function that sends every n to that
value and in that
sense now we can ask is this constant
function Big O of
n^2 and we can answer it the same way as
before by looking at the limmit of f
over G the limit of f which is a th over
G which is N2 2 as n goes to
Infinity that limit is zero so
yes yes a th is Big O of n^2 when the
limit exists it's great we're very
happy more
examples we're trying to be permissive
with constant factors right
so is it true that 3 to the N is Big O
of 2 to the
N if constant factors don't matter then
maybe I maybe I should be able to change
this constant to a different constant
and it won't really change according to
Big O is this
true and this time it's not because we
can try our limit test the limit of f
over G that's 3 the N over 2 the
N that's the limit of 1.5 to the
N which is
infinity so the answer is no changing
this two to a three isn't changing by a
constant factor it's changing by a
constant Factor n
times and that n um gets bigger and
bigger so the difference between the two
sides gets bigger and bigger so this is
uh this is a no
all right um some quick
notation I've been
writing F of n is in Big O of G of
n um and this is my preferred notation
this is set notation f ofn is an element
of this set so big O of G of n is really
a set of all the functions that have the
relationship we
described this I think is the clearest
notation it's what I it's what I
encourage you to use but you're going to
see some other not ations for example
you're going to see F of n equals Big O
of G of n which is just super confusing
I don't like it I don't recommend using
it but it is pretty standard in the math
community so you are going to see it so
I have to warn you
um you're also going to see f ofn is
less equal to Big O of G of
n this is again an an abuse of notation
FN is a function this thing on the right
is a set but it's communicating the same
idea in fact it's emphasizing that same
idea Big O means that g is bigger than F
roughly and so this less equal sign is
just a reminder of that so this is also
good notation I recommend it if you want
to use
it um you're also going to see f ofn is
Big O G of n instead of is an element of
Big O of G of n that's also fine um
pretty clear unambiguous
all of these mean exactly the same
thing sound
good all right what you should not write
ever um so we were
saying uh for example we know that merge
merge sort MN is less equal to Big O of
uh swap swort of n those two functions
we looked at earlier the n s one and the
N log N1 so this is a true statement
right the one was smaller if we want to
say that the S is
bigger should we say that SN is greater
or equal to Big O of M of
N and from the way I'm phrasing the
question the answer is probably no um no
we should not write this that's like
saying you must be at least 60 in or
less to ride this
ride how tall do I need to be
6 it's not correct um Big O is functions
that are smaller than M of N and if
we're supposed to be bigger than some
functions that are smaller than M of n
it doesn't make sense don't write that
however this is still an idea that we
often want to communicate s is bigger
than M we want to emphasize that s is
bigger than M instead of emphasizing
that m is smaller than S and we have
different notation for that instead of a
big O we use S is
big
Omega of M of M of
n so big Omega is just the the reverse
of Big O U we have our
definition f is in big Omega of g
means that g is in Big O of f let's take
that as our
definition and we're getting lots of
symbols around here so let's see if we
can compile them into a table
so we started with f is ASM totically
equivalent to
G um the definition is that the limit as
n goes to Infinity of f of n over G of n
equals
1 the idea the intuition is that f is
equivalent to
G um up to lower order terms lower order
terms that was our
intuition then we had Big O F is in Big
O of
G the definition this time was there
exists C greater Z there exists uh n KN
greater equal zero so that for all n
greater equal to
n uh F of n is less equal to C * G of
n so that's our definition
our
intuition is that f is less equal to
G up to constant values up to constant
factors and I'll say lower order
terms and ignoring small numbers but
that one does that
too please don't confuse the intuition
with the
definition and please don't use the
intuition language in your proofs use
the the definition language in your
proofs so think about it this way but
write it this
way and we Justus
defined f is in big Omega of
g means the definition is that
g uh is in Big O of
F and the idea is that uh G is greater
sorry is
that f is greater equal to
G up two
constants and lower order
terms right so we have a a more
permissive version of less equal that's
Big O A more permissive version of
greater equal that's big
Omega questions about
that all
right um what did I want to say about
that let me Define one more while I'm
over here f is in Theta
of G that's a capital Greek
Theta um and this is going to mean
roughly uh f equals
g sorry f is approximately equal to
G up to
constants and lower order
terms and the definition is just
f is in Big O of
G and G is in in Big O of
f so f and g are roughly within constant
factors of each other in both
directions uh and I want to call
attention to this first one versus this
last
one ASM totic equivalence said that f
and g were roughly equal up to lower
order
terms Theta says that f and g are
approximately equal up to con constant
factors and lower order
terms Theta is more permissive than
Tilda um where did I leave off on the
boards over here yeah over
[Applause]
here
B so we can say that our our s of n
function our our swap sort our simple
sort function n^2 over two and junk
uh is in Theta of
n^2 it's both greater than um n^2 and
less than n^2 if you're allowed to put
constants in
there all
right um what's not
true is SN is ASM totically equivalent
to N2 this is
false um because if you if you take this
and divide by that and take the limit
you get two not one that n^2 over two
matters um so this cares what that
constant factor is this doesn't um this
would be a true statement if you put the
one/ half in
there so the ASM totic equivalence does
single out that constant Factor whereas
Theta ignores that constant
Factor was there a question
um okay so the question was um similar
to your previous question um does f in
Theta of g
mean that there exists a
constant such that f is Tilda of C time
G that's a really good
question um
and the answer I will tell you um is
actually the other
way if there's a constant factor between
them and then the limit goes to one uh
then absolutely they are Theta of each
other but there doesn't have to be that
constant factor and let's look at an
example of that
let's see 3 + sin of
n is that
Theta of
one 3 + S of n we want to know is it
one so is it bounded below and bounded
above by some constant times
one and in this case yes it is because 2
is less equal to 3 + s of n Which is
less equal to
four so there's we can scale this by a
constant and it's always smaller than
our function we can scale this by a
different constant and it's always
bigger than our function and that's the
condition we needed for Big O on both
sides so yes this is
true however you're never going to find
a constant where 3 + sin of
n is ASM totically equivalent to that
constant * 1
because that ratio isn't going to have a
limit this is an example where the
limit of 3 + sin of n over
one does not
exist the function just keeps doing this
forever and never settles down and picks
a single
value so this is an example where the
limit between them does not
exist but still they are Big O of each
other
right um in fact in both directions we
mentioned earlier that if the limit
doesn't exist sometimes um they are not
Big O of each other can anyone think of
an example of that two functions uh
whose ratio does not have a limit where
f is not Big O of G
little
tricky uh let me give Let me Give an
example uh let's say that F of
n is
n and G of n is one when n is
odd and n^ S when n is
even so if we plot
F of n is just n g of n um is following
one or n s depending where you are and
it's sort of zigzagging between the
two if you scale G by a constant you'll
never be able to make it bigger or
smaller than
n um because the the ratio is is too
much depending whether you're looking at
the odds or the evens
um you can't scale it in either
direction so F in Big O of G is
false and G in Big O of f is also
false um and it was specially
constructed so that
limit of f over G as n goes to
Infinity um does not
exist because on the odds F overg grows
really big and on the evens f over G is
really
small sound good
nice all
right speaking of getting really big and
really small um there are two more ASM
totic symbols that we need to add to our
table uh and those are the last two I
promise um the first one I want to
Define is
called little o
so f is in little o of
G the definition is going to be that the
limit as n goes to
Infinity of f of n over G of
n equals z and the
intuition is that f is much much much
smaller than
G if we want to say that f is
insignificant compared to G
that's just saying that the limit
between them goes to
zero right so that's our that's going to
be our definition of little O notation
wise little o and Big O look
similar um so when you're writing those
by hand please try to exaggerate uh I I
like to write My Little O's really
really small um like even smaller than
other lowercase letters and I like to
write my Big O really really big not
like hilariously big but noticeably big
so no one's going to confuse it for a
little
o
um annoying notation that those look
similar so just be aware and uh try to
correct for it um and there's the
reverse f is in little Omega of G that's
the lowercase Omega compared to the
capital Omega up there means the
opposite that the limit as n goes to
Infinity of f of n over G of n equals
infinity
AKA G is in little o of
f so if we want to stress that f is much
much bigger than G we can use the little
Omega
notation that f is much much bigger than
G all
right and these are
useful I mean for the same reasons the
other things are useful they're giving
us more vocabulary to compare functions
um in ways that let us think about only
a small amount of information about each
function um but little o is sort of
exactly what we meant by lower order
term uh
claim uh that f is going to be ASM
totically equivalent to f plus
h if and only if
H is in little o of
f if and only
if the limit of H over f is
zero h of n over F of n as n goes to
Infinity so lower order term just means
the ratio goes to zero in the
limit uh and that's consistent with what
we've been saying with lower order terms
all throughout today lower order term
just means limit goes to zero and we
have a special notation for that
o um f is ASM totically equivalent to f
plus h means that according to ASM totic
equivalence the H didn't change
anything the H was insignificant so
that's another way to think about what
we mean by lower order
term make
sense
nice um cool last thing I want to do
today is a big old warning
Asim totic
notation and
induction don't mix
easily if you're ever doing astics and
induction in the same same
breadth step back take care let's see
what can go
wrong all right so
theorem question
mark 2 to the N is Big O of
one now we really really hope this isn't
true in algorithm terms this is an
algorithm that takes exponential time
this is an algorithm that takes constant
time certainly this one's supposed to be
the smaller one so 2 to the N should
absolutely not be in Big O of one but
let's prove it anyway proof by
induction let's do our base
case n equals z so 2 to the 0o is in Big
O of one
that's just that's saying that one is
Big O of one which it certainly
is all right inductive
step uh assume n is at least
zero and that 2 to the N is in Big O of
one want to show 2 the n + 1 is in Big O
of
one but
but well 2 the n + 1 that's 2 the n + 2
the
N which is Big O of one plus Big O of
one by our inductive
assumption and that is Big O of
one so 2 the N plus one is Big O of one
and we're
done we proved our
induction what the heck went wrong
yes 2 the N plus 1 is not equal to 2 the
N plus 2 the N um it is 2 the N plus 1
is just 2 * 2 the N um which I can write
as two copies of two to the UN added
together um I will tell you the mistake
isn't in this line at all I know I did
something really sketchy right here what
do I mean by o of one plus o of one
that's a set and that's a set why am I
able to add them also I accidentally Ed
that when I meant set membership instead
of
equality but actually this is kind of
fine this is an abusive notation we
didn't really Define what this
means but all we mean by it um o of f
plus o of G this is just the set of
functions um a plus
b where a is in o of F and B is in O of
G this just means the set of things you
can form by taking a one function from
this side and one function from that
side and adding them
together um and it is true that in this
case o of one plus o of one equals o of
one as sets so that's fine that's not
the mistake yes
all right um so let me reiterate um I
proved that every number two to the N is
Big O of one itself but I didn't prove
the function 2 to the N is Big O of one
that's exactly the idea so let's see
what we actually proved here this
here is a correct proof by
induction but what is it proving it it's
a proof of what we what we really proved
is that two to the is is that one is in
Big O of one that was our base case we
proved that two is in Big O of one four
is in Big O of one eight is in Big O of
one 16 is in Big O of
one we proved that each individual power
of two when considered as a constant
function is Big O of one so every
constant function is Big O of one yeah
that's true we proved it by induction
that has absolutely nothing to do with
the two to the N function has absolutely
nothing to do with the definition of 2
to the N being in Big O of
one so we didn't prove the right theorem
we proved something completely
irrelevant does that make
sense so this is why induction and
astics don't mix when you see a function
of n you can't break that function
into individual constant functions one
for each n value you can't induct on N
you have to treat that function
holistically as a single
function sound
good all right um does anyone have any
questions about anything we talked about
yes excellent question does little o
imply Big O uh so if we know that f o
sorry if we know that f is in little o
of
G does that imply that f is in Big O of
G yeah yeah absolutely um and let's
let's think about why this so little o
is defined by uh let's see f um sorry F
over G that limit equals zero
but remember we already said early on
that if the limit
exists then it tells you whether or not
it's Big O and in this case the limit is
zero so it tells us yes we are Big
O yep so little o is absolutely stronger
than Big O it implies Big O um we we
certainly don't go the other
way um likewise
um uh let's see there are lots of other
implications between this between these
so um Theta if f is a Theta of G well
that certainly implies Big O and big
Omega because that's how we Define Theta
and in turn these also imply little o
and little
Omega um because Big O implies little o
as we just saw which means big Omega
implies little Omega because we're just
swapping the
order uh so yeah so we have lots of
implications like this um let me write
it this
way this implies little o and this
implies little
Omega uh and as we already saw ASM totic
equivalence implies
Theta which in turn implies all the
others
yes I got these arrows wrong thank you
no
I'm see I I shouldn't add live at the
board I'm always going to get it wrong
um yeah I apologize Theta implies the
big ones not the little ones um the
little one implies the big one not the
not the other way around sorry for the
confusion um one more
question all right thanks everyone we'll
see you tomorrow at recitation