Today I'll be talking about uh immersive
real-time 3D ultrasound visualization in
augmented reality. Um so I'm in the
media lab in a group called the
conformal decoders. We make kind of
ultrasound uh devices uh both for
sensing and transduction. So we do
things like imaging and neurom
modulation and drug delivery.
Um but to start off
see I'd like to back up and kind of give
a picture of a vision um which is you
know superheroes. We've all seen these
comics. We know that Superman has X-ray
vision um meaning that he can see you
know kind of the bones of people. So, he
uses this power not that often, but
maybe to see bad guys through walls.
Doesn't really make sense cuz you really
need kind of a a sensor on the other
side. It's kind of more of a
transmission imaging. Um, but it's a
cool vision. Um, in real life, what this
kind of looks like is, you know, we have
in many military applications low light
or infrared cameras where you can see
body heat um in darkness. Um there's
also airport scanners u millimeter wave
scanners that you know cycle around your
body and give um a view of your tissue.
It passes through clothes um and can
show objects like weapons on your body.
There's also
Oh, come in. There's a little bit of a
lag. Sorry. Um there's also X-ray
transmission through through trucks. So,
you know, often they scan trucks passing
through the border to look for drugs and
other uh contraband. Um, but that also
creates an image um from one side of the
truck to the other.
Uh, what I was really more interested in
actually is I saw a different comic
where Superman is is using um his X-ray
vision for health to to look inside
people's bodies and to examine the
health of people's lungs. So this was in
1979 the health education con council in
in DC comics. Um but this is really more
of a cool vision for you know how this
superpower can be used. Um so we ask
ourselves you know in the medical
imaging modalities like what can we do
to look inside the human body? Um MRI is
a common form. It's nonionizing safe.
There's 150 million scans a year. Um,
and an image kind of looks like this
where you get soft tissue contrast. You
can see the bone uh brain.
There's also X-ray, which is far more
common, 3.6 billion scans a year. Um,
however, you don't really get soft
tissue contrast, and you can kind of see
uh bones very well, though. Um so um
however X-rays are ionizing meaning you
can only get a certain number of X-rays
every year um before you have a
potential developing tumors and genetic
mutation.
Um and then there's ultrasound uh which
is often used in fetal imaging where you
see images of babies uh in in their
mother's um wombs. Um but it's also used
in cardiac imaging um and it's
nonionizing portable um and 180 million
scans per year. So quite uh largely
deployed in volume. Um but if we look at
all these technologies on a scale of
kind of safety and portability and look
at what is the state-of-the-art
um here we see an X-ray system. So kind
of low on safety because it's radiative
but you know somewhat handheld. Um,
and there's also portable MRI now. So,
you know, they can wheel this around
into the patient room and fit it around
their head. Um, but it's it's very safe,
but it's still kind of cart bearing.
Needs to uh connect to a wall in a DC
power supply. Um, and then there's
ultrasound. So, a butterfly handheld
probe is very common now. It can connect
to the iPhone and stream real time
images directly there. Um, and they're
very cheap. they've become commercially
mass-produced and it's about $100 a
scan. So, in terms of safety and
portability, um you know, ultrasound is
really a great modality for
accomplishing this vision of of having
electronics that are um native and
wearable by the user.
So, if we also look at um kind of the
pipeline of of imaging today, you know,
it starts with the physician. The
physician orders a radiologist uh to
prepare you know a a scan and the
radiologist contacts an imaging
technician to perform the scan in
ultrasound case a synographer
um the technician scans the patient
delivers the report back to the
radiologist and that passes back to the
physician. So it passes through many
hands um just to often get a single view
of you know what's going on inside the
body. Physicians are also allowed to,
you know, do live examinations where
they can just use the probe directly on
the patient because it's safe and get a
feedback for surgical planning um or to
determine something about the patient.
So, uh there is a very long process, but
there's no reason why the physician
can't um examine the patient directly
and gain more information.
Um if we look at how this affects things
um we can see that you know 51% of
medical trainees report no formal
ultrasound training at their institution
and after they get trained they begin to
use ultrasound way more so around 64%.
Um and in uh synographer
went too far ahead uh in synographer
reviewed reports uh they found that
around 18% of the errors were due to
underreading or misfindings um 11% due
to lack of knowledge. So there there is
quite a gap in the training and use um
even among trained physicians.
Um and finally um ultrasound isn't used
to diagnose too many diseases but in
some liver diseases uh carcinomomas um
you know suboptimal liver ultrasound had
a five times higher risk um and a high
false negative rate. So um there are
real consequences to to using ultrasound
incorrectly.
Um but if we kind of just Google
ultrasound user um we can see that you
know every user kind of has is craning
their neck looking at a display and then
operating the ultrasound probe uh to the
side and it's a real pain in the neck
and something kind of we've just
accepted for the past 40 years. Um
so I think you know a better view of of
imaging modalities are that they should
be these immersive interfaces that are
dynamic, intuitive and augmentative. Um
we can see like in Iron Man he's got the
Jarvis display and it's an augmented
view um that you know overlays data
relevant information about about the
real world. So this is the type of
intuitive interface that we want to move
towards. Um and so the question is like
what should not X-ray vision but
ultrasound vision feel like? Um and you
know this is an image that you know
makes sense because underwater
ultrasound waves you know travel um
pretty much unencumbered and so if you
were a sea superhero with ultrasound
vision you would be able to you know
look inside of animals and treat them.
Oh, so uh this leads me to talk about
our work. Let's see. Scroll.
There we go. Okay. Um which is uh the
real-time ultrasound system for
visualizing um 3D ultrasound. Uh so this
is for my team at the conformable
decoders. Um I just want to mention my
co-authors uh Hari, Chennai, Tanisha,
and Bowen. Um um Hari and Bowen are
students at MIT. Um so thank you to
them.
Uh
okay, thank you. Um so yeah, in terms of
previous work, people have definitely
worked on overlaying ultrasound images
on top of real life objects using um
platforms like the hollow lens. Um, but
they often will take a bunch of plain
images and try to reconstruct them into
a 3D overlay that's not dynamic.
Um, there have been other works that,
you know, mix other imaging modalities
like CT scans and kind of use these
sorts of markers to overlay everything
including the ultrasound so that you can
provide cross context. Um, but again,
these are not kind of live images. these
reconstructions.
Um so we worked on a different work um
from a previous grad student Colin. Um
we worked on an a low power 3D
ultrasound imaging system. So this uh
system captures real-time volutric point
clouds with a synthetic aperture sensing
um and has a huge uh field of view 57
degrees and can um image objects up to
11 cm deep. Um because of this image
capture scheme, we can essentially use a
GPU and reduce the data rates and
perform all the 3D uh beam forming um at
two frames per second. Um, so here's a
picture of the system um with
customdesigned electronics. You can see
the transducer at the end. Um, oops. And
essentially we we have this stack that
allows us to produce uh 3D point clouds.
So you can see in this box um these are
different metal objects like springs.
Um, and this is kind of the live image
as it changes. So instead of a 2D fan,
we're producing kind of a box that
represents the volume.
Um, and so the question is now that we
have this system built, how can we port
this into the VR space and how can we
overlay this on top of real life view
and do this in a way where, you know,
there's minimal uh latency. Um so to do
to basically compress a million points
um and stream them across the wire we
had to come up with some special packets
and data frames um to utilize UDP
streaming um to the fullest extent. So
the UDP is a real time asynchronous
system. Um so as soon as you know we
have our beam formed images ready to go,
they're streamed into the gamer engine
and um there's two point clouds that are
overlaid. Uh one point cloud that is
kind of hand manipulatable and another
point cloud that is localized to the
object.
Okay, so this is uh we start with the
the Vario headset. So the Vario XR4 has
been a new release in 2024 and it's been
absolutely awesome. Um very high pixel
uh resolution um and it's much faster.
So we can do things like object tracking
or we can manipulate kind of a plane and
brush it through the 3D point cloud and
kind of see the 2D slices. Um, there's
also built-in eye tracking and
pupilometry, so we can see where the
user is looking. Um, and with all of
this, we can kind of map objects in the
scene, hands, interactions, what the
user is looking at. Um, and so in a
future vision, uh, we want to move
towards kind of a context where aware
assistant um that helps with alignment
or continuous image refinement or even
semantic segmentation.
So uh essentially this is the system. Um
so we're imaging kind of a a phantom
which is a gelatin molded object with a
spring inside. So you can see kind of
the spring and the point cloud overlay
and you know they match up pretty well.
Um
and this system you know also does uh 4D
capture so real time 3D OB uh volutric
capture. So you can see among each of
these time points we're tracking uh this
red small metal ball that's flowing
through a tube. So this is just to show
that um you know it does do these uh
renderings every uh two uh 20
milliseconds.
So again, yeah, this is the interface um
of using the headset. You know, there's
it runs off of a desktop and a laptop.
Um but there's point clouds inside that
that can be manipulated.
Um so essentially we we wanted to
perform a user study to capture the
system in action. Um in order to capture
that we needed to make you know each
pair wise combination. So 2D imaging and
on a screen is the conventional form. Um
but to understand the advantages of 3D
imaging plus AR we also created 2D
imaging and AR and also 3D imaging on
the screen and used these four systems
and brought you know 18 participants
through um a user study um to capture
the effects. Um but before that I guess
we also understood you know how accurate
is this visualization. Um so with the uh
vis visual fiducial marker tracking we
can get you know average errors within 4
millimeters. Um so seems sufficient for
uh certain identification purposes maybe
not um for certain localization things.
Um however
uh when the marker is oluded you can no
longer track the point cloud so then you
know it becomes very costly to lose that
tracking. Uh so instead we started using
the the Vario controller um and
developed a uh a snap fit mechanism for
our transducer to essentially use the
controller as as the tracker um and you
know localize a point cloud to that. Um
and that allows it to be still be
rendered when it's oluded and um it the
also doubles as a handle for our
transducer which um is ergonomically
nice.
Um so we performed this user study uh
where we lead 18 18 um you know
participants nine research experts or
clinical experts and nine noviceses
who've never used ultrasound through two
tasks. Um the first task is object
identification task um where there's you
know these cups you can't see through
them and there's all these metal objects
inside from springs to balls to screws.
Um we use these objects because they
reflect well in ultrasound and you know
are easy to see with our system. Um so
this is what the interface would be
would look like when the users um are
are working with the system.
Uh and this is a short video kind of
just capturing you know what it looks
like to do this task. So as the images
are are loaded this is in three times
speed. Um there's two visualizations, a
large one, um and a small one that's at
real life size. Um so you can see the
screw pretty well. You can see all the
threads in the screw. Um and then
there's, you know, another object. This
is a mesh ball. Um so you can kind of
see kind of the curvature on the ball.
Um the ultrasound tends to just reflect
off the top surface. So that's why
you're not seeing the whole volume of
the ball. But um yeah, so that was task
one um identifying the objects and you
know the results are pretty interesting
in that we see that this is an accuracy
plot versus our systems. We see that the
3D plus MR system participants were able
to perform uh you know most accurate and
with a smaller uh uh variance. Um and
then the other interesting thing is
between experts in orange and noviceses
in in teal um
uh we see that there's you know
comparable per performance um within our
system um between people experts who've
you know used ultrasound many times and
uh noviceses who've seen it for the very
first time. Um so it is an equalizing
force and you know they perform better
on average 17% than the other systems.
So um it kind of shows that maybe the 3D
aspect is also helping with object
identification. Um you can see in that
the other system that performed fairly
well is 3D plus screen. Um so I think
the 3D is giving context as to you know
what the objects are, what their full
shape is and how to mentally map that.
Um something else that we found was very
interesting was a perceived performance
versus accuracy. So we also captured
NASA TLX scores um on all of these tasks
and so we asked users how well they
think they performed. Um but we see that
for the 3D MR system
uh that you know users performed well
and they thought they performed well. So
they performed about as well you know as
as they they thought and with high
confidence um and the variance was much
larger for the other systems.
Um our second task was uh a task where
you know a localization task. So we have
a tissue phantom with a bunch of wire
targets in them. So that's what they
would look like if you know it weren't
oluded on the image on the left. Um so
these targets run through the phantom
and um in ultrasound appear as dots. Um,
so we basically cover that uh
visualization and have the user use the
ultrasound scanning systems and mark
where they think the dots are um to
scale.
Um, so that's an image of of Hari using
the 3D system.
Um, and what this looks like in
practice, who
is, uh, the user is given kind of a a
marker on the left hand to kind of
pinpoint virtual objects to real life
objects and then the visualization is
shown, um, and they use a pen to mark
where they think the points are. Um so
the task looks fairly easy um with the
the 3D system um because you know the
user is able to see both objects and
just mark where they see think the
bright spots are. Um so there is some
weird parallax effects that some users
reported was kind of um uncomfortable
but um by and large they're able to to
understand the points and mark them
accurately.
So the results of this uh were that um
our system as well as the 2D plus MR
system performed very well relative to
the screen systems which had kind of a
larger spread. Um
and you know I think this kind of
demonstrates you know with the outliers
even excluded uh that um there is
significance with the um MR systems and
that users no longer have to create a
mental map that is you know basically
reference to an exact scale dimension um
and instead they can just if they trust
the system they can just mark what they
see. Um so it's a difference in kind of
a mental framework too um where the
users are no longer relying on a mental
map but um which may be bad in some
contexts um but if the overlay is
accurate um you know they really are
able to perform better
and I guess we also saw similar levels
of uh performance
um with noviceses and experts. Um so
this slide is showing efficiency also.
So this uh represents the number of
points that were marked and the amount
of time that they used to complete the
task and kind of the average distance
away from the the true target. So you
kind of see that again with the 3D and
MR system um the average distance is low
which is good. It means it's accurate.
um there's a larger spread in
efficiency, but um users of this system
kind of reach the max um rates of points
per time. So they're able to both
identify points very quickly and mark
them accurately relative to the other
systems. Um we see also good uh you know
performance in 2D um plus MR.
So let's see.
Um so yeah, that that was kind of the
end of the study. Um these are results
are still to be published. But I guess
looking forward um what we really used
to do was to create kind of this image
processing pipeline that feeds things
directly into the AR environment.
However, we weren't really able to
capture other aspects like user states
and real-time inputs from the other
aspects of the system. Um, however, we
can feed all of these things through uh
potentially to give context to an AI
assistant to assess Gab's focus to help
uh 3D semantic segmentation and
eventually to create assets and generate
um guidance markers or view synthesized
views um and feed them back into the AR
environment um so that instead
potentially one day instead of this loop
we can have um a separate
intervention where a medical assistant
can kind of bridge the patient and the
physician um or even patients can
perform these um interventions on
themselves and scan at home.
Um so with that that's that's all I
have. Thank you so much for listening. I
just like to give a quick thank you to
um MIT Nano um the Center for
Translational and Clinical Research and
um the MIT Heels Collaborative. Thanks.
>> Thank you so much Jason. Uh really
awesome stuff everybody. If you do have
questions um feel free to put them in
chat and because we have two speakers
today we'll try to get to them uh at the
end. So for the interest of time I'm now
going to introduce April. So thank you.
>> Hi there. My name is April. I am a PhD
candidate in mechanical engineering uh
here at MIT. Uh I'm going to talk today
about a sort of different use of AR for
volume ultrasound. Um this is a I want
to say up front this is an ongoing
project and so we are um still in
development and excited about uh what's
to come. So again to start off very uh
broadly uh as Jason had mentioned uh
ultrasound is a pretty unique medical
imaging modality and it has some major
advantages over other modalities such as
X-ray CT or MRI. Um to name a few it's
tends to be lower cost. Um, you can also
look at real-time images. Uh, and so
imaging can, at least in theory, be a
faster process. Um, it's also safe
because there's no ionizing radiation
like with CT or X-ray. Um, and then it's
portable, so it can be used at the
patient's bedside, uh, which is a major
advantage over um, having to travel to a
CT or an MRI scanner. Um, that being
said, there are some things that limit
ultrasound. Um to name just a few again
uh one is the need for trained users. Um
so synenographers are the medical
professionals who uh train in depth on
ultrasound. Um but again as was
previously said a lot of other
clinicians so um nurses assistants MDs
uh etc don't have significant training
in ultrasound. Um and they have to go
through this this uh loop of uh ordering
an ultrasound exam. uh the synographer
comes and takes the images, those go to
a radiologist who interprets them and
then communicates the information back
to the original clinician. Um and so
that really takes away from some of the
uh potential advantages of ultrasound,
namely it being fast and uh convenient.
Um that doesn't really happen in in real
life uh if it has to go through this
sort of uh uh complicated loop.
Um, additionally, um, if you compare
ultrasound to CT and MRI, CT and MRI,
you've maybe seen the images of
scrolling through in three dimensions
because you've got this volutric image,
there's a lot of anatomical context
that's preserved. So, you can see not
only an imaging target, a particular
organ, but also what's going on around
it. Um, this is an example ultrasound
image here on the far right. Uh, it's
got the tip of the liver and then a
little bit of kidney under it. But I've
done a lot of kidney ultrasounds and I
can tell you this particular image could
be captured from a lot of different
angles. Um, and from this single 2D
image, it's not really clear um what is
surrounding this image, like what is the
anatomical context. Um, but this
honestly is the the type of image that a
radiologist would get to interpret. It's
just a single 2D image maybe that has
some labels or uh measurements on it. Um
these uh limitations kind of combine to
ultimately produce uh poor repeatability
and reproducibility in ultrasound that
really limits the uh potential impact
and the potential use of ultrasound in
the medical imaging space.
Um so we like to talk about volume
ultrasound as one potential um sort of
answer to some of these challenges. uh
to quickly go through some of the
specific applications of volume
ultrasound. Um I've got a few examples
here. One uh really simply is to
actually just improve volume
measurements. Um so in certain
applications, volume itself is an
important biomarker. Uh the graph on the
upper right is uh a a diagram of what
happens in a disease known as polycystic
kidney disease. Uh cysts grow in the
kidney and progressively impair the
function of the kidney. Um, if you can
see the blue line at the top, it kind of
stays flat for a long time and then
starts to decrease. That's a measure of
kidney function. Um, and you can see
it's just not very sensitive early on.
Um, and so it doesn't show changes in
kidney function until there's already
been significant damage to the kidney.
This is a lifelong disease that people
deal with over uh many many decades.
Uh, the colorful line, the green to red,
that's kidney size. So that's the total
kidney volume. Um in a lot of studies
that has been shown to be a more
sensitive and earlier biome for uh the
progression of of polycystic kidney
disease. Um and so there's been a
movement to use volume as the standard
uh biome for this disease because
earlier detection means earlier
treatment and um longer lasting
functional kidneys. Um
but uh those that those volume
measurements are typically done via MRI
which again doesn't have the same
advantages as ultrasound. It can't
usually be done in um in a or at the
bedside or at a clinical uh like
doctor's office setting. You have to go
to a special facility to get those um
scans. So using volume ultrasound, you
can get more accurate volume or you can
get more accurate volume measurements of
targets like kidney um which is useful
for for a variety of diseases. You can
also start to understand how a
particular imaging target such as a
kidney changes over time. Um, so when
you get volume, you can register
multiple volumes to one another and
start to see the way the shapes change.
Um, how uh different measurements might
be changing over time. And that's
something that can only be done with
with volume, not a single 2D image. Um,
those uh
uh those advantages also help uh the
repeatability of ultrasound. So we talk
about operator to operator repeatability
or reproducibility. Um, so if I take one
measurement with uh my ultrasound and
then I hand the device to another person
and that person tries to take the same
measurement, the chances that those
numbers are the same uh is is lower with
ultrasound. Um, but with volume, you can
start to see again the context of what's
happening. You can start to understand
the the whole shape and start to take
measurements at consistent locations
which improves the uh repeatability. And
then lastly, um visualization during
procedures. You can imagine if you are
doing a procedure in in a body, it's 3D
uh but you're looking at this 2D image.
So this particular image is uh the
placement of a central line. Um they're
trying to get a large needle and
catheter into that sort of squishy uh
black hole towards the top. Um there are
other things around it that you really
don't want to poke with a needle. And
that little yellow dot is uh the needle
that they're looking at. So you can
imagine it's just very hard to visualize
that needle in 2D when you're working on
this inherently 3D uh body.
So how do we achieve volume ultrasound?
Um Jason talked about one way. I'm going
to talk about a slightly different uh
method for it. Uh what it boils down to
is collecting two two streams of data at
the same time. The first one being the
ultrasound B mode images that you would
typically collect and the second being
uh the poses of the probe that you're
using to collect the images. So pose is
just a fancy word saying meaning uh the
translation and rotation of that probe.
Um and together that sort of describes
where the probe is and thus where the
images are in 3D space. There are
different ways to measure this uh these
poses. I'll just name a few. One is a
system like Optitra. Um so this is
what's pictured as a smaller version of
what the immersion lab offers in terms
of optitra. Um but that is optical
tracking of something like an ultrasound
transducer. They're also sort of um
heavier duty uh robotic arms. Uh these
are
uh very accurate in terms of uh tracking
probe pose. uh but they can be very
expensive and and not as portable. And
then finally, one thing we've used in
our lab is a little off-the-shelf
sensor. It's about $300, so it's very
cheap compared to the ultrasound probe.
Um and this sensor has a camera on it
and some sensors in it that help it to
map its environment and localize the
probe within that environment. Um, so
there's lots of different ways to
measure this these poses, but together
these two streams of information um can
uh be aggregated to form an ultrasound
volume uh like these two images shown
here.
Uh we can take this a step further and
talk about guided ultrasound
acquisition. So this is something unique
that volume ultrasound enables. Um you
start by doing the regular ultrasound
scanning again collecting the poses
along with it. uh you aggregate it into
this uh 3D volume. So you do the
reconstruction. This is an example of a
kidney model and then from that
reconstruction because you're
aggregating the information and placing
it into context you can start to
understand uh where information is
missing. So there's a little bit of a
lag but um in ultrasound we often have
shadowed images. So in this particular
kidney image, kind of right down the
middle is that shadow that's from a rib.
Um, and obviously you're missing
information there. From a different
angle, you can get that information. And
so what we can do with volume ultrasound
is we can direct a user to those areas
that are missing information or need
more certainty. Um, so we can guide them
and they can scan further and we can
continue the cycle until we have an
ultrasound volume that we're happy with.
Okay, so that's the ultrasound side of
things. Where does AR come into the
picture?
Um, I'll start broadly again and say
that AR for medical applications is this
this uh rapidly expanding and growing
field. This is just sort of a sample uh
I know it's hard to read, but a sample
list of uh FDA cleared ARVR medical
devices. Um until recently a lot of the
things on that list were uh along the
the lines of surgical guidance or
procedural guidance and visualization.
Um so in surgery being able to see
either pre-operative scans or where your
um instrument will interact with those
those um those images. Um a lot of
that's been sort of the leading use case
so far. Uh more recently there have been
um different use cases which is
exciting. Uh this particular uh uh
example just for one example uh is a
intended as an atome use device for
people with chronic low back pain and it
kind of guides people through like
breathing exercises and meditations and
things that have been shown to help with
chronic pain. And so u totally different
use case uh exciting that uh things are
expanding as we go. Um in the research
space not so much in the commercial
space but in the research space there
have also been applications specifically
with ultrasound. Uh so this image is a
person using um an AR system to biopsy
an olive within a turkey breast. Um so
he he's got sort of an image. You can
see the ultrasound image is projected
onto the phantom so he can kind of
understand where the image that he's
taking with the probe is in uh the
context of that phantom and how his
instrument will interact with it.
Um so it's a really rapidly expanding
space. Um how do we see AR being used
for our specific context?
Um there's a couple of of big um
uh things we'd like to use it for. So,
first of all, we're using a Microsoft
Hollow Lens 2. Um, this is an augmented
reality device rather than a virtual
reality device. So, uh, it's a pass
through, so you can see something
projected onto what's in front of you,
but you can also see, um, what's in
front of you in in real life. So, you
can see the phantom, you can see the
patient you're working on. Um, and we
hope to use this number one as a
tracking tool. Um, so there's uh
something called Aruko markers. I think
Jason mentioned them too, but uh they're
a little bit like QR codes, but they're
just um little pieces of uh paper in
this case uh attached to a probe that
make it easy to track. Um so we can use
computer vision algorithms to track and
get that pose of an ultrasound probe as
we move it um
as we move it over a phantom. So the
second thing we would like to use the or
we plan to use the the AR device for is
more for visualization. So there's a few
different sort of aspects there. The
first is what I call volume orientation.
Um so taking an ultrasound probe seeing
where that image is within the context
of the volume that you're scanning. So
volume orientation. Um another one is uh
voxal coverage. So if we talk about
reconstructing a voxal grid um and we
want to understand sort of where have we
collected a lot of information where do
we still need to collect information
that's image or that's information that
can be also communicated via an AR
application. Um and then the last one is
that guidance piece I mentioned. Um you
can sort of instruct a user where they
need to scan further in order to
complete an ultrasound volume.
So, a little bit a few more details
about our sort of system architecture.
Um, like I said, we we're using the
Hello Lens 2 headset. We've got an
ultrasound probe uh with that Aruka
marker marker attached. Um, and a
phantom. A phantom is a model of um
something we'd like to image in real
life. So, this phantom uh you can just
barely see in the middle is a model of a
kidney.
Um that's also got an Aruka marker
attached. And then, of course, there we
can communicate back to the computer. on
the computer we're running something
called uh ROSS 2 which is robot
operating system 2. Um and what that
does is it sort of manages uh multiple
streams of information.
So uh first of all like we said we can
use computer vision um and the hollow
lens to track uh the ultrasound probe as
it moves. So as it moves it can output a
stream of poses. Um, we can also track
the phantom, which nominally is not
moving too much. Um, but could
theoretically, you can imagine if that
phantom were a person, they certainly
would move. So that pose information
from both the ultrasound and the phantom
can be fed back to the computer.
We've also got the ultrasound
information
which can be fed to the computer and
then kind of like you had seen in those
other examples, you can project the
ultrasound image back to um the probe in
real life, back to the headset uh and it
can be displayed under the probe in real
life as sort of volume uh orientation.
Uh and then on the computer we've got
some image processing, the
reconstruction happening. Um and we can
do sort of a little or a lot in terms of
um the reconstruction and and how we
process it and um what sort of
information we want to give back to the
user. And then finally we take that
information from our image processing
and reconstruction um and feed it back
to the um hollow lens for uh guidance or
for visualization of uh the volume or
guidance.
Um here's a quick demo.
Let's see.
There it goes. Um so this is really
highlighting the tracking tool. Um, so
you can see we've actually got three
Aruka markers because more is better in
this case on our 3D printed model probe.
Um, and we're displaying kind of a a
placeholder uh image along the bottom.
You can see there's some lag. Uh, so
like I said, this project is in
development. And so here we're kind of
trying to test the limits of how well
this tracking works. And you can see it
does start to fail at some points. So
when the arro markers are not very
visible um it it struggles to um display
the image or if we move really fast um
it doesn't uh quite keep up. So uh
that's one thing we're doing now is is
trying to um define the limits of the
system and where we might uh incorporate
other uh tracking methods. For example,
optitra in uh the immersion lab to sort
of either supplement or replace some of
these functions that um may or may not
work as well as they can in theory. This
is sort of an example of a voxal grid.
Um, so if you can imagine, so now you
can see the image is within that grid.
So you can imagine you're you're
scanning a phantom. Um, and that sort of
image follows you as you're as you're
scanning. So very early example. Um, one
of the next steps that we're really
interested or really excited to think
about is how we communicate uh, our
guidance piece. So how do we visualize
the guidance that um, can happen with
volume ultrasound? As one example, I
want to highlight the work of my
labmate, uh, Chian Lynn. Um, she really
is the person who developed this
guidance. This is guidance on without
AR, so like on a 2D computer screen. Um,
but in essence, what she's got is the
lighter red probe is sort of uh where
you are, and the darker red is where it
suggests your next uh position should be
uh in order to gather all of the
information you need uh for a volume
ultrasound. So, that's one uh
possibility. Another possibility is this
is a 2D image, but you can imagine in 3D
um trying to almost color in like a
voxal grid um as you scan and get more
information. Um once a voxil is happy,
it turns purple uh and you move on to
the uncolored voxels. So we're really
excited to think about that next. Um
overall, we think this uh AR for volume
ultrasound could potentially be used for
education and training. Uh we can
envision if a clinician is wanting to
get to know how to use ultrasound and
they need to practice especially the
movements of of what ultrasound feels
like um and how to scan thoroughly over
a particular area. Um you could imagine
using a system like this um to to
supplement that training. We also think
this is potentially just an accessible
use of ultrasound um potentially in
remote health contexts um for somebody
who maybe doesn't have an expert level
of training for ultrasound. So we're
very excited uh to move forward with
this project and uh happy to take
questions now.
Awesome. Um Jason, if you want to come
up and uh there are a few people here in
the audience. So awesome, awesome work.
I mean it looks like a lot of stuff has
been done. Um a lot of progress since
kind of the beginning of of the semester
even. So let's just uh we'll look at
some of the questions in chat and if any
of you guys have any questions in the
audience, feel free to just uh say
something. Um but I'll get things
rolling. Um there was a quick comment
about who makes the $300 probe. That may
have been. Yeah.
>> Uh, so the probe, the ultrasound probe
itself is not $300. Point of care
ultrasound uh, probes are in the range
of thousands of dollars. Um, the
attachment that tracks the pose is an
Intel product that's around $300.
>> Awesome. Thank you. Um, and I did notice
some of you guys did join a little bit
later. This will be recorded, so uh, if
you guys have any questions after, feel
free to just email them. Um, but I I
have another question as well. So, it
looked like both of you guys used uh a
different headset in terms of virtual or
augmented reality. Could each one of you
just kind of highlight the reasons why
you chose that headmounted display over
the other? Um maybe Jason, you can
start.
>> Um
>> and you can come. I I love honestly the
the hollow lens system and I think it's
that sort of AR is important for medical
contexts because a lot of the times um
you know medical people need to trust
what they're seeing in real life. They
don't want a glitch to happen and all of
a sudden everything's off. So I do like
that aspect but the hollow lens is also
you know it's like wireless and um it
can't
compute as much. Um, so that's why we
needed the Vario. It's really just the
highest end of computation. It can plug
it directly into the PC, run the GPU,
and send the images directly across. Um,
and the other thing was it's the highest
resolution that I could find. So the
pass through is pretty fairly good and
they use it in like fighter jets and
stuff which is cool. So high stakes
situations, but it is very heavy and not
really practical in that sense. Yeah,
>> I think maybe for like one piece of
additional context, the Vario, the pass
through is basically like it it videos
what's around you and then projects the
video back to you. So you can still see
what's around you, but instead of it
being like looking through a glass,
you're looking at a video essentially.
So um that can sort of increase the
likelihood of motion sickness for some
people. Um but it's yeah, it's
trade-offs are definitely available for
both. I think a lot of the existing
medical devices that are FDA cleared out
there use hollow lens or something like
it um where you can see
uh through the glasses what's in front
of you.
>> The hope is they'll converge at
>> Yeah. someday.
>> Got it. Got it. Thank you. Um and on
that note, I mean you talked about the
computation, right? Being able to render
all of this and I saw in in some of your
videos you had a little bit of latency.
Now, was that due to I guess the the
rendering in in which it had to render
or is that streaming somewhere?
>> I think it's the the rendering. Yeah. Um
I think I think that's the slow point
because actually reading the poses like
actually tracking the probe is pretty
pretty good.
>> Okay.
>> U but it's rendering back the image is a
little bit laggy at the moment.
>> And and for you, I mean you have you're
going directly into the PC. So this is a
PC VR experience. Um I guess what is
kind of the minimum GPU requirement
that's you're you're kind of bottling
neck bottlenecking out of?
>> Um yeah that's a good question. So I
think uh one aspect of it was we were
looking through the VR software and I
think Unreal Engine was the only one
that supported kind of large point cloud
representations millions of points and
>> they do efficient representation with
octry representation. So it was it was
just specwise the only system that could
load the the um frames that we have in
in near real time. And then um but the
point processing I think yeah that that
was at that point it was just like okay
if we're using Unreal anyways let's just
use the best GPUs we can to um render.
>> Yeah.
>> But we I think we were running on a 3080
at some point.
It runs on a laptop GPU also sometimes.
>> Okay, good.
>> Um but it is laggy. Yeah. Sure. Awesome.
Um and we got a question. Um how to
increase the speed of integration of
visualization in real life of object
identification.
Um I am also wondering about dynamic
transfer function. Is it also crucial
for patients? Um so maybe we could start
with the first part of that question on
how to increase the speed of integration
of visualization in real life. Um so I
think and that's based on object uh
identification. So you're using um
>> codes.
>> Yes. Could you could you share a little
bit about that?
>> Yeah. Um the speed has been a consistent
issue and I think we've we've sort of
cycled through several different uh
potential solutions uh based on what's
out there with different types of codes.
So, our codes, uh QR codes, other sort
of um similar similar ideas. Um
increasing the speed.
Yeah, it's a challenge.
Um and I think that's that's common
across a lot of um a lot of these
applications. Um, one one slow piece is
like we're basically um taking an image
from what the headset is seeing and then
processing it. Um, and so, you know, and
we're doing that at a certain frame rate
to to try and decrease the lagging. Um,
so we can process at a slower frame
rate. Um, but there's a trade-off
between u again that sort of lagging
that we're seeing um in terms of when we
move fast. So if we're moving slowly, it
works really well. Uh but if we're
moving really fast, which usually you're
not with ultrasound, but um that's where
it starts to break down.
>> Okay. And is this one reason why you're
thinking of the optitra integration? So
to kind of that up using infrared
reflective markers rather than kind of
uh image recognition uh processing.
>> Yes. Nominally, we'd like to use both at
the same time and sort of compare them
and say like what are the limits of this
uh computer vision sort of solution um
compared to something like Optack where
we almost get ground truth.
>> Sure. Um but yeah, it is it is a big uh
snag point in this particular workflow.
>> Got it. Jason, do you have anything to
to add to that?
>> Yeah, I think the main thing we noticed
was we were struggling with the visual
markers for a little bit in terms of it
was just overloading the system and how
much computation it was having to do and
would crash the application often. So I
think that's we were forced to move to a
different solution which in this case
was just the controller. Um, but that
really sped things up because I think
it's all built in. You know, you can
overlay 3D objects onto controllers very
easily and it used them very quickly.
So, I think that was kind of the
inspiration of like, oh, let's just tie
everything to the controller anyways.
Um,
>> right.
>> But I I wish there were more tools like
that to track objects like like any
object and turn any object into a
virtually tracked object as well and
that you can overlay visualizations on.
I think that was the missing point is
what is real, what is virtual, how do
you get the user to unite the two kind
of in the interface.
>> Yeah.
>> And with your study, um, you compared
kind of the novice and and kind of
experienced users of ultrasound. Did you
ask as well if they were familiar with
virtual or augmented reality? Were those
first-time users as well?
>> Uh, many of them were and some of them
none of them had used augmented reality
before. I think some of them had used um
VR and some experts even in the training
context where you know they learned to
use the ultrasound tools.
>> Sure.
>> VR. Yeah. No, it's interesting because
people feel they have kind of different
comfort levels using these headmounted
displays. So um very interesting stuff.
All right. So yes, we have one question
here.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think and I know of a hide
tracker like Yeah. like their bands or
something or there's like a RF.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> It's just smaller version.
>> Oh, Cedric. Yes. Yes.
>> It's really tiny.
>> Oh, interesting. Yeah.
>> We also both
useful
now the Russian And it's like a pencil
that is very
you could actually scalp or gives you
all.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah, that's true.
>> I hadn't thought about that for a while
because their development ecosystem was
closed for for a little bit. Yeah. So
yeah. Yeah, that's be cool to revisit
for.
>> It's an exciting field. Like it it turns
over really fast and it's pretty pretty
interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> Awesome. Um we probably have time for
one more question. Uh what is the device
that the probe interfaces with? Um I'm
wondering if that is the
>> device
>> or the
um it could be the phantoms.
>> The phantoms. Yeah. Sure.
>> Jonathan, could you specify a little bit
of what device you're you're mentioning?
>> And for those who didn't hear the
previous comment, it was mentioning uh
MedVR as a as a platform to to work with
individuals on on related questions such
as these. And then the Hive tracking uh
or the Hive Tracker as being an
alternative um for for object
identification.
>> I have a quick question for Jason while
we're waiting. I know you guys did
interviews at the end of your your
studies. What were some of the like
qualitative feedback you got on the on
your systems?
>> Um yeah, so we we actually, you know,
were compiled that into this knowledge
graph which I I think reference maybe in
the paper. Um, but yeah, a lot of people
a lot of the the feedback was like,
yeah, it was it's kind of clunky and um
disorienting sometimes to use a VR
system when you could just look at
something and and try your best to
mentally map it. Um but I think there
was just two camps of thought of like
you know experts who are very
comfortable with the process of mental
mapping and that's just how they expect
things to be
>> and then the noviceses who really didn't
know what to expect. So the the VR
systems really help them to
contextualize
and learn very quickly. But I think at
some point there is some convergence
that's still needing to make a mental
model and how detailed and how accurate
that mental model may be affected by the
two things. But um yeah, I think when I
was using it, just regardless, I was
starting to, you know, try to think of
where things were um that maybe that's
just how you use ultrasound as as a
system. So
>> that's interesting.
>> Yeah. Awesome. Awesome. Well, thank you
again, guys. Just one one more round of
applause for those of you in here. Uh
thank you. Appreciate it. And um that
comes to the hour, everybody. So just
want to make one final uh final
announcement. Our our next immerse
series is actually already scheduled.
It's for Wednesday, November 19th at the
same time at 11:00 a.m. And this will be
the user experience for robotic TE
operation by uh Rolando Montasano. And
he'll speak a little bit about some of
the tools that he worked with here in
the immersion lab, including uh the Toby
glasses for for eyetracking. So um thank
you all for joining us and um we'll see
you next time.