good morning everyone welcome to the mpg
primer um we're excited to have Evan kot
here today Evan is a research associate
in the sun Lab at the department of
medical or biomedical informatics at
Harvard Medical School he applies
theoretical and empirical population
genetics approaches to better understand
mutagenesis variant function and how
natural selection shapes genetic
variation and complex trait he also
co-chairs an evolutionary focus group at
the nih's impact of genomic variation on
function the igf
Consortium and aside from Human genetics
research he also involves himself in
research on Wolf arabidopsis and various
pathogens he receives his PhD in ecology
and evolution from the University of
Chicago in 2018 and he was advi advised
by John November and Richard Hudson um
and today he's going to be talking about
uh introduction to population genetics
and please raise your hand or come up to
this mic I could bring one to you or you
could come here to ask questions
throughout or at the end
thanks thank you um yeah so I'm going to
give an introduction to population
genetics briefly um you know because
it's only a field that's you know been
around now for a bit over a century so
we should be able to cover everything um
and you know this is parenthesis here
model so there's a lot of amazing
empirical findings but I'm going to
focus on the models because I believe
that you know this provides really the
based understanding um that we try to
get when we look at uh genetic data from
populations yeah so we're going to hit
really three topics today um starting
with genetic drift as also sort of an
introduction into modeling a population
generally um then go on to Natural
Selection and in particular um negative
selection partly because this is you
know what I actually tend to work on
most of the time and and also because
it's the one that's most ubiquitous in
your
genome um and then we'll talk about
colesent the colesent and gen
genealogies um as like a sample focused
uh view of of genetic variation and
ancestry and touch a bit on the
ancestral recombination graph um as like
maybe a bit of a Hot Topic at the moment
and then briefly touch on uh the extra
treat of the selective sweeps in the
genome and then you know if there's time
at the end I'll go over a little bit
about some tools and
resources okay so to start at the
absolute uh very basic um place of
genetic drift and genetic variation in
population so right you know you could
have at one position in the genome here
um two possible alals let's say um A and
G and what we talk about most of of the
time in in population genetics is the
frequency of those leals the the how
common they are in the population as a
whole um so if you had a population
let's say of n dipl individuals um we
would just simply calculate uh the
frequency of of the of the G um by you
know the number of of haloid genomes
that that carry that Al and so for this
talk I'll I'll denote the frequency of
of an Al as uh p and then the frequency
of the uh alternate or referenc will
always be one minus P okay
so then let's let's think about a
population and this is not you know a
very large or realistic population maybe
but let's say you have some number of
diploid individuals and each of those
individuals is going to have uh a
genotype being you know either what of
the homozygote or the heterozygote
genotypes and we can then ask what the
frequency simply of of ourg is um is in
that generation right then those um
individuals can can pair up and produce
some number of Offspring denoted here in
the the second generation as as their
children and and given that we can
simply follow um melian segregation to
you know this is an inherently random
process to choose genotypes in the Next
Generation and so this combination
of you know variation in the number of
offspring that uh that parents are going
to have uh as well as the inherent
variation due to melan segregation are
going to mean that the frequency of that
geol is not exactly the same in this
next Generation as it was in the
previous and this is really what we mean
by genetic drift that there's these
inherent uh factors to U melan
segregation and breeding structure of
populations that leads to variation
uh in Al frequencies over
time right so how do we want to now we
want to actually model this what are we
supposed to do one option would be to
try to be uh realistic and actually
specify what the pedigree or some
pedigree generating processes in the
population this is an example of a
couple of wolf packs in in Northern
Italy and researchers have gone out and
actually mapped out uh their pedigree
which is great but as you can maybe see
from this it is enormously complicated
and it would be a ton of work to
actually model or or measure this for
every population we want to look at and
mostly impossible but we could do that
and then simply follow melan laws to see
how a Leal frequencies
change um we're not going to do that
that's way too hard um but what we will
do uh is come up with a simple model of
of reproduction uh that we can actually
work with and there's a couple of these
that are tractable and have you know a
lot of work done on them but the most
common is probably What's called the
right Fisher model and so that states
okay we have some population of n
diploids um at at generation p and then
we're going to choose a next gener a
next um a next generation of individuals
at time step t+ one so this is discrete
Generations um and then each of these
individuals in the Next Generation needs
you know two copies of their genome two
copies of this alal and they're going to
sample it at random from uh from the
individuals in the previous generation
and therefore we have you know the
variation variance in the number of aals
is simply going to be binomial uh
distribution um with you know simply the
the probability of getting that Al equal
to the the probability that it was in
the previous generation and there's
going to be no average change in alal
frequencies no directional change um the
expectation of this is going to be zero
but you're going to have this genetic
drift um due to that sampling
process now if we instead calculate the
variance in the change in Al
frequencies um this is going to be equal
to P times 1 minus p over the uh over
the deploy twice the deploy population
size right so we can you know just from
this very very simple model make a um
sort of qualitative statement about how
drift should work um it should be faster
in small populations when that n is
small and it and it should be um also
faster at high minor alal frequency so
drift will that variance and alal
frequency change will be fastest when
the alal frequencies is around
50% uh but what should we make of real
populations we don't want to do the
complicated thing and think about
pedigrees all the time uh we don't
actually believe that like a right
Fisher model is an appropriate one for
like the human population um so what's
commonly done is to try to make an
analogy between the drift that occurs in
idealized populations like this right
Fisher one um and real populations that
might exist in the wild and by matching
the rate of genetic drift and so we
introduced this quantity uh called the
effective population size or NE uh and
we want to choose the effective
population size such that the variance
in a Leal frequency from one gener
duration uh to the next matches this uh
this equation for the binomial sampling
and the right Fisher model um where
we've substituted an effective
population size instead now one aspect
of this is that you know when we're
choosing some alternative model some
real you know model that we think is
maybe more realistic trying to analogize
that to right Fisher ones the variance
needs to actually be proportional to P1
minus P for an effective population size
to exist thankfully that's like largely
the case but it's something you might
consider
consider um great so let's maybe take a
silly example of this um and think about
some model where you have a distribution
of family sizes sort of similar to what
I what I showed previously um this this
model over here with a variance of two
is going to be approximately um equal to
what you would see in the right Fisher
model but you might have populations
with you know a lower variance or you
know a much higher skew in the the
family size that um individuals might
have and if you you know say set the the
number of individuals in the population
to be constant and simulate alal
frequency sampling generation after
generation we can see that you know
indeed the the drift in these alal
frequencies increases with that variance
in family size as we might expect
intuitively and then you know in in
mathematical terms we can say that the
effective population size um and should
be four times the
the diploid size um over the this
variance in family size and a
contribution um to Mel from melan
segregation uh interestingly you could e
this also you know uh illustrates the
fact that even if the there is no
variant in family size you would still
get genetic drift uh in diploids just
from melan
segregation so then if we went through
and we actually scaled the population
sizes in each of these uh family size
models here so that they should have the
same effective population size you see
that indeed the the distribution of uh
alal frequencies after you know random
sampling one generation does actually
look very
similar okay so one thing that will
happen right we this sampling of AO
frequencies generation after generation
is that we let that go on for long
enough you're going to eventually remove
all the genetic variation from the
population and the AL are either going
to you know uh drop out of the
population go to a frequency of zero or
they might fix in the population and go
to a frequency of of one um now we know
that there is genetic variant variation
population so we need some mechanism to
add this back
in so that mechanism is is obviously uh
mutations which generate genetic
variation that then might be able to
drift up to higher frequencies and
maintain a balance between the addition
of genetic variation into population
mutation and drift which is going to
tend to remove it so then we're now
we're interested in questions of how
that genetic variation is maintained and
what is its distribution within
populations um this you know provides a
nice opportunity to introduce a second
approximation so we can think about this
right Fisher model we want to get it
even simpler actually so we're going to
now approximate that alal frequencies
aren't this like count in the population
we say okay well they're actually
approximately uh continuous which unless
you're a very very rare alal is is going
to be pretty good A population which is
some similar to saying the population
size is large and this diffusion
approximation the Dynamics of those Alo
frequencies are only really going to
depend on um the expected change in AO
frequency per generation and the
variance in AO frequency um change and
as we've already seen we already know
what the Varian is it's this P1 minus p
over the effective population
size um so now you can apply this
diffusion model and say you know
starting with some continuous
distribution of alal frequencies at
whatever starting point you want go an
arbitrary number of generations into the
future um and get what's going to happen
uh to that
distribution um we're going to call that
distribution of AAL frequencies um Tai
here and what's going to happen is
you're going to lose uh you're going to
lose alals at the zero and one
boundaries and that distribution is
going to flatten out as well and this
Evolution happens according to this
diffusion equation here which you don't
really need to think too much about
right now for the purposes of this talk
but you can see that it depends on this
expected and variance um in the alal
frequency change as well as what the
shape of the pop of the genetic
variation is at the given point in time
okay uh yeah so now if we ask for okay
what if we come to this balance we come
to this equilibrium what is the uh
distribution of genetic variation going
to look like and so we can add mutation
back and forth uh between our our two Al
set a mutation rate here uh is the rate
per gamet per per generation and then
the expected change in a Leo frequency
um uh is going to be mu this per
generation mutation rate as one minus 2p
and so you know at the boundaries you
know if that alil isn't actually present
in the population mutation's always
going to add it rate VI to to the
population
um and this is the the distribution uh
that one gets it depends only on a
compound parameter which we call uh
Theta which is sort of like
the a parameter um capturing what the
neutral genetic diversity should be in
the in the population and that depends
on the product of the effective
population size in the mutation
rate we can also see that most variants
are going to be rare because when you
get a a variant added to the population
by by mutation uh the most likely thing
that's going to occur to it is that it
will then just subsequently pretty
quickly be lost but some amount of the
time variants are going to drift up to
to high frequencies and you know add
this real genetic variation to the
population that affects things like uh
complex traits and and all other kinds
of good
stuff um now complicating things just a
little bit further this is maybe in the
previous slide a model for a single site
gen are are large and we don't
necessarily want to model it sight by
sight all the time so one trick that
that that can be do that we can do is um
use what's called an infinite sites
model and so now we have this stretch of
genome here and at each site there's
going to be um some ancestral Al
mutations are going to create um new
derived alals at you know some positions
there and occasionally they're going to
drift up to to high frequencies and
you'll have some them pile within this
stretch of of Al at some appreciable
frequency in in the
population and so you know what you can
do is at any point in time take all of
those drive alals that are you know
segregating having these drift processes
um at each point in in our um in our
pile of sequence and add them all up and
ask what like sort of the aggregate
distribution of those Al frequencies is
and this is what's called maybe the alal
frequency
Spectrum uh s here um and that's you
know going to be the number of sites
that we've considered in our stretch
here um it's going to be proportional
the number of mutations that you're
going to see in each of these
frequencies proportional to this um
Theta this um sort of genetic variation
parameter and it's going to be
proportional to the inverse of the alal
frequency um right and so this you know
we're assume most mutations are rare
events so we can model this as a CR on
process and that the diffusions that
independent position different positions
are just going independently and so now
we can make really nice calculations
from this alal frequency spectrum object
such as just calculating what's the
expected number of derived alals we
would expect to see um in some frequency
range and that's going to be Pon
distributed with simply this you know
how much mass is there in this frequency
range according to this a frequency
spectrum
object um great so
now we have this model for these latent
alal frequencies in the population as a
whole but a lot of the time what we're
working with is a sample from the
population we've sampled some um uh some
genetic sequences right and and what
we're going to do is calculate What's
called the sample frequency spectrum or
the or the SFS um and so what's that
what we're going to do then is for each
possible count of alals in the
sample um see how many observations
we make at that count right so if we uh
sampled six sequences here we would
count up the number of Al that we saw at
a frequency of two um so you have two of
those here um the number at frequency
one and so on and so forth um and add
that all up um and ask how many times we
saw alals at each possible derived
count now we can develop a statistical
model of this of this SFS
using this alal frequency spectrum let's
say if we took a sample of n haid
individuals from the population simply
by applying like a binomial sampling
from that latent distribution of of Al
frequencies and this has the nice
property of being Plus on as well and so
you can make very simple calculations
just from having this alal frequency
spectrum object applying this binomial
sampling to it and then getting a model
for what the distribution of Alo
frequencies should be that you expect to
find in your sample from some population
with a particular frequency distribution
that looks something like this here this
um black line being the latent frequency
spectrum um and then these blue dots
being the expected um counts that you
would get in in a sample and so you know
if we've sampled um some variant and
found it at let's say frequency .5 in
the population we can ask simple things
like well what's the latent distribution
of Alo frequencies um that that uh that
that 50% uh Al actually represents and
there's actually you know for a sample
of size 10 um there's going to be quite
some some variance in that and this is
going to shrink as um that's going to
shrink as as your sample size gets
larger but you know you might also note
that for low frequency alals the a lot
of the mass of um what the latent alal
frequency is um is going to be
substantially lower than what you
actually saw in your sample and so
you're going to find those rare alals
that you kind of catch by accident in
your sample at a little bit higher
frequency um in real populations in
human populations let's say um the SFS
doesn't look like this one one over uh
one overp curve so here this is from
from
Nomad um for non-finished European
individuals this um SFS object for
synonymous sites um and and here these
Dash lines show what would would expect
from uh this stable constant sized
population that we've just been talking
about and we can see that the the SFS is
a lot steeper you have an excess of rare
variants and it's very far from this
standal neutral SFS of one over
I um and this you know one way that this
happens and probably have other factors
that affect this as well is that um the
human population hasn't stayed constant
over over the past you know whatever
huge amount of time and so one thing
that people do is fit demographic models
using um using this site frequency
spectrum and so this is just one from
tennis and at all uh for for European
populations larly kind of trying to
approximate some sort of Out of Africa
events um you know so you have a assume
that there's some stable population size
at some long time in the past as denoted
by this dash line here and then evolving
that through a population siiz
trajectory generation after generation
in this diffusion model and then getting
what the what the Alo frequency spectrum
is at at the end of that whole thing and
that would be this black line here for
the for this Tennison model and so you
get like various features in here such
as this dip in genetic
diversity um due to Out of Africa
bottleneck as well as a large number of
of rare um of rare variance due to due
to population
growth and one thing I just want to sort
of impress you that all of this is my I
hope it doesn't sound too complicated
and please again interrupt me if you
have any questions um but it's actually
quite simple to to start doing
yourself um nicely with this program
daddy you can simply in Python set up a
frequency grid get your equilibrium
spectrum and evolve that Spectrum with
like one line of of code uh for some
number of generations and then ask what
a sample would look like and it's very
easy to start playing around with and
then you can start making calculations
for what you might expect in your sample
what might you expect from selection and
heritability contributions um and it's
very fast to do you don't need to do
complicated simulations you can get
these AAL frequency spectrums super
easily okay so now let's get on to to
Natural
Selection okay um so when you talk about
selection what we're talking about hey
Evan before uh you move on to your next
step we had a question online from sud
um he says we know about conserved
genomic locations is this knowledge
accounted for in the
model um I'm assuming you mean like
demographic they mean demographic models
um
and yes to the extent that when people
try to fit these demographic models they
try to find the most NE regions of the
genome that they can so they're not
going to use like missense mutations um
they'll use ingenic or synonymous sites
to try to you know be as unaffected by
by selection as possible yeah
yeah
yeah great great so what we talk about
when we talk about Fitness or natural
selection is alal frequency changes that
are due to um differences in Fitness
genotypes and we can Define Fitness
pretty broadly as the reproductive
contribution of an individual to to the
Next Generation Um and then we would
assign Fitness values to each of the
possible um genotypes at our site and we
can kind of think of these as average
values for each
genotype then the alal frequency change
due to selection in each generation the
expected alal frequency change um is
going to be proportional to P1 minus P
so this sort of genetic VAR Varan at
that Locus and the regression of this
Fitness value on on the genotype right
so we can code these genotypes as like
zero one2 or one by the frequency of the
AL within that genotype and then the
regression of Fitness on that is going
to tell us what should happen in that
generation on average to the to the Alo
frequency and so things can be additive
if there's simply a linear relationship
between genotype and fitness or you can
have more complicated dominance
relationships um you know where those
Fitness values don't necessar are have a
more complicated relationship let's say
with with Fitness
right uh yeah so right a lot of the
genome is constrained as the question
asker had asked um so there are various
estimates of this but let's say that
like maybe approximately s seven to 10%
of the human genome is constrained by
what we would call uh negative selection
this can vary a lot from coding regions
where it's really really high um to
transposable elements where it's almost
entirely absent um but a large
proportion actually of the of the human
genome is subject to some amount of
negative
selection and we're going to very simply
model this um by saying like Okay we
have some ancestral genotype let's call
it this a um and then the heterozy and
homozyg genotypes are going to have some
reduction in Fitness um due to selection
um and you know for Simplicity just you
know let these be S and 2s to do this
additive relationship and if that's true
the expected alal frequency change um
should be proportional to that selection
coefficient s here um times this P1
minus P right so now we can again apply
this diffusion model and a pone random
field infinite sites approximation
simply as we did before and just like we
got this Theta this NE times mu
parameter out the first time you add the
second parameter which I like to call
Big s which is the product of the
effective population size um and that
selection
coefficient right and so this gives us
then something we could call uh if
purifying selection is not too strong
some U mutation selection drift balance
whereas this compound s parameter
increases um you go from the neutral
sight frequency spectrum right which is
this uh this linear um relationship with
d dve Deo frequency and the the
frequency spectrum and you start
dropping off as you reach higher
frequencies and so we can conclude that
as selection coefficients go up that
natural selection prevents you from
reaching um higher and higher or as as
selection coefficient goes up natural
selection prevents you from reing
reaching increasingly low alal
frequencies and one way in which this is
conceptualized um is as a drift barrier
that approximately this 1 over s
frequency um selection will prevent you
from prevent that delus alal from
getting any higher and so that's drawn
as these Dash lines here and this
actually provides in many cases you know
a pretty good approximation to the to
the uh to the action of selection in the
case of weak weak weak purifying
selection um right
so one observation that's come out of of
a lot of work in human genetics and and
other organisms well is that a actually
a large amount of human mutations
generate this weekly deleterious
variation right we have all this
constrainted sequence in the genome but
we know that it's not anywhere close to
lethal because that would you know be
actually quite bad it's you're not
getting there um right so we can use the
SFS actually to estimate the
distribution of this weekly deleterious
mutation we have this uh sample
frequency spectrum SFS over here uh we
previously you know integrated over some
binomial sampling
right but we can additionally add to
this this distribution of Fitness
effects or or DFE that's hopefully going
to tell us how much of the genome is
creating selection at uh at different
intensities um and this is done by
comparing these um minor alal frequency
counts for different you know regions of
the genome so intergenic sites have more
genetic variation compared to even
synonymous and certainly non-synonymous
uh sites and you can use that to
estimate this distribution of Fitness
effects when this is done you do indeed
find this huge mass of mutation that
should be generating these weakly
deleterious uh
mutations uh these weakly delarius
mutations are of pretty high importance
because they contribute
disproportionately to trait and disease
heritability as well as the gowos hits
that we we actually find um so if we say
that like the additive uh the
contribution to additive genic variance
for an alate frequency p is this 2 Beta
P1 minus p
um and if we let this selection
coefficient let's say be proportional to
let's say the squared effect size they
then you can calculate what the expected
contribution to genetic variance should
be from um from mutations with selection
coefficient s um so if we plot the per
site contribution to to that genetic
variance against the selection
coefficient we say that it increases
with the strength of of selection and
that's even higher if you assume a model
of stabilizing selection which I versus
purifying selection which I won't
actually really explain but you know let
it suffice to say that like a large
amount of of heritability should be
contributed by deleterious alals and it
might even be more in this nearly
neutral range than expected from a
simple model and indeed when this is you
know this is from yal Simons and
Jonathan pritchard's group um you know
trying to estimate that DFE for gwos
hits for a large number of different
traits and again indeed you still you do
find this you know large mass of of uh
heritability that should be coming from
this intermediate range of weekly
selected
variants this also makes sense in terms
of a philogenetic constraint where if we
look at
phenetically um trying to find
phenetically constrained positions in
the genome that is places that don't
vary very much between um related
species such as mammals or
primates and annotating um variance by
this constraint in in philogynes shows
that this is you know perhaps by far the
the largest contributor to heritability
enrichment of any kind of annotation you
might provide
right and so how does that how does that
then coincide with our view of of weak
selection contributing a lot of
heritability well if we ask how often
should mutations fix relative to neutral
for for different strengths of
selection we can see that you don't
actually need that strong of a selection
coefficient in order to really prevent
almost any uh any fixations to occur on
on this philogyny so if we're talking
about getting to constraint up in this
area on on the right over here you very
quickly get there um uh you very quickly
get to this nearly neutral
range uh okay so that was week selection
um on the other hand selection might
actually be very strong and you can sort
of to almost remove the drift part of it
uh to get to what we might call just
mutation selection balance uh where at
equilibrium the expected frequency of
strongly selected mutation should be the
mutation rate um over the selection
coefficient and right this sort of makes
intuitive sense that as mutations
actually become lethal so it's
heterozygous selection coefficient goes
to one their frequency do just match the
denova mutation
rate right and you know in reality
there's a variance in this that's
determined by this uh by this Theta
parameter but for many applications
thinking about things in terms of this
deterministic um mutation selection
balance is actually really
helpful um right so now we want to
measure strong constraint in the genome
what are we going to do well you know a
large fraction of the genome has
mutation rates that are in the order of
let's say 2 * 109 per generation and so
if that's close to lethal that's like
your frequency in in the population and
that would require an enormous sample
size with any confidence that this
mutation was actually um having these
strong Fitness effects and so we still
need to group sites in order to estimate
the proportion that are under this
extreme purifying
selection uh where this is most commonly
applied perhaps is in the case of
selection on loss of function mutations
in protein coating genes where you know
in addition to protein truncating
variance you have a bunch of stuff that
affects splicing and then you can then
apply a model where let's say we've
estimated the mutation rate at each site
in the gene
and you can get this new parameter in
order to estimate that selection
coefficient um yeah this is you know
what's done sort of
fistic um in in this LT score maybe just
by comparing it observed versus expected
uh counts of loss of function mutations
taking that lower bound there uh and
indeed like when you calculate these
constraint measures they're you know
highly enriched in hlo and sufficient
genes and not in neutral
stuff um alternatively there's methods
that actually explicitly estimate this
heterozygous selection coefficient um
and interesting you might ask okay well
am I really getting at this uh you know
am I you know really getting the
calibrated s or am I just getting
something proportional to it and does
actually turn out seem to be the case
that you're getting something that's on
the correct scale um because we one
prediction is actually that these s hat
estimates if they're real should be um
you know approximately equal to the
fraction of of mutation
in any generation that are caused by
denovo the fraction of variant that are
caused by denovo mutations in any
generation and this does seem to line up
pretty well indicating that these sad
estimates are actually somewhat
estimating that that real population
genetic
parer um yeah and there's some available
estimates of this I won't go through
that right now though okay so now I
guess in the remaining time we'll get
through as much of of the coalescent uh
as we can uh and this is really going to
change gears a little bit um but it it's
another way of looking at genetic
variation that's extremely valuable um
right so we have you know a right simple
right Fisher like population here on the
right and in each generation individuals
are going to you know contribute some
number of uh Offspring to that
population you can go through that
generation after generation and this is
what we thought about as creating this
uh genetic drift right alter we can we
can view this as let's say we sampled
some individuals into the present and we
followed them backwards in time instead
um and so each generation were then
going to follow that variant to the
parents um and doing that step by step
and eventually what's going to happen is
that pairs that we sampled in the
present are going to find their genetic
variance in the same parent um at some
point in the past and meaning that they
you know inherited from that parent the
same the same genetic material and this
is what we call coalescent events and if
we're looking at things backwards in
time we this is where you know those
independent lineages actually merge and
eventually you're going to get back to
just one single uh lineage of sort of
some like Grand ancestor um of the
population at the very least of that
Locus and so there's two things about
this we want to model backwards in time
we also want to think about um genetic
variation in terms of of genealogies um
which is actually something that's true
regardless of what model of evolution uh
one
assumes um the most common statistical
model for this is called the the Kingman
calleson and it's a simple you know
model for building the genealogy you
know totally agnostic to any mutations
we think about the genealogy first and
so going back to this example we had
these three samples here and we had
their coalescent events here for
individuals one and two and here for
individuals 1 2 and
three and all that really matters is
this very simple tree here on on the
left there's a ton of evolution that
happened in the rest of the population
but if we've just sampled these three
individuals that doesn't have any effect
on the patterns of genetic variation in
our sample so we can really just focus
on what happens to the lineages
corresponding to these three
individuals
um so the the the generating process for
the under What's called the Kingman
coalescent is to say okay we've sampled
some let's say four lineages from the
population each pair is going to Co
coales at a rate inversely proportional
to the effective population size and you
know that's going to be so then we would
sample a time to to a coalescent event
these are going to be like competing uh
exponential distributions and then when
that coalescent event occurs we just
choose a pair of lineages to call less
and you can just apply these rules again
and again to generate uh random random
genealogies then the nice part of all
this is that the genealogical process is
totally independent of the mutational
process so you can sample your
genealogies and let's say we sampled
this tree over here for these four
samples and then you can add mutations
on top of that after the fact um and you
can really choose whatever mutational
model you want uh we might use the
infinite sites model as we had
previously and say that mutations occur
as a pon process along each brand with
some rate new and under this model each
mutational event would correspond to a
unique smv which is again the exact same
model that we considered previously um
with this Plus on random field and the
site frequency spectrum you know but you
could also put in some whatever
nucleotide substitution model model you
want and the important part is that
these neutral mutations are independent
of the
genealogy uh we can add recombination to
this Rec combination is a very complex
process and we're going to model it as
some probability of recombination that
occurs each generation with some uh rate
R and so the total Rec combination
probability for some sequence L would
just be L time
R now in addition to these coalescent
rates if we're viewing things backward
in time we can also add in recombination
events that are going to split pieces of
your sampled genetic material up into
independent lineages so you then have
this process where um lineages are both
splitting up due to recombination and
coalescing due to Shared ancestor events
and so this is a very simple you know
example here first you get this um first
you get this uh recombination event that
splits this up then this piece of the
genetic material uh coalesces with this
other sample such that you found a
common ancestor event for that first
piece of the the sequence there and then
eventually it's going to coales with the
rest of the sequence and what this would
lead to is a shorter Gene tree at this
first part of the sequence and a longer
one at the second
part this leads to correlated
genealogies along the genome right so
you're doing these recombination events
it means that the genealogies at nearby
positions even with recombination are
going to be correlated and this is how
we get you know correlation of genetic
variation and linkage dise
equilibrium um
so one way to then summarize all of this
you know complicated process the set of
geneological treats at each Locus is
through the ancestral recombination
graph which really says right this is
this sequence of geneological trees that
each Locus in the genome these
recombination events that connect them
and the locations and identities of of
mutations um and this is an object
that's you know a really um uh focus of
a lot of recent research and there's a
large number of models that are trying
to estimate this thing really for your
sample at each point in the
genome um there's two common features of
ARG inference um you know this is a
difficult process uh one trick is to
sort of cluster cluster your samples at
each point in the genome uh to then you
know get a position specific distance
Matrix between all your Hypes oops and
then use some clustering out and produce
trees and another trick is to sort of
you know if you have a if you have this
R you can thread
new Hypes onto those existing trees and
sort of combining both of those two
things you can get actually pretty good
estimates of of the AR genome
wide um so quickly for for Selective
sweeps just to touch on uh pause of
selection okay so why is this in the the
coalescent part well the one of the main
features of sweeps is that they have
this uh effect of selection on nearby
genetic variation so if we had a
positively selected Al it's going to
have this sort of like logistic growth
trajectory up from low frequencies to
high ones and the rest of the neutral
variation linked to that selected site
um is going to have to sort of follow
this size trajectory right and so that's
going to cause longer branches um
leading to more low frequency variance
but also reduce genetic variation
they're going to have to coess um
lineage are going to have to coales
before the origin of this mutation you
compare this to just like a neutral
genealogy and make some INF is about
where uh where selective sweeps occurred
in in in the
genome right so again okay so you can
have some example this is just from a
silly simulation of what genetic what
the what genealogies look like linked to
a sweep versus neutral ones and see
there's a lot of this really rare
variation down here and you don't have
as much of these um long internal
branches with uh with lots of
descendants right and so methods try to
estimate um sweep in the human genome
and elsewhere and it turns out obvious
sweeps are are quite rare in human so
there are certainly a large number of
high compix samples this is from this uh
Swiffer method from The ROC condrin
group um but in general like sweeps
don't seem to be particularly common um
and if you look around synonymous versus
nonsynonymous substitutions the patterns
of genetic variation are are actually um
actually quite similar indicating that
hasn't been you know these massive Flux
Of sweeps across human
history okay so I guess right before we
end I'm going to talk a little bit about
simulation so we've gone through a lot
of models and one thing I want to
impress on you is just try to make
calculations under these yourself and
when you do so start as simple as
humanly uh as humanly possible and so if
what you want to calculate is just a
summary some simple summary of AAL
frequency using simulations like these
daddy diffusion models is is really
great you can incorporate negative
selection it's incredibly fast you can
incorporate complex demographic models
and get this Alo frequency spectrum that
you can then make your Downstream
calculations from if what you want is
neutral mutations and you really care
about modeling liage dise equilibrium
coalescent simulations are the way to go
you can fast you can quickly simulate
very large chromosomes for instance with
this MS Prime method you can specify Rec
combination rate and mutation rate
complex metapopulations and even these
effects of selective sweeps on neutral
variation and if you really really need
to go more complex than that you have
interaction between multiple selected
sites and their effect on neutral um
genic variation as well as their own
frequencies then you might have to do
right Fisher simulations such as in this
slim uh slim framework this is
necessarily slow because it it's
simulating all of these processes
Generation by Generation Um and you can
ass stuff like polygenic selection
multiple variants but it's very easy to
make mistakes and not realize that you
did so and the manual is 850 pages long
um so you know I I would encourage you
to start start simple it if you
can
um yeah I guess we're about out of time
um I have some slides on you know some
resources and genetic data but you know
those will be posted online I suppose