Okay. So, so right. So just to remind
you, so so last time,
so last time we looked at we had this
sort of motivating example that we had a
graph, we had a function f defined on
some interval from a to b and it was
going inside the real numbers and it
started off negative here. This here is
f of a. This is negative and it ended up
positive
f of b and we wanted to say and this was
a continuous function
uh
and we wanted to say that there was some
c. So we wanted to
to um show
that there's a C between A and B so that
the value at C is equal to zero. So this
was the intermediate values then
and so this was sort of the motivation
for
the motivation this here was a
motivating example for trying to
understand what property of R do we
need. So so the so what property
of R. Do we need
uh to make this
to make this rigorous? So that was the
that was sort of the motivating example,
right?
And so in order to make this rigorous
well then we we need the concept of we
need need to concept of that r we need
to understand um uh the following
statement that r is a complete
uh ordered
uh field
and a field here. So field here just
briefly field here right was a set
with uh two operations
uh plus
and uh and what we call multiplication
each of these.
So each of these
two operations
have uh five property
and then there's an 11th property uh
plus then there's an 11th property
that chain them together
and the last one is usually referred to
as a distributive law.
So, so that was one of the two important
concept that we talked about last time.
The other concept that we talked about
was what's called an ordered set.
So uh so so that's a set uh with an
ordering
and the ordering has to have the
property that so this here the ordering
has the property.
So it has actually two properties.
[Applause]
Uh the first one is that whenever you
take an element x and an element y in
the set then either you should be able
to relate these two by the ordering. So
either
x is equal to y or x is smaller than y
uh or uh or uh y is smaller than x.
And the second property is what's called
transitive that if X and Y and C are
element in the set
and X is less than Y and
Y is less than C then
X should be less than C. So this is the
22 property.
So the first property again is that you
can compare any two elements and the
second one is this transitive law. Okay.
And then so that was the two concepts we
we talked about last time and then we
talked about uh what it meant to be an
ordered field. So so then we also talked
about
ordered fields and an ordered field is
right. You have a field that is also an
ordered set and then those two uh then
the then the relationship so this will
that one being less than the other one
have to interact. So this is these two
things that if you take x is less than y
and you're adding any elements on both
sides
then uh it still preserve the order.
So this is one thing and the second is
that if you take x that's bigger than
zero and y that's bigger than zero then
the product
of x and y should be bigger than zero
and so this is how the the right so an
ordered field again is a field that as a
set is also has an ordering and then the
ordering ing together with the operation
of the field should be chained together
by these two laws. Okay.
Now, so we are we are we're getting
close to understanding this, right? So,
so this question is so in order for all
of this to make sense,
we need to understand what it means that
the real numbers is a complete ordered
field, right? And so we have now this
part of it that it's an ordered field.
We understand that this here is uh we
need to understand what this means.
Okay. So now before I get into that
let's just talk about so what is the
difference
the difference
between
uh the real numbers and the rational
numbers,
right? Remember the rational numbers are
numbers of this form here where this is
an integer and this is a natural number.
So what is the difference between these
two?
But one difference is so one difference
is that that square root of two
um is is a real number
but
but not a rational number.
Okay.
Now let me try to explain why first why
it's not a rational number.
So let's try to see uh so what is square
root of two?
The square root of two.
You can think about it as a number x and
it has to have the property that if you
multiply it by itself, so x * x or if
you will x 2, this should be equal to
two, right? It also should be positive,
right?
Now suppose so I claim that square
of two is not a rational number. So by
that I mean that so so I want to claim
the following.
[Applause]
that does not exist.
A rational number
um x = to m / n. Well, again this here
is a integer. This is a natural number.
So that
x² is equal to 2.
So I claim that that's that that you
don't have a rational number that is
square root of two. Okay. Now let's try
to prove that.
[Applause]
So suppose suppose there was such a
number. So so we want to prove it. So we
prove by contradiction.
[Applause]
So assume
that there exist
x that is a rational number. So it can
be written in this form here where m is
an integer
and n is a natural number.
So assume that there exist a x that is
that is a rational number and so that
the square is equal to two right. Well
if that's the case then m
over n so this here squared is supposed
to be equal to two right. So this means
that so this implies that m2
over n^2 is equal to 2 and this just
multiplying over implies that m2
is equal to 2 n^2.
Now when we write x as a rational
number, of course we know that there are
many ways of writing it as rational
number because you can just if you have
one then you can just multiply the
denominator and denominator by an inte
by a natural number sorry and then you
get another representation right but we
can assume so we may assume
so when we have written so uh we may
assume Assume
that's m and n
and n does not have a common factor,
right? Because otherwise we could just
reduce it. So we could reduce it until
we they don't have a common factor.
Right.
Okay. So, so we we will assume that m
and n do not have a common factor. We
have now that m squ is equal to this.
But this means that m here must be even.
Right? So we have that since
since m 2 is equal to 2 n
squar. So it means that two is a is a
factor in m squ. So it must actually be
a factor in m. So it means that two here
is a factor
in m. In other words, m is even.
But so you can write m here as two times
another integer here.
Right?
But this means that m 2 is equal to 2 m1
squared which is equal to 4 m1 2 right
and we already know that that is equal
to 2 n^2
right so this means dividing by two on
both sides it means that 2 m1^ 2 is
equal to n but this means that sorry is
equal to n^2 so this means that two here
must be a factor in n right so this
means here that two is also a factor
in n but now you see that this is a
contradiction
so this is a contradiction because now
what we have is that two two is a factor
in m and two is a factor in n. So they
have a common factor but we assume they
didn't have a common factor. Right? So
this prove so so we argued by
contradiction. We assume there was a
rational number so that the square of it
was equal to two and we get a
contradiction. So that could not be a
rational number
um uh that has a property that the
square is equal to two. So so square
root of two is definitely not a rational
number. Okay.
Now
so now how do we think about
uh how do we think about square root of
two? So how do we fit
square of two into the number
system?
Right?
Well, square root of two
is if you think about it as a decimal
uh number, then it is uh it starts with
1.4
uh uh 136 and then it 136
and then it continue like this.
So one way of thinking about
uh square root of two is that it is and
we will come back to this at some later
lecture. So we think about so so one way
of thinking about
square is true. is
as a limit
of a sequence of number.
And that that that brings us to a
another really important concept uh that
we will talk uh much more about later is
this with sequences and limits. And so
if we want to think about it as a limit
of a sequence, we think about maybe the
number one
first and then we think about 1.4 and
then we think 1.4.1
and then 1.4
uh two etc. Right? And so you see that
this here is a sequence of numbers. And
so this is an increasing
sequence of numbers
of numbers.
and and square root of two
is the limit
of the sequence.
So again we will talk much more about uh
sequences and limits uh later but this
is just something to keep in mind as a
kind of also motivating why we need to
understand sequences and and limits and
their limits. Okay.
Okay. So this was so so we we now know
maybe not super surprisingly but but we
we know and you know see there was a
very simple proof why uh the real
numbers is larger than the rational
numbers contain in particular square
root of two uh that the rational numbers
does not contain.
we still need to and this is related to
the completeness of R and why the
rational numbers is not complete. Okay,
but this is again what we're now working
uh towards. So we're working towards
what it means to for a field to be
complete.
[Applause]
So let me just write that and and and
I'll explain it more but just this here
is what we aiming towards
completeness
which is and I'll explain that at the
least upper bound property.
Okay. So suppose you take a ordered set.
So suppose
uh S is an ordered set.
[Applause]
So and the ordering we as usual with
ordering
we do by by this.
So suppose S is an order set and suppose
that A here is a subset of S. Then we
say that
we say that um
m is an upper bound
an upper bound for the subset
for a
if for all
elements in a
um
m here
is bigger or equal
to a. So an upper bound is something
that h of for a subset is something that
has to be bigger than all the elements
in the subset bigger equal to it could
be equal to to one of the elements.
So that's a upper bound. And so of
course if you look at
So a couple of examples here.
So,
so if you're looking at if the set here
uh is
is um if if the set here is let's say
that the set is um so s is the natural
numbers here and uh the subset here is
one two three
then the element so then the element
four here is an upper bound
for uh a
um so four is an upper bound for a
whereas
right whereas um
whereas two is not
right obviously three is bigger than two
so uh two is not an upper bound
Another example is um another example is
if you take uh if you take say if s is
the the let's say s is the rational
numbers
and uh and a here is the natural numbers
then a
Then uh a here does not have an upper
bound.
Okay. And I I'll I'll return to this
uh this second example uh in just a
minute.
>> Okay.
So, so that is what it means to be an
upper bound.
So, now
there's another concept and that is a
least upper bound.
So there's another concept of the least
up above.
So again we have S is an ordered set.
we have a here is a subset of s.
Uh then we say that
it's a subset of s maybe let me just
point out that that is bounded
Um so A is a subset of S that is
bounded. Then we say that
then we say
that
capital M is an upper bound
is a a sorry is a least upper bound.
least upper bound
for a
if
m is
an upper bound. So it has to be an upper
bound
and
if
any other upper bound and for any other
B
other upper bound
we have to have that for any other upper
bound say M1 we have that m1 m1 has to
be bigger equal to m.
So it has a least upper bound
if a boundary set has a least upper
bound if there is an element that is the
smallest to so to speak of the upper
bound.
Okay.
And so now so now we are ready to to
state what it means to be a complete
order field.
So a complete
order field
um is
an ordered field.
It's an order field so that uh so that
uh any bounded subset
subset
has a least up.
Okay,
so that's a complete orders field and
and so we have the foreign theorem that
we're not going to prove because that
really takes us off field.
Uh but but um so we just take it for
granted. But there exist.
So theorem
exist the smallest
uh so there exist
a smallest
complete
uh ordered field
that contains the rational numbers.
uh numbers.
Okay, so this is a theorem. Again, we
won't prove it uh because it's really
kind of outside in the scope of this
class. It's not really what we want to
focus on here. Uh but um but it but you
can prove this.
And so
um so that field
field
is uh what we call r is it's a it's a
real numbers. Okay.
Um okay. So now I want to see
uh why I want to see that if we work
with that field instead of the rational
numbers then actually we have in
particular that uh the square root of
two is in that
So, so we will now see. So, we want to
show
that uh square root of two
is in the real. Okay.
So now I'm going to look at the set
A.
So I'm going to look at the set A which
is the element
um
which is the element in R
such that X here is bigger than zero.
and uh x2
is uh is less than two.
Okay. So I'm going to look at this set.
Now of course this set here so a here
is bounded. It's not empty. Let's say
first it's not empty.
Right? It's not empty since
since one here is in a right one is
positive and 1 squared here is of course
one which is less than two
so it's not empty and a here is also a
is bible
right because uh any element so for all
X.
So for all
X in A
uh you have that X squar is is it's X is
positive and is less than two. So this
means that X here must be itself less
than two, right? Because two of course
when you square it you're getting four,
right?
So it's a bounded. So a here is a
bounded subset of the reals.
[Applause]
Now
so now the real has the least upper
bound property.
So this means that I can now define
so define
square root of two
to be the least up about
define it to be
the least up
Okay, but a was a bounded it was a non-
empty bounded subset. So because it we
are in the reals
if you grant this theorem then there is
a least upper bound. Okay.
So now
let's denote. So it let me denote let me
use
denote
this number
by x. I'm going to denote it by x
instead of square root two because if I
if I denote it by square root two then
it's going to be confusing right and
it's like you know you will sort of
automatically use what you think square
root two should satisfy so let's not
let's call it uh let's call it uh
uh x
so I want to prove so it's clear that
since
X here is at least up about
for a
and
in particular one is in A then it means
that one here has to be less or equal to
X right and one of course is positive.
So it means that X here is definitely
false. Right?
Now we need to show that we need to show
that the square.
So we need to show
that
uh that x²
is equal to two. Right? That's what we
need to prove in order to prove that x
is really the square root of two. Right?
So I'm going to divide it up. So we
divide the proof
the proof
into two steps.
The first one is the first one is that
we uh we want to so the first step. So
step one
we're going to show that x² is lesser
equal to two. So this is what we will
show in the first step. Right? And then
the second step will be the reverse
inequality. And of course together this
would be the proof. Right?
So again just like we argue uh before
uh we're going to in this case we will
also argue by contradiction.
It's not a you may get the feeling that
we're always going to argue by
contradiction in this class and we won't
and it's generally thought of that is
better style to prove things directly
but sometimes it's a much more logically
logical and kind of easier in a way at
least easier at the first time to prove
it by contradiction and there's nothing
wrong with proving it by contradiction.
So we will show this by contradiction.
Okay.
And so
so right. So we're going to show that
[Applause]
So we show this by contradiction and so
we assume first. So assume
assume not.
So assume
assume that x² is not less or equal to
two. So we assume not. So
assume
that x² is strictly bigger than two.
Now I will look at x minus some small
number
and I'm I'm going to eventually prove
that if I'm looking at at x minus some
small number
I'm going to prove now that if this hair
was strictly bigger than two then I can
find some small number so that this here
would also be an upper bound. So x
h would be positive.
This here would be a number strictly
less than x. And I would show that this
here is also of a bound. That's what I
want to do. Okay. So I take x minus h
and I square it.
If I do that then I get that uh this is
x2
minus 2 xh
+ h 2 right the square is is not
negative. So this here is definitely
bigger equal to x^2
- 2 xh
and so you see that right
and so now
so now uh if you take so now you have
that x²
is uh by we have that x2 is bigger than
2.
So this means that x^2
minus uh 2 is positive. I am just
subtracting two from both sides. So this
here is we're assuming that this here is
positive. Right?
And so now if I just make sure that um
so if I now make sure that what I am so
if I so now
I'm going to choose so I want to choose
so I want to prove that x minus so so
want to show so I want to get the
contradiction
by finding a
finding
a h bigger than zero.
So that
x - h is also
an upper bound
for a right because this here is clearly
smaller than x right and this would then
contradict that x was the smallest upper
part right so that's what I want to do
and
and so now how do I do that so using
this little calculation here.
So what I want to do is so I want to
find so I want to find
h positive
so that
when I square when I subtract h from x
and I square it then I still get
something bigger than two right so I
want to find h positive so that This
thing here
is bigger than two, right?
And all I need to do is from I need to
show that I can find H. So that this in
here. So enough to show
to show
that I can find find
h such that
x^2
- 2 xh that this thing here is bigger
than two.
Right? And so you see I now I just move
over on the other side to say that this
here is bigger than two. It's the same
as saying I can just move this two over
on that side
and I can move this here over on the
other side. So I just need to find
h with this property. Right? But that of
course is equivalent to saying that h
has to be less than x^2 - 2 over 2x
is positive. This thing here is strictly
positive. So I can certainly find a
positive number. This is something
strictly positive. So I can certainly
find some small h so that is less than
this strictly positive number. Right?
Okay,
so this proves this is step one. This is
just showing that x2 was less or equal
to two. Right? Now I want to argue
similarly
um similarly to prove the other
direction. Okay.
I mean in this case there's not really
any difference, right? I mean the you
see in a minute that one inequality is
not uh any easier than the other. Uh I
have one I have a colleague here. He's
retired now, but he and he collaborated
with some other guy and they made a lot
of famous work and the other guy maybe
become even more famous and he used to
say that when you do mathematics so it
doesn't really apply here because the
two inequality is just as easy but he
used to say that when you do two when
you do mathematics there's three things
you do you locate a problem you prove
one of the two inequality whichever one
is easier
and you ask Ragu. Rau was his
collaborator to prove the other
inequalities.
Okay. So we so step two is um
so step two is that uh x²
is uh is bigger equal to two. Right? And
we will again prove this. So again show
this
by contradiction.
Okay.
So I assume
not
so I assume
that
uh x² here is strictly smaller than two.
Now what we want to prove is so then we
want to we want to get the
contradiction.
We want
to get the contradiction
by showing
that
X is not is not an upper bound.
An upper bound for A.
Right? X was supposed to be the least
upper bound in particular and upper
bound.
So how do we do that? Well, we we're
going to add just a little bit to X.
So this is sort of similar to how we
argued before.
So, so, so I'm going to add, so h again
is being positive.
So, h is positive.
And I'm going to add just a little bit
to x. And I'm going to see that if I
choose h small
then then um I can find something in the
set so that uh if I choose it so that x
so I can so I want to prove that if h is
small enough then x + h
is an a okay contradicting that x was an
upper bound. Okay.
And so h is going to be chos small. So
in particular, it's going to be between
zero and one. Okay. And I'm looking at x
+ h and I'm squaring it. So this thing
here is x2 + h 2 + 2 h x.
Now uh h here is less than one. So this
means that 8 squar since
since 8 is less is positive and is less
than one then you have that h squar here
sorry then you have that h squ is less
than uh than actually h right
and so this thing here is less than uh
x2
+ h + 2 uh h X.
Okay.
And I want to show So I want to show
that I can So I want to show that this X
+ H this is still in A. So I want to
show
that I can find that we can find
such a
such a h so that this here
this here squared
is still less than two. Right?
But so all I need to do is because of
this inequality I just need to find an h
so that this thing here is less than
two. Right? So I want to
to find
H such that
this thing here
is listen to right
now.
Now um right so now again we're just
moving over on the other side we're
moving this in this case we're moving
this x squ over here so we have h + 2 h
x is less than this is what we want to
find
right what to find
and h such that this thing here is less
than 2 - x^2 right this thing here is
now because x^2 is strictly less than
two this is positive right here you can
just factor out an h so you want to find
so if you factor out an h then you have
this thing here is less than 2 minus x^2
and this is just saying that you want to
find an h so that this thing here is uh
is strictly less than 2 - x^2 / 1 + 2x
is positive.
So this thing here is positive.
So this and this here is also positive.
So this here is a positive number. So
you can definitely find some x with this
property, right? And then you see that
so this means that this x + h would also
be in the set a contradicting that x was
an upper bound.
Okay.
Now
um okay so now a corner we immediately
get of this is that the
that the rationals
is not complete
right so
so we get the following corner
the rational number is not complete
Right?
And this is just because so the proof of
that is that we have already so um if
we're looking at the the this this
at a field that is complete and contains
a rational then we know that square root
of two is in that field. Right? So we
just proven
that
if f
is a complete field
containing the rationals
then
square root of two
is in that field.
Right? But we know that square root of
we have also proven we've also shown
we have also shown
also shown
that square root of two is not a
rational number. Right? So, so the
rational, so if you're looking, so the
rational in itself is not complete.
Um,
okay.
Now, the next thing I want to do is
prove what's called the Archimedian
properties. The Archimedian property.
And so, this is actually something that
was sort of used here. Um, sort of used
it I know it already, but let me just
prove it
because
so the Arimedian property.
So this is the following
that um that for all
for all
real numbers every time you take a real
number
then there exist
uh an integer
even a natural number
in such that
uh n here is bigger equal is bigger than
uh than than x. Okay, this seems like a
kind of trivial fact, right? But let me
try to actually prove it uh in a
rigorous way. So this is what's called
the Archimedian property.
And so again
we prove this by contradiction.
So suppose not
so if there existed an X. So that you
did not have this. Well then so suppose
not
then
there. So the negation of that statement
is that then there exist
an x such that
for all
natural numbers for all
you have that n here is lesser equal to
x
right it's actually yeah it's lesser
equal to x right because this is the
negation
of that.
But this means that
this means
that
uh x here is an upper bound.
Okay. And so now you could so now so so
then you could take so assume
So you could replace by this by the
least upper bound property.
So this means so it's upper bound. So in
particular
the natural number is a bounded set.
Bounded subset bounded subset
of of the reals. Right?
And then you could take so then we let
then
let's let's say y
be
the least upper bound
uh of the natural numbers.
If it really was if the natural numbers
was really bounded because it's a subset
of the real we could now take the least
upper bound.
Okay. So now what we have is that we
have that
for any natural number. So for all
we have that n here is lesser equal to
y.
But whenever you take a natural number
then add one to that nual number. So we
also have we would also have that
right. So so y is not just a upper bound
for n but it actually because n plus one
is also not actual number right. So y
here
would have to be big or equal to n plus
one also right but this and this now
hold for all n. So this means that just
moving the one over on the other side.
So hence
n here is less than y minus one. Right?
So this but this here say that so mean
this means
this mean
that y -
1 is also an upper bound
[Applause]
and that that and that this is a
contradiction right so this contradict
that
uh that why was the least up about
okay and that's the property
okay
now uh I want to give uh one application
of this
uh and so this is the following
What the hell?
So, so we now uh I now want to prove the
following corner of the Archimedian P.
And the corner is that uh whenever you
have two real numbers x and y.
So these are are real numbers and x here
is less than y. Then the claim is that
then there exist
a rational number
m over uh n
with
uh with a property that is between these
two. so that that x is less than m / n
and less than one. Okay, that's what I
want to prove using the archimedian
property.
And so so to prove that so to prove that
um
so to prove that I look at at better
saying better is y - x
and I'm looking at uh so y - x because y
is bigger than x this is positive
And I can now look at one over beta. So
one over beta is some positive real
number.
And now the Archimedian property say
that. So by the archimedian property
the Archimedian property there exist
there exist
um n a natural number
such that
n is bigger than
one over b,
right? That's the armedian property. It
gives us this n.
But now, of course, if that's the case,
this implies
you just take one over on both sides and
that reverses the inequality. This
implies that 1 / n is smaller than
better.
When we get that
and so now we are just looking at so now
we look at
so now that's this sort of defined as
step size to some extent. So we're
looking at so we have here
X and we have here Y
and beta bet better is really this
distance here this here is better
distance between the two
and uh n here is uh we now have seen
that there's a n so that when you're
looking at 1 / n then then uh so one / n
here is smaller then better something
positive and smaller and better.
So now you're looking at the at the m So
now you're looking at So now look at the
at the integers
so that uh m
minus one
so that m minus one uh is
uh uh is less than x *
So suppose you're looking at the right
this thing here right if you take x * n
this is an integer so there's definely
some m with this property and you can
find the biggest so look at
m with this property and let's and let's
denote n
and choose
the largest
such m.
So if you choose the largest such m then
you see that right so this inequality
here this will just tell you that m -1
uh over uh over uh n that this is
smaller than x right
but you would also have that because it
was the largest such m Okay.
Since
Since M was the largest
such
such m then you would have that if you
had m itself in the denominator then it
wouldn't be smaller than than x. would
actually be larger equal to x,
right?
And I just want to now prove that this
so this here is bigger than x. That's
part of what I needed to prove. I also
wanted to show that it's smaller than y,
right?
And um and so but if you now add, right?
So now but now the step size. So when
you have here here you have x here you
have y
1 / n 1 / n was smaller than this
distance. So if you are at some point
here this is where you are when you are
at m minus one / n then you can't go
further to the right. you you go one
over n uh to the right, but that can't
take you all the way past one, right? So
that's why if you're looking at at this
number here, this here must be smaller
than y.
Okay? And if I had just chosen m so that
this here was smaller equal to that,
then I would get this point.
Okay? So that's how
that's a corary of the Archimedian
property. I think there would be
something like something along these
lines on the homework. And again, I will
uh I'm just waiting for the the office
hour. I know that the office hour there
will at least be four office hours next
week. Monday
uh on Mondays and Wednesday the office
hours would be there will be office
hours from 5 to 6 on Monday and
Wednesday. uh um and and the other days
it would be 1:15 to uh 2:15. But you can
check the the the the time is actually
already uh posted. Uh the room number I
hope to have that today. Once I have
that then I will also assign the
homework probably today or maybe more
likely tomorrow the homework but it
won't be due next week just the
following week.
Any
questions?
And of course, I very much encourage you
to go to to the office hours. Um, and um
yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry.
>> Right. So remember that the minus1 was
this element that you had when you had
uh remember that a field had the true
operation plus and multiplication right
and and for each of these that had five
property they were sort of they were
sort of
almost the same property there was one
exception about that zero didn't have a
inverse right for multiplication but
minus one is is the right so you one but
one is the neutral element for
multiplication
right that was how one was defined right
and we prove that that there was a
unique zero right that same argument
would prove that there's a unique one
okay so there's just one one so it's a
well- definfined notion and then you can
look at the inverse element of that with
respect to addition that's minus one
right
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And that's a good question and I
will come back to that next time. And
and it it would seem more logical to
define both upper and lower bound. But
you can look at the complement,
right? And so if you take a set and
you're looking at the complement, then
the upper bound for that is the same as
the lower bound. So that's a kind of
sneaky way. That's the reason why we did
it. I, you know, I I might have done it
the other way around, but then it was
kind of a little bit overkill, but I
agree. It seemed more logical to define
both things, but it actually is
contained in this.
Any other questions?
>> Yeah.
I mean so we had so so again u we we saw
that square root of two is not a
rational number right and if We're
looking at all rational numbers.
All rational numbers so that the square
is less or equal to two. Right? That set
does not have a it has an upper bound in
a rational number, but it doesn't have a
least upper bound. Right? Right. And
that's because we we first prove that
there wasn't a rational number so that
it it multiplied itself was equal to
two. Right? We proved that.
Yeah, that's right. That's right. That's
right. That's right. That's right.
That's right. That's right. So, a field
by it's right. A field is complete means
that whenever you take a subset of that
field that is bounded then that subset
has to have a least upper bound and but
any bounds including the least of bounds
that always have to be in the fields.
Any other questions?
>> Yeah.
smaller than one because
we can do the
>> so this is in so so when we when we um
so you're saying so
so I just want to make sure I understand
so in the step two
we added something and we wanted to
prove that you could add something and
this is still less than two
And and so I was looking for h between
zero and one.
And so then I I got some equation
somewhere that is probably a raised now,
but it just require that h was
I mean h have to be positive but it was
less than something and that was
>> right. So, so you you Okay. So, I got I
don't remember what I got here. So, I
think I uh Yeah, you're right. Two. I
can I guess I can reconstruct it.
>> Yeah. So, now I So, so I think so what
you are saying is that so so this thing
here actually so this thing here is
positive, right? And so you want to
choose h so that is smaller than this
but also this here. So you don't but if
this is positive then I mean if this is
500 well uh I mean I'm not going to
choose 500 because it was supposed to be
less than one but I just choose it so
that it's less than one and also less
than this positive number.