There's something really interesting when
you walk into a classroom.
You hear so many different accents.
You hear students
from all over the world.
You meet faculty from all over the world.
It's very rare at MIT
to walk into a meeting
and be the only person who's a
foreign-born individual.
And you see people who
are drawn to MIT as a place
as much as they're drawn to
being in the United States.
They're drawn to the idea of MIT.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
MIT is a very special place.
And the more time is spent
here, the more you see it,
because there are so many
brilliant people around you.
We are a community, that is
diverse on who we are.
And that forces our
ideas to become better.
You walk around the Infinite
Corridor, and suddenly you
see a person who wrote a
textbook or the person who
won the Nobel Prize.
And suddenly it's not
any person in the field.
It's the person in the field.
We're all rational,
compassionate human beings first.
And then, oh, and by the
way, I come from Beirut.
By the way, I come from Macedonia.
By the way, I come--
it's something that we
take to be for granted,
that we come from somewhere, and we have
a unique story to tell.
A place like MIT is where
you could also do research
that you care about.
You can do the
science that you care about.
I've always been
fascinated by what's the problem
I'm solving what
difference does it make.
There was this draw to MIT,
because it was this mecca,
really, this place where
all of this amazing research
was happening.
My passion has been about understanding
long-run economic growth,
what makes some countries rich,
some countries poor.
I decided to work on machine
learning for small molecules.
It was really a new area.
What is this transition between an atom
and a bulk material?
How do authoritarian regimes and
dictatorships come about?
What explains regime durability?
So for me, the scientist is not a job.
There was a thing I
thought, oh, that would
be super cool to be.
I decided that I would work
on helping people get smarter.
What I do, I don't see it as a job.
I see it as a calling.
And so when I get up every
day, solving this problem
is what is always in my mind.
I get to think about
these lofty questions of where
do we come from and
what's out in the universe.
But then I get to go
in a lab and just build,
Just plain old build things, design things.
And so it's the best job in the world.