okay good morning nice to see everybody
um I'm just want to begin by saying as
MIT considers the impact in the world as
you just heard through the climate
project we're also taking the Bold steps
to strategize and Implement exactly what
we're saying we want to do in the world
but on the campus in the context of the
city the state the nation and the globe
so I'm going to give you just a little
bit of a teaser today as to how we're
framing this the work we've been doing
over the past decade um but of course
there's always room for dialogue with LP
members you know moving down the line so
just before I start I just had a couple
questions and I'm going to jump in how
many of you have Chief sustainability
officers in the companies that are
present here
today okay great and how many of you are
chief sustainability
officers okay a couple of you and then
how many of you have zero carbon
commitments or Net Zero commitments okay
great a handful of you so there's a lot
of relatability between what I'm going
to share with you is our methodology to
many of you regardless of your higher
education or industry and that's one of
the lessons learned that we've had over
the past um decade working closely with
ILP members and with the MIT climate
sustainability Consortium so we've
deliberately designed our approach so
that we can enable the exchange of
strategy and best practices across
industry municipalities and other large
organizations so I'm going to share with
you a bit of that so when we look ahead
as we frame mit's commitment to
sustainability we're thinking about MIT
is a city within a city and it's
completely directly like one of the
first meetings I sat in when I got here
was not only with MIT but it was with
the city of Cambridge so we completely
understood our context in Cambridge
Boston and the greater Commonwealth we
don't need to go through all the details
but that's just to give you a sense as
you think about your organizations how
you might relate maybe you're one
building maybe you're a full
campus the underlying structure that has
driven my entire career and underlines
the work that we're doing and MIT is
what is the organizational structure and
behavior that is responsive to Alters
informs and influences the climate
trajectory that we're on as we heard
Chris kidle say earlier this isn't just
a matter of climate Tech this isn't a
matter of of one Silver Bullet that's
going to change the world these are
complex organizations with complex
people with individual needs that we
have to figure out what is the
responsibility of the organization and
what is the responsibility of the
individual so our mission that we set
out to accomplish at MIT just over a
decade ago is how do we transform MIT
that was number one which we're in the
midst of but how do we ensure that we're
doing it with a framework that's
replicable scalable generates just
Equitable applicable and scalable
solutions for these unprecedented times
that we just heard about and we do this
through a very collaborative process and
we Elevate diverse voices and it's
really hard some of the time a lot of
the time but we love it and we have
amazing Partners across the operational
academic research and innovators uh on
our
campus one of the unique at uh com value
ads that we made actually to the field
was that we actually didn't launch the
office uniquely on a platform or a
definition of sustainability we launched
the office on a platform of thinking
about scales of impact so we thought
deeply about what is it that we're
solving for how how do we solve we can't
solve for sustainability and climate as
an MIT as an island it was so clear that
we were thinking about what what we were
here for the students education all that
you heard about through Richard Lester's
introduction before in terms of what was
coming out of MIT but we're thinking
about the role of the campus in the
context of this complex City in the
context of the regulatory environment
within the city the people the shared
resources streets Etc in the context of
the unique state of Massachusetts
obviously the nation and the globe so
everything that we work on from Food
Systems to Energy Systems to materials
to the way we build our buildings we
think about climate resiliency is always
run through all of these lenses what has
to take place on the campus what do we
have to partner with with the city and
what has to take place within the
Commonwealth and in fact on Thursday for
those of you in the area we're hosting a
forum on decarbonization we're bringing
in the director of the energy transition
I for the Commonwealth the new climate
uh officer for the city of Cambridge and
myself and we're talking about what has
to take place collaboratively across
these three scales in this unique
regulatory environment where we all have
shared commitments of zero carbon by
2050 uh industry Partners May organize a
little differently at the higher
education we've what we've done here at
MIT is think about the campus as a
sustainable system the campus is a test
bed where we can take some risks we can
be demonstrable we think deeply about
leadership and capacity building from
the operational and implementation staff
to faculty students and researchers and
of course we're deep into collaborative
Partnerships and we work with
universities all over the
world so this is how we work we we
organized around these systems we're
connected around these areas in a very
prioritized way on the campus and then
we apply this cross our scales of impact
so again for today I'm just giving you h
a teaser of the of the pieces but this
is how this is how we work at MIT and I
hope this can you know either if some of
you are working in the same way please
reach out or if there's something that
can be shared with you again please let
us share that with
you so how we're solving for climate
sustainabil MIT is also quite unique is
that we use this term many uh industry
high education us use the term living
lab test bed but it's really to think
about how do we demonstrate this and
demonstrate the the challenges that we
what can we learn from what's happening
on the campus and actually apply it to
all the climate missions that you that
you learned about about today we are
deeply committed to zero carbon
emissions it can't happen tomorrow
because we've inherited 100-year old
infrastructure that's below grade that's
connected to steam and a range of old
buildings so we're really trying to
understand what does it mean to
transform all of our systems so in that
and I'll get into that in a moment but
in that way we we uh we have strategies
that connect with our research and
course engagement and then we involve
all of the operational and campus
infrastructure folks and we bring
everybody together in this campus's test
bed approach and what's unique about the
way we've done this is that the campus
and operational infrastructure folks
they need standards and guidelines and a
blueprint on how to do this and and they
need to understand what are the
innovative solutions we can pull down on
the campus without taking too much risk
because we need to provide electricity
chilled water and heating to the campus
247 in a resilient manner to all of our
staff students and researchers and on
the research engagement side in the more
traditional way we need research and
Publications they need revised and
updated models and also innovative
solutions and new businesses as you
heard about earlier so you can actually
bring these pieces together so all are
satisfied and it can lead to new ways of
solving how we scale this is a 10-minute
presentation in of itself but I thought
for the audience today this is a teaser
to just think about the unique ways and
how might you put your own organization
on this model and so on the left-and
side we think about you know this is how
I set up the office starting from zero
in 2013 of saying brought in to say how
do you launch an impactful program
and I thought about okay what's our
value add to the system and so this
might not be all of them but we have to
be able to forecast and stay ahead of
the curve for on behalf of MIT we have
to assess and reduce all of the risk
affiliated with a changing climate and
sustainability and how we frame that and
we have to scale the investment for
implementation so we can rationalize
where do we invest where do we hold back
and we need to leverage these strategic
Partnerships like we're doing in the
room today and there are many great
examples so we started with a long
and then we're moving up towards this
decarbonization by 2050 and thinking
through what are the Staffing how do you
build out the workforce what are the
educational outcomes what are the
businesses that can be rolled off how do
we influence the workforce of the future
in in the Commonwealth so that's our
framework and uh we're at as you can see
between the 2020 and 2025 area
there okay last piece I'm going to just
um share with you I won't have time to
get into all these but I wanted to share
with you how strategic we are and how we
think about the Implement framing
strategy and implementation of climate
sustainability structures so we have
what I've framed in seven parts around
inquiry and design via these driving
questions like I shared with you earlier
really always coming back to what are we
solving for how are we framing for this
so we think about working from common
scientific models Across The Institute
we think about we have to set goals and
plan across scales we Foster City
University Partnerships we lead through
collaboration and we have to hold
ourselves accountable we leverage as I
shared the campus as a test bed we have
to Center equity and Justice and of
course we're only the model is only as
good as the implementation to
demonstrate impact over time and so I'm
just going to share three of these with
you of examples of how we've activated
the campus as a test bed we've got a
campaign on connecting the dots and we
ask questions about like could m these
buildings become as smart as the people
who work in them as a way to bring
people in to strategizing on new
Behavior as benedetto mentioned in our
own campus we have dashboards and data
available to the entire MIT community on
a unique sustainability platform where
we have our we have flood models we have
heat models some of which was were built
with Miho that you learned about so we
can use the campus as a test bed to
inform the mission that you just learned
about U and we teach classes many many
of us have designed classes Kristoff has
designed one my I've designed one where
we're actually bringing our own
operational folks into the classroom to
say this is how things work on campus
all right and the final piece we have 18
climate and sustainability commitments
in action and that with over a hundred
uh faculty staff and students involved
in informing and implementing these
commitments across campus and we are
deep in our DEC decarbonization planning
to reduce our emissions by by 50 we have
a Net Zero by 2026 commitment in order
to think about well one in order to
comply with the city of Cambridge we're
aligned with our friends at Harvard and
we're deeply committed to figuring out
how do we have impact in the world while
figuring out how to reduce emissions
manage Legacy infrastructure and we
think about we're working on a plan that
will come out in the spring on
generation distribution and of course
reducing energy working with Kristoff
and his building energy models so I'll
leave you with that hopefully want to
learn more and hopefully there's
opportunity for partnership so thank you
[Applause]