When we saw that there was a
bladesmithing class, we all jumped on
the idea of learning how to make a
blade.
>> It was just a awesome new class that
they decided to do because Bob Kramer
was going to be here.
>> When I heard that he was coming to MIT,
I knew this was a very unique
opportunity I wouldn't really get again.
>> Bob Kramer is a master bladesmith whose
specialty is actually uh cooking knives,
but beyond that, as an artist, the
pieces he makes are all singular. My
background is cooking and so essentially
I'm cooking steel. I'm making up new
recipes with steel.
>> If you look at the MIT logo, there's a
blacksmith, the men's a manus minds and
hands. And so the teaching uh and the
practice of working with metals has been
an important part of our department for
a long time.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.