Hello everyone. Welcome to those of you
who are in person with us today. Welcome
also to everyone who is joining us
online. My name is Daniela Rus. I'm
the director of the Computer Science and
Artificial Intelligence Laboratory at
MIT and I would like to welcome you to
the inaugural CSAIL Forum. Uh today we
launch a new platform for rigorous and
visionary intellectual exchanges at the
frontiers of computer science and
artificial
intelligence. And our inaugural speaker
is professor Phillip Isola whose
groundbreaking work uh is at the
intersection of computer science,
computer vision, machine learning and
cognitive science. And um this work has
consistently challenged conventional
thinking and so I am delighted to pass
the microphone uh to Phillip in just a
second. Okay. Yeah. Thank you for the
introduction. Um and happy to talk about
uh this work that we've done in my group
recently that we call the platonic
representation hypothesis.
And this is work with uh Minyoung Huh,
Brian Cheung, and Tongzhou Wang. They were
the initial authors that we on the paper
we put out last summer. And then Yulu Gan
and Ivy Zhao who are new students in my
my group have been following up and
doing more work on this. So um I've
given this talk a few times. Um but
there'll be some new stuff uh in it as
well. I'm going to update it with the
last six months of progress as well.
Okay.
So showing the intro animation that um I
forgot to press play on that. Okay.
Different ways of looking at the world.
Okay. So I'll start with this story
which
is one of the papers I really like from
the last decade. Um this is work from uh
Antonio and Aude Oliva uh and uh and
others. And what they found is that
object detectors emerge in deep scene uh
convolutional neural networks. So uh in
this paper from 2015 they took a neural
network and they tried to probe what
internally is it representing about the
world. So they trained the network to
predict the scene label like this is a
dining room and if you then go into the
network and you probe the neurons you
stick like electrodes virtual electrodes
in there and you measure what those
neurons respond to. They found that
there were neurons that would be
activated selectively for certain object
categories. So there was a neuron that
acted like a dog face detector and
there's another neuron that acts like a
um robin head detector. That's neuron B
here. So this is really cool because it
kind of showed that these systems are
not just uninterpretable black boxes
that you can actually dig into them and
they have internal structure that kind
of make sense. In order to understand
what is going on in an image in a scene,
you should first detect the objects and
then you'll know that it might be like a
park scene outdoors. Okay. So uh we did
this study a few years ago uh where we
tried to train a network to colorize
photos just predict the colors in a
black and white image and we ran the
same uh experiment as they did in the
previous work where we looked internally
and asked what are the units what are
the neurons uh selective to and the
really interesting thing is that we find
a similar pattern. So, you might think
that a network trained to just colorize
photos, like predict the colors in a
black and white image, would have a very
different internal representation than a
network that's trained to classify is it
a kitchen or is it a bathroom or is it a
living room? But it turns out no,
they're actually quite similar. So,
there is a neuron inside a colorization
network that detects if there's a dog in
the image and there's another neuron
that detects if there's a flower in the
image. In order to solve the problem of
just predicting missing colors, you get
these kind of semantic units. And this
is a story you might have heard before.
Uh it's it's appeared all over the
place. Uh for very um diverse kinds of
ways of training your neural networks,
you end up with internal structures that
uh always kind of look somewhat similar.
They they have face detectors. They have
edge detectors on the early layers. They
have gabbors and then they go up and
they create more complicated structures.
Um so there seems to be some kind of
similarity in the internal
representations in computer vision
systems across many different models and
ways of training them.
Okay, so that's led us uh to this point
where we really wanted to uh put a
hypothesis around that idea and
investigate to what degree is it um
going to be true. So the hypothesis
we'll investigate in this talk is uh the
hypothesis that different neural
networks trained on different data with
different architectures, different
optimization somehow converge to similar
or maybe even the same way of
representing the world. To what degree
is that true?
Okay,
so there's a lot of reasons why that
might be happening and you might already
have some ideas in your mind like okay
well of course these things learn
similar structures because they're all
trained on the same data sets right we
have these standard data sets imageet
and and so forth and now we train all
our big models on the internet so maybe
it's just the data it's all about the
data convergence is driven by training
on similar data sets okay also we all
use the same architecture right we're
all using transformers now could be the
architecture. Maybe it's the
optimization. We're all using Atom and
SGD. Uh maybe it's about us. Like I'm
talking to you, I'm telling you how I
did it. Maybe it's just sociotechnical
like we all converge because we're going
to the same conferences. We want to
follow the same trends. So I think these
are all part of it. But I want to argue
that it's something a bit deeper. Uh
that actually when we train our models
on different data sets systematically,
they also look like they have similar
internal structure. uh when we change
the architecture if we don't use a
transformer, it also ends up converging
to something kind of similar. So I want
to argue that uh it's all about the
world. We're modeling the world and the
world is ultimately the thing that
unifies all of these
representations. Okay, so I'll go into a
lot more detail about exactly what I
mean. I'll talk about these five things.
So first, evidence of convergence. Uh
second, some ideas for what is driving
convergence. Uh then a uh a thought on
what we might be converging to. what is
this ultimate representation that we
might end up with in theory? I'll talk
about some counterarguments and then
some implications and applications of
these
ideas. So let's start with evidence of
convergence. Okay. And at the end I'll
uh try to leave time for uh questions so
we can have some discussion at the end.
Okay. So I'm going to analyze
representations in neural nets uh using
kernels. So what I mean by that is we
will restrict our attention to
representations that are vector
embeddings. So neural nets that map from
data to vector in Rn. Okay, this isn't
everything, but this is a very broad
class of
systems. And we're going to characterize
a representation by how it measures
distance. Okay, so we do that in terms
of this function we call the kernel.
It's a standard object in machine
learning. uh it's the inner product
between the embedding for data point I
and data point
J. Okay, so this kernel is like the
similarity matrix in the feature space
of a neural
network. Okay, so here's what the kernel
might look like for a computer vision
neural network that takes images and
outputs embeddings. And what this kernel
is saying is it's saying how similar is
my neural network's representation of
apple to orange and that will be this
cell here and it will say that's quite
similar uh because maybe this network
has been trained to understand fruits
and it knows that those are similar
objects. Uh and orange and elephant will
be considered dissimilar. So this matrix
is telling me how does the neural
network measure distance and it's one of
the kind of fundamental structures that
people use to understand internal
representations in neural networks as
well as other areas of machine learning.
If we can un if we know the kernel then
we know a lot about the um about the
representation and what it can do.
Okay. So what we're going to be looking
at is the similarity between the kernels
uh given by two different models. So
here's one example of two different
vision models. One is called clip,
another is called dyno. These are
standard current computer vision models.
And we're going to ask to what degree
are their kernels the way they measure
distance uh similar to each other. So
it's a similarity measure between
similarity structures inside the neural
network. Uh so in this case Dino and
clip have some minor differences in this
cartoon but they're roughly similar
kernels. They both think apples and
oranges are quite
alike.
Okay. So this is the main metric that
we'll be using to analyze uh to what
degree are different networks finding
similar representations. And the first
experiment I want to run is looking at
different vision systems and asking as
vision systems get better and better at
the task of vision, do they end up
representing the world in similar or
different ways? So hypothesis one will
be uh no no there's many different
equally good ways of representing the
visual world and there's no reason why
you know current state-of-the-art
systems will all choose the same one.
There could be equally valid uh and
diverse approaches. And hypothesis too
is um actually no it turns out that all
strong vision representations are
somehow alike. They all measure distance
in similar ways. Uh and this this has
been described as kind of an anakinario
anaina scenario uh by bonsel at all um
in the past. So all strong
representations are
alike. Okay. So we ran this experiment.
We downloaded 78 different vision
models. Uh these are contrastive models.
They're recurrent models. They're resnet
models. They're convolutional models.
They're a bunch of different models and
they have different architectures,
objectives, and they're trained on
different types of data. And we grouped
them by their performance on this VTAB
benchmark, which is meant to be kind of
an assessment of how good is your visual
representation. You assess how good is
your representation in these models by
doing transfer learning onto a suite of
downstream
tasks. Okay, so here's the uh result
that we found. So on the y-axis is how
similar are the representations to each
other within a bucket of performance and
the buckets of performance are on the
x-axis. So what you can see is that
models that perform very well. So they
solve between um they they solve many
different vtab tasks. Uh they have very
similar representations. So all models
that solve uh these tasks well have
similar representations. models that
don't solve very many of the tasks uh
are much more diverse and there's many
ways you can be wrong but only one way
you can be right in in this particular
measure of performance called
vab uh we can look at that in a slightly
different way by just uh making this
kind of dimensionality reduction this um
visualization of here are all our
different models that we tested and you
can see they have different symbols for
different types of architecture and
objective and the color indicates their
performance on the VAB transfer learning
task and blue means high performance And
you can see that uh the main uh feature
that uh organizes uh how these models
group together uh which models are cons
are alike in their representations is
their performance. It's not the
architecture, it's not the objective uh
it's the performance. So the
wellperforming models all have similar
internal representations. Okay. So the
the the conclusion of this experiment is
that the anacrrenina situation is
seeming to hold here. Uh strong models
are alike, weak models are weak in their
own way.
Okay. So, I think that that was that's
an interesting result. Uh but maybe not
too surprising. You know, as we get
better and better vision systems,
they're going to perform well at the
same task. So, to perform well at the
same task, of course, they've got to
somehow, you know, find similar features
and have similar representations. Uh
we're going to now ask something that's
a little bit less clear which is do you
also get similarity between different
modalities. So representations of
language are they becoming more similar
or less similar to representations of
vision? Okay. Again we'll have a few
hypotheses. So hypothesis one is that
no. I mean as you get a better and
better language model it becomes a
language expert. It just gets really
good at syntax and grammar. But why
would it get better at recognizing cats
and dogs? That doesn't make any sense.
Okay. Okay, they might even get worse
because they're getting specialized
specialized to to language. Okay,
hypothesis two is well somehow language
and vision share common properties and
so actually better language models are
better vision models and there might be
in like a really strong hypothesis like
the very best language model is actually
the same as the very best vision model.
There's some like actual unification um
at the end. Okay, so we're going to run
um the same experiment but now we're
going to look at crossmodal similarity.
So we're going to take the kernel for a
vision system and compare it to the
kernel for a language system. But now
we're cross modalities. So in order to
ask if the language system is
representing Apple and orange in the
same way as the vision system is, we're
going to run the language system on the
captions uh that correspond to the uh
images that we ran the vision system on.
So we're asking is the word apple
similar to the word orange in the same
way as the image apple is similar to the
the image
orange. Okay, just to uh draw that one
more time. What we're asking is if
they're structured like this, does the
vision model embed apple and orange near
each other and far from elephant uh in
the same way as the language model
embeds the word apple and the word
orange near each other and far from
elephant. So, we're looking at the
distance structure is the same between
these two modalities. There could be a
rotation or scale transformation. So,
we're using a metric that's invariant to
those types of changes. We're just
looking at if if these two
representations measure distance in the
same
way. Similarity of embedding of apple uh
and orange is roughly the same as
similarity of of embedding image of
apple and image of of
orange.
Okay. So we measured this uh not over
emojis uh we actually downloaded real
photos and so we used the Wikipedia
image text data set. So we have a lot of
photos along with their caption and
we're evaluating uh do does the vision
system represent these photos of Euseite
uh according to the same distance
function as the language model
represents these captions that describe
those photos of
Euseite. Okay. So here is the the main
result. The main result is that we're
going to
plot alignment to vision. We're g we're
be measuring the alignment between
different language models and a computer
vision model. Here we're picking one
computer vision model which is the
Dynino V2 model. And we're going to uh
measure the alignment to the Dynino V2
model as a function of the language
models performance at next word
prediction. So as language models get
better and better along the x-axis at
predicting next word and sentences at
their basic task, do they end up
becoming more and more alike in their
kernels to vision models? Okay. Okay.
And so here's the result. So yes, the
answer is uh uh in within this regime
they do. Uh so this is a small uh vision
model. And as you look at different
language models ranging from 1 billion
parameter language models to 65 billion
parameter language models, the bigger
more performant language models end up
having higher kernel alignment with the
vision models. So better language models
represent the world in ways that are
more visual. And the trend goes in the
other way too. So better vision models
also become more aligned to language
models. So Dino Giant, it's a really big
computer vision model that's very good
at computer vision tasks, is more
similar in how it represents the world
to llama, a language model, than Dino
small is. So it goes both ways. Big
vision models represent the world in a
similar way as language models do. And
big language models represent the world
in a similar way as vision models do. It
looks like there really is some
convergence going on.
Okay. So, is it going to continue? Uh,
maybe. I'll I'll note that the metric
that we're using, I'm not actually
giving you all the details on that, but
we're not at saturation. We're at a
point about.16 on a metric that goes
from 0 to one. Uh, so you could get
better. Uh, maybe it's going to saturate
or maybe this trend will fall off. It's
just like a spurious correlation and it
won't it won't uh hold for next year.
And the last time I gave this talk, I I
I would stop at that point and say
speculation where this will go next. But
fortunately, just two weeks ago, you
know, some people ran these same
experiments, but they went up to 7
billion uh scale vision model. So we we
went up to 1 billion scale vision model
dinov v2 and we had a alignment of.16
and people at meta went up to 7 billion
a few weeks ago and measured alignment
as a function of size of vision model
and the trend actually
continues. So they they had some
interesting nuances in this paper so
I'll encourage you to look into it if
you're interested. Uh basically they
found that the trend continues as you
add more data but not necessarily more
model scale. But big picture uh this
this trend is continuing. It might be
kind of flattening out a little bit. So
who knows if it will go to uh go to one
and be perfectly unified. But uh we are
still seeing more alignment increasing
between vision and language models up to
the year 2025. Philip, do you understand
why from 1B to um 5B seems to be flat?
Yeah. Um so I need to look into the
details. The question is do I understand
why this part is flat here? uh 1b to 5B.
Uh I think the point that they're making
is that just increasing model scale
without commensurately increasing data
doesn't seem to have an effect on its on
its own. Uh but if you also then
increase data then you see the effect.
Um so yeah just adding more parameters
alone doesn't doesn't have the effect.
Uh but again this is not my work so I'll
need to look into those
details.
Okay. Um so going back to our work uh we
didn't just run this on dyno. We ran it
on a bunch of different vision models
and the trends are the are roughly the
same. So masked autoenccoders and
imageet classifiers also as you make
better language models they correlate
more with um vision model performance
and vice
versa.
Okay. Uh so if
uh I'm going to now move into some
explanations for why I think this might
be happening. Uh but if you're
interested in more evidence and more
measures of convergence and debates
about exactly how to measure
convergence, uh this is a huge field. It
generally goes under the name
representational alignment uh there's a
huge community in neuroscience that
looks at representational alignment
between the brain and neural nets. We're
looking at just representational
alignment between neural nets and other
neural nets. Uh and here are two uh
workshops that one of them is happening
in a few weeks. This realign workshop
and another one happens yearly at
Nurups. So if you're interested, there's
a lot more material to to get into in
this community.
uh but maybe suffice it to say uh there
is a large community that has found that
models are becoming more and more alike
in their kernel structure and other
types of internal
organization. Okay. So now I want to
talk about some ideas that we have for
why this is happening and I'm going to
first talk about some kind of machine
learning 101 ideas and then I'll I'll
talk about uh kind of a toy model of
what we might be converging to. Okay.
So, so one idea, what is driving this
convergence is what we call the
multitask scaling hypothesis. And this
is saying that if I'm searching for
functions that fit my data or fit my set
of tasks, well, if I have one task that
I train the model to perform well on or
one data set I train it to perform well
on, then this is the subspace um a of
hypothesis space, the subspace of the
set of all possible functions I could
learn that actually solve the task. And
so gradient descent will find a solution
within that space. But if I have two
tasks, now I have more constraints and I
have a strictly smaller subspace of
models that can fit two tasks. And as I
had more constraints, more data, more
tasks, then I get strictly smaller um
subspaces of hypothesis space that can
actually fit the data and solve all of
those tasks. Okay, so we're training
models on more and more data on more and
more tasks and you should expect that
that will cause some convergence.
uh this is related to two other ideas
that are out there. One one version of
this is called the contravarian
principle in neuroscience and then again
it's an anacreninet principle like all
happy representations uh have to solve
all the constraints and if you violate
if you you know if you're wrong in one
way you'll fail on one of the tasks uh
so if you have a lot of pressure to be
uh correct in all ways then it kind of
causes
convergence okay
um but I think that's not all there is
to it I think another condition that's
important is that you have enough
capacity
that there is a chance that two models
can actually find the same solution. So
we call this a capacity hypothesis is
that bigger models are more likely to
converge to a shared representation than
small models. And the basic idea is
quite simple. It's that if I have two
small models I go back 10 years in time.
Then the two small models like one is a
linear model, one is a quadratic model,
one is like a SVM, one is a random
forest. These things aren't universal.
They they they can only fit certain
types of functions. And the solution
found by one of the models uh cannot be
the same as the solution found by the
other model because the hypothesis space
spaces just don't overlap. Um so let's
say in the ambient space of all possible
functions the best loss is achieved at
this point in the middle here. But if
I'm only searching over small model
hypothesis space then the best I can do
in this model is here that model there.
If I make the models bigger they're
closer to being universal. there's a a
chance that they'll actually overlap and
that they'll overlap on the um the
lowest loss solution in the ambient
space. So as models get bigger um they
overlap more in the set of functions
they can represent and that gives them
the chance of actual convergence. Okay,
you have to have enough capacity for
convergence. Um okay and then uh the
last of these kind of ML 101 type
explanations is the simplicity bias. So
here we have the set of functions that
actually fits the data and solves all
the task. That was that kind of
convergent subspace of the hypothesis
space that I mentioned before. But it
still might be big. This thing is is
technically called the version space.
And the version space can be a very big
object. There can be many different um
networks with different parameters that
equally well explain and fit the data.
But within that in that space of
solutions that fit the data and solve
the tasks, which one do you find? And
here comes the idea of regularization or
what I'm calling simplicity bias that
deep nets are biased to find simple fits
to the data. There's a lot of
interesting papers on this. Um so I
don't have time to talk about all the
details. But we think that simplicity
bias and implicit regularization can
also be helping to explain convergence
that you don't only try to find a
function that fits all the data and data
scales and that becomes a smaller space
but you also have this pressure towards
simple fits and so that constrains you
to an even smaller space. And one of the
interesting results that we and some
others have is that uh actually bigger
networks have stronger simplicity bias.
And so you might actually expect that as
models get bigger uh this this
simplicity um pressure will get even
stronger.
Okay.
Okay. So as we train bigger models with
stronger and better regularizers,
they're going to maybe converge to a
smaller um subspace of solutions.
Uh but what is what's this all going to
converge to? If could we really we
really get this down to just like a
single solution like a single
representation that all networks
converge to and what might that look
like? So I don't know. I think that's a
long way off. Uh but I'm going to
mention one kind of toy mathematical
model in which we can actually show
exactly what that would
be. Um and this is where we really get
to this platonic idea in the title. So
uh the the basic idea for what I think
that we might be converging to is
something like Plato imagined with his
allegory of the cave. So he said that uh
you know this is this is a story that
comes up in machine learning vision all
the time. But what Plato said is uh
imagine that you know we have prisoners
in a cave and their only experience of
the outside world is the shadows on the
cave wall. And it's an allegory because
that's how we behave right. Our only
experience of the the world around me is
the photons bouncing off the shadows
like just the projections of the world
onto my retina. I don't have access to
the real world in any kind of direct
physical sense. I have to infer that
there's a world out there. Okay, so
we're imagining the same situation.
There is we think some you know world
out there Z. Uh and it gets projected by
different observation functions. X is
going to be a camera and Y will be a
caption that describes the image and uh
you could also have a mapping to the
text space via not that camera but via
um somebody just having direct
experience and talking about it. Um and
then if I unimotally train
representations on either images or on
text, well because there's a common
cause, there's a common world out there,
the latent variable Z, uh they should
somehow arrive at both being ultimately
representations of Z. That's the common
cause.
Okay. So how might that happen
mathematically in one concrete scenario?
I think this is just one toy model but
um as a starting point for getting kind
theoretical traction on this thing. U so
we'll imagine that the world consists of
a sequence of discrete events Z and that
these events are sampled from uh some
probability distribution over events Z.
And just like if we want to get a little
philosophical this is what I personally
think of as like the platonic ideal.
These ideal forms is it's just
statistics. just a distribution over
events that index into observations.
It's not necessarily actual physics like
physics is just um something we infer.
We don't have direct access over it.
Okay. But anyway, all all the data is
mediated by observation functions like
cameras and people describing the scene.
Uh and observation functions are
mappings from events to um data X and Y.
And in this world, we're going to model
model co-occurrences. We'll consider
that this is a time series over Z. and
we'll model co-occurring observations.
So at two different adjacent points in
time, uh what was my observation x at
time one and in time two? And we'll try
to model that distribution of
co-occurring
observations. And this is uh roughly how
modern contrastive learning systems work
in computer vision. They try to model
the co-occurrence distribution over
visual uh observations like like two
co-occurring patches in an image or two
co-occurring frames in a video. It's
also something people do in language uh
where they try to learn embeddings that
will uh model the co-occurrence of two
words in the same sentence. So going
back to models like word tobec for
example. Okay. So if you do this uh and
you do contrastive learning with a noise
contrastive estimation objective then
what you can show and what people have
shown is that this uh the solution to
this objective the minimizer of that
objective is the uh co-occurrence
function. It's a pointwise mutual
information function. So it's how often
do the two observations co-occur divided
by the probability that they would
co-occur if they were independently
sampled. Okay. So what this math is
saying is that uh we're going to learn a
representation f that maps data into
vectors. We're going to measure the uh
similarity between two representations.
So this is the inner product that gives
me my kernel and the kernel converges to
embeddings in which similarity in which
the kernel structure is equal to the uh
normalized co- occurrence rate. So in
particular the pointwise mutual
information
function. Okay. So that's that's the
platonic kernel according to this math.
Uh it says that apple and orange will
embed near each other because they
co-occur a lot together in nature in
kitchens and elephants don't co-occur as
often with apples and
oranges. And okay, now here comes the
big assumption of the model because I've
said that this is what uh your kernel
over images looks like. But what about
your kernel over text? So if we assume
that the observation is a bjective
function of the underlying event, so we
don't lose any any information which is
a huge assumption and not true in
reality. Um and we have discrete random
variables. then all the probabilities
kind of carry through the observation
function and the PMI over the
observation observations is equal to the
PMI over the underlying events and
therefore the PMI over images that's
learned by the model is equal to the PMI
over words that's learned by the model
because both of those are equal to the
PMI over events and so it implies that
the language model and the vision model
trained with a NCE contrast of objective
will converge to identical kernels.
Okay, so it's a toy model in which that
will occur. So it just says that the
word apple and the word orange will
embed near each other uh because those
words co-occur in descriptions of
kitchens in the same way as those images
co-occur in images of kitchens.
Okay. So I think this model deviates
from reality in some interesting ways
like we don't have discrete random
variables. We don't have bjective
functions but it's a starting point uh
for understanding what that platonic
kernel that ultimate representation
might look
like. Okay. So I now want to um go into
the last sections of the talk where I'll
mention some counterarguments because
you're probably thinking this sounds
like a little too too farfetched. like
maybe there's some convergence but like
come on it's not going to get to some
platonic kernel. So let's see some
counterarguments. Okay so the I think
the most important counterargument um
and so we talked about this in the
original paper but there's also been
some follow-ups that go into it in more
detail. Uh I think it's an important
point is that um hold on there's got to
be unique information in text that's not
captured in images and vice versa. So
different modalities, how could they
learn the same representation of the
world if they fundamentally measure
independent sources of
information? Okay, so in
vision, you can go and see a solar
eclipse and I think that's just an
ineffable experience. I don't know how
to put that in writing and convey to
somebody that that actual experience.
You have to see it for
yourself. Or in language, there's
abstract concepts
like freedom of speech. How can you have
a visual experience which captures the
same meaning as that abstraction freedom
of
speech? Okay, so these are cases of uh
where you don't have a bjection between
the underlying events, the underlying
platonic world and the observations in
vision or language. So language being
abstracted that means you lose
information or uh you could have a
partial observation like an image
doesn't actually capture the same
information. Okay, so these are places
where the mathematical model um falls
apart and so I think this is a real
limitation to the
analysis. Yet at the same time, some of
our best computer vision systems are
trained to reduce the world to language.
So clip is a state-of-the-art computer
vision system that just tries to
explicitly align images with sentences.
So it's trying to remove all information
about the world other than that which is
contained in sentences. And so somehow
our standard engineering practice in
computer vision is to remove unique
information about vision. Uh maybe
that's a a bad
idea. Uh I'll I'll point out this
interesting follow-up that uh Paul Leong
and others did over at MIT um here uh
which goes into this in more detail. So
uh they're showing that um basically the
platonic hypothesis will hold if you um
have shared information between two
modalities and everything is you know
mathematically bjective in the way that
I was describing but in reality that
might not be the case and you could get
other trends where as you get more
alignment between modalities you might
get worse performance uh of the models
or as performance gets better you might
get less alignment. So that there'll be
an anti-correlation between alignment
and performance on um on certain tasks.
And they say that this is going to
happen when a task requires the unique
signal in a modality that's not shared
with the other modality. And they even
show empirically that on some data sets
you do see that that um as models get
more and more aligned they actually get
worse in
performance. Okay.
Uh but but I do think we there's another
um you know saving grace to this which
is yeah language might not have the same
information as in a photo but maybe a a
paragraph or a book could have the same
information as in a photo. You know an
image is worth a thousand words. And so
we actually ran this this little
experiment where we said let's look at
the alignment between visual embeddings
and language embeddings but now we're
going to increase the length of the text
that we're going to embed. So, we're
going to take captions which are very
long, 30-word captions, and as you
increase the number of words in your
captions, your embeddings of those
captions become more and more aligned
with your embeddings of the the images
those captions describe. So, yeah, I
think maybe in theory if we have really
really descriptive text, then it might
actually capture the same information as
in a visual experience, but if we have
short text, then that's not going to
happen and there'll be a cap to the
alignment that you can
achieve. Okay. Uh the other big
objection uh which I think is important
is that a lot of this convergence might
not be platonic in some ideal sense. It
might be we're converging yes but not
not to reality. We're converging to uh
biases and we're converging to the
internet's view of reality which is not
actual reality and we're converging in
bad ways. And this could be due to bias
in the data. It could be due to
fundamental limitations in the
transformers and the models that we use
today. And it could be sociotechnical
that we all kind of compete on the same
benchmarks and that causes us to
converge but not for a good
reason. Okay. So uh in the last uh few
minutes I'm going to talk about um some
implications and applications. Okay. So
this was all a bit philosophical but
what can we actually do? Can we make
better systems now out of
this? Okay. So I think one important
implication is that you can share data
between modalities. So if the
representation if all roads lead to Rome
right if all different ways of modeling
the world uh lead to the same um you
know ultimate representation then we
should be able to get there through all
these paths and uh share information
between the different paths. So it
should be the the case that we can train
our vision models on language data and
make them do better. We can train our
language models on vision data. We're
going to look at two experiments here.
One is can we train better image
generative models, diffusion models by
aligning them to visual encoders? Uh,
and two, can we train better language
models by aligning them to to vision
models? So now we're running kind of
more causal experiments. We're not just
trying to look at trends, but we're
going to try to actually optimize our
models to be aligned and see what
happens. Okay, so the first one, um, can
we train diffusion models by aligning
them to vision models? Uh, this is not
my own work. This is work from signing
she and others at NYU. And what they
found is that if you do this kernel
alignment, so you take a diffusion model
that generates images from noise and you
take a pre-trained uh visual encoder uh
of the kind that I was like clip or dyno
uh and you simply uh have a additional
loss that says I want my kernel uh
structure to be the same between the two
models. If I want to uh have my
diffusion model uh use the kernel
structure inside my pre-trained vision
model, you'll get a much faster learning
of your image generation. So image
encoding and image decoding, image
generation uh
can benefit each other via this uh
kernel structure. They both have similar
internal
representations. Um okay, here's one
that we did. This is uh Yulu and and Ivy
um have been doing this recently. uh
it'll be at this realign workshop this
in a week or two at iClar uh where they
train a language model to be aligned
with the kernel structure of a vision
model and the question is do you get a
better language model better at modeling
you know predicting the next word doing
language reasoning tasks and so it's
roughly the same idea as on the previous
slide uh the visuals a little different
but we take our language model we train
it to predict the next word but we also
extract its kernel on some layer and
align that kernel with the kernel of a
pre-trained vision model like Dino and
we say does that actually make your
language model get better when you force
it to represent the world more
visually and the answer is yes it it
actually works so uh here is your
baseline language model and if you try
to align it its internal structure the
kernel to dino small you even get a tiny
boost on this like pretty bad vision
model this is like a llama like a big
language model so it's
uh trivial to get a boost and you can
get bigger boost when you align your
language model to bigger dynino models.
Giant Dynino model does better and then
interestingly there's some other models
that do do the best on this
task. Okay, so kernel alignment is not
just a spurious correlation actually
optimizing for it can improve
performance of language modeling.
Um, another implication is that
crossmodal learning between at least
language and vision should be uh
relatively easy because you can use the
kernel as a bridge. So let's say I have
my uh embedding trained on images to map
to an image embedding my my model
trained on text to map uh from uh like a
noise vector to output text. Well then
to learn translation I should just have
to somehow align these representations.
And if the representations measure
distance in the same way, then they're
related by an
isymmetry. They're related by a
transformation that preserves distances.
And that's a very simple kind of
transformation. Um so recently this has
been an old kind of goal of can you do
unpaired translation between images and
text. Uh
and the kind of platonic idea suggests
that it should be relatively easy
because the kernel can be a bridge
between those two domains. And recently
these uh there's an interesting paper
that actually tried this and they found
that okay so if I have a vision model
that has measured distance the same way
as a language model. So the triangle
like the uh these distances are all the
same then it's just a rotation to align
them. It's just an isometric
transformation to align them and they
can optimize to find this like rotation
or it can also have translation. It can
have a few things. Uh they can optimize
to find that transformation that will
align the two modalities without paired
data at all. And it's it works at a
non-trivial level. It doesn't nail the
problem, but they show
non-triv results. So you can translate
between text and image uh to a
non-trivial level with no paired
examples. You just you go to Mars, you
listen to the Martian speak, you look at
the rocks on Mars. No Martian ever
points out that this is the word for
rock and yet you can infer that what the
word for rock is just based on these um
the statistics of the word usage and the
uh visual observations. That's that's
roughly what they're claiming
here. Okay. Um there's some interesting
theory work that Lorenzo uh Rosako and
um and his colleagues have been doing uh
additionally on this idea of you know
under what theoretical conditions can
you actually learn uh to bridge between
modalities uh given that the kernels are
aligned. So you can actually bound the
um ability to stitch between two
different modalities by the kernel
alignment measures that that I've talked
about in this in this talk. Um, so I'm
not going to have time to go into this
one, but just another pointer if you're
interested in a theoretical lens on
this. Um, okay, one last one is I really
love this old problem called the Molyneu
problem. This, uh, philosopher Molyneu
wrote a letter to John Lock and he said,
uh, assume a blind man can tell the
difference between a cube and a sphere
by the way, uh, they feel when he
touches them. If the man were to be
given sight, could he immediately tell
uh which is the sphere and which is the
cube simply by looking at them? So, it's
this scenario. We're doing not touch and
vision, but we're doing vision and
language. If I have a language model
that knows how to understand this text,
and I then give my system a camera, can
I immediately learn to map from the
camera to the um the representation, the
meaning of the text?
And well if the uh representational
structure of the world uh you know is uh
if if if language modeling finds the
same representation as visual modeling
then this should this learning problem
should be relatively easy and if I
already have that representation I
already have that target that the thing
would have converged to it should be I
can learn it quite quickly. Um and but
Vonha and others in BCS have shown that
uh in fact if you do give children uh
sight who have cataracts and are born uh
blind but you give them sight at a
certain age uh they can't understand the
visual world immediately but they can
relatively quickly. It's not like they
have to redevelop uh along the same time
scale as um an infant would under uh uh
from birth. So new modalities can be
efficiently scaffolded onto existing
knowledge because they share similar
representational
structure. Okay. So final implication is
just if there really is some truth to
this platonic idea and there is some
representation that can be characterized
and can unify modalities. It seems like
an important thing. We should seek it
out. We should better characterize it uh
and see how far that goes. So I'll end
there and thanks to the co-authors and
all of you.
Thank you so much, Phillip. So, let me
kick off the Q&amp;A with a couple of
questions. Um, I wonder if you can
elaborate a bit on the metrics you have
used to decide that alignment and um so
uh so in particular did you try a lot of
metrics or or how how do you know that
you got the right one? Yeah.
Um yeah that's a great question. So we
did try a lot of metrics. So I I uh
essentially the metrics are uh different
ways of measuring how similar this
kernel is to that kernel. And I could
just look at like uklidian distance or
something simple. Um the one that we
ended up using for most of our
experiments is based on uh nearest
neighbors. So, it's asking are the
nearest neighbors in embedding space to
an uh are my nearest neighbors of this
image embedded by a vision model
um the same as my nearest neighbors of
the caption of that image embedded by a
language model.
Uh so if I embed a photo of euseity are
the image nearest neighbors eused in the
same way as the text nearest neighbors
or captions about euseity. So that's the
particular metric we used and why did we
use that one? Well we tried a bunch and
this one worked the best. So the way I
would phrase it is that we see
convergence of the kernel structure in
terms of the local neighborhoods. The
local neighborhoods are converging.
Maybe the global layout like there could
be scaling global scales that actually
are not being um converged. But doesn't
this just capture co- occurrence?
Yes, I think it I think that's kind of
that's kind of the um the theoretical
model we get to is that uh yeah um this
if two things co-occur the same way in
two different modalities then these
models will you know that will surface
in both of these models.
Okay. So I have two quick follow-ups and
then I will open uh for uh questions. We
have live a live audience. So we'll take
some questions from the live audience.
Also, if you would like to ask a
question uh on Zoom, please put your um
question your hand up. Um so my my
question is about what do we understand
from aligning uh language with vision.
So um when you in fact this was um in
one of your um most uh your your latest
uh charts. Yeah. So, if you can put that
back up. Um, this is the Yeah, that next
one. Next one. Next one. Yeah. So, um,
doesn't that mean that by connecting
language to uh, uh, to vision, uh, you
are finding some aspects of the physical
world that you're bringing into a
statistical system that otherwise does
not have a uh, predefined understanding
of the physical uh, world. Isn't this
what we're getting from um from this
kind of experiment? Yeah, exactly.
So um language models I think one of the
critiques right now is that maybe they
don't have a lot of you know embodied
experience. They don't they're not
grounded. Um and to some extent they can
learn this from massive data online that
talks about visual experiences, physical
experiences, but maybe it's not perfect.
And I think that might be part of the
idea here that you're injecting
knowledge from another modality uh that
uh is a more sample efficient way of
collecting that kind of data. But have
you tried um to do this alignment with
fantastical images that do not obey the
laws of uh oh yeah of uh physics? Um I
mean if you do it with imageet of course
those are all images taken from the
physical world. It could be interesting
to create a data set of fantastical
images to see what happens. I really
like that idea. We have some other work
on like uh these fantastical random
noise images. Uh this is a collaboration
with Antonio Teralba and others and um
you can train vision models on those and
they learn good visual features. They're
like random fractals and blobby images.
We haven't tried aligning language
models to that kind of data. That would
be really interesting. But let's work on
that. I also have one more quick
question. So the fact that uh we see
alignment uh between language models and
vision models is very interesting to me
that almost suggests that there is a
ceiling to what we can do with these
models. U your comments please. Yeah. Is
there just to suggest there's a ceiling?
I I think this Yeah, there's one
perspective is
um that maybe this is a bit diminishing
to computer vision like oh if vision
models converge to the same thing as
language models then it turns out that
there's these models are not actually
capturing all those like physical
details we thought that they're just
capturing semantics in the end. Um, and
in some sense that might indicate that
yeah, our approaches right now do have a
ceiling. Like the ceiling is the types
of semantics that language is good at
conveying. And um, you could read this
as evidence for that, I would say. Very
interesting. Um, all right. Any
questions from uh, the live audience?
Yes, in the back.
Far. So, if we draw a trend line, how
far are we from 1.0? So I'm these plots
were um some of them are on log scale so
it's a little bit hard
to hard to extrapolate uh linearly. Um
but additionally I think that even on a
log scale they're trailing off. So you
can see over here it starts it looks
like it's starting to trail off. And
then if I show you the the recent thing
from the the paper that came out just a
few weeks ago here again you see the
scale is going to 18 and we're going you
know 10 times bigger model to do that
and like 10 times more data
approximately. So this is all like power
law scaling and um I don't think we'll
get to one according to under these
current trends one will take like the
lifetime of the universe but maybe
there's a way to you know change the
slope of the scaling law. Uh let's take
a question uh from the online audience.
Danny,
hi Phillip. Uh can you hear me? Okay.
Yeah. Excellent. Um thanks for this
talk. Um I wanted to just present a
slightly alternative philosophical view
and ask if it changes what you think the
implications of your findings are. Um so
u the kind of victinsteinian view of
language as you probably know is you
know it it sort of says um uh meaning
uh there is no platonic meaning in some
sense we're all in the cave uh but we
have learned to function together in the
cave because of the way we use language
together and that me meaning arises
through use and I think I think as I
hear your findings, they're equally
consistent, maybe even more consistent
with that view that what you're showing,
I think, is that these models are
learning about what we as human beings
mean with with uh language and images.
Um, and I'm just curious whether that
changes anything if you kind of give up
on the Platonic representation and just
say we're we're kind of in the messy
soup of human language and there's
nothing really below that to find.
Yeah. Yeah. I think that's a that's um I
I completely agree. Uh we were playing
with calling it like the Vickenstein
Plato hypothesis, but felt like that was
a little too too pretentious. Um Right.
So I Yeah. I I think
that yeah, I don't know enough of the
philosophy here to know really what
those two meant. Um but to me this this
um you know underlying reality that
generates things it actually is just a
co-occurrence. It's just a statistical
distribution over events and that can
come in through observation of the
statistics of the of the word usage or
the observations of um reality through a
camera. Uh, and so that might be more
consistent with Vickenstein. Uh, but I I
think that that's the same as an ideal
form in Plato's language. He just
thought of he just phrased it
differently. So there's some
philosophical debate to be had there.
But um yeah, these are all just
metaphors to try to get us at kind of um
the problem. It may have something to do
with why these models are on this point.
We have time for one more quick question
uh from the live audience. Go ahead.
would that imply something about
uh yeah that I I think can this um tell
us anything about adversarial attacks?
Does this mean models are robust? Are
they vulnerable? I think that one is
like a um a pessimistic take would be
well all these models are vulnerable to
the same attack so there's a danger like
it's like we have a homogeneous
population and a virus can come in and
take over and and so if these things are
converging then they might all have the
same vulnerability or maybe the same
bias and this can be dangerous and a
positive take might be uh would these
all get better at actually modeling. So
if language models get better at
modeling the world in a way that is
aligned with vision models and we think
that vision models are more grounded and
actually are are robust in a way that
language might not be then it's kind of
a positive that if I just train on more
language data it'll eventually become
actually grounded in reality. Uh so I
think you can see it in both ways. Hey
one more quick question from online. Uh
your improvement in accuracy is 4%. How
are we going to get a lot of
improvement?
Oh yeah, that's a great question. And I
think you might even be um are you is
the question referring to if the
question is referring to this plot, I'll
say it's actually less than 4%. It's
1.5%. Uh there might be other plots
where we show a bigger improvement. Um
but yeah I I think
that at a certain scale the models have
unimotally become quite powerful and
already quite quite aligned and there
might not be that much more juice to get
by explicitly training them to be
aligned or explicitly sharing data
between the two domains. So how are we
going to get you know a massive
improvement by multimodal machine
learning? uh it might be in the regime
of enough unimodal data you just can't
because you already have saturated uh
but I would also say the jury's out and
maybe people will be clever and come up
with you know better techniques.
Let's thank Phillip once more and thank
you all for joining us. Uh see you next
week uh at the CSAIL Forum with Yoon
Kim. Thank you.