So thanks to all of you attending today
and uh special thanks to CTL the center
for transportation and logistics and our
two researchers Chris Mahia and Camilo
Mora and also to Neta and to Elix Carbon
for today's presentations. Uh keep in
mind that our next uh online event uh
schedule is for for June 11th at noon
which is a start startup exchange demo
day where we have a selection of
startups and uh you can go to our
website
ilp.mmit.edu edu uh member companies of
course reach out to your program
director if you have any questions you
wanted to follow up on any of the
presenters today and uh for those of you
who may not be in the startup exchange
you can certainly look at what's
available there and even uh there is a
the bottom of the page I believe there's
a asky-
uh
asky-enpedu which is just general
questions but uh we're certainly happy
to share uh the knowledge that we're
trying to you know provide to our member
companies and also you know help our MIT
connected startups our faculty etc. So
that will be all for us today. Thank you
so much for joining and we'll see you
next time June 11th. Keep that in mind
at noon for more startups.