Our next we'll have Sandep from Fitch's
lab will uh talk about tissue mosaic
which uses self-supervised
representation learning to um enable
cross sample differential analysis of
spatial transcripttoid data set.
[Applause]
Welcome. Okay. Hi, I'm Sundep. I'm a
graduate student um advised by FA Chen
and Marti. And I'll be talking to you
today about our recent method tissue
mosaic which stands for motif-based
spatial inference across conditions. And
so um this is a model that can learn
representations of spatial transcrytoics
data via self-supervision and then these
representations enable cross sample
differential analysis of ST data.
So just to give an overview of what ESKI
data is, this is a powerful experimental
platform that can measure gene
expression in native tissue context. And
what this allows us to do is start to
study how cell state is um sort of
modulated by a cell's local environment.
And so the way our data is structured is
for a given sample we'll have a list of
spots say 1 to n and for each spot we'll
have its xycoordinate and the measured
gene expression profile at that
spot. And so one sort of common uh
downstream task of interest with gene
expression data is differential gene
expression analysis. Let's say you have
a set of samples from healthy and
diseased tissue. um you can sequence
mRNA and then you can identify genes
that are more highly or more lowly
expressed in your diseased samples and
these are genes that are presumably
implicated in the underlying disease
process. And so we sort of set out to
develop a similar method to enable
differential analysis of our spatial
data. And so more concretely, if you
have a group of samples from control,
another group of samples from case, how
can we start to understand how tissue
structure changes across these two
conditions? And so one issue with sort
of answering this question is that we
need to define what the basic unit of
tissue structure is, the way that genes
are a unit of comparison for bulk RNA
seek data. And so if we could define a
similar unit for our spatial data, we
can then start to compare samples across
multiple conditions. And so in our work,
we call these units tissue motifs. And
our goal is to discover these motifs in
an unbiased way. And we heard some
really cool talks yesterday about the
importance of learning unbiased niche
representations and how these can enable
um differential analysis across control
and case samples. And so in a similar
vein, what we want to enable is a common
representational space that can unify
our entire spatial data set such that if
you extracted units or say patches from
these samples, you can then embed them
in a common latent space and you can
start using that latent space to compare
and contrast tissue structure across
samples and conditions.
And one thing I want to sort of
highlight is the spatial heterogeneity
that's inherent to tissues. So you can
imagine in this latent space we might
have so in this lane space like sort of
a motif as we defined earlier sort of
like a local organizational pattern that
appears. And so you can imagine some
motifs might be shared across control
and case samples whereas other motifs
are sort of enriched for control versus
case samples. And so in our differential
analysis procedure, what we want might
want to do is sort of focus on the
motifs that are over represented in our
case
samples. So this then introduces the
next question of how do we learn these
representations without any underlying
labels for tissue structure. And so to
do that we turn to self-supervised
learning which is a sort of framework
where you can define a proxy supervised
task to train your model. And in solving
that task, the model will learn
meaningful features that can then
generalize to other downstream tasks. So
one um common framework in computer
vision is contrastive learning. And um
just to build some intuition, the idea
here is that let's let you have an image
data set without any class labels, but
you still want to train a classifier.
What you can do is you can take each
image in your data set and then perform
two random augmentations of that image
and then you can instruct your model to
produce representations that are similar
to the two input augmentations then
dissimilar to the other images in your
data set. And so in solving this task,
the model will sort of learn what it
means for a dog to look like a dog and
how a dog might differ from say a chair.
So sort of inspired by the success of
these class of approaches in um on
natural images, we decided to take a
similar approach for our spatial data
and model them as cell type images. And
so what we do is for each spot we take
its XY coordinate and from the gene
expression we can infer the cell type or
cell type proportions at that spot and
then we can rasterize that information
into a multi-dimensional image where
each channel of this image corresponds
to a different cell type. And so on the
right we have an example projection of
what that image would look like for some
mouse testus tissue. And we sort of see
here the emergence of tissue structure
in the form of these
tubules. So once we have these cell type
images we can then apply random
augmentations to them. And so some of
the augmentations that we choose are
ones commonly applied in computer vision
like resize cropping, flipping,
rotations.
But we also designed some augmentations
that are tailored to our spatial
transcrytoics data. So one example of
this is channel or cell type dropout.
And this sort of forces the model to pay
attention to information that's present
in all of the cell types in your data
regardless of how rare or abundant they
might
be. Another augmentation, this straight
cut augmentation, sort of desensitizes
the model to any edge effects you might
introduce by sort of sampling a square
patch at the edge of a circular tissue
sample.
And so um we sort of have a set of 10 or
11 different augmentations and some
other augmentations can desensitize the
model to different technical artifacts
in your data which helps us overcome
some of the batch effects when you want
to integrate multiple samples together.
And in each training pass, we can
extract a patch from this image where
the size of this patch is a user
hyperparameter and sort of reflects your
expected length scale of your tissue.
And we can randomly select a set of
augmentations and then compose them
together to produce two augmented views
of your input
patch. And so then the way we train our
model is like given these two input
augmentations, we can pass them through
two different branches of our network
and then use this cross entropy loss
that sort of encourages the model to
produce representations that are similar
for the two input
augmentations. And so this um
self-supervised learning framework is
called Dino and has sort of shown great
success on natural images.
And once we've trained this model, we
can take this trained ResNet, which is
our feature extractor, and we can tile
our sample, our data set with a large
number of patches, pass each patch
through our train model, and then
produce a set of representations that
then encapsulate the local tissue
structure present in your data set. And
so then we can start to discover tissue
motifs that are present in our data.
And so this approach that we call tissue
mosaic enables several downstream tasks
um including motif query, gene
expression aggression and motif
enrichment. And I'll briefly go through
these um three tasks on two different
spatial data sets. One is of the mouse
testice and has three wild type and
three diabetic samples. And the other is
of the mouse is an um atlas of aging in
the mouse thymus.
So the the first task I'll talk about is
motif query. And the idea here is that
given an input patch, we want to find
other regions in our samples that share
the same motif as this query patch. So
in the testice there are sort of two
main motifs. We have these um RS tubules
in orange and these SPC rich tubules in
red. And so we can see that if we query
the sample with an RSR rich tubule,
we're able to retrieve other RSR rich
tubules where here we're plotting the
similarity of the retrieval
representation to the query
representation as an alpha transparency
mask. So the more opaque the retrieval
is, the more similar it is to the query.
And so what's sort of notable here is
that despite using square patches and no
other segmentation input, the model
starting to able to learn the circular
boundaries of these tubules.
We can do something similar with the SPC
rich tubules. And so we see here with
just a single example of each query
motif, we're able to separate our sample
into the two main motifs present in the
data. And so another task that's very
related to motif query is spatial
clustering. We can discreetly group the
learned laten representations to get
spatial clusters. And so in the mouse
thymus data, the two main anatomical
regions are the cortex in blue and the
medula in orange. And we can see that
when you cluster the tissue mosaic
representations, we get really good
concordance with these ground truth
manual annotations of the same samples.
And then we can quantify this
performance by a normalized mutual
information metric. We can see that we
can outperform um this baseline that's
just based on the cell type compositions
of the patches like treating each patch
as a bag of cells. And we can also
outperform several other existing
representation learning um clustering
methods. So sort of convinced we're able
to learn some meaningful representations
of tissue structure, we then wanted to
connect these representations to the
underlying gene expression through a
downstream regression task. And so here
I have this regression model for those
who are interested, but I won't go into
detail. Um, but just to build some
intuition, what we're trying to do here
is we want to identify genes that sort
of co-vary with their tissue motif
representations and essentially identify
genes that have high mutual information
with tissue structure which we sort of
formalize with this motif information
score.
So if we run this framework on our
testus data, we can get this
distribution of information scores
across genes and we can see that a gene
with a low information score like FAP P9
um we're also doing this conditioned on
cell type. So within a specific cell
type of interest. So conditioned on ES
cells, we're going to see a gene like
FAB P9 has a spatially random
distribution of expression. whereas a
gene like TNP1 that's at the tail end of
this distribution has a much more um
structured distribution of expression.
And so what's cool here is that even
though you can't easily parameterize
this spatial pattern, the model is still
able to pick it up as having high mutual
information with tissue
structure. And so we finally wanted to
return to our sort of motivating task
which was the differential analysis of
spatial data. And this is a task that we
call motif enrichment. And the idea is
here is that given a training set of
motif representations and their
condition labels, we can train a
classifier to predict condition label
from motif representation. And then on a
new held out sample, we can identify
different motifs that are similar to the
motifs in our training set that are
enriched for different conditions in our
training set. And then we can start to
do differential expression analysis at
this motif level rather than the sample
level.
So when we run this framework on our
thymus data um one hallmark of aging in
the thymus are the presence of these
antigen presenting cell aggregates. We
can see the model actually highlights
these aggregated APCs as having high
biological age. And so what this enables
us to do is to then run differential
expression specifically between the aged
APCs and the non-aged APCs. And um one
gene that this analysis highlights is
CD74 which has been previously
implicated malignancies of these
cells. We can also go beyond just um
magnitude of expression and we can also
start to identify genes that are
spatially disregulated across samples
from different conditions. And so we
demonstrate this in the testice where
one hallmark of disease is um the
presence of these disorganized tubules
where you kind of see that the the
periphery cells are orange or red sort
of get mixed with the blue cells on the
interior. And so we can quantify this
disorganization with this ES purity
metric. We can see the model is able to
highlight the impure ES cells as having
um a high diabetic scores which is we
think is a fairly like subtle phenotype
of disorganization in this data.
And what's kind of cool is that we can
then use our regression framework to
define this differential tissue motif
information score. And so this score is
essentially sort of a metric of spatial
disregulation across conditions. And so
in blue in this is a distribution across
genes. And in blue we have when we run
this regression framework just using
sample label. And then in um red we have
this distribution when we run it using
the enriched motifs. So kind of focusing
in on the regions that are enriched in
disease versus healthy samples. And we
can see that a gene like SMCP that's
known to be disregulated in the testice
during diabetes has a small negative
differential score. But by performing
this motif enrichment procedure, we can
detect a much greater effect size for
this gene. And we also developed um a
hypothesis testing framework that can
allow you to assign statistical
significance to these scores. And we
think that this sort of result is kind
of powerful in sort of ident starting to
identify genes and gene programs that
are sort of spatially disregulated
within diseased
samples. And so in conclusion here we
have tissue mosaic, a method that learns
representations of tissue structure and
connects these representations back to
the underlying gene expression. And then
by doing this we're able to enable cross
sample differential analysis. So we can
identify motifs that vary across say
healthy versus disease and then
furthermore detect genes that covary
with these motifs. And so by doing this
we can then see how changes in tissue
organization say due to disease start to
impact transcriptional programs and
start to sort of identify the functional
organization of these
tissues. And so um with that I'd like to
thank my mentors FY and Mr. Um, if you
want to learn more about our work, we
have a pre-print out. Um, we demonstrate
this in a variety of different
technologies and tissues to show the
model readily generalizes to different
data sets. Um, I'd also like to thank my
co-authors, particularly Luca, who made
a lot of contributions to the codebase.
And, um, yeah, I'd be happy to take any
questions.
[Applause]
Great talk. Thanks, Andep. Uh, we have
room for one question before our coffee
break.
So, when you do this dino like thing and
you've got did you come from the same
sample or were you the you know
augmented versions? Are there other
similarities so that you could take
things from different regions of
different images and still have like
maybe an external label that would let
you do that um cross entropy, right? So
you're saying instead of taking the same
like the the the you can contrast
against patches from different images.
Yeah. In the past we've done things
where are you the same fold are you the
same fold and function and of course you
then end up doing a ton of work to
figure out which of those relationships
are reliable enough. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, but have you thought about that so
that it's not just the are you two
augmented versions of the the same
patch, but you're actually two other
things that are substantively similar
across some other annotation. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So, we thought about that a
little bit in the context of a different
loss like Sinclair. So, here with this
dino loss, you kind of um we thought
Okay. So we thought about using the the
frame custom flare where you have like
negative samples you contrast against
and then maybe try to use that to like
overcome batch effects and things like
that by contrasting against maybe like
um patches from like um you can maybe
like specifically only have patches from
the same sample that you contrast
against and maybe then try to overcome
sample specific effects that way. But
actually what we found was that just
this not sort of we didn't need to worry
about doing any of that. just this like
straightforward implementation with
taking the same patch actually worked
pretty well at learning some integrated
embedding space and we think one reason
for that is that we're just modeling
cell types and so those cell types are
shared across all of the data and so
that's kind of how we get get at that.
Okay. So thank you to all the speakers
of this morning's session.
[Applause]