in this video we'll look at three basic
yet important inequalities in
probability markoffs inequality chfs
inequality and the turnoff
bound maros inequality says that if we
are given x a real valued non- negative
random variable then for every positive
number
Lambda we have the following
inequality the probability that X is
bigger is at least Lambda this
probability is no more than the
expectation of x divided by
Lambda one way to interpret this
inequality is that if x is a non-
negative random variable with small
expectation then it is unlikely for X to
be very high okay this is a very
important and useful inequality and let
us prove it the proof is quite
short we
can start with the expectation of X and
rewrite this in the following
way it is at least the
expectation of x times the indicator
function corresponding to when X is at
least Lambda so
this means it is one if x is at least
Lambda and zero
otherwise
okay
now claim next that the expression
inside the expectation is at least
Lambda Time 1 sub X being at least
Lambda because when X is at least Lambda
well X is at least Lambda
otherwise the both sides are zero so
this inequality holds as
well and finally we can pull out the
Lambda and get Lambda times the
probability that X is at least
Lambda Okay so
finishes the proof of Markov
inequality next let's move to chap shfs
inequality the statement of chapy shfs
inequality is that if we're given a real
random variable X then for every
positive real number
Lambda the probability that X deviates
from its mean by at least Lambda times
the square root of the variance of X so
this probability is at most 1/ Lambda
squar let me remind you that the
variance of the random variable X is the
quantity which is defined to be the
expectation of x minus the expectation
of
x^2 and it is also equal to the
expectation of x^2 minus the square of
the expectation of X okay so this is the
variance of the random variable
X yeah so intuitively what chap shf
inequality tells us is that if a random
variable has small variance then it is
unlikely to deviate too far from its
mean let us now prove this inequality
the left hand
side namely this
probability we can rewrite it by
squaring the inequality in this
expression which we doing this gets us
the
following on the left hand side we get x
minus the expectation of X squar on the
right hand side we get Lambda time
Lambda Square time the variance of
X and now let us apply Markov
inequality right so apply what we saw
earlier apply Markov to get the
expectation
of x minus the expectation of x^ 2
divided Lambda 2 variance of x uh but
you see from the definition of variance
the expression circled in red here is
equal to one and therefore the right
hand side is equal to 1 over Lambda squ
okay so that finish the proof of chabby
Chef's
inequality right the third inequality
that we'll look at is known as the
turnoff bound and unlike the earlier
inequalities which is for Fairly General
random variables the turnoff bound is
for a more specific setting namely a sum
of independent random
variables and more specifically let us
look at a case where the random variable
s subn is a sum of N different plusus
1es so each x i is plus one with
probability 1/2 and minus one with
probability 1/2 all chosen independently
at random so one way to interpret SN is
that we walk on the number line take end
steps each step we flip a coin and water
walk either one step to the right or one
step to the left and walk end
steps the conclusion of turnoff bound is
that for every positive Lambda the
probability that s subn is at least
Lambda time Root n is at most this
quantity here which is e to the minus
Lambda 2/ 2
okay so in other words let SN so where
we end up in this walk cannot drift too
far away from the origin and too far
here means some large multiple of
rudm it is worth noting that rot n
here is the variance
of so square root of the variance
of um s
subn so if we simply applied chf's
inequality to S
subn we would arrive at the following
conclusion the CHF tells us that the
probability that SN is least Lambda is
at most 1 over Lambda squar which is
already interesting bound but the
turnoff bound gives a much stronger
conclusion right so the right hand side
decreases very rapidly as a function of
Lambda compared to the chabby chef bound
which decreases only at the rate of 1
over Lambda
squar
okay let us now prove CHF the CHF
Bound for the proof we'll need to
introduce a new idea
and this is the idea of a moment
generating function so let T be a non-
negative real number and let us consider
the moment generating
function in this case given as follows
consider the expectation
of the quantity e to the T Time s subn
right so instead of considering for
example the expectation of S Sub let's
consider the exponential applied to the
random variable okay so this is the
expectation is over the randomness in s
subn well let us now rewrite this
expression by expanding the definition
of s
subn and we get
following and the next step is where we
crucially use the fact that the XIs are
independent random variables which then
allows us to split this expectation as a
product of individual
expectations okay
let's look at one of these terms right
one of these expectation
factors well x sub one is + one with
probability 1/2 and minus one with
probability 1/2 so this Factor here
equals to e to the t plus e to the minus
t / 2 and likewise with all the other
terms so the right hand side equals to
this quantity raised to the power
n okay so this exactly computes the
moment generating function of this
random variable x s
subn let us now try to manipulate this
right hand side expression to make it
easier to work
with so starting
with this expression for now temporarily
dropping the power of n so just look
look at what's inside the
parenthesis we can apply a tailor series
expansion so by Tailor
series okay I'm going to do the step
slightly on the quick side but I
encourage you to work it out yourself if
you can't follow the step basically we
apply the tailor series expansion and
note that the odd index terms all cancel
each other out so again I encourage you
to try out this calculation yourself
we get the
following
okay on the other
hand let's look at the expression e to
the T ^2 over 2 okay so I'll see where
this comes from in a second so this x
should be a t
so let's look at this e to the t^2 /
2 by using tailor expansion over here we
get the
following
X each term is
T to the
2K
over K factorial 2 to the k
okay so this is by writing out the
tailor series expansion for both of
these expressions and finally let's note
that even on a term by term basis one
has this inequality by comparing what
happens in the
denominators okay so I'll leave this as
an exercise but this is not too hard to
see this allows us then
to rewrite the previous line by
by upper bounding this moment generating
function by the expression e to the N
t^2 /
2 okay so that's what we just
deduced finally let us use Markos
inequality to
upper bound the probability that s subn
is at least Lambda time Root n right so
that's what we're trying to
bound as with
earlier well previously we squared both
sides but now let's take an exponential
of both
sides okay so for this step actually I
think I will need T to be strictly
positive for this step to hold so let me
change the hypothesis on
T okay so this is
true and then we can apply
marov to Upper bound this probability by
the expectation of this expression e to
the TS subn which is random and then
divided by the right hand side which is
a constant
okay and earlier we had determinant
upper Bound for the moment generating
function and plugging everything in we
get this following expression e to the n
t ^2 / 2us T Lambda s < TK
n okay so this expression this
inequality is true for every positive
value of t
and the next step then is to use a value
of T that works most in our favor and
one can do this by Trying to minimize
the expression on the right hand
side and you know you can do this and
turns out that the optimal T to set
is Lambda
over root n okay so you can determine
the optimal value of T by taking the
derivative and this is the optimal value
and set T into the
spound gives the desired
conclusion okay so if you set this value
of T into this right hand side Bound you
you will see the right hand side of
turnoff bound popping
out so that's the proof of the turnoff
bound
so the key idea introduced here is the
moment generating function and because
of the independence of the components of
s subm we can factorize the moment
generating function and through some
additional algebraic manipulations
derive the desired bound so all three of
these inequalities are basic and
Powerful techniques in
probability the turnoff Bound in
particular gives an extraordinarily good
bound on the probability that a sum of
independent random variables can deviate
from its expectation and over here
although we only looked at the case when
XI is+ one or minus one each with
probability 1/2 the same proof can be
applied in a more versatile way to other
settings as long as you have a sum of
independent random variables