Welcome to today's uh CSAIL Forum. This is our
platform for uh rigorous intellectual exchanges
that are at the frontiers of computer science
and artificial intelligence. Today I am delighted
to introduce my colleague Yoon Kim who will speak
about efficient and uh expressive architectures
for language modeling. So I'd like to welcome
all of you to be an engaged participant. Please
start by putting your name and your location in
the chat so that we know who is attending and
please put your questions in the chat. At the end
of the presentation we will have an opportunity
to do Q&A with a speaker. And with this I will
pass it over to Yoon. Yoon please take it away.
Thank you for the introductions. Okay, great. I'll
get started. Um, thank you for the introduction,
Daniela. Um, my name is Yoon Kim. I'm very happy
to be here and today I'll be telling you about
some efficient and uh some recent sort of
body of work, not necessarily from my lab,
but from the community on efficient and
expressive architectures for language modeling.
So before getting into the technical details,
I think it's worth stepping back and sort
of like reviewing the current AI uh research
program. And I think the high-level overview
goes something like this. So we have some data
uh some model with learnable parameters and an
optimization objective. Now in the case of
modern large language models, the data is
given by you know without an exaggeration a
civilization's worth of text. Um the model is
given by a transformer architecture we'll talk
about and the um objective is to actually have
the transformer tweak its parameters to give
high likelihood to the training data. And um
this is the maximum likelihood objective. Um and
in some sense in a real sense all you're doing is
compression i.e. maximum likelihood is minimizing
the uh uh code length of your training data using
the model parameters. Um now what is the purpose
of this? Of course um it isn't necessarily that
we want to compress the data itself but the
hope is with the right model um the the model
will be able to capture sort of the underlying
intelligences that produce the data which is given
by sort of external world and then in the case of
language models humans so intelligences sort of
uh deploying and using language that produce the
data and um there's sort of several additions to
this recipe um So um maybe we can think of this
as the language model pre-training stage and once
we have the model we can now have the model uh
execute actions in the world get verifications
generate its own data and then um compress that
using the weighted likelihood objective and you
know I'm being hand wavy here and maybe that's
roughly reinforcement learning and then um once
you have the model you can use it in various
ways and to do useful things and um this is uh
in in modern large language models um sometimes
called test time scaling. So um this is maybe
the current AI recipe and I think the argument uh
the view that I'm going to espouse in this talk is
that this model architecture really is a crucial
ingredient in this modern AI recipe. And as maybe
one evidence of this, I think it's worth looking
back into large language models back in 2007.
So this is a um very well-known paper from
Google and the title of this paper which came
out in 2007 is large language models in machine
translation and if you look at the abstract
uh we see they're actually training pretty good
language models pretty big language models. So
they're training a n-gram based language model
with 300 billion n-grams that's equivalent to
300 billion parameters and they're training this
model on two trillion tokens. So even by today's
standards, these are quite large language models
and the only thing that's different is what the
model is. So in the data just like in today's
language models, we have trillions of words and
the optimization objective uh is the same. It's
the maximum likelihood objective. Of course in in
uh sort of uh uh these lookup table n-grammed
language models, the maximum likelihood objective
is given by counting and dividing n-grams. Whereas
in today's transformers um the optimization
uh objective is solved by um using something
like stochastic gradient descent. Um but it is
pretty remarkable that we basically had the same
recipe from a high level standpoint but due to
the differences in architecture you know I mean in
2007 we had um improvements in machine translation
from large language model but no one was you know
talking about um chat GPT or AGI but applying the
same objective to today's architectures um we're
getting some um very useful systems like ChatGPT
so I think this is maybe one evidence that um
within this AI recipe uh having the architecture
right is is an important component. So today's
language models are based on um largely what's
called a transformer architecture. So how do
transformer based large language models work?
Well, basically language models are next word
prediction systems. So here I'm representing the
language model as a neural network. It gets in a
input text like MIT is located in. It produces an
output piece of text um output word and this
gets fed as input um and the combined input
gets fed into the LLM again to produce uh the next
word. What does this architecture look like? Um so
um this architecture by and large modern LLMs use
the transformer network. And what the transformer
network does at a high level, we'll get into
the low-level details in a in a few slides. Um,
but at a high level, what it does is it gets the
input, it represents each word as a vector. So
deep learning models operated over vector
representations. Um, so it represents each
word as a vector. And then it has what's
called an attention mechanism which uses the
current representation of the word and performs
a pair-wise interaction between all the previous
words um to get a new representation of the
current word and then it uses this representation
to predict the next word and then again you feed
what you've predicted as input. Um and then this
process continues and with this mechanism um
you can sort of produce infinite text given
any context. But the key point uh that's different
from uh previous neural network architectures is
this attention mechanism. Okay. And this is really
the salient difference between transformers and
other types of neural network architectures that
um many people were using like um convolutional
networks or recurrent neural networks and um
to the point where the original paper uh that
introduced a transformer architecture had the
very sort of like uh uh fun title attention
is all you need. So this attention mechanism
is again the key and this paper um which was
released in 2018 has been incredibly influential
and uh the transformer network has been found to
be quite effective for many other domains um other
than just language. Now what are some issues with
transformer networks? So they are very accurate
and they're an important prim so the attention
mechanism is an important primitive for accurate
sequence modeling. Um there are several issues.
One is that transformers have difficulty modeling
long sequences. So I described how at a intuitive
level the attention mechanism is performing
these pair-wise comparisons. And we can see
these pair-wise comparisons if you're doing this
at every time step how it can get incredibly
expensive as the the sequence length grows. And we
do want sequence models. We do want large language
models that can process long sequences, right?
So we want models that can process entire series
of books. And ideally we want models that
can produce uh that can um process sequence
lengths in other domains that can be you know
millions or even hundreds of millions of elements
of long um but attention um is just inefficient
at modeling long sequences because of this
pair-wise pair-wise interaction mechanism. Another
difficulty that uh transformers with attention
have is um they're impoverish with regard to
um being able to model certain phenomena. So
um one uh version of this is state tracking. So
state tracking is um in this case a synthetic task
where um uh one version of this is a synthetic
task where you might have a bunch of boxes like
this and the box has certain states like box one
containing a book, box two containing an apple,
so on and so forth. And then you have a bunch
of permutations of the boxes. So you swap box
one and three, I swap box two and five, so on
and so forth. And at the end you ask where is
the apple? So it turns out um you can show that
this type of state tracking problem i.e. tracking
permutations over uh a number of um number of
states is actually hard from a formal standpoint.
So um from a complexity theory standpoint and
this is un ideal right because these types of
state tracking problems it's quite toy in this
case but there I think um capabilities underlying
these types of state tracking problems are real
world capabilities that we want in our LLMs
um especially when it comes to for example um
having them produce code right so in in in uh
code um you're doing a bunch of variable swaps and
we ideally do want LLMs to be able to track them
um So uh the purpose uh I think what I'll talk
about uh this talk is on some recent developments
uh again from a community of researchers um
that suggest an alternative to transformers
that can maintain the accuracy and scalability
of transformers while being more efficient and
more expressive. Before I get into this um I
think it's worth going into a little bit sort
of technical details about how transformers work.
So transformers um taken a set of vectors um here
denoted from x1 to x5 and produces another set
of vectors um where the set of vectors has been
contextualized against one another. So transformer
is a function that does this. A transformer is
composed of transformer blocks. Um so a transform
modern large language models might have tens
or even hundreds of such transformer blocks.
Each transform block consists of a attention
layer which does these pair-wise comparisons that
I talked about a few slides back followed by a
feed forward layer. Again the real difference of
the transformer architecture versus other types
of architectures is this attention layer and this
is the sort of the portion of the transformer that
we're going to be focusing on uh in this talk.
Um more review uh about how attention works. So
how does this attention mechanism work? Attention
mechanism itself is a uh setto set function which
gets in a vector in this case of length L by um D.
Here L is the sequence length. So here L is five
in this example and D is a hidden state dimension
which in this case is three. So attention takes in
a vector uh set of vectors in this case you can
represent it as a matrix produces another matrix
O. Um what are the computations in attention?
Um first um you use the key query value matrices
uh key query value projections to get the key
query value matrices for each input uh embedding.
And then you use the key query matrix followed
by a mask to get an attention matrix. And this
attention matrix um is an L by L matrix where L is
again the sequence thing. And then um you use this
attention matrix um to get a uh convex combination
of the uh uh value vectors to get the output. And
this is how the attention mechanism works. So this
reduces an output matrix O that is L by D given
an input matrix L by D. And here the learnable
parameters of the attention layer are these WQ,
WK and WV matrices. And then of course this is
just a single layer of attention which and and
this is the layer that I'm going to focus on but
you should think of the other components of the
transformer being there as well. So that we're
going to have feed forward layers. We're going to
have attention layers um elsewhere but we're just
going to be focusing on how some how sort of new
how there are new sort of primitives that might be
able to replace these attention layers. Now what's
good about attention? So um recall uh so when I
explained the attention um nowhere in the sort of
the number of matt moles that I uh mentioned did
I mention the sequence length. So in particular
uh the number of matt moles that you're doing is
independent of sequence length. So certainly the
size of the mat mole is like of course a function
of sequence length but the number of matt moles
that you're doing is independent of sequence
length. And what this means is that attention
computation can be parallelized across time. So
you can compute attention for all time steps with
a single or sort of like in this case a number of
matt moles that is not a function of the sequence
length. And this is great because we know how to
do such mat moles efficiently and and there's an
entire industry of you know um GPUs and TPUs and
other other types of chips for doing this very
efficiently. So this is great because that means
we can um have very hardware efficient training.
Another thing that's good about attention
um and that's different from other types of
sequence models such as convolutional networks
or recurrent neural networks is that attention
um allows for more direct access into previous
elements. And I'm being sort of hand wavy here,
but we can sort of see how for you know this uh
representation to attend to the representation
five steps back there is a direct attention
mechanism uh that enables this. So you know
attention from here to there can you can just
have it assign high weights. Whereas whereas if
one were to sort of have this representation be
aware of the representation five steps back. this
would have to be mediated through these types
of intermediate hidden states in an RNN. So
um and so this uh this is one um sort of modeling
advantage of attention. Cool. And and this is
important because I think these types of the
ability to look back into context that you have is
an important capability that we want in our large
language models. Now what are some things that
are not so good about attention? So even though
uh attention can be parallelized. So again that
means the number of matt moles is independent of
sequence length. The actual comput the complexity
of attention the size of the problem does grow
with sequence length and in particular it grows
quadratically quadratically with sequence length.
And this means that um uh this is this means that
you just cannot apply exact attention to sequence
lengths um you know on the order of tens of
millions. So we've been able to be very clever
about structuring attention computations in a
way so that you could do exact uh attention over
elements uh sequence lengths of you know maybe on
the order of hundreds of thousands or even million
plus. going beyond that is just very difficult
because of this fundamental uh quadratic dependent
on sequence length of um attention. Another
inefficiency comes when it comes to inference.
So how does uh how do transformers work during
inference? We're doing word by word inference
and that means that to produce the next token
um we first have the key query value vectors for
the current token and then you use the current
um query vector with the previous key vectors
to get an attention distribution to get the
output vector and that's fed to the future layer
of the transformers to get the next output y and
this is fed as input and because uh attention
ion requires attending to everything that's
uh occurred in the past. That means during
inference you need to keep around what's called
a key value or a KB cache. And this memory
crucially grows linearly with respect to the
number of elements in the past because you have to
for each time step attend over all previous uh all
previous words. And what this means is that um
as you generate longer and longer sequences um
inference becomes slow um in particular um you're
having to move this KV cache that grows linearly
uh back and forth between on-chip and off-chip
memory which can get very slow because man memory
bandwidth is limited on modern hardware. So these
are some of the inefficiencies of attention and
um as mentioned previously um transformers with
attention without chain of thought have certain
sort of uh uh they're impoverished when it comes
to being able to express uh model certain types
of phenomena. In particular, they're in what's
called um TC0 complexity class. Um and they that
means they they just aren't able to solve
certain types of state tracking problems.
in particular the types of problem um where
I talked about before where you're swapping
where you have let's say permutations over five
boxes and you have to decide um what where the
apple is after a bunch of permutations. Okay. So
um these are maybe some of the things that are
not so good about attention. And again um for
the rest of the talk I'll talk talk about sort
of like a potentially a new primitive that can
maintain these benefits of attention while being
more efficient and expressive. And um I'm going to
argue maybe variance of linear transformers offer
uh a potential solution to uh to these problems
while maintain maintaining some of the benefits
of attention. Now what are linear transformers?
So um linear transformers or linear attention
transformers are a particular type of transformer
um that was proposed a few years ago and it's
quite simple. So it's a much simpler version of
the attention mechanism that we've seen. So in
this soft max the classic attention mechanism
we again have the key query matrix um after
which you apply the softmax to get an attention
distribution that you apply to the value matrix to
get the output. So that's during parallel training
um during inference um the output at time step
t is given by a convex combination of all the
previous value vectors. linear attention tells
us to do something quite simple. So it just tells
us why don't we just remove the soft max. Okay,
so um linear attention looks very much like
softmax attention but we don't have the soft max
here in the parallel form and we don't have this
expon these exponentials and the normalizer in the
recurrent uh version of the uh the equation. Now
from this maybe it's not clear we've done anything
interesting but I'm going to argue that this
actually does um does something quite interesting.
So in particular let's look at um this uh this
equation for obtaining the output at time step t
um during inference. Okay so we have the
output step um at time step t that's now a
linear combination of the previous value vectors.
So it's no longer a convex combination but it's
just a linear combination where the weights are
given by a dotproduct of the current query query
vector and the previous um key vectors. Now
because we no longer have this exponential
um here we can take the query vector for the
current time step outside the summation. And
what this means is now we can represent the inner
summation as a fixed dimensional matrix that's
size d by d. So we're going to call this S here.
And what that means is we can decompose linear
transformers into the following where we have a
matrix S of T that's updated by an outer product
of the current key and value vectors and the
current output is given by applying a query vector
on this hidden state matrix SFT. So what does this
look like um in diagrams? So here we have the key
query value vectors. uh you use the current key
and value vectors to get this matrix SFT and then
you apply the query vector on this value mat on
this SFT matrix to get the output and um what
what's sort of key about this is now um what I've
told you is like linear transformers are basically
um there are an RNN but unlike ordinary RNNs which
have vector valued hidden states like in LSTMs and
grew um linear transformers employ matrix valued
hidden states and what they what this means is
that they inherit the efficiency benefits of RNN's
right so in this case we no longer need to keep
around the key value uh vector for the previous
time steps all that is represented or all of that
is compressed into um this hidden state matrix
SFT and that's all you need to keep around so this
means that we can have as in ordinary RNN's linear
compute and constant memory sequence modeling
Now modern versions of linear transformers uh have
some additional bells and whistles. In particular
um they use a gating matrix G of T or gating
scaler G um that modulates the previous hidden
state um before the current key uh the outer
product of the current key value vectors are
added. And we can sort of think of this make the
analogy to um similar datadent gating mechanisms
and classic LSTMs and GRUs. And it turns out
these gated linear transformers are roughly
um equivalent to modern state space models. So
um there have been a lot of work on a lot of
really nice work on state space models
like mamba and mamba 2 and um it turns
out these are sort of like depending on how
you parameterize these gating matrix matrix
um these are basically the same thing. Okay, so
um these are modern gated linear transformers and
um I I think in so far as their RNNs, I'm going
to argue that maybe this lets us let's lets us get
around some inefficiencies of modern transformers.
In particular, now we have a sequence model
that has linear compute complexity and constant
memory complexity. unlike transformers which have
quadratic compute complexity and linear memory
complexity with respect to sequence length. Now um
how do we actually train this? So because we now
have a linear RNN um we can actually train these
efficiently. I won't get into the details uh but
the basic intuition as follows. So here's a pure
RNN view and in this case um when you're thinking
about training classical LSTMs um it's difficult
to parallelize the computation across sequence
length and that means it's difficult to have
hardware efficient training on modern hardware but
because we have sort of these linear updates or
associated updates um we can now re reparameterize
this RNN as a chunk level RNN and we can we can
perform the computations hidden chunk. So in
particular we can have these chunk level hidden
states and we can propagate the information from
previous chunks and then to get the output um you
can for this chunk let's say the second chunk we
can use the current um chunks query matrix and
interact this with the previous chunk hidden state
um to get the contribution from the previous uh or
the previous history and then we can have sort
of like more classic attention um to and this is
linear attention to get the contribution from the
current chunk and again I won't get into details
but this means that we can parallelize across time
uh we can parallelize linear transformers across
time and in fact um we can now have a subquadratic
parallel algorithm for training that can leverage
the computational resources of modern hardware.
Now what about expressivity? again um linear
transformers um even it turns out even gated
linear transformers or state space models are
still in this complexity class TC0 and therefore
they're unable to model certain types of phenomena
like state tracking over five or more element five
or more states even if the gating function is data
dependent as and um here's a very nice figure
from um paper by W Merrill where they have a
toy version of this problem and they train various
models on this and um as the sequence length grows
we can see how the minimum number of layers to
solve this task grows for a transformer um as
well as state space models like S4 and Mumba now
it turns out nonlinear RNNs shown in blue here can
solve this with a single layer um but nonlinear
RNNs because of the nonlinearities not they're
not parallelizable across sequence length um at
least not as easily which means um it's difficult
to train them efficiently on modern hardware.
But um so in this paper um they give a very
interesting version of a linear transformer with a
sort of a different transition matrix um and they
call this IDS4 where this is a linear RNN a linear
transformer um with a particular parameterization
of a transition matrix and they show that this
theoretically allows the model to go uh beyond
this TC0 complexity class and empirically it is
able to solve this uh synthetic task in a single
layer. Now what does this uh more flexible
transition matrix look like? It basically looks
like follows. So whereas um previously with the
gated linear transformers or state space models,
we had a uh uh sort of an element-wise gating
matrix or the gating scala um now we have a matrix
multiplication um as a transition function. Um
and this matrix is data dependent. Now what does
this matrix look like? Um so there there has been
various works that work with different types of uh
uh these structured map models. Um so there's a a
work called delta where the matrix is given by an
identity plus rank one matrix. Um there are more
there are recent works that propose alternatives
but they roughly look like so identity or diagonal
plus some low rank components and it turns out
sort of empirically um so this uh this paper which
used a product of identity plus rank one matrices
as this um uh transition matrix um it turns
out um this does allow these types of recurrent
models to solve these state tracking tasks much
better than transformers and very interestingly
Um in this recent work uh called RWK7 which
employs a diagonal plus uh sort of different
matrix rank one matrix um they theoretically show
that this type of transition function allows a
model allows a model to um go beyond the TC0
complexity class and and solve an NC1 complete
problem. Um and of course this is contingent upon
sort of um NC1 uh being not equal to TC0 which is
an open problem. Cool. Um, so, um, it turns out we
have now linear transformers with these structured
transition matrices, um, that can go beyond
transformers, at least when it comes to, um, uh,
state tracking. And I'm going to argue like we've
done something quite interesting and and cool with
this class of models. So, in particular, recall
that linear attention and linear transformers,
they were motivated from the perspective of having
better efficiency, right? So that's why we got rid
of the softmax function which made it possible to
reformulate this in RNN. But it turns out if we
sort of massage the um data dependent transition
function a bit more we now get a class of models
um that's still as efficient um but I mean still
more efficient the transformers but have better
expressivity. Now of course um you know nothing's
for free so we lose something. So in particular,
let's look at sort of how these models may
or may not be good with respect to certain
cap capabilities that transformers have. Um so
uh one aspect one way to measure this is called
associative recall. Um and a motivation for this
is like um given by uh looking at natural language
sentences and noticing that when when a model's
processing or modeling sort of natural language
we have like we reuse a lot of sort of let's say
entities or a lot of um words or entities that
occurred in the past. So in this case, Hakuna
mata occurred in the past and it would be nice
to be able to sort of attend or look back into
such context um to produ produce sort of the
next word matana given hakuna for example and um
uh uh this is a paper from Simon Aurora um where
they did very nice analysis where they showed that
a lot of the complexity gap between such RNN or
convolutional models and ordinary transformers is
due to the fact that um for these types of words
where you can predict it if you could look back
exactly into the past um these types of RNN models
and convolutional models are just not as good as
transformers that have this um sort of flexible
attention mechanism to attend over the previous
uh past. Now um it turns out some of the recent
models that I talked about like deltaNet or gated
delta net with these types of structured mat moles
as a transition matrix are better at these types
of associative recall task. So here um this is a
synthetic diagnostic task um again from Shimron
um where the key point is you have an arbitrary
set of key and values and a bunch of queries and
you need to predict the value associated with the
queries and on this synthetic task um certainly
these types of linear RNNs with more flexible
structured transitions do better um but this is
actually a fundamental limitation of recurrent
models. So um one of the fundamental limitations
um that that these types of even like more
flexible models can't get around is the ability
to do recall of arbitrary context and intuitively
this makes sense right so if you have like n bits
of information to actually remember this you can't
compress that into a memory that's constant with
respect to n um and um so I've mentioned how these
types of more flexible linear transformers are
more expressive than transform performers when
it comes to do being able to do straight tracking,
but they're also more impoverished. They're still
impoverished when it comes to do being able to
do arbitrary recall. So, how do we get around
this? Um, I think maybe one non-answer, but that
seems to work well empirically is just use hybrid
models. So, what do I mean by hybrid models?
Well, in so far as these types of transformers,
uh, deep learn uh, you know, deep networks with
multiple layers, you can use u maybe some of these
more efficient layers. um for most of the layers
uh but for a couple of layers you can still make
use of these full soft mackenum mechanism that
allows you to um again do associative recall over
arbitrary context. Now what this means is that
um from a complexity standpoint you still have
a model that requires quadratic compute and linear
memory but because you're not doing this for every
layer um things will still be much more efficient.
Um so um as an example um highlighting the
effectiveness of this strategy um we had some
work where uh we were training not the biggest
models 1.3b models on 100 billion tokens and
we found this hybrid strategy to work really
well. So here we have perplexity evaluation on
some NLP tasks as well as uh uh these types of
recall intensive tasks and what was surprising
was like um uh delta linear transformers. So
these are linear transformers with a particularly
um flexible structured transition matrix. Um they
do well but they don't do as well as transformers
when it comes to these types of recall intensive
tasks. But as soon as you add um these types
uh a couple of global attention layers um
it does better in terms of both perplexity and
retrieval. So this was at a much smaller scale. Um
recent work has shown that um this hybrid strategy
works quite well. So there's a very interesting
paper called Jamba um which uh interled mamba
layers with these types of full attention
layers and it turns out um they performed um
better than sort of just using mumba layers
or just using attention layers. Cool. Um so to
summarize um we've seen how linear transformers
or I've argued linear transformers are
potentially an efficient and expressive
architectural alternative to transformers
but they also still have limitations when
it comes to certain phenomena that we want
that you know capabilities that we want in
our LLMs like associative recall right we do
want models to be able to attend over you know
um code bases uh of you know like hundreds
of thousands of tokens And for that maybe an
appealing middle ground is to still make use of
global attention layers but not at every layer.
Um one thought I have is like when it comes to
really exploring the long range capabilities of
linear transformers. I think maybe language is
not the best domain in which to explore such
architectures because um you know we can do a lot
of things by attending over tens of thousands or
hundreds of thousands of tokens. But when it
comes to modalities like speech and video, I
think the quadratic attention quadratic complexity
of ordinary attention does really play a factor.
And I think maybe those are the domains where
we really want to stretch the we really want to
explore the capabilities of these
RNN like linear transformers. And
um just stepping back I think um when the
transformer architecture was introduced in 2017 18
um in some sense it was great because we now had
this general purpose architecture that could model
lots of different domains well enough and all we
had to do with like was like compute uh scale the
data and the model size and that strategy did
get us um to the current point. Um but I think
there's now you know a lot of exciting work um
coming from various uh groups on you know like
proposing these types of alternative architectures
to transformers and I think this is an exciting
time to do architecture research and with that
I'll end here and take any questions that was
really awesome uh thank you so much um uh Yun uh
we um were excited to see these uh more efficient
models and so let me um start with a few of my
questions. I wonder if you have identified any
tasks uh where the linear transformer alternative
you developed underperforms as compared to
transformers. Yeah. So when it
comes to being able to retrieve
uh things from context like for example um in
the synthetic case you're given arbitrary key
values and then an arbitrary query and you need
to output the value associated with that query.
um these linear transformers still underperform uh
classic transformers. And I think these types of
um recall abilities are capabilities that we
want in real world language models in so far as
they're important for things like processing
code. And these are still sort of like
um you know like capabilities that linear
transformers uh uh don't have or aren't as good
um versus ordinary transformers. And
um I think this is like a theoretical
limitation. Um and intuitively if you have
sort of an arbitrary length context that
you're compressing into a fixed dimensional
vector no matter as long as the vector is
sort of fixed dimensional and not a function
of input size then you can't do arbitrary in
uh unless there's some structure in the uh context
that you give um which motivates these types of
sort of middle ground strategies like hybrid
models. So for the um uh for our industry friends
uh in this session, can you give us an example
of a specific application domain where you would
recommend the use of linear transformers and
a specific application domain where you would
recommend a regular transformer? Yeah. So I I
think modalities where uh the deployment has to
be really fast and the sequence length is really
long. So these are modalities like real-time
speech processing or long video generation. Um
these types of models linear transformers are
quite promising and there has been some exciting
work applying some of these types of models to
speech and video modeling domains. Um and those
I think that's also like very practical in that
you know if you have uh a million frames it's
just very very slow and maybe even impossible
to do full attention over. Now when it comes
to uh language and doing reasoning, I do think
these are domains where I'm being hand wavy here,
but you want to attend and reason over all the
context that you give it. And I think that's why
some of the re uh that's why um especially when
you're doing sort of like processing language,
you you do kind of always want these types of
uh global attention layers somewhere at least.
So uh you mentioned videos and uh other types
of signals. I wonder if you can say something
um about how the language um uh angle of the
of the linear transformer extends to other data
modalities. Yeah. So um I think speech and video
is one natural extension where the sequence
length are just much longer than language.
um other domains like biology I don't know much
but um I get the sense for example DNA can be
in the billions of uh input length and maybe
there are exciting applications to be opened up
um have you tried some of these multimodal
uh applications multimodal we haven't but
there's been uh the community some some
research groups have and um there's been
interesting results applying these models to
these types of other so is the focus was then
on uh speech or on video or or what? Um people
have done uh speech uh video and DNA as well.
All right. So, uh I'm going to ask you a few
more questions and then I will open for broader
discussion with everyone uh in the session. So,
uh let's see. I wonder if you can talk about the
tradeoffs between your method and traditional
transformers in terms of training stability
and other properties like you know maybe
generalization uh out of distribution things
like that. Yeah. So when it comes to training
speed um if the sequence length gets longer
like in this so if each batch is over a sequence
of let's say over 10,000 these models are quite
a bit more efficient than regular attention. Um
now when it comes to maybe like thousand length
sequences 2,000 um the speed benefits uh not
as salient. Um stability-wise, we haven't found
these models to be particularly more difficult
to train um than regular transformers. Although
there are stability, you know, training
stability issues uh associated with training
regular transformers when you get to a certain
size. And what was the second question? Sorry.
Uh so let's see. So uh just the question was
about trade-offs between linear transformers and
uh and transformers uh with respect to stability
and generalization and any other properties
um you might want to highlight. Yeah. And and then
when it comes to generalization, we've actually
um I think some of these hybrid models have been
able to generalize along certain dimensions better
than regular transformers. And we don't really
have a good understanding of why other than
non-answers like um you know maybe these layers
are um capturing different types of phenomena.
So you're sort of having an ensembling effect by
making use of hybrid models. Um now pure linear
transformers versus ordinary ordinary transformers
on language tasks pure linear transformers still
do underperform uh ordinary transformers on just
language only tasks. So um uh let's see please
put your hand up if you'd like to address
your question directly to Yun otherwise I
see that there are a few questions in the
chat but I will come to you um in in just
a second. I do have one last question. Can you
talk about uh what kind of uh performance you
observed for tasks that require spatial
temporal correlations? We haven't um we
haven't investigated those task though we
we are currently investigating applications
of these models to time series data and but we
don't have this is just at so it's ongoing work.
Okay. So I have a few questions in the chat. Uh
let's see. Mike Stonereaker asks if the domain
is structured data say data warehouses do
you think any of this stuff will work well?
Um that's a good question and I think when we say
domain is structured data like data warehouses
um that itself is like still a big class of
uh types of different data but for example if
it's like structured data where an input of
this data is you know very long unstructured
text I think some of these uh methods may
be promising from an efficiency standpoint.
Okay. Um, Mike, do you want to follow
up or should we go to the next question?
Okay, maybe we go to the next question
from Danielle Pace who asks if you have
two clinical nodes and want to extract what
is new in the second one which architecture
regular transformers or linear transformers
would be the best in a sense you are tracking
states. So I wonder if the linear transformers
would be more efficient. Yeah, that's a great
question. And I think maybe from a theoretical
standpoint you might argue um some of these more
expressive linear transformers with particular
you know data dependent structured matrices um
might perform better. I will say from a practical
modeling standpoint um for these types of tasks
you want to use uh existing pre-trained models.
So you don't want to be training these models from
scratch. Um and by and large um these uh existing
pre-trained models still make use of just sort of
global attention layers at every layer which may
change over the few over the next few years but
um in so far as you uh going to be using these
offthe-shelf models I think you'll be restricted
to using um these types of uh global
attention layers. Now there's been an
interesting line of work on whether you can take
a pre-trained softmax attention transformer um
of which there are many you know uh in existence
because every sort of pre-trained LLM is pretty
much using this still global attention layers
and seeing whether you can fine-tune them into
some of these more efficient architectures and
that may be possible but that's very much sort
of ongoing research. Awesome. Okay, Rudong Wu
is asking uh with KV cache for auto reggressive
models the inference complexity remains
empirically closer to Oven within quite a
few tokens do you think state space models
have certain advantages beyond that and
if so where is the boundary yeah so that's a
great question so in so far as you know like
um compute is cheap relative to memory movement
and in so far as deployment is memory bound um the
compute complexity is maybe not the bottleneck um
with uh KV cache until you unless you get to you
know sequence length on the order of millions but
still you are paying a lot for moving the KV cache
back and forth from you know offchip memory to
onchip memory and um these models in so far as
you have a fixed dimensional representation
within entire context um the size of the data
that you're moving back and forth that's
going to be independent of sequence length
and that's going to be pract practically much
faster and you do see practical gains as you
get to sequence lengths, you know, um over a
couple of thousand with these types of models.
Yeah. Which which um which is like a one of the
reasons why these models are attractive for things
like real time speech processing. Now, I don't
see any hands um uh in my uh little icons. Please
put your virtual hand up if you would like
to ask a question directly. In the meantime,
we have a few more questions in the chat. And so,
Sebastian Ersheim is asking, "Have you had a look
into XLSTMs complexitywise? And do you know how
they compare to linear transformers?" Yeah, great
great question. So, XLSTMs make use of these
linear transformer layers. So you can roughly
think of um XLSTMs as having some of these linear
transformer layers the in particular gated linear
transform layers and then having ordinary um
LSTM layers and interle um both um I don't
think there's been a close comparison at scale of
these different types of architectures. One thing
um that's nice about LSTMs is XLSTMs is in so far
as they're still making use of classic LSTMs, they
are able to model have like the expressivity bene
benefits that you get from nonlinear RNNs. Now um
this is good from a model expressivity standpoint
but um bad from a efficient training standpoint
because as soon as you have these nonlinear LSTM
layers then it's very difficult to parallelize
across sequence train uh sequence length um
which is uh crucial for efficient training at
scale. Great. Thank you. Next question from
Jennifer Sunu. Uh, has there been metadata
collection upfront at time of input collection or
metadata assessment coupled with associated recall
mixed into the layers um that have been used
to help increase efficiency and reduce the number
of layers needed. For example, meta data like what
language or subject or common keywords the input
is related to. Yeah, that's a great question.
So in practice when you're using these types of
models to do retrieval um over documents um it
is helpful to um append such metadata about the
document so we can more easily sort of use that
metadata to reason or uh retrieve relevant um
portions. Um I I I'll say there hasn't been like
a study of whether for example um being able to
do this allows you to make use of smaller or
more efficient architectures. But in general
when you're work when you're doing retrieval or
retrieval augmented generation it is helpful to
uh attach such metadata to retrieve documents to
help the model do better in context recall. Great.
Thank you Yun. Okay, next question from Yongsung
Chung. In the experiment of the last few slides,
Young at all 2024, why linear transformer plus
two times soft max layer is even better than
the original transformer at retrieval.
That's a great question and we don't know
why and it's possible like uh a lot of this
is uh maybe this is within standard error
but it is curious that you know like in so
far as transformers are really good at this
associative recall why interle um these just
a couple of them along with these types of
um linear transformer layers does better we don't
have a good answer what how might you investigate
that yeah Yeah. Um I think maybe one is to really
make sure the differences are salient. So um have
uh do this over maybe like a more targeted
synthetic task. Um another thing is I didn't
go into the detail in the talk but you can um the
delta linear transformer that I talked about which
has this structured attention structured
um uh structured map transition matrix.
There's a view of that type of linear transformer
as actually doing um associative recall over a
vector space and this is related to like
um some stuff from the 90s and 80s on like
fast weight programming and um associative
memory from Paul Smelinsky and from that
perspective I think there is something to be
said about these delta transformers having
better inductive biases for associative recall
but still that's surprising that you So that might
that combined with global attention layers which
is actually even more aligned to doing associated
recall um combining both does better that's quite
still surprising. Well maybe we can um we can find
some collaborations to explore these questions.
Okay one more question in the chat uh from Isaac
Sanchez. Do linear transformers or
hybrid models have any implications
for interpretability? Uh that's a great
question. So I'll say like model interpret
model interpretability is hard in general. Um
my sense is these types of linear transformer
or hybrid models make it even more difficult. And
one reason is like with these uh softmax attention
layers although it's not perfect but you could
sort of peer into the attention mechanism and
see the distributions over tokens and maybe try to
um you know like see what's going on. And I think
attention to an extent is a somewhat human
readable uh sort of interpret human readable
output uh of the internal computations of a neural
network and that's because um these models are
normalized uh the attention is normalized to be
distributions. Now in linear transformers you no
longer have that right. So you no longer have
the soft max you no longer have a distribution
over the previous elements. you just have you
know dot products and it's unclear whether we
can interpret them as easily um as we have in
attention. Um now there is some work on getting an
attention matrix out of these sum of more complex
linear transformers and it's possible to do this
and um I I think actually that might be one window
into like why these models are computing different
things versus one transformers but I'll say um
to answer the original question um maybe some
of these linear transformer or hybrid models
are more difficult to interpret than regular
transformers. Awesome. uh Yun, thank you very
much for a very interesting and stimulating
presentation. I'd like to thank all of
you in the in the virtual session for
uh great questions and for very nice engagement
at the end of the talk and uh see you all in
two weeks. Next week we are hosting our industry
partners as part of the CSAIL Annual Meeting. So,
please join us in person for our CSAIL Alliances
Annual Meeting and otherwise see you in two weeks
for the CSAIL Forum. Thank you all for joining
us. Thank you, Yun. Thank you. Bye-bye. Bye.