We've known for the last 400 years about
our nine, well, eight planets in our
solar system. So, how are we now just
finding all of these other planets?
Here's an easy way to think about it.
This light is a star, and I am a
transiting exoplanet. When I pass in
front of the star, you can't see my
features, but you can see my outline,
and that's how you know I'm there. And
that's exactly how the transiting method
works. What scientists do is that they
monitor the brightness of a star over
time. And what they look for are these
tiny dips in the overall light. And that
tells you that there may be a planet
around that star. The transit method
needs planets that orbit their star
quickly so that we can get lots of
transit and get a good signal. It's
amazing that such a simple method can
help us find so many new planets. Just
by looking for dips in brightness, we
might be able to find a plant that can
host life. All we had to know was
exactly how and where to look. For more
MIT moments from MIT Open Learning,
like, subscribe, or