All right. So, thanks very much for uh
inviting me to come and talk to you
folks. Um, so, okay. So, I'm interested
in robots and in particular, I want to
make robots that are completely general
purpose, that are as good as you at
doing everything that you do every day.
So, I want to understand how do we make
general purpose intelligent robots? And
it's really hard. And it's hard because
if you think about it, there's an
enormous amount of variability in the
situations that you might encounter uh
in a in a day or a week or a month. The
state space if you think about it is
huge. Lots of objects, enormous amounts
of space and you might have to really
plan or reason out over a very long time
horizon. So super hard but important
problem. Um the current paradigm in
robot learning is roughly this. uh we
build a bunch of simulators of the
environments we want the robot to work
in. We make a very general purpose
algorithm for learning to behave in
those environments. We make a big
instance of the learning algorithm and a
giant instance of the simulators and we
run for a long time until it achieves
general intelligence.
Okay, so I don't know. So that seems
cool and beautiful. It's a lovely story.
Uh, I think that there's an argument
that maybe evolution did something like
this for you over really a pretty long
time horizon, but me personally, I don't
actually think that that can scale. So,
um, I'm a bit of a contrarian, so I'm
going to tell you a contrarian story.
Okay. So, first of all, I believe in the
external physical world. I don't know
about you, but I do like I'm standing
here on a stage and I think we can take
advantage of that. uh I think that what
we have learned from computer science is
that if you can divide your problem into
substructure and solve sub problems and
use those to solve the whole problem
then things go better and that's true in
reasoning it's true in learning and in
particular that learning at some kind of
moderately deep and causal level how
your actions affect the world state is
really good really powerful and it'll
give us better generalization so my
approach which is to try to engineer
general purpose robots. We start with
builtin fundamental learning and
inference algorithms. We build and
train. We take advantage of all the
awesome offline pre-trained enormous
models. But in the robot's own lifetime,
it learns more about how the world
works. Um, and then it thinks about how
to behave. So that's my maybe contrarian
recipe for making general purpose
rational robots. So, and it may be that
doing this I think it might work better
as an engineering strategy. It might
also make systems that are easier for
humans to understand and it may be more
like the way that humans work which
could be interesting from a scientific
perspective as well.
So, I'm going to talk I had to prune the
talk down. So, although I have 5k ideas
I'll tell you about four of them but um
I'll be h happy to answer questions at
the end. So, the first thing is about
the external physical reality. So, it
used to be that computer vision was
terrible and you could hardly get any
useful information out of computer
vision. But that's really changed. And
what I want to do is talk to you about a
system that we made in our group by
assembling
some existing pre-trained models. And by
now it's out of date and the you know
there's there are better things but I'll
just show you uh some movies. So this
system works from a single RGBD image.
So one image so like the picture of that
scene there. And our goal is to come up
with a 3D model of the world that we can
reason about, that the robot can reason
about interacting with. So it needs to
be segmented. We need to have a guess at
the 3D shapes of objects and so on. And
I just want you to marvel. I mean, I
marvel at this even though I, you know,
kind of participated in making it like
the robot from one view
can. So it the actual signal it gets is
the one that you see rotating there. But
then it can fill it in and build a
pretty decent model of what's going on.
And by having a pretty decent model in
its head of what the world is like, it
can plan and behave much better than it
could if it were really kind of
operating from a a much more superficial
perspective. So there's a a ton to talk
about there, but I just want to say that
that gives me hope and faith that we can
actually understand perceptually what's
going on in the world.
Okay. So now I want to talk about how to
design a rational robot. And I'll talk
about this system a little bit. It's an
older system, but it's uh the the
messages are still good. So first of
all, when people talk about a robot
controller, right, they often talk about
a policy, right? And a policy
fundamentally is a mapping from the
current image or a history of images
into low-level control actions for the
robot. And often we think of what goes
in the box between the image and the
control as one big old neural network.
But I want to think of it as something
different. And so I'm going to make a
box that goes between images and
control. But it's going to go like this.
It's going to first go through a system
like the one I showed you to produce a
kind of mental model that the robot has
of the world that says, "Oh, there's
some objects in the world and the
objects I can estimate their properties.
I can estimate their shape or their mass
or their friction or whatever."
A human gives me a goal. Here it's shown
written in logic, but really what we do
is you can talk to it in natural
language and we can convert it into some
internal representation. We call a
planning algorithm which says okay given
the what I know about the world and
given what the human told me they wanted
I try to come up with a set of actions a
sequence of actions for the robot to
execute. I execute the first one. I see
what happens. I re-evaluate and I either
make a new plan or I continue on the one
I had before. So I'll just show you this
now by example. I go on a Okay. One
thing that's important to know about the
system that I showed you before and
therefore this one is that the objects
don't have to be known in advance. They
could be anything. They they don't have
to be recognizable. They just it's just
stuff on the table.
Okay. So, here's an example where we ask
the robot
uh to put all the objects on the blue
map and uh so it looks at the scene and
from its perspective it can only see the
box. The other ones are oluded by the
box. So, it makes a plan to put what it
thinks are all the objects on the blue
mat. So, it has to take a minute to
think about what to do. And then it
says, "Okay, I will put all the objects
on the blue mat." And then it takes
another look and it says, "Oh, snap.
There are actually other objects." So,
now I have to do something else. But,
okay, but it's smart. Like, it
understands geometry. And so, it can
reason about how to put all the objects
on the blue mat. So, it just moved the
one out of the way and then it put them
all back. Okay. So that's that's like
smart, right? So here's an oh uh here's
another one. We told it put each object
in the bowl of the closest color. It's
never done this problem before. It's
never seen these objects before. It
doesn't always work exactly right, but
you know, it's kind of not terrible. And
it can do this because it understands
the world that it's in.
Uh this one I think is funny. Put all
the objects on the blue mat. I don't
know. Somehow this thing will just come
apart into lots of pieces and it will
eventually put all the pieces on the
blue mat. So, uh, you know, it's a
little maybe frustrating. If the robot
could be frustrated, it's probably
frustrated now, but it'll persist. Okay.
So, and and oh, and and it doesn't
matter what robot you work on, right?
Because once you understand the
kinematics of your robot, you can plan
to do stuff. You don't have to retrain.
There's no learning. Actually, there's
no learning in the system at all except
in the perception, right? So, whatever
it that it just kind of works.
Okay. So that was an argument that said
uh if we know how the world works and if
we have a way of reasoning about how to
behave we can do a lot. So now the
question is that world model that thing
that says how do the how does the world
work? How should we learn that right?
What what and in particular what
representation should we use? So there's
a lot of world models. People talk a lot
about world models and they're often at
this point now these incredible
beautiful world models that'll make a
whole like movie of a thing that you ask
for. So movies are awesome if you want
to look at them, but I would argue that
they're not awesome for reasoning
necessarily. Um, and that we have to
think about learning representations of
the way the world works that let us
learn them efficiently, that let us
learn them incrementally. Right? So, I
don't know, there's probably someone in
this room who's never soldered before. I
could teach them to solder. And in
learning to solder, it wouldn't mess up
their dancing ability, right? Okay. So,
that's really important. You really want
to be able to have a system that that
learns incrementally and kind of in a
compositional way and you want to be
able to reason efficiently from the data
that you have. So, this is too much and
too little I understand to communicate
to you. But roughly what happens is that
we learn these models that are neuros
symbolic. They have some aspects that
are kind of symbolic that talk about
objects that abstract over the objects
and that give structure in the model and
then they have some components that are
neural that describe how you actually
perceive something or how the position
of something will in fact change as I
behave. So we're able to learn these
models that mix discrete and continuous
stuff
and uh we have a strategy about
continual learning which I'm not going
to talk about. Okay. So let's look at
how we can learn these operators. This
is this is learning from demonstration
uh by Nishant. Um and we're not learning
actually what to do here but we're
learning the consequences of some
operations. Right? So we're learning
those causal models. So this is a I
don't know another demonstration. Okay.
Um and the idea is that from some simple
demonstrations a very few simple
demonstrations we can learn these
neurosy symbolic models of how the world
works and then we can generalize to
totally new situations like a situation
where now the actor is this robot. It's
a different table. It's different stuff.
But because it's operating at a suitable
kind of symbolic level of abstraction,
it can generalize from what it saw to
really a much different circumstance.
Um, the details of how we do this I'm
not going to talk about, but let me show
you another demonstration. So, six
demonstrations of how this world works.
The robot comes in and its job is to
let's see it's to put the coke can in
the recycling to have the table cleaned
off and to have the eraser in the bin.
So it comes in and it kind of looks
around and it'll make a plan
if I advance the movie.
Okay.
Okay. Yeah. All right. So that was that
was the goal. Okay. Okay. So, it comes
in, looks around, picks up the can, puts
it in the bin. That's good. It needs to
erase the table, but it also needs to
have the eraser in the bin. But it's
smart enough to know that even though
the eraser is in the bin, uh Oh, yeah.
Um, it has to has to dump it out. Uh,
pick up the eraser, go over, it'll erase
the table. Yay. And put the eraser back
in the bin.
Um, and if you take this much data and
try to use some other existing model,
uh, you know, this is a a a a vision
language model trying to do imitation
learning. Um,
it it it okay, I don't know. It picked
up the trash can and it put it back
down. And then it tried to get the Coke
can, but it didn't get it. Then it tried
to do this. And then it says, "Oh, I
have to erase the table." Okay, good.
All right. So, we shouldn't really make
fun of that. But um uh but this applies
in surprising ways. Like Nishant, the
student said, "Can I get a juicer? I
want to train the robot to do juicing."
Like, okay. Uh so, you know, he does
demonstrations of putting a fruit in the
top of the juicer and uh the juicer has
to has these cups under the spigots. The
juice comes out one side and the pulp
comes out a different side. So he does
this demo and we learned from the
demonstration that he does an
abstraction of how the world works. It's
not perfect, but it roughly says the
containers need to be empty and they
need to be in an appropriate place and
the lid needs to be closed and then if
you push the juice button the you'll get
juice in your cup. And we can then apply
it in a in a new situation. Right? So
this is a different place, different
cups. It is the same juicer. uh and that
same uh strategy of reasoning given the
learn model lets it perform this problem
in a really completely different
situation.
Okay. So uh I have talked about how
right how we can learn models of how the
world works and how we can compose those
models really to abstract and to solve
totally new problems. Um, one thing that
I'm not going to talk about in detail,
but I'll just say a word about is that
learning can make planning better. So, a
lot of people are worried about planning
as a thing that you would have inside
the robot or inside your head, but
you're all used to the phenomenon that
uh if you do something repeatedly at the
beginning, you have to think about it.
Like, you probably had to think about
which way to turn the turn signal in
your car at the beginning, but now it's
just autonomous, right? You just do it.
And so a lot of our work also focuses on
how you can take a system that once it
understands how the world works and it
can make plans to behave, it can make it
can learn to make the planning faster by
just by having more experience and by
caching little partial pieces of
information. The kinds of pieces of
information that help you like walk
straight home from work even in those
cases where maybe that's not what you
were intending to do.
Okay. So then another thing I want to
talk about so so learning can make
planning better right because we can
learn to plan more efficiently and
planning can also make learning better.
So I want to talk through this thing in
some a little bit of detail and leave
five minutes for questions. Okay. So uh
so this is a system that a couple of my
students did uh in conjunction with
people at the Boston Dynamics AI
Institute. Um so here are the ideas. The
robot has a set of skills. Let's say we
just delivered the robot to your house.
So it has some set of things that it
knows how to do
and you've asked it to do some things
today, you know, on its first day. So it
knows the kind of distribution of things
that matters to you, but it's not yet
tuned up for your house, right? It maybe
it doesn't know how things work in your
house. It doesn't it's not familiar with
your vacuum cleaner, whatever. And it
has some free time. So, you know, the
people have now gone to sleep. The robot
is free downstairs.
um and it decides to practice.
So it says ah I have to actually
explicitly work on getting better at
doing these things in this place. So it
says to itself okay which of my skills
[snorts] are a important for the jobs
that the person asked me to do and b am
I not very good at and it plans
using what it knows about about how to
operate in the world. uh it plans it
figures out which skills are important
and it sets up the environment so that
it can practice the skill. So uh it also
one more thing for something to practice
if it practices it for a long time and
it really isn't getting anywhere. It'll
also quit practicing because it's like I
don't know I guess I you know I just
can't do this. So I'll talk through now
this in a simple case. Um, so here's a
situation where uh I don't know, there's
some toys on the table. There's a kind
of a chair that's in the way. There's a
bin. There's a kind of a push broom
thing. And the robot is asked to put the
toys in the bin. So, it uses its planner
and it has a reasonably good highle
model of how its actions work. And it's
good at picking things up and putting
them down. So, it comes over here and
moves the chair out of the way. So, that
part's good. And it goes over, it
figures it might as well sweep all the
objects off the table in one go.
So it comes over here, sweeps the
objects,
but you know, it doesn't know its own
strength or the table is more slippery
than it expected. And so now the people
have gone to bed. And in this particular
example, it's just practicing this one
skill. So it's like, man, I have to get
better at the sweeping thing. So I'm
going to try to sweep. Oh no, still not
very good. So, it has inside a little
generative model for some parameters for
how to do the sweeping, and it's going
to tune that generative model up. But
notice that it's setting the world up
all by itself. So, this is totally
autonomous. It ran for like three hours
with only battery changes, but no code,
you know, and so it's just it's like
it's pretty determined. The people
upstairs are having trouble sleeping
because the robots down here are making
a ruckus, but that's okay.
>> [snorts]
>> Um so okay so it practices
uh
all right enough good
um and now you know it's the next
morning uh it it's got the same setup
but now it's this is where we really are
wondering has it figured out what it
needed to figure out and it comes over
here and it goes to do the sweeping and
yay. Okay, so it gets objects in the
bin. So spot learns something overnight.
But what's also important is that the
ability to plan and observe the world
and replan when things don't go the way
you expected is also crucial. And so
here's a situation where uh Nishant the
grelin comes
uh and messes up the robot. Okay, so
it's supposed to get both toys in the
bin. Now the bin is moved, the toy is
moved. It's like, "Okay, that broom
strategy is not going to work here
anymore. I need to pick the thing up,
but it's too tall. It can't reach up on
that shelf." But in previous times, it's
learned how to operate this platform.
So, it goes against the platform and
says, "Cool. I can I can go get the
toy."
Right? So, you know, zero shot, right?
It never used that platform to solve
this problem, but it understands the
effects that it can have on the world
and the way those effects enable it to
do other things. So that's my message is
that we can get really general purpose
robots by building in some fundamental
algorithms
using all the foundation models we can
to build stuff uh in the factory, right?
Take advantage of the perception, take
advantage of language understanding, all
of that. Make sure that we can
continually and compositionally augment
these models. Here I showed you
improving some skills it already had as
well as learning some models of some
skills. We're also working on learning
the skills online at the same time too.
And then reason to pick your actions. So
I think that we can do better, go
farther by using actually all the tools
that we have in the AI toolbox in order
to build these systems. So with that, I
will thank my students and colleagues
and then I have left five minutes for
questions. So thank you. [applause]
So that's a question I don't answer.
Sorry, I have no idea. And everybody in
AI has been in hot water since the
beginning of AI by trying to answer that
question. So
okay, in the first demo, the robot moved
the cup without tipping it. Does it
understand the concept of orientation?
No. So that's a very good question. Um,
in that particular example, I can't
honestly tell you, but it's certainly in
various versions of systems that we
build. Uh, when you're doing motion
planning, right? So motion planning
says, "Oh, you should move from here to
there." Generally speaking, you can add
constraints. We always have the
constraint or almost always have the
constraint that we shouldn't crash into
anything, but we can also add
constraints about the orientation of the
cup. And that's easy and not a problem.
So yeah,
robots making the biggest impact.
That's a really good question. Not the
part of the space that I'm working on,
right? So I'm working not at least not
in not not first, right? Um, I think the
things that are working right now are
cases where the robot needs to do
something a little bit repetitive, but
where there's some variation in the
world, right? If there's no variation in
the world, then we just program the ABV
robot to keep doing the thing. Okay, we
know how to do that. If there's enormous
variation in the world, I don't know,
that's the space that I work in and we
are not ready for prime time. But
there's there are cases where we have to
I don't know maybe use the same coffee
machine over and over again or uh fold
napkins is an example that somebody is
doing right now to good effect. So I
think cases that are more variable than
the factory robots can handle but not
like AGI that's where the impact will
happen and there's probably lots of
opportunities for that.
Choosy Selena. Huh?
Oh, could we do this in communitydriven
practice? That's an interesting
question. Um, I I think so, although
we'd have to solve a bunch of other
problems first, right? Like, uh, but but
I don't think that they're out of the
question, but you know, how does the
robot interact with and negotiate with a
person? And we decide that we're going
to go practice tennis now. Um, so that
seems like it's there's two aspects of
this that are hard. One is just is the
is the negotiation part, which isn't
even robot specific, right? That would
come up in the case that you have agents
that aren't physical. And then there's
some other part, which is being sure
that you're safe to interact in close
proximity with a human. And you know,
that's something that robotics people
worry about to some degree, but it's a
serious problem. And right now lots of
people are making humanoid robots that
are a little not safe to be next to. So
we have to work a lot on that before we
can send robots into people's houses or
or or close to them in the world.
How would I encode non-visible effects?
Oh yeah, absolutely. Oh, wind. Wind is
interesting. Super cool. Okay. So, one
of the things I care deeply about, two
of the things I care deeply about, which
I didn't really show you here, are
memory and uncertainty. Okay. So, uh
we'll start with memory, right? So, the
fact is the majority of robot technology
right now that people are building is
completely stateless. That is to say,
the robot has a view of whatever it's
doing and it maps what it sees at the
moment to what it should do next.
Um but that can't be right. And and the
some of these later robots I showed you
are not like that. They remember things.
You need to remember things about the
space around you. You need to remember,
you know, how to get back to your car.
You need to remember roughly where the
stuff is on the stage so that I don't
when I'm waving my arms, I don't whack
into the podium. All that kind of
remembering. You need to remember things
about the objects, right? Uh where did I
put my car keys? I'm not sure. I could
ask you where your favorite coffee cup
is. You could think about it and tell me
something about that. So there's a bunch
of questions about memory that are
really underststudied I think and that
is that are very important. Um but wind
is pretty interesting because for
instance you can't see wind but you can
see wind's effects right so if you have
memory and observation you could say huh
I put my empty paper cup down over here
and now it's over there and if I have a
causal model for instance of of what
wind does I might be able to infer that
it's windy and I might be able to infer
furthermore that if I put another I
shouldn't maybe put another empty cup
down because it's going to blow away. So
this is a good example where reasoning
can help you estimate physical
properties of the world or of your
objects, right? It could be that I think
um you know that that that remote over
there uh I could pick it up but then it
turns out it's velcroed to the table.
All right, I can't see that but as a
result of taking an action I can update
my belief. um uncertainty I think is
also important and a thing that we study
a lot right so in our actual
implementations of things we have not
maybe a single estimate of the shape of
an object but a a you could think of it
almost as a distributional estimate we
we say well it's at least this big but
it might be that big and we can take
that information into account in our
planning and in particular we can reason
that the robot should go gather more
information just like you saw this very
last robot reasoning that it should go
gather more information. So knowing what
you don't know is critical
so that you can use your resources to go
gather information either about how to
do something or about the state of the
world.
How can a corporation run the shown
experiment and apply the robot to
production and operation? Oh, okay.
Well, okay. So, you know, we did this
once in a lab. Um the question is
for production and operation
would you want the robot to be doing
that kind of experimentation. So I think
you really have to think a lot about the
application situation that you're going
into. If you know a lot about the world,
if you know a lot about the the
distribution of problems that the
robot's going to face and it's not too
highly variable, then you could train it
a lot offline, right? You could train it
in the in the in the factory, right?
Right. I mean, you before so before
putting it out in the world, they could
you could just try to to train it up a
lot, but to get it to actually maybe
practice its own stuff and set things
up, uh, I think you would only do that
when you were in the world where you
couldn't anticipate in advance very much
about what was going on. So, uh, what
capabilities would you need? You would
need better perception than we have. You
would need probably some more robust
controllers and so on. But I think it's
not out of the question that we could do
that. Yeah.
Can the representation layer encode
community level constraints? Oh, so the
robot's not negotiating with a person,
but negotiating with a distri How do you
I don't know how you negotiate with a
distribution.
I've never done that. I mean, uh I guess
maybe that's what I'm doing right now.
You guys are represent a distribution of
the world and I'm negotiating with you
about I don't know. Um, so I'm not I'm
not exactly sure how to do that. I'm
sorry. I think I'm gonna have to pass on
that one. Okay. And it looks like we are
done. Okay. So, thanks very much.