Uh last time we talked about the picard
uh lindelof theorem.
And so this theorem is about uh
solutions uh to
to ODEs.
And so specifically it's it's asking
that so you have a function uh f
and a function g
and uh f here is is is differentiable
and the derivative of of f as well as g
are continuous.
And then the problem is that you're
looking for solutions. So you want a
solution. So looking
for a solution
y to the OD
where the and the OD is that the
derivative
should be equal to f of y.
So at some point uh x
uh the derivative of y should be equal
to f of y of x plus g of x
and uh you are looking for that uh that
this function that y of zero say is
equal to a. Okay. So this is what's
called the initial condition,
[Applause]
right? And this is so the this is equal
to that.
And so in order to uh so we want ex you
uh existence. So want
existence
and uniqueness.
So existence just means that there is a
solution for a given a there is a
solution. Uniqueness means that if you
have two solutions
uh to this uh od then they will have to
coincide.
And so uh we uh the way we were setting
it up was that we were using so using
the contracting mapping theorem.
So the contracting mapping theorem is
the following that if you take a metric
space
X and this metric space is so X comma D
is a metric space is a cushy
complete
uh metric space
uh then a contracting map. So a
contracting map
um is a map
t from this metric space into itself.
So that um um and a constant
C strictly less than one. So that if you
measure the distance between the images,
the images are squeezed together. So
this means that the the distance between
the images is this constant that is
strictly less than one times the
distance between x and y. So this is a
contracting map.
And the contracting mapping theorem say.
[Applause]
So the contracting mapping theorem uh is
is the following
that uh there exist if you have a cushy
complete metric space and you have a
contracting map like this then uh t
has
a unique
fix point
and remember that a fixed point. So a
fixed point
this is a x in this space so that t
leaves it invariant.
Okay.
And so we proved this we proved the
contracting mapping theorem last time.
Now
how were we going to use this for this
OD?
So we define so if if um if I here is an
interval
containing
containing uh
a zero. Then we defined uh
n u is a function. So n u and sorry y is
a continuous function.
[Applause]
Then we defined t of y. So this is a
continuous function on on the interval
on i.
Then we defined a another continuous
function on the same interval as follow
that the
t of y. So this is going to be a
continuous function.
So in in x
this thing here is this is a
because we want it to have value at zero
a and then we're integrating from zero
to x of f
of uh y of s
plus g of s
ds Right.
And so this
so this here gives you a map from t
gives you a map from the continuous
function on this interval into the
continuous function on the interval.
And it also has the property that if you
take a function
and you evaluate it at zero then you get
a
okay. And now we observe that in fact
this the image here
the image is if you define when you
define it like this by the fundamental
theorem of calculus this function here
is differentiable.
So this function is so it actually takes
so t actually takes
the space of continuous functions
into the space of functions that are not
just continuous but actually
differentiable
and even the derivative is continuous
and the ones that are
um so this here is a space of functions.
So this is functions
that are um that are where where the
functions y so that y prime exist
and is continuous.
Okay.
So
right and so now what we saw last time
was that by the fundamental theorem of
calculus
of calculus.
Um
the derivative
Right? So by the fundamental therm
calculus the derivative of this function
if you take y and you take t of it this
is now a function and it's
differentiable and the derivative is f
of y.
So at x it's f of y of x plus g of x.
And so this means that if so if
y
is a fixed point
for the map t. So if it's a fixed point,
this just means that t of y is equal to
y. Well then
then this thing here is the derivative
of y. So then it means that y here
solves the
right. We have already checked that the
initial value we did that uh somewhere
here we already checked that the initial
value is what it should be and if it's a
fixed point then the derivative is also
what it should be. Right?
Okay. So we want to find a fixed point
and so what we did last time was that we
saw that if we if we restrict the
interval.
So last time
what we proved is that if we restrict
the interval. So last time we showed
so we set
m here equal to a absolute value of a +
2.
And then we saw that there exist a delta
zero
at delta zero greater than zero. So that
such that
if you restrict to the interval if
you're looking at the interval of
continuous function so the interval of
continuous function on this little
interval.
So this is a interval around zero and
you're looking at this map.
Then this map here well first of all we
already know that it takes this the
space of continuous function into the
space of continuous function. But we
have something more that we have that if
you're looking at the subspace of this
which is a space of functions y that are
here
and you also require that the norm here
is lesser equal to m.
Then takes
this space here into itself. Right? This
is this lema that we proved last time,
right? And and so okay.
So so this this space here, right? You
can think about this space here as we
did last time as then we defined we
defined
we define
uh capital R equal to
uh no actually so we we defined uh we
looked at the balls I guess just on on
this so we looked at the ball of
freighers capital n
in in in this around the zero function.
So this thing here is the closed ball
in the space of continuous function with
the metric that we've been using and
this set here we can think about if we
want as this set. Okay.
Okay. So now what we have is so we have
so the setup now is that we want to find
a fixed point for this map T right we
have a space that we want to look at and
the space is again now we're going to
think about so just to so this is the
space we're looking at but this is what
we before have denoted like the ball in
this metric space it's a centered at the
function function that is constant zero
and this is the radius right
and so I'm I'm now looking at this
this map so we have now shown that it
take this metric ball into itself okay
and I want to find a fixed point want to
find a fix
fixed point
of t.
Okay. So I need to I need to show So we
want to show
that T
is a contracting map,
right? Because if it is a contracting
map, then we already know that if you
take a closed interval like this
and you equip it with the usual distance
that we have, this here is this here is
cushy complete,
right? But now if you take a cushy
complete space and you're taking a
closed subset and this here is a closed
subset then this here is also cushy
complete this here is also
okay. So if we could prove that t from
this space into itself is a contracting
map. So it means that the existence C
strictly less than one. Then we would
have a fixed point and we would have a
solution to the OD. Right? The thing is
that this is not quite going to do it.
It's not quite a contracting map,
but so so we will need so for it
to be
a contracting map.
We need to restrict
the interval
further.
Okay. So by that I mean that we so we
need to find we need to
we need a delta to be
we need to show that there's some delta
it will actually be less than so we need
to show that there's some delta that is
smaller than this delta zero and so that
if you restrict to this space here now
it's a continuous function I won't
define the I won't I will denote the
ball by the same but this here is
actually a ball in a different metric
space because this is now a ball in the
continuous functions on this smaller
interval.
Okay, but it's for the same radius.
Okay, so if we restrict the map to this
space here then on this it is a
contracting map. Okay. So we need to cut
down the interval. Uh
okay. So now how do we do that? So
so we need a contracting property again.
And so suppose you take two functions.
These are continuous maps
on some interval say from
right here again delta is now that's the
delta we're looking for and it would be
smaller than delta zero so since it's
smaller than delta zero we already know
that t that so we have two maps like
this they are both supposed to be in the
ball so this means that this thing here
is less than m and we know we have
already proven just because delta is
less than delta zero that t of this
function here
has norm less or equal to m. Okay. So,
but now let's look at the difference.
So, t of y1
uh of x minus t of y2
of x,
right? And then we're interested in the
norm here.
And I and now x here is in this smaller
interval.
Okay. So now let's just write down what
the map is. So the map here is the
integral. So it's a sorry it's a plus
the integral from zero to x of f of y1
s
plus g of s
d s
minus
a + the integral from zero to x of f of
y 2 s + G of S
DS, right?
And now you see that the A's cancel,
right? The A's here cancel
and the G of S that those also cancel
out, right? So you left with that this
thing here is the absolute value of the
integral from 0 to x of f of um y1 of s
minus uh um f of y2
of s
ds.
Now
we
So last time
when we proved that at the map
He takes this ball into this ball we
used we defined. So let me just define
that again. We defined L1
and N1 was the the maximum
of actually uh
uh
um
I don't remember whether it was called
L1. Let me just call it L uh to not call
it some. So uh L here is the maximum of
FP prime
um of of offset
where set here
has no less or equal to M. Okay.
So this is so f prime exists and is
continuous. So on this interval here it
has a maximum. Okay. So it's a nice
finite number. And so now we use the so
by the mean value theorem
the mean value theorem.
By the mean value theorem, we have that
f of set one
minus f of set 2. As long as set one and
set two
are uh are in the interval from minus m
to m. Then we have that this difference
here is equal to the derivative in some
intermediate point set sigma
s I guess s times the difference between
the two set one minus set two. So we
have this right this is the mean math
theorem
and so we have that uh therefore we have
that the norm here of the difference
is bounded by this here when we take the
absolute value of this we're getting the
absolute value. So this here is is equal
to the absolute value of frime sigma
time z 1 minus z 2.
This thing here
because these two are in this interval
this is bounded by by capital L. So
you're getting this.
And so now if you use this fact here
[Applause]
and you use this on this. So this thing
here is less or equal to the integral
from zero to x and I can take the
absolute value in under the integration
sign. So I get f of y1
s minus
uh f of y2
s
ds right
and so now I can continue this string so
I have what I'm interested in is g of y1
at x minus g of y2
of x and I'm interested in the abs bound
for the absolute value and I have that
this is less or equal to the integral
from 0 to x of f of y1
s plus f of y 2
s
ds
and now I know that this interval here
right x is supposed to lie in this
interval here so this means is that that
this the length of this interval from
zero to is at most delta. So delta and
then I can take the maximum of this
or I can take the uh that's right I can
take the the maximum of this but you see
that this thing here is bounded by so
this is the maximum is the maximum
and if I use this inequality here it's
bounded by L and then it's applied this
here you should think about as set one
and this here for each x you can s you
can think about this as set one and set
two and so you're getting this thing
here times y1
s - y 2
s and here s will now lie in the
interval
um
in this interval here
oops
Right? And so now you see that this is
just a constant. So this is equal to
delta L. And then this maximum
S lesser equal to delta
Y1
minus Y2
like this. Right? This is evaluated in
S. But I wouldn't I don't write that.
Okay? And this thing here. But this is
just delta L. This maximum here is just
the distance between this function and
that function. That's how we define this
distance. Right?
And so you see that this right hand side
is now holds for all x. So this means
that we have that the maximum of this
thing here over x where x is in the
interval between zero and delta. So this
means that we have that the distance
between t of y1
and t of y2.
This thing here is equal to the maximum.
This is how we define that distance
after all.
Um and then it's of this thing here
sorry uh x
minus t of y 2
in x
right so we have that this and this
inequality say that it's less or equal
to
delta uh L D Y1 comma Y2
and so you see that now if you so L here
was just a fixed constant right if I now
set delta just to make sure that there's
no problem I'm setting delta equal to 1
/ 2 L I don't really need the one but I
I I'll just do it like this so I don't
have zero in the denominator if I choose
the delta to be equal to this. Right?
Well, then you see that this thing here
the the inner product of these two is
less or the the product of these two is
less than a half. So this is less or
equal to I can just place it by a half
like that. Right?
And so you see this is exactly what it
means to be a contracting mapping. In
fact, it's a contracting mapping which
is pretty nice
that the constant it's not just strictly
some constant strictly less than one but
it's actually a half right. So it's a
contracting mapping theorem a
contracting map and so now by the
contracting mapping theorem we have a
fixed point. Okay.
So this solve the OD. Okay. And it do
does more than that because a
contracting mapping theorem says that it
has a unique
uh unique fix point. Right? So this
means that and and if you have a
solution to this, right? If you have a
solution to this, then we saw last time
that if it is a solution, then it is a
fixed point, right?
Okay. So now we almost have existence
and uniqueness.
Uh let me explain what is missing to the
existence of uniqueness.
So for that
let me
backtrack a little bit and talk about
something about metric spaces.
bases specifically uh about connected
matrix bases.
Okay. So suppose you have a metric space
then we say
that
It is connected
if um if x here is the only subset
only subset. So, so the whole set itself
is the only subset
of of X that is
is both open and closed.
Right? Remember that if you take a
metric space then the sorry if
if X and sorry and and the empty set are
the only
uh subset of X that are both open and
closed. Right? Remember that if you take
a metric space and if you take the whole
set or the empty set, those are all
they're both always closed and open,
right? And so it's connected if those
are the only two subsets that are at the
same time open and closed. Okay?
And so now
we have that we have the following
we have the following lema
or theorem just call it theorem
that if you take a interval here with a
usual metric here so this is so I here
is a interval
then uh the theorem is that that that
uh this metric space here so is
connected.
Okay. So let's try to prove that.
So I take now a subset
here uh that is
is both open
open and closed.
And we want to show
want to show
that
if a here is non- empty
then it implies that a
is is everything. Right? So we're
assuming that it's non- empty and then
we should apply uh to try to prove that
a is everything.
So we let
x0 be an element in a right but right
we're assuming it's not empty so we can
let x0 be an element in a
and now I want to define
um I want to
I want to so I have here I have here my
interval this is my interval I
have here x0
and I take uh and I'm looking at the the
y
uh in
in a
so that um
that if you take everything
uh so that so y is an a and I'm going to
look at y in a with
y bigger equal to x0 and I'm going to
look at the y so that that this whole
interval here from x0 to y
is contained in a
so I'm defining so
so define
as subset here
B
of of I
so that uh it's the y this subset b is
the y in a with a property that it is
that y here is big or equal to x0 and
and you have
And this interval here
is contained in a
okay
and now I want to show that so let's say
let's say for the sake of argument let
me assume
that this interval is a closed interval
like this it works equally well the
argument with obvious modification
work each equally well if it's open or
half open uh interval.
Okay. So I take some y here and I have
so I have a y
and I and y is so it's a set so that
this whole interval is contained in a
okay
and what I want to show is so want to
show
that y is in a And this is the first
thing I want to show. One is that y is
in a
and then I want the second thing I want
to show is that y
is equal to b.
You see if I had proven both of these
property right then it would be that so
then um then
um it would mean that everything here
would be in a and including this last
point right and so this means that we
have this entire interval is in a is in
I sorry and then likewise we could argue
on the other side Okay.
So now how do we prove this? So
well the first thing is that if if um
if we take so if we set
sorry this is no sorry but that's this
here should have been
this here should have been y zero and
this should have been the soup
of y in Okay.
So these guys
and then this here and we want to prove
that this thing here is in in a
and uh and the second thing is we want
to prove that this soup is actually
equal to B. Okay, that's what we want to
prove.
So the soup of these well if you have if
y z is a soup of elements then you have
a sequence. So here you have y z and
this means that you have a sequence of
elements
which are then in elements in the set B.
This is soup of B.
Mine is the same as soup of B. Sorry,
soup of B.
I write like this.
So I take this set and these are the Y
so that this entire interval is
contained in a right and then I take the
soup of this set and I want to prove
that this soup is in A. And then I want
to prove that in fact the soup is B.
Okay.
So that it's a soup of of such
elements in capital B means that there
exists a sequence
of elements
in B.
So, so that y here y0
is the soup of b. This here implies that
there exist a sequence y
and these yn
are in a and you have that
x0
y
is contained in a and and then you have
that these guys converge to y z.
Right? This is what you get from that is
a soup. Right? These two things are that
the elements
are in that these elements. So this here
is just that's the y in on b.
Okay.
So now what you have so this here means
so here I have x0
here I have y z and I have these uh
these elements
y in
and they are in particular they are in a
okay but a is closed right since a is
closed since
y is in a
and
Y in and a is closed
is a closed
is a closed subset.
This means that that the limit here the
limit y z which is the limit this here
must also be in a right.
Okay. So we have proven the first
property right
we proven that that right so well so
we've proven that y0 is in a but now you
see that we have that for each of the y
in we have that this interval here lie
in a right and they converge to this so
it means that if you take anything to
the left
of y0. Well, then eventually there's
some y in to the right of that and so
this whole interval is in a right. So
you see that this it now means that not
only is y z in a but y z is really in
the set b.
Okay,
this here only used that A was closed,
right?
So now we need to use that A is open,
[Applause]
So now
suppose we take a element
suppose. So now here we have x0
we have here b and we want to show that
this y0 we define to be the soup of this
set capital b. We want to prove that
this thing here is in fact y zero.
Right?
Suppose not suppose that suppose not. So
suppose that you have here strictly
between these two this here is y z
now we already know that y0
is in a. This is what we proved here.
Right?
So but since since
um uh a here is open
there exist some tiny little interval
there exist
some interval here
around this y z. So if you take y z and
you subtract this epsilon
so there exists some epsilon greater
than zero. So that if you're looking at
this tiny little interval centered at y
z
then this here is contained in a. This
is just because a was open right.
But this means that that now you have
that. So this here is you assume this is
y z. So you have that this thing here
lie in the set capital A and this here I
guarantee you that you can actually go a
little bit past it right that even if
you go a little bit past it if you go a
little bit past it here then these are
still in A right so this means that this
could not be the soup right so therefore
this point here had to be B right it had
to be the final point.
Okay, so this proved these two property,
right? And so once you have these two
property, you have that the interval is
connected, right? That the only non-enty
subset of the interval that is both open
and closed is itself. Okay.
Now why is this related to what we want?
So this is just so we have
suppose you take two functions.
So why is this related to the uniqueness
for the OD?
So this is the following lema.
Suppose you have a interval. So this is
a interval
in R and suppose you have two functions
U1 and U2
they're functions on the interval
and they are both continuous
and then assume that for some assume
that
for some X0 0
in the interval
uh u 1 of x0 is equal to u2 of x0. So
they coincide in one point.
And assume you have a second condition.
And the second condition is
that if
uh if u
uh of u1 of x is equal to u2
of x then there exist
there exist
a neighborhood so a epsilon
where this is allowed. not to depend on
x.
So that uh u 1 is equal to u2 in not
just at x but actually uh on this little
interval x minus epsilon x + epsilon.
Okay. So you have these two properties.
So you have two continuous functions on
an interval. They agree at one point and
if they agree at any point in this
interval then they agree on a little
neighborhood of that point. Okay. But
the neighborhood may depend on the
point. Okay. And then the statement is
so the claim is that
that U1
is actually equal to U2 everywhere.
in in the interval where they defined.
Okay, that's a claim. Okay. And so now
you see that if you take
if you're looking at so the proof of
this is
that suppose so proof
suppose you define a function
uh and this function here is u1 of x
minus u2 of x. If you define it like
this, u1 and u2 are continuous. So f
here is continuous.
You also have that f of x0. Well, this
is u1 of x0 minus u2 of x0.
And these two function coincided at x0.
So this is zero.
You also have that if f ofx
so if f of x is equal to zero.
Well
right now then then you have by this
second property here this property here.
So if f is zero this is just meaning
that the two function coincided at that
x just means that there exist they exist
a delta
epsilon sorry epsilon greater than zero
such that
uh f
um of um of y is equal to zero in this
little
interval around
X and so you have that
and now I claim that so now the claim is
that the zero set so the set where the
function f is zero this is both open and
closed.
So the claim here is
that that the set
u capital a
this is the set of x in the interval
where f of x is equal to zero
that this here is both
open and closed.
Right? We already know that this set
this is follow up here that that x0 is
so since
since x0 is in this set then we have and
the integral is connected and
I is connected.
If this set is both open and closed,
then we have that then uh a is equal to
the whole interval. Right? So this means
that the that f is constant zero which
means that the two functions coincided
everywhere. Right? And so we just need
to prove that f is
both uh open and closed. But the zero
set if you take a continuous function
right. So if if f here is continuous
and you have a sequence
so that each element here in the
sequence is zero and these xn converts
to some x. Well then by continuity right
by by continuity
f of x would also be zero. This is by
continuity
right we already
so this means that this set here is
definitely closed right and the open
thing with the open is just exactly this
property that we're assuming that if you
have an element in it each element is
interior which means that there is this
little interval around it right so you
have we have proven that it's both uh
closed. We prove that first and also
open. And so we have that that if you
have two such function
defined both continuous and defined on
an interval they coincide at one point
and if they coincide at one point then
they coincide in a little neighborhood.
If you have two function with this
property then they must be equal in the
whole interval. Right? Okay. So now how
does this relate to the the uniqueness
that we wanted to prove?
So we're starting again. So we have the
so we have so this is again the picard
linder theorem and this is the
uniqueness part.
And so you're looking at again you're
looking at solutions
to to this OD.
Um and we have that now we had that um
in a we have that in a so and then we
let sorry and let y1
and y2 be solutions
and let's say that these two they may be
defined on different interval of course
you know but but you just take the
intersection of the two intervals that
they're defined. So suppose that they're
both defined say on the same interval
like this
and this interval here and I of course
has to include the zero where we want
this condition.
Well then we have what do we have? So we
have a interval and we have two
continuous functions. They're actually
better than continuous. They're
differentiable
and even the derivative is continuous.
But but never mind that. Uh we have that
we have that y1 of zero is equal to a
and that's equal to y2 of zero. So they
coincide at one point.
And now the you the Picard Lindelof
theorem said that because there were two
solutions if you restrict the interval
right to looking at this little interval
around zero but then there was a unique
fixed point right so it means that in a
small neighborhood
of the origin so two in a small
neighborhood
of the
origin. This is again this is thanks to
that in the contracting mapping theorem
you had a unique fixed point in a small
neighborhood of the origin y1
is equal to y2 right but actually the
pical line the argument would work at
any other point right suppose you take
any other point then you and you take a
solution to the OD well if If you take
another point then the value so suppose
so so if you take so take you any other
point so here you have zero
and so now take any other points let's
call it x0
and if you assume that these two
functions coincide at this point so
suppose that y1
of x0 is equal to y2
of x0. If you now restrict this
interval,
make it sufficiently small, then the
argument of picard lindelof tells you
that you had this unique fixed point. So
you had a unique solution on this little
interval. But since they coincide at
this point, it means that they must be
the same in this little interval. And so
you see that now we have the condition
for for the lema okay for the lema that
said that so you have these two
continuous function and they were equal
at one point and if they're equal at a
point then they're equal in a whole
neighborhood. Okay so these two
functions these two solutions are equal
on the on the interval where they're
both defined. Okay.
Now Okay. Okay. So now you might and and
then I want to do a little bit of review
at the end. So at least say something
about the the final. But before we get
to that, let me just make one more
observation
about the picard line.
So you may
say that in the proof of the picard
linder we kind of had to restrict the
interval. Is that really necessary? Why
should we restrict? Why should we only
be able to say that we had a solution in
a very small interval? And so if you're
looking at the example, suppose you're
looking at the example
where y where f
so f of y
is equal to y 2 g of x is equal to zero.
And so you're looking at the OD the
solutions here y so that's uh y prime is
equal to
y 2 and uh let's say equal to a
uh form
uh x
uh equal to x0
okay so suppose you're looking at a like
this
right so at this x0 you want the value
of the function to be so you want sorry
y of uh x0
uh equal to
want maybe I should maybe this is a
little bit bad notation so I want a a
function so that y prime is equal to y^
2 and I want y of x0 = a Right.
Okay. Now let's say that x0
and a are both positive.
So if you're looking at this OD
then
then you can just this one here is easy
to solve
because you have a function
you have a function y prime
equal to y
and now let's try to find a solution in
a neighborhood of x0 but there supposed
to be positive. So in a small
neighborhood it's positive. So I can
divide by y^2. So I can looking at so
this thing here is equivalent to that y
prime over y^ 2 is equal to 1.
And this thing here I can write as 1 / y
prime * -1. this thing here, if you're
looking at this function here by the
chain rule, it's equal to that, right?
And so this means that now you can apply
the fundamental theorem of calculus. And
if you're integrating this function here
and you're integrating it from
uh two values uh x0 to x
uh d
uh uh d of s sorry this is the prime.
Then what you get is that this thing
here is equal to well on one hand by the
fundamental theorem of calculus it's 1 /
y of x minus and then there's a minus
sign sorry this here because of this
minus sign. So it's minus this plus 1 /
y of x0
and on the other hand it's equal to this
and when you're integrating this on this
interval here so this also equal to x0 x
um and then one d s this thing here is
just x - x0
x - x0
okay So if you solve it then let me just
write the result. If you check what this
gives you,
this gives you that um when you solve it
like this, uh you're getting
you're getting that y here is so you
have this od here
and you're assuming that these things
here are positive and then the solutions
are of the form y of x
= a over 1 + a
uh x0 - x right
and so what you should observe here is
that this thing here right as this is
not defined. So this is note
that y is not defined
uh
on all of r. But instead as x here goes
to uh x0
um + 1.
As x0 goes to this, this thing here goes
to minus one. So the denominator goes to
zero. So the function blows up. Right?
So this is so this here show you that it
does in a neighborhood of this point. It
has a solution but that neighborhood is
not you know it's some relatively small
neighborhoods and the function you
cannot extend it past a you know past as
a a certain value you can't extend it
past in this case you can't extend it
past this point here so to the left of
this point
to the sorry to the to the right I guess
of that
Okay.
Okay. So now I want to say a little bit
about the the final. Yeah. Sorry.
>> Why is it that you can't um once you
reach that point where it blows up does
it like it never solves differential
equation past that point?
>> Yeah, that's right. So so the thing is
so
so right. So this here this OD is going
to force it to once this here once Y
become large then why become really
really large so it become large too
quickly so it becomes quickly so that so
it would give you some sort of OD like
this that you have some critical value
where you couldn't extend it past that
because it is it will have like a a
tangent that is that is going vertical
like this. Okay. And
>> so you can't So, so this means that
there's, you know, that's right. So, so
um but so, so you have a solution that
exists on some interval, but it doesn't
exist past this point. So, you can't
have a solution,
uh, you know, on some interval larger
than than this to the left. and and this
is probably a similar phenomena on the
other side, right?
Okay.
But and it's like a kind of standard
prop, you know, standard uh issue that
for uh differential equations you can
get blowups like this that that this is
a particular simple examp. Any other
questions?
Um okay, great.