okay good morning um really pleased to
see so many of you here at this uh
somewhat early hour uh my name is Will
Oliver I'm a professor in electrical
engineering and computer science that's
my home Department um also with
professor of of physics and I'm really
pleased to organize this day um where
we're going to talk about Quantum
Computing and before we get started just
want to thank the uh the College of
computing the schwarzman College of
computing for organizing not just
today's event but the the whole week um
many of you may have come for the events
earlier this week and uh it's really
fantastic that we do this during
IAP uh today is focused on Quantum
Computing I'm going to start it off with
an intro to Quantum Computing uh some of
this is related to a course that we
teach online through mitx Pro which both
myself and um Ike Chang who is our
second speaker um put together a few
years ago it's been it's been quite
successful um if you'd like to learn
more about Quantum and you have a few
weeks uh let me know because this this
is a great way to continue what we're
going to talk about today through the
mitx pro platform so this morning is
going to be an intro to Quantum
Computing um I'll speak uh and then
Professor ik Chong uh will speak also
for an hour we'll break for
lunch and then this afternoon we have
some more focused um Topics in including
different Quantum Computing platforms um
and also you know state-of-the-art or
Cutting Edge research where are we today
and it will include both Quantum
Computing um but also um security so uh
Professor venod uh V kathan will talk
about how do we mitigate or combat the
threat that quantum computers pose to us
um that's his expertise um Professor
Aram herrow will talk about um
algorithms um yena Naros will talk about
um integrated photonics and then Kevin
O'Brien I see that the the list here is
uh um oh no okay never mind the the
titles are on the top yeah so arum will
talk about Quantum algorithms yena will
talk about integrated photonics for
trapped ions and then Kevin O'Brien will
talk about electronic circuits that
behave Quantum mechanically we'll take a
short break then and after that we'll
have a panel discussion but really what
I'd like to do with that panel
discussion is really open it up to
questions and have it be a free flow uh
Q&A so with that if there are no
questions uh why don't we get
started good so so I'm going to start it
off with Quantum engineering of um
superc conducted cubits or Quantum
Computing uh more
generally um we often call Quantum
Computing Quantum 2.0 why do we call it
2.0 well there was a 1.0 what you see
here is a picture from the solv
conference in
1927 you probably recognize a lot of
these folks um many of them won Nobel
prizes uh either they had already run
won it or they were about to in fact one
person here Madame Marie C uh won it
twice this is what we call the first
Quantum Revolution Quantum 1.0 it's when
we first understood that nature around
us is not classical it's fundamentally
quantum mechanical and in certain limits
it behaves classical and that's
generally what we
observe now based on that we were able
to um develop several Technologies which
are manifestly classical but we could
not have understood them without quantum
mechanics as a foundation and I like to
start here I guess I'm an electrical
engineer so I would like to start here
with a history of classical electronic
Computing how did we get to these
fantastic computers we have today well
it took well over a 100 Years of
development we started with the vacuum
tube that was 1906 three terminal device
um it was used for radio transceivers
for almost four decades 40 years before
it found its use in a computer called
eniac uh developed at the University of
Pennsylvania a vacuum tube based
computer of course to get closer to
where we are today we needed the
transistor that's Bell labs in 47 and by
the mid-50s we had fully transistor
based computers this one called tx0 or
tixo it didn't look like the computers
we have today and the sense that those
transistors were basically soldered
together okay and the memory was
completely different a magnetic core
type memory to get closer even still to
where we are we needed integrated
circuits that was the late 50s in
geranium and then in Silicon and of
course it wasn't until the 70s that we
finally saw something that you would
look at and say oh yeah that's an
integrated circuit that's a chip this is
the Intel 404 a 4bit processor with only
2,000 transistors revolutionary at the
time to get closer still I remember
using Pentium Pros in the mid 90s
millions of transistors on a single chip
that was fantastic but remember that was
already 30 years ago and here we are
today with uh wonderful computers um
gpus CPUs xus all kinds of processing
units 3D integrated right and the system
on the chip now has 100 billion
transistors and that's fantastic and
these these computers today are amazing
but we can't forget that those amazing
computers their progyny is well over 100
years old okay why do I talk about this
in so much detail well because Quantum
Computing is nent in the 80s people like
Richard feeman said look if you want to
simulate or emulate a Quantum system you
should use another quantum system to do
it because it's really hard on classical
computers to keep track of all of those
degrees of freedom that was true in the
80s still true
today now people thought about this
and it wasn't until maybe 15 years later
that we started to see the algorithms
that one would imagine using or running
on a quantum computer when we could
build it no Hardware at this point um
and you know calling out to Peter Shore
and his algorithm which attacks uh
public key crypto systems we'll hear a
lot about that today but of course if
that were the only application it would
not drive commercialization we would
need it of course we care a lot about
security but to drive commercialization
we need algorithms we'll talk about
algorithms throughout the day today but
algorithms that are commercially viable
and relevant right people will pay money
to run and we'll talk about some of
those algorithms and many of them had
their seeds in the
mid90s and 30 years later here we are
today we have um small scale quantum
computers maybe 100 cubits to 1,000
cubits um they're real they work but
they're too small to be commercially
viable you know usually when people
think commercially viable they're like
okay when am I going to have a quantum
computer that tells me um the the
formula for um a pharmaceutical drug or
something like that that is going to
take a very large error corrected
quantum computer and we'll talk we'll
talk more about that throughout the day
but the quantum computers we have today
you can run algorithms on them they're
just small and you can prove that those
algorithms work and it also gives you
insight into how large a hardware
quantum computer am I waiting for for
this to be commercially
viable so the takeaway message here is
that Quantum Computing is real it's
transitioning for from what you might
call a scientific curiosity to a
technical reality that's happening right
now as Engineers we know that advancing
from some fundamental Discovery to a
useful machine it takes a Time takes a
lot of Engineering Systems right we have
to have that type of thinking we're
there now um the other thing is you must
be in the game to play and what I mean
by that is the companies that are making
these fantastic you know billion plus
transistor chips they didn't wait for
somebody in 2010 to figure out how to do
it and then just jump in and start
producing them right there's a lot of
Trade Secrets right this is hardware
it's hard tech and you got to be in it
from the beginning
okay a lot of activity going on
worldwide and I won't read through this
whole chart here but but the point is is
that funding for Quantum Computing
started largely with governments driven
primarily by the security concern of
Shores algorithm um but since then I
would say within the last 10 years
there's been a tremendous push uh
towards commercialization and this is
just this is not an exhaustive list it's
just what I could fit on the chart and a
few of these companies are trying to
build quantum computers or Quantum
sensors but most of them are trying to
figure out how quantum's going to affect
their bottom line in the future and then
some of them are the picks and the
shovels that are needed to make Quantum
Computing a reality so this
commercialization ation uh and ecosystem
is happening right
now so what are cubits like what is the
fundamental logic element of a quantum
computer well they come in two flavors
one flavor is the natural atoms that we
have in our periodic table of elements
you can see them here um and we know
that depending on the number of protons
the number of neutrons and the number of
electrons we form these uh bore type
atoms and each element has different
properties depending on those numbers
okay and some of them we can pick out
and use uh to be our Cubit and in
particular we look for those that have
energy levels such that we can call one
of them zero and one of them one okay
we'll talk more detail about that but
these are the natural uh
atoms another way we can do it is we can
build electronic circuits and the
electronic circuits have inductors
capacitors and Joseph's injunctions and
depending on their parameter values and
the number of elements we have and the
way that we put them together we can
form circuits that have properties that
mimic or look like atoms but of course
at the end of the day it's just an
electrical circuit it looks like an atom
in the sense that it has discretized
energy levels such as shown here with a
zero and a one we can
identify and in fact there is a you
could think of it as a mlay of table of
these types of circuits each one having
different properties um that we can
design as electrical engineers right so
so so these are the two general families
of cubits again we'll talk more about
them in detail natural atoms and then
synthetic or artificial
atoms okay so with that let's talk about
how Quantum Computing Works um we'll
then talk a little bit about superc
conducting cubits and Engineering
Quantum
systems okay so how is a quantum
computer different than a classical
computer I I often use this because I of
course I was trained on classical
computers um
classical computers of course are based
on bits transistor is the voltage there
or not um but it could be any two-state
system um the states are zero or one
that's it they're discreet transistors
are almost perfect we've really
optimized them well and the error rate
is something like one part and 10 to the
20 they almost never fail if we set it
in one we're going to measure it in one
if we set it in zero we'll measure it in
zero if something unfortunate happens
right now almost certainly it's the soft
Ware not the
hardware cubits are quantum bits we
pronounce it Cubit and we spell it this
way uh and it's really a quantum
mechanical two-l system or two-state
system and the way that we think about
it is with something called The Block
sphere uh but you can think of it as the
planet Earth and if you're at the North
Pole you're in state zero a classical
state if you're at the South Pole you're
in state one also a classical State and
so transistors classical transistors
they only live at the North and the
South
Pole but cubits like people can be
anywhere on the surface of the planet
Earth and when you're anywhere other
than the North or the South Pole you're
in a Quantum superposition of States
zero and one
simultaneously now you can have waiting
coefficients if you're on the equator
the waiting coefficients are equal I
mean equal superposition of 0o and one
and if I'm away from the equator then
I'm not I'm more weighted towards one
than the other but it is a Quantum
superposition
right and this is just like you're
standing at a single place on Earth this
is not a mixture of two classical States
this is a single state that has a
property that has aspects of zero and
one simultaneously and that that's weird
all right it's not classical
superposition one consequence is that
measurement is probabilistic if you're
on the equator let's say you go to a
point on the equator and I make a
measurement that gives me classical
information out so you need to snap
immediately to the North Pole or to the
South Pole which one it's random it's
one of the purest forms of Randomness we
know quantum mechanics that provides us
if I go back to the same place on the
earth and I measure again just like
flipping a coin 50/50 I'm going to snap
to the North Pole or to the South Pole
instantly because I get that information
out okay so what this means is that
quantum computers rely on encoding
information in a fundamentally different
way than classical computers do so one
consequence of this is um shown here so
a classical computer with n Bits a
number n Bits can form um an
exponentially large number of states 2
to the nth power but it only can
represent one of them at a time so it
could be that all the uh transistors
here are in zero could be they're all in
one and all permutations in between with
three bits there are eight of those two
to the thir
power and what that means is if for some
reason I wanted to calculate a function
with each of these as an input I
basically have two options the first
thing I can do is I could take one
computer and then serially in time put
in 000000 get the function of that out
put in 001 get its function out and I do
that an exponentially large number of
times the other thing I could do is I
could buy a large number of computers
and I could run them as Illustrated here
in parallel but either way if I have an
exponentially large number of inputs I
need either exponential time or
exponential Hardware to do this
task quantum computers you can have n
cubits and again there will be two to
the end components or classical States
but the quantum computer can put all of
them into a single Quantum superposition
state with waiting
coefficients and you can think of it as
this massive superposition State going
into the quantum computer computer and
then a massive superposition State
coming out we haven't measured anything
yet we didn't get any information yet
okay now what happens in here and we'll
see it Illustrated in a moment is
something called Quantum parallelism and
Quantum interference and this underpins
or is the foundation for the power of a
quantum
computer so how do we take advantage of
this so let's go into a little bit more
detailed to see how Quantum parallelism
and Quantum interference work we're
going to start with this Quantum two
level system this is an electron spin uh
in a magnetic field and when an electron
spin is in a magnetic field it has
different energy depending on whether
the spin is aligned or anti-aligned with
the field okay so those are our two
states spin up spin down they have
different energies we'll call that e01
let's call spin up state zero and spin
down state
one so again if you're at the North Pole
or the South Pole you're in a classical
state so when when this is pointed
towards the North Pole here this is just
the classical zero uh when we're pointed
to the South Pole that's classical one
but we know as we said that anywhere
other than the North Pole we can form
superposition states of zero and one
simultaneously with waiting coefficients
Alpha and beta constrained in this way
so that the unit Vector is
preserved now just like on Earth we have
latitude and longitude we can represent
this state using phases um Theta and fi
and we could write this state in this
way
so at the North Pole Theta is zero at
the South Pole Theta is pi and this is
like a latitude and then the longitude
is where we are um along the Equator
okay so so on the equator you could see
that we are in equal superposition of0
and one simultaneously meaning the
magnitude of the coefficients that sit
there is equal it's one/ Square < TK of
two um but we also have this phase in
terms of where am I pointing on the
equator that's another phase that we
have all right so if you have these
three spins you could just treat them
classically you can say I'm never going
to put them in superp position I'm just
going to use them as classical bits and
you could form a state Register which I
just list here all the possible
permutations and from running from 0000
to 111 and you could do classical
computation this
way alternatively Quantum mechanically
what we would do is we would put all of
these um classical States into a single
superposition State sigh with waiting
coefficients C1 through C8 you could
write it this way it looks more digital
but of course we're representing it with
spins and we'll just note here that it
looks like we have eight numbers but
actually those are complex number so to
represent this state takes uh twice that
number 16 okay so we can now make this a
Quantum State register with coefficients
C1 through
C8 and we can now see how a computation
might un fold and it relies heavily on
these two quantum mechanical phenomena
called parallelism and interference so
let's let's just get an intuitive feel
for what that is so we're going to start
with these um three spins and let's just
focus on the first one we're going to
drive it with a pulse and this pulse has
the right area um to do what's called a
p pulse okay what does that mean well if
we're pointed towards the North Pole a
pi pulse will flip that spin to the
South Pole it rotates by an angle of Pi
Pi if the spin were pointed at the South
Pole it would rotate it back up to the
North Pole also PI right and so what we
see is that if we were to apply this
pulse onto this first spin what we what
we see is that we're going to shuttle
the coefficients around and let's see
how that happens so the state Register
before and after the pulse is shown here
um for spin ups that come in with these
coefficients you can see the other two
spins have different permutation but
these four um portions or aspect of the
superposition all have a spin up and
when we apply this pulse we are going to
flip it to spin down and the
coefficients follow
along now instead in that superposition
State I should where the spin was down
those aspects are going to flip to up
and the coefficients follow along so
what did we just do this is amazing we
applied one pulse we applied it to one
Spin and we just shuttled two to the N
coefficients in our state space
simultaneously okay that's called
Quantum
parallelism
now Quantum interference we can look at
and we'll we'll now apply this pulse to
uh the spin on atom three and if you
notice it's basically half of the area
which means it's only going to rotate
half as far and let me just tell you how
it works so we have before the pulse and
after the pulse if the spin is pointed
at the North Pole and we rotate it
around this axis pointed to the right by
pi/ 2 it's going to be on the
equator and I'm just going to say that
that's a plus Direction Let's just say
that for the
moment um and what that means is a spin
up is going to go to a superposition of
up plus down equal superposition it's on
the equator and it comes with a plus
sign now I'm not worried about
normalization here for those who are
experts in quantum mechanics there is a
normal Iz ation but we don't need it for
this uh
illustration now what happens to this
spin right here that happens to be spin
up in uh with the coefficient C5 well
it's going to go to up plus down so it
now splits between two aspects and the
coefficient C5 follows along and it it's
Plus for both of them again without the
normalization I'm not worried about
that now instead for the portion of the
superposition state where the spin is is
down let's just look at this one case um
if you start at the South Pole and you
rotate in the same direction you'll find
that you go up to the equator but now
you're pointed in the opposite side of
the earth and so we're going to say this
comes in with a minus sign okay so this
spin down now goes to up and down but it
comes in with a minus sign which means
the coefficient C6 follows in the same
way plus C6 where it's up minus C6 where
it's down and now what we see is that
for example if C5 and C6 were equal they
need not be but let's just presume that
it's true then for this first up up up
portion of the state they add together
constructively it gets
bigger and for this portion C5 minus C6
they destructively interfere in fact if
they're equal goes to zero so there's no
more waiting on this aspect of the
superposition State this is what we mean
when we say quum
interference we're enhancing or
suppressing
coefficients and in fact this is also an
example of quantum parallelism because
it happens on the entire State space
simultaneously right so again to
emphasize we applied one pulse we
applied it to one Spin and all of this
happened at the same
time okay that that underpins the power
of a quantum
computer okay so how do we take
advantage of this and actually Implement
and run algorithms well it almost at
least conceptually is the same as a
classical computer we know on a
conventional computer we have classical
Boolean logic gates and I won't read
through the whole thing but we have a
not gate we have an and gate an or gate
with these truth tables shown here and
we know that we can form a universal set
um of gates Universal Gat set for
Boolean logic not with just one
combination but with several different
combinations the nangate the Norgate
there are many different combinations
of gates just a handful of them that
would enable us to run any Boolean logic
algorithm it's called a universal gate
set it does require at least one two bit
gate Quantum is basically the same just
in the quantum mechanical realm we have
Gates and those Gates represent
rotations around the planet Earth so for
example an xgate is a rotation around
the x-axis we can Define one of these as
X the Y gate is a rotation around the Y
AIS these are all single Cubit Gates we
also have a z
rotation and we have what are called two
Cubit Gates where the state of one of
the cubits determines what happens to
the second Cubit but it only involves
two cubits uh one example is controlled
knot the other is controlled phase and
with just a handful of these single and
two cubic Gates we can form a universal
gate set that runs any arbitrary Quantum
logic and again it's not unique there
are many combinations uh that satisfy
this universality
um one thing to point out is quantum
gates are by definition reversible of
course we do have examples in classical
Electronics which are reversible as well
um and it also requires at least one two
Cubit gate and it has to be what's
called an entangling gate I'll show an
example in just a
moment so let's let's look at an example
of a single Cubit operation and and the
analogue I'm going to draw here is to
the classical knot gate so a notot gate
if you put in a zero you get a one if
you put in a one you get a zero and the
quantum analog to this is called the
xgate where I put in a Quantum state
zero and I get a one or I put in a one
and I get a
zero this is what it looks like now what
you're seeing here on the left is the
planet Earth um the state is in blue it
starts at the North Pole and rotates to
the South Pole it's rotating around the
x-axis you can see this red uh Arrow
come in and out and that red arrow is
representing the envelope of the pulse
that I'm applying
to do this operation and that this pulse
envelope is tuned properly so the area
is exactly right to go from the North
Pole to the South Pole now as I'm
showing it here this is just a classical
implementation because I start at the
North Pole I end at the South Pole those
are classical
States but of course you need not start
at the North or South Pole you could be
anywhere on the surface of the planet
Earth and this gate will do exactly the
same thing it rotates by an angle Pi
around the x-axis and so here I started
in a superp position State I rotate
around the x-axis I end in a
superposition State and what this xgate
does is it swaps the coefficients Alpha
0 plus beta 1 becomes beta 0 plus alpha
1 okay this is just one example of the
single Cubit gate that we have okay
let's look at a two Cubit gate this is
the two Cubit controlled knot it's
classical analog is the exclusive orgate
now the exclusive orgate um has you can
think of it in this way as having a
control bit and a Target bit X and Y the
truth table is here and when the control
bit X is in zero the value of y is just
passed to the output
unchanged but when the control bit is
one we know that the value of y should
be flipped we do a not gate on Y and
that becomes the output you can think of
exclusive or this
way and the quantum version is exactly
the same you have two cubits one is the
control Cubit X and then there's a
Target Cubit y this symbolism is how we
represent the controlled knot and the
truth table aside from using this funny
notation called durac notation which
just says I'm talking about quantum
mechanical stuff it's exactly the same
the truth table is the same and so what
it means is that a rotation or an
operation on Cubit y the target depends
on the state of Cubit X the
control now quantum mechanics follows
linear algebra and we can just figure
out for ourselves how this works for a
particularly interesting input state
where the control Cubit is 0 plus one
it's an equal superp position that's the
uh control Cubit X and the target Cubit
is uh Y and it's in state zero classical
state so let's take this one at a time
so when the control Cubit is zero we
know that we shouldn't change the target
Cubit so it comes down here and you get
0x 0 y
but when the control cuit is one we're
supposed to flip the Y bit and so that
flips to one and now we see something
very interesting here this is called an
entangling gate precisely for this
reason which is that even though when I
started I could look at something which
was entirely x-like um tensor product
with something that's entirely y like
once I do this gate I can't do that
anymore you can see that X and Y are
intimately um tied to each other
and it's they're tied to each other in a
way that's called quantum entanglement I
can't Factor it anymore now this isn't
proof that it's entanglement you'd have
to look at this in different bases but
in fact this is an entangled State
called a bell
state so this is just one example but
Universal gate based Quantum computation
um is achievable with just a small set
of these single and two cubic Gates this
is how it
works so now let's think about an
algorithm what does it mean to write an
algorithm of course you'll use some
sequence of these single and two cubic
Gates and often usually um the quantum
computer will start in an equal
superposition state of all of these uh 2
to the N
aspects and the way that I think about
it is that this is an equal
superposition of all the possible
answers right I'm starting with this
equal each answer is equally likely
because I know when I make a measurement
I'm only going to get one answer right
we'll see that in just a moment and so
what the algorithm designer does is
choose as a sequence of single Cubit and
two Cubit operations so of course here's
an example where you have a single Cubit
operation on Cubit 3 and as we talked
about it's one pulse on one cubit but it
will change the coefficients um of 2 to
the N components simultaneously and it
does that through Quantum parallelism
and Quantum interference which changes
the co efficients now that sit in front
of this superposition state they're no
longer all
equal sometimes we'll have couple Cubit
operations where the state of one cubit
tells me what to do on the second
Cubit that follows Quantum interference
or followed by Quantum interference it's
also massively parallelized and so by
the end of the computation the goal of
the algorithm designer is to ensure that
the right answer is weighted by a
coefficient that's one or close to one
and all of the other answers that are
wrong have been suppressed to
zero and that's important because we
know when we make a measurement we're
going to project and the probability
that we get any one of these results
goes as the magnitude squared of the
coefficient remember if you were on the
equator it was equally weighted and it
was 50/50 whether you're going to go
zero or one you don't want that in
algorithm in an algorithm you want to
get the right answer 100% of the time
ideally and so we started with an equal
superposition of all possible answers
through the course of applying Gates we
suppressed all of the wrong answers we
enhanced the right one and then when we
make a measurement with high probability
that's what we get so it's a mistaken
it's often said and it's a not really
true that quantum computers will
calculate the output to all of these
inputs that's not what's happening in
the quantum computer right that that
would be you know mistaken concept what
it's doing is it's suppressing all the
wrong answers and enhancing the right
answer so that at the end you get the
right answer but you're not going to get
two to the end outputs you're going to
get one output that's very
important it'd be great if we could do
that but we
can't okay so there are many algorithms
that have been developed and um that
support this and I just showed pictures
of my colleagues here uh at MIT who do
work on either Quantum algorithms or
Quantum software but and and I won't
read this whole chart but let me say
that the categories of algorithm are
shown here on the left um Quantum
simulation is probably the you know
killer commercial app I would say um
simulating materials or chemistries for
example Pharma um I also showed the
classical time and the quantum time here
um in general the classical time is
exponential in the size of the system um
the quantum time is uh
polinomial factoring of course Peter
shor's algorithm sampling solutions to
linear systems of equations this is uh
Aram Aram Harrow and Seth Lloyd the
Harum Haro hium Lloyd algorithm um
optimization a lot of work by folks like
Eddie fary on this one
here they're clearly everybody's trying
to optimize something so there's clearly
a commercial need for it but the degree
to which quantum computers can help us
with optimization uh depends a lot on
the optimization problem okay do you
need the exact solution is a high
quality solution good enough okay that's
why there's a question mark here and uh
of course Grover's search algorithm of
unsorted data and that's a quadratic
Improvement not an exponential
one
so what are the ingredients for
commercial Quantum advantage and um I
borrowed this chart from Ike it's a
fantastic chart so first there better be
no fast classical algorithm if we know
how to do it on one of these computers
we should absolutely do it they're
fantastic so just solve that so first
off no fast classical algorithm for my
problem second is we need to know how to
solve it on a Quantum comp computer
there are many problems where there's no
fast classical algorithm and I have no
idea how to do it on a quantum computer
okay so so you need a fast Quantum
algorithm and then third ideally you'd
like it to be a useful meaning a
commercial problem there are many
examples of problems which are
instructive and we learn from them like
deuts josa right as an example where you
can prove that there's an exponential
speed up but it's for a problem that's
not commercially relevant and what we
would like is that this over La region
is The Sweet Spot we of course want to
make this larger and and that's a charge
to everyone here um especially students
and post dos that you know this is what
we need to do if quantum computers are
going to be um useful one day is
increase the the overlap
area we've already alluded to it but
there are two types of quantum advantage
that we have in quantum computers and
and you can think of them in the
following way the size of the system or
the time to solution
energy needed to run that quantum
computer is proportional to a polinomial
factor in the size of the system n uh
and an exponential factor in the size of
the system
n so algorithms like Grover's algorithm
improve the preactor we call this a
polinomial Improvement for example n
goes to square root of n okay that's a
big Improvement especially for large n
but it pales in comparison to an
exponential Improvement for example two
to the nth power going to n cubed n
comes downstairs that that's an amazing
Improvement and we don't often
experience it in our everyday lives okay
so here's here's an
example um of exponential growth that
I'd like to highlight um and and what
we're talking about here is I have a
quantum computer and I want to simulate
that quantum computer using a
conventional classical computer how much
memory would I need to store all of
those coefficients in my superposition
state if you have 30 cuits that's 2 to
the 30th power you you can do that on a
laptop a beefy
laptop but just go to 50 not even twice
as many and now we need to have a super
computer to do it worth of memory go to
80 cubits and now somehow we need all of
the computers on Earth linked together
and leveraging all of their memory
hopefully quickly you maybe we need
photonic interconnects or something to
make this work and then it gets
ridiculous like double that to 160
cubits and now we would need all of the
Silicon atoms on Earth and every silicon
atom is representing one bit of the
memory and now go to 300 cubits just 10
times where we started and now you would
need all the atoms in the known universe
working together as memory elements for
this fictitious computer okay this
doesn't tell us how to build a quantum
computer but it does give us a concept
of what exponential scaling
means okay so it sounds great uh why
don't we have quantum computers right
now or why don't we have large fault
tolerant quantum computers right now and
it comes down to these two times one is
coherence time and the other is the gate
time so the coherence time is basically
the cubit's lifetime how long does it
remain quantum
mechanical now I'm including here
coherence due to noise but it can also
be due to control errors our classical
control we start out with a computer
quantum computer in a known state of all
those cubits call it sigh and as soon as
we start trying to run our algorithm it
starts interacting with its environment
there are temperature fluctuations
magnetic field fluctuations the subway
just left kendle station and you can see
it on your cubits everything they're
very sensitive and over time you can
think of this state of my computer
blurring and eventually it's lost what
does that mean well the cubits are still
there but in some notion of a high
dimensional State space I was trying to
go from this starting point to this end
point which is the answer to my problem
and as I'm marching along with my gate
operations to get there the noise is
actually taking me somewhere else and I
don't know where I went at the end it's
blurry because I don't know everything
that the noise is doing okay the time
frame over which this blurring happens
is called the coherence
time the second time we care about is
the gate time how long does it take me
to do an operation um a typical time and
the figure of Merit then is how many
operations can I do within this lifetime
that I have okay more operations being
better now one caveat here is that
people often
trumpet you know my my cubid has a
coherence time of 10 hours okay great
that that's not a bad thing but what's
important is how many operations can you
do in that 10 hours and and to give an
example a little bit of a ridiculous
example think of a nutrino you might
think a nutrino is a perfect Cubit
because it lasts
forever but it's not because I can't
operate I can't even detect it right and
so it's not just having long coherence
times often the technologies that have
long coherence times they do it or have
that long coherence time because they
don't listen to the noise if they don't
listen to the noise they don't listen to
me either when I'm trying to run the
algorithm and it turns out as we'll see
on the next chart these Technologies
almost independent of their coherence
times have roughly the same number of
operations uh that they can do within
that time okay so why don't we look at
that
chart so what we have here is the number
of operations before an error and on
this horizontal axis we have the gate
speed how think of that as the clock
speed now the number of operations
before an error you might think of as
the gate Fidelity so for a given gate
what percentage of the time does it work
so if I have one ER in 100 that's 99%
one air in a th000 that's 99.9% Etc and
of course you want to be fast and High
Fidelity and so now we can take a look
at different competing platforms so one
is trapped ions which Ike works on along
with John Chavi at Lincoln and rajie RAM
here at MIT and you can see that trapped
ions have very high fidelity uh single
cubic Gates they're improving the two
cubic gate um and they're trying to get
faster to get into the upper right
corner I work on superc conducting
cubits along with Kevin O'Brien who'll
speak this afternoon uh Terry Orlando
Jamie Kerman out at Lincoln and we are
pretty fast um and we're trying to get
higher Fidelity and so in some sense
we're both equally far from you know
this upper right
corner neutral atoms have really started
to shine in the last couple years this
is where they are and some of our
colleagues here vladon Wolf Gang and
Martin working on this
technology uh nitrogen vacancy centers
or just generally speaking defects in
Silicon or other
substrates they can be used for
computing uh they really shine as
Quantum sensors magnetic field sensors
for example and then my own group is
starting to work also on Silicon Quantum
dots which probably is the closest to a
silicon transistor uh of the Cubit
Technologies
now these circles that just appeared
here are giving us an indication of how
fast we would actually be able to run a
computer in practice because we need to
do error correction if we're going to do
sustained uh computations over long
periods of time and so for the superc
conducting cubits it's about a megahertz
for some of the natural Atomic systems
it's about a kilohertz
and everybody's going to try to get
faster it matters it really matters
because all else being equal an
important caveat but all else being
equal if it takes me a day to run an
algorithm on a superc conducting quantum
computer at a megahertz it's going to
take me a th days on something that runs
a thousand times slower and even though
both
Technologies didn't take the age of the
universe it's an exponential speed up
over a classical computer it still
matters how long it's going to take
because I don't want to wait 3 years for
the answer i' like the answer within a
day and so the speed still matters in
quantum
computers okay lots of research going on
I would say there's no clear winner and
and also just like with conventional
technology uh classical Computing
technology it'll evolve over time right
we started with bipolar Junction
transistors uh we later had emitter
coupled logic and you know we worked our
way eventually to be at camos um it
didn't you know in fact we started with
vacuum tubes before that the technology
will evolve and change over time
okay
um let me check the time I'm probably
speaking a little too slowly yeah so let
me talk a little bit about
superconducting cubits these are
artificial atoms we build them um from
circuit elements like inductors and
capacitors this in fact is a Quantum
circuit element you probably recognize
it it's the LC oscillator and one
property of an LC oscillator is that
it's harmonic which means that its
potential is quadratic
and at room temperature you don't see
these discrete energy levels because
they're separated by the resonance
frequency 1ot of
LC um but if you cool it down to a low
enough temperature where the energy
scale of the temperature KT is much less
than the energy scale H bar Omega which
is the separation here you you will see
discretized energy levels for this
circuit I think that's amazing uh as an
electrical engineer um it's a great
circuit it is Quant mechanical but it
has this one issue is that if I want to
make a cubit from it with a zero and a
one um I could do that but when I drive
0 to one I also drive 1 to two because
it's the same frequency and two to three
it's the same frequency and very quickly
I leave my 01 Subspace that's a problem
so we have to do something to make the
circuit anharmonic and what we do is we
add a Joseph's injunction now for our
purposes here a Josephson Junction is a
nonlinear inductor okay Brian Josephson
gave us the current and voltage
relationship uh through this device it's
two superconducting leads separated by a
thin tunneling barrier but when you
combine it in the usual way to define
inductance you find that the inductance
value of this circuit element depends on
how much current goes through it that's
the definition of a nonlinear inductor
its value changes as the current
changes you could even integrate current
and voltage in time to get the energy
and what you find is the energy now is
shaped like a cosine potential rather
than this parabolic
potential and so if I made a LC circuit
but I made it with a nonlinear
inductor the potential profile now shown
in blue the cosine differs from a
harmonic potential it's an anharmonic
potential and what that translates to is
the 01 frequency is now different than
the one two frequency and that's what I
need to stay in the 01 Subspace I drive
that resonantly I'm off resonance with
the other transition okay this circuit
element in fact is a cubit that's used
today quite widely it's called the
transmon it's used at IBM um in
different forms it's used at Google um
you could think of this as the hydrogen
atom for superconducting cubits
okay now we have to cool them down to
very low temperatures as I mentioned and
how low well typically these cubits will
have a frequency that's around a few
gahz say 5 GHz that's a thermal energy
of 250
Kelvin if you equate KT and H bar Omega
you want to be much colder than this uh
you don't want the thermal environment
to excite it so we want to operate say
10 times colder around 20 Melvin and
that's great because these refrigerators
called dilution refrigerators get us
down to that temperature now 40 50 years
ago this was somebody's PhD project but
today they're commercially available you
just buy them we have 12 in our uh lab
the uh engineering Quantum systems lab
and many many faculty at MIT have
refrigerators like this and you can see
in here everything this about half a
meter across half a meter down um and
it's all at 20 Melvin right coaxes
switches filters attenuators over time
we've learned what works at these
temperatures and of course that's what
we
use superc conducting cubits are
fabricated um meaning that we
manufacture them on Silicon this is a
200 mm silicon wafer lots of cubits on
here if we zoom in on one of the
circuits you can see these five plus
signs in a row those are five
superconducting cubits the plus is
actually the capacitor so rather than
using parallel plate we just use
something that's lateral and why a plus
well we envision not just having a line
of them but we want to go north south
east and west so that's how we can
connect to neighboring
cubits if we zoom in further so that's
the capacitor to ground if we zoom in
further this little piece right here
this Loop um is called a squid it's
actually a Joseph's injunction two
Joseph's injunctions in a loop with a
property that if we put a magnetic field
through that Loop we can actually tune
the cubit's frequency that's useful the
cubit's in the fridge I'd like to change
its frequency how do I do that I just
apply a little bit of current to an
antenna and I can change the frequency
and then the smallest feature size about
100 nanometers is the Joseph's
injunction itself so we're not pushing
lithography here if anything these are
very very large uh devices
now how do we control it we control it
with microwave um IQ mixing and so this
planet Earth over here you can see the
Cubit state in blue going around the
earth and it's going around based on
these uh pulses in red and I apologize
the blue and the red on the left are not
the same as the blue and the red on the
right the blue and the red on the right
is a result of uh inphase and quadrature
mixing so the i port of a mixer we're
going to say is blue the Q Port is red
and your local oscillator going into
this mixer gets multiplied by the I or
the Q pulse and you just decide which
pulse you want to send am I sending it
to I or am I sending it to q and the the
mixer multiplies them together and you
get this pulse out and again if we tune
the area of that pulse just right we can
get either a pi pulse or a pi over 2
pulse the difference between I and Q is
a phase shift of 90 and that tells me
whether I'm going to apply that pulse
along the x-axis or the Y AIS of the
block sphere so just standard IQ mixing
is how we can control um these
circuits so using this in our group we
have more than four nines of single
Cubit Fidelity and more than three nines
of two Cubit uh Fidelity and the higher
the Fidelity the better as we
remembered now just to give a flavor the
research I think Kevin will likely talk
more about this in the afternoon is that
it involves a lot and that's actually
why it's taken a long time to develop
quantum computers in general is um you
need to develop the materials you need
to analyze the materials design the
circuit model it build your circuit
fabricate it maybe involves some bump
bonding some process monitoring then you
have to cool it down in one of these
refrigerators takes a lot of equipment
and then you get some result out and
then you validate or refute the
hypothesis you had and then you iterate
this many many times okay so we have
this today but starting out you know
this was basically a black box and
people had to figure it out but I but
things are accelerating quite rapidly in
this field over the last five years
precisely because we can now efficiently
do this
optimization if we look at the coherence
over the last I would say 20 or 30 years
first Cubit was about a nanc and today
our cubits are actually at a millisecond
and more and so that six plus orders of
magnitude Improvement is part of the
reasons why many companies are pursuing
superc conducting cubits they've
improved dramatically over the past many
many
years uh this is what quantum computers
look like today uh IBM's ospre here in
the lower left has
433 I think something like that cubits
this is uh Google's Willow chip uh which
just had the very large announcement
about the first time a Quantum error
correcting code was beyond threshold
that's a big deal uh this one in the
middle is a neutral atom quantum
computer called a Kila from qera a
startup company started by Folks at
Harvard and
MIT uh this is quanum H1 chip this is a
trapped ion chip in a racetrack style uh
this is d-waves quantum aner it's also
superconducting different type of
quantum Computing we won't get into it
today um this of course is not a quantum
computer you'll recognize this as the
right
flyer um it wasn't the first time
humankind had flown that that's actually
a misconception we had hot air balloons
we had gliders you know people jumping
off cliffs with wings but this was the
first time that it all came together
there's a person on board steering
self-propelled it took off it landed um
if you read the history of this they did
six flights that weekend crashed once or
twice they had to go back and fix it and
it I put it here because it reminds me
of where we are today in Quantum
Computing you know my students will say
that things crash and they have to fix
it every weekend probably but the point
is that when we saw this particularly in
hindsight when we see this event we know
that commercial Aviation will come it
clearly it's not ready yet but we know
that the it's matured to a point where
we can Envision commercial Aviation and
I think by analogy that the quantum
Computing systems that we see today are
likely equally IM mature but have risen
to the point where we can see that
commercial Quantum Computing will come
it's and to realize that we need to
engineer the systems that are robust
reproducible and
extensible so in the last this will be
my last slide because I'm running out of
time the Grand Challenge today is
quantum error correction so these
computers can operate for a certain
amount of time but eventually
decoherence takes over and we lose uh we
lose our Quantum
coherence but that's not the end of the
game uh fortunately um if we look at the
physical cubits that we have today their
error rates are one in 100 to say one in
10,000 and groups around the world
worked really hard to get the quality to
that point that's pretty amazing right
that out of 10,000 Gates only one
failed but you could ask what do I need
for practical you know commercial
computing
you need something in the billion to
trillion range I I need to run a billion
or a trillion operations in order to do
something that's commercially useful and
there's a big gap a giant chasm between
these two points and how are we going to
make it
up by the way the transistor I mentioned
before you know almost never fails and
you know maybe one day we'll get to that
point with Quantum Computing fortunately
we don't have to get there to see the
first commercial
Advantage so the way that we're going to
do it is called Quantum error correction
and you can think of it as forming a
team of cubits so rather than trying to
encode information in a single Cubit
we're going to form a team here it's a
3X3 array so nine cubits that are yellow
nine physical cubits together forms a
team and that team is going to ideally
outperform the uh individuals there now
you also see some blue cubits here and
the blue cubits are like referees or
Checkers they're going to look at the
neighbors they're going to say oh foul
foul they're going to let us know so we
can go back and
correct now when we do that we call this
thing a logical Cubit and when we do
that The Logical error the error rate of
The Logical cubit in fact has a
prefactor that makes it worse okay
obviously if we form a team um if we
form a team of cubits um we need to do
more work more gates more operations so
that's a penalty but in implement this
protocol we do get an exponential
Advantage um and it's exponential in the
size of our logical Cubit so the way
that I think about this intuitively is
Imagine imagine a room of
kindergarteners heartwarming 20 or 30
kindergarteners everybody running around
screaming having a good time okay those
were the cubits of 10 15 years ago all
right if you add more kindergarteners to
that class they're just going to get
worse it's not going to get better okay
but somewhere along our education
trajectory we get to a point where if
two people form a team they outperform
any individual or three people or 10
people or 20 people there's a threshold
that we cross in our education and when
we cross that threshold adding more
people to a team makes the performance
of the team better and better and better
and in fact we have companies that have
hundreds of thousands of people working
together and this penalty here is okay
now I need an HR department to keep it
all straight but the benefit of putting
all those people together outperforms
not doing it okay so that's the concept
of error correction and it's very
powerful what I'm showing here is The
Logical error per cycle uh on the
vertical axis the horizontal axis is the
error rate of the physical cubits and
you can see they're quite different
we're talking about a tenth of a percent
error rate on the physical cubits one in
a thousand but on this axis we're
getting down to one in a million or more
and the way that we do it is that we
have to be on this side of the threshold
the cubits they can't be kindergarteners
they have to be more mature than that
and the more mature they are the bigger
Advantage we get by aggregating more and
more cubits together into a logical
Cubit and every time I increase the size
of this distance three distance five
distance seven I go down by the same
factor that's this exponential
Improvement and this is what Google
showed or announced I should say in uh
December full disclosure I work with
them um and and was on this paper with
them but what they showed is that um
in red they have the distance three
code in blue they have the distance five
code and in dark I should say teal and
then in dark blue they have the distance
seven code and every time they increased
the size of the team the error R rate
went down by more than a factor two now
of course we want to do better than that
we'd love it to be a factor 10 but it
works and this is the first time that
this scaling with the size of the uh um
logical Cubit has been shown in any
technology this is a side of line we
want to be on because we want to build
quantum computers that have millions and
millions of cubits and as we add more
and more cubits the error rate better go
down if it doesn't then we're still in
the kindergarten era but we're not this
was the first time it was shown so they
demonstrated improved performance going
from a distance three to a distance
seven um there have been many
demonstrations of quantum error
correction with other modalities uh
encoding logical cubits showing that
they can turn the crank but this was the
first time that it actually
worked okay and so I think I'm going to
stop there in the interest of time um I
thank you for your attention and um we
may be able to take a quick question or
two but then I'm going to also invite I
up to switch over to the next uh talk
thank
you it was a very good Inu a few things
that I was confused about okay what two
questions what is the relation of a
coherence time and the error rate if the
coherence time goes up does the error
rate go down generally speaking yes for
for a given technology because it it
what matters is that you know how many
operations can I do within that
coherence time so if my operation time
is always the same and I make the
coherence time longer then I can do more
operations on average before Things Fall
Apart the second question is if your big
diagram you showed that the up time uh
was much if you only had one gate per
cubid versus two gates per cuq does
adding gate what do the adding Gates uh
reduce the amount of time by so much and
what is the advantage of having more
gates per human sorry can you say that
I'm trying to remember which slide
you're thinking of like 10 to the 5th uh
it was the big slide of of performance
of uh comparing different modalities yes
that one okay and and what was the
question again you had one cubit I one
gate per cubit and two gates per cubit
and you had two different numbers oh I
see yes so I didn't thank you I did not
mention that yeah so to do Universal
Quantum computation you need single
Cubit Gates and two Cubit Gates meaning
an operation that I apply to only one
cubit at a time or operations that I
apply to two cubits at a time and so if
we want to compare these different
Technologies we can't just look at the
single cubic gate although people often
will say hey my single cubic gate is so
good okay but you can't do Universal
Quantum computation with that what's
your two cubic gate Fidelity that's also
important and that's why I had those two
numbers on
there the up for the two Cubit gate was
much it tends to be harder that's right
it tends to be lower Fidelity um
precisely because uh it's more
complicated there are two cubits that
I'm trying to um operate in Tandem and
as a result it generally is slower
although not always um and it generally
has lower Fidelity
yeah good and I'll be around I'm happy
to talk more offline or at the lunch
today I don't want to eat into uh Ikes
time so um