hello can people hear me in the back are
we
good okay so uh welcome to the last
lecture of 604 oh no 61200 yeah um I'm
I'm totally sayane I can remember which
class I'm teaching uh welcome you made
it through the semester well
done uh okay so for today's
material we are going to you know wrap
up our discussion of
probability and in particular we will be
discussing uh tail bounds so you know uh
what happens if you have a a random
variable like what is the probability
that this random variable is like very
large or very small like you know very
different from from its expectation
okay uh so let's start with a a bit a
review uh
variance okay so I think we uh saw from
the last not last lecture two lectures
ago possibly uh so the variance of a
random variable
R uh is defined to be the
expectation of uh R minus the
expectation of r
uh
squared
okay uh and the standard deviation is
just the square root of that you know if
you've uh taken you know stats or
anything like that that's probably uh
you know something that you've seen more
more often than
variance uh another you know not a
definition but another useful formula an
equivalent formulation of this is that
the variance of r
is also equal to the
expectation of r
s minus the square of the expectation of
R okay uh so not the definition but it's
equivalent and uh I think in recitation
perhaps you uh you proved this um this
this formula is is a particularly useful
one for what we're going to be doing
today
okay uh we also saw that uh you know
Varian is linear subject to uh you know
certain constraints does anybody
remember what uh what you need for for
variance to be
linear
yeah
Independence okay so if you
have R1
R2 RN are
independent
then uh the variance of the sum is the
sum of the
variances
oops uh is that the right
constraint is it
correct who who believes this statement
who
disbelieves who's who's still
asleep oh okay maybe we'll we'll give it
a few minutes for people to wake
up uh okay um well this is a correct
statement uh however there's something
uh slightly stronger that we can say we
can weaken this this condition right we
don't need Mutual Independence what do
we actually need
pair ways Independence
yeah okay so if we have a bunch of
Parise independent random variables we
want to find the variance of their sum
we can instead just sum the variances
okay so another very useful fact uh
hopefully you proved it already in
recitations so we don't need to go over
the
proof uh but these uh well
these two formulas are going to be quite
useful
today
okay now time for the first of our
tailbones so before I uh give you the
bound uh let's let's think about an
example so looking at this room uh
suppose I pick a random student and uh
you know let the random variable R be
the the row that the the randomly picked
student is is sitting in okay so
guesstimate that this is about uh you
know the expectation of R is about eight
so so pick random
student R is the row
okay so for uh those of you who aren't
in the room those of you who are
watching the video uh what does that
tell them about uh the probability that
R is at least
16 so what's the probability that a
randomly selected student is sit sitting
in the last five rows I think there 21
rows here
yeah does anybody have any
idea so maybe I should label this as an
example
yeah one minus the CDF okay so the
people watching the uh watching the
video can't I assume they can't see the
room so they don't know what the CD
is right the only information they
know is that the expectation is
eight
okay
yeah oh can we find the variance from
that and then see how far away we are uh
no that uh requires more information
right like we we need to know a little
bit more about uh about what's going on
right like we we need to you know
somehow figure out you know the
expectation of R minus 8 squar so like
we need to know something more about R
than than just its
expectation
yeah yes there're 21 so 0 through
yeah can we assume that it's uniformally
distributed uh no and in fact it it is
not uh there seem to be
you know more students towards the front
than than towards the back
yeah yeah
yeah so your intuition is great though
right so um well we're using the
observation that uh that you know 16 is
is twice 8 right we're we're also using
the observation that uh you know the
rows are numbered 0 through 20 like
they're they're non
negative okay so what
happens if you know more than half of
the
students are sitting in the back five
rows
what does that tell us about the
expectation well if if more than half of
the students you know give us R is is at
least
16 right that tells us that the
expectation should be at least
eight right or sorry more than
eight if if more than half of the
students are in the back okay so the
converse of
that is that there are at most half of
the students in the back five
rows okay so let's try and formalize
this
intuition so this is what's known as
Markov in
equality uh so let R be a non- negative
random
variable uh then the
probability that R is greater than or
equal to
X is less than or equal to the
expectation of
r divided by
X
okay so for the example that we just saw
right the probability that uh R is at
least
16 it's at most the expectation which is
8 ID 16 so that gives us 1
12 okay does the uh does the statement
make sense to
people so basically it's saying that you
know you can't have too many super large
values because that would push the
expectation up too
high
okay so how could we prove
this any ideas how do we formalize the
intuition that we were just talking
about let's try let's try using the law
of total expectation
so how can we write the expectation of
R what might we condition
on we don't have too many events that we
can work with
right which of them might be useful
nobody so let's try let's try
conditioning on X greater than oh wait
was it
x
uh yeah R greater than or equal
okay so what does the law of total
expectation tell
us well this is going to be the
expectation of our conditioned on R
being greater than x
multiplied by the probability that R is
greater than
x okay
plus the
expectation are conditioned on R less
than
x times that
probability okay do people remember that
that coming back hopefully yes no maybe
few
nods
okay so what do we know about each of
these values
let's start with this one can anybody
bound
this
yeah yeah it's at least X if you
conditioned on R being at least X right
the expectation of R is is also going to
be at least X right every outcome is at
least
X okay
so this is going to be at least x
times well this is the probability that
that we're looking for so let's just
write it out as it
is
okay now what about the bottom
line what do we know about this
expectation
yeah is it one minus the expectation uh
of the other one uh no so the the
probability is one minus the uh the
other probability uh the expectation
does not work like that though
yeah it is at most X that is true um
we're actually looking for a lower bound
though
yeah so at least Z
yeah
okay right we know that that R is always
non
negative so you know conditioning on
anything R is still always going to be
non- negative so it's expectation has to
be non-
negative
okay so we we can drop this this is just
going to be
zero now we've got the expectation of
R is at
least x times the probability that R is
at least
X
okay now we can just move this x to the
other side
assuming X is not negative if x is
negative then it's a it's a very silly
question so you know or sorry assuming X
is
positive okay are people happy with this
proof do anybody have any questions
so another form of marov which you uh
May often encounter is the
following so the probability that R is
at least uh C c times its
expectation is at most one over
C
okay for any positive
C so essentially equivalent statement
just you know you might sometimes see it
in this form
instead
okay so let's take a look at a couple
more examples
so
suppose or is uh the test score of a
randomly chosen student instead of the
road that they're sitting in
okay and uh suppose that these are all
in the range uh
say 30 to
100% okay
uh can we use
marov to bound the
probability that R is at least say
90% how might we do
that h
sorry I completely forgot to give you
the expectation the answer is
no
uh okay now can you do
it hopefully it's a little bit easier
now
mhm yeah so find the value of C such
that c c * 75 is
90 uh
so I guess 75 over or 90 divided
75 that's what's
1.2 is that right
uh 75 is 5 by 15 right 90 is 6 by 15
okay nice arithmetic score okay so then
uh using
uh this formulation here we
have the
probability that R is at least uh you
know 1.2 times
uh expectation of r
is at most 1 divid
1.2 okay so this is going to be you know
something like
83%
okay people reasonably happy with
that
yeah oh the question is um can we
explain the difference between these two
formulations
sorry uh so yeah essentially there is no
difference like there're just uh you
know different ways of of thinking about
uh thinking about the bound you can
either think about bounding it in terms
of some you know absolute threshold or
you can think about it as like in terms
of some you know relative threshold like
you know multiply the uh the expectation
by some by some scaling Factor okay so
you know depending on on which of them
feels more natural to you uh we could
also used the first formulation to say
you know
probability that R is greater than
90 greater than or equal to is going to
be at most uh 75 over
90 which you know same thing
83% okay so either of them Works they
both give the same answer they're
equivalent formulations it's just you
know whichever one you find easier to
think about question
yes exactly okay so the question was uh
we don't just have a non- negative
random variable R right we we've
actually got an even stronger bound R is
at least 30 not just at least zero okay
so can we leverage that to get an even
stronger
bound okay so how could we do
that well let's try def finding
different random
variable
so let R Prime be Rus
okay so this is another random variable
right we're just going to take our
original R we're going to subtract 30 um
we're not going to do this to people's
exam scores in reality don't don't worry
uh but that this makes the the minimum
exam score zero
right so the hope is that you know now
we're kind of satisfying the condition
to to markov's uh inequality like more
tightly so hopefully marov will give us
a tighter bound okay so what bound does
it give us now what is the
probability that R is at least 90
well what is that in terms of R Prime
what is that
event
yeah yeah so this is the same event and
so the same
probability that R Prime is at least
60 now what happens when we apply Markov
to
this well this is going to be at
most
right the expectation of RP Prime
ID
60 what is the expectation of R
Prime yeah 45
yeah so this is going to be the
expectation of R uh minus
30 / 60 which is the expectation so
linearity of expectation we can pull
this or like we can you know split this
into two expectations so this is the
expectation of
R minus the expectation of 30 there's
you know not really any Randomness
involved there it's just
30 over 60 right so this is
45 over 60
okay does that make sense to
everybody so now instead of this bound
of uh you know it's it's at most 83% now
we've got the better bound it's at most
75%
okay so by shifting our random variable
we've managed to get a tighter bound
okay what
about the probability that R is at most
yeah mhm
so that that's kind of what we're doing
right the the the question was uh in the
proof of Markov right we're assuming
that the lower bound is zero uh here
we've got a lower bound of 30 instead so
do we need to do something more
complicated the answer is no we don't
have to but if we do it gives us a
stronger result so that's what we've
done here but we don't have to do it
right because zero is still a valid
lower bound right we could still say we
could say that the co- domain of R is 0
to 100 instead of 30 to 100 even even if
the range stays
unchanged okay so it's still a non-
negative random variable so we're still
allowed to apply marov to it it's just
that you know doing it on r instead of R
Prime gives us a weaker
result okay does that make sense to
everybody another question
uh so the question is what do I mean by
by a tighter bound when when we shift R
uh so tighter in the sense that it is
stronger right so uh r at least 30
implies that R is at least zero so r r
at least 30 is a stronger condition than
than r at least zero
okay so that that's what I mean by
tighter uh so the the difference right
is how we're applying marov right uh we
are in the first case we're applying
marov to R directly in the second case
we are creating a new random
variable uh and we're applying marov to
that and you know because uh you know
we've got a a stronger condition like
the the marov markov's um what do you
call it precondition is is tight
now uh we can get a a stronger
result okay
yeah uh could it go higher than 83%
uh okay so we will get to that in a
moment the the question is you know if
we're in a different
situation uh could shifting it give us
something that's higher than
83% and the answer is yes
is right in the case where we've applied
Markov incorrectly the first time then
yes but uh you know if we've applied
Markov correctly then uh you know the
first is a valid bound right
right so you know we we could in
principle improve it but uh you know
we're not going to do any worse by you
know imposing tighter
conditions does that like at least kind
of intuitively make sense I'll give you
a more complete answer in a
moment any more questions about this
before we move on to the next
example
yeah yes
it is a good thing uh so the the
question is is it a good thing that the
75% is smaller than the
83% uh yes we are looking for an upper
bound on the probability right so a
smaller upper bound is a stronger
condition so that's that's better it's
um it's a it's a stronger bound you want
a smaller upper or AER so that they're
the same smaller upper bounds are
stronger upper bounds
yeah so like less than or equal to 83%
implies less than or equal to uh sorry
less than or equal to 75% implies less
than or equal to to 83% so 75 is is
stronger
okay okay have people had enough time to
think about the probability that R is at
most
65 how might we use marov to figure this
one out
yeah
okay so R greater than or equal to 66 so
if we assume integer
scores
okay
um and what does marov tell us about
this
well the probability that R
is at least
66 right is going to be at most 75 over
which is bigger than
one so applying marov does not tell us
anything useful it tells us that this is
a probability that's that's bounded by
one which we already
knew so it is a good idea it's not quite
what we want here
so what if instead of uh you know
fiddling with the event we fiddle with r
again kind of similar to what we did
before
yeah yeah exactly so we're going to flip
R right so we're going to define a new
random variable let's say s equals
100 minus r
okay so now the probability that R is at
most
65 is the probability that s is at least
what 100 minus 65
okay can we apply Markov to that
I'm seeing some nods does anybody want
to do that and spare me the trouble of
doing
arithmetic nobody sadness okay
uh well what does Markov say well it's
at most the expectation of
X oh sorry
s divided by
35 okay what is the expectation of s
well using linearity in the same way
that we did a moment
ago this is going to be equal to uh what
100 minus the expectation of R which is
75 over 35 so that's 25 over 35 this is
57s
okay so does does that make sense to
everybody there is at most a 57th chance
that you uh did worse than
okay now perhaps not terribly realistic
in terms of exam scores but uh you know
what if say some of the students did so
badly that they got scores that are less
than zero like maybe you've got uh you
know R is in the range you know minus 30
to
okay same deal expectation of r
is
75 uh question or
um sorry um okay so what can we say
about the probability that R uh is at
least uh say
90 mhm
yeah exactly so the observation was
right if we try to apply marov to this
maybe I should call it a different call
it something different let's call it
t so if we try to apply Markov to
T right it's going to be the same thing
as as when we applied Markov to R before
it'll give us a bound of of 83% the
problem is that that's wrong that does
it t does not satisfy the precondition
for
Markov okay so what we want to do
instead is
toine T Prime = t +
okay and now if we apply Markov to T
Prime what do we get so the probability
that uh T is greater than
90 is the probability
that t Prime is at least
okay and by Mark of this is going to be
uh
expectation of T
Prime over
120 okay and you know same deal as
before linearity here gives us uh 75 +
30 over
120 105 over 120 that's
78 is that
right
yeah
okay so in this case we do get a you
know in some sense a weaker bound than
we would have gotten by applying Markov
to to t you know directly but you know
applying Markov to T directly doesn't
actually work this you know looks weaker
but it's a correct bound okay so
hopefully that answers your question
more fully
okay does anybody have any
questions so even though we couldn't
apply Markov directly to T we can create
a new random variable T Prime to which
marov does
apply MH
yeah
uh so using the lower bound of 30 making
the
the the statement stronger for for t for
S oh for S uh which one was s uh s here
um so that does not really help us in
this case um because that kind of
corresponds to uh an upper
bound right rather than rather than the
lower bound uh and you know upper bounds
don't really appear in in the proof of
Markov like we're not really using them
in any way so you know imposing a
stronger upper bound doesn't really
doesn't really help okay does does that
kind of answer your question okay
cool
yeah uh okay is it always the case that
the best lower bound appears or sorry
the best upper bound I guess appears uh
when uh when the the range actually
includes
zero um essentially yes
okay as far as correct bounds go
anyway
okay
[Music]
so I guess there's a question of like
morally why do we need this this non-
negativity um
and perhaps a very simple illustrative
example is suppose we have the random
variable R which is uh plus or minus one
depending on you know a Fair coin flip
okay so it's it's
uniform on positive one and negative
1 okay so if we try to apply Markov to
to that
corly
right what does that tell us about the
probability that R is greater
than2 well if we try to apply marov
directly right the expectation of R is
zero so you know no matter what we put
here marov would try to tell us that you
know the probability is at most
zero okay that is clearly rubbish right
because you know R can be greater than
1/2 R takes value one with probability
1/2
okay so basically our proof uh where was
it
here so if we if we get rid of the non-
negativity constraint then this no
longer
works right we can't kind of discard
This this term because that zero you
know if we don't know that the the
random variable is non negative we could
in principle have a have a negative
value there which you know we we we
can't get rid of
okay so another
question is Markov tight
so in other
words can we make a stronger statement
than what marov tells us you know out of
the
tin just with you know the information
that we we have the mean and we have a
non- negative random
variable is there anything stronger that
we can
say who thinks
yes couple of tentative hands who thinks
no uh couple of less tentative tons who
has no
idea okay well let's let's think about
some some uh simple examples then okay
so let's go back to the uh cell phone
check problem from uh was it last week
don't remember which of the lectures
last week Tuesday Thursday both both
okay okay so if we consider the Lazy
Susan version
right and we let R be the number
of
people
who get their
phone okay so this is the Lazy
Susan
uh how could we use Markov to bound the
probability that everybody gets their
phone back
so if everybody gets their phone back
right that's R equals
n what does marov tell us about this
probability
yeah yeah it's the most one over
n why is that well the expectation of R
is one as we saw last week right the
bound we're looking at is
n okay so there's at most a one and
probability that everybody gets their
phone
back what is the actual probability that
everybody gets their phone
back
yeah yeah the actual probability is 1/ n
so this is tight okay we can't say
anything stronger than marov without
additional
information okay does that make
sense so if we know something else about
our distribution then we might be able
to say something more but if all we know
is the expectation and the the non-
negativity then Markov is the best that
we can
do
okay on the other hand you know suppose
suppose we're permuting all of the
phones instead of you know putting them
on the Lazy
Susan Okay so
so in this case what does marov tell us
about the uh probability that everybody
gets their phone
back it's still one over n right we've
still got uh a non- negative random
variable with the same mean we're still
looking at the same threshold right so
marov gives us the same bound
okay what is the actual probability that
everybody gets their phone back
well that's that's exactly when you have
the identity permutation right you've
got n factorial possible permutations
one of them gives everybody's phone
back so what we're looking for is
actually one/ n
factorial okay so so marov is is very
much not tight in this
example okay
okay so the next question is what can we
say if we do have more information about
uh about a random
variable so suppose we know the
variance okay so the variance of those
two distributions is very different
right uh in the case where we put the
the phones on the Lazy Susan we've got a
very high variance in the case where we
have a random permutation it's much
lower okay so maybe the variance can
tell us you know
more about these
probabilities okay so this is a
different tail bound uh due to Chubby
Chev
so
probability that R minus the expectation
of
R uh you know an absolute value is at
least
X is less than or equal to the variance
of
x /
x^2 okay
so note that we no longer require non-
negativity here we just require
information about the
variance okay and well the mean we have
to uh we have to compute it relative to
the
mean
okay so but but R can be any random
variable we're we're no longer
constrained to to looking at non-
negative ones it can be anything we just
have to compute the variance
okay how might we prove chubby shvs
inequality any
ideas is that a hand or a stretch
yeah yeah so we're we're going to prove
Chev using
marov okay so in order to use
marov what do we need well we need an
all negative random variable
okay so kind of similar to what we were
doing earlier with shifting our random
variable we're going to define a new
random variable that we can then apply
Markov to and that should give us this
result
here
okay does that make sense to
everybody
yeah oh variance of R sorry thank
you yes variance of X does not make any
sense
okay so what might be a useful random
variable that we can apply Markov
to well maybe here's a way we can kind
of
cheat
uh in markov's inequality what's the
bound that we get
the bound should be the expectation of
our random variable
right so can we Define a random variable
whose expectation is the variance of of
R
yeah yeah exactly so R Prime equals R
minus
expectation
squared okay
so this is non- negative right it's it's
a square of some
value uh its expectation you know by
definition is the variance of
R
okay and also if we kind of squint right
we can fiddle around with this to you
know actually threshold R Prime instead
of this absolute value thing that we've
got here how do we do
that well we just Square the stuff in
the absolute value right as the same
square as if we didn't have the absolute
value okay so the
probability that R minus its
expectation greater than or equal to
x equals the
probability that R
Prime is greater than or equal to
x^2 right because those are exactly the
same event
okay they're the same event so they have
the same
probability and now this looks like
something we can apply Markov to okay
less than or equal to the
expectation of R Prime
oops divided by
x^2 okay does that make sense to
everybody
so let's take a look at an
example so let's look at those test
scores
again oops sorry my bad
so our same deal we've got test
scores
expectation is what did we have 70 75
75 and say that that the
variance is
okay so now what can we
say about the probability that R is uh
most
65 any
ideas how how could we how could we
apply treby Chef to
this that doesn't quite look like the
theorem statement right
but we can observe that this is at most
the
probability that R is at most
or R is greater than or equal to
okay right if we take the union of two
events that Union has you know at least
the probability ility of one of those
two con constituent
events so this is only increasing the
probability if we add in this this extra
you
know extra half of the
event
okay and what do we know about this
probability how could we rewrite that in
a nicer
way
yeah
exactly so this is just saying R
deviates from its mean by at least 10
okay so now we've got it in the form
that chubby CHF
likes so we can apply chabby
Chev this is at most variance of
r divided
by uh our threshold is 10 yeah 10
squ okay
25 over 100
equals
one4
okay
now we've got a much stronger bound this
time than we did earlier Yeah question
ah okay so explain this
equality okay uh so R less than or equal
to 65 or R greater than or equal to
85 um we could rewrite this as you know
R minus uh well r -
75 is uh less than or equal to -10 and
this one is r - 75
greater than or equal to positive
10 okay um so you know if you absolute
value both of these you know they're
both you know greater than greater than
or equal to 10 okay does does that kind
of make sense
okay any other questions about uh about
this this example
so because we have more information than
we
had here right we can get a stronger
bound okay knowing the variance helps us
out so equivalently we could you know
rephrase this in terms of uh you know
standard
deviations uh um where would be a good
place to write
this how about
here so the
probability of
being at least two standard
deviations from the
mean is at most
1/4 okay
does anybody have any objections to that
last statement
so if you've uh taken a stats class you
probably heard something very different
from
that oh nobody nobody's taken
stats that's good high school stats is
terrible um um oh that's on camera um
never mind stats are great just uh it's
it's good that that you've saved it for
University instead of doing it in high
school
um okay so yeah if if you're looking at
a a you know a normal distribution right
you actually have a much a much better
bound than than 1/4 it's something like
you know a few
percent okay uh so why is
that any ideas
well for normal distribution right we
know a lot more about the uh about the
random variable than just its
variance okay so if we know more even
more about a random variable than its
variance it turns out we can make even
stronger
statements okay just like adding in the
variance was an upgrade from marov let's
see how we can upgrade this again
yeah what's upal distrib oh what's a
normal distribution uh think of a normal
distribution as um you know number of
heads if you flip a whole bunch of coins
it's that's not quite it but you know
roughly
speaking good
cutch oh okay
um
so
okay so yeah as I just said if you flip
a whole bunch of coins let your random
variable R be the the number of heads
right uh you know a lot more about uh
about this random variable than just its
variance right you're you can decompose
the random variable into a sum of a
whole bunch of
indicators okay and all of those
indicators are mutually
independent
okay
um in order to use chubby Chev right you
don't need Mutual Independence right if
you had something of that form you just
need parir wise Independence right like
you need to compute the
variance okay
but if on top of that you have mutual
Independence it turns out you can do a
lot
better okay so
suppose
uh T1 T2
T3 up to TN are mutually independent
random
variables and uh well let's say in
addition they're
bounded
um
okay and the random variable we actually
care about is T which is their
sum
okay
then oh and uh say we've also got some
threshold C which is at least
one uh the probability
that t is at least c times its
expectation uh close that as well less
than or equal to e to the
negative C log of C minus C +
times uh the
expectation of t
okay so a little bit of a
mouthful but what exactly is going on
here so basically marov was saying right
uh that the the probability that you you
know deviate from from the mean by a
large
amount uh it's at most you
know it's at most linear in in you know
how how far you're you're you're
deviating okay Chev said it's uh you
know at most quadratic this is saying
it's at most exponential or like inverse
exponential okay so you have a much
stronger condition that gives you a much
stronger bound
okay uh and how could we prove
it not like this
any ideas
maybe a proof sketch we we won't go
through the entire proof
so what what tools do we have already
what might we be able to do
well what happens if we apply
Markov how can we apply
Markov in order to use Markov right we
need a non- negative random
variable so in order to prove chubby
right we uh you know took a square that
made something non-
negative what might be a reasonable
thing to try in this
case
yeah add
one uh okay so
look at t + one instead of uh instead of
T so that's actually going to that's not
going to help us right T is already the
sum of a bunch of non- negative random
variables so it's already non- negative
right like we're we're not looking to
you know turn a non- negative or sorry
turn an arbitrary random variable into a
non negative one we are trying to find a
more
useful uh non- negative random
variable okay
yeah
yeah take the log of both sides close
what happens if we
exponentiate
so take T Prime equals c to the T
what do we know about t
Prime for
well we're taking something that's at
least one right or you know raising it
to some positive power well some non-
negative
power
okay so T Prime is a non negative random
variable
do we know anything more about
it yeah it's at least one
yeah so maybe we try applying markup to
this okay so now we've got a random
variable that takes values in the range
from 0 to uh C the n c the N minus
one
okay now how could we rewrite this
condition T greater than or equal to C
* expectation of T in terms of T Prime
well because C is at least one
right exponentiation is
monotone so this is the same as you know
C to the T greater than or equal to uh C
to the C *
expectation of
T
okay and we don't have too much time so
I think I will refer you to the book if
you are interested but the the main idea
right
is this step here
okay you take the random variable you
care about and you exponentiate
it okay and then if you apply apply
Markov to that right it actually gives
you a much stronger bound like you know
if you're if you're using the the mutal
independence of all of the component
random variables
right this will give you a much stronger
bound than uh than even Shoff okay so I
promised you last week that uh you know
we would revisit the uh the coin tosses
so let's do that
briefly okay so
suppose R is the
number of
heads uh if you flip end coins
okay so if you recall we were looking at
uh the
probability that R is uh equal to you
know n
over4
before okay so or maybe
equivalently three over
4 might be a better way to
to
analogize okay and I promised you that
we would
revisit this probability R greater than
or equal to 3 n /
okay now what happens if we apply
uh each of our three tail bounds to
R well first what happens with
Markov so let's call this p
p is at most
what well the probability that R is at
least you know some
threshold it's going to be the
expectation of
r divided by this
threshold okay what's the expectation of
R and over
two
okay so this is going to be 2/3
what about chubby
shf so similar to what we did with the
first chbby Chev
example right p is going to be at most
the probability that uh R differs from
its it expectation in either
direction right by
n/4
okay so what does that give us uh
probability R minus let's say over
two
uh greater than or equal to n
over4 is at most
bar of
r divided by uh n over 4^
s okay so what is the uh what is the
variance of r
does anybody
remember we've got a sum of a bunch of
indicators right they're all mutually
independent so the variance is
linear what's the variance of a single
indicator
nobody yeah
yeah n over four oh for for R not for a
single
one
okay so n over 4 / n^2 over
16 equal 4
n
okay so much better right much better
than the 2/3 we just
got what happens if we use turnoff
okay any
ideas
yeah plug in three halves for C so c
equal 3
Hales okay
uh okay um why don't I uh put TR off
back up
here
uh
okay and what does that give us
probability that uh R is is at least 3es
time expectation of
R is less than or equal to e to the
minus is it C log
C minus C + 1 so this is a constant
times the expectation of
R
okay so the expectation of r R is n
/2 right this is a constant so we've got
something that's exponential or inverse
exponential in
N oops
uh e to the minus order
n
okay so marov gives us gave us a really
bad found chabby Chev you know
linear pretty reasonable turn off gives
us
exponential okay so that's all we have
time for today sorry I went a little bit
overtime uh it's been a pleasure
teaching you all this semester um and uh
let's see we have uh the rest of our
instructors and at least one ta hello
Lily uh yeah if anything went wrong it
was probably my fault um anything that
went right uh you have your Tas to thank
for it um including Lily ly Lily's
amazing um so yeah perhaps I will see
some of you uh next term in uh in 61 121
um good luck on the final make sure you
take the right one uh thanks for being
students in this class it's been lots of
fun yeah
[Applause]