Good morning, everybody.
It's really nice to
see you all here.
Thank you for joining us.
I'm Nergis Mavalvala and I'm the
Dean of the School of Science
here at MIT.
I share President
Kornbluth's excitement
and wonder at all that we have
achieved in the life sciences
at MIT over the past decade.
MIT has been a place where
fundamental knowledge
and understanding
of biology happens,
where rapid conversion
from ideas to discovery
to translation happens, where
computation and policy meet
science and engineering
comfortably,
where innovation is
a natural destination
on the journey from
discovery to societal impact.
As well as we do all of this,
as you heard from Sally,
we know we can do better.
And I couldn't be more energized
to be here with you today
to celebrate and
dream of the future
that the MIT HEALS
Collaborative will help create.
By catalyzing collaborations
in fields like immunology,
neuroscience, AI,
sustainability, and healthcare,
and strengthening MIT's
ties with Boston's
extraordinary hospitals
and industry leaders
in biotech and pharma, the
MIT HEALS Collaborative
aims to spur discoveries
with broad and lasting
real-world impact.
Now, you couldn't come
up with a better example
that aligns with those ideals
than our very own Dr. Phil
Sharp.
He has been at the vanguard, not
only of scientific discovery,
but also MIT's collaborations
with biotech, biopharma,
the healthcare industry,
his entire career.
Now, before I tell you
a bit more about Phil,
let me say a few words about how
the MIT HEALS Collaborative came
about.
It does involve Phil,
as many wonderful things
that happen in the life
sciences at MIT does.
Little over three years ago,
at the instigation of many wise
colleagues and friends of MIT--
and many of you are in the room
here today--
Dean Chandrakasan and I
charged a faculty-led committee
to study what we
might do better,
to coordinate all the fabulous
but disparate work in the life
sciences being
carried out at MIT,
and also how might we
better nurture and curate
collaborations with
the life sciences
research being carried out
in the biotech and hospitals
around us.
That study, led by professors
Tyler Jacks and Kristala
Prather, culminated
in the VITALS report.
VITALS stands for Vision to
Integrate, Translate and Advance
the Life Sciences.
A key finding of that report was
the hunger among MIT researchers
for more opportunities
to collaborate
across disciplinary boundaries.
The opportunities identified
and the recommendations
of the VITALS report were
embraced by President Kornbluth.
And with the prodigious
energy of our chief innovation
and strategy officer,
Dean Chandrakasan,
here we are today embarking
on a truly vital endeavor.
Upon hearing of the faculty's
interest in collaborating
with each other and with
our award-winning hospital
systems, the Kendall Square
biotech ecosystem, and beyond,
Phil set to work helping
us build those bridges.
A pivotal moment for me was a
gathering where a group of us
were brainstorming about what
this collaborative effort might
look like and what big
ideas would we lead with.
Lots of ideas were
being batted around.
At one point, Phil
challenged the group.
What do we do best
at MIT, he asked.
Everyone in the room must have
had their favorite answer,
but only Phil had an answer
so succinct and fundamental
and yet so universal
for us here at MIT.
We measure, he declared.
As a physicist, I can
admit I have never
directly peered into a
microscope and seen a cell.
But I do know measurement, and
that resonated tremendously.
Our obsession with
inquiry, with observation,
quantitative characterization,
experimentation, discovery,
and invention were all
wrapped into those words.
At MIT, we measure.
It's part of MIT's secret sauce
that Nancy Andrews alluded to
in the video you saw at the
beginning of our session.
It's what makes me so optimistic
about the unimagined discoveries
waiting to be made when we
bring seemingly disparate ideas
and tools together
through cross-disciplinary
collaborations.
This is the promise of the
MIT HEALS Collaborative.
And I'm very grateful to
Phil for his clarity, wisdom,
and encouragement as we
embark on this endeavor.
For those of you who
don't yet know Phil,
let me introduce him to you.
Dr. Phil Sharp is an
Institute professor
at MIT in the Koch Institute
for Integrative Cancer Research.
He is also the chair of the
advisory board for the MIT Abdul
Jameel Clinic for Machine
Learning in Health, or J Clinic.
In 1993, he shared the Nobel
Prize in physiology of medicine
for the discovery
of split genes.
These are genes that--
the genes in DNA are not
one contiguous segment
of information as
they are in bacteria.
In fact, they are split.
And that messenger RNA
has to be processed
by splicing before it can be
translated into a protein.
This fundamental discovery
would alter the course
of how we understood genetic
disease and the development
of potential treatments.
In 2004, for this
work, he was awarded
the National Medal of Science.
You'll learn more about that
discovery from Phil shortly.
At MIT, he joined the Center
for Cancer Research in 1974,
serving as the director
from 1985 to 1991,
before becoming the head of
the Department of Biology
for eight years.
He was also the
founding director
of the McGovern Institute
for Brain Research
from 2000 to 2004.
Phil co-founded Biogen,
serving on its board for nearly
30 years, as well as Alnylam
Pharmaceuticals, a leader in RNA
interference-based therapies
with Professor Bartel
and Professor Emeritus Paul
Schimmel and MIT postdocs.
Phil is an elected member of the
National Academies of Sciences,
the National
Academies of Medicine,
the American Academy of Arts
and Sciences, the American
Philosophical Society, and
the Royal Society of the UK.
His accolades, his advisory
board service, his awards,
and most importantly, his
500-plus research papers are too
numerous to recount in
the time that we have.
Even with our ample
measurement skills at MIT,
it would be truly hard to
measure his impact on biology
at MIT and beyond.
Please join me in welcoming
Professor Phil Sharp.
[APPLAUSE]
Wow.
[LAUGHTER]
What a day.
What a way to start
a beautiful day.
I couldn't be more excited.
I couldn't be more enthusiastic
about MIT, MIT HEALS,
and what it's going to mean for
patients, people, the country,
Massachusetts, and MIT.
What I want to do in
the next few moments
is to give you a brief
overview of a journey
that I think tells you why this
initiative is so important.
I know I'm going to be
looking backwards and setting
the stage for what you're going
to hear today, looking forwards.
But I do think it
illustrates why we're here
and what we hope
continues to come out
of this great collaboration,
of which I am sure it will.
So I'm going to look
back over 50 years.
50 years is when the
Center for Cancer research
was established here at MIT.
I'm going to bring that
journey to where we're at now.
And I'm trying to emphasize what
changes, what major initiatives,
had this impact.
I have conflicts of interest.
Alnylam is the only one that I
will mention some relevant data
to.
Let's look back
at the late 1950s.
MIT's leadership looked at
the Department of Biology
and decided that in the
future, biology at MIT
will be gene-oriented, molecular
biology, driven mechanistically,
incorporating chemistry and
physics into this marvelous
discovery of the structure
of DNA by Watson and Crick
in Rosalind Franklin's data.
And that led to the recruitment
of Salvador Luria to MIT.
Salva was a founder
of molecular biology,
the mentor of Jim Watson, and
came to MIT in the late 1950s
with other faculty and people
at MIT to create what is
the Department of Biology today.
In early 1970s, Salvador Luria
led a number of people at MIT
to apply for a basic cancer
research center here.
This is after the National
Cancer Institute Act
in Congress.
Leading that initiative was
Luria and Dave Baltimore
in molecular cell
biology and virology,
Herman Eisen in immunology, and
Phil Robins in cell biology.
Here in the early '70s,
the pillars of much of what
we're talking about in health
care, molecular immunology,
cell biology, was established
here as a basic cancer center.
And remarkably, the culture
of this cancer center
is a culture of MIT.
It's a culture of
collaborative interaction,
of people sharing ideas,
sharing initiatives.
What is shown here on
the slide is the group
of molecular cancer biologists
in the Cancer Center with Dave
Baltimore peeking
down at the left,
Bob Weinberg over his shoulder.
I'm up on the right side.
But this was a collaborative
group of sharing ideas--
an MIT mode of science.
And it had an enormous effect.
Dave Baltimore received a
Nobel Prize in 1975, one year
after the establishment
of the Cancer Center.
And then Susumu Tonegawa, who
was recruited to the Cancer
Center--
shortly thereafter
another Nobel Prize.
After that-- and
then Bob Horowitz
at MIT, who was in the
Department of Biology
and a member of the
cancer center, also
received a Nobel Prize in the
period of the Cancer Center
in its site in the chocolate
factory on Ames Street.
I want to illustrate why this
initiative of the Cancer Center
was so timely.
Here in the early 1970s,
there was the beginning
of the understanding that
the pillars of biology--
which was the central
dogma illustrated here--
as DNA information flowing
to RNA flowing to protein,
had just been established
by Jacoby Meno in 1961.
And what you see here
is a simple diagram--
that the RNA is being copied
from the DNA in a colinear way
and proteins translated from it.
And there is a sugar that is
metabolized by these proteins
and that sugar regulates
the expression of this gene.
This is how we understood
molecular biology in the early
1970s.
But we thought that the world
was more complex than that.
When we started talking about
multicellular organisms--
was the gene and how it
was expressed the same
in multicellular organisms?
And there were hints-- and
I won't go through those--
that there was
something different.
And that, for example, led to
the understanding and discovery
that genes in our systems
have different structures.
They are split.
And they are expressed
by an intermediate step
of the splicing of the RNA,
removing the dashed lines shown
at the top of the slide,
and joining the black boxes.
The black box is the sequences
that code for the protein.
So here, the complexity of
the genome and complexity
of how it's expressed
and how it's regulated
was much more complex
than it was in bacteria.
And it led us to
understand that we
were in a new territory of
understanding disease processes.
I also want to note, the
splicing pattern on those genes
vary from cell to cell and
condition to condition.
And therefore, even though
we have 23,000 genes,
we have many more proteins.
They vary between cells
from those proteins
by alternative splicing and they
carry out different functions.
And we're just in the
last several years
able now to look at a
single cell and say,
this is exactly what the gene
is expressed at in those cells.
But also in the
same time period,
in 1975, we had this
convergence or confluence
of remarkable discoveries that
created synthetic biology--
the ability to make organisms
that had never existed before.
And that was this
recombinant DNA technology--
DNA sequencing and
chemical synthesis.
So we could take DNA and
we could make new genes
and we can put
genes in organisms.
This technology was
recognized to be
a transformational technology.
And the first biotech
community or company
that was established
in 1976, Genentech,
was by Bob Swanson
and Herb Boyer.
Swanson, an MIT graduate--
Boyer, as a scientist
at San Francisco--
led to this
foundation of biotech
and the whole biotech industry.
And I had the pleasure of
collaborating with Wally Gilbert
at Harvard and six
European scientists
in establishing Biogen in 1978.
The idea here is, this
technology had been
developed in academic labs.
And it wasn't going
to benefit anyone
until it was translated
into the private sector,
gained capital and
investment, recruit people,
and make a difference
in people's life.
Be innovative in
this technology.
And that led to
Biogen first being
established in Geneva in 1978.
When the situation became a
little clearer in Cambridge
as to what you could do with
recombinant DNA In the early
'80s, this moved to Cambridge.
And what I show you here is what
Cambridge looked like in 1975.
What you see to
the right of that
is Main Street and
MIT across the street.
But you see a large parking lot.
A parking lot, for
historical reasons, was open.
And Biogen began in a little
building on Binney Street
on the left side of that slide.
So here, Cambridge was the site
in which this new technology
was beginning to nucleate.
Genzyme and other companies
established in the same area
shortly after or
at the same time.
But then it grew
and it consolidated
and it collaborated.
And that became the Kendall
Square area in 2012,
where that same
space is now occupied
by companies that are
making marvelous advances
in important ways.
And as Sally said,
it happened because
of the great universities,
the hospitals
across the street with
remarkable faculty
and clinicians, and the New
England finance and venture
capital acceptance.
This continued to grow.
We're the most concentrated
biotech community in the world.
Life science-- it's
a remarkably dynamic,
collaborative, networking
community that is reflecting
a very important part.
And I forgot to mention,
it wouldn't have happened
if it wasn't for MIT engineers.
MIT engineers allowed us
to take these products
and make new components of it.
So all of this happened.
And now we see what
Cambridge is like.
I should illustrate
here in 2018 that
large pharmaceutical companies,
research stations, research
institutes, have moved
into the community.
And there's probably
50 or more small to
medium-sized biotech companies.
Biogen has grown.
And Alnylam, which I'm going
to talk about in a moment,
and then Broad--
I'm going to talk
about immediately--
as additions to
this community that
empowered a lot of
remarkable advances.
So we move to 2000, the
turn of the century.
And biotech took on
another acceleration
in the country because of the
development of the human genome
initiative and the
human genome sequence.
And it's interesting to think
about the origins of that work.
Whitehead was
established in 1985.
It was a new institute
relationship to MIT.
MIT was open to bringing new
resources and new structures
to being part of
the community at MIT
at the Whitehead Institute.
Excuse me.
Dave Baltimore recruited
Eric Lander, who
started the genome initiative.
And that genome initiative then
moved with additional resources
to the Broad Institute, which
is across the street from MIT--
associated with MIT and Harvard.
Again, a collaboration.
And that led in 2003, with an
international initiative highly
influenced and led by
the Broad Institute,
to the whole human
genome sequence.
This was a accelerator because
then we had in our hand
the sequence of every gene--
the sequence of the genome.
And we could begin to
integrate complex genetics
and molecular tools into
this identification of--
this powerful technology
of recombinant DNA.
This allowed us to more
rapidly translate our science
and our technology
into patients.
And just to illustrate
how that happened
or the consequence of that,
I will speak about a subject
that appeared in 2000, and that
is with the genome sequence.
In previous science,
it was recognized
that our cells encode another
500 or more genes that we
didn't know about, that
encoded small RNAs.
These small RNAs were
called microRNAs.
The initial discovery
of the first
was in 1993 out of Gary Ruvkun
and Victor Ambros' [INAUDIBLE]
network.
It was done initially
with collaboration
in Bob [INAUDIBLE] lab.
And out of that came this
discovery of microRNAs.
And as you will note, that was
recognized by a Nobel Prize
in this year, 2024.
This microRNA pathway is
present in every cell.
It was totally unrecognized
until the 2000s by David Bartel
and others.
And it has become a major
regulatory-- involved in cancer,
involved in many processes.
And then at the
same time, in 1998,
there was a discovery by Fire
and Mello of the fact that
double-strand RNA--
most RNA is single
stranded in the cell.
But you can see double strand.
And double-strand
RNA from a gene
will silence the expression of
that gene in many organisms.
Their work was done in
the worm C. elegans,
but it was soon recognized
that that work interdigitated
with the microRNA work.
And this led us to
an understanding
that there was another
biochemical system
in the cell we didn't know.
Andy Fire was a grad
student here at MIT,
but did the work
after he left MIT.
Using that work, and with
David Bartel and Phil Zamore
and Tom Tuschl, postdocs, and
Paul Schimmel's influence,
it became recognized
that this whole process
of silencing a gene
with RNA offered
a new therapeutic modality.
We could use the natural pathway
in the cell, design a drug--
siRNA-- from the
sequence, and then
treat a patient if the
modulation of that gene
would have an impact.
So that was just another way of
possibly benefiting patients.
And that led to then the
establishment of Alnylam,
and the confrontation
that the big problem here
was delivery of the RNA.
We turned to engineers and other
chemists to solve that problem.
Delivery of RNA into
cells is difficult
because RNA is hydrophilic
and your cell has
a membrane that's hydrophobic.
And therefore you have to
transport the RNA into the cell.
But once it's in the cell, it
will enter the microRNA pathway
and carry out-- if it's
complementary to the messenger
RNA--
destruction of the messenger
RNA and then be catalytic.
So the big issue
here was, could you
introduce this RNA into cells?
And that led to the development
of lipid nanoparticles, which
look like a virus.
They have a cationic
lipid of a certain type.
Pieter Cullis taught us--
that is a Canadian scientist
who made major contributions
to this.
Impacting the RNA into
these nanoparticles
would, with the right ionic
pH and PK, give you then
a change in conformation
of those lipids
as the particle enters the cell.
In your blood system,
you have a pH of seven.
In the cell, it's nearly a
pH of 5 in this endosome.
And that creates
this transition.
That same technology--
similar technology
was used in the
vaccination in COVID that
rescued us from the pandemic.
It has then been used to
treat billions of patients.
Here again, you see
the collaborations
between molecular
discovery, to innovation,
to the translation
to benefit patients.
And then other people using
those insights to further solve
a major societal
problem in the pandemic.
So that brings me
to looking forward
at what you're going to hear
in the next several hours
from my remarkable
colleagues here at MIT.
And that's what we've
called convergence.
With the discoveries of the
structures of sequences of DNA
and the genome pathways
and the cell mechanisms
by which the cell carries out
communications between cells,
we have the makings--
not a complete understanding,
but the makings--
of how the cell works
and the components.
And if we look back over time,
that's a product of research
from the mid '50s--
as recruitment of Luria--
the establishment
of the institutes,
research advances,
discoveries of multiple types.
And then we are at a
stage in which engineering
can take those components
and add to our tools
and understanding
these processes.
Adding AI can change how we
can empower our scientists
to benefit patients
to solve problems.
And that's what we've
called convergence.
And it's what MIT HEALS is
a major component in making,
and it is the future
of life science.
And it's a future of benefiting
a large number of patients.
The Koch Institute is one
of the examples that have
been established around it.
You will hear more
today about the Koch
Institute and its technology.
But its faculty
are a combination
on every floor of engineers,
life scientists, chemists,
and physicists.
We are a very interdisciplinary,
integrated institute.
But if you look at the McGovern
Institute in Brain Research--
the Picower in brain research,
the Reagan Institute,
you see this integration
of technology
and molecular cell
and cell biology,
and the whole premise of
looking outward and impacting
on patients.
And it is a remarkable,
remarkable--
and I should include
the Reagan Institute--
a remarkable set of institutes
associated with MIT.
No other institute
that I know of
has been able to create this
body of collaborative institutes
in a community with such a
powerful biotech community
and hospitals that is looking
forward, as our governor said,
in making MIT--
Massachusetts-- keeping it an
absolute leader in this space.
So innovation continues.
Here is just the number of
companies over the last--
from 2007 to now.
That faculty in the Koch has
continued to use technology--
to make discoveries
in technology
and translate to patients.
And that is the continued
engagement with society,
changing the outcome
of our patients
in our country with
this technology.
So I am really grateful to have
this chance to speak with you.
Everything I've
talked about is a, we.
Everything has been done by
collaboration with many people--
with faculty, with our
students, our postdocs.
I show you here
reunions of my lab
over the last 30 or so years.
All of MIT and all
of my colleagues
have contributed to
making this moment.
And I am terribly excited
about what MIT HEALS means
for MIT and for the country.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]