good evening everybody again uh thank
you so much for joining our diverse
views at MIT Sloan uh our
lgbtq alumni and current student panel
so our moderator this evening uh is
sukasa who is a part of the MBA class of
20125 um uh who give a brief intro about
uh themselves and then introduce you to
our panelists for the evening so sukasa
the floor is now
yours okay so let's get started so hi
everyone it's my pleasure to be here
with these amazing panelists my name is
SCA I'm the second year MBA student at
MIT St and my program is a dual degree
with um the MIT ston and Howard Kennedy
School so before I came to St my
background is Consul team and this past
summer I did internship at the
government of Jordan in Middle East
supported them in creating um Innovation
ecosystem here at St I serve as the VP
of admission at Pride so that's yeah
let's go to the yeah the everyone's
introduction so next slide
please so would you mind introduce
yourself for
each sweet I guess I'll go first um
thank you sucasa very much for sort of
organizing or leading this panel um as a
quick introduction I'm Austin deay I am
in lgo or leaders for Global operations
uh graduate from
2022 prior to Sloan I was a mechanical
design engineer um working on various
medical devices and then immediately
after went to work for a product
development consulting firm where I was
both part engineer and product manager
sort of leading client relationships on
various engineering
projects um more recently I switched
roles and I'm now an engineering manager
at intuitive surgical where we sort of
design and develop uh medical robotics
uh products um in my role currently it's
uh a lot of leadership of sort of
younger novice Engineers focused on
their Career Development as well as
leading various projects as related to
some of our medical devices and I'm
happy to be here to answer any and all
questions so next is Zoe hello everybody
I'm Zoe Abid Boyd and I was a 2023 MBA
graduate prior to Sloan I started my
career at Fisher Investments and I was
there for six and a half years in their
institutional group and I started as an
entrylevel analyst there was nobody who
was focusing on environmental social
governance investing and I watched a TED
Talk where it was like fake it t make it
so I was like I'm the
ESG expert uh and then over the last six
years that kind of became the truth uh
and I ended by managing their ESG
program so back then that was about $30
billion spread across 26 funds in four
continents and that was a load of fun um
post loan I'm at Goldman Sachs and I'm
in their private Wealth Management Group
and so I help families as well as
nonprofits think through all elements of
their financial careers and that's been
a lot of fun
L hi guys uh good morning good evening
uh wherever you're calling in from so
I'm calling in from Singapore so I see a
bunch of folks from from Asia as well
and cuos to the Indian folks because
it's really early for you guys um yeah
so I am leet I am a 23 MBA um just uh
just graduated last year but feels a lot
longer than that prior to SLO for or the
earlier part of my career I was at IBM
during Tech Consulting um and then kind
of just before Sloan and we well Zoe and
I joined uh around the right after the
whole pandemic um piece so all that
confusion lots of stuff happen happening
around there um uh and I ended up with a
startup So currently uh I'm still doing
that I did that through Sloan as well um
the co-founder and CEO of safe space um
that's qu in Singapore but we operate uh
in about 20 countries right now so we're
a mental health startup uh providing T
Health um and counseling uh mental
health uh counseling and
education uh for folks in varus
countries mainly focused on uh the Asia
Pacific region so yeah that's what I've
been up
to
Drew hello everyone um happy to talk
with you this morning evening um before
SLO I was working as a CPA at
PWC um kind of in
Consulting and I joined as an MBA 22
because I wanted to somewhat similar to
Zoe to Pivot my career into renewable
energy specifically um kind of project
finance and excited to talk all about
that experience it led me to Marathon
Capital where I did a couple years in
Investment Banking right after
graduation here in Chicago and then I
just um as of kind of two months ago
transitioned to work at a battery energy
storage developer also based in Chicago
called HEC grid where I um lead kind of
m&a processes project financing um and
other internal Finance processes so
first question for the panelist is why
you chose Stone so what was your
motivation to um come to the stone like
when you like thinking out the the
school so let's go with
Austin yeah absolutely um I think mainly
due to the ability for me to get that
dual degree between the you know diving
technical knowing that I enjoyed and
loved engineering but also recognizing
that in my own career I wanted to sort
of develop that ership toolkit to sort
of further develop and and cultivate you
know the skills of others and being able
to do both of those together in a
two-year program was very very enticing
um which is sort of what ultimately led
me to wanting to go to this R
Salon thank you how about the The
Zo yeah um well I was not also in lgo I
loved having lgo friends so that was a a
nice part of the program just all being
in classes together I think um there was
a couple things like I think the way
Sloan was structured even with their
application uh it it was to explore and
learn and be curious so I loved that it
was the only school that I was looking
at that did not ask what your
future plans were like you know other
schools are like tell me your one-ear
plan your three-year plan but I think
you know Sloan is all about exploration
discovery and also what I think is a
little bit more realistic is you're not
really sure and so I love that the core
semester was a semester you know other
other schools it's like an entire year
so you know we had the required
curriculum but then beyond that we could
do all sorts of different things another
thing that appealed to me was the
entrepreneurship uh I took a lot of
classes in the Martin trust Center and
uh if if any of you are thinking about
that I highly advise Bill Let's class
Paul Chek they excellent professor
um and I think also just when I visited
the campus it just like people just came
up to me they're like oh hi like why are
you here like do you need help like do
you want directions and I was like oh
I'm just here to learn more about the
school and they engaged with me and
talked with me in a way that I didn't
see at some of the other schools I
visited so I would say the culture of
career and exploration the
entrepreneurship and the collaborative
environment
that's true um the first the first um
Point zo mentioned like um MIT won't ask
you about the future goal in the
admission um um admission like a
application um they they they always say
um the past achievement is will show the
the um the what you going to do like for
the future and your capability for that
so I think it's quite um different
things that of the MIT St from the
different
schools how about you okay just one more
100% like I didn't go to Sloan being
like I'm going to be a private wealth
adviser Goldman Sachs I had some ideas
of things I wanted to do I worked on a
startup I went through mit's Delta V
accelerator program I thought I wanted
to do VC like but the point I'm getting
across is there was just there was a lot
of room to explore and I wasn't pigeon
to hold into one
thing great how about you Linette what
was your motivation to come to SL oh I
wanted to be around a bunch of nuts like
me
yeah so I stayed on the I stayed in the
Doms um and I felt like I was on the set
of Big Bang Theory uh with the rest of
of MIT um uh and their equations on the
walls and all that uh yeah but yeah okay
to to be honest it was more around the
well both the intersection of tech and
and um entrepreneurship um I did my
startup through through Sloan um and I
want all the support from that and what
I loved is yes I did a love the
entrepreneurship classes so I go to
class in in in the day and then straight
away I can apply stuff that uh we
learned from the professors who were
largely all practitioners and had their
own startups as well or or well no
longer startups but by then huge
companies um and apply it uh with my
business right at night so a lot of that
around that and I I I do
um zo Point as well but books are just
really
nice
yeah thank you
JW yeah for me I very similar to Zoe I
kind of had an idea of what I wanted to
do going into my MBA I wanted to
transition my career into sustainability
but didn't exactly know what that would
look like in terms of type of company
and what my role would be within that
company and so I kind of immediately was
drawn to Sloan because it had one of the
first and strongest kind of bestd
developed sustainability programs out of
really really any MBA program you could
compare it to so that was one of the
first things and then I was really sold
I um was able to visit campus actually
at an lgbtq visit day which was which
was perfect um but there's just
something different about kind of once
you get to campus once you join the
class everything else that's got that
happened you know everyone doesn't
really care what your prior career was
or what your prior work was it's really
what are you going to make of your
program going forward and everyone was
there to support you to make that
transition or make that change it really
felt like a a very supportive not
cutthoat at all culture and so the
combination of the program with the
people I really wanted to be around
there just really wasn't another program
that had both those things for
me that's that's really true um like for
me also I feel that way I'm very
tightnit community and supportive and we
are quite close to each
other so next question is about the the
your experience in the community as
longan so um for the lgbtq students we
have the long pride and we I want to ask
about your experience and mement into
the the St Pride or other kind of the
community here
so the we can ask the L how was your
experience in the community in
thr yeah um I mean to be honest I wasn't
that active with a lot of um slown sub
communities right but um from the first
after settling it for a couple of months
um uh I I decided to go for an impromptu
hike with some folks from SLO pride and
right after that I ended up going for
everything that was organized by by them
um and in my second year I was part of
the admissions team um as well within PR
even though I had no intention on
joining a student group to that level
just with the just with the my work
commitments as well um yeah so Pride was
really the only student grp that I was
very dedicated to let say um lots of
nice uh lots of great folks um that I'm
still in contact with uh and we we did a
lot of things together I think um I see
some questions also around like like
activities that were were done like
Halloween nights uh RBA was huge for um
folks who um look into recruiting and
also meeting uh private folks from the
other the other business schools as well
so highly recommend attending that as
well
um and yeah uh we had very good
precedence as well the year that um yeah
the years that we're around um what I
also like about pride is that they were
very welcoming to uh SOS or and part
Partners as well um it feels like they
they're an extens they are an extension
of of the SLO community and sometimes
it's nice you just hang out with the
part you hang out the partners sometimes
more than the students if they are
studying too much or stuff um
yes so that's my my involvement with SL
PR
least thank you lyette um what about you
zoy how about your involvement and
experience in the community here in
stone yeah yeah no I'm smiling at the
Lynette's comment because uh you know we
obviously the same year we're good
friends and um one of our our Pride's
co-presidents was actually an so so I
couldn't Echo enough how welcoming the
group is to partner
and you know I've been thinking about
this a lot this week because I knew I
was going to speak on this panel and I'm
a year out and it's funny because the
experience was incredible there uh it
was the first time in my life that I was
actually part of a pride group and I
think I'm only in hindsight realizing
how impactful that was so you know
growing up I remember you know my
brother went to the University of
Chicago he's four years older than me I
looked up to him at the time he was like
my mentor poor and you know my family's
liberal they don't like they didn't care
that I was gay but he said you know oh
like gay people you know it's fine I
don't care they're gay but they're just
so obsessed with being gay um and he
said that to me when I was in high
school and I remember like I think I
internalized I was like oh crap I I
don't want to be one of those gay people
that's always being gay and so
unbeknownst to me I spent like the first
like before Sloan the first half of my
professional career kind of covering
being gay um it's one of the weird uh
you know we're minorities and for what
you know but we can hide it you know I
can I can be straight if I if I need to
be in a certain situation um and I don't
think it was until I went to the first
Pride Retreat like echoing what Lynette
said and I just I
immediately felt the power of having
everyone in a room who has a shared
experience one of the Fantastic things
about Sloan which I don't know if we've
mentioned is like how diverse it is like
I think my year was like 43%
International so I'm in a room with
people you know from Singapore from
India and Korea and all over the world
and in a lot of ways like we have lives
that aren't similar but we all kind of
without like we we don't need to talk
about we just sort of have this Mutual
understanding and connection and I felt
that immediately through the slone pride
group um so you know in terms of events
they have a fall Retreat and we we rent
out a huge cabin and spend the whole
weekend together they have a Spring
retreat to providenc toown Rhode Island
which I didn't know until I went that's
like a a gay town and a really fun place
to be and going through all of those
different activities was incredibly
meaningful to
me yeah we we in the St Pride we have
the different type of the events like a
small gathering to um the big um The
Retreat like go into the some um big
house and we going to stay there and we
have the different type of activities
there so which is quite nice for me also
so I want to shift the topic to the
about the recruiting and the any like
kind of resources to support the lgbtq
students in the recruiting so um how
about your experience
htin if you use any um resources to
support your recruiting
Journey yeah I might this is probably
not the best person the anth this
because maybe I'm a littleit of an
oddball but I didn't use too many
resources at the time however I
recognized afterwards that there were
several you know certainly to Drew's
Point there's the lgbtq visit day which
can be super impactful to kind of
experience slan and understand maybe
even what the Prides Community is all
about and even at MIT as a whole there
are other additional resources such as I
think the websites lgbtq mit.edu
that has several different resources to
prepare you as a queer student on campus
um and
so I wish I'd capitalize and utilize
those as trying to learn more
information um and I think those are
something that we should you know talk
about more and people should
utilize thank you how about your
experience
through do did you use any kind of
resources like a for the the support
yeah um like many other kind of top
Business Schools slan um attends Ramba
which I think glennette mentioned
earlier which if you're not um familiar
with Ramba it's kind of the largest MBA
Gathering um for lgbtq folks it's
usually in October or November um and so
that's a great opportunity especially
kind of depending on what recruiting
cycle you're looking at it kind of gets
you in the door sooner um pretty much
every company will start filling their
summer internship spots with folks from
Ramba before kind of opening their their
General application so that's a um a
great thing to get plugged into even um
on your first couple days and weeks at
Sloan and slan pride always sends a huge
contingent there
um so that is one of the kind of the
best recruit
options the CDO the um I think it's
career development office at also has
someone um specific to son Pride members
to um think through lgbtq
specific um uh questions you may have
going through interviews or how to
portray something on your resume um if
there if you have any particular
questions about um you know about how to
portray your identity or something like
that so there's certainly a lot of
resources specific to our community that
um someone puts together that to really
make your recruiting um
successful thank you so much um this
year RBA is happening in the Los Angels
like this I think it's is September and
yeah like a lot of companies like from
the Consulting of pharmaceuticals or
like to the international uh
organization will come and to have the
the network and uh yeah so like that's
it's a good resource for the the
students like in the stor
Pride so um my question is uh about the
engagement in the communities outside of
the stone so there is like a MIT white
um lgbtq um Association also and there
is the Harvard there is greater Boston
community so is there anyone like
engaged into in the communities outside
of
um I would say not I would say from my
involvement the biggest one was kind of
cross events with the Harvard MBA um
Pride group and so we hosted a few
different happy hour mixer type events
which was um fun especially um t ually
related you can cross register for
courses at Harvard Business School um
and most people will take advantage of
um some cross register opportunity
whether it's at HBS or somewhere else at
Harvard so um a lot of times they were
classmates and then you would get to see
them as well at kind of mixers or other
events that we would host between the
two groups so I think that for me was my
most involvement but to the broader
question of the community in Boston
um I would say it's a very welcoming
open City there wasn't ever a time with
me and my sort of identity that I didn't
feel comfortable um being out um with my
partner or with the pride group in
general or specifically even just
wearing kind of the pride shirt which um
for Sloan you know has MIT and uh big
kind of rainbow colors I didn't ever
feel uncomfortable wearing that out and
about um
so but I obviously that's specific to me
I know other people could have different
experiences thank you so much htin yeah
I think also generally with the
community to to Drew's point you know
beyond I think the the cross
MBA you know there are a lot of
opportunities to or smaller
opportunities that might be a little bit
harder to find in terms them engaging
with the queer community in say
Cambridge or Boston like you know silly
things that I you know there's a a
poetry night every Wednesday night at a
bar in Central Square and that is one of
the weest safest spaces I think I've
ever been to where I can kind of put my
mask down and listen to people you know
share their Beautiful Stories whatever
that is or you know within like other
other cities as well there's some lgbtq
specific sports leagues um so if you
ever find the time as a a business
school student to go beyond Sloan um
there are those as well where you can
kind of connect with the community with
people over really all ages um I was
fortunate enough to do that when I
immediately after graduation when I was
in the Boston area and so a lot of those
I think resources or activities or
things exist it does require maybe a
little bit additional amount of
searching and exploration but to Drew's
Point Boston is a very you know safe
City at least in in in my experience
granted I also admit I'm a cisgender
white male so um it might be a little
bit different experience for others but
um it is the community is there and it
is
strong yeah no I totally Echo that um
and the swag I thought was the best out
of the pride Club there's some good swag
it's SL but the pride Club the gay
sweaters are wonderful and I also wore
them all the time my partner wears them
all the time like no issues uh the only
thing in terms of recruiting I wanted to
add these are more nonprofits on the
National level but they all have Boston
chapters is there's out professionals
and so that's a phenomenal nonprofit um
that is really as the title means like
just bringing together lgbtq
professionals across Industries and then
there's a couple that are like more
industry specific so like start out if
you're working on any kind of uh startup
they have a ton of resources while I was
working at a startup at MIT I got a
mentor through start out and that was
fantastic and there all across the
country um and then there's there's more
like specific ones so there's out in
Tech um and then there's out in finance
so there's there a ton of organizations
out there that can help and then rhoma
was phenomenal definitely go to the rhba
conference because there's recruiters
from every major company that you'd want
to work at there and you can get coffee
chats and it's a really great way to
connect thank you so much
so last question for the the panelist um
is about your experience um after the
graduation so which means um how you
engage yourself with the community of
the MIT like Alam Association or any
kind of like a community that really do
to MIT so how how's your experience like
after
graduation is there anyone
kle um working in Renewables there's
definitely a very strong contingent of
sonies working all across Renewables in
terms of both very established large
companies startups and everything in
between so that's been um great not only
because I was recently job hunting but
even before that just you constantly had
every company you interact with or every
place you go or running into
sonies um another opportunity again sort
of specific to energy but it applies
pretty much in any sector you would go
into there's a renewable energy Finance
Round Table hosted at Sloan I think it's
twice a year
um uh once in the spring and once in the
fall and so I participated in that it's
a great um just group of sonies working
in energy and Renewables from um so all
sorts of programs and class years coming
together to think through what's kind of
the next Frontier what's the um next big
problem that we would want to solve and
um you know as these things happen as I
was looking for a job one of the people
in the room that I've kind of connected
with has been a mentor for me was said
hey like I'm looking for someone with
this type of experience like let me know
if you're interested and that sort of
stuff I think happens a lot with the
son's helping son's mindset um if you
need help getting connected to someone
or
[Music]
um uh are just looking to get
information on something Aon is always
your first place to turn because either
they'll know or they'll get you
connected to someone who can so the
elimin network post sonone is probably I
thought it was important while you're at
s but it's even sort of more important
now how about you Lynette I think you're
back to Singapore but how was your
experience um after graduation
yeah um so one thing that I did not
expect is the number of wedding invites
you get like in the one year one or two
years after SL like everybody gets
married after school uh which is great
and that's an excuse to meet up again I
see all the other panelists smiling you
know it's true um so I me socially
that's one thing in
um it's I've gotten connected with like
the MIT Club of Singapore uh the broader
the broader MIT um Network out here um I
would say primarily in Southeast Asia or
Asia um H that you've got folks who are
I mean the most active ones are are
those who graduated um MIT maybe 20
years ago um so that's a that's a Fun
Bunch to kind of be connected with and
and get to know uh for SLO itself there
is a southeast Asia gang so actually I'm
meeting a bunch of them this weekend uh
because somebody from Thailand's coming
to Singapore and then everybody who's
been singing for just kind of uh uh
turns up for all these gatherings um
additionally yeah I what Drew said
around son helping sonies and if you
want an introduction to anybody um I've
had countless of of examples of folks
who have introduced me to clients or or
investors just by saying like oh hey I'm
uh like I'll text somebody from Pride
actually I say uh who is no long he's
Indonesia but he's uh and but based in
in um Washington now but um yeah I just
messed him hey I'm going to jaka next
week is there anybody whom you think I
should meet and then boom all the intros
just happened um so yeah people are
nice and uh yeah the the Alumni network
is what also if you just Reach Out C to
a uh an MIT Alum or or and especially in
SL Alum um I would say % of the time you
will get a response from
them that's hear that so um next section
is about the the Q&A session with the um
the attendees so I will get back to the
Staten yeah absolutely I'm back so um to
that point first I'll start off by
saying thank you everyone for for
sharing your own experiences and
providing all the um uh the account that
you've had from your own uh Sloan
experience and we definitely have a few
uh questions for everybody in the chat
some pointed more uh just trying to get
uh an Insight from your own experiences
so I wanted to start off by asking a
couple of questions about the Sloan
curriculum um and really to start off um
you know many of our uh attendees know
that the Sloan's course load can be
considered regular rigorous especially
if you're in the lgo program um is there
an example that's uh you can provide
when you were academically challenged
and then in addition to that what
resources were at your disposal that
leveraged you to
succeed sure I
guess for my I think the biggest
resource is honestly the culture of the
people so for example with lgo program
in the fall we're taking all those
standard classes um as an typical
business school student will and on top
of that we might be already taking
another one or two engineering classes
or if someone really likes to get busy
they'll be doing research or something
crazy like
that there are various moments during
that I think that work overload where
everyone always collectively comes
together in order to help solve these
problems to work together so if you're
in the same class as someone business
school engineering whatever might be
five of you are going to be getting
together to finish that homework or to
finish that report or finish that paper
and you know you're bouncing ideas off
of each other you're learning from each
other and that experience and it makes
everything a bit easier or significantly
easier I think that is a huge
resource um a second resource that's a
little bit more tangential is that MIT
has really good mental health services
um so if any point you do feel
overloaded or stressed they are a easy
call Easy consultation away um which has
been um at least for some of my peers
super super useful to help sort of kind
of help you take control of your own
situation whatever that might be um
de-stress um and figure out what a best
path forward might
be
awesome um I just thought of one thing
that relates to this so I'll add to that
um one thing also that really drew me to
Sloan versus other um programs is that
we do have some classes that are case
based but we're not 100% case based and
some things really fit a case model and
some things just don't right um so I
think that Variety in coursework really
um kept things challenging but probably
more importantly
interesting um and then to the point of
when I was challenged most I just kind
of remembered this so I wanted to share
of course you can take as many like data
classes and super Advanced Finance
classes as you want but one of the times
I was most challenged was um in a the
course was some called something like
difficult conversations and basically
each week all we did was um talk through
a particular situation where you would
have to have a difficult situ a
difficult
conversation examples would be when you
would experience or or see um some sort
of discrimination in the workplace
either you experienced or someone else
and you would just literally inclass
practice intervening or practice saying
how you would um follow up on something
um if you were pushing and some of them
were identity based and some of them
were you know you're you're pushing for
raise or you're you need to apologize to
someone for something that you did those
were I think actually some of the most
um academic I guess like challenging for
me because it was really taking sort of
what you might think as everyday
situations but putting them into
practice for like multiple hours a week
and really thinking through um not only
the ideas behind it but but implementing
that thank you both for um uh providing
that perspective I think to to tag on to
that question another one focused in on
um our curriculum is could you give an
example of fun or interesting ways that
you took advantage of the academic
freedom to take courses outside of the
required curriculum whether that be some
of the electives that you took or even
opportunities to um cross-register with
the broader MIT Community Andor some of
our um partner schools such as harbard I
suppose for myself um you know because
you're able to take classes across MIT
as a whole there is a wide variety that
you'd be surprised about like for
instance I took this very fun design
class around interaction design which
had nothing to do with either my degrees
but allowed me to get like a different
insight and maybe to what an industrial
designer would look at I knew a
different lgo that took a music class as
an elective um specifically I think
around music composition
um so it's like one of those little
extra freedoms where you know maybe it's
not ultimately what you're going to be
doing long time down the road uh my
friend is definitely not a professional
guitarist but it allows you to you know
sprinkle in you know maybe some of your
other passions or interests um
alongside
uh I guess maybe some of your classes
specifically towards career
goals yeah for me um I said uh I did
intership at Jordan the Middle East but
which I didn't expect before I came to
SL actually and I took one class about
the entrepreneurship ecosystem uh in the
spring semester and I focused in the
Middle East and some countries there and
I got interested in that and I tried to
reach um the the opportunities there so
um some some um opportunities are not
expected like like a when you like apply
to the St or when you come to Sol but um
I think um you can find a lot of
opportunities um unseeing for you right
now yeah I took a couple of classes um
um with wider outside out outside of SLO
uh MIT uh community so one of them was a
well still kind of this still related to
to my work but uh what was a kind of VC
cause for engers um and what was fun
about that class was that we actually
look at some of the undergrads um and I
think it's like if you get an MIT
undergrad uh that's a whole different
level right um what was fun about that
class is that we the professor actually
had us go to um uh lawyer and VC offices
um downtown to have that simulation uh
practice of like negotiating a term
sheet um going through prepping with
your lawyer um and then kind of seeing
uh what kind of things you can push back
on which ones are like reasonable u fles
in your term sheet but that that
practical exercise of actually speaking
with a a real lawyer and a real VC um
that was that was very impactful uh the
other one I did was a was a mental
health um mental health Tech uh course
and it was taught by is taught by by the
like the guru of it um uh rosart and the
um yeah she's been doing work in this
area for for over 20 years um so what
was cool about that class was again it
was a very diverse mix of people who are
just interested in mental health but um
the level of like Innovation and stuff
that she was sharing and that she had
speakers come in to to talk about for
for this area was was phenomenal but
that that that CA remember the workload
was really heavy for it so I so I
audited the class um and you can do that
too you can just sit in and and not have
to do the work or the class that's
that's also a nice way around it I
guess awesome thank you everyone so we
have a few more questions coming in uh
for this one um uh this is open to
anyone who'd like to answer could you
speak to how you personally exemplify
Sloan's mission statement which again is
to uh develop principled Innovative
leaders who improve the world and
general ideas that advanced management
practice I love this question because I
wondered this the entire two years I was
like what does being a principled leader
mean like what you know um and they when
you go to graduate they actually make
you sign uh like this mission statement
like I agree to do these
things um and so I think it's I think
it's different for everyone I think the
cool part of the curriculum is starting
in core semester but then throughout
your time at Sloan there's a lot of
classes across different like you know
even like Finance to organizational
development to entrepreneurship to
philosophy that really make you think
about um what your leadership style is
and how you embody that as a leader so I
think for me over the two years I
ultimately came to the conclusion that
um being a principled leader was being
authentic and as that relates to Pride I
mean that was really me being my whole
self in the workplace and so um you know
I mentioned like before Sloan and before
the pride group and before thinking
about being a principal leader I thought
it was unprofessional to talk about your
orientation and I was like oh that's not
that's not business related um but then
I realized like that was actually
holding me back from um being my you
know authentic self but also just like
in weird ways that you can't exactly
measure so post loan I mean for my team
I'm in charge of our business
development and I've literally put being
lgbtq
into my business plan um and so you know
I'm the only
lgbtq private wealth advisor Goldman
Sachs in their San Francisco office and
I think that's like a huge opportunity
to look into our community and to
connect with our professionals and the
lgbtq Chamber of Commerce and to tap
into that and I don't think I would have
thought about it that way had I not gone
through the exercise of thinking about
the mission statement thinking about
what leadership meant and then how I
could embody that because you know I say
I'm the only one but I maybe I'm not I
don't know I mean I I came out when I
was 16 which I I didn't know if that was
young or old during Pride I met a lot of
people who you know were 30 and still
weren't out um and so I realized it's a
it's a journey for everybody but I think
being a leader is being yourself openly
so that you're just you know for the
21-year-old maybe that just started
working there they and maybe they are in
the closet they can kind of see oh I you
know this is an inclusive space thanks
Zoe So for our next question uh Austin
if you don't mind i' actually like to
direct this to you uh first but then of
course anyone else can jump in um uh but
for this particular question the
community Salone sounds amazing how does
it support specifically budding
entrepreneurs and VC
networks it might be a better question
for Lynette considering she has a
startup
absolutely right yeah um so the mutton
TR Center um is great it hang out there
in between classes and it's um they have
a lot of programs uh a lot of pitch
competitions um a lot of class uh some
classes as well uh but just hanging out
in the Mantra sector and random
conversations that you or introductions
you get made uh yeah folks to get
introduced to who are who are there as
well there are a lot of people who go
into slow interest in entrepreneurship
and there are also a lot of people who
get bitten by the startup bug um after
joining slow and it's it's it's great
and it's exciting and it's something
that you can uh try out as well so um
for for entrepreneurs we've got the 100K
um Pitch competition you've got a ton of
classes that I found very helpful things
like entrepreneur sales entrepreneur
Finance um I did a class thought by uh
one of the founders of hub spot um and
that was also uh a great uh that was
scaling entrepreneur venture so yeah
classes wise um and all that VC networks
um there are a lot of events that will
also
be um either through the
entrepreneurship Club so the SLO e club
or uh all through the mar trust Center
um and and they are very active there
there's no shortage of U mixers and all
that to go for to to meet folks and you
do meet different people at uh at all
these events
awesome thank you Lynette so in the
interest of time I think we have uh
opportunity for two more questions for
our panelists I'll try and sneak in one
more if I can before we get into uh
closing out this evening's programming
um but for this uh this next particular
question um it's a two-parter so open to
anybody um uh the first part is how did
you find adjusting to the workspace as
successful uh queer individuals um I've
had different experiences depending on
the workplace and I'm curious if you
have any wisdom here and the second part
of that question uh additionally how can
I continue to stay engaged with the the
Salone queer Network and Community
during the application
process so the other thing about slow
that we're all pretty shy we' got you've
got to way to be allocated a question to
ask which is not difficulty for other
business schools um I can take a step at
this so um in terms I would say after I
did become a lot more out um after SL
and I think simar that's this is my
first um I only started getting plugged
into the career community at s and then
since graduation um for before that um I
think in the cas was very do tell
consider UK kind of tell right but um
yeah but people just that we didn't we
talk about it um out in even out here in
Singapore uh
recently um my partner and I have also
founded a quer business Collective um
well when Singapore for queer business
um Ro um lbq owners uh business owners
in Singapore to kind of um Provide
support and resources to each other so I
would say if if um
if there's a gap in support or something
in your experience at the workplace or
whatever um create it uh there are
people who would who would benefit from
it as well who are willing to give back
their timee and not now some of these
books are are my closest friends um the
second part of the
question I believe was
around the second part of the question
um as a refresher was um in regards to
staying connected with the uh slan uh
Sloan pride and queer Community during
the application
process
LinkedIn that's my yeah LinkedIn and uh
I
think might have some stuff around that
as well sure so um we have um kind of
like a Google form like for the um the
any applicant to like get the connection
with the this the pride students so like
um if you like Google the storm pride
and you will find um the the form so
like you can get the connected with the
the current
students
excellent all right we may have time to
answer this one very quickly but this
will be a great closing question um for
our panelists if you could uh wind back
the clock and start your time over again
at Sloan
uh what's one thing you would do
differently I think for me um I knew I
wanted to take a lot of Finance classes
because ultimately I wanted my career to
um to be in finance but as a you know a
lot of the other panelists have
mentioned there are so many other
opportunities to um take classes outside
of your interest or to cross
or to take um classes outside of Sal at
the rest of the Institute I did do that
some but I certainly would have if I
could go back um take classes you know
totally outside of my already identified
interests and just enjoy some of the
access to the rest of the institute in
Harvard and kind of the entire son
experience
yeah I think to double down on a point
that Zoe made you know quite a bit
earlier there's a level of exploration
into to choose Point as well that is
worth doing you know beyond that first
semester you know think through anything
that might potentially peque your
interest whether it's through a club
through a class or whatever it might be
you know you know put your foot partly
in that door um explore see what it
might be because I might Peak an
interest that you are surprised at
peaked and that could lead to a a career
shift that you didn't expect um you know
I'd wished i' had done a little bit more
of that exploration up up front versus
maybe a little bit later on during my
second year um but
it to Drew's Point there's a lot to
offer at MIT and at
Sloan um and just utilize you know your
time there your first year your second
year to kind of like find that out
Zoe Lynette anything to
[Music]
add I think these are great points um
maybe one a lot of my friends were
organizing conferences and I organized
one conference our first impact
investing one but I think I was like why
why are people organizing conferences
just seems like so much work and then it
occurred to me now I was like like oh
it's a great opportunity to get to meet
really fantastic people uh and I don't
know why that didn't occur to me as a
student so um you know whatever area of
interest you know we have so many
different conferences like sports
analytics impact investing
sustainability and especially if you're
trying to Pivot into a space or you're
just curious um or help organize a
conference like it's it's some work but
then you get to meet phenomenal people
and yeah I have no idea why that didn't
occur to me as a student
I'll throw in one more thing that we
didn't cover um in this comp which is I
would have gone out more okay I would
have gone and I would have gone for more
tracks um so I only I guess really
learned to balance my time in the second
year where so I was able to do that a
lot more but these are essentially I
mean the tracks are essentially trips
organized by your fellow classmates who
are locals so um in particular I went to
I went to
uh Mexico Brazil and Texas uh Houston um
the different tracks and and the
experience is different and I I don't
think it's something that can really be
replicated you also get a lot closer to
your classmates during on a trip right
so I think making time for that and of
course the pride uh Retreats were
absolutely my favorite um so making time
for these socials uh activities and yeah
um it's a great bonding to and to build
uh
relationships with folks who are who are
going to be your friends for life