hi there I hope you were able to take a
couple minutes to think about how you
might represent pitch I'm back better
camera hopefully a little bit better so
what are the consequences of the pitch
representation that we might
choose that's what we're going to be
looking at now let's say that we decide
to work with the numeric representation
P equal
440 how would we represent then a type
of continuous pitch like
aando since we only have one number or
even just thinking about the performance
perspective how do we represent how do
we go from a number like 440 into
something that a performer would be able
to see on a staff and play with and are
we just going to have a whole series of
numbers so maybe the string based thing
will be a little bit better but then how
do we manipulate it what does p+2 mean
are we just going to have a whole bunch
of python errors that we can never add
things together that
way so what we're going to be thinking
about in the first group discussion is
what are the
consequences of the particular
representations that we
choose other words what kinds of
applications can be done with a
particular representation that can't be
done with another
representation another way of putting it
is which stakeholders are included or in
excluded depending on our
representation so the next thing I'd
like you to do is to
think of three different ways that you
might represent pitch on a computer and
then think about for each of those what
does this way do well and what does this
way do badly at and then think about the
stakeholders a stakeholder might be a
musician or it might be a programmer or
it might be
a a a record producer or it might be
somebody who is more specific like uh a
rock music verus a clal musician or
something of that s and who are the
stakeholders who are excluded or
included by what you've done