I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it
[Music]
works from the MIT energy initiative
this is what if it works a podcast
looking at the energy solutions for
climate change I'm Cara Miller you might
know me from the public radio program
Innovation Hub which I hosted and now
write the big idea column for the Boston
Globe and I'm Robert Stoner the
president of the Kendall Square project
and former director of the MIT energy
[Music]
initiative good to see you cara good to
see you too so let's talk about why
we're doing this podcast and I know you
kind of wanted to start off with a story
here well you know I'm in the business
of finding solutions to climate change
finding those lowc carbon technologies
that are going to enable us to move the
economy of the world into a very
different place I'm optimistic about it
I mean you got to get up in the morning
and do this stuff every single day and
it's how I feel but I'm always surprised
and disappointed and worried when I see
people who often young people very very
worried upset even I got into a cab this
morning coming back from the
airport with a guy who was worried that
there wasn't going to be enough food if
climate change kept on going um somebody
the other day was telling me that they
were worried about their house being
washed away in the flood that's not
what's going to happen for one thing the
time frame is a lot longer and for
another thing we really have a lot of
great ideas and technologies that we're
moving forward quickly so a question
about the technology you're a
professional here I'm not to what degree
do we have the solutions like are the
solutions to climate change still in the
lab still being worked out or do they
exist it's just people haven't thrown
enough money at the problem and haven't
scaled it up yes yes and yes so I mean
we have to keep all of these thoughts in
our minds right yes
we have maybe not all of the solutions
we have a lot of solutions and they're
good Solutions yes people are still in
the labs and they need to be working in
the labs and yes we're implementing all
these Solutions the problem is that many
of them well they all require an
investment of some kind very often
they're replacing something that's still
perfectly good we have to throw it away
that has an economic cost it affects us
it affects how we can live it affects
our ability to apply those resources to
other things that would improve our
lives in other ways
so these are nuanced issues and they
have to be approached that way in other
cases the Technologies are there but
they don't work together well and we
haven't figured out how to put them
together in an efficient way and the
obvious example of that is our
electricity system where we're trying to
add a lot of solar and wind they don't
produce any carbon they're relatively
cheap now and we can put them up
everywhere but the sun doesn't always
shine and the wind doesn't always blow
as they say so we need batteries and
those batteries are too expensive and we
need too many of them with the way we
operate the system we're not really
adjusting our demand to match that
intermittent generation so somebody said
to you you know here's a bunch of money
but you can only play with the pieces on
the chess board right now like we're not
going to develop anything more in the
lab we're not going to do any more of
the basic research we're done with that
do you think the technology that exists
is enough to to address climate change
no no okay no no and you know it it's a
big piece of it but there's a lot more
that needs to be done yeah I mean I was
just talking about the electricity
system there's a lot more to the Energy
System than the electricity system we
use energy in all kinds of ways we heat
our homes with it you know I burned
natural gas in my apartment in Boston
and in our summer house we burn wood in
the stove those things all emit CO2 and
they represent a lot more energy than I
use at least in the form of electricity
and so we have to find ways to replace
those too so electrifying everything is
a great idea and at the same time
deploying a lot of zeroc carbon
electricity generation solar wind
nuclear but we've got to find ways to
decarbonize other parts of the
transportation system than just personal
cars that work pretty well as EVS we've
got to find a way to decarbonize
Industry all the things we make that
produce CO2 because they
is really a problem because it not only
consumes natural gas to produce the heat
that's required which emits CO2 into the
atmosphere but that chemical reaction
that takes place creates CO2 and so we
even need a different material in that
case so I know one of the things we're
going to do over the many episodes of
this podcast is we're going to look at
like all these different Technologies
but also funding but just since you
mentioned cement let me just Dive Right
In you know I once had somebody say to
me who invests in Green Technology
investors like Investments they can
understand something like you know
electric vehicles is kind of like a sexy
technology and like cement I don't know
not super sexy generally do you think
that there's a problem where there's a
misalignment of what people are throwing
money at and what they should be
throwing money yet absolutely okay um
cuz most of us are just like not there
in the back rooms and we don't
I know people assume that if there's a
lot of money being thrown at electric
cars maybe like that's the problem and
that'll solve everything if we switch
over well let me give you a more
sophisticated answer than
absolutely we you know a lot of the
problems that are represented by the
things that we need to change right now
like electric cars are easy to
understand we have cars and we need to
not use internal combustion engines
anymore and fuel we need to use electric
cars so we need batteries so an investor
can understand that I have an new
battery technology and I want you to
invest in it and they can understand
they can sell those batteries for new
cars but then there are other things
that we're going to need in the future
for which there aren't currently markets
things like long duration storage
batteries for the Grid or um you know
direct air capture of carbon dioxide
from the atmosphere both things we
really really need but there isn't a big
market for them right now so the first
thing the long duration storage
batteries is that like oh we captured a
whole bunch of solar from this you know
solar farm in in Arizona but we need to
like put that somewhere so that we can
transport it or we can keep it for the
night time or whatever is that yeah and
return it to the grid right exactly and
the more the grid is decarbonized with
solar and wind the more storage you need
now we're at an early stage though in
deploying solar and wind it's still a
relatively small fraction of our total
electricity Supply so we can deal with
the inter mcy just by turning up and
turning down the existing generation
systems we have the gas and with
fortunately uh less and less frequency
the coal plants that are still out there
so just to like get back to this
hopelessness question if some of the
technology has not been developed if a
lot of it has not been scaled in the way
that it should be if people are not
necessarily deploying money towards the
right things and we've already seen
these massive heat waves and we've seen
the Earth Heating up what makes you
hopeful because that doesn't sound
necessarily like a recipe for hope so
tell me like what makes you I know
you're a very hopeful person so like
what makes you hopeful I grow up hopeful
every day I get up hopeful every day but
well I I think it's a question of
thinking about what where are we going
to get to I mean what what is the
objective here the bad news is that
we're very close to the 1.5 degree
threshold that people are concerned
about and it's a real threshold that's
not an arbitrary number it it represents
a temperature Beyond which the CO2
concentration in the atmosphere is
probably so high that we won't be able
to get it a temperature back down to
where it was earlier in the century if
we go beyond it to two it kind of hangs
around too and it might float up a
little bit take a long long time to come
back down again so this's a sort of a a
transition that occurs there so what
we're trying to do here is stay as close
to that threshold as we can not go far
beyond it and also give ourselves time
to adapt to the changes that are going
to occur it's already warmer it's going
to get warmer right water's going to get
higher people are going to have to move
because agricultural productivity is
going to shift around it's not going to
go away and the more time we give
ourselves to shift around with that
productive capacity and and other
aspects of the way we live the less
stress there will be on society trying
to do it very quickly creat stresses of
of another kind I and we're all familiar
with the the life issue that people are
confronting in the in the midwest that
has become a political issue of the
decline of industries that use
conventional energy if you you know push
very aggressively to shut those
Industries down those people really
suffer and they suffer just exactly in
the same way they're going to suffer a
100 years in the future as a result of a
global temperature rise so you know one
of the big questions I have about this
is human behavior and sort of how you
innovate around human behavior it seems
like asking people it's not like
vegetarianism is new for example and yet
when you look at like the percentage of
Americans that are vegetarian it's very
small I'm I'm not sure 5% less something
like that I also look at the cars around
me I feel like during my lifetime
they've gotten really really big now
they're they're just a lot of huge huge
cars so
I think many
people both who eat meat and who drive
big cars will tell you they do care
about the environment so I also feel
like one of the big questions is do we
have to kind of innovate around human
behavior you know what I mean because
human behavior seems to be like looking
for comfort and looking for what feels
good and it's hard to it's hard to like
cut things out of your life yeah we are
the people we are and somehow though we
people in North America don't think of
things the same way that they do in
Europe or in many parts of Asia as well
I mean they they have made choices and
we have to make choices too it's not
necessarily a question of being better
it's a question of being more thoughtful
about the choices we have before us and
maybe to some extent thinking about our
children and and their Futures they
don't have to be bad choices though it's
not like we have to decide to start
wearing hair shirts I mean EVS are
pretty cool um Heat pumps are pretty
cool I mean energy efficient buildings
are pretty cool and warm depending on
what you need so we shouldn't hide from
these choices I mean the society really
has to engage with them and and get on
with it we develop policy and programs
that are you know intended to drive
people toward these sorts of choices and
you're right they seem to be kind of
ineffective sometimes I mean on the on
the other hand like when you talk about
policies you think about like the energy
saver sticker that you see on washing
machines like you can also from from a
governmental level I guess say
California is doing this we're only
going to sell this kind of car or we're
only going to sell cars with this m
gallon or above so whatever you choose
you can choose anything but 15 miles a
gallon you can't choose you're right you
know President Biden came out recently
with with a a new policy that is trying
to constrain car companies to produce
cars that are less emitting overall it's
not requiring people to buy electric
cars and it's not requiring car
companies to make electric cars it's
just saying that overall you got to make
cars that have lower emissions as a
fleet you can try to do that and and
it's a perfectly reasonable thing to do
it doesn't force people to give up their
internal combustion engines it does sort
of push Society in a particular
direction and and those sorts of
Standards which are called Cafe
standards have been very effective in
cleaning up the American Automotive
system we still tend to favor these
gigantic cars right you know and the the
electric Hummers is just sort of a
classic example of what are we thinking
so then when you think about human
behavior and how science thinks about
that and tries to mitigate climate
change when you get together with
Scientists what do what do they say in
terms of I mean because you you actually
have to have something for a lot of
people depends on what what it if you're
a government regulator it's different
but like if you're creating something
that's coming through the market you
have to have something that people want
so if you're like here I'm selling this
very tiny car and people like yeah I'm
not really that interested in that
that's not I mean that's not going to
work yeah but we know we don't invent
cars at MIT well not we focus on the
technologies that enable cars to run
cleaner and so we're not trying to make
those choices for people we we're in the
business of trying to create options for
people to be able to choose but you do
have to choose I have a colleague a very
close colleague who I won't name uh who
drove around a chef Dey Suburban for
many years an old one drove it all the
way from California to come to MIT to
join the faculty and its license plate
was tax CO2 in other words I'm not going
to make that choice unless there's a
policy that forces me to make that
choice and I think the reason is
interesting I'm not going to make that
choice myself alone unless I know that
everybody else has to make that choice
too and suffer in the same way and I'm
not ready to get rid of my car my car's
not that old I'm going to hang on to it
for a few more years so you know back
off about me driving this big car this a
reality that we live in it's interesting
about that car that issue of the carbon
tax because I talked to a couple
economists a Republican and a Democrat a
few years ago and what shocked me was
that they agreed there should be a
carbon tax and as far as I can tell
there is zero Traction in any sort of
carbon tax like in National politics I
can't imagine people just don't really
like taxes so I don't know that doesn't
seem like an idea that's getting the
ground but it what just shocked me was
that people on like academics on either
side of the aisle were like yeah it's
obvious we should totally do that it is
obvious I mean it's the it's the obvious
thing to do if you tax CO2 emissions
then you know people will emit less it's
exactly what you should do we do use the
tax system but we use it to provide tax
credits you know we've got this system
now of carrots no sticks uh as provided
by the these two major pieces of
legislation the inflation reduction Act
and the bipartisan infrastructure law
which is not bipartisan and the
inflation reduction act isn't very
inflationary reduction either but but
they're good at naming things in DC
accurate naming so the you know the
federal government has said that's the
way we're going to go we're going to try
to incentivize people to do the right
thing at the state level we have applied
not necessarily taxes but we've applied
mandates that say you got to have this
much zeroc carbon electricity in your
system and
it it's possible to trade in renewable
energy credits that are created through
those mandates to do something like
apply a tax to the industry force it to
go in a certain direction they've been
very effective the Canadians do have a
carbon tax and it's one that's going to
wind itself up to something like 170
bucks a ton wow okay by 2030 so it's a
very aggressive carbon tax and I I was
talking to a Canadian yesterday who was
complaining about it so it must be doing
something the Europeans are about to
Implement something called the carbon
border adjustment mechanism cbam which
is going to tax the CO2 associated with
products imported into the EU they're
going to say or washing machines or
whatever yeah China you're going to make
that product that we're trying to make
in the EU we're going to tax carbon in
the EU we're going to tax your products
as they come into the EU unless you're
going to either clean them up so they
don't have very much carbon in them or
tax them yourselves we're going to see
more of that and that kind of thinking I
think is is sort of almost dangerously
but intriguingly aligned with this sort
of tariff enthusiasm that certain
political candidates have
demonstrated so let me ask you a little
bit about China and India and actually
I've been hearing a ton about China uh
making electric cars that are a fraction
the price of what we have here but I
don't we don't have them here because um
because ter they have them in
Europe but but yeah there's just a lot
of protectionism uh at least with cars
here but I think one thing you know we
were talking about this question of Hope
and do you have hope and on the question
of climate I think for a lot of people
um China and India Loom large in you
know a lot of people together almost
three billion people and they both have
Rising middle classes that want things
like air conditioners not surprisingly
it's hot and washing machines and like
the things we have so it's hard to say
don't have those things because they are
very energy hungry while we live in like
3,000 square foot homes and have air
conditioners you know but like again to
this question of Hope isn't it kind of
worrisome that so many people are sort
of moving up to the middle class and
wanting energy hungry appliances yeah
but that's a good thing no it is good it
is good of course so this is an example
it's like attention right yeah it's it's
attention exactly I mean gez I mean the
situations that they're emerging from of
grotesque poverty are the sorts of
things we fear in our future future as a
result of climate change so trying to
persuade them not to economically
develop so that we won't have a problem
in the future as absurd and and and it's
it's offensive to them and a losing
proposition probably nobody's going to
buy that and and we have in large part
exported our manufacturing related
emissions to these low-income countries
at the same time and to turn around now
and sort of insist that they decarbonize
themselves mindlessly is unfair we need
to encourage them to decarbonize
themselves and develop lowc carbon
economies but we're going to have to pay
them to do it we're going to have to
either pay more for the product so that
they can have carbon taxes within their
own Borders or we're going to have to
literally make transfers via the
multilateral and bilateral development
Banks the World Bank usaid and other
other organs of the US government to
make it possible for them to invest in
these Technologies when they have the
option to invest dirtier technologies
that cost less that's a really hard
thing to do and talk about a political
problem which of those things if either
or both do you see happening you think
about Walmart and how many things at
Walmart are made in China and you go in
to buy your blender or your bike or
whatever does that mean it's truly going
to be more expensive because we're
saying like we have to add on the toll
that's taking on the environment or are
we just going to transfer money to
people and say like here this this is to
scale up this technology I think things
are going to get more expensive okay the
blender is going to get more expensive I
mean we're very least even if these new
technologies cost less or the same as
the Technologies they're replacing very
often those Technologies still have a
lot of useful life in them like which
two which new technolog like a coal
Generation Plant in China for example
was built 10 years ago okay that plant
should last for 30 or 40 years for them
to turn that plant off means somebody's
not going to repay his bank loan that
they use to build that plant in the
first place so who's going to pay it the
government has to pay it or somehow
people who buy electricity will have to
absorb that financial burden through the
electricity rates that they pay so that
it can be paid off the money the debt
doesn't go away and so so this this
limits it introduces a sort of viscosity
into the rate at which we can we can
force these changes to happen they're
literally isn't enough money in the
world so a you know make stuff
cheaper uh B make choices in society
about where we're going to apply the
scarce resources that we can muster only
to climate change mitigation what about
education and Roads what about healthc
care uh what about space exploration
telecommunications I all all the other
things we got to do they're hard choices
so if we just go back to the coal fire
power plant in China That's being used
to you know make our blenders let's say
and the person who owns it is like doing
fine making money who is going to be the
person who says I know we can get 20
more years out of this but it is like
ruining the planet we should not do this
yeah well it has to be probably the
government and and the government has to
come to terms with that and would they
do that maybe or why would they do that
well because they begin to worry about
the impact of climate change and I think
maybe they begin to worry about things
like seam and the fact that they may no
longer be able to sell their goods
abroad which would have a tremendously
dilar effect on their on their economies
but there are other things they can do
as well and this is the kind of stuff we
work on at MIT and and people work on at
other places you can look at that coal
plant and say well what else can I do
with that coal plant maybe I can find a
way for it to continue to be a
productive asset but burn something else
maybe it can burn biomass and I can grow
more biomass and it will absorb CO2 from
the atmosphere and I can use it in that
plant that has happened in a sort of a
way in Europe and and it's it's possible
up to some level there's probably not
enough biomass to get very far in
dealing with that problem you could look
at gas plants you know of which we have
a great many in this country and say
well maybe we could burn something other
than gas in that gas turbine maybe we
could substitute ammonia which doesn't
contain carbon and when it burns it
doesn't prod produce CO2 produces other
stuff that you have to mitigate but
maybe there are other zero carbon fuels
we can find a way to use in those plants
and other plants to make those assets
work longer and reduce that burden the
Japanese are very very intent on this
they live in a world where they have
basically no primary energy resources
other than sun and wind right they're
not going to like drill for oil they
don't live they don't yeah exactly no
oil not even that much coal uh no
natural gas so they're importing all
these fossil fuels and that's very very
burdensome and very very different from
the situation in this country we've got
enormous amounts of gas we're the
biggest gas producer in the world
biggest exporter of gas in the world now
so they're very motivated to find other
ways to generate power and to use assets
and we're working with one of the
Japanese power manufacturers who trying
to figure out how to retrofit Machinery
around the world that they make to run
on ammonia instead of natural gas that
kind of innovation is really really
important and and it's coming from
outside the United States it's driven by
their shortage of
options the transformation of our Energy
Systems is very very different in every
country we all have a different set of
resources different sun and wind
different economies and each will take
its own
path the nature of of innovation which
is in part new technologies but also in
part systems and how things go together
will be driven by these very local needs
and we need to be watching it's a very
important driver of international
[Music]
cooperation let me just go back to this
question about India and China you've
been involved so much in international
discussions about climate change I know
China is the number one emitter right
now more than twice I think what the US
admits though I should say on a per
capita basis we still admit quite a bit
win yeah exact if that's a if that's a
prize you want to win then yes um do you
hear from those countries I mean you
were talking about Japan before and it's
just a much richer country I'm guessing
on a per capita basis than China what do
you hear from those countries do they
care about climate change because there
are pressing issues like you have to
care if people are going to eat next
week before you care if things are going
to be too hot five years from now you
know yeah it depends on the country I
mean we're talking about rich countries
when we're talking about Japan it's
still a very very large heavily
industrialized economy very highly
educated population very high standard
of
living they are motivated to mitigate
climate both I mean they're looking at
the at the temperature increases and
they're saying gez this is going to this
is going to cause real disruption in our
country if we have to suddenly start
shifting things around and people have
to relocate and our agricultural system
falls apart I mean that's bad oh and
people are dying during
heat we don't have to persuade countries
like Japan that that they need to do
something about climate change but their
their options are very constrained they
not only have very limited primary
energy resources if they decided to
continue to burn f fuels they don't have
anywhere to put the CO2 if they somehow
find a way to capture it and want to say
sequester it in the ground using a
technique called carbon capture and
sequestration which we've been
developing in in America and it's been
developed in other countries as well
they'd have to actually pay someone to
take their captured CO2 away to another
country and put it into a geological
formation that would accept it okay so
like on a boat okay so the these
countries have very very constrained
options and they really do need to be
creative to be Innovative to find new
ways to put them together you know it's
a painful thing in the near term but in
the longer term it just might turn out
to be a driver of innovation that makes
them leaders in the world's future
economy and we need to look out for that
in America I mean it it's tempting here
to just throw up big trade trip barriers
and you know keep Chinese products out
and raise our tariffs on them and and
Japanese products favor our own car
industry
last time we favored our own car
industry with that sort of policy we
ended up with really lousy expensive
cars and we still haven't even worked
our way out of that problem so we risk
cutting ourselves off from the flow of
global Innovation and I have to tell you
there's a lot going on in India as well
I mean this is a country with very
uneven primary energy resources they'
got a lot of coal very dirty coal some
people call it mud which they burn and
it produces not only a lot of CO2
because it's it burns inefficiently you
got to burn a lot more of it to get the
same amount of energy out but it also
throws out a lot of Ash and contributes
to a lot of the uh air pollution
problems they have in India they don't
have any natural gas so not much to
speak of that's all imported they've got
a lot of people and amazingly over the
last 10 years they've managed to connect
all of those people to the electricity
system when I was working in India in
the mid
2000s 60% of Indians didn't have access
to the grid and then it became 40 and
then 20 and the government got very
serious about it now everybody's
connected but the system is dominated by
coal generation so they've now got
growing demand people are getting richer
accustomed to using electricity for
stuff like air conditioning that didn't
used to have and they've got to deal
with it very urgently and so they're
also looking at co-firing with zero
carbon fuels in existing facilities but
they're really looking at solar and wind
and here you have a country that's very
motivated to to do this and a a very
large educated engineering Workforce a
very large lowcost labor force and
they're finding ways to to do solar
projects and onshore at least wind
projects that are much less expensive
than than we know how to do that's
really interesting and so they can begin
to do things at a scale that we're on
accustom to seeing really interesting to
think about that then spilling over into
their manufacturing industry and
suddenly we got a country with a growing
manufacturing base that's got a clean
energy system and they're exporting
actually there was a this line that you
said just a couple months ago that
really caught me and I have to go back
to it I think you said something like
the US risks cutting itself off from
like Global Innovation or something here
we are 2024 we've had a democrat in the
white house for three years in general
Democrats are a lot
more like care a lot more about climate
change or even talk a lot more about Dem
demat some Democrats so I mean really
like we risk cutting ourselves off when
you start trying to subsidize things I
mean trying to do even the right thing
yeah or throw up trade barriers you're
distorting the economy you're making it
possible to do something that didn't
used to be possible okay fine but but
that does carry risks because you're
also reducing the competitiveness of the
companies that begin doing those things
they're getting paid to do them whereas
companies that do the same thing or want
to do the same thing in in other
countries may not be getting paid to do
them so they've got to really push hard
on Innovation and finding ways to get
the cost down what tends to happen is
the rate of innovation can be faster in
those countries and and you know at the
end of the day you're you can't
subsidize Forever at a high rate or the
subsidies are simply overwhelmed by the
cost advantage that obtains elsewhere
you you you end up with lousy stuff that
cost more you mentioned um the auto
sector do you feel like we have too much
prot ISM in the auto sector we have I
think we we got over that but my point
was that it just takes a long time to
catch up once you you know fall behind
but we're still not getting those like
Chinese I mean like Europe has these
electric cars from China byd byd and I
mean I think these things are like
$112,000 for like pretty pretty nice
SUVs they're all electric I mean you
just you could not walk in to any auto
dealership and get anything close to
that price for anything close to that
sort of of right quality now you got to
of course ship those cars over here on a
ship and that that adds costs and um but
but right we could we can manage to make
those cars very expensive here to make
room for our car industry to to develop
and Thrive and that's fine for a while
but after a while you're supporting if
sort of a not very healthy not very
Innovative car industry if you aren't
careful my point is not that we
shouldn't have these subsidies we we've
got to somehow jump start this kind of
activity but it does create these sorts
of risk risks let's just talk about in
some ways we're talking about the future
but part of that future is what's
already baked in in terms of climate
change and I know one thing that we'll
talk about on future episodes in
addition to like all this green
technology and you know we talked about
solar panels wind how can we you know
batteries that are better there's like
this also this whole other category
right of okay well things are getting
hotter how do you live with that you
know whether it's sea is rising or
whatever I just wonder what you how you
think about that because that seems like
a pretty real problem even if like
tomorrow we really were able to
accomplish whole lot yeah well these two
things are going on at the same time one
is what is sort of mitigating the risks
as best we can by developing low carbon
technologies that will deliver less CO2
and other greenhouse gases to the
atmosphere in the near
term but you know temperature is rising
and it will continue to rise even if we
stop emitting CO2 tomorrow because this
this sort of momentum in the atmosphere
and in the climate but that will give us
more time and and it's it's more time to
adapt and so there's this other Force
called adaptation that we need to be
thinking about increasingly now
Technologies like temperature resistant
or drout resistant crops the ability to
engineer waterways so that we can
re-root water and try to protect our
coasts dkes Coastal reinforcements I
mean I hear people talking about seaw
wall sometimes like you have to choose
what parts of New York or Boston or
Shanghai or whatever that you need to
protect and yeah yeah we see that we
kind you know and if if sea level rises
by a meter or two in a year we couldn't
possibly build those dkes fast enough to
to preserve our environment if it takes
50 years we got a shot and so reducing
emissions now well it might seem sort of
hopeless is really really important
because it stretches that timeline and
it's all about balancing mitigation and
adaptation I guess a final question
about money I know there are Venture
capitalists out there who are pouring
money into green technologies obviously
the government has done this with
varying levels of success I remember
times you're in the Obama Administration
where people are like look this went
wrong and you know but sometimes it
really has been successful
universities are working on stuff is
there a huge deficit of money is there
plenty of money but not enough good
stuff to throw it at like give me a
sense of what the money situation looks
like well we've gone through a couple of
waves of venture capital in renewable
energy the the first one was in the sort
of mid 2000s through 2010 12 or so on
and a lot of money was thrown at
Technologies for which there was no
demand or very little demand and the
result was that a lot of those
Investments were kind of disappointing
and and that created a low but we're
back into a period in which there is a
lot of investment and there are a lot of
really good ideas emerging and demand is
also emerging for those Technologies as
we we know we get more sun and wind on
the grid we got more demand for storage
all of a sudden as the government begins
to subsidize hydrogen production as they
have through the
IRA the inflation reduction act suddenly
there's a lot more demand for high
quality efficient electrolyzers the
devices that use electricity to convert
water into hydrogen and
oxygen so we're going to this other this
new I think very important wave there's
a lot of chaff there's so many
inventions coming at us that sometimes
it's hard to know which ones are are
worth funding and you know may the
smartest venture capitalist
win in that battle but a lot of money
will get was isn't that always how it
works no it isn't okay I mean the the
the risk return ratio is high uh in
these things but there really are some
great ideas and and they should give us
all hope and we're going to talk about
these course of the next many episodes I
think one of the most exciting ones is
Fusion magnetic Fusion sometimes called
nuclear fusion but it is a different
nuclear technology from the one we're
all familiar with that that uses uranium
to generate electricity and also
produces a lot of uranium waste in the
process that we're not really good about
dealing with my opinion this is the kind
of waste that they put in like yucka
mountain and Nevada yeah well they don't
put in yucka Mountain the problem they
don't put it they've discussed putting
it in the mountain and probably
neighbors are like we don't really want
to be near yucka Mountain in law is our
national repository but we don't put
stuff there okay because there's
resistance in Nevada to using it for
those purposes there's concern about
transporting nuclear waste along
railroads and so what we do is we leave
it in the parking lots of nuclear power
plants or in the cooling pools above
nuclear reactors in those power plants
Without Really the near-term intention
at least to move it away it's not unsafe
but it doesn't look very tidy and it's
not doesn't make a convincing
demonstration that we're kind of on it
okay um and and I think that probably
contributes to public resistance to
Conventional nuclear power we got to
have conventional nuclear power and and
there's a lot of work that's that's
going on in s but but in companies as
well that will enable us to have very
Advanced nuclear reactors that really
are very very safe
operationally we've got to build them
small modular reactors that maybe can be
built in a factory environment in a in a
much more repeatable way and as a result
maybe a little bit less expensively are
also emerging and they're being
subsidized by the government push
forward as fast as they can the
Canadians are making you know real
strides but we've got to figure out that
waste problem U the the fins have built
a repository of a kind that's been
suggested for the United States by
Americans it's called midterm Storage
storage that will be very safe
geologically for periods of centuries
it's not long enough we need maybe
thousands of years but long enough for
us to put it out of Harm's Way and think
about what those multi- thousand year
Solutions might be so that's great and
it's moving and I hope we transition
onto that track here but at the same
time magnetic fusion and and other forms
of fusion not fision which combine light
nuclei together to release energy okay
are advancing rapidly um this is
technology that people began working on
in the 50s in in the UK and in the US
and in Russia I think I heard somebody
joke that this was the kind of
technology that was always 30 years away
50 50 whatever you know it was like
every time you asked it was didn't get
any closer but it seems like now it
really is getting closer like here in
Massachusetts Commonwealth Fusion
systems has taken over an old military
base right yeah leveled it and created a
a a new reactor we are building what I
think will be the world's first
functioning magnetic Fusion reactor and
like when do you imagine that it maybe
would come into use well it will be a
demonstration initially um and my
understanding is that within something
like two years they will have a
functioning unit sitting there that will
be producing more energy than it
consumes from the electric grid that
ratio is called the Q so the amount out
divided by the amount in we've never
crossed a q of one in the world in
Fusion yet they're aiming to be able to
operate at cues of between 10 and 20 in
the future and that that's all about
making these plants work very
efficiently learning how to control the
systems that make them work these Fusion
reactors have two major systems one is
is a superconducting magnet system
that's used to confine the plasma of
burning dyum and tritium and the other
one is a cryogenic system that's used to
keep that magnet cold they're both very
expensive systems and and together they
constitute the majority of the cost of
the fusion reactor and these things all
have to be put together along with the
containment system that captures the
energetic neutrons released by that
reaction and then the energy has to be
transferred somehow through a a series
of heat exchangers into a power plant
that will produce electricity that's all
going to take a lot of time and and the
materials problems associated with those
subsystems are very complex and they in
some measure will gate how quickly we
can bring those systems to bear in
practice we're at the point now where we
have demonstrated the magnets we need
and this is a breakthrough that occurred
at MIT using high temperature
superconductors for the first time to
produce magnets of the size and strength
that are required for that confinement
and that's what triggered the massive
investment that the fusion industry has
received but Commonwealth Fusion systems
in particular has benefited from that's
enabled them to go forward as though
this is a venture fundable business
which is where we started in this
discussion so this is a startup of sort
of Epic scale and is it a game Cher do
you think in terms of like creating
energy in the US or around the world KY
this is the thing that could change
everything if if we can really make
fusion work we think we can make it work
affordably and and if we can make it
work safely we think we can make it work
safely it's inherently much much safer
than
fision then this could be the technology
that enables us to really decarbonize
the whole world it it won't happen the
day after we get that reactor working in
two years we have a reactor that
actually generates electricity this one
will only generate heat but a reactor
that generates electricity within about
5 years after that and we'll meter it
out onto the grid that will be another
sort of experiment prototype but then
they'll they'll begin developing
commercial reactors that will be sold
kind of in the middle of the next decade
end of the next decade and those things
could go to scale by the middle of the
century I I guess it speaks to something
we were talking about at the very
beginning which is like putting a lot of
bets out there because you don't
actually know when you said like this
could be a game changer but we don't
know and could really be amazing but
there's stuff that's sort of to be
determined still about it and there's
probably a bunch of
really really good bets out there maybe
some not so good bets but you have to
kind of go in and start placing them
right yeah exactly and and you know God
Bless The Venture Capital Community and
a lot of established companies that
really see themselves having to
transition into these new systems new
forms of energy uh in order to to
transition their businesses God bless
them for investing the the billions
that're investing in in these
Technologies Fusion alone as a as a
class of Technologies has attracted over
$6 billion doll worth of investment in
the last few years globally um two
billion of that has gone to Commonwealth
Fusion systems but there are 40 some
maybe 45 other Fusion companies in the
world 25 of them in the United States
trying to do Fusion in similar ways or
in some cases very different ways uh and
it's created a tremendous amount of
excitement and believe it or not we now
have not we don't just have Fusion 50
years in the future the way we did we
have a competition to be there first so
I I mean sort of looking ahead for us
we're going to talk Fusion we're going
to talk wind we're going to talk solar
we're going to talk a whole bunch of
different Technologies batteries
obviously but I think we're also one of
the things I want to dive into a little
bit is the economics of this I mean sort
of looking at all these things like how
do we get from here to there and what
technologies are going to take us there
um what economic approaches are going to
take us there or are holding us back and
we kind kind of talked about the carbon
tax and everything I mean I think that's
our goal right is to think how do you
get there and like start breaking that
down for people in a way that they can
understand what if it works yeah exactly
there we are so we have all of these
Technologies and they're advancing and
they're advancing at different speeds
and different places we have gaps we
have to figure out how to do stuff with
electricity that we don't currently do
with electricity a lot of industrial
processes a lot of Transportation
processes you ever see an electric air
plane you ever seen electric jet uh no
but there's starting to be electric
Freighters out there on the oceans
there're starting to be methanol powered
freighter out there on the oceans maybe
there'll be ammonia powered freighter
out there on the oceans stuff is
advancing we have to figure out how to
put it together and make the new economy
work with all of these different
ingredients we have to train people and
that that unfortunately is a is a
generational problem and that's again an
aspect of
dealing with it right uh and still being
optimistic one of my sort of rules of
thumb is that to replace the energy
infrastructure of a country costs about
a GDP of that country like a whole year
of them earning money and all the stuff
like the value of all that everything
goes into it for year obviously you
can't do that people can't eat they can
nothing else happens so how fast can you
do it well we currently spend something
something like a couple of percent of
GDP on energy infrastructure okay so
that would be 100% divided by 2% a year
so that's 50 years and that's kind of
the natural rate of turnover okay of the
energy systems infrastructure and that
that lesson is pretty much true
everywhere 50 years is too long I was
getting one you thought that was a
little too slow yeah one year is way too
short though so the right answer is
somewhere in the middle so how far can
we push our economy to make stuff happen
sooner is the answer 20 years maybe it
is for the United States is it 50 years
maybe it is for India what is it for
China I don't know it's getting to be
rich a lot of a lot of industrial
capacity there a lot of motivation to
move quickly we don't know we need to
stretch it and we need to adapt well I
look forward to continue this
conversation to keep asking those
questions and just to ask what if it
works and we'll we'll look at all the
things that are currently working and
and may work in the future it's going to
be fun I'm looking forward to
it what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your podcast you can
you can find an archive of every episode
all of our show notes and a lot more at
energy. mit.edu
podcast and you can learn more about the
work of the energy initiative and the
energy transition at energy. mit.edu
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Robson
thanks for listening
[Music]