so now I'd like to introduce our second
speaker Professor admir mesich admir is
Professor of civil and environmental
engineering and principal investigator
in the concrete sustainability Hub at
MIT adm's research focuses on the
science enabled engineering of
sustainable construction materials for
large scale infrastructure Innovation
and today admir will be speaking about
multifunctional concrete and as a quick
reminder if you do have questions for
admir during his talk please do pull up
the Q&A panel type those in there and
we'll get to them as best as we can at
the end of the talk so admir welcome
thank you so much for being here stage
is all
yours thank you very much for the kind
introduction and uh thank you for the
opportunity to uh share some of the work
uh we have been doing in my lab CS Hub
concrete sustainability Hub and the
newly established MIT EC Cube Hub so uh
today uh I would like to uh tackle a
couple of challenges that our society is
facing in the near future uh one of
those is energy storage uh uh uh
Challenge and U um mainly the the uh
issue of uh moving from uh uh
nonrenewable energy uh infrastructure to
renewable energy uh sources
infrastructure and the challenge is the
following if we want to match the
demand uh for energy that during you
know 24 hours is going uh to increase
during the day but then reach a Peak at
about 800 PM in the night if we want to
match this demand we just burn more coal
oil or gas and uh we meet
uh needs uh very easily uh with
non-renewable uh energy sources
nevertheless if we want to move to
renewable energy then uh you know we
think about solar wind and tidal for
example sources then during the day yes
we can satisfy the demand but in the 800
PM night we we really cannot use solar
panels wind is kind of intermittent and
and tidal is oscill and so so the pace
of the transition from fossil fuel based
economy to a renewable energy economy
will strongly depend on the availability
of bulk energy storage solutions to meet
these uh demands so if we think about a
a Solutions of course batteries are uh
uh could be a solution nevertheless
there is a a big problem associated with
batteries minerals for batteries are
Skyes and you see here I plot the
availability of uh uh you you know uh
lithium uh uh from Continental brins
from silicate ores or other sources and
you see there are only few countries
that can supply us with this precious
metal but we need to scale energy
storage we need uh storage solutions
that are available everywhere and which
everyone can uh use now I want to uh
talk about concrete that is close to my
heart uh of course and it's close to my
high because it's strong durable
versatile you can make it in any form
and you see here example of 3D printing
of concrete and mortars you can really
it's very versatile but most important
is extremely inexpensive construction
material it's so inexpensive that uh uh
you know uh if we plot the compressive
strength uh and the price in this Ashby
plot uh the concrete occupies the space
of see 10 cents per kilogram uh which
space very difficult to uh me access
with any other available material
including wood ceramis glass polymers
Composites or Metals so so that's uh
something important about the concrete
another uh uh uh aspect of of concrete
is that demand is increasing constantly
and that's the second challenge we are
uh uh uh you know facing a challenge of
uh population on the planet Earth by
20150 un is predicting to have a 10
billion people on our planet and out of
these 10 billion
6.7 billion people will live in the
cities and that translates into a need
to build cities and need for
materials uh so we are talking about
13,000 buildings every day uh uh needed
to support that migration from rural
areas to urban areas and that will
require materials and materials uh uh
that build our cities are you know uh
cement steel and polymers we just
learned a a beautiful talk before me
about polymers but but you see uh uh
concrete is the most produced material
on planet Earth uh uh it uh uh uh is
made out of cement and if we look at
this graph of production of cement we
talk about four billion metric tons of
cement per uh um per year and uh uh if
you then translate the uh the the amount
of CO2 emitted during this production
which is about 89 ton per uh ton of
cement produced then it turns concrete
and cement me into a problem 8% of
global CO2 emissions can be Associated
only with this material concrete and of
course if we now talk about a carbon
tax and and you know for each of these
tons we have a uh uh we have to uh pay
taxes then the uh the price uh uh point
that uh is advantage of this material
becomes questionable and and so we are
discussing the future is there a future
of of this concrete looks like that
there is no future if we don't transform
and disrupt the industry so uh Port
Association released in October 2021 the
industry is 2050 carbon neutrality road
map uh unfortunately uh uh in this road
map uh we know how to mitigate with only
50% of the emissions associated with
cement and everything else is a part of
exploration and research and what we
believe in in our lives that the that
the key uh uh way to make this material
carbon neutral if not carbon negative is
to introduce new functionalities into it
new functionalities that will
systematically reduce uh uh emissions
Associated uh with the production
through avoided emissions so we could
use less by Design but also improve
longevity maybe through self-healing uh
and uh use concrete as a carbon sink or
even use it as an energy storage device
and this is what I'm going to cover
today we capitalize on chemistry uh here
in my lab and I like to always mention
our colleague Henry vanam who in 2018
published this paper where he says that
concrete is a remarkably Rich deposit of
interesting and contemporary research
questions all contained in its
ambiguities granular or continuous
liquid or solid crystalline or glassy
smooth or rough porous Britt or ductile
material or process all those are
questions associated with this material
and we are really putting effort in
understanding this material from
molecular uh standpoint so let me talk
about one uh functionality that is
improved longevity uh uh American of
civil
engineers uh gave a grade to America's
infrastructure and the score is really
not great it's C minus and uh we really
need to come up with better materials
that perhaps self-heal end last longer
um so there are concretes around the
world and this is the example of of
Roman concrete that uh lasts lasted at
in quite good conditions for 2,000 years
instead of 500 years of power
infrastructure and so so we uh really
would like to understand what are the
origins of the this extreme long-term
durability of ancient Roman concrete and
and how we can translate these
properties into into mod but you see uh
Romans uh made uh their concrete a
little bit different from what we are
doing so they combine volcanic ash with
lime uh and sand and Aggregates to then
and up with a a calcium Alum silicate
hydrate cache that is chemically similar
to what our modern
cement is but it's quite heterogeneous
so you see compared to our modern analog
we we have these uh uh inclusions of
lime that are not present in in modern
systems and and we uh asked the question
of how Relic lime CLA these inclusions
are formed in ancient samples but also
how can they be uh missing and could
they be the missing link for
self-healing picture and uh we
analyzed ancient uh materials and lime
classs and we found out that Relic lime
clust might serve as a long-term source
of reactive calcium which is really
important for selfhealing and uh we also
found out that they are formed because
the Romans probably hot mix their
mortars using quick lime calcium oxide
instead of uh processing lime quick
climb before introducing into the mortar
they added the quick climb directly you
see in this video directly into the into
the mix you you add a quick climb and
and here we go and and then this mortar
heats up you see and and you will see
temperatures that go up to 90 degre C
80° C uh with hotpots of maybe 200° C in
the in the mix uh maintaining leaving
these lime class isolated and uh
available for healing and this is what
we then demonstrated in the in the
modern analog here at the bottom where
line clouds that we uh managed to
incorporate into modern concrete then
reflect the morphology and the chemistry
of the Ancient Ancient ones so we of of
course tested these new uh designs uh
for selfhealing which is a typical test
you take these cylinders you break them
and and make a crack of standard
distance Dimension and then you let
water flow through and you get healing
that actually um uh in our sample
systematically healed uh uh whereas the
uh The Standard Concrete would never uh
never stop the water from flowing and
heal in the cracks we observed a filling
agent that was a cite showing that
indeed calcium rich uh um um components
eventually reacted and healed and we
published this work uh in 2023 and uh it
received a lot of media
coverage the good example is that this
article at the MIT news was the most
viewed article ever to appear on MIT
News website which was kind of uh
shocking to to to to us more importantly
uh we uh patented this uh uh these mixes
and eventually uh started a a startup
dmat um that Cory mentioned and and now
this technology is AA available uh ready
to use anywhere in the world it's
self-healing concrete Roman inspire
uh concrete that uh uh increases the
lifespan of 50% and uh uh
50% allows 50% cost reduction compared
to other self-healing Solutions uh to
addition to this also reduces the uh uh
um emissions associated with this mix by
75 kilogram so you can for example sell
these as a carbon credits if you want
good so dmat let me move on to the other
function that is electrical conductivity
and energy storage uh solution and here
you see we are talking about electron
conductivity but concrete is an great
material but insulator so uh you can
though make this material conducted by
introducing
particles in in it in our case we
introduced Nano carbon black particles
and created this carbon black cement
composite that indeed conducts
electricity uh uh it conducts
electricity to this Nano viring that
happens through the process of hydration
and liberation of pores for carbon black
to self assemble magically you know in
the in the poe structure leading to then
a a a continuous volumetric wire uh
Network maintaining though the load
bearing characteristics and now we have
this electron conducting carbon cement
based material or electron AC Cube or
also electron conducting carbon concrete
which uh uh yes gives you conductivity
so resistivity drops but the price is
still in the range of
inexpensive materials and uh allows a
lot of uh different app applications
which could be a free store resistance
self heating energy storage or even high
electron uh high power electromagnetic
impulses um um shielding so uh I will
just quickly touch two of these
applications that we find very exciting
uh one is self heating it's a standard
Jewel effect you apply a voltage to a
material it's like in your stove play
uh based on voltage temperature
increases and you see if you put 6% of
carbon black into your cement composite
and apply five uh volts potentially you
get 100 degre C temperature of your slab
and and we uh use this recently in this
demo in in saporo in Japan with our
Japanese colleagues at the AC Cube Hub
you see minus 3° C
uh there was a snow melting on these uh
on these uh snow melting walk sidewalks
for example and here is the national
television reporting on this there is a
nice part where uh where indeed um they
show the moment where the
snow is coming it's snowing you know and
and these um these SLS here you go they
are covered by snow but as soon as you
apply the potential see 24 Vols nicely
uh nicely melts quickly and 12 volts is
slower a little bit but still eventually
ends up U uh uh melting all the snow and
we are very excited to uh use this
technology in the real world in saporo
uh and uh let me uh finish with the
energy storage so here we are talking
about the uh uh the
energy transition and the current
battery technologies are difficult to
scale to the size we need for this
transition and and we need a bulk energy
storage and this could be a solution so
concrete batteries actually they are not
batteries they are super capacitors and
super capacitor is very similar to
battery it has two electrodes but
instead of using chemical energy uh uh
translating into electrical energy here
you have just electrolyte splitting and
charging is just a a separation of of
electrolyte ions uh and uh this is
possible in our material because the
carbons that we use have a high surface
area and and we can you see build little
uh units of super capacitor with a KCl
um electrolyte and and then you can
connect them in series one one and and
live this nice LED make 12
volts series or this is a 12 volt
mesoscale our EC Cub set per capacitor
and the important number here is this
number here 300 V hours per cubic meter
uh which is of course diluted uh you
know it's not super dense but it's a
good number because we can imagine to
use the 30 35
cubic meters of this material to satisfy
daily need uh of 10 kilow
hour uh per day for a household uh also
this paper received a lot of visibility
and even we got a a priz from National
Academy of Sciences in 2023 POI prize
finalist uh so now though uh the
question is how do we use this and and
this opens really a new uh uh space for
system design and you know
multifunctional concrete that uh maybe
it's going to be these bricks that will
you know store energy and we will use
them in the walls of our new houses or
we build foundations 33 cubic meters you
see of of our material will satisfy
daily need and so off grid home
foundations uh and walls as the
batteries is a is an exciting
perspective of course high end would be
be to allow transition from not electric
cars to electric cars by using our super
capacitor energy storage units
underneath roads that collect renewable
energy and then charge the cars through
induction and uh and yes we think that
concrete has a bright future it's a
multi-functional future uh renewable
energy storage early age CO2 secretion I
didn't have time to talk about this but
it's 15% of CO2 total emission can be
mineralized in concrete and enhanced
durability are ways to go for We Believe
for this material and and ancient Rome
experienced architectural Revolution
through Discovery and use of concrete uh
we may be on the verge of a new
breakthrough that could completely
revolutionize our perception of concrete
architecture and the overall built
environment and its multifunctional
concrete with this I would thank you for
uh your attention uh I want to
acknowledge
collaborators uh that are many here and
um I'm happy to take
questions admir thank you so much for a
really interesting talk I see we do have
some questions uh coming up in the Q&A
panel again if you have questions please
drop them in there this is from Larry
why hasn't fly ash based concrete moveed
forward demonstrated in 2005 that fly
ash is a on toone replacement for
Portland cement it cures quicker and
stronger and of course deals with a
major environmental problem that's right
it is there uh it's um the problem is
that is in the part of my pie chart of
50% uh that we know how to deal
with so so flyash replaces the ordinary
Port but you always need to have 50% of
OPC in these
mixes uh it's you cannot push it Beyond
those numbers you have to have always
50% uh uh OPC and the and the other uh
uh you know replacement that then uh
plays the job do does the job you cannot
100% replace
it thanks adir okay let me um jump
around a little bit here too uh I see a
question from Yos how does lime cast
based self-healing concrete compare with
bacteria based self-healing Concrete in
terms of relative performance crack
healing efficiency cost and
scalability that's a great question so
imagine
bacteria uh uh in these self-healing
Solutions are dormant they uh are
activated where the crack goes through
uh they then basically uh uh start
producing calcium carbonate and and uh
deposit the crack you know deposit this
material in the cracks and heal and
stops the water so from the performance
standpoint they are very comparable
there is a main difference that uh
bacteria need to be fed uh to uh do the
job and that's the challenge that these
Technologies face uh uh and and this uh
Roman
inspired calcium source is inorganic of
inorganic nature and therefore uh
doesn't need any sort of U um
food but they are very comparable in
terms of
performance interesting thanks adir so
I'll on that note excuse me and to blend
a couple of questions that I see here uh
from harri Pria and also from
Mike on the topic of Roman concrete how
does the strength of Roman concrete
compare to high strength concrete also
what would be the impact on the quantity
of lime used to produce regular versus
Roman concrete and then I think to
Mike's Point uh are there any downsides
to the Roman inspired concrete perfect
these are that's the reason why the
Roman concrete is not being used right
now and we stick to ordinary Portland
cement because mechanical performance of
ancient Roman recipe is not good like
it's 10 megap Pascal Max okay and this
this performance cannot compete with
with anything we use and cannot be used
for skycrapers uh you know uh in in New
York a beautiful high aspect ratio
skyscrapers where the concrete has to be
super ultra high performance uh uh but
the um important thing to say the Roman
inspired is not the Roman recipe is just
the self-healing component that is
introduced into a modern uh analog
maintaining performances and of course
you need to tune it and demat did a huge
work in tuning the proportions so that
we are still in the in the range of of
uh uh standards uh that are applied in
the in modern industry but maintaining
the the performance and demat is the
right place to go to ask all the details
how they manage to to do this and I
think they are doing a wonderful job uh
in in um in moving this Roman inspired
self-healing uh products into a space
that is available right now you can
right now go and uh and buy thead
additives that are going to make your
concrete
selfhealing uh here's another one from
Ariel how resilient is the conducting
concrete to seawater
we don't know that's a great question uh
it's it's something that we we are
actively working on uh this uh
conductive concrete composite is
something that is new uh and there are
many questions around this and the EC
Cube Hub uh is a newly formed industrial
Consortium uh um that uh will tackle all
these questions in next five years
another question from Nick who wants to
know will
self-healing concrete cause will
self-healing cause cause the expansion
of the total uh components over long
times no no because uh it's just gonna
fill the pores and
cracks understood okay uh another
question here too uh what is your TRL
technology Readiness level I believe for
electron conducting concrete what are
the constraints and challenges involved
in Manu manufacturing this products I
mean it's a new material on the so now
you see it's a material that we
understand fairly well but every
application will require a separate you
know piece of knowledge that uh will uh
need will be needed to then uh move into
the real world and for example for this
uh uh
self-heating uh slabs I showed that
there is not many bottlenecks apart
tuning the mix and M putting some
reinforcement because of thermal
expansion of of layers that uh they
undergo through from minus 3 degrees to
40° C uh 50° C that we apply with the
voltage so so that's I don't think there
there are limitations there uh uh to
move quickly into into real world uh of
course if you talk about uh you know
energy storage and and having these uh
35 cubic meters of material underneath
the house there is there is needed a lot
of uh design input and Engineering to
really come up with solutions that are
you know within standards that maintain
mechanical performance uh but still it's
for us the most important thing is that
it's scalable first so there are no
Metals in it it's just carbon black and
cement and concrete and the number that
came out about the charge density is in
the orders of magnitude of what we would
need maybe that number could have been
you know 100 cubic meters instead of 30
cubic meters that it's like a problem
and so so we we are very very positive
in uh in you know uh uh possibilities in
of translating this into the
real and Mir thank you thank you so much
for a very interesting talk I see we
have an abundance of questions here and
unfortunately uh we are just about over
time so I would encourage everybody to
reach out directly admir to you if they
have questions um and uh I I can
certainly uh uh help with that as well
so edir once again thank you for being
here and thank you for a wonderful talk
thank you very much
okay so thank you audience for being
here uh at your lunch hour here on the
East Coast uh this concludes today's
Leading Edge webinar on sustainable
materials Plastics and Pavements and
again if you have any additional
questions please feel free to reach out
to the the re researchers directly and
for ILP members uh you can also contact
your program director who can help with
follow-ups as well so in closing before
we go just I'll leave you with a couple
reminders of some of our events here
again on April the 1st 2025 we have our
MIT artificial intelligence conference
that's on campus in person and also live
streaming April the 10th starting at
10:00 a.m. eastern time it's the next
Leading Edge webinar the topic for that
is computationally assisted materials
Discovery and if you really like Brad's
talk I I think you're going to want to
tune in for that next webinar as well
May 8th 2025 that's MIT polymer day
that's everything polymers the focus
there is on a very well-run poster
competition if you're interested in
speaking to the researchers in polymer
MIT great event to go to and then
finally don't forget our startup
exchange if you're interested in any of
the startups such as dmat that admir
mentioned today please go to Startup
exchange. mit.edu and you'll find a
whole bunch more there as well and then
a post note excuse me is that this
webinar actually will also be
rebroadcast on Friday the 28th of March
it's two weeks approximately from now
and that is at 12m Japan time again
Japan time Friday 28th March and that is
for the convenience of our East Asian
and Southeast Asian audience so thanks
again so much for tuning in thank you to
our speakers thank you to the audience
you thank you to our production crew for
this webinar I hope you have a great
afternoon and I hope to see you on
campus soon myself take care