Welcome to the MIA 10-year anniversary
celebration. I'm Caroline Ooler,
director of the Eric and Wendy Schmidt
Center at the Broad Institute, which has
been proudly hosting the models,
Inference, and Algorithms MIA meetings
for the past few years. We're so excited
to bring the MIA community together
today for this milestone event. It's the
perfect chance to reflect on the past 10
years, celebrate all that's been
accomplished, and look ahead to the
dynamic future of MIA. A special thanks
to our panelists, Alex Blowmendal, one
of MIA's co-founders, Aviv Rev,
Alexandrina Goeva, and Gavororg
Gregorian. We're so happy to have you.
MIA has been instrumental in bridging
communities across mathematics,
statistics, machine learning, and
biology. We've been hearing from leading
and emerging researchers about the
latest research that's going on, but
also the motivation and intuition that
go into the development of the proposed
methods. Again and again, participants
leave the talks having absorbed new
ideas that they apply to their own
research, and that's what makes MIA so
unique. Through these meetings, we're
proud to have built a community where
disciplines meet and new ideas spark. We
can't wait to see what the future of MIA
holds and the broader interdisciplinary
field it continues to shape. And now
I'll hand it over to other members of
the steering committee. Thank you for
being such an important part of the MIA
community.