(air whooshing)
(text buzzing)
- "What are the current limitations
of LLMs in financial contexts
and how might future advancements in areas
like causal reasoning and
knowledge representation
unlock new possibilities?"
Well, that's a really
interesting question.
There are a number of limitations
that I think many people know about.
LLMs are not that good at numbers per se.
They're very good with language,
but for whatever reason,
when you start asking numerical questions,
they easily get tripped up.
A friend of mine recently
just gave me an example.
Try asking LLM to name all of the capitals
of European countries and
rank them by population.
That seems like a pretty
straightforward question,
but you'd be surprised how difficult it is
for typical LLMs to get that correct.
And there are all sorts of conjectures
as to why that might be the
case, but we don't really know.
And so at this point, we
need to start coming up
with better ways of informing LLMs
with respect to these kinds
of numerical questions
and to be able to integrate them
into their text-based abilities.
That's a key aspect of financial context
because everything that we do
in finance is both numbers and language.
In terms of causal reasoning,
now this is getting on the
border of the theoretical
and beyond it the science fiction.
The question that I sometimes
get asked by my students is,
do LMS really understand?
And you know,
I have to answer the
question with the question,
which is, well, what do
you mean by understand?
And that's a very difficult
concept to deconstruct
because we ourselves don't understand
what we mean by understand.
But lemme give you an idea
of how I'm beginning to
understand understanding.
The way that you test
whether somebody really
understands something is very much
like how we test our PhD candidates
when we give 'em the oral exam.
And I'll tell you how I give my oral exam.
I'll start with an easy question,
and if the student
that's taking the exam
answers it correctly,
I'll move on, and I'll
give 'em a harder version.
And if they answer that correctly,
I'll give them yet another
version that's even harder.
And I'll keep increasing
the level of difficulty
and changing the context of the question
to really probe the limits
of that student's knowledge.
Because what I wanna understand
is how much they understand,
how deep is their understanding.
So at some point, I'll get to the point
where a student will get it wrong,
and that tells me that they
don't really understand
the particular question that I'm asking.
And I'll ask them one
more question after that,
that is deeper still,
just to see whether or not it
was just a careless mistake
or whether or not it's really true
that now we're in deeper waters
that they really haven't ever tread.
And if they continue to
falter, I will have determined
that that's their level of understanding.
So let's apply that approach
to a large language model.
We ask it a question,
it provides an answer,
and the answer seems correct.
We'll provide a harder version,
and that seems correct.
At some point, we will reach a level
where the LLM will not be
able to answer correctly.
And so you can think of it as going down
below the level of knowledge to the point
where there's no more
answers to be gotten.
That kind of depth of knowledge
is a form of understanding.
Right now, I would say that
LLMs are quite shallow.
They can answer in complete sentences.
Most of those sentences make sense.
And if you ask them questions,
they can usually provide
reasonably correct answers.
If you ask them to write a piece of code
that engages in certain calculations,
they can usually do that correctly,
perhaps with some modification.
But that tells me that their level
of understanding is very shallow.
The next generation of LLMs
ought to be able to answer questions
at 2, 3, 4 levels of depth.
And there will come a point in time
where they will exceed our capacity
to answer those questions.
And at that point,
I believe we will then
say they understand,
and then causal reasoning
will be possible.
So it's coming, but in the world of LLMs,
it's gonna take a while
before they get to the point
where we consider it to be
truly causal understanding.
We've got a question from one
of our social media followers.
"Applications of machine learning
to forecast in clinical trial outcomes
and improving investment performance
in the biopharma industry."
Thank you for that.
That's referring to some research
that I've done over the last few years
with a number of my collaborators
applying machine learning techniques
to predicting the outcome
of clinical trials.
I got interested in that
because a number of friends
and family were dealing
with various kinds of
cancer a few years ago,
and I realized that actually
money plays a huge role
in drug development.
It turns out that money can be scarce,
particularly at the very
earliest stages of drug discovery
because that's when the
risk is the highest.
And so the so-called valley
of death between, you know,
early stage research and the
first in human clinical trials,
that's the area that I
started thinking about
how do we get more money
to come into that space
to help get over this valley of death?
And the answer of course
is you need investors,
but how do you attract investors?
The way you attract
them is by demonstrating
that there are some
attractive opportunities
to make money with their capital.
And in order to do that,
you need to have some kind
of statistical framework
for thinking about risk and reward.
Over the last few years, my collaborators
and I have applied machine
learning techniques,
and now we're using large language models
to try to read all of
the body of information
about medical clinical trials
and what kinds of features tend
to make them more successful
and other features that
make them less successful.
And use those features to predict outcomes
so that we can tell investors,
under what circumstances
are you likely to do better
or worse, we can actually
provide them with a framework
for thinking about how to manage risk.
And if we do that,
we assume that they will
then be more willing
to deploy their capital as
they have in other industries
where these tools have
been made available.
So stay tuned,
and hopefully we'll be able
to tell you more about that
over the course of the next few years
as we apply these models
in practical circumstances.
Okay, another social media post.
"What's the dark side of AI,
and what's the bright side,
and which is more likely to occur?"
Well, that's the age old
question of good versus evil,
and happy to talk about both.
I think I already mentioned a
bit about the dark side of AI.
Powerful tools can be
used for adverse purposes.
Things like cheating on your tax returns,
coming up with fake news
that will fool a certain
part of the population
for financial or political gain.
Those are the kinds of things
that not only can AI be used for,
but I suspect that has
already been used for.
And so I think that we really need
to consider ways of guarding against that.
We need antidotes for fake
news and for manipulation.
That really is not what we
intend with these amazing tools.
On the positive side, I think
there is tremendous potential
for AI to transform society.
I'll give you one very,
very simple example
that's already being done.
If you take patient medical records
and look at the various
different kinds of behaviors
that people engage in
and the diseases that they suffer from,
we now are able to come up
with all sorts of hypotheses
for certain kinds of things
that we can do to improve our health.
Now you already know some of
those things, like exercise,
have a proper balanced diet,
sleep well, so on and so forth.
But there are lots of nuances
to those broad-based pieces of advice
that have to be tailored just to you.
And so this is where
LLMs can really shine.
They can take your medical
records, they take the sum total
of all of the knowledge
that's in the medical system
and ultimately tailor that advice
to be suited to your
particular health goals.
Now we're not there yet because obviously
the hallucination problem
can be very, very dangerous
in the medical context,
but I don't think we're that far away,
particularly given the rapid pace
at which we're making progress.
Okay, another social media post.
"How can non-engineers
get involved in AI?"
That's a wonderful question.
One of the reasons that I
was so excited by the advent
of broad-based large language models,
and you've already played
with many of them, I'm sure,
large language models have democratized AI
so that you don't have to be
an engineer to make use of AI.
That wasn't true a couple of years ago.
If you wanted to use machine learning,
you needed to have programming experience.
There were very few generic,
non-technical machine
learning engines, if any,
that would allow people
who didn't understand the intricacies
of these various different
random forest models and so on
to be able to use them in any
way that would be beneficial.
With large language models,
we can actually speak in plain English.
And moreover, there are
a number of non-engineers
that I've met who have
become extraordinarily good
at formulating just the right
prompt in order to be able
to get their desired outcome
from these different LLMs.
So I think the answer is absolutely
non-engineers can become
extremely adept at AI.
And the way to do it is to use it,
start playing with your favorite LLM
and just talk to it, ask
it a bunch of questions.
In a way,
that's kind of how we
develop relationships
right now with our human friends.
We begin by asking them questions
and gauging their answers.
And based upon what we hear,
we either decide to become
better friends with them
or decide stay away, we're not interested.
With LLMs, we need to talk with
them in order to understand
how they operate, understand
where they're coming from,
understand what they can do for us.
And once we develop that
kind of, dare I say rapport,
we will then be adept at
being able to prompt them
in the most efficient manner.
You do not have to have
an engineering degree
to be able to do that.
Anybody watching this video can do this,
and I would urge you all to try
doing it as soon as you can.
Another social media post,
"Are cryptocurrencies
a temporary phenomenon,
or are they here to stay?"
Yes, they are here to stay,
but no, the cryptocurrency
that your trading may not be here forever.
The idea of cryptocurrency
is extremely powerful,
and it provides enormous benefits
for financial transactions of
a variety of different sorts.
At the same time, it also
has a number of flaws
that can be exploited by bad actors
and the improper usage of crypto.
A lot's gonna change over the
course of the next few years.
In fact, one of the biggest changes
that I think we all
should all watch out for
is when a very large and
stable sovereign entity decides
to issue crypto of its own.
For example, imagine the
United States decides
to issue Fed Coin and that
becomes the cryptocurrency
of preference for the entire world.
If that happens,
then the existing cryptocurrencies
may not do as well.
Without a doubt,
some of them will become
worthless overnight.
And if that's your currency
that you're holding your wealth in,
that's not good news for you.
In a way, this happened in the 1800s,
because as the west was
being developed in the US,
a number of banks arose to
finance that kind of development,
and these banks would
print their own currency
to be able to hand out to
workers that wanted to get paid.
And of course, these are like bonds
that the banks were issuing.
The problem is that every once in a while
these pieces of paper
would become worthless
because the bank would go outta business,
they would extend too far,
and they couldn't basically make good
on all of these pieces of paper.
Now, these pieces of paper
often had pictures of wildcats on them
because that's what,
that's the animal that dominated
the population of the west
as it was being developed.
And so this phenomenon
called wildcat banking
became quite prominent in the mid-1800s.
And at some point, the number
of failures became so bad
that the US government stepped in
and basically shut down this
whole wildcat banking system
by creating the Federal Reserve
and providing a much broader base of laws
and the US currency
that supplanted all of
these wildcat currencies.
So pretty much overnight,
as the US began to issue its own currency,
that made these particular
smaller currencies worthless.
If a sovereign entity were
to issue a cryptocurrency
and that ended up taking the place
of a number of existing
currencies, you need to worry about
whether or not your currency is the one
that's gonna become worthless.
So that's one of the challenges
of investing in crypto.
But without a doubt,
the technology that is used
in crypto is here to stay.
And I believe that
cryptocurrencies themselves
as an asset class are here to stay.
But you need to think about
how to manage that risk very carefully.
Can't believe it, but
this is the last question
from our social media friend.
"How can we deal with large
scale market manipulation
now that LMS are so cheap
to deploy at large scale?"
Wow, what a question to end on.
So it turns out that one of the things
that large language models
could be very capable of
is providing fraudsters
and other bad actors
with the appropriate technology
for disrupting financial stability.
Now, this may seem farfetched,
but I bet you if you ask
the large language model
how to build an atomic bomb,
you'd probably get a
pretty reasonable answer.
And so it actually scares
me that now the knowledge
of the entire financial
literature is available
to bad actors who can
use large language models
to summarize the ways
that they can involve
their various different nefarious plots
within the financial system.
The regulators also have access
to large language models,
and I believe that they are
also using the tools of AI
to figure out how to detect
these kinds of schemes
while they're being hatched
and before they occur.
But as I said earlier, it is an arms race,
and this is one of the reasons
why we at CSAIL are making these videos.
We want all of you to start thinking about
how to use these tools to
make society a better place.
There's no doubt that
there's tremendous value
in these new technologies,
but there's also some potential dangers
that we have to worry about.
And the only way that we're
gonna get better at it
is if more and better people are involved.
Well, that's it for the questions.
Can't believe that we're all done,
but thank you so much for
taking the time to submit them.
It was fascinating,
and I look forward to seeing
you in the next video.
Bye-Bye.