Good afternoon everyone. Good afternoon.
It's so wonderful seeing you all here
and also with appreciation to our
virtual attendees. I'm Alexia Hudson
Ward, associate director of research,
learning, and strategic partnerships for
the MIT libraries. On behalf of our
director, Chris Berg, I welcome you to
our hybrid MIT Reads spring 2025 event.
Our MIT Reads program invites the MIT
community to hear from leading authors
and to engage in solution centered
discourse on some of the most complex
challenges facing our campus community,
the nation, and the world. Thank you so
much for joining us here in person and
online. Now, before we begin, and
because we are all friends, I'm going to
ask you to place any device that rings,
chimes, chirps, barks, meows, or moves
into vibrate or silent mode. Please,
right now, our event tonight will be
recorded and posted for future viewing.
Many thanks to Sylvia Figurora Ortiz, Ya
Fuja Ross, and Emily Kramer of the MIT
Libraries Community Engagement Team for
coordinating tonight's event. Special
thanks to our co-sponsors MIT's Women
and Gender Services Office, the ICO
Office, and Mind Hand and Heart for
their generous financial support. and to
our promotional partners MIT Health, the
MIT Press, and the Graduate Student
Council's Diversity, Equity, and
Inclusion Committee for their assistance
with promoting tonight's event. Our
feature book is available for purchase
this evening from the MIT Press who have
a table set up adjacent to this meeting
space. And also, our colleagues from the
MIT Health Unit are here giving some
giving away some goodies as well. The
event flow is as follows. After
introductions, our speakers will give a
presentation and then we'll move into
dialogue with our speakers and the
moderator. After the dialogue, the
floor, both virtually and in person,
will be open to your questions. The
authors have also generously provided
some of their workbooks and we will
raffle them off at the conclusion of
tonight's event. After our event, we
invite those who are attending in person
to join us for a book signing and also
the light dinner that's hosted by the
libraries and actually the books are
already pre-signed so you can pick them
up from the press accordingly. And so
now on to the introductions of tonight's
speakers and moderator. Many thanks to
this evening's moderator, Dr. Karen
Singleton who is the deputy chief health
officer of MIT Health. A graduate of
Bark College, Columbia University, and
the City University of New York. Karen
was also the interim executive director
of student health services at Columbia
University Medical Center and the
director of student mental health
services prior to joining MIT Health in
2016. She is the past director of that
school's sexual violence prevention and
response program and a practicing
clinical psychologist with expertise in
sexual trauma, grief, eating disorders,
and issues related to race, ethnicity,
and sexual orientation. She has
consulted to a wide range of
organizations and publications including
the United Nations, Essence Magazine,
the Journal of Ethnic Minority
Psychology, and the Takeback the Night
Foundation, and has served on mental
health and well-being advisory
committees for many universities
including Princeton, Harvard, Cornell,
and the University of Chicago. Karen is
one of the proud recipients of the 2021
Leighton Whitaker Memorial Award for
Excellence in Counseling Center
Scholarship and also serves on the
advisory board for the Health Systems
Initiative at MIT Sloan. We are pleased
to welcome Dr. Emily Nagoski and Dr.
Ameilia Nagoski, who are yes, sisters
and identical
twins, and the co-authors of the New
York Times best-selling book, Burnout:
The Secret to Unlocking the Stress
Cycle. referred to as quote a primer on
how to stop letting the world dictate
how you live and what we think of
ourselves by bustle. Burnout
thoughtfully approaches complex topics
such as human giver syndrome and
unlearning helplessness with compassion,
wit, and a plan. Emily is also the New
York Times best-selling and
award-winning author of Come As You Are:
The Surprising New Science That Will
Transform Your Sex Life and Come
Together: The Science and Art of
Creating Lasting Sexual Connections. She
earned an MS in counseling and a PhD in
health behavior, both from Indiana
University, with clinical and research
training at the Kinsey Institute. She
now combines sexual education and stress
education to teach women how to live
with confidence and joy inside their own
bodies. She lives in Massachusetts with
two dogs, a cat, and a cartoonist.
Amelia Amelia was the associate
professor and coordinator of music at
Western New England University. She
specializes in educating others on the
application of communication science and
psychological research for audiences of
other professional musicians, including
embodied wellness for conductors. She
has a doctorate in musical arts and
conducting from the University of
Connecticut and lives in New England
with her spouse and her pets pets.
Please join me in welcoming both Ameilia
and Emily to MIT. Thank you so much for
being here. Thank you.
Oh, I have the
power. Uh, for those who are wondering,
I am the Emily one. This is the Amelia
one. My pronouns are she, they for the
record. Yeah. Uh, we need to update your
bio. Oh, probably that's a new thing.
Whatever. Keep going.
Okay. Uh, so we talked about it this
afternoon and, uh, we were like, we want
to get as much science in as fast as
possible. So, we're going to skip a lot
of the fun, entertaining anecdotes, but
if you saw that photo of us as children
and are interested to know the story of
the missing front teeth, please ask that
in the Q&A. I tell the story in in my uh
most recent book, Come
Together. Okay. So, we're starting the
story with me because I'm a musician.
How did I come to co-write a book about
stress, especially like a socially and
scienceinformed book about stress? And
you can go ahead and and click the thing
because the answer is is that person
over there. Um, when I was in my
doctoral program, I uh was hospitalized
twice for stress induced illness. And
meanwhile, Emily was writing her first
book, Come as You Are, the secret to
whatever the thing subtitle is. I don't
even know. I'm so sorry. Uh when she
went all around the world talking to
women about the science of women's
sexuality, which is what that book is
about, they would come and say to her,
"Amelia, Emily, whoever you are, the all
that all that sex science is great, but
you know, the part that really
resonated, the part that meant so and
changed everything for me was that one
little part about emotions and stress
and processing your feelings." And she
was really surprised. She spent so much
time on the sex science. Uh, and
I was not surprised at all because I She
said, "No shit." Yeah. Because I
attended a conservatory and in my
musical training, I was taught
explicitly how to process and express
emotions for the purpose of performance
on stage. What I did not learn was that
that was the thing I could apply
daytoday. And when I did learn that
stuff, it saved my life twice. and she
said, "Oh, we should write a book about
that." So, if you click the slide again,
that book will appear. And there it is.
It's burnout is the result of that. Um,
so what we're going to talk about today,
click the slide again. Um, are those
things the things that I learned that
saved my life when I was the most burnt
out uh people get without dying. Uh, and
that's going to be seven concrete,
specific evidence-based things you can
do to feel better right now. Our goal is
that as you are sitting here with us
today, the way you feel now will be
improved by the time you leave this
room. Heck yeah. I'm hoping that's I'm
hoping that's a realistic goal. We're
also going to tell you, look, is there
anybody aware who already knows that
sleep is good for you? Did you do you
know sleep good for you? You already
knew. So, there's going to be
um some of this stuff is going to seem
obvious. So, we're going to talk about
why even though we know some of this
stuff, we're not already doing it. The
answer is not because otherwise we're
just up here like exercise, sleep,
right, friends. Yeah.
The problem is not that you're not
trying hard enough or that you're not
already working hard enough. You you are
already trying as hard as you can all
day every day. So why doesn't it work?
We're going to talk about what that
barrier is. And of course, because we
are focused on
solutions, how to overcome that barrier.
So we got to define our terms first.
We're going to talk about what burnout
is. And first we need to give our
definition of wellness which is wellness
is not a state of mind or a state of
being. It is the freedom to oscillate
through all the cycles of being human. A
state of action. So stress is not your
enemy. Getting stuck is your enemy when
you are no longer free to oscillate.
Which is why we're st starting here in
what looks like a deep dark cave. It's
not a cave. Turns out it's a
tunnel. So if you're going to get
unstuck and escape the tunnel, that's a
fantastic metaphor. As Emily says,
emotions are tunnels. You have to move
all the way through the darkness to get
to the light at the end. And yes, she
choreographed the thing. Yep. Um, so, so
how do we get unstuck? How do we get out
of the tunnel? Oh, can I do this whole
part? You got to do the whole thing.
Yeah. Excellent. Great. I'm probably I'm
probably gonna end up like standing up
and walking around. Both of us are
physically disabled by long COVID
because long co um but I often cannot
resist getting up and walking around
even. So um the most if you remember
nothing I'm going to say this multiple
times. If you remember nothing else,
remember this one thing.
The process of dealing with the stress
in your body is separate from the
process of dealing with the things that
activated the stress in your body.
There's your stress and then there's
your stress sores and the strategies for
dealing with the things that cause your
stress. So, for example, if you're I
don't know, maybe you're a woman for
example, couple of people here might be,
and maybe you have a boss who um isn't
always awesome.
The way you deal with your stress or is
you go
mhm. Thank you for that
feedback. And then and then you walk out
and you
go the first one. Thank you for that
feedback is dealing with the stress or
appropriately because you want to keep
your job. The second one is dealing with
the stress itself. So let's talk about
the stress itself because it turns out
because we are monkeys and we're
monkeys, not just apes because you can't
evolve out of a clay. That's a sentence
I can use here and it makes me
happy. Because we're monkeys,
our biology doesn't differentiate much.
It differentiates a little, but not much
between evolutionary stressors and
modernday stressors. So, we're going to
talk about what our body's physiological
response is. First thing that happens
is you are confronted with a stressor.
For example, being chased by a
saber-tooth tiger. These illustrations,
by the way, are by from Erica Men, the
cartoonist who also illustrated Come as
You Are. Um, and your whole body floods
with adrenaline and cortisol and
gluccocorticoids. Oh my. And the purpose
of all of this chemistry which results
in massive changes in your physiological
functioning. Your heart rate goes up and
your blood pressure goes up and your
digestive system gets suppressed and
your immune system gets suppressed and
blood moves away from the surface of
your skin because if you get cut you'll
bleed less that way like massive physio
attention changes so that you are
focused on like the here and now tunnel
vision I just need to fix this one
problem so you lose creativity when
you're stressed out all so that you And
what?
Yeah. And when you're being chased by a
saber-tooth tiger, what do you do to
survive? Run. You run. Yes. Absolutely.
And when you're being chased by a
saber-tooth tiger, Emily, they're
running as an
animation. At this point, there's only
two possible outcomes. Either you get
eaten by the saber-tooth tiger, in which
case none of the rest of this matters,
or you escape. So, let's imagine a world
where you manage to run back to your
village this very You're faster than a
saber-tooth tiger in this hypothetical
situation. And you like somebody sees
you coming and they wave you into the
door and you both stand with your
shoulders against the door and you roar
in the scraping at the door and
eventually this saber-tooth
tiger leaves up, walks away. It's going
to find somebody else to feed to her
children. And when you see the
saber-tooth tiger walk away, how do you
feel?
Relieved.
grateful to be alive. You love your
friends and family. The sun seems to
shine brighter. You want to tell this
story. And oh, are you going to tell
this story over and over and over again?
That is the complete stress response
cycle. And it's easy to think that it is
the running that completed the stress
response cycle. It's easy to think that
it is the disappearance of the
saber-tooth tiger, the dealing with the
stressor that got rid of the stress that
completed the stress response cycle. It
turns
out running is great. It is one of the
most effective and efficient strategies
for completing the stress response cycle
because when that stress response get
activated, it's for activating you to
escape, to survive as so many people
said. But uh running is not always
available to all of us all the time.
Fortunately, we
have more than seven concrete specific
evidence-based strategies for completing
the stress response cycle which will put
you in a good enough physical and mental
state to be able to deal with whatever
the stressor was in the first place.
Because alak alas, we are almost never
chased by saber-tooth tigers anymore.
in order to get unstuck because most of
us are walking around with countless
incomplete stress response cycles. The
beautiful thing about the human body is
it'll just hold on to it for us. Like it
gets activated and it's like, "Oh,
you're not going to you're not going to
do anything about this. Cool. I will
stuff this in another organ system."
Maybe it's your digestive system. Must
be it's your muscularkeeletal system.
You may have an intuition about which
organ system your body chooses to put
your incomplete stress response
cycles. Fortunately, it will hold on to
that for you for as long as it needs to.
It will eventually cause disease, but
that's in the long term. You can get
unstuck. all of those incomplete stress
response cycles in your body, you can
get
unstuck if you deal with the stress
itself, which is a separate process from
dealing with the things that cause the
stress. Ready? Seven concrete specific
evidence-based strategies. We're going
to complete the cycle. We're going to go
through the tunnel. The first thing, as
Emily was saying, is physical. Who knew
that exercise is good? Good for you. You
did. You already knew. This is this is
the main reason why. And at a population
level, your body at a population level,
bodies learn that they have the capacity
to move you from danger to safety when
you move them. Um, Emily, my identical
twin, raised in the same house with me,
could go for a bike ride. We grew up in
Delaware. She could ride all the way
into Pennsylvania to the farmlands with
the cows and the sk and come back and
feel like the weight of the world is
lifted off her shoulders. And I thought
she was making it up because I identical
twin raised in the same household have
never had that experience because at a
population level, yes, it's the most
efficient thing. That doesn't mean it's
true for any one individual. Doesn't
mean that the science isn't right that
it's the most effective at a population
level. It just means it's not true for
everybody. And we are a great
illustration to show you don't know who
is going to respond to what. Um, there
are other limitations to physical
activity that people don't like to talk
about, like physical ability. I no
longer have access to the kinds of
physical activity that might even begin
to complete a stress response cycle in
my body because Yeah. Yeah. Um, it used
to be very [ __ ] effective for me. No,
now I can't do it. Yeah. Uh, in the Q&A,
feel free to ask me how I feel about
that.
Uh there might be other reasons like say
you know that going for a nice brisk
walk strut down the street you are going
to come back feeling like a new person
like you're ready for anything. You know
that you have passed through the
threshold of stressed out into a space
of
of readiness of certainty of a feeling
of safety and then you get catc
calledled on that walk. And now that
physical activity that was going to help
you manage your stress has become a
source of stress, right? You're trans
and you're gonna go use the gym, but
boy, if you choose to use a locker room,
you could be taking your life in your
hands. It's just more complicated than
exercise is good for your stress. It's
so much more complicated. But we have
six other concrete, specific,
evidence-based things you can do.
Emily is not going to give her one-hour
talk. This I have fully an hourlong talk
about sleep. I am not going to give it.
Sleep is good for you. There's a whole
chapter about
rest. College people, people under the
age of 25 in their adolescence. On
average, how many hours of sleep do
people in that age group require in
order for their body to get the rest
required to complete the stress response
cycle? cuz your body is doing amazing
stuff in the midst of sleep and you
don't even have to be there for it. It
is doing it for you. But how many hours
does a person sort of between 15 and 25
need?
Yeah, it's like nine and a quarter on
average, which means for some people it
is
more. And also people vary. 7 to nine is
the typical range for adults. Again,
identical twins, seven and a half hours
typically. Ameilia has always been a
nine hour sleeper. That was before I had
long co. Now it's 10 and a half1. Yeah,
cuz that's how much cuz people and for
like did you not have experiences of
feeling I learned in high school we
needed eight hours of sleep. I would
sleep eight hours and feel exhausted and
I thought I was lazy.
Nope. Just turns out I'm on the higher
end of average. Yeah. Turns out short
sleeper privilege is a real thing. Early
bird privilege is a real thing. That's
the schedule capitalism chose. Yeah,
100%. I am both a short sleeper and
you're talking about way too much about
sleep. You should talk about the stress
response thing and then move on. Sorry.
So, you're a good sister. There's
there's Okay, so we're going to talk
about in deep sleep. What happens is the
physical healing. If you're a person who
engages in physical activity and
benefits from it, uh if you do not get
adequate deep sleep in particular, your
body is not going to heal from the
damage you did to it with the physical
activity. So, you're not going to get
stronger. Physical activity is not
complete without sleep. If you study and
you don't sleep, your brain gets nice
and smooth and slippery and stuff
doesn't stick to it. So, it is not worth
studying if you're not going to sleep.
Allnighters are the I'm not going to
talk about
it. Ren sleep, which is the sort of like
dreaming uh hyperassociative phase of
sleep, is your emotion processing when
your brain is like putting together all
the emotional experiences you've ever
had in your entire life. My husband
texted me that he had a dream about
walking from Florida to Massachusetts
because he had to come take care of the
dogs because he's all alone right now
with the dogs. And the more he walked,
the further he got. Like that was his
brain working out his stress response.
What a gift it is that his body could
complete the stress response cycles in
his sleep. We got to We're done. Sleep
is really important. Get a lot of it.
Ask questions. Ask questions about
sleep. There's so much more that she
would love to be saying right now, but
I'm as a conductor, I'm trained really
firmly about keeping to a schedule. Like
my audience is usually instrumentalists
who are being paid by a union who So
like I'm I'm not being strict because
I'm a jerk. I'm being that's my that's
it's a strength I bring to this
relationship. The third concrete,
specific evidence-based thing you can do
to complete a stress response cycle is
engage your imagination. Because the
good news is your brain doesn't really
know the difference between doing a
thing with your body or imagining doing
that thing with your body. You put
famous research, you put a pianist in an
fMRI machine, have them play a little
electric keyboard, see where the brain
lights up, take away the keyboard, have
them imagine they're playing that
electric keyboard. Same parts of the
brain do the same work. Your brain
doesn't know the difference between
what's happening and what you're
imagining is happening. Not much. Um uh
that means that when you're sitting on
your couch with a controller on your
hand moving literally just your thumbs,
this is not an aerobic workout. And yet
when you are rescuing the princess from
the dragon or whatever, your heart is
pounding. Your breath is coming faster.
You are experiencing all of the physical
experience of completing a hero's
journey of going from a state of danger
into a state of safety. So that when you
get to the end of the game or the movie
or the show or the book when you want to
like stand up and cheer at the end, your
body has gone through the physical
experience even though you didn't do
anything with your body. That's the
power of using your imagination to
complete a stress response cycle. I do
want to make this one little caveat
because it sounds like engaging with
entertainment does the thing. And there
is a difference between entertainment
that completes a stress response cycle
that makes you feel a thing that changes
your physical state versus entertainment
that is soothing uh that is numbing. So
if you can sit and stare, I play a game
where I just swipe on my phone, right?
We all have the phone swipe. We watch
the shows that make us go British big
off. People being nice to each other for
low stakes, right? I love it. That is
numbing and it is an important part of
the process
cuz burnout, stress, like any wound
needs to be treated both with, you know,
cleaning out the wound and stitching up
the cut. And if the hospital sent you
home after just stitching it up when not
numbing anything, you would have
received poor health care. Not just
because you'd be like, "Ow, why are you
so mean?" But also because relieving
pain leads to better healing. Healing
itself can cause stress that slows sorry
pain itself can cause stress that slows
healing. So in the healing process of
dealing with burnout and stress
management if you need to eat a pint of
Ben & Jerry's using Pringles for a scoop
because that makes this moment here
tolerable and gets rid of the pain so
that you can live to do the next hard
thing you have to do. Yeah, do it.
There's research. Refined carbohydrate
is analesic. Yeah. Um, it is if you went
to the hospital and all they did was
numb you up and send you home and they
didn't clean out the wound and didn't
stitch it up, that would also be
terrible medical care. You got to do
both. Uh, but so entertainment can serve
as numbing potentially, but the one that
completes a stress response cycle is the
one that makes you want to stand up and
cheer, makes your heart rate faster,
gives you a physical experience of
having achieved something. Yeah, which
brings us to creative self-expression of
some kind. So, uh, for me it's writing.
Um, I had a particularly difficult day
at
work. That's all I need to say. Um, and
I needed to come home and trans like I'd
absorbed a whole lot of people's very
difficult emotions. Um, so I was writing
a romance novel. I skipped right to the
proposal scene of my romance novel. I
put my hero on his knees, begging to
deserve the love of my awesome heroine.
And I'm sobbing on my keyboard. And I
can feel my body transforming all of
that stress I absorbed from other people
into this story of the happily ever
after that I am creating. It's not going
to be writing for everybody. For some
people, it's going to be knitting little
booties of rage. It's going to be
painting or sculpting or theater. Oh my
god. Engage in any or playing in a band
music. So good for you. Engage in any
kind of storytelling in particular is so
good for you. And again, your brain
doesn't know the difference between a
fictional thing and a real thing. Not
much. Uh so using your imagination and
creativity in this way. Uh, one pro tip,
make it something you're never going to
be awesome at so that you're never
tempted to monetize it and turn it into
your job. Cuz there's no faster way to
make something you love to do that makes
you feel awesome. She gestures to the
professional musician. There's no faster
way to make your creative
self-expression no longer good for
managing your stress than to make it
your job.
That's real. That's real.
So, we are now on the 1, two, 3, four,
fifth concrete, specific, evidence-based
thing you can do to manage your stress
right now. And um probably there are
some of these you went, "Oh, yeah. I'm a
natural exerciser. I can go for a run. I
come home feeling great. I I play this
game and I know it helps me. I I I
belong to a drum circle and I whenever I
come back from the drum circle, I feel
safe and big ups, right? So, you
probably already know which of these
work for you and which of these are hard
for you. And this is another one where
we can illustrate the differences
because the next one is a big old cry.
And Emily could come home from high
school, high school, 15 years old,
auditioned for the play, did terribly,
came home, closed my bedroom door,
sobbed for 15 minutes, and I was over
it. and I had to be taught by my
therapist in my in her office how to cry
when she was in grad school when I was
in my 30s. It took someone with a PhD
from Yale to teach me how to cry. Um so
if you are someone who knows that you
can like lock yourself in your car, so
for five minutes and feel much better,
do that. If you are someone who goes, I
never understood why that works for
people, there are techniques you can do.
Um, if pe there are people here who are
interested in knowing that, please ask
in the Q&A. Hey Amelia, how do I cry in
a way that doesn't just make me cry
non-stop forever?
Yeah. The next one is closely
related. Uh, just like a big old cry is
your body because the thing is like you
so you move through it, your body goes
through the tunnel and you come out at
the other end. People are afraid if they
start crying they're never going to
stop. That's just not how bodies work.
Um, laughter is another one of those
things where your body physiologically
releases just the stuff that you've been
holding on to. Oh my god, 10
minutes releases all the stuff you've
been holding on to. Now, we are not
talking about social
poised that kind of laughter. It is the
helpless belly aching crying like it
hurts. You're laughing so hard
especially if you're laughing with other
people. Um, it can be laughing over a
shared memory or it can be just
remembering a time when your friend did
that. And the last thing that we're
going to talk about that's paper's
favorite thing. I'm sorry and we're
going faster. That's just all there is
to it. Um, and the last thing and
people's favorite thing is loving
connection. Uh, a 20 second hug. Not
about the 20 seconds. It's about the
time you and somebody you really love
and trust spend in close physical
contact. And you wait long enough that
your body shifts and you'll feel it.
Oh, that's right. I'm safe here. I
can't. And it doesn't have to be a
connection with another person. It can
be a connection with an animal, a loving
divine presence, your own inner child,
the ocean, the nature, uh connection.
And uh the unnamed barrier. Holy [ __ ]
we have 20 more 30 more minutes of
things to talk about. Can you do human
giver syndrome super fast? Yes. Um so
we've adapted a new language. This is
the barrier just to be clear. Yeah,
those are all the things like again
you're like, "Oh, friends are good for
me. Sleep is good for me. Exercise is
good for me. Why don't I do those
things? This is why it's because on the
day you were born,
uh people slapped a label on your body
and they cast you in a role that you are
supposed to play. Some of us, this is
like 99 point something percent of us
were cast either into the giver role and
you were given this handbook that taught
you to be pretty, happy, calm, generous,
attent, unfailingly attentive to the
needs of others, warm and playable,
regardless of the cost. And some of you
get cast in the role of the winner to be
strong, stoic, ambitious, competitive,
independent, infallible, and confident.
And I'm not saying anyone in particular
gets cast in any particular
role, except I am. And there are two
problems with this. One, if you get
taught that you only have certain
emotions available to you and you are
stuck in some stress response and you're
like, "But I don't have any rage,
Emily." Cuz you got taught from the day
you were born, you don't have any rage.
How are you going to complete the stress
response cycles associated with rage?
And if you get taught that you're not
ever lonely, how are you ever going to
know that you need connection? And the
other part about it is, oh yeah, so
these these are the only emotions you're
allowed. These are the emotions you get.
If you're a human winner, you are
allowed to be angry or allowed to go
faster. Winning horny, happy, grateful,
and supportive exclusively if you're a
human giver.
Okay. And this creates We hurried so
Ameilia could sing a song. I hurried so
I could get to Czechov's ukulele. Um cuz
this is how you're going to remember the
thing long term. Go ahead and hit the
thing. There's a is it is a gap between
who we are and who the world tells us
we're supposed to be. No, don't. It's
supposed to whatever. You can just leave
it. Song goes like this. Who does the
world say that I should be? And what do
I do if I don't agree? Rational me says
that I am enough. My primate brain says
not fitting is rough. Solutions are
clear. I should be myself and deal with
the world when it puts me through hell.
Or easier still is to be what they say.
That only requires I give my soul away
to the
abyss.
Abyss. Two opposite goals here. ask you
to choose. Whichever you pick, there's
something to lose. But you're not alone.
We're all on this road. And going
together is a journey of hope through
the
abyss.
Abyss. There's a chasm. Yeah. Right.
between who you truly are and who the
world taught you you are supposed to
be. What do you
do? We're gonna skip the story metaphor.
Click. The answer is Hunger Games, but
we're not going to explicit that. And
we're just going to sing remember who
the real enemy is. Yeah. The real enemy
is not any of the children who are
trapped in the dome with you. It is the
people who trapped us in this dome
together. And the solution, how that
looks in real life is that burnout is
not the cure for burnout. Cannot be
self-care. Because when you are trapped
in the arena, when you try to just fight
for your own
life, 90% everybody, one person's going
to die in the arena. And when we all
care for each other, nobody slips
through the cracks. But that means we
need to surround ourselves with those
people who are going to turn toward our
needs and say, not, "Oh, you got 9 hours
of sleep last night. Well, I was awake
till 3:00 a.m. baking cookies for
Becky's birthday party, but good for
you. 9 hours of sleep. Self-care is so
important." Instead, you surround
yourself with people who care about your
well-being as much as you care about
theirs. And there's a song about that,
too. That's much more fun than me just
doing the thing. Did you get the thing?
Okay, sure. Just do it. Yeah. I want to
do and be everything that the world has
demanded of me. Sometimes I feel I don't
deserve love. Not until I'm productive
enough. That's when I need supplementary
help to reinforce my boundaries.
In the bubble of
[Music]
love, I am
enough in my bubble of
love. There are people who care about my
wellbeing as much as I care about
theirs. It's better when I sing it,
right? We guard each other from outside
messages, showing each other we
[Music]
care. Cuz I wanna want and like all the
goals that the world has set for my
role. Sometimes I fear I don't deserve
love. Not until I'm successful enough.
That's when I need supplementary help to
mind what gives life
[Music]
meaning. In my bubble of
love, I am
[Music]
enough in my bubble of
love. I'm here to prove that you don't
have to be a professional musician to
sing in public.
[Applause]
Oh my god, we actually made it within
the last Oh god. Sort of. We did it.
Sort of. Sort of. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Please ask questions. We skipped
so much. Yeah. But also, we have a whole
page of questions. You do from one of
the ultimate badasses on the face of the
earth. So, it's going to be an amazing
conversation. Wellness, not a state of
being. State of action. Wellness is the
freedom to oscillate through all the
cycles of being human. Uh oh, we didn't
say explicitly, but here it is the
chance to say burnout's caused by
accumulating incomplete stress response
cycles that are imposed upon your body
by
unseasoned and unmeable goals.
And um to cure burnout, you got to
complete the stress response cycle with
movement, sleep, love, creativity,
imagination. Yeah. Uh and a near
universal barrier is the human giver
syndrome, aka the gender mirage. Mirage
because it seems like it's there. like
any mirage, it really seems real until
you get closer. And to defeat that, um,
you need to remember who the real enemy
is, not everybody else who's down here
fighting for resources that we've been
told are limited, even though we kind of
just invented most of them. Like money,
we made that up and we're going to claim
that it's limited. Oh, anyway. Get it?
And of course to be surrounded by the
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. surrounded by the
bubble of love and the people and the
magic trick we're gonna do when we talk
about meaning.
And that is the PowerPoint presentation
portion. Okay.
Wow. Wow. This was
incredible. So, I have lots of questions
about sleep. So, why don't we start
there? Yes. Okay. Take a break. Go
ahead. I'm ready. I'm actually just
kidding. Okay. Oh, man.
I have so much to say about sleep. It's
so important and there's so much
science.
I know you do. But we want everyone to
read the books. Yes. Yes. Yes. We want
everyone to read the books. So, I wanted
to start by asking a little bit about
what you just talked about because I
read the book and I felt like it was so
helpful to me and I thought there are so
many quotes that I've been using since I
read the book. I've been talking a lot
about it and talking with you. So, I
thought I might throw out a few quotes
that I thought were great and just have
you talk about them. Great. Does that
sound good? Okay. So, we've talked a lot
about facing challenges and how so much
of it is about reconceptualizing how you
think about challenges. And so, what I
think, you know, my assertion, if I
understand this correctly, is that we
need to prioritize connection, meaning
making, and rest. See, I got that in
there. Okay. So, I'd like to ask you a
few questions about some of these
things. First is a quote. Meaning is
found. It's not found. It is made. I
have a song about that. Okay. Oh, the
song is the cabbage song. I don't play
this much because we say meaning is a
leafy green. And I've been told by Emily
that cabbage is not technically a leafy
green. It's a brassica. It's a brassica.
But the notes the word the letters c a
bb a ge r e. Can I do like two sentences
of introduction? All right. So when we
say meaning is made not found, it's
because you make meaning in your life by
engaging with something larger than
yourself. Um, and I was like, it's like
you have to eat the kale in order to get
the nutrients. You have to be in the
sunlight to make the vitamin D. You have
to engage with your something larger to
make the meaning. And I was like, so
it's like a leafy green. And I was like,
it's like cabbage, but then cabbage is a
brassica, but all the letters in
cabbages are notes on a keyboard. So
Ameilia wrote a song and the research
shows there are three ways to achieve
meaning through engaging with your
something larger. Three types of
something larger and so I'm gonna sing
them.
C A B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B
B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B
B B B A A G E meaning is a leafy green
kind of grow it yourself
[Music]
by connect or sing with me. Emily, give
me a one. One, no. Give me one. One,
leaving a legacy behind. Two, or heeding
the call to serve mankind.
Or loving
someone. Loving someone. That's enough.
C A B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B
B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B B
B B B A A G E meaning is kind of a leafy
green. So, what were the three?
Leaving a legacy. Leaving a legacy
behind serving service to serve mankind
or loving
[Music]
someone. That's now you'll remember
forever.
It's also in chapter four. Yes. No.
Three. I wanted to call it vitamin
Y. Get it? Cuz you But Emily thought
that was cheesy.
Okay.
All right, moving on.
So, another quote. Happiness versus joy.
Right. This isn't actually our quote.
This is Britney Cooper. Britney Cooper
stands, y'all. Right. More Britney
Cooper stands. Bodies not apologies. The
book that's highly recommended. No, no,
no. Bodies not apologies. Sonia Renee
Taylor. Oh my god. It's racist.
I got him confused. I'm sorry. I forgot.
Eloquent rage is eloquent rage. I sorry
they're next to each other on my
bookshelf and I what can I do? Yeah. So
eloquent rage Britney Cooper writes that
uh happiness is about happenings. It is
the circumstances of your life whether
or not life is going well.
Joy is about feeling a firm sense of
connection to your purpose in life. We
just talked about three ways to engage
with your something larger to have
purpose. Most of that is going to come
through connection with other people.
Um, I'm going to skip the long story
part and just skip to it is a normal con
part of the human condition to need to
be told that you are enough and to need
to remind the people you care about that
you are enough. That reminder to each
other, that kind of connection is a
profound source. You meant reminding
them that they are enough. That they are
enough. That's what I meant. Thank you
very much.
Um, joy comes from the connection with
something larger and your community
which is much larger, deeper and because
your source of meaning, your something
larger resides within yourself. You c it
can never be taken from you.
Circumstances change.
For real Z though, Moana.
Yeah, for real Z though. um be anybody
who's happy in the given circumstances
of America um has been doing a really
good job of not paying attention. Um but
that does not reduce our access to joy
because that's not about the present
circumstances. It's about our connection
to our sense of purpose.
Love it. Okay. So speaking of joy, you
tell this story about practicing singing
with a chorus. Ah, and I really like
that story because it's a difference
between aiming for perfection Yeah.
versus having the sound engineer feel
joy. Yeah. Yeah. Nobody hears a
perfectionist. Right. Right. Yeah. So,
uh, this story is about dealing not with
the stress in your body and not dealing
with a stressor that you can change or
control. Well, no, it is about dealing
with a stress or you can change and
control. Um, it's about changing the
goal so that you're not trying to do a
thing that's perfect. Because like in
coral singing for example, there just is
literally no such thing as perfect. It's
not 1 plus 1 is two. It is
embody the spirit of the conduct of the
composers. It's not there's no such
thing as perfect. So, how do you feel
satisfied when you are singing in a
recording session where you sing three
measures over and over and o and it gets
so tedious and you need to be alive in
your body and connected to the intention
every time over and over and not make it
mechanical and bored. You need to set a
a goal. Good goals need to be something
that is soon certain, specific,
concrete, positive, and personal. It's
chapter two. It's chapter two. I'm not
going to go in detail, but I will tell
you that I've seen this work when you
change the goal um in a recording
session when we were having this like
just drilling this same thing over and
over again. And I was like, "Okay, we're
going to change the goal. Instead of
trying to be perfect in every take, we
are going to change the goal to filling
Andrew. Andrew was this very cutie
patootie recording producer who'd come
in and move cables around and adjust the
microphones. And then he's listening
backstage. Thank you, choir. That was
lovely. I need you to take from measure
two again, beat three. Yeah. The breath
there was a little loud and I heard a
page turn. Can we try it again?
And our goal was to fill Andrew with joy
so that when he listens he goes choir
that was really lovely. Thank you. We
wanted to get that response from him. Um
and so instead of thinking like we have
to do this right every time we're
thinking about this person who we all
admire who we know is listening and the
effect we'll have on him Grammy award
experience. It's such a more meaningful.
It was soon certain, specific, concrete,
positive, and personal. And it changed
how everyone felt in the recording
session. Not trying to be perfect
anymore, just trying to do something
that was important in that moment.
So much so that like you I mean like it
gets boring. But eventually the soprano
is like,
"Andrew, are you filled with joy?" And
he actually went, "Yeah, yeah, I really
am."
changes everything.
I really love that example. It's great.
A completely true thing. 100%. Yeah. So,
I wanted you to talk a little bit about
this idea of perfectionism
and you talked about toxic perfectionism
and I thought maybe you could say a
little bit about that because you know
because we use the term perfectionism
and I'm a perfectionist. We use that
colloquially to mean I'm really
interested in doing things as well as I
possibly can and I don't feel really
proud of thing until I know I've put my
best effort into it. And there is
nothing toxic about having high
standards and being detail oriented.
Yeah. But when your idea of achieving
perfection leads you to believe that if
a thing is not perfect, it is worthless.
That imperfection, something that's
going to be imperfect, you shouldn't
even bother starting. That is when
perfectionism starts to stop you from
feeling joy and uh connecting with your
something larger. Connecting with your
something larger and the the cure for to
talk that kind of toxic perfectionism is
self-compassion. And I don't know if you
want to talk about that separately or if
Emily should do a whole thing. Well, I
was actually going to ask about that
next. So, it's
Yeah. So uh when you are uh the kind of
perfectionist who feels like it has to
be perfect or it is absolutely worthless
or the kind of perfectionist where you
feel outside pressure to succeed at
every single thing you do. That's
probably not familiar to anybody in this
room. No, not at all. Right. Um then you
end up having a lot of harsh
self-criticism. You have uh in the in
the chapter we call it the mad woman in
the attic which is Peggy Macintosh's
language from the 80s. Um, as people
with multiple diagnosed mental health
issues, we feel comfortable reclaiming
Madwoman. Um, which is that voice in
your head that beats the crap out of you
for being such a terrible failure of a
human being. Um, one of the anecdo uh
that's her lashing herself. This is so
we grew up our father grew up Catholic.
So, this is the like hair, shirt, and
lash of like beating the crap out of
yourself and inflicting wounds on
yourself because you feel like you need
to punish yourself for falling short of
someone else's standard of who you're
supposed to be. In the abyss, the mad
woman arises out of the abyss and only
has two potential objects. Either she
can be incandescent with rage at you for
falling short, in which case you beat
the crap out of yourself, or
incandescent with rage at the world for
having these bogus expectations.
Sorry, I didn't think you'd say bogus. I
thought you were going to say something
else. I'm I'm really trying to like not
swear. Not. Yeah,
it was hurtful. Um, so the mad woman
decides, is it your fault of not
achieving what the world told you to do,
or is it the world's fault? So, y'all
can imagine I had a speaking gig on a
Sunday. Emily was actually visiting over
the weekend that this happened. Um,
snowing. Yeah, it was snowing. There was
like a foot of snow on the ground and I
get a text from saying, "Hey, Emily,
we're ready. Where are you?"
Because I had put the event in my
calendar for Sunday and the event was on
Saturday and I was supposed to be there.
I was at home in my pajamas under a foot
of snow, no less than an hour away from
the
event. That
expression, so
so I followed my own advice in this
moment like you have. I have just
screwed up royally. This is the only
thing I have ever fully just missed.
I've done a bad job sometimes, but I
missed it. Uh, and so like the mad woman
in my head, uh, whom I we Moana came out
while we were watching it, and when I
saw Takah the lava
monster throwing balls of lava at Moana,
I was like, it me, my mad woman is Tea,
the lava monster. But what does Moana do
when she sees Tea the lava monster?
Okay, TLDDR spoilers for
Moana. Moana is given the heart of
Teiti, which is a glowing green stone
with the squirrel in it. And she has to
restore the heart of Teiti. She has to
cross the horizon, find the demigod
Maui, and restore the heart of Teiti.
And her last worst enemy is Tea, the
lava monster. And because all Disney and
Pixar stories now are like the journey
of an individual human through her own
psyche, which is what all Yungian
storytelling interpretation and dream
interpretation is. It's actually Moana
has to go deep and confront the worst
most difficult part of herself to
restore the heart of Teiti. And what she
notices is that the swirl at the center
of the stone of the heart of teiti
matches the swirl on the center of the
chest of tea the lava monster. So
instead of fighting which is what Maui
does. Maui gets in full haka mode and is
like I'm going to I'm a tiny demigod but
I'm going to get this lava monster. But
what Moana does Moana's superpowers she
can see below the surface. She holds up
the heart. I have crossed the horizon to
find you. She says to the ocean, "Let
her come to me. I know your name." She
strides toward the lava monster. I have
stolen the heart with her hair.
Waving. And she stands bravely in front
of Tekk, the lava monster.
And she says, "This is not who you
are. You know who you are." She turns
toward the lava monster with kindness
and
compassion and she says, "You know who
you truly are." And she stands forehead
to forehead with her worst most
dangerous enemy that lives inside of
her. And she puts the stone at the heart
of Tikka and all of the lava drops away.
And this monster transforms into Teiti,
the goddess of abundance and life. The
moral of the story is I was sitting here
beating the [ __ ] out of myself this
January in western Massachusetts and I
turned toward Tea and I was like, "What
do you have to tell me? What do you need
from me? I know you're trying to help.
This is not who you are. I'm not gonna
beat you up. I'm not gonna beat myself
up. We're gonna get through this
together. what do you need from me? And
she said, "My lava monster come." I'm
like breathing breath together with her.
She says, "If you because you have made
this mistake, you're never going to get
another job. They're going to know that
you're a total fake and a loser and
you're going to die
alone. I'm trying to keep you
safe." She was trying to keep me safe.
And I thanked her. I recognized that she
was working really hard and it must be
exhausting to have to work that hard.
I'm literally just sitting in the living
room sobbing imagining this. This is
internal family systems work for people
who are interested. Yeah. Parts work.
Yay. We're going to quote Moana Moana
and several therapeutic modalities. Yes,
that's just what you get. This is this
it sounds like whackadoodle nonsense.
Storytelling Moana. I'm talking to
myself. But uh this normally science
based. There is like there was so many
references for this. I had to cut a full
paragraph of like different therapeutic
modalities that do this kind of work cuz
the editor was like this is very
boring. But it's totally evidence-based.
The point of it is that
self-compassion is the intervention that
is the opposite of the harsh
self-criticism that is so dangerous. It
is so easy to believe. Another Oh god, I
should stop talking. One more. One more.
One more. Okay. So, when the mail
carrier drops off the mail, our dog goes
bananas. And then the mail carrier goes
away. And our dog is convinced that the
mail carrier goes away because she went
bananas. Here's the thing. The mail
carrier was going to go away anyway,
right? So many of us believe like, I
have gotten so far in life. Anyone in
this room has accomplished so much in
life. It is really easy to believe that
we got this far in life because we beat
the crap out of
ourselves. We were going to do it
anyway. Imagine if we had been working
this hard and we had not been inflicting
injuries on our own psyches this whole
time and having to work with those
injuries and do the healing from those
injuries. What if what if we were not
beating? What if we were so strong
because we were not
constantly opening wounds that we're
trying to close? And a key difference in
what the research shows this turning
toward your inner mad woman is different
from like the popular notion which is
like just shut off that inner voice and
ignore it. You don't need all that hate
in your brain. Tell it to go away. Yeah.
If if you just tell tea to go away that
tea is going to get even more mad at
you. Right. the that's what happens in
the story and it turns out that that's
not an effective way to deal with to it
doesn't give you the benefits of
self-compassion that when instead of
just like shutting down that inner
critic or ignoring it pretending it
doesn't exist and trying to move forward
like you that's still in there the
effective thing to do is to turn toward
it to turn and face the strange and be
like this is a hard thing to confront
and doing that in a many situations
turning toward the hard thing is what's
going to get you to healing and
recovery. This is the last chapter
because it is the hardest thing to do.
Yeah.
Wow. So, I I want to take that in for a
moment because I want to skip around to
a question that I think is connected to
this that I think speaks to this because
I think it's pretty deep because this
all makes perfect sense to me as a
therapist and referencing these
different
modalities. Um, so it's this concept of
knowing what's true and facing what's
uncomfortable and how that's different
from acceptance. Mhm. So that really
struck me as a really important
distinction and connected to what you're
talking about now. Yeah. Do you agree?
Is that true? Is it is that all part of
what you're saying?
100%. My bad day was related to being
confronted with multiple people's trauma
in a day. Uh I trained as a therapist. I
did not become a therapist because I
don't have the magical thing that it
takes to sit with people in pain over
and over and say
uh what was that like for
you? I like I don't have that magical
thing. Um I'm an educator by
temperament. Uh some people can do both.
Uh
so helping do education around trauma
stuff is what I got confronted by
students with the idea of like
acceptance which in like Buddhist
practice as it gets translated into
English the word acceptance gets used
and that feels like accept that this is
true and will always be true forever and
that's not actually what it means. So,
uh, instead I use the phrase
observational distance. If you can, if
you're like in the stream, if you're in
the rushing river of your own internal
experience, if you can take one step out
of the rushing stream and witness it
instead of being in
it, you can know that that is like this
is the thing that's happening right now.
And you have to acknowledge the given
circumstances. Nothing James Baldwin
famously nothing uh can be changed until
it is faced but nothing
uh that is not faced can ever be
changed. Um
and our job is to acknowledge what's
actually happening in the here and now.
That is not the same
as believing that we can't change it.
In fact, the only way you can change it
is to recognize 100% of what is true.
This also comes from my work as a sex
educator where I I tell people I teach
people to live with confidence and joy
inside their bodies. And a student
raised her hand and said, "Can you
please define those
terms?" And I was like, "I'll get back
to you next week." Um, and what I
figured out, and indeed this is very
parallel to the work of Sonia Renee
Taylor, confidence is knowing what is
true about your body and the world and
the things that you've been taught about
all those things. Um, and joy is the
hard part. Joy is loving what's true
about your body and the world and what
it's like to live in this moment. Um, so
that's the hard thing is recognizing all
the things that are true. The things
you've been told should be true. I'm
going to add an active practice, a thing
that people can do, and that is I uh I
started learning Taichi is one of the
first things I did to help myself
recover from the burnout that put me in
the hospital. Let's do a thing. Huh? So,
if you can sit in whatever way is
comfortable for you, I'm going to sit
forward. If you want to like rub your
hands together and get like a little bit
activated in your body and aware of the
energy that's happening inside you,
you're gonna reach out to the world in
front of you, scoop up some of the
universe and like look at it in front of
your face. And this is we're at MIT. We
are on the North American continent on
the planet Earth in this the solar
galaxy in the universe as infinite as it
might be. Look at all of that. And then
we're going to just like settle back
into a comfortable position. I'm going
to let my hands kind of hang here like
this. And this is we're going to call
this mountain pose. It feels comfortable
and stable and sturdy. And then we're
going to like reach out and scoop out
and grab some more of the universe and
look at it as it is like America as it
is and our bodies as they are and you
know our day as it has been. Um and you
know what is also in this scoop is is
the past history as it has always been.
And in this scoop is also the future of
what is possible that's going to happen
next. and we look at it and we're going
to we're going to call this tiger and
we're going to like okay let that go and
like return to mountain and then we're
going to scoop up some more of the
universe. So, we're going to take a look
at it. The tiger as as violent and scary
and also like a a nurturing parent could
be a thing that a tiger is and soft and
cute and fuzzy and also really sharp
teeth and all the things that a tiger
can be and we're going to be like,
"Yeah, I'm going to embrace everything
that a tiger can be and I'm going to
return to mountain." And in Taichi, like
there's a lot of gestures that could be
associated with this. This is kind of
like scoop up the universe and look at
it and then return to mountain. Embrace
Tiger return a mountain is a active
practice for teaching your brain that it
doesn't need to react to fear and and
uncertainty with a fight orflight
response every single time you can look
at oh my god that's really dangerous oh
look I have access to mountains still
does that make sense
oh it does it not only made sense but it
felt really nice okay
good talking about dark things but Our
goal is for you to feel better by the
end. Yes. And with that in mind, I have
one last question before we open it up
to the group. It's about the practice of
practicing gratitude. Oh yeah. So
gratitude everybody. I would like you to
talk a little bit about your ideas about
practicing gratitude because a lot of
people practice expressing gratitude.
They write about gratitude. They journal
about gratitude, but you had a a new
take on it that I really appreciated and
have incorporated into my own practice.
Yeah. I was hoping that first you could
share it with everyone. And then second,
I wanted to express my own gratitude for
being able to meet both of you and for
your work. That was both very nice and
very smooth.
Can I ask content and excellent rhetoric
like just what is the thing that you've
incorporated? Well, I love the way that
you were talking about being more
specific. So, when I think about
gratitude, you know, you've been I don't
know sort of indoctrinated in the world
that this is a good thing to do, but
it's also it's done in generalities.
And so, the way that you all talked
about it was it really does need to be
specific and detailed around your own
life. And that really helped me to think
about every day and also in terms of
setting an intention for the day. Yeah.
Yeah. And the the thing about our new
take is that our take is just reporting
what the research into gratitude
actually says as opposed to just doing
like the popular version of like keep
track of what you're grateful for. It
turns out that's not what the research
says is an effective intervention. And
when I tried doing it that way, I felt
like an
[ __ ] Look at all this stuff I have.
Why am I not more grateful all the time?
And also like like yeah, I'm really
grateful to have a roof over my head and
also this apartment is enormously
overpriced and I'm going into debt for
it while I'm getting this degree that
I'm so fortunate to be able to get, but
I am exhausted all the time from this
degree. So I like I couldn't I I hated I
hated gratitude. And then I read the
research and I was like, "Oh, that's
different." So there's two. Um, one is
gratitude for who you have is one is
gratitude for how things happen.
Gratitude for who you have is the easy
one. It is
like especially if you can write it
down. Write a letter to a person who has
been really important and impactful for
you, who has provided you with
resources, who has provided you with
emotional support, instrumental support.
I wrote a gratitude letter to my
clinical depression because it taught me
so much.
I don't want anybody to have to feel
like I should be grateful for things
that caused me to suffer,
but it's a thing that's possible.
Millia actually sings a song called
Gratitude and she sings it to her
depression.
It's very moving and effective. Yeah. Um
so that's one. And boy, if you want like
a big shot of well-being that will last
a long time for you and the other
person, read that letter out loud to
that other person. Can we do the magic
trick? Uh, let me say the uh how things
happen. So, what the research actually
says about like gratitude for like life
events is like what's a thing that
happened today that you're grateful for?
What are the circumstances surrounding
it that made it possible for this to
happen? Like I'm grateful to have a roof
over my head. How did this happen? Oh,
we could buy a house because my
husband's excellent human being of a
father died and we got enough money to
be able to put a down payment on a
house. Like we Oh. And suddenly I'm
grateful to have a roof over my head is
I am profoundly grateful for the human
being responsible at least in part for
raising this excellent human being who
is my favorite person on earth. So it's
not about the roof anymore. It's about
like the generations of humans who
created the human who shares a home with
me. Um and that's in the last chapter
like there's the full details of like
the step by step. You do it every day.
It changes your brain. Yeah. Magic
trick. I thought maybe we could end
really with the magic trick because okay
so the thing we talk about as the magic
trick is a combination of many things
we've talked about already today which
is moving your body in time and space in
connection with other people toward a
shared goal. Um and we're going to count
backwards from 10. That's our shared
goal. But we're going to do it by going
10 98 72 and then going 10 with your
other hand and 10 with your foot and 10
with your other foot. You can stand up
if makes you happy to do that. I'm gonna
do it sitting down because standing up
makes me fall over. I'm gonna stand up
with my cane. Okay. Um, so we're gonna
do it and then we'll go from nine. And
here's the trick. You have to do it in
your good news voice. Like you have good
news for somebody who's way over there
and you go, I have good news. Can you
all say good news? Good news. In your
good news voice, you're going to count
backwards from 10 and shake. Go. 10 9 8
7 6 5 4 3 2 1 10 9 8 Good news 5 4 3 2 1
10 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 10 9 8 7 6 5 Good
news 97 76 5 4 3 2 1 9 7 5 4 3 2 1 9 7 6
5 4 3 2 Okay. 9
8765 43 2 1 8 765 43 2 1 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1
8 765 43 2 1 8765 43 2 1 7 6 5 4 3 2 1
765 43 2 1 765 43 2 1 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 6 4
3 2 1 6 5 4 3 2 1 6 5 4 3 2 1 6 5 4 3 2
1 5 4 3 2 1 5 4 3 2 1 5 4 3 2 1 5 4 3 2
1 4 3 2 1 4 3 2 1 4 3 2 1 3 2 1 3 2 1 3
2 1 3 2 1 2 1 2 1 2 1 2 1 1 Y
[Laughter]
[Applause]
moving in time with others toward a
shared goal. That one's called the
countdown shake, but dancing, singing,
marching in a
protest, worshiping together, that these
are all things that hook into going to a
concert where you all sing a lot. It's
these are all ways to hook into that
same like Yeah. Does anybody feel better
now than when we started? Y.
Okay. Mission accomplish.
So, we have questions, I'm sure, from
the audience and also virtually. And so,
we have Sylvia in the back. Do you want
to start? And please raise your hand if
you would like to ask a question. We
have a question in the front.
I'm gonna start over there. Oh, thank
you. Oh, I'm sorry. And there's Emily as
well. Thank you, Emily. Thank you so so
much for being here and for this talk
and for the conversation and for the
book. I enjoyed all of it very
thoroughly. So, and very very humorous
conversation. So, I really enjoyed. So,
thank you so much. We talk about the
patriarchy a lot. So
um in the book I really really
appreciated the notion of how important
it is to find meaning and how that can
be very helpful and also I really was
intrigued by and appreciated the idea of
how we can find meaning from experiences
that are sought after and desirable and
that are pleasant and at the same time
while there are experiences that we
didn't desire and didn't want it's still
possible to make meaning from those and
how that can be really really helpful to
do. I'd love to hear any further
thoughts you might have on that or any
examples or anecdotes you might have
from people you've worked with or things
you've witnessed. Yeah. So, I feel
inclined to tell the story. Uh, anybody
here willing to say they were old enough
to vote in the 2004 election?
Oh, yeah. Many for that. So, I was in
grad school at the time. I'm a sex
educator. Uh, my work was directly and
immediately impacted by the policies of
the federal government. Um, uh, the 2000
election was was the first time I was
like, "Oh [ __ ] our democracy is
crumbling. I should maybe do something."
So, I invested a lot in the 2004
election. Um, I got trained in how
elections happened. I considered
dropping out of grad school and working
for a political campaign instead. Um,
but so I spent a week leading up to the
election volunteering in Ohio, a crucial
swing state in 2004. Uh, and I like I
drove home on election night. The
results were coming in. It was sounding
really good. I woke up the next morning
like I had put so like two years of my
life invested in this election. And what
everybody told me was that if I work
really hard, if everybody just does
everything they can, we're going to make
this happen. And I John Kerry, but like
like let's make John Kerry happen. Uh,
and I woke up and I went to my best
friend's house and he was sitting in the
living room watching the news and I was
like, "It's it's bad." And he was like,
"It's 100% all the way bad." And I uh
cried the kind of crying that like
fluids are dripping from every orifice
in your face like can't breathe. Uh
despair because I had done everything
they told me I was supposed to
do in order to accomplish a goal. And
I was crushed and got as depressed as
I've ever been in my life. Um, I didn't
know what to do next. And the question
was about like, how do you find meaning
in the really terrible things that can
happen? Um, and it took me several
months to figure it out. But I figured
out that my job as a sex educator, as a
health educator, was to help people, to
teach people to live with confidence and
joy inside their bodies, to be able to
experience pleasure inside their bodies,
to have access to full bodily autonomy.
And every day that I do that work is a
day that I am doing something about
whatever is going to happen over the
next four years because whatever was
about to happen over the next four years
was really bad. It was just as bad as we
expected and what's happening now is
even worse. Um, and again, I invested
real hard. But this time, I knew that
even me doing the absolute most I could
do, and the most I could do this year
was so much more than what I could do
when I was a grad student, and it still
wasn't enough. But because I am still
anchored to my something larger, it's
inside me. It's like the tide always
falling and
rising. Your sense of connection with
your something larger. I am fortunate to
be able to articulate specifically why
I'm on earth is to teach people to live
with confidence and joy inside their
bodies. And any day I do that, some days
it's easier to access. It's like the
tide. It's always falling and rising.
Some days it is more difficult. But any
day that I have access to that is a day
that I have led a meaningful life. What
meaning does is enhance and enrich the
good times in your life and give you an
anchor to continuing to exist through
even the worst of circumstances. You'll
probably remember uh the story from
World War II, a journalist traveling
post-war through the countries that had
been invaded by uh Germany.
This journalist wandered into a basement
where a family of Jews had been hiding
through the entire war. And on the wall,
written obviously in German was, "I
believe in the sun even when it's not
shining. I believe in love even when I
don't feel it. I believe in God even
when he is silent." Which of course has
been turned into a song that is like,
it's been said to music several times.
Several times. And it's like crushing.
Uh but I I think about that a lot and I
think about like just because I don't
feel contact with my something larger
today doesn't mean it's not there. I can
find it again and it will give me a
reason to continue doing the work that I
do. Does that make sense? And at the
same time we can remember that nobody on
Moana's island gave two bits about the
ocean. She felt called by the ocean and
everybody around her was like, "No, no,
and no one leaves what that we all
belong here. We all have a role to play.
This is what we're all a part of here on
the island and she felt called by the
ocean." And despite nobody else being
supportive of that, she went on her
journey and did the thing. So sometimes
you're not going to get the support, but
you're going to get the connection you
need from the meeting itself.
Thank you so much. I want to check and
see if there are any questions from the
virtual audience. Yes. Amelia, how do
you cry? Uh Amelia, how do you cry? Is
question was the how do you cry? Uh
okay, so here's what you do. You're
overwhelmed by the feeling. Something
terrible happened and you are sobbing.
What you think is uncontrollably you
it's just taken you over and the crying
starts to happen. And if you're me, you
think, I'm going to feel like this until
the problem is solved. I'm I feel like
this because of the circumstances that
occurred. And so you keep thinking, I
can't believe he did that. I can't
believe she said that. And the crying
keeps happening. And h why would it ever
stop until that changes? Turns out like
stress, whatever emotion caused the
crying is a cycle with a beginning, a
middle, and an end. And if you let it,
it just ends. And here's how you do
that. You take the thing that in that
initiated the crying, and you put it on
a little shelf, and you think about that
later. That's the stressor. You're going
to deal with that in a separate process.
to deal with this process right here.
You turn toward the discomfort of crying
and you
just notice without judgment or
evaluation. Okay, how hot do I feel
right now while I'm crying? You know,
how many ounces of fluid are dripping
out of my face right now? And where is
there tension in my
body? You're crying and you're noticing.
And you're crying and you're noticing
and the thoughts will come out of your
mouth. And the thoughts will come, I
can't believe he said that to me. What
an [ __ ] and you put it on a shelf
and you're going to deal with it later,
but you're the feelings are all you're
dealing with right here, right now. And
eventually you're trying to find the
feelings and there's no more feelings
because the feelings are a cycle with a
beginning, a middle, and an end and they
and they end you. The the trick is to
not feeding the crying with additional
thoughts about the thing. The key is
dealing with the stress and the stressor
in separate processes. Would you say you
create observational distance between
yourself and the experience or I'd say
you turn to face a difficult thing with
observational distance? Yes. You step
out of the river. I want to check in
with I to see are there any questions?
Not flow like
Okay, perfect. Sylvia, um, is there
anyone on this side? I thought I saw a
hand. Excellent.
No one's going to ask about sleep.
I'm going to
your favorite. So, it's actually like
sort of related to the crying question
where like sometimes when I'm stressed
out, it's really hard to sleep.
And the number one indicator, like the
number one reason people don't get
enough sleep is cuz they're worried
about not sleeping.
But I think also just like when you're
stressed out, the brain is so active and
like, you know, it's just one of those
days where the meditation won't work,
the music won't work, the old towel or
whatever else. Um, so yeah, I just
wanted to hear your thoughts on that.
Yeah. So, how do you fall asleep
basically? Um, one, do as much as you
can during the day to complete the str.
So, how often does stress get activated
in your body?
At least every day. Yeah. So, how often
do you have to do stuff to complete the
stress response cycle? Every day. Yeah.
Like every day. Wax on, wax off. You
just have to keep doing it. Um, there
will be days when the stress outpaces
your ability to drain it off. Um, so if
you get in bed when your body is still
like this, if your body's like, I'm
being chased by a saber-tooth tiger
right now, or if you wake up at say 3:00
in the morning
and like as soon as you wake up, your
body's like, I'm being chased. Is being
chased by a saber-tooth tiger a really
good time to be asleep?
No. Yeah. So what you do is you
recognize, oh wait, my body's in a state
where it's trying to help me out by
keeping me alive, by keeping me vigilant
so I don't get eaten. Am I actually
being chased by a lion right
now? Am I actually now in
danger? And sometimes the answer to that
question is yes.
Usually the answer is I can get through
tonight. I'm safe enough tonight. And a
gratitude practice can be incredibly
helpful to ground you in like the ways
that you are safe. There are two uh
additional ways of uh doing a gratitude
practice. One is gratitude for safety.
What are the resources available to you
in the here and now that are protecting
you? Sometimes it is a locked door.
Sometimes it is your best friends.
Sometimes it is the meal you ate today.
People with a history of food insecurity
are going to be like, "I ate today. I
ate right before I got in bed because my
stomach will keep me awake if I don't
have food in my stomach when I go to
bed." Um, so one is gratitude for
safety. What is it that's keeping me
safe? And the other is gratitude for
pleasure. You think about like what
happened during the day. Pleasure is the
thing your brain only has access to when
you are safe enough. Um, so by tuning,
first of all, if you're regularly
practicing either one of these, it will
tune your brain to what are the things
around me that are keeping me safe and
what are the things around me that are
granting me access to pleasure. Which
means that when you lie down and you're
like, am I safe enough? Does my brain
have access to pleasure? You can dwell
on those things. Here's a really cheesy
recommendations. There's a podcast
called Nothing Much
Happens Fans. Uh it's narrated by this
Michigander lesbian. Her little bit of
Midwest accent because I lived in
Indiana for so long. Uh it just like
feels like home to me. And it's these
like very quiet. She's a yoga teacher.
She tells stories about
like we went for a muddy walk with the
pets and then we washed the dog's feet
and that's the whole story. Um her goal
so she the goal is to transition you out
of the default mode network which is
like a bad place to be when you're
trying to fall asleep and you're
stressed out into a task focused mode by
paying attention to the story. There's a
reason why we read children to sleep at
night because it's this like very gentle
task that their brain can focus on and
slide into sleep instead of letting it
do its own thing because with the way
our brains are being stimulated lately,
bad things happen if we let our brains
to their own devices. Does that help? I
had a student who had this brilliant
trick. She would lie in bed and she
would imagine a field of stars and she
would make the stars go
out and before she got all the stars to
go out she would fall asleep. You had
that other student who would when she
couldn't sleep right against it she
would imagine the times that she was
sitting in class like you know this
happens.
So she'd imagine that experience. How
cruel is it that you're sitting in class
and you're like like I want my education
and like your brain is like no
no and when you lie down and ready to go
to bed suddenly you're
[Laughter]
like so uh this this genius genius idea
of just remember really viscerally and
vividly what it felt like to fight sleep
that time that you had to fight sleep.
It works. It's called the ironic
process.
Thank you so much for that. We want to
check and see. I think there's time for
one more question. We have a raffle. Um
and then we're going to wrap up and I
need to make an amendment. The books
have been pre-signed, so there will not
be a book signing immediately following
our event. I see a hand up. Please go
right ahead. Two hands.
Um thank you so much. I'm so excited
you're here. I love your book. I've read
it too many times. But I wanted to ask
you about the Star Trek metaphor, which
like changed my life. um and like the
unwinable game, but I find that like if
you're Yeah. Yeah. If you're not like
holding it yet, I can remember the word,
but if you're not holding it in your
mind, it's really easy to like to lose
it. You know what I mean? So, I was
wondering if you have like some like
real world examples of like how to
center yourself when you're like in that
place of like nothing I'm doing is going
right, everything is wrong and it's all
my fault or whatever. Like how
to just some I guess real world examples
or anecdotes of that.
between that library.
I can't think of any real world
examples. Oh, of like actually doing it
right here. I do think about the
Kobayashi Maru all the time. The
Kobayashi Maru in Star Trek is part of
this training at the Starfleet Academy.
The captains go through this thing
called the Kobayashimi Maru, which is an
unwininnable scenario. And the goal is
not to win the scenario. It's to see how
the captain acts in the event of an
unwinable scenario. How well do you
lose? Right? Um, I think about it all
the time, but I can't think of any real
life. Oh, okay. You got Yeah. Go. It's
called death.
We're all going to die. Sorry to be
confronting. I mean, that's why I think
about the Kobe Hashimu all the time. I
didn't feel like that was like a
practical life. Okay.
I mean, unless you have a different kind
of faith belief than I have, like life
is an unwinable game. It is not you're
not going to
win. So it's about how you lose, how you
play it every day. Um thinking at a
larger especially so remember when I was
talking about when the stress response
gets activated your thinking shrinks and
narrows down to just like I've got a
hammer which means every problem in
ahead of me is a nail and I'm just going
to do this one thing and if it doesn't
work I'm just going to do it harder. as
opposed to when you can step out of the
when you're not activated in the stress
response cycle, you can be much more
creative and think uh at a much larger
scale to contextualized. So like yeah,
there's those times when you're like
everything is terrible and going wrong
and there's like the mad woman in your
brain being like and it's all your
fault, you
loser. And like take a step back and be
like this is an unwininnable game. It's
about how I play and like what are your
priorities and values? What are the
things that matter to you about the way
you navigate this unwinable scenario?
Um, our dad's uh not an awesome human
being. He's a terrible human being. The
one really excellent piece of advice he
gave us was the point of uh education is
to learn how to make them let you
out. We both have three degrees.
So like we love school, we are good at
school. But school is about navigating a
system in a way to like earn your degree
so that you can jet. Uh so when you are
confronting problems whether it is in a
workplace or in a school
setting, none of this the capitalist
ciseteropatriarchal systems through
which we are all navigating uh are
designed for us to win. It's unwinable.
There's a reason why the character that
we gave the narrative I know I'm talking
too much too much. There's a reason why
we gave that narrative of being a Star
Trek fan and finding meaning in the Star
Trek fandom. Um, that character is a fat
black cisgender woman
because it's an unwinable game. The odds
are stacked against you. It's about how
you play. There are composite stories in
the book so that every chapter something
happens to each of these composite
characters and you follow a single
individual through each of the things
that's in the chapter. That's what she's
referring to. Sophie is one of those
characters. And what she does by
following like the meaning that she gets
from Star Trek is like what matters to
her in playing this unwinable game is
making sure that the people who come
behind her don't have to play the same
unwinable game. they play a slightly
easier and more fun winnable game. So
like for me, the people who come behind
me have a slightly more
fun, more enjoyable, unwinable game to
play like
Tetris, right? Does that make sense?
Does that help at all? It was a long
answer for it not to be helpful, so I
hope it was. Can we do Well, I know
we're so out of time. We Yeah, we're
running behind, but we just we want to
thank you all so much. This was so
delightful. Thank you Emily and Amelia
and Karen for such a wonderful
conversation.
Yes. Thank you so much for questioning.
Thank you all for putting on pants
tonight and coming out. We know that's
hard. Hold on because we actually have
the raffles and so I can't recall how
many um workbooks do we have? All
right, Mary
Prosco. All right. Oh,
can we get a slight bribe? If you get a
workbook, tell us one important thing
you learned. Doesn't have to be the most
important. Just one important thing. Oh
my god.
Sorry. I wanted to make sure you were
heard.
Oh, I don't know if we need that. Uh,
people. Yeah. Oh, perfect. Uh, that last
question and discussion was incredibly
powerful for me and just I can't wait to
carry that. We're all going to die.
Yeah. think I would know that already,
but sometimes you need to be reminded.
Thank you. Thank you. Next up is Anna
Cabria. Y
the book is 80,000 words with 26 pages
of references. The workbook is for
people who don't need receipts. They
just want results.
Thank you so much. Something that really
resonates to me was like the difference
between joy and happiness and happiness
being the h happenings. So, thank you so
much for that. Thank Britney Cooper.
Yeah, Britney Cooper,
Wendell Coburn.
Uh I I love the unwininnable game and uh
just the reminder that we get like
really small uh hyperfocus when we don't
remember that. Yeah. Uh can we think
about that one for a while? Yeah, thank
you so much. Thank you for humoring me
with the like wonderful. Oh, absolutely.
Haley Miller,
it's just like just this is like Oprah
like I don't know what what did you do
this side of the room.
Um, I think for me the main thing was
just like when you were talking about
how uh you both require different
amounts of sleep, just how we're all
different and I'm like, "Oh yeah, I'm a
little bit different from like the
average in a lot of different ways and
that's okay." Yes, 100%.
Mary Francis uh
Gadi on the other side of the room.
You're welcome. Thank you so much. Being
on Oprah. I love this. It was actually
the whole even when I listened to the
audio book. I didn't read the book, but
and I liked hearing your voices in the
audio book. um how often we're stuck in
the stress cycle and not completing it
and not having realized that we didn't
complete it and that was really
revolutionary for me. So, thanks. Me,
too. Yeah, it was Amelia's thing.
And our last person this evening is Ree
Canoe.
Hey, I had to sit in the second row to
get a book apparently.
Um, importance of sleep.
Yeah. What a strong way to bring us
home. Thank you so much again for those
of you all who are here in person and
you would like to enjoy something to
eat. We have dinner for you. To those
who are virtually, thank you so much for
logging on. This concludes our season
for MIT Reads. Happy finals, happy
studying. We look forward to seeing you
who will be coming back either online or
in person next fall. And thank you all
again for such an amazing Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.