(Logo whooshes)
Hi everyone, very happy to be here.
I am Armando Solar-Lezama.
I am a distinguished
professor of computing
here in the Schwarzman
College of Computing at MIT,
and I'm also the associate director
of the Computer Science and
Artificial Intelligence Lab,
also known as CSAIL.
And I'm very excited to be here today
to answer all of your questions
about the future of AI and programming.
And so let's start with
the first question.
How is AI reshaping the
very idea of programming,
what it means to write code?
And what remains uniquely
human about that process
as AI grows more capable?
I think what's going to remain very human,
regardless of whether
you're writing research code
or whether you are doing
brand new development
for a startup, is going
to be this question of
how do we actually tell the system,
what is it that you're trying to do?
What are you actually
trying to accomplish?
And this is where software
developers bring a lot of their
human knowledge and human
expertise about, you know,
what should this piece
of software actually do?
And how do we break down what
might be a very high level,
very ambiguous statement of the goals
that we're trying to accomplish
with this piece of code
down to a very precise
description of step-by-step
what needs to happen in this process.
And now exactly how you do it
and the nature of the notation
and the tools that you do
this are probably going
to change quite dramatically
in the next few years,
just as they have changed
quite dramatically,
even in the time that, you
know, I have been working
with computers for example.
But I think what's going to
remain very uniquely human
is this creative process of figuring out
how do we bridge from the needs
to what we expect this piece
of software to do in a very precise way.
So question number two.
Do you see programming
shifting from writing code
to simply expressing intent,
where human specified goals
and the AI handles the implementation?
So I think one of the
things to make clear is that
already today for people
doing software development,
a lot of programming is
about expressing intent.
We have a remarkable ability
with modern programming
languages to abstract away
a lot of complexity so that
the focus of the programming
really is on expressing your intent.
It is true that people who are starting
to program often struggle with the syntax
and the unnaturalness of the notation.
But the fact of the matter is,
once people get to the point
where they're writing
software for a living,
the core challenge becomes
expressing their intent
at a level that is detailed
enough and precise enough
to actually build software.
However, there is no question
that these new programming
tools are going to allow us
to be able to express
things more concisely,
to be able to lift the
level of abstraction
at which we describe things.
And to get around some
of those limitations
of the current programming tools
where sometimes you still need to write
very large amounts of
code to do what you want.
In your recent CSAIL study
on autonomous software engineering,
you identified key roadblocks.
Which ones do you think will fall first?
So making predictions about
this technology is difficult
because of how quickly the
technology is developing.
For example, one of the things
that we've seen in recent
years is this reasoning models
that are able to think
through challenging problems
step by step, and in many
cases, solve problems
that they have never seen before in ways
that are really exciting and surprising.
One of the big challenges
that we see in tools today is
their inability though, to
do this at scale, right?
And to do this at the scale
of reasoning that is required
when you're dealing
with a large code base.
However, we have a lot of tools coming
from more traditional
programming systems technology
that can help us manage some of that scale
and manage some of that complexity.
And so I do believe that
as we get better at incorporating
some of that knowledge
and some of those tools into
the current AI based processes,
we're probably going to
be doing much, much better
at dealing with larger and
larger software systems.
Now, this is just to one
dimension in which current tools
still have shortcomings,
but I think it will actually
make a really big difference
in terms of using these
tools in the context
of harder, larger scale
software engineering tasks.
Now, we have another question.
How close are we to truly
automated debugging, testing,
and refactoring at the scale
of real production systems?
So all of these thing:;
debugging, testing and refactoring
come at many different flavors
and many different scales.
Debugging for example, you can
have a bug that is, you know,
just one line of code that
is doing the wrong thing.
And once you identify it and
fix it, the software works.
We have also seen bugs where you realize
in analyzing the bug
that there is a problem
in the way you structured your computation
and in the way you
architected your solution
that actually is going to make
that bug really hard to fix.
And so the first kind of bug,
I think we're actually
already there, right?
You can already use many of these tools
to identify those kind of
finger error type of bugs
where all it takes is a
small change in your code
in order to fix it.
And once you see it, it's very clear
that there is a bug there.
By contrast, the kind of bugs that arise
from a faulty reasoning
and faulty assumptions
about your problem domain.
I think we're probably still many years
before we can have systems
that can do that kind of debugging.
And I think similar things have to do
with things like testing
and refactoring, right?
There are some refactorings
that are very standardized
and relatively simple
and that can be implemented
pretty mechanically
even with tools that
existed prior to LLMs.
But the really challenging
refactorings are those
that really require rethinking
the architecture of the code
that require very non-standard changes
that span the entire code base.
And again, I think those
are the kind of things
that we're probably many, many years
before we would trust a
completely automated tool
to do them.
So I think to reframe these questions,
I think it's not so much about the scale
of the production systems,
but about the complexity of the task
that you're trying to perform.
So now we have a question
here about the research
that we actually do in my research group.
The question says, in
DreamCoder, you showed
how AI can learn reusable abstractions.
Could this lead to systems
that invent domain specific
languages on the fly?
So for those of you who are
not familiar with my research,
let me give you a little bit of context.
One of the challenges
in software synthesis
in generating programs is
that you're often restricted
to the building blocks
and the abstractions
that were already there present
in the existing software,
in the libraries that the
system has already seen
in order to produce the code.
And one of the things
that we're trying to do
with this DreamCoder project
was to allow the system
to discover its own building blocks,
to identify common recurring
patterns in the solutions
that it generates, and abstract
these into new components
that can then make it
easier to build new software
in a similar way that humans
build software, right?
The first time around you might just write
a whole bunch of code, but
then you start thinking about
how do I abstract this so
that the next time I have
to solve the same problem, I
can build on the abstractions
and I can build on these building
blocks that I had before.
And so this is a really
powerful capability
to give our AI systems.
And I do believe that in
the future it will help us
not just write code
and write solutions for the
problems we have at hand,
but actually allow us to do more
of what real software engineerings do,
which is plan for the future, right?
And plan for those abstractions
that will not just help me
solve the current problem at hand,
but that will be useful
to build the problems
that I'm likely to
encounter in the future.
So the next question here
is about natural language.
We talk to each other in natural language.
We would really like
to talk to our machines
in natural language as well.
And this is one of the things
that this large language models
really brings to the table.
And so the question here is,
what role do you see
natural language playing?
Could English or other spoken
languages effectively become
the new programming interface?
So, no.
Being able to speak in
natural language is great
and you know, this is
what we're familiar with
from the time we were children.
This is what we used to
talk to our colleagues.
However, when it comes to
building really big systems,
natural language is very
insufficient, right?
If you've ever tried to read
the terms and conditions
of some of the software you use,
you've probably run into
some of the limitations
of natural language when it
comes to communicating things
that are really detail
oriented and complex, right?
Any kind of legal document, you know,
natural language very quickly
starts feeling very unnatural
once you start having
to communicate things
above a certain level of precision
and above a certain scale.
And this is where programming
languages really shine, right?
As much as we like to
complain about the fact
that programming languages are too brittle
and they're too clunky
and it's hard to learn how to use them,
the fact of the matter is,
they are the best notation
and the most sophisticated notation
that we've been ever
been able to come up with
to describe really complex
behaviors at scale.
And so, no, I actually
don't see natural language
completely replacing traditional
programming languages
as the programming interface of choice.
It doesn't mean that there
won't be a really important role
for natural language in how we interact
with our programming tools
and how we talk about our goals
with the software systems.
But at the end of the day,
it's really important to have
that notation that can
support the precision
and the scale that we need
for software development.