so hi everyone welcome back to the crash
course lecture series for the autoimmune
disease machine learning challenge in
this lecture we're going to cover uh the
data that you'll be working with during
the three crunches uh how the data is
organized uh and then what are the
actual crunches what are the actual
tasks that you're going to be working on
with these data sets so first I'd like
to give you uh a really brief recap of
the first two lectures before we go into
the data so in the first lecture you got
an introduction to autoimmune disease
and you learned about ulcerative colitis
and how Pathologists study ulcerative
colitis tissue by doing these h& e
stains and here again we have this
comparison between healthy colon where
you have these nice ordered Crypts and
aler of kitis where you're seeing this
inflammation and really massive changes
in the tissue structure and organization
so you know this is really great
Pathologists can learn a lot from these
images but in the challenge or these
crunches we really want to move beyond
that
and then we also want to ask can we use
these images to inform uh predictions
about uh the development of cancer in
these
patients the second lecture we cover the
technologies that are used to measure
gene expression programs so you remember
the gene expression programs are groups
of genes that are turned on and
regulated together during a biological
process and they dramatically change
from Health to disease so from Health to
ulcerative colitis or from healthy colon
to colar rectal cancer
and then we've also introduced three
different Technologies to profile these
colon tissues they're these h& stains
the Pathologists use and then there's
the spatial transcriptomics measurements
where we can profile hundreds of genes
at a time while maintaining spatial
information and then there are these
single cell RNA seek or single cell
transcriptomics measurements where we're
measuring thousands of single cells and
getting gene expression for all 20,000
genes but we lose the spatial
information okay so that's a brief recap
of what you've already seen and now
let's go into what data you're going to
be working with so we'll talk about the
clinical samples that we're working with
and the data that's derived from them
from them and then finally we'll go into
the three different
crunches so first the clinical samples
so the collection of the clinical
samples uh from ulcerative colitis
patients was spearheaded by uh Dr Ron
mavier who again is one of the
organizers of this of this Challenge and
also uh with help from Dr Angela shei
who is a pathologist at Harvard Medical
School and Massachusetts General
Hospital and they collected eight tissue
samples from patients with colon
inflammation so here we're showing again
non-inflamed colon and inflamed colon
this is the view from a
colonoscopy and most of the samples
you're going to be working with are from
ulcerative colitis uh and we have pieces
of the tissue that are both from
inflamed and non-inflamed regions we
also have a few samples from a more mild
form of inflammation called
diverticulitis um we provide these
samples because there's less change to
the colon spatial organization in
diverticulitis so this is a good thing
to compare to when you want to think
about what healthy colon looks like
versus what inflamed or heavily inflamed
colon looks like in ulcerative colitis
so this is a good point of reference
when looking at the changes in spatial
organization as inflammation
increases so each tissue sample was
prepared by uh a group of doctors and
Pathologists for uh processing an h&
image and also collecting spal
transcriptomic data and for each tissue
uh our pathologist Angela shei um looked
at uh the tissue and the h& stain and
diagnosed the disease type and how
severe it is and also looked for
evidence of dysplasia which you'll
remember is a sign of precancer it's
these early abnormal growths in the
epithelial
cells so here is the tissue processing
pipeline uh that each of these samples
went through uh the this is work that
was done at the Bro Institute by Osa
seopa and crystalin and what they did
was they take the colon tissue that's
been taken out of the patient and they
chop it up and they identify the
different layers of the tissue then they
embed the tissue in paraffin paraffin is
a rigid substrate it's like Wax and once
the tissue is embedded in this wax you
can make very very thin slices 5 Micron
width and that's ideal for microscopy
and imaging so you make these uh
paraffin blocks you make these very thin
sections as you see here and then you
can stain those very thin sections of
the colon tissue with the h& stain and
Angela the pathologist come look at it
and start to annotate the image and tell
us uh what's happening from the
histopathology
perspective so here are the first four
of the eight samples you'll be working
with these are the h& images of ulcer
colitis samples an inflamed piece from
patient one and a non-inflamed piece
from patient one in addition to
diverticulitis samples which look a lot
more normal in terms of the colon tissue
organization you see clearly all the
layers and not really evidence of uh bad
inflammation and then here's the next
four tissue sections you work with um
these are all ulcerative colitis uh
patients an inflamed then a non-inflamed
piece and then two other inflamed pieces
and then uh importantly uh when Dr
Angela shei was looking at this sample
uh she spotted that this patient has
dysplasia which again is a mark of
precancer so let's look at that h& stain
a little more closely um so just to
remind you uh there's a Continuum of
cancer where we go from normal colon
mucosa to dysplasia which is these
abnormal growth of epithelial cells all
the way to carcino which is the coloral
cancer and so here's the h& image of
that patient uh col tissue that was
taken out and Angela noted that this
region of the mucosa that's darker has
displasia and this region that's a
little lighter and looks more a little
more normal and ordered is non-cancerous
so this was very interesting to us
because we wanted to know you know
what's different between these regions
and can we learn more about the regions
with displasia and better identify them
from pathology images and on the right
here we have some of the notes that Dr
shei made about that image but the most
important thing is that was remarked was
that there's this low grade dysplasia in
this region
here so that's an overview of the tissue
uh the clinical tissue samples you'll be
working with and now we will discuss uh
the data that's derived from those
samples