So so
let's recall where we were last time. So
we are trying to prove protection
theorem. I guess I will state it again
uh later. But uh last time we hopefully
accepted the following fact as true. Uh
okay. So maybe
if
a subset of 01
is a okay so given s
there exist
ea and epsilon positive depending on s
and if we have a set which is a an S
delta delta to the minus EA set
then there exist a little A in the set
such that the size of A plus little A a
grows by delta to the minus epsilon
compared to the size of A.
So Larry pointed out okay so initially
instead of this we have some polomial Q
of A such as AA minus AA. So Larry
pointed out to me that if you follow
exactly what you did in the finite field
setting to go from Q of A to this you
need to use the non-conentration
condition that we are trying to prove
but it is possible to do it in a way
which is not circular. So
okay so I said I was not going to cover
all of the details. So using pruning
corusa so pruning corusa is the main
tool and switchable double counting one
can really improve this without using
something that we haven't proved yet
okay and the goal is to improve this by
showing that a plus a satisfies a better
non concentration condition that will
allow us to iterate. So the goal is to
show that a plus a a actually contains
because
it is not true that it always is but it
contains
a delta s plus epsilon
delta to the minus
maybe let's call it prime
um set.
So the can get worse when one iterates
but one iterates finitely many times. So
this is not serious.
Okay. Um, okay. Maybe for a different So
the epsilon is also going to change.
Okay. So, um,
so suppose
so I'm basically going back to what I
did at the end of last time, but I was
rushing a bit. So I'm going to be a bit
more precise hopefully. Suppose that a
is a delta s delta to the minus ea squar
set.
Well in particular it is an s delta
delta to the minus
so I guess the delta goes first. Um in
particular it is it is a delta s delta
to the minus ita set because it is a
very small number. But why did I square
it? Because um then
it is okay. And as we saw last time, if
we take a subset of a which is uniform,
delta m uniform for some good choice of
delta, delta will have to be chosen
small enough in terms of EA but nothing
else.
uh then so we may assume
let's call it delta uniform
or delta
depends on ea so that basically this
doesn't change maybe one has to multiply
by two but essentially doesn't change
well then uh this uh set because it's
uniform now is also a row s
delta to the minus ea square
for every row
and then this implies that it is also a
row s row to the minus ea. So the
problem here is that now we have row
here but we still have delta here but we
replace it by it squared so that so that
we can have also row here
and this will be for every row
between delta and delta to the ea
right because we started with delta to
the minus ea squ
okay we don't go all the way to one but
almost it is very very small. So morally
this is almost one.
So from here to here we use the
uniformity. So one consequence of
uniformity that uh I explained last time
is that a uniform delta set is also a
row set for every row. And this is just
trivial inequality assume that row is at
most delta to the ea.
[Applause]
Okay. So this in this means that we can
apply what we already know for every
scale row between delta and delta 2
theta because it satisfies the
assumptions.
And another thing that I explained last
time is that even though a priority we
only know that there exists an a so that
a plus little aa grows by applying that
to the set of exceptions we get that
this is true for almost every a in a
strong sense. So if you put all of this
together,
what we get is that
okay so maybe let's recall what I just
said. So in fact um
the set of a
okay so let's work with some finite set
of rows which are powers of delta again.
So we have delta delta square
up to delta to some
maybe m prime. So that this is equal to
delta to the
recall that little delta is delta to the
m. So m prime is less than m but it is
close to m.
And again this is a
finite set of scales. Well, not really
finite because okay this it is finite
but it grows with delta but it grows
logarithmically with delta. So m is
logarithm
of little delta in base
delta. Big delta is fixed. So it's it's
logarithmic in delta and m prime is
smaller. So it's also logarithmic in
delta. Okay. So uh for each row
we know that the set of A's so that A
plus row A doesn't grow sorry little A
but measurement scale row doesn't grow
by row to the minus epsilon
has size at most row to the eater
times the size of a.
And why is this true? Because
uh if
this was not true then we could apply
the statement above to the scale row
to the set of exceptions to this set and
get the contradiction.
[Applause]
Okay. And this is very small in terms of
delta. So row to the EA is at most delta
to the EA squar
sorry here.
Okay.
Okay. So here we are counting a set of
A's. So the only way in which we can
really count a set of A's is by
measuring it at some scale. otherwise
could be infinite. So we always have to
choose a scale. Um
so scale row okay row to the EA is at
most delta to the squared
and this means that um
sorry this is wrong.
Let's go back and fix it. So delta is is
is too large. So delta is a constant. So
I want to be away from one. Uh not away
from zero but away from one. So the rows
that we consider are delta to the m
delta to the which is little delta delta
to the m minus one. And then we stop at
delta to the ea.
Sorry about that.
Okay. because we are only looking at
logarithmically many um values of delta.
Okay, one has to work a little bit more
because here we are measuring things
that scale row but uh row is far away
from one
and there are only logarithmically many
values of row. So putting all together
what we get is that
for all aside
of a small set.
Maybe something like a set of size
delta to the ea
I don't know cubed times the size of a
we get that a plus little a grows for
every scale in this family.
Okay. And now it looks like we are
getting close because well we want to
show that this contains
a delta
s plus epsilon something set and a
necessary condition is that we have
growth at every scale.
So if you have a set with that, so if
you have a
delta s plus epsilon something set, then
this will be true.
And if we knew that this set is uniform,
we would be done because for a uniform
set, the condition of growing at every
scale is necessary and sufficient.
But we don't know that this set is
uniform.
So we are not done yet. So we are
getting closer, but we are not done yet.
Any questions? So, this is more or less
where we were last time.
Okay. So, in order to be able to finish,
we still have to work a bit and uh there
was a claim that there was explaining
last time that we can improve this. So
here we are projecting a * a. So this is
pi a of a * a. So we can improve this to
project an arbitrary dense subset of a *
a. So claim
uh if
g is contained in a * a and it has size
at scale delta let's say delta to the
square or something like this
relative to a * a then
pa of g
already grows
and in fact we this we will also want to
apply
at many scales or maybe not. We'll see.
Okay, let's start with scale delta. Then
we'll see what we actually need. Uh then
this already grows let's say by epsilon
/ two.
Okay. And I guess at this stage uh we
claim that there exists such an A.
But once again, if there exist an A,
then it is true for nearly all A by
applying the fact that there exists an A
to the exceptional set. So we can play
this game as many times as we want and
we want to play it many times.
Okay. So uh last time we were in the
middle of proving this. So let's start
the game. Uh assume that one is in a
this is just tool to okay just for
notation and simplicity it's not not
important.
Well, if a equals 1 works,
we are done because we are trying to
show that some some element of a works.
So, if the element one happens to work,
we are happy.
Otherwise,
[Applause]
one doesn't work. And the fact that one
doesn't work means that there exists G
which is dense in a * A
[Applause]
and such that pi 1 of G doesn't grow too
much.
And this okay the f so all of these
together are exactly the assumptions of
alumericic hours or rather the delta
covering number of Alexic hours but as I
explained a couple of lectures ago
valuic hours works exactly the same for
delta covering numbers.
So maybe let's recall
the hours for delta covering numbers. Um
if
uh a a scale delta has size n
and
there exists g contained in a * a
such that the size of g at scale delta
is at least 1 / k times the size of a
plus a at scale delta
And if we project in the direction one
the set g
uh this doesn't grow a lot compared to
the size of a.
If all of this is true then there exists
a set a prime contained in a which is
fairly dense. So the size of a at scale
delta is at least k to minus a constant
times the size of a
and a prime has a small subset.
The doubling constant for a prime is at
most k to a power to to a constant power
times the size of a prime.
Okay, this is valuic hours.
Well, here we can take well n is just
the delta covering number of a and we
can take k to be the minimum between ea
square
delta to the minus ea square and delta
to the minus epsilon / two which is
really delta to the minus ea square. You
should imagine that is smaller than
epsilon even before squaring.
[Applause]
Okay. So we apply maluic hours
and let a prime
be the corresponding set.
Okay. And then uh
a prime is dense in a
and has more subset.
Okay. So, A prime is a dense subset of
A.
A is a delta S something set. So, A
prime is also a delta S something set
because we saw that subsets of delta S
something sets are delta S something
sets where the constant. So basically we
have to multiply the constant by this
but a was a delta s delta to the epsilon
square set. So this is still a delta s
delta to the minus o of epsilon square
set.
So we can apply what we know to a prime.
So a prime is a delta s delta to the
minus o of it square set.
So there exists a in a prime in a prime
sorry such that a prime plus a a prime
grows
by applying the fact from the beginning
to a prime. It still satisfies the
assumptions. We have lost a constant
here but this is harmless.
Any
questions so far?
Okay. And now we apply something that
you've seen in the finite field setting.
And again, it works. This works exactly
in the same way for delta covering sets.
What you saw in the finite field setting
is that if you have a set with a small
sums set,
so small pi 1 projection and large pi a
projection,
then in fact the pi projection remains
large if we pass to a dense subset of a
prime time n prime.
Okay, so this is another recall from the
finite field story.
If a prime plus a prime let's say again
it goes by at most k
and a prime plus little a prime
let's say
so a prime has small doubling but if you
apply projection by a it grows by
something
then in fact this implies that for every
g in
a prime * a prime which is dense
let's say dense with threshold 1 / k
everything measured with delta covering
numbers
the projection is still large
and I think it's K to minus some
constant and DL basically survives.
Does this look like something you've
seen before?
Okay. Does it look like something that
Okay.
Well, go back to your notes and or
otherwise just believe me this is true.
Um Larry told me you've seen something
like this. Maybe with different letters
very likely with different letters. But
the point is you have a set with small
doubling but large PA projection. then
the PA projection is large even after
passing to a subset.
Okay, so it looks like we've almost won
because look at the claim
and look at what we have here.
Okay, have we really won?
Not exactly because the claim was for A
and we got it for A prime which is a
dense subset of A but it is not A. So
one has to work a bit to
really win but you will have to trust me
that one can win from here. So the claim
was that
what we obtained for a prime is true for
a
and we got it for a prime not for a. So
I will briefly explain how to get it for
a but I will not do all of the details
because otherwise we'll be here forever.
Uh maybe let's keep
the objective inside.
Okay, we can upgrade
a prime to a
and the idea
is well either a prime is a in which
case we win or if a prime is not all of
a but it is almost all of a in the sense
that a minus a prime is really small we
still win uh because
so if if the difference between a and a
prime is really small you just apply
trivial bounds on the very small part
and we still win. So
if a minus a prime is very small
very small maybe of size less than delta
to the plus e to something like this
times the size of a
we are fine otherwise
do the same so apply the same argument
to a minus a prime.
If a prime is not very dense in a, then
a minus a prime is still the delta is
delta to the minus theta square set. And
we can do the same and get a new a
prime.
So maybe the original a prime we can
call it a prime one.
And if we apply the same thing, we get
an a prime two. Now uh at the same time
we have to play the game that if
something is true for one a is true for
nearly all a because we found that there
exist an a and there exist an a prime
but in fact there are lots of a but the
a prime could depend on a so one has to
be a little bit careful
but
but one can play this game and
eventually uh one gets
so all of these sets have large size
because they are dense in a prime.
Where is it? A prime is dense in A. So
at some point
and they are all disjointed. They are
all disjointed because we take away the
previous ones when we apply this again.
So at some point
we reach a step where
we have exhausted almost all of a
let's say something like this and then
we stop.
Okay, but I'm cheating here because
and then then we stop and then basically
we win because if we have a set G which
is dense in a in a * A. Okay. Uh we
still don't really win yet. But if a set
G is dense in A* A, it will be dense in
A I prime time A
G prime. Maybe a different prime. Okay,
so one still has to work. Okay, plus
some work plus more work.
And I'm basically ignoring a here, the
little a here. But it's okay to ignore
the little a because everything you
prove from one little a is true for
nearly all little a.
Maybe forget what I said. But okay, this
is one thing you have to do. Just
iterate.
So iterate this. Here we get a dense a
prime. We want to get all of a not the
dense a prime. We iterate plus some
double counting.
We get
that claim
any questions
so one has to work here so I I haven't
proved it so I don't expect you to see
the proof so one thing you have to do in
the proof is iterate but you have to do
more things and double count carefully
um but eventually one gets that so one
is able to upgrade a prime to a okay so
that claim is True.
So that claim says that there exists an
A and once there is one A there are many
A's nearly all A's. So that the pi A
projection of any dense subset of A plus
A grows
and now we are really close to the to
the end of that goal.
So a prime a plus a a plus little a a is
not necessarily uniform but we know that
it contains a uniform subset and when we
pass to a uniform subset we can make it
large
for any sub additive
function set function mu.
Okay, so this is the mu we are going to
use now. So mu of b
is going to be okay. So
fix little a for which the claim holds.
[Applause]
So this is the clean star. So we fix a
little a so that this holds
and then let mu of b and here b is a
subset of 01 so it's a subset of a
really
is the delta covering number not of b
but of pi a inverse of b.
So this is sub additive right because
what is mu of b1 union b2 well uh if you
take pre images
you get something which is contained in
the pre image of the in the in the union
of the pre images and then the delta
covering number is sub additive. Does
this mean pi a inverse of b intersect a
cross a?
>> Yes. Sorry. Thank you.
So this is finitely subjective
because delta covering number is
subjective and we are just taking delta
covering number together with the
pre-image which is already subjective.
Okay. So by lema from last time by the
uniformization lema from last time
there exists
an a prime contained in a
uh which is uniform.
Sorry, not in A. Ah, there existed B
contained in A plus little A A.
So we are going to apply uniformization
to A plus little A A.
We are trying to show that this set
contains a delta S plus epsilon set. So
this is our ultimate goal and we know
that if this set was uniform, it would
be enough to show that it grows at every
scale to reach the conclusion. So we
want to make it uniform but we need to
know that the uniform subset grows at
every scale.
Okay. So by uniformization there exist a
b in a plus e a such that this mu
of b is larger than delta to the minus
ea squar
times the measure of a + a a. And what
is the measure of a plus a a? This is
just the delta covering number of a * a.
Okay. So this is the delta covering
number
of pi a inverse of b.
So this is a sorry again I forgot to
intersect with a * a.
So this is the g to which we can apply
the claim.
So this is a dense subset of a * a.
And we know that for every dense subset
of a * a the pi a projection grows.
In particular, the pi a projection of
this grows. But this is pi a inverse. So
if we apply pi a we land in b and in
particular we land in a plus little aa
but in particular we land in b which is
uniform.
Okay. So apply
claim star
to g equals pi i inverse of b
intersection a * a is does satisfies the
density assumption
and this is because uniform sets can be
taken deaths. So again here I have to
choose maybe a different delta than
before although I guess the same delta
works because it's the same numerology.
So that this is true.
We can make we can take uniform sets
which are as dense in the exponential
sense as we want. This is exactly what's
going on here.
Okay. And the conclusion is that
the delta covering number
grows
sorry not by a b ah
by a of a *
intersected with B, I guess.
Okay. So, um,
okay. So now we are getting so we are
one step closer uh because now we have a
uniform subset of a * little a a
and the delta covering number
well I guess B is a subset of this. So
here one could have just B. So the delta
covering number grows.
We know that if a set is uniform and the
row covering number grows for every row
and in fact we don't need every row we
is enough to consider rows which are
powers of delta then they are h
delta s plus the growth set. So we just
repeat. So here we have something for
for delta but then um
okay let's see what is the right order
to do this. So I want to claim that what
we did for delta we can do for any
scale. So there is nothing special about
delta because a itself is uniform. All
of this that we did for delta we can do
it for any other scale uh row.
But uh the uniform set that we get can
depend on the scale.
So what is the right order to do this?
So the goal is to use the lema from last
time that says that if it is uniform and
the row covering number is large for
every row and in fact one doesn't need
every every row. It's enough to consider
powers of the delta based in the
uniformity.
then it is a delta s set where the s
comes from the size of the row covering
numbers
and okay by using this idea for every
row so we did it with for delta but the
assumptions hold for every row at least
for every row which is not very close to
one so we can do the same
uh the only danger is that we could get
a different b for different rows we
could get different beasts.
And I'm not very happy about this. So,
how do we deal with this?
One thing one could try to do but I
think we lose too much is okay delta is
delta to the m. Now we want to go to
delta to the m minus one. So we could
just replace
a plus little a by b.
But then we will have another subset of
b and we are going to lose this factor
logarithmically many times and that is
too many times. So yeah I don't want to
do that. I will lose too much. Um,
okay. So, there is something I'm missing
and I'm not going to figure it out right
now. So, uh, because I told you that
Yes.
>> Um, can you prove the claim
simultaneously for all scales, replace
that delta by rows, all the different
rows, and then then I think that would
fix it.
>> Yeah. You want to have the same G for
every scale.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. uh
>> if you conclude that's stronger claim
then it will solve
>> yes but why can't we get the same G for
for all the scales
okay because I told you I wouldn't give
a complete proof and just a sketch of
some of the ideas well here is a sketch
of some of the ideas and is is something
technical that so really the ideas are
what I explained and what I'm missing is
something technical it's not
fundamental I would
just to summarize what's been what's
been going on. I still have to explain
once we prove that goal how to continue
with the rest of bans the proof of the
rest of bans theorem but really this is
really the most difficult step where
things really change from the final
field setting okay so let me uh
sort of briefly explain again everything
that's been going on uh so we know that
a plus a grows but we want to show that
it also satisfies a stronger
non-conentration assumption that the S
in the non-conentration assumption also
grows.
Okay, first we can take A to be uniform.
If A is uniform, then we know that A
itself is a row set for every row. And
this allows us to reach conclusions for
every scale row, which is something that
we have to use in the step that I'm
missing as well. We use it we used it
before, but clearly we have to use it
again.
And then we know that a plus little aa
grows at every scale. If it was true
that a plus little a a was uniform
then we would win because for uniform
sets we saw last time that if they are
large at every scale then they satisfy
the corresponding non-conentration
condition.
So we have to take a large uniform
subset of a but large with respect to
what? Well, large respect to this
because this is what allows what allow
us to use the fact that if we project
something dense in a time a then we grow
and how do we know that if project
we have to combine two things firstic
hours and valid hours. So for valued
hours we just take an arbitrary element
of a in this case we took one but it can
be an arbitrary element of a we apply
hours. So either that element already
works and we are done for that go for
the claim star or if it doesn't work
then we are under the assumptions of
valuic hours. we apply valuic hours and
then we end up with the set that
satisfies the assumption of something
else that you've seen in the finite
field setting which is that if you have
a very small subset an expansion under
pi a then this expansion under pa is
robust under passing two subsets. So in
either case we get that pi a of d subset
of a * a is large and this allows us to
use uniformity with this mu.
So that's a bit of a summary of the main
steps to show the goal.
Okay. Plus technical details
I can recall right now. Sorry about
that.
Uh this implies the goal.
the goal that goal.
Okay. Why did you spend so much time
towards this goal? Because now we can
iterate. We knew that if a is a delta s
delta to the minus epsilon set, then a
plus a a grows. But not only it grows,
it contains a delta s plus epsilon delta
to the minus ita prime set. And then we
can iterate.
So a plus little a is our new
a.
So iterating
a goes to a plus little a
for every epsilon uh maybe let's not
call it epsilon for every toao
there exist a polomial that depends on
toao is a very large degree if tow is
close to zero
such that qa of A is a delta
1 minus toao. So the s can become
arbitrarily close to one.
Delta to the minus some eat tilda that
depends on how many times we have to
iterate set and by is I mean contains.
Yes,
>> you said that epsilon is going to change
a
>> yeah I think instead of epsilon is
epsilon over two
>> so but then if the epsilons are
shrinking how are you getting arbitrary
close to
>> yeah that's a good question so epsilon
okay epsilon in some sense is shrinking
but okay so there there is one epsilon
which is the epsilon for the size of a
plus little aa and there is potentially
a different epsilon
If we want to find a delta s plus
epsilon set inside a plus little aa
those two epsilons I think one is
epsilon the other is epsilon / two but
the point is that they depend on s
continuously both of them
so they are continuous they can be taken
to be continuous functions of s because
they are continuous functions of s as
long as s is less than 1 minus toao s is
bounded away from zero so we reach 1
minus towa in finitely many steps
Maybe let's write this here because it's
important. So epsilon
is or can be taken continuous
uh function of
s.
So remains
bounded below
as long as s is bounded away from one.
So we can do we can achieve this by
iterating finally many times.
[Applause]
Okay. And why is this good? Because this
allows us to do instead of a plus little
a a now we can do x plus little ax where
x is potentially much bigger than a.
[Applause]
So the next step
and I think this step is the same as in
define a field setting. So I'm basically
just going to state it. Uh if x
is a delta t uh okay x in 01 still
and x is a delta
uh maybe let's call it u. So u is going
to be t / 2 soon. uh delta minus epsilon
set
and a
is 01
is a delta s maybe let's write ea here
for consistency delta to the minus ea
set. So now instead of one set we have
two sets potentially of very different
sizes and okay they are both strictly
bigger than zero and strictly less than
one and the interesting case
is when s is less than u. So this is the
case that that we don't already know.
Then there exists little a in a
such that x plus little ax grows.
It grows by some epsilon that depends on
s and u
Okay. So uh just briefly so the idea and
again I think you've seen this in the
final setting but the idea is that it's
true
for
maybe not for a but is true for Q to of
a
and here you have to take toao uh so
that q to a is bigger than X.
So we can take toao for example to be 1
- U / 2
something like this. Then this is much
bigger than X in size. So these are sets
but it has size much bigger than X. Once
once uh the set of directions has size
much bigger than X we can do double
counting and get growth with this
instead of this. But once we get growth
for a polomial instead of a we apply
pruna one million times and we go back
down to a.
Okay. and then apply
plunic
triangle inequality
double counting
and then it is also true for a.
So this part is really exactly the same.
So we already had to go from Q of A to
to little A uh before. So initially we
proved that A a minus A a is bigger than
A and we use that to show that A plus
little A is bigger than A. So it's the
same the same reduction here and I think
you've seen something very similar in
the finite field setting and modular
technical details. This part is the
same.
But in order to get here, it's important
that we can make this set bigger than x.
This is what we wanted to iterate.
Potentially x is much bigger than a. But
we can expand a by a polomial so that it
becomes bigger than x. And for this we
have to iterate. This is why we worried
so much about iterating.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay, the next step is to
prove Bans projection theorem.
Okay, I'm not going to do the whole
proof, but just basically recall what it
is in the final setting and explain
again where one where one has to be a
little bit careful, but hopefully by now
you will not be so worried about the
part where we have to be careful. So
proof of region theorem.
Okay. Now I regret calling this xx but
it's too late.
So let x be uh in the unit b 2
delta t delta t the minus ea set where
ea is very very small and t is between
zero and two.
Let d be a set of directions
which is a delta s delta to the minus ea
set
and what is the goal?
So what is the claim of protection
theorem? It is that there exists some a
in d
such that pi a
of g
exceeds the trivial bound by some
epsilon
and the trivial bound is the
square root of the delta. Okay, sorry.
In the version we are that I stated the
size of X is delta to the minus T. So it
matches the non concentration condition.
So here we can just write delta t the
minus t / two. This is the square root
of the size of x which is the trivial
bound and we exceed it by some delta to
the minus epsilon. And this is true for
every g which is dense in a * a.
Okay. So this is projection theorem.
This is what we want to prove.
Okay. So uh in the finite setting I
think to prove a similar statement uh
what you did is first consider three fix
well just pick three directions in D
in order to apply hours. So again it's
similar to what we did before. Either
things already work or we can apply
hours. Here we have to be careful about
how we choose the three directions.
Uh because if the three directions that
we choose are very close to each other
uh this is going to be bad news. We are
going to lose a lot.
So um well even though this is in 01 we
can sort of change coordinates
[Applause]
so that 0 1 and infinity are in D
and this can be done in a way where we
don't lose too much using that D is
spread out
Because of these non-conentration
conditions,
there are three points in D which are
far apart from each other. But that
means that if we send these three points
that are far apart from each other to 0,
one infinity. So the are really the
slopes. They are not the angles, they
are slopes. So uh so this can be done
with a linear change of coordinates.
of distortion.
So the distortion is the norm of the
corresponding matrix
delta to the minus O of EA.
So this distortion is because EA is much
smaller than epsilon.
If we have a gain,
well we have to decrease the gain by
what we lose in this range of
coordinates. But this is mild.
[Applause]
>> A to be like pi 0
x.
>> We Yeah, we are going to look at the
vertical and horizontal projections of x
and and the the pi one of x. Yeah, I'm
just saying there's X and A in the
>> Oh, sorry. Uh,
>> sorry. In X in X. Sorry.
>> X
in X. X. X is in R2
>> in X.
>> X is in X is a two dimensional object.
>> And the point is you want to try to
prove this using a= 0 infinity X.
Yes. Yeah, that's the point. But yeah,
so sorry there was a typo here. So x is
already two dimensional in what we have
been doing. We have a cartitionian
product or here we have a cartitionian.
Okay, bad board management again. Now
it's hidden. So okay, we want to apply
this which unfortunately is going to be
hidden. Okay, so x this x is going to be
some like the projection of x horizontal
projection of the x in R2.
[Applause]
So it's really similar to the final
field setting. So I'm I'm going to I'm
skipping details. I'm going to continue
skipping details mostly focusing on the
differences. So one difference is that
we have to be careful with the three
directions that we take. If they are too
close to each other, the distortion will
be too large and we will it can be so
large that we lose all the gain. But
because the set of directions is spread
out by the non-conentration condition,
we can do it in such a way that the
distortion is controlled.
Okay. So now x is contained in x1 * x2
where this is the
horizontal projection and this is the
vertical projection.
So uh if because we are assuming that
also one
is in d. If one works we are done
because we are trying to show that
something works. So the claim is that
there exist an a and d with this
property. So if we are so lucky that one
has this property we are done.
if one doesn't work.
So this is very similar to what we did a
bit earlier but somehow we have to do it
twice. Once to do the iteration for a
plus e aa and then again to conclude the
proof. If one doesn't work then there
exists some g
which is dense in x1 * x2.
Okay, sorry. Why is it dancing X1?
Ah,
okay. Actually, uh,
yeah, this is more complicated. So, one
has to be careful. So, okay. So, um,
okay. So I want to assume that X1
has size roughly square root of the size
of X with the idea that if he had size
bigger than the size of X we would win.
But in fact in order to reach this
conclusion we have to apply the G
already because the conclusion we want
is not only that the projection of X
grows but the projection of every dense
subset of X works. So
okay so what one really has to do is
apply
hours three times. So for zero one and
maybe for zero infinity and one in this
order either it works or we apply
hours
to replace x by x prime and then xp
prime and then x triple prime. Okay, I'm
not going to do all of the details, but
uh
did something like this happen in the
final field setting? I think it also
this part has to be done in the final
field setting.
So
>> we didn't we didn't do this stronger
version in detail.
>> Oh, okay. So you didn't do the strong
version in detail. Okay. Uh also I'm not
going to do the strong version in detail
uh because the 20 minutes I expected to
take are turning into the whole lecture
again. Uh but I'm leaving today. So now
I really have to finish it over the next
20 minutes. So okay so we okay either
zero one or infinity or I guess zero
infinity
or one
work
or
in each case
we can apply
valuetic words
and pass to subs to dense subsets of X
of X and the corresponding projections
of X.
So evalu
if the horizontal projection
has the property we want, we are done.
Otherwise, there exist a dense subset of
a with a small horizontal projection.
But we can imagine that the horizontal
projection is some other projection. So
it's the same thing we did last time uh
we did a bit earlier and then we have to
replace x by some x prime and then by
some xp prime and then by some x triple
prime. So
I'm not going to do it in detail. I'm
sorry. Yeah, I see many of you are
confused and that's okay because uh one
has to do it carefully. It's not obvious
how to do it but it can be done. Okay.
Okay. So eventually
after renaming the set back to X,
we are in the following situation.
This situation where
Okay, let me just write it here.
where the horizontal and vertical
projections
have size at most delta to the minus
epsilon t / 2 + epsilon.
Okay, I guess um let's say we apply
valuic hours twice. Uh so we don't apply
to pi one yet.
Okay. And just to see how this goes. So
suppose that uh pi one
So suppose that one doesn't work.
Suppose that one doesn't work. And that
means that pi 1 of g uh doesn't grow
for some dense subset of x.
And if it's a dense subset of x, it is a
dense subset of x1 * x2. This is x1.
This is x2.
So this is x1, this is x2.
Okay. Then we can apply valuic hours. So
here you see that we are in the setting
to apply hours. So we're going to apply
hours. Okay. So uh it looks like after
applying barometric hours lots of times
and I skipped the details but you have
to trust me that this can be done. We
are in the setting where we can apply
this and be done
but not so fast.
What's the issue? Why not so fast?
So all of the part that I'm not
explaining here, you also have to do it
in the finite field setting. If you want
to get the stronger statement that the
projection of a dense subset grows, not
then subset of the of the given set. If
you want to prove that in the final
field setting, you have to do this
multiple values hours. So this is not a
difference. Okay, you haven't done it in
detail in the finite field setting. But
this part is not a difference between
the finite field setting and the ukian
setting.
But there is something which is a
difference. So what what is the issue?
Why can't we just apply? Okay, we we can
apply this but why do we have to be
careful about applying this?
>> Yes.
So if I balance separated we get like a
prime cross a prime and then
or
call y cross y that covers a lot of g
and then if I want to apply what's on
the left board I would need to know that
y is a delta u something x
>> exactly so here we have a cartition
product okay so one small issue is that
instead of x1 * x1 we have x1 * x2 but
this is not important the issue is that
x1 One is a projection of X and we are
assuming that the size is roughly the
square root of the size of X. But why is
it not concentrated? In order to apply
this and conclude, we need to know that
X is non concentrated with U equals to T
/2.
So it's is very similar to the issue
that we had when we we needed to
iterate. So we knew that a plus little
aa is large but we didn't know that the
non concentration condition also
improves. It's a similar issue here. We
know something about the size of these
projections but apparently we don't know
anything about the non concentration.
We need these projections to be non
concentrated. Okay. So
maybe ignore all of these and just say
the following. Using balmic hours many
times in a clever way, we can reduce to
the to the case where the set X is a
product set. You can even assume it's a
product set of something a self product
set. So using many times we can assume
that X is X1 * X2
and then using again.
So BIC hours allows us to go back and
forth between dense subsets and test
everything. So this is what what allows
us to do. So we can assume that this we
are in a in in in a the setting of a
product set and then we want to apply
this
but not so fast because we don't know
that the projections satisfy the
concentration assumption of priority. So
we have this problem again. So it's very
similar to the problem we had before and
it is solved in a similar way but it has
to be solved. So in some sense so you
can think of it of it in this way. We
say that t /2 is a triv trivial between
codes bound for projections. What we
have to show is that this trivial bound
actually holds in the non-conentration
sense.
So we have to show that the projection.
So here 0 1 and infinity are just
generic projections. So we in fact if we
picture three random points uh in D this
will work because three random points
will be separated. Three random points
will not be too concentrated because of
this. There are not too many points in
in a single ball. So if you randomly
sample three points in D
the linear map that makes these points
horizontal, vertical and diagonal will
have small distortion.
So we need to know that the random
projection of X is a delta T /2 S set.
In some sense the goal is to show that
the random projection is a delta T /2
plus some gain S set.
But to prove that we need to show that
it satisfies the same thing but without
the epsilon but the nonconentration
version of that.
And this can be done. It can be done in
several ways. One way is a similar thing
to what we have done today.
Well today and last time but basically
go from growth to non-conentration
uh by uniformizing everything uh
carefully
and it can also be done by some careful
double counting similar to but not
exactly the same that you've done
before. So there are several ways of
doing it because it's like the easy case
but but it has to be done. Okay. So
maybe let's write that down.
[Applause]
Okay, so we need a last fact.
If x and d are
as before
as in bulans projection theorem
then there exists some a and d and once
again once there is one once we know
that there is one a and d that means
nearly all a and d have this property
such that by a of x contains a delta t
/2
Delta 2 maybe all of epsilon or va
set
again t /2 is like the trivial bound but
it's not so trivial in this case because
we are claiming some non-conentration
for the projection but because at the
same time
for covering number so for the covering
number version of this is is sort of
obvious because again if we have one set
you look at two projections
in more or less orthogonal directions
and most one of them can drop by more
than square root of the size of the set
and this is true at every scale.
So you see that if we knew that this is
uniform we would be done. So it's really
very similar to what we have been
discussing in the rest of the lecture.
So this can be proved
[Applause]
using
a similar strategy
as for
a plus little aa or it can also be done
without using uniformization
by double counting. So okay
uh I guess one needs uniform some okay
maybe not uniformization but if one
doesn't use uniformization maybe one is
some sort of frostman's lema but okay so
it can be done but I just wanted to
point out that this is yet another place
where we need to worry about the fact
that so the difference between the
uklidian setting and the final field
setting okay
and now once we know this we are really
done because using balance
three times we can assume that x is a
cartitionian product and we just need to
know that the projection uh in a given
direction grows and it is given by
Listen,
[Applause]
hey,
And then uh we apply double star.
Okay. So since there are five minutes
left, let me summarize what what's been
going on. So what is the idea of like
general idea of the proof both in the
finite field setting and the nuclear
setting? First we work with the set in
one dimension and shows that if the set
is not already everything then is
expanded by some polomial. Then we
simplify the polomial using plunicus.
Then we iterate. In order to iterate one
has to be much much much more careful in
the uklidian setting in order to show
that the hypothesis of the expansion are
satisfied when we apply the growth once.
So we can iterate but eventually we can
iterate that means that we can expand
the given set a to almost everything by
some polomial. Once we can expand by a
polinomial to almost everything we get
this growth.
It is still of some product type but the
difference is that X now can be much
bigger than A. And the fact that X is
much bigger than A is not an issue
because instead of working with A, we
work with a polomial applied to A which
has size bigger than the size of X. And
finally uh we want to project something
which is not a product but by looking at
three projections to begin with which
are far away from each other and
applying bioicical hours many times we
can go back to this setting.
So that's the short version of the proof
and they are again in the ukian setting
one has to be careful to show that the
projections
uh satisfy the assumptions needed to
apply this fact. So you have to be so
really you need some at least some non
concentration on x because again if x
was a small interval
then this never grows for any a so one
needs some assumption on x. So one needs
to prove something like that. But okay,
one can prove it and then eventually one
uses this.
Any final questions?
>> How many times have we used PSG?
>> Uh
so either four or six. I'm not
completely sure. Uh I think no. I think
the first time we already have a
product. Yeah, I think once for a plus
little aa and then three times
uh to reduce to this setting.
>> Okay. Like
is it for like well we just want the
projection of like x itself is big in
one direction or it's like for the proof
that's for any subs.
>> Yeah. Okay. So indefinitely setting is
as you are suggesting is much easier to
prove that the projection of X itself is
big than proving it for dense subsets.
But in the ukidian case even if your
goal is to pro is proving that the
projection of X is large and you don't
care about dense subsets you are still
forced to care about dense subsets
because you need the dense subsets to
prove the non-conentration assumption
when you iterate. So how did we prove
that a plus little aa satisfies the
stronger non-conentration assumption?
By proving that the projection of dense
subsets of a * a are large. So even if
your your ultimate goal doesn't involve
looking at dense subsets, you still need
to look at them subsets along the proof
and you cannot avoid that. Or maybe you
can, but at least with this method of
proof, you cannot avoid that.
Yes.
>> Can you say a little bit more about how
to handle the issue that the uniform
subset at different scales might be
different?
>> Yeah. So I unfortunately I didn't
realize this issue would arise so I
didn't check carefully.
>> Um but yeah it's a it's a it's a very
good question. Um
yeah. Okay. So I'm not exactly sure but
let me say something that might work in
this case but it certainly works in
other cases. So I explained an idea
superficially of first getting an a
prime and if that a prime doesn't
exhaust a we take it away and find
another a prime. One can do something
similar for uniform sets. So rather than
taking one uniform subset, one can so
one is given a set and one knows nothing
about that set and we can nearly exhaust
that set by a finite union of uniform
subsets. So one finds a dense uniform
set takes it away finds another uniform
set takes it away and in this way we
essentially cover the set with a very
small error by uniform subsets. Uh so
this is one way to get around the issue
that one uniform substate itself is
maybe too sparse and then at different
scales different things could happen.
So that's I think that could be one way.
I don't think that's what we do in the
paper but I think that's one thing you
could do to bypass this issue.
>> Yeah. You said last time that there was
possibly a way to simplify this.
>> Uh we we are not sure yet. Uh we are
hopeful. Yes.
Yeah. again um this so bugan's original
proof uh is different in the sense that
he didn't construct an expanding
polomial at all
but it is similar in the sense that
uh he proves this and then uses the many
back symmetric hours to
to to get the full statement but to
prove this he did something different
but okay other claim is more difficult
than what I explained but I don't know
it's a
yeah now now we have this idea from last
week uh that yeah might be a so
basically it would be a much easier way
of doing this to go from this to the
full statement the only way we know how
to do it is how Bang did it by doing the
many barometric