OEERS. What are they? How can I find
them? What do I do with them? Glad you
asked. Hello, my name is Carlos
Gutierrez and I'm an intellectual
property coordinator for the online
worldwide learning services or ALS team
at MIT Open Learning. The focus of this
video is to introduce you to open
educational resources or OEERS and then
engage in a practical exercise using a
resource guide. It was developed by MIT
libraries and anyone can use it to find
and source OEARS. But first, let's go
over a brief disclaimer. The purpose of
this video is informative, meaning
nothing I say here should be construed
as legal advice. All right, with that
out of the way, let's outline what we'll
cover. What is an OEAR? The OEAR
resource guide. What can an OEAR be used
for? A walkthrough of the resource
guide. And then finally, we'll try an
activity.
Let's start with some definitions. What
are OEARS? OEARS are free and openly
licensed educational materials. This
could be books, articles, diagrams,
presentation slides, assignments, and
the like. And they can be used for
teaching, learning, research, and other
purposes. You'll notice that free part
first. The idea is that they're not
offered for profit. The openly licensed
part pertains to its copyright status,
which we'll cover further in the video.
Now within the category of OEARS, we
have to make a distinction between open
access materials versus open license
materials. Open access as a term relates
to content that can be viewed by anyone
free of charge without any other barrier
except perhaps registering for a website
account or logging into one. Open
license relates to reuse and what
obligations, if any, we need to follow
to engage in that reuse. In some cases,
open access and open license rights
overlap, which means you are both free
to view and free to reuse. In other
cases, they don't overlap and some
restrictions do apply. The OAR resource
guide is a tool for others interested in
finding OAR materials. It was put
together by one of MIT libraries expert
librarians, Nicholas Alba, who helps
source many OAR repository options.
The MIT open resource guide compiles
OARS by category and shows you where to
find them. It includes books, articles,
teaching resources, and news
organizations. Okay, so now that we know
what an OEAR is and we have a tool to
find it, but here's another question.
What can OEARS be used for? They can be
used to teach workshops or provide
reference assistance. They can
supplement materials for massive online
open courses or other course types. and
they can aid with educational content
creation in
general. Now, here's the thing with
OEARS. Remember when I said they could
be either under open access or open
license or both? Well, that's the tricky
part. It's not always clear. So, once we
have a resource that could potentially
be an OEER, we need to determine its
license type. To do so, we need to first
identify copyright ownership and any
restrictions that apply.
Something that can help is that the
repositories or databases linked in the
guide may have openlicicensed and all
rights reserved materials categorized in
their search results. However, open
licenses can still carry obligations. In
the exercise, I'll go over how to
determine what those obligations are and
how to parse them out. For now, let's
focus on finding OEARS.
The resource guide can be helpful to the
sourcing process since it's a gateway
for various OAR options all in one place
and therefore can prove useful for those
who create educational content. Here are
some of the main repositories it
compiles. There are article options like
core and the digital commons network.
OAR book options are also included like
the directory of open access books as
well as teaching resources and news
organizations including one you may be
familiar with called open courseware or
OCW. So now that we know all this, we
can engage with the resource guide in an
activity and put everything I've talked
about into action. The first activity is
a simple search for a specific OAR
article in the core online database. The
purpose is to find the copyright
information related to the article and
then examine how open the article is.
Here it's important to know the
difference between open access and open
license. Let's go ahead and do that.
Navigate to core and search for this
article. Quote the role of synthetic
biology in NASA's missions. End quote.
Or use the keyword synthetic plus
biology plus NASA. Once you find the
article, locate any copyright
information you can spot. If you get
stuck, you can find a direct link to the
article by clicking download from data
provider. Based on what you found,
answer this question. How open is the
resource? If you want, you can hit the
pause button and come back to this video
once you Finished.
Great. That article is in the public
domain, which is often the case with
resources created by the federal
government. Now, let's try something a
little different. For our second
exercise, we're going to go back to the
resource guide and navigate to the
digital commons network. Once there,
search for these keywords. quote Salish
C end quote. Click on the keyword
filters on the left to sort out the
results. Find quote the toxicity of
dopamine on Salish C phytolanton end
quote by Allison Lombardo and locate any
copyright information you can find in
the
results. Once you've done that, answer
this question. Is this article allowed
to be used for commercial purposes? You
can pause here and come back to the
video once you're done like before.
That paper is free to use for scholarly
purposes. So if you wanted to use it as
part of a presentation or assigned
reading, you're good. But if you want to
use it for a commercial purposes, say by
selling it as part of an educational
product, you need permission from the
author. For our final exercise, we're
going to try more of a free form type of
approach. I'll help you get there, but
what you find is completely up to you.
Return to the resource guide and
navigate to core. Pick a tool keyword
combination to search for. It can be
whatever you want. Then select a
resource from your search results. Now,
attempt to locate the copyright
information in the result and determine
how open the resource is. You can pause
here and come back for the final part of
the video.
Hopefully in the last exercise, you got
to put what you've learned to use and
maybe even found a resource you can use
in your own teaching environment. I hope
this walkthrough and the resource guide
have been useful in helping you delve
into the world of OEARS and I want to
thank you for your time and attention.