Great. Uh, thank you. We're now going to
wrap up our webinar. Thanks to all of
our speakers and to everyone who joined
us today. What you heard in this session
captures what the MIT industrial liaison
program is all about. Connecting
industry with MIT researchers and
startups who are redefining what's
possible. Whether it's postquantum
security, AI, or other frontier
technologies. Our goal is to help member
companies understand these advances
early and apply them when and where they
matter most. If you'd like to learn more
about the ILP and ILP membership or
access recordings of this and other
events, please visit illep.mmit.edu.
We also request that you kindly take a
moment to fill out the short survey that
will show after this webinar. So on
behalf of MIT corporate relations and
the entire team here today, thank you
for being part of securing the future
AIdriven postquantum data privacy. We
hope to see you again at a future MIT
event soon.