All great ideas start out bad. Most look
horrible at the start. And yet, this
should come as a relief. That idea you
had or heard this morning that everyone
laughed at could be the start of
something. That's right. The idea does
not need to look disruptive or scalable
or exponential or like a business. You
can start with what you have. This is
often difficult for people to accept.
Most innovation stories are told in
hindsight, [music] which creates a
cognitive bias. If you have read a lot
of innovation stories, it may be hard to
accept that the start of those great
stories is a poor fit for the
innovations they became. But success
isn't hiding in the idea. It follows
from what you do next.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit [music]
learn.mmit.edu.