Thank you for the opportunity to present
my company, Borite. Uh my name is Pavl
Biski. I'm the co-founder and CEO of
Boronite and I'm an alum of the MIT
material science department. Um we
started Boronite 10 years ago and the
goal initially was to develop commercial
scale technology for producing boron
nitride nanot tubes. Uh hence the name
boronite.
But the technology is versatile. we can
use the same reactors to synthesize
carbon nanot tubes and boron nitrate
nanot tubes. So today I will talk about
electrical conductors. Uh the need that
we see uh that is worldwide is for
better conductive solutions. uh
electrification needs are growing
exponentially especially with u uh the
the new data center needs and um legacy
materials like copper and aluminum are
really inadequate. Uh copper is really
heavy. uh the mechanical properties are
insufficient and so our solution is to
use the carbon nanot tube technology
that we have developed to create the
next generation of electrical
conductors. Uh in the reactors that we
built, we spin carbon nanotubarn
straight out of the reactor. So these
it's like spinning fiber from smoke
essentially.
These nanotubarn are the strongest
material known. They are in terms of
mechanical properties, they already
compete with the best carbon fiber
available and they're pretty good
electrical conductors. But for power
applications that we target, uh we need
better conductivity. Uh so we have a
patented technology to metalize the CNT
yarn to improve conductivity while
keeping really good very low weight and
really strong mechanical properties.
Uh this is the facility that we have
built here in Burlington, Massachusetts.
uh here you see the uh the reactors
uh where we synthesize either boron
nitride nanot tubes or carbon nanot
tubes it's as I said same hardware but
different chemistry and then uh in
we we also have hardware here uh to uh
post-process the material into these
better conductors uh this was built with
financial support from uh many uh
government government contracts.
So, uh the technology that we have
developed uh I'll show you an example of
a power cable uh built with these uh
materials. Um this is a u conductor that
uh was tested to more than 500 amps. Uh
and to give you an idea, so this is a
quarter inch cable 4T long. To give you
an idea of the disruptive potential of
this technology, this is 96% weight
savings over an equivalent uh commercial
cable that is rated 500 amps.
And um so the uh
see there we uh the markets that we're
pursuing uh initially before we're able
to fully scale up uh we're looking at
any uh any markets uh where technology
needs to uh achieve ex extreme weight
savings. So, uh, uh, electric aircraft
and spacecraft, UAVs. We're currently,
uh, building a 600 ft, uh, power cable
for a powered drone for the Navy that
will be tested next year. And then when
we scale up the technology, we'll be
targeting electric motor windings, uh,
where weight savings are also really
important. And really the killer
application is electric power lines. Uh
power transmission lines where uh
building new corridors is really
expensive, very difficult with
regulation
um and uh to to to build these new
corridors. And so with this technology,
we can reconductor existing corridors,
improve and double uh potentially double
the transmission capacity uh without
having to build new corridors. So we
welcome partnerships. I would like to
talk with anyone interested in this
technology. We have a booth next door.
Thank you.