Great. Okay. Excited to get the flash
talk started. So my name is Tavorvor
Baharov. I'm a secondy year posttock at
the Eric Mundi Schmidt Center and I'm
here today to talk about TE-C cells. So
through the process of VDJ
recombination, T- cells recombine their
genome uh an alpha beta pairings
constituting on the order of like 10 to
the 15 different T- cell receptors. This
massive diversity makes estimating an
individual's T- cell receptor profile
both a difficult and important problem.
So traditionally single cell is used to
identify these pairings between alpha
and beta chains. However, this is
expensive and can't profile too many
cells. Bulk on the other hand is cheap
and can profile many cells but doesn't
give you this pairing information. So
together with Jeremy Simon and Rafaari
have been working on these kind of
combinatorial problems and integrating
these two different modalities and
beyond just bulk and single cell and
we've developed some new statistical
methods which we're working with Dr.
Kathy Woo's lab to validate. So please
come by and chat with me at poster one
if any of this sounds interesting. Thank
you.
Hi I'm Cilate. Um I'm mo my my work is
motivated by the question of how does
the genome sequence encode phenotypic
structure across levels of complexity.
So we have experiments now that measure
genotype phenotype associations from
cells to tissues to organisms and we
have really good algorithms that predict
these associations and learning from
functional genomics and other kinds of
data. So are there any universal
principles that let us derive uh
measured genotype phenotype associations
uh akin to natural laws in physics? So
the computational task is to recover
measured genotype phenotype associations
from just one phenotypic measurement for
example one tissue or protein sequence
and the reference genome and that's
without annotations genotype phenotype
coariation or mechanistic information.
And what's surprising is by searching
for structure preserving codes that is
codes that uh assign genome genomic loi
to photypic units preserving similarity
we can actually solve this problem and
recover measured associations across
scales. Um so yeah come check out my
poster number two.
All right thank you cil. Can I have
Shenan up next?
Um hello everyone my name is Shiny Chen
and I'm a postto in Jen Shu lab at
MGH and thank you for the great
opportunity to share our work today. So
we are building a value for biology
basically a gene to image foundation
model called Jin Vinci. So this work is
supervised by professors
colle and Jen Shu. So
gentri can turn single cell gene
expression into different kinds of image
modalities including h images that
immunofllororesence neuromorphology and
electron
microscopy
and just like deli that can generate
images from text. So Juventi can aims to
be a multimodel view of cell states.
If you are interested, please come to
our poster number five. Thank you.
Thank you. Can I have Jillian up next?
Hi, I'm Jillian. I'm a PhD candidate
with Ben Rafael at uh in the department
of computer science um at Princeton. Um
and I want to talk to you about LAML. Uh
so one recent approach to studying cell
development leverages dynamic lineage
tracing technologies which involves
incorporating a lineage tracing system
which is a genome editor that's going to
accumulate edits at specified target
sites in a cell and then that cell
divides and you can use that to
reconstruct the cell division history.
So the computational problem there is
taking those edits summarized in a
character matrix which I have on the
left in the input in the inputs
summarized in a character matrix. The
computational problem is to infer the
cell lineage tree. So, LML or lineage
analysis via maximum likelihood uh
infers the maximum likelihood lineage
tree and also parameters like timecaled
branch lengths and missing data rates.
Um and LAML infers this is on the right
hand side now LML infers more accurate
tree topologies uh on simulated data but
we also see evidence of this in real
biological data. Um and more importantly
more recently as of the last two months
we've reimplemented some key inference
steps and now we have the most scalable
method um compared to methods of
comparable accuracy. So this is very
exciting. So if you work on any linear
tracing or are just interested in cell
development, please come talk to me. I'm
at poster number six. We also have a new
method that's coming out soon. This is
Laml Pro which adds obser modeling of
observation error. So thank you so much.
Thank you Jillian. We have Yasha up
next. Hi everyone. My name is Yasha
Ecifi. I'm a PhD student at Harvard
Medical School. co-vised by Marine
Kazitnik and Maha Farhad and I'll be
talking about my work in Fleming.
Tuberculosis is one of the leading cause
of death worldwide by infectious disease
and although we have antibiotics to
treat tuberculosis every year those
antibiotics become less effective due to
drug resistance. We need new antibiotics
now. However, developing these drugs is
timely and very cost and and costs a lot
of money. And so to address this, we
developed Fleming, an AI agent for
developing antibiotics for tuberculosis.
Fleming is basically a large language
model that we've given a bunch of tools
that will help it to design a drug. For
example, a generative model to generate
an antibiotic and a discriminative model
to predict given a small molecule
whether inhibit the growth of TB or not.
And we show in our work that Fleming is
able to mimic the reasoning of medicinal
chemists and potentially design new
antibiotics to treat TB. If you're
interested to hearing more, please come
by my poster, poster A. Thank you.
Up next, we have Wenbin.
Um, hi everyone. Um, I'm Wbin and I re
I'm a recent graduate from UCLA. My work
is about the modeling of DM melation
states. So conventional approach uh you
only cares about the first order
statistics uh limiting the average
metholation level. Uh this will ignore
the size dependency of different sites.
So here the information loss is more
evident from the toy example where we
have the two pattern here disting
pattern they have the same metholation
level. So when it comes to uh generation
the pattern pattern one will be more
likely if the sites are truly
independent but this is not the case in
real data we observe for higher mutual
information between adjacent sites uh
than the what what the independent model
predicts. So we propose uh two approach
to model the sati dependency. One is a
heterogeneous headmark model where the
transition probability is model as a
function of genomic distance and the
second one is to implicitly the
dependency structure uh using the
birectional longshortterm memory uh
network and uh if you want to uh know
more about the generative models and
also the epigenomics uh I would love to
talk more at my poster and uh here is a
QR code uh if you are if you want to
check the code and details. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Next we have
Akquil.
Hi everyone. Uh so I'm Akil coming to
you from UT Austin and uh I'll present
some work on matrix completion for
biometically inspired missingness
patterns. Here on the screen you see
certain kinds of matrix structures which
arise in settings that people in this
room care about such as serum virus
interactions, metabolic networks and
gene expression. In one sentence, what
we do is combine transfer and active
learning in a statistically optimal way
for these kinds of problems. More
precisely, we have a scalable and robust
algorithm which both tells you what
matrix entries to select. So this is an
experimental design or a gentic
component and how to estimate given
limited data which is the transfer
learning uh component. So for
binformaticians the takeaway is that you
should in fact use and critique these
models on your data set. This is very
flexible and can be used with several
different kinds of side information
which makes it very advantageous for
practitioners and for biostatistitians.
What's interesting about this work is
that we develop theoretical guarantees
and rigorous algorithms and so we'd love
to get your thoughts on those as well.
So please come stop by poster 11 and uh
talk with us.
Thank you male. Next up we have
Christopher.
Hello I'm Chris a first year postdoc at
the cast broad. So our work focused on
the on the cat discovery in in a very
similar way to
what Jean Philip discovered earlier
today. Thank you. So we explored
multiple fidia models for
for
molecular molecular representation using
the broad prism propertating data as our
SR train data set with
the state-of-the-art temprop model.
Unfortunately, the results were fairly
mediocre, but with graph graph
isorphism network model
minimal thankfully it worked it worked
significantly better. So, minimal is a
graph modia model pre-trained
on millions of molecules. So I think
this enables significantly better
represent significantly more meaningful
embeddings. So currently we're trying to
arrange the love validation with the
broad center for for development for
development of therapeutics. I also I
also I also want to thank our sponsors.
This work was funded by Z MGH CR family
center for cancer research and the human
frontier science program. Thank you.
Thank you. Next up, we have Alex.
Hi, my name is Alex. I'm um a graduate
student for two more days in Miriam
Haymon's lab. Um we were interested in
characterizing um novel transcription
factors to rejuvenate old neurons.
Inspired by a bunch of um transcription
factor rejuvenation um projects in the
field, we wanted to um atlas the uh
build a perturbation atlas to find
potential new transcription factors. So
we used a bunch of algorithms to predict
transcription factors and the um
transcriptional effects that they would
have. From that we selected a library of
transcription factors that we predicted
would be rejuvenative. Um we did a large
invivo perturb seek study to um to
validate those. We packaged the ORFs for
156 transcription factors in AAVs. Um
and we generated this large single cell
data set from which we're able to
validate the um many algorithms that we
used to predict the transcriptional
effects of those transcription factors.
So um if you want to hear more about it,
come talk to me at poster
14. Thank you. Up next we have Pisha.
So TE-C cells are the building blocks of
the human immune system, but they're
very difficult to predict which antigens
they would bind to, which threats they
can recognize because of cross
reactivity and data sparity. So we deal
with this by introducing a new uh
related but cheaper task of T- cell type
prediction. So this multitask approach
introduces biological context and allows
the model to mirror the way the human
immune system actually works and be able
to better predict how it would respond.
So the model actually uses a shared
representation from a TCR representation
model as well as task specific
characteristics from separate
classification blocks. So this shared
learning really allows for more
generalized representations. And when is
this shared learning actually useful? If
you'd like to discuss this, you can find
me at poster 16. I'm Prica. Thank you
very
much. Thank you. Up next, we have
Victoria. Hi, I'm Victoria Schuster. I'm
a posttock at the Schmidt Center and
formerly at the University of
Copenhagen. Um, sometimes we deal with
highdimensional data, but not quite as
many samples as we would like. So for
this purpose we've developed a decoder
only generative model that is highly
data efficient compared to traditional
autoenccoderbased models and learns very
expressive latent representations. We've
applied this to single cell multiomics
data and because there's no encoder
certain things become quite easy for
example integrating novel coariantss um
without fine-tuning and incilical
perturbations. My latest project has
been to improve how we can understand
what is learned in latent
representations. And for this purpose,
we use sparse autoenccoders to extract
features and automatically annotate them
with terms from different knowledge
bases. Come see me at poster 17 if you
want to understand how this works.
Thank you, Victoria. Up is Young Gang.
Hello everyone. I'm Jen from Vrien Women
Hospital and Har Medical School. Our
study mainly focus on how to leverage
large language model to support
automatic assessment of cognitive
function sector for dementia patients.
As we know each patient has many
electronic health records in hospital
system. Oral list nodes contains rich
clinical information but actually they
are also longitudinal large scale and
the clinical demand specific that may be
hard to understood by the large language
models. So we need to integrate several
LM technology such as summarizations
such as uh knowledge enhancement with
exter external source such as uh pad or
Wikipedia. So if you are also interested
into improving uh large language model
application in clinical health uh please
feel free to stop by the number 19 to
talk more. Thank you.
All right thank you Leang
Ying. Uh hi everyone. I'm a first year
post fellow at the Eric administ center.
So uh qualifying and quantify the exact
role of individual genes and uh their
direct and total uh causal effects on uh
complex traits is crucial for a better
understanding of the complex uh
biological mechanisms leading to complex
traits variations. So we propose a novel
based network based framework that
integrates JVA's data and gene
expression data from different data
sources to construct the gene gene
phenotype causal network. It allows the
gene expression data and disease traits
to be estimated from different samples
and it exhibits high uh specificity and
precision in identifying causal genes
and showed significantly improved causal
effects estimation accuracy and also the
identified colins in the UK bang for the
uh disease trees were significantly
enriched for their corresponding
targets. So overall it provides a
flexible and framework for illustrating
the genetic basis of uh complex traits
through a system system level and causal
inference approach. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Up next we have
Shinhi.
Thank you. Hi, my name is Shingho. I'm a
graduate student at Harvard University
and Broad Institute. Today is my
pleasure and honor to present to you the
AI cyborg system that enables adaptive
modulation of organoid maturation. So in
this work we integrate stretchable
tissue-l like mesh electronics within
human iPSC derived cardiac organoids
allowing for continuous electrical
stimulation and recording without
disrupting the tissue development. So
based on the electrical data we
construct a pseudo temporal trajectory,
a concept adapted from the genomics
analytical methods to represent the
organoid maturation functionally. And
based on this trajectory, we employ a
basin optimization framework with
Gaussium process surrogate model to
learn stimulation policies that
dynamically adapt to the biological
evolving state to achieve optimization
with high sample efficiency. This
approach embarks a new paradigm for
cybernetic control for biological
systems that's integrating real-time
sensing, learning, and actuation. To
learn more about this work, we invite
you to visit us at poster number 21 as
well as our manuscript on bioarchchive
in the QR code. Thank you.
And last up, we have Chase.
Hi everyone, I'm Chase. I'm a first year
posttock at Broad in Harvard Medical
School. And uh one of the benefits of
being last is I see how much time I have
left, which is plenty. Everybody did
such a great job going, which means I
get to take as much time as I want, I
think. Um so what I'm going to uh
reemphasize here is uh we heard earlier
in our talk this morning that 90% of
drug targets fail. But one of the things
that uh genetics actually provides is
for instance if you use G-W was data um
Eric medical here showed that uh G-W was
supported drug targets and genetic
supported drug targets actually
increased the success the relative
success of um of drug targets in a
clinical setting by almost like a factor
of two. So what I'm going to walk you
through here is our our current model of
of how do you basically integrate
genetics with uh functional annotations
because while genetics supports drug
target discovery, I think a lot of
researchers are still using traditional
meth methods of science which are coming
through the literature doing our own
experiments collecting all of these
types of relationships to to then
support what they are looking at for
their drug targets. So here we introduce
this model pigeon where we try to take
these gene annotations or gene sets that
share common pathways use genetic
evidence from G-W was to introduce this
new concept of what we're calling
indirect genetic support where genes
could be supported from other high
genetic evidence genes that share a
functional annotation. And then we use
that to actually prioritize targets. And
what we see here is if you have now that
you have this these two axes of direct
support and indirect support you
actually can have a continuum of drug
target success and by using both of
these modalities in the statistical
basian framework here uh you can get
actually really good relative success
related to just even using genetics
alone. So if you want to learn more come
to uh closer 22 and let's run some
pigeon on some of your prior knowledge
and your gene sets. Thanks.