every day we rely on a substance that's
harder than iron or steel our teeth
braces tether your teeth pulling them
together or pushing them apart and when
mechano receptors in the PDL sense this
kind of smaller but sustained Force they
signal cells called osteoclasts which
spew out acid and proteins to dissolve
parts of your jaw bone then the mech
receptors signal osteoblasts to come and
those cells deposit minerals that make
bone osteoblasts rebuild the jaw bone in
a new shape that lets the PDL hold teeth
in the new position but your body is
actually breaking down and rebuilding
bone using osteoclast and osteoblast all
the time not just if you have braces
it's easy to write braces off as a form
of medieval torture but it's kind of
amazing that this mouth torture actually
works and the technology that makes it
possible is not just in your braces it's
in your bones for more MIT moments from
MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow