We are trying to make our way through
these four as yet intractable dilemmas.
Um the last time we met we talked about
the curse of the familiar, the edtech
Matthew effect. Um today we're going to
be looking at the trap of routine
assessment. Um the anybody want to try
to articulate the sort of the the core
puzzle that's at the that's at the heart
of the trap of routine assessment.
What do you got Dana? um kind of along
the lines of, you know, teachers are
teaching students a subject and they um
schools have like such an emphasis on
like final exams and what they're
preparing for these standardized tests.
Um but we're also fighting with the idea
of like what a computer can grade. So if
you're trying to standardize some sort
of way of grading something, you can
only really focus on teaching students
things that computers can do. But if a
computer can already do it, then why why
is that the emphasis of what we're
teaching students? So, it's kind of the
idea that like if you look at the ven
diagram, there's like this whole other
half of the subject that ultimately we
probably should be focusing on. Um, but
we are really only talking about that
overlapping aspect of what students were
saying should learn because we can
assess it. Good that that that the
technologies we have for assessment sort
of constrain what it is that we can
assess at any kind of scale. Anybody
want to add what what else seems
important to Dana's um initial offering
there?
I think something you brought up in the
reading as well is that there's like a
connection to the labor markets, right?
So schools are supposed to help us
prepare us for the labor market, but
we're learning these routine things that
are being taken over by automation. And
how is that actually doing what the
school is supposed to function for?
Okay, good. So, so, so schools operate
in in between a couple of different
things. One is like like what do we need
kids to do changes over time as we
develop new technologies. Um there's
some you know like like none of you
should teach your stu well I mean you
shouldn't teach your students to operate
a loom on the basis that will be a
source of gainful employment for them.
Although there probably are a small
number of people who are like very
profitable, you know, small business
loom operators and particular kind of
thing, but like generally speaking, like
not a good bet. Um uh and so, you know,
it makes sense that as technologies come
along, we change the kinds of things
that we teach to young people. Um and
and computers uh you know over the you
know in various ways once a decade over
the last 10 years like cause new kinds
of problems for us to as as computers
capacities expand what we think about
teaching people um changes at the same
time as computers technologies expand
there's maybe new or different kinds of
ways that we can use them for
assessment. Um and so those two things
are kind of interplaying with each other
uh all the time. Um any any We got some
seats up here. There's plenty plenty of
room. Kadus, nice to see you.
Um other other introductory things that
seem important, Omar. Yeah, that's like
that's not to say that and you mentioned
this in in the reading. Um like we're
not trying to say don't teach like time
tables and stuff like that where it's
like stuff that's uh yes, computers can
assess that, but stuff that students
need fundamentally to build on for other
more complex tasks that they will learn
now more. Good. that makes this even the
the whole conversation even more
complicated because there's stuff that
we need people to be able to do in their
lives. We there also might be a class of
things that's called like stuff that you
need to learn in order to be able to do
those complex things like even though
computers can do those simpler things
there. So there's there's some class
there's some class of things that
computers can do that we just don't need
humans to ever do anymore. Um, I think I
joked with you all that one of the first
times I talked with my students at MIT
about large language models, somebody
said, uh, I'm using large language
models to do the latte formatting of our
of my papers. It's like great. Never
think about that again. Like if no
student ever thinks about that again for
the rest of their lives, we're probably
fine as a civilization. Um, but like
single different single digit
multiplication is not like that.
Singledigit multiplication can be
trivially done by computers, but it's
actually quite important for human
beings to learn. So there's sort of some
complexity in those kinds of things.
Um, anything else that people want to
add to just the like the initial framing
of the trap of routine assessment?
I guess just to add on even more, there
is this aspect that our society values
these routine assessments. Um, so that
like even though you're trying to change
this and branch out and expand what we
teach students, they're still always
constrained by the market itself. Um,
and ultimately like teachers have to
fight against that and let your own
independent wishes. So as much as we
think, you know, you can just do it, you
can't actually. Good. So, so I mean I
think you could go to almost any
educator and say something along the
lines of like are standardized tests a
good mechanism for capturing all of the
important things that students should
know. And the answer is like clearly
not. There's almost no educator in the
world who believes that to be the case.
Um there's more debate over the question
of do standardized tests capture some of
the important things that we want
students to know. Um how and then and
then a sort of follow-on problem that
there's then this class of stuff which
is like pretty important for students to
know but we're not very good at
assessing. Um, and it's hard to
prioritize those things in education
systems because it's hard to reward
students and reward educators for
teaching things that we don't know how
to measure um or don't know how to
measure in some kind of systemic way. We
don't know how to how to measure with
the kind of of of fairness that we would
want to use for high stakes assessments
for things like graduation exams or
college entrance exams or other kinds of
things like that. So the so all of these
are parts of systems that get wrestled
with every day by educators at all
different kinds of levels. Um in in in
the United States, teachers are are
unusually responsible for wrestling with
these issues because we don't have
something like a national curriculum. We
don't even really have something like
national entry exams or something like
that. Um where you know where like the
whole system kind of has to work
together to respond to some of these
things. Teachers in the United States
have sort of unusual discretion. um for
for thinking about these kinds of
challenges. Uh I thought the place that
I would start with you all um is uh a
little bit towards what Tai suggested um
and and we're probably going back um
20-ish years to the last to one of the
last times computers really got
educators and labor economists quite
upset. Um, so we're in another one of
these moments right now with LLMs where
people are pretty stressed out like like
how is this going to change the labor
market? How is this going to change what
we expect of our students? How should
this change school systems and things
like that? And to me it's always helpful
to remember like oh we've done this
before you know like the introduction of
personal computers into most households
in the United States that was a big
deal. It was a big change in the capac
like the introduc introduction of
personal computers into workplaces that
was a big deal. the introduction of the
internet um you know broadband internet
connection in these spaces like that was
a big deal that that evoked all of these
questions in the past. Um and uh one of
the best summary pieces to read from for
probably what was like the sort of like
2015 summary from this debate is a paper
called dancing with robots um by two
economists. One who is here Frank Levy
um and another who was at Harvard who is
actually my adviser Richard Mine. Um,
this was based on another book they
wrote called The New Division of Labor.
Um, and the original research for the
new division of labor is like kind of
right when personal computers are really
starting to widely spread in workplaces
and people's homes and things like that.
Um, an early bet that economists made
was something like e one of the things
economists think about all the time is
like what do jobs require? And um
education economists then start thinking
about like okay what do jobs require and
how do you teach people the things that
the jobs that we actually have require
um that you know um computers are going
to complement highwage workers and
they're going to replace lowwage
workers. That was like a pretty early
bet that a bunch of economists had had.
Um and there was something about that to
Frank Levy and Richard Maneine that
didn't smell right. They were like h I
think it's going to end up being more
complicated than that.
Um so they thought a lot about the
specific kinds of things that people did
in jobs and how those jobs were
changing. Um how many of you have ever
checked in to get on a flight by talking
directly to a human
being? Okay. So it looks like people how
how many of you the majority of times
you get on a flight you check in with a
machine. Okay. So we so so look this
actually surprised I'm surprised that
almost everyone in the room who raised
their hand said that at least once. Um
you know when I first put together this
slide like 15 years ago something like
that like this was a pretty novel
experience. So you know when I when I
was in college you would you would not
interact with a machine at all to get
onto a flight. Um you would have like
called the airline or called a travel
agent to buy a ticket. You would have
like a physical ticket. You would take
that physical ticket. You would show it
to a human being. Um now the interesting
thing about those conversations with
human beings was that they were highly
standardized. They were highly routine.
So post 911 it would be uh you know like
who are you? This is my ID. Like where
are you going? This is my ticket. Do you
have a ticket? Yeah, this is my ticket.
Where are you going? This is where I'm
going. Um uh do you have any bags with
you? Yes. Did you pack your bags
yourself? Have they been in your
possession the whole time? Yes. Um and
then off you go. So the like over, you
know, the vast majority of times that a
person went to a ticketing agent to have
a conversation with them like highly
structured, highly routined, we know
what kinds of questions we're going to
get as passengers, we know what kind of
inputs we need, we have the the
conversation successfully, we move on.
Um, and so as computers, you know, as
computing technology becomes more
sophisticated, as user interface becomes
more sophisticated, as all these things
become less expensive, someone's like,
"Hey, we can just program those
conversations into a machine." Um, and
so now overwhelmingly you have that
exact same conversation. You just push
the buttons to say like, "Yes, I have a
ticket. Yes, this is me. Yes, my bags
have been in my possession the whole
time." Um,
however, there, you know, for as long as
we've had kiosks, there has always been
a number of cases in which the kiosks
can't respond to the demands of the
moment. Um, so there's something really
weird about your ticket. there's some
problem that's gone on with your booking
that the machine hasn't anticipated or
can't understand. Um, or you have some
kind of communication issue. Um, for
some reason a human being can't
communicate with the kiosk. Maybe their
glasses are broken that day. Maybe they
are like trying to travel, they don't
speak the language that the kiosk is in.
You know, they're like so angry at the
airline for what they've messed up they
just go banging on the kiosk. And then,
you know, so you got to think a lot like
there's one person behind this row of
kiosks whose um whose job it is to have
all the conversations that the kiosk
can't have. Um if you're a labor
economist, like that's a pretty
interesting question. Like what is that
human being doing that we couldn't
program into all of those machines? That
that was the kind of question that Frank
Levy and Richard Main were kind of
asking. Like like in a world where
there's lots of kind of work that we can
put on computers, what is it that humans
are still good at? um in economist term
like what is it that humans still have a
comparative advantage over computers
around um here is another funny example
of which I think I wrote about in the
book about how some of these things
change. Um so in something like
1987 my parents bought a cabin in
Vermont um which had an old boiler in it
um like a hot water heater that was
attached to a tank um and my mom passed
away. I inherited the house. So sometime
around 2007 um about 20 years later this
boiler dies and I'm responsible for it.
Um the original boiler was inst
installed by this guy named Dan
Mastersonson who lived on Masterson Lane
um in Bethl Vermont. Um and I was like
trying to find a plumber to replace this
hot water heater and the guy I found was
Dan Mastersonson who lived on
Mastersonson Lane in uh Bethl Vermont.
So a guy had been a plumber for 20
years. Um and we decided that instead of
doing an old school hot water boiler
we're going to install one of these uh
on demand systems. Um, so this is like a
very beautiful picture to me. Um,
because there's no hot water tank that
can freeze. Like it just like heats up
the water exactly when you need it. Like
you can see how nicely all these pipes
are. The last building had pipes all
over the place, things like that. Um, so
Dan installs this system. Dan, as you
can imagine, now is like getting towards
the end of his career as a plumber. Um,
and I say, "Great, Dan, like show me how
to use this system." He's like, "Well,
you walk in here and you open this
little door. Um, and when you look at
the system, it should say good."
I was like, "All right, Dan, what do I
do if it doesn't say good? You guys
can't see this?" Well, he's like, "See
this little button that says R? Push
that." Um, so that's the reset button. I
was like, "All right, I can push the
reset button." Like, "Well, what do I do
if that doesn't work?" He's like, "You
see this electrical outlet up here? Just
like unplug it and plug it back in." I
was like, "All right, I will recycle the
power in my hot water heater if that
doesn't work." And I was like, "Okay, so
it doesn't say good. I've hit R. I've
unplugged it. It's still not working.
Then what do I do?" He says, um, there's
one guy in the upper river valley of
Vermont who has flown to Scandinavia,
um, to get the training on how to
reprogram these systems. And so, if
those two things don't work, go find
that guy. Um, and I tried to imagine
like Dan Masterson probably in like
1970, 1975, something like that, like
going through his plumbing
apprenticeship training. Um, and like he
learned how to solder pipes together and
how to do some basic electrical stuff
and things like that. like if you like
if he went to the same training now like
you have to be an apprentice computer
programmer to be a plumber. And not only
that, um the systems are designed to
solve all of the easy problems. Like if
a problem is easy, it'll just like solve
it itself on reboot. The things that you
have to be able to solve as a computer
programming plumber are the the
illststructured problems like when the
system can't figure out what's wrong
with itself and can't correct itself. Um
and those kinds of things. So, so not
all I mean the reason I'm trying to
bring these two cases to your attention
is we could say all right um there are
some classes of jobs that are going to
disappear and be replaced by computers
like there used to be I mean the other
thing about these people if you're just
think about this in a broader social you
know there used to be six people behind
this desk um and they wore uniforms
maybe they had a college degree maybe
they had associates degree they probably
made a middle class living like you like
you could make a decent living as a
person who checked people into airlines
and most of those jobs are gone Um and
even in places where jobs remained
they're being transformed by you know
what the capacities computer offer in
these systems. Um so one of the cool
things about the research in uh the new
division of labor is that they basically
go the department of labor collects all
of these uh uh names of jobs and the
description of jobs. Um and they do an
analysis of those descriptions to see
how they're changing over time. Uh and
what they find is that you can you can
break jobs down into maybe four
categories. Um one of those categories
would be routine manual jobs. So that
involves jobs that are like lifting,
moving things around, stuff like that.
Routine cognitive work. Um so that would
be things like filing and stuff like
that. That would be things like having
standardized conversations to check
people into a airline.
Um, two others are what they call
illststructured problem solving. So,
solving any kind of problem where like
you don't know what inputs you need, you
don't know what the outputs look like,
you don't know what the correct answer
with, you're sort of solving that as
you're figuring out the problem or
complex communication tasks that require
um like figuring out like any kind of
solving the problem requires talking to
people. Some of that could be like
marketing and sales kind of thing,
figuring out what people want, but other
that could be like a home health aid um
does a ton of complex communication. Uh
and their and their basic thesis was
that things that are routine are
disappearing from the American labor
market. Um this is a huge problem if you
want to have a stable society. Um like
in the 20th century there were many many
people who performed routine labor for a
reasonable middle class wage and like
had a perfectly suitable life doing it.
Um some of the kinds of jobs that are
growing are like service jobs that don't
really require rout like they're a
little bit of routine manual work, a
little bit of routine cognitive work and
they pay like the absolute minimum wage
possible. um that's a little bit less
concerning today where you know you can
get jobs doing um doing service work
that pay you know you can work at some
place in McDonald's and make $15 an hour
$17 an hour things like that um but when
there was a surplus in the labor market
10 years ago 12 years ago like all those
people would have been paid $725 or
whatever the federal minimum wage was at
the time um but the two kinds of jobs
that were growing were things that
required non-rine analytical skills um
and social skills some of this was
updated by this guy David Atur who's
economist uh who's here now as well. Um
so if you're if you're an educator, the
thing you got to be thinking is like man
um we have a we have a different job in
front of us. Like it's not sufficient to
prepare people to do jobs that require
routine cognitive work or routine um uh
uh manual work because those jobs are
disappearing as a part of the labor
market. And even when the same job title
exists, even when like they're still
plumbers, but plumbers are increasingly
called upon to do ill ststructured
problem solving and to do um complex
communication. This was an update of
this, I guess, from 2012. This is just
another like, you know, um here's a 2 by
two where jobs that require social
skills are here. Jobs that require math
skills are here. Um these are the the
jobs that are in green are the ones that
are growing. The jobs that are in red
are the ones that are disappearing. And
you can see that they're sort of
clustered in the in the things that
require social skills are growing and
the things that require fewer social
skills are disappearing. Um truck
drivers is one that that uh people are
often particularly at the time people
were pretty this was like 2015 2017. You
know there 3.5 million truck drivers in
the United States. That's about one in
every hundred Americans is a truck
driver. Um and uh pro probably 10 years
ago was was some of the like the
headiest time where computer scientists
believe that like it was reasonably
possible to replace all of those people.
Um that you would be able to develop
artificially intelligent systems that
would be able to drive trucks. So like
um Uber went to Carnegie Melon and
bought their whole robotics department.
They didn't actually pay for the
robotics department. You just pay each
individual faculty member um to go leave
and and join your company. Um and and
this didn't you know that like there's
still 3.7 million truck drivers in the
United States or however many there are
because we this turned out to be a much
harder problem than we thought. Um but
this is the kind of angst that exists in
society when these new systems are
developed. Like what would it you know
what would it be like um if uh you know
there's all like what if every kid in
school today who's destined to become a
truck driver we have to find something
else for them to do? Like that's pretty
challenging thing to think about. Um uh
this was another 2017 example. I don't
know. I was glad to go back and revisit
this um because you know there's lots of
things that are going on today about
like man LLMs are going to like replace
all this work that people are doing like
but for the last two decades we've been
building software that replaces the work
that people is doing. Like there's all
kinds of machine learning based systems
that can do what lawyers do and things
like that. You don't necessarily need
LLMs to do it although maybe it will
sort of accelerate uh some of these
kinds of things.
Um, so when I when I was giving this
talk to educators seven or eight years
ago or something like that, uh, this
would be the point where I would say
like, imagine you could go into your
school today, imagine going to the any
of the Cambridge public schools,
Somerville public schools, whatever it
is, and grab every homework assignment
that had been given out that day. Um, so
go to all the classrooms, collect every
single assignment that was given out and
put them in a big pile and start going
through them. um start classifying those
homework assignments like how many of
them require some kind of ill
ststructured problem solving or expert
thinking? How many of them require some
kind of complex communication? And how
many of those homework assignments ask
people to do the kinds of routine work
that we no longer need human beings to
do? Um and my like most educators
confronted with that question be like ah
I think we're doing a whole lot of the
routine stuff. Um and conceivably those
you know that's something that we should
be uh that we should be revisiting as
the world is changing. Um how many of
you encountered the idea anywhere in
your study of education of 21st century
skills? Is that a thing that people
still discuss or I Courtney when you
were ever working on products did people
talk about 21st century skills in your
um no I was most in like ELA and medical
so yeah you might have had some where
where did you encounter so um in the
nonprofit space in India for education
there's a lot of people that are trying
to do 21st century skills it was a buzz
word I think a while ago
yeah once you're like 25 years into a
century the idea of 21st centur skills
becomes like it was it was it felt more
urgent in 2004 2005 what were you gonna
say just stem in general I think came
out of that yeah there there was sort of
this notion that like okay now that we
have computers saturating our workforce
there's some new set of skills that
we're going to have to teach um young
people how to do um and uh it it was
kind of interesting because if you like
there I don't know there were probably
like a dozen different organizations
that came up with lists of 21st century
skills. Um, for a while there was this
thing called the five Cs like uh
communication, collaboration,
creativity, critical thinking. There was
a fifth one, maybe it was the four C's.
Maybe I four C's, five C's, some H
four the the four C's, something like
that. almost it was interesting because
actually if almost all of those lists at
some point cite me and Levy's work like
the only people that did sort of like
original empirical analysis were these
two economists and then everyone else
kind of freestyled on top of that. Um,
but there was, you know, I think there
was something s significant there. Um,
that you could kind of tell by I mean
these this I think the new division of
labor is 2005 or something like that,
but like 20 years ago, you could have a
sense that like, man, um, we're going to
need uh, you know, we're going to need
many, many more people with far more
cognitive skills than we've ever needed
before to to fill our labor market. like
we're just going to need more people who
can do expert thinking, ill structured
problem solving, complex communication
than we've ever needed before in the
history of the American education
system. Um, and that's a sort of
stressful thing to contemplate. So
that's like one set of fundamental ideas
like like a way of thinking about what
do we want people to know? Um a kind of
analysis that uh um people will be doing
in the labor market, you know, education
economists, labor market economists in
the next 5 years is something like well
okay how do LLMs change this equation?
Um how does generative AI change this
equation? Does it simply accelerate
trends that have already been existing?
Is there some kind of like new set of
answers to these questions? You know are
there like are there further are there
different classes of skills? um this uh
um David Atur who's one of the people I
just mentioned just wrote a I don't know
what he I think he wrote a I think he
wrote a working paper that was then
quoted in the New York Times or
something like that. Um he's actually
he's he's been a person who for decades
has been saying like oh computers are
like pretty bad for the middle class.
Like a figure like
this this is a bad figure for the middle
class. Like this is where the middle
class existed. Um these people are
disappearing. These are like either rich
folks getting rich or poor folk the
service line is poor folks getting poor.
Um but um he just recently came out with
something which is like actually um LLMs
are going to be good for the middle
class. Generative AI is going to be good
for the middle class because there's
going to be a whole class of jobs that
people can do with AI support um that
they wouldn't have been able to do
without like graduate training or
something like that and now they're
going to be able to do it with these
sort of systems that are helping them.
Um and then there's another economist
here Darren Asameloo um who was like I
don't know David I think in the New York
Times article he's like oh that's pretty
optimistic I'm not sure that's going to
work out. Um but these are the kinds of
things that people are wrestling with
now.
Um the the heart of the trap of the
routine assessment um is that the kinds
of things that computers are good at
assessing it almost exactly overlap with
the kinds of things that computers are
good at doing. Um and those are the
kinds of things that we don't need
people to do anymore. um the kinds of
things that we can build tools that are
good at assessing human performance are
almost always very closely overlapping
with uh the kinds of things that
computers are good at, the kinds of
things you don't need them to do
anymore. So here are a couple of
examples. Um here's a framework um for
mathematical modeling. So one of the big
changes in the common core state
standards that came about 15 years ago
or something like that um was that we
wanted to teach students not just to do
procedural kinds of things in
mathematics but to be able to conduct
exercises in mathematical modeling and
that those exercises in mathematical
modeling um you can think of it having
kind of five steps like first you have
to find some problem in the world um
what is an interesting thing to view
then you have to set that up as a model
you have to you know whether that's an
equation or a schematic or a table or
whatever it is you have to take a
problem and they have to frame it in
some kind of way. Then probably once
you've developed that model, you have to
compute some kind of solution inside
that model. Then you have to sort of
explain your solution in terms of the
real world. So was it 27 board feet or
was it 27 kittens or was it you know 27
acres? Um and then you have to be able
to sort of explain why your solution
makes sense. Like why did you follow a
series of reasonable mathematical steps
to come up with that solution? Um, of
those roughly five steps, um, what what
do we have technologies to
evaluate? What what have you of of those
five things, what have you ever been
tested on? I want to say three. Yeah.
Computing the solution. The only thing
the only thing of those five steps that
we can like reliably get computers to do
is evaluate whether or not you can
compute a solution. If you use
mathematics in your profession, which of
those five steps will you almost never
actually
do? Computing the solution. Um, like a
computer can't tell you which problems
are interesting. A computer can't tell
you like, oh, this would be a good
problem to think about through this kind
of equation or through this kind of
formula or through this kind of framing.
Um, a computer like is not that good at
taking the outputs and being like, okay,
this is what it means for the real
world. And computers are really not
particularly good at explaining to you
why what just happened mathematically
makes sense. But the one thing that you
will assuredly do if you're a
professional mathematician is have the
computer do the math. Um the computers
are like significantly more reliable
than you are at those kinds of steps. Um
so there's there's if if you go and sit
down for any mathematics exam that's
given in a standardized way at any level
um you will spend the vast majority of
your time computing. Um, if you're a
mathematician, you'll spend almost not
really a mathematician, but if you're a
person who uses mathematics in their
work, you will spend almost none of your
time computing. You will spend almost
all of your time doing those other kinds
of things. Um, that's a real problem.
That's a real problem. Um, a a useful
concept to um that uh that people who
study, psychometricians, people who
study testing, um they have a they have
a term for how we misunderstand math
tests and it's called or tests in
general. It's called the reification
fallacy. Um, reification means sort of
the naming of something. Um, if you call
something a math test, people will think
it's a math test. But calling something
a math test doesn't make it a math test.
Um, so for instance, every time you take
a math test, you need to know something
about language. You probably need to
know something about test taking
strategies. Um, there's probably a whole
bunch of other like cultural things that
you need to know to function at a test.
And the test is effectively evaluating
all those things. Um, the other thing is
a test can like there's no test that can
say that you know all of eighth grade
algebra. Um, the way we take that would
take you forever. Um, instead what we do
is we sample out of a domain. We say
here's all the stuff that might fit in
eighth grade algebra and like we're
going to pick some of this stuff and
some of this stuff and some of this
stuff. Um, a way you could think about
this problem is that we over sample
computing and we under sample all of
these other kinds of things. Um, now
what? Um, well, maybe let's do let's do
one more that's like this. Um, here's
here's one of my very favorite
paragraphs that's ever been written
about computer programming by Hal Abson,
who's here, and some of his colleagues.
Um, this is from a a computer science
textbook. Um, first we want to establish
the idea that computer language is not
just a way of getting computer to
perform operations, but rather that is a
novel formal medium for expressing ideas
about methodology. Thus, this is
probably the key sentence. Thus,
programs must be written for people to
read and only incidentally for machines
to execute. Second, we believe that the
essential material to be addressed by a
subject at this level is not the syntax
of particular programming language
constructs, nor clever algorithms for
computing particular functions, nor even
the mathematical analysis of algorithms
and foundations of computing, but rather
the techniques used to control the
intellectual complexity of large
software systems. Um why would it be
important for programs to be written for
people to read and only incidentally for
machines to run? People are the ones who
are maintaining the code. Can't
understand it. And how are they going to
maintain it? People have to be able to
maintain it. What else? What might folks
say?
Yeah. The way you add new features, the
way you collaborate, the way you build
large complex systems is that you build
a system that people can read and
understand what it's doing. um uh when
you can't read and can't understand what
it's doing. Um now when you when you all
take introductory computing classes um
and you submit your homework assignments
and they're automatically graded, what
are the kind of characteristics of your
programming that those systems are good
at grading
sort of the output of whatever occurs?
Okay. So, um the the assignment
presupposes some kind of engineering
test and figures out whether or not you
pass that test, like but did your spell
check dictionary detect the misspelled
words or not? Um uh if it passed a
series of randomized test cases from
input to output. Okay, good. So, similar
kind of thing like we we throw a b we
throw a bunch of possible inputs in this
system. Does it all come up with the
outputs that it's supposed to come up
with? Other kinds of engineering tests.
Dana just going to say like sometimes
they'll implement like a time like does
your code does your code run fast
enough? Good. So there could be a you
know that's one kind of efficiency
metric. I think there are other kind of
efficiency metrics that maybe have you
ever done things where you like you only
have a certain number of lines or a
certain number of characters or
something like that to try to
generate some parsimony or something
like that. Some classes here do have
like these like style checkers. I'm not
too sure what they check exactly, but um
they check for certain like stylistic
choices you made in your coding, but a
lot of them also depend on you to have
like to have like correct
computationally code to then give you
the style point. Yeah, good. You know,
and I think the style starts getting at
the sort of programs must be written for
people to read. Now, they probably don't
check things like did you name your
variables and your functions something
sensible that somebody else would be
able to to understand later on or other
kinds of things like that. Um, but you
could think of those style guides as
like like initial, you know, like we
have pretty good tests for the kind of
incidentally for machines to execute.
That's kind of our like our efficacy,
our efficiency evaluations. um you know
in some in some ways like the style
checkers you're describing also they
might be kind of silly but like another
way to think of them is like as a as a
reasonable first step towards these
kinds of things like what are all the
machine readable parts of style um that
we can get a computer to evaluate and
how over time would we build
increasingly sophisticated um style
checkers, computer assessors that would
just do a better and better job year
after year of pull of evaluating more
and more features of code that have to
do with humans understanding and
communicating with each other rather
than just machines. What were you going
to say? Uh I was just going to add that
uh basically I've been a part of a
course where they also do like design
checks for the code on
top. So they're checking like are you
writing good efficient loops? are you
writing redundant code? But even so, I
really feel that within this
introductory like programming space,
they're mostly checking for how well the
students are overfitting to the given
problem space already. Like what they
want to test for is problem solving, but
that's just really hard to do. I think
good. So that you that it's very
difficult. So a in the solution of any
given problem, it's very difficult to
detect for something that would be sort
of like generalizable problem solving
skills. And even worse, it's essentially
like so far it's proven more or less
impossible to design assessment machines
that can detect something like
generalized problem solving skills. Like
to some extent like anytime we build
these things, you know, the our most
sophisticated assessment tools sort of
like work best on particular problems
that you've like fit them to work on and
other kinds of things like that and they
work less well um on more generalizable
kinds of things. Um what are what are
some other domains that we could think
of that are sort of maybe I'll have you
chat with each other for a minute. Um
talk about talk about two things. Um
what what are what are just other
domains that you can think of that are
like this where computers can sort of
test something in the domain but they
may not be able to capture like the most
important or like big important classes
of things in that domain. Um think about
that for a few minutes. That might be
like the sort of putting a pessimist's
hat on to think about that. Um, and then
put on your optimist hat for a minute or
two and say like in the next 5 years,
where do you think we're most likely to
see the most progress um in sort of
thwarting the trap of routine
assessment? Like where are we most
likely to develop um assessment tools
that actually evaluate people on things
that we really care about and want human
beings to be able to do? Um turn to the
person uh next to you or a couple people
and talk about those two things for
three or four minutes. Ready? Go.
Let's do let's do the let's do the first
one first. Um what are what are some
domains that you could think of where it
seemed like ah we were like we really
are having a hard time using computers
to get at the important stuff here
like essay writing or short stories or
anything to do with like writing in
literature. Great. And that's pro like
that's probably one of the most studied
most examined domains. Um and again it's
a place where like we have a like at
least the baseline in that field is
pretty well understood. Um so some of
the very worst assessment like just like
the most disappointing kind of
assessments we do is people's long form
essay writing on standardized tests. Um
there's a guy here named Les Pearlman um
who used to um joke about the quality of
standardized writing assess assessment
by noting that that he could pretty
reliably score essays from across the
room um because you just hold them up
and see how long they are. Um and just
by glancing them he could be like oh
that's two that's a three that's a five.
Um he also wrote pretty early on a
pretty fun piece of software. um there
are all these companies that were
creating automated essay graders. And so
he got a group of MIT students to make
software that generated nonsense text um
that did really well on these automated
essay scorers. Um which was just it it
was pretty fun to read these things
which just were like complete
hallucinations of madness and then you
know some system would be like five. Um
but uh um we we we actually have
developed software tools. Um so think
you know when like the GRE essays are
scored or things like that. So humans go
and score them. It's incredibly
disappointing how they do that. Um they
read them all very quickly. They score
them holistically. The people who do the
scoring are like not particularly well
paid, not particularly well trained. As
you might imagine, like it's enormously
boring to read essays over and over
again about like, you know, who is the
person in your life that inspired you
the most or, you know, I don't whatever
other ridiculous questions they ask. Um,
and and but anyway, you can train those
people to be reasonably uh similar in
their scoring to one another. Um, and
not only that, but for a given question,
like if we ask people over and over
again, who is the, you know, person that
inspired you the most? you have a bunch
of humans evaluate it. You feed all of
those essays into some kind of machine
learning algorithm. We can build um
machines that are roughly as reliable as
those humans. Um so um we can we can
create automated essay scoring tools
that do a reasonably good job that that
predict what a human would score an
essay about as reliably as two humans
would would predict what the other
person would score the essay. Like about
as reliable as two people are. um it
doesn't those systems don't work for
shorter answer things. Um so you have to
you have to be in the realm of a few
hundred words before these systems
become reliable. They're also not very
useful for novel questions. If you
invent a new essay question you want to
give someone, you can't take one of
these algorithms off the shelf and run
it against the system and have it work.
you have to like you know have which is
which is why like I don't know I don't
know how they do it exactly with essays
but these standardized test companies
like you know some fraction of the test
that you take every time you take it um
is not scored and it's just used for
development for these kinds of things
like that you know so you're somehow
like we've convinced you to pay $75 to
do voluntary work for giant test making
companies and things like that um but
yeah that's a that's a you know um that
is a domain in which pe People will also
disagree. Some people will be like,
"Man, it's great that we have these
systems because if you have tools that
can automatically score essays, then you
can encourage people to write more
essays." Like, if we didn't have these
machines that could score essays, like
we uh they wouldn't be on standardized
tests. And if they wouldn't be on
standardized tests, then teachers
wouldn't assign them, and then we would
teach less writing. And so, like, even
as crappy as they, you know, maybe there
are some critiques about their concern,
maybe there are some concerns about
their quality, but they're still good
for the system. Um but uh but yeah,
clearly not everything that is important
about writing is captured in those
things. Like sort of closely related is
like language learning. You can very
easily assess whether someone knows a
lot of vocab or verb conjugations or
grammar or whatever by by a computer.
But like that's not really the point of
language learning. Like language
learning is a lot of it's about like
speaking and listening and and writing
and stuff. And like especially like the
speaking and listening part like you
probably it's probably going to take a
long time for computers to do that well.
Especially like when you have
variability due to like accents and
regional stuff like it would be hard to
assess whether or not someone really is
fluent in a language by simply
interacting with good. And you know
language learning is such an interesting
subject in general uh because it shifts
so much in the middle of it. Um there
there aren't that many things that like
like you know the kinds of things you do
when you teach social studies to third
graders is not that different from the
kinds of things that you do when you
teach social studies to 12th graders. I
guess it's more complicated but it's
along the same lines but the initial
learning of a language sort of more like
a math or a science and then the later
parts of a language is more like a
humanities or a social science or
something like that which is cool. Um,
in the book I write a bunch about um,
automated automated pronunciation
detectors. Um, which to me I think are a
great example of advances in language
learning, especially when you think
about the classroom contexts in which
people learn to pronounce things. So,
like take yourself back to your middle
school Spanish class or whatever. Um,
and there's 26 kids in the room and
there's one teacher and the teacher
walks up to you and goes, "Hola, kumo
estas." And then you respond and and
maybe the teacher gives you some
feedback about their pronunciation.
Maybe they're just whipping around the
room, but you're getting at best like
126th of that teacher's attention for
that pronunciation evaluation exercise.
It's extraordinarily inefficient. Um I
als I remember this a lot because I'm
both bad at language learning and bad at
pronouncing things. Um and you know so
teacher like I would say stuff and the
teacher would just like nod at me like
okay go on to the next word like clearly
I'm not learning this. Um but it like
you know I can open up a computer that
has an automated pronunciation detection
and I can just you know mispronounce
poor favore over and over and over and
over again. And this thing doesn't care.
It'll listen to me say it as many times
as it want. you know, as they get
better, they might be able to find they
can at least give me examples of correct
pronunciation. They might be able to
fine-tune my pronunciation. Like, that
seems like, you know, a place where
computational assessment might really be
a whole lot better um than human
assessment, like in a domain that's
pretty important. What was your example,
Sabrina? I was going to say using
computers to analyze art. like it can
tell you about the color
compositions, time period that it's
from, um what makes it objectively
appealing to look at, but it doesn't
necessarily go into the artist's
background or like the
emotional message behind it or um why it
was created in the way that it was. I
think with art there's like it's usually
not like the surface level which I think
that the computer is like really good at
hitting. Um but maybe the overall
meaning message is missed entirely.
Yeah. I it's it you know I mean there
are AP studio art classes and things
like that where you can submit a
portfolio and I don't I've never I never
thought about it before you brought it
up. Um, but to my knowledge, there's no
application of software in evaluating a
student's art portfolio. But it's a kind
of fun exercise to start thinking about
like what could you assign an AP studio
art student that could be graded by a
computer that people would generally
think is fair. Um, now clearly like
abstract painting or something like
that, like probably no one will think
that's fair. um certain kinds of still
life like where the where the task is
like like reproduce this bowl of fruit
as closely as possible to what the bowl
of fruit actually looked like I would
imagine I would trust a computer to do
that as well or better than a human
would you know but I'm not an artist
maybe there's something about still
lives I don't understand but the only
application I can think of and I am very
biased because I do a lot of photography
is detecting and even then it's
difficult detecting if something's been
like altered in any sort of after the
um like Photoshop and I know Adobee's
working on like their own thing to like
detect. What would what would what would
be a thing that you would want a novice
photographer to be able to do pretty
well that a computer could tell whether
or not they could do it well? Whether or
not a photo is I think the most
fundamental thing is like whether or not
a photo is exposed properly without
having to do any digital alterations.
Yeah. Yeah. No, it's and again, you
know, if you can get a computer that can
do that evaluation, then you can then
you can have all of the photography
students get more formative feedback.
Um, maybe you can get them to have more
high stakes feedback. Maybe, you know,
we could admit students into arts
colleges based on their photography
portfolio or we can just ask them more
questions in their portfolio. We can say
like, humans, go see like whether their
intimate portraits like evoke the
character of the person. Um, and don't
waste your time figuring out whether or
not they can expose photos correctly
because like we got machines that can do
that. Um, yeah, that's a that's a neat
example. Um, so where were you most
optimistic? Where do you feel like
there's going to be the most improvement
in the next five years and where are
those improvements going to come from?
Um,
I sort of have a followup. Oh, sure.
Yeah. Yeah. Um, sorry. I was just
thinking that if if the photo photos
exposure level is detectable by a
computer and then so you begin to not
have humans evaluate that on admission
tests anymore then soon you'd have to
drop that right from the test like that
portion of the value because students
would then have access to these kinds of
softwares as well which means they would
never submit a photo that was not
exposed. That is a great description of
the trap of routine assessment. um that
if if computers can detect performance,
then computers can probably do that
performance. Um if we if we can build a
machine which tells whether or not a
photograph was taken with the correct
exposure, then we can just build cameras
that will only take photographs with the
correct exposure and then we don't need
to teach humans how to do correct
exposures anymore. And so that is like
part of this loop that educators are
sort of constantly wrestling with,
constantly thinking about. Um, and a and
a thing that makes this so hard for
educators is it's really hard to predict
um when your old high school friends are
going to call you.
Um, it's it's really
hard. I won't say anymore. um uh it's
it's really hard to predict um like in
what ways these kinds of disciplines
will change like like how will
photography change over the next five
years um is a really hard thing for for
photography educators to guess right
now. So um I was think I've been
thinking about this a lot because we I
shared this paper that we published with
you um that's called that was generative
AI and K12 and MIT perspective. I didn't
share with you all. I shared it with my
students. Um, and uh, one of the claims
that we make in there is like we can be
pretty sure that computer programming is
going to change and that co-pilots are
going to be a really sort of central
part of computer programming and so
computer science teachers should
probably start thinking about how
they're going to change their
instruction. But I was just at a
conference the other day um, where
someone from Cornell Tech stood up and
was like and the whole premise of the
conference was how should what guidance
should we give to computer science
teachers to change their instruction?
And this woman stood up and was like do
not do that. you have no idea how
computer science you how computer
programming is going to change. You have
there's no reason to give any new advice
to teachers right now because we have no
idea what that would be. Um and uh I
started thinking more and more like well
yeah like in part because I've been
hearing from people who teach
introduction to computer programming
that their early efforts to incorporate
co-pilots in instruction were going
pretty poorly. um that basically like
people like students were using them and
then like week four, week five would
roll around and they're like these
students are totally confused. Like they
haven't learned fundamental things they
need to learn and that I talked to other
software engineers who are saying things
like every hour you save programming
with a co-pilot will cost you an hour in
quality assurance later. Um that the
things like like you solve little
problems but you end up creating bigger
runs for some of the reasons that Hal
has on the screen right here. And so
then you start saying like, man, maybe
we don't know like may like it's pretty
it's pretty hard to think about how you
should change um you know the like some
people might say like why are we
assessing computer programming at all
anymore like the bots are just going to
do it for us and then other people be
like I'm not so sure about that like we
might actually need people doing this or
doing parts of this. Um it's a you know
the other thing I think about a lot um
is that his like historically educators
are not very good at this. Um, so if you
read like in the 19th century, the 20th
century, like in you know, in the 19th
century, there were a whole bunch of
people who were like fervent believers
in diagramming sentences. Did any of you
have to diagram sentences when you're in
elementary school? You know, subject,
predicate, adverb, all these kind. I
mean, there are people who went to their
graves believing that like if we didn't
teach young people what the pl perfect
was, like then, you know, society was
going to collapse. And they were totally
wrong. They laugh at them today. But
there's all kinds of stuff that you and
I would sit down with a bunch of
curriculum developers and be like, "Man,
it's incredibly important that kids in
2024 learn X." And some fraction of
those things are absolutely going to be
vital in 20, you know, 75. And some of
those things that we would like
passionately defend right now, people in
2075 would be like, "Can you believe
those folks 50 years ago thought that
people needed to learn X?" Like what
kind of mor, you know, those like the
knuckleheads who believed in the Plue
perfect in the 19th century or something
like that. Um these are they're very
difficult things to predict. All right,
let's talk about more optimistic things.
What are other things, Dana, that um we
had a really interesting conversation
where we were saying if you go back to
what you were talking about earlier in
how AI can help teachers inspire or I
get AI can inspire teachers um with new
homework assignments. Um but then we
brought up this weird like edtech
Matthew effect where um AI only pulls
like specifically like say Chad GBT is
only pulling from existing literature on
the subject um other than the initial
time that it like maybe accidentally
puts in a random word and starts going
off the walls and makes something crazy.
It's really only pulling from what is
already out there. So in the idea of
bringing up um the middle class and the
teachers with new inspiration, you
almost have to pull ahead the elites to
then produce the literature that is
necessary to then inspire AI with new
things that will then trickle trickle
down to the middle class um for them to
use. So it was almost like this
interesting idea that AI can be useful,
but it needs to have the right like
literature to back it up. Um, and
there's like this that interesting
dilemma of like who is going to create
that and how do you inspire people to
push them ahead in that sense to help
the the little guy? Yeah. What what kind
of training data gets used is enormously
important. We were talking about this
with one of our guests from WPI who was
saying that uh maybe whoever was doing
that presentation can explain it better
than I can, but that uh um uh like as
LLMs generate more code and that code
has problems with it um then future LLMs
will pull in all that buggy code and
suggest more bad code like you know like
me. Yeah. Do you want do you want to say
more about what the what the problem is
there? So uh I used it
to anyway so it was that LLMs are
trained on copilot uh on GitHub code. So
they essentially get all of uh the badly
written code that copilot generates. So
when students are generating that code
uh they are essentially going to
generate the same bad code and they're
not going to fulfill the needs of what
is required from the question as in uh
when you uh give someone an assignment
uh there the ways to test it is to give
them uh some test cases but those test
cases essentially do not solve the
entire problem. Uh so teaching students
uh how to build those test cases that
covers the entire input space is more
important than for them to be able to
write code. Good. Yeah. And so um uh
that was a I mean who knows if if what
Shay just said is true, but that's a
great kind of claim about the future.
you know, building certain kind of test
cases is going to be more important to
the future of computer science than um
you know, being able to write certain
lines of codes or or knowing certain
other programming principles or things
like that. Like this is exactly what
educators are wrestling with every time
there's some new technological change.
Um you know, do we still teach kids
spelling in an age when we have spellch
check? Do we still teach kids
computation in an age where there are
computers? These kinds of things come up
over and over again. um or avo um
something that maybe could be an
optimistic outcome is that like software
is a
languageoriented I mean discipline and
that's kind of why like top language
based model is so good at doing it but
there are things that aren't like analog
circuit design is very visual and right
now signal processing like training
machine learning models with like images
and things is a lot more difficult so
for at least a few decades hopefully
analog circuit design and other things
that are related to hardware will be um
good skills probably to teach kids and
to build like decent fields to work in.
Also, even though there are co-pilot
things for things like cadence that does
like um layout for like semiconductor
chips or whatever, I don't think they're
good. I also don't know how they work.
So a more strong emphasis on teaching
kids kind of like the basics of how the
things that they are I guess catering to
if tattoo actually work. What I'm trying
to say is that I hope that people like
have this shift towards understanding
how things work from the bottom instead
of the top which is good because then
you can build things from ground up.
Wow. Great. Yeah, I like that. What were
you gonna say? I don't know. I'm just I
have a I have a disagreement with the
analog circuit design, but that's just
purely because anything because it's
still a visual software that's doing it.
So there is some translation that could
be considered. It's like probably I do
know a couple of analog circuit design
softwares that just translate down to
XML and you can just stick that XML
which is a structured object oriented
language into chat GP get new XML back
validate that it's correct see it and
it'll probably produce a correct circuit
in some capacity. But can you like I
mean where are you starting when you get
like designing the amplifier or
something?
Um it's it's starting from you have well
the same thing when you started now. Not
nobody had code when it first started.
You would have whatever data set of
people has all their amplifier files
that are all lined up whatever it is.
Then you would ha then you would decide
okay let's get the let's get the textual
representation of this in some
syntactical language which XML was just
one that came to my head but it could be
anything that can represent the image in
text form since that's all the software
is doing since it's just the inputs and
outputs where you connect from wire a to
wire wherever it is and that can usually
be limited and then you take that text
train the LM on it you run it through it
you get some out you then say okay
generate me an amplifier and it will
generate you an amplifier with that XML,
you put it back into the visual
software. Now, look, you now have an
amplifier. Okay. My new hope is that all
of this becomes proprietary and they
don't like,
you know, and I think what's what to me
what from an educator's point of view,
what's so sort of challenging about
these kinds of questions is like I know
nothing about your domain and so both of
the cases that you just made seem
totally plausible to me. um and that
it's really hard pe people seem to be
really bad at predicting the kinds of
things um that AI are going to be useful
for in the future like which of these
problems are solvable and which are they
not um so you can imagine somewhere out
there there are people who like run the
you know AET engineering um uh
curriculum certification kinds of things
or people who are department heads or or
people who are writing textbooks or
things like that like which of this
stuff do we want to keep because human
beings we'll still need human beings to
So you know for the three categories
which of the stuff is like nah like in
the future just AI will build the c like
it'll just tell the a you know you'll
tell some machine learning system AI
system the kind of circuit that you want
and it'll print it out and so you don't
really know that need to know that much
about it. B um yeah an AI will probably
print out most of these things but it's
still useful for humans to be able to
understand this thing um because that
gives you some kind of insight about how
you would build other technology other
things like that. Um or no there's no
way computers are going to be good at
this stuff. We still need human beings
kind of primarily to do it. like those
are at least three categories of things.
Um, and it's really hard to predict sort
of which things move into which
categories. And it's very difficult to
get education systems to be good um at
doing new kinds of things, which is why
like most of the schools that you went
to um you know had very little computer
science education and stuff like that,
you know, because in the 19th century
when we designed high schools, there
wasn't computer science and so we didn't
put it in the curriculum. Um and uh and
we're a lot better at doing the kinds of
things we've done before than doing new
kinds of things.
Um all right good. Were there other
observations or thoughts about that? I
think it can technology can u bring
about change in the legal system. So a
lot of people
um lawyers spend a lot of time reading
stuff and building upon that uh for a
specific case. So and that's what
determines their career. How big you get
and is depends on how much you've read,
how much you've experienced. So if all
this knowledge is really available to
them uh for a specific test case then
probably it's going to make their lives
much more easier. Yeah. You know I think
some of the sort of framework that that
Levy and Maine offer also help us think
about like what kinds of things will
lawyers need to be good at in the
future. Like to me it strikes me as very
unlikely that computers will have much
impact on the part of trial lawyer work.
Um which is convincing juries of things.
Um like like the people who actually
like get in front of juries and try
cases and things like that. Um like it's
very unlikely that we'll have you know
AI machines that generate scripts for
them or things like that because that
kind of persuasive complex communication
seems to be the domain in which human
beings are most specialized at. Um we
probably like you know expert thinking
seems to be the domain in which you know
um like I'm sure you know like like are
people going to write AI software that
detects tax loopholes? Um absolutely
like somebody is going to you know um
you know come up with all kinds of new
ways that you know they're much faster
at humans at finding ways to defeat the
tax code. Um but there probably still be
human beings um who for instance recogni
like who who are much better at machines
at recognizing like oh well like this
part might be like stri slightly
strictly illegal but because of the way
or like like like un like its legality
is not tested but I happen to know
because of everything that I know about
like the functioning of society that
like this is a particularly weak point
in the tax code and would be a good
place to um you know uh uh shelter or
profits and those kinds of things. Um,
and then there does seem to be some kind
like the more the more a legal task
veers into the routine category um the
more it's it's uh hey we just need to
you know know how many times in these
documents these things are said or
something like that. Um but it is I mean
to me it's useful to recognize that like
I mean people were people were stressed
about that in in 2017
um you know with the machine learning
techn so like like there's still lawyers
in the United States there's still law
schools like our legal system has not
you know profoundly changed from um from
what machine learning offered in fact I
think like legal education has probably
barely changed at all um on the basis of
these things except maybe you could like
take it I don't know this for sure I
have no expertise in this but I assume
you could like take an elective in
computers in the law or something like
that or machine learning and the law now
that you wouldn't be able to do
before. Do you guys some thoughts? Yeah.
Uh in terms of the first in terms of
when you initially say back about
lawyers and being a and not being able
to generate scripts. Yeah, I would very
much agree. There was actually um
there's actually a case where I think
two lawyers got heavily sanctioned. I
think it was with the airport where they
pretty much just tried to generate an
entire script purely through tax. I
think it I think it was a filing and I
think the filing included uh like fake
citations and stuff like that which is
really not the best.
Yeah, and you could definitely see it
where basically if you give it you could
basically make a much better search
database using if you happen to stick in
all these thousands of cases where all
the where all the lawyers are where all
these lawyers are pretty much having
decisions that change and ones and maybe
one that benefits your benefits your
stance could have been ruled on earlier
on earlier on in that year. Maybe it's
for the specific county there something
different. You can definitely I
definitely see that in the future. I
don't know even if within that five
years. Yeah. Being a being able to like
being able to do scans of precedents for
a case or something like that. Um maybe
one other domain we should talk about
before we head out is just um you know
one of one of the biggest places in
which we will see pushes in the K12
education system with new tools will be
in formative feedback for writing. Um
there going to be many there are many
many people right now who are building
systems so that like you assign students
to write an essay they turn in the essay
to you and or before they turn in the
essay to you um you offer a bunch of
formative feedback um and I'm very
interested in the development of these
systems I was talking with the
um someone who's building one at UC
Irvine and I guess I was reading about
some others too. Um it struck me that
one of the things that these systems
have the capacity of doing um is saying
something like here are 10 or 15 or 100
things that I want you to check for
every essay. Um does it you know does
the does a paragraph start with a topic
sentence? Um is there a transition
sentence between does the paragraph seem
like it has evidence? Does the
introduction appear to have a thesis?
Um, does the conclusion tie? You know,
you can think about all the things that
you've been ever been taught to write.
Um, a thing that I'm really interested
in is that I my hunch is I mean I
thought about these a lot because a lot
of what I do is grade writing um give
feedback on writing is that like some of
this sort of seems intuitively helpful
to me like oh it would be great if I
could just tell students like hey before
you turn in your your assignment like go
run it through this thing and make sure
that the beginning of every paragraph
has a topic sentence even better than a
topic sentence some kind of mini thesis
something that presents the argument of
the paragraph. Um, but I was thinking
too like probably the most important
thing that I do when I give feedback to
someone, um, is figure out of the dozens
of things I could comment on, which one
I will choose to comment on. Like one of
the things I've learned about as a
writing teacher over the years is like
it is really not helpful to tell someone
everything they've gotten, you know,
they can improve in their essay because
that's just too much stuff to work on. I
mean, you guys note that like I don't I
mean, I I used to have people turn in
printed essays and I used to like make
marks on them and things like that. Um,
but I found over the years like really
what I want to do is be like these are
the two things that you want to work on.
Um, and how do I decide what those two
things are? Like I sort of have in my
head a model of people's developmental
trajectory and some of that model is
based on like all MIT students ever. Um,
like you know when I see an essay that
looks like this, I'm pretty sure the
next thing they should work on is blank.
And then as soon as I've gotten like two
pieces of writing from someone, then I
can be like, "Well, the thing you were
working on last time was this. Why don't
you work on it more? Here's like the
next thing after that to work on or
something like that." Um, that seems
like the kind of discernment. It seems
way way easier to me to program a
machine that can like find every kind of
problem than it is to program a machine
that can figure out like what are the
next two problems you should be working
on as a learner. um based on you know
who you are or where I think you're
heading or what's important for my class
or other things like that. I feel like
that opens up the idea of um breaking
out of the trap of routine assessment.
Um if a computer can do those type of
things, then maybe teachers can now
focus more on what does revision look
like? Um, so like a student, you know,
goes through an essay or writes an essay
and then puts it through this machine
and the machine tells you like, oh, and
these introduction sentences like they
could be stronger in X, Y, and Z ways
and how do you develop those critical
thinking skills to take something and
feedback and perform it or like change
it in some way? Like you were always
saying like anything that you published
was never your first draft. You said
like on day one, one of your good skills
was being able to just like get down a
first draft, right? CHBT can do the same
for you. But how do we teach people in a
world where AI can give you that
baseline? How do we elevate it to a
status that like is like acceptable for
like a human? Like I feel like there's
like AI can give us a baseline, but
humans take that imagination and
creativity to that next step. And so you
can kind of take the idea of like here's
an essay. How would you change it to
make it even better? Yeah. I you know
for for these writing software
developers I I mean a big well when I
talk to them I think about like what is
the whole system that you're
constructing like not every capacity
that you build will end up being useful
not just because it doesn't work but
because like using it is not that
helpful you start thinking things like
all right what if there is a what if
there are these sort of you know
formative feedback systems um where I as
an instructor can say like okay um you
know start this package of uh um
machines or something like that or or uh
I select in advance that I want the
machine to give you know to give to
automatically give you formative
feedback on these things and then on
this other class of things I want you to
show me the feedback that you would give
to a student but I will pick from those
things and then there'll be some way for
me to sort of add to it like some of
those sort of human machine combinations
seem pretty exciting to me good um well
why don't we wrap there for the Okay.