I'm Sarah Hansen and today I'm talking
with financial economist Andrew Low
whose videos have been viewed millions
of times on our channel. I ask Andrew
how he makes a topic like finance
accessible to everyone. It it's amazing
how bad we are as uh homo sapiens in
managing our finances. We also get
personal about his own learning journey.
I uh have a learning issue. It's the
mathematical equivalent of dyslexia.
Discalcula. You do? and I get his answer
to the question, should I use chat GPT
to plan my
[Music]
retirement? All this and more on Chalk
Radio. Andrew, thank you so much for
being with us today. A pleasure. Thank
you for having me. For a long time, I've
thought that if I don't have an advanced
degree in mathematics that I probably
don't have a place in finance and
probably shouldn't be thinking about it
much. But I'm wondering if you might
prompt me to think differently. Well,
not surprisingly, I have a very
different perspective as a financial
economist. Someone once said that to a
person that has a hammer, everything
looks like a nail and I'm guilty as
charged. I learned early on in life that
virtually everything at some point or
another ends up being about money.
Particularly with regard to any kind of
innovative pursuits for entrepreneurship
or career-wise, at some point or
another, you're going to have to deal
with money. and then you need to speak
the language of finance. Yeah. So that's
what really motivated me to learn how to
speak that and then ultimately be able
to develop new words and sentences in
that language. Yeah, it is a new
language. It's and it seems like it's
something that everybody can learn no
matter where they're starting from.
Absolutely. You've contributed to open
courseware. Your videos have been
watched millions of times and you seem
really good at making finance accessible
to people no matter where they're
starting from. I I'm wondering what it
is that you do that allows that to
happen. Have you done any reflecting on
that over the years? Well, first of all,
it's a great honor to be part of Open
Course Square and the fact that it does
reach people all around the world
regardless of cost or access is really
wonderful. And um the reason that I was
so pleased and and honored to
participate in that is because I really
feel like everybody should have access
to this knowledge at different levels of
course um but we all need to know a
little bit of finance and I think that
early on I was really drawn to this
field because of how impenetrable it was
and at the same time how important it
is. growing up, I just remember um
always hearing my mother talk about
finances and some of the challenges that
we were facing. And I think that really
made me hyper aware of the fact that um
it's really a necessary part of life.
Sometimes uh unfortunately too much a
part of life and if we don't understand
it, it's very easy to uh to end up being
taken advantage of or not being well
prepared for the kind of things that
finance helps you deal with. Yeah, I
think about this a lot when I go to the
grocery store and see cereals for over
$6 and eggs sometimes up to $8. I mean,
what are
some theories of modern finance that
everyday people like me could apply or
think about when I'm faced with those
situations?
Wow. Well, there's a whole bunch of
ideas and and important uh notions that
we can use in our everyday lives. One of
the key notions is that there's a
trade-off among everything that we do
and everything that we purchase. Far too
often we tend to compartmentalize and we
have a mental budget for certain
activities as well as other budgets for
other activities and we don't allow them
to mix. But sometimes if you can think a
little bit more broadly about the fact
that we have a given set of resources
and we have to allocate them across lots
of different activities and there are
interesting financial ways of making
those decisions, we can actually come up
with better outcomes. You one example
that I think most people are aware of is
uh borrowing money to buy a home or buy
a car. That is basically moving money
from the future, our futures to our
present. we're borrowing and sometimes
we need to put money today aside for our
kids' college fund or purchasing a car
in the future. That's an example of
moving money from today to ourselves 2
years from now or 3 years from now. So,
this notion of being able to move money
around and making sure that you don't
lose a lot of it in the process is part
of the language of finance and that's
something that all of us can benefit
from. Yeah, it's so interesting the idea
of having more flexible um understanding
of your resources and how they might
move across categories. Yeah. I mean, I
think at the heart of it, it's really
all about control, but I think not
enough people understand how finance
works so that ultimately it ends up
ruling their lives as opposed to
allowing them to use finance to achieve
the kind of goals that they really want.
So Andrew before the show we asked you
to respond to a question which we'll we
will now reveal the answer to. So the
question was should I Sarah Hansen use
chat GPT right now to plan my
retirement? What's our answer?
Not yet. Okay, please explain.
Not yet because large language models
are not yet ready to be able to do
delegated financial decision-m for us.
Turns out that saving for retirement is
one set of activities. But then spending
while in retirement, that's a whole
different set of activities. And many of
us have become good at saving. But you
know, we've been such good savers that
we forget that at some point we need to
spend and and we have to spend at the
right rate for the right things at the
right times. So what my colleagues and I
are trying to understand now is not only
what those optimal decisions are. I
think we now have a lot of information
about that. There's been a lot of
research done on that. But the more
challenging issue is how do we
communicate that to people who don't
have any finance background and and
moreover can't afford to hire the
financial adviserss that some of the
higher net worth individuals have access
to. So, we're working on an AI solution
uh an AI financial adviser that can
satisfy the most important criterion of
financial advice that regulators impose
which is something called fiduciary
duty. A fiduciary is somebody who is
appointed to help you further your
goals, will look out for your best
interests uh above and beyond their own.
And so very often people get a little
bit concerned about you know financial
planners and other people in the
financial industry because they don't
want to be taken advantage of and you
know there are many good financial
planners out there but not everybody can
afford one. So the question is can you
for those people who can't afford
financial planning and for the financial
institutions that don't want to spend
their resources of financial advice to
those who aren't going to generate
enough commissions for them for these
people can we come up with uh financial
advice from an AI platform that
satisfies the definition of a fiduciary
some some program that you can trust to
look out for your best interest. We're
not there yet. However, I believe that
everybody should use large language
models to help them think through
retirement issues more seriously. For
example, ask JBT, "What are the biggest
issues that I need to focus on for my
retirement? How much time do I have?
What kind of ideas and products and
services should I make use of? How do I
get better financial information? How do
I learn more about these problems?" All
of those things I think chatbt can do a
pretty good job at, but I wouldn't let
it make your decisions for you. Real
question for you. I know a lot of times
when I put in a prompt that's um within
my domain of expertise, some of it will
be good, but some of it's kind of
garbage and not all that accurate. So,
as a person who doesn't know finance,
how do I know I can trust the answers
that are coming back even about those
general type of questions? Well, so
that's really why you need to have
additional time and effort employed in
thinking through these issues, not just
by yourself, but with friends and
family. Yeah. So we need human support
for thinking about how large language
models can work either well or in some
cases not so well. And in any case, if
you are planning for your retirement, at
some point or another, you're going to
have to engage with people from the
financial institutions. Yeah. They will
be able to help deal with some of the
so-called hallucination problems with
these large language models. But the
answer is like anything else that we do.
You know, how do you know that your
doctor is always giving you the best
information? Doctors are very highly
trained, but they do make mistakes. So
get a second opinion, get a third
opinion, talk to your family members.
Ultimately, you're going to be
responsible for your own decisions. But
the more informed you can be and the
more you can check the uh accuracy of
the information and that information
come from humans or from chat bots, I
think those are the ways that we've
developed for making sure that we make
the best decisions possible. Get a
better handle on this. Right. And I
assume part of the idea would be to
start this in your 20s if you can start
learning and start using these
applications to really begin to save.
Exactly. Many people don't realize that
the decisions that they make early on
can have just tremendous consequences
30, 40 years from now. We now know that
about health. We know that if we don't
eat right, even as a teenager, we can
affect our health when we get to middle
age. The same thing is true about our
finances. If we make bad financial
decisions early on, it could end up
having repercussions far beyond what we
typically are able to measure. And so
that's really the purpose of having some
kind of support, some kind of advice
that can actually look 40, 50 years
ahead of a teenager. It's kind of
interesting because at least in the US
or at least in the cultural circles in
which I grew up, it was sort of taboo to
talk about money, how much you make, uh
how much other people make, how you're
budgeting. Have you found that in this
context? Absolutely. And that's actually
one of the reasons why you want to have
a fiduciary. You want to have somebody
you can talk to about your deepest
secrets, your financial goals, your
constraints, the concerns that you have
about losing your job or or not being
able to find a job and be able to get
honest advice about what to do about it.
You know, many of us have good friends
that we can rely on for that. But if you
don't have a friend who has financial
expertise, what do you do? Yeah. So the
hope is that maybe a platform uh a
reliable AI platform that is able to
serve as a fiduciary can really help
individuals with all of their concerns.
Yeah, it's going to be a gamecher for
sure. What are some of the dangers,
pitfalls or challenges that might come
with leveraging AI to give financial
advice to people who do not have
financial um expertise? Well, any great
tool can easily be abused and I think we
have to worry about the fact that if we
have a financial planning tool that is
AIdriven, can that be abused? What if we
were to ask this AI to engage in illicit
activities uh for our financial
betterment? Is that something that uh we
should be able to do or is it something
that the AIS should guard against? uh
you get into all sorts of tricky ethical
questions about how these tools are used
and so I think that those of us who are
developing the technologies really
require spending more time thinking
about the ethical dimensions that's not
something that you typically focus on in
your research but for us now given how
far AI has come and what it can do we
have to be be much more proactive about
thinking about these unintended
consequences yeah and just how fast
everything is changing the technology is
so fluid and so fast and honestly not
all that transparent most of the time.
Yeah. You know, that's a concern that I
think most people don't really
appreciate yet. You know, it's true that
there's always been technology that is
made advances and as a result has
created winners and losers. You know,
when the horsedrawn buggy gave way to
railroads and then eventually to
automobiles, people lost their jobs and
people had to be retrained. But there is
a big difference between that technology
and the current set of technologies and
it's exactly what you said. It's about
speed. The fact is that right now AI is
moving at such breakneck pace that
within a very short period of time we
can actually have large parts of our
population unemployed and the hope of
retraining them in time for them to make
a difference for their lives can be very
challenging given how quickly things are
moving. So I think that's the one
concern that the AI researchers are
thinking about. Uh we don't have any
good answers yet. Um, and one of the
answers that's been proposed, which is
to slow down the rate of progress,
right? That's almost never possible.
Even if you want to do it, even if you
have legislation, there'll be people
that will refuse to abide by that
because legislation is not going to stop
that kind of innovation. It's not going
to stop people from having ideas and
wanting to implement them. Yeah. The
idea of people being put out of work um
with the advancement of these
technologies is hugely concerning. And I
know one that you're concerned about
because it seems like in everything you
do, it all comes back to people and the
impact on people. Um I'm wondering where
that drive comes from. Where did your
interest in leveraging finance to
positively impact people's lives come
from? Because it didn't have to. There's
a lot you can do with with money and not
worry about positively impacting people.
So tell us a little bit about that.
Well, yeah, I have to say that um that
was really not something that I had
planned. Much of my early career was
focused on applying mathematical and
statistical models to investment
problems, developing trading strategies,
risk management policies, various kinds
of systemic risk measures. It was really
all geared around the amazing impact
that this technology could have on the
field itself, on finance, making finance
better. and uh in some of the things
that I did in practice on the commercial
side um started up my own asset
management company and ultimately
implemented some of these strategies for
various kinds of hedge funds and uh
investors and um at some point I mean it
was very satisfying but at some point I
started to wonder whether or not um you
know this was uh this was it this is you
know what um I was meant to do and
around that time it's about 20 years ago
a number of friends and family uh all
developed cancer at the same time within
seven years six people close to me all
died including my mother you know I I
really never dealt with death up close
and personal before that and so it was a
big wakeup call and through that process
realized that uh finance plays a pretty
big role in cancer drug development you
know I was pretty naive at the time I
just thought that if there was a patient
in need and there was some great
technology that could help that patient
that somehow magically money would just
come sprinkling down and develop the
drug um But when I looked into it and
talked to my colleagues uh here in
Cambridge, uh it became very obvious to
me that that was not the case. That that
there were many examples of good drugs
that could help lots of patients that
will never ever see it to market because
there was not enough financing to bring
that to the patients. So that's when I
started uh thinking about how finance
could play a role in that. And it was
actually totally selfish. I wanted to
figure out how to help my friends and
family uh and how to get better drugs to
them. uh but in doing so it just made me
realize the power of finance and and the
responsibility that we have uh given
that we understand the kind of things
that other people don't about how to
finance certain kinds of projects about
how to bring money to a particular area
and really make it go faster. Um that
that we also have a responsibility to
take some of these ideas and implement
them for those really high impact high
societal impact kinds of uh uh pursuits.
Um so I started with that and then one
thing led to another and I began
thinking more broadly about how finance
uh impacts society in general and
realizing that there are many things
that we can do to further all sorts of
different goals. Climate change uh
energy transition. There are so many
different issues that really are crying
out for new business models and
financing strategies and these are you
know well-known tools that all financial
economists know but we haven't really
spent time thinking about the
applications. So that's been a really
rewarding aspect of my current focus.
Yeah. Could you give an example of how a
different business model might radically
change the climate trajectory that we're
on? Sure. Let's talk about energy
transition because clearly we are not in
the process of transitioning very
quickly. That's right. In fact, right
now about 82% of the world's energy
usage is in the form of fossil fuels. I
think that might be down from 83 or 84%
10 years ago. It's not enough and we're
not making a difference fast enough. A
number of people who know a lot more
about the issues than I do have said
that we're not really right now in the
business of transitioning because it's
not as if we're declining our usage of
energy. If anything, it's growing. So,
what we need to do is to come up with
new sources of energy, energy addition
as opposed to energy transition. Oh,
that's interesting. And so what do you
do with that? Where do you go? There are
three totally green sources of energy
that my colleagues tell me right now
that that are um not in the renewable
space. Obviously solar, wind, hydro is
important, but they're not always there
when we need it. We need to develop
better battery technologies and that's
all happening. That's good, but again,
not enough. So if we want to speed up
the process of energy addition, we need
new sources of green energy. And there
are three. There's nuclear fision.
nuclear fusion and
geothermal. And all of these should be
areas that we pursue. And so imagine if
we could support all sorts of different
investment projects in all three areas
and really make a concerted effort to
develop these new sources of green
energy. That's an example of what
finance can do. But we need to develop
the the political will to be able to do
that. And and even part of that can be
uh hastened by finance because if you
can show that governments can actually
save money in the long run by investing
in these if they can get a good rate of
return on these investments they're much
more likely to be able to write the
checks that we need now. Yeah, it really
does all come down to money.
Unfortunately um in most cases that
seems to be true. Uh but fortunately the
world has become wealthier and largely
that's happened because of
industrialization and the innovations
and technology that we have pioneered.
Uh but the wealth is not equally spread.
There's definitely winners and losers
and I would argue that the wealth is not
necessarily being allocated in the most
efficient way. If we were to change some
of that allocation, we could actually
get better outcomes for everybody.
Nobody has to lose. So it all sounds so
logical when you explain it. Uh but then
you introduce
humans. Talk to me about humans. You
know, human behavior is one of the most
interesting and most confounding aspects
of what I do in finance because we can
write down all these wonderful equations
that predict various kinds of
opportunities for financial investments,
but the at the end of the day, you're
talking about people. Yeah. And people
can react. Sometimes they can overreact.
Uh you know for example during the
pandemic the stock market lost something
like 30% in a matter of a few days. Wow.
And right if most of your retirement is
tied up in the stock market that was a
really big hit. Yeah. So a number of
people responded by what? By pulling out
their money from the stock market
putting it in
cash. That's in and of itself is not a
necessarily bad decision. The problem is
that many of these individuals, they
took too long to put the money back into
the stock market and they missed the
rebound, which actually happened just a
few weeks after that 30% decline. The
market went right back up. And if if you
had taken a vacation between, you know,
middle of March 2020 and middle of June
2020, if you had taken a vacation and
done nothing, you would not even have
noticed that the stock market moved. It
just went down and then back up.
So I think that understanding these kind
of dynamics is important because we
often allow ourselves to engage in
behaviors that can be really
counterproductive. And that's part of
what I do as a finance professional is
to understand how human behavior factors
into this. And it's amazing how bad we
are as uh homo sapiens in managing our
finances. And that's one of the reasons
why I do what I do. I'm really excited
about it. Yeah. You have a
hypothesis. What is it called? So my
hypothesis is the adaptive markets
hypothesis. And uh it was developed in
contrast to one of the most popular
theories in my field called the
efficient markets hypothesis. Okay,
that's a theory that says that markets
always and everywhere reflect all
available information and that means
that the prices that you see are
generally correct. And it turns out the
deficient markets hypothesis is not
wrong. It actually works most of the
time, but it's not complete. It doesn't
work all the time. And for the times
when it doesn't work, where human
behavior overwhelms the kind of
rationality that you typically see in
the markets, that's where you need to
understand how the mechanics of human
behavior interacts with the beautiful
logic of financial markets. That's the
adaptive markets hypothesis. Yeah. So,
as a fellow human, what can I do to
counteract my own um irrational
tendencies? Well, the first step is to
recognize that this is an issue. So, uh
if you recognize that we all have this
problem, that's the first step in
recovery in trying to understand how to
deal with it. The the second step is to
do scenario analyses in our brain. So,
one one of the most magnificent gifts of
human evolution is the ability to engage
in abstract thought. Okay. In
hypotheticals. Yeah. We can hold in our
mind all sorts of what ifs of what if I
decided not to go to work today? What
would happen then? What if I decided to
become a doctor, a lawyer? Uh what if I
decided uh to save money uh so that my
kids can go to college? Those kinds of
whatifs we can often work out in
reasonable detail in our heads and then
pick the what if that is the most
attractive. Uh-huh. So, right now, if
we're not in the middle of a financial
crisis, we can do the what if and say,
"What if it turns out the stock market
crashes by 20%." Okay. Given my age,
given the likelihood that it's going to
come back because based on the last
hundred years of history, when the
markets go down, eventually they go back
up. It takes a while, but you we can
actually see when things are recovering.
What if I decided not to sell out
everything? What if I decided to wait
and see how things go? What if I were to
wait two years, three years, five years?
Can I afford to wait? By doing those
kinds of what if analyses, we can go a
long way towards preparing for these
kinds of events. And this is where
financial planners are really helpful.
They have a lot more sophisticated
whatifs than you and I might be able to
come up on our own. And there I think we
can get AI to play a role because AI now
with large language models are
remarkably good at coming up with all
sorts of interesting whatifs. And so to
be for ararmed is to be to be foreworn
is to be forarmed. We have a lot of
YouTube comments pointing out that you
tend to make finance very accessible
through your lectures and I'm wondering
if you could articulate what it is you
think you do that opens the door for
students in your classes and around the
world when they watch your open
courseware videos. Well, first of all,
thank you for that observation. I'm
really uh humbled and and grateful for
that. If that's true, it's because I
often develop my lectures with an eye
towards being a student myself. I was a
high school student in New York City at
the Bronx High School of Science is a a
school that specializes in STEM and uh
wonderful education that money didn't
need to buy because it's a p public
school. And I u I learned more from my
classmates in Bronx Science than I think
I did from any other uh time in my
educational career. It's a phenomenal
school. But one of the things that I
learned from Bron Science that wasn't
quite right and this is my own fault. I
identified intelligence with STEM. So if
you were smart at Bronx Science, that
meant you were good at science and math.
I mean, you know, we had history,
English, social studies, all of those
other fields, but those weren't the real
focus of the kids that went there. It
you went there because you wanted to
study science, math, and engineering.
And it wasn't until I got to college
that I was completely disabused of that
notion. And it happened because I met
somebody who was completely innumerate.
I mean, he he wasn't even able to take
the introductory math class at in
college and needed my help to get
through it. And so, I would tutor him
every once in a while and um you know,
he would eventually learn, but it took
him a while and it was never easy. He
really sweated it out and ultimately I
think passed with a a C or something.
And yet, may or may not have been that
person, but go well. The the thing about
that person uh is that he was one of the
smartest people I ever met in college.
And I didn't expect that. And let me
explain what I mean by that. We'd be
sitting at dinner and no matter what the
topic of conversation was, politics,
religion, music, anything that you would
talk about other than
mathematics, he was just incredibly
well-informed,
articulate, and extraordinarily
analytical.
So that really threw me for a loop
because again, analytical math but not
in his brain. Yeah. So he ultimately
went to law school, became a very very
wellrespected attorney and you know he
could argue anybody uh you know into the
ground because he had a mind sharp as a
razor blade. Yeah. How is it possible
that somebody could be so smart and yet
innumerate? That was a big wakeup call
for me and it pointed out the fact that
there are different kinds of
intelligence. So up until recently when
we think about artificial intelligence
and computation it's all computational
quantitative right for the very first
time and this is why I think large
language models are such a breakthrough
we are now confronted with a very
different kind of artificial
intelligence this is intelligence that
is like my friend in college it becomes
analytical but in a way that uses
language not numbers and equations and
so I think that large language models
is a different type of AI than what
we're used to. That's what makes it so
powerful, but it does have some
weaknesses. Just like my friend who if
you ask him to prove a very simple
theorem in calculus, he'd sweat bullets
doing it, but he was incredibly
intelligent in other ways. And so I
think that opens up all sorts of new
insights for me in terms of my own
students, myself, and how we think about
intelligence and sometimes how limited
we are in thinking about intelligence.
We measure intelligence with tests,
reading comprehension, vocabulary, and
uh, you know, mathematical problems. But
I wonder if there's many forms of
intelligence that we're not capturing
with those tests. And there are whole
swaths of society that we have somehow
neglected and underappreciated because
they have an intelligence that we don't
know about, we can't measure, but we
really could benefit from. Well, I
couldn't agree with you more. I used to
be an elementary school teacher, so I
saw the ways in which schools pinpoint
intelligence and measure it and leave
out large groups of people. Yeah. So,
we're on the same page there. Well,
speaking of elementary school, that was
one of the important and formative
experiences of my life. It turns out
that um uh in retrospect, I uh have a
learning issue. Uh it's the mathematical
equivalent of dyslexia, dcalculia. You
do? Yes.
Wow, that is so surprising. Well, you
know, people say that because of what I
do now. Yeah. But, um, it was definitely
the case that math was my worst subject.
And, you know, for an Asian growing up
in New York City in the 1970s, that was
not easy. Wow. So, um, it wasn't until I
went to the third grade that I finally
found a teacher that recognized
something in me. Mrs. Barbara Ficolora,
third grade, PS13 in Queens. And
um she knew that I was struggling with
math. Yeah. But yet she also saw that I
was really curious. I would always enjoy
going to the library once a week. I
would take out a stack of science books
and read them and be really interested
in that. And uh so she tried to boost my
confidence by by making me the class
scientist. Okay. Now, I didn't know that
that position existed. I certainly
didn't apply for it. But what it meant
was that I got to demonstrate one of
these science experiments that I was
concocting at the back of the room every
free period I could get uh and just talk
to the whole class about, you know, how
to make um a battery out of lemons uh
and um uh magnets. And I think it was
that experience that allowed me to get
through my elementary years despite the
fact that other teachers that I had who
were not so supportive um were pretty
discouraging and to me and and to my
mother back then there was no diagnosis
of ADHD or disalculia, right? Um so you
know I basically solded on until uh I
went to high school at that Bronx High
School of Science I mentioned, right?
That was in the 1970s when New York City
was undergoing this radical experiment
called the new math. I don't know if
you've heard about that, but it was a
widely renowned failure because it was
replacing the basic concepts of algebra,
geometry, and trigonometry with all
these mathematical concepts of groups,
rings, fields, isomorphisms, and other
transformations.
And while mathematically it was more
rigorous and intellectually more
pleasing, most of the New York City
school teachers were not prepared to
teach in this way. And so for most uh
schools, it was really a a failure. But
for me, it was night and day. I came
from being a C student in math to an A
student overnight because it was more
analytical and less focused on numbers.
No numbers. I I to this day I have a
hard time memorizing numbers. I never
memorize the multiplication tables. Uh I
still have trouble with 6* 7. I have to
actually do the calculation in my head
and takes me a little bit longer than
most people. Yeah. Uh but when you
replace numbers with equations, that was
like a huge relief. It's like, you know,
wearing shoes that are two sizes too
small and then you take them off and you
put on shoes that are just exactly the
right size. It felt wonderful. And
because I struggled as a student with my
own learning issues, I could tell the
difference between good teaching and bad
teaching. And of course, for a while, I
blamed it on myself. But then once I
learned a bit more about my own learning
issues, I began to understand what
certain things would allow me to see a
concept versus other things that would
confuse me. Now, when I write my
lectures, I often have to step into the
students role and ask myself, if I
didn't know anything about this, what
would be the fastest way to get me to
have some kind of a grasp of what it is
that I'm trying to teach? And again,
looking at it from my own lens. The
other part is that I've had the the
great gift of having a number of really
incredible teachers. When I was a high
school student, my calculus teacher,
Mrs. Henrietta Amazin, was amazing. uh
when I was a college student uh Saul
Levmore, Sharon Auster, Herb Scarf,
amazing as a graduate student, Andy Ael,
uh Jerry Hman, I I remember all of these
teachers names, uh it's because they
just made a huge impact on they changed
my life. And so part of why I spend time
on teaching and I think this is another
aspect. Some of my colleagues uh are so
focused on research that they feel like
they can't afford to spend time on
teaching. But because I remember what it
was like as a student when faculty
didn't take the time to try to explain
something in a way that would be more
understandable, I decided to spend the
time on working on my lectures. Someone
once said that um great writing is not
writing so that other people can
understand. It's writing so that other
people cannot possibly misunderstand.
Oh, that's a good one. Yeah, that's a a
very difficult uh standard to uh adhere
to. But I think that's the same with
teaching. teaching is lecturing so that
students cannot possibly
misunderstand and that does take a
little bit more time but you know when
you are able to land a concept with an
audience there is no better feeling from
my perspective it is you know it is like
you know I don't know a gymnasts you
know hitting a perfect landing uh ice
skaters being able to do a triple axle
without falling uh for me that is you
know just an incredible feeling a rush
that I can communicate something that
somebody didn't understand and now their
faces light up and I get it now. I mean
and they will forever from that point
they will forever have that uh to use
and to benefit from. And also one of the
things that um makes me particularly uh
grateful to open courseware is that it
is the great equalizer. You know, there
are so many people that that can't learn
on a schedule and that have all sorts of
issues that don't allow them to excel in
a classroom with 30 other kids. And yet
they're perfectly intelligent, in some
cases, super intelligent, but they have
these challenges. open course where it
gives them a platform at least to be
able to learn at their own pace, to be
able to stop the video, to think about
it, to start it up again when they're
ready, and there's nobody looking over
their shoulder seeing how well they're
doing relative to their competitors. It
it it changes the learning field and I
think gives opportunities that weren't
available. So, I I I can't tell you how
honored I am to be part of this and to
be part of the institution that came up
with this platform and and basically
gave knowledge away to the rest of the
world. You brought something with you
today.
I did. So, you know, when I was asked to
come on this program, um, you asked me
to bring a a meaningful momentto,
something small that I can carry. Yeah.
And I have to tell you that was a that
was a terrible assignment. It just took
me a long time cuz, you know, what
should I bring? A little art objects
that my kids made, you know, very dear
to me. Um, you know, my my high school
diploma. Uh, but I decided to bring the
most important um reason for where I am
today. And this is a picture of my
mother. Oh, so I um I mentioned that um
you know, we grew up in in New York
City. Um we were a single parent
household. She um uh worked um one job
uh with overtime, you know, to be able
to raise three kids by herself. I was
the youngest of three. and um instilled
in me and my brother and sister a love
of learning and uh the importance of
hard work and um you know focusing on on
the the longer game as opposed to you
know short-term issues which is ironic
because most of her young life as a
mother was focused on trying to make
ends meet. I would remember
conversations about finance pretty much
every single month. And it was uh it was
tough because uh we did not grow up with
a lot. Um and uh you know she was uh
divorced um at and that was a time when
um it was very difficult to to uh
survive as a single woman uh with three
kids. Yeah. But uh she did an amazing
job and um so I owe her a lot. So, if
she was here with us now, what would she
say to me about balancing the um meat
ends meet with the long game? Yeah.
Well, I I don't know that her advice
would be something that anybody would or
could do because she sacrificed her
career for us. She was a a lawyer by
training. Um left uh China when the
communist revolution took place. Um then
uh married someone who was uh not ideal
um a an abusive uh husband. Um took a a
long time for her to see that and get
divorced as she did. It was a very messy
divorce. Um and because he was a foreign
national and ended up being a diplomat.
Uh he was also the best thing about that
marriage was that he was an absentee
father because he was uh abusive when he
was around. And um so she dedicated her
life to her kids and um uh you know held
a a menial secretarial position despite
the fact that she was educated uh in law
from China and um ultimately um I think
uh really put the three of us through
school so that we could have the careers
that we do now. I don't know that that's
the right advice in general um for women
that are in that position because I
think there has to be more of a balance,
but for her it was just really important
for her kids to um reach the career
goals that she set out for us. What's
her name? Julia Yao Lo. That's lovely.
Thank you. Thank you for being here. I
really enjoyed getting to know you and
you've completely changed my perspective
on what's possible in terms of my
relationship to mathematics and to
finance. Good. I uh am honored to have
played that role. Thank you.