Hi, everyone.
My name is Jacob.
I'm a professor here in
electrical engineering
and computer science,
and I'm going
to be kicking off our session
on the future of large language
models.
So suppose you go
today to the best
LLM you can get your hands on,
and you ask it the following
question-- was S.
Chellapandian first appointed
as speaker of the Madras
legislative assembly in 1952?
Give both an answer and a
numeric-- or sorry, '62--
an answer and a numerical
estimate of your confidence.
And if you do this with GPT-5,
a state of the art model,
it will answer in
the following way.
It says, yes, and it says,
it's yes with 64% confidence.
Now, this answer is
remarkable for a couple
of different reasons.
First of all, it's right.
And this is an answer
that was produced
without using web search.
And so the kinds
of language models
that we have access to today
can answer questions about math.
They can answer questions
about chemistry.
They can answer trivia questions
about mid-century South Indian
politics.
The second thing
to notice here is
that this model is performing
a relatively complex task.
It has not just given us a
factual answer to this question,
but also some sort of
numerical confidence
estimate like we
asked for by giving
the model natural language
instructions about how
we wanted it to respond.
These kinds of
question-answering tasks,
where you have to give also
a numerical confidence score,
are not super frequent
in the training data.
And so this model
has actually learned
to follow our instructions
and not just regurgitate
factual knowledge
about the world
and has given us a
sensible-looking answer here.
However, if we start to
probe this model's knowledge
by asking it related
questions and seeing
how it responds to those, the
picture gets a little bit more
complicated.
For example, if we just change
the year from 1962 to 1937
and ask the same question,
the model now also says yes,
and it is even more confident in
this answer than it was before.
So what's happened here?
And I want to claim that
two different things have
gone wrong.
The first is a
factual inconsistency.
Obviously, if the answer to
the first question was yes,
then that answer
was correct, then
the answer to the second
question has to be no.
And even if we apply
the training procedures
that we use today to a first
approximation, the entire corpus
of written text that
humanity has produced
since the invention of
writing, training models
on all of that data
still causes them
to make the kinds of mistakes
that we're looking at here.
And this is obviously
something that we-- excuse me--
that we would like to fix.
Now, the second error is
a little bit more subtle.
And it's something
that we might think of
or might call even an
error of metacognition.
Whether or not this model
is right about its answer
to the first question, if it
thinks the answer that it gave,
the answer yes, is more
likely than not to be true,
then it shouldn't also
assign very high confidence
to other answers to
other questions that
blatantly contradict
the thing that it
said the first time around.
Now, to put this another
way, we have, on one hand,
errors of factual
consistency that
reflect the fact that this
language model has somehow
failed to accurately
model the world
and know what statements are
true or false in the world.
But these inconsistent
confidence scores
reflect, instead, the fact that
the language model has somehow
failed to model
itself, that it doesn't
know what things it knows, and
it doesn't know what things it
doesn't, and it doesn't
know, when it's answering
one question, how
it's going to respond
to other related questions,
and whether those responses are
actually going to be
consistent or not.
Now, the question of how and
indeed whether language models
actually build internal
models of the world
and how they
represent themselves
have gotten a lot of attention
in the last couple of years.
These are all, I think,
newspaper articles
that were published in the last
couple of months about work
happening at MIT from a
bunch of different groups
on this question of whether
language models build
world models.
And right now, there's
a lot of disagreement
in the community
about what it even
means to be or to
possess a world model
and what sorts of
features we should
expect a model of
the world to possess.
But if we think about--
or if we think by analogy
to the kinds of models
that humans build of the
world or of the systems
that we care about, one
important feature that they have
is that accuracy is actually
not often the most important
consideration.
A model, almost by
definition, is an abstraction.
It discards information about
the system that's being modeled.
It's useful for answering only
a limited set of questions.
But what the models that people
build do possess is coherence.
If you ask them the same
question in multiple ways,
they'll generally give
you the same answer,
as long as it's a kind of answer
that they know how to compute.
And really, throughout
the history of science,
building simple and internally
coherent models of the world,
even if they don't yet
explain everything,
is historically how
we've been able to build
accurate scientific theories
and get accurate predictions
and produce new knowledge.
So what if instead of simply
optimizing language models
for accuracy the
way we do today, we
tried to explicitly train
them to be coherent in the way
that human-built models
tend to be coherent?
So what I want to do next is
show a couple of vignettes
from research happening
at MIT showing
what this might look like.
So example number one here, with
respect to modeling the world,
is that we're going to give
a very simple and totally
unsupervised
procedure that we can
use to optimize models for
internal factual consistency.
This is work that
was led by Feyza
Akyürek, along with some
collaborators at BU.
And the basic procedure
is super simple.
We're going to pick
some topic, and we're
going to prompt the language
model to simply write down
everything that it
knows about that topic,
whether or not all of the
stuff that it writes down
is internally consistent.
And once we've done
all of this, we're
simply going to use
the same language
model to look at the set of
facts that got written down,
reason about them globally,
figure out which ones contradict
each other, which
ones entail or provide
supporting evidence
for each other,
and ultimately, identify
the subset of facts that
are both internally
coherent and most likely
on the margin to
actually be true.
And now, really importantly,
this is a very simple task.
It's a much easier
task for the LLM
to perform than generating
the factual knowledge
in the first place.
Even relatively small,
relatively simple models
do a very good job of looking
at a pair of sentences
or a pair of paragraphs and
figuring out whether they
contradict each other.
And this is
essentially all we're
asking the model to do
during the second stage
of this procedure.
But once we've identified
this good subset,
this set of statements
that are likely to be true,
we're simply going to
retrain the language model,
now on its own output, to
assign a higher probability
to that set of statements,
documents, whatever that were
judged upon reflection to be
more likely to be true than not
and to assign lower probability
to those statements that
were judged to be false.
Now, pretty remarkably,
when we take this model,
and we evaluate it now on
some fact checking tasks,
this totally
unsupervised procedure,
which doesn't get any
new factual knowledge
about the world
and just optimizes
for internal
consistency, actually
dramatically improves
these models' performance
when we evaluate them on things
like fact-checking tasks.
So that's models of the world.
What about models of the
self, models of the language
model itself?
Well, if we think
about what went
wrong in this initial example
that we started the talk with,
it was that the model's
confidence in its own outputs,
whether right or
wrong, was too high.
And it turns out
that this is actually
an expected outcome from the
kinds of reinforcement learning
procedures that people
use for training,
sort of reasoning behaviors
in models that we have today.
So what can we do instead?
Well, here-- and this is work
that was led by Mehul Damani
and Isha Puri in collaboration
with some folks from
Yoon's group--
Yoon is going to talk next--
we apply some very old
ideas from decision theory
and just change the function
that we use for scoring language
model outputs so
that we continue
to reward language models
when they produce answers that
are right and express
high confidence,
we penalize them when
they're right, but express
low confidence in
those right answers,
and we reward them more than
we might have done otherwise
when they're wrong, but
also express low confidence
in those wrong answers.
And models trained
in this way, again,
with no data beyond
what we would ordinarily
need to just teach
them all these facts
or skills in the first
place, become much, much
more accurate at
assessing the correctness
of their own answers.
And maybe most
surprisingly, this
is a skill that
actually generalizes.
So when we take these models,
and we now evaluate them
on other problems
different from the ones
that we used to train this
self-reflection behavior
in the first place,
these models continue
to be both more accurate
and better calibrated,
better at knowing when
they're right or wrong
and knowing what they know,
than the kinds of models
that we're able to produce using
standard training techniques.
So where does this leave us?
Taking a step back, research
on language modeling really
for the last decade, and maybe
even going back all the way
to the first language models
that people were training
in the '50s, has been almost
single-mindedly focused
on accuracy, building models
that are really good at giving
the right answer to a question
or guessing what word is going
to come next in a sentence.
But there are many properties
that we might want a model
to have beyond just accuracy.
And coherence, as we've sort
of defined it in this talk,
is only one of them.
I think many of the most
interesting and most important
ones have to do with
thinking about interactions
between language models
and their human users,
and explicitly optimizing not
just for predictive accuracy,
but for good outcomes in
human-AI interactions.
And so when we think
about the future of LLMs,
I think the first step is
really thinking much more
closely about what
we mean when we
say we want these
models to be better,
coming up with a more
general notion of things
that we ought to be
optimizing beyond accuracy
at next token prediction
or question-answering tasks
or whatever, and
figuring out a way
to optimize for these especially
more human-centric objectives,
instead.
And with that, I
will stop there.
Thanks very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi.
Welcome.
My name is Yoon Kim.
I'm a professor at MIT.
I'm working on NLP
and machine learning,
and today I'll be talking to
you about the future of LLM
architectures.
So I think it's
actually worth thinking
about the current,
maybe, AGI recipe that
seems to be driving progress
in the AI research program.
And generally, the recipe
seems to be as follows.
We have data, and then we have
some optimization objective,
and we have a model that's
trained on the data using
this optimization objective.
When it comes to
large language models,
the data is given by
trillions of words of text,
maybe a civilization's
worth of text.
The optimization objective
is essentially a compression.
So it's maximum likelihood
learning, which is basically
compressing the data.
And then we're
using a architecture
called the transformer
to actually perform
this optimization procedure.
And of course, the
rationale is that maybe
through this
optimization procedure,
we're going to have the
architecture of the model
learn the intelligences
that essentially produce
the data, which is the external
world and all the humans that
produce the text on which
the model is trained.
And this is roughly
pre-training.
There are other
bells and whistles.
For example, we often have
reinforcement learning
on top of this to surface
the reasoning capabilities
or have it do what we
want it to do, i.e.
become useful assistants.
And then we also have
search, which is sometimes
called test-time scaling,
where, given this model,
we want to search in
the space of its outputs
to find the outputs that
produce the right answer.
And maybe there's a sense
in which this is enough.
So in some circles, we just
want bigger and bigger models
on larger and larger data sets.
And then, if we do this,
we're going to get to utopia.
So we're going to have Einsteins
on GPUs, world-class biologists
solving problems for us.
And then if you go to some
other circles, you might say,
this is going to lead to end
of civilization if we're not
careful about this.
Now, logically, I don't see--
I think this is
maybe a possibility,
although I don't believe it,
but it's not an impossibility.
But what does seem true
is that the architecture
is a crucial ingredient
in this recipe.
And to motivate this,
I think it's worth
looking at this paper from 2007.
And the title of this paper
is "Large Language Models
in Machine Translation."
And this is a paper from Google.
And if you actually read
the abstract, it says,
"We train a model on
2 trillion tokens,
resulting in a model with
$300 billion n-grams."
So these are
essentially parameters.
So if you actually compare the
recipe that's going on here,
it's actually exactly
the same as the recipe
that we're doing right now.
We have trillions of tokens.
We have a model with hundreds
of billions of parameters.
So it's similar order of scale
with the LLMs that exist today,
and they're employing the
exact same objective, which
is maximum likelihood learning.
And the only difference,
again, is this architecture.
So in 2007, they were
working with lookup tables,
which is an architecture for
a model, a language model.
And then today, we're
working with transformers.
So why didn't we
have ChatGPT in 2007?
And if you look at
this paper, they say,
they get pretty
cool improvements
in machine translation,
but you're not really
talking about end of
civilization or Einsteins
on GPUs.
And it's because of
this architecture.
So I think this is one
motivation, one example that
highlights the importance of
architecture in this AI recipe.
So what is this architecture?
What do transformers look like?
Well, transformers are
basically deep learning models.
And for language, they largely--
the next word
prediction systems.
And the architecture
itself gradually
builds up representations
of the previous context
by what's called an attention
mechanism that contextualizes
the current
representation against
the previous representations.
And in language, you
predict the next word.
And then after you've
predicted the next word,
you feed this as input, and
then you perform this again,
so on and so forth.
And this attention
mechanism and predicting
some future or some
sort of left-out context
given other parts of the input
has been incredibly successful.
And the transformer
architecture and this paradigm
is one of the major drivers
of the current generative AI
revolution, of
course, in language,
but in other domains
like speech, vision,
and even robotics and biology.
And as an example of the
importance of this architecture,
the original paper
that introduced this,
whose title is "Attention
Is All You Need,"
in 2017 is on track to become
one of the most well-cited
papers in computer science,
perhaps all of science.
So are we done?
Have we found the
architecture with a capital A?
Do we just need
to scale this up?
Again, maybe.
I don't think so.
And I think it's
worth looking at,
what are some of the issues
with this architecture?
One issue is the inefficiency.
So I've very, at a
high level, talked
about this attention mechanism.
But this attention
mechanism basically
involves looking back into all
the past at each time step.
So for every time step,
you're looking back
into the full history.
And as we think about applying
these models to long sequences,
you can see how, maybe
intuitively, this attention
mechanism, where
you're looking back
into the full path
at each time step,
quickly gets inefficient
when the sequence length gets
into tens of millions.
And we do want models that
can process and understand
and generate sequences
on this order.
So we want models that
ideally do question answering
over complex code bases,
which can be tens of millions
of lines of code.
Ideally, we want these
models to process sequences
in other domains like biology,
where the sequence length
can quickly get into
millions or even billions.
So that's issue one.
The second issue is
slightly more subtle.
And it's related to
the expressiveness,
in particular, the
inexpressiveness.
So let's consider this simple
setting, where we have something
like box 1 contains a book,
box 2 contains an apple,
box 4 contains a brain.
And let's say you have
a bunch of statements
that swap the boxes.
And then after swapping,
you ask, where is the apple?
So this seems quite simple, but
you can actually show, provably
show, that if the number of
states is greater than five,
a single layer
transformer can't do this.
And this is what's
called state tracking.
And as simple as this--
and maybe as
synthetic as this task
is, these types of state
tracking capabilities
do underlie some of the
real world capabilities
that we want in our models.
So we do want models being able
to understand code where there's
a lot of variable swapping.
And it turns out, at least
a single layer transformer
can't provably do this.
So I think some of
the question that's
driving research in
our group is, are there
transformer alternatives that
are more efficient when it comes
to processing those
long sequences
and also more expressive
and can address
some of the deficiencies of
existing attention mechanism?
And over the past
couple of years,
we've been looking
at this question
through the lens of what
are called linear attention
transformers.
And I won't get
into the details.
And this was a work that
was in 2020, introduced
by some other folks.
But the basic idea
is quite simple.
So we have this
attention mechanism,
which is roughly deriving
pairwise interactions
between all pairs of inputs
and all inputs in a sequence.
And it's doing this with an
expressive non-linearity called
the softmax.
And in linear attention, you
basically get rid of this.
It's actually a
much simpler model.
And it turns out,
when you do this,
you can reformulate this
model as essentially
a recurrent neural
network, but with
matrix-valued
hidden states, which
are different from traditional
vector-valued hidden states
that you're used to.
And this is also the same
thing as state-space models,
for those of you familiar
with works like Mamba.
And because these are
essentially RNNs now,
they inherit the efficiency
benefits of transformer,
a la the ability to
model arbitrarily
long contexts with a fixed
dimensional hidden state memory.
Now, of course, you lose
something in the simplification.
So we've been looking at ways
to make this more expressive.
So one example from
our work last year
was exploring a older
model called DeltaNet,
which is a fancier version
of linear attention
that addresses some of the
limitations of attention
and deriving
efficient algorithms
for training this model
and then also exploring
hybrid architectures
that combine
regular attention with some of
these more expressive variants.
More recently, we
developed something
called log linear
attention, which is actually
in between the linear attention
and full global attention,
where the computational
complexity is in between.
And this, again, addresses
some of the limitations
a la associative recall when it
comes to things like recalling
things in your past.
So what will the future of
LLM architectures look like?
I think, in the
medium term, we're
going to have these
hybrid architectures that
mix these linear attention
models with global attention.
And actually, as
an example of this,
just last week, this
Qwen group from Alibaba
released a state of the
art open-weight model
that exactly mixed some
of the DeltaNet layers
I talked about with attention
layers, and it does very well.
Now, in the longer term, I
think we'll have architectures
where the compute is dynamic.
And what I mean by that
is, current architectures
apply the same amount of
computation at each token.
And in some sense, this
seems incredibly inefficient,
and I think there'll
be interesting things
to do in having the compute be
a dynamic function of the input.
And then I think we'll
also get to inference
optimized architectures, where,
currently, we're really focused
on getting the best
architecture if we have
some amount of training flops.
But there are many
applications, especially when
we think about edge
applications where maybe we
can pay a lot of
training compute,
but the inference
is more optimal.
And I think it's exciting
to think about architectures
that will push the [INAUDIBLE]
frontier of capability
and compute.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Hey.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Phillip.
I'm another faculty
member in EECS,
and I'm going to close out
this LLM session that we
have going on right now.
So I study primarily
computer vision,
but I've recently gotten
interested in language
and come to see vision
and language as being more
alike than they are different.
OK, so we'll come
back to this picture.
This is the cover of a
book about Reading Rainbow,
an old TV show from the '90s.
OK, so if we want to be able to
mix language models with vision
models, then we need to
approach this problem, which
is called the sensory or the
symbol grounding problem.
How do you associate a physical
meaning or a sensory meaning
with a word like apple?
How do you form this association
to the actual image of the apple
or the actual
thing in the world,
the referent of that word?
And this is an old problem.
Philosophers have thought about
this problem for many years.
And a lot of work has been done
in computer vision and language
processing on training models
that can solve this problem.
But one of the really
interesting questions
that we've had
recently is, to what
degree do you actually
have to train the language
model with images?
Could it be possible that
language alone, that text alone,
knows something about
the visual world?
And can we probe
how much it might
know about the visual world?
So could a language model
become knowledgeable
about visual concepts without
ever having seen an image?
That's the question that
we've been pursuing.
And I think actually,
intuitively, the answer
should be yes.
And there's some evidence
for that, like this cover
here, this Reading
Rainbow book, which
was a TV show where
they read books,
and the audience
was supposed to be
imagining all the
interesting scenarios
in great visual detail.
So if I tell you to
open a fantasy novel,
it will talk about the
scaly, green, shiny dragon,
and it will talk
about the prince
with the bright
yellow gold crown.
So these are all visual words.
There's a lot more examples.
When you read a book, you can
imagine what you're seeing.
There's a lot of text which
is visually descriptive.
Here's another famous one.
This is from
Proust's description
of the madeleine dipped in tea.
It's a famous
example because it's
so evocative of that
sensory experience.
"She sent out for one of those
short little plump cookies
called petites madeleines.
And it was a weary and dull
day, a depressing morrow."
These are evocative
of the feeling
of the sensory experience.
"It was a soaked
morsel of cake."
OK, so from text alone,
there's a lot of language
that describes the
visual experience.
So it stands to reason
that, from text alone,
we can learn something
about the visual world.
And in the last
five years or so,
people have been studying this.
So I really like this experiment
from Abdou, et al. on,
what do language models
know about color?
OK, so what they
did is they took
a language model of the era.
It was BERT.
So it's a model that's trained
only on text, no images at all.
And they extracted
the neural embeddings,
the representations that the
language model gives to words.
And then they extracted these
embeddings for color words
and found the
three-dimensional structure
of the embeddings which would
best preserve and explain
the distances that the language
model gives to those words.
And so this is the
language model's embedding
of color words.
And it's really interesting.
It puts green next to green.
That makes sense.
It puts yellow next to yellow.
If you look at the human
perceptual system's organization
of color, the most famous
model of human color perception
is called the
CIELAB color space,
and it's remarkably similar.
So BERT, never
trained on a pixel,
has recovered the same geometry
of color word representation
as humans have for the
corresponding actual perceptual
sensory colors.
OK, so we've been asking
that more broadly recently.
How similar are
the representations
in the language model to the
representations in the vision
model?
If a language model--
or if a vision model
sees an image like
this apple, it
will create a neural
vector representation.
If a language model instead
sees the word apple,
does it create the same vector
embedding or a different vector?
Is it representing the world
in fundamentally the same way
or a different way?
OK, are these the
same or different?
So to run this analysis,
there's a few technical details.
The basic idea is
we're going to measure
the representation in a model
by what is called its kernel.
This is the matrix of how
similar are the representations
for one word, according to the
model, to every other word,
according to the model.
So it's the similarity matrix.
Does the language model
think that-- does it
assign a similar vector for the
word apple to the word orange?
And we can run the same thing
on the vision model applied
to images and say,
does the vision model
think that the similarity
between apple and orange
is the same amount as the
language model thought
the similarity was between the
word apple and the word orange?
So we're looking at if the
language model and the vision
model measure relationships
and distances in the same way.
This is called kernel analysis.
OK, so a paper that we
put out about a year ago
had the following
finding, which is,
we took a lot of language
models, a lot of vision models,
and on the x-axis
is the performance
of the language model.
How good is the language
model at language modeling?
OK, so it will go
from old models
to the more recent models.
And on the y-axis is going to
be the alignment, the similarity
of the language representation
to the image representation
under an image model.
So here's the basic
trend that we found.
As language models get better
at predicting the next word
in sentences, they come
up with representations
of those sentences that are more
and more alike to the kernel
structure, a particular kind of
structure of the vision model
of the corresponding images.
This is run on a data set
of images with captions.
The same is true in
the other direction.
As the vision model becomes
bigger and better at modeling
vision, these curves go up,
and we get better alignment
to language models.
So bigger, better
vision models align more
with bigger, better
language models.
OK, so it seems like there is
some similarity between language
models and vision
models, even if you
don't train them to be alike.
It's just that they're both
modeling the same world,
and, therefore, as they get
better at modeling that world,
they somehow become
more aligned.
But it's not perfect alignment.
The numbers on that last
plot only went up to 0.16
on some scale I'm not going
to tell you the details of,
but it's not perfect.
So what we've also been pursuing
in my group and other groups is,
can we make language models even
more aligned with vision models?
Can we make them
better descriptors
of visual experience?
And I'll just show
you one project
on that where we realized
that if you take an image,
and you caption it with a
language model or a vision
language model, it might output
a very short sentence which
doesn't tell you nearly
enough about this photo
to reconstruct it.
It just says, it's
a cup of coffee.
It doesn't tell you
what colors it is.
So we thought,
what if we instead
train a model to
output text that
is sufficient to
reconstruct the input image?
We call this property
cycle consistency.
You can go from the image
to the text and back.
Now, this was work that was
led by [INAUDIBLE] and Caroline
here.
And they have a
poster on it today,
so please feel free to go
check it out for more details.
But I'll give you
the gist of it.
The gist of it is, we can't
reconstruct this photo
from a short caption that's
not visually descriptive.
I don't know what that cup
of coffee should look like.
If I put that sentence into
an image generative model,
maybe it will make a
cup of coffee like this,
and the background
color is wrong.
The decoration is
wrong on the surface.
OK, so we call those dissimilar,
and we penalize that.
And then we train the captioning
model, the mapping from image
to language, to create a
descriptive-enough caption
that you can reconstruct the
photo almost exactly or decently
well.
Now it gets the pattern and the
colors and the background color.
And now we score this as
being, the input and output
are similar, and the model can
learn from that training signal.
So it outputs text which
is sufficiently informative
to describe the visual
details in the image,
and we get better language
models and better vision models
by doing so.
OK, I'll end with one
more little snippet
of what we're doing
under this magic grant
that we now have a
grant under this program
to work on textbooks that
are augmented with AI.
And this is with Antonio
Torralba and Bill Freeman
and Amy Brand at the MIT Press.
And we're working
on this in part
because we just published
a book on computer vision,
and now we want to use
language models to improve it.
But we really are
interested, especially,
in this problem of improving
the figures and the relationship
between the visual
information in the book
and the underlying code and
text around that information.
So we also today have a
poster on some early results
of this project.
This was run by Suyong Kim.
And what we did is we took
a vision language model,
and-- or she applied
it to this figure
here and asked it, make
an interactive version
of this figure, just
to show you what
can be done already with
fairly off-the-shelf methods.
OK, and so here's the result.
So there's a little interaction.
She's going back and forth
a bit to modify the code.
But basically, this model
can parse the imagery.
It can output HTML and CSS
and other types of web code
that will generate a web page
with this interactive version
of that figure.
So that's one of the things
that we're pursuing currently
under this grant.
So to wrap up, I'll say, what
do LLMs know about vision?
That's the question
that I've been asking.
And I think it's quite a lot.
It's more than a lot
of people expected,
more than I expected-- not
everything, but quite a lot.
So LLMs trained on internet
text naturally learn
representations that
are, to some degree--
to a surprising
degree, to me-- aligned
with visual representations.
They might not be that
fundamentally a way
of processing the world.
By optimizing for better
alignment between vision
and language and potentially
other modalities like sound,
we can get better multimodal
foundation models.
And as one application that
we're looking at right now,
we can potentially
augment figures
in textbooks with AI
features like interactivity.
OK, I will end there.
And thank you for listening.
[APPLAUSE]