uh my name is sh from happily. We're the
magic behind happy High performing
culture over the past 10 years we've
been trying to figure out how to really
change organizational culture um we were
built on found foundational research at
MIT and people analytics where we found
that there were real patterns that just
showed us that people relationships
strong relationships were just at the
heart of all the um you know great
organizational health and also great
organizational performance and there's
also ample research that shows us that
companies with great culture just
outperform their peers by a very very
large margin um the problem however with
culture is that it's not very tangible
and it's very hard to measure and
because of this um all organizations uh
are just paying these hidden costs from
the very top of the organization where
you have CEOs that struggle to really
get alignment they spend more time
explaining their decisions than actually
trying to you know drive drive things
home we have middle managers who are
reacting to problems as firefighters
more than anything else and then we have
employees who you know when they joined
yesterday they take forever to really
build the the right relationships to
understand how things work here and
really understand their role and how
that aligns with organization purpose
and that's where culture comes in and
without this we have employee turnover
um rising and we have absenteeism and
and disengagement that plagues
organizations that's where happily comes
in we've built natively into our
platform Three core compon components
first is analytics where we have the
most fine grained people analytics in
the world getting realtime reliable data
on people secondly we use technology
like AI to really power um how we
understand people within organizations
and help them and finally we buildt this
behavioral change engine where we are
able to take feedback turn them into
insights and turn them into nudges
almost instantaneously and driving
behavioral change in a very powerful way
through Empirical research we found that
there were four main capabilities that
we need to bring into organizations to
really move culture in a very measurable
and and positive way the first of which
is creating psychological safety our
people science and our Behavioral
Science really Powers new ways to create
this openness and transparency within
organizations where people can share
their problems and opportunities in a
safe way secondly we've used AI to
develop human skills and emotional
intelligence in a measurable way uh
skills empathy and self-awareness that
sometimes are lacking more today than
ever we are also making active in their
roles today managers bleed and make
decisions mainly using intuition that
fails us even harder when we're not
working in person while now we have data
to help us make more informed and
precise decisions to support our teams
and finally what we didn't realize would
be so important but now is the pillar of
all is uh turning company values into
behaviors that drive daily actions and
decisions and these values become the
direction in which your culture
changes what we've done is we've
gamified the product so it's something
that people want to use every day um
it's led to this really sticky Hab
behavior that drives powerful habits so
today we have very high adoption rates
that lead to really powerful outcomes
and because we're able to create this
real meaningful feedback loop that
people want to participate in
organizations have a whole new way to
understand their people and their
organizational Health imagine having
Google analytics but about your people
so you know how happy everybody is you
know how engaged they are you know who
your impactful people are um just by
looking at the behaviors and and and and
the algorithms that we've built around
understanding people more effectively uh
with less bias as
well um the outcomes that we've been
able to produce um um over um the past
10 years have been on many many
different metrics and skills where along
creating great adoption we're able to
improve employee Satisfaction by in a
very very big way on average by 48
points on the emps scale um a operations
unit in a large luxury uh retailer was
able to go
from using employee listening surveys at
negative3 emps within a year they're at
positive 84 um a score so high that they
got call a call from HQ because they
thought the data was measured
incorrectly uh we're also able to
improve something as fundamental as
employee well-being and just showing
that there are different shapes of
change that can happen we these are
sample of four companies that we work
with and the change the distribution of
well-being scores before and after them
using happily uh we can uh increase
while being by as much as
37% um and the different variances here
are what we found is that it's dictated
one by the initial state of
psychological safety within the
workplace and two how responsive
marriages are
um and our partnership ask is that we're
looking to work with CEOs and HR leaders
who want to take culture to the next
level using wheel uh quality data our
ideal pilot is a 50 to 100 person
company or business units and so we have
um if you connect us with CEOs um and or
chief people officers or chro of
innovative Enterprise companies we'd be
very grateful thank you so
much thanks so much tarf great to know
so um tell us a little more about how AI
is used by happily.
AI sure um so you know starting about
eight to 10 years ago our AI was first
used to help us predict things and we
knew that a person was going to probably
leave the organization at enough
certainty we can proactively um help
retain them uh now it's we're using it
for a lot more we use generative AI to
improve the quality of feedback we're
also using it as a skill development and
learning tool as well
great and tell us a little more on how
you work with a corporate what the
onboarding is like and so on sure so
we're based in Thailand so we work with
companies across the world um primarily
in Asia but also now in the US um and
other parts as well um onboarding is
relatively light it takes less than two
weeks to really get started uh with a
platform like happily um and Within
These two weeks we're basically learning
more about the organization their goals
and their values so that we can tune our
Ai and also so configure um the
questions and and and the interactions
to make it
fit okay thank you so much again tar
thank you to learn there as well