um hello everyone um it's great to be
here so my name is Ashish Kapur I did
did my PhD at MIT in 2006 um since then
I have spent 17 years at Microsoft
research and then uh took my research
group out to found scaled
foundations um you know we are a group
of very passionate robotic roboticist
some of them you know very very um
accomplished machine learning and AI
engineers and u over the course of last
decade or so we have founded some
foundational Technologies um in robotics
at the intersection of deep machine
learning large language models and uh
and robots so the specifically our
insight has been is every single robot
AI startup right now is struggling
because of lack of expertise lack of
infrastructure and in general
fragmentation of the robotic tooling you
know everyone is waiting for this Chad
GPT moment of Robotics and what we have
realized and after working almost a
decade in this field is that first we
need pyo equalent of Robotics so
consequently what we bring to the market
is a system called grid which stands for
General robot intelligence development
platforms essentially it is every robots
AI team if you go and look at any
Enterprises academic groups startups you
know government Labs behind behind every
single robot that's operational there is
a team of AI scientists researchers and
developers that is trying to make it
work and in fact it should be the
opposite so what we figured out that you
actually need an infrastructure that can
um that can replace and account for all
of this manual work that's going after
uh you know manual work that's going in
to build these robotic infrastructures
so specifically what grid is grid is
your collection of AI models simulation
data generation pipelines Cloud
infrastructures as well as Edge
deployment infrastructure so that you
can run as fast as possible as an
Enterprise to go and land robot AI I
will give you a very specific example um
you know recently there have been many
many startups that have raised hundreds
and hundreds of millions of dollars they
are spending essentially 18 months to 24
months 18 18 to 24 months just to go and
build this infrastructure that now we
are bring to the market for every
aspiring robot AI Enterprise I will you
know show a couple of customer studies
so specifically Royal Dutch Shell you
know they have more than 50 Robot use
cases that they need to deploy on their
infrastructure including oil and energy
gas pipelines um you know it's it's a
small team of 10 roboticist which is uh
scattered throughout the world and there
is no way they can go and accomplish the
these many robot robot tasks so when
they saw grid they were immediately sold
and basically they were able to land
many of these proof of Concepts the
initial prototypes of their robotic
tasks within a few months as opposed to
many many years that they have been you
know they have been trying to land those
things in similarly another another
example is rain. Arrow is a startup that
we work with in California and they are
trying to do autonomous
firefighting um you know when we spoke
to them they are a well capitalized
company but they AI team the AI robotics
team is only two people and between them
one of them was trying to scavenge AI
model from hug and face another was
trying to bootstrap off uh you know
gazebo simulator you know between those
two they were really really stretch thin
again enter grid as soon as grid was
there you know their acceleration in
terms of Landing autonomy in terms of
developing AI for robots just just was
um um you know immen
so in essence what grid is it's every
robots AI engineering team you know my
ask to all of you is that if you know of
groups Enterprises startups you know
research teams that are struggling with
Landing AI on robots please connect them
to me I do believe that we can help them
run faster in the end you know the
problem with robotics is is not that um
you know it's a hard problem the problem
with robotics really is that the tooling
is really fragmented and they are not
enough experts right now to land this uh
you know as fast as we want right with
that I'll conclude thank you very much
thank you Ashish so touching on that um
on how Enterprises can run faster can
you tell us a little more about that and
how your technology actually works
absolutely so um grid is a collection of
softwares that we distribute as
containers so as a robot Enterprise if
you have inuring team who have already
built some infrastructure we can
interface with them very straight very
straightforward manners in in using
cloud apis and with those apis you get
the power of you know pre-trained as
well as um you know uh fine-tunable AI
models for your use cases in robotics be
It Slam be it object detection be it
computer vision be it control we can
pretty much uh take take care of all of
those and what other areas in robotics
are you focusing on yeah so we have a c
you know our strength was aerial robots
that's where was uh you know where we
started but since then last week we we
announced integration with uh with uh
Nvidia Isaac so now we are also going
into humanoids manipulation arms as well
as uh quadrupeds so we do are covering a
wide spectrum of of of robots of course
our biggest strength and Leadership is
in aial
robots thank you very much aish thanks