thanks Ben thanks for having me and
excited certainly to talk about our work
here uh as Ben mentioned my name's John
Leu uh my background really is uh first
physics mechanical engineering and
started to Pivot towards issues in
manufacturing uh during my post-doctoral
work and at this point um I teach
mechanical engineering at MIT and I
specifically lead a group that tackles
issues in learning engineering my group
we are using design principles to solve
challenges in learning to essentially
meet nextg learning uh issues in stem
competencies and we do that essentially
through three thrusts uh one uh we're
looking at new learning Technologies how
do we develop and design arvr everyone
is doing that these days but how do we
do that in a thoughtful way uh to
actually scale and enhance stem pedagogy
uh number two digital learning so my
group actually manages the uh Department
of mechanical engineering's portfolio on
Mass of open online courses and then
three which is really what I'll be
focusing on today uh is we're working on
future generation uh stem Workforce so
let's go there let's go there now I
usually like to start with some high big
picture data uh what you're seeing here
is manufacturing productivity over time
um actually from Ben Armstrong's work
here uh what you're seeing here is peer
groups um like EU Germany Japan uh
really increasing in productivity in the
past few decades what you see on the Y
AIS is value added per employee and
Manufacturing firms across countries and
groups and the US is in purple uh We've
stagnated over the past one plus decade
and this is quite a big uh of of a
concern now we know that a primary
driver of uh productivity is technology
adoption so we could take a step further
and take a look at uh what are firms
doing to adopt Technologies and and and
to what extent they're doing that so
again what you're seeing on the y axis
is uh robots installed per 10,000
employees it's a little hard to quantify
adoption of digital Technologies or iot
Technologies but we can count robots on
a floor and so you're seeing again um
peers like Germany or Japan you know the
kind of typical players that you'd
expect and the US is all the way down
here at number 10 uh not only is that
concerning but also by density it's uh
less than a third of the
leader and so this uh certainly begs uh
the the the the the question you know we
know that advanced Manufacturing
Technologies you know from robotics to
digital production it can transform the
factory but it definitely requires uh
kind of worker to implement it uh the
issue is these people need to integrate
Technologies uh new technologies into a
current system so often you have a bunch
of Legacy equipment that you might want
to bring in a new piece of equipment
there's never uh kind of transformation
overnight and so one has to understand
in order to integrate new technology one
has to understand a larger picture uh
systems level so how do you drive techn
technological advances and drive that
Innovation and when I speak to firms
many companies say hey I wish Engineers
had Hands-On skills I wish technicians
had analytical
skills uh and it begs the question do we
actually just need a new kind of worker
not to just run the machine but to
integrate the system and Al integrate
these Technologies and that kind of new
worker I'm calling the technologist and
so we set out to test this hypothesis uh
when we interviewed over 30 firms in New
England manufacturing companies who are
involved um that we were connected with
and what we're doing here is we're
taking BLS uh tasks task definitions uh
in engineering from the bureau labor of
statistics and we're asking companies
one do you see this gap between
technicians and engineers and if so uh
look at these engineering tasks which
ones would you actually want uh
technologist to do on the floor and what
we're finding here is companies are
saying that they wish that they had a
technologist someone in that bridge
occupation to be able to analyze
performance of systems equipment to
determine operational methods to analyze
data to improve operations to monitor
these operations on a meta kind of meta
summary it's someone with strong
analytical skills someone who can
identify areas to increase efficiency or
productivity someone who can communicate
uh both up and down and now these might
look like familiar engineering
competencies but the point here is this
is someone who's on the shop floor
someone who is in the technical
Workforce and so the takeaway here is
really that advanced manufacturing
requires workers with both the
technician's Practical knowhow
understanding the equipment and the
actual process and an engineering's
comprehension of processes and
systems now of course that begs the
question well okay but how do we
actually Dev Vel this kind of Workforce
uh we want to be able to get to Advanced
manufacturing but to get there uh to
develop this kind of Workforce we
actually have to address a primary
challenge in advanced manufacturing
Workforce Development namely that
advanced manufacturing impacts Workforce
by reducing the shelf life of technical
skills so if you want to be serious
about getting a Workforce that can do
Advanced manufacturing we have to be
able to be serious about tackling this
challenge now to kind of intro this
concept here or the challenge one could
kind of summarize how we treat
conventional manufacturing training uh
using this old adage give a man a fish
feed him for a day train a man to fish
eat them for a lifetime and that kind of
summarizes how we've been approaching
how to train our manufacturing Workforce
in the past 00 years plus the problem is
if you extend this analogy to Advanced
manufacturing it's really more like this
person needs to fish this year and hunt
deer in two and trop Lobster in five
years and the question is if you knew
this a priority would you actually train
or educate your Workforce in the same
way now in the first case uh when you
are going to be uh fishing your entire
life it makes sense let's just focus on
the fishing skills uh how to how to work
with your tackle or your bait but in the
in the right hand case in advanced
manufacturer when your game is changing
it might not make sense to pick up a
skill set and throw it out and pick up
another skill set in this case it might
actually make sense to take a step back
and think about what are the principles
that underg all of these activities even
if they do change that don't change no
matter uh which year you're in no matter
which generation you're in in that case
maybe the why of uh of game and hunting
and in this case may perhaps in this
analogy perhaps it would be something
around animal sense for example how do
you take advantage of animal senses to
bait how do you take advantage of animal
senses to hide from these animals and so
well it turns out that in manufacturing
in the past two decades uh here at MIT
we've been able to distill a set of
principles in manufacturing uh that are
so core to manufacturing they actually
don't change these are what we would
call the wise why of manufacturing
namely that regardless of which industry
or company you always have to understand
the concepts of flow and variation along
four levels and the levels are
manufacturing processes systems Supply
and people and it doesn't matter whether
you're in 1800's printing press or you
are in uh 2050 you will always have to
be able to manage flow and variation
along these levels and in fact this is
how we teach our Master students at MIT
namely the masters of engineer
engineering and advanced manufacturing
design and five years ago I help helped
stand up a program called the
micromasters which takes this these set
of principles and classes turns it into
an online program when we were targeting
Professional Engineers and to this date
we've at this point enrolled over
200,000 uh unique Learners across the
globe so we know that these principles
are actually incredibly powerful in the
in the industry and the question is does
it make sense then to use this to be
able to educate the rest of the
workforce right not just Master's level
but folks who don't have University
degree
and so this is our curriculum uh uh kind
of design where we have essentially a
hub and spoke model in the hub is what I
just talked about the process the system
the the supply the people that's the
part that doesn't change that's the why
of manufacturing and around that we can
structure what we call the spokes that's
the how of manufacturing digital
manufacturing and additive manufacturing
microelectronics those things are
specific to companies they are specific
to a generation robotics in 2024 will be
different than robotics in 2030 and so
our approach here then is to empower the
workforce by educating on that critical
thinking why the things that don't
change and then link it to The Cutting
Edge how this the things that are
changing and so if your Workforce
actually knows uh and understands the
why then they're not tied to a piece of
equipment when a new one when you're
interested in integrating something else
they can continue to operate effectively
if you're not tied to recipes you might
be able to think about how might
something be done differently how might
something be done better you might be
able to think through trade-offs and
then if you're not just tied to being
told what to do you might be able to
make recommendations or contribute to
decision making and so we see that this
is a Broadway to empower really the
larger part of the manufacturing
Workforce those without University
degrees and you might be wondering okay
great what does that person actually do
um these are more operational level uh
definitions of the tasks we would
imagine a technologist do like detecting
and analyzing changes and problems in
operations uh employing design of
experiments for process optimization uh
even making recommendations based on
their understanding of how a process can
be pushed making recommendations back to
the design team hey you can make this
well thinner or you can actually change
this parameter here and etc etc
optimizing flow through systems and so
turns out that industry mapping really
works very well these these in priority
competencies really map very well to our
Hub and spoke
model now we see this technologist not
just as a connector in operations I've
already mentioned that they could Bridge
tasks between technicians and Engineers
but also along three other levels one
one could imagine a star technician
becoming a star technologist and then
after year more education a star
technolog is becoming a star engineer
and so uh can we provide and create a
new career pathway in manufacturing
that's formalized uh and also companies
are seeing that well I'm paying my
technician 20 plus I'm paying my
engineering 40 plus perhaps there's also
a wage Gap that we can fill using this
technologist role to be able to connect
these uh different roles and education
often is disjoint we have uh associate
degrees being offered by community
colleges we have University degrees Rees
uh that are four-year programs usually
if someone with an associates degree
wants to do a bachelor's degree they
have to start completely over but I have
universities in New England who are
saying hey if MIT offers this program
people take it in a community college I
want to offer Credit in my four-year
engineering technology degree and so we
can connect in education as well and the
final thing is our dissemination
Partners namely community colleges in
the area are serving areas that are in
rural areas or have high levels of
poverty and so we can Bridge or connect
opportunities as
well this is just a a sample uh uh of
what the kinds of uh the kind of
manufacturing Workforce training system
that I'm planning on creating uh we will
be launching in the fall of 2025 but you
can see a number of different uh
community colleges interspersed through
Massachusetts Rhode Island and
Connecticut and we're currently focused
on Aerospace and defense and also uh
submarine industrial
base uh for more for more uh you know I
published in a National's Journal policy
facing uh earlier this year we where we
make uh kind of a larger argument for
this new occupation the technologist so
feel free to take a look and then on the
right hand side that's just more
information from MIT news on the project
itself so thanks so much for your time
and uh happy to take any questions
John it looks like that we have a
question in the chat how how can you
split each of the principles I I think
that um they might be referring to the
hub principles uh saying they're they're
too wide was was the comment
so can you can you go in a little more
depth into the Hub definitely absolutely
so um what we're really interested in is
you know what kinds of information and
insights are available on the shop floor
that someone uh who is in shop floor
operations can actually take advantage
of right so we have companies who are
saying hey I have you know my star
technician or Star operator I want to
promote them to become a sell leader um
or a shift leader but I have no way of
getting them there right now they just
like I just promote them and the next
day they have this hat uh what kinds of
technical skills are actually actionable
on the shop floor so for manufacturing
processes what we're doing is we are
starting to give them a basic set of
statistical process control and
troubleshooting for processes so on
statistical process control we're
looking at uh creating run charts we're
looking at design of experiments anovas
linear and nonlinear regression things
that you know these technicians and
operators they're looking at the process
every single day they should be the ones
who can inform the engineers hey these
are ways that our process could be
refined but they don't have the skill
set yet right and so we want to be able
to give them a basic engineering skill
set to do that on the system side and
I'll just choose these two as as
examples on the system side um you know
one could say uh you know I think our
technicians are so tied to a piece of
equipment but there's really Concepts
around flow uh troubleshooting uh around
uh identifying bottlenecks how do we
alleviate those and so that is a big
piece I think that we're looking at
these folks were involved with the flow
of of product and components through the
line they don't really actually
understand how a system works and how we
can optimize it um and so that's that's
how I would you know a couple examples
on a little bit more detail around those
uh principles certainly and it also
seems like there's there's the advantage
I I I think about it from an employers
perspective why would you send one of
your operators for example to this
program what you know conrete value
would they um would they experience and
I think one is just being able to
interact more efficiently with the
engineering team if they're um currently
don't really have the language to to
have certain conversations about you
analyzing the data that are coming off
the off the line this could really you
know lead them to more added value the
the another question that comes through
uh there's someone in the audience who's
amazed that you don't reference
generative AI as a mentoring coaching
tutoring tool I I'm not amazed for a
variety reasons but I I wonder what your
perspective on on using generative AI as
part of your teaching is um irrespective
of using it on the factory floor yeah I
mean I I think there's a lot of very
interesting work uh right now being done
in gen I think a lot of it is still
pretty early and somewhat untested um I
think there are there is some work uh
that's being done around using course
materials to train llms uh one of the
issues I think that we're concerned
about is certainly hallucination ations
and when you're on the manufacturing
floor and you get a hallucination uh you
know you're trained in a particular way
uh because these are situations where
safety comes an issue we're very kind of
hyper sensitive uh to incorrect guidance
and so we're going to be a little bit
more careful I think when it comes to
implementing gen um that said you know I
I'm not presenting on this but we have
another work where we're designing an
intelligent tutoring system in order for
you know workers to learn psychomotor
skills so that's something that we're
working on but I don't think it's ready
for roll out uh next year right this is
like a re these are research projects
what I'm presenting here is this will be
a live program in a
year yeah and I just think about the
some of the highest performing
manufacturers and how they train their
workers they train them to do a process
analog first before they train them how
to operate automated systems I think
about BMW's um early Factory in um in
South Carolina they they already knew
how to do to to run an automated Factory
but they didn't introduce the automation
until the workers knew how to um you
know understand the processes without
the automation uh introduced and I feel
like that's the Hub before you learn
about robotics you're learning about the
Hub and the core uh kind of Timeless um
art of manufacturing absolutely yeah and
that's really what this is about like I
this is why often I'll shy away from the
word Workforce training because I think
training is very much on the how like
how do you operate a piece of equipment
whereas we're very much interested in
principles and conceptual understanding
and Analysis here so I would consider
this more on the education side which I
think MIT is much better Set uh set up
to do yeah and and you know I I find
this all very exciting I think it
responds to a real need that we hear um
that we hear about from employers and
you've been working on this now for for
years and you're going to deploy it in
Fall 2025 what's your biggest concern or
the biggest risk you think about with
deploying this project you know what are
you what really needs to come together
for it to succeed that you're not really
sure is there
yet uh that's a really
interesting uh that's a really
interesting question Ben I think there's
uh maybe two things that that come up to
mind um one is we are trying to take
you know this this this thing is a
essentially it's a on the education side
it's this big experiment on can we
actually take grad
level uh material from
MIT uh and and adapt it so that we can
educate folks without a University
degree without understanding of calculus
without exposure to statistics uh can we
kind of embed all of what you need to
understand just as we're posing problems
in the program uh and a context or
situation and so you know we flip the
pedagogy so that right you know
University level pedagogy often you are
introducing math concepts first and then
like in week 10 you're applying them um
in our program we are doing the reverse
like we present them with uh your line
is down or like your parts are out of
spec what are you going to do and we
time it so that every single week uh we
are they're just picking up the math
tool or the technique that they need to
solve that problem and obviously the
tools and the techniques and the
problems become more and more advanced
but it is a big experiment on our end
because we are you know kind of tying
from uh you know grad level courses that
usually have a pretty deep understanding
on the math like the Manufacturing
Systems the MIT version of Manufacturing
Systems like you are learning Markov
chains by week two um so like how do we
translate that material so that someone
like a I think in theory it sounds
simple like oh just you know then they
just need to use the tools uh but I
think in practice to be able to create
something uh that is we're very much in
the weeds there I think another one is
just the interactions with companies so
like when a company wants to send right
now this is a Clos enrollment program
and what I what I mean by that is we're
not going to just give this to a
community college for them to offer to
anyone we're only going to launch this
program if there are companies in that
region around a community College who
are saying we are going to send enough
employees to fill out the cohort namely
15 students per cohort and I think the
interesting thing the challenge will be
to work with these companies to see can
they actually fully utilize a
technologist like perhaps their
operations really are more on
conventional models that aren't
interested in technology adoption maybe
they're interested in like a Delta a
small Delta in in productivity but all
of a sudden they have a technologist who
like understands these principles and
wants to integrate technology how do we
work with this company to kind of shift
the conversation and you know that's a
larger conversation then it's not just
how do we use this technology uh
technologist but it's an organizational
conversation you know it's it's also
about risk and investment and so I would
I would anticipate that's a longer term
conversation but it's certainly you know
one of the challenges that we're looking
forward to engaging in well John that's
the perfect segue to what I'm going to
talk about so this uh it's a than and
and I do think
your your first comment that this is
really a leap of faith in um in workers
who have a ton of untapped talent and
skills and you're opening them up you're
you're essentially saying welcome to to
MIT even though you might not have a
college degree welcome to an MIT
graduate curriculum and then the
question is will employers actually make
use of the of the untapped talent and
skills that you're trying to cultivate
so I I I it's a very exciting experiment
I think it has a ton of promise and uh
if anyone is is uh in the audience who's
interested in learning more um feel free
to I think to reach out and I'm not sure
if you're expanding your network of
employers quite yet but um but I think
it's always good to get more uh employer
interest
absolutely
great okay we're we're moving right
along thank you John I thought that was
a a terrific um kickoff to the morning