really it's a pleasure to be here to
tell you about the research that's going
on in my academic laboratory at the
broad Institute and as well because we
work on so many collaborations you'll
hear a little bit about what's going on
in other labs that we're collaborating
with and you'll see a few examples of
startups that have launched from this
kind of work so let's get started I'm
going to talk today I know everyone here
has different background some some uh
most I guess biotech um but some AI my
work is computational but as you'll see
everything is is quite grounded in
application to the pharmaceutical
industry so um first of all I'm guessing
most of you are familiar with at least
one of these two laws um moris law which
is just this mindblowing uh success of
human technology human Ingenuity has
allowed compute to get cheaper and
cheaper and then the very depressing
AR's law just sort of the opposite where
discovering new medicines is just really
challenging and um we're all aware of
this even outside the Pharma industry
you're aware of um how uh how many
diseases go uncured and how expensive
medications are to develop so uh there's
been significant enthusiasm maybe AI can
get us out of this pickle maybe AI can
help us to um increase the speed of
identifying new drugs and I think when
we say Ai and Drug Discovery it covers
so many different potential um steps in
the pathway we just heard about an
excellent one um and so I want to talk
about a very specific uh type of
Technology that's being applied to a lot
of different steps and the most of the
work I'll talk about it's sort of free
open source technology um available to
anyone to to use and um so can data help
us make predictions to accelerate drug
Discovery I understand some don't have
the the same background as others so
just very briefly let's get back to
First principles um the only way we
really know if a drug is going to work
is if we take compound give it to a
diseased human and end up with a healthy
human however we cannot do these
experiments and we've seen today some
great examples of assay systems that try
to uh mimic a human environment or an
organ system or some kind of a a
biological assay system that mimics the
the capability here so we try to come up
with these approximations right we try
to come up with some kind of a system in
a in a dish whether it involves
micropolitics or co-culture systems or
um some kind of a system that represents
the disease as best we can get while
still maintaining some amount of high
throughput capability some amount of
ability to test lots of samples so if we
can miniaturize an assay or if we can
get the the reagents and the equipment
to be cheap enough then we can um in an
assay system like this then we can scale
it up to test lots and lots of samples
and so what I'll talk about today most
of the projects involve High throughput
screening where we are creating some
some kind of biological system testing
it in very high throughput each of the
samples in the teeny little Wells of
these 384 well plates involves um cells
growing with some kind of um addition
either drug or a genetic perturbation or
maybe a different patient uh cell line
and so in each well we have a different
sample and we do hrut microscopy robotic
microscopes that capture images because
the bottom of these plates is clear so
we have a microscope peeking up through
the bottom IM ing the cells and saying
how did these cells respond to this drug
how did these cells respond to this
genetic perturbation and so on so my
work has focused largely on image
analysis and we we write this open
source software that's used now
throughout the Pharma and and biotech
Industries for high throughput image
analysis and 20 years ago this was a
very unsolved problem uh today I'm happy
to say that just about any kind of um uh
cell-based system where you can see what
you're looking for it's usually pretty
solvable by image analysis software
today whether it's it's cell profiler
which has some deep learning
capabilities as well or any number of of
other kinds of um algorithms that are
out there it's a pretty well solved
problem that images um uh with
particular phenotypes can be uh analyzed
in an automated uh quantitative kind of
way so that's been very powerful for all
kinds of assay systems um in the in the
world and once you've identified the
different components of a cell that
you're interested in then measuring them
becomes very trivial so the basis of my
work that I'll describe today um it's a
little bit abstract but it relies on the
fact that we are just measuring all
kinds of information out of every single
cell and every image that we're that
we're analyzing here so measure
everything is kind of the Mantra we can
measure thousands of features of cells
that include some of the obvious things
you would think of like you know how how
big is the nucleus how how squiggly EDG
how how squiggly are the edges of the
cytoplasm and so on but they can also be
more esoteric things like various
texture measures and um and intensity
and correlation
relationships um so uh my lab over the
past two decades has been focused on
helping biologists around the world um
and and in the broad Community the MIT
Harvard Community to screen all the
things um so each of these examples I
won't go into detail but the long story
short is each of these represents some
kind of a disease some kind of a
biological mechanism and can we automat
ially quantify the difference between
the cells or worms in in some of these
cases that um have a particular disease
versus U maybe treated with a drug to
reverse that type of a disease and so
these are all different examples showing
this sort of uh process and this work
has had clinical impact so these are
just two examples of some clinical
trials that have been successful based
on using image analysis to either
identify drugs in the first case or in
the second case I I wasn't involved in
this experiment directly but they used
our software in order to identify
whether a given patient very
personalized medicine will this one
patient respond to any of these dozens
of drugs that we might give them and is
there going to be a good
response so uh those projects that I
just described were were generally um a
biologist had an assay system in mind
they had a phenotype in mind they had an
idea of if I could only measure this
thing then I can potentially cure my
disease of Interest what we'll talk
about for the the whole rest of the talk
is this one level more abstract where we
use images instead as a data source and
we say okay you have cells growing in a
dish you could you could count how many
green cells are there how how big are
they um do they have squiggly edges or
not um but what if we don't know what
we're looking for what if we don't know
what um what is going to best represent
a disease and um and perhaps even if we
do know maybe there's more in the images
that we could Leverage do really
interesting things with so this is this
concept is called image-based profiling
is very similar to transcriptional
profiling or proteomics um and the idea
is you have lots of measurements lots of
samples let's look at the patterns of
those samples to tell us something
important about biology okay it's a
little abstract let's make it concrete
with some individual stories and this is
you know simplified version of the drug
Discovery Pipeline and let's see if we
can um figure out whether we can use
images to identify signatures of disease
when we don't know what those might look
like and then and then find drugs so the
first example comes from actually the
University of Utah I wasn't involved in
these original studies but the
researchers there studied cerebral
cavernous malformation and uh they
thought well this is a relatively easy
disorder you knock out this Gene you get
the disease very simple um genetics and
they thought well let's knock down this
Gene CCM in cells and see if we see a
difference as you can very well see um
you don't need to know anything about
biology or image analysis okay there's a
difference here and what's lovely about
this kind of an assay is once you see a
difference and once the computer can
quantify it then it's pretty
straightforward to take cells that are
in the diseased State and ask Let's test
drugs one by one are there any that can
reverse this um unhealthy State and try
to make it healthy again that's really
the concept that is at play here and
although in this case it's completely
obvious to our what the difference is
you can easily now imagine I hope well
wait a second if we can do this for this
one particular disorder with this one
gene why not do it for all the all the
disorders and all the genes maybe some
of them won't be so visibly obvious but
we can take the same strategy and that's
what led to the founding of recursion
Pharma um one of the major Tech bios um
that is now public and this is exactly
the strategy they began with and now
have hundreds and hundreds of disorders
that they've attacked in this way in
order to find drugs that that can um
reverse disorders so five clinical
trials uh more than that now um and some
of them starting to read out um in the
in the field so very exciting what I
think is a really neat aspect of this
academic study that launched this uh
trajectory is that the um drugs that
were chosen by the automated analysis of
the images even for a very obvious
phenotype like this they actually
outperformed those that were chosen by
experts looking at images and so I I
love that that they bothered to do that
side by-side comparison and the ones
chosen by the computer are the ones that
succeeded Downstream and eventually are
now in the in the clinical
trials okay that's one way to identify a
disease is to knock out a gene that is
known to be causative to for a disorder
but not all Gene diseases are that
simple many of them involve very complex
genetics and metabolic disease is is
absolutely one in this category Molina
clausnitzer is a researcher at the the
Bro Institute and she is focused on
metabolic disease and had the idea well
she can't just go knock out the one gene
that causes diabetes there's many
potentials and there's all kinds of um
interactions at a genetic level but what
she could do is take cell lines from
patients that either have a high or low
risk for developing metabolic disease in
their lifetime so this higher low risk
is is designated by a polygenic risk
score so sequence your whole genome
figure out are you at high or low risk
of having metabolic disease take a
number of patient cell lines with and
without the the risk and look to see if
there's a difference again you know
quite obvious here visually and and
there's quantification behind it as well
but our ey of course we see very
dramatic differences in the lipid
droplets these green blobs but
interestingly there's also quite a
difference in the actin um cyto
cytoskeleton of the cells that can
distinguish these two um diseased versus
non- diseased populations they've gone
on to do all kinds of very interesting
work using this basic model system and
Molina is um is working to launch a
company focused on using this basic
approach to start doing drug screening
for metabolic disease which is otherwise
extremely um difficult here you have
very foundational um genetic
underpinnings um that that really tie
the the target Discovery ultimately to
um to human genetics which I think is a
really neat aspect of what she's
doing all right and now the Third Way um
to find a difference between diseased
and healthy cells and back in my own lab
is uh a collaboration with moty at the
University of Toronto so his uh this is
this project I'll describe is the is the
work of a single graduate student so
that gives you a sense of the scale she
tested 3,500 variants that are
associated with human disorders and for
each one look to see can I find a
phenotype that is a drug screenable PHA
type so 3500 it's incredible scale but
Theo approach is quite straightforward
she took for each variant Express the
normal version of that protein in cells
and it's Tagged so you can see where
where that protein is normally located
this is a gene called lz1 you don't need
to know anything about what that protein
does what its normal function is all
we're doing is looking where is it in
the cell and if you express that same
protein but with a mutation that causes
a human disorder you can see sometimes
there is a change in the localization
again don't need to know anything about
the disorder but what I want to draw a
parallel here consider that a a human
pediatrician is looking at a a child's
face I would look at this child and say
oh they pretty typical to me but a
pediatrician is very trained to
understand uh what are the features of a
face that can tell you ah this kid
actually has this disorder in the same
way um we don't need to be quite so
skilled to see there's a very obvious
difference in the localization of this
protein and just as the structure of the
face can indicate a disorder the
structure of the cells is also
indicating a disorder so now that we've
got this phenotype associated with a
disease we can now do drug screens to
reverse the phenotype and and we can
also do genetic perturbations to find
potential targets or Pathways so she
tested 3500 variants only 250 of them
had uh disease phenotypes it's around
16% of the pathogenic um variants you
might think 16% is a small percentage
but when you're considering um all the
diseases in the world and finding a a a
screenable phenotype this is something
that people often spend um years and
decades trying to identify for a single
disorder to so to find 250 in the course
of your PhD thesis is is pretty
remarkable um and we have an even uh an
even bigger scale project coming along
where we're testing 80,000 variants so
we'll have thousands of these disease
phenotypes and that creates a new
bottleneck we would love to do a drug
screen for each one of these each one of
these disease phenotypes represents a
population of patients who in in the
vast majority of cases these are rare
disorders that we tested here have no
medicines whatsoever so we would love to
do a drug screen for each of these
patient groups but in an academic
environment we can not afford to do 250
uh at once and that leads us to like
let's fix this bottleneck so to fix this
bottleneck we're using an approach that
was um originally developed by Paul blay
at MIT and developed by JT JT Neil at
the broad in his lab and the idea is
let's parallelize this by barcoding and
pooling the individual disease variants
so um forgive me it's it's a bit
abstract for those who are not so
familiar with these experiments but in
each well of this 24 well plate we put a
ton of cells and then we put a mixture
of the healthy and the diseased version
of those proteins that are tagged and uh
we add a single compound to each
different well and we're asking in this
well does this compound cure any of
these disease phenotypes and the way we
do that is we first image the
localization of the protein and then we
clear those stains away bleach them away
and then we do this inc2 bar coding so
basically these little dots are flashing
a
ttgc telling us which cells got which
Gene and was it the normal healthy
version or was it the disease Associated
version of that Gene and so that allows
us to ask whether the localization is
affected by a given drug and then we can
follow it up from there so we're just
getting started on this project it's a a
very exciting one and in fact we've
launched um a a Consortium called Vista
uh Pharma companies are welcome to join
us in this and um the idea is if this
works I think this is a technology that
could readily be incorporated um the the
technology is sort of free and open
source any Pharma company could adopt it
internally if they would if they would
like and our Consortium aims at at in a
small scale let's just start with 100
diseases and 500 drugs and see if we can
make any matches so that's called
Vista and the next example of uh so so
we just went through three different
examples of how do we find a disease uh
phenotype and so that we can do a drug
screen there's other things we can do
how do we find drugs um if we already
have a phenotype that we're interested
in can we find chemical Regulators of
that Gene or disease um profile so how
does this work here we take a particular
Gene of interest that we would like to
Target and we perturb it in cells and we
we look at the cells with the computer
and identify do the have the cells
structures changed in any detectable way
if they have we can then search for uh
in a database of compounds chemical
compounds that have previously been
tested and just ask have we ever seen
cells that looked like that have we ever
seen cells that had that same kind of
phena type that same kind of very
specific um change that we see and um if
we do see uh those we can take them and
then go do whatever follow up
experiments make sense so we did this in
a an an experiment with um first a lot
of of course known Gene compound matches
and aimed to try to figure out uh the
the kind of success rate overall and
we're we're shocked really to find such
a high percentage around 32% of the time
we could use this strategy to find a
compound that is known to to Target a
particular Gene um if you consider
compare that to the high through bit
screening that a Pharma company
typically does typically that involves
step one make a customized assay for the
gene step step zero figure out what the
function of the gene is step one make an
assay that that addresses that function
that that takes six months and and a
considerable amount of effort and then
lastly screen a million compounds or
100,00 compounds um to try to find drugs
that that impact that Gene so to be able
to do a computational query in an
afternoon using an existing public
database and get 30 30% of the time get
a good hit um is is pretty remarkable
and and would save the industry billions
if they if they could take this approach
we also um the 32% was using known
matches and sometimes it's easy to fool
yourself with um saying oh look we
discovered what was already known like
our our system did a good job so we also
tested it prospectively we said okay
here's seven genes that we would like to
find new compounds we don't have any
compounds um that that are uh useful so
we want to find new compounds and we
found a 42% success rate among those one
of them was Yap one where um my
collaborator Dr eisinger at Penn was
very interested to find Regulators of a
hippo pathway and identified some that
mimicked Yap one but do not direct L
Target it so they direct a they impact a
novel Target in the hippo pathway and
yet have this capability of killing
saroma cells which caused us to launch a
startup company that is now seeking
funding and and Partnerships um called
sizon um to pursue those compounds and
in general com compounds that hit
targets that impact solid tumors coming
from multiple directions um not just
killing cells which is shown here but
also impacting The extracellular Matrix
as well as prompting the immune system
to help Target the
tumor and then uh lastly can we identify
various types of a toxicity this is
another approach to use images um in a
in a a datadriven kind of way to
accelerate the drug Discovery process um
here we are collaborating not just with
pharmaceutical companies but also
agrochemical companies that aim to
reduce toxicity in their products and um
some of this work was carried out by a
postto rdet seal in collaboration with
Andreas Bender at Cambridge University
and um and you can see a number of
examples here the basic gist of of most
of these papers is let's um take images
of cells um that like I've described
already in the talk take images of cells
extract lots of features from those
images and say can we use that data to
predict whether a compound will be
cardiotoxic or liver toxic or have
certain pharmacokinetic U parameters or
MotoX and so on or bio activity in
various different kinds of assays um so
this this basic strategy seems to be
fairly effective and and these are some
examples of
them and that led us uh that and many
other studies in the field led us to
think um there's such a push to get rid
of animal models not just because uh we
don't love using animals and they're
expensive but also because they just
aren't super uh predictive of human
toxicity uh wonder if we could find uh a
way to use cell painting image-based um
approach that I've been describing as
well as transcriptomics and proteomics
in a variety of different cell models to
assess safety and we decided to start
with hepatotoxicity liver toxicity as
our test case and developed this
Consortium which so far has 16 of these
um mostly Pharma companies and uh
together our goal is to collect this
giant data set I'll I'll skip most of
the detail but just to say that the idea
was to uh collect compounds that are
known to have some kind of in Vivo
Associated data both rat and human and
then um develop a um test those
compounds in a few different model
systems ranging from um again human and
rat as well as some some of the fancier
models like liver on a chip and
organoids and then uh carry out these
various readouts cell painting um images
as as as my expertise but also mRNA and
protein and then carry out this data
analysis and and share it with the
community to identify are there any outs
among these different types of um
profiling methodologies that can well
predict different types of liver
toxicity so that's uh that's it I just
wanted um to point out that you can
download a PDF of the slides at the the
URL that's shown here at the bottom and
and feel free to take a picture if you
like there's all kinds of other things a
person can do with images and we've
developed a lot of different
applications some examples are shown
here um there's lovely communities of of
people meeting at conferences that are
listed here and some review articles if
you want to learn more about this um
general research area and with that I'm
uh happy to answer any questions thank
you thank you that was fantastic um see
a question in the
back thanks
Karina could you use thisen
as you develop an understanding of how
difficult expression cell level
corresponds
yeah I love I love the idea so the basic
idea is um take cells from patients
whether that's biopsies because they
needed a biopsy for something or whether
that's just take some blood you know a
blood blood sample or some other readily
available type of biopsy that's less
invasive um in theory one could
certainly capture images corresponding
to every human at you know whatever
decade intervals or something like this
and then try to correlate what do we see
in the images and what do we see in the
patient response in the HR over time uh
really cool idea and um to my knowledge
I mean it's a logistical challenge is is
more than anything else I don't think
it's a scientific challenge because I
think such a thing would be a really
great data set and would really you
would really learn a lot from it can I
ask a follow-up question order of
magnitude what does it cost to run one
of these oh yeah I'm glad you mentioned
that because um it is vanishingly
cheaper to run Imaging essays as
compared to mRNA or protein profiling
and it's inherently a single cell
technology so you get single cell
thousands of cells for each sample um on
the order of like a dollar a well um so
it's it's roughly 30 to 100 times
cheaper than mr& or protein profiling
and yet I didn't show the data in this
talk but there's lovely data if you
compare I mean if I just asked you if I
snap a picture of cells stained with
five stains and then I capture an mRNA
profile of let's say like a thousand
mrnas which one has more information
content I I think every sane person
would probably say the MRNA profile
should be more specific because it
should capture a lot more biology um but
it turns out that they actually are
pretty neck and neck and the and that
Imaging is again 30 to 100 times cheaper
and single cell um versus bulk so it's
it's really quite a to my mind I mean
I'm a fan of Imaging obviously um but to
my mind it was quite a shock when we've
seen how how powerful it can be by
comparison
great talk um we do
single I appreciate it very much we do
Dynamic time lapse based so our
limitations on scaling are a little bit
different and they driven by like speed
of stages on microscopes Etc um for a
lot of the applications here you know
the cost of um let's say a petri dish or
something similar and the cell is small
as you say what are the big limitations
for these applications for getting to
scale in in a productized manner that
can be used in any lab I mean the
already the cell painting strategy I
which is basically just a subset of all
image-based experiments um it's already
just extremely widely adopted through
throughout the the far Pharma industry
and Academia as well so um the cell
painting essay itself is just add a
bunch of dies to cells fix them take
their picture um it's it's really about
the simplest possible image-based assay
um you can get um so yeah I would say
it's already widespread there's really
nothing limiting about it the only times
we felt limited is oh well we can do
100,000 samples in a raid format Pharma
does this all the time at the millions
of scale it's not it's not overly
burdensome but the pooling the barcoding
pooling is has gotten us over that just
one step further to allow drug screening
at a a super big scale which which is
which has been a a main limitation
this will have to be our last question
um but I'm sure there opportunities
following I'm happy to stick around and
chat with people thank you br talk so
can you comment on the future
possibility so we can embed the
biological knowledge into AI analysis
image based pipelines to build a world
model and use image based analysis for
example you have cell painting analysis
pipelines so if we can IDE biological
Network knowledge into sell painting
image we can decompose that yeah yeah so
I I emphasize today because we've been
spending the last decade or so trying to
gather evidence and and trying to figure
out how powerful is this image based
data um I think it's a really great uh
um it's been very valuable to see how
can we integrate this data with other
data types so um we've got done a number
of experiments so far that show that
mRNA profiling protein profiling and
image-based profiling are um varying in
cost but they all produce complimentary
types of data some overlapping and some
complimentary and um so they are
absolutely not redundant with each other
um which to me is very exciting because
um there's not been a ton of work
integrating those three data types um as
well if you're working with drugs you
would want to incorporate chemical
structure information together with
those other data types if you have so I
think there's a lot of possibility for
for multimodal data integration across
all these different ways they're all
just different ways of measuring a cell
State thank you