today and next lecture we are going to
turn to a topic that's as I've
highlighted previously woefully missing
from this class and from Bas a lot of
basic economics which is we're going to
start talking about Equity this class
has been totally focused on efficiency
we've come back and back again to ever
since we did the lecture on consumer and
producer Surplus we've talked about a
particular normative perspective which
is the goal of society is to basically
maximize total social surplus the goal
of societ is really to maximize the pi
and we don't really care how it's
distributed and this is Illustrated as I
mentioned before nowhere more starkly
than the fact that two different Market
outcomes have the exact same welfare
consequences one is a perfectly
competitive
market and one is a perfectly price
discriminating
monopolist both of those Market outcomes
yield maximum social
surplus yet they feel very different and
outcome where consumers and producers
split the pie feels to us innately very
different than an outcome where
producers get to keep it all and that's
because innately we as humans care not
just about efficiency but fairness about
equity and we actually care about not
just how much stuff gets produced but
who gets
it now in that particular
example you get two very different
distributional outcomes with the same
level of efficiency but that's actually
pretty unique it turns out generally
that different distributional outcomes
different levels of fairness come at
different levels of efficiency and that
we leads to what we fundamentally call
the equity efficiency
tradeoff that basically to get more
Equitable outcomes often requires less
efficient
outcomes and our goal as economists is
to decide is it worth it how do we think
about whether a potential sacrifice in
efficiency is worth a gain in equity
your fairness and the best way to think
about this was posed by The Economist
Arthur
Oaken about 40 50 years ago God it must
be 50 years ago
now Arthur Oaken
OK posed the example of the Leaky bucket
which is the best way to think about
redistribution he said imagine the way
imagine a society with the rich people
and poor people and imagine the way we
redistributed from rich people to poor
people was by literally the rich people
putting money in a bucket then someone
carries that bucket and dumps it out in
front of the poor people the simplest
possible view of distribution and we
probably and so Arthur Oak's question
was imagine simple world where a rich
person puts in a dollar someone carries
over and gives that dollar to a poor
person how many of us would favor that
probably most of us probably most of us
would think that the rich person would
miss the dollar
less than the poor person would value
the dollar so probably most of us would
think that if you could take a dollar
from the rich and give it to the poor
that's a good thing to
do now Oak can ask but what if the
bucket was leaky what if along the money
along the way some of the money leaked
out so the dollar you took from the rich
became less than a Dollar by time I got
to the
poor what if it was 90 cents 70 cents 50
cents 30 Cent 10 cents or Nothing At
what point do you stop wanting to make
that
transfer like I said for most of us if I
said to you you could take a dollar from
a very rich person give to a very poor
person you'd say well that seems like a
good deal what if I say get a dollar for
a very rich person and give 50 cents to
a very poor person is that a good deal
that depends that depends on how you
feel about the relative value of money
in the hands of the rich and the poor it
becomes a harder question and and that
is the equity efficiency tradeoff if you
can redistribute shares of the pie
without shrinking the pie we probably
would be in favor of that but once it
involves shrinking the
pie maybe it's not such a good idea or
maybe it is maybe even if the dollar
from the rich becomes nothing to the
poor you'll still favor it because you
think inherently there's uh there's a
problem with
inequality so ultimately the question we
want to think about is where what's the
leak that you accept in your bucket
what's the leak that you're willing to
accept to transfer money and we're going
to discuss that issue in four steps in
the next two
lectures the first step is we're going
to ask about social
valuation of
transfers how does how do we
think the issue we've avoided through
this whole course how do we think within
our base economic framework about how
Society feels about taking money from a
and giving it to
B the Second Step we're going to ask is
what is the actual inequality that
exists in
society what are the facts on who has
the dollars what are the motivations for
potentially addressing these
distributional
issues the third thing we're to ask is
where does the leakage what are the
sources of leak
leakage where does the leakage come
from where do the leaks that where do
the leaks that that leaky bucket come
from why is it
leaky and then finally we're going to
ask about transfer
policy how does government actually go
about taking money from some people and
giving it to
others those are the four steps we're
going to go through we'll get through
the first three today and F focus on the
last one on
Monday so let's start with the first one
which
is how do we think
about
social
welfare of
allocation so far we've just thought
about the social welfare of total if
total efficiency we haven't thought
about
allocation imagine we with many
different
outcomes different levels of efficiency
but also different levels of equity a
world with different with with buckets
that are different leakages and
different amounts of money going to
different people how would we compare
them well here we're going to use the
same tool we started with in lecture
two how do we think about any valuing
any combination of goods from a consumer
well we say they have utility function
and we say how do those different
combinations of good enter the
utility well to think about socially
optimal
allocation we're going to think about a
social utility function or what we're
going to call a social welfare function
we're going to say look if we want to
think about the value of goods in the
hands of person a versus B we have to
write down a mathematical function for
how Society feels about the value of
goods in the hands of person A or B that
is Loosely a utility function for
society essentially
aggregation of each individual's utility
so the function per utility one utility
two all the way up to utility 3 150
million okay so this the social welfare
function for the United States is
literally some aggregation some
mathematical function of everyone's
utility and you should be able to see
for a given mathematical
function I can then evaluate how I feel
about transfers because I can look at
what those transfers done each person's
utility I can use this function to
translate to new social
allocation okay so to see that let's
look at figure
231 these draw what we call isow welfare
curves now in our two-dimensional graph
the trade-off is between goods to two
people Homer and Ned okay we have Homer
and Ned Society consists of these two
people and we want to think about how do
we feel about resources in the hand of
Homer versus Ned and we could say for
example that we're indifferent between
the allocations u1h
u1n and u2h u2n say we're a different
between Ned having a lot and Homer
having a little or Homer having a lot
net having a little then they'd be on
the same isow welfare curve but by the
Moors better principle we're certainly
happy as a society with both having
more just like any indifference curve
the ISO Wells our curves the further out
the better off we
are okay so basically um this is
essentially a
mapping of a social welfare curve of a
social welfare function just like
utility function gives us an
indifference curve
mapping a social welfare function gives
us an isow welfare curve
mapping so then we just simply have to
ask what does a social welfare function
look like we talked about what utility
functions look like we talked about
their General print properties and that
common example we use of the square root
utility function but we said basically
we can use a broad class of functions
you've seen on problem sets and exams a
broad class utility
functions what about social welfare
function social welfare functions
typically we work in economics with a
couple of different forms of social
welfare
functions the most common form of social
welfare function is what we call
utilitarian social welfare function the
utilitarian social welfare function
simply poses that social
welfare is simply the linear sum of
utilities U1 plus U2 plus dot do D plus
u350
million that is utilitarian it's
literally I I don't know I don't I have
no base Society for caring any more
about one person than anyone else just
going to add their
utilities the person this guy named
Jeremy Bentham a famous British
philosopher uh couple things to not
about Jeremy Bentham first of all he
also invented the modern he invented a
modern design of Prisons which is quite
interesting he was a broad thinkinking
philosopher he also um when he died his
stuffed body with the head separated was
on display at University College London
um until it turned out students would
take the head out and play soccer with
it so they no longer do that so um he's
a famous philosopher cample the
utilitarian social war function it's
sort of a natural starting
point and if you think about it it's not
really sort of cons you wouldn't look at
this this is conservative or liberal
right you look at to say oh that's a
lefty or righty it's just it's neutral
it's just saying look I care about
everyone equally that seems pretty
neutral and yet this neutral social
utility function has radical
implications for
distribution in particular it says we
should always
transfer between any two
people if the transfer makes person two
happier than it makes person one
sad that means we're indifferent between
one udle to you and to Bill
Gates now that sounds kind of
conservative we're indifferent like
you're poor than Bill Gates we should
care more about you but remember I said
we're indiff in one udle between you and
Bill Gates that doesn't mean we're
differing than $1 doll between you and
Bill
Gates okay indeed who would we rather
with this social work function who would
we rather have the dollar you or Bill
Gates and why let's say there's a dollar
up for grabs with the utilit social
welfare function would social welfare be
higher if you got the dollar or Bill
Gates got the dollar and
Y
yeah L the margin of dollars higher to
you to you and less to Bill Gates what
this says if you maximize this if you
maximize this this implies you should
set the Marge utility of all individuals
equal I'm put 350 million because 350
million people in America okay this
implies you should put the margin
utility of every person equal that's a
pretty radical implication
that says literally you should reute
money until everybody values the dollar
the next dollar the same that say you
should massively redistribute from the
rich to the
poor right because the rich value the
next dollar way less than the poor Bill
Gates couldn't give a about the
next dollar where some poor homeless guy
mean could be difference between a hot
meal and not having a hot meal today on
a cold day so clearly this is fairly
this suggests that we dimin as long as
there's diminishing margin
utility you should have fairly strong
preferences to redistribute from the
rich to the poor despite the fact that
when I wrote this you didn't look at it
and say wow this is some Lefty crazy
utility function it has sort of Lefty
implications right it says we should
redistribute strongly from the rich to
the poor it sort of makes sense the rich
care about the money less than the poor
care about and that's your sort of
underlying intuition why we all start
with this notion that redistribution
makes sense indeed this goes further if
individuals are all
identical this if individual are all
this suggests we should have an equal
distribution of income a pretty radical
concept that's never been achieved
anywhere in history by any
society if individuals are all identical
this says we should have an equal
distribution of income pretty radical
from a pretty straightforward
concept now in fact to many
people this is actually a very
conservative approach to think about
about income distribution indeed
typically conservatives often start with
this point many people on the left start
with an alternative approach what's
called a rollan w r awl rollan social
welfare function named up philosopher
John rolls famous philosopher at
Harvard RS said that utility that the
social welfare of society should be
measured as the men of everyone's
utility that a society should be
measured by the living standards of its
worst off
member that as Society we should care
about those who are poorly off and
Society should be measured by the
utility of the worst off member that
sort of has some appeal okay we should
care about these people but it's
incredibly extreme in its implications
think about it for a second let's say
say there's a society consists of
everyone in the world everyone in the US
has
$40,000 except one guy has a billion
dollar and one guy has
$39,000 this says that we should be
willing to take the billionaire all the
way down to
40,000 just to get the 39,000 guy up to
40,000 that's pretty radical it says
that basically we don't care about any
anything people have about the minimum
we just care about making sure everybody
gets to that
minimum so that is very that makes this
look like a conservative fantasy this is
an incredibly radical approach which
says we should take everything from the
rich just to make sure the poor have
enough
okay but that's that's um clearly under
utilitarian social war function that
make us bad off clearly Bill clearly is
the guy who goes from a billion to
40,000 is made sad than the guy goes to
39 to 40,000 is made happier so clearly
that would not be a proper thing to do
under utilitarian social welfare
function but it would under
Ry now of course on the right there's a
on the on the conservative right there's
a crism that of both of these approaches
and that
view there's there's a criticism on the
uh uh which is that basically uh the
conservative criticism
criticism says that
basically look this whole discussion is
misguided it says look let's say we
started in society with everyone having
the same amount of
money let's say start everyone you and I
have the same amount of money and let's
say that you were willing as you should
be willing to pay $100 to hear me
lecture and so so you come in every day
and you give me a $100 to you hear me
lecture a
bargain okay at the end of the semester
I am richer or you are poorer is that
unfair what's unfair about that you paid
for something you
wanted I had something you wanted and I
end up richer how yet under utilitarian
social Ware function we'd call that
bad we'd say wait a second John's rich
or you're poor John should give that
money back to you but why you gave that
money to me voluntarily
so conservative criticism says that
look as long as everyone has equal
opportunity we shouldn't care about
outcomes that what matters is
opportunities not outcomes as long as
has equal opportunities then let people
spend their money as they want and let
people end up and whatever income
distribution results if Michael Jordan
ends up rich he's the best at basketball
so be it as long as everyone has equal
opportunities this is a theory which
says worry about
opportunities not
outcomes
now this
approach has two fundamental flaws it's
pretty compelling the story I told is
pretty compelling except for two
fundamental
problems okay the first problem with
this
approach is what does opportunities
mean by definition my kids have better
opportunities than the kids born to a
poor single mother living in a poor part
of
Boston they have more resources there
are better schools things like that so
in subsense equalizing opportunities is
actually by itself pretty radical that
would involve a large social structural
change okay so first of all equalizing
opportunity is not as easy as it sounds
we don't all start equal it a large
social upheaval to get us to that point
we started equal
the second problem with it is it turns
out that much of what accounts for
success in life is not skill or hard
work but
luck and in that
case it's not true that rich people are
rich because they deserve it or because
they have skills or or they're
just lucky and why do we necessarily
want to reward luck indeed can't we
think a redistribution is kind of luck
Insurance imagine a world where random
events going to happen to you you get
hit by a car we talked about why we want
insurance right want Insurance to make
sure if we get hit by the car don't get
hit by the car we're in the same off
well same thing RS talked about behind
the veil of ignorance imagine before
you're born you don't know if you're be
rich or poor you would choose a system
which would ensure you against being
poor and that system which would involve
transfers so if much of success is due
to luck we're going to want a system
that shoots the rich to the poor because
the rich got lucky the poor didn't
that's uncertain we want to ensure
against okay fascinating fact if you if
you interview people around the world
and ask
them is Success mostly due to hard work
or to luck in the US people say hard
work in Europe people say luck in Europe
they have much higher redistribution
than we do in the US because they have a
view that much more success comes from
luck now the answer is it's both in
every case but sort of an interesting
way to two ways think about the world
and then finally there's a totally
different alternative which has a lot of
appeal which is called commodity
egalitarianism commodity egalitarianism
this view has a lot of appeal as well
it's simply says
look let's get rid of this Focus on me
versus you that's just
destructive let's take a page from R's
book and say look let's just make sure
that the poor have enough to live and
beyond that let it
rip so Kam the view is much like RS who
want to make sure the poor are a decent
level but we don't care then how much
more the rich have as long as the poor
have achieved a standard of living where
they can survive then let it rip I don't
care how rich Bill Gates is as long as
each of you can have shelter and food
and basic health care and other basic
needs
met it's kind of a compelling it's kind
of a compelling um argument right that
basically why should I care about guy
who was a billion versus the guy who was
a million all I care was making sure
everybody can lead a decent
life it's in some sense a nice
compromise between a lot of these
different views in many ways and it
speaks to a key issue we'll talk about
later which is should we really be
giving people money or should we be
giving people the goods like housing and
health care that make up a decent
standard of
living so these are four different views
only two of them can been easily
expressed mathematically these obviously
can write down models but they're more
complicated but the bottom line
is with all these
views given those views you can figure
out whether a given policy that
transfers a person a to person B makes
sense
these are different ways of providing a
social welfare
framework okay questions about that
yeah sure yeah they're related so here's
the difference let's say we all decide
that everyone needs $50,000 to lead a
decent life in
America what commodity Garian say is
once everyone has $50,000
I don't care how rich people are above
that RS would say I do I don't want I
only if everyone is
$50,000 but one guy's 40 but but but if
I was $50,000 and someone else is a
billion dollars we we' rather make
everyone else that $50,000 and3 and that
guy back come down to 50,000 and3 we
don't want anybody above the minimum we
want to make sure the minimum is high as
it possibly can be where T says as long
as the minimum is the decent state of
living let the rich guy have as much as
he
want RS cares about inequality is a
concept commodity G terrorism
doesn't good question other
questions okay so armed with these views
let's talk about the facts what do we
know about
inequality and here I'm just going to
run through some facts from my textbook
that I used from
1441 so let's start with figure
23-2 this shows relative income
inequality in the United States how do
we do that we divide the population to
quintiles that is fifths of the people
so each of these rows is 20% of the
people each number shows the percent of
income earned by that share of people in
other words in a perfectly equal Society
every number in this table would be 20
in a perfectly equal Society every fifth
of people would get a fifth of the money
but in fact that's never true anywhere
you see always the higher
quintiles control a larger share of
income that's always true what's more
notable is how it's changed over time
from 1967 to 1980 it stayed relatively
flat but look from 1980 to
2019 the share held by the poorest has
fallen by about
25% the poorest 20% of people used to
earn 4.2% of the income now they get
3.1% of the income the richest 20% of
people in 1980 had 44% of the income now
they have 52% of the
income Society has gotten much more
unequal this has been driven not just by
the richest 20% to be clear the richest
just to fix ideas here the richest 20%
of people would be people with incomes
above say nationally PE with incomes
above say
$85,000 so it's not Mega Rich okay or
maybe $100,000 not Mega Rich it's well
off but not Mega rich but this trend has
been driven by the very
wealthy figure 233 shows the share of
income going to the top 1% of income PE
holders this people income above about
$500,000 these are the
rich
okay at the turn of the C 20 Century
1913 and peing right before the Great
Depression the rich held about 25% of
all in income that is 1% of people got
25% of the income that fell then fell
precipitously till in the early 1970s 1%
of people only about 10% of income and
it's risen dramatically since so we're
back at the level actually above where
we were at the peak of the 20th century
with one with the top 1% earning more
than a quarter of all the resources in
society so it's a very unequal
Society now you might say well how do I
know it's an equal what's what's the
natural state what I want to do is
compare countries figure 234 Compares
countries this is just a small
comparison of some countries that are in
the um o just a subset alphabetically of
countries that are what we call
developed countries from countries that
we consider our peers like the UK or
Sweden the countries that are poor like
Czechoslovakia or turkey what you show
here is the share of income held by the
bottom
10% the bottom 20% and the bottom 40% as
well as the top 40% the top 20% the top
10% just compare the bottom two rows the
bottom row is the average for all
developed countries so on average on
average across all developed countries
the bottom 10% of people have 3% of the
income and the top 10% of people have
25% of the income in the US the bottom
10 perent of only 1.6% of the the income
and the top 10% have almost 30% of the
income so the US is unequal it's much
more unequal indeed we are the most
unequal what's considered developed
country except for
Mexico we're unequal that any other
country consider a developed country we
the most unequal except for Mexico and
maybe turkey there's some debate
there okay so we're very
unequal
now many people particularly people in
these camps three and four would say
well look that's all well and good but
why you so worried about inequality sure
we got some rich
guys but we don't care about that we
just care that poor people have enough
to live that's what matters we want to
focus on what is the standard of living
of the
poor well in other words they want to
shift their focus
from
relative inequality
versus
absolute
deprivation that is how what are people
actually living on well to do that
relative the problem with that is
relative income inequality is easy to
measure just look at what group has Rel
to another it's unit
free once you want to measure absolute
deprivation you have to make a stand on
what it means to be
deprived the the US has taken such a
stand and we've created something called
the poverty
line the poverty line is the US
measure of what you need to lead a
minimally acceptable life in the
US okay below which what does it mean to
be in poverty now this is a pretty
foundational
concept yet its Origins are very modest
for those of you who think that working
the government doesn't involve pH being
government bureaucrat doesn't that much
power in the mid 1960s a mid-level
government bureaucrat made this number
up she said well look her name was Molly
oransky she said look poor people spent
about a third of their budget on food
let me just price out what a n
nutritionally adequate diet costs
multiply by three and we'll call that
the poverty line that exercise updated
by inflation is literally the way today
we transfer trillions of dollars in the
United
States okay so that has remained our
standard for what is
poor the poverty line itself is shown in
figure
23-5 so the poverty line for a family of
one is considered to be about
$133,000 it then doesn't double per
person because we view that living
together has economies of scale we don't
think you need twice as much money for
two people to live together
as you do for one person to live
together because for instance a
two-bedroom apartment is typically not
twice a one-bedroom apartment certainly
a so basically there's economies of
scale so it doesn't double but it goes
up thereafter So a family of four we
think as a poverty line of about twice
the poverty line for an
individual now is that a fair number is
that correct well that's a debate for
another day we can come to 1441 we spent
a lot of time talking about it it's a
very controversial number for many
reasons let's take that as given for now
what does it implies happen over time
well look at figure
23-6 which shows poverty rates over time
what you see if you look at the blue
line that's all people you see for all
people poverty rates fell dramatically
until about
1979 and then have been pretty flat
since that's been that's a combination
of a dramatic fall in poverty for those
I'm sorry that's not the Blue Line uh
yeah let's see no the I'm sorry the blue
line is I'm sorry the red line is all
people my bad it fell for dramatically
until about 1970 and then it's been flat
since that's a combination of a dramatic
Fallen poverty for the elderly which is
the blue line and actually poverty kind
of has been risen a bit for the for the
for youth that's under 18 but the bottom
line is you look at this line for about
1980 onward and it all looks pretty flat
right contrast that
to I'll go all the way back to table
232 table 2 32 seem to show that
inequality's gotten a ton worse since
1980 so how you feel about what's
happened to American society depends
very much on how you feel about fig
table 232 figure 232 versus figure
236 do we care about what's happened
relatively which is the rich Rel to the
poor which approach one and two would
say we should care
about or do we care which happen
absolutely which is what the poor have
which is what approach for we should
worry
about and there's no right answer but
how you think about it determines how
you're going to um end up uh end up
thinking about the
problem to my mind I think you want some
of both but to my mind the simplest and
most striking way to think about this is
the following example which is just
stunning many of you may remember about
10 years ago there were the maybe less
there was the Freddy gray riots Freddy
gray was a prisoner arrested in a poor
neighborhood of Baltimore he was killed
in the police car on the way to the
police station it led to uh as part of
the black you know one of the founding
events of black lives matter movement
led to a lot of riots and things like
that in
Baltimore those riots highlighted how
much inequality there is in
Baltimore go to figure one of my I think
one of the most stunning figures I've
ever seen figure 237
this figure this is just a graph of
Baltimore this shows neighborhoods in
Baltimore and the life expectancy in
each neighborhood how long you expect to
live and I'm going to highlight two
neighborhoods Sandtown
Winchester which is where Freddy gray
was from and Roland Park which is three
miles
away where Freddy gray was from the
average life expectancy unless Roland
Park Roland Park is a wealthy
neighborhood typical sort of wealthy
suburb the average life there is 84
that's above the US average three miles
away where Freddy gray is from the
average Lifey was
67 that is below the life expectancy of
North
Korea three miles and a 17year
difference and how long you can expect
to
live I don't see how anyone can look at
that and not care about inequality
how can you not care about a world where
people living three miles apart have a
17-year difference and how long they
expect to live what's going on three
miles away the average income in Sant
toown is four times the average in the
average in sorry Roland Park is four
times the average income in Sandown in
Roland Park 2.5% of kids live in poverty
in Sant toown 55% of kids live in
poverty okay three
miles and and the odds a kid lives in
party is 20 times
different these are the reasons why many
of us feel very strong that we need to
address inequality as well as simply
absolute
deprivation okay questions about
that now with that in mind let's talk
about what do we do about it so let's
say I've got you at least
motivated let's say you came in this not
really thinking about rich versus poor I
hope at least motivated you think it's
interesting problem and think about
maybe it's something we might want to do
something
about well to do so we run
into an important problem because
remember with the Dismal science right
nothing's
easy okay the problem is the efficiency
costs of redistribution remember I said
life isn't typically like our example of
perfect competition versus perfectly
pric monopolist typically in life if we
want to take money from one group we
give it to another there's a leak in the
bucket what is that leak in the
bucket okay well there's fundamentally
two leaks so let's say the way we do
redistribution in reality is we tax the
rich and give money to the
poor okay well that leads to S two
sources of
leakage the first source of leakage is
when you is the dead weight
loss of
Taxation when you tax an
activity you create less of it and that
has a dead weight loss because there's
social optimal trades that no longer get
made that's the first source of
leakage the second source of leeches
leakage is the is the dead weight loss
of transfers which is a little more
subtle but actually works the same way
when you
subsidize a lack of economic activity
you create more of it that's the moral
hazard problem we talked about last
time so you tax something activity you
create less of it when you subze a lack
of activity you create more of it
transferring from Rich to poor involves
both ends of that so it's double weight
loss you
create okay so to see that we're going
to go through a fairly large example
here we're going to end the lecture with
sort of a strong example which
illustrates this point okay in this
example we're g to say everyone earns
$20 an hour so our example the wage for
everyone's Society is be $20 an hour so
everyone has the same
underlying marginal product of labor
every side he ears $20 an hour marginal
revenue product of labor
but different people earn different
amounts of income and society's
utilitarian the government utilitarian
so it cares about that different
different amounts of income so let's say
that the government wants to make sure
that there's a minimum guarantee the
government's a commodity
galarian the government says you know
what I want to make sure there's a
minimum guarantee of
$5,000 I want to make sure that everyone
in society has at least
$5,000 because I feel like you can't
survive with less than
$5,000 but I have to pay for that so the
way I'm going to pay for that I'm have
I'm gonna have a
tax and the tax is going to
be that anyone with
income
um oh I'm sorry let me go back so let me
go back let me finish this first there's
a guarantee of $5,000 but here's the
thing I'm not going to give everyone
$5,000 I want make sure everybody has
$5,000 but if you have some money
already I don't want I don't want to
guarantee you have $7,000 I'm make sure
have $5,000 so what I'm going to do is
I'm set up a transfer program that's
what we call a negative income tax the
way it works is if you have zero I give
you 5,000 you have 100 I give you
4,900 if you a th000 I give you 4,000
that is I top up your income to get you
to 5,000 in particular I give you a
transfer I give you a transfer which is
equal to
the
max of 0 comma
5000 minus y That's the transfer I give
you I give you if your income's above
5,000 I give you nothing if your
income's below 5,000 give you enough to
get up to 5,000 that's how I Implement
my commodi egalitarianism solution I get
everyone up to 5,000 people clear on
that I get them up to
5,000 okay and to assment of a
tax the tax is going to be only on the
rich so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say anyone whose earnings is
above
$20,000 is going to be is going to pay a
50% tax
rate
above 20K just on your earnings above
20K so all earnings below 20K I don't
touch but on any earnings above 20K I'm
going to take back half of it to finance
this
program okay that's the way the program
is going to
work well let's see how that affects
people's budget
constraint let's go to figure
23-8 this is a standard Leisure
consumption
tradeoff okay we people remember I said
earn 20 bucks an hour so without the
government the budget constraint is the
black line they can work up to 2,000
hours a
year and have no no
consumption I'm sorry they can take
2,000 hours a year Leisure my bad
leisures on the exsis they 2,000 hours
year Leisure and have no consumption or
take zero Leisure and have 40,000 in
consumption and let's assume we're going
to measure price of goods is all one so
consumption is just like this
consumption bundle like we talked about
this numer good idea that basically we
think of dollars and units of
consumption
interchangeably so basically consumption
costs a dollar the price consumption is
a dollar so basically the trade-off is
simply for every hour I take of leisure
I give up $20 of
consumption and that leads that black
line the program I just described
changes that line as follows first of
all on the leftand side if you
take if you take uh first of all I'm
sorry on the right hand side my bad on
the right hand side if you take more
than 17700 50 hours of
leisure we're going to give you money
why because if you take less than $750
of leisure you're going to have more
than $5,000 already look at the X look
at the y- AIS 750 hours of leisure at
a$2 wage means you're working 250 hours
mean you got 5,000 in income so your
income's below
$5,000 that means you must be taking
more than 1,750 hours of Leisure for
those people who are simply going to say
look we're going to make sure you have
at least
$5,000 what does it do the budget con
Str that says it becomes flat from the
point of 1750 all the way to the point
of 2,000 and then drops back down the
new budget constraint on the right is
the red segment it's a flat segment
because we're saying no matter how much
leure you take above 1750 you always get
$5,000 in income we just send you a
check for the
rest like likewise we're going to pay
for that by a tax on those who earn
above
$20,000 well at $20 an hour that means
people who take less than a thousand
hours of leisure are the ones who earn
more than $20,000 so on those people
were're taxing them 50% so that lowers
the slope of the budget constraint now
for every hour you work above a
thousand you take home only $10 an
hour so that lowers the opportunity cost
of work lowers the budget constraint to
the upper left right
side okay questions about
that okay now let's
assume that there's three people in this
world okay person
A and B have the same utility function
their utility function is U equals c to
the 34
time L to the
one4 person C has a different function
they have
C to the 1
nth L to the 8
9th okay so person C really likes
Leisure rela to person A and B right
person A and B have a 3/4 weight on
consumption versus one quarter on
Leisure person C is a one nth way to
consumption Rel to eight nths on Leisure
person C likes
Leisure okay that's the utility
function
okay
now in the optimal Choice
set people are going to set their
mrss equal to their
MRT okay that's going to be the choice
people are going to make in the optimal
Choice set
okay so basically what they're going to
do is they're going to find given this
budget constraint the one I depicted in
figure
238 what is their optimal
choice and what we're going to
see is
that um without the government scheme
we'll see that in figure 239 and we'll
we'll you we'll solve the math and
section of this example we'll solve the
math in section so you can go through it
but I'm showing you what the answer
answer is we'll go through the math in
the section you'll see person A and B
will choose to be at that intersection
on the left on the black line A1 B1 that
is the choice they'll make given this
budget constraint and given these
preferences they will choose in figure
239 be the A1 B1
intersection unsurprisingly person c
will be choose to be way down on the
right at the C1 intersection why because
they love Leisure person C cares way
about Leisure consumption it's the way
down the right okay we'll work out the
math just take it to me take take my
word that's what the math
delivers now we put in the tax and
transfer scheme what happens to person C
why do they move to
C2 why do they move to
C2 well if you think about it think
about income and substitution effects
for person C the substitution effect is
when you're at like person C there is a
100% tax
on your
earnings look at this 100% tax because
every dollar you earn you get less in
transfer substitution effect says don't
work right because if you work you get
nothing the income effect is your richer
you're getting a transfer income effect
also says don't work so they don't work
turn that if you pay people not to work
they won't we learned that in the
Netherlands last time so all the people
who were C1 go to C2 they stop
working what about A1 and B1 well here
it's
unclear they now face a lower wage
effective wage of $10 of $20 whether
they work more or less depends on income
versus substitution
effects here I'm going to assume
substitution effects
dominate so they work
less so the new equilibrium is the
person C works less
and person A and B work
less what have we found leaks in the
bucket we thought we could raise a bunch
of money from taxiing and being given to
C but we missed two things first of all
A and B don't work as hard so we can't
raise as much money from
them second of all C doesn't work so
hard so we need to get more money to see
so if you started with 0.1 A1 B1 and C1
you would have a certain estimate of how
much money you have to take to get
person C1 the transfer your estimate
would be too low why would your estimate
be to too low because you'd miss the
leakage you miss the fact that A1 and B1
going to work less so you raise less
money from them and C1 is going to work
less so you give more money to C1 those
are the leaks that's a graphical
illustration of the leaks in the bucket
that is how the Leaky bucket works it
causes
taxation causes assuming substitution
effects dominate taxation causes the
rich to work less hard which means you
raise less money and it causes the poor
to work less hard which means you have
to spend more money and those the tour
so leaked that was very fast and
graphical in section you go through the
math but that just gives you a sense of
how the leakages work we'll follow up on
Monday