Hi everyone, my name is Ena Maria and
I'm originally from Colombia. I'm also a
chair at Latinx Abroad and have been
working here at the Broad Institute for
the last seven years. Um I'm especially
happy to be here today introducing our
talk, especially as we're closing the
celebration for Hispanic Heritage Month.
So before I start introducing our
guests, I just wanted to share a little
bit about the origins of this series and
what we at Latina Broad aim to achieve
through through these kind of talks. So
we started the series about three years
ago with two main goals in mind. Our
first one was representation because we
truly believe that it's important to see
ourselves reflected in science. Um
representation remind us that we belong
in these spaces that our voices and
perspectives matter and hopefully it
keeps spiring Latino scientists to
continue pursuing their passions. So
since we got we began in early 2022, we
had had over 30 speakers all over from
Latin America and the US and they all
come from a wide range of fields and
different stages of their career. So we
had had you know early career
researchers as well as established
leaderships in their discipline and our
second goal of this series was to create
connection and community. So we wanted
to create a place where people could
come together, learn from one another
and also build professional
relationships. Um so I just wanted to
share a quick story about how we have
created connection and community through
the series uh and how that reflects the
importance of creating these spaces. So
we had um an undergrad student who
attended one of our talks a few years
back and you know afterwards he reached
out to the speaker. he was very
interested in the work that she was
doing and those conversations eventually
led for uh him being hired into into her
lab. So that's just one example of how
this series can achieve community and
connection between everyone that is
joining here. So that's also um a call
for you guys that are joining to you
know take the opportunity to engage with
the community and hopefully explore new
opportunities. Um so thank you everyone
for joining us today. Now I'm going to
move on to introduce our speaker of
today. It's an honor for me to have here
today um Dr. Sylvia Restrepo. Um I
actually had the privilege of being her
student and I have always admired her
passion for science and her commitment
for student for her students and her
dedication to you know advance the
field. So Sylvia is a renown plant
pathologist and she's actually the first
female president of the Boyce Thompson
Institute. Um in her career she has had
several leadership leadership roles
which include being vice president of
research for universes in Colombia. She
also served as the dean of school of
science um in there and she also has
received numerous awards including
recognitions from the war academy of
science in 2009, the Louis Malise prize
in 2010, the national order of merit
from the French government in 2018 and
most recently the Jacob Ericson prize
from the Royal Swedish Academy in 2023.
So her research has focused on plant
pathogens and that impact food security
combining molecular biology, genomics
and the field study to understand these
organisms, evolve and adapt. Um so today
she will be sharing her journey studying
pamplatology. So please join me in
welcoming Sylvia to our series.
Thank you so much Anna Maria. It's a
really an honor for me that my former
students invite me to this seminar. So
that means that I left something in in
every each of of my students. But it's
is it's is really nice. Yes. So today
I'm going to talk about my research
about the plant pathology. I left the
the universes logo in here in this slide
because most of the of the work was done
in universes. But let me take some time
to talk about the boy Thompson Institute
where I'm the the president right now.
So the Boy Thompson Institute is a
nonprofit organization
uh specializing in plant sciences. I'm
going to talk a little bit about that.
But we are in the Cornell University
campus. We are not Cornell. We are
affiliated to Cornell, but we are in the
middle of the campus. So if you come to
the campus, you cannot miss our building
that is totally in the middle of the
campus. So you cannot miss visiting us
and I I I hope you can visit us. Um
so a little bit some numbers we last
year we celebrated 100 years in in
operation. Uh we have 15 research labs.
Um we are close to 34 administrative
staff but combining with research
personnel we are 110 120 people in the
building from 40 different countries.
not at the same time but we have people
we have had people from from different
countries and we have six core
facilities and probably Anamaria can
recognize some of the crops I have in
this slide because we come from the same
country that is Colombia and we have
research not only in the usual crops
tomato potatoes etc but in some
neglected crops like ground um Cape
Gooseberry or golden berries coffee etc
uh I invite you to follow our uh
history. We had last year we made this
collection of the 10 decades of
research. I cannot go into to details
but I'll let you uh scan this QR where
you can find all the history. I'm only
going to highlight some moments in our
history. As I mentioned, we started 100
years ago actually in Yonkers, New York.
So we were founded by Colonel Boyce
Thompson. He was inspired by the he went
to Russia after the first world war and
he was impressed by the problem with
food security. So he started this uh
this institute to to work for for food
security. Um we in the in the 40s 50s we
were more focused on the environment
especially the effects of pollutants.
But then uh in the 70s BTI moved to ITA.
We included new lines of research like
plant pathology and then of course
chemical biology, genomics and
biioinformatics.
Um as I mentioned we have 15 labs. These
are the the 15 labs. I cannot go into
detail but we work on on food security,
nutrition, resilience to different
stresses, productivity, health. We have
one lab working on human health and
biodiversity.
Um we are also committed with the
formation and of the new generation of
young scientists. So we have this
amazing uh reu program. Um it's the in
the summers where we receive close to 30
up to 40 students during the summer. not
only in BTI of course we don't have
enough space in BTI but we um we run the
program also with Cornell um and our
last pillar so we have this research
pillar this education pillar and the
third one is the translational program
we have our own uh incubation of
technologies here in the in the
institute so we call the translational
program but is a tech transfer office
plus all the industry relations and
collaborations so we have worked
For example, in in this technology, the
the hi-fi,
the hi-5 that is um um insect lines to
produce vaccines, but we also have work
on products like you can see here the
fitalics that is a component to uh
protect plants against diseases.
So, and we have these specialized
research services. We have a plant
growth facility, a phen phenotyping
facility, masspec, um transformation and
editing for plants, um the the
computational the biology computational
biology center and a cell imaging
center. So this this is the the lab the
the institute in a few slides and now
I'm going to jump to the research to
what my my passion is is in research as
Anna Maria told you and I'm going to
tell you two stories. I'm going to focus
on on a pathogen that I have worked for
most of my life is phytotera the genus
phytoera. I'm going to talk a little bit
of what is phytotera and how we discover
a new species of this pathogen in
Colombia but also I'm going to tell a
story about how to control the plant uh
this plant destroyer
um so phytoinestance
is um is a pathogen uh funguslike
actually was classified as a fungus a
long time ago but nowadays we know that
it's not a fungus is a proteise. So it's
in totally different location in in
taxonomy and it attacks a long um a
broad range of plants in the solenacious
family. So if you think solanatious is
potato tomatoes but we have in South
America a lot of different crops that we
from the solenacious crops that we don't
grow here in the state but I'm going to
talk a little bit about. So what are the
the this these organisms? So phytoera is
right here in the proise is in this
super group that is called the sar that
are the stropy alveolata and raria. You
probably know the alveolata because the
the causing agent of malaria is right
here and so phytoster is closely related
to this uh pathogen to plasmodium. And
in this uh we have uh so the phytoeras
in the phytoraa genus we have more than
100 species we are I think close to 150
in 10 clates but I'm going to focus only
in one of these clo cate that we call
the cate one and I'm going to tell the
story about uh this cate among them is
the famous phytoraa infestance it's
famous because it caused Um it it causes
this disease on potatoes and in due to
some political issues it caused uh the
famine because it destroyed all the
potatoes in Ireland in 1840s in the
1840s. So causing the death of more than
1 million people and and also 1 million
people also migrated to the United
States. So and to different countries
but mainly to the to the United States.
So it's famous because of that. It's
called the plant destroyer because it
can totally destroy um a crop in uh in
in few weeks. Okay. So I'm going to talk
about the phyto infestence and this can
sound very complicated but it's not. So
phyto infestence sensto in the USA and
sulatto in Colombia. What does that
mean? that it means that in in the
states in USA we only have one species
that does fit of phyto infestants but in
Colombia, Ecuador, Peru where we have
the center of diversity for the host of
the solenacious crops we have a lot of
species species of phtoa cohabiting in
uh the different host in our countries.
So um
no. Okay. So in the states I I work in
Cornell 25 years ago. I came back uh 25
years after. But 25 years ago we
conducted these simple experiments. We
only had one species. So we planted
tomatoes in the field. We made some
experiments. But when I went back to
Colombia in 2000, 2004, 2005, I um saw a
total different environment where you
have a potato field here and the potato
field starts to the right. But this is
the small garden from the grower. When
we went to this field, we saw that there
was a huge problem because in his
garden, the grower has some plants that
can be the reservoirs for the pathogen.
He has golden berries, uh, lulo, the
sanum ketoeni, he had peppers, he has
three tomatoes. So, it's a lot of plants
that can be the reservoirs for the
pathogen. So, no wonder why his potato
field was totally infected with the
pathogen. So when I I went to back to
Colombia, what I started to do is okay,
what is the real host range for this
pathogen. So we went out in the field in
several localities, several states of
the country and we collected a lot of
solenacious and we could describe these
solenacious species. So potato, yellow
potato, tomato, tomato, lulu and cape
gooseberry. But also we found the
pathogen in wild species like this one
solenum varum. So we described this the
the the phytotera phytora were thriving
in all these host everywhere in the
country and it's I guess the same in
Ecuador and and Peru. So a quick guide
to understand what I'm the the story I'm
going to tell you. Uh so I'm going to go
through this quick guide. So what we
call in phytoera we we the population of
phytoera are comprised of what we call
the clonal lineage.
A clonal lineage is all members
descending from a single individual. So
we call them US1 if they are the first
described in US or EC1 is the first
lineage described in Ecuador or co if
it's Colombia etc. So depending on the
country and the discovery we are going
to call them US1, US8, US12. Uh right
now we are up to US 25 here in the
states.
And a clonal lineage uh is defined by
the fingerprint that is with a marker
that the young people will not recognize
that is RFLP that we used back in the
past. But it's something like that. If
you see that in a gel, so each member of
a clonal lineage will have a set of of
bands in the gel that is unique to the
clonal lineage. So you see on top of the
gel the US1, US7, US8, they have each
one a pattern of bands in this gel. But
also clonal lineage is described not
only by the the the markers in the
genome, but also the mitochondrial type.
So it's also we amplify um a region of
the mitochondria and we um use uh
restriction enzymes to to to cut it and
depending also in the pattern we say
that it has the mitochondrial type 1 a 2
a 1 C you will see that is important in
my in my talk uh so this is like it
looks like when we do the amplification
and the restriction of a region of the
mitochonding
pattern we have 1 a 2 a etc. And finally
a clonal lineage is defined by the
mating type. So the three components
define a clonal lineage. So what is the
mating type? Mating type is because this
organism is eterotalic. It means that it
needs two different mycelia two
different vegetative states to be able
to cross and have sexual reproduction.
We call these two states or these two
mating types A1 and A2. So to determine
which mating type we have, what we do is
we take one reference. For example, we
know that US23 is mating type A1. So we
put a little bit of of the oh my seat
that we don't know US25. We didn't know
what it was. We put it to and so the two
strains cross in the middle of the petri
dish. We take a sample of that middle
and we see if they form the sexual spore
that is the O spore. If they form is
because A20 US 25 was A2. If doesn't is
because US25 is A1. So we define the
clonal lineages that way. So when I went
back to Colombia, I started to see what
we did first is determine the the host
range and then we characted to
characterize the population of the
pathogen. So we use what I mentioned the
RFP. So which clonal lineage do we have
in Colombia and we found that we have
the EC1. So is the Ecuador one. So
apparently we have the same clonal
lineage in Ecuador that is bordering
Colombia from the south to the north and
apparently it replaced the US1
population that was described in the 80s
and the '9s. So when I arrived to
Colombia the population was dominated by
this clonal lineage EC1. But I wanted to
study this population a little bit
further. So I used some markers that are
nuclear markers, mitochondrial markers
and some genes. This AVR3A gene is a
virulence gene and we found that the
population was not so diverse in terms
of the sequences of this gene. But we
saw this in the south of Colombia. We
saw this explosion of diversity in a
region that is bordering with Ecuador.
So I continue to do my studies but at
some moment I said wait
there is something happening in the
south of Colombia that is very strange.
Why do we have this explosion of
diversity only in that part of Colombia?
So we went back to the literature and we
found all of this. So we found that in
2000 a group in Ecuador published this
um paper saying that they found an
overpopul of phytoera similar to p
infestance attacking wild solenum
species in Ecuador. So attacking solenum
tetropetalum and solanum braolium. They
described that oh we have the mating
type A2 for the first time in Ecuador
and for the first time in the north part
of South America because all the strains
belong to A1 until that moment they
found we found a new mitochondrial
hloype 1C for the first time in
phytoraala history and these strains are
not pathogenic they don't attack
potatoes or tomatoes
so remember these are A2 1
So in four years later this group
published okay this um this A2 and A1
the ones that we have here that I
already mentioned A21C
um are well we we can describe them but
we found a new genotypes associated with
wild solenum species that they call the
anariconmum complex
that are A1 and 1 A in mitochondrial HLO
type. So this new population so a new
clonal lineage called EC2 that has A1 as
a mating type and a mitochondrial hlo
type 1A. So now we have like two groups
of strains in attacking different host
and also nobody mentioned this one that
is important in our talk. a new lineage
EC3 that is also A1 1A but has a diff
different markers in the genome. So
that's why it is called EC3 and not EC2.
And then in 2004 so finally they said
okay we are going to group all these new
strains in a new name that is phytora
andina and they published and in
Colombia somebody published somebody
know sorry the group of um lucistella
meital published in 2008 this uh
interesting paper where they say these
strains when we do we use these
molecular markers AFL they group in two
different clusters.
one that is associated with tree tomato
and the other cluster that has these
strains that were isolated from potato.
And finally, what probably made me react
the most is this publication in in 2010
by my friend Ricardo Lea. But they
published that they have this new
species phtoandina a newly identified
pathogen of solenacious host in the
Indian region. And the weird thing from
this publication is that they put in the
same species different clonal lineage.
It's like you define a species with um
as a polygenetic entity that is totally
an oxymoron. So you cannot define a
species
from different genetic origins. So we
published this letter we wrote this
letter to the editor that we were not in
agreement with this publication from
Ricardo is it's important to say that
Ricardo and I are very good friends but
this is academic discussion that are
very important in science. So we
published this letter saying wait you
cannot say that this pandina that has
two clates two filogenetic clates in the
genome and in the mitochondria very
different 1 C and 1 A you cannot say
that these two entities are the same
species and even worse because in 2016
this group in Peru published wait it's
not only two or three it's more than
that we have another group of strains
associated ated with other crops that we
will call also phytotherandina. So now
we have three is is a paraphilletic
species defined. Um so we were not um we
were not okay with this. So
we question or our question was do we
have more than one species? Do the
isolates collected in three tomato
belong to a new species? So we also
published this paper saying wait in
plant pathology we really need to have a
framework to define a new species. How
can we accurately define new species in
plant pathogen microorganism? We cannot
only define a new pathogen because we
found it in a new species and what are
the main mechanism of speciation in
implant pathogens. We found that we have
all the mechanism of speciation. We
found some cases where we have
pre-mating um isolating mechanism is it
means that um that we have for example
the crosses fail to produce hybrids or
they cannot infect the same host. So
they can never be together in the same
uh environment or we have postmating
where the the hybrids are produced but
they are not viable. um that is what we
call postigotic but the most common was
this one the premating where we have
different strains that will never meet
in nature because they have different
preferences of host preferences.
So our working hypothesis that we have
two different species pandina uh EC2 is
pandina but pandina e3 was a different
species that finally we demonstrated
that is p beta. So we went back to the
south of colombia and took a lot of
sample of these strains that were
attacking tree tomato and decimating the
trees in this region. And we took a lot
of lines of evidence to show that we in
reality had a a new species. This is
this is really interesting. We have the
three species here to the to the left.
So we have pandina p infestance and
pibeta say and we put them to grow in
different media in petrate dishes. But
look at the last two columns is PDA
potato and three tomato aar. Look at P
beta say it doesn't grow at all in
potato but it it loves the tree tomato
aar. In the contrary p infestance grows
very well in in potato but doesn't grow
so good in in the tree tomato. So we
started to see a preference for a
different host. So we run a phoggenetic
relationship or phoggenetic study with
more marus in the whole um in the whole
genome and we started to see that we
have in fact two different clates one
with pandina and the other one with p
beta what they call previously the the
EC3 and we did um with population study
where we saw that it was clearly that
the genetic backgrounds of the three
species pandina in in yellow, P
infestance in red and petate in in blue.
we they had different genetic
backgrounds and you can see in the in
the PCA and the DPC analysis that they
are really separated in the cluster and
look at this PCA where I'm I'm I'm
showing you here that the the what was
classified as the P&D3 in the previous
studies is clearly related to with these
strains we collected in the south of
Colombia from three tomato but we
conducted the two assays that I think
are the the um the the gold standard to
show that we have a different species.
The first one is we took the the strains
from the these three species and we
inoculated in all the different host. We
couldn't inoculate it in the wild
Solanum plants because we didn't have
them in in Colombia but the same that
they describe in Ecuador but we use tree
tomato tomato yellow potato and potato
and you can see that the pibet say only
infects uh tree tomato but it cannot
grow in the other host. So what we have
here is a strong ecological reproductive
isolation between p infestance and p
beta. We have never isolated the
infestant from tree tomato in the field
and we haven't be able to isolate
peta say from potato or tomato in the
field and what is the real the gold
standard in biology is to show that we
have this reproductive isolation. So we
attempted to do the crosses between the
three species and I'm only going to show
you the results of the crosses between P
infestance and P beta and what we show
is that the hybrids this is all sport
that is not viable. So the hybrids are
totally absent from the the the crosses.
So we have the reproductive isolation
showing that we have two different
species. So we published the the new
species with the idea and corroborating
that pandina is formed only on the uh
from uh strains of the EC2 clonal
lineage but P beta uh is comprises the
strains from the EC3. So we have a case
of ecological speciation. The three
species are reciprocally monopiltic and
the most probate scenario is speciation
with secondary contact. And then we
showed we we went to different three
tomato crops in the in the in the middle
or in the center of the of the country
and in the central part of the country.
And we showed that the peta say was also
present in in in this region not as
present in in the south. You can see in
Putoayo for example all the strains or
most of the the majority of strains are
peta say in the rest of the country we
have the two species uh cohabiting in
sympatric um presence um in the two
regions and we again corroborate that
these strains coming from three tomato
from the central part of the of the
country u belong to the peta
um species. You again see that they
separate very well the three clusters of
the three species pandina pepas and pin
infestance and something interesting
that I couldn't uh study more in
Colombia is these strains the the ones
that I'm showing here in the middle of
the PCA that were collected from tomato
and apparently they also are probably a
subspecies or a new species in phytora
so this host preference is really
driving the speciation of this pathogen
in our countries. And why is important
to define a good taxonomy because then
we realized in in some experiments that
I I will not show you today because of
time but we show that the P infestines
are very resistant to fungicides while
the P beta are not. So you can work with
these different fungicides to control
one disease or not the other. So it's
important the taxonomy for plant
pathologies is really important because
based on the on a very good taxonomy you
can uh design control strategies and
disease management and this is important
also because you can see a different
outcome of the disease. Here we
conducted more experiments to understand
the disease. So we use three tomato
leaves and we infected them with
phytotherabetas and pin infestant. And
you see again that phytoerabetas loves
the tree tomato. It goes right away
infecting it. The sporates where I have
these arrows here and you see the white
spotting is where the pathogen
sporulates. It is happy reproducing
while p infestance doesn't drive in in
this host um cause a disease that is
contained. This after the 120 hours
after the inoculation it stayed the
same. it didn't progress at all. And if
you see the the we follow the infection
with microscopy with light microscopy
and and um electronic electron
microscopy and you can see that phyto
infestence releases soul spores while
phytother beta state takes um it it time
to to to
germinate but finally germinates and
they produce this um at at 9 hours post
inoculation both of the pathogen try to
establish um communication with the host
to uh steal the nutrients with this
structure that are called hostoria where
the the oh my seed takes the nutrients
from the plant cells.
So we did also an experiment because our
hypothesis that is that some genes that
we call define the host of the plant
pathogens. So we did uh transcrytoics
experiments and we showed that the
pathogens in culture have a different
gene expressions that the pathogen
implanted. This is the the figure in the
in the left but in the right you can see
that the pathogen behaves as a
hemibotroof.
That means that in early time points of
the inoculation, it behaves in a way and
then when the plant tissue is is um
dying
the pathogen expresses order genes and
the transcriptto changes completely from
what we call the early stages to the
late stages to from biotrophy to
necotrophy and you can see that in I
don't expect you to to to see all the
the gene expression here but we have the
different time points after inoculation
in the x axis and you have all the genes
in the y- axis. What I want to highlight
is what we have four three different um
patterns of expression. We have the ones
that are in culture, the ones that are
during the biotrophy, the early time
points of the infection and the later
time points of the infection in the
necotrophy.
So we went and analyze the genome. what
is going on in this genome of
phytotherra beta say compared to the
phytother infest they have to have
something different because they cannot
infect the same host. So let's start to
look at the at the genome as a whole and
we were surprised first because we knew
that the genomes of pin infestance that
are the two ones to the right are full
of transposon and repetitive sequences
in the genome. But when we saw the
genome of P beta that actually was
bigger than the P infestance one, it was
not because of repetition. It was
because it has a whole genome
duplication.
So when you take some regions from the
phyto infest genome, you see them
duplicated in the genome of B beta. And
is very intriguing because it's the
first time we see this in the phyto
lineage. And I'm going to talk also
about the genes. So what are the host
range determinants? When a pathogen
attacks a plant, it will secrete a lot
of proteins, what we call the aectors.
So a pathogen like phyto secretes what
we call the cytoplasmaticus.
So I'm going to talk about the factors
that are secreted during the early
stages that we call biotrophy and
someectors that the pathogen secretes
when it goes to necroty. So I'm going to
talk about the RXLR and the
prinrossectors
and it also has a lot of apoplastictors
that target host enzymes and other
targets and it's interesting because
when you have this figure that is the
the and I I forgot to put the y- axis
but in in the x-axis we have the three
prime flanking intergenic region in the
y- axis the five prime. So in the lower
end of the figure to the to the left and
the bottom you will have these gene
dense uh repeat pull regions and in the
other corner you have the gene sparse
repeat rich regions and we say that the
phytoter species have these two two
speed genomes because they have these
gene dense repeat poor regions but you
have these gene sparse where you will
find all the aectors. Most of the
aectors are in these repetitive regions
that the pathogen uses as a reservoir
for new um variations and new um new
aectors to attack different pathogens.
So we focus on these um secreted
proteins. We found that PETA has a
higher number of secreted proteins. You
can see here that you have the secreted
proteins and and you have more in the in
the PET
and you have and it was interesting that
we have more RXLR. So these aectors that
are secreted in the biotrophic you can
see peta say at the last one with more
of these aerox xlr proteins but less of
the necotrophic crinkler ones
and then we compare which were where
were where which ones were unique to
beet to the different species and is
really interesting work that one of my
students did because we could find
comparing the genomes of all these
pathogens all these phytoeras that we
can find that peta say for example has
more unique of these rxlrs
that are I I'm not going to show you but
we also compare with the the
transcripttoies and are the ones that
are expressing plants so so the the the
the hypothesis I think it's it's right
that these unique help phtotherabetas to
attack these three tomatoes. What we
have to do of course is to silence these
aectors and to see if we have a
different disease outcome. But we have
as mentioned less crinkle uh aectors.
You can see PETA here uh the ones that
are secreted during the necroty.
And we compare the two. We again we see
that PE pa cell has less unique of these
necotrophic aectors but has more of
these biotrophic aectors. And again
these um necotrophic and or these are um
in these gene sparse region that are the
ones in in green um the RXLRs. And we
confirmed that this biotrophy well
actually we didn't confirm that this
biotrophy are more expressed in the
early time points because we saw a very
diverse pattern of expression. What you
are seeing here is the pattern of
expression during the time points after
inoculation but we confirm that the
necrophy are indeed express in the
necrophy part of the ex of the
inoculation that are the later time
points. Okay, I'm going to jump very
quickly to end up my presentation to
talk about what we also uh try to do to
control this pathogen and is a very nice
study conducted by some of my students
back in Colombia where we targeted this
denovo pyramidine biosynthesis um
pathway
and we described all the the synthesis
of pyramidine and we found that some of
these enzymes enmes have been attractive
attractive for drug development. Um
actually the one of these enzymes the
human enzyme the fourth enzyme that I'm
showing in here has been attractive for
drug development and is the target of
one compound but also in plasmodium
fiparum
uh they have uh as said and they are
undergoing phase two of clinical trials
of another compound that is targeted
against this enzyme and remember that
plasmodium is very closely related
with our phytoter. So we started to see
when when during the infection these
enzymes are expressed and it was
interesting that all the the enzymes
that are in the novo pathway the ones
that produce the pyramidine are
overexpressed induced in the biotrophic
moment of the expression. is really
clear in the f in panel A and panel C.
While in the salvage um the the the
enzymes that are in the salvage that is
the ones that take the pyramidines from
the host are repressed in the early time
points but are induced when the plant is
dying and the pathogen is stealing the
the the nutrients from a death plant. So
what we did with another student is to
take one of these compounds that is
already registered that is know we know
that is safe in humans and see if we can
control the enzyme. So what we did first
is to confirm the mitochondrial
localization of the enzyme. So we show
that is located in the same in in the
same places where we have the
mitochondrial marker or reporter. We
then uh did some assays of this compound
to see if inhibits the grow of the
pathogen and indeed if we increase the
dose we have less grow of the pathogen
and we compare that with corset that is
a fungicide and finally something that
is important is like we show that this
compound doesn't affect the host the
solenum the potato enzyme as well as the
phytoera because if we want to use that
compound we cannot
inhibit the enzyme from the potato. So
what are the new avenues of my research
here in Ithaca? Uh so I'll still focus
so I arrived here two years ago. I only
started my lab one year ago but I'm
going to focus in phyto infestence
working in the population dynamics. We
still studying the population genetics
of the pathogen here in the states
monitoring the population. We are going
to show uh to assay new compounds that
are already registered to see if we can
control phytoera with new modes of
actions, new molecules. But I'm starting
a new pathway in in this research that
is the study of the microbiome because
the microbiome is the first line of
defense that a plant has. When the
pathogen lands on a on a leaf, it has to
defend against all the microorganisms
that are on that leaf. So we want to
understand how the microbiome interacts
with the pathogen. Why some some plants
like golden berry are totally resistant
to the pathogen while we have others is
besides the genetic makeup of the plant.
I was telling you that I'm continue to
monitor the populations of the pathogen
here in the states. we are going to
assay all the registered compounds we
have for um this pathogen or another or
other pathogen that are closely related
to phytora but I'm going to start
working also on the microbiome because
the microbiome is the first line of
defense that the plant has when a
pathogen lands on on it on the leaves or
on the stem etc. So we want to
understand what is the role of
microbiome in the disease outcome and we
cannot forget that I come from the
second most biodiverse country in the
world. I have described a lot of its
biod diversity especially in fungal
species. We have described a lot of
fungal new fungal species and um from
macro or micro fungi. So I will love to
continue exploring this diversity in a
very sustainable way because I think it
has the answers for a lot of problems we
are facing now. And finally I would like
to thank my my lab at BTI. This picture
was taken from the last field season
during the summer my collaborators
around the world and my group in
Colombia the funding sources for this
work I presented today. and I will be
very happy to answer any questions you
may have.
>> Yeah. So, thank you very much Dr. Rest
triple. Um, what we would like to do now
is open the floor for questions. We also
have a brief survey that we will send
through email and possibly through the
chat. Um, so if anyone has questions,
please feel free to ask. Now the well,
one of the first questions I have is are
you seeing um differences in the
pathogens as climate change has occurred
over time? Like are you seeing them
moving into different areas? Are they
moving up more north now?
>> Yeah, in Colombia we saw that, Ricardo.
We saw that every time we go to the
field, the breeders are putting the
potatoes up in the mountains uh to
escape from the pathogen that we see
more oper and and surviving freezing
temperatures. So um and so they go up
and up. So because they also come from
the from other crops. So yes, in
Colombia we saw that. I haven't seen
this in the states because I'm I haven't
studied so long this population here,
but I'm sure we will see some changes
especially the survival of the spores uh
in heat and temperatures.
>> Yep. Yeah, it's an interesting question
uh agriculturally because you know the
potato famine in Ireland caused a huge
economic disruption and potentially you
know if it gets into a monoculture
potato crop like the US or or you know
somewhere in North America it could also
be very disruptive. Do the diverse
proteins in P betasai have more
specified functions to better infect
tree tomato cells specifically and
contribute to its high affinity for tree
tomatoes versus other members of the
Solanosa family?
>> Yeah. Well, this is a very good question
and um well until now it doesn't appear
to to have so many different um
different functions. Apparently they
belong to the same families we have seen
in other intestines but um we have new
targets. So probably these new targets
are the one that confer the the ability
to infect a new uh beta say. So we are
seeing new targets in in enzymes of the
host but we cannot say if it's exactly
those new targets that are making the
difference or the combination of
different aectors. That's why we want to
now start um silencing the different
aectors to see if we have a different
outcome in PE beta in in the solenoium
sorry
>> what contributes to the geographical
changes in lineage distribution is it
vectors agricultural practices import of
contaminated seeds/imp imports
>> uh my good friend Julian thank you for
the question so yes well actually
everything contributes. Um well, for
example, in Colombia and Ecuador that we
have the same lineages because we have
this like porous borders that everything
goes and come through our borders in in
South America. But um we see that we
have different um lineages in different
countries is um Julian I think is
because we have different host for
example when I didn't show that but when
we saw the difference of lineages from
Colombia and Venezuela we saw that we
have different lineages in the two
countries is because you we use totally
different potatoes. When I went to
Venezuela they use cultivars that we
don't know in Colombia. So the pathogen
gets adapted to those um to these
different varieties of potato.
So I was wondering like do you also see
like these pathogens do you also see
horizontal gene transfer where they pick
up um like um features from other types
of pathogens and and make them like a uh
they evade some like host immune system
traits just make them a better pathogen
overall
to make them more difficult to deal
with.
>> Sorry Ricardo, can you repeat? Oh, I was
asking um if you see um indications on
these pathogens for for like gene
transfers between pathogens.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh yes and actually not only from
pathogen to pathogen but also from
bacteria to these pathogens, fungi to
these pathogens we see and we have also
described some viruses that live within
the iy of the of the pathogen. So it's a
yeah it's a jungle out there. Yeah.
>> Is P betaai easy to manipulate with
tools such as crisper? Could that be
used to study gene function?
>> Thank you Dylan for the question.
Actually we haven't tried in beta say we
have tried in pinfestance and we have
transformed pin infestant in your
crisper. uh is not something that is
very reproducible right now and we are
going to collaborate with a group in
Denmark that apparently do that better
than us more reproducible but I guess
once you can do it in infest and I don't
see why we can do it in um in peta say
because the the cell wall is the same um
I think it's um the the
actually it can be simpler because P
beta say is deployed while P infestance
sometimes is triploed or have three
zombies so it's more complicated to do
and that's why it's so less reproducible
but yeah we haven't tried but I guess it
will be easier than in P infestence
>> would you expect in the US population a
diversity driven
more by cultural practices instead of
host diversity
>> okay thank you Nadia it's so nice to see
all my students asking me questions um
and from Canada in different parts of
the world. Well, Julian is close to you
but but Nadia is in Canada. So yes, I
would say yes Nadia because we don't
have that explosion of diversity but we
are seeing more Cape Gooseberry growing
in the states. You can actually you see
to the grocery stores and you see these
ubas in different markets, but we put
those in the field this last summer and
they were so nice. Nobody attacked them.
They are like the captain Americas of
the they have the shield and no pathogen
at all in the cape gooseberries we put
in the field. So I would say that
diversity is going to d is going to be
um more
caused by practical cultural practices
than host diversity. Yes, that's a very
good question and and and if I can say
more about that question is what we see
in the states because in the states we
see preference very strong host
preference between the potato strains
and the tomato strains. So it's only
that but within the potato strains you
see difference because of cultural
practices that you can see different
kind of population in in North Carolina
to the ones in New York to the ones in
Idaho. Yeah.
>> Interesting. What uh what direction do
you want to take for the host
microbiome? Because I'm here at the
Broad which is known for the Stanley
Center and there's been links with kind
of like autism and microbiome and some
of these psychiatric disorders. So
there's a host of health issues that you
can look at the microbiome through.
>> Yeah, I think that we can take a lot of
examples for the human microbiome.
Ricardo, actually it's been very
inspiring to read all these papers about
the the the cases in humans to to
understand what we should do in in the
plant and in the plant. I have studied
the endopites is these organisms that
live inside of the plant without co
causing symptoms or apparent damage and
there is a lot of different um organism
manipulating the host immunity. So I
want to understand what is going on if
on top of this microorganism we put a a
pathogen and then we change the
microbiome and we can see if there is a
difference disease outcome like in
humans if we change the microbiome can
we control diseases can we do something
and I'm sure we can we can find
something interesting to control the
disease. Yep.
>> Right. Well, thank you very much again
for your presentation. It was very
interesting. Um, we have two more
minutes. If we get any more
questions, we can answer them, but I
think we will end at the top of the
hour. So, if you have any questions for
us, please feel free to ask. We're super
interested in in this type of work. Um,
I used to work I started my PhD well, I
started my research career in a plant
biology lab, actually. Um, and you know
>> what happened, Ricardo? What happened?
>> I I I ended up having
>> What did you do?
>> I ended up doing psychiatric genetics
and looking for genes for autism and
stuff. But
>> okay, you can come back anytime.
>> Anytime.
>> Yeah, it was it was really nice to to be
here and to to have this opportunity.
Thank you again, Anamaria, for the
invitation and you all, Ricardo. And
awesome.
>> Thank you again, everyone. Thank you,
Sylvia, for joining us. And um thank you
for everyone's participation because um
this is what we wanted out of the
speaker series. So this is a great way
to end Hispanic Heritage Month with with
this kind of of of work. So uh we hope
to see everyone in our next next series
next month.