in this video let us look at an
application of the probabilistic method
to graph Theory we'll prove what is
known as The Crossing number inequality
now what is the Crossing number of a
graph if I give you a graph sometimes
it's possible to draw the graph on a
plane without Crossings for example the
complete graph on four vertices can be
drawn on the plane without having any
pair of edges cross such graph is called
a planer
graph but sometimes it's not possible to
draw such a graph on a plane and the
classic example of such a graph is K5
the complete graph on five
vertices and then in that case maybe you
want to know what's the minimum number
of edge Crossings you can have in any
possible drawing of this
graph so the Crossing number of a graph
is defined to be the minimum number of
edge Crossings of a drawing of G of this
graph G on a plane using continuous
curves as
edges it is a classic fact that K5 the
complete graph on five vertices does not
have a planer drawing but it is possible
to draw this graph using only one
Crossing and we can do this by adding
one vertex to this K4 drawing and draw
edges like this and the final Edge we
need to do a crossing over
here okay so this example illustrates
that the Crossing number of K5 is
one if you give me a graph with lots and
lots of edges should I expect that its
Crossing number is necessarily
High turns out that's what the Crossing
number inequality always
guarantees the theorem says that in a
graph G with vertex set e vertex set V
and Edge set e
if e this Edge set is at least four
times the number of
vertices then the Crossing number of G
is at least the following quantity so on
the order of the number of edges cubed
divided by number of vertices squared
here C is some constant some absolute
constant
okay so this is a theorem that we'll
prove in this video before proving it
let me illustrate U one Cory to uh yeah
let me stay one Cory to illustrate how
to think about this
result
if the number of edges in this graph
is on the order of the number of
vertices squared so
this notation here means that it is
larger than some
constant v^ 2 so here C doesn't have to
be the same as a c
earlier
then plugging this hypothesis into the
theorem we obtain that the number of
Crossings of G
is at
least on the order of V to the 4th power
so if has a lot of edges then the graph
must have a lot of Crossings and in fact
this is the right order of magnitude
because you can only have at most e s
number of Crossings each pair of edges
cross at most
once even if you just lay out all the
vertices in general position on the
plane and draw the edges at straight
lines okay so in the rest of the video
let me demonstrate the proof of the
Crossing number
inequality I'll split the proof into
three
steps the first
step is an analysis of planer
graphs namely graphs with no Crossing
the following turns out to be true that
if G is a planer
graph so planer means that it is
possible to draw G in the plane without
Edge
Crossings then okay so in other
words The Crossing number of G is equal
to zero okay so then the conclusion is
that the number of edges of G is at most
three times the number of
vertices another way to say the
conclusion is that the average degree of
this graph is at most
six this conclusion can be
deduced
from a fact from topology known as
Oilers
formula which says that if you draw the
graph in the plane in some way so for
example this is some
drawing then the number of vertices
minus the number of edges plus the
number of faces equals to two here by
face we count each individual cell as
well as the outside cell so this drawing
has three
faces and it has four vertices and five
five edges and you can verify that this
Oiler identity is true in this case but
it is also true in
general starting with Oilers formula we
can then put some bounds on the number
of edges and faces and vertices relating
them to each other using some
inequalities to derive this conclusion
and so let me not do that step I refer
you to the lecture notes if you want to
see the
details the second step of the pro
Pro allows us to go from one Crossing to
many Crossings
okay so here's what
happens so
given a graph
G it may not be planner so maybe it will
require some Crossings to draw G in the
plane but starting with such a Crossing
we can delete some edges to make it
planer right so given G
by
deleting The Crossing number of G
edges we
can make
it pler okay so if you had so an earlier
example of K5 where this is not planer
but there's only one Crossing and by
deleting one of the edges corresponding
to that
Crossing and we remove one Edge and we
end up with a planer
graph well in this planer graph the
inequality in step one must be satisfied
so the number of edges of G minus The
Crossing number of G so these are the
deleted
edges must be at most three times the
number of vertices of
G
rearranging this
inequality we obtain the lower
bound on the Crossing
number being the number of edges minus 3
* the number of vertices
so the idea here is really to go from
one Crossing namely that if this
inequality e less than equal to 3 V is
not satisfied then we get at least one
Crossing but then keep on deleting these
Crossings we can go from one Crossing to
many
Crossings let's pause and examine this
bound that we just proved it is a valid
bound but it's not that great for
example in this corollary when e is
under the order of quadratic and number
of vertices the conclusion that we will
get at this stage is also quadratic in
the number of vertices which is not as
high as we would like which is the
fourth power in the number of
vertices so this brings us to the
third step and this is a step where
we'll use the probabilistic method and
this step I'll call the bootstrapping
step where we go from a weak bound to a
much stronger Bound by using
sampling in this step
let's consider some P while decide this
P later on so to be decided but it's
some number between zero and
one and let's consider a subgraph of G
obtained by keeping
every vertex
of
G
with
probability P independently at
random and deleting the other vertices
when we delete the other vertices we
also throw away all the edges that are
adjacent to the deleted
vertices this process then produces a
different graph G
Prime which contains a subset V of
vertices those V Prime so those are the
vertices that are kept by this random
process and then V and then e Prime is a
set of edges that were kept namely the
edges of G that fall between the
remaining vertices in V
Prime let's think about this graph G
Prime here well it is a graph so
whatever we proved in step two still
applies to this smaller
graph namely The Crossing number of G
Prime is at least the number of edges in
this G Prime minus three times the
number of vertices in this G
Prime okay so this is a true and valid
inequality
let's well remember that g is given as a
graph is deterministic but we introduce
some Randomness to produce G Prime G
Prime is a random
graph so this inequality is true for
every instance of this random
graph but it's also Al true than in
expectation so let's take the
expectation of both
sides expectation on the left and the
expectation on the right which by linear
of expectations we
can distribute the expectation into each
term
okay let's think about the various terms
the easiest one to think about is the
expected number of vertices that remain
while each vertex is kept with
probability P so the expected number of
remaining vertices is p * the original
number of
vertices next the expected number of
edges well an edge is kept if both its
end points remain and the probability
that both its end points are chosen is
p^ s
so this quantity is p^2
time the original number of
edges and finally and the slightly
tricky one is the expected number of
Crossings now if I have a Crossing in my
original graph
G one way to go about thinking about G
Prime is to what take the same planer
drawing take the same drawing of G on
the
plane and use that drawing for G Prime
so G Prime is obtained by keeping some
of the vertices and so if we use the
same drawings then this Crossing is
kept with probability P to the 4th
now G Prime is a different graph it's a
smaller graph so potentially there's a
different way to draw G Prime that
produces even fewer
Crossings but nevertheless we have an
inequality because we could have always
kept the cross the drawing from
G and so we do always have this
inequality here so so this inequality
comes from keeping the same drawing but
keeping in mind that it doesn't have to
be an equality because we could have
chosen a different drawing for G
Prime
okay so we derived this inequality here
and by bringing this P to the 4th power
to the other
side and rearranging we obtain the
inequality that the Crossing number of G
is at least P to Theus
2times the size of the edge set * 3 to
the pus 3 * the size of the vertex set
of
G
okay P was some parameter that we we
have yet to specify and from this
expression then we can optimize for the
value of
P so and one way to do this and because
we only look for a bound that is up to a
constant factor is to set P to be
four time the number of vertices divided
by the number of edges of the
graph and it is important here that the
hypothesis of the theorem the number of
edges is at least four times the number
of vertices so that this p is indeed
between 0o and one if P ended up being
some number bigger than one then this
proof would not have made sense it would
not make sense to choose with
probability bigger than one but p is
between zero and one so this makes sense
and with this choice of P continuing the
earlier expression we find that it is
equal to
1 over 64 * the number of edges cubed
divided by number of vertices squared
and that finishes the proof of the
result showing that the Crossing number
inequality holds with C being the
constant 1 over 64 although the precise
value is not so
important this is a beautiful
demonstration of the probabilistic
method and let me Recall review what
happened in this
proof first we looked at what happens to
planer graphs those with no Crossings
and here we derived some bound on the
number of edges that such a graph can
have and then we said that if you start
with a graph and then remove all its
crossings by removing one Edge according
to its each Crossing we can then deduce
some lower bound on the number of
crossings from the first step
then it gives us this fairly weak bound
lower bound on the number of
Crossings and the final step I think is
the most interesting mathematically is
this bootstrapping step where starting
from a fairly weak
bound we then take our graph G and
Sample it down to a smaller subgraph and
apply the weaker bound to the smaller
subgraph this allows us to boost the
weak bound into a much stronger bound
that turns out to be the what is claimed
in the result in the
theorem so this finishes the proof of
the Crossing number
inequality and it's just one of many
beautiful demonstrations of the
probabilistic method in combinatorics
and graph Theory