Okay, Tar has just joined us, I believe.
>> Hey, everyone.
>> Hey, TK.
Well, welcome. Uh and just as a a brief
introduction, um I'm really very proud
to introduce Tar Mansour to everyone. uh
he graduated from MIT
about six years ago or seven years ago
and he was actually in this class and so
uh we're really very pleased that he has
come as a guest lecturer and his
background he left when he left MIT he
joined really the giants of Wall Street
um Goldman Sachs, Citadel and
Bridgewwater. daughter. I'm sure most of
you are very familiar with those names.
And three years ago, he uh started Khi
with uh Luana Lopez Laura uh another MIT
student uh and I think it's been a
phenomenal success especially in the
last month. So let me hand it over to
Tar to share his experiences and details
on Kelshi.
>> Well yeah well first of all thanks for
having me Peter um you know really
really excited to be back in the class.
I know the one I did last year um and I
think I did the year before that um and
uh maybe I'll talk a little about
background uh uh you know sort of
leading time. So, the way I'm thinking
about doing this is just I'll talk a
little about the story of Cali, how we
decide to do it, what is the long-term
vision, what we're trying to achieve.
Um, and then we'll do a little bit of
Q&A. Um, uh, and then basically we see
how it goes from there.
>> Excuse me, T. Just a quick question. Um,
your your video isn't uh on for us. I
don't know if you can turn it on. That
would be great.
>> It should be on, but let me check. It's
on for me, so it's on on Zoom. So, let
me check. Let me double check. One sec.
Oh, that's great.
We can see you now.
>> Oh, great. Great. Sorry about that. I
think I'm in a little bit of a unstable
uh uh unstable Wi-Fi. Um so, yeah, I
mean I I um maybe I'll talk a little bit
about my my background. I I really like
going back to to to this class because a
lot of sort of the interest um in
financial markets and math um I think
stem from the class. So I I was born in
California. I grew up in Lebanon. I
think one of the
things that I basically really enjoyed
doing in in in middle middle school and
high school is I I actually really love
math. I I really really like math and um
I think felt like MIT was the right
place to go. Um
if for someone who basically really
loves math and and so got into MIT and
the thing I realized is the best
application of math is is finance. Um so
started working in in a number of um
whether it was like sell side or buy
side. So so banks like Goldman Sachs, I
worked at Citadel, I worked at small
prop a few small prop shops. Um and then
the thing I realized is like I would say
like I realized two things. I mean one I
like trading. I really like enjoy
trading but I I I I realized I prefer
sort of building more. I I I like I like
the sort of notion of building new
products, building something new that is
sort of tangible
and two um when I was at Goldman I mean
I think a lot of the things um that
we've sort of seen is that like you know
financial instruments do get developed
over time they take a long period of
time but there is a lot of opportunities
to basically develop new things and
there's always needs for a lot of new
things. One example in 2016 is that a
lot of people were actually trying to
get a hedge or an exposure to Brexit um
and they didn't really there weren't
really like the right instruments for
that. People use traditional financial
instruments like stocks and options and
others to get that sort of binary
exposure that people were looking for. U
and um it was just not perfect. it was
not as it was was a proxy was indirect
and and it was super expensive um
because it was what we call over the
counter OTC traded um and so what we
thought you know and it was kind of
really early at the time like well what
if we have a financial market so we have
a financial market for equities so that
prices equities one that prices credit
like bonds and so on one that prices
commodities and we have financial
markets for currencies what if we had a
financial market that prices basically
any question about the future any event
that is in the horizon that that is
meaningful economically or socially or
culturally. And I think the the thing
that became very apparent is
one if if such a market were to exist,
it could it has the potential to be the
biggest financial market of all. Um
mostly because it's just broader than
anything else that came before it. And
two, um there were a lot of regulatory
issues with that with that type of
market. Basically, historically, US has
made these uh illegal or unregulated.
They haven't let anyone do it. And you
know, at the time, we were very naive.
Um we
we thought, well, that sounds like a
problem we could solve. Um and
uh we just got into it. So, we decided
to start a company. Uh I didn't go back
to Citadel and and uh um and so we just
decided to start Koshi. And the premise
is really like it's like you know how
about what if we build sort of the first
large scale operation market and we want
to do it as a financial exchange a
regulated financial exchange. Um so that
this can become an asset class that's
traded one day by the large hedge funds
and institutions and and brokers and so
on and so forth. Um and you know when we
first started it was it was tough. So I
think that the the the the the
well well any company is really tough to
start but I think this was particularly
tough because like we it was kind of
funny story was like we called pretty
much every single securities derivatives
lawyer in the country and asked them
like hey we're trying to do this like
what what you know can you help us um
and the answer was basically like
everybody sort of like the range was
like either being laughed out of the
room all the way to sort of like hey
this is this is just not going to work
like the the CFTC and the regulators
just like never wanted to do anything
like this. And
the reason we kind of kept going is
because none of the answers are actually
intellectually satisfying. Like there
wasn't a kind of a clear answer like
okay why they're like well because of
you know there's they could be
manipulated like okay but like that's
solvable same it was solve with the
stock market. Um and then the other one
is like well it could be gambling. I was
like, well, why is it gambling and you
know something like uh you know a grain
futures not I mean you know some people
are specking on on grain futures and
sure some people are hedging on great
future but it's the same thing for
Brexit like a lot of people are exposed
to Brexit and
um we kept going we basically got the
company uh regulated uh we took three
years so we took two years and a half to
three to basically get it reg regulated
and we basically launched the first
legal exchange or legal prediction
market in the US after that um it took
us a very long time was it was very long
journey. Uh but we got the exchange, we
got the clearing house. Uh well, we got
the exchange at the time and we got up
and running. Um and you know um I think
Peter has seen the sort of journey of
the company. Um we um we we started
running and then we we we grew a lot and
then we had a bunch of sort of like I
would say like issues and and and
um and and infighting between us and the
federal government, the CFTC uh
especially this kind of prior
administration which was kind of really
tough on financial financial services
and financial innovation. Um and the big
thing that happened is they didn't let
us list the election market uh which we
always believe is kind of one of the
biggest markets uh of all basically we
uh it was a you know we took a very long
time to make that decision. It was very
tough one uh but we ended up suing the
federal government. So we were really
one of those sort of first you know uh I
would say examples of a of a of a
regulated company suing its own
regulator. Um is very tough and painful
decision to make at the time. Obviously
it was the right one now. uh looking at
looking back in retrospect um and we won
earlier this fall and and so that win
was actually the first time in a hundred
years that you can actually trade
legally on the election in the US and
that opens up a lot of opportunities
beyond the election. Uh because what the
lawsuit was about is like you know it's
really expanding the universe of of
things that are considered financial
instruments now. Um, and so where Kashi
is at now, um, you know, we've grown a
lot over the last few years, but
definitely the last month. Um, we have,
um, um, we've done over a billion of
volume in the last in the last month
alone. And, um, uh, you know, now kind
of as we think about our future
expansion plans, um, we're getting into
a number of different categories. Um,
you know, financial services, like just
just basically like financial markets,
sports. We want to basically have a
market for every single piece of news
that's out there in the world. And uh we
want to over time what we're doing is
like we're integrating some of the large
brokerages where we're going to have um
um you know people can come to cash.com
to trade the asset but also if you want
to trade the asset from your own
brokerage account like 041k in your
stocks you'll be able to do that on
Schwab, Robin Hood, Fidelity and so on.
um we'll talk a little bit about sort of
um you know kind of finishing the
narrative of arc and then I'll talk some
of sort of personal stuff going from
being a student to starting a company
and so on but one of the things that um
you know was interesting throughout the
journey is uh a lot of what it basically
ends up taking is is just perseverance
um uh around um uh basically
perseverance towards the goal that
you're trying to achieve. Um, we, you
know, you know, I mentioned in the
beginning that we were naive when we
first started and in retrospect, I think
that was actually one of the best things
that or I'd say one of the best tools
that we had actually being naive. Uh,
because a lot of the people that like if
if we knew how hard it would be, we
probably just wouldn't have done it. Um,
and there's something to be said about,
you know, when you climb a mountain,
people tell you um just look at the next
step, one step at a time. uh don't look
at the at the summit just because you
know when you look at summit you get
tired. Um and I think there's a lot to
be said. I think this applies to pretty
much anything meaningful in life. I
think just doing anything meaningful
basically requires a lot of
perseverance. Um the company has raised
um u more than $100 million from a few
investors. Sequoia um KKR Schwab itself
uh YC and a bunch of others in Silicon
Valley. Um, and um, I think that's about
it. I think I covered most things. Um,
Peter, I was thinking we could do a
little bit of Q&A and then we can sort
of orient the conversation some of the
places that the students want to hear
about.
>> Yes. Great. Thank you, T. And let's see,
with questions just uh, so Tar can hear
you, we'll hand you a microphone or
we'll pass a microphone to you.
>> One, two.
>> Okay. I don't know where you can see me
from. Um this so yeah this is um like
really fascinating. I I I um I'm just I
have a question which is like what what
is the difference between like this and
like a betting market? Like um to me it
sounds like the same like you're you're
betting on an event. Um because surely
like if someone wanted to hedge against
Brexit, they could just go onto a bet
betting market and bet you know a
certain quantity of money on on whether
Brexit happens.
Um, a few things. So, there's a lot of
similarities. I mean, and I would say
there's a lot of similarities between
betting markets and just any traditional
financial market. There's a lot of
people that like are speculating or
betting or gambling on a lot really a
lot of markets including crypto and
stocks and really anything. But I think
like it's it's a bit more of a
structural difference. Like first of
all, this is an exchange. People are
trading against each other. We're not
there's no book there's no bookie.
There's no concept of bookie. And
actually any institution that wants to
hedge against Brexit would never do it
in a vetting market. Um just because you
know the prices are set by the bookie.
Uh they would do it probably with an
investment bank which is what they're
doing right now. Uh but the prices are
kind of bad at the investment bank. It's
like over the counter you know you
negotiate bilaterally with the
investment bank instead of just
basically doing it on on exchange where
like there's other people that are
independently pricing the events uh uh
so that you can basically know what the
right price is to basically make the
transaction at. Um I I I think like
there are a lot of similarities and
frankly like I I I haven't you know we
we don't really discern them quite quite
much. I I think like over time the two
are converging and they're going to be
end up being one and the same. Uh the
fundamental difference I would say like
from a regulatory or legal perspective
but also like sort of like why is it the
financial instrument is like are you
trading on natural risks or are you
trading on artificial risks? Right?
Right. So, like when you go to casino
and you roll a dice, um that's like a
risk that you're creating for the
purpose of entertainment. Whereas, you
know, um Brexit, that's that's not a
risk that you're creating for the
purpose of entertainment. That's a risk
that exists that some people have and
they're exposed to and they may want to
basically transfer it to someone else
and and so that's sort of the
delineation of why this is a financial
market and why um you know uh uh having
it on a on a financial market is
appropriate. Um but yeah, I mean I think
the two main difference like it is an
exchange like we have an order book
people are trading it the same way as a
stock market the same way they trade in
a stock market and then two um it's it's
it's risk that exists and so people can
basically do what they want with that
risk whether they want to get exposed to
it more by speculating or they want to
expose get exposed to it less by
hedging.
>> It's a great question.
>> Thanks. Can I just ask a quick followup
which is like is and this has just come
to my mind so it may be a silly question
but is there any like has there been any
like arbitrage opportunities between
like the betting markets and and this
exchange?
>> Yeah. I mean well well we're the only
legal one in the US. So there there's
kind of I mean in terms of there more
there's more arbitrage
between us and traditional financial
assets. So with the election for
example, people were arbitrage like a
lot of hedge funds were arbitrageing um
the election market with um uh other
assets like crypto or or like S&P and so
on and that we see we see a lot of that.
>> Okay. Yeah, that makes sense. That's
fascinating. Thank you.
I think Stephen, I don't know if you can
give him uh I don't know if you can
unmute yourself or
>> question.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yep. Yep.
>> Yeah. Um I'm also like interested in
careers in in trading as well and I find
it fascinating as well. So it's good to
hear that you were um interested in that
um and did that as a career. I was just
wondering how did your experiences
working um in trading kind of help you
to um or if if those skills helped you
with um like what you pursued at Pulse
or
>> um I I would say like um
maybe like a few things. So, so, so one,
I mean, it's always good to get
firsthand exposure into how things are
done in a market that you're you're like
trying to be trying to to to disrupt.
It's like good like you have to have a
reasonably good understanding of how
things work. And the thing I'd say is
like it's interesting like if you stay
in an industry for too long, it actually
gets a bit harder to disrupt it. you get
too conditioned for to how things are
done and and uh you you maybe you get
maybe you it gets harder for you to
become to to have any degree of of
diabete which I so I think it's not a
very good thing but I think some degree
of experience is good so that you have b
like based on understanding of what your
end customer how your end customer
basically thinks about the world and how
they use different products and adopt
them. Um, the second thing I think is
I would say I learned a lot from the
from the Citadel culture. Maybe less
from Goldman and some of the others, but
Citadel
u I really enjoyed working at Citadel.
Um, I I really like a lot of the aspects
of the culture and the way that things
are done. And I would say like it it was
interesting because I think had sort of
this like ultimate version of um
um
let's call it like sort of like
performance-driven culture but but but
and what I mean by that is like it's a
full meritocracy is very little sort of
like management layers even if you're
young they will give you a lot of
ability to sort of take risks and and do
big things. Um, and they're uniquely fit
to do that because in trading that
something that's very unique to trading
is that you you have a P&L. It's
undeniable whether you're doing well
versus not. Uh, you know, if you make
money, you're doing well. If you're not,
you're not. Uh, whereas in a lot of like
in tech and others like there's a lot of
politics like you know, the boss likes
you versus not. I mean, there's just
like a lot lot of noise and and I think
we try to kind of bring that to to to
the culture of the company as much as we
can. We're very flat as a company. like
we have a lot of people, you know,
they're a few years out of college, a
lot of them are from MIT, you know,
they're they're running huge huge chunks
of the company already and with teams
and so on. Um, and and and just because
like, you know, for us it's very similar
like if you do well, you basically grow
extremely fast within a few months of
the company and if not then um and and
so and that comes a bit from the trading
culture, I would say.
>> Okay. Yeah, that makes sense. Thank you.
Uh I can feel in a question. Uh hey,
good to see you back in the class.
>> Um
>> good seeing you.
>> Good to see you. So uh can you talk a
little bit about uh your margin
requirement and also maybe uh central
clearing I guess uh you know you have
two parties right taking the opposite
side of a contract. I mean the payout
let's say is 100%. They they may have
paid you know a percentage of that total
payout. When the market moves do you
require them to post a variation margin
or how do you how do you monitor that?
>> Yeah. So we we are fully cash collarized
right now. So what it means like people
put the money up front for their
positions
um and then we basically mark to market
every day. Actually mark to market on a
real-time basis. So we we we do it real
time. Um
we are going to introduce leverage next
year I think and that's going to be
pretty interesting. We're thinking about
you know kind of our margin model is
going to be um and maybe for the class
to explain. So so in a lot of financial
markets
you what what people consider kind of
margin or leverage is like when you buy
when hedge funds basically buy let's say
you know um an interest rate future or
like S&P future uh let's say they want
to buy like a million dollar worth of
S&P future. They don't put up a million
dollars with the clearing house and the
exchange. They put up, let's say,
$100,000 or $10,000, which would be 10%
1% margin. And then as the thing moves
over time, you know, the clearing house
asks you to, you know, if you if you
made a little bit of money, the clearing
house pays you. And if you lost, the
clearing house asks you to put up a bit
more margin to cover your losses. And it
goes like that over time. Uh, Gaus is a
simpler model where like we actually ask
for 100% upfront. We tell everyone like,
"Hey, give us all the money up front so
that there's no risk in the system." And
you're always sure that anything you
lose is like what you lose up front,
like what you put up front. You cannot
lose more than that. Um, over time,
we're going to start introducing
leverage, which is like we don't take
100% up front. Um, and that's what Jake
was asking about. And I think it's a
complicated that's a complicated thing
because regulators are becoming very
strict about how we do this and we have
to be very we need to make sure that
nothing like 20 2008 can happen again.
Um and so there's a lot of like
requirements around how this needs to be
done. Um and
uh um you know so we expect to basically
increase maybe margin like end of next
year potentially um uh and you know
we'll see how that goes. We do have some
products where for example if there's a
lot of strong correlation between two
products we return some collateral to
the participant um and we've already
started doing some of that. Um but you
know over time we'll do more and more.
Yes it's a great question.
Yeah. So I I have a question on like
kind of how the projections for the
company have changed since the election.
Like I assume there's a lot more volume
going through Koshi during that election
period. Have you guys been able to
retain a lot of that trading volume or
did you see a huge falloff and like how
did just the election general change
where you see the company going?
>> Yeah, I mean I think I think it's like
the election. So, it's obviously it's
super huge, but it's interesting because
our volume right now is actually higher
than it was um in the days leading up to
the election. So, and I think that's how
exchanges work like once you kind of
acquire a lot of like acquire and on
board and open accounts for customers,
they kind of retain they stick they do
other products. Now, we're seeing a lot
of uptake in crypto um we're seeing a
lot of optics in our economics product.
We're seeing uptake on a lot of the
politics like who's going to be in the
cabinet, who's gonna there's kind of all
these questions about like what what's
government going to look like in the
next year. Um and then you have a lot of
like you know crazy categories like
weather people like come and are very
active on sort of daily weather markets
and then entertainment markets and so
on. So we see a lot of opportunities
across all these categories. Um and uh
yeah I mean I don't think like so you
know it's not going to be the same
levels that what we've seen in the kind
of two days leading up to the election
but I think we're we're we're you know
at a much higher level than what we were
prior to the election. Now it was a huge
think of it as like a huge marketing
marketing moment for the company. Um and
sort of and that enabled sort of the
product to go mainstream.
It's
>> yeah good to see you. Yeah. Um
>> seeing you.
>> Yeah. Um a a question. So uh can you uh
reveal how what's the percentage between
institutional clients and and
individuals uh on culture at the moment
>> right now I say the breakdown of volume
is like 30 40% institutional uh and the
rest is retail um um and I expect it to
basically go towards 50/50
um over time um
it's interesting like institutions do a
lot more volume But you can charge them
less whereas retail like you know
individual customers they do less volume
but they can be charged much more and
you know historically you know people
have seen the business model of being
kind of institutional first like the
large exchanges like you know NASDAQ or
CME they're mostly institutional
um uh but I think it was kind of a
strategic mistake and I think they're
waking up to it. They're realizing like,
oh god, like people on Reddit and
Twitter and and average people now hold
a lot of the power, right? Like, you
know, they can decide that a company
like Nvidia is going to be worth, you
know, a few trillion dollars like and
and and that wasn't possible before.
Like people are richer now. People are
more involved in the financial market.
Um, and they're less price sensitive.
And so you see companies like Coinbase
are doing incredibly well. And yes, they
have much less like Coinbase volume on a
yearly basis is around like I think like
50 to 60 billion. Um, CME's volume is
like a quadrillion, right? Like it's
like not even comparable. Um, but
Coinbase charges a lot more, right? They
they charge you a lot more per per
dollar traded. Um, and and I think we
see that same balance and and I think
that the you know, it's interesting like
the thing that we see
and I see this trend sort of continuing
in the next few years, especially with
the Trump administration. um like
there's a very strong appetite for new
like new financial markets and new media
like there's a lot of distrust in the
system both in the sort of Wall Street
and financial markets but also media
people just don't don't really believe
the kind of pundits and traditional
social authorities and and I think like
prediction markets are very uniquely
suited to be at the intersection of both
and that's a fun like that's a like
that's a retail first market. It's like
a retail first and then the institutions
follow rather than institution first and
then figure out how to get the retail to
adopt essentially. Um and and we're
seeing that. We're seeing that.
>> Right. Very interesting. Thank you,
>> Stephen.
Yeah. I had a question about because you
said that you were trying to also get
into sports as well, right? Uh, so I was
wondering if you like plan on offering
like or similar things to like other
sports books and stuff like traditional
bets like money lines and and stuff like
that or would it be more of like the
more more like a broader prediction type
sports bets?
>> We um
um that's a good question. Uh both
basically is the way I put it. Uh I I
you know I think uh both um you know the
the the prediction stuff is the one
that's more interesting because that's
the one that like people and news thinks
about like what are some of the kind of
big things that are going to happen in
the next few few few months or years and
then the money line is just like very
retentive like people come back and they
do it over and over and then they engage
with the product meaningfully in a very
consistent way. So I think that yeah I
think that the answer is both. We have
some regulatory work to do on that
front, but the the next administration
is gonna be very favorable. I mean,
Trump himself has been coding our
markets a lot. He loves the market. He
loves the company. He's I think it's
gonna see a big shift from, you know, um
an administration that was somewhat
anti- financial innovation to admission
is going to be very very pro financial
innovation and prediction market
specifically.
>> Okay. Yeah, that makes sense.
>> So, Tar, I feeling another question. Uh
I don't know if you can talk about the
revenue of the company. Is the company
profitable so far or the revenue model
is from a commission model just to kind
of give students some idea how uh why
you know the investors are interested in
owning the company.
>> Um the company can be profitable if you
want to but uh we don't right now. Um
and you know it's you know often times
it's a little bit of a counterintuitive
thing but I think you know increasing
the like
growth at this stage is more important
than profitability in a lot of cases. Um
and because and the reason why exchanges
like exchanges are very popular
businesses. They're very hard to set up.
It's unbelievably hard to get an
exchange up and running. It's just
really really difficult. But when it's
up and running and you have liquidity
it's actually one of the best form of
businesses. It's some of the most
profitable businesses are exchanges
actually. Um uh and so right now the
strategy is basically like hardcore
expansion just grow grow go mainstream
get people used to the asset. um we're
making revenue but it's just like we're
reinvesting it all into marketing and
growth and then over time we're
basically like you know as we deserve
taper taper and as we get to even larger
scale basically like you know turn on
the the profit machine and the source of
revenue it's interesting like we make
money on um uh on tra trading fees like
like CME or New York Stock Exchange you
take you take a fee of every transaction
like if you put $100 on cash we take one
to $2 and then uh on market making so we
have a separate arm it's a bit like
Citadel market making on this product
and they're already kind the one of the
prime market makers. They have
competition so they compete a lot
against SIG which was one of our major
partners and then there's a few other uh
prop shops or like market making like
like a hedge fund in the in the the firm
and then three over time right now we
make it all free and open source but the
data is very valuable. We have a lot of
very valuable data about like trends and
where where the word is going um and and
and and there's a lot of demand to kind
of like get the data but for now we're
just like making it open source. Anyone
can use it. Anyone can make use of it
over time. We can basically capture
value at that as well.
Just a follow up on that. Uh you know
you mentioned Citadel SIG those market
makers. Uh how do you incentivize them
to uh you know come to uh Koshi and uh
are there any requirements of how tight
the bid offer the spread they need to
make um when they make market on certain
contracts?
>> Yeah. So no there definitely
requirements. So, so you know, I'll give
you an example. In the election market,
there had to be one cent spread with a
million dollar on each side, uh, at
least. Um, and it was funny because Jeff
Yas, the founder of SIG, actually texted
Elon and asked him if he wanted to do a
$100 million trade on Koshi uh during
the the election, but then Elon was too
concerned of conflict of interest and
uh, and a bunch of things, but and they
could have done it with one cent. So,
the spreads were very very tight. I'm
saying this because like they could have
done they could do up to $100 million
within like one cent slippage uh which
was which is really awesome and so yes
there are requirements around spread and
and and
u and and depth. I think the way we
think about like the ecosystem needs to
be or the way that it's structured
um um um uh you know you give some
incentives at the beginning of market so
that after that you basically let let it
do and their incentives basically they
they're getting flow they're trading
against a bunch of other people and then
they hope to make money market making
and doing like getting better ass spread
essentially and so that's a sort of like
it I would say like the structure and
it's pretty common structure in in in in
the traditional markets I think your
question is good Because the stock
exchanges, they do a lot of incentive
because stocks, there's a lot of stock
markets. There's like a lot of stock
exchanges. They're very competitive with
each other because of the way that the
SEC has set up rules. In the CMC world,
there's not a lot of competition. It's
actually very monopolistic in nature.
Like each one has their like CME has
interest rate swaps and and S&P. ICE has
all the energy stuff. And I think we may
be able I think looks like we're going
to be able to dominate anything that's
event related over time. Uh, so um I'm
just intrigued as to how you've gone
from like just like working in like um a
company like Citadel or Goldman to just
having this idea of this um exchange and
like actually just being able to make it
because to me it seems like even if I
had like an idea of like oh this would
be a great thing to turn in into an
exchange like just the idea of actually
making that happen seemed really um like
hard to achieve. So, like how from like
like from the idea to actually like
getting it into a reasonable um like uh
product, how did how did you like what
did you have to do? Did you just like
have to literally start emailing people
in the industry and then start like
working your way up? How did that work?
>> Yeah.
>> So, yes. Yes. That's it. I mean, that's
literally it. like I there's one of the
um
I I'll say a few things about this and
because I thought about this a lot. So,
um,
it was a tough decision to leave Citadel
like when I and I I don't I think Peter
you and I had a conversation about this
as well. Like I I think at the time like
we um
you know Citadel pays a lot of money,
you know, like like even as a first-time
it's like crazy and and so like you know
I didn't come from a very privileged
background. So like I remember I had a
conversation with my parents like like
hey I wanted to start this company like
oh what is it about? I was like oh this
thing called prediction. viously they
had no idea, you know, what what what I
was talking about and I was like, "Yeah,
yeah, I mean, there's another problem."
So, it's like illegal in the US now. And
and you know, and I want to do this and
and they're like, "Okay." And and so
like you have to leave your job. I was
like, "Yeah." And then they obviously
got inflamed. They were like, "Well,
what are you talking about? Like these
guys are paying all this money. Like
what doesn't make any sense?" And and I
think like the thing that pushed us to
do it is like I I think I kind of like,
you know, some people make decisions
based on regret minimization. It's like
in 10 years, what part would I regret mo
most? And I just thought I would regret
if I hadn't done it. I just thought like
I would be very regretful if I didn't do
this or at least try or give it a shot.
And so I I I just had to do it. And then
I really like the idea. I just like
really love like I love the idea of
basically creating a market where you
can price anything and making the world
just smarter about the future. Um
so then like okay like what did we
actually do?
uh
the the simplest way to describe
like like what it takes to build a
company. So, so Mark Anderson has this
code, I forgot if it's Mark Anderson or
Ben Harwoods, one of the 286C guys, um,
about how like when he talks about to a
lot of CEOs, he basically has this kind
of whole thing about like all the, you
know, the the the pretty like the good
CEOs usually respond with like, okay,
like when he asked them, "How did you do
it?" They say, you know, it was like a
great strategy, uh, you know, great sort
of execution, we had all these great
decisions, blah blah blah blah blah. And
then he says, "The absolute great CEOs
um usually their answer is um is we
didn't give up. We just we just pushed
harder than anyone else." And and I I
think there's a lot of truth to that. I
I really do. Like because like when
you're young, like people say, "Well,
when you're young, you have to wait and
get experience to build a company." And
there's pros and cons to both. When
you're too experienced, I think it's
harder to be to be a little crazier and
do like bolder, crazier ideas. Uh but
when you're younger, you kind of don't
know much about anything really. Like
you don't know how to manage people. you
don't know how to uh you know raise
money. you don't do any and you just
have to stumble like you just have to
kind of like run and and fall and then
stand back and run and fall again and
stand back and then you do it enough
times then you get used to falling and
then getting used to falling is actually
one of the best superpowers you can ever
have literally like I think the the
capacity to kind of fall and stand back
up I think is the single best
determinant of the entrepreneurs that go
furthest really and and you can look at
it even you don't need to look at small
private companies like or big private
companies you can look at public like
massive large companies like you know
just look at the stock price of Meta and
Tesla and see how it goes. It's never
it's just not straight to the right.
It's you know goes to the [__] for a
few years then goes back up and then it
it repeats and and every cycle it goes
higher than the prior cycle and they
keep going. So, so I I think that's
really what it is. And I I you know kind
of when I think about sort of my younger
self like what is the type of advice I
would give you know I I think take more
risks and this one of the things I
learned a lot from my co-founder Lana
like she's always she's always been risk
loving. She never really really worried
about much. I I was more of like a
person that would think about optimizing
my career and what's the highest
expected value path and like you know
how how and what I learned over time
from the company from earlier is like
actually you just need to take more
risks just taking risks is a very good
is a is a very good way to live a life
because like what's the worst case you
fail and then you do it again um
and um I I would say number two is like
um pick something and just stick with it
like just try to pick something. If you
don't know what it is yet, that's okay.
Like, take a few years to figure that
out. But once you feel like you really
like and enjoy working on something, you
just pick pick something and just stick
with it. Like, just go for it and, you
know, have conviction. Um, and usually
the results the results end up being
pretty positive. It's a very very tough
road. I mean, Professor Gaming can tell
you about all a lot of the stuff we had
to go through to get here. It's a very
tough road, but if you have conviction,
you're excited about what you're working
on, I think you can get very very far.
>> That's great. So, did did you ever set
in your mind like um essentially like a
stop loss where you thought like right
well if this person like you know I've
asked I've asked this many people if
this person says no maybe it's not
actually possible or did you just never
have that in your mind you just kept
going
>> you know what I' what I've learned um
not really basically I mean like
definitely not like a people driven
thing like like what I've learned is
like also a lot is like don't don't
really listen to authority figures. Like
you'd be surprised by the extent to
which like
people just don't really know what
they're doing. And and by people I mean
like not like average I'm talking like
like the president of the United States
like the the the Supreme Court judge,
the you know Elon Musk, like like Mark
Zuckerberg, like people don't really
know what they're doing really like
everyone is figuring it out on the fly.
And it's interesting because like
if anyone had the answer of whether
something is going to be a multi-billion
dollar company, sorry about the noise by
the way. Um if anyone had the answer of
if anything was going to be a
multi-billion dollar company, they would
just do it like why like you know why
why didn't they just do it? So so in a
lot of cases like you cannot really get
the answer from outside. Like it's it's
interesting like you really can't you
just have to have it have it inside you
and you may be wrong. That's a risk. You
may be wrong and you may fail and it
might suck but that's a risk that you're
taking and um um but it has to come from
within you. It's like do you have a
conviction in this thing and do you
believe it it can work one day and if
you do then you know go for it.
>> That's amazing. Thank you so much.
>> So Tar, if I could just chime in there.
I think what uh Tar
um has is passion,
um persistence
and energy and you know knowing how hard
he worked and how inspiring he was um
that inspiration you know led to
significant investments from top people
in finance and so you know I think it's
you know a testament to those
characteristic He mentioned also um it's
a great uh benefit to have a good
partner and Lana Lopez Laura really I
think is a great uh partner with Tar and
they've uh helped each other achieve
this. though.
>> Yeah. No, I really appreciate I mean
maybe like my last few kind of parting
words unless there's any other
questions. I mean I think like
um you know kind of I was still at MIT
and I don't know how many of you are
sophomores, freshman, juniors, seniors.
But here's all the stuff I would tell
myself if I was still at MIT. Like um I
would take more classes like Peter's
class and less classes that are sort of
purely theoretical and like far removed
from from practical many practical
things. Um I would probably study a
little less and have a little bit more
fun. Um, and I would worry a little bit
less about the opt optimal career paths
and just sort of explore what interests
me more. Um, it's it's crazy the extent
to which a lot of these things matter,
much less than you think. And um uh uh
and a lot of life is just actually
trying things out and seeing what works
and just making sure you're excited
about the things that you're working on.
Um, but yeah, if you guys have any
questions, reach reach me. Just please
don't share the email, but it's
tarcy.com.
my first name at the name of the
company.com. Um, happy to help in any
way, shape or form. Um, but yeah, you
know, congrats to to you guys making it
to MIT and hopefully get out of MIT. Um,
and really excited to to be here. Thank
you for having me.
>> T, before you go, I have to ask you this
question. Uh, what was the most
memorable thing you learned from this
class when you took it? And do you
recall anything, you know, interesting
you heard from this class?
advice to the students. Yeah,
>> I I I I think I think there was like I
really like that every mathematical
concept had an application towards
finance
and and I think there was like a very
probable thing essentially like it was a
very very probable thing was like okay
well you know you kind of learning this
mathematical concept it's pretty cool in
of itself but then when you apply it to
finance you see there's likeual real
practicalities to the whole thing um and
um I think that stuck with me like I I
that that because a lot of the other
classes I was taking was basically
mostly pure math or like you know kind
of very removed from industry whereas
here like I remember one of the projects
we had to do was um there was this paper
we had to write
u um and I think the one I wrote it's
been a while it's been like I don't know
now like six years seven years but the
paper I had to write was um
we were running some form of regression
it's kind of complicated form of
regression on on
Now I remember I wrote a paper that was
trying to kind of use reinforcement
learning to predict the stock market. Um
and it was like I think our final paper
of the class and
that was pretty hard. I I don't think
our model worked as you would expect. Uh
but it was really interesting just
trying like I think that was very useful
after when I got went into trading like
you know people would be talking about
like markup chains and like how they
wanted to apply them at Citadel and I
kind of had already done that in the
past and and had already applied them
and when I used it at Citadel you know
um the P like holy [__] this guy's a
genius I'm like you don't know anything
like that people do this every day you
know um and that was the next MIT guy by
the way who's now you should Google him
John Termas he's one of the most
successful portfolio managers on on on
Wall Street um you know like one he's
he's a G like totally this this desk is
one of the best performing desks at
Citadel um the reports is that
apparently they made $2 billion in 2022
alone and they've been making more since
then and then they were impressed by
some of the stuff that I learned in this
class that I was applying on the desk so
um and I think this goes to kind of the
broader thing that I was I was
mentioning like I think it's just good
to be practical just just very good to
be practical like get very very smart
but also be practical because a lot of
the world is and you see it left
like like the people that have run
the largest company, even the largest
hedge funds are not exactly the
smartest. Maybe Jim Simons is like an
exception, but they're not exactly the
smartest. LTCM blew up and those were
the smartest guys. Um, you know, um, a
lot of the others like Steve Cohen and
and some of the others, they're pretty
smart, but they're more well-rounded.
They're just more much more wellrounded
than just being the best at math. and
and and I think there's a lot of
learning to that.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Well, great. Well, thanks thanks so much
for having me everyone and hopefully
we'll catch up soon.
>> Great. Thank you very much, TK.
>> Thank you.
But um but I think his his comments
about
um basically having passion and
persistence and energy you know you can
really achieve many things and achieve
your dreams. So uh I do want to you know
encourage you all to you know take stock
of that. Um and just as a general
comment about my career, um I started
off in academics and then found
consulting projects to be very
stimulating and engaging and I decided
to leave academics and start my own
company and ended up uh starting a
couple of hedge funds and then doing
investment management for 20 years. Um
then uh 10 years ago I uh had the
opportunity to come back to MIT and
teach and I've been savoring that uh
experience as well. So um don't be
afraid of changes in your life and you
know changing your paths and uh you know
taking risks you know leads to great
opportunities. So
hopefully you'll all benefit uh from
that kind of uh perspective. All right.