Caitlyn Becker reminds us that to design
a product is to design the processes by
which it is made. And approaching
problems at the interface of design and
manufacturing offers opportunities for
disruptive change. Navigating design,
manufacturing, and material spaces in
parallel becomes increasingly relevant
as we address modern challenges with
materials or environments that bring
both unique and beneficial attributes.
while at the same time imposing
stringent restrictions on design and
manufacturing. Today, Professor Becker
will discuss how taking an integrated
approach to design and manufacturing has
improved the reliability and extended
the reach of soft robots, enabling deep
sea exploration and biological sampling.
Please welcome Professor Caitlyn Becker.
[Applause]
[Music]
Thank you very much. I'm very excited to
be here. Uh let's see. Uh I'm going to
talk about how I use some uh materials
in non-traditional ways. And um I do
that kind of at the intersection of
machine design and manufacturing. I use
soft materials to make robots. I use
glass to make
structures. Now, um just a little bit of
context on me uh to give you some
background. So, I actually started at
MIT for undergrad uh in mechanical
engineering where I'm back now over a
little bit over a decade later, but then
I worked in manufacturing for a little
while and then went back to school at
Harvard to work on unusual robots and
now I'm back in the mechanical
engineering department. I worked in
medical devices, subcutaneous defibrills
and surgical staplers. Um, and then I
worked in nanop fabrication. So I had a
very hands-on approach to manufacturing
where essentially I figured out how to
replicate this structure, this fatonic
structure, first from a silicon wafer
and then by hand into
polymers and then turn that into a
machine that could do this in a
roll-to-roll format. So all by hand I
made everything that you see there and
basically figured out how I could
replicate features on the scale of a
50th of the diameter of your hair in a
roll-to-roll continuous format. And so
now what I try to do is then teach my
students how to be able to do this
fluently. how to go from kind of these
basic robots into something that's a
little bit more functional and then go
from kind of bespoke projects into
something where they can make largecale
kind of decisions and design. And so
what I'll talk about yesterday is a
little bit or sorry tomorrow is a little
bit of what we do with that with making
yo-yos and taking students into uh
industry. But then I'll also talk about
now kind of one some of my inspiration
of finding the intersection between
design and manufacturing and that was at
MIT in the glass lab where I now have
been actually a technical instructor for
15 years. So I teach manufacturing by
day for my day job and then at night I
go over to the glass lab and I teach
manufacturing for fun and for art. But
the reason I think this is relevant is
glass is if nothing an art form of
process design. And this is a piece that
I made about uh 10 years
ago. And actually the gentleman who's in
the background there is my collaborator
for the additive glass manufacturing
that I'll talk about in a little bit.
But essentially we have a lab in uh MIT
where basically the equations that we
teach in mechanics of materials and heat
transfer in manufacturing actually come
to life in the material and you can
actually experience those. And I would
say this has given me the inspiration to
have two minds about how I approach my
research. One is an artist or maybe more
accurately a craftsman that tries to
make things that um are really hard to
make look beautiful and simple. So these
are actually kind of a take on a
traditional Venetian technique of cane
work. Um that I
then if we can advance
um and the color work actually is kind
of what looks like the complicated part
but it's really the form here. So the
artist in me wants to say I want to make
something that's very difficult to make
look very simple and beautiful. And the
engineer wants to take something that
looks incredibly complicated to make
like the color application here and make
it actually relatively simple. And I do
that with simple tools as well. So I
start from just clear nuggets of glass
and white bars. And I use essentially
metal sticks to turn those into white
stripes. I turn those into cane, a form
of essentially you could think of it as
like pieces of lace. The lace then gets
fused together and morphed around a
sphere.
Now, the most direct transition to my
research would be if I then took you
into the additive manufacturing of
glass, but we're going to go to soft
robots
instead. meters underwater picking up a
sea cucumber. Now, the marine biologists
I work with don't actually care too much
about sea cucumbers, but this was a
demonstration that while withstanding
many uh like thousands of pounds, sorry,
of the units of hydrostatic pressure, I
could also gently pick up an animal
without stressing it out. Important to
the marine biologists that I collaborate
with because these animals when they get
stressed change their DNA expression,
which meaningfully affects the science.
And so then when what we're really
looking for is endangered coral, I can
show them this picture and say, "Look, I
picked up the sea cucumber. It was safe.
It did not express stress in the sense
that when these creatures are stressed,
they'll actually, it's not the most
pleasant thing right before lunch, but
they'll avert their stomach as a way of
saying like, "Hey, here's my wallet.
Please don't mess me up." Um, we're able
to pick it up, give it a hug, put it
back down. But the way that I actually
make these robots differs a little bit
from the traditional machine design that
I learned in undergrad. And so I have to
think about kind of how do I then use
soft materials to make something that's
traditionally rigid. What functionality
can I get out of using a different
material? And so we take a lot of
inspiration for things like from things
like octtopi and actually to be honest
cartoons. I think Disney has done a
great job in imagining what we could do
if our robots were a little bit more
compliant and friendly. And so then how
do I build that into reliable machines?
Well, I'll tell you I don't do it the
way I do with rigid materials. If you
try to bolt squishy things together, if
you try to glue them or braze them
together, they will delaminate. It will
not end
well. So then when trying to make soft
hands reliable enough for deep sea
biological sampling, it was my first
application. Um I have to think about
how to make them last longer, how to
give them higher payloads, higher burst
pressure. And so I'll go out to sea on a
vessel like this for maybe about a week,
a little bit longer. Um, I don't go in
the water. You couldn't pay me enough to
go any more than 10 meters underwater.
So, we send an ROV like this, Hercules,
down thousands of meters underwater. And
by the way, this is actually the boat
that discovered the Titanic. And I think
this pointer won't work on here, but um,
Argus, the ROV on the left is actually
the ROV that discovered and videotaped
the Titanic in that initial discovery.
But what I what I see when I'm on the
ship, everything comes out of this
bubble cam and I have a rigid
manipulator that I'm frankly not
controlling. It's the pilots who do a
wonderful job. But if you see what this
looks like, as talented as the pilots
are, let's go back and see if we can
start
this. Um, it's a difficult task. You
have a rigid manipulator that was
designed for construction and demolition
laying oil pipeline trying to pick up a
squishy little mobile creature. And then
sometimes when you pick it up, it's no
longer
mobile. Oops. Um, even more so, um,
sometimes when you pick things up, they
start to break. And so if you could make
a compliant gripper, not only are you
reducing the stress, you're actually
increasing the success rate of
retrieving some of these samples by
making something a little bit more
compliant. So I pioneered this. I think
this was work from 2015, 2016. On the
left here, we went down 300 meters
underwater in the Red Sea. And then a
more recent example of one of my
prototypes uh went down to 4,000 meters
underwater and was on display in the
American Museum of Natural History. And
to see what this looks like a little bit
in situ. This is still kind of older
videography of the um grasps, but here
we are picking up the sea cucumber or
giving a holoran a hug. Um, but
essentially one of the things that's
really helpful is that by working with
materials that are more compliant,
closer to the compliance of the
creatures that we're picking up, I can
actually passively adapt to them. Now,
this is one of the squishiest things
that I pick up. But if it's a crab or
coral, then the fingers can actually
adapt to the creature that we're picking
up. And then another challenge with
rigid materials is seawater is actually
incredibly corrosive, but the silicones
that I use are so inert that I can
actually use salt water as my hydraulic
fluid. So if I spring a leak, I'm not
contaminating the coral colonies that
we're studying. It's really
important. Okay, what I won't talk about
so much today is some of the design that
I do around this. Basically adding
structural adaptation essentially not
using artificial intelligence, but using
physical intelligence. I program
behavior into these underlying materials
to make them behave in certain ways and
have certain limited contact pressure. I
can tune the contact. Imagine if you
could turn the friction of your
fingertips on and off while manipulating
something to give you more dexterity. I
will tell you a little bit about the
distributed contact. We'll come back to
that. But I'll also skip some of the
sensing and control that we do in the
lab to talk more about the manufacturing
because really that's the most important
piece when doing this work at sea. It
costs $60,000 a day or more to operate
one of those vessels and a dive of the
like so sending the ROV remote operating
vehicle down might last for over a day.
So if one of my hydraulic actuators, one
of my squishy balloons pops a leak,
that's a lot of opportunity lost. Um,
not to mention kind of how that looks
when we're in live broadcast and then
with the uh marine biologist sitting
right next to me. Now, the trick to
getting these to be more
robust was actually figuring out how to
monolithically mold complex geometries.
So, imagine that pink thing there is a
gummy bear and that's getting a blue
casing around it. You let it cure and
then you pull the gummy bear out.
Basically, I can make very complex
actuators without any seams because
seams is where things seams are things
where where things usually burst. Now,
if you really geek out about the
manufacturing though, you can get into
the fact that we're using additive
manufacturing to make the
molds. And if you think about some of
the vestigial effects and the
nitty-gritty details of the additive
manufacturing and which technology we
use, you can then get another doubling
of operating
pressure. So, by nerding out about the
manufacturing, I've quadrupled the
operating pressure and increase the
cycles of failure by over an order of
magnitude. We then take more of the air
out by transferring some of that from a
handcasting process to a laboratory
scale injection molding process which
then makes it something that we can
scale more easily if we then want to use
that for a larger
production. Now when I learned to design
things as an undergraduate I mostly was
told you know use small deformations and
rigid materials right no problem. Well,
for the most part when I'm designing
things, the most successful things have
large deformations and a lot of the
software that we use kind of caters
towards that. So, we're now bringing
together different pieces of software to
bring in functional
requirements and then manufacturing
limitations and then explore the design
space that's possible to get large
deformations, but then with that be a
little bit more nuanced about what the
functional requirements are. So a lot of
soft roboticists, I don't expect a lot
of you necessarily to be familiar with
this, but they might say, "Oh yes, I've
optimized the performance of my soft
robot. I have made it curl at the lowest
pressure possible." I go,
"Congratulations. You have now made a
weak gripper." So if it curls at a low
pressure, I can also unccurl it at a low
pressure. So I care much more about kind
of what is the contact force, what is
the gripping force, the bandwidth, some
nuances about also kind of at what
curvature does it actually accomplish a
certain
pressure. But this is all assuming that
I have a really good idea of what it is
that I'm trying to pick up. And that's
not always
true. So in this case, I have a glassy
sea sponge. You can guess what's
probably going to happen.
And you might be surprised. I was
surprised that it actually bends like
rubber. So I often don't know what my
specimen are going to do when I pick
them
up. But even if I did know, I wasn't
going to be able to do anything with
this. So I thought, what if we actually
change how we think about robotic
grasping? Instead of trying to make
things more precise, what if we actually
embrace
stochasticity? What if we add to
material compliance some structural
compliance? So we essentially have a
physical intelligence that passively
adapts to whatever it is that we're
picking
up. I'm basically showing you the same
thing here. So I have six different
trials of the same thing overlaid. So
you can see it is actually random.
They're a little bit different every
time, but the effect is the
same. Okay. And so the idea here is that
essentially the object that I'm picking
up actually shapes my gripper. And I do
this. These are actually pneumatically
or hydraulically actuated filaments. I
call them essentially tubes that are a
little bit thicker on one side. So they
curl up when you inflate them. And an
important piece of this is I don't make
very precise molds. I actually have open
face molds. I just use dipping. Um so
it's a lot like candle dipping
essentially. Here's my candle dipping
fixture if you will. I use surface
tension to then tightly control the
dimensions of my actuators without
having an expensive
mold. Now, if I have everything with a
constant film thickness like this, then
I have a very uninteresting robot that
requires some mechanical programming.
So, I won't go into details, but I also
use things like gravity, fiber
inclusions, electric fields, and surface
tension to mechanically program, if you
will, these actuators. So, they do
something interesting when I add
pressure. Just to give you two quick
examples, the array on the top is
mechanically programmed with gravity and
the bottom has a arbitrary vector field
programmed in with fiber
inclusions. So I use this for marine b
to work with marine biologists who study
siliary motion. Um, but a little bit
more interesting is once you make those
longer, you can actually use them as
very adaptive grippers. And again, what
I'm showing you here is that those
grippers then adapt to whatever it is
that they're picking up.
Um, this is hard to characterize with
squishy materials as you can imagine. If
I try to pinch that with some calipers,
it'll just deform. So, we actually take
CT scans. And I'll skip through this
mostly quickly for time. Um, but
basically, we can then turn that into a
digital model that we can then do more
mathematical analysis on to really look
at the degree of entanglement. If
anybody wants to geek out about this,
please ask me in a break. Um, but
essentially we can quantify how
entangled these actually are. And then
what it ends up looking like is um we
can even show you kind of which type of
object they'll best pick up. And then
going forward kind of what we show is
that essentially the it doesn't just
matter kind of which filaments are in
contact with an object because not every
filament in this gripper is going to be
in contact but actually the overall
grasp the whole is greater than the sum
of its parts. So every individual
contact is actually very weak and
gentle. But when you factor all those
together and then the friction between
each of the filaments touching other
filaments, it becomes actually fairly
robust grasp while still being
gentle. And so we use this in the deep
sea. Um but you can see kind of we works
best with irregular, fragile, squishy,
topologically complex objects. And then
we hope to transition this to something
a little bit closer to home. But you can
imagine and as we have clearly found out
loud and clear from talking to uh
stakeholders, nobody really wants to be
uh approached by a squishy robot from
above. But we've been working with uh uh
physical therapists from Spalding Rehab
Hospital to think about ways where both
in parallel or when forced to kind of do
remote operation of physical therapy, we
can use some of these grippers to be
kind of a friendly and gentle way to add
kind of an intouch sense for
teleaalthcare.
So I'll thank the team that I work with
the soft robots and then move over to a
different material that I use in an
interesting and unusual way. And so my
group the fabrication integrated design
lab has been uh collaborating with even
line. And so even line is really only
two people. One of which was that
gentleman that you saw in the picture
longtime glass blowing partner of mine
and a colleague from undergrad. And
actually we then use a 3D printer which
he invented and I um basically consulted
on the first generation of we use a 3D
printer to then additively manufacture
structural masonry out of glass. And so
again I'm using an unusual material but
a lot of what I care about and I do
research on is then the manufacturing
and mechanical design side of this. Um
just kind of some context of where the
technology is. In 2015 was the first
printing of kind of like individual
units. In 2018 out of Ner Oxman's group
in the media lab at MIT then they built
a column for kind of a visual display.
And now most recently in 2024 we showed
how we can use this for structural
masonry. And so we're going from
individual unit again to column then to
an array. And actually what we're doing
in current research in collaboration
with TUD Delph is looking at the inner
layers of these because what we can do
is we can actually use recycled material
to prot to print structural masonry but
then the masonry itself can actually be
recycled again fully as long as the
inner layers then are completely
separable. So that's what we're working
on with TUD Delft. And again kind of so
this is a view of the printer and just
to give you a sense of kind of again
what I focus on is not just design for
manufacturing but looking at how the
design of an artifact comes from
functional requirements but then the
design of an artifact then defines the
process by which we make it and the
architecture of the 3D printer itself.
So some of what I'm talking about here
is for kind of terrestrial construction,
but then we've also looked into you can
actually take moon dust, moon dirt,
lunar regalith, and if you batch it
appropriately, melt it appropriately,
turn it into a glassy substance. So then
our printer looks very different if it's
an operating on the moon, both for
temperature reasons, but also clearly
environmental reasons as
well. Okay. So why would you potentially
want to use additive manufacturing for
glass, particularly structural glass?
Well, other than having aesthetic
freedom and design, you can actually
optimize each individual brick for
strength. So, if you have a brick kind
of at the base of your construction, it
needs to be fairly strong. It's
supporting all the load of the bricks
above it. But as you start to move up in
your structure, you can actually reduce
the amount of material that you use. So,
you're reducing material overall, but
then you're actually reducing weight,
which then further reduces how much
structural material you need on the
lower layers. And then also with uh the
printing method, we actually have an
atomically smooth printing surface
because we have fully melted the glass
and extruded it. And so then you get a
really high surface quality which is not
just nice from aesthetics but actually
lends itself to strength in the glass
itself. If you have glass that is free
of defects and scratches on the surface,
it will be stronger. And then by making
a discontinuous process, so we have a
smaller kiln for the glass printing and
then printing one brick at a time before
we start the next one. we can actually
experiment with more materials and
specifically recycled materials. So if
we're worried about contamination then
we actually have a much lower capital
risk than for example you would for
float lines. So we can actually be much
more experimental with the materials
that we use in this
process. We have some precedents that we
can look to for inspiration such as the
crystal house which was built in 2016 in
Amsterdam. We're actually working with a
couple of the engineers from this
project. So these are cast glass bricks
and the engineers we're working with um
Fedra and Tesla at are in the rework
group in uh TU Delft. So there's some of
the civil engineers that we're working
with in those inner layers. Um but we
can also look for inspiration in
concrete additive manufacturing from the
block group in ETHZurich. And so these
are actually printed masonry. They're
non uh reinforced that are used in kind
of compressive loading to create a
bridge.
Okay. So then the question is how do we
turn glass bricks into some form that
can do the same thing as those concrete
bricks. So again taking some inspiration
from TUDalf we can start to make
something that looks a little bit like a
Lego
brick but there's some challenge in the
manufacturing there. So what we've done
is uh add essentially a standardized
what we call lovingly the peanut
structure with two studs on top. Why a
peanut? Why the same shape? I did just
tell you that one of the magical things
about additive manufacturing is that we
have a lot of design freedom and here
I'm printing peanuts over and over
again. Well, I am also an engineer and
we wanted to do this to just have
standardization and to be able to do a
feasibility test. So, I apologize that
it's only the peanuts. You can imagine
that some of these have wonderful
fantastic surfaces printed on them as
well. Now, so we have the studs for
interlocking and lateral loading. Um,
but all of the vertical loading actually
trans transfers through the sides of the
bricks themselves. Like I said, we're
working on inner layers so that we can
completely reuse them and disassemble
them in between structures.
Um, and like I said, we we're keeping
these identical for now just for
testing. Okay. So, with that structure,
the hardest thing right now for us to
print is that little overhang, that
pesky little 90 degree turn between the
studs. Um, for those of you who are
familiar with 3D printing, this will be
obvious. For those of you who are not
familiar with 3D printing, you might
think I have two heads right now. Trust
me, it's a manufacturing uh challenge.
So, we have three different ways where
we're exploring how to do this. One is
skip it entirely. Just print a hollow
block and have something else. Let's say
a metal inner layer in between where you
can have them interlock or you could
have a print uh cast glass part. which
then led us to the next option is like
oh well what if we actually have a
hybrid manufacturing technique where we
both print glass and then cast into it.
I'll come back to this. Um and then we
have finally figured out how to fully
print
this. So if I look at these peanuts and
cross-section where I have this kind of
light green gray is printed glass and
then where there's black is cast is what
I'm trying to portray here. And this is
what it looks like as we're looking into
the machine and having these kind of
coil pots of glass
printed. So for the hollow unit, it's
just entirely printed. We cut off the
top and the bottom. We polish a little
bit. We're done.
Easy. For the print and cast method, we
start again with a fully hollow
unit and then we place it on top of a
graphite mold and then actually cast
into it.
So the nice thing about this is that we
actually get a higher a tighter
tolerance from casting than we can get
from the printing. But then it also
gives us ideas of well if we wanted to
cast glass and get more adventurous with
the forms that we're casting. Normally
with cast glass I have to make a mold.
If I want a different form I need a
different mold again. And so that's both
a consumable but also something that at
the end of the day um creates waste. So
in this case, you can create or print
custom forms and cast into them. So your
tooling becomes part of the final
product and does not contribute to
waste. Okay, so here's a picture of our
final cast brick printed on the sides,
cast on the bottom, and then we have the
fully printed brick. We use the same
graphite mold. We put it in the printer,
we print on
top. So here we
go. And then we have the three bricks.
Again, I realize it's very hard to see
those because I'm taking a picture of a
clear thing on a white
background. Um, but then the next step
is then of course to do some mechanical
testing. Will these actually stand
alone? So we tested these both as if
they were stacked in a column, but more
importantly to start building kind of
larger structures and walls as if they
were spanning two bricks above and
below. So I have that accomplished
essentially in aluminum fixtures. And
then we put the aluminum fixture around
the brick and crush it with a lot of
pressure. And so the first thing that
you're going to see is the initial
fracture. And so we track when that
first fracture
happens. And then we keep loading it
until there's no brick
left. Wait for
it. Okay, that seems scary. But the
difference in those two loads is quite
substantial. So the nice thing we see
here
is you have a lot of uh loadbearing
capacity to begin with kind of
approaching with just the hollow units
the sort of stress that we could sustain
with concrete. Um but then there is also
a very big jump to ultimate failure
because it's not about with glass or
even concrete whether something will
break. In every building, in almost any
material, something will break. And so,
it's about designing for redundancy and
having indicators of when you might have
a risk. And so, a we already have plenty
of strength for this to be a structural
material. But then, we also have plenty
of warning if there is an initial
failure and time to then remove that
brick and put something else in its
place. By the way, if we remove that
brick, we can put it right back in the
printer and print again. So, all of that
material can be reclaimed.
And so we look at kind of then from this
these are really early studies. Remember
I showed you this was 2024. So just last
year is when we started using this for a
structural material. So now what we're
doing is diagnosing kind of what are the
different factors that actually affect
strength. I won't go into the details
but if you're curious you can ask me
another time. Basically a lot of the
post-processing is a big factor. So how
did we grind it? How much did we polish
it? What surface do we print it on?
These are all very important things that
really highly affect the strength of the
brick. Remember I said if you have a
pristine if you have a perfect surface
you have a stronger piece of glass. As
soon as you scratch it then you have to
start worrying about okay do I have a
different strength
performance other things you know this
was a very manual process and so we have
defects you saw my colleague then
casting into our printed brick we have
small defects for where the casting
didn't fill entirely. Turns out these
also can then affect the performance
which is part of why we see the fully
hollow unit is something that then
performed much better and again why
we're working with TUD Delve to then
work first with the hollow units and
then we'll revisit some of these
hybrids. The next thing to go through
then is um just printing with recycled
glass. So we've actually been able to
use bottle glass. So like these Bombay
Sapphire gin bottles that I have taken
the label off of because I can't show
them. Um, but it's a really lovely blue
to print out of. Um, so we batch those
and print those into bricks. We've also
used float glass. So my colleague
Michael Stern, who's uh the founder of
Evenline, is a artist and residence at
Pilington. So we've gotten Pilington
float glass that we've then printed into
bricks. Um, I'll spare you the uh
calibration between different materials,
but not all glass is the same. They melt
at different temperatures, but we can
then calibrate by having the same
temperature or different temperatures to
achieve the same viscosity is what we
really care about. Um, but then a more
artistic demonstration of this
calibration are these three pieces
printed in three different types of
glass. The first is a studio color that
you would use as a glass blower. The
second is Bombay Sapphire gin bottles.
The third is a float glass. And if we
zoom in, what we've done is essentially
while in line and printing, we actually
just jog the nozzle off a little bit and
then come back on. let a little bit of
the glass drip down the sides. My
colleague calls this uh kind of the
series of ticks. And if we look then
comparing those to the three objects,
you can see kind of with the cooling
time and viscosity combined, we actually
get the same result from those three
glasses, giving us some confidence
visually that we've been able to
calibrate the machine. The last thing
that printing with recycled float glass
buys us is again an opportunity to work
with a hybrid setup where we can
actually print directly onto flat glass.
So, we've actually cut up one sample
here, um, and are still in the process
of testing some of those joints. Um, but
you can see that a we can both print
directly on flat glass, but we can also
and preserve its flatness. We can then
also preserve some of the high
temperature coatings that Pilington puts
on their glass for a nice either visual
and/or functional effect. Lastly, we can
use these then for facades um, both for
kind of decoration, but also then
stiffening in the face of load shear or
wind shear, excuse me. Um, and then can
print some of our bricks uh directly on
flat glass. It's hard to see, but there
is a piece of flat glass on the front
there, which can then get assembled. So,
this is an osteomorphic shape inspired
by the TU Delft group. Um, and then some
of where this is going is then working
in both um kind of glass, but also
collaborating with a group at MIT. And
this is a rendering that they made where
if I could gesture at the like columns
with a pointer, I don't think I can.
Um, go
back then. And basically those are all
made from modular reusable concrete uh
units. And so basically in this
rendering all of the concrete supports
and glass are reclaimable and reusable
and with the glass and they are also
then fully
remeltable. And so with that um we'll
take if you have I we may not have time
for questions. I realize we've run over
so maybe you all want to get to eat but
I will at least say thank you to my
group and thank you to you all for
listening.
[Applause]
Well, thank you very very much, Dr.
Becker. And I think maybe we'll keep the
Well, we have one question. Uh, do you
see potential for scaling this
integrated design model beyond research
labs and into industrial settings? If
so, what are the barriers? Um, I think
some of those were probably training and
that's something that I'll talk about a
little bit in the workshop tomorrow. So,
it's something that um Dr. Leu and I
actually work on in some of the
manufacturing classes at MIT and trying
to get students more fluid with the
transfer between design and
manufacturing. And I think we're up
against a little bit of kind of not just
kind of resorting to, oh, you can Google
that, but really having them kind of
feel the physics and see the consequence
as you move back and forth. I think some
of these were hard learned lessons um
for me that I really appreciated from
working in industry. But then we can
build some of that into our classes by
having very hands-on programming. And so
maybe similar I think industry has its
own opportunities for teaching. You
don't have to fabricate those, but at
least kind of starting with engineers
coming from uh uni or college that have
some of those built into their
experience. So they have a framework to
start with. That sounds great. Thank you
so much. And