[Music]
Hello, I'm Laura Hessie Fischer and
you're listening to Today I Learned
Climate, the climate change podcast of
the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology. And today we are talking
about digging for energy, which is a
familiar enough idea. It's what coal,
oil, and gas companies have been doing
for over 200 years. But there's
something else down there. a clean
source of energy that doesn't contribute
to climate change and it's not a fuel at
all. It's not even something that you
can hold in your hand. Well, so the
interior of the Earth is very hot. We
have this molten core and all of that
heat radiates out towards the surface
and basically passes through under our
feet every hour of the day, every day of
the year. My guest today is Professor
Roland Horn. I'm professor of energy
science and engineering at Stanford
University and I'm also the director of
the Stanford geothermal program.
Geothermal literally it means earth heat
and for billions of years it's been
sitting there under the earth's crust. A
molten stew of energy radiating from the
pressurized metals that make up most of
our planet. For all practical purposes,
this energy is infinite and
inexhaustible. What we call renewable
energy like the wind and the solar power
that are driving the clean energy
revolution today. But in one crucial
way, geothermal is very different from
solar and wind. The principal difference
between geothermal and wind and solar is
that geothermal is 24/7. It runs all of
the time. Doesn't matter whether the sun
is out. Doesn't matter the wind is
blowing. just runs all of the time. And
that gives it a different position in
the energy mix to those intermittent
sources. And most importantly, it
actually substitutes that same kind of
availability that we have from, for
example, coal or gas or nuclear.
If you're using geothermal power, you
don't have to worry about the weather or
when it's nighttime. You don't need
batteries or a backup generator or
anything else to provide the reliability
that we're used to from fossil fuels. So
why haven't we been using geothermal all
along?
Well, people have been using geothermal
energy since the Roman times and
probably long time before that as well.
So you know there are many places in the
world where hot water discharges at the
surface and people have been using it
for bathing and you know medicinal
purposes for thousands of years. But in
a modern era people first generated
electricity from geothermal energy in
1904. So the last 120 years or so. Okay.
Here's how it typically works. First you
dig two holes into the scorching hot
rock beneath the earth. You call one
hole the injection well and the other
the producer well. The injection well is
for pumping water underground. You
inject it into the rock. You need to
choose a rock that has enough pores and
cracks to hold this water. The energy in
a geothermal system is contained in the
rock itself. And in order to recover it
at the surface, you have to sweep that
energy out by passing the water through
the rock. And that's why you need
permeability.
Inside these natural fractures, the
water gets very hot. When the water gets
hot enough, it rises out through the
second hole, the producer well. And at
the surface, as the water escapes the
intense pressures of the earth, that
water turns into steam. And that steam
can be used to produce electricity, just
like in a coal or a gas plant. The steam
spins a turbine which powers a generator
and voila, electricity. Then what is
left is cooler water and that is put
back in the ground. It gets heated up
again and produced a second time. And
that same water goes round and round and
round. There's a lot more nuance here,
but those are the basics. You drill deep
enough to reach high heat. You pump in
water, create steam, repeat. Sounds
simple enough, right? I mean it's not
simple enough that you can go do it in
your backyard but this is a mature well
understood technology or at least it is
in places where the geology is just
right. Geothermal electrical plants tend
to be focused in places which have
relatively recent volcanism or on the
edge of tectonic plate boundaries. So
all around the Pacific Ocean for example
uh there are many geothermal fields in
New Zealand, uh Indonesia, Philippines,
Japan, California, Mexico, Costa Rica,
and then down into Chile.
There's also a ton of tectonic activity
in the northern Atlantic Ocean and in
East Africa. Iceland, which is the home
of geysers and hot springs, gets a
quarter of its electricity from
geothermal. And Kenya is rather
interesting in that almost half of the
electricity in that nation is generated
from geothermal sources. So they're not
the largest in generation, but the
largest in percentage of their energy
coming from geothermal.
The leading producer of geothermal
electricity in the world is, you want to
guess? It's the United States and nearly
all of it comes from just two states,
California and Nevada. The rest of the
United States, according the whole of
the East Coast, basically has none. Why?
Well, because the rest of the United
States and the large majority of the
world does not have the right geology.
It doesn't have the nice combination of
high heat near the surface and open
permeable rocks. Which is why all told
just.3% of the world's electricity comes
from
geothermal. But that's just the story so
far. The real opportunity for geothermal
might just be getting
started. For instance, why limit
ourselves to electricity? We need heat
too, right? for big things like smelting
metals and manufacturing cement and for
small things like keeping our homes
warm. So why not get that heat from the
earth? In fact, there are places where
nearly everyone gets their home heating
from geothermal.
The district heating system like the
ones they have in Rekavik, for example,
in Iceland, it's just another pipe that
comes into your house from the utility.
So they have one pipe that brings cold
water in the house and they have another
pipe that brings hot water into the
house. This geothermally heated water
travels through whole neighborhoods or
in Iceland's case through almost the
entire country. The hot water then
exchanges heat with your radiator,
boiler, or central air system, heating
and sometimes also cooling your home. In
Iceland, a lot of that hot water is
actually waste water from their
geothermal plants, but that's actually
not even necessary. Boise, Idaho has
district heating, for example, that
takes advantage of naturally hot water
underground. Now, these systems like
geothermal electricity, they need really
high heat underground to work. But the
rest of us can take advantage of
geothermal heat, too. Because it turns
out that no matter where you live, you
can get 50 or 60° F right near the
surface. And you can use that heat to
run what's called a groundsource heat
pump. And when I say near surface now,
I'm talking about the top few meters of
ground. So, a ground source heat pump is
a system much like an air conditioning
unit that you might have in the window
of a motel, but instead of discharging
the heat into the atmosphere outside, it
discharges it into the ground. You might
not realize it, but the way that an air
conditioner works is that it's not
actually creating cold air to blow into
your home. It's actually drawing heat
out of your home and then shedding it
into the air outside. And that takes a
lot of energy because in the summer the
outdoor temperature might be 90°
Fahrenheit or more. It's pretty hard to
shove more heat into that. Whereas if
you have a ground source heat pump,
you're rejecting that heat into the
ground which is actually cool because 3
4 m into the ground the temperature of
the soil is about the same the whole
year round. So in the summertime you've
got very cool ground into which you're
discharging your heat. And in the winter
time you're actually taking heat out of
the ground to heat up your building. So
it's cheaper even than natural gas. So
that's a big advantage.
On average once it's built, this kind of
geothermal is the cheapest way to heat
and cool a home. It has a catch, though.
If it's not installed when you're
building the home, then you have to do
some expensive and disruptive digging to
add a ground source heat pump later
on. So, if we can have geothermal heat
far away from any hot springs or
volcanoes, could we also have geothermal
power? Enter enhanced geothermal systems
or EGS.
The technological advances that have
made enhanced geothermal
systems suddenly the object of
enthusiasm have been basically borrowed
from oil and gas. And that's because
enhanced geothermal uses some of the
same techniques as fracking. You see,
EGS is all about making the right
geology for geothermal where nature
didn't provide it. So if you have a rock
like a big granite tombstone for
example, it's hard to imagine water
flowing through that. But if you
fracture it, you can actually make
cracks through which the water can then
pass and then recover the heat from the
the hot rock. And there are plenty of
places around the world where you can
drill to modest depths, again talking
about 3 km or so, and generate an
enhanced geothermal system. That's
roughly 2 miles, by the way, which you
might be surprised to hear is modest. 3
km, in fact, is kind of an everyday sort
of a well that gets drilled thousands of
times per year in the oil and gas
industry.
So, just like in a regular geothermal
power plant, an EGS project will start
by drilling two wells into the earth.
But those wells don't just go straight
down. Deep underground, they turn,
making a sort of Lshape. And at the
bottom you get two horizontal wells
running alongside each other. Those
horizontal wells are for manipulating
the surrounding rock. Inside them,
engineers use a combination of steel
bullets and pressurized fluid to create
fractures in the surrounding rock. And
the fractures kind of take off as much
as 500 m from the wellbor in all
directions. And in the end, you've got
the perfect rock for producing
geothermal energy. The first commercial
project like this just turned on in late
2023 and is now powering some of
Google's data centers in Nevada with
clean, renewable, and reliable energy
from the Earth. Already that company has
started drilling a new EGS project in
Utah that they say will be over 100
times larger, producing about 400
megawatt of electricity. That's enough
to power 400,000 homes. You know, I've
been following EGS systems for 50 years,
since
1975, but nobody's really made any money
from EGS over that whole time. And to
see companies now, you know, raising
money and going out for 400 megawatt is
very exciting,
which is really the scale of project
that we're talking about when we imagine
running our whole society on clean
energy. EGS is a young technology. It
may not pan out, but the current cost of
these systems is showing us that the
heat underground might just be as
affordable as coal or gas in many parts
of the world.
We actually did a study here at Stanford
looking at the price of electricity
expected from EGS systems nationwide.
And if we look at an average cost of
about $70 per megawatt hour, that's the
nationwide average, then geothermal is
competitive with that over more than
half of the United States.
So, we've talked a lot about clean
energy sources on this show, and a lot
of them are very exciting, but today
only two of them, wind and solar, are
both cheap enough to compete with fossil
fuels and possible to build in a wide
variety of
places. Is a third one waiting right
under our feet? One that runs around the
clock and provides heat for our homes
and our industries, too.
The Earth contains a positively vast
amount of energy, enough to power human
civilization hundreds of thousands of
times over. But it's kind of that
underground energy that nobody ever has
heard about. And I think one of the
things that is very encouraging right
now is that people are hearing about it.
And that gives the possibility that it
can move ahead in a much more
significant way in the near future.
That is our episode for today, but there
is a whole lot more of TI Climate
available at
tilclimate.org. Tio Climate is the
climate change podcast of the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
Aaron Kroll is our writer and executive
producer. David Lashansky is our audio
producer. Madison Goldberg is our new
editorial coordinator. Welcome, Madison.
Michelle Harris is our fact checker. The
music is by Blue Dot Sessions. and I'm
your host and senior editor, L Hessie
Fischer. A big thanks, Professor Roland
Horn, for speaking with us. And to you,
our listeners, keep up the climate
curiosity.