Welcome to the MIA 10-year anniversary
celebration. I'm Caroline Ooler,
director of the Eric and Wendy Schmidt
Center at the Broad Institute, which has
been proudly hosting the models, Inference, and
Algorithms MIA meetings for the past few years.
We're so excited to bring the MIA community
together today for this milestone event.
It's the perfect chance to reflect on the past
10 years, celebrate all that's been accomplished,
and look ahead to the dynamic future of MIA. A
special thanks to our panelists, Alex Blowmendal,
one of MIA's co-founders, Aviv Rev, Alexandrina
Goeva, and Gavororg Gregorian. We're so happy
to have you. MIA has been instrumental in
bridging communities across mathematics,
statistics, machine learning, and biology.
We've been hearing from leading and emerging
researchers about the latest research
that's going on, but also the motivation
and intuition that go into the development
of the proposed methods. Again and again,
participants leave the talks having absorbed
new ideas that they apply to their own research,
and that's what makes MIA so unique. Through these
meetings, we're proud to have built a community
where disciplines meet and new ideas spark. We
can't wait to see what the future of MIA holds and
the broader interdisciplinary field it continues
to shape. And now I'll hand it over to other
members of the steering committee. Thank you for
being such an important part of the MIA community.
MIA is the avenue where you get the most
cutting edge development and application
of machine learning. MIA is a seminar series where
we bring in scientists and researchers from other
universities and even from all over the world. So
it it just creates communities which is important
in science. All are coming together to solve a
problem that will eventually impact patients life.
That's the community that NIA has created. It's an
interesting community, right? I mean now the field
of machine learning or artificial intelligence
or modeling is really you know fusing essentially
with the biological systems. 10 years ago the two
fields would really speak different languages,
have different cultures, different taste and
so on. and more and more I think we're seeing
a convergence of the biological sciences and the
computational ones becoming part. It's wonderful
to have such a seminar hosted here uh where
different researchers can come and and also
focusing on some of the details and technicalities
that go behind behind the methods that have been
developed for biological data. MIA community is
very unique in the sense it's very cross-sectional
because we focus on models and inference
and analysis as opposed to like a specific
biological problem. The current place where
MIA is especially with its strong association
with the Schmidt center is that there are a lot of
people who can provide input to projects that are
happening in other parts of the broad and maybe
even contribute. So I think kind of harnessing
that availability of computational expertise and
the variety of computational expertise I think
would be very helpful. I've found mentors, I found
collaborators, people that I get to just kind of
talk to about my science um thought partners. It's
been really fun to be a part of the community and
then just kind of be able to like if I have a
random idea, I be like, "Oh, this person had
talked about something adjacent to it." It's quite
exciting how much MIA has evolved over the past 10
years. But I feel like that central theme of being
a community of people that can work together and
like kind of just rift off of ideas has stayed
true, which is exciting. I hope that, you know,
as as the field evolves, we're able to continually
kind of change what we're talking about and change
the nuances that we are considering in these
conversations. Personally, I've I've gained so
much. I love this community. I presented here
six years ago and it was probably one of the
most like interactive talks I've ever been in with
like the most like diverse group of computational
people probably that I get to interact with. You
have people who are in statistics and math and
physics and they all have this interest in biology
kind of widely speaking. The richness of always
trying to to look out for new ideas and uh I just
think it's a special community. This community is
important because it's really important to stay
grounded in both like the fundamentals as well
as like the new things that are emerging in our
in our field. I think it really helps in cross
crosscontamination between different fields. Like
I think those are one of the few places where you
can take a computer scientist and a biologist and
both of them can enjoy the talk while in other
cases one of them will not have enough knowledge
to understand what we're talking about. Presenting
at MIA is a very uh unique experience. The
separation between the primer and the main
talk forces you to sit back and think about
what is actually the best way to deliver this
material and to engage with the audience. Getting
to hang out with a bunch of cool speakers and cool
organizers. And so I think that the MIA is just
a very fun community in that regard. The concept
of MIA is very special. In that span of a few
hours, you're getting a beautiful throughine from
foundational concepts all the way to the research
that is state-of-the-art. I hope that others who
attend the talks, they really do feel welcomed
to join in the conversation, whether they're in
the room or online, and recognize that MIA is more
than just the talk series. We're putting a lot of,
you know, powerful heads together. We're getting
a lot of people in the same room who, you know,
don't have the same background, may not have
the same goals, but have have to understand
in principle all of the same uh types
of uh of things. At the end of the day,
what's cool is that um you have a core group
of people from at the broad, other institutions
and also industry that are coming that you see it,
you know, again and again. One thing that's really
cool is that we have a lot of junior people um
and they feel comfortable asking questions and
and having discussions and I think that um makes
it really a lot more lively. The community that
the MIE has created is so meaningful especially
because it's trying to bridge the gap between
industry and academia that has existed for a
long time in this field. And I think with AI
needing more computational resources, bridging
that gap is super important right now. Hopefully
this community grows more and more and more
people are involved and learning a lot from it.
Um so uh our panelists today are uh Aviv Rev
um currently at Jenn um yeah
please come up. Um uh absolutely
um
uh right we have so we have a vivv um you know
formerly of the broad and currently in Jennche
um uh we have Alex Blowendall who is uh still at
the broad one of the MIA co-founders uh we have uh
Alexandrina Gova who was a former MIA co-chair
currently University of Toronto does a lot of
single cell uh and uh you know uh neuroscience
and things like that. And we have uh Gavorg
Gavor Gavorian currently at Gen Generate Biio
Medicines. Um all people with some history here in
the program. And I guess just to get us started,
um I guess I would just like to for you to each
sort of tell us a little bit about you know your
your history uh with the broad with uh MIA and
the the field in general and you know in light of
it being such a uh dynamic and you know uh almost
turbulent last 10 years. The last 10 years have
been so big for for biio medicine and u uh machine
learning. this intersection. Uh tell us a little
bit about something that may have surprised you,
something that you weren't expecting that
did happen over the past uh decade or so.
Um you'll have to turn them on though. There's a
little switch. Yeah, I'll get started. Please do.
Um I'm Aviv. I'm currently in Janet and Ro and I
was um for many years actually here at the Broad.
uh I was a faculty member here and at MIT I was
at the use and I founded and actually ran the
Clarman cell observatory um for several years in
way back more than 10 years ago we had a process
at the broad that we called broad next which
was about that was when broad turned 10 I see
no I'm nodding some people here are you know have
been here for a while um we had a process at the
broad to try and imagine what our next 10 years
should look like and I had the pleasure to chair
the scientific frontiers part of it which was was
like what would our science look like at that in
the future and in some way that I can't remember
I ran into Alex and John I just can't remember the
context we were doing and then we did these things
with the math department you remember but I can't
remember exactly why but it was in the context
of the broad neck then and they had this idea to
do MIA and my contribution to MIA is that I said
well we had a little bit of funding for scientific
frontiers to do things and we paid for the
bagels. That is actually historically accurate.
It is literally true. I think we also helped
a little bit at pulling the math to the front.
Something that struck me when I watched the video
is when I came here, people did math on the walls,
right? Because you couldn't do actually the
science without it, but they didn't do math on
the slides. It just wasn't there. When you would
come to I would do the same when I would prepare
my talk, I would bend over backward to make it
go away, right? to simplify, to cartoonify it,
to explain the intuition, but never to actually
put the equation because there wouldn't be
anyone in the audience would resonate with the
equation or would want to know it. And moreover,
it was actually a deterrent. It was something
that would make oh the talk is inaccessible.
This doesn't matter for me. This is why are you
showing me that? I think MIA brought the maths
back on the slide, weirdly enough. Yeah. And and
that was a huge thing. I was asked what surprised
me in the last two decades in the last decade
and I'm going to just use two things. There's
probably many others but they are very personal
to me. First of all, I never would have imagined
I would use the word artificial intelligence with
a straight face every day and actually mean it
right. It was always you don't use that word. You
just say machine learning. It's all just machine
learning. I treat it very differently now. I think
that surprised me beyond my wildest wildest dreams
and I've seen a lot of science dreams come true in
the last decade. Single cell genomics happening,
crisper happening and deep learning happening
in a single year was like the best thing ever.
But the the AI piece that came later that was
it was kind of the dream but beyond the dream
and being able to just say it every day is fun.
So I just do. So that's one. And the second one
which is more of a motivator is and that's for
me related to my own personal move is that I
never imagined how hard it is to make medicines
and how satisfying it is at the same time. Doing
something that's like that failure and yet you
sometimes get bizarre satisfaction out of is
unusual. Um but but that's for me the other big
thing. I do think AI can actually help with that.
real move next. True. Um,
yeah. Um, I just want to say first of all, this is
it's just um feels a little bit surreal to be at
this. Yeah. And emotional. I'm having really good
emotions. No. To to be with all of you and and the
the folks who have helped build this community.
And I'll say more about that in a moment. Um,
but yeah. and and Aiv, you're hard act
to follow, but it's also amazing to be
sitting next to you on this panel after all
this time, you know. Yeah. Yeah. Awesome. Um
I'm Alex Blumenal. I am an institute scientist
at the Broad. Um I'm focused uh at this point
on on interdisciplinary and including external
collaborations that bring to bear, you know,
sort of state-of-the-art computational techniques
on the problems of uh translational genomics and
genomic medicine. And so right now I'm working
with the translational genomics group at the
at MPG the program for medical and population
genetics. Um where I I for a while I was at the
data sciences platform um and you know um I spent
some time in um well let let me go back to the to
the beginning. So I joined the bro 10 years ago
um originally um in Ben Neil's group co-founding
uh the hail project for scalable uh genomic
analysis with John Bloom who's in the audience. Uh
and um and with cotton seed uh and we were sort
of all mathematicians getting really interested
in in you know genomics and genomic medicine.
the opportunities that that we sort of started
perceived as we started to get to know people in
the broad community. Um, and trying to learn a
lot in a really short amount of time and trying
to sort of teach ourselves as much genetics and
computational biology and machine learning, you
know, as as as we could. And uh you realized
there were all these amazing people here working
in these in these areas in their individual groups
and labs, but that there wasn't a central kind
of community for people to come together and
share ideas and teach and learn, you know, teach
each other and learn from each other uh and and
spark new collaborations and all of that, you
know. Uh and so I mean it sort of started as
uh a reading club and and then it grew quite
quickly and people stat math reading club smirk.
That's right. In the data sciences platform and
then it it sort of grew and and for that there was
this like FOMO moment where people were like hey
I heard about this thing why am I not invited and
then we were like okay we definitely need to you
know move to the auditorium and make it bigger and
uh at that point you know and and have bagels and
have bagels. Yeah. Now there was a desperate need
for those bagels. Yeah. Alex, can you remember
some of the first sort of topics that you you
in this reading club and kind of Yeah, I mean
we we focused on basics which you know uh for
for a while uh really foundational stuff like you
know dimensional reduction and you know different
different aspects of regression and you know um
yeah yeah yeah regularization and you know and
that was that was good for my own learning as
well you know and and you know to teach us to
learn twice and all that and I'd done a a lot of
teaching in in in math mathematics before but but
to really get into that space in this in this
sort of interdiciplinary field was a whole new
thing. Um yeah so a Aviv's sponsorship um not just
at the level of bagels but at the level of like
institutional support um actually meant a lot and
I I really want to call that in a serious way. Um,
no, it it changed changed everything and made
it possible for this for this community to grow
in the way that it did. And um, and so did the
whole, you know, team of people that that sort of
formed. I mean, John and I quickly realized that
we couldn't host a seminar series by ourselves,
that this was uh, neither scalable nor
like a good idea. Um, and and to to bring
in people who represented all these other areas of
expertise and all these other perspectives and um,
Alex uh co-chared with me for a long time too
and and really helped build this community. So,
it's awesome to be sitting next to you
and see you again as well, Alex. Um,
uh, and then, you know, and and so all
the people on the steering committee um,
are incredible administrative assistants. Uh, I I
believe it may have been, correct me if I'm wrong,
but it may have actually been Leticia's idea.
She's unfortunately no longer at the Broad, but,
uh, to to do this 10th anniversary. Wait,
there's 10 years like we should do a thing,
you know. So um you know and we've had incredible
incredible energy and and you know organizational
support and then also the AV team you know
Scott and Russell and all the other people
on that team. So I I want to express a lot of
gratitude as well. um as I sit here today. Uh
oh, the surprise. Yeah. Um the part that
something that surprised me I I guess,
you know, I've I've the not just how challenging,
but how interesting the challenges are of true
interdisciplinary collaboration. Um, it's a bit
of a bit of a a kind of vague vague answer maybe,
but it's really like the devil's in the details.
Um, getting people to actually come together. Um,
realizing that, you know, people don't necessarily
understand the words you're using or the way
you're using them and really just digging in
and finding that shared understanding and and
cohabiting a problem space together and really
making progress with people across different
disciplines toward one shared goal. Um, you know,
it's it's just it's been totally fascinating.
I don't think I would have predicted
um how satisfying it is to spend time
on that specifically to look to to you know
as a as a primary challenge um 10 years ago.
Wow. Hi everybody. This this looks like like
MIA like I remember it. A room full of people.
Um I don't know why we're not writing on the
whiteboard even though equations on the slide.
Yes. Uh but also a lot of whiteboard to to to proc
to process stuff. Yeah. So yeah, my name is Alex
Gova. I'm so happy to be here. Um it brings a
lot of emotions to be back and I I don't know
if I can speak to the whole 10 years of MIA or
ML and biology or AI and biology because actually
came to this field maybe about seven eight years
ago and it was through maybe a chance encounter
with Alex who came to give a seminar talk at at
my PhD department which was BEu math and stats
department. So I was doing theoretical uh what
we call machine learning now uh at that time not
biology uh but was thinking maybe not about the
next 10 years of biology and AI. I was thinking
about the next 10 years of me in science and was
um really um just feeling a pull to use that rigor
that I like to work on but to channel it in both
pedagogical directions and also in applications.
And I had a passion for biology since high school
but I wasn't working working in it actively. And
so when I met Alex you know another mathematician
who was now working at the broad and of course I
knew the broad I had walked by it so many times
and knew about the amazing science but realizing
that there can be a use for someone with my skill
set at the place like that was really inspiring
and MIA already existed. Alex let me know about
it. I started attending it, met John and Alex. And
then just one thing led to another. I I became a
postock here and was one of those people that was
um recruited to to help with the organization of
MIA. And let me tell you now that I've been away
from the broad for about a year and a half at my
position in Toronto. I I can really appreciate how
special MIA is and how special the broad is for
being able to cultivate an environment like that.
It's really unique. Um, okay. Now, briefly,
something that has surprised me. Um, yeah,
perhaps as someone trained in math
where things follow logically and
usually always lead to the same conclusion
every time, um, it definitely surprises me
that the same data in the hands of different
people could lead to very different results.
I don't know if artificial intelligence can help
us with that, but we'll see. The same person on a
different day that that right hopefully not. Thank
you. Yeah, I know. Hi everybody. My name is Gorg
Gregorian. I'm a co-founder and CTO at Generate
by Medicines. Um, so my relationship to MIT, uh,
I I've never been at the Broad, but I was I was a
PhD student, um, and in the biology department in
Amy Keading's lab. Uh, so I was more the have
walked by this building many times and then,
you know, have been inside since then many times.
Um, but yeah, I think I MIT is where, you know,
many ways my scientific journey started. I was a
PhD student here. I I studied protein design uh at
a time when we won't say how many years ago it was
but it was a number of years ago at the time where
the field was really just starting um and um and
it was really fun um and I was you know schooled
in the in the frame of thought that was the
predominant one at the time uh for understanding
molecules which is the what I call the bottom up
you know the the standard reductionist approach
where we characterize details of molecular
interactions, atomistic interactions and then
integrate them forward to make predictions.
Um I went on to um do a posuck in in in in
at University of Pennsylvania build similarly in
protein design and started my lab uh at Dartmouth.
Now the thing that I think has been surprising
first of all I think it's just been such an
amazing time to be probably in almost any science
but but especially in sort of generally molecular
science and that that connection between molecules
and biology because the methodology happened the
kind of the experimental methodology to look
to see to measure to understand at scale sort
of happened at the same time as the methodology
to integrate over all those data and and come up
with some you know interesting generalizations.
All of that happened at the same time. So when I
actually think back to my PhD days, all the things
that we used to muse and dream about as surely
unrealistic, but boy wouldn't it be amazing if
that were true actually happened. Right? So that's
that's maybe like broadly surprise number one.
I I very much relate to what Aviv said about AI.
I mean when we started generate you know I was it
was a hard and fast rule like no you know piece
of PR or anything that came out of generate allow
was allowed to use AI. Well I I people wanted to
say because we had smarter PR people than I than
I am and they wanted to use AI. They wanted to get
on that train and I was like no way you can't do
it. It's not scientific. We're scientific here.
You know, other companies can say whatever they
want, but we're going to say machine learning.
And it's actually this year, Aviv, I don't know if
it happened earlier for you, but it's I eventually
gave in. I Yeah. No, I gave in late. I was when it
was like, okay, I think this doesn't this doesn't
make matter anymore. You can call it whatever we
you want. The point is it's amazing. Um so that so
I relate to that surprise but I think that the
deep scientific surprise for me and it kind of
actually is the through line for for my career
my scientific career why I started generate and
all of it when I went to my pos so I learned kind
of like the molecular view of the world in my PhD
and I went for my postoc and Bill Degrrad he's
a trained chemist so he was very interested in
protein design and computational techniques but he
could also just look at structures and understand
stuff about them, right? In a way that I was just
completely blown away. And it got me that that was
the thing that got me curious about well clearly
he's not computing Vanwell's energy in his head,
right? He's just looking at this stuff and
somehow from experience from having seen other
things before coming up with fairly quantitative
ways to think, describe and predict these things
and they actually work more frequently than my
calculations do. So I think that kind of where
that seed of like huh is there maybe a different
way to tackle this sort of set of problems. Um you
know I was always into rigor you know data fitting
was was a bad word right like I was not into that
but but at the same time I couldn't really I
couldn't I couldn't otherwise explain what I
was seeing. So that got me down that path. So I
think the surprise was that when I finally said
okay well let me see what you can accomplish
with a datadriven model you know can can you
build some type of a you know rigorous statistical
methodology maybe doesn't assume anything about
atoms or understanding of physics and nevertheless
works I think the surprise was that out of the box
in immediately that worked better than anything
that I had done you know previously in my entire
kind of scientific career now it didn't work a lot
better. But this is where the benefit of having
hit your head against that wall for for decades
came in because what I saw I already knew this is
the way to tackle this problem and then came many
written grants that people didn't understand and
like just frustration why isn't thing things why
aren't things moving faster which is why you know
I eventually founded the company and that kind of
that's how I scratched that itch but I think the
extent to which that sort of crazy idea actually
turned out to be true and sort of really flipped
how you think about complex systems. At least for
me, I think that's that's my big surprise. That's
really that's that's really fascinating. You know,
this from all of you getting the sense that oh,
it's amazing that it works, but from Alex
and Viv, there's also the side of, you know,
there's there's deep challenges to getting getting
it to execute. And it seems that you guys started
MIA with this um you know, intuition that learning
from data was the thing that we needed to learn.
Um, and as a community, we're all really focused
on, you know, thinking about what are the skills
that are going to be relevant for the for the
future and how how we set ourselves up for those.
Um, you know, it' be great to hear, you know, what
what do you think those skills are going to be for
the next 10 years? Is there a core set of things
that we all need to all need to do or is there,
you know, how do we differentiate ourselves
in this kind of turbulent time where stuff is
really exciting and works really well, but also
there are some genuine challenges to be solved.
I I can try and and comment on this. I will start
by saying I'm not the most planful person. I think
people retrofit the story after it happened is
a very typical thing. It's also done by the way
in how people write papers. We did this and
then we did that. Whereas you know for a fact
you didn't do this and then had a brilliant idea
and then did that. You did this for one reason,
you did that for another reason. When you put
the paper together, you finally see that this
is actually related to that. It's fine. It's just
not a historical account. But um I think one one
thing to really realize is that you can be in too
many in two different points in science and we're
decidedly in one kind versus the other. Most of
the time you're within an established situation.
So there's kind of a foundation of knowledge, a
way of doing things. It's not just the knowledge,
it's also the way in which you think in the
science and the way in which you operate. what
is considered to be an interesting answer which
by the way is dramatically different from field
to field. Physicists and biologists have exactly
opposite views on phenomen phenomenology which
physicists love and biologists don't. They just
don't and that's it. You can't really say why
but they don't and the others do. So that kind
of distinction really matters. That's if you're
in a field in it in its more established moment,
all of these things are there. And then questions
like what are the skills for are really they have
a very low uncertainty related to them and that's
most of the time and then once in a while you're
in a moment where the field does not exist even
no one has had it before. So if you wind back
to like 2012 and single cell genomics there
wasn't single cell genomics. It didn't exist. So
the first time you got data, there was nothing.
There was no skill you could learn or paper you
could read. You kind of had to hack it together
and cobble it. And sometimes seven years later
when people still do it that way, you're like,
it was just some idea. It wasn't even a good one,
right? It was just some way to get ahead with it.
So in my opinion, we're in that moment, but way
more big time than in anything else that I have
seen in my my years in science. And I agree with
Gavfork. That's why I said for me 2012 was the
dream 2011 2012 actually it started in 2011 a lot
of things were already happening there in 2012
you see them out right either your own or that
those of others and you're like all of my wishes
just came through I just don't know how that is
possible and it takes 10 years to see how they all
play out but you know okay so this is the moment
now just like way more amplified I think like in
several ways and fundamentally because the way of
thinking about science is changing dramatically
and you're going to make it happen. And you're not
going to make it happen by knowing ahead of time
what are the skills because those skills have
not been invented yet. You're going to invent
them by actually doing it. If you go back to other
moments in science that were like that. It was the
same. There weren't skills and techniques
and approaches. People kind of, you know,
they hacked them together and they existed because
they had a passion for the problem and a sense of
the opportunity. And the human mind is still a
pretty unbelievably amazing thing. It just comes
up with stuff way out of distribution. So it's to
me that's that's where you want to anchor in more
than in the specifics. And you want to remember
that just like the algorithms learn, so does the
human brain. And if there's some skill that you
will need, you're smart. You're going to go ahead
and you're going to learn it. And the things
we do today are definitely not what I learned
when I was in uh university. I'm sure not what you
learned when you were in undergrad. And it doesn't
matter. Math will carry you through. By the way,
that's one of the one of the really really awesome
things about it. So kind of everything is going
to change. I'll give you two examples of why I
mean it's going to change. So one is in biological
sciences people still look for the answer in the
data. in the data that they actually measured
to the vast extent. And we're moving to a world
where you look for the answer in the model, not
in the data. For biologist, this is a dramatic
shift. So if you look at single cell genomics,
for single cell genomics, you want to find a cell,
go profile a lot of cells, you'll find a cell. No
one has found yet a cell out of a model. Not one,
as far as I know. Maybe they have, but they
haven't published it. Or maybe they've published
it and I haven't read it or the AI didn't read
it for me. But in any case, the the you discover
it by its existence in front of you, measured
from the system. If the models really get there,
they will say, well, there needs to exist a cell
type that's like that and it's going to look like
this and it's never been measured. That means the
model actually found something interesting for me.
It didn't just organize, represent, allow me to
do all sorts of parlor tricks. It did something
fundamental. If you live in a world like that,
you think differently in science, in biological
sciences specifically and maybe other things will
change too. Labs are going to change dramatically.
The way labs and computation will change. So a
computational scientist will have to will will
have as part of their algorithm. They will have
the experiment. The experiment will not generate
data on which you will work. The experiment will
be part of the algorithm, the technique that you
develop. It won't be like this and then that.
Those kinds of things are a different way of
thinking and it takes time to adapt to it and it's
it's done as a collective. No human does it alone.
So that's that's to me the skills uh question.
Maybe if I can add to that I I I completely
agree with what Aviv said and and um and what
an eloquent way to express it. Maybe one thing
I would add is a I hear this question a lot a lot,
right? And I I think a little bit of the question
behind the question, it's not everything, but a
little bit behind it is um these tools just came
out and they're like really good. They're really
smart. They know a lot more than I do. They can do
a lot more than I can do. What what is it that we
need to learn anymore? Do we still have to teach,
you know, you what about me? Do we still have to
teach kids? Like how does that change education?
And I think um you know maybe just to step back
and think about that for just a minute. Obviously,
how do we kind of typically instruct science,
right? There is the skills and the knowledge,
right? That we we we teach people for a while,
right? We kind of tell them about the ideal gas
that this thing exists. This is the equation.
Maybe we derive it for them. That kind of
understanding, we tell them how real gases behave.
Then we teach them how to integrate by parts and
give them a thousand examples. So, they get really
good at. So, that that's a really important part
right now of becoming a scientist. And then later
when you sort of prove yourself as an artisan
that you can do these things that you have the
knowledge and you know how to use the tools later
in the current curriculum you get to think about
new questions think about science because now
you've got you you've got the capacity and that's
what you know I don't even know what the right
word for it is but let's call it like the art
of doing science right that's where you develop
your taste that's where you kind of develop your
algorithm for how you put a problem into parts
and solve it I think people are really worried
about what about the skills like which skills do
we teach do we still teach people to integrate
you know how all that stuff and I think that's
maybe getting ahead of the ourselves a little bit
like that stuff will shake itself out for instance
we still teach kids to calculate many many years
after calculators are you know exist and we they
will always do better than humans at every kind
of calculation but we we turned it turned out
it's still important to have people have intuition
about quantities piece because that that's really
helpful. Um I think something like that will
shake out in other things as well. But what is
happening is because the of these tools I think
we can move up that that artistic part of science
much earlier because maybe you don't actually
need to like prove yourself out on all aspects
of every every passive piece of skill set to
actually start engaging with real questions. Maybe
that's actually what you know LLMs and automatic
reasoning kind of systems allow you to do is to
introduce for for folks for students the ability
to engage with real interesting questions much
earlier and teach them to do the real research the
real question asking much earlier at least that's
that's kind of one one thing I would add I guess
I just want to um give a gentle counterpoint which
is just to maybe strike a note of caution not to
skip the basics because I think it can be tempting
to fly with these these new techniques and these
giant data sets and you know you know um into this
space which I I wholeheartedly agree u with a
gavor um it's it's that's where the future is
uh and but at the at the same time um I think it's
important to understand what you're doing and just
like we teach kids to multiply and you know and do
long division I think it's important to understand
you know basic what we really do still think
of as ML models what nobody would call AI you
and and to understand what it means to train and
fit these models and what is actually going on
when you when you fit these models and you know
so I just you know if if the question is about
students then I do I do think it's important to
to take some time to not skip that you know I
just want to say to the record that I fully agree
I didn't actually answer the question for say an
undergrad student high school student even in
the grad student phase you're still kind of in
that transition I think the audience a lot of it
is a little a little after that and still asks,
but I I think at every point in your career, there
are some basics that you actually don't know.
Yeah. Or that you've known and you kind of started
forgetting. Totally. And it's kind of you notice
it when you have kids and they're at a certain age
and you're like, I totally know this stuff. And
you're like, I don't remember. I haven't touched
it in many, many years. this angle of math or
this aspect of of another area of science or even
something like in you know human history that you
knew you really knew you understood you had a deep
understanding of it even and it's kind of like you
it's gotten fuzzy. So first of all you can very
easily re-enter into it. it's actually here.
You kind of have to like try it a couple of time
then it's like click and it's like yeah it's like
riding the bike piece and having that inside you
shapes your thinking every day. So I agree with
the calculator in that versus the calculations
the basics and so on and also you have to remember
this is really a formidable computational thing
and you need to feed things like that. You have to
train them. You have to you pre- trainin them. You
have to fine-tune them. All those things we do all
the time. That's what makes them go. So I am I'm
completely with you. I was just trying to give one
other thought that occurred to me when you were
talking. I think the question is 50% fear like
what's going to happen to me. But there's also
going to be a lot of frustration along the road.
I think you mentioned frustration. Frustration is
an incredibly positive emotion if you think about
it from the opportunity side. It's like you get
frustrated when you think something can happen
but it's not happening. Not happening makes you
unhappy. So that's the negative side but something
can happen. So when you get frustrated go and feel
that something can happen. And as Gavorg said he
just went and did something a little different and
it all worked out really nicely. Yeah. Yeah. I I
agree with all of the points made so far. And just
maybe to put it more abstractly, I would say the
core skills that I think are important and will
continue to be important are to think creatively,
collaboratively, and critically. So you have to
be able to come up with questions and creative
ways to solve them with other people. But you also
have to be able to think critically. And this is
a lot of where that rigor is is really important
to know whether um a solution is is worthwhile.
Um I think I have one last piece which is about
communication. I I think you should you know
that part deserves to be taken seriously as a
as a first class um skill uh especially in in
this interdisciplinary context. So, you know, um,
practice explaining your ideas to people who don't
share your background and, you know, realize when
they don't use the words the same way you do or,
you know, and and this is related to teaching,
but it it goes all the way through to to,
you know, the cutting edge research. That's a
very familiar for me as a a physicist who had
to talk to a lot of biologists, especially in my
PhD and posttock. In light of time, I think we're
going to move to the next question. But we've I
have to add one more thing because Alex Alex by
now said Alex Alex that Alex said by now twice on
rigger. There's going to be so much vibe and fuzz
actually in the world now because of AI AI. Yeah.
A lot of it and people could seem like they know
what they're talking about. That's actually going
to become more and more and more of a problem.
It's an it's an empowering thing too because
you can kind of manage around things you don't
exactly know with help which is nice but rigor is
going to be extraordinarily important and I I at
least have never found something that teaches
rigor in the same way that math does which is
why I think that fundamental is is extraordinarily
important but it's literally needed in order also
to serve as a counterpoint to something that will
become almost there fuzzily there vibe like there
but it's not actually there. So that's that's
a responsibility I think for this community.
Absolutely. Um so we've been talking a little bit
about you know questions like what are we going
to be what are the questions going to be? What are
the questions that people have and as researchers
we're always asking questions and you know there
have been a lot of interesting questions that have
been at the seed of these efforts that sort
of brought out new fields like single cell
etc. you know almost denovo you know we we ask
these questions and we realize we don't know the
answer and that pushes us forward and I think that
uh we're sort of at an interesting space in uh
machine learning and biio medicine right now where
uh number one new questions are sort of you know
coalescing uh still sort of in coate um but at the
same time they are not really as uh uh localized
just in the academy as they might have been
so like you in Genentech you are producing you
know and you know a lot of these pharmaceutical
companies are publishing cutting edge machine
learning papers uh in ways that I don't think
would have been you know uh understood or expected
uh 10 years ago and I think you know how I guess
my next question is going to be how are we going
to what are the kinds of questions that we're
going to be addressing in this new context and
how are we going to be splitting the effort for
addressing these questions between the you know
the academic community, you know, medicine itself
like medical schools and also industry um and you
know, how are these sort of new configurations
going to be um pushing forward the science?
Maybe I can jump in um this time. So yeah, I
think maybe I I'll answer the first one and I
think there's a piece of an answer for the second
one. So which is you know what questions are going
to be important? I mean so first of all like
I think it goes back to Socrates if I remember
correctly right asking the right question is
half the answer or something like that in a
Socratic method and and so I'm a big big believer
in that um but my interpretation of that concept
is is less that you know life is about winning the
question asking lottery that like you just have to
ask the right question and then everything will
happen. Um because I think actually the limiting
resource especially today is not the questions.
I mean they can be come up with almost at scale
nowadays and I'm not just saying everything has
to be done by AI but AI can help with that. We
can ask questions. I think the limiting resource
is just curiosity is kind of a good question is
a question that you're really curious about
enough that you're going to you know going
to keep digging and and get to an answer. Um I
think it's very difficult to predict a priori
what's really going to move science. I mean,
you know, we can have some predictive ability,
but I think it's a lot easier to ascertain whether
you're curious enough about something than its
ultimate impact. And I would I would definitely
index a lot on curiosity and make sure that what
you're asking you really, really want to find out.
Um, and there's a good chance if you do it well,
it'll be impactful and useful. And I would care
less my my personal opinion. Maybe others have a
different algorithm, but I would care less about
predicting, you know, the right question to ask to
land the right paper to land the right, you know,
next job and so on. I would actually mostly mostly
really index on on curiosity. Now, in terms of
how so maybe that there's a there's a thing in
there about how to divide. I mean, do we have
to divide? I mean, if if we go by curiosity as
a as a as a principle, then I think a company
should be answering questions they're really
curious about and academia should be answering
questions they're really curious about. Well,
let's not divide, maybe collaborate. Yeah.
Yeah. There's a lot of industry academic
collaborations especially blowing up in the
farm space right now. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
I think that that's amazing. I I I just think that
there's a moment now where you know particularly
around biology and scalable techniques applied
to biology and insights and so on where you know
let's be honest profit motive on the one hand
foundational understanding on the other hand are
are just kind of converging right and like we all
want the same thing probably for different reasons
uh or a mixture of reasons but let's let's use
that to our advantage and correct some problems.
share some reflections. I I think the really
big questions tend to stay for a really really
long time. So it's more like they're more specific
formulation shifts and often that form sometimes
that formulation shifts for interesting
conceptual reasons. People literally do not
see something is there until they know it's
there and then they ask questions about it.
Nice example is cells. Before the 1600s, we
didn't know cells existed. No one would ask
questions about something they don't know
is there. But once you know it's there,
people ask a lot of questions about it. Same
is true for atoms for that matter. It's not
unique to cells. I just like them. So that
type of thing you don't get that often. And
then the questions tend to last for a really
really long time. For many of those things,
they tend to end up being in science complex
enough that we don't solve them that quickly.
There's a second layer which is sort of how you
formulate the question and that often shifts but
what you can actually do rather than the concepts
that you have and when you can start doing
something you start asking questions that fit
the things that you can do. So that's the way in
which in which those things shift but many of our
questions kind of kind of stay really the same.
I would encourage people to think maybe about two
two perspectives that could be useful. Sometimes
a question in biology, I'm focusing specifically
on that biology, molecules, medicine. Sometimes a
question sits in kind of firmly in the not really
tractable category for a while and it become not
really practically tractable and can move into
the tractable territory or I would say possibly
tractable territory and when that moment can
happen that's something to pay a lot of attention
to and you want to ask yourself that. So a nice
example of that is combinations in genetics.
combinations in genetics was seen as a practically
impra intractable problem because you could very
quickly do back of the envelope calculation
the number blows up you cannot do that many
experiments actually I can repeat that not you not
anyone can do that number of experiments there's
not enough biology physical cells in the world for
example for all the experiments you would need to
do in order to test every possibility and hence
the problem sits firmly in that category except
in some in the general sense in the specific
sense you can always do an experiment and see
what happens. But in the general sense, I won't
be able to tell you what will happen in the next
one. People don't think that anymore about this
problem. They understand it differently. Partly
because data changed and partly because our our
our computational understanding changed on what
can happen. And those two together have said, "Oh,
the system might be organized a little differently
than I thought." And if it's organized this way,
today I understand that things like that might
actually be much more generally addressable. That
opens up a whole industry of people I don't mean
in the corporate sense of people solving the
problem which is not solved yet. It's not even
close to solved yet maybe but it's definitely
moving as a problem that people are working on
rather than a problem that sits in that other
category of there's no point because you can't
there are others other problems that are like that
and some of them are very big and can be very very
impactful. I agree with Gavorg that I wouldn't
worry too much about how the problems partition.
People go after a problem when it's relevant for
what interests them and interest includes their
curiosity. But humans tend to be curious about
things that they're interested in. Why? Sometimes
they're interested for this reason. People are
motivated by many many many different reasons. But
once they're interested, they work on something.
So I I agree that you will see the problems and
the places in the world that tackle them to be uh
to shift like that based on it. Uh and finally for
the industry versus academia divide at least for
the biological and biomedical sciences industry
scientists and uh academic scientists tend to
work on the same problems. This is actually
not new at all. It's no no correct for decades
and decades and decades because it's actually
the same problems in industry. People just try to
solve it ultimately in the human organism because
they try to address diseases and diseases of
humans happen in humans. So that adds a whole
world of constraints and considerations and so
on but it's actually the same problems. So it's
very interesting that you guys raised the issue of
pragmat the principles of you know curiosity but
also pragmatism what you can actually do but you
know the things that you choose to do for example
Alex you you know chose go over you chose to leap
into biology that's that shaped your curiosity
and so how do you how do you think about that and
you know reflecting on that on that decision Alex
uh you know yeah do you see yourself driven by
pragmatism ism or curiosity or you know how how
do you think about that? I mean when I made this
shift myself a little over a decade ago it was
both. It was very much both. Um I think um I was
I was mo I I had always been sort of fascinated
from afar by you know the genetic code and the
secret of life and all of that. um but uh hadn't
realized the you know uh the opportunities of
bringing like quantitative tools to bear because
of the you know the way that data was scaling up
the way that sequencing was becoming cheaper and
more scalable and all that. Um and then I but I I
also was myself I was very motivated also by the
uh the potential of um these things to you know
getting that actually transform our understanding
of health and disease and get all the way to
the clinical endpoint like this this this this
problems that are actually in the physical and in
in particular in the in the human world. um you
know as a as a pure mathematician who was used
to thinking about you know abstract theoretical
frameworks and theorems and proofs this was kind
of revolutionary to me and and very motivating
um you know and so I it it was very much both
for me um and uh and I guess I guess a third
motivation for me was getting to work uh not just
with a community of of fellow experts in the same
sort of subd discipline but getting to work in in
an interdisiplinary way and and you know the the
dynamical nature of that kind of collaboration
was was a huge draw for me too. It was just it
was just more fun. um you know so I guess um I
wanted to reflect a little bit on something that
came up in the previous question too if it's okay
to go back u just give an example of the kind of
um I I think some of these grand challenges stick
around for a long time um but I also think there
can be these these shifts that occur on kind of
decade time scales and I just wanted to give an
example of such a shift um you know one of the
one of the sort of two grand challenges that
Todd Gallop the current road director laid out uh
recently as we kind of enter the next decade after
the first 20 years of the broad is is you know
um converting genetic variation associated with
disease into mechanistic insights that can inform
you know therapeutic hypothesis and and this is
uh for a long time it was let's get all the
genetic variation associated with disease and
that was like the thing and it was sort of I guess
there was this this this assumption that that you
know that that would show us the way and then we
would then in then we would understand you know
the the gene pains and the cell types and and I
guess partly due at least in common and complex
disease the the challenges of polygenicity um you
know due to for various reasons it it just that
that next step of translation into mechanistic
insights has been far from automatic and it
turns out like that's the thing we totally
need to focus on as a field there you know
um the the other by the way the other the other
grand challenge um from the broads perspective
around is around programmable therapeutics and
scaling up genetic medicines to really be scalable
across Ross common and rare disease. Um but um I
guess it's um it's just it's it's interesting to
watch these shifts occur at at the sort of macro
level of the fields and then have that inform the
problems that we that we each think about. I
I think the division between I want to speak
briefly about that too. Division between different
kind of sectors of the biomedical ecosystem. Um
there I don't know if I have a single uh you know
insight there but I guess I do want to surface
uh a concern I sometimes have that I think we
should all be thinking about as members of of
this community and just of society more broadly
which is um sometimes I worry that the incentive
structures that we have um don't necessarily
guarantee that the fruits of all the research that
we do and then this you know the curiosity and the
research enterprise guys will actually transform
the standard of care and bring benefit to all,
you know, um and uh not just those who can afford
access to sort of cutting edge medicines. And this
is this is to be sure a conversation that goes
beyond science to the policy level, but I I think
as scientists in a changing and challenging world,
this is, you know, we need to be part of that
conversation and engage with these problems. Yeah,
that's a that's a that's a really good point. Um
Alex, just a quick comment. Yeah, on the on the
on the questions question. Um yeah um yeah the
the the yeah the pragmatism versus curiosity and
and bi interdicciplinary side of things. How
how do you yeah I I can relate to all of the
three main motivations that Alex shared with us
as well. Uh I just vividly remember my PhD office
in a basement without windows and my occasional
interactions with other humans around my research.
And um it uh was and remains very
important for me to be useful. And
I just found that I'm more useful when I
have regular opportunities to interact with
humans. Not everyone's like that. I I just and
I might change. But that was a big motivation.
So do we have time for some audience questions?
Um, I think we actually are at basically at time
now. We've managed to to fill the entire block
and we actually have a couple of lightning talks
coming up uh right now after we get set up. We
have and we're going to be starting with uh Tvor
getting set up. But I would also like to thank
our lovely panelists for a really enlightening,
insightful and uh you know a grand perspective uh
in this discussion that we've just had here. So
I'd really I really appreciate all of your
your insights and uh contributions here.
I want to take an a second to close back to
where we started like how MIA started and I
told you about that scientific frontiers effort.
I said this many times I just want to say it on
the record that I believe from all the things
that we actually did out of scientific frontiers
formally this which was the investment of
the bagels was by far the most impactful.