Well, welcome back. Despite having
access to the same technology, some
organizations consistently realize value
more quickly than their competitors with
a smaller financial investment. In this
session, John Carrier will discuss the
technological, organizational, and
psychological factors behind this
phenomenon and how an understanding of
systems dynamics and lean operations
developed at MIT can help accelerate
your organization's successful
transition to a digital future through
organizational leverage. Please welcome
John Carrier.
[Music]
[Applause]
Good afternoon everyone. It is a
fantastic pleasure to be here and uh as
Randall said, I'm going to talk about
some of the more practical aspects when
you go to implement some of this
technology in your own organizations.
So, most important about my uh resume is
I do spend about half my time on the
factory floor. I am not taking off this
suit because I rarely get to wear it. Um
and the other thing I'd like to bring up
is I uh aside from uh being a control
engineer by training and going through
industry 3.0, zero. Uh I now teach the
lean operations course in our leaders
for global operations course. So uh
actually uh lean operations that term
actually comes from uh out MIT and it
was John Kraik under the uh guidance of
uh Jim Wulmarmac and John Shook uh was
really looking at in the auto industry
why does some organizations achieve
twice the results with half the input
and we heard Ben Armstrong allude to
that with the uh Numei example. And
while John uh Kraik was at MIT and doing
these studies in these factories, I was
at my desk at MIT doing lelass
transforms. So anyone who wants a lelass
transforms lecture, we can do that
later. Uh but the important point is uh
you have to get out of your desk to make
this happen. So, strangely enough, I
here I am teaching the course at MIT
that John Crafts really initiated and I
wanted to draw uh out of some of those
uh higher level lessons from the
automotive industry to basically uh any
group and you know that what those
companies do they think differently,
they act differently and they
communicate differently. But I want to
make one other point is there's actually
a middle layer within the organization
that we often forget. It's many of the
roles that you and I do and we are so
important to driving this part of the
organization yet it's not always
recognized. Okay, just to warm us up
with a quiz. Uh does anyone uh you're
driving down the road, you look out your
rearview mirror, you see a car like this
driving on the highway. Does anyone know
where you
are? Could be in Italy. Yeah, you could
be in a like a city like you could have
been in Stoutgart. You could have been
like in Milan. This is actually taken in
Detroit, right? And what that means, my
hometown by the way. Um, and what that
means is, does anyone know what that
means and why that car is like that?
Pardon?
Yeah. It's a um it's a it's a new design
that they're testing on the road, right?
So, they don't want anyone to see it.
That's camouflage, right? And uh I want
to tell you why that's camouflage. So,
this is that that's actually if you look
really close, that's a Lincoln
Navigator. But um what happens is if
you're a GM or or or a Ford and you
design this new uh car, it's going to be
three years till you get it into
production. Now the issue is Toyota can
get it into production in two years. So
if they see your car, they will have it
out on the market before you do. And the
reason I raise that point is there's a
lot of misconceptions about what lean
operations is and it's about being more
efficient. That's merely a part of it.
When you look at lean operation or you
go back to TaiichiOo from Toyota, it's
really about I want to go from customer
order to customer cash as quickly as
possible. Now for existing products and
services, that's a lot of efficiency,
but for new products and services,
that's about actually tuning up and
finding your new customers and getting
there much more quickly. So, um, just
really understand that when you think
about this production system, we're
always trying we're running a race from
start to finish, right? And whoever gets
the customer first and takes their cash
first wins. And if you satisfy that
customer, they'll come
back. So, um I do want to show you a
lesson from my MIT students. So, I teach
a course and uh what I did was I hear so
much talking about the new technology,
but we rarely spend time looking at our
own systems. So, I asked my students to
make a threeinut video of something they
do every day and actually find out where
all the waste was. And then finally, if
there's a technology, apply it and see
it. And I've got some amazing examples,
but I just want to talk through one.
This was um about three years ago, and
they shot the three-minute video. I just
took a screenshot from that. And what
happens that uh when you come to class,
you need to uh uh you're teaching, this
is for another professor I was helping.
Um you have to get four or five computer
programs to be running so you can
participate in the class. Well, how well
do you think that works when you're
asking everyone to get their computers
up and get all on the same page? Um, so
they decided to fix that problem. A lot
of variation. And what they found out
was when they uh did it manually, um, it
took 113 seconds. And this is if you did
everything correctly to basically start
up your computer and be ready to go for
class. Right now, you will notice one
thing that's interesting. A Windows
machine took twice as long as a Mac.
Right? And that you can trace that back
30 years which is just fascinating. And
then uh what the team did is uh and
there's a threeminute video and I'll
post it online so you can watch it at
high speed. They got it down from uh
basically to 18 or 12 seconds. So now
when you come into class students are
all ready to go and uh everyone's on the
same page and no one gets ahead and
behind. And the reason that's so
important is because uh I think the
number one complaint I'll ever get from
uh teaching is I didn't finish on time.
Right. content does not matter if you
don't finish on time. And then I figured
out why there's a really important
professor teaching after me and they
need to get to their class. So you must
uh uh first is finishing uh really
looking at your existing system before
you start applying this technology. Now
did we all talk about value? So what's
the value to this? So I asked the
students to calculate this and
essentially you know it probably comes
out to about two hours of teaching out
of a uh you know 20 session class. So
does that seem like it's
uh
important? The student like yeah what if
you did for all your classes? Oh what if
you took it to your job? And so before
they'd be like this isn't important but
now the question I get couldn't you have
just done that with Genai? So I can
never win. However, my point is there's
there's not a lot of thousand dollar
bills lying around, but there's a lot of
pennies lying around. And if you can
sweep those pennies up and save little
time here and there, all of a sudden it
starts adding to something that impacts
the customer. So, just a uh and this is
really for this group, a system
perspective of management. This is from
Russell Akoff, uh the famous uh
management theorist. There's uh really
we do deal with three things in
business. puzzles, problems, and messes.
Now, puzzles are are are basically
homework problems. It's a well-
definfined problem, and because it's in
a textbook, you know there's an answer,
right? Then the next level, when you get
into business, you start doing projects.
We have a well-defined problem. We just
don't know the answer. I would say that
90% of what this group deals with here
is what he calls messes. It's not a
really well- definfined problem. We
don't know if it's going to work, right?
So, and if we don't have this
coordination layer, nothing will get
done. No new technologies will get
adopted. No new customers will be
served. So, uh I just want to say, you
know, you really got to strike at
people's feelings and emotions if you
want to get them to uh uh uh connect and
head in the same direction. And this to
me feels like the challenge of the
modern organization. You know, you're
stepping up, you're trying to do
something, and there's a thousand little
things tied tying you down. And first,
uh the sea level doesn't fix this.
That's not what they're interested in.
they have other things to do. So that's
left to this this other second layer to
fix. And so I think it's really helpful
to look at a very simple diagram. Since
we've been talking about management
stacks and uh financial capital stacks,
this is kind of the management stack. At
the top level, you call that the
strategy, the C level, the direction
level. and they set the direction for
what the organization is going to do,
the customers are going to serve, what
they're going to invest, and then they'd
like to send that message down to the
execution layer to execute these jobs on
our our our excellent direction
strategy. And uh so when they send that
message down, they don't send that
message directly. They send it to a
group like this. and we are are
responsible for matching that high level
direction to what uh is going to be
executed on the daily work and that
basis. Now you notice uh we're really
developing a feedback loop here. So this
is the control signal, right? This is
the top down signal. There's also
another signal, right? There's the
corrective feedback signal. So uh the
execution layer, they'd like to send
messages up to the to the uh CEO level,
but they don't normally get there,
right? they go through our layer and
then we
normally filter it so that's uh it's uh
acceptable to both of those layers. Now
the issue is are we actually filtering
out the important information that needs
to be known or are we actually using it
to solve problems so that that we
actually can synchronize the direction
of the organization to what actually
gets done on the factory
floor. And sometimes it's not being
about being thinking better or smarter.
we actually need to think differently.
So this is Carl Dunker uh the famous uh
um uh European uh psychologist who spent
his last years in Massachusetts and he
came up with this great idea around if
you can't solve the problem make it okay
not to right reframe it right that's
been a popular notion but it goes all
the way back to Carl Dunker and I want
to show you um uh a very amazing
reframing that you might not be aware of
so first is let's talk about remember in
the early days late 90s they they're
starting these things called online
bookstores and there's many of them. We
I think we all know who survived. But
does anyone know what the worst part
about owning a bookstore
is? Books. Yeah. Inventory. Right. So
that's right. The books. The inventory
is the worst thing you can own. And and
uh why I'm showing that photograph is
because um that is a book that's unsold.
They they tore the the uh book seller
tore the cover off and had to send it
back to the uh uh uh publisher to get
their money back. So, in the old days, I
mean, the number of books that were
never read and the covers were sent back
was awful. So, okay, you're a company,
you're Amazon, you want to sell books
online, but you don't want to own books.
So, what do you do? One, you moved to
Seattle. Does anyone know why they moved
to Seattle? It was one of the two
largest book warehouses in the United
States. So, uh, what they would do is
you would order from Amazon and then
Amazon would
order from this large warehouse. So, now
they don't have to hold any books, but
they're selling books. One problem. This
uh warehouse wouldn't take orders less
than 10 books. So can you imagine if you
order one book and Amazon had to order
10 and wait for someone to buy the other
nine. So what did they do? Well, they
found out that if you ordered a book
that was very rare and not published,
they would basically uh put it on hold.
So what they do is they order 10 books
that no one would that were out of print
and the book they wanted and then the
company would ship the book they wanted
and then they cancel the other order. So
and the reason that's important is maybe
that seems tactical but these are the
type of tactical decisions that survive
while these other startup companies
capture books and uh thank you for your
lecture before using venture capital to
buy book inventory just seems like a bad
idea. Okay. So, we've got to think
differently. Um, I want to talk about
installing sensors. So, this is uh
actually a factory. I was on the factory
floor a few months ago and um uh I was
first of all, I'm always on the floor
watching what people do, right? Because
that tends to be neglected. So, it's an
easy first way to show advantage, help
the people on the floor and build your
trust and relationships. So after we
finished doing some of that work, uh
they said, "Hey, let's uh look at our
digital digitalization of the plant."
And they said, "Uh, oh, we just
installed 300 sensors." And I said, "Uh,
what do you what have we learned from
those 300
sensors?" Pause. We haven't had time to
look at the data yet. Okay.
Um, first of all, I like making bets. So
I go, "First of all, can we look at it
now?" And they're like, "Yeah, it's all
online." I go, "Okay, let's look at it."
So I go, I bet you that 20% of those
sensors aren't even reading anything
useful information. So they went and did
it. They won. By the way, 17.8% were
reading nothing. Okay, that's pretty
good. Okay. Um, but the second question
I asked
is why don't we just why don't you just
put in 30 and the most pieces of
equipment and just done that. And then
there was a pause, right? They're like,
yeah, we probably should have done that.
And then we thought about well why
didn't you do why didn't we do that
right uh because we're given this high
level message to make a big digital
transformation and just putting 30
sensors doesn't seem like a big
deal and and then um uh and remember
these are you know we were taking these
and this is a very good organization and
uh so one of the things I wanted to the
next thing I wanted to ask is you know
the question you want to ask is um a
classic paro principle if you're a new
plant manager and this uh person was
relatively new in the role. Um, and he
was thinking, I'm going to just expand
this and be the best digital
transformation in our whole uh uh
footprint of plants in Latin America.
Like, you know what? I'm I' I've been 30
years. That's if you do that, you will
be amazing. So, let me give you a
recommendation. Make a list. List the
five piece of equipment in this plant
that if they break, you're going to get
in trouble. And send that to the send
that to this VP of operations. and if
the plant goes down because uh uh uh
equipment piece 11, we'll just take that
and learn. So, that's a great idea. So,
then they left and then they didn't need
to engage me anymore because I gave them
the answer. Um but we're always talking
about balancing investment with return.
And if we sequence things properly, the
first round is basically getting it's
more about getting to know our own
system than it is actually the new
technology. And then once we start to
clean up our system and understand it,
we're going to be much better users and
and and and purchasers of technology,
that actually makes life easier for the
vendors, too.
Okay?
So, if you ever want to end a meeting
and you there's a project you don't want
to work on, you all know this, but we'll
just say it anyway. Just raise your
hand, say, "What's the ROI of this
project?" It'll just stop, right?
So, um, if you, uh, if you're in North
America, you probably have the same
thing in Europe, too. Is I, I I all want
you to know, you're all making
investments that have negative ROIs that
you will continue that you never hope to
use, right? All right. You all do,
right? And I'm going to give you a hint.
At least in North America, if you're
watching television, they show you all
these commercials with these animals in
it, like a duck, an emu, or a gecko,
right? Like, what are these things?
Well, they're all uh uh mascots of
insurance companies, right? So, I don't
know about you, I pay a lot for life
insurance or health insurance, and I
never ever want to use it. Right? That's
lesson number one about ROI. The lesson
number two about ROI which uh we just
touched about the sensors is uh think
about payback period right it has the on
the numerator it has here's all the
benefits we're going to get here's the
cash value but there's also a
denominator which is how much we invest
say why don't we cut that down to 20%.
We never really thought about that and
the reason we don't thought about that
is we got this mix between uh big change
has to require big investments and I
think maybe it does but you can sequence
it in pieces so that you can actually uh
start to get your returns while you're
actually making the investment and like
I said second good investments are
driven by good information every time
you implement the next incremental
technology and and actually propagate it
through your facility you have a much
better idea of what your plant needs,
how your how your uh people solve
problems and uh your your investment
will drop and your returns will get
better. Now I want to uh uh then so
that's really around thinking
differently. I want to show you another
example around once you think
differently when you go and actually
start implementing these technologies
you act differently. So this facility is
a um they make power uh uh distribution
boxes. It's a midsize company in the
United States. Um, so if uh any sort of
public event, military event, concerts,
they're using these types of boxes. And
um this company had been losing money
for eight years straight and they were
about to shut it down. And they just
finished spending $2 million for digital
consultants, which resulted in nothing.
So they brought in a a good colleague of
mine to come in and just automate a line
for us and then we'll copy the rest of
it. So I was fortunate enough being only
uh the plant was 70 miles away. So I
actually observed and worked with them
through the transformation. And just a
couple things I want to point out about
uh uh acting differently. So the first
question you ever want to ask is uh when
you're in a facility is uh and this
works for orders and uh software as well
is how long does it take for a customer
to get an order once they place the
order? And if anyone uh if you order a
couch in North America takes about eight
weeks. Now is there eight weeks of labor
in that couch? There's about four hours.
So with this uh same with this box, it
uh not only take eight to 12 weeks to
get a box that only had about 12 hours
labor, then when you actually looked at
the basic concepts, it was hard to see
more than two or three hours of labor
just from watching uh them put together
the boxes. So one of the things that uh
we noticed right on the first day is you
see uh you're basically wiring up this
box and uh one of the questions uh my
colleague asked is why do you put the he
saw people struggling. So the first
thing you ever want to do when you want
to look at a floor watch people
struggling to do their work. So he's
like so why do you put the box together
first while you're struggling? And um I
guess they never really thought about it
and um what they realized why don't we
build assemblies first and then we'll
put the box around it. So that cut the
labor down from eight hours to two
hours. The other thing I want to point
out is these are smart intelligent
people and we know that because they
basically they're the people that turned
around this facility. So the system
itself was not so smart, right? But as
we uh we all know and this comes from uh
Jay Forester, our founder of the system
dynamics group at MIT. A bad system will
defeat good people every time. And this
is just another example of that.
Okay. Now I want to talk about tech. I
don't want to sound I do not want to
sound like I'm anti-technology
especially from the uh institute I come
from. But you do want to be your first
few steps of technology be very careful
and then then good things will happen.
So uh and if you come from the
automotive industry, the one way to get
into trouble is invest in the wrong
technology at the wrong time. So when I
first came on site, my colleague, he had
this, uh this monument sitting in the
middle of the facility, and you can see
it's actually showing um uh uh uh
blueprints and diagrams of what they're
supposed to of what the team can be
building. So the first thing I went and
looked at and said, "What's the date on
it?" It was actually from that plan was
from yesterday which means they're
actually using this on a daily basis.
And then second I asked you know you
never invest money in technology. How
did you did you what what changed? He
goes oh no when I we were cleaning up
the other part of the facility uh that
was a display kiosk marketing was using
in Las Vegas and then it broke. So they
just threw it in a corner and left it.
We fixed it and someone in the facility
basically just set up the uh proper
Google connections and now they get the
daily and while I was there I saw people
coming up and looking at it instead of
walking around the facility all day. Um
so that was a very successful uh uh
investment that was based on money
they'd already spent. And you know what
marketing said when they saw it? Can we
have that back?
But I also want to say is now that
they've done sort of this kind of really
seeing some results from uh low uh
investing in the technology they already
have, they're now starting on new
product development. So when they
develop new products and they're
actually they're uh investments getting
larger, it's actually going to be uh uh
return a cash flow from new customers.
And by the way, within four months, they
went from minus a million dollars a year
to slightly cash positive. So pretty
amazing result. And so that's around
acting differently, how you go to the
floor and work with the teams and
introduce technology. I also want to
talk about communicating differently and
uh my good uh friend and colleague
professor Ron Westerm back in the 1980s
realized that information flow which is
something we consider uh as part of uh
control systems actually is deeply
impacted by the culture of your
organization. So for instance like when
I uh when I wire up a pump uh uh to a
PLC from different manufacturers they'll
talk to each other equipment to
equipment sometimes they won't but when
I pass on information to people we all
change the message right and
understanding how that message gets
changed is really critical and uh uh the
organization this he was working started
with was really pathological in that uh
the messengers were shot so that led to
low cooperation operation that's around
10 to 15% of organizations. The second
organization of which we're all part of
are bureaucratic right and I just want
to talk about one consideration is that
when something fails there's modest
cooperation we stay between the lines
when something fails we go to stay with
justice and novelty leads to problems
right because these are large organ
there's there's challenges to scaling
something right it can't the systems
can't handle too much novelty then you
go to a generative which is a
performance organization culture and
failure instead of leading to correction
leads to actually inquiry and
understanding and learning to a new
result. So the point here is not we'll
always have bureaucratic organizations.
The reason we do is they work. It's just
when does that organization have to
sometimes show some of these generative
uh uh uh properties of failure leading
to enquiry and getting that balance
right is key.
So when you go back, I'm going to ask
you to apply this and and uh during your
next break, you're going to actually
think about all the steps that you do in
your jobs that fit in that
synchronization level and what would
happen if that layer just disappeared,
right? And so one of the things this
layer does is that the the top layer is
we're being told future disruption,
right? We've got it. We uh have to
protect against the future. We want all
the new technologies. And then the the
bottom layer is make my day easier,
right? And if you go into a hospital and
you talk to surgical teams, doctors,
nurses, etc., still the same, right? I
have these highfrequency daily
emergencies, yet we still have to deal
with the long-term uh uh consequences.
And that is really the layer that this
uh group addresses. And I think the only
way we're going to get through it is
through our through our creativity. Not
only our own, but tapping into the
creativity of others. And isn't
technology really just a type of frozen
creativity that someone else has done?
So I think it's very important that
Slayer recognizes this and uh you know
this did make me think of a famous
Austrian movie star uh HD
Lamar and she came up uh basically
during uh pre-World War II she came up
the idea with some colleagues this idea
of frequency hopping where you move from
one frequency of communication to the
other. In this case it was so other
people couldn't track you. But I think
our jobs in many ways on one uh one at
8:00 we're communicating on the factory
floor. Then at 11:00 we're talking to a
senior level person and then we got to
jump back and forth. And I think just
acknowledging this fact that we're this
balancing high and low frequency events
uh is really critical to to what we do.
And perhaps this is a way to uh uh
introduce technology. By the way, how
many of us here, don't raise your hands,
but how many of us here do more of the
real work when we get home than what we
do during the day, right? That is this
phenomenon. And by recognizing it, we
can make it better. And uh uh this is
basically the transition process I use.
Um and uh it's really based on two-step.
I won't go through all the details, but
I'll explain the key parts of it is when
you think about your uh uh uh long-term
vision of your digital transformation,
which is on the far right. That's the
this uh exemplary vision state. You're
actually starting over here at your
current state. And the key part here is
you want to put one or two phases in
between that transformation or
transition. And the first stage should
be more on taking away elements of the
current system that you don't want and
and just sparingly add new technologies
like simple sensors. Uh start using
information in the cloud and standard
algorithms. And once you've made that
transition to phase one, company's
working better, we've got some free cash
flow. Um we've built working
relationships with our colleagues, then
we're ready to start introducing those
next set of technologies. And the speed
at which you do that is basically
determined on on our abilities to manage
and
lead. And uh I just finally why we do
it. Uh this is uh the final uh picture
after the uh transition when the company
went cash positive. And uh not only do
they have 150 employees uh in this small
community, this these 150 employees
support their families and their other
small businesses from those paychecks
they get from that uh transformation
company. And again, uh, their next step
is they're actually starting to use some
of the more, uh, sophisticated tools
like Genai as they're developing new
products. But they showed basically a
profitable stress-free transformation as
they move through this. Okay, this is uh
really the key slide about when people
say, you know, what do we what do I do
or what value do I really add to a
company? Why am I there? Um and whenever
you look at some sort of a performance
metric over time, uh
normally there's going to be a dip,
right? Because we have to invest
something first or learn and then it's
going to curve back up and uh generate
money. And of course, uh uh accounting
figured out a way around it. They call
it net income, right? They hide that
investment. Um and if we're doing our
jobs right, we can basically move from
this very poor
standard mindset that we have to invest
a lot of money first to by sequencing
investments we can actually have a much
smaller dip and in fact we might even
exceed expectations if we combine
creative problem solving with the new
technology and finally uh you'll ask why
I drove this by hand it's I I made I
spent about uh five or six hours putting
this all nice and and uh digital it took
the human element out of it so I went
back with the human element
And then I just want to give this a last
word from Jay Forester uh who founded
the system dynamics group uh at MIT and
uh has too many uh accomplishments to
mention but he said few people realize
the role that feedback loops play in our
everyday lives. Okay. And so just in
summary, uh do we explicitly understand
and value our roles of this middle layer
in the organization and where can we
incrementally add technology to change
the dynamic response of the organization
and then finally when we look at where
we spend our day like when I look at my
calendar and spend my daily time is it
actually matching up with uh that
synchronization goal that I should be
having with the organization. So, uh,
with that, I'd love to, uh, thank you
and just, uh, take any questions if you
have
[Applause]
them.
Okay, let's see, John, I think we have
time for a few questions
here. Okay, what are common reasons why
digital transformation efforts fail and
what should we avoid and look for? Okay.
So, I would say the the biggest one is
we uh haven't scoped. We've gotten to
the 1,00 foot level, the technology that
we want, and we don't invest enough in
getting for the first three months from
the thousand foot to the on the ground
level of what we're going to do next,
who's going to do it, and when we're
going to show results. That would be
number one. And then second, related to
that, you'll typically find something
that they you can show results in three
to six months. when you share that
message with senior leadership that will
create uh uh that that feed that
positive feedback loop and
communication. So I'd say that would be
the biggest one. And we have time for I
think one more question. How do you
recommend building momentum for digital
change when frontline teams are already
stretched thin? So uh uh I I've I got
the magic two words that uh I heard uh I
got I got from several of my colleagues.
It's called go to the floor and watch
for them where they're struggling. Then
ask them why they're struggling and make
a list of that. And then make a list of
the technologies you have. And out of
those 10 things they said, three of
those will match up with the new
technology. And that's what I would
recommend. Great. Well, thank you so
much.
[Applause]