hello I want to give a sense of how some
problem sets are going to work or the
majority of the time generally speaking
you'll be given some instructions on
what to do like write a routine that
takes a string representing in harmonic
with minus sign for Flats we'll talk
about that in a bit and number sign for
sharps and rning a new string that is an
n and harmonic you're not allowed to
change it but I can here that is an and
harmonic of the pitch you will be given
valid input only I will always tell you
if you have to check for invalid input
um if there's more than one valid
inharmonic you can give any inharmonic
up to double Flats of shuts then below
you're going to be
giving um the name of the routine that
you're going to need write along with um
usually the name of a variable that you
should
use and the type if you haven't looked
at python typing this can be really
exciting and what's
output at this point you need to define
the routine what often you can take some
of the language from above but make it
in your own words to see uh what
happened but put it in the active uh
voice takes in a string representing a
pitch sorry I should say representing a
pitch earlier U and returns a valid and
harmonic for
it um if there's specific things that
constrain what the valid input might be
I'll tend to write it here or you should
be writing it in
we write for humans to read not just for
computers to process so it's always
going to be important that uh that your
code be documented and that your
variable names be things that humans can
understand okay so then you can go ahead
and write your code and if you're uh not
so great programmer maybe you'll start
with if and harmonic in is
the flat we then use minus signs for
flat return
DP otherwise return C Shar and at least
maybe you'll get it right
sometimes
great now I will sometimes give you one
or two test cases so maybe I'll say
assert FP and
harmonic E flat
equals
gar and can see that that
works maybe if I'm very nice I'll give
you two of them up and you can see that
doesn't
work I am not going to give you all of
the interesting and
fun test cases part of the thought
process of this class part of why you
get humani credit is is that you need to
be thinking about well what are the
weird cases okay uh I can put it if it
this it's E flat and if it's dsharp it's
E flat and so on oh
but we going to need to make sure
that this
works or maybe I need to make sure
that that
works or at least that it's a valued
answer
ha and so part of what you need to do is
be thinking about how do we write test
code what are the test cases that
Professor cord is going to be putting in
such that it's going to challenge how I
write you'll probably need to rewrite
your code as you go great let's get
started