thank you everyone um it's a pleasure to
be back in Houston I think for the sixth
time in the past uh two months so I'm
here a lot and uh some people even told
me that I should find a place to live
here because then I could you know
reduce the carbon footprint that I
generate uh through my trips so what we
do is we build pretty large scale Data
Solutions in solutions for customers in
the energy space and
um see how I use this is this just click
yes so before I um describe our products
I want to show a survey that was
conducted at this year's SP advanced
technology um conference um from all the
data professionals at the conference and
basically the question was what's what
what was their biggest challenge in
working with data and data science you
know and the answer as some of you
probably know here the biggest challenge
is not building data science models the
biggest challenge is is first just to
get the data that you can use for data
science and this is followed by
difficulty in scaling because
performance is hard once you have large
scale Solutions and lack of skills so we
solve a lot of these problems for our
customers so essentially what we start
with is we built this things called Data
pipelines um you may not be familiar
with it but it's basically real time or
historic data going through the data
workflows it gets cleaned gets processed
and so that is ready for AI to use um we
can get process uh process data from
your rcks from your production sites and
if you already have the raw data in um
in um uh your data warehouses or
historians we can grab those and clean
that up and the next thing we do is we
convert that data into something called
events so typical energy data industrial
data they are time series data right
pressure temperature there there's
actually very little you can do with
those data but once you can convert them
into events either like simple events
like like alarms or very Complex events
like um component models all of a sudden
you can do very large scale uh bi
analysis AI LM digital twins so you know
the conversion um of events is actually
very critical and doing that at very
large scale is
difficult so if I ask all of you today
that how do you build this type of Data
Solutions I think every company does
this to some extent I think the majority
of you are going to say what we do it in
software of course that's how we know
how to do the sort of things but all of
us also know that software is super slow
to build requires very expensive
software developers who do not have the
domain expertise and um um it's it's
very inflexible to make any changes
right so instead of doing things in
software we do it in Gra graphical uh
workflows these are just drag and drop
blocks connect them by wires and that's
how we process data and this graphical
workflows can be uh deployed to
different locations because your data is
not necessarily all in the cloud right
they are on your RS production sites
they can be in your private private
Cloud so there's little there's this
little you know containerized data
engines that can run in all different
locations collecting processing all your
data then we can fuse all of them
together and that's how we build
Solutions much much faster and also
simpler than software development and I
think you know once you can do this you
can really accelerate how you can use
the data in your
organizations the other thing that we
focus a lot is optimization of the
computer architecture so once you scale
up there's two bottlenecks you're going
to face one of them is performance which
keeps getting worse as you process more
more data the other one is actually the
compute cost everybody knows how
expensive Azure and uh and AWS are so we
have to really optimize at the CPU level
in order to use every single CPU cycle
so that we can scale the solutions very
efficiently so let me give you example
of a solution this is what we call
operational digital twin solution for
drooling rcks with our partner Precision
droing one of the largest um droing
contractors in North America and what it
does does is basically monitor all the
drolling equipment like mud pumps top
drives generators and it uses a huge
amount of data right billions of data
points per day tens of millions 57
million database queries in order to to
generate those events it's already
deployed at over 100 RS and who uses
this it turns out it's not just the
field Ops when you have a really good
digital twin solution everyone uses it
and this is not a dream this is actually
how Precision uses today so from the
field Ops the rig managers to the remote
Ops team that use a lot of the
automation feature in order to very
quickly figure out what their problems
are over 100 rigs right so they can only
spend about two minutes per every rig to
fix issues so many many of the things
have to be automated and obviously
electrical engineers they look at the
the data to understand what's going on
um to data teams right generating bi
reports uh procurement CFO to look at
budgeting forecasting and even the CEO
gets a monthly report on what's going on
with the r how much how much spending
are happening so a good solution ties
all the different units together this is
something I want to show very quickly
this so how fast once you have this kind
of graphical te technology how fast you
can build Solutions the the the text is
a little small there but basically took
just two months for us to finish the
digital twin solution from the M mud
pump and another month to iterate with
two rig teams you cannot do that in
software ever and once the field teams
tell us what they want you know we we we
we get the solution you know implemented
within that one month time and then they
start to scale up and you can see we
start to add AI models we start to build
digital twin for the other equipment and
in a year it's over 50 rcks in a year
and a half it's over 100 rcks right so
this kind of you know development
framework is super fast and it gets a
field to get engaged in the solution if
they're engaged they're going to use
it so this is just the example screen of
a mod pump um um monitoring screen shows
you what happens to the pump what
components um are running to the close
to the end of life uh digital log G for
them to put in what components replaced
you know what issues they've seen those
data actually goes back into training
for the AI and there's also a very
interesting AI behind the scene you know
the field doesn't even know what
technolog is behind it why do they care
right they just wanted to get their job
done but they say I predicts every
single component lifetime issues from
the day you put them in to the day of
end of life right so it doesn't just say
oh now it's vibration something's going
to happen but instead the first day you
put it in it's going to tell you what's
is going to happen through its life and
uh so we build these large Solutions we
build them very quickly and uh if you're
interested come to see our technology
and our um uh demo thank you