Hi. Uh my name is De Patel. I'm the
co-founder and CEO of Blue Shift. Uh
we're building a mining processing
company with a mission to accelerate
economic resilience and enable uh
resilience of these critical mineral
supply chains and the scalability of
them. We are building out of the engine
and green town. um and my co-founder um
professor David did his grad study at uh
MIT.
The problem we are facing is
u the upheaval of critical mineral
supply chains. You know we are seeing a
shift of focus from globalized supply
chains to more uh resilient and domestic
supply chains. And we have seen a
concentration of some of these supply
chains happen especially for a country
like the US which currently depends on
uh currently depends 100% on imports for
21 of these 50 critical minerals and
these minerals are used in industries
that amount around 90 trillion uh
dollars. Yeah. And uh one of the
critical ones amongst these are the rare
earth elements which are used in
everything from missile guidance systems
to uh uh to your smartphones and China
has recently enacted a ban on these uh
causing a major supply constraint on
that.
Um the solution we're working on is
building a mining processing solution
that is profitable, autonomous and
simplified.
We are building something that will
preserve uh margins at scale being
highly energy efficient. We're building
something that is autonomous uh and can
operate modularly leverages IoT and an
AI layer on top of that. Um and we have
significantly increased the intensity of
the process. simplified it and hence
results in something that is low capex.
So we have a very versatile process that
turns uh current liabilities into
products. So we are taking an input such
as collash malings etc running it
through our modular process u and
extracting minerals such as nickel
generators through our patented process.
Uh, one example of a untapped resource
is the coal flash that currently sits in
the US which holds around five decades
worth of uh rare earth elements.
Uh we're looking for partnerships on the
on the way side. We're looking for
people in the utility space that own u
collash liabilities. would like to
partner with them to uh deploy smallcale
tests and also enter in long-term
partnerships. Similarly, in the mine
waste space, we're looking at people
that have boxite residue, aluminina
tailings, etc. um and broader mine
tailings as well and do similar small
scale tests with them. on the uh you
know downstream side, we're interested
in partnering with people that put these
rare elements in uh magnets and you know
developing that supply chain alongside
with OEMs uh in the automotive and
defense space. Thank you.