[Music]
One of the things I'm focusing on over
these conversations is what I call
facilitative leadership. I'm talking
about facilitative leadership in the
broad sense of skills and attitudes. A
facilitative leader helps parties focus
on
issues, not their stand on the issues.
Issues, not positions. Credibility and
authority for a facilitative leader.
Credibility and authority derive from
performance, not
from entitlements bestowed by those in
top positions. Your credibility and your
authority as a facilitative leader are
not given to you. They are earned in the
face of the people you are working with.
The goal is to look at a series of 10
micro skills that I'm going to assert
and that you will see are at the heart
of facilitative leadership in the public
sector. Micro skills like stakeholder
assessment. How do you decide who should
be involved in some effort at
collaborative decision making? Agenda
setting. You've got a group, you've got
a problem, but now you've got to lay out
the work for the group. Ground
rules. How do you help a group work when
it's not it's not a corporation? It's
not an organization where everyone has
internalized the same set of
understandings. It's an ad hoc
collaboration that the public sector
generates causes to have happen all the
time. And we're imagining you're either
the person creating that context or
you're in it and you're trying to help
manage some ad hoc assembly toward a
solution to a problem. You
need ground rules. What do you know
about formulating ground rules for such
a
context? Joint factf finding. How do you
get people with very different views of
things, very different levels of
capability to engage together at
analyzing, understanding before they
seek to reach agreement on something?
mediation. You're either being mediated
upon or maybe you be a mediator. Maybe
you be formally appointed the mediator.
Maybe you're just the person who takes
on the mediating function within a group
because there isn't one and nobody else
is doing it. And somebody needs to help
the group deal with the internal
difficulties of a lot of people talking
at the same time with very different
ideas about what to do. Generating
options for mutual
gain. Anybody in a group can help a
group when they're trying to problem
solve generate proposals or options.
Creating value in a problem solving
context. What does that mean? How do you
do that? using objective
criteria. It's a very specific idea for
how to help people when they have a
bunch of options and they're trying to
choose amongst them and they all want
different things. How can you help them
argue for their view in a way that helps
the group toward agreement and doesn't
just make the discussion less difficult?
Building consensus. What does it mean to
generate consensus which is not the
least common denominator acceptable bad
alternative but rather an agreement on
the best way of dealing with the
differences that the group has helping a
group learn from its mistakes or
organizational learning. I'm going to
argue these are 10 micro skills that
somebody trying to facilitate in a
leaderly way in a public sector context
needs to have. So that's a set of
general ideas, key concepts and what I
wanted to move to this evening. I'm
suggesting there's a series of micro
skills that you can use, draw on, build.
When we think about what's taught in
planning schools in general and planning
department here in particular, um I'm
afraid we're not naming these as skills
that planners need. So, I'm trying to
fill a gap because I mean, you may have
picked these skills up in your own work,
in your education, because people here
come from many different backgrounds and
areas. But I want to say a word or two
about each of these. And then I want to
throw you into
a situation, a roleplay simulation. When
the negotiation starts, you will have a
role assigned to you. I'll give you some
general uh background about this, but
the material you have in front of you is
your
confidential instructions for the role
that you've drawn that you'll be
playing. Every trio will be playing
exactly the same game. And when we
start, I will encourage you to take your
chairs and find space for yourself out
of your shot of the other trios. give
you roughly half an hour to see if your
three people can agree on three things
and then we will stop. Everyone will
stop at the same time whether you have
reached the satisfactory conclusion from
your standpoint or not. You need to get
to a minimum score for there to be an
agreement. So the idea is you can use
these micro skills in this
negotiation. The goal is to get a good
result for yourself. There's no total
score for the trio. There's a score for
each person. We want to see what
strategies people used who got a good
outcome. I want to give credit to my
friend, my very dear friend John
Forester who invented this with Bruce
Stiffel. Okay. stakeholder assessment.
There's a technique for getting the
right people to the table when it is
your job to
convene stakeholders. City says, "Oh,
we're thinking of changing policy. We
want to have a public meeting. Uh we
want stakeholder engagement."
Who? How? How do you assess who the
relevant stakeholders are and how do you
get them to participate? Those of you
who are involved in the renewable energy
facility sighting task force know that
we have teams working with different
communities trying to bring together the
relevant stakeholders who are fighting
about whether a renewable energy
facility should or shouldn't be built.
There's no point convening a process to
build a consensus if you can't figure
out who the stakeholders are and get
them to be present and then figure out
how to engage them in ways that uh take
account of differences amongst them uh
effectively. So stakeholder assessment
is a process and it's a product. It
generates the agenda when you do it
right. It generates the agenda with
everybody's participation in setting the
agenda. It also helps to set and uh
legitimize ground rules for the group if
the process is run properly. But the
product of a stakeholder assessment is
uh basically a matrix of actors down the
side, stakeholder groups and their
interests across the top. And you fill
in all of those cells in that matrix.
And the only way to do that is to talk
to lots of people. I'm arguing that
stakeholder assessment is a skill. It
can be learned. I hope that hearing
about this this evening will encourage
you to at least read about it. if not
find a way to study it uh while you're
here because planners are constantly
asked to organize opportunities for
stakeholder engagement and nobody's
talking about how you know whether you
have the right people there. What's the
point if you can't have a way of
identifying the relevant stakeholder
groups and who can speak either like
them or for them? generating options for
mutual
gain. Uh you're going to be in a
situation there's three issues. Uh
there's specific options under those
three
issues. Those options were generated by
earlier conversations amongst these
parties and others in the city.
Generating options in real life is
getting people to have the equivalent of
that score sheet. You say, "Come to an
event or a task force." Okay,
participate. Okay, we're talking about
X. Okay, I like it or I don't like it.
But what you really want is for them to
have what you have in your scoreeet,
which is here are the issues we're going
to try to get agreement on. Here are the
options under each issue that have in a
sense been vetted for technical
feasibility or plausibility, and here's
where I stand on each option. If
everybody comes with that, you have a
chance of negotiating an agreement. It's
when people show up, they don't know
what their score sheet is. They haven't
talked to their people. They don't know
what the agenda sub items are. They
don't know the options under it. If
you're at the beginning of such a
process, you want to try to help
generate options for mutual gain.
Knowing how to do that is a skill.
creating value. You're going to be
talking with three people about three
issues for 30 minutes. There are
actually ways of framing
packages of the three issues that create
value. And either you know how to do
that or you don't. The good news is I
can teach you how to do that. The good
news is you'll probably infer it from
the result of this halfhour exercise.
But it is a skill to create value by
helping multiple parties
package multiple options under multiple
issues in the right way. Make the power
larger through value creation. Building
consensus comes off of that which is
you've got three people. They come with
very
explicit priorities and directions. You
start with in many cases angry parties.
You got people who are there to protect
their interests. You got people there
who are there to advance their interest.
You have people who are there to
sabotage the whole
effort almost always. And you're trying
to get
agreement because if you can get
agreement, you can guarantee everyone
that's what's going to happen. You were
empowering everyone there by saying that
the decision rules a consensus. In this
case, this is an advisory process. Well,
you want to have an effect as somebody
in an advisory process. Get unonymity
amongst all the adviserss and then hand
that to whoever the elected official was
who said I'm creating this advisory
process and say we reached unanimous
agreement. We hope you'll go along with
it. But we are your constituents, all of
us, and we have reached an agreement.
You want to empower people, help them
reach a consensus. When a process of
public engagement is organized by some
elected or appointed official or entity,
they're trying to get ideas about what
they can go forward with that people
won't vote against them, won't fight
them, won't bring litigation. That's a
way to empower people through
consensus using objective criteria in
distributive negotiation. Whatever
agreements you get are going to get
different scores for each person. You're
talking about an agreement that
distributes value across the three of
you. You each have some minimum you have
to get. You have some goal you desire
and you have time limits. And if you get
an agreement, it distributes value
across the three parties. How do you
make a case for the package that
distributes the most value to you that
you most want? You can't say, "I like
this one best because it's best for me."
And expect that to carry the
day. Well, what else should you say? So
and so likes
it. You could say that. Maybe some of
the people would say, "Well, then okay,
I'll go with what you want because so
and so likes it." That's a pretty weak
way forward. If I had an hour, I'd ask,
"What's your theory of practice at the
moment?" and ask people to tell me what
you would say when you present the
package that's best for you and you're
trying to get the others to agree to it.
One of the things that you can learn how
to do is to argue on the merits for the
option that's best for
you by not making it a test of will with
the other two parties, but
rather trying to focus on what the other
two parties would agree. any other
neutral observer who knew everything
that was going on would agree that
that's the best option. That's an
objective measure. It doesn't mean
correct in the sense of objective. It
means what would any neutral or
independent party say is the best
outcome hearing everything. And I want
to be able to refer to the prevailing
norms or the past precedent that the
same communities use. Something that's
not about it's best for me, that's why
you should go along with it. Something
that refers to an objective standard
independent of your interest. Mediation
you're going to see practice because one
of you is a mediator in this exercise.
One of you represents the homelessness
task force appointed by the city.
There's a task force, but only the head
of the task force is coming. There's a
group of neighbors in this area who are
very, very concerned about the idea that
there would be a homeless shelter down
the street where they live. Part of the
concern of the neighbors is what they
think will happen in this shelter. Will
people just have a place to sleep at
night? Will it provide job training for
people so they could go from the shelter
if they're staying there to a job or at
least a job interview? How many
beds? What mix of
activities will go on in this shelter if
it's built? You also have to decide when
this shelter is going to open. It's
perfectly usable in its current form,
although a lot of people would like to
fix it up in a variety of ways depending
on their idea of what the shelter's for
and who it's for and how many people
it's going to serve. But some people are
really keen to get this thing to open
right away, and other people wouldn't
mind if it didn't open for a very long
time. You have to agree on an opening
date. You have to agree on how many
beds, what's the mix of uses, and you
all come with very strong views from the
homeless task force or from the
neighborhood about these
issues. The third person there works is
the city planning assistant director,
works for the mayor directly. The mayor
has a huge stake in this getting solved,
but the city council has a very
different idea from the mayor of what
this should be and who it should serve
and how it should be funded and all
kinds of stuff. The mayor would like
credit for settling this and avoiding
giving it to the council to decide.
The person there for the mayor is the
planning director and the mayor has
said, "You be a mediator and help these
two who initially seem to be at odds and
get an agreement because I want there to
be an agreement." So, you'll see some
form of mediation in action. Uh I can't
guarantee anything about the way the
mediation will play out, but we'll talk
about that especially afterwards. The
last two are not a big deal for us. this
evening, but I'm arguing they're really
important skills. If you're in a setting
where something goes on for a while and
you don't help the people that you're
trying to involve in this understand
what's happening as it's happening so
that they can learn from and modify
their way of working together, you
failed as a leader. Organizational
learning, encouraging it is a leadership
skill. Similarly, at the individual
level, people engaged in some practice
should take some time to reflect. Even
if they're angry at each other, even if
they haven't reached agreement, they
should try to learn something about how
the way they're approaching things is
working. People should be encouraged to
reflect on their engagement in processes
like this. and you as the leader need to
encourage them to reflect either
together or small groups or separately
so they get to be more effective. I
would argue that's a leadership skill
helping people improve modify their
personal theory of practice. So each
group has a number on your confidential
instructions. So all three people in the
group should have the same number. It
will work better if you're not in
earshot of each other doing exactly the
same thing in a different way next to
each other. So, um I want to give you
half an hour, 30 minutes. You are the
role you're assigned. Confidential means
confidential. You can't show your piece
of paper to the other person across you
says, "Sure, I believe it. It says it
right here." You you can't prove
something is the truth by pointing to a
piece of paper. You can in a game, but
you can't do it in real life. When
you're done, if you want to share your
confidential instructions, I'm fine with
that. But that's when you're really
done. Okay? It's in your hands. Find a
comfortable place for your trio to be.
We're trying to get to a position of
whether or not we can come to an
agreement on getting a shelter
developed. I am Mr. Goldmith, uh, the
planning director. I've been around
Westfield for 20 years. I remember the
old social service center that's now
unused. We are looking at how uh we
could make sure that we agree to uh
reopen this social center service to a
shelter job counseling a kitchen and
medical care along with housing or beds
for people who would otherwise be in the
street. Now it's uh already December. It
will take 6 months, we understand, to
rehabilitate the center to get it ready
to happen, but we would like this to be
open as soon as it is possible. I'm Jay
Woods. I'm part of Neighbors Together.
We're really glad that we were here
having this meeting. I've been living
here in the same house for 18 years and
so I understand the history of the
multi-ervice social center. Previously
was a daycare, before that a teen
counseling center. Many of those stayed
in the area. My concern is that
homelessness is just a systemic national
problem. It's a big problem, but it's
not clear that turning buildings into
shelters would do anything about the
problem itself. It's addressing a
symptom, not the cause. So my question
is, did the task force consider job
creation strategies that help these
people earn income? The homeless task
force claims to have reviewed all the
available sites in our city, but it has
only taken 6 months to do so. So I'm
just slightly confused as to how you can
have such a confidence in such a short
period of time. I think it'd be
fantastic to set some complete grounds
for the world in this discussion. Thank
you both for your introduction. I think
it's going to be really important for us
to just recognize that we are uh all
have
interest. The neighborhood association
does not have a problem with opening
beds. The problem is with the services
so as to make sure that people are not
going to stay here for a long time so we
address their homelessness issues right
now. We want a limited space but limited
amount before we continue maybe can
spend some time recapping your timeline.
We were told that it will take until May
and I think if we work together along
with the resident try to help them get
jobs. So we want to make sure that a we
do some work together to try and reduce
homelessness and that's my body control
but b we also have the capacity next
year to make sure no one has we're
concerned about the long-term impacts it
has on the people in the neighborhood um
property values and why can't this
energy be poured
into creating more affordable housing in
the city? Why are we not exploring these
options and have this more comprehensive
like official probing to what sites are
better as well as accompanied by
employment creation opportunities and uh
relying on already existing medical
facilities instead of building something
new wasting all of that time. It would
be helpful for me to do some mirroring
so that we are all on the same page of
what was stated so that we can identify
where there are key tension points um
between each other and how we can
address some of those tension points.
Thankfully, we're all on the same page
that we want to find a solution for
homelessness. A point that Miss Woods is
bringing up is there hasn't been enough
community engagement. Their request also
is that um can they get some more
statistics on what the exact need is if
we have a capacity of 60 an addition of
60 people into a neighborhood that just
found out about this one seems so we are
very concerned about what
this are as well agrees to conduct
additional engagements of the
communities over the next uh grace and
we will be providing the support
necessary to make sure this consultation
happens as soon as possible. We're just
concerned about what this will mean for
us as well. We want to support our
homeless
outside make sure that we're okay with
the city work to try and address the
issues of this
post. it would be worthwhile discussing
whether or not additional services were
um communities um concerned about the
home.
We agreed to an engagement process to be
conducted until next spring and we
agreed that we can start at a discussion
of 20 beds with additional services of
workforce programming um and agreed that
this facility can be used and should be
used for um services to support um
homeless. We also agreed that we would
engage very soon. We'll pick this up.
All right. Great. All right. Excellent.
This is a scatteragramgram of the
possible agreements when people follow
the rules. The numbers are just a list
of the possible agreements. This is
Hutter's score along the bottom and
would score this way. The mediated score
isn't plotted here. You can see that the
high score is 157 for wood. Hutter gets
105 and the high score for Hutter 165
when Wood gets 120. And then there's a
bunch of other possible agreements. So
all all eight groups got agreement in
the limited time available but the
agreements were different. This
scatagram is designed to show that it's
possible to create different amounts of
value and distribute them differently
all within the same frame of allowable
agreements. All of these are legitimate
given the minimum that each party had to
have. And
yet some pairs were
able to generate a high score and some
only were able to get a low score or all
legitimate agreements following the
rules. I'm showing you what the maximum
is in your role that you could have
gotten while your counterpart got an
acceptable amount for them. And so the
question is, were you just satisfied
with less or was the way you approached
it destined to get you less than what
the maximum is you could have gotten?
There's no way to really compare it to
anybody else unless you have all the
score sheets and all of the confidential
instructions. There are um a lot of
possible agreements in this same
context. Almost all of the Goldsmith
roles got over a 100 points. I overheard
one group where both the parties said,
"Yeah, sure. We'll give you 20 points
each." And
then the person in the Goldsmith role
said, "Well, I do have to tell you I had
a hidden agenda." I was working for the
mayor. The mayor insists that this not
open until next winter. Now, this person
is passing themselves off as a neutral
mediator, but the fact of the matter is
they have an agenda. They also have a
personal agenda of wanting one group to
to do better, do as best as possible
even at the expense of the other group.
That's not neutrality. We typically
define mediation as neutral or
nonpartisan assistance to parties in a
conflict. Mediation is a and
facilitation are functions. They're
tasks. They're services that can be
provided. We happen to have this sort of
analytic backdrop where we can see, oh,
the
mediator had a
bias. The source of the bias in this
case was they worked for the mayor and
the mayor said, "You're my person at
this thing. I don't want this to fail
because I don't want to give my city
council counterpart the opportunity to
take over this issue and run it the way
he wants to run it. On the other hand,
uh you should help the parties reach
agreement."
So the mediator had to struggle with
their mandate and their personal beliefs
and the perceptions of the parties. So
Claudia, um you you got the the high
score. Um, I'm curious what your
counterparts have to say about uh your
way of working with them since uh you've
got the the highest score substantially
higher 157. Did she seem to be pushing
you around? She she did something to end
up with the highest possible score in
that role.
Same information, same cards dealt,
different result as a mediator also just
yeah need to adjust those numbers on
mine. Just what should it be? 68. Ah,
okay. Now I understand.
Jennifer was was great to speak with. I
think she had really clear goals and was
also really amendable to to working with
the housing task force. Yeah, she's very
firm advocating for the residents and
she also is very clear about coming to
an agreement like I kind of feel I need
to giving some like the things I want in
order to reach. Yeah. I mean your score
is perfectly fine. It just happens to be
less than it could have been. Yeah.
because your counterpart uh got the most
possible. Yeah. And I'm trying to see
whether there was anything that she said
did that made you feel like you should
lower your expectations or do you feel
like your expectations were met? So
fine. So she got a high score. So what?
I feel like the way she said is helps us
to like empathize a lot with the
residents. I think that's why Yeah, I
think Jennifer was really clear on the
fact that it sounded like the
neighborhood that you were part of had
had frustrations in the past and that
like you didn't want this this to recur
and you were I think really clear about
the impact that that had on you and and
your constituents.
So, you've got the high score at the
other end of the 150. What's the
reaction of your partners to hearing
that whatever it was you said or did got
you the highest possible score? You
didn't get a bad score. It's just a low
score. I think we maximized the winning
of the both parties or the three parties
even. I appreciate the point. I mean it
you in this context people have a
minimum score. If they get the minimum
score they can go back to their group
and say we got a we got what we wanted.
But you can create more value than just
the minimum for each side depending on
how you proceed. If you presume that
your goal is your minimum, then you're
not going to look for possible trades
that will create more value for both
sides and the other person isn't going
to say no because you're offering
something better than what they would
otherwise get and you're getting more
for yourself. This is about creating
trades for mutual gain.
And the only way to do that is to play
the game of what if. And I didn't listen
in uh to your tables, but usually the
way you find your way, if you imagine
that everybody's starting down here at a
bare minimum and you want to go as far
to the northeast, you can presume
there's a paro curve, which is the list
of options that go across the top. So,
you're starting down here and you want
to move as far as you possibly can to
the northeast. You don't know how far
you can get because you don't have all
the scores ahead of time, but you know
you want to move that way. So, if I say,
"Well, if you offer me seven, agreement,
seven down at the bottom, it's barely
acceptable. 100 107 for wood, 105
uh for for Hutter." And then I say back
to you, if I'm would, how
about if we go to 13, you get
more. I do too, but you get more. I'm
moving from seven to 13. And I'm looking
for a package where
I offer you more by making a change on
the list of which option I'm agreeing to
under one of the issues that seemed
important to you. if you will move to a
different option on another issue that's
most important to me. The two parties do
not value the three issues the same.
They have different
priorities. If you can't discover that,
then you can't offer a
whatif. So, understanding the other
side's interest is the first step in
creating value for mutual gain. That's a
what if. It's a trade. It's a package.
And I don't know what to offer until I
know what's important to the other side.
I won't know that if I don't ask. And
I'm exploring all the possible whatifs
until I get to the puditive, but I don't
know where it is exactly paro frontier,
which is this outer edge from top to
bottom of scores. Now you can be in
economic terms at the outer edge. You're
superefficient. You've used up all the
value because that you've moved out to
this frontier, this surface across the
top. But there's a lot of places that
you could be that that curve goes all
across the whole spectrum. It's no more
about efficiency. It's
about equity. Anything on that curve,
it's no more value left to split.
But I can move along the curve where I
do better, you will do worse. When
you're talking about a a paro efficient
curve, you are talking about a zero- sum
situation. There's a maximum amount of
value. And as long as I go to the
northeast and hit that curve, I haven't
wasted any possible value. I've explored
enough whatifs, understood enough about
our differing interest that I can move.
But where on that curve I end up, that's
not about using all the value. That's
about who gets what. In the process of
building consensus, in any effort to
create value, in any effort to generate
new options, packages for mutual gain,
but we're both advantaged by the more we
move out to that surface. So for people
who read books about win-win, it's an
illusion because there are constraints
on both sides relative to what issues
they can agree to or can't or there are
legal limits or there are time limits.
You can see how you did relative to the
extremes. First of all, you got an
agreement though that was good. Now,
within the frame of agreement, did you
set your goals too low and thus accept a
deal that was fine but not the maximum
you could have gotten if you had been
more aggressive? Did you set your goals
too high, hit a wall with the other
side, and collapse down to a barely
acceptable agreement from both of you
because there was no more time to create
value? I'm talking about the context in
which these kinds of micro skills come
into play. The more confident you are in
what you're doing when you're doing
these, the more you will feel yes, I
should keep posing more questions to
understand their interests better
because if I don't understand their
interests, I'm never going to propose
something good for them and great for me
because I don't I can't do the first
part because I haven't asked enough
questions. So the more confident you are
about the search for value creation, the
more you're going to ask questions. Not
just for the sake of counting how many
questions, but for the sake of
understanding the other side's
interests. And the more confident you
are, the more you'll search for
unexpected trades, unexpected whatifs.
The more confident you are about this
underlying structure, the more assertive
you will be about your interests, the
more focused you will be on the other
side's interests, the more confident you
will be about suggesting packages and
options for mutual gain. So, it's not
just about learning what these micro
skills are. It's also about being able
to use them with confidence. I want you
to take away the sense that there's
micro skills you can work on to advance
your leadership
capacities. Next time we meet, I want to
be able to talk with you and get as many
individuals as I can uh to say, "Oh,
what do you see as your own strengths
and weaknesses relative to facilitative
leadership?" Because what I want to
provoke is your plan for what you're
going to do and I want to put that in
the context of being here in the
department and in the degree program
you're in. How you going to enhance your
capabilities? The answer is going to be
personal and different. I'm also
expecting some people to say, you know,
I'm not so worried about being in a
leadership role. I'm content to be part
of a team and be working on something I
believe in and the leadership doesn't
appeal to me or I don't see myself that
way. If that's how you think, I hope
you'll say that. I want to be sure
you've asked and answered it in a
thoughtful way so that you can use the
time you have here appropriately to the
extent you want to take facilitative
leadership roles. So, I'll see everybody
next Thursday and dinner once again.
[Music]