the MIT energy initiative presents
shrinking inks nail polish and smelly
bacteria high school students spend
their summer building a lowcost fuel
cell written by Deborah halber in a lab
on the fourth floor of mit's building 56
a group of Massachusetts high school
students gathered around a device that
measures conductivity Vincent Newen 15
from salus thought of the times the
material in their sample electrode
flaked off the moment they took it out
of the oven or how the electrode would
fold weirdly onto itself the big fails
were kind of funny but discouraging the
students had worked for a month
experimenting with different materials
and 17-year-old Briana Tong of mden
wondered if they'd finally gotten it
right would their electrode work well
enough to power a microbial fuel cell
the students secured their electrode
with alligator clips someone hit start
and the teens watched anxiously as the
device searched for even the faintest
electrical
current capturing electrons from
bacteria in July 2022 Tong nen and six
other students from malen Catholic High
School commuted between the lab of MIT
chemical engineer Ariel L first and
their school's chemistry lab their goal
was to Fashion electrodes for lowcost
microbial fuel cells miniature
bioreactors that generate small amounts
of electricity by capturing electrons
transferred from living microbes these
devices can double as electrochemical
sensors first the Paul m cook Career
Development professor of chemical
engineering uses a mix of
electrochemistry microbial engineering
and Material Science to address
challenges in human health and clean
energy the goal of all of our projects
is to increase sustainability clean
energy and Health Equity globally she
says electrochemical sensors are
powerful sensitive detection and
measurement tools typically their
electrodes need to be built in precisely
engineered environments thinking about
ways of making devices without needing a
clean room is important for coming up
with inexpensive devices that can be
deployed in low resource settings under
non-ideal conditions first says for
17-year-old Angelina Ang of Everett the
project illuminated the significance of
coming together to problem solve for a
healthier and more sustainable Earth she
says it made me realize that we hold the
answers to fix our dying planet with the
help of a children's toy called shrink e
inks carbon based materials nail polish
and a certain smelling bacterium the
students got literally a trial by fire
in introduction to the scientific method
at one point one of their experimental
electrodes burst into flames other
results were more promising the students
took advantage of the electrical
properties of a bacterium shanella o
andensis that's been called Nature's
microscopic power plant as part of their
metabolism Shu andella o andensis
generate electricity by oxidizing
organic matter in essence they spit out
electrons put enough together and you
get a few milliamps to build bacteria
friendly electrodes one of the first
things the students did was culture
shanella they learned how to pour a
growth medium into Petri dishes where
the reddish normally lake living
bacteria could multiply the microbes
first notes are a little stinky like
cabbage but we think they're really cool
she says with the right engineering
shanella can produce electric current
when they detect toxins in water or soil
they could be used for Bio remediation
of Wastewater lowcost versions could be
useful for areas with limited or no
access to Reliable electricity and clean
water Next Generation
chemists the Malon Catholic MIT program
resulted from a fluke encounter between
first and a molden Catholic parent Mary
Margaret odonnell saaki then a medicinal
chemist at a Kendall Square biotech
startup met first through a mutual
friend she asked first if she'd consider
hosting high school chemistry students
in her lab for the summer first was
intrigued she traces her own passion for
science to a program she'd happened upon
between her Junior and senior years High
School in St Louis the daughter of a
software engineer and a businesswoman
first was casting around for potential
career interests when she came across a
summer program that enlisted scientists
in Academia and private research to
introduce high school students and
teachers to aspects of the scientific
Enterprise that's when I realized that
research is not like a lab class where
there's an expected outcome first
recalls it's so much cooler than that
using startup funding from an MIT energy
initiative seed Grant first developed a
curriculum with molden Catholic
chemistry teacher Sheamus Maguire and
students were invited to apply in
addition to Tong and nen participants
included Shen xang luu 18 from China
Christian Agata 14 of Wakefield Kenneth
Ramirez 17 of Everett Isaac Tuscano 17
of Medford and Mary Katherine Zaki 15 of
Riv and Wakefield odonald Zaki was
surprised and pleased when her daughter
applied to the program and was accepted
first notes that women are still
underrepresented in chemical engineering
she was particularly excited to Mentor
young women through the
program a conductive ink the students
were charged with identifying materials
that had high conductivity low
resistance were a bit soluble and with
the help of a compatible glue were able
to stick to a substrate first showed the
malen Catholic crew shrink you inks a
common polymer popularized in the 1970s
as a craft material that when heated in
a toaster oven shrinks to a of its size
and becomes thicker and more rigid
electrodes based on shrinking inks would
cost pennies making it an ideal
inexpensive material for microbial fuel
cells that could monitor for instance
soil Health in low and middle inome
countries right now monitoring soil
health is problematic first says you
have to collect a sample and bring it
back to the lab to analyze an expensive
equipment but if we have these little
devices that cost a couple of bucks each
we can monitor soil Health remotely
after a crash course in conductive
carbon-based inks and solvent glues the
students went off to Malden Catholic to
figure out what materials they wanted to
try Tong rattled them off carbon Nano
tubes carbon Nano fibers graphite powder
activated carbon potential solvents to
help glue the carbon to the shrinky inks
included nail polish corn syrup and
embossing ink to name a few they tested
and retested when they hit a dead end
they revised their hypotheses they tried
using a 3D printed stencil to dubb the
ink glue mixture onto the shrinky inks
they hand panted them they tried
printing stickers they worked with
little squeegees they tried scooping and
dragging the material some of their
Electro materials either flaked off or
wouldn't stick in the heating process
embossing ink never dried after baking
the shrink in a recalls in fact it's
probably still liquid and corn syrup had
a tendency to boil seeing activated
carbon ignite or corn syrup boiling in
the convection oven was quite the
spectacle after the electrod was out of
the oven and cooled down we would check
the conductivity says Tong who plans to
pursue a career in science if we saw
there was a high conductivity we got
excited and thought those materials
worked the Moment of Truth came in first
MIT lab where the students had access to
more sophisticated testing equipment
with their electrodes conduct
electricity many of them didn't Tong
says at first we were sad but then Dr
first told us that this is what science
is testing repeatedly and sometimes not
getting the results we wanted Lou agrees
if we just copy the data left by other
Scholars and don't collect and figured
out by ourselves then it is difficult to
be a qualified researcher he says some
of the students plan to continue the
project one afternoon a week at MIT and
as an independent study at molden
Catholic the long-term goal is to create
a field-based soil sensor that employs a
bacterium like shanella by Chance the
student's very first electrode made of
graphite powder ink and nail polish glue
generated the most current one of the
team's biggest surprises was how much
better black nail polish Works than
clear nail polish it turns out black
nail polish contains iron based pigment
a conductor the unexpected wind took
some of the sting out of the failures
they learned a very hard lesson your
results might be awesome and things are
exciting but then nothing else might
work and that's totally fine first says