how many of you and raise your hand is
somehow familiar with this
map okay for the few hands not raised
let me explain this to you this is Trump
winning
okay at a higher resolution if you zoom
in this is somehow different you notice
that the blue dots which are the big
cities in the US are very different from
the previous map you see that in in
cities uh there is a prevalence of blue
which is not
Trump and we know that cities has grown
has born uh more than 10,000 years ago
because people wanted to get to live
together to
exchange experiences to exchange ideas
to exchange chromosomes and this is
basically the birth of of cities we know
today that cities behave somehow in a
different way in a special way well
fortunately we can study today's cities
with the help of digital Technologies
this is Lisbon seeing in real time from
the lens of data produced by the public
transportation we are lab here at MIT
we're not interested in politics we are
interested in science and the science of
City we are the sensible City lab we use
technology to better
understand what are the rules of cities
how we can converge the digital world
that we live in with the physical world
that we live in and we do this all over
the world with many companies with many
cities and with few research Partners so
let me give you some examples of our
research today for example something
very peculiar that we find in cities is
that there are a lot of environmental
information that change in space and in
time take pollution for
example you have a very good air quality
in this point of the city you go down
the block go around the corner and you
have a very bad air pollution and air
quality this is normal it's how cities
behave well how to monitor this we
decided to build our own sensors and
instead of deploying them every meter in
our cities we equip some cars so that
normal cars can bring around sensors and
those are multi-purpose multiplatform
sensors they're equipped with cameras
you can take pictures you can take
thermal pictures and multispectral
pictures you can have readings on
temperature and humidity and again air
quality and um why is this useful this
is useful for example to build these
kind of
maps this is a way of democratizing data
you show to Citizens and to companies
and to municipalities data at
everybody's doorstep what's the air
quality in front of your house in front
of your kids
school it's interesting that if you
bring this technology to different
cities or you show it to different
companies everybody find somehow their
own value in New York we were working
with the mayor and with the municipality
to look at how the underprivileged
communities the lower income communities
are disp disproportionately exposed to
better air quality if you go to
Stockholm they were interested in heat
waves and understand how the heat
bubbles in the city are
created I'll show you something that
we're doing in Rome and we're monitoring
trees Rome today has a big problem of
tree Health there are small parasites
that really like to eat those trees
and those very beautiful sentennial
trees are are dying so we're using the
same technology attached to cars with
few different sensors normal camera
multispectral camera with some AI to be
able to detect the
tree and understand how the three is
performing
photosynthesis and we're doing this with
the forest corpse in Italy the the
Carabiner so we're equipping their cars
with our sensors collecting a lot of
data and and then eventually down the
line they're going to use satellite
pictures as well to to complement the
view that we have from down from Road
level but talking about trees uh let me
give you this number
65% of insects are at risk of Extinction
due to climate
change this is quite dramatic it's quite
dramatic because it means that all the
ecosystems that basically rule the world
are at the edge of collapse
and ecosystems in cities are even more
fragile and those little bugs um even if
they're very annoying for you and for me
as well there a very good proxy of the
biodiversity of a city or an environment
counting these bucks is crucial to
understand at which point our ecosystem
is going up or down well it turns out
that all this counting are happening
manually there are people going there
with a notebook noting the bugs there is
very very little AI on this so in our
lab we said let's try to not only
recognize automatically there is an
insect in this picture but we built a
platform we built a library noce library
that is able to categorize the insect PC
and this may sound very you know trivial
or a computer science exercise but then
we talked with some companies with um
with an engineering and architecture
company
and they were saying well we actually
need to monitor the biodiversity in oral
de developments and uh and and projects
so why don't you develop something more
so we decided to embed this intelligence
in a sensor and build together with some
experts in
biology some Gardens some physical
Gardens with the right mix of trees and
flowers to attract these insects and do
the counting
automatically there's a some of the
research that we do we we partner with
many companies all over the world with
many cities in three of them the one
that you see in the map Dubai Amsterdam
Ando de Janeiro we actually build some
MIT Labs so we have permanent MIT
researchers there to really create an
ecosystem of innovation together with
the local stakeholders in Amsterdam for
example we're working on self-driving
boats we call them robots because they
are robotic boats
this is a long project that we are
developing with them you see here some
some of the true videos uh if you go to
Amsterdam you can try some of them and
not only they are autonomous for people
but with the same kind of Technology you
can use you can address other City needs
like trash collection for example the
challenge here was really to design the
technology for enabling a urban boat to
go around to design it and to understand
what are the urban uses for this and
we've done everything from the hardware
to the software to the urban cases if
you go to Rio De Janeiro for example
we're interested in this kind of
environments
FAS the shanki
towns a town that has grown without
rules and that's a result well many of
the planning techniques here are failing
Amazon doesn't deliver here why because
there are no street address there is no
catas
so we're using new technologies we were
the first ones to create 3D maps with
lighter or these
environments and this is the base for a
digital twin of a
fava that eventually enables us to you
know give property titles to people
understand what's the airf flow
understand what's the risk of
TB and plan for surgical interventions
instead of just demolishing everything
like many politicians are are claiming
for so those are some of the research
that we are doing here at the lab we are
lucky enough to do together with ILP our
big conference our annual Flagship
Conference of the lab here on campus
happening tomorrow it's called being
physical because we this year we're
really going to explore how the physical
proximity of people in cities are
fostering for a more resilient
environment and and for a more resilient
Society
it's going to be in person only many
people ask me is there remote connection
no it's being physical so it's going to
be a physical conference here on the MIT
sber Conference Center it's going to be
on two days so first day tomorrow
tomorrow
afternoon we're going to have some
panels with some experts on these topics
and then in two days on Thursday in our
lab we're going to have a demo day where
we're going to show some of this
technology we're going to do some deep
dives into of these projects and uh for
ILP members there is complimentary
access so just use this QR code use the
Forum ILP 2024 com code and you're able
to
register it's again free for for ILP and
we're really looking forward to
welcoming you tomorrow at uh at Samberg
here and in general to develop a
conversation with with our researchers
for maybe starting some research
topics some research Explorations with
you guys thank you so much