Hello. Um, my name is Sasha Servin
Shriber. I finished my PhD here at MIT
about four months ago and I'm now the
co-founder of Tinfoil where we're
building confidential AI in the
cloud. Uh, we're actually a team of
four. Uh, two of us are PhDs from MIT in
computer security and cryptography. Um
and we're really excited to join uh Y
Combinator for the spring batch starting
in a week and we're also part of the
NVIDIA inception
program. So data privacy uh slowing is
slowing down AI adoption across the
enterprise. Um and the reason for this
is if you're using AI today, you have to
send all your potentially proprietary or
um sensitive information to the AI
provider or the AI application.
Um and then this means that the
application and provider can access and
train on all your
data. Indeed,
57% of IT professionals site uh data
privacy as being the number one
inhibitor for Gen AI
adoption. Um and this is not that much
of a surprise because 48% of
organizations
uh put p um private company data into AI
systems. And in fact, 4% of employees
put uh sensitive data into AI systems on
a weekly basis, which makes this problem
only compounding over
time. Um, unfortunately, existing
solutions for data privacy are not a
great fit for the AI age. data privacy
agreements are difficult to enforce
especially if you're dealing with small
c um smaller companies building AI and
traditional cyber security uh best
practices do not really fit well with um
AI deployments and so a lot of
enterprises are now forced to shift to
on-prem uh deployments of their AI
systems which uh creates a a demand for
or requires a lot of engineering effort
to uh deploy and manage
Um and so Tinfoil is providing a way to
um get confidential AI in the cloud. So
what this means is that you get the
convenience of the cloud uh but the
security of an on-prem deployment. Your
data is always encrypted uh from the uh
source all the way through the inference
process. So even Tinfoil cannot see your
data.
Um, Tinfoil provides several guarantees.
The first is that you have data
confidentiality, meaning that everything
you put into the AI system is going to
be hidden even from the cloud or
tinfoil. Uh, we also provide model
confidentiality. So if you put a
proprietary model into tinfoil, uh, no
one can access the model weights uh,
directly.
and our infrastructure is transparent
and verifiable, meaning that you can
check for yourself that these two
properties are
enforced. The way we achieve this is by
building on top of Nvidia GPUs with
confidential compute mode. So this we
create a secure enclave on an untrusted
server that we uh run and all the data
from uh your end user is encrypted
directly to this secure enclave where
it's then processed and sent back.
Because we're building on top of
state-of-the-art GPUs, there's no
performance overhead relative to um
traditional inference.
We made it really easy to integrate
tinfoil into existing deployments of um
AI. So if you uh are running open source
models like deepse llama with one line
of code change you can uh start using
tinfoil and secure your AI
inference. Uh we're currently working
closely with NeoCloud and inference
providers who are looking to secure the
their AI offerings. We're also building
private rag and AI agents uh for
user-facing applications and we work
closely with an encrypted messaging
application uh to build uh content
moderation and spam filtering in a
privacy preserving
way. As the CTO of uh Microsoft Azure
said the future of the cloud and the
future of computing is going to be
confidential. So if you're interested in
uh deploying confidential AI inside your
enterprise, we're interested in finding
design partners uh across uh several
verticals in the biotech space, finance
or healthcare. So come talk to us. We
have a booth um and really looking
forward to talking with you all. Thank
you.
Thank you Sasha.