It is my honor and pleasure to introduce
our second keynote speaker, Jimmy
Olahir. Jimmy is an entrepreneur, an
adviser, an advocate for uh cickle cell
disease. He's also a father, um a
mountaineer who has climb climbed
Kilamanjaro. He also happens to be a
cast jevy recipient. Um, it was
participation in this groundbreaking
clinical trial that led to his staunch
interest in cell and gene therapies and
it has also led to a career in
advocating for accessibility to these
therapies regardless of your zip code.
Um, Jimmy, we are so honored that you're
here to share your story with the broad
audience and welcome to the ladders to
cures community. Jimmy, everyone, thank
you.
Thank you for having me. Um, I don't
have slides, so this morning we're going
to have to rely on our imagination like
we did when we were kids. Can you guys
hear me? Is my mic on? All right, good.
All right, so first I want to start with
my diagnosis story, how I was diagnosed
with uh cle cell disease. Um, as you can
tell, maybe not. My last name is of
Nigerian heritage. Um, back in 1985,
um, when I was conceived, my mom didn't
have access to something as simple as
newborn screening. Um, I like to call
myself the most fortunate person with
cle cell disease. Um, fortunately for
me, my parents were able to fly to the
US, get that prenatal screening done. It
confirmed I would have cle cell disease.
Uh so they decided to give birth to me
here in the US which is probably one of
the reasons I'm standing in front of you
here
today because the type of cle cell
disease I had was SS. It was severe. Um
people with cle cell disease that I have
from where I'm from they die at the age
of five most likely after a stroke
because they don't know they have cle
cell disease. So to be here and you know
get that simple test in Washington DC um
really preserved my life. So we went
back to Nigeria. Um I grew up there as a
toddler and um I remember the first time
I actually knew personally when I had
cle cell disease was um I'm a big fan of
football. You guys call it soccer here.
I don't know why. you know, we're using
our foot to actually kick a ball and
football you're throwing with your
hands. So, that confuses me. Um, we can
go on all day about that. Uh, and I am
playing football with a group of friends
in school and I noticed every 20 five
minutes actually, I'm lying. Every five
minutes I had to stop, catch my breath,
ask for a drink of water and then I'll
go back in the game. Five minutes, same
thing again. Stop. Need water.
Breathing. Can't catch my breath. And it
got bad. I I became that proverbial kid
that you're standing at. People are
picking teammates. And I never got
picked. And I I was fed up with it. So I
went home that day and I called to my
mom. I'm like, "Mom, I don't understand
why I can't run like everyone else. I
can't play football. I need to drink
water. I need to stop. I need to catch
my breath." And as mothers do, she told
me I have this disease, but she laid it
out in such a simple fashion that she
actually unprepared me for the harshness
of the disease. Um because that's what
mother is. They want to protect us. So
like, you have this disease. It's not
bad. You're going to be fine.
Everything's okay. Life is going to be
good. And um unfortunately, that's not
what happened. Um as I continue to get
older, that disease compounds on itself
is the way cell disease is. And I'm not
going to go into the mutation in a room
full of scientists. You probably know
more about it than I do um as to why
what it's already it's basically a
mutation um to protect you from malaria
if you live in those regions of the
worlds that um high have high prevalence
of
malaria
and it got worse. Um I I've been
fortunate to experience cle cell disease
in a low resource setting and in in the
west and I remember dealing with my
crisises which is the hallmark of the
disease is pain but it's not the only
disease it's not the only symptom of the
disease you know there are multiple uh
manifestations of the disease on your
body it's but the pain side of it um
growing up in Nigeria was extremely
difficult um I mean it's disable
anywhere I I didn't have access to the
things I eventually had access to here
in the west. Um, so I remember having
those pain crisises and all we had, you
know, to alleviate that was a
paracetamol and a menthol rub and my
parents would just go at it alternating
through all hours of the night massaging
my back until eventually the pain became
so torturous that I would pass out from
it, you you know, and I I remember
waking up the next morning. I don't know
if you guys remember that song,
Sunglasses and Advil. Last night was mad
real. That was my life growing up in
Nigeria. Um I was just in shock as to
the night we had just had as a family,
you know, with two sisters that were
sleeping, three sisters rather, and
didn't know what was going on in mom and
dad's room. how you know crazy and
visceral my both my parents were trying
to alleviate this pain that sometimes is
quite
indescribable. Uh and then you know at
some point they were like listen you're
born in the US why don't we have at
least you move there and see if this can
help um you know slow down the
progression of this disease or just make
it a little bit more bearable more to
manage. And so I I ended up moving back
to the US. I I live with my aunt and
I'll never forget my first uh I I got uh
connected to my hematologist. I was
living in New Jersey at the time. It was
Robert Wood Johnson and um we had like a
support group and the hematologist and
the whole support staff basically gave
me the layown of what happens here in
the US if I have a crisis like all right
so what's going to happen if you get
this pain just dial 911 you know
someone's going to come pick you up
we'll take you they'll bring you to the
ER and you know we'll work on you from
then and they even went to they even
went to into some other things that I've
been facing in Nigeria that I thought I
was crazy. I used to do this thing where
I would eat chalk after school. I would
run to the chalkboard and steal chalk
from the teachers thing, eat it. I'll
eat foam. I had like a couch in my house
that I had completely destroyed cuz I
was eating foam. And I thought I was a
kid that was just going crazy. And I
never expressed this to
anyone. And in this support group,
someone came up with that same issue. I
eat chalk. I eat foam. I find myself
eating toothpick. All these great
things. And the hematologist said it's
something called pah, you know, where
your body is severely lacking nutrients
that you are pushed to start eating
weird things to make up for that lack of
nutrients. And I was just like, oh my
god. You know, when I lived in Nigeria,
I thought I was crazy. And here in the
US, turns out that is actually a
diagnosed disease. So, you know, I was
happy to be here that, hey, listen, you
know, this is going to help. The fact
that we've solved one issue that I
thought I was just mental that is
actually a thing, a side effect of cle
cell disease.
So, fast forward to my first crisis in
the US. Um, I was in the basement. Um,
basically lived like Harry Potter, but
that's another story. Um, I was in the
my basement room and I I called 911 and
um 7 minutes, 10 minutes tops, they were
down there. Um, I was in the back of an
emergency room and before you knew it, I
was, you know, looking at the bright
lights of an emergency room and a doctor
came in and infused me with like
morphine. And 5 minutes later, I was in
no pain whatsoever. And I was just in
shock as to how different these two
health care systems are. Um, just
because of where I'm born, the simple
things that have made my life easier, at
least I thought so far compared to where
I come from. And you know, I felt better
at the time and I thought my disease
would be controlled. Um, but cle cell is
quite resilient and it gets worse as you
get older. You have school, you have
different stressors and for me that
exactly happened. I was living in New
Jersey at the time. The weather was
cold. So that compounded to the disease
and everything um went pear-shaped.
Everything started to fall apart. Uh I
couldn't finish school. Every semester I
had to withdraw. Uh I would get sick
constantly non-stop. I I lived um they
had a bed reserved for me in the
hospital. That's how bad it was.
uh and you know everything came to a
head for me when I had gone through a uh
many times I'd come close to losing my
life but this particular one um it was a
simple porticath
insertion and what's standard of care
with cle cell disease is when you have a
surgery no matter how minor you need a
blood transfusion because you're going
to lose blood your blood counts are
going to drop um but the surgeon he and
I had he and my wife I should say not me
I was I I never advocated for myself and
you know that's one of the things I'm
lucky for. I had very good advocates in
my life partner and my parents but we
were advocating for this blood
transfusion and he was he got so upset.
He's like you don't tell me how to run
my O. I'm putting this port in and
you're going home. So we're like all
right. So we do the port and on my way
it was you know outpatient surgery. On
my way home, I suffered a cardiac arrest
and my wife actually had to pull over on
the side of the road and they another
emergency uh ambulance came and they
took me back this time to a different
hospital where um I was in there for
probably about in the ICU for about 2
weeks and and you know that's where
things really got bad and I I realized
probably there's no surviving this
disease. Um, you know, my mental health
had really gone down the drain and I had
basically giving up. Uh, you know, I had
no interest in wanting to be alive. I
remember actually I had like a bad blood
transfusion once and um I I I had a coma
uh for 24 hours from that blood
transfusion and I when I woke up I was
so disappointed that I woke up that I
was that's how bad my life my mental
health everything had gone that I I was
upset from waking up from a coma. Um so
a after that um tragic uh crisis uh my
parents were really worried um obviously
and they started pushing that I go for a
bone marrow transplant and I have three
sisters so my my three sisters they were
living in the UK at the time they they
came over and we did a be a match test
making sure like I have three sisters
one of them is definitely going to be a
match and as sisters do they disappoint
you all of them none of them were a
match
I I still love them. Uh which at the
time was quite disappointing but you
know in hindsight turned out to be a
good thing because that was one of the
eligibility criteria for a gene therapy
clinical
trial. Uh but at the time still I I
really wasn't really interested in doing
anything. I was just done with living if
I'm honest and but as parents still like
I said they kept on pushing pushing
pushing and you know I was quite tired
of it. you know, I'm like, you know, I'm
going to do this research just to get
you off my back, you know, in an attempt
to pacify you. I'm going to research I
think I've cle cell disease is a genetic
disease and I've seen these things. I
I'm not sure what it is, but I've heard
of something called gene therapy. Maybe
20, 30 years from now, if I'm still
here, this can potentially help and you
know, you guys can leave me alone. So, I
had done this research and I I did a
simple Google alert and that was it. if
anything comes up with cle cell disease
and gene therapy in the content, I'll
get that alert in my inbox. And I had
done that research and six months after
I had done that research, I got an NPR
article in my inbox about a woman named
Victoria Gray who was the first person
to go through a crisper-based gene
therapy um to alleviate the symptoms of
her cle cell disease. I can't say cure
cuz people get upset. We're not sure
yeah if it's a cure. So I use alleviate
instead. Um and
um at the end of that article they had
the contact information of the principal
investigator for that clinical trial.
This was in 2019. Uh so I reached out
and the next day to my shock he reached
back out. Um which was quite special
because with cle cell disease it it
almost felt like I like to call it the
back of the bus disease. you're never
really number one. Um, no one really
cares. Um, which is not the case now.
Um, but back then, so the fact that this
principal investigator called me back
the next day, I was like, whoa, they're
actually interested in helping, you
know. So, I was quite shocked and
excited and my wife and I had this um he
left a a phone call actually. He left a
voicemail. We we like to call the the
perfect phone call, which we don't have
anymore, unfortunately. And in that
phone call, he basically said, "This
could be something that you could
qualify for. I'd like to talk to you."
And they did everything they could. This
was in 2019. Um, also, mind you, for 7
years, I had my wife and I had tried to
become parents and I'd been unsuccessful
in that regard. One of the reasons why
is because I was on a therapy called
hydroxyhea which um supposed to help
with cle cell disease in the um
expression of HBF um but very
inconsistent works with some people
doesn't work. So for me um as an
immature kid it didn't work and as adult
um I'm not sure if it worked. But anyway
I was on that and that had caused um you
know was one of the reasons why we
couldn't have children. But at this time
in 2019, my wife was actually 8 months
pregnant. Um because we had gone through
a round of IVF and that had become
successful. So my mindset was completely
different from where I was a few years
before where I didn't want to live to I
desperately need to need to be here. I
didn't want to pass the burden of
caregiving um to my children. I didn't
want to have my wife be the only one to
take care of our son. And I just kept on
having this picture of me in in the room
with the violent cle cell crisis and the
baby crying next door and not being able
to do anything. And so my mindset had
switched really quickly to desperately
wanting to be alive, which is such a
strange feeling for me from desperately
not wanting to be alive. Uh so I was
desperate for this clinical trial. Uh I
wanted I wanted to qualify. Uh they I
remember Vert.Ex text like sending that
big consent form or and it was massive
and I didn't even read it. I was just
like, "Where do I sign?" And they like,
"No, slow down. That's not how you do
this. You have to read before you sign."
And we read through it and I saw all
these, at least to my wife, all these
scary things of offtarget editing
potential for cancer. And I'm like, I I
don't care, you know, one, two, three
years, if this works, you know, is worth
it. If I live 3 years from this, even
one year, and I get hit by a bus the
next day, it's been it's been so worth
it that uh I don't mind going through
any of this to potentially get any of
this side effects because I I had unlike
Victoria, people try to call me brave
and maybe to an extent I am, but unlike
Victoria, she went into this with no
light at the end of the tunnel. No, she
was patient number one. So, she's
actually the definition of brave. Uh,
but I had the good fortune of looking at
her data and the other patients before
me and I I I had a feeling that this
could potentially work. So, I was all
in. Um, so I got
the good news. Uh, we we traveled to
Nashville. This was in 2019. We traveled
to Nashville in November where the which
was the study site and we went through a
series of tests where you have to be
sick enough but at the same time healthy
enough to go through the you know rigors
of a clinical trial which fortunately I
passed and in January of 2020 I began my
journey at the time I think it was
called CTX 101 uh in in the clinical
trial setting I I started that journey I
started off as uh patient number 16. Uh,
and at this time, my family and I, my
wife and I in particular, we've moved
down from New Jersey to the Atlanta
metro area in an attempt to just improve
my quality of life. Um, we were thinking
that living in a state that has a warmer
climate would make my cle cell disease a
lot better, which a little I think it
worked a little bit, but still, like I
said, you know, cle cell disease is
still going to do what cle cell disease
does. Um so at this time we're living in
the southeast and the clinical trial was
in Nashville which is also in the
southeast and as you all know 2020 uh
pandemic hit uh so when we started in I
think we started like literally January
2nd I had to report to Nashville and in
March they had to close down the
clinical trial um because of the
pandemic. Um, I started off as patient
number six, but because I 16 I should
say, uh, but because I lived in the
southeast, uh, they opened back the
trial and the principal investigator
reached out to me and told me, "Listen,
if you would like to continue, you could
drive. You know, all my other patients
that live in coastal cities or middle
America that can't fly anymore, they are
going to have to wait, but you you're 4
hours away. If you want to continue,
we're more than happy to continue." So
because of that, I actually got elevated
from patient number 16 to patient number
four. Um, which was um unreal. It was
kind of a weird thing, you know, looking
at that ticker at the bottom of the TV
and seeing people the the count people
losing their lives every day and here I
am getting the opportunity to save my
life. Um, you know, it was very very
strange. So, I continue with the
clinical trial and um I like telling
this part of the story because I've
gotten feedback that scientists actually
love hearing what the clinical
manifestation of a clinical trial looks
like. Um so, it is four steps. Um the
first step is something they call for
cle cell disease at least is something
they call keeping you on ice. Uh what
they mean by that is they basically
giving you red cell exchanges, blood
cell transfusions, making sure that
you're healthy. And then the second step
is uh the collection phase um where you
get collected. Um in my case you you get
woken up in the morning and you you
think the nurse is bringing you like
coffee or something but she's bringing
prolax and you get that shot and what
that does is it stimulates the um you
all know this the stem cells into the
blood cells and then it's collected for
eight hours. you sit sit next to an
ephreesis machine and it just sucks
blood and separates the stem cells but
in that process you lose a lot of blood
too. So uh at the end of every
collection I I needed a blood
transfusion. Uh for me I had to get
collected four times which was very
unusual. Um we really don't know why. Um
that's one of the biggest um
disappointments in the lack of clinical
trial diversity that why things happen
and and we don't know why. They're just
not many men that look like me enrolled
in clinical trials to figure out why
some of us have to get collected four
times someone once. Um so we need to do
more work there. And after the
collection process you go through the
conditioning phase which of course you
all know well. Um, for me, I think the
collection and the conditioning were
probably the most difficult part. Um,
I'd never had chemotherapy before. Um,
but you know, you see it on TV, you've
seen people that have cancer, and I was
under the impression that, you know,
once you get infused, I it was built for
about 5 days. Once you get infused with
that uh chemotherapy that you feel the
symptoms instantly um but that's not how
it works as you all know it probably
takes about two weeks and I was in the
mindset that I had somehow escaped the
symptoms of chemotherapy and they kept
on telling me no Jimmy that's not
possible I'm like it is it's been 5 days
I don't feel anything I've been working
out I'm on this bike I'm the best
clinical trial patient ever all that
stuff and Dr. Franco who was the P just
kept on laughing. Oh man. So I went into
when the symptoms finally came it was
kind of really sad because I I I thought
I had kind of mindseted my way positive
mindset out of my way out of um
chemotherapy symptoms which was not the
case. It eventually came and it was it
hit me like a train. Um I think the
hardest thing was the mouth sores. You
you really don't understand how
debilitating mouth sores can be. Like
there's no amount of explanation I can
give you that you to tell you how
painful it is unless you just go through
it yourself. You know that's how bad it
is. And after that conditioning the
final stage is the infusion which was um
extremely antilimactic. Um, I literally
saw them take bags of stem cell, red
stem cell bloods out of me for like two
months and the carrier will be right
there before the collection was ended
and shipping it with all this urgency.
And at the end of the day, they come
back with like three clear syringes. I'm
like, that's it. Uh, and that was it. It
was just three clear syringes and the
smell of canned corn, which apparently
is preservatives. Um, and you know, you
get infused with with that. And for me,
and it's going to be different for
everybody, I think it was about
probably 7 days, maybe two weeks max,
that um, with my cle cell disease, I've
always had this lingering pain um that I
couldn't escape even with pain
medication. And I noticed that pain
slowly start to dissipate. And um I was
in a really really weird place because I
was expecting to be excited, happy that
you know for me this is the beginning of
the end of cle cell disease but I was
actually kind of lost and worried um
because I'd lived with cle cell disease
for 35 years to finally disengage from
the disease. I I really didn't know who
I was meant to be or how I was meant to
move on. My my my wife when we got
married literally told me your one job
in life was to not die. So I had no life
skills except for not dying.
Um so um and for so long I had used pain
as a way to motivate myself. Um you know
I'm going to do this as well as you can
and I'm going to do with pain was my
mindset. I had like a quote on my desk
that said never waste your pain and now
I had no more pain. So, I went through a
serious identity crisis that uh and uh a
really bad um survivor's guilt. Um this
came after um when I realized that after
I'd come public with my story that these
gene therapies cost $2.3 to $3 million.
And I'd gone public with my story
talking about how great it could
potentially be physically, at least how
great it's been for me, not knowing that
the bulk of the population is not going
to have access to it anytime soon. Uh,
and it was it was tragic to to even when
the approval came in 2023, um, to know
that we now have a bonafide gene therapy
too actually for cle cell disease. And
the patient population in dire need of
these therapies are not all of them are
many of them are going to die without
having this therapy. And um that's when
I really dedicated myself to you know
doing everything I can in my power um my
very limited power to try and make sure
these therapies eventually um get to the
patient populations that are in dire
need of it. I mean cle cell disease is
the rarest the most populous rarest
disease in the world. 100,000 Americans
suffer from it. Um 4 million people in
subsaran Africa 100,000 babies are born
a year. 12 million
globally
and 35 maybe more than that 50 people
worldwide have received a gene therapy
for cle cell disease. Um it's the the
numbers are just staggering. Um and so
when uh a gentleman called Luke
Timberman reached out to me, hey, we're
doing this campaign um with a company
called Sickle Forward to raise money to
purchase uh to acquire basics like
newborn screening, hydroxyera, newborn
screening obviously very pivotal in my
survival. You know, I jumped at the
chance. Um, you know, there was a bit of
uproar in the community that what is
this kid that still has cickle cell
disease going to do in Kilanjaro when we
both know that he's still going to
sickle. Um, and he's not supposed to be
over 10,000 foot in altitude. Um, but to
be fair, the goal you the the organizers
that told me that the goal for me wasn't
actually to summit Kilimanjaro is just
to be there and advocate. Um, so I
jumped at the chance. anything I could
do um to make sure that we can get more
people eventually when these gene
therapies eventually proliferate you
know alive and with a somewhat healthy
quality of life the only way to do that
is one making sure that they know they
have cle cell disease and two you know
when they are have you know early
intervention with with hydroxyheeria so
I was excited to do it and to be fair
I'd already been you know for the first
time I finally had full control of my
And I'd already been um physically in in
in good physical shape that I thought I
could do it. There's this Stoic quote
that I like. It's it's better to be a
warrior in the garden than a garden in a
war. And I'd been doing that my whole
life. So I'd like, oh, absolutely. This
is a challenge I can take on. So, you
know, we started training for Kilanjyro
all summer of last year. I did all the
peaks on the eastern seabboard in North
Carolina. And then eventually we went to
Colorado to do um some high altitude
training. um we got to 14,000 and I
think that's when my teammates and I
started um realizing there's a potential
that this kid could actually summit
Kilamanjaro you know and I'm sure most
of you know that um the gene therapy I
went through castvi doesn't um attack
the cle cell mutation it goes for bcl1a
silences it and then you produce uh
hemoglobin F which we all used to
produce in uterero and with the
production of HBF apparently it has a
better affinity for oxygen. And I
actually saw that on in Colorado before
we were gotten to to to to Kilara when
my some of my teammates were exhausted
and h having a high autism and I the one
with diagnosed cle cell disease I was
still able to continue going. I'm like
oh wow maybe I am cheating here with
HBF and um you know it's a good thing.
So so we get to Kilanjaro and um it was
extremely hard. We couldn't have made it
without the porters. I see my teammate
here, Doug, who we summitted Kilanjaro
together. We shared a car from Arouchia
to Kilanjaro and we've become good
friends today. Um, and it was extremely
difficult. Um, but like I said, I had
been training. The physical part of it
for me, um, I think living with cle cell
disease, I I knew I could handle the
physicality of the climb. It was, um,
the altitude that we were kind of weary
of. And beforehand I had done some tests
with my friend Patrick Hines who um runs
a company called Functional Fluidics
where they test red blood cell health.
So they had induced hypoxia into my red
blood cells and they saw that there is a
chance I mean there absolutely
effectively I have the cle cell trait.
So for sure in extreme situations I
would sickle. And when we got to 15,000
ft, I remember that morning I went and I
peed and I noticed for the first time in
like 5 years my pee was brown. But I
didn't really bring it up to anybody.
I'm like, "Of course my pee is going to
be brown. I'm I'm doing something
extremely hard." And then it wasn't
until like lunchtime in the tent,
Patrick ran to me and like, "Jimmy,
you're jaundice. I don't know if you've
noticed." Um, and that's when I like,
"Oh, well, maybe this is actually
serious." So they decided to put me on
oxygen prophylactively for the rest of
the hike which was disappointing. I had
this oxygen tank on the whole time while
I was you know um summit in Kilamanjaro.
Uh but with the oxygen helped um there
were no other adverse effects. I every
night, you know, when we would go to bed
in our tents, I was just making that
mental decision. You know, if this is
actually something that's dangerous, if
you start to feel like a true crisis,
you know, you have to make sure that
you're honest with yourself and you
start to
descend. And if you if you if your eyes
are just yellow, if it's just ja, I'm
going to continue. So, I made that
decision. I was going to continue unless
I started feeling something different
physically. And thankfully, I didn't
feel anything different physically. I
felt tired, exhausted like anyone but
nothing like what cle cell disease used
to be like. Um and then you know um
summit night we did it the whole team
all of us we did and like like I I think
for me I've really learned to detach
myself from outcomes because summiting
was antilimactic as well. Um while it
was a personal goal I really love the
journey the bond you build while you're
climbing the every day the grind one
step at a time. That was the the fun
part of it for me and um yeah it while
that was a personal achievement um in
being the first person with cle cell
disease to summit Kilimanjaro I think
the important thing was the trip um we
were able to raise $1.2 $2 million and
we got the goal of getting newborn
screening and hydroxyeria to a patient
population that's in desperate need of
cle cell. They don't have access to the
basics. Um and what we find out what we
found out while we were in Kilamanjaro
some of them don't even know what cle
cell disease is in the metro cities in
countries across Africa they they might
know but in in in the villages in the
farms people there don't know what cle
cell disease is. So this was uh to be
able to achieve this and bring some
education uh to these populations and
you know take a very small step into
preserving their quality of life till
eventually gene therapy becomes
accessible um was was huge aside from
the personal achievement. Uh and you
know it's been it's been great ever
since um in terms of continuing to do
the advocacy work.
Um my goal is really just making sure
that these therapies um as an advocate
one day get get to the patient
populations that are in need of it. Um
one of the things that I think um Dr.
Weissman talked about it and we're
seeing a lot as well in cle cell disease
come up is a lot of clinical trials with
invivo um gene therapies focusing on
LMPS lipid lipid nanopaticals to to
eventually get these therapies to to
patients that desperately need them. But
also we have to, you know, as a patient,
I'm not going to sit here and um
pontificate because I have no idea, but
we have to work on these um IP issues. I
have no idea why an IP cost five to six
to seven to tens of millions of dollars.
But you know, when I put my patient hat
on, I see that as a barrier to getting
patients to the other side of a chronic
illness. Um so while I'm here at the
broad where you know most of these
research comes from I really want to
encourage while you're working on this
science the research that I know I
should have had some slides that could
have hit home a bit more but just um
think of patients like me um that would
not be here if it wasn't for gene
therapy and how many are not going to be
here and how many you could potentially
save if the work that you're doing can
get to them you know so I just wanted to
leave you guys with that message. Thank
you, Jimmy. Thank you. Uh I know I speak
for all of us when I say thank you for
your advocacy and also for sharing your
story today.