e
okay I think we could probably get
started with the sort of formalities
um so welcome to Nano Explorations today
um before I introduce today's speaker
just a couple of words about sort of
the uh housekeeping items um please hold
your questions to the end of the session
that will be a Q&A session and to ask
question you can do this three ways you
can use the Q&A you can use the chat or
you can simply raise your hand and we'll
keep track of the ones that raise their
hands and make sure you get a chance to
actually speak up and with your
question so today's speaker is ziling
Chen who is a go by the name of
Zach I'm fortunate that my name is Claus
Jensen and I'm Jin in chemical
engineering Material Science and I'm
been fortunate to be the mentor of Zach
here at MIT uh Zach did his uh
Bachelor's in chemistry at Cornell and
then went from there to uh
Berkeley uh where he worked with
Professor Omar yagi and you will see
much of the work that he did for his PhD
in his talk today on atmospheric
harvesting with nanoscale metal organic
Frameworks um Zak is a excellent
presenter he has had opportunity to
present at m at many different
um small small and large
venues ACS meetings mrss meetings and so
on um and as also at universities um and
he's really uh in what you will hear
today is is really on using large
language models uh to help research in
um metal organic Frameworks but he's
also used this while he's been a postet
MIT to do completely different work on
um new ways to come up with reactions
for uh electrochemical reactions for
oxidation
reactions so um I don't want to take any
more of Zach's time uh I think we can
turn it over to Zach it's about 1105 so
we can start so um with that Zack if
you're ready yes okay so thank you CLA
so much for the nice introduction so
good morning everyone so my name is Zach
and today so you know know as CL this
discuss so you know I had my PhD in uh
UC Berkeley uh for you know experimental
work in the moth and later you know I
transition into you know combining both
Ai and moth you know for the material
Discovery and now at MIT I'm doing the
larg input model for the uh chemical
reaction uh designing and optimization
so today you know for the topic of this
talk so I will be mainly focus on the
you know like the work I have done in my
uh PhD which is mainly focused on the
experimental side and that is on the
topic of you know uh trying to study how
quizine materials can actually be
engineered at Atomic level to address
the global challenges such as the water
shortage so to begin my talk I want to
first uh starways you know like some of
the backgrounds here and so particularly
you know in terms of topic of the global
water shortage as I mentioned so in fact
nowadays uh nearly half of the world's
population lives in a place where you
know clean and drinkable water is not
accessible year around so if you you
know look at this uh figure so actually
the this number is ised to grow about
five billions in the next few decades as
you know predicted by the you report so
why is that so as you can see so in this
figure so the main reason of you know
this kind of growing you know population
in terms of water shortage is that there
is uneven distribution of the Water
Resource across different location at
the different times of year so while
some places you know receive plenty of
the precipitation during the winter time
so the Water Resource may be quite
Limited in the summer and you know there
are some geological difference in terms
of making some region make the necessary
infrastructure to deliver drinkable
water so finding a way to assess water
at any place at any you know time of a
year is very important to adjust you
know this situation and fight against
the water
shortage so one proposed solution here
is that you know we can actually harvest
the moisture directly from the air so in
fact the amount of water contained in
the air is actually six times larger
than the volume of the sun of all the
rivers on our planet so that's a huge
amount actually however making this you
know water exraction process directly
from the air actually you know um can be
energy consuming and sometimes you know
making it like a energy efficient way to
get this drinkable water is actually a
big challenge so in recent years so it
was you know increasingly uh uh study
that you know using sance as a way to
assist you know the condensation of the
water fly air uh can be a very feasible
solution and you know this technology
which is called you know Soban assist
atmosphere first world har thing has G
increasing attention so among all of
these you know commercial Sant or the
problem that is being studied in the lab
actually metal organic Frameworks have
shown great promise you know for this
application so now the question you know
you may ask is that what is metal
organic Frameworks which is prev as moth
and how do this you know moth you know
capture water so essentially you can
think of you know this Mo material as
like a logo set where you know you have
different bricks of various shape and
sizes so in this case so you can
customize you know this material
materials at Atomic level by precisely
tuning the types of metal and the
organic molecules to change both their
physical and chemical properties for
instance with this you know mo C3 uh
which you know uh has this luminum you
know building blocks as well as this
organic Linker which is uh parazol 35 di
carboxilate so you can actually create a
very hydrophilic Pro environment you
know in its cavities by using this par
Linker which has two nitrogen which is
shown in the green here uh to make it
very you know attractive to the water
molecules so in this case you know a
typical proc size is about one nomer and
as you can see this periodic exan
structure uh can make it into you know
the narrow scale particles or even
sometimes grow into the much larger
single crystals and you can essentially
Sy of you know this you know M materials
as a very tiny crystaline sponge and you
know you will just chart water based on
its microscopic structures so since this
is a very highly crystaline structure we
can actually use the single Crystal X3
defraction to precisely show to see that
how it interact with the uh water
molecules which is traveling inside its
you know cavities so in this case so
here I'm showing you like a 3D structure
of the M ser3 as you can see here so
this is a highly Pros materials with a
very large internal surface area and the
fre volumes so when we zoom into this
specific channel so you can see that you
know as in the videoos play so you you
can exactly learn from the single
Crystal X3 that where the exact position
of this water molecule emerg and it's
actually attracted by the uh the uh the
hydrophilic nitrogen atoms and then so
once you get these four four first you
know water cluster so they will just
accumulate by attracting more so at the
end of day you know than to this large
pole volume so it can store a
significant amount of water inside its
cavities under the ambient
conditions so in fact you know uh this
motivates us to actually you know
incorporate this material as a sent to
the device and it it has successfully
been test in the moav desert back on
2019 to harvest water from the dry
Desert Air however at that moment a few
challenges remind to further expand
application of what water harvesting
with Ms first of all the synthesis of
the MS remind to be low yield and could
only be made in the milligram scales
which I will talk more later second so
it will be ideal if we can uh have the
solent to be adapt into different
environmental conditions for instance
like to answer question of how can we
make land to be even you know to take
more water or even make them to be
energy efficient when dissolving the
water molecules so the so you know so
which means that the so LM M the
designing principle for the water
harvesting MTH should be developed for
the tailor
properties so you know let's start with
the first challenge which is the
scalability in a typical M ser3
synthesis so typically you know as you
can see in this you know panel on the
right so like a 4 M uh culation V is
used to produce just a few milligrams of
Ms under the solo thermal conditions
which you know involves in mixing the
starting materials like aluminum
chloride and the pgdc Linker and
incubating them in an oven it may sound
surprising but it's actually true that
how much Mo you can actually make per
batch depends on the size of the oven so
typically you know the larger oven you
have like the more space you know you
can put with even like a larger jar
however you know even with this you know
like large you know 2 lit jar as I show
you here or even like if you go to about
like 10 lit so you will only get about 3
to five grams of Mo each time because
the reation yield is so low under this
Soo thermos synthesis and what is even
worse is that it takes about 24 hours to
complete the entire formation of the
microcrystalline powders so if you were
to shorten this reaction time so you
will actually end up with the more
aerous product with much less water
uptate capacity so in this case you know
the SpaceTime yield for this you know
Mor production under the soo Theros
synthesis is pretty low and if you
remember the device photo I show you in
the previous slide you know which is
this one so actually for this device
that was test back on 2019 so it
contains about 1 kilogram of M sent
about half a kilo to 1 kilogram of mbant
now you know simply just doing the mess
so I told you you know 4 the2 lit gel so
you have about four grams of moth and
now for just one device you need about
you know like one k that means you need
to repeat this you know dry and gel for
about like 300 times considering that
you know you uh you retra you you you
expect ideally have most of you know the
product recover after the purification
so which you know in this case is very
resource and label intensive and
preventing you know the further you know
uh deployment of this device you know in
a larger scale so now you know when I
began my you know uh PhD uh study so my
first research project was focused on
developing a high yield and scalable
method to overcome this traditional
limitation of the solo Theros synthesis
for the water harvesting Ms also you
know since the py me requires the use of
DMF you know which I show in the red
here so this is essentially the
abbreviation of the uh solvent dial
format which is uh you know many of you
if you are coming from a chemistry
background know that it's a very toxic
solvant so you know no one will actually
want to drink water uh Harvest from like
like a compound that is made of the
toxic solvant you know even though you
know you can uh uh convince people that
you know you have already use enough
washing to remove this one however you
know this still a challenge so I was you
know actually interesting in you know
replacing it with a more Beni solvent
you know such as you know water so which
can make uh which you know to make it to
be a green synthesis so essentially you
know uh towards this end so I actually
uh threw off some you know re
optimization and some you know like
Trail and arrow so I discovered that you
know by using the right story atric
amount of the in organic base and in
this case which is the sodium hydroxide
so the reaction could actually be done
using a conventional heating you know
with just constant Sterling in like a
oil base so essentially you know you can
just run this in like a organic
chemistry uh way like in a one port or
uh one port one button flux synthesis
and you know have having it to stir at
the reflux temperature of the water
which is 100° uh and now you know
exciting news is that so with this
better heat transfer and the constant
reagent mixing uh you know with this
conventional heating method so the time
required for the M crystallization is
greatly reduced and the product can be
actually made just within two hours
compared with you know the previous MTH
which will take you know like 15 hours
or even a day to uh
finish so now once we will be able to
show we can find alter alternative
method to make this compound so I was
actually be able to confirm that the
crystalinity of the product synthesized
by this Greener measure uh you know can
have the you know exactly the retention
of the same performance as you know the
traditional method so I was able to you
know run the PO X3 defraction and the
procity measurement to confirm this one
so as you can see on the uh on the
bottom left so which is the result of
the part XP defraction so you can see
basically you know in terms of the the
ph and the uh and the intensity of this
Pak so basically the traditional method
and the new meth uh pretty much you know
have the exact same you know pattern and
agree with each other and on the other
side you know if you do the BET surface
um bet surface area measurement you will
find that you know they essentially
retain the same procy meaning that you
know we are not doing any kind of
compromise by replacing you know like EX
in DMF with the new you know Greener me
and essentially they can achieve very
similar water
uptake so now you know uh encouraged by
the results from the you know the reflex
synthesis that is condu at the Grand uh
scale so I next move to the pilot scale
synthesis of Mo 33 by building up you
know by hand a 200 lit reator you know
in the lab so as I mentioned previously
so the traditional s server synthesis is
limited by the size of the reaction vers
and you know like the space you have in
the oven yet for this you know reflux
method you can almost you know have no
registration in terms of the synthesis
scale and you know but just which will
only depends on you know how large you
know the reator you want to build so
what was even more exciting is that so I
found this method can actually be
transferable to a lot of other aluminum
based Ms which can also be used for
outward harvesting so not just limiting
you know to the m 33 so in this case I
was be able to synthesize a whole series
of mod such as Calon D3 mu 160 aluminum
fery and so on and actually was be able
to produce them at at all kilogram
scales with over 90% of you as well so
as you can see on this you know
photographs on the bottom right corner
so up to about six different kinds of
moth were made by in high quality and in
a kilogram scale with this green M and
the calculate SpaceTime U is about a 100
times larger than a traditional s ccle
synthesis of the mths so so far I have
been showing you that you know how we
adjust the challenge of the scalability
and now you know we are moving to the
next challenge which is you know how to
answer the question on you like how we
can better design of the moth to you
know tailor for different environmental
conditions which you know by taking the
advantage of their
tunability so in this case uh we
introduce a mix Linker uh structure
which you know combining uh Hydro pH par
Linker which you show in in the previous
slide which is the Linker we use for the
M 33 and this is now abbreviate as
letter P with another you know
hydrophobic cyop Linker now abbreviate
as letter t uh uh to make this moth so
together so we can form like a series of
you know different moth structures by
you know having different input ratio of
these two linkers so you know to
understand this structural property
relationship of this you know new class
of the mixed Linker Ms so we first exam
that using the powder X3 defraction and
the SCM EDS so in both case so these
techniques show that you know those two
linkers were actually homogeneously
incorporate into one single phas rather
than forming like a mixture of just two
moths you know from Two linkers and in
this case you know for example you if
you look at the result from the Eds
images and if you look at this green
roll which is you know showing the uh
nitrogen percentage for you know each
you know uh composition so actually you
know you can see like the percentage
gradually you know uh decrease when you
move from PTA Z which you know you have
entire you have moth entirely made by
all the P Linker and when you are moving
to the uh pt0 a which is the mo that is
entirely made by the T Linker so there
is like a trend in the decrease and the
reverse Trend can be also see in terms
of the element software uh when when you
are moving in the same direction so this
is actually a result of you know the
similarity between the bond angle of two
Cabos linkers in both Paro and a cell
Linker so since they are very similar to
each other so we'll be able to
incorporate both of them within the same
framework rather than you know having
two separate framework function
together so in this case you know you
may ask you know why are we interesting
in incorporating both of them in the
same framework rather than just having
you know simply the fixed physical
mixture of two of them so the reason
behind this is that we want the precise
tuning of the structural composition
results in you know like different
properties in this case um so you know
um actually layer structure layer water
harvesting profile which you know in
terms of like how much water they can
take and and what humidity they start to
take water is actually influenced by
their you know uh internal composition
made by the Linker so in this case we'll
be able to show that you know by having
different composition of linker we can
actually fine tune the operation
humidity you know by by a very wide
range which is up to 20% using you know
different ratio of PN T Linker in the
synthesis so in this case uh we found
that the exact output composition ratio
in the framework is correlated with the
input ratio of the linkers we use during
the synthesis and in in some other case
you know let's say if you want to get uh
uh if you want to get sbin that is to be
applied in a more you know every region
which you know can be much drier so you
can actually have like more P Linker uh
to take place which can allow it to you
know Harvest water at early stage and
you know if you are actually want to you
know uh make a function at a less you
know every region so you can increase
the amount of the T Linker which will
you know uh decrease its oper which will
actually increase its operational uh
relative humity range but it will reduce
amount of energy and the requirement for
the uh dissol temperature it will take
for uh for the water to dissolve so in
this case um I was able to show that you
know we can actually control the
Regeneration temperature during the
temperature swing uh for the you know
like the M cycling so as you can see in
this you know bottom right panel so
depending on which structure you choose
so there is up to 14 degrees of
temperature difference in terms of you
know um dsorption temperature which
means that you know you can have like a
more energy efficient uh sent in terms
of specific condition so for instance
you know if you pick a composition with
a lower regeneration temperature for a
place where average relative humidity is
higher so you will actually reduce the
uh overall energy you will use during
the you know recycling of these
Ms so other than you know Shifting the
water isogen left and right which I
shown you in the previous slide uh by
you know tuning their composition so we
are also interested in make this water
abortion profile shift up and up and
down so which is controlling their water
capacity in this case by collaborating
with Professor from University of
Chicago and University of Minesota so we
can actually use the computational tools
to simulate the watertion profile for
different designs of moth and was able
to uh discover that you know if we can
actually insert a venal group you know
which is this CC double bond between the
heterocycle and the carate so we can
essentially retain the same topology and
you know like the connectivity between
the Linker and the metal as well as L
you know po geometry of the uh water
harvesting Ms while you know we also can
use this to make the Linker to be longer
which will essentially enhance their
paracity and the water soltion
uptake uh in this case you know uh so we
we actually move Beyond just the DFD
calculations and actually went to a lab
to synthesize this you know new linkers
since the calculation show that you know
they can have the retention of the same
geometry while increasing the water
uptake and you know convert these
synthesized molecules uh into the into a
moth by optimizing the synthesis
structure so on the right panel so you
will find the experimentally measured
isogen and isobar curves for uh for this
you know new Mo that we you know made in
the lab and where you know this Orange
Lines rep then the new moth with the
longer linkers which we call this one
long arm moths and those ones you know
as I shown you with the shorter Linker
we saw the insertion of the venal group
uh to be the original Mod which is shown
in the black lines so as you can see
clearly you know there is up to five 50%
of increase in terms of their water uh
harvesting uh properties uh and the
uptake also you know meaning that this
new compound can serve as a very
promising candidate for the next TR
generation of the waterhousing device by
having even lower dsorption you know
temperature and
energy so once we you know gain a lot of
you know knowledge and a designing
principle on both how to scale up the mo
and how to better Design This Mo for the
water harvesting application so we next
move to the next uh the final stage
which is building a device for the real
world application you know we just don't
we don't want just you know making them
off in the lab and just you know measure
their performance in the the lab scale
by rather we want to see if it can
actually you know translate into the
real world application uh by you know
setting up the proof concept device so
compar with the previous uh you know mo
water Harvester I show you earlier in
the slide which you know relies on the
use of solar p uh Power and electricity
you know to run this kind of
regeneration of the moth so in this case
uh our focus of this new generation uh
design is to answer the question of
whether or not we can have like a
portable device that can allow us to
just Harvest water without any human
intervention so that is essentially like
you know you have those kind of solar
panels on the top of a roof where you
know you can essentially think of you
know the analogy of this water
harvesting panel which you know you can
put on the top of your house and you
will just you know run it by itself and
then at the end of day you just collect
all this water so in this case so I want
to show you you know how our design you
know make this happen so first of all
you know during the nighttime so
actually you know the moth which is
placed in this you know moth chamber can
actually collat water from the air so
layer poles are actually very
hydrophilic enough so nothing need to be
done by just exposing it to the air and
it will just you know naturally get all
all of the water you know from the air
uh to be captured within its pole and
once it get saturated it will just
sitting there and waiting for the
sunlight to come in the daytime just
like a sponge so once it gets water so
the next the next job is to how to you
know we can get water out from these
solent so that's happening during the
daytime where you know the sunlight will
heat the mo band which cause it to you
know uh increase the temperature and
then you know dissolve the water so
since moth is a very highly quizzing and
periodic structure so the dsorption
requires much lower you know temperature
spring compared with the other sob and
can be down you know in a very short u
short time to evacuate all these water
molecules so in the end you know in this
way so you all get rid of the need for
the solar panels and electricity for the
dsorption but rather just rely on the
ambian sunlight to you know get water
out so at a fundamental
level uh the design of this device is
quite similar to like a a rotary
evaporator some of you if you are coming
from you know like a chemistry
background may maybe may may see this
design very you know familiar in this
case so you ually you are creating a
temperature you know gradient by hitting
one side and then just placing like a
condenser on the top to collect the
liquid so in order design you know the
way we collect the you know uh liquid is
that we put like a you know reflector
which you know can reduce the solar
ingredients on the top so the cooler
temperature will be achieved on the top
side while you know when the sun hit the
bottom so the water molecule will become
hotter and once they travel to this top
side so it just become uh condense and
you know uh turning into the droplet and
a drinkable water so now you know we
have you know this design of the moth uh
assemble and then so once we you know
test it on the laboratory environment so
we were actually very excited to you
know to find a place that we can you
know do the fu test to to to make sure
that you know it can actually you know
run under you know the actual real word
condition so in this case so we decide
to test it only Des Valley National Park
so many of you may have already known
that you know this place is very famous
for the hottest temperature on this
planet because you know in Califoria the
Sia Nevada just uh mountains just you
know uh hinder all this kind of moisture
from the uh Pacific Ocean and which
making you know the lowest position on
the North American which is des Val to
be you know one of the driest place on
this uh on on the North America so our
motivation behind this is that if we can
demonstrate that this device can Harvest
water even under such extreme uh
condition so that basically means that
you know this device has a potential to
be you know um to be uh to be
functioning in most you know other place
on this planet so for a typical you know
testing cycle so as you can see on these
you know like uh animations so we
typically start at about 700 p.m after
the sunset by you know setting up the
necessary sensors to collect the
environmental data and just leave there
without any human intervention for the
next 24 hours and in particular you know
as you can see in uh both two figures so
you know we have like laptop to just
monitor you know like the uh temperature
and the uh humidity level around the
device but in reality you know when you
are trying to run this device you don't
have to have this laptop you can just
have this you know device to sit in
there and then to harvest water and we
also you know decide two different place
to you know test our device um one is at
a central of the you know like the Death
Valley so if you go to the Death Valley
National Park so one of the M VY place
will be this you know Furnace Creek
which is known as the you know lowest
place on the uh North America and it's
usually famous for its very hot air
during the summer and we did it you know
in
2022 summer of 2022 which is you know
one of the historically hottest time
during the
um only that's very National Park and
the other side we also choose was only
uh e bound of the park which has a
slightly different landscape and the
environmental condition so and then so
you know we will actually so after
running you know the device at you know
two different location so we were
actually very excited to see that you
know this device works really well under
you know both uh condition and could
consistently produce water during the
daytime so as you can see from you know
this these two diagram from the right
which is the result from the sensors
which monitor the temperature and the
moisture so the moth bad which is you
know represented by this uh red curve
can heat up to uh about 100 degrees
Celsius uh during the day and which you
know uh create about like a 40 degrees
of the uh difference with this uh
temperature from the condenser as you
can see in this uh blue line so that
means that you know even under such you
know hot conditions this you know uh
temperature difference is huge in enough
to make sure you still be able to
condense drinkable water into the
droplets under such you know extreme
condition which is nearly you know
impossible with most of the other
Technologies thinking about the fact
that Des Val was like pretty hot during
the data in the
summer Additionally you know if you look
at this blue curve on the uh on the
bottom right corner so you will see that
which is you know essentially the
relative humidity inside the uh the
reflector so it actually you know
quickly erase about two hours just after
the sunrise and start you know to uh you
know generate the water consistently and
you know here's a photo of you know
three of us uh standing uh in front of a
thermometer as you can see so you know
when we are testing this device so it
actually reaches about 122 degree
Fahrenheit which is 50 degre Celsius so
this is actually by far uh in my opinion
the one of the most extreme conditions
ever test for the atmospheric water
harvesting in the fueld test and in this
case so as you can see in this you know
data on the middle and this you know
video so the device constantly produce a
lot of water and even compared with the
previous work using Mo absorbance so we
are actually getting much more in terms
of Water Production in this case so in
addition you know since the mo has a
great you know structural stability
actually we also run the cycling
experiment and which which was actually
done in the last because you know we
want to see how many cycles it can
actually run so the result actually
turns out that it can you know last for
about more than 5,000 Cycles with less
than 5% of rul in the overall capacity
that means that you know you can keep
the same Mo chamber running for about
like 10 years or even more which you
know in the long term is uh will reduce
the cost of you know the Regeneration of
the water since you know it relies
nothing other than just the sunlight and
you don't need to replace it you know
for the next 10 years if nothing happens
so you also you should should also
acknowledge that you know besides Mo so
there are also like other great you know
soent like hydrogels and zelit you know
out there to be uh explored by the other
you know research groups and the
commercialized companies for these
technology and we envision that you know
overall this device design you at a
design level will be helpful you know to
further expand incorporate other choice
of the Sant to make this technology you
know more widely spread and you know be
being accessible to everyone and
ultimately you know uh provide like a
clean water solution to many water
shortage
areas so with that uh hopefully you know
today uh as a summary hopefully today I
have been showing you a story about uh
the development of these narrow scale
crystalling materials for water
harvesting application so we talk about
how you know we start from the uh
synthesis optimization to solve the
scalability of these na scale materials
also I show you you know how the
insights from the designing principle
for the water harvesting at atomy level
can help control its properties in terms
of the water harvesting and eventually
you know how to connect this you know
structural property relationship
actually all the way back to the device
level performance to maximize their you
know like real world applications in
terms of water output so the above
mentioning technology is actually has
turned into you know patterns and the
startup companies which is actively
working on expanding the use of mos to
address the global challenges and
provide the solution to the Water Crisis
so with that I would like to you know
express my thanks to my PhD advisor
Professor Omar yagi and Professor
Jennifer Chase and Professor Christian
Bros for their invaluable guidance I
would also like to thank you know my
labmates from the UC Berkeley and the
funding agencies for their support and
also I would like to thank you know the
MIT narrow exploration for these
wonderful opportunities to present my
you know PhD work here and finally I
would like to thank all of you for your
attention and being here and I'm looking
forward to the questions thank
you thank you Zach for AIC talk so um
that is now open for questions as I
mentioned earlier on you can ask
questions in the Q&A section uh which is
a special session that you can use for
webinars the chat or you could simply
raise your hand and we'll keep track of
of the hands I see that there already is
one and so
um so I'm going to read it to you uh
Zach uh when you discussed reflux
synthesis of MAF 303 using sodium
hydroxide does the addition of sodium
hydroxide and use of water show any
noticeable effect on poze structure and
performance that's actually a great
question thank you for uh uh thank you
for this question um so let me just go
back to this slide and I think you know
it's on the right side so the question
is about uh how you know like the choice
of you know the sodium hydroxide and the
water influence the you know I I think
the the pr size so I think you know my
uh we actually run some analysis in the
pr size distribution of the mob and was
actually very happy to find that you
know it just have a very consistent you
know in terms of the uh uh process
distribution as well as you know like
the uh uh performance which you know if
you can look at this you know uh Bett
surface area measurement so we uh at a
very early stage so we can actually run
L you know like calculation to you know
analyze their procise so they were both
you know very consistent you know in two
methods and but one F you know one
interesting observation we found that
actually you know if you slightly vary
the amount of the uh sodium hydroxide in
this case so you may like slightly
difference in terms of the uh particle
size of the M which is by about I think
like 10% to 30% you know depending on
like how how how much more sodium
hydroxide you use for instance if you
use 3.1 equivalent instead of three so
you may be expecting actually like a
slightly 10% smaller particle size for
this compound but overall you know when
we are uh measuring their you know uh
procity and water update so they behave
in a similar way the other thing is that
typically for water harvesting smaller
Pro size usually have like a slightly
stronger hesis so if you know you use
instead of you more sodium hydroxide so
compare with the original synthesis we
see that uh sometimes it may result in
certain H uh hesis which is undesirable
so that's why you know I I had some kind
of tra Arrow to make sure we use the
right amount of the sodium hydroxide so
I hope that answer that
question so the next question is how
will this device do in low temperatures
great question and in this case so
essentially the idea is that we want to
create a certain uh temperature
difference you know between the top and
the dot so obviously you know like there
there should be like a bottom limit for
this you know techn for instance you
cannot run this below zero otherwise you
know the water will just you know frozen
into the ice so that doesn't make any
sense but essentially you know in any
kind of you know like most conditions
that across the entire planet so you
know I will expect it you know you
around you know ambient temperature so
in this case you know we are still you
know creating like a temperature
difference because when the sunlight
hits the mo essentially you will just
try to increase it and once this kind of
temperature difference exists so you
will be able to still condense water uh
to into a drinkable
form um how much does it cost to build
one of those water harvesting devices
that you demonstrated in Death Valley
great question great question uh so for
the cor size uh for for the device uh
let me actually go back to the uh to the
the photo of the device so it has the
the most of the C come from two parts so
one is you know like the C we have to
synthesize the m so and the other part
is you know to customize you know this
device for the device part so for this
single device it takes about I think
$400 you know to just customize this you
know like Mo chamber as well as this
reflector so some of some of the parts
are actually 3D print which you know
adds up to the total cost and for the m
so I think you know over the past few
years so the price drops a lot because
you know just just as more and more
people are you know get involved into
use of this Linker so like people are
just reducing the uh price for this
precursor at a you know like Industrial
Level and I think for this device if I
remember it correctly so the moth will
only cost about uh $100 to $200 which is
even you know cheaper than the the cost
for the device and the end of day I
think it totally adds up to about $500
to $700 each for this device but you
know like there is a startup company
that is currently you know
commercializing this this technology and
I think they are trying to reduce the
overall price and you know in my opinion
in a l in a l run so this can be you
know eventually goes down to be even
like a lower cost for the entire
device okay
and then the next one is what are the
stabilities of MAF under the cycles of
water uptake and
release okay great question uh in terms
of the stability so as I uh as I
mentioned previously I think I didn't
have like a figure for that but actually
we run like a 5,000 uh uh Circle testing
in terms of the uh uh stability and uh
once we you know run this you know uh
cycling experiments so we actually being
able to to see that you know the the m
still retains up to 95% of its water
update after this 5,000 cycle meaning
that you know they are still uh
retaining their structural Integrity as
well as the
crystalinity uh so so pretty much I
would say you know this MO is very
stable you know under a lot of cycling
experiments and then I have one more
this is
uh have you checked the MAF 303 water
ABS absorption capacity
after long-term testing yes yes so uh
it's kind of relevant to a previous
question so we actually run the you know
like the aborption test after you know
like 5,000 cycles and then so we realize
that it retains about 95% of the uh uh
capacity still after you know this such
long you know uh kind of recycling
experiment
M and does the sunlight's angle of
incidence have any effects on the volume
of water output
great question so in so so this is
actually like a um like a special design
we had for this you know device which
you may notice that you know we
intentionally use this cylindrical you
know design which means when you are
placing it you know on the ground so
ideally you know let's say the sound
raise from the East and as he travel you
know to the top of head and finally you
know like sunet on the other side
essentially this cylindrical you know uh
shape will allows you know allows us to
maximize you know like the sunlight
Radiance no matter you know which
direction he you know end our Wass
during the daytime and in this case so
uh you know there is like no influence
in terms of the angle but rather you
know it will just consistently you know
maximize the uh ingredients to heat up
the uh the moth
bed and why the use of the nickel foam
plates oh great question so in this case
uh so for the uh Nic I believe that uh
there are uh two ways we we we use that
one is that so overall uh we want to you
know make sure you know like this uh
this moths uh can kind of separate from
each other so sometimes you know if you
get uh all the mo just you know like uh
uh all the moth B you know just having
just only the mo so sometimes it cannot
maximize the water it uptate so you need
some kind of space in between each other
but still you know uh you cannot just
have it to be uh like a empty space just
like you know thinking of the Oreo right
so if you are want want to you know uh
make sure you have the Oro so you have
the white black white black thing and
this you know like Nick form essentially
are very poal so you still allow it to
you know get water into it but they are
actually not holding water but
facilitating the their neighbors which
is the uh moth bed to get water
saturated well thank you I think we are
uh out of time at this point it's
exactly 11:45 and U that was a good set
of questions so thank you very much
that's for taking this giving this
webinar thank you thank you car for
hosting thank you to the participants
for the active participation with
questions and so on