I'm excited to introduce our next
speaker, Leon Glicksman, who is a
professor of building technology and
mechanical engineering post tenure here
at MIT. Let's hear for Leon.
Thank you, Jim. Um, he didn't mention
one of the important attributes I have.
I'm a MIT lifer. Uh and if you have some
time later on I can tell you about what
Kendall Square looked like when I was an
undergraduate. It was a little different
than what we see now. Uh progress goes
on. So uh Jim asked me to talk about
this I think because I was the founder
of the building technology program which
is a uh a collaboration between the
department of architecture, department
of mechanical and civil engineering. And
the idea is to try and bring those
engineering and science principles in to
the issues related to architecture. Um,
and in fact, Professor Reinhardt, who
talked to you this morning, is one of
the distinguished faculty members in in
our group doing work in these particular
areas. Um, what he maybe didn't know, I
also did work before that in the heat
transfer lab. So, I'm going to try and
bring both of those kind of elements in
in the uh in the talk today. Uh, a
little truth in advertising. The way is
described as essential explore best
practices and emerging frontiers. Well,
emerging frontiers, we've got quite a
few when we talk about cooling within
this uh this realm. Um but best
practices, the problem we're facing is
I've just pulled out of one of the
literatures. This are some of the
tradeoffs or are options you have for
advanced cooling techniques. And and
certainly years ago when we're talking
about traditional kinds of data centers
um the issue about cooling was really
sort of hot K hot aisles cold aisles
kind of a thing using air cooling as a
way of cooling the system. Now in
present days and as we talk about future
trend we're talking about much higher
energy levels and we're talking about
challenges of really some different ways
of dealing with this. Um so what I'm
going to try and do is give you sort of
perspective both from the point of view
of heat transfer. What are some of the
basic heat transfer uh things that we're
dealing with as we look at a few of
these uh advanced kinds of techniques
which are available um and also what can
we say from the point of view of
building HVAC in terms of dealing with
issues related to the to the cooling.
And again as you've seen I'm sure and
know about there's all of these huge new
data centers which are going up and
there's the questions related to the
engineering of the uh and some of the
particular components. Um and if we do a
comparison between conventional
buildings and data centers one of the
things we see is very different kinds of
of of uh uh things that we're looking
after. Uh the building HVAC is
traditionally a very conservative
industry, very difficult to introduce
new technologies. Um uh people who build
buildings are really concerned about
minimum first cost. Um possibly energy
efficiency and the like. Uh but that's
uh that's not a particular concern.
Obviously in the data center we're
talking about rapid changes, new
technologies, major invest in
investigations and and and investments
in these types of things. Um uh also
when we're talking about uh buildings,
we're talking about energy per square
meter or floor area which may be 40 to
85 watts per square meter. Uh if we go
to labs, it's somewhat higher. And then
finally in clean rooms uh where we're
talking about where we essentially uh
develop some of these new integrated
circuits and the like we may get to high
energy levels but nowhere near the
energy levels when we talk about data
centers. So again different order of
magnitude in many cases a different way
of approaching the solution to these
kinds of problems. Um and as as you look
at the data center cooling systems, it
really sort of breaks down in my mind as
to three specific components if you
will. At one hand, uh we have the heat
transfer from individual chips. How do
we where we now are talking about
smaller and smaller integrated uh chips,
higher and higher power levels, how do
we deal with the heat transfer and
maintain these at some reasonable
operating temperatures. Second is um if
we can cool these, how do we transfer
that energy from the rack and from the
individual chips to the exterior. Uh and
third is what do we do at the exhaust
end of it? How do we essentially uh
exhaust this to the atmosphere or
possibly find some useful applications
for this kind of thing? um uh this the
the intermediate one the transfer energy
is one that requires some very serious
engineering but in general we're talking
about a water coupled system that's
going to use from individual racks to
the exterior and I think in some cases
the bigger technical challenges are at
the two extremes what do we do for
individual at the v individual chip
level and the other extreme is where we
have these huge amounts of thermal
energy which we're exhausting to the
environment how do
deal with that both from an
environmental point of view and how do
we possibly get some useful applications
from that that system. So if we first
talk about at the chip level surface
cooling of advanced devices u there are
different technologies which people have
looked at um this is a a review a recent
review that came out and one of the
techniques is what one might call direct
contact cooling and that's a a situation
where we have a chip and directly in
contact with it is some kind of cooling
medium usually a liquid in some form
which is used for there Um now included
in that was the conventional air cooled
system that we've talked about briefly.
Um and again that's relatively
straightforward. Again hot aisles, cold
aisles to do that. There are some issues
of engineering there um uh to make sure
the air goes where we want it to go. Uh
uh and uh some issues is uh here's an
underfloor uh cooled system and then a
system that brings the air to a
refrigeration unit which cools the air
back down. Again relatively
straightforward in the design of that
particular kind of system. The problem
that one gets into in the air cooled
system uh if we look at the purple bars
um the amount of fan power which is
required uh as we look at more advanced
systems we're talking about much more
energy required for the fan power to
essentially circulate the air in these
kinds of systems. The last bar if you
can see on the right hand side the lower
one is a water cooled system or again
the energy requirements as percent of
total power in the system is much lower.
Um
uh just to do a little bit of heat
transfer and there won't there won't be
any tests at the end of this hour but
just give you some some background in
heat transfer. Basically when we're
talking about direct contact what we're
talking about is hot surface. to be the
surface of the chip with the with the uh
electrical energy uh developed there and
then a cool fluid which is adjacent to
it. It may be force flow. It may be
essentially uh uh natural uh uh
circulation which required. Um and the
rate of heat transfer between the hot
surface and the cool fluid is going to
be a function of the surface area
required. And the temperature difference
between the surface of the chip and the
fluid temperature and by fluid
temperature I mean the bulk temperature
of fluid not the fluid directly adjacent
to the surface but the bulk temperature
of the fluid as it flows by the
particular surface. Um and if we want to
get a more technical we have a uh
component which is called the convective
heat transfer coefficient. Um basically
all the physics in terms of this cooling
are really wrapped up in that particular
um and those of you who have ever uh uh
dealt with this in many cases when we
get to convective heat transfer all they
know about is g that one correlation
after the other but what we're going to
talk about is the physics rather than
than that. So just order of magnitude
things. If we're talking about air
cooling, um we have a typical value for
what that heat transfer coefficient is.
Or maybe a better way to look at this is
given a certain temperature difference
from the surface to the fluid of say 20째
K. Uh we can get an idea of what the
heat transfer per unit area is. In this
case, it's about uh a tenth to 210 of a
watt per square centimeter. Um now if we
want to compare with what we need if we
look at some ideas of what the energy uh
uh is in these modern chips again as uh
uh as the number of transistor counts
keeps going up the amount of power
required and that's the upper curve that
you see there uh which can be read from
the lefth hand scale um that continually
goes up and also the uh heat flux which
is again the power per unit area
increases considerably from uh average
in 2000 maybe u uh the order of 10 now
in the orders of hundreds of watts per
square centimeter. So we're talking
about a huge increase in that heat flux
rate. And again just to get an idea of
more modern things I tried to get some
numbers from the recent Nvidia chip u uh
numbers which are quoted as something
like 2700 watts and uh the area given
there. So we get something order of over
300 watts per square centimeters. So
again much higher heat flux rates that
we have to deal with in this kind of
thing. Um and there is the issue of just
what really is going on in Nvidia but uh
we can we can make some guesses on that.
So one of the ways that people are
talking about in the now and in the
future is some way that we can directly
immerse the electronics in fluid. Now
this would have to be a dialectric fluid
obviously that doesn't conduct
electricity. um uh and the hope is with
this kind of direct immersion or a
system of this sort we can get much
higher rates of heat transfer. So if we
want to look at what are some of the
heat transfer mechanisms first of all we
would have simply natural convection
that's we have a heated surface and
because the fluid next to the surface
temperature goes up uh its uh density
goes down and we have a buoyancy effect
so in fact the fluid will start rising
and what you see on the right hand side
is a graphic of the temperature
distributions adjacent to the surface of
a heated surface and you can see that um
uh uh the fluid tends to rise on that
particular surface and we can get if we
had a liquid like water we can get heat
fluxes of the order of maybe one to two
watts per square centimeter. Again, not
good enough for the kind of things we're
talking about for advanced systems. If
we go to a force convection where
essentially we force a fluid over the
surface of the chip, we can get to the
order of 10 to 20 watts per square
meters for this kind of thing. So we're
approaching the kind of uh of uh uh uh
uh performance we want. And then finally
what people are talking about now is
using boiling changes of phase as
essentially a way of doing that heat
transfer for that surface of the chip.
And what I've shown here on this plot is
um the heat flux and and look at the
left hand scale of that watts per square
centimeters as a function of the
temperature difference. This is the
temperature of the uh surface relative
to the temperature of the saturated
temperature of the fluid or the boiling
temperature if you will. And one of the
things you can see here is it's a
nonlinear kind of relationship here. For
example, as the this temperature
difference goes from 5 to 10째 you can
see a uh order of magnitude increase in
the heat flux rate. Why so? Well, what's
happening then as you increase that
temperature difference initially at low
temperatures, you'll start to see one or
two points where in fact vapor bubbles
will form uh will attach from the
surface. And what that's doing is as the
vapor leaves the surface, cool water is
rushing back into the surface and
essentially providing the cooling that
we see in this kind of system. As we
increase the temperature difference,
more and more of those sites are now
starting to perform uh uh develop vapor
bubbles, we get much more action in this
particular kind of system. So it looks
really great that we'll just essentially
increase the delta t and we'll get
higher and higher heat flux rate. And I
guess this is some work pool boiling
results for dialectric fluids. We see
the same kind of thing that we've seen
before in this particular kind of
system. But let me caution you, we
sometimes run into, and that's just some
some visuals of what that looks like. As
we go to higher and higher heat flux
rates, we can sometimes get to what's
called the critical heat flux. And what
happens in that case is um the vapor
bubbles now completely cover the entire
surface. So much so that the liquid
water that's going to quench the surface
can't get into the surface. So
essentially, we have a complete vapor
layer over the surface.
uh and then the vapor bubbles form from
that. That means very poor heat transfer
and so-called critical heat flux in some
time in the field we call it the burnout
point for obvious reasons. If I have a
electrical input, if I get to that point
beyond I can't pro provide the cooling
that's required. So in fact we get into
a situation where essentially we get to
very high surface temperatures where in
fact radiation heat transfer becomes the
mechanism. So again a caution if we're
going to use this kind of system we have
to be careful about what the upper
limits are when we use it. Another
approach is a so-called indirect contact
cooling system and there are again a
number of different options which are
available for using this system. One of
the most common ones that people are
using is what's called the microch and
this is where we have a a high
conductivity material for example
copper. we have a whole series of micro
fins which are formed on this particular
channel and then we flow fluid the
cooling fluid through this particular
channel. Um and there's a series of heat
transfer resistances here from the the
red which is indicating what would be
the uh uh the chip itself to the uh
initial surface of this uh of of this uh
uh device. uh and we can see conduction
there and in fact that helps to even out
if we have any disparities in what the
heat flux rate is across the surface. U
then heat transfer up to the surface of
the fins and then from the fins to the
fluid and the fluid is flowing down
between the fins. And what we find out
is in most cases um we're in what's
called laminer flow. Uh and the
resistant to heat transfer is going to
be directly um uh inverse to the
distance between the fins. So we get the
fins closer and closer together. We get
smaller resistance, higher heat transfer
from the surface to the fluid. Um and in
fact this chart gives you some idea and
this is in terms of the the blue line
which is idea of what the resistance is
as we reduce the fin spacing and you can
see that the resistance goes down
significantly in this case. But
unfortunately we run into a problem and
that problem is that um we have to flow
the fluid between these channels. as the
channels get smaller and smaller, the
pressure drop to force the fluid through
the channels gets higher and higher so
that we run into a a a significant
problem here is what's practical from a
uh uh engineering point of view.
Um now if we can do better in the microf
channel uh uh heat transfer, one of the
things we can look at is the so-called
boiling again. And the idea now is we
send a fluid through this channel
which saturation temperature is close to
the temperature of the fins. And now in
fact we can have boiling occurring here.
First nucleate boiling then as we get to
higher flux we get to so-called slug
flow annular flow. And it's interesting
parallel because years ago we looked at
the exact same kind of problem of
flowblowing but it had to do with
nuclear reactors because one of the
issues one of the main uh uh uh methods
for designing nuclear reactors was
so-called boiling uh uh boiling uh
nuclear reactors where essentially we
force water through the channels um and
uh we allowed that to to change in phase
and there was a huge amount of research
it's related to the issue of what's what
what are some uh safe measures and uh
safe levels for using those particular
kinds of things. So it may well be we
want to go back and review some of that
literature of that uh era to try and see
how we can get some uh ideas how we can
do a better job of designing these
particular kinds of systems. Uh again,
if we're talking about the situation
with flow blowing, we've got a number of
different uh uh uh flow regimes. You can
see a flow regime where we have vapor in
the in the middle. We've got liquid
around the periphery of these types of
things. Uh again, in this particular
case, this is a time sequence where we
see what's going on over a period of
time for again micro channels in this
case. Um and you can see when we get
down to the bottom channel we have again
a problem which may be very severe and
that's the issue was sometimes called uh
burnout. And that again that's is our
situation where essentially there's
vapor on the surface. We don't have
liquid. We do not get high heat transfer
rates and in fact we may get into a
problem here in terms of uh uh uh are we
going to get safe operation for our
particular systems. Um there are some
other issues mechanical issues you need
to talk about. How do you bring the
fluid into the uh uh microchs uh if the
if the uh entrance flow on the right
hand side is so-called horizontal inlet
which is the inlets at the same plane as
the microchs we may run into problems
because we won't get uniform flow
through all the channels. Um it turns
out in fact in this particular
simulation if we do it what's called
vertical where in fact the inlets are at
right angles to the plane of this we can
solve most of those particular problems.
And again for the horizontal you can see
this is the speed of the air in
individual channels and you can see very
great disparity in what that speed is.
So it's again something we need to worry
about. Um um there are a number of
design parameters that we need to uh
concern ourselves with if we want to
optimize this. One has to do with the
cross-sectional geometry. How small
should these channels be? What geometry
should they be? What's the surface
roughness? Can we enhance the heat
transfer if we make the channels rough?
What's the velocity?
In some cases, we can look at a
situation where rather than having
laminer flow, we can have what's known
turbulent flow. And in that case if we
do that if we add surface roughness and
that we can substantially enhance the
rate of heat transfer for these types of
things. So again all opportunities which
can we use to try and optimize the
design of these this for the future uh
systems that we have to deal with. Um
also the question of what can we use as
working fluids. um liquid metals I think
are really sort of extreme and and these
kinds of things but possibly uh the I
adding uh particles to the fluid to
increase their uh thermal conductivity
would work and again flow boiling issues
of instability and the like um and if we
really want to look in the future here's
a slide from um uh the DARPA uh the
defense people are looking at even
higher heat flux rates where they're
looking at uh how do we deal with heat
flux rates where in fact we have heat
flux of the same order as the heat flux
on the surface of the sun and the
question is how do we find some
solutions for this? Uh now they're using
it for high power lasers and things of
this sort but it may well be again as
the chips keep getting smaller and the
power gets higher we may have to deal
with uh those kind of heat transfer
rates. Now at the other extreme is what
do we do with this huge amount of energy
which now we've transferred from the
racks to the outside. What do we do with
this area? In fact, here's one example.
Uh, NEC is talking about example. Again,
this is the old air cooled kind of
systems. And you notice in this
particular case, um, they've already
estimated what the temperature is. And
one of the challenges and we need to
look at is if I assume that I'm going to
run this so I can cool the air or the
liquid to 20째 C, can I essentially do it
in a location where the ambient
temperature is lower than that? or if
not so do I have to use liquid
evaporation as a way to get to the wet
bulb temperature which might give me the
20째 C that I use. So again something we
have and again part of the issues we
have to look at is how the exhaust from
the individual units integrate with each
other and how they and affect the
environment. Uh so there's been some
computational fluid dynamics looking at
that. Certainly evaporators have the
same kind of issues. Uh and again uh
similar to what Elsa has talked about
when we talk about so-called free
cooling we're talking if we use
evaporation
to meet this uh the this heat load which
comes out we're talking about huge
amounts of water use estimate I've done
is that we're talking about 200
megawatts and we're using water
evaporation to meet that need we're
talking about the water consumption of
roughly a community of 15,000 people and
as we scale up the even larger size
systems, we're talking about huge water
water uses. And the issue is where does
that water come from? Uh, another issue
if we're talking about so-called wet
cooling towers, we see in the HVAC
industry something called Legionnaire's
disease where if we're not careful about
how we control the uh uh the the quality
of the water in the system, we can in
fact get into situations associated with
that. Um another problem of similar or
is some people have talked about well
why don't we just use saltwater cooling
towers. Um and the problem of course is
we don't then have to use fresh water
but then the question is what about the
drift from those saltwater towers. Where
is all that salt then? And then we have
the environmental issues that we have to
deal with in that particular case.
um other people. Here's a proposal in
Portugal. And the idea here is we're
going to use uh the we're going to site
it close to the seawater here. Uh we're
going to draw seawater in uh use it for
cooling and then the warm water will
exhaust. Again, the problem and again in
work I've done in the past on cooling
towers is people who design power
plants, there's always the environmental
issues. What do we do? If we have a warm
uh exhaust, we have so-called thermal
pollution. There may be problems
associated with the aquatic life.
Similarly, at the inlet, we have to
worry about possible damage there. So,
again, not simple problems to deal with.
And and as you can see, a number of the
new um data centers are not necessarily
located near large bodies of water. So,
we may not be able to use that
particular kind of system. Um people
talk about using nuclear plants. One of
the things we have to keep in mind is a
typical operranic
efficiency of a nuclear plant is about
33%.
That means for each uh gigawatt of power
which we we produce we have two
gigawatts of thermal energy which we
again we have to inject to the
environment. So that says the whole
complex nuclear plant plus data center
we're talking about 3 gawatts of thermal
energy that we have to deal with. So
again it may compound some of the
problems that we've talked about before.
Uh people also talked about some
applications using thermal energy for
distillation for refrigeration
uh and the like. Um and then finally um
let me just end up with the economist
magazine's uh solution for data centers.
So with that I'll end. Thank you.
>> Eric Schmidt just bought a rocket
company and when somebody said, "Is that
for this?" He had a one-word reply. Yes.
>> Other questions for Liam?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Glost lost, but you you flipped through
organic ranking cycle. Do you see any
viability for for heat to power
recovery?
>> There certainly is some, but again,
there's a trade-off. To get any kind of
reasonable efficiency from that, you
have to increase the temperature that
you're rejecting the heat. And the
trade-off, of course, is what does that
mean in terms of the lifetime of your
electronic components if you get too
high. But yes, that's certainly
something that would that can be
considered.
>> Would 60 CD be at all infra?
It would certainly in the in the realm
of would start to start to look
reasonable. Yes. Yes.
[Music]
>> Okay. Anyone else?
>> You can hand out the quizzes now.
>> Okay.
>> Perfect presentation. I want to know
about if we build the data center in the
mountain or maybe in very cold weather
is it help for the cooling system?
>> Well certainly yeah if it's very cold
weather in fact we probably don't have
to use evaporation at all. We can simply
just use what's called a dry cooling
system where essentially we bring in the
cold air over heat exchanger tubes and
use that to cool the cool particular
system.
>> Yes sir. Uh
>> yeah. So I also wonder like what if we
build the data center like as at a part
of uh the city sewage system because
like there's constantly water flow in
which channels the heat energy and uh
yeah
>> would that be viable?
>> I think again it's a question of order
of magnitude. We've people have even
looked at essentially conventional power
plants. Could we use somehow use a
sewage system for providing the energy
storage? In most cases, the flow rate is
one order of magnitude lower than what's
even needed for heating and cooling a
large uh metropolitan area of buildings.
So probably uh doesn't make sense. Now
um what does make sense in some cases
the so-called cogent plants um where
essentially just as in power plant power
systems what they do is they use the
exhaust as I've showed um with a a a
absorption system to prevent to provide
cool water or in the in the summer or
heating in in the winter. So some in
fact New York City for example has
codegens. Boston traditionally had some
of those particular systems. There again
is the question um uh really just the
engineering of uh is the city close
going to be close to where your data
center is. If it's far away then the
whole problem of how you transfer the
probably heated water or steam from the
data center to this part location. In
many cases we find the economics of that
doesn't really make sense.
>> Yes sir.
>> Thank you. Uh you were talking in the
beginning of the presentation about uh
liquid cooling for the servers or for
the chips and the different types like
micro channels etc. Do you have any idea
which type of liquid cooling is the best
or which you know is going to be the
solution of choice in the long term?
>> Well, it's it's
um I think again there's a number of
different choices. I think the microch
is one that's been very popular in this
particular case. Um but I think as I
said looking in the future it's a
microch with a liquid cooling where
essentially you have a phase change
where you have boiling occurring in that
particular kind of system that'll give
the highest rates of heat flux to the
particular fluid. But as I said there
are a lot of technical problems to make
sure that you don't get situations where
you create too much vapor so you don't
get the kind of cooling levels that you
want. So that would be one I' I' I'd
sort of put my bet on and maybe it's one
Nvidia is doing right now.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> All right. Uh this might be an
interesting question for you. Um so I'm
a I'm a research analyst for Uptime
Institute. I write about cooling systems
day in day out. Um I wanted to skip back
to the start campus in Portugal that's
doing the heat rejection to seawater.
>> Yes ma'am.
>> Um you had raised the concern of um heat
pollution in the water from raising the
temperature of the outgoing water.
>> Right.
>> Um a few data centers have been built
this way. One of them got environmental
approval on the Stockton River in
California because their delta T was
only 4 degrees Fahrenheit. Um
so what would well slight pivot but
still on the same topic. What would you
say to the uh the the assertion that
that heat is being put into the
environment anyway and if you can
control your delta t in the seawater is
it really more impactful?
>> Well, if you can control the delta t so
that the energy rise is very modest.
Yes, that certainly is a a reasonable
approach. But again looking at the
experience that large power plants,
nuclear power plants and the like have
had just the environmental licensing to
prove to people that the delta t is not
going to be too high. Uh and then the
question is where do you measure the
delta tree right at the point of where
the hot water is uh uh brought into the
sea or do you say some distance away
because clearly it's going to change
over time. Uh and a lot of the
environmentalists say you've got to
measure right at the point where the
where the hot water enters the the the
sea and uh and then you've got to relate
that to the what aquatic species around
are they going to have any damage or
they're not. But it's it can in some
cases what people have found after they
built it in fact that it's helped the
aquatic life by raising the temperatures
to some extent. But again, it it just
seems like it almost every one of these
large plant there's a large series of
questions you have to go out. But you're
right, if the delta t is small, this
kind of system works quite well. But if
you're talking about something which is
a gigawatt,
you would have to have a huge outfall.
So in fact, that the delta t would stay
small.
Okay.
exercise. Sorry. Um,
>> uh, there's been a little bit of
divergence in perspectives on inlet
temperature with Nvidia maintaining a
45C inlet, which is much higher than a
lot of the other providers. Um, they're
trying to defend the sustainability of
that going forward. Uh, do you see a
horizon on that or what's your
perspective on how long or or if they
can maintain that that high inlet
temperature? Well, in some sense, I
think the answer to the question is
outside my realm of understanding and
it's the issue of what does it mean for
the electronics to be running at higher
temperatures and you know I I see in the
suggestion the literature as you go to
higher temperatures you have problems
about how the failure of these
particular electronics. So as I said
there's that that kind of trade-off one
has to make. Yes, if you can get the
higher outlet temperatures, you can have
more useful purposes for this. Okay, but
then what does it mean in terms of
particular components that you have?
Okay, let's hear it for Leon.