hello welcome to the autoimmune disease
machine learning challenge thank you for
joining us my name is or ashenberg and I
a director of computational biology at
the Bro Institute where I work at the
interface of machine learning biology
and human disease we have put together
these three introductory lectures to get
you up to speed on autoimmune disease
and how we hope to use machine learning
to better understand and treat these
complex diseases since the completion of
the Human Genome Project in 2023 the
live Sciences have been in an ongoing
Revolution where our ability to measure
and perturb biological systems in both
health and disease has been radically
transformed however these new
technologies generate complex
high-dimensional multimodal data that
requires advances in machine learning in
order to distill biological meaning and
translate to clinical impact and that's
where you will have a chance to really
make a difference so let's get
started so first let me give you an
overview of the crash course so there
three lectures the first is going to be
the biology of autoimmune disease and
then the second lecture will be the
technologies that we use to profile
autoimmune disease and then the final
lecture will be on the data that we've
assembled for this competition and the
three crunches that you're going to be
working on over the course of the
competition so let's start with the
biology of autoimmune
disease so this lecture is divided into
four parts first we'll discuss what is
autoimmune disease then we'll talk about
autoimmune disease in our gut
and how a pathologist can make a
diagnosis of this type of disease and
finally we'll talk about how certain
autoimmune diseases can increase your
chances of catching
cancer so first let's talk about what is
autoimmune disease to understand this we
need a basic understanding of our immune
systems so our immune systems operate
throughout our bodies to protect us
against Real threats such as cancer
viral infections bacteria and when your
immune system encounters these threats
it initiates inflammation and the
classic symptoms of inflammation are
swelling pain redness um we're all
familiar with this and this triggers a
very big immune response that ultimately
uh Works to recognize the threat
eliminate the threat and promote tissue
repair so that's what we want to happen
in a healthy immune response now in
contrast in autoimmune disease you get
these same forces acting but they're
getting activated in the absence of of
any real threat so you start to get
inflammation in your colon or your
kidney or your brain and you get this
big immune response that leads to tissue
damage and this causes diseases such as
lupus uh multiple sclerosis type 1
diabetes and ulcerative colitis which is
the focus of this
competition and you might be asking well
why would your immune system respond in
this way well first of all all of us
have different uh variants in our genes
in our body and these variant give us a
different predisposition to certain
diseases so somebody might be at greater
risk for ulcerative colitis and somebody
else might be at greater risk for Lupus
but it's not the genes alone that
determine whether you get an autoimmune
disease it's also the interactions with
our environment so a change in diet or
air pollution or toxins in the
environment can increase your chances of
autoimmune disease in addition the
microbes living in our gut or different
uh viral infections for instance so
those are some of the reasons people can
get um autoimmune
disease now very concerningly the
prevalence of autoimmune disease is
increasing around the world and this
comes at huge cost to patients and
public health so here we're looking at a
graph of different autoimmune diseases
and their prevalence over time and you
can see that all these diseases have
been going up over the last few decades
and in particular um inflammatory bowel
disease which is what you'll be working
on in this competition has really gone
up over the last 20 or 30 years