so good afternoon everyone uh I hope you
have been enjoying uh the program so far
my name is Rona Han uh I'm an associate
professor of the Department of eecs uh
and also I'm the associate director of
MTL uh I will have the great honor to
host a few sessions in this
afternoon uh next we will have a
15minute brief session and I would like
to invite uh the representatives from
five of our MTL industrial um group
members to come to the stage and uh
share with us uh their experiences with
MTL over the years um so the first
speaker is our long-term friend uh Sam
Fuller from analog device and the next
one is Dr hosi uh Suzuki from Hitachi
and then the third speaker is Yan Suzuki
from Morata he's also currently the
visiting scientist of MTL and also we
will have uh yat Radu from soyac he's
the head of soyac us research and also
uh our next speaker is uh uh Jim Wiser
from Texas uh instruments so uh let's
start from
Sam is uh Sam
here well may maybe we can start from
Hiroshi is youhi here
nice okay thank you
Professor oh
har uh I'm Hiroshi Suzuki from Hitachi
Hightech corporation in
Tokyo it's great honor to be here today
uh and make a brief talk about uh the
long-term collaboration between m
and hitach
Hightech our partnership began in uh
2010 it it for uh 14 years ago and uh
first research topics was uh microix
circuit and sensing for chemical
analytics
technology and uh at the time young
engineer of our company was stayed in
MTR
more than one
years
and Partnerships were built on a mutual
respect and common goals and became uh
Stronger since then uh our interests
have changed from time to time and
different research topics for example
inspection and measurement uh new
materials new devices and the new
semiconductors but then MTL covers a
wide range of research topics that is
very important for us to uh grow our
business business
area for this reason uh together we have
continued to push the boundaries of
innovation we would like to express our
uh deep gratitude to all of you you at
MTL for your continued uh support and
effort your commitment has uh
contributed to our
success we are confident uh that our
partnership will continue to uh sur
survive thank you again for this uh
opportunity to speak we look forward to
a fruitful cooperation in the future
finally and congratulation on mt's 40
years anniversary thank you so
much thank
you the next speaker is Yan Suzuki from
Morata
youran uh thank you for introduction
okay we are Johan and Aki from murata
electronics and murata is a Japanese
manufacture of the electrical component
like a capacitor inductor and RF
wireless communication modu sensors and
so force and this robot I mean this
adorable guard is a m leader and uh
thanks to our tons of component and
Technology she can balance on the board
and synchronize with other charity
members and uh even dance okay and uh we
have the 10 DEA and two substitute
members in our Charing team so please
check our website and YouTube okay and
also the we Morata just joined the MTL
uh January this year and uh yeah thanks
to MTL support so that so far the our uh
project is uh yeah some project is
ongoing
and okay and M helps us to explore some
the potential The
Innovation and we are really honored
being the to be a member of the uh MTF
and Mt MIT and MD system helps us uh
yeah great Innovation so congratulation
for this anniversary and uh thank you
thank
[Applause]
you and the next speaker is um um IAT
Radu from soyac us
please hello everyone uh thank you for
uh giving uh the opportunity for me to
speak in front of you so I'm yonut Ru
I'm with soy I don't know if everyone
knows soch is the largest manufacturer
of engineer
substrate uh we are a little bit younger
than uh MTL 34 years old uh or 33 um and
uh similarly we have started uh the
company is known for SOI manufacturer uh
we started with silicon but in the last
5 10 years we Diversified into new
materials Gan and uh ptic materials and
some other compounds um so in the in the
in the history uh we we had many
collaborations with MIT especially on so
SOI um and uh we decided recently uh
2023 uh to join MTL and already working
with couple of uh faculty members and
looking forward to expand to to more uh
more Technologies and more
opportunities uh one of the reason we uh
we decided to engage with MTL is uh
diversity of the research topics you you
have and this fits pretty well with our
strategy uh to to further develop and
Advance uh innov Innovative materials
thank you and congratulation for for the
anniversary
[Applause]
and the next speaker is Jim Weiser from
Texas
instrument well first of all I'd like to
uh congratulate MTL in their 40 Years of
success and hopefully another 40 Years
of success in new technologies that have
come out from Texas ins standpoint uh
I've been involved primarily only about
10 years because I came across from
National stor acquisition but it's been
enlightening to work with MTL and the
one word I have to say for them is micro
system which is part of their name it's
spanning from devices through systems
and software and so forth that's one of
the attractions that we have for we've
gained benefit from looking at devices
our Gan technology which is now
commercialized had roots in MIT and MTL
and then the other aspect of it is the
ecosystem that we get access to from a
Technologies and research standpoint but
also from the other relationships that
MTL has and MIT has with other companies
that maybe are customers for us and had
three-way collaborations and research
which have been very useful from
anywhere from medical and in industrial
applications and so forth uh we look
forward to what MTL can do next we're
looking forward to the life sciences if
anybody was here yesterday and how that
works out with our CTO Dr Ahmad bahai
and so again congratulations on your 40
years and thank you for all the support
and Technologies over the
years yeah thanks to all of our speakers
um and also I would like to take this
opportunity to thank all the friends
from all the mck members for their uh
longstanding supports to MTL thank
you um so next we'll begin an very
exciting session that highlights the
remarkable work of the Next Generation
leaders and innovators emerging from MTL
uh so this is an excellent opportunity
for you to see The Cutting Edge research
and uh ideas uh shaping the future of
microelectronic Technologies so for the
first part of this session uh I am
thrilled to welcome four MTL young
professors uh let me introduce them the
first one is uh Gan Kim uh Jan is the
associate professor in both the
department of mechanical engineering and
also mechanical science and engineering
uh Jan also explores the new uh
Frontiers in material Innovation and
then we will have Kevin O'Brien Kevin is
the associate professor in the
department of electrical engineering and
computer science uh innovating in the
wave engineering and also
electromagnetics uh our third speaker is
saraj Shima so he's an assistant
professor uh also in the electrical
engineering and computer science
department uh he contributes to
groundbreaking work in electronic
devices uh last but not the least uh we
have Joe kasamento uh Joe is an assist
assistant professor in the department of
uh Material Science and Engineering uh
his research is tackling the critical
challenges in Advanced Materials uh so
let's give a warm welcome to these
speakers uh as they share their
inspiring work let's start from gan
[Applause]
okay thank you so much for having me
here uh I am 10 years older than Mt so
so caliz me as a young faculty member
I'm I really appreciate that so and yeah
it's my 10th year in MIT and um today
I'd like to yeah so I'd like to
introduce our my La of you know activity
on material Innovation for Next gener 3D
integration so I put it uh the the title
as a simless wher free monel to 3D so
what I'm going to talk about today is
why material Innovation is so so so
important to to build three dimensional
chips okay so please have a look at this
uh 3dh so you know if you're um the
member of MTL you must you know you
should be very familiar with this you
know uh right now we don't have the uh
you know uh space for for for um
integrating the memory and logic anymore
and we try to go go vertically also for
efficient communication between logic
and memory you know instead of going
laterally we want to go vertically so to
do so conventional way to
um should I do
this okay so I better do
this okay so conventional way to uh
integrate the chips vertically is all
most of cases will be done by tsv
through silicon VR process right the
reason is that first in order for you to
have high quality high performance
devices you would need to have single
crystalling devices in order for you to
have a single cryst devices you need to
have single cry wafer so wafer is
necessary building block for for for uh
having the high quality logic and memory
materials on it after that you really
want to vertically connect them each
other then you cannot help but dring the
hole through the wafer like like you can
see here here that is called the uh
where is my CER yeah called the uh you
know tsp process we utilize tsv process
through the whole through the wafer we
fill the Gap with the copper then by
doing so um it you know we are able to
stack the chip vertically but there's
ton of ton of
limitation especially there's a
limitation alignment because you finish
the chip already you finish the chip
already then you would need to align
each chip area each device so alignment
problem Sor not only that stacking the
chip during the hold through the wafer
is is not is is not trivial task so we
already know this is really problematic
process but there there's no other way
to do so but you know the architect
architecture Community they have been
calculating what's going to happen if we
connect the chip without having any rfer
what if we make some sub Micron you know
pitch interconnect among the among the
devices then what they found is that
they could substantially reduce the
power others are made to lower and they
could boost the performance others
augmented to higher so that has been
calculated already that has been
simulated already but the
community you know do not have the much
option to do this wafer free mon 3
integration when I say mon 3D
integration that means you do the 3D
integration without having any wafer
okay so there's option for you know mon
3D integration but it's not easy so in
order for us to do the W for free thre
Dimension integration you know this
could be done by two different method
again you really want to do the monor 3D
of a single Crystal material to make a
advanced logic transistor okay to do so
you need to grow you would you may be
able to grow single crystalline Channel
material on the amers on the back end of
the line finish it wafer or you may want
to transfer single crystalling device
material from other wafer to the another
wafer and and in this case you peel off
the active device layer for from one one
other wafer to the finished electron
circuitry what is so special about this
here's the thing monol the integration
you provide the material first on the
circuit Tre that's a key you provide the
material first on the circuit Tre then
you can align your devices towards the
underlying circuitry compared to tsv
technique this could
enable fine featured interconnect up to
the hundreds of nanometer which is
amazing but big challenges material
first how can you grow single Crystal
material on back end of the line finish
wafer the surface of B wafer V fin wafer
is composed of Amo Force insulate
and poly chring metal interconnect how
can you grow inry material on it right
that is a big question also how can you
grow single cryst material at the
temperature lower than
400° where the copper inter interconnect
could survive
right so this already you know sounds
like really really tough task then then
okay then you may want to peel off the
circuit Tre or peel off the material
then transfer onto circuit
this sounds little easier than grow okay
so here's a strategy that we do in in
microed MIT right
so on the left hand side I demonstrate
the our you know schematics about the
growth based monity 3D integration
meaning that if you control the kinetics
and thermodynamics during the growth you
can really grow single cryst material on
armorers here here's a very reap idea if
you comine the nucleation in very narrow
small area selectively that you can
comine the nuclei inside this this
trench okay so you have a single nuclear
in one trench then this trench is small
enough that you can just do a little bit
of lateral growth then you could do the
grand boundary free perfect single Mater
onop this is the first demonstration of
of growing single cryst oners at a
temperature lower than 400° C like I
mentioned if we secure this technology
you could do the really growth based mon
3 integration meaning that you can stack
the chip by the growth you don't have to
bond you don't have to drill the hole
through the wafer another way to do so
is you grow perfect s material on the
substrate that you can peel them off it
can transfer as you just have seen it if
you have graphing Cod is sub straight
then you can still do the epex by
following the underlying softs Crystal
information this is what it is so even
if there's a monin you can still do the
epital growth on graphine on the
substrate then why B you do this if you
once you grow perfect s material on
graphine you can peel them off okay this
technique has been uh you know
discovered in in 2015 MIT then uh we
found the way to utilize it for the mon
integration as you can see we grow
single material on graphine then we peel
them off this sing material could be gum
Mar IND Force any 35 any3 nitrate gum
nitrate alumium nitrate and complex
oxide lithium lithium niobate or or or
lithium tantalite all sorts of compound
material could be grown grapping and
paed off okay then here the uh you know
impact area of this this our unique mon
3D technique so by utilizing this
confined growth technique and remote app
technique you could make the 3D logic
and memory by The Grow now by the tsp
also you could do the AI Hardware
Advanced AI Hardware by stacking by
stacking the uh you know memory and
logic in very in in in close Manner and
you can can revolutionize display
technology as well because you could do
the RGB stacking so then you can do the
arv kind of micity system and also you
can produce ultra thin single membrane
that can you can wear that Ultra
membrane on your body or you can
Revolution photonics and sensing so I'm
going to briefly touch upon all of this
technology we have developed so far or
this six different areas based on our
monolitic 3D integration scheme which is
completely based on Material Science
okay so here you're looking at the first
demonstration of vertical seos done by
the grow not by the stacking the wafer
you're looking at the uh you know MOS
pimos single CST underneath by the grow
on on half oxide cor silicon wafer then
we fin
the integration of pimos pimos on it
then we we encapsulate this with the
oxide then we grow perfect single
crystalline OS again on top okay this
integration was done just simply by the
growth at the temperature L 400 Dees is
all the circuit is survived so then we
are able to demonstrate foros OS pimos
you can already tell by utilizing this
you can double the denser of the
transistor right so this is just
beginning of you know showing the impact
of this growth based monolith 3
integration so what could happen in the
future you could you could build the
threedimensional memory right so like
hbm currently to to construct hbm what
needs to happen is that you would need
to thin down the wafer after the
integration Dam on Silicon wafer you
drill the ho through the wafer you you
do the copper interconnect and
bonding tsp process still problematic
maximum Stacks that you can make is 12
stack that was recently done by SK heix
but still is not enough for AI operation
okay so for that for that if you can
utilize this technique mon 3D by the
growth you can just have a DM stack by
the grow by The Grow then how could you
make this kind DM stack conventional DM
stack you cannot do conventional DM St
all you got to do is to replace
our high electric with Ferro electric
High K di electrics that way you can
convert convert this transistor in onto
onto pH electric memory then you can
construct Chamis DRM out of it then you
can consecu speack them out by the grow
not by the transfer not by the tsv also
you could do the same process to have
the logic transistor vertically on and
on not by the transfer by The Grow okay
but here one thing that you you could
consider is a hit spreader right here's
the thing logic transistor generate a
ton of hit but if you only work with a
membranes you can put the heat spreader
right next to the membrane so that you
can effectively you know dissipate the
heat out of it so you may be able to
stack the logic consecutively that is
kind of exciting feature that we are
developing right now also AI solution so
in the industry in order to um
enhance the performance of AI chip what
they're trying to do is to put the logic
and memory close each other just keeping
the vman Computing method they just try
to put them together and closure each
other which is called the pin processing
in memory when they tape out the chip
when they tape out the logic transistor
no no when they tap the tape out the dam
they take out some portion of DRM then
replace that portion with the logic
transistor so then you can physically
put them together but you have to
sacrifice the area what this could be
done by the our method you can do memory
logic memory logic alteration by the
growth all right so that can be done
also our collaborator Pro s Li in
Georgia calculated even before the data
going out of the Asam if you can stack
Asam and logic together then you may not
need you may not need Advanced node
transistor for AI chip so here's a very
simple Ben Benchmark here you know um by
utiliz advanc no transist if you
construct AI chip which is mvidia Chip
it's uh band with is one t per second
but by utilizing this concept SRAM and
logic vertically stack that you could do
you could you could have a water made to
higher bandwidth even utilizing Lego
transistor that is the beauty of
exploring monolitic 3 integration okay
so that's my point also my lab is
working on you know non-conventional you
know for non noral Computing method
where we utilize a synapsis to do some
you know NE Computing task you know I
list up here if you hear about neic
Computing Computing memory in memory
Computing physical unit they're all same
time at least to us and the device for
this is nonvolatile memory or memory
sech or rram that's kind of like a
devices so here uh what we do is you so
far we've been developing Advan memoris
devices to to have the actual inference
task but so far because of these three
problems we have we are not able to
build the actual inference machine the
thing is that this switching mechanism
of nonb time memory is based on
stochastic you know Behavior so it's
very hard to have the uh you know
reliable switching operation also by
because of that there's a reduced
accuracy also the weight that you
register on the artificial synapsis
easily Decay because that's the nature
of the material so recently we try to
not utilize this you know memory
resource or RM or other number time
memory for this so so we thinking back
we think back you know why do we need to
program the arrays to do the inference
task what's the meaning of inference
task inference task means you already
know the
information information so you can
already register the wave value in
existing geometry you don't have to
program it if you utilize this kind of a
um register at the crossbar then you can
have super accurate stable inference
test we already demonstrate 8bit
operation of this AI Hardware that is
the best performance that has been ever
shown so so we point is that if you
point that you do not need to program
the race you can just pre-register the
pro program register then you can do the
inference test with very very high
accuracy that's kind of like air harder
that we are doing my le MIT next is
display based on mon3 integration like
like I mentioned current micro display
technology uh for especially for the
weable like arvr application you would
need to have 5,000
PPI display pixel density PPI 5,000 ppi
is needed but conventional L arrangement
of the chip chip RGB chip doesn't work
because of the you know um accuracy
alignment accuracy also manufactur
ability my lab try to utilize our remote
epex concept to do the monity 3D
integration by the transfer as you can
see Here We Grow red green blue LEDs on
graphing and peel them off we simply
stack them up first we transfer red LED
material that we integrate then we align
them each other by using mon inte ation
so with this we are able to
um based on that we are able to you know
collect all the pis in in MIT not only
for the micro LEDs but also for the QD
LEDs and and so on we recently launched
the MIT program on small display so I
hope you get an attention on this okay
so these are the sort of like um you
know area that we can visit by utilizing
this mon 3D integration lastly I'd like
to emphasize that by having this single
free membrane you can also revolutionize
the wear of electronics because you can
have perfect synch and Chip you can wear
that chip on the body impact is huge so
here I try to you know demonstrate the
impact of this free sending membrane by
the remote thexy impact of confined
growth to the mon through the
integration by the growth okay these are
my team at MIT my lab and they are
working hard to make this progress and
we have the uh three spin off one is for
the gum nital free membrane and the
other is this monity 3D integration by
the grows the third company is micro
companies okay so thank you so much for
your
attention so let's uh thank the speaker
again thank
[Applause]
you maybe we can take uh one or two
quick questions if there are
any excuse me
oh it's on the screen
oh
use oh absolutely yeah we use this for
silicon carb gum nitrate can you sub do
before of course absolutely yeah you can
do the grow you can peel off silicon
carbine you can p up G nitr yeah you for
anything great so if you have more
questions uh please uh feel free to come
to J Juan uh after the session and then
uh a lot of interesting discussions
thank
you so our next speaker is Kevin
O'Brien um so I'm really excited to be
here at at the MTL 40th anniversary to
talk about the research in my group the
uh Quantum coherent Electronics
group so uh you may have gone to the the
quantum track earlier and uh seen um
will Oliver's really nice analogy for
the state at which Quantum Computing is
at where um we're essentially at the
stage where um right after the first uh
right flyer is taking flight and uh the
industry is progressing the community is
progressing towards um useful commercial
Quantum computation but we're you know
closer to the to the right flyer than to
the the jumbo jet um so the question is
what fundamental science and engineering
advances do we need to to get there and
and that's what is um of interest in my
group particular um I'm really
interested in what are the fundamental
limits on device performance imposed by
the rules of quantum mechanics and how
can we actually not just know what these
limits are but how can we actually
engineer devices fabricate them measure
them to reach these limits and then can
those limits be surpassed are those
actually the real the real limits can
you figure out uh better ways to to um
surpass these um and I want to give a
couple examples um so for example can
Cubit readout be 10 times faster
um making Cubit read out fast is is
really important because right now
cubits are very lossy they decohere they
interact with their environment so to
realize a large scale error corrected
quantum computer you need to measure
these cubits and then perform
Corrections on them and the time it
takes to measure is a time in which
you're not doing this error correction
so it's it's important to measure them
very fast so the way you measure cubits
right now um I won't go into like all
all the all the physics of it but you B
basically have your Cubit you couple it
to a resonator for example with a
capacitor and the resonator will change
frequency depending on the state of the
Cubit then you send in a microwave pulse
or a microwave signal and measure the
phase associated with that resonator and
then that tells you the Cubit State and
right now this takes around 50 NCS which
is pretty good but not not where we want
to be so if you look at how the SNR of
this process scales it scales both with
the Decay rate of the resonator so how
large the resonator's linewidth is then
you can use a faster pulse and also with
the nonlinearity of this system meaning
like how much your cubit's response
changes in response to uh um additional
photons and the way if you look at the
different parameters of this scaling um
you might want to try making Cubit
readout Faster by just just driving it
harder using a stronger tone but that
excites your Cubit into some spous
states which isn't a good uh way of of
of doing it but if you increase the
nonlinearity and increase the the uh
Decay rate of your resonance
then you can increase your readout speed
in an unbounded way so this is what
we're interested in in doing and the way
that we've uh proposed uh to do this is
we develop kind of a cool type of uh
circuit called a a a Corton a purely
nonlinear coupler this is essentially if
you have a spring and a mass two masses
instead of putting a spring in the
middle just a normal spring we put this
this nonlinear spring which acts like
something that has infinite inductance
but it still gives you that type of
coupling you need for Cubit readout and
and this breaks the the trade-off that
you normally have in increasing this the
strength of this nonlinearity so we
proposed this device and we recently
experimentally demonstrated this and it
has the strongest nonlinearity the
strongest nonlinear light matter uh
interactions that's ever been measured
in any system including superconductors
and and you know all the all the other
systems uh which we think is really
exciting and now we're working towards
um using this for cubit readout to
instead of couple together two cubits to
couple together a cubit and a resonator
and use this to um uh realize 10x faster
than state-of-the-art readout which you
could check out our paper if you're
interested in um another problem that's
uh of of quite a lot of interest to
myself and my group is how well can you
amplify how well can you measure uh
Quantum signals using this super
conducting cubic platform and can we
reach the ultimate limits imposed by
quantum mechanics and it turns out that
indeed we can um and the the trick and
doing this over a broad bandwidth and
the trick is really matching the modes
of the free space to the modes of your
amplifier and using something called
flate Theory and this allows us to make
uh amplifiers that have near zero
dissipation and extremely high Quantum
efficiency uh these were fabricated at
MIT lincol laboratory in their sill
Foundry and when we characterize them we
find that uh intrinsic Quantum
efficiency of these amp amplifiers is is
around
98% now we also want to build these in
mit. Nano uh for a couple reasons one uh
shipping it out to a Foundry is is is
good especially if The Foundry is really
good like MIT lincol laboratory but it's
also good to have students involved in
the process to train the future
Workforce and it and just something
magical happens when you unleash
students on a problem and they can
really figure out tune all the knobs and
and and and figure out what's going on
so we developing in collaboration with
Will Oliver's group a 6 and 8 in uh
superc conducting Cubit process in mit.
Nano um we're using a lot of
state-of-the-art process Metrology
similar to what one does in the seos
industry uh for example uh we'll make
test Wafers of of of 80 40,000 880,000
Justice injunctions room temperature
probing of all of these and we're able
to get 100% yield in um for some of the
design parameters and then um we can get
less than 1% % Junction relative
standard deviation uniformity this is
important for precise targeting of
cubits and precise targeting of of of
amplifiers reducing their um Ripple um
so as a function of the different
Junction areas we can get these
state-of-the-art numbers in in mit. Nano
um you can also uh fabricate devices uh
for example this is an amplifier showing
over 20 DB gain um near Quantum limited
noise performance fabricated in in mit.
Nano um um one and you know we were
asked to kind of give our our our vision
and and philosophy so I want to one
thing that
um as when I'm teaching electrical
engineering one thing that I always find
challenging is the kind of high barrier
to entry I think um people find this a
lot in Hardware Fields where you know in
software students can just go download a
GitHub repo and be doing
state-of-the-art machine learning but in
you know Hardware it's often more
expensive uh more challenging so I find
that in research as well I think that
developing open- Source uh Eda for
Quantum is is very important um and you
know this isn't something just thought
by me a lot of companies like uh IBM has
kis kit kis kit metal uh other company
um other groups have thing tools like SC
cubits um I think this is very important
for increasing the accessibility of
quantum and allowing rapid Innovation um
in that in that field so one of our
contributions to this was developing an
open- Source um uh harmonic balance
Simulator for uh parametric processes
and superc conducting circuits which is
10,000 times faster than the uh
typically used open source software uh
it's used by MIT Google NIS reik and
others and we also you know I'm not
against commercial Eda vendors by any
means we collaborate with um uh with
kyite to uh improve their Eda tools and
and compare them and and really build a
powerful uh uh ecosystem for um
simulating Quantum systems
um so with that I want to um acknowledge
my my research group acknowledge the
funders and also um you know thank the
audience and and hopefully have time for
a couple questions thank
you so a few questions for
Kevin no questions okay that's thank Uh
Kevin
again thank
you our next speaker is Chima hi
everyone thanks for having me so my
group works on F electric
micronics where we try to re reimagine
or redesign integrated circuit building
blocks towards more energy efficient and
energy autonomous microelectronics so by
integrated circuit building blocks we
mean things like transistors capacitors
diodes things of that nature so the
motivation behind my group's work is
trying to address Energy Grand
challenges but from a microelectronics
perspective so one way we could think
about that is looking at the energ
demands from Computing over the years
and we see that Computing right now is
somewhere between 5 and 10% of the
global energy or electricity demand but
the concerning trend is is Computing is
exponentially Rising while our worldwide
energy production is only linearly
increasing so we'll obviously come at an
impass pretty soon which calls for the
need for new paradigms of
computing and the way we typically think
about that is mors law as we make
transistors smaller and smaller we make
them more energy efficient and now we
could have more energy efficient
Computing but there's a certain limit to
how much device miniaturization we could
do so
here we're going to I'm going to show a
brief result later on on how F electrics
could be inserted into the transistor
and have us have help us have a lot more
energy efficient transistor
operation and this is towards a broader
goal of getting an adual switch or just
as low power switch as possible another
aspect of where this concerning trend of
exponential rise in energy consumption
from microelectronics comes from is
actually from the fact that our
Computing demand from AI has been
outpacing our increase in in normal
transistor Energy Efficiency operation
so if we're requiring a lot more
Computing than our Energy Efficiency is
rising uh that's where this kind of
increased energy consumption comes from
so we're ALS we're also going to want to
kind of develop new forms of AI Hardware
which is nicely summarized by these
papers here AI Hardware has this energy
problem because we're trying to use
classical transistors so can we
design new analog neural network
Hardware or other types of designs that
allow us to compute better for these
neural networks
and another maybe underrepresented
aspect of where this energy demand comes
from is the fact that we have all these
Internet of Things devices between
smartphones smart watches Etc and we're
eventually going to want them all to be
self-powered if possible so that means
we're going to need to have sensing
energy storage energy harvesting all
integrated on chip and the way we
typically people think about energy
storage on chip is micro super
capacitors or micro batteries but those
have a lot of integration challenges and
it turns out that we could have
electrostatic capacitors that actually
could compete with lithium ion micro
batteries iies and other commercial
Technologies so all of these examples
are go into how F electrics could help
um improve the performance of those
incumbent Technologies so first I just
wanted to show like kind of the big
vision of our group which on the left
I'm just highlighting all of the
different ways in which faral electrics
could be integrated into different
devices and give you more energy
efficient operation so I'll show one
example of for logic we could integrate
the fact that we could scale down F
electrics to the atomic scale thickness
and induce a effect known as a negative
capacitance effect again really energy
efficient transistor operation we'll be
showing some results on how we could
build a really highly scalable analog AI
Hardware based on F electrics by
leveraging their intrinsic diode effect
and um as Professor Kim mentioned
there's a lot of other exciting
opportunities for integrating fer
electrics with logic and having these
stacked high band withd memories or
compute near memory rather than Compu in
memory and then on the other side of the
coin we have all of these different
Energy Technologies or quote unquote
more than
paradigms we could leverage with ferric
so again ferric is a really really
versatile phenomena I'm not getting into
the specifics but basically in a ferric
you could apply an electric field and
tune an intrinsic dipole in your unit
cell up and down so it's really
promising for any charge based device so
it could respond to touch for through
the p Electric effect it could respond
to temperature through the py electric
effect it could convert waste heat into
energy which then could cool down your
ship through the electrocaloric effect
and it could even respond to light
through the bulk fot of the take effect
intrinsic to fer Electrics so again fire
electric is such a versatile phenomenon
and it gives you there's probably no
other material system that I could think
of that can enable all of these
different Technologies from the same
material class or material system so
because of that and another key aspect
of what we do is we integrate everything
with low temperature Atomic layer
deposition so Professor Kim was just
mentioning how important it is that
everything we do if we want to be
relevant for microelectronics and 3D
integration we need to be working at low
temperatures at the wafer scale and also
the nice aspect of Atomic layer
deposition is 3D conformal so now you
could imagine filling 3D shapes or gate
allaround transistors
Etc and that's again inspired by
Professor Kim's Vision of 3D uh
monolithic integration we could also
Imagine a future where a lot of these
different aspects are improved with fer
electric so it's very complimentary to
all the work done in the semiconductor
space we're just engineering the
dialectric which could then fit in with
whatever backend of the line
semiconductor that's being developed
whether it be 2D materials or oxides or
Gan we can inte integrate these f
electrics for either you know high
frequency performance memory logic AI
Hardware even these Energy
Technologies so the key aspect of our
group we're we're really specializing or
focusing on Al halfs of chum monoxide
fire electric in films why is that
because that's the dialectric already
used in today's logic transistors and
Dam capacitors so nothing has to change
from a Foundry process so this is what
allows us to whatever research result we
achieve we could quickly translate it to
either MIT Lincoln Laboratories or a
Foundry and um see the you know high
volume manufacturing
benefits
so for today's talk I'm just going to
briefly briefly introduce um how we
could replace the conventional
dialectric using all of these integrated
circuit building blocks with a fer
electric and show how you get improved
performance so I'll first start off with
the transistor where we replace the
conventional High K dialectric apum
oxide with a quote unquote negative K or
negative permitivity ferroelectric and
see ultra low power logic transistor
operation then I'll briefly touch on a
recent result where we go from the
classic again whenever when anyone
thinks about energy storage they usually
thinking about electrochemistry in the
form of micro batteries or super
capacitors can we go from
electrochemical to electrostatic
paradigms for energy storage and not
only have ultra high energy density but
have ultra high power density because
electrostatic capacitors could be
charged and discharged much
faster in terms of the memorist I'll be
showing that the conventional technology
that's used in rram and a lot of two
terminal devices today are based on are
based on defective switch or defective
filamentary formation can we instead
have a collective phenomena inherent to
your unit cell that won't have the same
variability issues as R and then the
last result is a recent results from our
group where we could see we have really
high not just onoff ratio but also
rectification and rectification is an
often underreported aspect of developing
these non-volatile memories for computer
memory arrays and that allows us to have
the most array scalable AI Hardware so
in each of these cases you could think
of we're we're transforming from an old
Paradigm and we're just making a very
very minor change to get a new one we're
either going from high K dialectric to
Nega k f electrics from Collective from
defective to Collective switching
phenomena but again it's all in the same
material this was already half monoxide
based this was already half new monoxide
based
Etc so I'll first start off with the
transistor example um just in the
interest of time I won't really explain
the kind of materials and physics behind
it but just know that it is actually
possible to put one material on top of
another so typically on top of S2 we
always have this native oxide on top of
silicon we also have this native S2
which depending on your process is
around 8 ANM thickness we can actually
add our halfs or corium oxide material
on top of it and have larger capacitance
than we started with so this is what we
refer to as a negative capacitance
effect and because of this we're not
changing the physical thickness than
what's in today's Capac in today's
transistor gate stack so we see no
Mobility leakage or reliability
degradation compared to what the
incumbent technology is while getting
all the benefits of having higher
capacitance which namely is you're
allowed to operate your transistor at
lower lower
power so here's just comparing our haum
zonum oxide based gate stack compared to
Conventional technology today um and you
can see that our leakage is the same
because we're not changing the physical
thickness so we have the same tunneling
and because of that we're able to
achieve this the same leakage current
but at much lower eot and the same
Mobility at much lower eot without
having the typical transport
degradations that others see when they
try to thin down their
S2 um we've integrated this into MIT
Lincoln laboratory because again we're
using the same materials the same atomic
layer deposition technique that's used
to today so even though Lincoln MIT
Lincoln lab goes down to 90 NM gate
length transistors we're able to match
the transconductance scene in much more
advanced transistor Technologies so
we're actually going to be working with
these foundaries now to integrate our
material into these more advanced gate
lengths to actually see these record
setting trans conductance values so
again this is all derived from the fact
that we're getting this capacitance
boost without having any transport
degradation so our carrier velocity is
not degraded so GM is a nice metric for
us to look at we also could compare the
I on ey off Behavior again at very very
more you know Legacy nodes compared to
the more advanced nodes these aren't
even the advanced nodes but just as a
comparison we're getting a multiple node
technology boost integrating our gate di
electric material compared to tsmc IBM
and other foundaries so this again shows
and again these Lincoln laboratory
transistors don't even have the strain
silicon or rour strain or the other
bells and whistles that give you
improved eye on eye off performance but
just from purely the gate stack changing
it from this high K to negative K
dialectric we get all these performance
benefits and in terms of the impact we
made in foundaries like I mentioned
we've been integrated into MIT Lincoln
Laboratories prototyping Foundry Samsung
Electronics integrated this exact same
Gat stack into their finfet process and
show that they're getting the limit of
60 MTS per decade subdural swing um and
we've been highlighted in a recent
review from Intel on the uh 75th
anniversary of the transistor as this is
the future for uh more energy efficient
transistor performance and we'll be
working with more foundaries to
integrate these into more advanced
transistor geometries so the nice thing
about this skate dialectric is it's very
flexible platform in the sense that no
matter where technology goes in the
future where whether we have planer
transistors finfets Nano sheets stack
Nanos sheets or we go from Silicon to 2D
every transistor will need a dialectric
so we could still use this negative
capacitance effect to increase the
capacitance and have lower power
operation and then just a quick quick
result on the capacitor I'll just all I
want to say is that we did a lot of
material science engineering to increase
um the performance of these capacitors
the main thing we overcame like in the
last case we overcame the leakage eot
tradeoff and dialectric materials here
we overcame the fact that primitivity
and breakdown strength tend to fall on
this uh empirical line where your
breakdown strength is proportional to
the permitivity to the minus one half
power but if you think of the energy
storage as 1 half CV squar pretty much
all di electrics will cancel out but if
we could actually boost the permitivity
or the capacitance of our materials
without sacrificing the breakdown we
could actually have breakthrough energy
storage performance and it turns out we
do we actually have you know orders of
magnitude higher energy storage and
power density than any other
electrostatic Paradigm and we're 100
million times faster than a commercial
lithium microbattery while just being
one order of magnitude away in energy
density so we're starting to close the
gap on a commercial lithium microbattery
so now you can imagine a phone that
charges in a microsecond or a nanc the
only issue is it'll you'll have to
recharge it a little more often than a
commercial lithium ion so we're still
looking at how to close this Gap and how
to scale up so with that I'll I'll stop
right here but I just wanted to mention
that again we could reimagine all these
different integrated circuit Elements by
replacing the dialectric with the fer
electric um um there's a result on a mem
we have a result on the F electric diode
um that also gives kind of breakthrough
results in terms of rectifying ratio and
array scalability for computer memory
arrays and um with that I'll stop here
it just allows us now to really build
this 3D integrated Ship by integrating
our fer electrics with different
semiconductors by working with all the
great groups on campus here at MIT
working on semiconductors and we could
achieve all these different
functionalities with fer electrics
thanks
thank you for sharing all the exciting
results um do we have any question for
S okay if you have any question please
talk to him thank you uh our last
speaker of this session is uh Joel
kaso do you have a slide thank you
okay hi everyone so I'm very happy to be
here today to talk to you about what we
think are some of the needed Innovations
for material syntheses and devices in
the case of nitride semiconductors and
all the Technologies we think we can
impact so as we know in Innovation
continues we know that today a lot of
the uh transitions deviate just from
lateral scaling in Mo's law and as we
look towards actually chiplet
diversification and 3dh I think this
actually is a really good opportunity
for new materials integration where you
where you can now not have to consider
well I have to invent my new materials
on the latest node we can design each
node based on a certain functionality so
hopefully this is what I think could be
a self-fulfilling prophecy so I always
viewed that new materials can lead to
new circuits so hopefully this is a time
where we can actually be complimentary
in materials
design one of so the general tricks we
have our at our disposal from a direct
growth both perspectives some of them
are outlined here right so the case a is
kind of home up a taxi where everything
works out well you have the same last
parameter that usually doesn't happen
case b is when the atoms are strained a
little bit but the interface is still
pristine this is usually what happens a
lot Case C is an exaggerated case where
you know you don't have the right
crystal or lattice Arrangement so you
break bonds at these interface and
you'll form the threading defects so
from a sythesis perspective we always
want to try to either eliminate this
case or basically constrain the
thickness the other one is
an area that Professor Kim mentioned
where you can use a mask and and lateral
laterally overgrow from a selected area
so we're hoping from a new materials
perspective what we need to do is be
able to suppress these dislocations and
be able to grow thicknesses let's say 2
nanometers to two microns be able to
control buffer layer thicknesses and
also be able to do this in ways where
you can control doping at low
temperatures which is generally hard to
do with in the nitride semiconductor
ecosystem so if we can if we can solve
this there's a lot of Technologies you
think we can impact and here here are
some examples that that I'll describe
where we're talking about Gan devices so
Gans a wonderful material as everybody
knows where you have applications
ranging from 10 kilovolts down to 10
volts as you look at 3dh and different
system designs right uh on on chip
voltage voltage regulation heat
management right High thermal
conductivity of Gan is important a lot
of the limitations we have are by
conventional epitaxy techniques like
mocvd you're going to form a lot of
threading dislocations at this interface
and that sets a thickness limit for your
buffer layer that you before the actual
Crystal will crack and relieve stress
these dislocations are also a source of
leakage current in your in your high
voltage diodes this is also an example
of work that's come out of Intel where
they're using layer transfer to again
grow Gan at 900 C or above by mocvd and
so that that changes their integration
schemes so it' be great if we could have
the same epot taxi material deposited a
C okay one one aspect we're really
exciting and things I worked on during
my PhD as well was sort of the the front
end modules right so this is Gan for Gan
based hemps for the high power let's say
w band 94 GHz and higher frequencies
right so this is your monolithic
microwave integrated circuit for the
base station applications where these
new materials and this is the case of
sorry this is the case of aluminum
Scandium nitride where we're adding
alloing Scandium to aln you have a
really new design space of band Gap and
lattice parameter it's really important
for photonics that you haven't had in
the traditional nitride family because
of the difference now you have new
material properties you have a change in
spontaneous and pzo electric
polarization you're actually changing
the charge density in your channel right
so this is a new way to engineer devices
compared to the commercial aluminum
Gallum nitride barrier layers that are
used in lateral devices and the biggest
thing that this buys you other than in
potentially inreased reliability from
from strain engineering is the fact that
you can overcome potential limits which
has been hypothesized in this paper is
that you can overcome the Bode Fano
limit because you can use this higher
current density you can draw your load
line differently and so it's projected
that we're not even near the material
limits yet and that using new materials
like aluminum Scandium nitride in the
existing metal polar device geometries
can actually even outperform all the
great work that's being done on the N
poar hemp at 94 GHz currently
the other is thinking about just new
device designed right so we have new
materials that we're working on in our
group in addition to actually new
functionalities enabled by the new
properties so building on what Professor
Chima said before is that we have now
Fair electricity and also the nitrides
that's a relatively new phenomenon in
nitride semiconductors so what we can
see here is Guided by simulation this is
where you forming your electron Channel
you can utilize this new material so
this is aluminum scum nitrite in the
barrier layer of the lateral hemp you
you're getting up to 3.5 amps per
millimeter 4 amps per millim on current
densities and these devices are are are
not passivated either so there's a lot
of room for improvement as well and with
these new material properties you start
seeing some memory Windows some
threshold voltage tunability uh you
actually you're also seeing sub 60 molt
per decade sub threshold slopes at room
temperature so we believe there's a lot
of nice opportunities in the ferel
electric ecosystem here where you can
really just rethink electrostatics
generally right and actually maybe even
ways that can combat short Channel
effects that are known in nitride
semiconductors where you get the
electron uh saturation velocity rollof
we also think that utilizing these new
materials is a way to actually have
improve your gain at high frequency
Beyond just the uh device scaling and
the tricks that we play to enhance trans
conductance so we're really excited
about this new type of device we coined
the the Ferro
hemp the other area that I'm really
excited about is actually the new
materials new deposition schemes for
silicon photonics right we know there's
a there's a big demand for high-speed
data transmission right so whether it's
Optical interconnects wave guides so the
current state-ofthe-art is thin foam
lithium Nate and while there's been a
lot of revolutionary advances in the
technology over time lithium nabate
itself is not without its challenges
right it's generally an ion implantation
a smart cut process which Li which
limits your thickness and your
wavelength range right it's not easy to
integrate on Silicon directly so we have
materials like aluminum Scandium nitride
where they they have even higher band
Gap than lithium nabate and we can grow
them directly on Silicon so we believe
that this is really a platform that
could revelage nonlinear Optics right
these are some measurements here that
were done by collaboration of far and
R's group at Cornell that's showing you
can get really large enhancement in the
nonlinear Optical coefficient compared
to aluminum nitrite so other groups are
seeing this we think this is a big
opportunity this is a very uh exciting
area right now
the other the other aspect to at the
other end of the RF front modules right
so the Acoustics and integration on RFS
SOI is looking at new materials for the
space what was maybe not as known at the
time was a lot of a lot of the
Innovations Came From A Material Science
perspective people were looking for
elements to increase the bandwidth right
by increasing this is your material
figure Merit roughly ignoring the
quality Factor right this is KT s so it
gives you larger bandwidth and more and
better outof band rejection in your
resonator so people showed is you had a
large increase in the Paso Electric
coefficient boost which was interesting
because one of the plots that we made
was to try to show well fundamentally
what materials do you need right you
want a more compliant bond which is more
pzo electric but that also hurts your
stiffness right for a resonator you want
it to be very stiff analogy someone gave
me is that you're stretching a tarp over
the length of the football field and
that cannot bend more than a millimeter
was was that was the analogy someone
gave me so we believe if you think
aluminum scum nit was great for
resonators which it is it's already
commercialized we have ideas for new
nitrides that are going to do even
better than aluminum scanning
nitride so how so how are we going to do
this and the answer sounds uh simple in
pract simple in practice but it's hard
sorry simple in theory but it's hard in
practice is actually utilizing the
periodic table so nitrides revolutionary
progress in the last 30 years but we
believe there's a lot of legs left by
expanding the elements that we have at
our disposal right for the last 30 years
we're mostly here as we expand into new
elements and even new Crystal
chemistries we believe this is going to
be very fertile ground for the
combination of Material Science and Rich
physics where we can integrate new
materials even such as nitride perides
and we can make the nitrides look like
oxides in a
way so these are these are just some
examples showing about how we're going
about this or how we how we going about
the epaxial growth at low temperatures
with these new chemistries so this is an
example of a project IED where we're
actually using magnetron sputter epitaxy
to grow aluminum boron nitride this is a
semiconductor material with a greater
than 5.5 EV band Gap and we did this at
only 300C so you getting Crystal quality
comparable ToBD at much lower
temperatures and we can overcome the
traditional limits associated with
growth for nitride semiconductors where
we can get breakdown voltages in excess
of 8 megga volts per centimeter and
pristine surface morphology right this
is something that you can't do
commercially with with Mo cvd on
it another aspect ECT is just thinking
outside the box for new material
synthesis this is an example where we
actually used uh ther thermal epitaxy
this is MBE we grew a nitride
semiconductor with no plasma just
nitrogen gas this is the first time it's
ever been done we're actually showing
that depending on our synthesis we can
actually catalyze nitrogen Bond so a lot
of new opportunities here to think
outside the box and how do we just
engineer micr structure in new compounds
so we're so we're really excited about
the about the possibilities here
the other is actually looking forward
into Al there old saying if if it can be
done by Al it will be done by Al so
we're actually looking at um can we
actually change the form factor for
nitride devices right can we put these
polarization induced channels anywhere
right and then can you for acoustic
devices can you integrate multiple
frequency bands on the same chip so this
is an example of work that we've done in
MIT Nano where this is truly cais
oriented Gan grown at only 250° C and
this case this was on Sapphire so we
believe that this is actually a
promising First Step again for lower
temperature
deposition so the one thing I wanted to
say and I'll leave you with is I believe
that the future involves answering the
hard problems of how do we change our
thinking and our thought process of
direct growth and I think a lot of this
comes down to how do we better
understand the plasma physics like this
is an example of magnetron sputtering
you're looking at the recombination
event in the plasma there and so can we
look to the the past to enable future
Innovations this plot on the right
there's a lot's a lot of information
this is a sputter Zone diagram that was
developed for Metals this first plot was
made about 55 years ago and actually
understanding this plot led to some of
the Innovations in for the passive
components in integrated circuits and in
summary what this plot on the right is
showing you is that there's multiple
ways to reconsider effective temperature
when you're doing your deposition right
so we think of temperature as the only
means to increase surface add and
Mobility in header structure what I'm
what I'm saying what the community is
starting to realize is that there are
other ways as well to consider as a
different knob so if we can utilize this
to devel to develop new electronic grade
materials at low temperatures we we will
have we will have the new performance
devices in the circuits of the future
thank you