the MIT energy initiative presents an
education and climate change new
multidisciplinary climate change
curriculum for high schools aims to
engage and mobilize teachers and
students written by Lita
Zimmerman several years ago Christopher
kid's father then a math teacher shared
a mailing he had received at his high
school when he opened the packet alarm
Bells went off for kidle who is the
George P Schultz professor of energy
economics at the MIT slone School
management and the deputy director for
policy at the MIT energy initiative
Mighty it was a slickly produced package
of materials purporting to show how to
teach climate change he says in reality
it was a thinly veiled attempt to Kindle
climate change denial kidle was
especially concerned to learn that this
package had been distributed to schools
Nationwide many teachers in search of
information on climate change might use
this material because they are not in a
position to judge its scientific
validity says kidle who is also The
Faculty director of the MIT Center for
Energy and environmental policy research
Seer I decided that MIT which is
committed to True science was in the
perfect position to develop its own
climate change curriculum today kidle is
spearheading the climate action through
education Kate program a curriculum
rolling out in Pilot form this year in
more than a dozen Massachusetts high
schools and eventually in high schools
across the United States to Spur its
broad adoption says kidle the K
curriculum features a unique Suite of
attributes the creation of climate-based
lessons for a range of disciplines
Beyond science adherence to state-based
education standards to facilitate
integration into established curriculum
material connecting climate change
impacts of specific regions and
opportunities for students to explore
climate Solutions Kate aims to engage
both students and teachers in a subject
that can be overwhelming we will be
honest about the threats posed by
climate change but also give students a
sense of agency that they can do
something about this says kidle and for
the many teachers especially non-science
teachers starve for knowledge and
background material Kate offers
resources to give them confidence to
implement our
curriculum partnering with
teachers from the outset Kate sought
guidance and Hands-On development help
from Educators project manager Ashling
ogrady survey teachers to learn about
their experiences teaching about climate
and to identify the kinds of resources
they lacked
she networked with mit's K through2
education experts and with anre
Danielson Mighty Director of Education
bouncing ideas off of them to shape the
direction of her effort she says she
gained two critical insights from this
process I realized that we needed
practicing High School teachers as
curriculum developers and that they had
to represent different subject areas
because climate change is inherently
interdisciplinary she says this Echoes
the philosophy behind mighty's energy
studies minor she remarks
which includes classes from mit's
different schools while science helps us
understand and find solutions for
climate change it touches so many other
areas from economics policy
environmental justice and politics to
history and literature in line with this
thinking Kate recruited Massachusetts
teachers representing key subject areas
in the High School curriculum Amy block
a full-time math teacher and Lisa buatti
a full-time science teacher both at the
Governor's Academy in bfield and
Katherine decross a full-time language
arts teacher at Newton North High School
the fourth member of this cohort Michael
kek is a full-time history teacher at
Newton South High School where he has
worked for 24 years kosek became engaged
with environmental issues 15 years ago
introducing an elective and
sustainability at Newton South he serves
on the Coordinating Committee for the
climate Action Network of the
Massachusetts Teachers Association he
also is president of Earth Day Boston
and organized Boston's 50th an iversary
celebration of earth when he learned
that MIT was seeking teachers to help
develop a climate education curriculum
he immediately applied I've heard time
and again from teachers across the state
that they want to incorporate climate
change into the curriculum but don't
know how to make it work given lesson
plans and schedules geared toward
preparing students for specific tests
says kak I knew that for a climate
curriculum to succeed it had to be part
of an integrated
approach using climate as a
lens over the course of a year kak and
fellow Educators created units that fit
into their pre-existing syllabi but were
woven through with relevant climate
change themes kak already had some
experience in this vein describing the
role of the Industrial Revolution in
triggering the use of fossil fuels and
the greenhouse gas emissions that
resulted for Kate kak explored
additional ways of Shifting focus and
covering US history there are for
instance lessons looking at West
expansion in terms of land use expulsion
of indigenous people and environmental
justice and at the baby boom period in
the emergence of the environmental
movement in English language arts there
are units dedicated to explaining terms
used by scientists and policy makers
such as anthropogenic as well as lessons
devoted to climate change fiction and to
student originated sustainability
projects the science and math classes
work independently but also dovetail for
instance there are science lessons that
demystify the greenhouse effect
utilizing experiments to track fossil
fuel emissions which link to math
lessons that calculate and graph the
average rate of change of global carbon
emissions to make these classes even
more relevant there are Labs where
students compare carbon emissions in
Massachusetts to those of a neighboring
state and where they determine the
environmental and economic costs of
plugging in electric devices in their
own homes throughout this curriculum
shaping process ogrady and the teachers
sought feedback from MIT faculty from a
range of disciplines including David
McGee associate professor in the
department of Earth atmospheric and
planetary Sciences with the help of Kate
undergraduate researcher Heidi Lee 22
the team held a focus group with the
sustainable energy Alliance an
undergraduate student Club in Spring
2022 Kate convened a professional
development Workshop in collaboration
with the Massachusetts Teachers
Association climate Action Network Earth
a Boston and mit's office of government
and community relations sponsored by the
Becker Foundation to evaluate 15
discreet Kat lessons one of the workshop
participants Gary Smith a teacher from
St John's Preparatory School in Danvers
Massachusetts sign Dawn is a volunteer
science curriculum developer we had a
diverse pool of teachers who thought the
lessons were fantastic but among their
suggestions noted that their student
cohorts included new English speakers
who needed simpler language and more
pictur says ogrady this was extremely
useful to us and we revised the
curriculum because we want to reach
students at every level of
learning reaching all the
schools now the K curriculum is in the
hands of a cohort of Massachusetts
teachers each of these educ ERS will
test one or more of the lessons and lab
activities over the next year checking
in regularly with MIT Partners to report
on their classroom experiences the Kate
team is building a climate education
Resource Network of MIT graduate
students postdocs and research staff who
can answer teachers specific climate
questions and help them find additional
resources or data sets additionally
teachers will have the opportunity to
attend two in-person cohort meetings and
be paired with graduate student climate
advisers
in Spring 2023 in honor of Earth Day
ogre and canid want to bring Kate first
adopters High School teachers students
and their families to campus we envision
professors giving many lectures youth
climate groups discussing how to get
involved in local actions and our team
members handing out climate change
packets to students to spark
conversations with their families at
home says ogrady by creating a positive
experience around their curriculum in
these pilot schools the Kate team hopes
to promote its dissemination to many
more massachusett schools in 23 the team
plans on enhancing lessons offering more
paths to integration in high school
studies and creating a companion
resource website for teachers kidle
wants to establish footholds in school
after school in Massachusetts and Beyond
I plan to spend a lot of my time
convincing districts and states to adopt
he says if one teacher tells another
that the curriculum is useful with touch
points in different disciplines that's
how we get a foot in the door kidle is
not shying away from places where
climate change is a politicized topic he
hopes to team up with universities and
states where there might be resistance
to including such lessons in schools to
develop the curriculum although as day
job involves Computing household level
carbon Footprints determining the
relationship between driving behavior
and the price of gasoline and promoting
wise climate policy kle plans to push
Pate as far as he can I want this
curriculum to be adopted by everybody
that's my goal he says in one sense I'm
not the natural person for this job he
admits but I share the mission and
passion of Mighty and Seer for
decarbonizing our economy in ways that
are socially Equitable and efficient and
part of doing that is educating
Americans about the actual costs and
consequences of climate
change the K program is sponsored by
Mighty Seer and the MIT vice president
for research