Last time we start looking at what's
called the rebound intervals.
So we have for the reman integral we
have a function uh f that is defined on
some interval from a to b
into r and this function is bounded
and then we have a p here is a partition
uh of this integral
And so this means that we have a number
of dividing points
where uh a is the first
and then we have x1 x0 that is a x1 x2
and so on up to say uh xn and that is
the uh final point uh endpoint of of the
interval.
So this is a partition. You know these
are the dividing points.
Then we look at the length of each of
these sub intervals. So we have the sub
interval from x i minus one to x i and
uh the length of one of these sub
interval we denote by delta x i and so
this is x i - x i minus one
and then we we look at
right so here if you have the function
here this is the function F.
Uh, and here we have the interval from A
to B.
And so this here is the first dividing
point. This is the last dividing point.
And then we have these other dividing
points uh in between
and this maybe extra like that.
Then we look at the function uh on uh
one of these sub intervals. So we look
at um
[Applause]
we look at the function and we restrict
it to one of these sub interval.
Right?
And then remember the function is is
bounded and so we're looking at it on
one of these and we defined capital mi
to be the soup of f over this sub.
And we defined likewise we define little
mi to be the in
right and this makes sense the finite
number because the function is bounded
and then we look at the upper and the
lower sum. So the upper
sum
so the upper sum is that we have this
given partition
and we look at the sum here of the MI
times delta xi
and we're summing this is from one to n.
So this is the upper sum of the function
for this partition. Right? And likewise
we look at the lower sum.
This is where we sum the infom and we
wait them by the length of the
intervals.
So we look at mi and then delta x i and
i = 1 to n. And this is uh the lower sum
for this partition.
And then just using
then just using that.
So of course for these MI
here it's the infant sum on the same
interval. So little MI is lesser or
equal to capital MI. Right? But this
also means right that these weights are
the same. If this here is less than
that, it means that that the lower sum
is lesser equal to the upper sum.
Now the second thing we looked at is so
so again we looked at again we have this
partition P and we looked at P1 is a
subartition
subartition or refinement.
This is if uh if
P1
has the same
dividing point
as P and then presumably some
then uh then positive I mean then uh
some more
Right? I mean you could have uh that you
could have that the two partition was
exactly the same and you would still say
that one is a trivial subartetition of
the other but this is but in general
right a subartetition would have more
dividing points right
and so then the thing is that um if
you're looking at so let's say that so
so
that p here again has the partitions.
This is it's a partition that comes from
P
and um and let's say that P1 here
let me illustrate it as if P1 have one
additional so here you have X0 which is
A here you have X in which is B and then
you have two others say this is X1 maybe
and this here is X Okay. Then you have
bunch of other this is the partition P
and then um then um
um uh P1 let's say have one more
dividing point it could have many more
dividing points but if you're looking at
so you have here
X I minus one and then you have X I and
then maybe uh the the P1 P1 this
partition have an additional dividing
point just called that Y right
well then the contribution that you get
from from to the lower and upper sum so
the contribution that you get from this
or that for for P you can think about
that as MI this is the contribution from
the lower sum And here you have the
contribution from the opposite.
But now
um now you see that um that for the sub
partition
then you have that so the intervals for
the sub partition this here is the
interval for the original partition P
but uh for the sub partition it's this
is now divided into two intervals this
here and that here right
and so Uh so you have that so this thing
here this is in this case is split into
two and one of them is y - x i -1 and
the other is x i - one right
now for if you're looking at the say the
lower
sum for this for this sub partition
Right? So this thing here so the
contribution that you get from this here
well you have now you have two intervals
and so you're getting a you're getting a
contribution which is the in
on this thing here on this little
interval here
of f
times y - x i -1 and then you get a
second contribution which is n on this
interval here from from uh from y to x i
of f and then it's x i - one right so
this is a contribution that you get from
this interval here
but this thing here is smaller equal to
the it's actually sorry this here is
larger equal to the in where you take
the in over the larger interval that
goes from this point to that point right
so you have that this is larger than y -
x i minus one this thing here is is also
larger than this little m i and then is
x i minus y
and now you can just factor out so
you're hitting MI and then when you add
these two together right then you see
that this gives you exactly X I - X I
minus one so this is little MI time
delta X I right so this means that if
you so you see that the contribution
that you get on this little interval for
this is larger than the same
contribution that you get from this
larger equal two, right? And so when
you're summing over all intervals,
then you get that if you if P1
is a refinement or subartetition,
then this lower here, the lower sum
go up.
So this lower sum go up. And if you do
it now, if you do the same stuff
for the upper sum, then this here would
instead of being in, it would have to be
the soup.
This here would have to be the soup.
But the soup on the smaller interval is
now then the this inequality would
reverse. It's less or equal to and then
it becomes a soup on the larger
interval. This here remains the same.
This here again becomes a larger one.
So this here becomes
less than this. This here becomes less
than this.
And so what you see is that the soup
here go down. Right? So the the lower
sum go up. And uh um and if you're
looking at the
upper sum
this here decrease.
So you have that right. And so putting
this together you have that uh that you
have that the lower sum
for for the partition P is less than the
lower sum for this sub partition which
is less than the upper sum for the sub
partition
which is less than the original upper
sum.
Okay. So you have that
and so this is this is like a key key
fact. It's sort of an obvious fact but
it's a key fact.
Okay.
So now so that was
that was the upper and lower sum.
So now we define the
upper and lower
integrals.
So we define the upper
and lower
uh reman integrals.
We define them as follow
that uh the upper one
we denote like this
and this here is now the in
of all partitions
of the of the upper sum.
And likewise we define the lower reman
integral
of this function this bounded function
to be the soup
of the of the lower
sums like that. So soup of all
partitions. Okay. So that is the upper
and lower sums uh remals.
And so now
we say that the function
this boundless function f is reband
integral.
So f here.
So f
is set to be
a reman integral
and rewrite uh and rewrite that f here
is like this.
So it means that it's remain integral
uh if if the following is the case. So
if
uh this lower integral here
is equal to the upper integral
and if this is the case then we just
write and then uh and then the reman
integral
uh of of f is then denoted by just like
that.
Okay.
And so so this is so this is uh this is
reman's way of defining integrals. There
are other ways uh but this is I think
this was the first way where
um where you have a where it's it where
you have a a definition that really made
sense.
Uh okay. So now the first thing I want
to observe is
that for a general function you always
have
so in general so
we always have whether the function is
reman integraable or not. We always have
that the lower integral here, the lower
reman integral
is lesser equal to the upper.
And so why is that the case? Right? So
this is because
right this is because if you take a a
partition
so fix a partition
uh then you have that
You have that the lower
sum here
uh is
um is of course less or equal to
uh this thing here
right because this here was was the soup
of all partitions.
So you have that
but in fact what you also have that you
but More importantly,
uh you have that this L of F here
uh I claim that this is uh lesser equal
to
uh the upper sum.
um
for any
any other any other petition for any
petition.
So I claim that you always have this
here. If you take two partition P and P
star then the lower sum for one is less
or equal to the upper sum for the other.
Why is that the case? This just uses
that inequality over there.
It uses that together with this
inequality. So let's see.
So if you take
if you take if P here is a partition
and P star is a partition
then you could take a partition. So, so
let
bar be the partition
that has
all the dividing points
of P and all
the dividing points.
of P star
right so the dividing point of P bar is
a union of the dividing points of the
two partitions right but it but this
means that P bar here so
P bar here is a refinement it's a it's a
refinement of subartetition
of both
uh P and
P star, right? Because it has all of the
dividing points of either, right?
But this means that remember that the
lower sum
so if you're looking at this the lower
sum if you take a subartetition
that goes up right.
So if you take a subartetition the lower
sum will go up
but the lower sum is always lesser equal
to the upper sum for a given partition.
Right? But this here is now a refinement
of P star. So the upper sum go down. So
this here is lesser equal to U F of P
star.
Right? And so there you have it that
this thing here the lower sum for one
partition is always smaller than the
upper sum for the other. Right?
And so this means that if you now take a
petition,
so now
so now it means that for for a fixed
partition
P. So we have that this thing here
is less or equal to
this
single about P is being fixed but this
is now for all other for all partitions
P star. So this is for all
P star. But if it holds for all this
here is a sorry say is lesser equal to
if it holds for all then it also this
inequal this is a fixed number. This
means that this here is a lower bound
for for this family. So this means that
L f of P
is less or equal to the in
of those guys,
right? It's less or equal to the in but
that here is just the this here is by
definition
the upper reman sum up reman integral
right
but this means but this is for each so
now you forget about the p star you have
that this thing here is less than that
number so this means that this number
here is an upper bound for this whole
family Okay. So this means that also the
soup the smallest upper bound must be
less than that. Right? So this means
that the soup soup of
of l f of p
must be less or equal to this thing
here.
But the soup is by definition the lower
integral.
Right. So you always have and this is
this this claim over here. Right.
Um okay. So, so that's the that's the
first let's look at so
let's look at um
let's look at a function
uh that is I I added just a little bit
if if you know if you find it
interesting I find it interesting but
maybe you don't but a little bit about
reman that's uh he died rather young uh
of tuberculosis
But he had an incredible impact.
He had an incredible I mean this is one
of his contributions. His first
contribution
his he was a student of another really
famous
uh
mathematician perhaps the most famous of
all time Gaus. Uh and so
uh at those times when you wrote your
thesis
then you had like six months to write
your thesis and um
and and you you know sort of formally
you couldn't choose your subject but it
was always you it was always anyway you
always got permission to choose it. So
you had to give three suggestions for
something you would write your thesis
on. And so but it was always it was you
know a sort of unspoken rule that your
advisor always picked number one and
that's what you wanted. And then you
could add some other crazy stuff as two
other suggestions.
But so Reman had you know three
suggestions and the third one uh which
he have absolutely no idea about was um
to make sense of uh curvature in higher
dimension and and so he just put it in
there. He knew it wasn't going to be
selected
but actually at the time this was what
Gaus was interested in and so Gaus said
to hell with the rules. I'll pick number
three. And so he had six months and
nobody had figured this out. You know,
Gaus is considered by many the greatest
mathematician of all time. And so but
after six months actually so reman came
up with something called the curvature
tensor which is this object in all
dimension
and that generalized uh Gaus's work and
and this lay the foundation for general
relativity. Yeah. Came you know many
years later you know or
uh uh 70 years or so later.
Um so that was the Reman's first. This
is one of Reman's other contributions
and there are other things that was only
published you know long time after his
death that have had tremendous a
tremendous contribution in other areas.
Anyway, so this is so this was Reman's
uh way of defining the intercourse. Uh
let me um
[Applause]
look at a function. So we talked about
that a little bit but we didn't actually
define it. So so here's an example of a
function that is not reman integraable.
So it's a function defined on the
integral from zero to one. same it's
bounded and so the function is uh f ofx
is equal to
uh one
if uh if x here is rational
and it's sure uh otherwise
Okay.
And so of course this function here is
always between zero and one. So it's
it's definitely bounded, right? But if
you take now any interval
so the so
this here so I claim here
uh uh f here
is not
uh remmanageable.
And so the thing is that if you take uh
if you take a
interval like this and you take a sub
partition
like that
uh and now you have that and now you're
looking at one of these
mi. So here you have x i minus one and
here you have x i
and so you're looking at
mi. So this is some little interval like
this. But on any kind of small interval
you know if it's really a proper
integral if it's not just a point but
it's a proper integral interval then
there's always point that are rational
and always point that are not rational.
Right? So this means that this here this
here the soup here would have to be one
but the in here would be zero
right and so this means that for the
upper so this is just any partition and
so this means that for if you're looking
at the upper sum
the upper sum here but it's now the sum
of these capital mi delta xi this here
is one so it's just a sum of the length
of these smaller interval but that's
just one because the whole interval is
from 0 to one and likewise for the lower
interval a lower sum this is the sum
here of these small mi delta xi
these here are zero so this whole thing
here is zero
so you see that if you this is for all
partitions.
So this means that if you take the
infreom of this you still get one and if
you take the soup of these you still get
zero. So so those two numbers are not
the same. The lower and the upper reman
integrals are not the same. So the
function is not reman integral.
So now the next thing is
um right the next thing is so we want to
know which functions are remman
integraable uh and so here's a useful
little criteria
uh so lema
so you have a function again that is
bounded
uh then um then f
is reman integral and again we write it
like this. So it's reman integral if for
all
epsilon greater than zero uh there exist
a partition
p so that the
um so that the uh upper integral
upper sum. Sorry. So that the upper sum
minus the lower sum. Remember that this
is always bigger than the lower sum.
If this here is less than epsilon.
Okay. So if we want to check that a
function is remman integraable then we
just need to check that for all epsilon
we can find a partition
um um uh with this property here. And so
this is a statement that is if and only
if. So I should say if and only if if
and
if if
and only if
if if.
Okay.
So just try to prove that and then we're
going to use this later on
to
prove that a lot of functions are reman
integral.
So,
so suppose that uh that f. So, if
f here is reman integraable.
So if it is reman integraable then we
know that this
lower reman integral
is equal to the upper reman integral.
This here was the soup of all. This here
was the soup of all lower sums for all
over all partitions.
And this here was the in of all upper
sum
like that over all partitions.
And now
um so this means that so therefore
given
epsilon greater than zero there exist
a partition
P1
right because this has a super wall
partition So it means that uh there
exist a partition so that this lower
uh lower sum here
is uh bigger equal to
this here
minus epsilon / two right it's just
because it's a soup over all these
numbers so there must exist one that
comes this close to to the soup.
Likewise,
likewise
there exist
Likewise there exist
a partition
P2
sorry this here should be P1 right this
is the soup over so so there exist a
partition P2 so that the right so that
for that this is one of the one where
this value here is really small so this
is not too much larger than this so this
means that this for P2
is um is smaller equal to this here
upper
upper remain integral
uh plus epsilon / two.
So now we let So now let
be the partition
with
uh all the dividing points
uh of both
P1
and P2, right? So it has all of the
writing points on P1 together with all
of the biting points on P2 right but now
for this partition we have that well for
this is a refinement of P1
so if it's refinement the value here
goes up
and this thing here is so this is less
than the upper for the same thing
and since it's a refinement also of P2
we have that it is less than the
opposite for P2
right
but now you see that uh this thing here
so uh L right so the difference between
these two the difference between these
two numbers so this is the difference
here so u FP
minus U F
P sorry LFP
right this difference here this here is
bigger than that so if you take this and
subtract this you're getting something
non- negative and this the spread
between these two smaller than the
spread between these right so this is
less than Q of F p2 minus L of FP1.
Uh but this thing here
is this thing here is less than uh u f
P2 minus this upper integral here
the the assuming that it's remain
integral. So the upper and lower are the
same. So it's so this thing here we can
write it as this plus uh minus sorry
um
uh l
uh f
p1 minus
uh the integral here
like that right I'm just you know
subtracting and then adding back the
same thing
And this one here we already found that
this here was bounded by epsilon / two
right this here is remember we're
assuming that it's that is reman
integraable so this here is the same
thing as when you have the upper one
right and this thing here is this here
is uh is also bounded by this is
actually right this is this is negative
but it's It's right. So this thing here
is
is um is bigger equal to maybe I should
write it as um
well let me write it like this plus uh
and then I can write it as the integral
from a to b of fx dx minus l f of p1.
Right? But this thing here was bounded
by epsilon / two also. So epsilon / 2
plus epsilon / two. So this is uh equal
to epsilon. Right?
So, so again if you want to test that a
function is reman integral you just need
to find for a given for any given
epsilon you need to be able to find a
partition so that the upper sum for that
partition
uh is uh minus the lower sum for the
same partition is less than epsilon.
Okay.
And so now um so now this leads us to
the next theorem. So the next theorem is
that any continuous function is rem
integraable.
So any reman sum sorry any continuous
function any
in a continuous function
on
integral like this. This is you know a
and b are real numbers
uh is uh reman integral.
Okay, so this is the next theorem that
we want to prove. But in order to prove
that we need a tool and so this is
what's called uniformly continuous.
So to to show this we need the notion of
being uniformly continuous.
So what is that?
So,
so in the proof
we need
the notion
of uniformly continuous
Okay, so that's the following that you
have a function defined on some interval
say could be all of R for that matter.
So you have a function like this and f
is set to be
is uh set to be
uniformly continuous.
Uh if if
all
uh epsilon greater than zero,
there exist
delta greater than zero such that
as long as x and y
are less than delta, then their images
is is less than epsilon. Okay.
So what is the difference between this
and continuity? For continuity you
always you you looking at functions
continuous if it's continuous at all
points right and so it's continuous at a
point is so there for to be continuous
at a point is like you're fixing one of
these two. So it's like x is fixed and
then you're looking at if y is
sufficiently close then the value the
difference between the value at x and y
is smaller than epsilon. But here it's
like that the same delta works for all
x. You don't have to fix one of the two
points right the same delta work. Okay.
So let's see uh where this is not the
case.
So let me look at two examples.
So just to understand the difference. So
to understand the difference
the difference
between
continuity
and uniform continuity.
Uniform again refer to that that X is
not fixed right or X0 usually we call it
X0 and X so one of the two points was
fixed that's the and uniform means that
you don't need to fix it's like the same
uh the same delta works for all X0 okay
and so so here is is an example
that suppose you take the function f ofx
= to x^2. This is now on on r.
So this function well we already know
that this function is continuous right
and so if it was uniformly so if f was
uniformly continuous
then
for a given
epsilon greater share there would exist
a delta so that the value at X and the
value where you say added
uh delta
this difference here
would have to be less than
if you want if you don't like it you
could say delta over two right if you
want it to be strictly the difference
between but but it doesn't really matter
I just say like that this hair would
have to be the case right for and this
hair would have to be the case for all
x.
But what is this here? This here is x +
delta squared. That's the value of the
function in this. And this is the value
of the function in x. Right?
But this thing here just squaring out
gives you x^2 + delta squar plus uh 2 x
delta
right and this thing here would have to
be less than epsilon
right?
Delta is positive
and so sorry this here minus x
would have to be less than delta epsilon
right
and so you
get rid of these two delta is positive
so uh if you have this you would
definitely also have that so this would
implies that or delta actually this
delta square I guess is positive
regardless but you would have that 2x
delta here
would have to be less than epsilon right
and delta is now now I'm using the delta
is positive so this here would have to
be the case for all x
but if you just let x be delta is now
supposed to be you know you're supposed
to find some delta so that this here
works for all x so this means that delta
is fixed
But if now delta x becomes incredibly
large then of course you don't have this
inequality anymore right so so this
function is not uniform continuous right
yeah
>> because it's it only helps us right so I
I I I you know if this here is less than
that this is positive this means that
this here surely is also less than
epsilon
okay so that's one example
Um
the other example
is
and and actually let me draw a picture
to just illustrate it.
So if you take so again the function
sort of roughly looks like this. This is
f ofx
= x.
This meaning of that it's uniform
continuous means that if you take some
epsilon right for any given epsilon so
if you're looking at a interval over on
the y ais here so that this is between
you know this here is like a epsilon
interval and you're looking at so if you
looking at some point here. This here is
this point here is taken to to this
here. And now you want to look at some
small interval so that you end up in
that interval. Right? And the thing is
that as you're moving further and
further out this the length of that
interval would have to be smaller and
smaller, right? But you can't use the
same uniform size, right? So that's why
it's not uniformly continuous.
The other example
uh I'm going to look at is where you
take a function.
We're taking f ofx equal to 1 /x and x
here is now in the interval
from zero to one. One is included but
zero is not. Right?
And so there the picture is
that this here is the function.
And so you see that as you're getting
closer here's one and as you're looking
at things closer to zero
then even a really small interval the
functions the value of the function
right would deviate a lot on even a very
small interval right so you couldn't use
the same interval size to say that the
value of the function right is smaller
and some epsilon. So ju just make that
precise.
If you take um a sequence xn equal to 1
/ n and y = 1 / 2n
then and you're looking at
you're looking at the difference. So if
you're looking at xn minus y
right
here you have we don't really need to
calculate anything for the first thing
here you have xn here you have y in so
this means that the difference between
these two is certainly balanced by this
here so of course you always have you
have actually something much better but
this is actually smaller than one /
And if you're now looking at the value
of the function, this thing here is 1 /
xn. So that's n
and uh f of yn
is one / 2n. So this is 2 n. So this
means that f of xn
minus f of yn here this here is equal to
this difference here is equal to to 2 n
right
and so you see that you couldn't you
know it's not like it's not for any
given epsilon it doesn't work that if
these two points uh you know there
doesn't exist a delta so that if these
two points are delta close then the
images is at most epsilon right
>> I don't know if this is too broad of a
generalization but is that essentially
just the same thing as saying that the
scope is
>> yeah it's it's like that right I mean
sort of like that I mean it's not I mean
you know uh uniform continuity doesn't
require
uh I mean sort of like that but not
exactly uh because uniformly uh you So
slope is something about being
differentiable,
right? And and and you can have a
uniformly continuous function that is
not differentiable.
Uh but it's it's definitely related.
Yeah.
Um
okay. So, so anyway, so uniform again
means that for a given delta for a given
epsilon you can use the same delta
u for you know at at all points right
otherwise for continuity you were always
fixing one of the points and then you
were looking at other points close to
that point. Okay.
Okay. So now the the first thing that we
want to prove is so we want to prove
that so we want our goal here is to
prove this theorem let's say that if you
have a continuous function on a
closed interval so closed bounded
interval compact interval from a to b
then the function is actually rem
integraable okay but uh and and to prove
prove that we need again this notion of
uniformly continuous and so the first
thing we want to prove is we want to
upgrade continuity to uniform
continuity.
So what does that mean? So it means that
if you take a function
on a compact interval like this.
So if so if you have a continuous
function
then
uh f is uniformly continuous.
Right? So if the interval actually is
compact then the and then a continuous
function is uniformly continuous. Let's
just look at the two examples we had. We
had two examples. In the first one f ofx
was equal to x^2
but it was defined on all of it was
continuous of course but the thing is it
wasn't on a compact interval. It was on
all of R. In the second this function
here is also continuous
but it's not a compact interval because
zero is not included. Right? Yeah.
>> Compact
is
>> compact. So remember that um that so
compact in
that compacts
you can either think about it as as we
talk about compact uh metric spaces or
compact sets right but for a subsets of
um of the real line right compact is the
same as saying that it's bounded and
closed Right? And so this in here when I
writing it like this A and B are real
numbers and they are both included.
Right? And again like if it was like
this here then one endpoint is included
but the other one is not. So it's not
actually compact. Right?
Okay. And so so if the function here is
continuous then it's uniformly
continuous. So that's what we want to
prove right. So, so want to again if the
interval is compact
then then actually uh you get the
stronger continuity.
So now let's try to prove that
suppose not
if this here was not the case then it
meant that so we take the negation of
the definition of uniform continuity. So
this means that there exist a epsilon.
So suppose not then
there exist
epsilon greater than zero
such that
such that no delta would work. Right?
such that for all
delta greater than zero there exist
x comma y.
Um
so that the difference between these two
is less than delta
and the images
is bigger or equal to epsilon. Right?
That's just the negation of the
statement. Right?
But now we choose a sequence of delta.
Right? And so we we do this. So this is
for all delta. So really if we take
advantage of that we look at at a
sequence of of such delta.
So so we look at a sequence of such
delta and this is where so we use this
for delta equal to 1 / n. Right? So n
here is again a positive
it's a natural number like that.
So this means that we for each n you
have x n and you have yn
they're both in the interval from a to b
and you have that xn minus yn
is less than 1 / n and you have that the
images f of xn minus f of yn
is bigger equal to epsilon, right?
Epsilon was positive should be positive.
But this means so now we have xn so the
these are in this interval. So this
means that we can find a subsequence by
compactness right we can find
of the balsano vio theorem we have a
subsequence that converts to some x
right this is just a subsequence of
these x ends right but now you can just
look at
so now if you're looking at the
corresponding subsequence of the y ends
so you have that y in k - x
this thing here is less or equal to by
the triangle inequality this is less
than equal to y n k - x n k
plus
x n k - x right
and we have that this thing here. This
here was less than 1 / n and we have
plus this here.
But this thing here is actually over n k
sorry n k right
and you have but you have that this
thing here this here this subsequence go
to x. So this here goes to zero and this
here goes to zero. So this means that
these yn
k actually also converts to x right.
So you have but now you have so you have
this and you have the y n k converts to
x. So now this here together with that
the function is continuous means that
fxn
k
converge to f ofx
and you have that f yn k converts to
also f ofx.
Right? This is just because uh since
f is continuous
but now you just look at
now you just look at the
right. So now you have that. So again fx
n k converts to uh f ofx
and this here
converts to f ofx. But I claim that this
here but we also have that fx n k minus
f y n k we have that this thing here is
bigger equal to epsilon right
but then you can't have if this here you
this here is clearly a contradiction
right because if this here converts to
that this converts to the same thing
then these two things here much gets
closer and closer together, right? But
they're saying that there are some
fixing apart, right? So that's clearly a
contradiction.
So this prove that if it is continuous,
it's also uniformly continuous. Okay.
So now let's use this to prove um to
prove that if you take a function. So
now we are ready to get back to the
zero. That was like our main interest.
But so you see also like in the two
example I had it was no accident again
that in the first one the interval was
unbounded. In the second one the
interval was bounded but it was not
closed. Right? And so either case it
failed to be compact. And that was why
you could have a continuous function
that wasn't uniformly continuous.
And so now we get back to this theorem.
And so the theorem again is theorem give
you this nice criteria for when a
function is remman integraable. So if
uh f here is continuous
then uh then f here is rem integraable
and again this here should be it's
understood that it's it's f f
is defined on an interval like this
interval.
Okay.
And so now the proof is like this.
We showed earlier
we showed
earlier
that
we only we that we need
need only show
that's uh given
epsilon greater zero. There exist a
partition
so that if the uh such that the upper
sum
minus the lower sum
for this partition
is less than epsilon. Right? That's all
we need. We need to prove that for each
epsilon there exist a partition so that
the upper and the lower sum are within
epson of each other. Okay.
Now
uh so now you use the so now using that
so so so now so given
given epsilon greater than zero
since
f is uniformly continuous
right so actually proving that if it is
continuous on this compact interval,
it's also uniformly continuous.
Since uh f is uniformly continuous, it
means that there exist
delta greater zero such that
if uh x - y is less than delta
then uh let's say delta is let's say
less than true delta.
Then uh then
then the images
then uh f ofx minus f of y
is now uh smaller than
uh and then instead of epsilon I using
epsilon divided by the length of the
interval sorry and this would be
strictly less.
Okay.
So now we let
let P here be a partition
where
each
delta XI each little interval here
uh is is equal to delta Right?
You just have to be be say less or equal
to delta but you can make it equal to
delta.
So now if this is the case, but then we
have
So now if we're looking at one of these
smaller intervals here.
So now if you're looking at one of these
smaller interval here, here you have x i
minus one and here you have x i. So if
you're now looking at one of these small
interval then you have that the function
is continuous here. So the
if you're looking at the soup of this
interval. So the soup on this interval
this is the soup of one of these
intervals here of f the soup here. This
is it's it's actually achieved by by the
extreme value theorem. This is achieved
at some point
if say uh y uh y a y and maybe that's
bad my uh so let's just say y right
and likewise on this little interval
the in here
is also achieved
and let's call at Y star.
So the infreum is also achieved and
that's
achieved at some Y star.
But now this interval here have length
this here is at most
at most delta right. So this means that
the difference in the value of any such
two points right so they are actually
less strictly less than two. So it means
that the value differ at most like this.
So this means that so it means that f of
y which is actually the soup. So this
here
so since it's a soup I don't even need
this here is larger than that. So I
don't need to even take absolute value
sign on it. But it means that the
difference here is now less than um
epsilon over b minus a
right
and so this here again is is m of i
minus m of i like that right
and so now you see that so now let's
look at the contribution so for the
upper sum
We have that this here is these capital
mi and then delta xi. For the lower sum,
we have that this is the sum of the
small mi delta xi.
Right? And so now let's look at the
difference between these two.
Right? That's the one we need to prove
is strictly less than epsilon. So if
you're looking at this u
f of p minus l f p this here is now the
sum here and then it's so you're summing
this thing is the same so you can write
the sum here the difference well let's
maybe just write it first write it out
like this
but then now I can once I have written
it out like this see that I can Write
this in here as a sum of capital mi
minus little mi
time delta xi.
Right?
And this thing here I already figured I
already have a bound that this is each
of these is less than this. So I just
write in that bound. So this here is
less than uh and then the sum here
epsilon over b minus a. and then uh like
this.
But now this is just a constant. So this
just I can just take this out of the
summation sign.
And so I get this thing. So this is the
sum of the small interval but the sum of
the small interval is the whole
interval. So this is epsilon b minus a *
b minus a.
And so this is epsilon.
And so you have exactly it's a this
difference here is strictly bounded by
epsilon. Okay. So this proved that that
if the function is continuous
then it is on a compact interval then it
is uh reman integral. And now let me at
least state some of the basic formulas
uh for uh reman integrals.
Um, and so maybe we might prove some of
these next time.
So the first one is that if you take so
have this theorem here.
Uh the first one is supposed to take a
function that is remman integraable on
some integral like this
and c here is constant is a real number
then uh then the uh this constant times
f is also man integraable
and the integral of this function here
is equal to C * the integral reman
integral like that. Right? So that's the
first one.
Uh
uh the next one is that if you take two
functions
f and g
suppose you take two functions
uh f and g that are reman integral
uh and uh now let's look at the function
that is the sum of these two. Right? So
this is a new function and the claim is
that this here is also remain integral
and the integral of the sum
is the sum of the integrals. Oops.
Okay, that's the second one.
Uh and the third one is that um so the
third one is that if you take if you
take a function two functions
again they are both reman integraable
uh and you have that f here is lesser
equal to g then the reman integral of f
is lesser equal to the reman integral of
G
like that.
And the f fourth rule
is that
uh the fourth rule is a little bit
different. So this is
this is if you split the interval.
So the fourth one
is like this. Again I will prove some of
them not all of them but I'll prove some
of them uh next time but not all of them
I won't prove the first one for sure. So
the fourth is that if you take so
imagine so you have this interval here
from a to b
but imagine that so here you have a here
you have b imag imagine that c is
somewhere in between
uh a and b
and suppose that you have a function
that is remman integral on this interval
then the claim is That's that then if
you take the function and you restrict
it to either of the either this interval
or that interval, it's still remand
integral
and f here is also
in uh from C to B
and and the claim is that the reman
integral
on the original integral is the sum of
the reman integral.
Okay, like that. Okay. And so if you
think about it in terms of kind of area
below the graph, right? If you take a
function like this,
if you if this here was if this here was
C, then the area below the graph here,
I guess this here would be sign area
below the graph. But if you just took
the area below, if the function was
actually positive and you think about
the reman integral as the area below the
graph, if this here is C, this here is
A, this here is B, then this area here
plus this area is the sum of these two
is the sum underneath the the whole
graph, right? So it makes sense.
Okay, any questions?
Okay, great. See you next time.