I am excited to introduce today's
speaker Courtney Shear is a fourth year
PhD student in Deborah marks group at
Harvard Medical School she's interested
in developing machine learning models to
learn from past Evolution present
population and future experimental
biology sequence data for therapeutic
sequence design and predicting clinical
variant effects she's going to share
with us some exciting uh work today so
please if you have any questions feel
free to come up to the microphone um or
raise your hand if you're online feel
free to um raise your hand there or on
mute to ask your question or just Ty
type it in the chat so thank you again
Courtney for joining
us can you hear me great okay so the
actual title of my talk is can we
computationally predict Varian effects
so we can do a few experiments um and
like we just said you know feel free to
come up and ask questions like as you
like you don't have to wait till the end
you also can wait till the end like
whatever you like um so this is like
it's more fun if you you know talk and
ask questions because the primers are a
little bit more of an introductions to
the bulk of this talk in the beginning
will be truly like oh you know basics of
like varing effect prediction and then
towards the middle half of the talk I'll
go into a couple um specific modeling
methodologies that the Marx lab has uh
put together over the years so the
beginning will feel uh hopefully uh not
too um intimidating and certainly uh
nice to listen to at 8:30 a.m. in the
morning um so with all that the main
question we're answering here not to
make this over complicated is can we
computationally predict uh Varian
effects so we can do fewer
experiments maybe okay so what's the
goal goal here is to learn what variants
cause disease and this simple picture I
have here we have a DNA strand on the
left um and then a individual who has
some non-desirable phenotype as depicted
by red spots and a um frowning demeanor
so how do these variants cause disease
that's a uh that's a question we have we
always want to know if we do see
variance in uh an individual how are
they causing this non-desirable or
potentially desirable but in this case
non-desirable phenotype um things we can
use uh to try to assess this we uh
classically have used things like
genomics epigenetics
transcriptomics proteomics and then with
all these things we try to um you know
understand how these uh molecules might
be manifesting and um you know
mechanisms and Pathways that ultimately
lead to uh the phenotypes we're
interested
in so how do we think about this
variation generally when it comes to I
didn't make this I'm not like an artist
this is AI generated um so classically
we'll think about things um from like a
proteome perspective where you have tons
of molecules being made I suppose from
like um I guess this doesn't show the
magnitude of the difference and
distributions of the size of the genome
that might produce these things but the
proteome will produce uh you know
proteins and the non-coding genome uh
usually won't produce proteins as we
tried to Define our
annotations um but to get into the types
of Vari we might see we'll start with um
a simple depiction um here where at the
top we have uh you know some reference
and I mean I'm sure we've all heard of
uh single nucleotide variants which are
just single based pair changes they
occur approximately in one in every uh
kilobase of um sequencing
data we can also see things like small
insertions and deletions which are a bit
more
rare and then we'll even start to see
like like predicted regions for
structural and copy number variants
which are supposedly um more rare unless
our sequencing data uh isn't good at
picking them
up um so anyway the types of these uh
single nucleotide variants that occur in
proteins um you know they have a
propensity to disrupt uh codons that
will actually um you know be translated
and turned into the protein
structures um of course we can have
variants that are silent having no
effect on the protein
sequence allegedly um and we can have
missense variants which result in an
amino acid
substitution and then we can have
nonsense variants that um substitute a
stop codon for an amino acid so all of
this is a little bit of refresher keep
with me it'll maybe get more exciting
for some of you um in addition to the
proteome I'm not going to go into any
numerical descriptions here but just
invite this uh you know uh complex uh
interaction system that we might uh view
when we're thinking about non-coding
variants and just as a speculation this
complex architecture is certain to
invite disruptions by uh all types of
variants of certain sizes but as a you
know foreshadowing to the future of what
I'll talk about at the end potentially
longer um variants might uh be more
disruptive than uh single nucleotide
variants so how are variant
distinguished well a lot of times in uh
population genetics literature these are
some ways that we like to distinguish
how we talk about variants aside from
where they are in the genome aside from
how big they are we talk about them as
reference versus alternate we talk about
them as um with respect to their
frequency and a population of Interest
we might call them the major variant or
the minor
variant um we might talk about them um
in terms of which variant matches the
most recent ancestor shared by um a
recent species and with respect to
humans this might be uh primates or
chimps when we might call this ancestral
versus
derived and we also talk about these
variants in terms of their um
association with increased uh disease
risks so we might call these risk versus
non-risk clever um classifying variants
um we can also classify these variants
further by minor alal frequencies so
instead of just thinking about things as
minor and major you can start to think
about the frequencies of these variants
in maybe a spectrum like this where on
the far end of the spectrum you have a
variant occurring in one person and then
on the bottom side of this uh Arrow you
can think of these in terms of like you
know strict cut offs based on
percentages but we also use some of
these words at the top such as very rare
rare low and
common additionally we can expand this
on the left a bit and people will talk
about variants using language such as
the noo if a variant is even part of one
person being in a sematic cells as
opposed to
germline and these are just a few uh you
know ways we can begin to describe
variants um when we're talking about
them in
literature so how do we associate these
variants with diseases because remember
that's our that's our big question
that's what we want to know we can
describe these variants in many ways um
and but we're really concerned about
this question you can tell me all the
ways you want to describe a variant I
don't care I want to know how does the
variant affect cause the
disease
so the bulk of um you know um uh
genetics and statistics gentics has kind
of looked at this kind of lens of
Association where we begin to look at
variant again on the bottom here in
terms of their um minor Al frequency but
we also want to know about their effect
size how much an individual variant
actually contributes to the phenotype
we're interested in and we kind of P
classify variants into these broad um
you know discreet um regions of this uh
two-dimensional um um um um coordinate
system and we can say what studies are
used to find these causal
variants uh we can have variants that
are extremely unlikely they're common
variants with major effects it's
extremely unlikely to find those we have
gwa studies which are very good uh
allegedly at finding low frequency
variants with intermediate effects or
common variant with small
effects we have rare variant analysis
which is is good at finding rare
variants with small effect size and then
we can use some things like tools like
family studies to look for rare variants
with major effects and even sometimes
grab some of those low frequency
variants with intermediate
effects so all that is great finding
these associations but even if we find
them there still is this big question
here of can we predict how the variant
affect the trait so what about all this
stuff in the middle how are we going to
get
there so we could do this
experimentally uh we can use tools to
look at the proteome such as deep
mutational scans where we basically
perturb each um amino acid and see how
it changes uh something simple like the
protein uh folding or some Downstream um
you know assay uh uh that we're
interested
in uh we can also look at more so I
guess as this is called for the
non-coding regions we can look at what
are called um npas massively parallel
reporter assays where we essentially
exogenously go in and stuff our variant
of Interest into a plasmid and see if we
have um potentially expression happening
um from some uh gfp Etc or we can even
assess things like Star seek we're
looking at uh enhancer binding
Etc we also can look at things like
crisper mutagenesis where we can
potentially go and indirectly um you
know edit uh regions of the endogenous
cell and see how those um edits you know
manifest in some Downstream uh cellular
phenotype and even further look at those
at the organism level but that seems uh
fairly
expensive so why not do all these
experiments seems like a good idea well
the human genome has about 20,000
protein coating genes average protein
length is 470 amino acids Poss amino
acid substitutions per position is
approximately 19 variance per protein is
around that number this leads to a a
very large total of possible amino acid
uh substitutions just singles um for
double mutants this goes up to 15.9
trillion combinations and triple
mutations becomes
astronomical okay well I don't care I'm
going to do a low through preny
experiment anyway okay so a cloning and
DNA preparation might take two days
protein expression two to three days
functional assays 1 to three days data
analysis one day not so bad total time
for variance seven days you have a team
of five researchers you're going to test
your variance in parallel 50 for 50 per
week okay it's going to take you about
68692 years okay I'm going to do a high
throughput experiment low throughput
experiments that's old new mes okay I'm
going to do 50,000 variants per
experiment that's going to take me about
a month and then I'm going to do this
that's still going to take me about 300
years ah dang okay so I should never do
an experiment again no you can use
prediction from some magical Oracle of
tools which I'll try to convince you
about next uh for this initial screening
of variants you might want to test then
you can validate these high impact
variants
experimentally and then you can do this
in a continue feedback loop to improve
predictions
yes thing I always think about with your
previous slide is are you testing it
even in the right cell type and so you
need to multiply all of those by all of
the different cell types and states that
ever exist in the human body yeah and we
only Define cell types that we Define
discreet cell types but of course you
know that's a bit
artificial so it's entally inflite if
you wanted to like time Point any
potential cell um
as it's uh differentiating okay so maybe
you believe me okay so anyway so this is
a body of work um from a group of us uh
um uh variant effect prediction
Association um led by uh Joe
Marsh um we put out this guidelines for
releasing a variant effect predictor you
can check it out if you like has some
good um descriptions of what a variant
effect predictor would be do but
essentially a variant effect predictor
it aims to take in data information from
maybe these potential modalities on the
left um and uh be useful you know for
highlighting uh variants with this
evidence that you can use the filter
down the variants you might want to be
testing um to see if they have clinical
relevance so what types of models are
there what types of variant effect
pictures are there how can we think
about this we can have supervised models
can have unsupervised models we can have
Ensemble models supervised models
they're great we can learn directly from
known disease variants and we get strong
performance on wall variant types U
requires on requires labels if you have
it you have it use it unsupervised
models May Advantage no Reliance on
disease labels better generalization to
unseen variants maybe we can use these
to find things we don't already know
about and we can utilize evolutionary
sequence data in theory you can use
other things but in the context of the
variant effect prediction models that
are out there a lot of them you'll see
using evolutionary sequence data right
now you can also do a an ensemble model
might heard CAD things like this where
they aim to combine multiple sources of
evidence uh together which can be very
powerful um depending on your
question for the sake of this talk we're
going to continue and we're going to
focus on unsupervised models because
this seems to be um the next fr frer in
terms of like being able to uh
potentially say things about variants we
don't know things about going into this
space of um better General
generalization to unseen variant unseen
variance I think we've seen all the
variants no way so why unsupervised
models are gamechanging but this is just
a simple analysis looking at um believe
uh uh clingen and Nomad what we have is
just focusing on this is just focusing
on the 3% of the genome that is proteome
so you can imagine like if you had a
bigger pie chart you know like how much
we wouldn't know about the non-coding
genome but this is kind of the label
data we have so it's pretty awesome to
think about the potential for some of
these other methods in terms of
providing us evidence for going in and
um you know learning things about these
um variants that we've never seen or
been able to characterize
before so now we'll go into the part of
the talk where I try to sell you some of
the models you know that we work on in
my lab in the Mark's lab um so these
models are particularly interesting
because they rely on this assumption
that we can use this piece of orthogonal
information for uh human genetics that's
found in um the 8.7 million species in
the biosphere so we can look at
evolutionary sequence data where in
principle this Evolution has done a ton
of experiments for us already to
highlight variants that are uh desirable
and to tell us stories about variants
that maybe weren't desirable and so if
we see those variants of either category
in the human population maybe we can
learn a bit of evidence as to what
variant might be more or less
desirable so the distribution of
sequences across all these organism
teaches us a lot about constraint um
like I just said here's like a
mathematical uh formula of what I just
said we can think about uh potentially
variants that um are less probable
meaning they're less likely to be seen
in this like learned uh distribution of
sequences we see in evolution they're
less probable they're probably less fit
and we can create that as like kind of a
proxy for deleteriousness a proxy this
is not uh 100% this is deleterious this
is
evidence okay so to go into this a
little bit more
um deep learning models capture complex
conservation patterns which take the
full sequence context into account um so
looking for patterns and sequence
constraints is a relatively old idea
until recently only column conservation
was considered in this model you say oh
I'm going to take all my sequences I'm
going to line them up and I'm going to
say oh which one happened the most often
which one didn't happen the most often
that's a very simple idea if only only
uh biology was that simple um so um as
like a next step on top of that idea we
might start to look at pairs so this
might be uh best described in proteins
when you're seeing pairs because of
contacts where if you see residues
contact in contact with each other
presumably if one has a disruption
you're going to see A disruption um in
the other one so this is a somewhat uh
not I'm GNA say old but like not uh
breaking
news oh that's nice
okay um so some other potential models
you might consider you might ask
yourself oh well what about Beyond pairs
what if there's um more interesting
higher dimensional interactions well
things like variational autoencoders
other types of models they start to
address this question of like going into
this potentially nonlinear space um
mathematically and being able to pull
out um you know some of these higher
order
dependencies um we also see a lot of um
models these days you'll see from like
protein language models Etc which also
use slightly different strategies um
they a lot of times they don't
necessarily rely on strict alignments of
your data and that can be really
advantageous especially for proteins if
they don't align very well such as uh
antibodies which might have
hypervariable regions Etc um and then
you could imagine how this is even more
attractive potentially which I'll get to
towards the end if you wanted to look at
uh you know non-coding aspects of the
genome where you have uh you know less
constraint defined by structure that you
would see in proteins and they become
Less ad meable to alignment based
models so how do our models compare with
lab
experiments uh model predictions to lab
experiment yeah okay so Eve predicts uh
Eve is one of our models it's this model
here the vae so you can think of it as
like a deep learning model that's able
to pick up on higher order dependencies
um in the data so just breaking Beyond
uh pairwise dependencies it's still
going to get pairwise it's still going
to get sitewise but it can be
more um and what we published this work
back geez like 2021 I think now so like
right when I started my PhD um and what
we're seeing here is that basically the
model um is able to predict um you know
if a variant is uh uh benign or
pathogenic just as well as if you took
some mutational scanning experiment and
put that up to the same uh the same task
so it does it's as well as experiment so
in theory if you never had this model is
not trained on the experimental data we
made the experiment to confirm this or
to find new things so in theory you
never needed to do the experiment
because we don't do experiments to
validate our machine learning models we
do them to um well we might do that but
we should be doing them to find evidence
for clinical
variants uh so Eve is good at predicting
clinical
labels but many variant effect
predictors perform well at predicting
clinical lab labels and chlorate well
with experimental data
but they are not designed for comparing
uh variants in distinct genes we here on
the right originally we have Eve model
here that is unable to distinguish its P
its uh scores for two different classes
of genes the purple one or the one on
the top being Hao insufficient genes
where you would expect A disruption in
that Gene to be uh quite
deleterious whereas compared to a loss
of function tolerated Gene whereas you
had a varant in that Gene you wouldn't
expect it to be quite as deleterious as
the half loone sufficient Gene so what
we did is we said oh what if we could
combine this evolutionary information
with uh information from um
biobanks so we use a two-step uh modular
approach for building a whole proteo
model um where in this example we're not
taking like a single Eve model for a
single protein we're going to make
models for the whole proteum I don't
think we've quite reached 20,000 but
we've got a lot um
um and with this model we basically have
a VAR a variable for an evolutionary
score that we're getting from these uh
Eve models or other potential um protein
language models that might be ensembled
in some way and we basic basically uh do
a conditional distribution where we're
taking the probability of a variant
being seen in some um biobank in this
case the UK biobank and we're
conditioning this on um its evolutionary
score and um we can parameterize this as
a simple Bly distribution where our
prior um our prior uh is a gum process
prior and aside from this gum process
prior what's cool about this is we also
can have some measure of uncertainty in
the model so sometimes the model would
just give you a score and they'll tell
you how to interpret that score and
you're like great but wouldn't it be
nice to know how uncertain the model is
about that score because that might give
you an additional piece of evidence as
to say like how much can I trust this so
parameterizing models like this can be a
a powerful technique for giving the
researcher more um you
know uh more information about what the
model is um able to
discern um so in this case we see on the
top with our Eve model our original Eve
model which had no population data and
it's a little bit confused about how to
score the half insufficient genes versus
the loss of function tolerant genes and
then we see once we do um train a new
model with pop Eve we see um ignore the
actual um numerics on the x-axis there
it's about the comparison of the two box
plots not the actual numbers so what
we're seeing here is that the blue box
plot is slightly shifted higher meaning
it has a higher likelihood happening
meaning it's less deleterious versus the
purple box it's shifted left meaning
it's has a lower likelihood of being
seen under the distribution and
therefore it is um predicted to be more
deleterious
yes which Eve or po the eve
model it distinguish between the red and
the green bonds presumably like Capal
sufficient genes would have maybe more
like conservation than lolf tolerant
genes across species I think it would
but it's um you know I think like the
hypothesis here is that uh you know
you're you're losing some of those like
um characteristics are based on the what
we've seen in humans and you might want
to have more current uh standing
variation considered heavily in your
model which is why we add the additional
information from Human populations to
kind of get the model to say okay I'm
gonna focus more on the human variation
that I'm seeing but also consider some
of this evolutionary sequence uh
information as a prior that makes sense
and this is just like you can see it in
the data like that that's true but like
that's the intuition yeah
yeah
okay so you can try out these tools
um on the left is Eve
and I guess there's no links here for
you but you can Google them um for
trying out Eve and pop Eve mutation uh
portals they're pretty cool they'll also
I think I don't know if it's Eve or pop
Eve they'll also let you see the
mutation like in a three-dimensional
structure this is a little bit like
short changing them just showing you
this like ugly like front door but like
it well it's not ugly but it's like not
as cool as it could be if you put it in
an actual U thing to search there's
they're cooler than that I promise you
okay um so how can we evaluate these
models um so now I'm getting towards the
end uh but this is a very cool piece of
work that um uh Hillary fukan and others
here at the FR have uh worked on where
they've basically made uh this
collection of benchmarks uh and they
call them genetics gym where you know
there's a lot of variant effect
predictors out there which one do I use
for my problem for my variant who knows
uh I don't really believe in this world
where one model is King I think based on
your question and based on the training
data of the model you should decide you
know which uh pieces of evidence to
consider I don't I personally don't
believe in this like God model that you
can just feed all this data into and
it's going to um give you some like
crazy answer okay so how can we evaluate
these models in this paper I believe
they looked at Pop Eve which was the
model I just showed you this model
called
Misfit sorry if I don't know all these
models MPC they looked at Alpha mistons
which I believe we had a talked about
earlier in the year esm 1B primate
a3d and the first uh wish that was a
little bigger sorry about that and the
first uh evaluation they basically
looked at denovo mutations and severe
disorders um where they're comparing
mutations and individuals with
developmental disorders Etc versus
unaffected controls and for bit this
particular case you see um models like
pop Eva really shine which is awesome
you know we should just go home we
solved everything let's not look at
anything else we're the winners clap
please clap Okay no Okay so now we're
going to look at some other evaluation
um because you know this is science and
we need to not basically Champion our
own methods we need to say okay what
methods globally would be good um for
different questions so for this next
question they're looking at very rare
variance in psychiatric conditions where
you can kind of I didn't mention this
sorry but you can kind of think as I go
across here you can kind of think of
this as a spectrum whereas on the left
you might have things that are under the
highest constraints such as denovo
variant so if you recall back to my
beginning of the presentation when I had
that Spectrum so the ones all the way on
the left would be like variants that
under the strongest selection they're
not going to occur very often um so pop
Eve is very good at picking those up but
for the next one we might think of these
as being under moderate selection
potentially we see other models
potentially really shining at
this um and I suppose you could read the
paper to get more of an expose as to why
some of these underlying training datas
uh and model architectures are
particularly well suited for picking up
um uh signal from these different
variant classes called genetics gym um
so in this next one they're looking at
common disease variants which are under
weaker selection and they're looking at
rare and common variants associated with
v various phenotypes different biobank
datas like UK biobank engin
Etc and in this last one they're looking
at at F map variants so they're looking
at population genetics validation data
uh using newly observed variants and the
new Nomad V4 data but not in earlier
versions of nomad to independently
assess both Gene level and variant level
prediction of performance um maybe I
should have had that at the beginning
but anyway so that's the selection
pressure so what you can see here is um
these tasks you can kind of conceptually
think about them as being more or less
um having more or less selection
pressure and we can see very nicely here
that different models some of them look
like rock stars in the beginning um some
of them look like rock stars at the end
it's really uh um up to us like as um
computationalists who want to use these
tools build these tools to think
critically about what the underlying
data is and not blindly jump on the hype
train of new model I wonder if this is
going to give me the answer like no
consider them all think about it look
for really well done guideline studies
such as this to kind of give you some
bearings of how to like interact with
the models in these fi in this
field um so this is something I'm
working on my PhD don't read all this
sorry I should have done an animation
but basically well you can now say okay
what about unsupervise non-coding
variant effect prediction I talked a lot
about proteins what about non-coding
variant effect prediction so this is
like a big mess um but people are trying
to get out this question we've seen like
this year small conference papers such
as uh Bend um which one of my
collaborators wrote where they basically
took all these different some of these
different models you see her on the
right um that are allegedly training on
um non-coding information in an
unsupervised way and they're subjecting
them to um a lot of different uh t tasks
but I highlighted in the red box here
this variant effects task and you know
there is still a lot of room for
improvement on this task where the
variant effect here is going from you
know uh that beginning DNA sequence all
the way to the person with the the red
spots on their face so a lot of these
tasks also here on the left you can
think of them as like oh can I go from
sequence to to um you know RNA seek
expression can I go from sequence to uh
epigenetics like those are all kind of
those are good questions but you have to
keep in mind uh we don't know always
like when we have a change in expression
if that's good or if that's bad it just
is so um there's very there's a lot of
room here for being able to go all the
way across um all the way across uh from
uh you know molecular genomic
information to uh phenotypic information
inform um and you can check out I just
put a pre-print out um earlier uh I
don't know I think last week um on my
new model called La leave which is
basically trying uh uh to do this um
where essentially it uh trains on
promoter regions explicitly with uh
across Evolution and tandem with um uh
uh protein language model embeddings to
give you a prediction of uh the
delerious or pathogenic effect of indels
um and that's kind of all I'll talk
about here because it's kind of in the
weeds but you can check it out or ask me
about it afterwards but um not saying
this is solving the problem at all um
but it is like trying to get at that
question again of if we can do um you
know uh find mutations in our genetics
they go all the way a phenotype um in
the non-coding space so you want to
build a very effect prictor too how
Noble um so here is a commentary that we
just put out from the marks lab uh that
you can read I think it came out like
two or three days ago um on doing uh on
towards trustable use of machine
learning models a varant effects in the
clinic and this is a very important
piece of to read because you know it's
gonna highlight some of these questions
of like you give it model data and you
ask it to Pi something it
will but like
maybe you should ask the question of
what is it training on and then is this
like relevant for what I'm interested in
you have to ask these questions or else
you're you know you know you're blindly
trusting something and when it comes to
clinical uh clinical problems we can
blindly trust
nothing all right so thanks uh for your
time here's some
pictures um thanks to Harvard I think
Debbie's also associated with the broad
so thanks to the broad um and then
thanks to the NSF for funding me um and
yeah I'll take any questions if anyone
has
any thank you Courtney for an amazing
presentation uh please if anyone has a
question come on up to the
microphone do you think that the models
can eventually be able to understand
interactions between variants because if
a person has the dilar variant maybe
they have a a variant that compensates
and then it's doesn't affect them at all
that kind of thing love that question um
can they do it now I don't think so but
I think um I would like to believe that
given the right training Paradigm they
could pick that out but I think it's
hard to have good validation data for
those questions um so that's my answer
but I think that is an amazing question
that I'm very interested in um because
because you could imagine like even some
of these protein language models that
are predicting clinical effects um even
such as flppy vinance whatever okay they
predict that this variance is H
potentially alterus or pathogenic maybe
it's not so bad if there's a
compensating variant in a promoter that
turns that Gene completely off so I
don't know I think those are that's very
important for like getting like a global
picture of variation in in the
individual but um I think that's the
question I'm trying to get at maybe with
my models by coupling uh promoter
regions with um uh the actual protein
embeddings is then you could actually
ask the model that question like I could
ask the model that question right now
today would I know if it's right oh I
gotta find some good validation data so
that's a bit harder
yeah I know that there have been many
papers that have kind of set out when
people are doing function assays what
are the characteristics of those assays
that make them most amenable to
subsequent use in model building um do
you have any particular uh favorite
traits for those of us who do design
functional assays um in terms of either
how the experiments are designed or how
they're reported that make them more
usable for your models um I guess for my
particular lens on like non-coding
variation I'm always looking for like an
endogenous editing because um I want to
see how that variant actually manifests
in the functions of the cell and I'm
always looking for things that are more
lended towards growth screens um where
you see the cell type growth change over
time because I think that's a bit more
similar to what we might imagine as like
more of the organism level uh change so
for me when I think about like going all
the way across that Spectrum I want to
see things that do that and I'm not as
um not that it's not useful but I'm not
as interested in like these like
intermediate molecular
phenotypes oh another
one what is the what is the uh like
compute cost of running your
models well I mean I can't like just
tell you like
uh you give can give an estimate sure H
for pop Eve here's an estimate for we
needed like 500 more Eve models within a
short period of time and I think that we
spent $5,000 on like Google Cloud for
that but it can be upwards of like 20 to
30,000 if you're doing a lot of models
which is why we have some you know
industry people like ran a bunch of e
models for us and they paid for it yeah
they did it wrong there's also I don't
know the answer to that because for my
models like at Harvard we have like a
really nice cluster they built so I have
no idea how much that costs but it's
free to me but like uh like I was
training La leave on like really beefy
gpus like um
h100s yeah I don't know who paid for it
yeah so maybe that's a debie question
but like yeah um it's I like to see
think it's nominal um compared to
experimental costs
but maybe I'm
not great well thank you so much for
such an excellent talk today please go
ahead and grab a little more breakfast
and then we'll reconvene at 9:30 uh down
the hall for MPG