but now I'm very pleased to introduce Dr
George Westerman principal research
scientist at the MIT SLO School of
Management Dr Westerman is a world
recognized thought leader in leading
transformation and competitive advantage
through technological innovation he
works at the really exciting
intersection of executive leadership and
digital Innovation to provide continuous
valuable sites to leaders in all
Industries George
welcome thanks
Todd it's really great to be here and um
I'm it's especially great because at
home we got 5 Ines of snow yesterday and
there was no snow on the ground here so
that's a good thing so um yeah I teach
in the management school and so what I
focused on he said Technology Innovation
leadership I Tred to take Technologies
and make them to Dem mystify them to
help leaders understand what's happening
there and really think about how do you
design your organization and how do you
lead transformation so I did some of the
earliest research on digital
transformation 15 years ago to tell you
how long ago that was nobody used the
word digital transformation back then
right and so wrote some book on that I
I'd done work with it organizations
before that I've done work in skills and
careers and now of course AI all of
those things come together AI is
affecting all of that and so uh what I
want to do today is talk to you a little
bit about how do you think about
generative Ai and how do you work that
in your strategy now Eric has been doing
AI for almost as long as I've been alive
right and
um I want to try to tell you about AI
from a management standpoint and that
means it will I will try to make it
crystal clear for you in trying to make
decisions in your organization but it's
also means that if Eric and I disagree
he's correct okay so that's where we
want to go my job is to be as as clear
as possible help you figure out the
questions you can ask the instincts to
develop as you are making decisions
because all of you probably are having
to make decisions with AI how can I help
you understand that a little bit better
or if I could say it a different way um
how can it make a little bit less scary
and make you feel more competent in
dealing with this stuff so you ready to
go
um three pieces here number one is what
is AI uh now Eric already talked about
what is AI I'm going to give you my
version of it okay and think about these
these elements of the different kinds of
AI and how to think about it number two
is Gen AI because that's really where
we're spending a lot of time now a lot
of attention on chat GPT and Gemini and
mid journey and all these Sora and all
these others how do you think about
making that work in your organization
because it's tremendously powerful but
also very risky and how do you think
about that uh and then the last is what
what does that mean how are companies
innovating with this right now so uh
first what is AI and like I said it's a
little bit scary after having followed a
a AI Professor but like I said it's
mostly correct and hopefully very clear
when we talk about it uh what is AI well
the thing about what is AI is it's
really hard right the definitions Eric
gave were from
2003 now Google does not track Google
Trends back in 2003 they start in 2004
and look what generative
AI nobody was talking about it because
it didn't exist back then right uh but
then deep learning he talked about that
and you could see how that came on 10
years ago or something like that that
was really cool we had a thing called
the work of the future initiative and
the question there was with deep
learning doing what it is doing what
jobs will be left after the robots eat
the jobs okay and we found out actually
they don't eat the jobs they eat pieces
of the jobs right and also there's a lot
of extra effort that goes in it's not
just the technology but that was the
scariest most interesting Ai and now
what do we call that we call that
traditional AI right that's how fast
these things move go back a little bit
farther this is uh machine learning uh
and you can see you know it it why is
why is it bigger well it's a it's
actually a super set of these other two
and then artificial intelligence and the
interesting thing about this you see
artificial intelligence was more common
and now it's less common because
artificial intelligence back then was a
different kind of thing than it is now
just like Eric was talking about right
so with these with these elements how do
you make sense out of this mess when it
keeps moving so quickly I'm going to uh
really first give you my important law
that if you remember nothing else
remember this you know Moore's Law right
you know Mo's law and the exponential
right these things keep growing at an
exponential rate okay um this is
westerman's
law westerman's law is different
technology changes quickly organizations
change much more
slowly this is I know this to be true I
should not have to say this is true but
I know it to be true and you know it to
be true but our technology people often
forget this and your technology vendors
often forget this the hard part is not
adopting the technology it's changing
the way you do business it's not the
digital it's the transformation is the
hard
part and so what does that mean
technology is not the problem
transformation is so it's not really a
technical problem it's also very much a
leadership
problem we need to get both of those
things in there right and so you know
for example in talking about AI we've
talked to two we'll talked to a lot of
Executives but here's two that we can
quote right uh Matthew Evans who who
worked on AI for the manufacturing
process at Airbus he says says strictly
speaking we don't invest in AI or
natural language processing or image we
are always investing in a business
problem or if we go on to the Home Depot
fim squ uh another thing I do is I run
the MIT Sloan CIO leadership award every
year and fim was uh one of our finalists
last year and Home Depot is a HomeGoods
store right if you need Hardware or saws
or wood or anything you go to Home Depot
I am renovating a house right now so I
spent a lot of time in Home Depot and
fim and his team have created a really
good experience for a really really
complicated store he says we should
always be looking for Extraordinary
experiences we want to bring joy to the
user we want to Delight the technology
that's secondary and once again we
forget that all the time but we can't
forget that because technology provides
zero value to your
company what you do with the technology
is what creates that value you okay how
you change your business or your
products to make it work
better so what's the first thing from a
management side what's the first thing
you need to know about
AI artificial intelligence is not
intelligent okay and Eric mentioned this
and we should continue that right it is
a basically it's it's a program that
executes but it doesn't have that
context knowledge right um and we have
to remember that it's basically
executing a formula and that formula is
what you've programmed it to do what
what it's learned how to do but it may
not be the right thing uh a Oliva a
Oliva who uh has created AI that can
actually read what you are thinking
right with brain scans one of the
smartest people I know she says
artificial intelligence should be
artificial
idiots that's one way to think about
this okay it's not intelligent but the
thing is it can act very
intelligently and that's very useful as
long as we are careful as long as we do
it in the right way okay so the digital
transformation research this is an
update we started this in 2010 this is
an update from 2021 where can you look
for opportunities not from AI not just
from AI but from mobile and from
internet of things and from other
Technologies you're facing four good
areas you can look one is creating an
engaging emotionally emotionally
engaging targeted personalized customer
experience number one right number two
is operations not just automation but
the ability to adapt and adjust as
things go on right that's industry 4.0
the uh business models not just being
the Alibaba or the Amazon of your
industry but what can you do with
information to make more lwh hanging
fruit turning your products into
Services these kinds of things and what
we rediscovered we should have noted
before employee experience employee
experience is a critical part we know
that good satisfied employees lead to
satisfied customers we also know that if
you have a bad employee experience it's
a very good indication that your systems
and your processes are not running the
way they should or your incentives right
so when you're looking for what to do
with AI it's the same way we think about
any the other digital transformation
work you can look in these areas and not
only in these areas but the opportunity
to go across Like Home Depot has done
like Airbus has done okay um you'll see
also that this rides on top of your
systems your data your systems and if
that's a mess it's hard to do this AI
actually helps a little bit with that
messy data but the better your data is
the cleaner your processes are the
better you will be okay so uh I really
think of AI as the next stage of digital
transformation the same principles apply
but there's more that you can do and
there are more powerful
opportunities and so we still need to
lead this but we need to think more and
more about what we can do okay so here's
some things we could do with generative
AI um I I have designed courses over
time we're doing one in the Philippines
right now instead of courses and instead
of me standing up and stand putting a
suit on and going in front of a camera
now we just type words in and she will
say it instead and if you don't like how
she looks somebody else that looks
different will do it and they can do it
in a different language and frankly I
can do it with a deep fake very easily
right I don't need to go to a studio
anymore right uh also any any corporate
literature you have can be in any
language you want instantly with a push
of a button right uh over here certainly
coding many people are doing coding
right now how many of you are your your
programmers are they using co-pilots and
things like that well if they are not
it's time to start this really does help
now there are questions about whether
it's better for the senior people or the
junior people but there's a learning
process and it is better it's not only
better for coding but also enforcing
standards and making documentation
people hate doing that the computer can
help them okay what else is there well
Cresta Cresta is uh is a call center
tool especially for sales and you heard
some really good startups um this in a
randomized trial at MIT they found that
everybody using this tool got
better uh the most senior people got 14%
better the most Junior people got 34%
better if you have the senior and the
junior people they raise the bar for
everybody and it moves up what does it
do it listens to you talk and it gives
you hints while you are talking that
person is getting confused explain the
product better okay uh that person's
getting angry try this to calm them down
okay and then at the end it comes back
and says looking across what you've been
doing you don't close fast enough try to
get to the sale Fester these kinds of
things it becomes what a good supervisor
would be but it's with you all the time
and I'm working on a project right now
with the media lab where we are creating
a personalized tutor for the programming
class the first python class
for
um small uh sorry
minority institutions minority learning
institutions the idea is if we can get
people through that first class with an
individualized tutor they're on a set
for a career that they never would have
had possible but people drop out of that
first class because they do not have a
tutor so we're developing that right now
okay and then last but not least those
of you using any products whether it's
sap or workday or adobe this is being
integrated into all of your products
right so this is happening all over the
place but once again it's not the
technology it's what do you do with the
technology that makes better the other
thing that's really important here is we
talk about generative AI
Solutions but most of the best Solutions
are a
combination generative AI traditional AI
boring old it and also people and
process in there so lemonade uh they
have a very the very specific niche in
the insurance Market they write 98% of
their policies 98% of first claim
notices and they handle 50% of claims
off automatically through this
combination of different AIS and also
traditional systems what about that 50%
well the easy stuff the computer does it
and the hard stuff they give it to a
person to figure out what to do that's
how their model works okay um
and this is Cisco this is not the the
technology company Cisco this is Cisco
the Food Service delivery they have I
one of the largest truck fleets in the
world restaurants are around the world
gets supplied by these and here are all
the different ways that Cisco is
applying AI in what they do now this is
not a high-tech company they deliver
cans of stuff to restaurants but you
could see all the different things they
have on the customer experience side
over there and also on the back office
and uh when um Tom peek when I was
talking with him about what he does uh
all those little brains those are
opportunities where generative AI can
help you know we think about generative
AI in helping to figure helping a
salesperson figure out their call
planning but how about generative AI in
helping you route things around a
warehouse or uh how you know we we don't
have this thing that want we don't have
this kind of mushroom but this kind of
mushroom will work right so all kinds of
opportunities there so um if you
ask three AI experts what are the
categories of AI you will get five five
different
answers nobody can really agree so I'm
going to give you my four
categories and I'm not going to tell you
this is right I'm going to tell you it's
mine okay if that helps so um four
categories and this should look familiar
because Eric talked about a lot of this
right and what I want to do is walk you
through these just to give you a little
bit more Instinct on what to do about
these things okay so number one
rule-based systems Eric called it expert
systems put a lot of if then statements
together 1984 when I first started
programming my one of my first jobs was
to create an engine for a rule-based
system and like Eric said these things
don't work right beyond the simplest
problems but now rules engines are
better and if you use them in the right
environments
prescriptions loan making these kinds of
things within the limits in which they
are good they are useful but don't try
to get outside that context okay um then
there's a conom metrics which is
statistics most of us learned in school
deep learning generative AI let's walk
through these things okay so expert
systems we talked about this how do you
program them you talk to an expert and
the expert tries to figure it out but
there's a nice Paradox which is that we
know more than we can tell or as Eric
said your two-year-old understands
physics but couldn't tell you how that
works okay and we have that problem all
the time but you have to talk to an
expert you don't need any data the
expert the good thing is these are they
will give you a PR precise answer and
they will give you the same answer every
time but they do not
adapt right you add a rule things get a
little tricky so that's one thing
econometrics that's the next thing right
that's statistics we many of you
probably learned statistics you've
probably forgotten much of it but we
still use this all the time right if you
have structured data meaning data that
you can put into a spreadsheet usually
numeric data these things work and they
work really really well okay they're
pretty pretty cheap to uh to program and
especially the two things right how do
we create a formula for those two
Dimensions that will help us to figure
out is it a blue thing or a green thing
okay and they tend to be they are false
positives there are false negatives but
they tend to be pretty good okay the
other is looking at the trend line
looking at the regression okay these
things actually work remarkably well
with numeric data and also things you
can turn into numic data like is he
going to buy my product based on what I
do to him okay um you can also do
multiple Dimensions finding that trend
line with two Dimensions easy try it
with 100
Dimensions we U I have a team right now
currently looking at 100 million CVS
resumés and tracking people's careers
through that 100 million rums to try to
figure out what is a more or less
productive path you're not going to do
that by just looking at two dimensions
right um and then of course you don't
have to just look at lines but you do
have to have an idea of what the
functional form is that you're looking
at so it's awful numeric there's some
things but you can do this it's
relatively cheap it works really well
you get precise answers you get the same
answer every time but it has to be
numeric
data then you have deep learning and
Eric talked a lot about deep learning
this was the coolest thing ever 15 years
ago and it's still pretty darn cool okay
now the thing is Eric also showed you
there like 50 different versions of this
right so I'm just going to give you one
archetype this picture do you know what
that picture
is it's a neural net but you know what
this picture mostly is it's a thing that
people use to scare you right it's a
complicated looking thing and it looks
there's a little bit of magic involved
in there so Eric explained this but let
me explain it also a little bit more
you're taking inputs you're running them
through a set of weighted averages and
coming out with a prediction of multiple
different states at the end
okay and it sounds very
easy but it gets Beyond human capability
really fast okay you you train it with
labeled data you need to know the truth
that's why every time you log in and it
says prove you are
human tell us where there is a car tell
us where there's a bicycle you are
labeling data to train these things
every time you get on social media and
they do the the Aging challenge show us
you and show us you 20 years ago you're
creating labeled data of old and young
people right you need that data um and
then you do the the outputs are
repeatable but they are in no way
explainable our smartest people are just
starting to figure out how to make this
explainable and it's going to be a
little while okay but I'm going to give
you an example now an
MIT I'm going to get a little
complicated on you but I promise not too
complicated the good thing is I'm going
to try to take this scary picture and
make it a little bit more real Eric
started I'll try it and after the two of
us hope it will make sense okay what are
those
anybody they're
numbers now try to tell me if we were to
say features right loops and lines and
these kinds of
things tell me the formula the set of to
look at the number two how would you
create the rules to decide what is a
number
two well it has a little loop at the the
top it has a loop down here and then the
number goes down right that's how a two
looks except that uh no Loop there right
and there the line is going across
instead of going down right if you were
to try to program this with a bunch of
features you would probably not get very
far but 35 lines of code 25 to 35 lines
of code can do this no problem at all by
by doing this kind of thing what do you
do well first of all you take these two
dimension objects and you turn them into
a one-dimensional set of numbers okay so
28 by 28 image becomes 784 pixels now
what you have just done is you've thrown
away all the relationships between what
is on top of each other you've thrown it
away and the algorithm doesn't care and
then you put the numbers in the left
hand side and you have random numbers
here and it spits out 10 estimates 0
through n How likely is it that that is
the number okay and so you come through
and you get this well maybe we think
maybe it's a two a one we think
maybe it's
a two maybe it's a seven okay and some
stronger or less strong estimates and
then you go back and say hey it's really
a nine and you go back the other way and
you turn all the knobs to make it a
little bit better
okay now if that bothers you
how much do you turn each knob it should
bother
you because nobody knows how much you
turn each knob but we do know if you do
this 10,000 times the knobs end up in
the right
place so if it sounds like magic to you
it is Magic it's the magic of large
numbers and good algorithms okay and so
if you're wildly uncomfortable then you
are like the rest of us we are all
wildly uncomfortable with this but it
does
work so you do that 10,000 times and it
get gets there now what does that mean
well that means you got to have labeled
data you need to know what that number
really is you need to do the
reinforcement over and over again and
you need to back chain to to adjust
those numbers okay if your data is
biased let's say we have only data on
men but not women well then what happens
when a woman comes in this Amazon found
this out they were reviewing resumés to
try to figure out what resumés look like
their best to engineers
and they were routinely rejecting
women why was that none of their
Engineers were women and women talk
differently right uh by the way if you
were the captain of the women's swimming
team you would never get a job none of
the men that they trained it on were
ever captain of the women's swimming
team right and also different use so
they had to go five and fix that bias
same thing if you train on men versus
women children versus adults different
parts of the world okay so you got to
get rid of that you got to test that
bias you also need to make sure you
actually have some kind of accuracy in
your data so that's it no more on the
neural Nets do you understand that
picture I could test you and you would
know how to say that now okay well at
least nobody can scare you anymore all
right so then G continues and as Eric
said you know what they do now not only
they're using a lot of these similar
algorithms but they're also inventing
and they're saying okay given what you
told me and everything I know what's the
next best word or pair of words to say
and then it says okay once I have that
given everything you told me and
everything I know plus everything I just
invented what's the next best word
what's the next best word and it can get
things very right as you've seen you can
also get them very
wrong I first did my bio with cat GPT
and it the bio was really good expert on
digital transformation and Innovation
strategy author of four award-winning
books blah blah blah I loved it right
I've only written three
books I don't know what that fourth book
is but it and it wouldn't tell me right
so you want to be careful but the
interesting thing about that is well
I'll come back to that in a minute it
randomly generates the next so why do
you get a different answer every time
because it is random it's meant to be
that way okay and you can use that um it
creates new things it doesn't just
classify it creates new right it can be
used for good as bad you can get some
boring stuff you can also get creative
stuff but you also get this the
hallucinations right uh my favorite is
this this lawyer prepared all of his
court documents using chat
GPT and unfortunately some of the cases
that he cited as precedent for what he's
doing were not
real that made the judge very angry okay
so not only did he get in trouble with
the judge but he ended up in all the
business press as being the laughing
stock don't do that right but here's the
thing we are so worried about these
hallucinations but how many of us know a
perfect
employee people make mistakes too right
and so the idea is not to expect a
perfect answer maybe except if your car
is driving right um but the answer is to
get these things to work well and put
the right controls in in case they are
wrong the same thing we do with people
so why do we expect the computers to be
better than people in every Cas is why
don't we just put the right processes in
place to account for the fact that these
are sometimes not
right um the other thing of course huge
training data this thing needs and huge
amounts of energy and so um these are
other other topics we can talk about
over time so what the problem is you got
to use the you got to start with the
problem and figure out the right
technique so one way to think about it
is there are questions you can ask how
accurate do I have to be and how what's
the cost of being wrong getting in a
traffic accident or making a wrong
medical decision there's a big cost
sending the wrong marketing message to
somebody no cost at all right do you
need the answer to be explainable
because if it does then those first two
are probably useful those NE those last
two they're not
explainable how do you do that right do
you need the answers to be the same
every time you're not going to get that
that with generative AI right and
confidentiality and confidentiality is
less of a problem right now you can get
these generative things that are going
to keep you or at least the vendors
promise they will keep you safe right
but these are things to think about
right then on the other side is the
data do you have a source of truth and
how true is that data and number two is
it generalizable or are you going to
reject all women that apply for your
company okay so as you're thinking about
how to do it these are questions you can
ask about this problem I'm trying to
solve right
now and the the questions either you can
make the decision or you can ask these
questions of your technical people and
first of all they will now be a little
bit afraid of you right but second of
all you will have a better conversation
because you are asking these
questions so first bit what is AI four
things here's how to think about them
here if he likes traffic lights here's a
nice little chart you can use right to
think about these things where are they
good and bad but that's only part of the
problem that's the part saying okay I
have a specific problem I want to solve
how do I I think about what the right
technique
is the real problem is how do I make
this work in my
organization so I have more questions
for you maybe some more answers you
ready
okay how do I make it work to the new
organization Remember come back to this
technology is not the problem
transformation is what is how do we put
the processes the the policies and the
capabilities in place to do this the
right way because doing it once is hard
but you need to do it over and over and
you need to make it mix in with the rest
of the stuff that you
do here are three challenges to think
about when you try to make this stuff
work in your organization and I'd like
to say this is only geni but this is
basically anything how do we work this
in right but with generative a how do we
prioritize what to do and what not to do
what do we do first what do we do second
and what do we never
do number two risk management you know
what if we are wrong what if we have a
privacy problem these kinds of things
and last is the capabilities so four
sets of questions you can ask for that
and then after this I'll I'll have one
more little section for you
okay how do you ensure the safety and
the value of what you're doing and one
of the big and the other ones is
learning how do you not only learn about
this Innovation but how do you learn
across Innovations so you can choose the
best way to do things and you don't end
up doing the same thing 10 times
okay um one of the big questions to
think about here is what how does
your governance process look
and what we've seen in generative AI is
multiple approaches but they tend to
fall into top down this is a very risky
very expensive thing let's control
everything okay and the good thing about
that is we're not going to make mistakes
we're not going to throw money away
we're probably not going to kill a lot
of
people but we're also not going to
innovate very well because the central
part of large organizations it doesn't
always know the best opportunities okay
the other side is the is the
decentralized way hey go out and
innovate do whatever you want okay now
here are some rules you know don't don't
steal money don't do be bad to people
right but here are some rules innovate
within these rules and tell us about
what you're
doing it's a tremendously good way to
discover really interesting ideas at the
edges but it's a great way to waste
money also okay and also depending on
how careful are being you can also break
some laws when you do that because where
the central might try to be very careful
the edges might not and so what what we
saw in gender of AI is the very top down
safe but
slow or the very decentralized very fast
but more risky and more costly we saw
both of those coming out so at Society
Jal one of the big French
banks they had a they did it in a very
centralized way but they asked everybody
to say if you did if you want to do this
what would you do and they got 700 use
cases and what they decided is they did
a few of those right away but the rest
they said wait because all these cases
an intelligent agent is important a
chatbot to talk to people is important
programming is important let's do this
the right way and we will build
everything on top okay so they did a few
things fast they did they told other
things to wait until they had these
other capabilities set up they tried to
bridge the centralized and decentralized
Cisco that I told you about they did a
different way they said you know what
this is just another
technology we have a way we think about
this and the first thing we think about
is can we buy this instead of building
it and if we can we will do that the
second thing they say is if we think it
needs to be programmed can we do it
cheaper and easier with expert systems
and statistics or do we do the fancy
complicated stuff and only when it
answers all those questions do they do
the Leading Edge the generative AI so
you see these these governance rules
they fit in there right you got to
figure out what works with your company
and how does it fit the risk profile
that you're thinking
about some other questions you want to
ask though are also just as important is
our culture ready for
this what happens when the computer is
just as smart as our expert
person 15 years ago this started
happening in Banks where the computers
were as good at judging a high quality
or a lowquality loan than people were or
Insurance the computers were just as
good at underwriting some things as
people the people felt very threatened
by that and it was a whole process it's
happening in all kinds of jobs now if
you've seen the movie
Moneyball have you seen I don't know
whether America you know baseball's a
big deal I don't know if it is here but
you know there's big question right how
do I tell who is a good potentially new
employee for this
company maybe the computer is better and
people don't like that okay so do we
have the humility to work with these or
do we fight against
them do we have ethics to do the right
thing and not the wrong thing right and
also in the culture how good are we at
experimenting and trying things and
failing fast rather than trying to have
the first answer the right answer before
we start
okay the culture's got to be ready for
these things and the way you do that you
have to drive that you don't just say
plug in the model you got to help people
get comfortable right with Innovation
units other things and another one also
with people being
comfortable do we have the skills but
what does this mean for
careers a friend of mine uh Daniel Rock
looked at gpts and he has calculated
through a very rigorous process that 46%
of all jobs are likely to have 50% of
their tasks replaced by AI over
time now some jobs it'll be
100% these are just 46% percent of jobs
will have half of their tasks go what if
you do that job how do you feel about
that and am I going to am I going to go
along with this or am I going to reject
this because I think it's going to hurt
my job so what do you what do you do
about this certainly we've done I've
done some some writing on this and
certainly after lunch you're going to
see some really interesting stuff on
that but AI doesn't have to replace you
how can it make your job easier reduce
your cognitive load how can it do one of
the things I do it for all the time I'm
a pretty good writer but I'm not I don't
do those sexy creative titles so I let
AI do it now give me five potential
titles for this right uh or I can give
it my text and say make this more
exciting
right um and the other thing we did not
expect is the ability to learn with ai
ai is a tremendous teaching tool and I'm
finding I'm learning all the time just
by having it help me think having it
asked questions about what I'm doing or
uh and certainly I talked about this
tutor we are doing and and many places
are doing these tutors including at
Cresta and at one of the startups we
talked about right so it does not have
to replace us are you having that
conversation with your people
about how this you're not just saying
we're not going to hurt you because
nobody believes that right but can you
have the conversation about how we can
help you introduce this uh so for
example denu creative an advertising
firm that is a firm that you might think
should be a little bit nervous about
these
things and um what they're finding is
that these creative people love this but
they're being very systematic in the
company about how they introduce this
first of all they are saying all the
boring stuff your planning your
proposals those kinds of things it will
do that for you take a few words and
turn it into a proposal that's great
what they didn't expect and that they
love now is let's draw a picture and
instead of saying Go away and in a week
we will have a design for you now they
say go get a cup of coffee and in five
minutes we'll have a design for you and
now we can iterate that and iterate it
you can do it with the client it's
better for both they didn't expect that
right the other thing they're doing
though is they're not saying you use it
you use it what they're saying is
everybody use it we will help you and
let's get together and share your ideas
what is working for you what's not
working for you these office hours where
people share their tricks so people are
investing as a group in getting better
and you see what happens it frees up the
T the time that creatives need to be
creative all the stuff they hate they
don't have to do they can't see
themselves going back to the old way so
what they did they were very careful
about helping people understand how this
can be good for them not just bad for
them they involved them in that process
and that's how they they they avoided
the rejection and they get better with
this in coding in your marketing people
in many places you will customer service
you will have this thing going on a lot
of
fear we've done a thing called the
global opportunity Forum where we are
getting companies talking to companies
about career
questions how are you developing your
people what are skills that you need
what's the best way that you can do to
help your people grow with you instead
of being afraid as you grow and so if
you're interested contact me about how
to how how we are getting companies
together to think through this
challenge so that's that you ready for
the last part of this
talk we talked first of all about types
of AI four types and if you have a
particular problem how do you decide on
the right type and I gave you questions
you can ask then we talked about having
your company be have the capability to
use this well to transform in a better
way and questions you can ask there
about culture and helping your people be
ready so we just completed a study it's
coming
out tomorrow in Sloan management review
about how are company's looking at
transformation with generative Ai and we
were looking for these giant
Transformations let's change the entire
underwriting process in a firm or let's
turn over all of our
sales and customer service to a
computer we didn't find those but we did
find a lot of smaller Transformations
happening that people are starting to
get a lot of value from this and setting
themselves up for the bigger
transformation over time so what we do
is if you think about the big
Transformations as being transformation
with a big capital t
what we found is that companies doing
are doing a lot of transformation with a
litty smaller Transformations but
they're doing it in a systematic way
that is helping them get ready okay and
it looks like
this level one is most companies already
are thinking about individual
productivity here is a version of the
llm that is safe to use or here's our
own private version right McKenzie for
example has an llm that looks across all
of their slide
decks and it's not perfect but if you
need to know about energy generation in
Southeast Asia McKenzie probably did
this once before and it can help to
answer some questions for you okay so
not only the public things but the
private things they're starting to do
from the individual productivity
standpoint very low risk they're just
informing people it's a good way to get
started okay number two is to specialize
roles and tasks let's start to transform
form that so we're seeing it in call
centers a lot we're seeing it in coding
we're seeing it in some other things
typically a human still stays in the
loop but sometimes for low-risk
things they're letting the computer take
over okay like at lemonade right
lemonade is 50% of things get processed
automatically 50% they the the more
risky things they take up and so that's
starting to happen and then then what
we're we're not seeing as much of except
in technology companies is actually
doing the Direct Customer impact okay so
how do we think about this in the first
level individual productivity summarize
these documents uh many many banks I
know that the minute a company releases
its
financials a minute later five minutes
later all the spreadsheets are
updated you you had to have a lot of
interns that did that before now it just
happens right these kinds of things
could happen sum well sorry that that's
the next piece but summarizing documents
hey what what just happened at my
meeting right and in the company
specific llms the opportunities in the
tasks are like that one can we make
sense of the the latest quarterly report
for financials um can we think about
customer support that's human in the
loop right they tend to be lower risk
and you keep the human in the loop to
help mediate that risk even
more and last but not least we're seeing
this farther thing the direct engagement
and we're seeing this in online right
now uh the people that make coach and
Kate Spade
things things that only this big but
they cost a lot of money right um
they're personalizing a very
conversational approach to help you just
as if you went in the store and that
person would make you buy that handbag
that pays that you charge too much money
for now online they can start to do the
same thing relatively low risk those
kinds of things are starting to happen
um and also the idea of doing the first
or second tier of customer service and
then these are happening right the
product companies are already doing it
because they have to right what we're
seeing less of is this bottom thing
transformation of
large processes what will happen from
what we're hearing is that you're not
going to get geni replaced in the hole
but
combinations will do it gen will have a
part so many companies we already have
them the forms that you give generative
AI will translate that into into Data
that the rest of the processes can use
and then it will translate it back into
conversational later you'll see these
combinations happening more and more
okay so you want to think about the
risks and the capabilities What's
Happening Here we call this the risk
slope how as you grow you grow your risk
management capability but you all also
grow your capability to do more and more
bigger things over time okay here's the
reason why this is so
important the proofs of concept it's
easy to do them but making it work at a
large group of users or
customers getting from the lab to
reality is really hard and in fact in a
large bank she said The more stuff you
do the more stuff you find to do she did
not mean more features we can build she
meant more errors we have to
solve and what one way to think about it
is H&M the fashion company it's almost
like putting a tire on a car how many of
you have changed the tire on your
car not many people well if you've ever
changed the tire you know that you do
not put all put a bolt on really hard
and another one because you will bend
the tire you'll bend the rim put a
little bit a little bit a little bit a
little bit okay that's how you want to
think about your AI capability in your
companies do it here learn from there
for the next thing the next thing okay
so what's the conclusion I just gave you
a lot of
stuff but that's okay this is MIT right
you're smart
people um AI can seem to be intelligent
but be intelligent in how you use it but
remember just because it's not perfect
that doesn't mean it's
bad your people also make
errors put the right processes right
controls to deal with the fact that
people are sometimes wrong okay number
two start with the problem not the
technology and many times the answer
will be combinations not just one of
these you look at the task that needs to
be done number three get started now
because because if you're going to put
that tire on your car little bits you
work up the growth slope the risk slope
and every time you do something you
learn more to be better at
it you got to help your people be
ready because if they're not ready they
will fight you and they will fight you
either very actively or more likely
they'll just say oh that's hard I don't
know what to do right those of you who
have te teenagers you know they do both
right so um and last but not least
continuous improveed what can you do
with small T Transformations that will
help the large te Transformations later
on okay so I have exactly 10 seconds
left so I'm going to ask for questions
even though I'm not allowed to so let's
take a few questions but I won't go too
far over okay can we do some
questions so by the way lots of good
reading if you want it including the new
article so thank you very
much what should we do with questions
ah they're up
here I don't get to choose the question
this is scary um or just pushing
everyone to use AI even the blueco
collar workers is this the right move is
it necessary for everybody the
interesting question thing that you said
in there is they're pushing
everyone how can you encourage everyone
you see the
difference if I say you have to do this
half the people are going to say you
can't tell me what to
do if you say hey this is a fun set of
tools that's try to help you think
through it they might be a little bit
more interested so what I suggest is
have encourage everybody to do it and
you might learn something and if you
encourage everybody to do it they might
actually suggest some Innovations and
fight this a little bit more okay what's
another question there we go um many of
our works revolve around achieving
efficiency and optimization when AI
can when AI can do that better what
would be the F focus of humans work so
certain we had the the work of the
future initiative Ben's going to talk
about this more also after lunch some
really fascinating things but there I'm
convinced there will be plenty for
people to do and in an Ideal World you
take all the boring
stuff let the computers do that and you
let the people do more interesting stuff
now that's an ideal world but can we get
closer if you think way automation has
worked all over time it has always taken
the routine work but there's still been
a role for humans and when you look at
the way Advanced manufacturing works you
still have people in there they're just
not doing the really boring stuff
anymore right so I think there will be a
role for humans and the tricky part is
trying to figure out how to introduce
the right things in the right way and to
engage your people in the
process um the global opportunity Forum
we're talking about is another
opportunity there next up how do you
balance creativity with and without AI
what are the advantages
disadvantages of flexing ideas I don't
see any disadvantage actually I do see a
disadvantage I do it all the time what
are some creative ways to think about
this you can always ignore it but what
would I do without the computer I would
go to a couple friends what's a creative
way to think about this okay so I don't
see a problem with helping the computer
be more helping the only challenge is
sometimes you start down a route and you
get stuck in that route so just as if
you're talking to people when you're
talking with the computer be ready to
back out of that route and try a
different thing you know you can get
uncreative because you get stuck in a
certain path okay um but absolutely Flex
the ideas all you can you don't have to
accept those ideas uh how can we prepare
young people for a job 15 years from now
that might not exist due to AI anymore
hopefully if you are training sorry let
me say that differently certain people
you train to do a job right we have
vocational training all over the place
you train them for that job because they
nobody should expect that you start a
job now and it will be the same job in
years now there are some you know my my
mom was a school teacher 15 years later
she was still a school teacher but she
was teaching differently uh my uncle was
a
fireman 15 years later he was still a
fireman but there were new tools he had
to learn to use okay you should so you
train people people for the job if
you're training them for a job but they
should also get the ability to learn
they should gain the Comfort the growth
mindset to get things and you should
always train that okay as far as
training people for what will the good
things be um creativity working with
people critical
thinking these don't seem to be going
out of style this this generative AI
stuff those don't seem to be going out
of style for a while right actually
writing those emails maybe but knowing
how to tune those emails to be the right
kind of interaction with people AI will
help but those things will happen so
what I I call these human skills and we
have a framework we call the MIT human
the the in in when I was in open
learning the human skills framework
right and that framework we think about
how
I think how I work with others how I
manage myself how I lead others those
skills are probably not going to go away
and so how can you get those in college
how can you get those in high school
teamwork
writing and communicating leading things
even when you're 12 years old okay okay
I think that's the end of my time so I
want to thank you and I'll be bring
around at lunch if you want to talk bye