Video
five, prototype problems, not products.
No one likes uncertainty. If you're
innovating, that's all you have. Think
about it. You're tackling a problem no
one has before. without a ready-made
problem statement, with a technology no
one has used quite that way before and
you're working off a hunch. Really, all
you have is uncertainty. I am using the
word hunch because it's the best word in
the English language to describe the
state of your idea at the very start.
When you start, that idea isn't really
fleshed out. At best, it's something
exciting you want to work on, but you
know you need to flesh it out before you
can even work on it. And so instead of
talking about ideas and putting all
those attributes and ideas as scalable,
disruptive, and what not, I invite you
to think of everything you're thinking
about at the start as a hunch, something
that should get you excited for what
comes next, as opposed to stressed out
for how big or disruptive it needs to
be. The only way to move forward is to
get real. The sooner the better, so you
can get on with the job, which I told
you already, is fixing what's wrong
about your idea. You start by
prototyping the problem. Yes, the
problem. You may be tempted to start
prototyping some product or the pitch.
But if a user, the product and the
solution are known, then someone else
must have worked out the problem for you
like in math class. That's how much we
dislike uncertainty. This is how it
typically goes. You end up taking a
gamble on the solution you imagined and
stop paying attention to the problem.
You leave no room for being wrong. And
by the time you discover how you were
wrong, failing is the only viable option
you have left. In 2013, in an interview
with National Public Radio, Chris
Hatfield, the Canadian astronaut,
described how astronauts prepare for a
mission to the space station in a way
that I believe captures the difference
between prototyping a problem and
focusing on the solution.
Half of the risk of a six-month flight
is in the first 9 minutes. So, as a
crew, how do you stay focused and how do
you not get u paralyzed by the fear of
it? And the way we do it is to break
down what are the risks. And a nice way
to keep reminding yourself is what's the
next thing that's going to kill me? And
it might be 5 seconds away. It might be
an inadvertent engine shutdown or it
might be uh staging of the solid rockets
coming off or it might be you know some
transition or or or some some key next
thing. We've already say had one
computer fail and we've had one
hydraulic system fail. So if these three
things fail now we're you know we need
to react right away or we're done. So we
don't just live with that though. And
and the thing that is really useful I
think out of all this is we dig into it
so deeply and we look at okay so this
might kill us. This is something that
would normally panic us. Let's get
ready. Let's think about it and we go
into every excruciating detail of why
that might affect what we're doing and
what we can do to resolve it and have a
plan and be comfortable with it and
practice it. In this interview,
astronaut Chris Hatfield is talking
about focusing on the problem. To them,
that's going to the space station and
making it back to Earth. And the way
they do it is by discovering what might
go wrong and finding ways to fix it in
the rocket, through practice, or
whatever. When the mission starts, they
are prepared for everything they
foresaw, and they're ready to handle
many things they could not have
predicted.
That is what I mean by prototyping the
problem.
When you prototype the problem, your
goal is to make the problem tangible
enough for you and others. The more
tangible your description of the
problem, the easier it will be for you
and them to see ways to solve the
problem. In contrast, prototyping a
madeup solution for a problem you do not
understand is like putting the carriage
before the horse. You do not want to
wait until launch day to see if you're
working on the problem. If you do,
you'll miss out on everything that's not
captured by what you imagined to be the
solution. It would be as if the
astronauts had picked ahead of time the
one thing that might go wrong and
prepared only for that. There's more I
would like to tell you about how to
prototype the problem. I am also aware
old habits die hard. You can find out
about more strategies in my book,
Innovating Adors Manifesto or in the
many materials I've shared online. For
now, let me just give you a tip for how
to get started. This is how you can
start practicing.
Come up with three solutions to the
problem.
Prototype all three. Then ask yourself
or someone else the following two
questions. Are these three solutions
sufficiently different? And how would
you know either of them actually solves
the problem?
Once you start getting real, you realize
there's multiple ways to chip at the
problem and have an impact.
[Music]