hello Within the Music 21 Corpus there's
another subcorpus which is a pretty
useful one and that is the Corpus of the
complete corals of jsbach I'm really
thankful to Margaret Green Tree who
contributed all of these before her
untimely passing so within music 21
let's go ahead and import Corpus because
that's going to be pretty useful
and we
can have within the Corpus a sign called
Corpus doc
corals and see that there and there's a
sign called the Corpus Coral's iterator
which will go through this and so we can
say for Coral in the Corpus Coral
iterator print Coral do metadata that's
the data about the data the data about
the piece and we can print its title and
it's going through and it's a little bit
slow because it's actually parsing them
and along the way as it's going that'll
take some time so you can go ahead and
interrupt that uh while it's going so
not every Corral has four parts so
sometimes as we want to do um if
Coral L
Coral or spell
Parts not equals 4 will
continue then let's do this let's print
Coral
metadata title and we'll
say that we just put a call in at the
end and then for I in range 4 012 3
right P equals coral. Parts
I print
I and then the the length of P do flat.
notes we curse will be a little faster
but we'll have to do that and we'll
say the end of that
is let's I'll put comma space something
like that and now we can go through oops
or interrupt
that I think it's probably useful to
print a new line afterwards and we can
kind of see how the various parts are
and you can imagine that you can go
through this and play with it and have
um so interesting things on which parts
have more notes and which parts have
fewer notes and so
on some of the things that we could do
with a complete Corpus of crows are look
at the types of motion where do climaxes
appear here where can uh
we find uh repeats uh what are the kinds
of time signatures that appear in Cals
basically all the things that you guys
did uh in problem set three which is
just wonderful um or probably yeah to
talk about what you can do with the
Corpus corals so this is the coral
Corpus if you want to quickly go through
and just find particular ones you can
say that the
return type is something else uh file
name and this will allow you to pass
them into the converter
if1
one in
Coral real
Coral equals Corpus
parse
C and there are all the CRS with 11 in
the name so these are just some things
that you could um be working with and
you can even this is a small enough
number we can show each of
them and I'll take a little bit of time
but we'll start getting to see all all
the crows in a
piece our friends at Intel bum bum bum
bum have created a tutorial on how you
can use B Cals and work through the
iterators and explore the data and begin
looking on emotion recognition and so on
from the bach corals and even do
artificial intelligence and plot various
things we'll show you this in a second
and Pitch throughout tie very short
video thanks for watching