Good morning.
My name is Carol Macon.
I'm the faculty lead for MITHIC.
I want to extend a welcome
to everyone online watching
this, as well.
Thank you so much,
Rick and Agustín,
for that important
conversation, which I think
will resonate
throughout the day.
So we have four sessions today.
And I'm just going
to talk a little bit
about the structure of them.
And then I'm going to disappear.
So I will come up
introduce the session.
We then will have two
presentations of research
that was supported by MITHIC.
A moderator will join
the presenters on stage
to lead a conversation
looking for common themes.
And then I will return to stage.
And I'll be here to moderate
questions and answers
from the audience.
So as you hear
these presentations,
do think about the
questions you may have.
So our first session is on
two education initiatives
supported by MITHIC.
And I noticed that we have a
parallel to our first session
in that we had Agustín,
a philosopher, and Rick,
a political scientist.
We now have Kieran
Setiya, a philosopher,
and Lily Tsai, a
political scientist,
talking about their work.
So they'll be joined by
Melissa Nobles, our Chancellor,
to moderate the conversation.
But first, let's
start with Kieran.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you so much.
As is appropriate for a
presentation about great books,
this is going to
be very low tech.
This is the only slide I have.
It will be almost
entirely papyrus-based.
Now what we're calling a
great books initiative at MIT
is, so far, a sequence
of two subjects,
Classics of Western Philosophy
offered in the fall,
and Ancient Authors offered
by literature in the spring.
The courses are
loosely integrated.
They have common themes.
There's minimal overlap.
So it would make
sense for a student
to take both, which
we're going to encourage.
They don't have a unified set
curriculum of great books.
And in each case,
the subjects were
ones we were really keen to
teach but unable to staff
reliably without
donor-directed funds.
So we have a three-year
pilot right now
for which we're
extremely grateful,
to race data and analog devices.
So why were we excited
about teaching great books?
And what does it mean
to talk in those terms?
There are grounds
for skepticism.
So great books, courses,
programs and colleges are
an artifact of the first
half of the 20th century,
beginning with John Erskine's
General Honors at Columbia
in 1920.
It was discontinued in 1928,
but then revived and revamped
as Literature
Humanities in 1937.
Meanwhile, Columbia
defector Mortimer Adler
left for Chicago in 1930.
And that took up the mantle
of great books education.
And then another landmark was
St. John's College Indianapolis
was the first college
devoted to a great books
curriculum in 1937.
If you flash forward to the
present, programs like these
are notable for their
relative absence.
And they've come
to be associated
with political
conservatism, and those
who advocate for great books
with a reactionary narrative
that has three parts that
I want to talk about.
So one is an idea that
the Western canon reflects
the key ideas,
democracy, liberalism,
maybe the scientific
method of something
called Western civilization.
The second idea is that
academics enamored of feminism,
post-colonialism, and
multiculturalism dismantled this
canon in the 1980s and 1990s.
And the third idea is that
the predictable result of this
was the decline of the
humanities, which had betrayed
their cultural inheritance.
Now every element of that
narrative is misleading.
In an essay on
Western civilization--
I encourage you to read it,
published in The Guardian--
Kwame Anthony Appiah argues that
there's really no such thing.
Now he begins with a
probably apocryphal anecdote.
But I'm going to
repeat it anyway,
which is that when he
was asked what he thought
of Western civilization, Mahatma
Gandhi is said to have replied,
I think it will be
a very good idea.
But where Gandhi implies
that the West was never
truly civilized, Appiah
goes one step further,
suggests that Western
civilization is a bad idea
intellectually.
It distorts our
understanding of history,
in part because the
meaning of the West
is so wildly
indeterminate, first
drawing a contrast
with the Islamic world,
later with the Orient.
And then in the
Cold War, contrast
with the other side
of the Iron Curtain,
more recently, part of a
more complicated contrast
with the Global South.
If we go back to the root,
Christianity versus Islam,
we find religious conflict,
but intellectual common ground.
So the fathers of Western
philosophy, Plato and Aristotle,
had their works preserved by
scholars in the Arab world.
And Muslim, Jewish and Christian
thinkers, Averroes or Ibn Rushd,
Maimonides, Aquinas, all did
the same thing of synthesizing
Aristotle with their different
monotheisms in the 12th and 13th
centuries.
They were all humming
the same tune.
The idea of the West as a
distinctive heritage seems to be
an invention of the 1890s.
And then it gets transformed
through the Cold War.
But actual
intellectual continuity
with Aquinas, let alone
Plato, is very minimal,
as slogans about liberalism
and democracy attest.
Neither Plato nor Aquinas
was a fan of either.
What about the university?
Did woke academics undermine the
Western canon, the Great Books
course, and with it
their own enrollments?
Not really.
It's true that the
canon was, I think,
rightly questioned and
expanded by academics.
I mean, insofar as
inclusion in the canon
is a function of influence,
it tracks social and political
power and the
injustice with which
that power has been exercised.
But courses like Erskine's
and Adler's were still
being offered, if
somewhat revised
and less commonly required.
And humanities enrollments
actually peaked in the 1990s.
So whatever was going on,
students were not put off by it.
Enrollments fell and
continued to fall,
not because of woke, but due to
external pressures, the soaring
cost of higher education,
increasing competition
for desirable jobs, the
mistaken sense that humanities
graduates are not employable,
and a consequent push
to tailor education more
directly to the needs of labor
markets.
MIT is in a special
position with respect
to this in many ways.
One is that the
issue of enrollment
is less relevant because the
supply of students in house
subjects is relatively fixed.
There was no bubble at MIT.
So if the conservative
narrative doesn't hold up,
what reason do we have to
revitalize the Great Books
course?
The short answer
is because there
is an urgent need for
students to grapple
with expansive questions about
human nature, human knowledge,
ethics, society, and politics.
When change is rapid
and unpredictable,
like the unfolding climate
crisis and the socially
disruptive impact of AI, we need
the wider horizons, imagination,
and creative insight
fostered by close engagement
with great books more than ever.
Now we know from
enrollment numbers
that when we're able to offer
classics of Western philosophy
consistently, students
want to take it.
The class size has doubled
over the last three years.
So we're not proposing
new requirements.
We're proposing
courses that we believe
students are excited to take.
Our focus on Western
philosophy, which I think,
unlike Western civilization,
does name something
blurrily coherent,
if rather porous,
is a concession to what
we're best equipped to teach.
That goes along
with self-awareness
about the limits of that
tradition and acknowledgment
of its indebtedness to others.
But given sufficient
resources, there's
a world in which SHASS could
offer a range of subjects
across geographic and cultural
borders that would introduce
students to far-reaching
questions about humanity
through other texts
and traditions flagged
as Great Books courses.
What exactly is the value
for students of spending
time with these books?
It's not to absorb a fixed
body of established wisdom.
It's to learn to
think for themselves
with the help of
living documents that
give historical perspective
and repay close study.
We sometimes argue for the
Humanities and Social Sciences
at MIT as sources of
knowledge and understanding,
of culture and history, society
and social change, ethics
and politics that will
make students better
people and better citizens.
We're not just
preparing MIT students
to land high-paying jobs,
but to solve human problems,
and so to make the
world a better place.
SHASS contributes to this.
And great books courses
can play an important role.
But if all we're
doing is creating
well-intentioned
problem solvers,
we're missing something vital.
I'm reminded of a quip
that was attributed
to the poet WH
Auden, who put words
in the mouth of a social worker.
Quote, "We are all here
on Earth to help others.
What on Earth the others
are here for, I don't know."
If the best we can hope
for is to solve problems,
we'd be better off not having to
face, why bother to live at all?
In the original
meaning, liberal arts
were understood in
opposition to servile arts
or vocational skills.
Liberal education was
fit for a free individual
working out their own
conception of how to live,
including the positive
goods that make life worth
living in the first place.
Art, music, and literature.
Love and friendship.
The beauty of scientific and
mathematical understanding.
Reading profound works of
literature and philosophy,
history and anthropology
can help us to do this.
Of course you could
still ask whether we
need to examine our own lives in
order to live fulfilling ones.
Maybe the unexamined
life can be worth living.
But unless you've
examined that question,
as you would in classics
of Western philosophy,
I'm afraid you're in
no position to say.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
I'd like to introduce
Lily Tsai to the stage.
[APPLAUSE]
Sometimes the world can
feel a little crazy.
That's because things are
changing fast, really fast.
It turns out, though,
that what we need to do
is not to move fast with it, but
to stop and reflect and think.
What kind of world
do we really want
to build so that
we're not constantly
overwhelmed by complexity
and chaos and noise?
MIT was originally
built to support
an industrial society,
one that was based
on machines and manufacturing.
Now we're transforming ourselves
for a digital age, one with AI
and computing and
synthetic biology.
And all of these things are
just making change faster.
More than ever, we need to
have moral, intellectual,
and aesthetic judgment.
These are the things
that AI cannot replace.
Don't get me wrong.
Some of my own research is on
designing AI for democracy.
But AI can't tell us if
something is beautiful.
It can't tell us
what a good idea is.
And it definitely can't tell us
what is right and what is wrong.
But if we're not
paying attention,
we're going to fall into
believing that AI can substitute
for these judgments.
So we need to
prepare our students
to reason for themselves
about hard human questions
so they can work together
to build the social fabric
and civic infrastructure
that we need for the future.
Compass teaches students to
build for the common good based
on clear principles and values,
investigated with rigorous tools
from the humanities,
arts, and social sciences.
The first thing that we've
done in the Compass Initiative
is to design a class with the
input of 31 faculty and 30
students from 22 departments.
It's truly a team effort.
And many people, including
Kieran, who I think
joined for our very first
organizational meeting,
and Susan Silbey.
And I'll call out also
Rebecca Sachs and especially
Emily Richmond Pollock, Adam
Albright, and Lila Friedland.
But it's truly a team
effort across the institute.
And it wouldn't be possible
without all of these people
to have all of Compass's
multiple facets.
Compass gets students to grapple
with hard human questions
and to read what great thinkers
have said about these questions.
It teaches students to
debate not in order to win,
but in order to
listen and understand.
Most importantly, we teach
students to apply all of this
to the rapidly changing
world around us.
Here's an example.
We start in the first
week by reflecting on what
holds communities together.
We read the US Constitution
and the Mayflower Compact
and the MIT value statement.
Then we discuss how great
philosophers like Thomas Hobbes
and John Locke and
Jean-Jacques Rousseau
have answered the
question of how
we can have liberty
and individual freedom,
yet still be constrained
to obey the laws
and rules of our communities.
After this, we get
students to apply
what they've learned by
collaborating to write a class
compact together.
You can see a copy of one
of these with the students'
signatures on the bottom.
So each week follows
this basic pattern.
Students read great thinkers.
They debate and deliberate
on a fundamental question
about human existence.
And then they apply it
to a real world problem.
We're hopefully
remaking a liberal arts
for the digital age.
But that's a talk
for another day.
In Compass, we investigate
three big questions.
And we keep coming back to them.
What do we value, and why?
What do we know?
And how do we know it?
And what do we
owe to each other?
What is the kind of world that
we want to build together?
After discussing John
Stuart Mill and Immanuel
Kant, virtue ethicists like
Aristotle and Confucius,
we map our personal values.
And we figure out whether or
not our professional values
in our fields reflect that.
We read Dante and Shakespeare.
This semester, we took students
to Verdi's Macbeth opera
and Beethoven's
Seventh Symphony.
And we asked them to
reflect on the value
of aesthetic and artistic
experience and expression.
By the end of the
semester, Compass students
have started to
surface the structure
and principles of history,
politics, science, poetry,
and music.
This focus on reasoning about
hard human questions using
rigorous tools from the many
disciplines in the humanities,
arts, and social
sciences is the essence
of Compass's unique approach.
Let me show you what I mean.
True or false, MIT
is a meritocracy.
If you ask a room full of
MIT students this question,
many, probably even
most of them, say true.
But why?
What does it mean
to be a meritocracy?
What is merit, even?
Is mathematical ability merit?
Is hard work merit?
And how would one
value these things
in the context of a university?
And how do we know
someone's merit?
Do we measure it with
problem sets and tests?
Or do we figure it
out some other way?
And once we know what
we value as merit
and how we know something
is meritorious, what
do we owe to those who have
merit in this context and those
who do not?
So you can see how a simple,
knee jerk, true-false response
quickly unspools into a long
string of difficult questions.
These kinds of questions need
the different disciplines
of philosophy, political
science, anthropology,
and history in order to
know how to reason about how
we should answer them.
You might ask,
why does it matter
if we can reason more rigorously
about these kinds of questions?
Well, one, it helps us
diagnose disagreements.
If two people disagree
about whether or not
MIT is a meritocracy, is
it because they disagree
about the values or
because they don't agree
about the facts on the ground?
Breaking down the
question allows
us to figure out the
points of agreement,
and maybe uncertainty,
and to be clear about what
we do disagree about.
Two, it invites us to be more
reflective and intentional
about our own beliefs.
If we think math
skills are meritorious,
are there other kinds
of merit that we
should prioritize just as
much based on the same logic?
Finally, it helps
us take action.
If we're in a position of power.
What kinds of decisions
would accomplish
the rewarding of merit?
MIT students need to be fluent
in reasoning about answers
to these hard human questions.
Some of them will
become engineers.
And they'll need to know
the values and impacts
of the systems they design.
Some will become
parents or educators.
And they'll need to know
what to reward and why.
Many of them will
become leaders.
And they'll have to make
policies and decisions that
influence institutional
and societal structures.
And all, we hope, will
face disagreements
about hard questions
with respect and humility
and tools for
understanding differences.
The multidisciplinarity
of Compass
gives people all the puzzle
pieces together at one table
to understand, what are the
multisystemic challenges
of the digital era?
I don't know of any
other place where
an approach this deep
and complex is happening.
Even though we've just
started piloting it,
people and
communities are asking
us to build a version
of Compass for them.
And I get why students
have been writing
in their anonymous
feedback cards things
like, I wish
classes were longer.
Those of you who are
students and faculty
know this doesn't always happen.
You can see one student has
written on their index card
something like, banger
class, absolute cinema.
And I actually don't
know what that means.
But I think it's positive.
Some of the professors
who teach Compass--
and some of you are here today--
are doing this beyond
our regular course load.
That's how much it means to us.
Compass aims to give people
the habits, tools, knowledge,
and capacity to act
from their own most
fundamental commitments.
And people are really
craving this capacity.
We all know that MIT has
always existed to do good
for the nation and the public.
And we're not just
educating technical leaders.
We're also educating
citizens, civic leaders,
and whole human
beings that will be
functioning in the digital age.
At Compass, our mission is to
help students see themselves
that way so they leave ready to
build, both for the joy of it
and for the greater good of it.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
So I'll now be joined by
Chancellor Nobles and Kieran
Setiya for the panel
part of the discussion.
Where do you want us?
Good morning, everyone.
Can you hear me?
Yeah.
Great.
Well, this is terrific.
Thank you.
I'm Melissa Nobles,
I already said,
but they told me I had
to reintroduce myself.
So I have a few
questions to start.
I think we're going to go about
15 minutes with questions.
And then we're going to have
questions from the audience.
I'll begin.
The first-- I'm going to
start with you, Kieran.
So I was reading
yesterday-- it's
connected to what
you were saying,
but from a different angle.
So in The Chronicle
of Higher Education,
Danielle Allen at
Harvard wrote a piece
about returning to the
classics in the age of AI.
And I thought, OK,
this is for you.
And so she said that
part of the challenge,
and I think we heard
it this morning,
is that AI is, as she says,
a part of the story, but not
the only part of what ails us.
That we live in an era where
capital-intensive tech companies
are fracking our attention
with addictive algorithms
designed to force every
bit of our attention
to the surface for monetization
for advertising revenue.
She goes on.
But the point is
that young people
are beset by an epidemic
of anxiety and distraction.
She claims that
returning to the classics
will help cure that addiction.
What say you?
I think it's both
a challenge and--
and this is the MIT response
and a huge opportunity.
So yeah, I think
one of the things
about reading Plato or
Margaret Cavendish, who's
a early modern philosopher who
wrote the first science fiction,
these books are hard.
And they're often very alien.
I mean, we think of the idea of
the Western tradition suggests
familiarity.
But actually, the
strangeness of these books
and the demandingness of
them is central to why
they're interesting and
worth engaging with.
So I think one of
the things that's
very hard in teaching
classics of Western philosophy
or any kind of
great books course
is that part of the
pedagogical goal
is teaching students
how to read.
But how do you read
something long and sustained?
And we think of that
self-consciously.
So part of the
curriculum is, how
do you read a book
that you're not
going to understand
first time, a book that
is extremely challenging?
And how do you create space in
which students have the leisure
and luxury to do that, and
the incentive to do that,
because they'll be part of a
conversation in which they're
accountable for having
done it, but also
get to share their
reactions with others.
And I will say, I think the
goal-- this is aspirational--
but I think it's not
unrealistic-- is what we want
to do is not just
to create students
who can read
difficult books, it's
students who want to read them.
There's this
wonderful formulation
from the critic
Gayatri Spivak, who
describes humanities
education as the non-coercive
rearrangement of desire.
And I love that formulation.
What we want is students to
leave a course like this wanting
to continue reading
difficult books,
engage with difficult ideas.
And then there's a
further challenge
for academics like me, which
is we have to then write
the books that they can read.
That's another story.
I think this can be a venue for
tackling that problem if we're
self-conscious about it.
Right, I'm going to
be a bit provocative.
So you can imagine a
student saying, I mean,
when we were growing up back
in the day, it was Cliff Notes.
What would make a student
not think about that again,
even if they're open to the
challenges you're describing?
And I have no doubt that
students will be open to it.
But how would you--
I'm asking you to think
in the future, of course,
how to manage that in a way that
deals with the current reality
and still gets at what you
describe, which I would agree
is very important.
I mean, I think there's
two sides to that.
One is classroom management.
How do you deter students
from taking shortcuts that
will impede their education?
And there are also
things you can
do in the class in terms
of testing or setting up
classroom settings in
which they're writing
without access to AI and so on.
The other part of it, I
think, is about modeling.
I mean, one thing about teaching
a course in which you read
Plato or Margaret Cavendish is
that going back to those texts
is energizing for the teacher.
You find something
new every time.
And modeling to them that I've
been doing this for 25 years.
But I need to read
this again because I'm
going to see new things
is a way of showing them
that what you get if
you ask AI to summarize
this is not the thing itself.
And hopefully sharing that
excitement and novelty
of actually engaging with the
richness of the original texts
is something we can
do in the class.
So I think it's a mixture
of thinking about strategies
for managing the classroom
that limit access or limit
the incentives, and
partly really just trying
to make the case by
example, that there's
a kind of intellectual
excitement
that their teachers get and that
they can share that would just
not be available if what they
were dealing with was, ChatGPT,
could you summarize
Plato's Republic?
Maybe I can share.
Yes, please.
I was going to ask you, Lily.
Go ahead.
I mean, it's
actually really funny
because I was
actually at Harvard
a couple of weeks
ago at a workshop
that Danielle Allen organized
on trying to design something
like Compass at Harvard.
And one of the things
we talked about
was actually something
that came up,
I think, in the conversation
between Dean Ryan and Dean Locke
earlier about meeting
students where they are.
And so it is true, attention
has been fracked, actually.
And I think that that's
just an empirical reality
that we have to adjust
our pedagogy in order
to accommodate.
And so one of the things
that we've tried out
in Compass to create a success
is actually getting the students
in the classroom to do a table
read of Shakespeare's Macbeth
from front to back.
So we sat in a room
for three hours.
And a group of us
read Macbeth together.
This is actually a
little bit like something
I think colleagues at
Virginia Tech are doing,
where they have a class
that's eight hours long.
For the first six hours,
you sit in a room.
And you read together.
And then the last two hours,
you discuss what you've read.
And it's incredibly
popular, apparently.
So I think this is actually
an opportunity for us
to become really, really
creative about pedagogy.
Another thing that I think
is interesting is that--
and students, as
Kieran is saying,
want to be held
accountable, actually,
for doing difficult things.
MIT students love to do
the most difficult things.
And so when we got them
to debate and deliberate
about the kind of
class constitution
they wanted to write for
themselves this semester,
a lot of them
actually said, we want
to be held accountable
for our reading.
And so luckily, we had
actually already instituted
reading quizzes.
And so they were
like, that's great.
That can be an implicit
part of the class compact.
So I think there's a
hunger for it, actually.
As Kieran is
saying, it's getting
students who want to do
difficult things, who
want to grapple with
difficult ideas.
And this is exactly what MIT
students are so special at.
Yeah, I will say just
briefly, to follow up, just
in total agreement with that.
One thing we're extraordinarily
lucky at with MIT
is the students are
totally wonderful.
And my experience of
the AI opportunities
is that it sort of saved
us from ourselves is often
their attitude.
It's a collective
action problem.
They don't want
to take shortcuts.
But the temptation is there.
And so I think they will
collaborate with initiatives
in the classroom to make the
experience more intellectually
satisfying.
So in a way, both of
you are describing
a place where the classroom is
becoming a safe space of sorts.
I mean, a different kind
of space, a space where
time is differently--
For attention.
--experienced.
Oh, yes.
Absolutely.
And I think it's so interesting
to watch students in Compass,
because they really
relish this time together.
It's a space where
it's safe, I suppose.
But what's more
interesting is that it's
a place where they can be free.
It's like a space where they can
freely discuss and debate things
with each other and
build relationships
and a sense of community around
these fundamental questions
that, frankly, all of us will
struggle with our entire life.
So space, just to clarify,
I meant, yes, safe
from devices, or from
the attention, the siren
call of those--
Oh, the devices.
Of the devices.
So, Lily, thinking
about the Compass class,
one of the things I thought, I
mean, first, it's just amazing.
I read the report.
It's something to see
the levels of engagement
of both faculty and students.
And the readouts of
the student reports
were really quite positive.
But one of the things
that you wonder about
is, what lessons is
it possible to know?
But I imagine all
of us are wondering.
So what happens after that?
So you take this great class.
And there are some things that
are stirred within, presumably.
And the students
take that forward.
Are there ways of figuring
out how students are
bringing those things forward?
Are they becoming
evangelists of sorts?
Are they perhaps
expressing more interest
in taking SHASS and
other kinds of courses,
non-technical courses,
as a consequence?
I mean, I imagine that would
be our expectation and hope.
But I'd be curious to know.
I know it's pretty early on.
So I'm asking prematurely.
But I wonder if you have
any views about that.
Yeah, I mean, when we
started Compass-- again,
also with the help and
support of race data--
one of the things that
we really committed to
was actually making this
a learning experience
for the faculty.
And part of that is
actually making sure
that we're following
students in their journey
through MIT over
four years and seeing
what they're bringing from
Compass through that journey.
And so one of the things that
we've asked students is, are you
more likely to take a class?
Or what disciplines are
you more likely to take
a class in that you
wouldn't have actually known
about before?
And so we have data
on things like,
are they taking linguistics?
Are they taking philosophy?
Or are they taking
anthropology and sociology?
So that's one way in which
we're learning about how
Compass affects their journey.
The second thing
that's been interesting
is that people seem to want
something like Compass.
They want an
opportunity to grapple
with great books
and great thinkers
and these fundamental
questions at inflection points
in their life.
So we've had second
semester seniors
ask if we could have a
Compass version just for that,
because they're just about to
go out into the real world.
And they want a time to
think about those questions.
Somebody from Sloan's Executive
MBA program actually asked if we
could do something for
40-year-old mid-career MBAs
because they, too, have had 20
years of professional success.
And they're wondering what
they want their legacy to be.
And so that's been
really interesting.
Finally, we're also
like Concourse,
which is another fantastic
program at MIT that
has many of the same goals
that Kieran and I have.
We've learned from Concourse
that one way to continue
this journey with
these questions
and great thinkers is to involve
Compass alumni in becoming
TAs for Compass, because
there is this kind of-- oh,
Esther's here.
I didn't even see you here.
Esther Duflo is also
part of the Compass team.
One of the great ways
of solidifying things
is that kind of thing that
you hear from medicine.
You see one, do one, teach one.
And at MIT, we've figured
out doing, learning by doing
is incredibly important.
But this is also
a way of getting
them to learn by teaching.
That's terrific.
I have just a couple
of minutes left
before we turn to the audience.
So I talk a lot about his
chaffs about the whole student.
And a big part of
that is the classroom.
But another part
of it is outside
of the classroom,
so which is part
of the reason why I was asking.
Both of your descriptions
of your classes
are, it sounds at
the end, a commitment
to making our students
just better people.
So it's as much a story of
inviting self-examination
as it is imparting
screaming at students,
but more stirring
the self-learning.
As both professors, how
has it affected you?
Because here's the
challenge, is that we
may have all taken these
classes when we were in college.
But we came of age
at a different time.
So how do you meet students
where they are, but also
recognize that you
are we all are being
changed by our current moment?
Do these classes help you?
Yes.
I mean, it's been amazing.
I think part of the reason
the faculty are willing--
the faculty on the campus
teaching teams and design
teams are willing to
put all of this effort
above and beyond their
regular teaching loads
is because we're all
learning from each other.
And it's really like a
master class in learning.
And I actually wish there
were more opportunities at MIT
to do something like
this because all of us
are learning from Esther.
When do you get to take a
class, a little mini class,
from a Nobel
Prize-winning economist?
Or Sally Haslanger
and Alex Byrne, these
are amazing philosophers.
And you get to sit there.
I'm a political scientist.
And I get to sit there and hear
what these philosophers think
about cutting-edge thinking.
So I think that's been
intellectually enriching.
And I think we also try to have
Compass co-taught by professors
from different disciplines.
And both for the teachers
and for the students watching
that kind of interdisciplinary
conversation, is just,
it's a very rare experience.
And it models interdisciplinary
collaboration and debate
that we need, again, to address
these kinds of challenges that
are going to be multi-systemic.
You have to have people
who are able to translate
across disciplines and figure
out where the synergies can be.
And we're hoping to model that.
Yes?
Just to add, the
only thing I would
add to that, which I
totally agree with,
is there's also just
learning from the students.
So one thing about manifesting
the freshness of going back
to a text you've
read many times is
that the students will notice
things that you didn't notice.
And I think it's really
exhilarating for a student
in a class to make an argument
and have the professor go,
I never thought of it that way.
You're a genius.
And I think that I
learn a huge amount
from the students in more or
less every class I teach at MIT.
But I think this is that's
one way in which they can come
to see that they're
part of a conversation
that they wouldn't get
if they took shortcuts.
Thank you.
So it's time for the audience.
I've asked my questions.
They are roaming,
roving mics, I think.
That's right.
First question,
over at the back.
Hi, thank you very much.
This is wonderful and
exciting and encouraging.
I'm just curious if you could
talk a little bit more about,
you both mentioned great
books and great thinkers.
And I'm just wondering if you
could say a little bit more
about what makes a book great,
what makes a thinker great.
Thank you.
That is a very--
I mean, it's a
very hard question.
I think one way to think
about the criterion we've
tended to use is, what are the
books that have the feature that
returning to them and
engaging with them again
and again and again is going
to be incredibly intellectually
productive?
And I think we're fairly
open ended in what counts.
So one thing about the
two-semester sequence
is we're coordinating.
But we didn't come up
with a fixed curriculum.
It's not like there's
a list in which we've
had to answer the question,
what are the great books?
It's more that we
were, what are books
that are in conversation
with each other,
and that students will find
fruitful to engage with,
professors will find
that will enable them to think
deeply about how society should
be structured, how
life should be lived,
what the role of technology in
life and in society should be?
But yeah, we have not tried
to pin down a canon more
determinedly than that.
Yeah, thank you, Linda,
for that amazing question.
This is Linda Rabieh,
who's one of MIT'S
amazing political philosophers.
And I think when I think
about that question,
I think we have a Nobel
Prize-winning physicist, Sam
Ting.
And he once said
that in physics,
what is really important is
having the best data possible.
And interpretations of the data,
models of the data come and go.
But as long as you have
the best data possible,
that will stand
the test of time.
The way I think
about great works
is that there's
material in there
that people can continue
to engage with in order
to refine, again, their moral,
intellectual, and artistic
judgment.
So it's through that
process of engaging
with this really
rich material that
enables them to enables us
to sharpen our discernment
and judgment.
And that's what I think of.
But of course, people
should actually
also ask Linda what she
thinks of that question.
Michael, yeah.
Thank you.
All this has been wonderful.
I have a question, I
guess, for both of you,
more towards the
Great books program.
I have spoken with many
alumni, our older alumni
from MIT who took great
books classes like this,
and really credited it as one of
the fundamental distinguishing
blocks of their MIT education,
that it helped them stand out
from other engineers who had
only technical educations,
and from colleagues from Harvard
who had no technical education,
but that they were
able to have them both.
How would you speak about
what we're doing today
to that audience of
alumni who really valued
that part of their education,
what is what you're doing today?
How is it different?
And how is it similar?
And I think I would ask
the same on the Compass.
How is what you're doing today--
how does it relate to
that MIT tradition?
And how does it bring
it forward in a new way?
I mean, I do think it's a
revival of that tradition.
I think there are logistical
ways in which it's different,
which is that the broadening
of students ethical and social
understanding right now is
under the auspices of the Haas
requirement.
And it's very dispersed.
You can take all kinds
of different things.
And right now, we're
not thinking, well,
we want to introduce
requirements.
But I do think the salience
of these courses, the student
demand for them is there.
And I think they can
be brought to recognize
that these courses can play the
kind of role they were playing
at that earlier moment.
And so I think
there's continuity.
I think there's
probably a greater
flexibility in understanding
what the canon is.
I think you just would read a
more diverse range of culturally
diverse, geographically
diverse range of thinkers
in a classics of Western
philosophy course
now than might have
been true when people
had more of a fixed curriculum.
And I think there's
probably more
attentiveness on
the pedagogical side
to the difficulty of doing this.
So I suspect that when people
were teaching these courses
in 1955 or 1970,
there was a sense
that students were prepared
to read books like this.
There wasn't this
crisis of attention.
And so one way in which
I think this has changed
is that we do think of
ourselves as not just imparting
great ideas, but imparting
skills of attention
that I think students can
then carry on into the world.
And that is a new challenge
that I think classes like this
and like Compass can
really help to address.
So I've been asked to keep
the trains running on time.
So we will have an
opportunity at lunchtime
to continue the conversation.
But for right now, I'd like to
thank Lily, Kieran, and Melissa
for this wonderful chat.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]