good morning good afternoon let's go
ahead and get started welcome to lecture
16 this is the last lecture worth of
material that we're covering before our
quiz all right let's talk about counting
this is lecture 16 on
Counting and where we left off last time
was I had just mentioned the generalized
product rule and we used the generalized
product rule to count the number of
permutations of a deck of comically
oversized playing
cards uh we had 52 cards and we decided
if we want to choose an order among all
these cards well we have 52 options for
the first card Queen of Diamonds this
time after that we have 51 options left
for the second card four of clubs this
time now we have 50 cards left 5050
options and
notice what whatever first two cards I
chose um
initially whatever cards I chose is
going to change the set of available
options left if I had instead of
choosing the queen of diamonds first if
I had
chosen the eight of clubs first then it
would be this 50 cards that are
remaining on step three rather than the
previous set um but still on step three
we always have 50 choices
left so now we're choosing the two of
hearts on step four we always have 49
choices left then 48 47
Etc um and so we were able to sum this
up into a general principle called the
generalized product rule which basically
says if you're making a sequence of
choices and at every um at the E choice
you always have a fixed number n i of
possible choices at that I
step then the number of ways to make all
your choices in sequence is just N1 * N2
* N3 all the way to
NK uh and that's what this says in text
so if a is a set of length K sequences
where there are exactly N1 possible
choices for the first one so 52 choices
for the first card and then N2 possible
choices at the Second Step no matter
what you chose for the first step then n
three um for the third step no matter
what your first two choices were and so
on all the way down then the size of
your set is just the product of the
number of choices you have in step one
times the number of choices you have in
step two etc
etc does that idea make sense let's do
one more example here um and this
example is about money money is a fun
topic right um so anyone who has a
dollar bill on them doesn't have to be a
one just any dollar bill go ahead and P
pull it out for a second and then give
it to me no you can keep it um but take
a look at the serial number so every
dollar bill has a serial
number which is a
length eight sequence of
digits how many possible serial numbers
are there there might be some letters in
there ignore the letters there are eight
digits how many possible serial digits
are serial numbers are there how many
ways are there to choose
a sequence of eight
digits
yes eight
factorial eight factorial
serials any other suggestions
yes 10 to the eth 10 to the eth any
other
suggestions
yes okay 10 * 9 * 8 all the way down to
three cuz we're only choosing eight
digits instead of choosing all 10
digits okay I'm going to put another
suggestion in there 8 to the
10 so which of these is
right so importantly I never said that
the digits had to be distinct and in
fact very often they're not
distinct so if we choose so here 2 3
four five six 7even here are the eight
digits we're going to choose a number
for each like if I choose a seven for
our first digit
well I had 10 options
right how many options do I have for the
next
digit 10 right I'm allowed to choose
seven again if I want to so I have 10
options here maybe I do choose seven
again how many options
here still
10 maybe I choose a four this time and
so on I can fill this in every time I
have 10 options for my next digit so the
number of choices is 10 * 10 * 10 8 10
8 does that make sense cool this in fact
is just the regular product rule we
didn't need the generalized product rule
here because the set of choices I have
is just all 10 digits the set of choices
I have is the same all 10 digits um the
set of choices isn't changing as I make
more choices just ju just regular
product rule I put 8 to the 10 up there
just to be a bit of a troll um because 8
to the 10 and 10 to the 8 are easy to
get
confused um and so if you think about it
this way how many options do I have for
this choice for that choice for that
choice it'll be easy to tell which one
of these is right and which one of them
is
wrong uh so 10 to the8 serial
numbers but we had um some of these
formulas were sounding like we wanted
the digits to be distinct they're not
always but maybe sometimes they are so
everyone who pulled out a dollar bill uh
can you check your serial number and if
all of your digits are distinct can you
raise your
hand no
one can you raise your hand if you
checked a dollar bill and it
failed okay so I'm seeing about like 20
25 people that carry cash uh so out of
those $25 bills none of them had all
distinct
digits um which is a shame because if
someone did have all distinct digits I
brought Candy so maybe check the other
dollars in your
wallet um but this gives us a natural
counting question how
many
serials have
all
distinct
digits and let's see if we can count
this using the product rule or maybe the
generalized product rule um once again 1
2 3 4 5 six 7even eight I like to think
about my choices in order one at a time
so I just draw a little bar to remind
myself I'm going to choose something
here and remind myself how many options
I had so let's see if we can construct
serial numbers that have all distinct
digits length eight how many options do
I have for my first
digit 10 absolutely I have 10 options
here maybe this time I chose a
three how many options do I have for the
second
digit nine is it always nine what if
this digit had been eight still nine
right no matter what I did here there's
always nine options left so maybe I
choose a seven how many options here
eight I've used two I'm not allowed to
reuse them so there are eight options
left then seven then six then five
then four then
three and therefore by the generalized
product rule by the generalized product
rule um the number of length eight
serial numbers with all distinct
digits is 10 * 9 * 8 all the way down to
three just the product of the number of
choices I have at each step which by the
way someone had had guessed previously
so well done with
that um and now you could ask out of all
the serials out of all 10 to the8 serial
numbers now we know how many of them
have all distinct digits what fraction
is that well we just divide um this
number divided by 10 e um tells us there
are actually only about 1.8% of dollar
bills that have all distinct digits so
about less than 2% so since we had like
25 or $30 bills that we checked
collectively it's it's no surprise that
we didn't get any of them uh that fit
this this
Criterion um if more people carried cash
maybe we'd be seeing some some candy
payouts today
shame um questions about the generalized
product
rule wonderful let's move on to the next
rule which is the division rule
wonderful um so so far we've seen the
bje
rule so if F from a set a to a set B is
a
bje then the size of a equals the size
of
b um a bje by the way is also called a
one:1 correspondence one two
one
correspondence um where the picture in
your head should be that every one thing
on the left corresponds to one thing on
the right they're paired up one to one
um thinking of this function in our
directed arrow drawing fashion
everything from a has exactly one Arrow
out and everything in B has exactly one
arrow in that's what it means to be a
bje so it's a one to one correspondence
one Arrow out one arrow in let's we can
generalize this a little
bit
so um if
instead every a in
a has
exactly one Arrow
out and every B and B
has
exactly K arrows
in then we can conclude that the size of
a divid k equals the size of
B so here's my
picture everything on the left has one
out everything on the right has two
arrows in exactly two arrows in every
time then there are double as many
elements on the left as there are on the
right if it were three arrows
in if everything on the right has
exactly three arrows in then there are
three times as many things on the left
as there are on the
right so this is a generalization of a
bje or a one:1 correspondence uh to
what's called a k to1 correspondence
because what this ends up doing is
saying that we've divided the left side
into groups of size K that correspond to
each one thing on the right so this one
thing on the right matches one two three
things on the left and everything on the
right is paired with three distinct
things on the
left and so this is a useful tool for
counting that generalizes the projection
rule we don't have to match up match
things up one to one as long as we know
that we're matching the same number of
things every time and then we just
divide by that
thing all right let's put this to
use okay so
example Knights of the Round
Table so the set here is we're going to
have n
Knights maybe it should have been K
Knights n Knights all sitting around a
round table
um around a round
table at n equally spaced
seats how many different
arrangements are
possible if
rotations of a seating
assignment are
considered equivalent
so n Knights sitting around a table if
you have one seating assignment and you
have a second seating assignment that's
just a rotation of the first then we
want to consider those two assignments
the same seating assignment we don't
care which exact seats they're in as
long as the cyclic order around the
circle is the same so for example if n
is four and we
have um like one here then three here
then four here and two here that's one
possible seating
assignment well here's a different one
one here three here four here two
here but this assignment is the same as
that assignment because we've just
rotated the table and we're just saying
we don't care about rotating the table
so in fact we want to consider these to
be equivalent seating
assignments right just like we want to
consider this to be equivalent to one
then three then four then two this way
and equivalent to one then three then
four then two this way so all four of
these rotated seating assignments are
equivalent because it's the same order
they're just starting in a different
place does that make
sense cool so that's our question how
many different seating arrangements for
these end nights are possible given that
we don't care about
rotations and to solve it let's see if
we can use a k to1 map because that's
what we're trying to learn at this point
in this lecture
um so here is the map I'm going to
recommend um let's let's let a be the
set of
permutations of one through n
permutation just means a reordering so
it's all of the
orders of the set 1 through
n and
B is the set
of cyclic
seating arrangements so B is the thing
we're trying to
count how many different seating
arrangements are
possible well a we know how to count
what's the size of
a what is it n
factorial that's exactly right um that
was our first example of generalized
product rule on Tuesday there're 52
factorial orders for a deck of cards
they're n factorial orders for a set of
n
nights all right so if we want to use
the division rule we have a set a where
we know the size and we need to be able
to define a function from a to the set B
that we care about and make sure that
it's a k to1 map for some
K and here's the map we're going to do
so f is going to take in a permutation
so an element of a so A1 A2 up to a
n so it takes in a
permutation an element of a and it needs
to spit out an element of B so it needs
to spit out a cyclic ordering of these
numbers and it's going to spit out this
cyclic
ordering that just sits them in that
order around the
table Yeah the the most straightforward
thing I can think of to do here
now that we have this
function let's check if it's a k to1
map
um all
right so what does it mean for f to be a
k to1 map is f a K2
one map well it means that everything in
B needs to come from exactly K elements
of a
so we
want
every cyclic
order comes from
exactly
K
permutations and when we say comes from
we mean via this function
f via function
f so as an ex example maybe n is five
this time and we have the order 4 5 2 3
1 some cyclic order
here how many different permutations of
1 through five maap to this cyclic
ordering who can give me one of
them so we have this this function f
that takes a permutation of 1 through n
and just lays it out around the circle
so who can give me a permutation that
becomes this once you lay it out around
the
circle I'll see if we can get some new
hands yes
please 1
14523 1 four five 2 3 if we lay that
around a circle we're going to get 1 4 5
2 3 looks good to me excellent who can
give me
another
yes 452 31 452 2 3 1 if we lay that
around a circle we're going to get 4 5 2
3 1 looks good to me same cyclic
ordering all we're doing is choosing a
starting point if we know what cyclic
ordering we're aiming for well we just
have to choose who we're going to start
with and then list the rest of them in
order around the circle and that's how
we can reconstruct all of the
permutations that map to the cyclic
order if we start with two then it's
going to look like 2 3 1 4 5 If instead
we start with three it's going to look
like 3 1 4 5
2 and the only one we haven't done yet
is starting with
five 5 2 3 1
4 5 2 314 and I claim that's all of
them so in this case for this particular
cyclic ordering there were five
permutations that map to
it
right in general
I claim uh for
each cyclic
ordering there exist
exactly n
permutations that map to
it um for the same reason we just saw
for this example the only additional
information we need to reconstruct all
of these permutations is which starting
point we're
choosing because
just need to
pick a starting
point all
right so every for every cyclic ordering
there exists exactly n permutations that
map to
it which is exactly the condition we
need for f to be an N to one
map
n21 map everything on the Right comes
from exactly N Things on the
left and what do we conclude now that we
know f is an N to one
map why are why are K to1 maps in
general helpful
yes yeah we can understand the size of b
k to1 maps are helpful because they let
us relate the size of a to the size of B
and in this example we know the size of
a we know it's an N to one map and
therefore we know the size of
B so the size of B is just the size of a
divid n cuz we decided it's an N to1 map
and therefore the size of B is n
factorial / n also known as n minus one
factorial does that make
sense cool I see some
nods I see some blank stairs again you
know that's that's fine ask questions
when you have
them
okay let's look at one more example of
the division rule
um I want to look at increasing serial
numbers again but this time just length
three let's make it easier on ourselves
uh so the number
of
Serial uh serial
numbers length
three and now I want to know how many of
them have all three digits that are in
um sorry one moment
sorry I got ahead of myself different
example still length three serial
numbers I just want to count these
that's all I want to do how many length
three serial numbers are there um with
distinct
digits and we already have one way that
we know to count this uh we had the
generalized product rule method that we
used for length eight we can do the the
same for length three I want to propose
a different method that uses the
division rule instead and here's what
I'm going to
do let's let P be the
set of
permutations of 1 through 10 uh sorry of
0 through
9 and let's let s be the set of length
three uh serials
with distinct
digits all
right and I just checked my notes again
I I got myself confused yet again
forgive me let me change the details of
the uh of the of the example just a
little bit um I want the number of
serials of length three
with not only distinct digits but
actually digits in increasing
order so I'm okay with two and four and
nine I'm okay with
01 3 012 is fine uh I'm not okay with 4
2 3 cuz four and two are in the wrong
order I'm not okay with two to
25 cuz I want strictly increasing so how
many length three serials have strictly
increasing
digits is the question
clear okay thank you
um and let's do the same thing we were
doing before uh let P be the set of
permutations of 1 through nine of 0
through N9 and let s be the set of ser
of length three serials with
increasing digits strictly increasing
digits
and let's see if we can relate p with s
in order to count the size of
s and here's what I'm going to do let's
define a function let's define a
function G from P to
S and it's going to look like this uh G
of a permutation a z A1
A2 up to A9 that's a generic element of
P that's going to go to the serial that
has a z A1
A2
sorted so take those three digits and
sort
them all right that's a way to turn a
permutation into a serial number with
increasing
digits by the way a different way to
think about this problem um you can
think of s um s is equivalently
the set of uh size
three size three
subsets of zero through nine if we know
they have to come in increasing order
then all we care about is which three we
chose right so if I tell you my serial
has increasing order and has the digits
of five and four and
N then I know it has to be
459 so just the set of three digits that
we chose is enough to know which serial
it
is so if we want to think about this as
instead the set of size three
subsets then this function G would look
like
this would just go to the set a z A1
A2 so this is a way to map permutations
of of the digits 0 through 9 to subsets
of size
three all right and now let's see if
this G is a helpful function let's see
if it's K to one for some
K okay so the question becomes for every
size 3 subset of the digits how many
permutations ma to
it for
example how many
[Music]
permutations map to Three 6
7 one permutation maps to to the set
that was one
suggestion anyone have different
suggestions is it more than
one in the
back three factorial okay um so we have
one we have three factorial any other
suggestions
yes 7 factorial times 3
factorial here I'm going to put a
question mark next to each of these
because they're there are guesses let's
see if we can figure out which one is
right okay so let's see how many
permutations map us to this set well we
need to pick some permutation 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 some permutation of the 10
digits what do we know about these three
digits our function says you take the
first three entries and you form them
into a set and that's the output
so if our output is going to be
367 then these first three entries have
to be 3 six and 7even in some
order yeah 3 six 7 in some
order I don't care which
order because I'm just going to take the
three of them and plop them into a set
and a set doesn't care what order they
are okay so I know that 3 six and 7 have
to be in have to be in some order at the
beginning of my permutation what about
the end of the permutation what do I
know about
this what constraints do I have on it
knowing that g of this permutation
equals this set
y right you can't have three six or
seven you have to have all the other
digits in some order but anything goes
yeah so it's the
other seven
digits in some order
this is exactly the set of
permutations um where G of that
permutation gives the set 367 so we have
to put 3 six and seven in some order at
the beginning put the other seven digits
in some order at the end and how many
ways are there to do that well this is
product rule it's 3 factorial here on
the left 7 factorial here on the right
so 3 factorial time 7 factorial is
indeed the number of permutations that
map to this set
was that specific to this set if I chose
a different set of three digits would I
get a different number of
pre-images like if I instead chose zero
and five and
eight well it would be it would be the
same constraint right I would have to
have 0 five and eight in some order here
and then the other seven digits in some
order here it's still going to be 3
factorial * 7
factorial so in fact
G is K to
1 where k equals 3 factorial time 7
factorial yeah because the the same
argument we did for this particular
example in fact works for every
example great and since K is since since
this map is K to 1 and we know K we can
compute the size of our various sets
on one hand we had permutations of 0
through 9 so that was 10
factorial we put it through a a k to1
map where K is this so 3 factorial * 7
factorial in the
denominator and this
equals the size of the set
s sound
good so we map from permutation
to the set of the first three elements
and we decided that every time we do
that there U we lose by a factor of 3
factorial * 7
factorial um and so this is the number
of size three
subsets of 10
objects this by the way is an extremely
useful formula um let me generalize this
so the
number
of
subsets of size
K from a set of size
n is well we can do the same kind of
argument here map permutations and
factorial of them where we take the
first K elements and turn them into a
set um and that reduces the number of
options we have by K factorial on the
left and N minus K factorial on the
right right the same way it did here so
this is n factorial
/ K factorial time n minus K
factorial this is a really useful
formula you're definitely going to want
it on your cheat sheet but in fact
hopefully by the time the quiz comes
around next week you'll be so used to
this formula and so sick of you I mean
you'll love it so much um that you
aren't you aren't going to need it on
your cheat sheet because you're going to
know
it um
and in fact we have a special notation
for
it we write it as n on the top K on the
bottom surrounded in
parentheses notice it's not a fraction
we're not dividing n by K so don't write
n divided by K in parentheses it's just
n on top K on the bottom parentheses on
the
sides and this is pronounced n choose
K so n choose K is written like this we
have a formula for it like this um and
it's pronounced n choose K because well
we're choosing K things out of a a
possible set of end
things and like I said really useful
formula if you're ordering pizza for
dinner there are 15 sides or sorry 15
toppings that you can choose from to put
on your pizza and you're supposed to
choose three of them for some special
promotion how many ways are there to do
that if we've got 15 toppings
we want to
choose three how many ways are there to
choose what your pizza is going to look
like we don't care about the order of
the toppings we just care about the set
of three toppings that you pick it's in
the name 15 choose
three 15 choose three also known as 15
factorial divided 3 factorial 12
factorial
yeah wonderful um if I need to select
four volunteers out of this class of
let's say 200 students um how many ways
are there to pick a a set of four
volunteers 200 choose
four if I flip a coin 100
times flip a coin 100
times how many resulting sequence
quences have 50 heads and 50
tails in some
order there are 2 * 2 * 2 * 2 100 times
number of options in total 2 to the 100
options how many of those results result
in exactly 50 heads and exactly 50 Tales
possibly you know
intermixed well if we remember from
Tuesday we had this
bijection between binary sequences and
subsets where we can turn a binary
sequence into a subset by just taking
all the ones and leaving out all the
zeros take the indices of all the
ones and you can do that here as well if
we're looking at length 100 binary
sequences with 50 ones and 50 zeros
where one is head and zero is tail so
number
of length
100 binary
sequences with 50 ones and 50
zeros from the bje we talked about on
Tuesday this is injection
with um
the number of size
subsets of one through
100 all we're all we're doing is
choosing 50 out of the 100 flips to be
ones to be heads and the rest are going
to be tals so we're choosing 50 out of
the 100 it's in the name 100 choose
50 that's the number of ways to flip a
coin a 100 times and get exactly 50
heads and 50 Tails did that make
sense wonderful interestingly um it's a
little wet sorry 100 choose 50 divided
by um what is it 2 to the 100 so the
ratio the fraction of all results that
have exactly 50 heads and 50 tals out of
the total number of results you can have
um turns out this is about 8%
which to me is a little counterintuitive
like 50/50 has got to be the most common
result it's right in the middle assuming
we have a fair coin um and yet it's not
actually all that
likely turns out we're pretty likely to
be very near
50% um but it's kind of hard to hit it
exactly if we doing a thousand flips
instead of 100 I think it's closer to
like 1% and it gets rarer and rarer as
you go but but now we have the tools to
count things like that questions about
this n choose
k um for reasons that we'll see next
week this n choose K is called a
binomial
coefficient so binomial coefficient is
the general name for these n choose K
terms um again we'll see why on on
Tuesday but if you see this term know
that that's what we're referring
to all
right
nice now the last technique I want to
talk about the last counting
technique um is extremely useful and
extremely uh versatile but that also
means that there are lots of ways to
apply it and also lots of ways to apply
it
incorrectly so let's talk about how to
do it and more importantly let's talk
about what we need to make sure of
before we know with confidence that we
can apply
[Applause]
it and in fact
conveniently it's built exactly on the
generalized product rule this next
technique that we're using in fact I'm
going to keep that up so we can look at
it
okay and this technique um the book
calls it
oops
counting with
sequences um or counting with
recipes excuse me the general idea is if
you have some set you're trying to
count well it would be really convenient
if you could sort of build up your set
build all the elements of your set via a
sequence of convenient
choices where you always have the same
number of choices every time um so then
you can use the generalized product rule
so counting with sequences or recipes is
just a way to construct your set with an
easily digestible sequence of simple
choices and as long as you ver ify that
that does indeed construct your set
exactly then you have your count with
the generalized product rule um this
will make a lot more sense when we start
applying it so let's start doing that
and the example we're going to use is
counting poker
hands um so we're going to use a
standard deck of
cards
um a standard deck of cards has um 13 of
what are called ranks and four suits um
so um I'm told that some of you in the
back can't see my comically oversized
playing cards um so let's do
better uh so we have four suits we have
Spades and hearts in my left hand we
have clubs and diamonds in my right hand
those are the four suits and then there
are 13
ranks no way this is going to work that
goes Ace to I I I'm not going to try to
Fan them out sorry uh three four five 6
7 8 8 n 10 then Jack then Queen then
King those are the 13 different ranks um
sometimes in poker the ace is the lowest
of the numbers sometimes it's the
highest of the numbers we're not really
going to care about that so much um all
we need to know is that there are four
suits and 13 ranks and the deck consists
of every combination of one of each so
13 * 4 is 52
cards so 13
ranks four
suits these are called Hearts clubs
Spades and
diamonds um and there are 52 cards
corresponding to every way to choose one
rank and one
suit that is the standard uh deck of
cards we're going to be assuming that
for these next
examples come to me
notes um and in poker a poker hand is a
set of five
cards so a
poker
hand is a subset
of five cards out of the 52 possible
cards and some subsets have more
specialized properties they're less
common and so they're more powerful and
you you get to beat your enemies with
powerful hands um that's poker
right so let's see some different kinds
of poker hands and the first one I want
to look at is four of a
kind kind
so poker hand is called a four of a kind
if you have all four
cards of some
Rank and then some fifth
card so four of a kind because you have
all four options of the same
Rank and we want to count how many four
of a kind hands are there in a standard
52 deck 52 card deck all right and we're
going to do this
this by counting with a recipe
here and basically I kind of already
wrote The Recipe but let's do it
carefully um step one I'm going
to choose a rank
R and
take all four
cards of that
Rank and then I'm going to
pick one other
card and putting the these two steps
together we have now constructed a poker
hand a set of five
cards um and the claim is that this
recipe is going to help us count the set
of four of a kind
hands great we can be a little more
precise with this um what we've really
done
done excuse me um so first we've set up
a set I'm going to call it a is going to
be the set
of R and
C where R is a
rank C is a
card with rank not equal to
R so this is sort of following our
recipe we choose a rank for the four of
a kind and then we choose a fifth card
which can't be one of the four we've
already picked um and B is the set of
four of a
kind
hands we have the set a of pairs of
sequences this is where counting with
sequences comes
in but B is really the set we're trying
to
count and we've set up a map from A to B
we set up some function f from A to
B which takes a rank and some other card
and turns it into the hand rank of
Hearts rank of diamonds rank of Spades
rank of clubs and then this other card
C does that make sense how this
description of a recipe turns into this
set this set and this map between
them wonderful no objections so I'll
continue um and now the
claim f is a
bje this is where counting with recipes
this is what the technique is we want to
construct some set of sequences where
we're making a sequence of choices in
order and we want to prove that the
resulting set is
injection with the set we're actually
trying to count and as long as we can
verify that bje then we know the size of
B because we know the size of a with
generalized product
rule so we need to verify f is a bje and
then we need to count the size of a in
order to figure out the size of B so
what does it mean for f to be a
bje well we need F to be
a
function
total
surjective and
injective okay so what does it mean for
f to be a function it means for every
input there's at most one output and
that's usually built into the process um
we have some deterministic way of
turning this pair into this hand and
there's not ambiguity this pair can't
turn into seven different hands usually
we get the function side for free and
it's not really worth commenting on much
what does total
mean total means that um every pair
turns into at least one hand and since
we know it's a function every pair turns
into exactly one hand specifically turns
into a hand in the set we care
about so we have our first first
meaningful
question um
is f of r c a four of a
kind for
every way we have to fill out our recipe
so is everything we construct are all of
the hands that we construct really four
of a kind hands or are we constructing
some extraneous stuff if we're building
extraneous stuff then we're not counting
the right set cuz we're not building the
right
set so first meaningful question for
every way we have to fill the recipe is
the hand that we've
constructed a hand that we're trying to
count and in this case well we can see
that yes yes it is because we have all
four cards of the same
rank um and we have a fifth card that is
not any of these cards because it has
rank that's different from R so this
really is a size five sub set with four
cards of the same rank so in this case
yes
great we need F to be
subjective what does it mean to be
subjective it means every four of a kind
hand everything in B comes from
something in
a all
right um can
every four of
aind hand
be
built so can we really construct
everything that we're trying to
count uh in this
example uh let's look at an example if I
have the four of a kind hand that has a
three of Hearts the seven of Hearts the
three of diamonds the three of clubs and
the three of SP
es how do I build that from my recipe
how do I get that as an output of my
function
f what is r and what is
C
yep okay all right R is three and C is
the seven of
Hearts
oops that's exactly right the rank R is
supposed to tell us the rank that we
have four of we have four threes so the
rank is three the card C is supposed to
be the fifth extraneous card in the hand
that isn't part of the four of aind uh
and that's the seven of hearts in this
example was there any
ambiguity um or sorry more importantly
will we always be able to do this this
for every four of a kind hand will we
always be able to pick out a rank and
pick out the fifth card yeah yeah so we
are
subjective we can build every hand that
we care to
build the last thing we need to
check is our function
injective all right and what it means
for f to be
injective
is can every for of a Kind
hand be
built in
exactly one way exactly one way is what
it means to be surjective and injective
combined so for every four of a kind
hand is there only one way to build it
with our
recipe and in this case yeah for for
kind of the same reason we know which
rank we have four of we know which card
is the other card that is that doesn't
match that Rank and there's only one way
to do that in fact there's exactly one
way to do that so we have built
everything in our set exactly once with
our
recipe so in this case yes which means
it is
injective and now we've decided
therefore f is a bje
are we
done wait what were we even trying to do
oh yeah we were trying to count the
number of for
kinds okay we did one of the two
important
steps we showed that a is injection with
B but now we need the actual number the
actual size of B we need we need the
count and if we want to count the size
of B now we know it's enough to count
the size of a
so we can
use this time the generalized product
rule so size of a well remember we're
choosing an r and we're choosing a
c so how many options do we have for our
rank r
13 there are 13 ranks Ace through King
we can choose any one of them
freely how many options do we have for
this last card C that doesn't have this
rank
MH 48 perfect there are 52 cards in the
deck we've already chosen four of them
of this rank there are 48 options left
so by the generalized product rule
the size of a is 133 *
48 so that's the other thing our recipe
needs to
satisfy it needs to form a bje with the
set we care about but it also needs to
be easy to count with the generalized
product
rule and that's the strategy break down
your set you can think of it as building
up your set via a sequence of simple
choices
make sure it's a
bje and then count it with generalized
product rule let's do that again let's
look at another example this time I want
the number of
hands with all four
suits how many hands have all four
suits these are useless in poker this
this doesn't actually get you anything
um unless it has some other coincidences
as well but it's fun to count how many
hands have all four suits and let's see
if we can break this down into a recipe
all right here's my
recipe choose a heart
card uh choose oh sorry my notes have
choose a club card first then choose a
heart
card uh then choose a space
card choose a diamond
card and
then choose a fifth
card here's my recipe choose a a heart a
card that has clubs a card that has
hearts a card that has Spades a card
that has diamonds and then whatever
other card I want to fill the last
spot and let's see if this is a valid
recipe for this problem
and we can boil that down we don't
always have to think okay injective serg
all that all that fun stuff we can boil
it down into sort of these bullet points
which we can even compress a little
further um so first of
all is every
hand constructed using our
recipe um actually in our set
so does every hand we construct really
have all four
suits and
finally um does
sorry can every hand in our
set be
constructed in a
exactly one
way these are the two questions we need
to ask can we build everything we care
about
and uh can we build everything we care
about in exactly one
way and if those two things are true
then our map is a bje and our recipe is
valid um but these are maybe easier to
think about and remember than going
through that bijection rigal just
remember that it's a bijection
underneath that's that's what we're
doing that's what the Shepherds do they
count with
bijections um so let's answer these
questions um is every hand constructed
with this recipe actually a hand that
has all four sets all four
suits yeah yeah absolutely these first
four cards are always going to have all
four suits and the fifth card doesn't
really help or hurt us so the answer to
this first question is yes yes yes it
does can every hand in our set can every
hand with all four suits be constructed
via our recipe in in exactly one
way and let's look at an example for
that examples are really
helpful so here's my hand I'm going to
look at the six of
diamonds the Queen of Hearts the Ace of
Spades the two of clubs and the Jack of
Spades let's say we're trying to build
this particular hand using our
recipe well what does it tell us to do
first choose a club card all right I'm
going to choose two of clubs then choose
a heart card great I'm GNA choose um the
Queen of
Hearts then choose a spade card uh great
Ace of
Spades then choose a diamond card uh six
of
diamonds and then my last card whatever
that is it's Jack of
Spades so these are the choices I make
in the five steps of my recipe I indeed
have built this
hand can I do that in exactly one way is
there only one way to fill out this
recipe in order to get this hand
can someone find another
yep yeah the ace and the Jack the two
Spade cards those could have swapped
places in step three when I was told to
pick a spade card I could have picked
the Jack instead and then the ace would
be my fifth my fifth extraneous card at
the
end so there are in fact two different
ways of filling out my recipe in order
to get this particular hand
so it's not a bje we have failed our
second condition this recipe does not
work with this
method sometimes you can salvage it in
this particular example you can salvage
it it turns out um this map that we've
constructed is two to one because there
are always exactly two ways to fill out
the
recipe whichever card you have in the
spot it can potentially swap places with
its partner that has its same suit but
there are always only two ways to do
that so instead of constructing a
baction we've constructed a two to one
map which means we can still count the
number of ways of filling out the recipe
and then just divide it by
two so let's do
that um number of ways to fill out this
recipe actually let's just do it right
here
how many ways are there to choose a card
that has
clubs just call it
out how many Club cards are there in a
deck 13 yeah I think I heard that let's
pretend I
did um how many heart cards are in a
deck
13 how many Spades 13 how many diamonds
13 how many choices do I have for my
last card 48 again
I'm allowed to choose any card that
isn't one of the four I've already
picked which means the number of ways to
fill out this recipe is 13 * 13 * 13 *
13 *
48 so our
answer is 13 to 4 *
48 divided by two because we decided it
was a 2: one
map so this is the number of hands that
have all four suits
did that make
sense this is a perfectly valid way to
do this um this counting with sequences
technique um generalizes very nicely to
this K to1 mapping instead of uh one:
one mapping a bje BS are maybe more
elegant or easier to think about if you
can make it but if it's if it's two to
one instead that's great just divide by
two um just so we can see some different
strategies uh here is a way that we
could have done that uh with a bje
instead of needing a two to one map
um so a different recipe is the
following so
first choose a suit
s
um that will have two cards
so in in every hand that has all four
suits there's always one suit that has
two cards and the other three suits have
one card so first we're going to choose
which suit has two
cards all
right call the other three
suits uh T1 T2 T3 in alphabetical order
so once I've chosen which suit I'm going
to single out for the pair I've just
given names to the other three suits and
it's in alphabetical order so there's no
ambiguity there so now my four suits are
s and T1 T2
T3 all right next thing I'm going to
do choose two
cards um with suit s
choose one
card with suit T1 then choose one with
suit T2 then choose one with suit T3 and
that's my
recipe all
right and it turns out that this really
does give a bje this is a onetoone map
between ways of filling out this recipe
and hands that have all four
suits because that ambiguity of which of
these two cards are we choosing first
well we're not choosing them first we're
choosing them
together uh so we've gotten rid of that
ambiguity by doing it in this way and
let's see how many ways there are to
fill out this recipe first we have to
choose a suit s and there are four suits
to choose
from then we have to choose two cards
with suit
s and there are 13 choose
two ways to do
that now choose a card with suit T1 13
ways with suit T2 13 ways with suit T3
ways and so the answer is four * 13
choose two * 13 * 13 *
13 which does look a little different
from the answer we got up there but if
you check they're actually the same
answer does that make sense sound good
wonderful one last example I want to
look at how many hands
how many hands have at
least one
pair so pair means same
rank so how many hands have at least two
cards of the same rank so at least two
queens at least two sevens something
like that maybe you have three or four
Queens maybe you have two queens and two
sevens or three sevens all of that is
fine as long as at least two of your
cards have have the same
rank all
right and here is my proposed
recipe
okay choose a
rank for the
pair uh let's let's call it choose rank
R for the
pair choose two
cards with rank r
choose three other
cards here's a recipe to build up hands
that have at least one pair we know they
have a pair because here's the pair in
step two everything we build has at
least one pair and that's the first of
our two important questions um does
everything we build have our
property the answer in this case is
yes does every thing we want to build
come from our recipe in exactly one way
is the other question we need to
ask does every
hand
with at least one
pair come from
recipe in exactly one
way right this is the other question we
need we need to ask usually this is the
harder of the two questions because
usually when trying to build our set
we're building it in order to have the
property we care about so that first of
the two important questions is usually
fine is this
true um and let's let's look at an
example here um so what if we want the
hand Ace of
Hearts Ace of
Spades two of clubs two of diamonds
three of
Hearts how can I get this hand with my
recipe can someone give me
away
yep mhm
okay let's choose our rank as
a for our first step second step is two
cards with rank
Ace Ace of Hearts and Ace of Spades for
our second
step um and for our third step the other
three cards in this case that's two of
clubs two of diamonds three of Hearts
this is a way to fill out our recipe in
order to get that hand who can give me
another way
yep all right rank equals
two all right um then then the two cards
of rank two we're going to pick are
going to be two of clubs and two of
diamonds and then the last step of our
recipe is choose the other three cards
which in this case are Ace of Hearts Ace
of Spades and three of
Hearts so we found two different ways of
filling out our recipe to get this
hand so we've already broken our second
question um this this answer is
no but we've already seen a possible
backup if it's always two:
one then we're fine then we just divide
by two and get our
answer but let's look at a different
example uh what if our hand is
instead Ace of Heart Hearts Ace of
Diamonds Ace of
clubs three of clubs five of
Spades a recipe really breaks down into
two phases first pick a pair and then
pick the other three
cards right pick the rank for a pair
then the sorry pick a suit for the pair
then the ranks for the pair really pick
a pair and then pick the other three
cards is what our recipe says well there
are lots of ways to do that for this
hand we could pick this pair for our
first two steps of the recipe and then
choose the other three
cards or we could pick that pair and
then choose the other three cards or we
could pick that pair and then choose the
other three
cards so this one had two
ways this hand has three
ways here's another example
Ace of Diamonds oops Ace of clubs three
of clubs and then three of Spades same
example as before but now these are both
threes instead of a three and five How
many pairs are there now 1 2 3 four
different pairs so there are four ways
to build this with our
recipe let's keep going what if we have
a four of a kind we have all four
aces on and then we have the Queen of
Diamonds uh so that was clubs hearts
spades diamonds now there are 1 two
three four five six different pairs so
there are six different
ways to construct this hand with our
recipe did all of these examples make
sense cool and what we've learned here
is that this recipe is utter garbage
this recipe does not help it doesn't
make a bje because there are multiple
ways to build this hand it doesn't make
a k to1 mapping because there a
different number of ways depending on
which hand we're trying to build so we
can't just count this and then divide by
two or divide by three um
question yeah uh so with with this
hand um steps one and two really say
pick a pair and then step three says
pick the other three cards well how many
pairs can we pick in this hand there
are four choose two ways to pick two of
the aces 4 CH two is
six um or we can just look at it it's
one two 3 um four five six those are all
the
pairs yeah good question so this
recipe does not help I don't care how
many ways there are to fill out this
recipe I don't care how easy it is to
count with generalized product rule the
thing it's counting is not at all
related to the problem we care about so
this is the thing you need to watch out
for and that's why these two
questions are the things you should ask
yourself about every recipe you see can
you build everything you care about and
is everything you care about built in
exactly one
way and it it takes some practice and
some skill and some patience to figure
out the right recipe in order to satisfy
both of these constraints and to work
out any of the ambiguities that we see
in an example like
this all right that's everything I have
thank you so much