Okay. So let me first remind you uh
about so we we'll be looking so last
time
then we were looking at we had a
sequence of functions
uh on a interval I
uh and we have a function f on that same
interval.
And then we talked about two notions of
convergence.
Uh
one is was the pointwise convergence.
So this meant that so we say that this
sequence converts to f pointwise
if for all
x fixed
you're looking at the sequence fn of x
right so x is fixed and that this here
converts to f ofx right so that was the
pointwise convergence
And the second uh convergence that we
talked about was a uniform convergence.
So this is two
uniform
convergence,
right? And so we say that this sequence
here converts to F uniformly.
if
um for all epsilon greater than zero
there exist a n so that if you're
further out
then n then the difference
between fn of x and f ofx is smaller
than epsilon and this here has to hold
for all
uh X
right and so again uniform uniform
uh refers to that is that is for all
for all x
right so it's uniform in x
okay and and so there was one example
that was particular illuminating
uh
and that was that we took so if I here
was the interval from 0 to 1.
And if we're looking at the function
f(n) of x that was just x ^ n and f of x
is then the function that is uh that is
zero
uh unless
zero if x here is between zero and
strictly less than one and one
uh if x is equal to one. Right?
And so the picture was that um
right so the picture was that so that
you have this sequence here they are
defined on the interval from zero to one
they all end up at one and then as as n
go as n become larger and larger these
functions become more and more steep
towards one right like that Right? And
so then we had that this sequence fn
converts to f pointwise
because if you fixed
x then really these values here converge
either to if you know if x is not equal
to one then as n become large
uh they converge to zero. If n is one
then the fn of one is that's always one
right. So, so it's clear that it's
converging pointwise, but but um but fn
does not converge does not
not converge
to f uniformly,
right? And the reason why it didn't
converge uniformly was that we saw that
for each if we by the intermediate value
theorem if we were looking at a half
here then for each of the function there
would be an xn
so that the value at xn was one right
and so was a half sorry the right so you
you define x xn so that the value of
this is a half. But now if you're
looking at f of x minus f of um of xn
like that.
And if this here sorry is n then this
here this difference here is is is is
actually just a half. Right? And this
difference here should be small. If n
was sufficiently large, it should be
small for all x. But it's not there. We
used one particular x to show that it
wasn't right.
Okay. Um that was just a quick uh review
of some of the things we talked about
last time. Now
let's get to a theorem.
And so maybe also one more thing about
this example is
that you see that these functions here
these functions fn
they are all continuous right but the
limit is not continuous right so
pointwise so note that uh so note
that pointwise convergence
Um
is not enough
to guarantee
that limits
of continuous functions
uh um that that the limit
of continuous function is continuous.
Right?
Okay. So that's what this example
illustrates. So now instead we have the
following theorem that so we have this
interval and we have a sequence fn and
we have f all defined on this interval
and if we assume that uh that all of
these that these fns
are uh continuous
and B. We assume that the convergence
here
the convergence of FN to to F is
uniform.
Then the claim is that then
then
uh f here is also continuous.
[Applause]
I'm okay. So let's try to prove that
right. So so point mass convergence is
not enough to guarantee that the limit
is continuous. Uniform convergence is
enough.
Uh now uh let's see. So let's prove
that.
So uh given
given epsilon gradient zero
uh there exist
there exist
uh capital n such that
if little n is bigger equal to capital n
then fn of x minus f ofx
is smaller than uh epsilon over three
for all x.
Right? This is just this just follows
from that the sequence converts
uniformly. Right? So this is the first
thing
and the second thing is so so
this was was since fn converts to f
uniformly.
The second thing is that's that. So now
we have a n this here holds for all
little n bigger equal to capital n but
in particular it holds for capital n. So
now since
f capital n is continuous so this is a
fixed function. Now
uh then
then
given then for any
for any fixed
[Applause]
X0 we have
that
uh we have that there exist
uh delta greater than zero such that
if x - x0 is smaller than delta then uh
this function the value at these two
points points differ at most.
So this is for the fn.
Um the value at these two points differ
at most
by um epsilon over.
Right? So again, so we have a sequence
fn f little n that converts uniformly to
some f. We want to prove that this f is
continuous. So we just need to prove
that for each x0 fixed it's continuous
at x0 right first I'm using that the
sequence is converging uniformly
so given this epsilon there exist this
capital n so that if you're further out
then you have this I'm not even going to
use the part that is further out I'm
just going to pick this capital n right
and so then I'm using that this f
capital n is continuous and it's
continuous at x0. So I have this right
and so now we need to estimate
we now need to estimate the difference
right so what we really interested is in
f but the f capital n that's going to
help us estimate the difference between
these two numbers
and so these two numbers so x here x was
this x0 was this fixed point that we
want to show that that f is continuous
uh at that point and the delta well the
delta came from
f capital n. So we're looking at this x
this close where the delta was given by
f capital n and now we have we use the
triangle inequality. So this difference
here is so you may as well think about
this one here and you could compare it
with the value at the same point. So I'm
just writing down I'm writing this
difference down as a sum of things. So
and then afterwards I use the triangle
inequality. So here minus f capital n of
x0 and then I'm adding back this here
again f capital n of x0 and I'm
comparing this with f of x0
right so you see that here this is
really the same because here I'm
subtracting this thing that I didn't
have but I'm adding it back subtracting
this thing that I didn't have but I'm
adding it back so I'm just left with
those two things which is that
And so now we use the triangle
inequality
that this is now bounded by f ofx minus
f n of x
plus f n of x
minus f capital n of x0 like that plus
and then f capital n of x0 minus f of x0
with absolute value sign like that.
Now
this thing here is smaller than epsilon
over three and that came from that it's
at this evaluated at the same point and
the convergence was uniform. So it
really was the first part here right so
that is less than epsilon over 3.
This one here comes from that the
difference between x and x0 is is less
than delta and that this function fn was
continuous at uh x0. So this is another
epsilon over delta. This is this second
part here.
And then the last here is again the same
that gave us this bound namely that the
convergence was uniform and is evaluated
at the same point. So you have that
right and so what we've proven here is
that so for this given x0 if the
difference between x and x0 is less than
delta then the difference in the images
is less than epsilon. So this means that
the function f is continuous at x0
um and x0 was was was arbitrary. Okay.
Now
um
now the first application of this is
that suppose you take
suppose you're looking at the following
example
uh uh x n of x is the sum here from k =
z to n of x k over k factorial. Suppose
you're looking at xn like this.
Then uh then the xn here
of x uh they are all are all continuous
right? They are sum of polinomials you
know they're just a polinomial actually
the sum of of um
of of of of what's called homogeneous
polinomial but they are themselves
polomial so they are all continuous
um and via stress M test so and by
v stress
M test that we proved last time
by a bias M test the convergence here
to
E where E here is the exponential
function. So it's this power series sum
from uh k = 0 to infinity of x to the
power k over k factorial. The
convergence this convergence here is
uniform. It's uniform
assuming that you that you do it on a
compact interval. So it's uniform
on any
fixed interval.
of the form
say
minus L to L right so if you're fixing a
interval like this then the convergence
is is uniform and so this means that
since these guys here are continuous
then it implies that this one here is
also continuous Yes.
Right. So this is this is implied by the
theorem that we just proved.
Now
uh so now this will uh this will uniform
convergence.
There's another way of thinking about
uniform convergence
that in a way is
this makes it makes it more natural.
So because so
remember that if we looked at so if we
take a interval let's say
that this is a interval from a to b a
and b are real numbers
then we looked at the space of
continuous functions
on this interval right
and this space had a natural metric so
uh so so I'm using here that both end
points are included included. This space
here has a natural
a natural metric
and that metric is that if you take two
functions,
two continuous functions on the
interval, then the distance between
these two function
is just the max
of the um of the the max of the
difference
between the two functions,
right? The difference again why is this
by the difference is continuous. So this
means that the maximum is the difference
is continuous. So this is a continuous
function and it's still continuous. If
you take absolute value and so this
means that the maximum by the extreme
value theorem is achieved. Right?
Right. And so this here was a natural uh
distance between them. Right. Now to say
that the sequence here to say that the
sequence f little n is converging
uniformly
you can think about that in terms of
this distance. So,
so we have the following proposition.
FN converge uniformly
to F
if and only if
uh FN
converts to F in the metric space.
with this with this metric. Okay.
Now, why is this the case? So this is
just that uh so proof of that it's
really just a oneliner because the you
see that to say that the so that so that
f ofx
minus fn of x
is lesser equal to
uh
uh to uh epsilon for all X.
If this here is the case, well, this is
equivalent to saying
that the distance
between FN
and uh NF
is less or equal to epsilon for all X.
Right? Because if this here is the case
for all x then the maximum is less or
equal to epsilon. This was the maximum.
And on the other hand if the maximum
well then it holds for each x right. So
this is sort of a tology.
Okay. And so now we see of course that
if if the sequence so you have that but
this means
so this means that if the sequence
therefore
if this sequence fn converts to f
uniformly
well then it means that for all epsilon.
If we're sufficiently far out, then this
here can be for any given epsilon. If
you're sufficiently far out, this here
can be made lesser equal to epsilon,
which means that this hair can be made
lesser equal to epsilon if you're
sufficiently far out. So you see that if
this converts uniformly, then it implies
that this thing here
converts to zero.
But that's exactly what it means that
this sequence fn converts to f
in in the met in the metric space
and the other way around.
If if this sequence converts fn converts
to f in the metric space, this is
equivalent to saying that this hair goes
to zero. But if this hair goes to zero,
right? This means that if you're
sufficiently far out, but given epsilon,
if you're sufficiently far, this hair is
lesser equal to epsilon, but it means
that this hair is less than epsilon,
right? So that means it really converts
uniform, right?
Okay.
And that's a in a way that makes it much
more natural. Uh I mean yeah the so it's
um
un it makes uniform convergence much
more natural.
Okay. So now let's prove the next
theorem.
So for this theorem
we're going to think about uniform
convergence
in terms of this metric and in terms of
convergent in this metric space. So the
theorem is then
this next thing that say that if you
take a interval from a to b
and you're looking at the continuous
function
and you equip it with this metric that
we talked about
then this here is this space which is a
metric space. So this metric space
is a cushy complete.
Okay.
So remember kle in a metric space means
that if you take a cushy sequence so
just let me just record here over here.
So uh cush so if x comma d
is a matrix space.
Then C complete
means
that any secret
uh is convergence,
right? That's what it means to be a
cushy complete. And of course, an
example of of a cushy complete
um metric space was just if we took R
with the usual with the usual metric
Okay. Down. So what we have here is so
let's try to prove this.
So we need to prove so
so this here is now we need to prove
that if this here is a
cushy sequence
then uh then
there exist
[Applause]
an function that is also continuous.
And so this sequence here converging to
f
uh in the metric
D, right? That's what we need to prove.
Okay. So in in in in particular we need
to first construct a function
f right.
[Applause]
So now so let's try first to construct a
function.
So,
so we first
construct
f as follows.
Well, if you fix
fix x, right? So x is something a point
in the interval.
And now look at this sequence fn. This
is now a regular sequence.
And so but if you're looking at the
sequence then we have that fn
of x minus f m of x. If you have two n
and m like this, then the difference
here is lesser equal to
the max
where this is for all set in the
interval
of um of f mn
of set
minus uh fm um of set
like that right because of course you
know it means like in particular if x
set was x right so you have clearly this
but now you see that uh so I claim so I
claim that this means so there so I
claim
that this implies that the this that
this implies
that this sequence here.
Sorry. This sequence here fn of x this
sequence here is a which is a sequence
of real numbers. is here real numbers
that this here is a cy sequence
of real numbers.
Why
why is that the case? Well, it's the
case because
because given
so this is just because given given so
this is
the case
because
given
epsilon greater than zero
since
fn N is a C sequence.
In the metric space
in this metric space then um there exist
capital N. So that if little n and
little m are bigger than capital n then
the difference between these guys sorry
the difference between this function
here and that function
is less than epsilon
right this is because the work sequence
and so now this thing here is of course
this thing here that's what we just saw
this is like the maximum form. So this
is bigger than when you evaluate it in
just one point
like that, right?
And so so this proves
this proved right that that this when x
is fixed these guys here is a cy
sequence of real numbers.
So now we use since
r here is cushy complete
and
fn of x is a cushy sequence.
then it means that uh that the sequence
fn of x that this is converging
and it's converging to some number right
so just one number and that number we
can call
f ofx right so we just defined f to be
the limit of this sequence right and
that's what defined because there's just
one number right so for each x it gives
you a number.
Okay. So now what we have proven is
that so now we have a candidate
so namely we have shown
that
so now what you have we've proven here
is
that we have found a function. So we
have now proven that this sequence here
is converging to some function f the
convergence is just pointwise
and we don't know whether this function
is continuous or not right it's the
convergence is pointwise this is just
because it convert for each fixed x it
was f of f ofx was defined so that it
was a limit of these guys fn of x right
okay so now we need to promote this
convergence so the point was pointwise
and we need to promote the convergence
to uniform convergence right and so so
now we need so now
uh given
so given epsilon greater than zero
again Since since these guys FN was a CC
sequence
in the metric space in
in this metric space
then then as we saw over there they
exist
there exist capital N. So that if little
n and and little m are bigger than this
capital n then uh then the difference
between these two then fn of x - fm of x
this thing here
is lesser equal to
and I'm using epsilon / two for all X.
Okay.
So you have that
but now this here holds for all M and N,
right? Let's just fix N.
And now we can use that it's it's still
true. I can still let M vary, right? And
so if you let m go. So now letting so
fixed fix
n bigger than capital n and
let little m goes to infinity.
Right? Well
this here is just some fixed number. But
as m go to infinity this here go to f
ofx. Right? And so since this difference
is always less or equal to epsilon /
two, it's also the case that the
difference here
of the limit
is lesser or equal
to epsilon / two. So you have this here
for all x,
right? This is just letting m goes to uh
to the limit.
But this of course say this say that
that the max if you will. So you have
that. So this implies
that the max of fn of x minus f ofx
that this thing here where x is now in
this interval that this is lesser equal
to epsilon.
Right?
And but this is like the same this here
is just the distance between fn
and f right. So say that this distance
here here is less than uh I guess I had
epsilon / two. So it means that this
thing here is less than strictly less
than epsilon. It's actually less or
equal to epsilon / two. So it's strictly
less than epsilon.
But that's exactly what it means for
this sequence here. So this is the same
this is the same
as saying
that fn converts to f uniformly.
right
here. Sorry, here I should have taken
the soup. The reason
why I should take the soup here is
that f is just a function. It's not
necessarily continuous at this stage.
Right? So, but it was clearly the case
with soup. So, the maximum appro may not
be achieved yet. But now you see that
they converge
these fn converge to f uniformly right.
But then and these these guys here was
continuous. Right? These are continuous.
So this implies that by this theorem we
just proved that f is also continuous.
Right? And so you see that so now you
have that the limit is indeed in the
space and we already proved here that
the convergence to this limit is is is
in is uniform which means that it's it's
in that in the metric. Okay.
The next thing is that right so this is
this here was just a little bit
different way of thinking about uniform
convergence that you think about it sort
of more abstractly as a convergence in a
metric space right and it's a useful way
of thinking about it the next thing we
want to look at is
how this uniform convergence
uh gives you a way of uh computing
things. So in particular if you have
some power series
um and so and we talked about that a
little bit last time we didn't prove
anything
but one of the one of the motivation for
this is that suppose you take a power
series like this
and we we'll return to this in just a
second but suppose you take a power
series like this and You are inside the
radius of convergence. So inside
radius of convergence.
[Applause]
So you know that this thing here makes
sense, right? That this for each x gives
you a number.
And so it gives you a function. And so
you're interested in what is the
derivative of that function and what is
the what is the integral of that
function. How do we integrate it and how
do we take the derivative? And the thing
that worries you a bit is that it's if
it was just a finite sum, it would be
trivial. But it's a infinite sum, right?
And so is it okay? So the the natural
question is is it okay if you want to
take the derivative, can you interchange
this infinite sum with taking
derivative? And likewise, if you want to
integrate this infinite sum, is it okay
to inter interchange the infinite sum
with taking the integral? And the and
the answer is it's okay. Okay. And so
let's see that. So we do this. So we
have two versions of this. One that's
dealing with taking integrals and
another version that deals with taking
derivatives.
Okay.
And so the first thing is that I take so
first theorem is the following
that I have some interval
from a to b.
Um
um and then I have a sequence of
functions fn
that are um that are integraable.
They may not be continuous. They're just
integraable.
So in particular they are uh they are
bounded.
And then I have that uh fn here
converts to
f uniform.
Okay. And I want to prove that. So the
claim is that
that fm
is also integraable
and the integral
of f
is equal to uh the limit
of these integrals.
Okay.
So, so in particular, of course,
those integral here has a limit, right?
It's part of the statement.
[Applause]
Okay.
Um
right. So now um
Right. So what do we want to what do we
need to prove? So prove
remember that. So we want to show So we
first want to show
that
f is integraable
and we had a criteria for doing that. So
we're using the criteria.
So we can use
that's uh all we need to show
to show
is the following that given
given epsilon greater than zero
there exist
there exist a partition P of of the
interval
from A to B
so that uh so that the upper sum of f
with respect to this partition
minus the lower sum of f with respect to
the same partition that this thing here
is less than epsilon right that's all we
need to prove we need to prove
For each epsilon we need to prove that
there exist a partition. Right? So if we
have that then we already know that then
f is integral. Okay. And then then so
that's just achieve this this first task
and then afterwards we need to prove
that.
No,
right. Okay. So now how do we prove
that?
So
um so the first thing we observe is
that if we take uh if we're looking at
uh suppose that f n
and f here suppose that this um suppose
that fn of x
minus uh f ofx
suppose that this thing here was less
than
uh was less than
epsilon over 3
b minus a.
Okay, suppose you have that
and you can of course this here can be
achieved, right? This here can so
epsilon is now given, right? And so you
have that so so maybe I should just say
that uh so epsilon is given. So since
fn converts to f uniformly
this means that there exist there exist
capital n so that if you're further out
than capital n then actually you have
this thing here right b minus b b and a
are fixed this is just something fixed.
So this is just another epsilon, right?
Okay. So if you have that now suppose
you take
uh so remember we defined when we do uh
did the when we had the partition the
partition had the dividing points
with dividing points
x i. So we were looking at these small
intervals x i from x i minus one to x i
and we're looking at the soup of the
function.
So if you're looking at the soup of
suppose you're looking at so this here
is on this little interval
but it's for f right
but the function f here you see the
function. So you have that f of x
this function here sorry I don't need
the absolute value but f ofx is less or
equal to uh f uh n of x
uh plus of course uh f of x minus f n of
x
right and so this means that this thing
here is by this thing here is less or
equal to fn of x. This thing here is
bounded by the absolute value of it,
right? And and so this thing here so
this is fn of x and this here is just
epsilon over
over 3
uh b minus a
like that right
so this means that if I take the soup on
this little interval of f then it's
bounded by the soup of this function
plus that number right so I have that so
I have that
that's
[Applause]
So I have that the again the soup of f
on this little interval.
This is what we call m i of f.
that this is less or equal to because of
this inequality is less than the soup of
fn
of x on the same little interval
plus epsilon over 3 b minus a right
and likewise likewise
so so likewise
for for the in.
So again I let little mi of f this is
now the infom
on this little interval
oops on this little interval of f right
sorry here here here I wanted to I
wanted to insert what this thing was so
this is m right I just the notation for
this soup here is m I FN
and uh the infreum the interim for f on
this little interval the notation for
that is that is is this little m i refer
to the interval f to the function
and so similarly if you take the uh
infom
infom So and you compare it to the infom
of this fn on the same interval
then the same
argument with obvious changes means that
m i
f here
is now bigger equal to
m i fn
minus
epsilon 1 over 3 B minus A.
Okay,
it's the same thing.
Okay, maybe I'll just explain it, but
it's the same sort of thing that you
take.
Oh, maybe I shouldn't erase this one.
So, it's a sort of the same thing that
you're looking at. You have f ofx
again uh is equal to fn of x plus uh fn
plus f of x minus right. So you have
obviously this.
And so this means that f ofx
is um is big or equal to
fn of x
minus. If you think that this here
becomes negative and the maximum it can
become negative on this little interval
here on uh this little interval
the the worst this here can become
negative is epsilon over
uh actually for any interval is a is
this like that. So you always have this.
Okay.
And and so if you take now the infom on
this little interval then you're getting
m i f bigger equal to m i fn minus
epsilon
over 3 b minus a. Right? So you have
that. So that's what we claim over
there.
Okay. So, so we have we have this thing
here and we have the corresponding
thing. This is less or equal to the
maximum of the function on the same
interval.
And then that's and the uh and then this
equality here this equality here was
that it's bounded by this guy here plus
epsilon / 3 b minus a. Okay,
so this is for the little M's, the
little MIS and the capital MI. And now
we need to sum these guys and we need to
uh multiply those with a delta XI. So
this means that if you're looking at So
what we're interested in is we're
looking at this
times delta XI.
This gives you the the the sorry this
gives you the lower sum of f
with respect to this partition right
where you're summing here over the i
if you're summing
the soups
then you're getting the upper like
there, right?
And so now,
[Applause]
so you take
you take this equality, this inequality,
the string of inequality,
and you're just multiplying by delta
xi
on both sides
and then I'm summing right so if I
multiply so let's call this here star so
multiply
star
by delta xi
and sum
over
i right if you do that then what you get
is you're getting mi
fn
um
time minus epsilon over 3 b minus a
times
this time delta x i this is less or
equal to
m i
f delta xi
which is less or equal to this one here.
Sorry. And I should also sum
summing over I
like this.
And then I have one more inequality
namely this right hand side. Uh so less
or equal to
I'm summing over I
uh and I have this is m i
f + epsilon over 3 b minus a
time delta x i. Okay,
so we have that. Now let's try to figure
out what this means.
[Applause]
So this here.
So now if you multiply this out
the first thing right the the the
top left corner that gives you when you
multiply the bracket out the first term
you get is the m I fn
times delta xi but that is just the
lower
sum with respect to the partition p for
fn Right?
But then you get an another term which
is you get one other term. you get this
minus and then you're summing over the i
of epsilon 3 b minus a * x i right
and then the then it's less or equal to
the same the the the term uh up there
that's just the lower sum
of f with respect to the partition. The
next term is the upper sum of f with
respect to the partition.
And then the last inequality, the first
term when you multiply this bracket out
the first term here is and unfortunately
there was a missing n
I copied it from here. Sorry,
there was a missing end. I just copied
from this one.
[Applause]
Right? So now when you multiply this
bracket out, the first term you get here
is um is so you're getting less or equal
to the first term you get there when
you're summing over the i. That's
exactly u
fn
p.
And then the second term you get is this
I epsilon over 3 B minus A delta X I
now this thing here
when I'm summing here right then uh I
this is just a constant so I can just
pull that constant out and the sum of
these differences that just give you B
minus A Right? So if you put that in and
this exactly the same you get on this
term then you have that L fn
P minus epsilon / 3
is uh is lesser equal to LF
uh P
and which is lesser equal to U FP
And this is less or equal to
uh u fn
p
plus epsilon over three.
Okay. Now what have we used so far? So
far we have just used P was any
partition and all we have to you all we
have used is that the FN converts to F
uniformly and then for this given
epsilon we chose this capital N
sufficiently large right
but now
now you see that now we can just fix so
now we just Let
uh little n we just set let this be
equal to this capital n. Right? We just
need to use it for one uh for one little
n.
And so but and then we can and now we
have that since
this particular function this one
function was integraable
then there exist a partition
but this is now a partition that is
that's comes from right it's determined
from this function here but there exist
a partition position so that so that the
L uh sorry so that the difference
between the difference between the upper
sum
for this function
minus the lower sum for this function
is less than say epsilon / 3. Okay.
But so you see that
this number here
uh right so you see that the difference
now I can erase this thing here.
So now
the first
so we observe now
that
that this number here
this number here because of this this
this
number is always larger than that.
Right? And so this means that this thing
here is u by this inequality it just
tells you that this is less than that
this thing here. Let me continue here
below that this thing here is less than
l fn
p
plus epsilon over three. This is coming
from that this one here. Just moving
this over on the other side. Then you
have that this is bounded by that and
then you have another epsilon over
three.
Fine.
And so you see that those two things
this here and that here is squeezed in
an interval of length epsilon. Right? So
it means that the difference between
these two is is bounded by epsilon.
Right? So, so
LF
with respect to this partition and U FP
right they are in a in both lie
both lie
in an interval
of length
epsilon right so it means that the
difference between the two right so the
difference between so this here which is
always positive
but this here the difference must be
less than less I guess less or equal to
doesn't matter
right okay so and this proves so this
show right so this show
that that f here is integraable
it's integraable
Right? Because to show that this
function was integral, we just needed to
for a given epsilon, we needed to find a
partition so that the upper the
difference between the upper and the
lower sum was less or equal to epsilon.
Right?
So the function f is is is is
uh is integraable. Now I claim that it
also proves that um it also show that
that the limit is what it should be
right because you see that we now know
we now know that the function so Now, so
we have
now
that
this integral of f dx this exist right
because we prove that it's integral so
it means that this exists and this is
always squeezed
between
for any partition it's always squeezed
between these two things,
right?
But now you see that so this means that
that it would have to lie
in this string of inequality.
It would have to lie here between these
two numbers. Right? But this thing here
um you know if you make this right so we
have also
right so so what do we have
we have that
that so
so we have that this integral here from
a to b of f dx is less less or equal to
u f with respect to any partition.
Same thing here.
And now if we if we um right if we let
the if we looked at if we used this uh
if we we used that for this given
epsilon that n here was bigger than
capital n big or equal to
then we have that this thing here was
bounded below from this inequality l fn
p minus
uh epsilon / 3
and we had that it was bounded from
above. So this is just this inequality u
fn
p plus epsilon / 3 and so now we we made
use of and so we do this for this
capital n.
So in particular it holds for capital n.
And now we made use of that. Uh so now
all I want to do is here I want to
estimate the difference between this
integral here
uh and this integral here and the
integral from a to b of f uh capital n.
Right? And I want to prove that if I'm
very far out this this here is very
small right but I now make this one
here. So if I take if I when I choose my
partition so that this number here so
then I can just make sure that this
number here when I
prove the when I uh choose the partition
then I just said that I choose the
partition so that this thing here
minus this lower here
for this capital n that this here was
smaller than epsilon over two. Right?
And so this means again but now you see
that um this integral
of this integral here this is always
squeezed between these two numbers. So
this is always
squeezed like this.
Right?
And so now you see that this means that
um that this integral is in this
interval here.
Uh but in fact um
in fact of course in this interval
between these two numbers
between actually the these two numbers
by by you know even if there wasn't a
plus in that interval that uh this
integral here would also lie right so it
lies
even more comfortable in this larger
interval where you adding epsilon over 3
and subtracting epsilon over 3. So, so
this integral lie between these two the
same is the case for this
and this interval again have length
epsilon. So this means that this
difference between these two number is
also less than epsilon
right
and so this really proved that if it was
sufficiently far out then the difference
between these two integral was bounded
by epsilon right so this this prove that
the integral are converging okay
let's look at So how do we use this? So
what we were interested in was uh using
this fact
uh in the case of a power series. So let
me just
look at an example for that.
So suppose that en of x so this is the
same as in the previous example
um where I'm summing here from k =0 to n
xn over x k sorry over k factorial right
so these are the function xn and x is
just sorry e en and and the function um
to this is the function Here the
function e is just the exponential
function. So which I think about as the
infinite
uh series the power series
like this.
And now I had so we already observe that
by the bio stress uh so by bio stress
M test
uh uh by V size M test the EN
converts to E
on any interval
you have to restrict the interval.
But if you're fixing an interval like
this then it's converging uh uniformly
right so this is what bio size m game
right and now these functions here they
are polomials the en are polinomials so
it's easy to integrate them so you have
that that the integral here of en
dx x from uh let's say some interval
from a to b. This thing here is now uh
equal to the sum here. So you can so now
it's just a finite sum. So you can
exchange that and then you're
integrating from a to b of x k over k
factorial.
And of course that's very easy to do,
right?
uh so dx
and and the theorem with that we just
proved that this thing here is because
the convergence is uniform each of these
is integraable. This means that the
limit here is also uh integraable and
the integral of
of the exponential function
is the limit of these integrals
right and so this the point here is
again is that
um if you have uniform convergence then
you can sort of I mean you're using the
uniform convergence that we have from
bias size M test then we can interchange
this infinite sum with taking integrals.
Okay,
let me just I I I I had wanted to do one
more thing but I
I don't have time to do that quite uh so
I I'll pick up on that next time but let
me just observe
that when you're integrating here when
you're integrating this this thing here
right so what is the integral of this so
when we're just calculating this so
you're integrating uh x to the k over k
factorial. When you're integrating a
polomial, you're looking for you're
using the fundamental theorem of
calculus. So you're trying to look for a
function whose derivative is this,
right? Such a function is often called
the anti-derivative.
And so what is that function? So a
function so if you're looking at x to
the power k + one right so you know that
you have to because it's a polinomial
you have to add one right to the
exponent and then this as when you take
derivative this come down so you have to
look at
k + one factorial right because if you
take when you take the derivative then k
plus one come down and it kills the
first one and the rest is this right
and so so when you evaluate this
integral then it's this here is the
anti-derivative
and you have to ex
uh insert
the boundary values like this right so
that would be the integral
okay so I'll just stop here and next
time I'll go through the one theorem I
didn't get to which is how to
interchange the differentiation and uh
and uh right if you take a sequence of
functions that converge uniformly and
you want to take the derivative of these
um how do you relate the derivative of
the sequence to derivative of the limit
okay so but it's in the notes I already
posted the notes but I'll go through
that next Any
questions?
>> Yeah.
>> That's okay. Right. Because um right so
I um I'm not 100% sure I I needed
epsilon less or equal to epsilon. It
doesn't really matter, right? because
you just picked that I I had chosen it
uh with the epsilon over three and
epsilon over three
* b minus a that was just to have it
worked out. So it was epsilon in the end
but you could of course have chosen it
even smaller than you would have had
strict inequality. It's possible it was
actually strict inequality anyway.