it's a pleasure to be here with you
today uh to present the startup
lightning talks we've invited four
startups for you to meet uh but before
that I'd like to take a few minutes to
tell you about our
program so uh startup exchange was
created within MIT corpet relations to
support MIT connected startups grow
expand and solve The World's great
challenges and we do that by fostering
collaborations and Partnerships with
industry such as um corporate members of
the industrial Leone program and the MIT
Innovation
ecosystem um so at startup exchange we
focus on startups that have a strong
connection with the Institute and this
connection might come either through the
founding team the technology as well as
through their affiliation to some of our
peers on campus who vet and support the
startups throughout the year um such as
start. Nano or MIT Cale startup connect
plus just to name a couple um today we
have a network close to a thousand
startups virtually working in any sector
and this is possible because startups
can come out from any part of Campus any
of the five schools and one college um
some are created throughout um uh mbas
other courses and there's a considerable
number of companies as well graduating
from the many entrepreneurship resources
that exist at MIT and there are over 80
um if you'd like to uh learn more about
them you'll find most of them listed at
orbit. mit.edu that our colleagues from
the trust center
created um besides being sector agnostic
we are also location agnostic so
startups may be located in any part of
the world and we typically start working
with them when they have a technology or
a product that is ready to be tested or
used in a real
environment so everything we do at
startup exchange is to expose and
connect startups and Industry in a very
creative way and we also provide
learning opportunities to both parties
and this includes um launching calls
launching calls for startups that are
based on carpet's own priorities or
challenges facilitating one-on-one
meetings between them and um hosting
different kinds of events such as demo
days that take place virtually once a
quarter uh speed networking events and
startup lightning talks at U uh forums
or or conferences and the the learning
opportunities are provided at uh
workshops we're starting to co-organize
with our peers so at the end of the day
the goal of all these activities is to
twofold um to help startups validate to
in some cases pivot in other cases
expand your customer base and to help
corpetes learn about Technologies and
products that are coming to the market
um or speed up uh their internal or
trans um internal uh Innovation or
transformational processes and in some
cases even expand your portfolio of
products and uh um uh start uh new
business
lines um this slide features a small
sample of the success cases we at to
date that uh typically include proofs of
concept uh pilots and in some cases even
Acquisitions which is super exciting um
this is startup Exchange in a nutshell
if you'd like to learn more about it
happy to uh talk after the event and um
before passing the word to the
entrepreneurs I'd like to invite you to
some of our upcoming events we have
three coming up in no in October uh a
webinar uh a regional event in Paris
about Ai and our sustainability
conference um later in the month um at
the Marriott and then in November we are
hosting our uh annual research um and
development uh conference and um with
that it is my pleasure to kick off the
start of
presentations um which one will do a six
seven this time is 7 Minutes pitch and
uh later you can uh during lunch you can
meet them all