um okay so today uh despite my
admonition doesn't look like a very good
attendance so I'm going to give you all
the answers to the midterm just to
reward you for I'm I'm joking but uh I'm
glad you decided to come because it's a
fun lecture and it's very relevant to
what is going to be what we're going to
be learning really for the next few
lectures
which is thinking about models of
oligopoly once again an awesome
word which is really just a description
of what most markets in America are so
we've covered two extremes we've covered
one extreme for markets which is perfect
competition doesn't really exist we've
covered another extreme which is
Monopoly which is which does exist but
it's still fairly rare the more common
form of markets is what we call
oligopoly which is when there's a small
number of firms competing to provide the
good so it's more than one firm so it's
more than Monopoly but it's less than
free entry it's less than a large number
of firms driving profits to zero so
let's see about the prototypical example
of oligopolistic Industry the Auto
industry most cars in America are sold
by fewer than 20
companies but they're sold by well more
than than one so if you drive on the
road you see cars from you know
primarily 10 but maybe even up to 20
different car
companies so is that enough to drive us
the perfectly competitive outcome that
is those 10 to 20 car companies enough
to drive us to zero
profits probably not but is that enough
that each company can simply set its
price and pick its point on the demand
curve probably not either so we're
somewhere in between we're in an
oligopolistic market now an
oligopolistic Market firms can behave
two ways they can behave cooperatively
or non-cooperatively
okay when there's one firm there's no
issue just yourself when there's
thousands of firms you can't figure out
how to how to how to uh get together but
when you have a small number of firms
you can imagine behaving cooperatively
non-cooperatively cooperatively would be
to form a cartel so if you want to
cooperate you form what's called a
cartel which is a Cooperative
organization of otherwise competing
firms the classic example of this is
OPEC the organization of petroleum
exporting
countries this organization formed in
1970s of the Middle Eastern countries
that responsible for about two-thirds of
the world world's oil they got together
and said let's produce
cooperatively and we'll decide how much
to produce and what price to set as if
we were were sort of a collective
Monopoly so in other words the idea of
calization is you effectively turn
yourself into a shared Monopoly with all
the benefits we've talked about in terms
of profits and
things okay so basically the idea is
look what do monopolies do they don't
they get rid of competition they sort of
maximize profits given the elasticity
demand they face when you for a cartel
you essentially say look let's do that
let's get rid of competition let's just
create a as big a piie as possible we'll
figure out some way to split
it okay now of course the Other Extreme
is a
non-cooperative oligopolistic market
where firms don't get together and
compete where firms where firms I'm
sorry don't get together and agree um uh
on what to do and in fact that's more
realistic and we'll talk about reasons
why next lecture next lecture we'll talk
about how cartels work and why they
don't typically
last so today we'll focus on the more
realistic case of a nonco
Cooperative
oligopoly which is when there's a small
number of firms in an industry and they
can't get together and and cooperate
which makes sense I these are firms
which grew up hating each other sort of
makes sense it be hard to cooperate
we'll talk about next time why that
is so what do we
do in that case well in that case things
get
hard the reason we start with perfect
competition Monopoly is because they're
relatively easy to think about oligopoly
it gets super complicated and we have to
turn to a new tool the tool of gain
Theory
okay um basically the idea of game
theory is to think of these firms
interacting as if they're playing a
game think of there's there's n firms in
a market where n is
small they're they're sort of playing a
game against each
other and so there's two key pieces of
Game Theory to keep track of think about
playing a game what are sort of two
things you want to figure out the first
thing is your
strategy what is the right strategy to
win this
game the second point you want to figure
out is
equilibrium when is the game over when
does the game settle into an answer that
all parties agree on with Monopoly
there's a set of rules once everybody
else is bankrupt you win that's the
equilibrium okay so basically any game
has a strategy and an equilibrium
rule it turns
out defining equilibrium in a rule with
in a game with explicit rules is easy
defining in a game where firms are just
competing in this blood in a potentially
bloodthirsty manner is not so easy and
it turns out there is an enormous field
in economics all about how do you think
about equilibrium in game theoretic
markets how do you think about when
things finally settle down and end up
and the most famous of these ideas of
how to find equilibrium is what we call
the Nash equilibrium any you guys ever
see or read a beautiful
mind that movie a little bit raise your
hands yeah okay so a bunch of you saw it
so it's about John Nash fascinating
character um he was a mathematician
brilliant
mathematician uh who whose fundamental
insight and if you see the movie this is
so Illustrated well in a bar with the
group of men are trying to pick up a
group of women and again with this
fundamental Insight that competition can
be bad now if you think about economics
we've learned everything we learn about
competition is good competition is good
it delivers better outcomes for
consumers it reduces deadweight loss but
he he actually came up with a theory
that where actually in certain
situations competition can be bad and
cooperation can be better and that was
sort of his fundamental insight
okay and then he went insane
unfortunately as can sometimes happen
and the movie is sort of all about that
it's very interesting it's a very
interesting movie well acted interesting
story about this poor guy who uh had
these B insights and then and then
developed mental illness severe
schizophrenia um so what John Nash
defined is the Nash equilibrium and the
Nash equilibrium is defined as follows
precisely a Nash equilibrium is the
equilibrium where no player wants to
change their
strategy given all the other players
strategies so you're an equilibrium
where no player wants to change their
strategy given all the other player
strategies that is a Nash equilibrium
that is formally if you hold all other
players Behavior
constant I can't do any better when I've
reached that point I'm in equilibrium we
reach to a point where I can't do any
better holding everybody's strategies
constant than I'm an equilibrium and the
best example of this is example some of
you may have heard about and you've
certainly seen in movies the example the
prisoners dilemma okay the prisoners
dilemma is a famous movie device but
almost a f example which is two guys are
arrested for a crime it's not airtight
that they did it they think the two guys
did it but they really to really make it
airtight
they'd need them to admit it so let's
say in this example and we'll give you
examples like this and you'll need to
think out interpret them so the example
is two guys get arrested right now today
there is enough evidence to send each of
them to jail for one
year okay enough just one year but if
one guy squeals and says no the other
guy did it if he turned States evidence
whove learned a lot about this in the
FBF trial and the upcoming Trump's trial
okay the idea is if one person turn
States evidence or squeals then they get
zero they walk away and the other guy
gets five
years okay now if they both squeal they
both get five years okay so basic the
situation is if nothing happens they
each get one year if either tells on the
other person then the person they told
on gets five years so what the way we
analyze game theoretic situations like
this is we write down we call a payoff
Matrix so write down a payoff Matrix so
the payoff Matrix look as follow you got
prisoner
a on the Y AIS here and prisoner
B on the x- axis okay and you've got
four
situations okay in one case let's say
prisoner
a is
silent he doesn't talk
and prisoner B also stays silent they
don't talk then in that case a gets one
year and B gets one
year now let's say that prisoner a stays
silent but prisoner B talks prisoner B
squeals then prisoner a now gets five
years and prisoner b gets
zero over here we have what if prisoner
a talks well if prisoner a talks and
prisoner B remains silent then prisoner
a gets zero and prisoner b gets
five but if they both talk they both get
five okay questions about how I set up
that Matrix given the words given the
description of the problem you're going
need to be able to take these descript
set of matrices like this so any
questions about how I did that
okay now what we want to ask is what
should each player do and the the sort
of cheat in National equilibrium games
the first step is to say look the
easiest case would be if there is a
dominant
strategy if there's a dominant strategy
is there one strategy which no matter
what the other guy does you want to do
then that's the Nash equilibrium right
that's that's the outcome that you're
going to do if there a strategy that's
dominant that's the strategy you're
going to
play okay the best thing to do no matter
what the other person
does okay now if they could agree to
cooperate if the two of them got
together in a room beforehand and they
trusted each other they could Rec
cooperate then clearly what is the
dominant coop operative
strategy yeah they both stay silent they
both get a
year but let's say they can't do that
they can't get in room together they
never put in room together in the movies
right they keep them separate and
they're scummy criminals they don't
trust each other okay so basically what
happens now if you're prisoner a and
you're not sure what prisoner B is going
to
do what should you do if you think
prisoner B is going to stay
silent yeah
talk because your
payoff is better what should you do if
you think prisoner B is going to
talk yeah talk because your payoff if
you think prisoner B is going to talk
then you should
talk okay so I'm sorry I wrote I wrote
this uh did I do this right yep I did
this wrong that's what I did wrong it's
no better if they both talk I say they
both get three that makes more sense I
set the example up wrong if they both
talk they both get three that makes your
answer is still right but this makes it
non-binding that that involves
inequality this is this is non-binding
so clearly prisoner
a is better off talking no matter what
prisoner B is going to do what about
prisoner B what's their dominant
strategy yeah same thing it's a
symmetric problem these problems won't
always be symmetric but it's a hell of a
lot easier when they are so you only
have to solve for one person you assume
the other other person does the same
thing so prisoner B's dominant strategy
is to talk so we have a situation where
both dominant strategies align therefore
we have an
equilibrium and that equilibrium is what
it's they both
talk and they both get three
years here's what's fascinating they are
worse off than if they both stayed
silent competition has yielded a worse
outcome we haven't seen that before in
this class
competition in the sense of trying to do
what's best for you at the expense of
the other guy has yielded the worse
outcome than
cooperation that's what's incredibly
Innovative about that's what Nash Nash
even though being a mathematician won
the Nobel prize in economics in Game
Theory went from something which was
kind of relatively new when I was a grad
student in the late 80s to now being a
quarter of the
introductory uh training that graduate
students PhD students in economics get
game theory has become a dominant so to
speak uh element of all economics
training because it provides such a
valuable tool for thinking about this so
basically you end up with What's called
the prisoners
dilemma which is prisoners are each
better off by ratting on the other and
it ends up they both end up worse off
and this also shows us how to solve a
nash game a game with a Nash equilibrium
which is you look for each player's
dominant strategy
and you find the point where they
align the point where the two dominant
strategies align is by definition an as
equilibrium why because they're both
doing the best they can giveing the
other person now if the two dominant
strategies don't align there may not be
an
equilibrium you have situations where
A's dominant strategy different than B's
Domin strategy they don't align then you
might not get an equilibrium but in this
case they align and most cases will give
you they align so you get a Nash
equilibrium where they both
align okay
now this is all cute and stuff but like
this is a class about economics not
about
crime but it turns out the same logic
applies to playing economic games so
imagine let's take the market for soda
and imagine there's two big players
Pepsi and
Coke and let's imagine there's a $16
billion soda
Market let's further imagine that absent
any advertising they would split it that
with no advertising C and Pepsi would
each get 8 billion
out of the
market
but they can
advertise adverti advertising costs five
billion so if they advertise they only
take home three billion
net however if they advertise they drive
the other guy out of the
market so the choices don't advertise
and split the market advertise in which
case um if you um
in which case if you advertise and you
win the other guy's
gone okay and you get you get the whole
Market but if you don't advertise and
you don't win and the other guy
advertises you're gone so what that
payoff Matrix look like well let's write
that
down you've
got
Coke and
Pepsi Coke and Pepsi Coke can not
advertise or
advertise okay Pepsi cannot advertise or
advertise if Coke and Pepsi both don't
advertise they each get
eight if Coke doesn't advertise and
Pepsi does coke ends up with zero and
Pepsi ends up with 11 which is the 16 is
wrong in the notes by the way Andrew we
should fix this um which is the 16 uh
that they um the 16 that they got from
having the market minus the five they
spent in
advertising on the other if Koke
advertised and Pepsi doesn't then Koch
gets 11 and Pepsi gets
zero and if they both advertise Coke
gets three and Pepsi gets
three so once again the dominant
cooperative strategy is they both don't
advertise but the dominant
non-cooperative strategy in each case is
to advertise Koke is always better off
if it
advertises than if it doesn't Pepsi's
always better off it advertises than it
doesn't so they'll both advertise and
you'll end up with both parties being
worse off they just agreed not to
advertise this is not an irrelevant
example until about I don't know it's
got to be about 10 years ago hard liquor
you know whiskey vodka things like that
never adverti on
television now as a kid I thought that
was a law but it turns out it wasn't it
wasn't a law it was a Cooperative
agreement among the manufacturer of hard
liquor not to advertise on television
they literally had reached the
Cooperative equilibrium and then it
broke down and now you see the ads on TV
I don't know what be interesting I don't
know what caused the broke down actually
Andrew let's make a note I should do a
case study on should add that that'd be
good to add be be interesting to think
about what caused that but they used to
cooperate and they don't okay so B
basically this an example of how the
prisoner's dilemma can lead to a worse
outcome questions about
that okay this doesn't just
apply to Coke and Pepsi or prisoners
think about Andrew here let's say Andrew
is in a new relationship still try to
feel out the his partner okay and they
have a
fight and Andrew is thinking two things
can happen I can go apolog oliz and I
can go eat crow and say it's my fault
let's say they're both at fault Andrew
can say I can go eat crow and say it's
my fault but then if my partners say
it's their fault I'm GNA feel like
the partner's thinking the same
thing they' both be better off if they
just apologize because they're both at
fault but they both don't apologize
because they don't want to look like the
loser and they break
up okay prison is a lemon action in
personal
relationships okay basically it's hard
to form Cooperative relationships
and non-cooperative equilibria can lead
to bad
outcomes okay now this is the very very
tip of the incredibly exciting field of
Game Theory Game Theory is a wonderful
exciting field we have a great course
called
1412 which is Game Theory which takes
this little bit as its first lecture and
from there develops a whole semester of
Game Theory you might say well how you
do a whole semester well let me give you
one
example let me give you one example of
how you can solve
the prisoners dilemma without explicit
cooperation how do you solve pris
without explicit cooperation you can do
it through playing a repeated
game a repeated game so imagine the
following imagine Coke and Pepsi play
this game every year these is annual
numbers play this game every year
forever they play this game every year
forever okay now imagine Coke says the
following to Pepsi it's not it's not a
cooperation it's it's a threat coch says
to Pepsi I will not advertise as long as
you don't
advertise but the minute you advertise I
will advertise
forever so coke says to Pepsi I they
start with no advertising Koke says I
won't advertise you don't advertise but
the minute you advertise I'll advertise
forever now think about Pepsi's decision
if Pepsi advertises in Period
one in Period one they get the whole
Market because kooch is committed to not
advertise they get
11 they get
11 and then kooch says screw your
advertising forever they get three plus
three plus three plus dot do dot do
dot what if Pepsi doesn't
advertise then they get eight
forever you don't to be a math genius to
see this is a bigger
number so it changes Pepsi's dominant
strategy
Koch simply issuing that threat changes
the Domin strategy no cooperation here
simply a threat and yet it enforces the
Cooperative
equilibrium but that doesn't work unless
the game is
infinite imagine that we know 100 years
from now the US will ban soda and Coke
and Pepsi know that they know at some
point this game will end so do Market's
going to go
away what is Pepsi's optimal strategy in
the 99th
year yeah because last year it's the
last year Coke can't punish him it's
over but kooch knows that so what's
Coke's optimal strategy in the 998th
year advertise because I know Pepsi's
can advertise in the 99th year they
might as well get ahead of the game and
advertise 998th year you can work
backwards to see the game
collapses from year one no will
play because they know working backwards
that as soon as someone commits not to
advertise they're going to advertise and
then just going to advertise
forever so here's a solution that works
but only under particular conditions
which is an infinite repeated
game that's pretty
cool okay and that is once again the
kind of things you could think about
with the tools of Game Theory what 1412
does is show you how to mathematically
to prove these things how think about
all the cool games it depends on who has
what information who has what bargaining
strength there's all sorts of cool stuff
that comes into play here
yeah don't know it's not but you don't
know that
stop you know I I think I think that's
my I should have saved my whiskey
example for this which is
somehow the whiskey companies had
decided they were playing this repeated
equilibrium this this repeated game and
somehow it broke down now I don't know
what broke did they suddenly think G
people losing their taste for hard
liquor we better get you know get get it
while it's good I don't know it's a good
question but in reality sometimes it
works sometimes it doesn't and that's
what is exciting about game theory is to
think about deriving the conditions
under which it's likely to work and not
likely to work good question other
questions so that's game theory in a in
a big uh sort of in a in in in in a
nutshell okay what we're going to do now
is move from this vague concept of Game
Theory to a particular model a
particular game theoretic model and
that's the model we'll focus on in this
class as the model of non-cooperative
oligopoly but I'm going to tell you it's
one model of an enormous class of models
it's just a models particularly
convenient to work with and it gives the
intuition without the math being too
hard okay so we're going to move to one
particular model but recognize the model
we're using is one of a class of models
one could use to model non Cooperative
oligopolistic equilibria that may be the
most complicated three words I'll use
together in this class non-cooperative
oligopolistic equilibria okay so we're
going to talk
about the Corno
model of non-cooperative equilibria this
is basically a version of the Nash
model okay so what we're going to do is
we're going to take the general Nash
model and we're going to enrich it
saying beyond having two choices you
have a whole schedule of choices your
choice isn't just a versus B but there's
a large set of choices you can make
which is true in economic context
usually not a versus B there's how much
you're going to advertise Etc there's
whole set of choices you can make and
but we're still going to consider two
firms playing because it gets really
messy Beyond two firms although once
they get 142 I'll teach you how to
handle that so let's imagine the world
of
flights from New York to
Chicago okay and let's imagine due to
the hub and spoke problem we discussed
last time there's only two firms that
fly New York to Chicago United and
American obviously there's more than
that but just to make this example easy
imagine only two firms that fly to these
two firms do dominate the market to
Chicago 90% of flight to Chicago one or
the other of those so let's say that
that these two firms the only firms in
the
market and now we want to ask how does
each firm KN the other firms out there
how does each firm decide on what price
to set and how many flights to run to do
that we are going to set up the Coro
model and the Coro model is going to say
we're going to look for the Nash
equilibrium but in terms of set of
phrasing in a vague term like dominant
strategy will phrase the Nash
equilibrium as follows this is a long
sentence so bear with me the keno
equilibrium is the set of
quantities for each firm so such that
holding other firms quantities
constant no firm can obtain a higher a
higher profit by deviating say it again
the set of quantities for each firm such
that holding every other firm's quantity
constant no firm can raise their profits
by
deviating so it's a schedule a set of
quantities a schedule of quantities that
sort of maps out your dominant strategy
it's not like there's one dominant
strategy there a dominant schedule of
strategies to see that let's go to
figure 131 this is an example of the
kind of figure you're going to become
familiar with over the next few
lectures figure 131 shows the market for
American Airlines as if it was a
monopoly imagine American downside a
monopoly and imagine we're going to
write down arbitrarily that the demand
curve for flights to Chicago
is 339 minus Q where Q is the total
number of flights that's the demand
curve for flights to Chicago just arbitr
written
down and let's say further that
arbitrarily that marginal cost equals
$147 so it's 339 minus Q's demand
marginal cost
147 so what would a monopolis do well
good practice for yall for tomorrow
night what would a monopolis do
monopolis would set marginal revenue to
marginal cost well what's revenue
revenue is
339 Q - Q ^2 what's marginal revenue 339
minus 2 Q so monopolis sets marginal
revenue 339 - 2q equal to marginal cost
which is
147 and you get that the alha Monopoly
quantity
qm is 90 is
um qm is 96
flights and the optimal price is
$243 we get the optimal quantity by
solving this equation get the opal chice
by plugging that back in the demand
equation so if this is a monopoly this
is what they're going to do note of
course that price is well above marginal
cost because it's a monopoly there's a
markup okay so that's what they would
and we could see that in figure 131 by
drawing the monopolis problem you see
the marginal cost is at
147 you see the the main curve is the
Blue
Line the marginal revenue curve is the
red downward sloping line the maroon
line the darker red line we find the
point where marginal revenue intersects
marginal cost which is at 96 flights
96,000
whatever and then to find the price we
read it off the demand curve which is
the 96 flights the price is 243 and
that's the Monopoly
outcome okay questions about
that now imagine and this is a weird
weird case but just imagine for a minute
somehow through the indust through
industrial Espionage America knew that
United imagine how United is in the
market it's no longer Monopoly and
imagine americ knows United's going to
fly 64
flights 64,000 is Thousands but doesn't
matter Dr the unit I don't know somehow
it knows they're going to do
64 well what should American do given
the knowledge that United's can do 64
flights well what it should do is it
should compute its residual
demand what's its residual demand it's
the demand that's left over after United
does the 64 flights so what's its
residual demand well it's its residual
demand is 339
minus what it's going to fly now it's
little Q because there's two firms in
the
market minus the 64 flights that
America's going to
provide so its residual demand is
275 minus Q
Suba Q sub I'm sorry Q sub two yeah q75
minus Q Suba that's its residual demand
well arm with that residual demand we
can go back and redo the Monopoly
example so look at figure
132 americ is originally the outer Blue
Line D the fact that United is flying 64
flights shifts it to the inner demand
curve the residual demand curve D
Prime but from there the magic is the
same we compute marginal revenue which
is Mr Prime we find where marginal
revenue equals marginal
cost okay so what what's marginal
revenue marginal revenue here is going
to be 275 minus 2 QA that's the marginal
revenue I just multiplied that by q and
then took the
derivative marginal cost is
147 so the new optimal Q subet is
instead of 96 they're going to fly 64
flights so the new optimal Q sub a
remember now Q sub is the old big Q
because there's now two firms not one
firm the new optimal Q sub is 64 flights
and the optimal price is
211 the price has come
down
why because now part of the Market's
been taken so if they want to sell at
this Market they've got to have a lower
price so you get the new equilibrium
which is where the maroon line the MRP
Prime hits the red line the
MC that's a 64 flights and a price you
read off the man curve of
21 questions about
that
yeah no it the question is doesn't
matter what price they're setting
actually it doesn't because all you
because your curve here is just depend
on how many flights they're going to
sell now in reality it would but in
practice it doesn't because we're
assuming that this we're basically as
long long as we know the other firm's
conditions in particular if we know
their marginal costs and things we're
good here we are going to assume that
the marginal cost of American equals the
marginal cost of United and that makes
the problem easier in
reality you would you know in in reality
it'd be more complicated but as long as
we assume the marginal cost the same I
don't need to know what they're going to
set the price at I know what they're
going to set the price at because
they're like me it makes the problem
symmetric the marginal costs are
different it's not symmetric it's more
complicated okay good question
okay so basically in
general in general of course American
doesn't know how many flights United is
going to fly so what American does is it
asks for every quantity that United
might fly how many do I want to fly it
creates what we call its best response
curve and that you can see as the Blue
Line in figure
133 figure 133 is the best response
curve we know two points on this curve
we know if you so what is this what let
me back up what is this graph this graph
has American this isn't price this isn't
demand graph anymore this has the
American quantity on the x axis and the
United quantity on the y- axis so we're
no longer doing a demand curve this is
now a best response
curve we know already I've already told
you two points on this Blue Line I've
told you that if United flies zero
America flies 96 that's the x intercept
of the Blue
Line I've also told you that if United
flies 64 American flyes 64 that's the
6464 Point all this line is technically
he going through this exercise over and
over again for every possible qu
quantity United could
fly so this this exercise saying for
every possible Quant United could fly
what is my best response in other words
if
United is going to fly
192 passengers in a quarter I should fly
none now this problem is
symmetric so United's best response
curve is just the flip of American's
best response curve they have the same
cost structure marginal cost is the same
and they face the same market conditions
they're in the same demand market so
it's a symmetric problem
so United's best response curve is the
flip if American flies
nothing United should fly 96 which is
the Y intercept of the red
line if American flies 64 United should
fly 64 and if America flies 192 United
stat should fly
nothing these are the graphical
illustration of each firm's dominant
strategy
their cor no strategy remember is asking
what's the best thing I want to do given
what the other person's doing well I
told you what the person's doing so the
dominant strategy for American is to
plug in every possible thing United
could
do and then ask what's the best thing
for me to
do United does the same thing they plug
in every possible thing American could
do and ask what's the best thing for me
to do if those two curves intersect
we have
equilibrium the Koo equilibrium here is
at the point
6464 why because that is the one
point where given what United's doing
American doesn't want to change its
strategy and given what Americans doing
United doesn't want to change his
strategy
yeah what's that what
there's uh once again that's why you
take 1412 there's all sorts of fun
things what if there's two intersections
what if there's no inter intersection
all sorts of fun examples take 1412
we'll go through all of them we only
have a couple lectures for Game Theory
here so I can't go through all those but
it gets complicated let me just say that
you basically it's called a multiple
equilibria and it basically then where
you start determines where you finish in
this model doesn't matter where you
start there's one equilibria that's
robust okay but um uh in a multiple
equilibria uh where you start could
could determine where you finish so in
my example with Andrew okay in a single
equilibrium model it doesn't matter sort
of who started the fight okay but the
multile model you might have very
different outcomes based on who started
the
fight okay so basically that
is the
intersection okay and you can't be
here's the key
Point American can't be can't say look
gee but my profit I I I I liked it much
better when I was doing this like I had
96 lights at a higher price
okay so I like that much better why
can't I just do that well they can't
because American because America won't
let them or americ can't because United
won't let them they have to account for
the other firm's response and that's
what's cool about oligopoly that's why
the game theory because you have to
account for the other firm's response
okay that's the graphics let's go
through the math okay let's do the Coro
math to show you how this works
mathematically
yeah
begin well that that's a great great
question you're asking about sort of
market dynamics we're calling this sort
of a steady state equilibrium think of
this as short run versus long run in the
short run probably not right in the
short run you'll buy a certain am planes
they'll buy certain planes you'll you'll
fck around for a while and then you'll
say ah this is the point at which in the
long run things are stable so let's kind
of think of this more sort of a long run
versus a short run
okay other questions good question other
questions okay so basically let's look
at the math of the chono
equilibrium okay
so the first thing we do we don't do
this whatever the hell that
is the first thing we do is we solve for
each firm's residual demand curve and
it's a symmetric problem I could solve
this for one
firm and I know what I'll get for the
other firm I have to solve for one firm
so what is American's residual demand
curve well it's
339 minus QA minus qu I plugged in 64
before because I had some industrial
Espionage it was told me 64 but in
general I don't know what United's going
to do so I just put in this amount
qu
okay now what is revenue then revenue is
339 QA this is American's calculation of
its
Revenue minus QA 2 minus qu
QA what is marginal re Revenue well I
differentiate with respect to QA this is
American's decision so what it's his
marginal revenue it's
339 minus 2 QA minus
qu so now I've got a a new term in my
marginal revenue equation I didn't have
before in other examples the other
firm's quantity enters into my marginal
revenue so we set this equal to marginal
cost which is 147
once again symmetrically I said marginal
cost 147 for
everybody set that equal the marginal
cost
okay by the way let me go back one
second go back to the figure go back to
figure 131 and 132 one thing that's
implicit I didn't say is an example
average cost also equals marginal cost
for the relevant range right because
marginal cost is flat so the relevant
range we're examining here average cost
equals marginal cost it' be marginal
cost could be the same and average cost
could be structure be different and then
it get complicated again so really what
assuming is basically cost structure is
the same across the companies at least a
relevant range okay so you set that
equal to marginal cost you solve and you
get you solve that and you get the
QA equal 96 minus 12
qu okay so now we don't get a
deterministic answer we get that what I
should fly is 96 -2 qu guess what that's
the Blue Line in figure
133 check it out it's 96 minus 1 12
qu well it turns out the problem
symmetric so United has the same best
response
function I could do the same math for
United and i' get the qu equal 96 - 12
QA
qu = 96 - 12 QA because it's symmetric
so guess what I have two equations and
two unknowns I have two best response
functions intersecting or maybe not two
equations two unknowns so I can solve
this these two equations in two
unknowns and I can get that QA equals 64
and by
symmetry qu equal 64
so that is how I just mathematically
solved for that intersection now once
again you might solve this if find no
intersection two equations two unknowns
you might get no rational answer and
that would mean the market would just
collapse okay or you get multiple
answers and that's more
complicated but generally you get one
answer in this class at
least okay and that with equilibrium
yeah
great question does anyone know great
question because what's big Q here big Q
now in the market is 128 and what's the
price well we know the demand curve the
demand curve hasn't changed demand curve
is 339 minus Q it's one market demand
curve so the new price is uh 339 minus
128 so 211
okay but Q is 128 whereas when just
America is 96 great question
why
yeah like firm that controls everything
PR PR well they're they're in between
price takers and price makers but
effectively the way we model it they're
price takers but the intuition is when
I'm
monopolist I am maximizing the profits
for me
finding out what Max has my profits
which is a high price and a low quantity
once I'm sharing the market think about
the Monopoly poison effect this is a
great hint for what we'll cover next
time think about what happens the
Monopoly poisoning effect if I sell more
in the market who bears that poisoning
effect both of us because once Q goes up
once big Q goes up the price Falls we
both suffer from lower fall so it some
says I'm offloading half of the
poisoning effect when I'm monopolist
every additional un price I want to
sell low is my profit when I'm in this
larger group there's sort of a sharing
of the poisoning effect so each firm so
you end up selling more what we'll show
next time is why ex exactly this
intuition will be clearer next time
leads to cartels not to be
functional and it's why we'll show next
time the limit of oligopoly is perfect
competition okay but the bottom line is
when you get when you have a Coro
equilibrium you end up with an answer
that is not perfect competition remember
what would perfect competition say the
quantity would be can anyone tell me
what would the quantity be under perfect
competition what would big Q be in this
market with perfect
competition it involves one one equation
solving one equation
yeah it'd be n and how'd you get that
uh no perfect competition perfect that's
exactly this question here if there's
perfect competition what would yeah in
the
back what 64 how'd you get
that well well okay that's one way to do
it what's another way to do it well if
it's perfect competition what do we know
come on guys got ready for tomorrow
night what's the profit maximizing
condition perfect competition price
equals what marginal cost so we just say
well look you want to competition price
equals marginal cost so what's the price
what's marginal cost 147 so you know
price equals 147 and then you simply
know that demand that the quantity is
339 minus
147 the quanti is going to be 3 339
minus 147 which is going to be uh 192
right is that right uh
no uh no I got this wrong 33 9 - 147
that's a hard math
340 340 so
200 200 yeah 192 right yeah 192 I don't
have I'm really insecure about my math
skills okay so 192
192 is much bigger than Monopoly which
was 96 it's also bigger than what we got
in the oligopoly
case so what we see is oligopoly leads
us to be in between Monopoly and perfect
competition and we'll come back next
time review that and tell you why that
is show you why that is all right okay
let's stop there good luck tomorrow
night I'll see yall bright and early on
Wednesday and we'll continue this
discussion