Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
MPG primer. You probably missed us over
the last two weeks. Um we're back. Um we
have Kirk Smith who is thankfully
presenting online. He's saving us all
from some flu germs. So thank you Kirk
for for doing this remotely.
Um let's see. Kirk graduated from
Virginia Tech in 2015 with a bachelor of
science in mechanical engineering. And
then after working as a mechanical
engineer for several years, he pursued
graduate studies at the University of
Michigan, go blue, where he received a
master's of science in medical
engineering in 2019. In 2021, Kirk
joined Dr. Udler's lab, um, where he
focuses on using genetic clustering to
study complex genetics diseases. Um, I
just talked to him and he actually ran
this on one of uh, my favorite
phenotypes, nefertic syndrome and this
is what he's going to talk about today.
Um, if you have questions, he obviously
might not see you. Um, so just come up
to these microphones and cut in at the
appropriate time or raise your hand and
I can bring you a microphone. Um, but
yeah, let's have some conversations and
thank you Kirk. Thank you for the intro
and um, thanks everyone for joining and
uh, yeah, for for those in person.
Sorry, sorry I couldn't be there. Um, as
was mentioned, I'm recovering from being
a little sick all week. So, uh, thought
I'd be cautious and present virtually.
Um, so yeah, uh, today I'll be talking
to you about our lab's research
regarding the clustering of genetic
lossi to study complex
diseases. Um, in today's presentation,
I'll start with our motivation for
performing soft clustering analysis on
genetic lossi. I'll then describe the
actual soft clustering method that we're
using which is called basian non-gative
matrix factorization or BNMF and we'll
go over some of its primary benefits. Um
and then lastly I'll go through a number
of potential applications and downstream
analyses that can be done with these
clusters. And um before I move on I just
wanted to mention that I'll be
referencing type 2 diabetes a lot in
these slides since that's the primary
focus of our lab's research. Um,
however, pretty much everything that
we're going over today is applicable to
any complex disease. Um, so just keep
that in
mind. All right. So, when most people
think of genetic diseases, they think of
a monogenic disease such as cystic
fibrosis where a single dysfunctional
gene is the primary issue. And we can
picture this as a single pipe rupture
which produces a massive but uniform
puddle. And then by contrast, complex
diseases such as type two diabetes arise
from dozens or hundreds of variants in
different biological pathways. So each
variant is only a small leak on its own,
but together they pull into a shared
disease risk. And because these leaks
are coming from various different piping
systems, our puddle can be very
heterogeneous.
And so this metaphor demonstrates why
monogenic diseases are relatively
speaking um easier to diagnose and find
drug targets for and while complex
genetic diseases can be much more
difficult in that same
regard. So this same concept was
captured in the pallet model proposed by
Mark McCarthy in 2017 to illustrate T2-D
heterogeneity. Um on the far left we
have several pathways associated with
type two diabetes such as beta cell
function uh insulin action and atapose
distribution. Then to the right of that
we have patients A through D which each
have a varying degree of disregulation
in these pathways. The amount each
pathway is contributing to their overall
disease risk will determine their final
location on the pallet or their final
color shade. So this also means that
each patient might show different
symptoms in the clinical setting or
respond better to certain
medications. So until we start to
untangle this heterogeneity, it'll be
very difficult to make strides in
personalized medicine. So the question
is how do we how do we begin to do
that? There are a number of different
approaches that um one can use for
studying disease heterogeneity, but each
has its own challenges. The most
straightforward method might be to
perform phenotypic clustering where
patients are grouped together based on
the traits they have in common such as
BMI or fasting glucose. The issue here
is that this clustering is looking at a
single snapshot in time. A patient's
phenotype will vary depending on where
they are in disease pro disease
progression or treatment. So this means
that a patient might change clusters
after a few weeks on medication or had
they come into the clinic at a different
time point, they could have been grouped
into a completely different
cluster. Additionally, with this
approach, we don't learn much about the
disease-causing
mechanisms. So that brings us to
genetics, which is a much more constant
data type, and we can assume it has a
one-way causality with the disease.
Now the first step in connecting
genetics to disease is often doing
variant discovery using genomewide
association studies or G-W was. G-W was
involve looking at the genetic data of
thousands of people and finding variants
associated with your phenotype of
interest. Going back to our piping
metaphor, a G-W was can help us locate
all of those tiny leaks, but it doesn't
tell us how they're contributing to the
disease risk. For one thing, the
majority of variants are found in
non-coding regions. So we may not even
know what gene a variant is affecting.
This means that after conducting a G-W
was, we still need to figure out which
genetic loi are acting together in
distinct mechanistic
modules. So to do this, our lab's
approach is to leverage genetic genetics
informed by physiology. So rather than
clustering patients based on their
genetics, we cluster the snips
themselves based on their trait
signatures. This starts by extracting
the T2D associated variants from one or
more G-W was ideally using the largest
publicly available studies. Next, we
look up those snips in G-W was of key
metabolic traits such as BMI, glycemic
measures, lipids, etc. to get their
zcores. Finally, we align everything to
the T2-D riskinccreasing alals and put
it all together in this variant by trait
matrix. This matrix encapsulates encap
encapsulates how each genetic variant
affects each trait. And at this point,
it's ready to be thrown into some type
of clustering algorithm. Um, what you're
seeing here on this slide is essentially
a very high-level overview of our entire
workflow. Um, and it shows you how we go
from variants associated to the disease
of interest to looking at the traits
that they those variants are associated
with to putting that information into a
clustering
algorithm. So now the the next question
is what clustering approach do we use?
There are a ton of different clustering
algorithms out there which can generally
be categorized as either hard or soft
clustering. The hard clustering label
simply means that each data point is
assigned to a single cluster. Some uh
common examples of this are K means and
hierarchical
clustering. Determining the true number
of clusters which we call K can be very
difficult with some of these uh hard
clustering techniques. There are many
different um cluster quality metrics
that can be looked at to pick the
optimal K. Um but anyone who has uh done
clustering before knows that often these
metrics will point to different values
and the user end is uh ends up being
required to make some type of gut
decision on on what metric to use and
what final K value to
use. So in addition to that um after the
clustering is done the user is also
required to um determine which traits
are driving each cluster. Um so this
could uh involve doing some type of post
hawk um trait association testing or um
some other type of analysis. But um
essentially the takeaway is that what
your clusters are forming around isn't
um apparent right away when you use most
of these hard clustering
techniques. Soft clustering on the other
hand uses weighted assignments. This
means that variants can belong to
multiple clusters which is more in line
with how biological systems overlap. Um
this is demonstrated in the the panel on
the right here by these um by the stars
which you can see are in the kind of
overlapping regions of these different
clusters. Um clearly these data points
are kind of in between the clusters. So
it's it's can be expected and that these
data points are kind of contributing to
multiple signals.
So um from here on out I'll be focusing
on our specific soft clustering method
which is called basian non- negative
matrix factorization or
B&MF. Now with BNMF the optimal clusters
are um given as an output of the model.
So that takes away any or most of the
user bias in terms of picking the
optimal K and then in addition to that
we get the trait loadings for each
cluster as an output of the model. So
that gives us immediate insight into
what is driving each
cluster. All right. So um I'll now give
a a relatively quick overview on how
B&MF actually works and I'll mention a
few more specific um benefits of this
method. So um to start the user does
have to input a maximum number of
clusters to consider which we'll call
KAX. Um, so typically this would just be
a number that would be way above the
number of clusters you expect. So you
would just kind of pick a safe K value.
Um, so perhaps you think there might be
10 clusters in your data, you could
input a K max of 20. Um, and then the
BMF algorithm will consider anything
below
20. So um, we then initialize two random
matrices which are called W and H. W
will contain the variant weights. So its
dimensions are the number of snips by K
max and H will contain the TRO the trait
loadings. Its dimensions are actually K
max by the number of traits times two.
Now this is because of the non- negative
requirement of BMF. We're actually
forced to split each trait into a
positive and negative column and then
multiply the negative column by minus
one. So you can see this reflected in
the um the H matrix on the right. how
each trait now has a a positive and
negative such as BMI plus and BMI
negative. So once we have these random
matrices W and H, we begin alternating
fitting and pruning. The fitting
involves minimizing the error between
our original matrix X and the matrix
product of W * H. There's also a comp
complexity penalty involved to avoid
overfitting.
Now the pruning is a very important part
because it shrinks clusters that are not
contributing to the approximate
approximation of X. Um I've tried to
highlight that in this example with the
color coding. Um so you can see how the
first column of W is tied to the first
row of H and so on. So in this example
we started with a K max of five. Um
however all the elements of the fifth
cluster were pruned to zero. So we ended
up with just four clusters. So this is
kind of a a
um simple example to show how we go from
kmax to the optimal number of clusters.
Um the BMF pruning essentially gets rid
of all of the unimportant factors. Um so
we end up with the true number of
clusters in our data set rather than the
k that we started
at. Now this um shrinkage is encouraged
by the gamma prior and it also makes our
um final weights quite sparse. So um in
an actual clustering run you would see a
lot of zeros or very very small weights
in the final um matrices that you get.
And so this makes interpretation much
easier because you don't have to look at
um weights uh you know weights for
hundreds of variants and traits for each
cluster.
So, how do we define the clusters once
we get these final um W and H matrices
from B&MF? Yep. Oh, sorry, I was muted.
Can I ask a quick question? Is there an
upper bound on the number of traits you
could put in? Because I would imagine
with type two diabetes, you have some
ideas of where to look, but if you're
unsure what's driving your phenotype,
you might want to include a lot more GWS
traits. And I don't know if there's an
upper bound to the number that you could
put in.
Yeah. Um, okay. So, I have a uh in two
slides I'll go over that. Oh, great. I
think it's set up. Yes. Uh, maybe three
slides, two or three slides. Um, I'll
cover that. Um, so I'll hold off on
answering till then. Um, okay. So, um,
in terms of defining the final clusters,
um, one approach would be to consider
all snips and weights with a non zero
weight or sorry, all snips and traits
with a non-zero weight. Um there's
nothing wrong with that approach.
However, our lab's approach has been to
focus more on the components that are
most heavily driving each cluster. So to
do this, we compute a cluster specific
um or sorry, we compute a weight
threshold to maximize a signal to noise
ratio. So from there, all the snips and
traits with weights above that cutoff
are assigned to a cluster. Um I've
demonstrated that here by highlighting
in yellow the variance in traits that
are above um the cutoff in each cluster
for this
example. So then um if we wanted to zoom
in on cluster one for example um we
would see that uh snips one through four
are above the cutoff. So those are
included in the cluster. And then we can
see right away that um we also have
increased BMI and glucose in this
cluster and decreased height. So um you
can see right away how having these
trait loadings makes it super easy to
begin interpreting these clusters
immediately rather than having to do
some post hawk
testing. Um and then for anyone uh that
ends up reading any of our um papers um
you might see uh you'll see these circle
plots which are sometimes we get asked
about but these are just essentially
showing the same information as the bar
plots to the left. um just showing the
weights um the weights of the variance
and traits that are driving each
cluster. So, same information that I
just described here just in a kind of
nicer
format. So, um a few more quick notes on
BNMF. Um certain inputs and traits might
not end up in any cluster which you
might have noticed on the last slide. Um
so this will depend on several things
such as the B&MF pruning or whatever
approach you take for the weight cutoff.
Um with our method we often see around
50% of snips contributing to one or more
clusters. And in line with that same
idea um one kind of nice benefit of this
method is we're not forcing snips into
clusters that they don't belong. So say
there's a snip associated with your
disease that doesn't end up in any of
the clusters. um this, you know, maybe
is disappointing at first, but um in
reality it could be very informative
because it tells you that that snip is
not acting through a mechanism that's
captured by the traits you're using. So
looking at this example in um sub panel
2, um if we were using a method like K
means, we essentially would have had to
stretch um some of these clusters to
encapsulate these outlier data points.
So um not only would we kind of
be maybe wrongly classifying these data
those data points but we um could be
skewing the cluster centroidids which
are later used for some other um
downstream
analyses. And then um lastly it's
important to remember that your results
will depend on the quality and quantity
of your genetic inputs. So the more
powerful G-W was that you have means the
more snips you have as inputs and also
the more reliable your variant trait
associations will be. And then
additionally the number of traits you
input will have a big impact on the
number of clusters that you get.
However, a big caveat there is that it's
not necessarily the number of traits but
the number of relevant traits.
So um now getting kind of into that uh
trait selection question um our our
group's approach has been to take a
datadriven um approach for deciding on
what um traits to include. And this is
probably actually the most common
question that we get for running um B&MF
is how do we go about um deciding on
what traits to include in this variant
trait matrix. So um there there is no
correct answer for for this. Um some
people prefer to handp pick traits but
our method has been to include as many
trait G-W was as feasible. And um the
thing to keep in mind there is that that
involves um downloading and formatting
all these trait G-W was uh which is
actually probably the most time
consuming part of this entire workflow.
Um, and also the more traits that you
include in the pipeline, the longer it's
going to take to run. Um, so it's just
something to keep in mind. It's, you
know, a limitation that can be overcome,
but it's um, to give you an idea, in our
most recent paper, I think we included
about 160 traits um, initially and then
um, the final clust matrix ended up at
around 110 traits. Um and then so uh
this slide kind of goes over how we get
from that 160 to that
110. So once the initial variant trait
matrix is formed, we've we have our T2D
snips on the Y-axis and we've pulled all
the Zcores for these initial traits that
are on the X-axis. Um now we start
pruning the traits. So the first thing
we do is we remove traits that have low
sample sizes. Um this sounds like
something that could be done prior to
running the pipeline. How however often
GWA studies will report a maximum N. So
um they might say that um they took the
uh genetic data for up to 15,000 people.
However, once you start um actually
pulling um snips and data from the
summary statistics file, you might find
that a lot of the variants that you're
interested in, they actually only
measured in a few hundred. Um, and we
typically look for a median sample size
of at least 10,000. Um, so sometimes we
do lose traits due to a lot of the snips
um, not having enough sample
size. Um, so next we remove traits
without at least one bonfrron
significant snip. This is probably the
most important filter because this is
kind of what allows us to throw traits
into the pipeline that maybe we suspect
are associated with our disease, but we
aren't entirely sure. And then if it
turns out that none of our T2D snips are
associated with that trait, um we simply
remove the trait and therefore we're not
add any adding any unnecessary noise to
the
clustering. And then finally, if we have
two traits that are highly correlated,
we just keep the one with the strongest
signal. This is to make sure that the
traits are representing um independent
signals when the clustering is done. Um,
and kind of an a common example for this
is we often will include um two versions
of a trait, one adjusted for BM BMI and
one unadjusted, and then we can let the
pipeline figure out which one um to
keep. Um so hopefully that answers the
question about um kind of picking traits
to
include. Um now as I mentioned
um this whole process can be uh very um
there's a lot of steps to it from
formatting the G-W was pulling the
summary statistics and everything. Um
and for the original paper that Dr.
Udler published on this topic in 2018
um all of this summary statistics
wrangling had to be done by hand um
which I I can't imagine. Um fortunately
uh right before I joined the lab in 2021
a few members of our team created this
high throughput R pipeline which
automates almost the entire process. Um
essentially the only requirement from
the user is a list of file paths for the
input G-W was. Um so at this point
pretty much the main work for someone
that wanted to start a new project would
be to figure out what traits they want
to include. Um, and if we don't have
those trait G-W was already available
somewhere on our server, um, they would
have to download and, um, do some
formatting to the summary statistics
files. Um, and then they input those
paths to the pipeline and pretty much
everything else runs on its
own. So this means that we can now apply
our method very efficiently to any
complex disease of interest. Um, as you
can see in this list, we've already
published several papers on diseases and
traits outside of type two diabetes, and
we have several more in the
works. All right. So, um, I'll now get
into applications of the genetic
clusters. So, probably the most useful
downstream analysis we can do with these
clusters is generating cluster specific
partition polygenic risk scores or
cluster PPS. The steps for doing this
are very similar to what would be done
for a full disease risk score such as
the a T2D PRS. As we discussed earlier,
we start by defining each cluster's
variant set shown here with the blue
bars for cluster one. So this includes
any snip that was above the weight cut
off um for that
cluster for a given patient. We then
pull their genotype dosages at those
snips. uh these are shown in the blue
circles and so these will be either a
zero, one or two depending how many
alals that patient has for the given
snip. We then compute the dot product to
get a partition PS for the cluster. This
is repeated for each cluster to build a
PPS profile for that
patient. We can then determine each
patient's dominant genetic pathways and
compare PPS profiles across patients. So
as you can see um looking at this
example of patient one we can see that
much more of their T2D risk is coming
from cluster one than from cluster 12.
Um and this is tied to the um their alil
dosages for the um snips in each of
those
clusters. Sorry.
Um all right. So um once we have a
cluster PPS um generated for a cohort we
want to see how those clusters are
associated with various
phenotypes. So clinical data can be or
is typically very noisy. So these
patterns are often not visible at the
individual level or from a simple
correlation test. However, once we
employ more powerful regression models
and account for covariants such as age,
sex, and race, we start seeing some
really nice signals for these clusters.
In cases where we are um testing traits
that we used in the clustering, we
typically think of these as validation
tests as the clusters. So for example um
confirm as you can see here in the kind
of the top plot um confirming that the
obesity cluster has a strong association
with
BMI. Now when it's a new continuous
trait um we consider an exploratory
test.
Now we can of course also do the same
analysis with discrete outcomes such as
shown in um figure two. So we can look
at how clusters are um cluster PPS are
associated with um other diseases such
as CAD or CKD. Um and in the same manner
we can account for things such as um
age, sex, and race so that we're only
looking at the effect of the cluster on
that outcome.
Um, and then while I won't go into
detail on this today, I wanted to note
that we're also able to generate cluster
PPS at the G-W was level. Um, and this
is a really can be a really helpful
analysis because that means we can run
this for traits that aren't available at
the indivi individual level or perhaps
if um we want to take advantage of a
larger sample size that a G-W was might
have over um an individual level cohort
data set.
So it's also of interest to determine um
which tissues and cell types of clusters
are active in. To do this um in our uh
recent paper published in 2024, we
created credible sets for the variants
in our clusters and we then over
overlapped the credible set variants
with cell type and tissue type genomic
annotations. Um this was done in these
uh two epigenomic data sets catlas and
road map. And then finally we used uh
permutation testing to determine the
cumulative post posterior probability
for each annotation. Um the the results
you see on the right um show the
significant um tissues and cell types
for each cluster. And um we saw some
really cool results here that supported
our interpretation of these clusters
such as the beta cell clusters being
enriched for pancreatic eyelet
annotations and the liver lipid cluster
for hpatoblast
annotations. So um this is kind of
confirming that these genetic clusters
are capturing variants with distinct
effects in specific tissue and cell
types.
Now, in addition to studying how the
clusters behave across tissues, we can
also look at how they differ across
populations. Um, in these figures from
our 2024 paper on the left, we see the
proportion of total T2T risk coming from
each cluster broken down by population.
For example, um we see in East Asians in
blue, the two lipidrophy clusters
account for a notably large larger
fraction of total PPS than Europeans or
Africans. Um now just a quick note,
you'll you'll notice that um for each of
these clusters, the kind of maximum
value is um very different um across
each cluster. And that's based off of
the total um sum of weights for each
cluster. And so for this analysis um I
would it's important to note that we're
not comparing um risk across clusters so
much as we are looking at um populations
within a cluster. if if you wanted to
somehow try to look at um the risk
coming from each cluster, you would have
to probably normalize
um normalize the weights or the the PPS
across clusters before doing that type
of analysis. So um kind of the takeaway
here is that we're looking at population
differences within a cluster.
So um kind of going back to this
difference that we see in um in the East
Asian population in the lipid clusters.
Um we um in figure two we modeled T2D
risk versus BMI um and plotted these as
curves for each ancestry group and we
adjusted for age, sex and PCs. So you
can see that the Europeans in orange
have a TTD risk of about um 9% at a BMI
of 30, which is kind of the standard um
threshold for obesity, while East Asians
have the same risk at a BMI of only
24. Next, we adjusted these models for
the lipid 1 and 2 PPS and we saw that
this difference in risk decreased by
about 67%.
So um this is essentially quantif
quantifying how the genetic differences
in this these atapost dysfunction
pathways um are explaining part of the
well-known lower BMI threshold for T2D
in East Asians. Um, so this was actually
probably the coolest result from our
2024 paper. Um, since this
um this tendency for East Asians to
develop TTD at lower BMI has kind of is
a well-known phenomena, but it hasn't
been
um uh studied to a large degree or
figured out. So um the fact that these
clusters are capturing this difference
um was a really interesting finding.
Um finally I wanted to highlight some um
really exciting work from Dr. Molina um
Clausnisser's lab. Um so from
subcutaneous and visceral fat biopsies
um Dr. Clauser's team derived meenymal
stem cells. The cells were
differentiated over 14 days into mature
adiposytes with imaging and molecular
profiling at days 03 8 and 14.
Now um when they stratified by total
T2DPRS there was really no difference in
lipid accumulation or mitochondrial
markers. However once they stratified by
high versus low lipidary PPS there was a
huge signal in the subcutaneous day 14
adiposytes. This included differences in
um lipid droplet size and mitochondria
activity. Um so this analysis was really
cool in that it demonstrated how these
genetic clusters are actually capturing
um functional differences in cellular
biology. Um now before wrapping up I
wanted to mention that these genetic
clusters are constantly evolving as G-W
was and computational methods become
more powerful. Um as I mentioned earlier
Dr. Uler first published this work in
2018 and then the development of our
high throughput pipeline allowed us to
um expand that analysis in 22. So that
included
um increasing our number of snips by
over threefold in addition to adding
more traits and then uh more recently in
2024 we published a new set of clusters
that expanded from Europeanon uh G-W was
to
multi-anccestry. So, in addition to G-W
was becoming more powerful and diverse,
we're also constantly working on ways to
improve our BMF pipeline. Um, and I just
wanted to kind of mention this because
it goes to show that, um, even if
genetic clustering has been done on a
disease or phenotype that you're
interested in, uh, there's almost always
room for improvement.
Um, and kind of in line with that, for
anyone that's interested in applying our
workflow to their own research, um, we
do have a GitHub page, um, that, as I
mentioned, we we are constantly trying
to, um, update it and make improvements
to our workflow. Um, so you're welcome
to check this out and try running the
clustering yourself. Or if that seems a
bit um, overwhelming to you, um, feel
free to reach out to Miriam um, if you
have any ideas for a collaboration
project.
Um and then I lastly I wanted to touch
on the limitations. Um I I know I've
kind of painted this uh approach as some
magic clustering tool today that's
perfect but as with any clustering
method there are um some limitations
involved. Um so number one uh the trait
inclusion um as I touched on this a bit
earlier but um we're still at this stage
where we have to manually download and
format each trait G-W was before we can
include it in the pipeline. Um so this
is actually um again as I mentioned
probably the most timeconuming part of
the workflow. Um for example the UK biio
bank has several thousand brain imaging
related traits and it would be great if
we could throw them all into the
pipeline for our Alzheimer's project and
see what sticks but the data processing
um is a lot of work and the more traits
you include the pipeline can also take
expens exponentially longer to run. Um
and then another one also kind of uh
related to the trait inclusion is data
availability. Um I think this mostly
applies to projects focused on
non-European populations. Um while the
population you're interested in might
have a powerful enough G-W was for the
main disease you want to study. If there
aren't enough trait G-W was for that
population then you might be a bit
stuck. Um, you can always fall back to
using multi- ancestry G-W was, but this
is just kind of a limitation to
consider. And then finally, something
that we're looking into a bit more now
is tuning the hyperparameters of the
BNMF algorithm. Um, there are things you
can adjust such as the tolerance
threshold or the gamma prior that will
affect the clusters that you end up
getting. Um so I think for future papers
it might be important to do some type of
hyper um some type of sensitivity
analysis on these
hyperparameters and I think this could
actually be a really useful analysis
because it might help us um identify the
most robust
clusters. So um in conclusion um complex
genetics diseases lead to heterogeneous
heterogeneous phenotypes. Um soft
clustering of genetic lossi by
associated traits using BNMF is a unique
approach for untangling this
heterogeneity. And then variant trait
groupings provide mechanistic pathway
insights while cluster PPS are useful
for patient stratification.
And um kind of takeaway for anyone um
interested in applying this to other
diseases is that this method is very um
uh flexible and you we can apply to
essentially any complex genetic disease
as long as the data is
available. And lastly, I just want to
say um thank you to everyone um in my uh
lab and in Dr. Uler's group and also to
um the many other collaborator
collaborators have helped on uh this
project over the last few
years. Um yeah, and that's it. Let's
think Kirk
again. And uh next two weeks we'll be in
here. So see you soon and please join us
across the hall for Steve Parker um also
from U of M.