Uh today we have a special uh guest
lecturer uh professor Andrew Loe. A lot
of you may have already know uh
professor Low, but I still will make a
quick uh introduction.
So, Professor Low is um professor at the
MIT Sloan Business School uh for many
years. He's also the director of uh the
laboratory for financial engineering and
uh uh a principal investigator with MIT
CEL which is the computer science and
artificial intelligence uh lab.
uh he also has many uh other active uh
involvement with uh uh say just a couple
of examples Santa Fe Institute and uh uh
MBER which is uh national bureau of uh
economical research
um and uh professor Los's research areas
are very broad too so I think it will be
too long for me to uh read through them
I think instead of that I will pass it
on to uh professor low for the today's
lecture.
>> All right. Great. Thanks very much,
Jake. Um thank you, Peter, for inviting
me to 16 or 18642.
Uh happy to be here and um I'm going to
be talking to you about um some big
ideas and some big challenges uh
particularly for your generation because
um uh our generation has created the
problems that your generation is going
to need to deal with. And so what I'm
hoping to do today is also to give you
some of the tools by which you could
deal with some of those problems.
Problems like climate change, like
dealing with cancer, uh various kinds of
uh energy demands that are growing uh
exponentially even as we speak. So by
background um I'm a financial economist
by training and trade. Um got my PhD at
Harvard in economics, financial
economics. uh then ended up teaching at
the Wharton School and for the last 35
years I've been teaching at MIT at the
Sloan School in the finance group and
when I teach my first year MBAs in
finance I start off by telling them
finance is the most important subject
you will ever take at a business school
and you know I acknowledge that my other
colleagues in departments like
accounting and marketing uh operations
research they may feel the same way
about their subject but the key
difference is that in my case I happen
to be right and and the reason is
because no matter what you do, no matter
what field you go into, no matter what
industry you choose for your job, at
some point or another, when you want to
do something really important, really
transformative,
you will need money and at that point
you will be speaking my language. you
will need to understand the basics of
financial analysis, things like cost of
capital, net present value calculations
and so on. So in this very short and
compressed lecture, I'm going to give
you an exposure to all of those concepts
in the context of dealing with some of
society's biggest issues and I'm going
to focus on two in particular. One is in
biio medicine and the other is going to
be in energy particularly fusion energy.
So let me first start with an
observation on the first set of examples
and that is that that biio medicine is
at an inflection point. Now some of you
who are biology majors you know this
actually do we have any biology majors
here in this class? Anybody doing
anything in bioengineering? How about
chemical engineering, chemistry?
>> Okay. Okay. All right. Well, people do
math and other subjects. But anyway, um
it turns out that in biio medicine,
things are different than they've ever
been in the history of the field. And
I'm going to give you two examples of
that. The first example has to do with
these two kids, Caroline and Cole
Carper. They were born with a rare
condition known as lib's congenital
amorosis. It's a single gene mutation, a
typo in your DNA that causes blindness
starting at birth. You're born with a
normal pair of eyes, but this mutation
prevents your eyes from producing a very
important protein. And without the
protein, you start to go blind. So, by
the time you're six months old, you are
legally blind from that point on. And so
these two kids were part of a clinical
trial in 2016 started by a
Philadelphiabased drug company called
Spark Therapeutics that used a really
remarkable therapy to try to deal with
their genetic mutation.
It's a treatment known as gene therapy.
And the way it works is this.
You take the correct version of the gene
that these two kids don't have. You
insert it into a virus and then you
inject the virus into the back of the
eyes of these two kids. One time
injection.
And what happens is the virus infects
the cells and takes the correct gene and
swaps it with the incorrect version
in those cells. And from that point
forward, these kids cells in the back of
their eyes start producing this protein.
And let me tell you what Caroline said a
few days after she received the
injection.
I went outside when it was snowing and I
was like, "Oh, I can see the
snowflakes." It was really cool to
actually see something that I've never
seen in my life before.
One time injection. and now she can see.
The second example has to do with um a
disease known as Canavan disease. So
this is also a single gene mutation, a
typo. And what this disease does is
pretty subtle.
it um prevents your nerve cells from
being able to maintain the myelin sheath
that basically provides the insulation
for that nerve cell. Now, you all know
that nerve cells have a nucleus and
they've got an axon, right? this long
long um string that conducts electricity
and allows you to basically take an
impulse and transmit it to various parts
of your body. And the purpose of this
myelin myelin is a kind of fat, right?
The purpose of this fatty sheath that
goes on the outside of every nerve cell
is insulation. It's like a wire that has
to have some kind of insulation to
prevent the electrical
impulses to cross to other wires. When
that happens, you get short circuits.
And obviously, that's a bad thing. But
turns out that kids with this single
gene mutation after they're born, the
myelin sheets in their body begin to
degrade. And so the electrical impulses
start to shortcircuit. And so you have a
hard time controlling your muscles. And
so generally these kids have a lifespan
of about 10 to 12 years. Uh this is a an
example of a Canavan patient. Um he's
probably uh uh close to his end of life.
Um they generally don't grow beyond uh
15 just because it's becomes harder and
harder to control your breathing, your
heartbeat. All of the bodily functions
that we take for granted become much
more difficult in canavan patients.
You'll notice that that he's leaned back
on his wheelchair. The reason is that
his head tends to be larger than normal.
This hi hypo hyper uh uh incphily your
head gets bigger uh is part of the
symptom of the disease. And at some
point your neck because there's no
muscle tone because you can't use the
muscles because of the nerve impulses
that get shortcircuited. Um it's very
easy to snap the neck if you just lean
over like this. And so you have to
always be in a prone position uh and
your head protected by um by these
cushions.
There's lots of other terrible symptoms.
Uh let me tell you what they are.
Children with canniban disease cannot
crawl, cannot walk, cannot sit or talk.
Over time they may suffer seizures,
become paralyzed, eventually delayed,
blind, and have trouble swallowing.
Deafness may also result. Many children
do not live past the age of 10 and at
present time there is no cure for
canavan disease. Treatment involves
managing the symptoms
and so the typical canavan patient the
disease uh generally affects you
starting at birth but in some cases it
ca it can be get progressively worse uh
over time.
the the doctors that know how to
diagnose this disease typically what
they tell their parents is go home and
love your child.
That's their treatment. That's it.
That's all they can do.
So it turns out that you can treat this
disease using the same technique gene
therapy. take the correct version of the
gene, put it into a virus, inject the
virus, in this case into the brains uh
of these Canavan patients. And well, I'm
going to show you um a video clip of
what happens with one particular
patient. This is patient number three, I
believe. And what you're going to see is
a clinical trial of the uh patient
before the treatment after she's
diagnosed. So they know that she's got
this mutation.
You can see the symptoms that are
developing. And and the frustrating
thing is that you are born relatively
normal, but because your body can't
maintain the myelin sheets, you begin to
degenerate over a period of time. So um
let me show you uh what's going on here.
So this is June 2022, just before the
treatment.
>> So this is the uh um patient.
>> You eating your blueberries?
>> And she's about one year old. And so at
this age, you should be able to move
around, but look at her hand motions and
how jerky her control is. She It's going
to take her quite a while just to grab
one blueberry and put it in her mouth.
So this is going to get much much worse
at this particular um rate of of uh
degeneration. Now this is uh
[clears throat]
about 6 months after that one time
injection.
>> Wow. Look at you trucking along. Come
on.
>> She's actually walking.
>> Even though it's with a uh a walker,
>> she's actually walk now. You can tell
>> recovery.
>> She can't walk on her own yet. you
strong.
>> But this is only six months after the
treatment. Okay.
>> Now, this is just around the same time.
>> She is now getting ready to actually
stand on her own.
>> And this uses an enormous amount of core
muscles. You probably all know you have
to exercise your core. So, she's
developing core muscle strength. It's
it's it's
>> quite She can't quite do it yet, but
she's close. Very close. And
>> there you go. [laughter]
There she goes. She's just about to do
it. That's it. For the very first time,
she actually stood up on her own.
Amazing. Now, this is a month after
that,
>> she is walking without the walker. She
can't do it all on her own yet because
remember, it's only been about seven or
eight months since her body is able to
deal with this myelin sheath problem.
>> But way better.
Now, this is about nine months later.
She's on a bike. [crying]
>> Extraordinary. And she's motioning to
her dad to give her a push and to help
her out.
>> And here she is uh just a few months ago
this year. So, this is now about a year
and 3 months after that that dose of
gene therapy. She's about to be able to
walk on her own for the very first time.
There has been no canniban patient in
the history of the disease that has ever
been able to do this. Got it,
>> girl.
>> And so this is remarkable,
>> remarkable uh progress.
>> Can you believe it?
>> Thank you, honey.
>> She is actually reading now. She's
starting to learn the letters of the
alphabet and she's responsive. She can
actually interact. This This is
extraordinary.
The blind shall see, the lame shall
walk. You know, that's a phrase that we
usually associate with religious
experiences.
But it's happening. It's happening now
thanks to the miracles that are being
developed by these scientists and
clinicians.
And our colleagues uh Phil Sharp, Susan
Hawkfield, and Tyler Jax, they published
a paper uh in 2016 to describe this new
world that we're living in. They call it
convergence. the convergence of the life
sciences, physical sciences, and
engineering. All of these fields are
coming together to be able to do things
that people were not able to do before.
The other term that people in biio
medicine use is the OMIX revolution. All
of these OMICs have experienced
tremendous progress over the last even
five years, never mind 10 or 20. and um
you know genomics the science of
sequencing your genes. Epigenomics, the
onoff switches that cause certain genes
to be switched on and others to be
switched off. Transcrytoics, the uh the
various different uh ways that you can
turn sequences of genes into proteins
that are in your body. Proteomics, the
20 to 25,000 proteins that are being
produced every day by your body.
Metabolomics, the chemical reactions
that make life possible. And finally,
most recently, microbiomics, the
colonies of bacteria that inhabit our
bodies that that keep us healthy. All of
these OMIX have given us tremendous uh
uh new knowledge based upon research
that's been going on thanks to
convergence
with the exception of one. There is one
OMIX that's in the bottleneck to
progress. And you know what that Omix
is? Economics. uh because you got to pay
for stuff and we're using the same old
stuff, the same old business models to
try to do those kinds of financings. So
what I want to tell you about is a
challenge that economics is facing and
how we can get around that challenge.
And the challenge is this, the valley of
death. When I first started getting
interested in healthcare, I would talk
to scientists and and doctors, you know,
in in Boston, Cambridge. We have a lot
of them as you know, very very uh uh
good ones. And I would ask them, you
know, why isn't there more progress? And
they keep telling me about the valley of
death, the valley of death. So I'm
thinking, what does Southern California
have to do with uh progress in the biio
medicine? And then they they tell me,
"No, no, no, it's not a place. It's
actually a metaphysical concept of the
period between scientific experiments at
university and medical centers and first
in human clinical trials. That period in
between those two milestones is the
valley of death. Meaning that it's
really hard to raise money to fund those
kinds of things. And so money is
something that I've spent a lot of time
studying. So my initial reaction was why
why is it the case that there is a
valley of death? I just assumed that if
there was a patient in need and there
was some technology that could help that
patient that magically money would
appear to fund a drug or a device and
everything would be hunky dory. Turns
out that that's not really how the world
works. And the more I studied the
problem, the more I realized that
actually the valley of death exists not
just in healthcare but in many fields
because of increasing risk and
uncertainty.
Now what do I mean by risk and
uncertainty? I think you all know what
risk is. Risk is the kind of un the kind
of randomness that we can parameterize.
So you know normal distribution, gamma
distribution, kai squared, we can figure
out the probability laws of risky
things.
But the uncertain things, those are what
economists refer to as the unknown
unknowns because nobody's ever done them
before. There's no data. So you can't
assess the probability that this could
possibly happen. And so that's the
challenge that the valley of death uh
ultimately needs to overcome
because drug development is a very
lengthy process. As some of you may
know, you have to go through clinical
testing. And because of that process,
there are three things about investing
in drug development that investors have
to get their arms around. One, it costs
a large amount of money to do the
testing. hundreds of millions to
billions of dollars in order to get one
drug approved. Second, that process is
generally very very unlikely to succeed.
Low probabilities of success.
And third, it turns out that developing
a drug could take 10 to 15 years from
beginning to end. So if you compare that
with developing an app, how many of you
have actually developed an app already?
Yeah. So, I imagine that it doesn't take
you a hundred million dollars to do that
and it doesn't take you 10 or 15 years
and it doesn't take you uh a whole team
of people where you're going to fail
with a probability of, you know,
whatever 95%.
So, that's the problem with investing in
this. Um, and so I'm going to give you
an example of why this is so challenging
by asking you to think about investing.
Um, some of you may already have
invested. I especially given that we're
at MIT. I often encounter undergraduates
who are actually quite uh accomplished
traders and and portfolio managers. But
um let me give you uh the example that I
give my first year MBA students and see
how you do with this. I show them four
different financial investments. I don't
tell them what they are or even over
what time period they span. I just tell
them this is what happens when you put a
dollar into it and you leave it there
for an unspecified multi-year investment
horizon. The green line turns a dollar
into $2. Not very rewarding, but not
particularly risky. The red line turns a
dollar into $5. Way more rewarding, but
way more volatile. Lots of ups and
downs. The blue line turns a dollar into
about eight dollars. The most rewarding
of all, but also the most volatile. and
the black line somewhere in the middle.
Not the most rewarding, but relatively
reasonable amount of risk. So, if you
could have only one of these
investments, you can't mix and match
them. If you only could have one to put
your life savings or or better yet to
invest your grandparents retirement
money and you had to you had to do it
for them. They asked you to help them.
Which would you pick? How many of you
would pick the green line to invest?
Wow. No takers.
Okay. How about the red line? How many
people will take the red line?
No takers for the red line. I want you
to remember this moment because I think
some of you may want to call your
brokers afterwards when I tell you what
the red line is. How about the blue
line? How many people want to do the
blue line? Okay, we got one or two
entrepreneurs in here or hedge fund
managers. Okay, good. And then now the
black line. How about the black line?
Yeah, by far the most popular choice in
my NBA class as well. And when I ask
them why, they say, "Well, you know,
it's got the the best tradeoff between
risk and reward." Yeah. Question.
>> The block is like a Ponzi scheme.
>> Really?
>> I don't know. Let's see. First of all,
let me tell you what the four assets
are, and we'll talk about that. The four
assets are the green line, treasury
bills, safest asset in the world. At
least for the next few weeks. We'll see
whether the budget discussions go well.
As long as we agree to pay back our
debts, yes, safe asset, but you know
what? You put your money in it in 2008,
you would have earned pretty much
nothing. And actually, you would have
earned less than nothing because of
inflation if you look at the real
return.
All right. The red line that none of you
picked, that is the US stock market. I
bet you some of some of you may already
have an investment in the S&P 500,
right? But if you didn't pick it or if
you did pick it in 2008,
congratulations. you would have done
just fine since then that right very
very good return
the blue line that only one of two of
you picked that is the single
pharmaceutical company Fizer one of the
largest pharma company in the world and
if you had picked Fizer in 2008 well
double congratulations you would have
spec done spectacularly well uh since
then lots of volatility but but really
quite well now the black line that is
the returns to a fund called the
Fairfield Century Fund, which most of
you probably never heard of, but that
was the feeder fund for the Bernie
Maidoff Ponzi scheme. So quite right,
you got the the uh the correct answer.
Um I had to stop it in 2008 because the
Ponzi scheme ended up blowing up then.
Now I show this example to students
because I want to explain to them
something very common about human nature
and that is that we all as investors we
want high yielding lowrisk assets and we
have a name in finance that describes
it. It's called the sharp ratio after
Bill Sharp, the Nobel Prize winning
economist from Stanford who pointed out
that people care about the expected
return of an investment above T bills
per unit of risk that they're taking.
They want to have the highest expected
return per unit risk. High sharp ratios.
So what's the sharp ratio of these
investments? Well, it's.33 for the S&P
uh sorry.34 uh for Fizer.33 for the S&P
and on paper the Ponzi scheme had a
sharp ratio an order of magnitude higher
and that's how Bernie Maidoff suckered
all of these poor investors to put money
with him. $50 billion
of investor money that he essentially
stole uh because of this common fact.
Now,
it turns out that biio medicine has had
a sharp ratio that's been declining over
the last several decades. Not because
the numerator is unattractive. There are
many biotech companies that just do
super well. But the problem is the
numerator. The numerator is growing even
faster. The risk
as well as the uncertainty is growing as
we become more sophisticated about the
science uh and uh medicine of disease.
And so we need to figure out how to
increase the sharp ratio. That's that's
the goal.
So I know this is a math class. So I
could not possibly do a present
presentation here without giving you at
least one equation. So, I'm going to
give you an equation and it's going to
be a very difficult math challenge about
how you can increase the sharp ratio.
Okay? It turns out there are two ways of
increasing the sharp ratio.
And let me tell you, for those of you
who aren't as mathematically gifted as I
am, uh you can increase the numerator
or you can decrease the denominator.
Those are the two ways. Now, of course,
in my NBA class, I have to have a
student who raises his hand and says,
"Professor Lo, there's actually a third
way." I said, 'Oh, really? He said,
'Yes, you can do both. So, yes, I agree.
You can do both. It turns out that we
are doing both. Better science, better
engineering, better organizational
structures, on and on. All of those are
designed to increase the numerator and
decrease the denominator.
But the one set of techniques that have
not been used as much in biio medicine
as well as in other industries that I'm
about to tell you
is new financing and business models.
And that's the interesting opportunity
for mathematicians. Believe it or not,
there are ways of constructing new
business models using math that could
actually change the riskreward tradeoffs
of these investments. So let me show
you. I'll give you an example.
Suppose I give you an opportunity to
invest in a new fund that I'm creating.
I need $200 million
to launch my fund and I'm going to be
investing in all sorts of special
technologies that only I have access to.
You don't. So, it's proprietary. It's
going to take me 10 years before I give
you any payoff whatsoever. So, don't
bother asking me before the decade is
out whether or not I'm going to give you
anything back. It's going to take at
least that long.
And in full disclosure, the likelihood
that I give you anything back is 5%.
95% of the time,
I'm not going to be able to produce
anything after 10 years. Okay. How many
of you would invest with me?
>> Depends on the return.
Thank you. Most of you didn't even
bother raising your hand, but you you
want to know what the return is. Fair
enough. That's absolutely right. For
most of my MBA students, they don't
bother asking. When they hear $200
million,
wait 10 years, 95% failure rate, no
thank you, not interested. But I will
get one or two uh MBA students who will
ask, "What's the return?" So, let me
tell you, these are the back of the
envelope calculations for what a single
anti-cancer drug will do in terms of
potential revenues and success rates. It
takes about $200 million to do the
clinical trials. It takes about 10 years
to do them. And in oncology, the
historical success rate is actually a
little less than 5%, 3.4%, but I'm going
to use 5% as round numbers.
If you are successful though in the case
of cancer drugs, you will get $2 billion
of revenues from years 11 to 20. Why 11
to 20? Well, because it takes 10 years
to develop a cancer drug. So, if you're
successful, then starting in year 11 is
when you begin to generate cash flows.
And why until year 20? It's because
that's how long a patent lasts. After
year 20, your patent is gone and people
can compete with you and your profits go
way down. 2 billion 2 billion 2 billion
from years 11 to 20. That is equivalent
to a single payday of $12.3 billion in
year 10.
Okay. So now let me ask you the question
one more time. I need $200 million up
front. Wait 10 years. 95% of the time
I'll give you nothing, maybe a warm
handshake and goodbye. And 5% of the
time I'll give you a check for 12.3
billion in year 10. How many of you
would invest in that?
>> Depend on how much money we have.
>> No,
no. I'll take any I'll take whatever
>> a million. I'm not going to
>> Whatever Whatever money you have. How
How many of you All right. I'm getting
one or two hands, but not a lot. I'm not
you're not all interested because for
most of you it is was way too risky.
Takes too long. Probability of success
is too low and it's just not your cup of
tea. And sure enough, if we calculate
the rate of return, this is an expected
rate of return over this 10-year period
of about 12%. With the standard
deviation of 423.5%
for a sharp ratio of like close to zero,
nobody's interested in this.
or very few people.
So this is where financial engineering
can make a difference and where math
comes into play. A very very small
amount of math.
Instead of investing in one of these
drugs, why not invest in oh I don't know
150 of them all at the same time.
If we did that, if we invested 150, you
might say, well wait a minute, that
takes 150 times 200 million which is $30
billion. That's not the kind of math
that would make anybody excited. $30
billion. Where are you going to get $30
billion?
And as an economist, I have a very
simple answer for that. The answer is
assume we have $30 billion.
I'll come back to this. I'll come back
to this in a minute. But if we had $30
billion and if we assume that the 150
projects are statistically independent
and identically distributed, and I'll
come back to that assumption later. If
that's the case, then
the expected rate of return for the
portfolio is the same because they're
identical projects,
but the risk now goes down by the square
root of the number of projects. Why?
Because the variance of the sum is the
sum of the variances when they're iid.
And so if the variance is the sum of the
individual variances, take the square
root of that to get the standard
deviation. That's why it goes down by
the rate of the square root of 150 which
gives you a 34.6%
risk rate. Now if I calculate the sharp
ratio of this, I'm getting a sharp ratio
that is an order of magnitude higher.
How many of you would invest in this
fund? Show of hands.
I'm getting a lot more hands.
That's where I'm going to get the money.
I don't have 30 billion, but you do in
the aggregate. If I can make this
investment attractive enough to get you
to put some of your 401k money or some
of your summer internship money into a
fund like this, I can raise $30 billion
very, very quickly. Now, the question
is, can you really raise $30 billion?
And the answer, of course, is it
depends. It depends on these
calculations that I just did. It depends
on the math underlying this portfolio.
The mathematics will tell you whether or
not this is feasible. So I'll give you
an example where not only does um that
should it work, but it actually does
work. And um the example has to do with
rare diseases. So I gave you two
examples of rare diseases at the
beginning. Canavan disease and liver
congenital amorosis. Turns out there are
roughly 12,000
different rare diseases.
And so individually a rare disease may
have a small patient population like
cystic fibrosis, hemophilia, luger's
disease or any a number of other
diseases. But in aggregate there are
more than 30 million Americans that are
suffering from one of these 12,000
diseases. I suspect that somebody in
this room knows a friend or a family
that's suffering from a rare disease.
Anybody just show of hands? Do you?
Yeah. So, it is clear that it may be
rare for any individual, but it is not
rare over a population because of just
the the number of mutations that are out
there. And so for a lot of reasons uh
it's actually relatively easier to
develop a drug for a rare disease both
because typically we know what's wrong.
There's a very serious problem and you
can trace the origins to one particular
organ and within that organ to one
particular mechanism and to that
mechanism one particular gene. So you
know a lot about it, but the other
reason it's often more uh uh successful
to develop these therapeutics is because
it doesn't cost as much money because
it's a rare population. So when you run
the clinical trials, you can run them
with a smaller number of people and
still be able to demonstrate that the
drug works. like the case for spark
therapeutics in the case of that that
libra's congenital amorosis I think they
got an FDA approval with something like
30 or 40 patients that's it 30 or 40
patients in the clinical trial and where
they when they were able to restore
their site the FDA said you don't need
to do any more testing we're ready to
prove it this is an amazing drug
but the key component is the fact that
because these rare diseases are so
different from each other
there's very little correlation in the
successes and failures of different
therapeutic programs. So when you
calculate the variance of the sum, it
really is the sum of the variances. If
we don't have correlation, then can
anybody tell me what the formula is for
the variance of a sum of random
variables?
>> Sum of the variance.
>> Exactly. How many coariances?
a lot of them. Exactly. Because you've
got A versus B, A versus C, A versus D,
B versus C, B, all the combinations. And
so it turns out that when there's
correlation, it's almost always
positive. And so when you calculate the
variance of a sum of a portfolio of
typical investments, you're getting not
just the individual variances, but all
the pair-wise coariances. If there
aren't any pair-wise covariances, that's
where the risk reduction comes from. And
so rare diseases have this really cool
property that I I have to admit I'm
quite proud. I was the one who wrote a
paper that recognized it. Frankly, I
didn't think it was that big a deal
except for this particular application.
But it turns out that the in the in the
biomedical field, nobody had ever
thought about this. the fact that
because the diseases are so different,
you ought to develop them not separately
but together in a single portfolio to
get the risk reduction. So instead of
$30 billion, you only need 4 to 500
million, instead of 150 projects, you
only need 10 or 20 to get
diversification.
And so what did I do with this
information?
I wrote a paper. That's what we do in
academia. published a paper, ran a Monte
Carlo simulation to show that if you
actually used relevant industry numbers,
the kind of rate of return you're
looking at is around 22% per year
and with a volatility that could be
quite a bit lower than that, meaning a
sharp ratio greater than one. Now, you
can ask Jake afterwards about whether or
not a sharp ratio greater than one is
good. As a professional investor and a
risk manager for Harvard management
company, he can attest to the fact that
this is a very attractive and very rare
kind of opportunity.
But there are, remember, there are
12,000 rare diseases. So, it doesn't
seem that rare to me. So, the question
is, does this really work?
And the reason I wrote the paper was
because I wanted people to try it out.
And I got a phone call shortly after the
paper came out from a former student of
mine. Somebody who was a PhD in chemical
engineering here at MIT, took one of my
finance courses when he was here, then
went on and became a biotech VC and
called me up said, "Professor Law, I
read your paper. Really interesting. Um,
would you mind rerunning your
simulations not with your assumptions
but with mine?" And I said to this
former student, of course, I'd be happy
to. You know a lot more about the
industry than I do. I'm just using
industry averages, whereas you actually
have hard data based upon your own
portfolio investments. So we ran a model
with his parameters instead of mine. And
the results, they look better. And so
then I suggested a few other tweaks
based upon what he was telling me about
the industry, the way it works in his
field. And we ran my version and it
looked better still.
over six months, I think we ran 35
different versions of this model.
And
at the end of that six-month period, he
came into my office and said, uh, I just
want to let you know, I quit my job
yesterday. I'm going to do this. I'm
going to build this company. And I got
to tell you, that scared the hell out of
me. I had never had that effect on any
of my students. And he had a young kid
in his household. And I said, Neil, are
you sure you want to do this? I need
maybe you should let me run a few more
simulations. And he said, "No, no, no.
My wife is cool. I think we're ready to
do this." I felt guilty enough that I
invested a small amount of in the
friends and family round. And in
retrospect, I wish I would have invested
a lot more because that's probably my
single most uh uh profitable investment.
In uh in 2017, this company Bridge
Bioarma came out of stealth mode. And um
we had our first investor was um not a
uh venture capitalist but a private
equity firm that prior to this company
had never invested in biotech. The
company is called KKR. You may have
heard of them. Some of you undoubtedly
will be doing internships with them uh
sometime in the next few years. Um we
raised about $40 million in that very
first round after the friends and family
round. Uh a year later we raised another
135. A year later yet another 300. So we
were right around the 4 to500 million
range. We had about 15 projects just
like the simulations. And at that point
we did an IPO and after the IPO we
raised another 750. Um and as of uh this
morning or early this morning uh before
the market opened uh Bridge Bio is
currently trading at about $4.6 billion
dollars of market cap. All of the
investors myself included have done
better than we ever would have expected.
Uh a great rate of return. But uh you
know what that's not what this company
is proud of. what they are most proud of
is the fact that there are other
portfolio companies that have gotten
started thanks to us and and uh this
it's now become a thing that you can use
portfolio theory to reduce your risk as
this McKenzie report in 2021 put out and
um at this point bridge bio has about 20
different projects in the clinic two
drugs have already been approved in 2021
uh a drug focusing on a very rare kind
of uh enzyme deficiency
as well as a uh a rare kind of of bile
duct cancer. Both of them were approved
in 2021. Um a uh a third blockbuster
drug looks like it's going to get
approved uh sometime later this month.
So watch the news for an announcement
from Bridge Bio.
And um you know that gene therapy for
that little girl who had cannavan
disease that turns out to be a bridge
bio drug and as of last year that drug
with 10 patients have shown efficacy in
every single one of the patients that
have the disease. So we expect that the
uh FDA will approve that drug sometime
next year. uh really amazing and um I
got to tell you the the proudest
professional accomplishment that I've
ever experienced um was this moment here
uh when I met that little girl. Uh she
actually lives in Boston uh in Jamaica
plane and uh here she was. the parents
found out about um the business model
that that I developed along with Neil
and asked to meet with me and it was
really kind of a a scary and extremely
emotional meeting. Uh this is the flower
bakery um right across the uh the mass
or the the salt and pepper bridge um
where uh Mass General is. That's where
they were going for their care. And I
went into this um uh flower bakery uh to
meet them. And um my first vision was
walking up the stairs uh holding her
father's hand and she kept pushing his
hand away because she wanted to do it on
her own. is just an extraordinary
extraordinary moment. Th this is the
power of financial engineering. And let
me be very clear, I had zero to do with
any of the scientific decisions that
Bridge Bio made. Um I often tell people
that, you know, finance cannot turn a
bad drug into a good one. But the lack
of financing or the wrong kind of
financing can easily take a good drug
and destroy it and make sure it never
reaches a patient. And so finance uh is
an important aspect of drug development,
but it is not the most important aspect.
You got to start with the science and
then figure out what the right financing
is.
So I'm going to turn to my second topic
now, which is energy transition. I want
to illustrate the fact that finance is
not just about biotech, but it really
can transform any industry. And I know a
number of you are concerned about
climate change. So am I. So is Jake and
Peter. And the question is, what do we
do about it? Now, there is this thing
called energy transition. Um, and
there's a report that I read a couple
years ago that I highly recommend. It's
an a rather harsh dose of reality.
People talk about energy transition like
we're going to get off of fossil fuels
soon. And what this paper argues is
that, you know, that's really not the
right term. We are not
taking less and less of our energy from
fossil fuels. And here's a graph that
illustrates it. So this is a graph of
how much energy we are consuming as uh
broken down by different sources. So
here oil um you can see you know
certainly uh natural gas and coal all
three forms of fossil fuels are growing
in the amount that we're consuming year
after year. Now now how can that be?
Because we are making progress with
renewables, right? So here's wind and
solar. This is in in uh in blue and here
is you know nuclear here. um they're
getting a little bit wider but not
nearly as fast as the fossil fuels are.
And it's because human population is
growing. And also the the the kind of
people that we have on this planet
that's changing. We are now having more
and more people that are moving into the
middle class. And when you move into the
middle class, what do you want? You want
a better life. You want a a house. You
want two cars instead of one. You want
to take a vacation by flying somewhere.
And all of the things that you and I
take for granted, there are millions to
hundreds of millions of people that are
for the first time being able to
experience it. And that's why the
consumption of energy is growing far
faster than our ability to create uh
non-greenhouse gas sources of energy. So
the problem with energy transition is
that, you know, if you just look at
what's going on, we we we can't just
rely on renewable energy. We need to
have lowcarbon forms of energy that
don't pollute the atmosphere and that
are on demand available. So what are we
doing? How are we transitioning from one
energy source to another? It's not
really transitioning. We're not
declining our usage of these kinds of
sources of energy, but we need to be
adding to them with lowcarbon sources.
And so from what my experts in energy,
my colleagues here in the geo uh um uh
department are telling me, um they're
telling me that there are three sources
of
renewable of of energy that is
non-renewable. They're not wind and
solar, but they are ultimately going to
be infinite close to infinite sources of
energy. And that is fusion, fision, and
geothermal. And for a variety of
reasons, we're not going to see a lot of
progress in the near term for fision. We
already have nuclear power plants. Uh
but the problem from a political point
of view is nobody wants to have them
near where they live and nobody wants to
deal with the mess of the fuels that
ultimately uh when they degrade become
radioactive and dangerous. So um because
the prices of fossil fuels are highly
path dependent, this energy transition
is very very difficult to predict. And
what that tells us is we need to start
thinking about alternative sources of
energy that are going to be sustainable.
And so it turns out that nuclear energy
is the main source of sustainable energy
for the for the for the long-term future
of the human uh species. And there are
only two forms of nuclear energy, fusion
and fision. So as you probably know,
fusion is when we split an atom and you
get more energy out than you put in. But
fusion energy is where you squeeze atoms
together. And it turns out that the
squeezing gives you a lot more energy
than the splitting of an atom. It also
turns out that fusion energy is the most
abundant form of energy in the entire
universe. Why? Because this is what
powers stars and that's where we get all
of our energy other than geothermal.
It's basically we're getting energy from
the sun.
So fusion turns out can produce roughly
four times more energy uh per kilogram
of fuel than fision. And here's the the
kicker. It does not produce longlasting
radioactive waste. When you uh uh are
are are finished using fisionbased
energy systems like uranium, plutonium,
you will have radioactive waste that in
some cases have a halflife of 100,000
years, which is a lot longer than I plan
to live. So that's the problem. Whereas
with fusion energy, it produces
water and helium and maybe some tridium,
which is radioactive, but it doesn't
last that long. And moreover, tridium is
something that we need as part of our
fusion um uh inputs. So the problem with
fusion is you need three things to
happen. The so-called loss in triple
product.
You need to take a compound, some
matter, and you need to squeeze it
together really hard because that's how
you're going to get atoms to fuse.
Unfortunately, just squeezing it is not
enough on this planet. You have to
loosen them up. Loosen them up so that
they will come together. And that means
you have to heat it to a very very high
temperature. And then you have to hold
on to it for a long enough period of
time so that the fusion reactions can
happen. [snorts] So these are the three
things that have to happen. Temperature,
pressure, and time. Now it turns out
that in the on the sun or in the sun
this happens relatively easily. The the
pressure gets created by gravitational
pull and the temperature increases as a
function of how it pulls in through the
gravity the different uh combustible
items. And as we know once you ignite
fusion it lasts and lasts and lasts for
many many hundreds of thousands to
millions of years.
So something pretty amazing happened
here in Cambridge on Labor Day weekend
2021.
What happened is that MIT in
collaboration with a spin-off that it
created called Commonwealth Fusion
Systems.
They created a magnetic field that was
so strong that it will in principle be
able to contain fusion reactions to the
to the the degree that we need in order
to achieve ignition. It can actually
light this plasma. And this
demonstration occurred about five blocks
from here on Albany Street. uh they
created a 20 Tesla magnet. 20 Tesla
magnet that is an extremely strong
magnetic field. And the interesting
thing about what happened here is that
three months later, this Oh, and by the
way, this is yours truly. I was there
for this event. Um I had collaborated
with Dennis White, the head of the
plasma science infusion center. Uh so he
kindly invited me to be there. This was
by the way Sunday morning at 7:30 a.m.
Labor Day weekend. I was out on the Cape
with my family and I abandoned them to
come here. That's how nerdy I was. Uh
but it was an extraordinary historical
event. What happened after that of
course was we saw that um the uh uh
Lawrence Livermore Laboratory at
Berkeley. They actually created a truly
exothermic fusion reaction, meaning more
money more power came out than money
went than than energy went in. which
basically says you're creating money out
of nothing. If money is energy, then
you're putting more money, you're you're
getting more money out than you're
putting in. Um, also the regulatory
authorities have agreed that fusion
should not be regulated the way that
fision is, which is pretty big. And yet
another repeat of fusion uh in 2023.
So the question that that um my
colleague in the plasma science and
fusion center Dennis White and I have
asked is can we use finance to fund
fusion. So we wrote a paper about this
too and in this paper we do a
calculation that shows yes there is a
path of creating a portfolio in order to
fund fusion. Now a portfolio of what? So
so I I have to I have to answer that
question. In order for me to answer a
question about portfolio of what I have
to describe what do I mean by saying
fusion. What do we mean by fusion?
What I mean is to create a commercially
viable power plant or reactor that will
generate enough heat to create a turbine
that will spin and generate electrons to
be put on the power grid. That's what I
call fusion. And so what that means is
you need this. You need a fusion reactor
that will do its thing and generate
heat. The heat will basically heat up
water. Water will turn to steam. That
will basically cause turbines to spin.
As the turbines spin, you generate
electricity and the electricity goes on
existing power grids. So this whole
thing is what I'm calling fusion.
That's what I want to do. That's what I
want to invest in.
Now, how do we do that? How do we invest
in fusion? And the answer has to do with
what it takes to achieve fusion
electrons on the grid. These are all the
components that experts tell me are
needed in order to get fusion to happen.
And so the question is,
how do we do that?
And the answer like anything else is
break it apart. Look at it one by one
and figure out what you need in order to
achieve these different components. So
one of the things we need is high uh
sustained high temperature plasma. So
plasma is a fourth state of matter. When
you heat something up to a certain
temperature, it becomes plasma. The
problem is as it gets hotter, it's
harder and harder to contain this uh
kind of matter and so you need to have
some way to hold on to it. Well,
magnetic bottles are what we're
considering in one form of fusion. But
if that's the issue of uh creating high
temperature plasma, then let's take it
and break it apart. What do we need just
to do that? And by the way, just to let
you know what high temperature means,
we're talking about 100 million degrees.
100 million degrees. That's hot. So, how
do we achieve that? Well, it turns out
that there are a bunch of things you
need in order to do it.
So, what do we do? This is the portfolio
I'm talking about. I'm talking about
creating a portfolio of technology
that when combined will allow you to
achieve fusion, but even if never
combined, they have value in and of
itself. For example, advanced vacuum
systems. It turns out that in order to
create achieve really high temperatures,
you have to have ultra pure conditions
with no contaminants and no air in
particular, you need to have a vacuum
system that works far better than your
typical Hoover vacuum cleaner. It turns
out that if you can create that vacuum
system, it has applications in many
other things like for example in, you
know, drug development. And so if you
think about fusion not as one thing but
as a portfolio of a whole bunch of
different technologies that have value
in and of themselves but that when
combined will have value for fusion. you
can basically break it apart and do the
kind of financial analysis that we just
did with a single drug development
project and then put them into a
portfolio maybe 150 of them and figure
out the risk and reward and be able to
finance it. So the idea is to create a
multi-billion dollar fusion mega fund
just like we did with the cancer mega
fund and finance all these different
technologies and you know imagine
creating an incredible board of
adviserss on the scientific side you've
got people like you know Mike Campbell
University of Rochester expert in laser
technology Steve Chu former energy
secretary Nobel Prize winner uh Rob
Goldstone Dave Labbersteier Ernest
Monise also another former energy
secretary that was a MIT faculty member.
Uh Dennis White, the former head of the
plasma science infusion center and so
on. And then on the business side,
you've got people like Sam Alman, Jeff
Bezos, Peter Diamandis, Bill Gates,
Venode Kosla, so on and so forth. People
that can actually help us manage the
business models.
Now you might say, well, wait a minute,
you know, how are you going to get these
people to be part of this effort?
And that's a challenge because, you
know, the folks in blue, they're not
motivated by money. So, if I call them
up and ask them to be part of this, I I
I would doubt that they would even
return my phone calls. They've never
heard of me. The folks in green, uh,
they have all the money. And so, I'm
pretty sure that, uh, and actually I
know a number of them already. So that's
why I know that if I call them, they
will not return my phone calls. But if
you raise multi-billion dollars to
deploy capital, all of them will return
your phone call. Not not just because of
the money. As I said, the people in
blue, they don't they don't care about
money. And the people in green, they
have all the money. They don't need your
money. But if you can actually show that
there's a business path that allows you
to achieve your goal of ignition,
they'll all want to be part of it. And
finally, how many of you, if I created a
fund like this with these people, how
many of you would put as a one-time
investment, just one-time investment,
$1,500
of your 401k money that you may have
saved up after a summer internship or
after your first year working at your
job. How many of you will put a
hundred,500 into a fusion fund?
That's where I'm going to get the
multi-billions of dollars because with
130 million households out there, if 3%
of you put in $1,500, that's more than
$30 billion right there. We can do this.
This can actually be be done. So, there
are many other examples of this. Yeah.
Question. Um, wouldn't the portfolio for
the fusion like all those different
things, wouldn't they be highly
correlated by these different industries
as opposed to drugs that wouldn't be?
>> Well, that's a great question. Let's go
back and take a look at it. So, it's
true that the entire fusion reactors of
many different companies will be
correlated, but they will not be
perfectly correlated if they're using
different ways of achieving fusion.
Right? One uses magnetic, the other one
uses inertial. And so there are
different technologies but more
importantly if I look at this portfolio
of technologies. So one of them is
plasma heating systems. How to make
things really hot. The second one is
advanced vacuum systems. How to keep
things really clean and pure. A third
one is magnetic confinement
technologies. So how you shape the
magnets in order to keep the bottle from
uh becoming unstable.
Each of those things have nothing to do
with each other.
>> Oh right. Okay. I thought I thought they
might. That's all. That makes sense.
>> Yeah. The technology, the component,
some of them do, but most of them do
not.
>> And that's where you're going to get the
diversification. You're right.
>> So, um, lots of other technologies. The
key to all of these are that they are
long shots. Very, very low probability
or unknown probability of success. They
cost a lot of money. They take a lot of
time, but the returns to society are
huge. And so that's why you need to have
innovative financing for these long
shots. The key to all of this is to have
the right narrative,
the right story to tell investors about
how you're going to give them a return
on their investment. And that requires
the right business models to be able to
do that. So, I'm going to wrap up with a
story that I use lots of times because
when I first heard it, I was so
impressed that I decided that that was
going to be my motivation for doing what
I'm doing. Um, it has to do with this
man, Professor Harvey Lotus. He's a
biology faculty member here at MIT in
the Whitehead Institute.
Harvey when he uh was an assistant
professor in 1983 was approached by uh a
businessman asking whether he would
collaborate with him to create a um a
treatment for a rare disease called
gocha's syndrome. This is also one of
these genetic typos which prevents your
body from producing important
housekeeping enzymes. And without this
enzyme, fatty acids build up in your
your um spleen, your bone marrow, and by
the time you're a teenager, if you have
a very serious version of this disease,
you're dead.
And so Harvey and his colleagues, they
developed a treatment to deal with this
disease by replacing the enzyme with an
artificially developed version of it.
And um this little company in 1991 got a
drug called Seriday uh approved by the
FDA, the first ever enzyme replacement
therapy. They would just put back into
these uh individuals bodies the missing
enzyme that uh you know they they their
bodies don't produce. They could produce
it outside and give it to them. And um
you may have heard of Harvey's little
company uh it's called Genzyme. And in
2012, 2014, Genzyme was purchased by
Seni for $20 billion.
Now, that's not why I want to be Harvey
Lowish. Although that's not a bad
reason, by the way. I'm an economist
after all. Uh, see, I want to be Harvey
because of what happened in 2002.
In that year, Harvey's daughter was
pregnant with her second child. Harvey
and his wife's second grandchild, a boy,
uh, named Andrew. Great name, by the
way.
Andrew was diagnosed in utero with gocha
syndrome.
What are the chances of that?
So I I talked to Harvey about this. I I
asked him, you know, it was very
emotional conversation. I asked him,
Harvey, did you know in 1983
when you started Genzyme that you would
be developing a drug that would someday
save the life of your as yet unborn
grandson?
And um and Harvey said no. He had no
idea. He said, "I I thought that, you
know, if I could do some cool science
and and help some patients, that would
be great." 1983 was two decades before
the human genome was sequenced. So, you
know, I had no idea that I was carrying
the mutation. And in 2012, when his son
uh turned 10, he developed the
full-blown symptoms of goches. So he
would be dead if it weren't for the drug
that grandpa developed. That that's why
I want to be Harvey Lotish. I I don't
have an MD or PhD in molecular biology.
I will never be able to develop a drug
that will save my as yet unborn
grandchildren.
But I realized something. I realized
that you know what? We can all be Harvey
Lotish if we invest in the drugs that
save our as yet unborn grandchildren.
Finance doesn't always have to be a
zero- sum game if we don't let it. With
the right business models, the right
scale at the right time, we can do the
thing that everybody says they want to
do, but very few of us ever get to do,
which is that we can actually do well by
doing good. And with your help, um, you
know, we can do this.
[music]
>> Thank you. I teach MBA students, so I
have to use sound effects. I'm sorry.
Thank [applause] you.
We have some time for questions. Sure.
>> Yeah. Questions or comments?
>> Yeah.
I know you mentioned about the like when
you're talking about the farming part
from like years 11 to 20.
>> Yeah.
>> And you're saying that after
how long the last
>> That's right. I was wondering after that
you said that other people could compete
um after that like I guess like I I was
too sure about how the whole process
works like after like how competition
affect the
um you
>> sure so when you have a patent it gives
you the right to use the information in
the patent exclusively meaning nobody
else is allowed to use that information.
And so typically for drugs, what is that
information? It's basically a chemical
formula for a particular compound that
doesn't exist in nature naturally. You
created it, you came up with it, you
filed a patent disclosure, and the
patent office said, "Yep, this is new
and useful. Uh, we're going to grant you
the patent." So for 20 years, only you
are allowed to use that idea. And so
when you use that idea to create a drug,
you're the only one that's allowed to
make the drug. And so if people want
that drug, they got to pay you. And so
you end up charging a price for the drug
that will generate a lot of value for
you.
At the end of the 20 years, what's the
deal? The deal is
everybody gets to use that idea. And so
now you got companies that can produce
the drug because typically the producing
of the drug is pretty cheap, right? Once
you give me the formula, I can
basically, you know, get a chemical
manufacturing plant to come up with it
relatively cheaply. you know, a few
pennies a pill.
The the expensive part was developing
the clinical trials to get the FDA to
give you the license to do it. Once
that's done, it's all profits for you
until such time as now everybody gets to
produce it for relatively low amounts of
money. So, it's like aspirin. At one
point, aspirin was patented. Now,
anybody can make it because you could
look up the patent. There's the formula
right there. You can do it yourself if
you know how to mix those chemicals and
you don't have to pay anybody for it.
But before the patent expires, you're
not allowed to use the idea. Or if you
want to use the idea, you have to pay
the owner of the patent a fee for using
their idea. That's that's how it works.
>> Yeah.
>> How do you find these investment
opportunities or how do you even begin
to research these
Yeah, that that's a great great
question. The answer is you need to have
expertise.
So I mentioned as I mentioned Neil Kumar
the co-founder of Bridge Bio and the
person who who created it really um Neil
has a PhD in chemical engineering but he
didn't go off and become a chemical
engineer. He went off and first worked
at McKenzie advising biotech companies
about their corporate strategy and
ultimately he decided to start investing
in various different ideas because he
had the expertise. As a chemical
engineer, you have the science
background, the engineering background
and then as you work in the industry,
you learn about how the industry works.
So you learn that aspect of it. That's
what gives you the expertise. And then
once you have the expertise, the
companies that have the money to invest,
the venture capital firms, the private
equity firms, even the big pharma
companies that have corporate venture uh
divisions, they will want to hire you to
help them manage the money. That that's
how you ultimately end up being able to
do that. You got to have the expertise.
And by the way, that's one of the
reasons why MIT graduates are so popular
among Wall Street investment houses
because you all not only have expertise,
but you have the ability to learn and
develop new expertise as needed. That
that's really important.
>> Yes.
>> How do we invest?
>> What's that?
>> How do we invest in this
>> in How do you invest? Well, you know,
that's actually the same question I
have. How do I invest in you?
You all are the next generation of
investment opportunities. And you know,
I'm not saying this just to flatter you.
This is a biological fact. You are going
to be around a lot longer than Jake,
Peter, and I. And therefore, all of you
are the future of innovation. And so,
yes, I I would love to figure out how to
invest in terms of investing in these
kind of companies. The the biotech
companies or bridge bio is publicly
traded, so anybody can invest. And I'm
not suggesting you should invest in
them. uh there's risk very very high
risk by the way in biotech companies. So
you need to be very careful about that.
Uh but the much harder areas to invest
are the private companies because by
definition they're private so you don't
know as much about them as publicly
traded companies where you've got you
know a lot of published information
and you probably are already aware but
if you're not you you should be that MIT
is an incredibly attractive place for
private investors to come and look for
opportunities among the students and the
faculty. Y you are in a wonderful
position particularly those of you who
are majoring in math because your skills
are portable to virtually every industry
out there. I don't know of an industry
that doesn't need math. Maybe the
Hollywood film industry but you got to
count your money. You know somehow Tom
Cruz has to count his money. So you got
to have math for that. So um I think
that there are lots of of venture
capitalists hanging around Kendall
Square and MIT to try to understand
whether they can invest in you. Uh you
will find that to be a very very
interesting phenomenon. Uh yeah I'll
come back to you but uh you are first.
>> So niche thing that like you want to
invest in. Do these groups already exist
that are like trying to do this these
things but they need money or is that
like the investment going towards
starting XYZ that does this specific
thing? Well, there is still a valley of
death in the sense that there are lots
of groups that want money to do the kind
of cool things that you are all going to
come up with on your own. By the way, to
put in a plug for Dennis White, he
teaches a course on fusion on nuclear
engineering where as part of the course
they come up with ideas, a number of
which ultimately end up becoming
commercialized and real startups. So
there are a number of companies that
can't get funded because of the valley
of death. Um MIT has a much better
opportunity set than if you were say at
um uh Duke University or University of
North Carolina. Uh that's part of the
research triangle uh down south and
they've got some really cool ideas,
smart students and faculty as well, but
because they're not part of the Boston
Cambridge ecosystem, they don't have as
many venture capitalists down there
looking to fund various different
projects. So, I would say that there are
still lots and lots of of smaller groups
that are looking for funding that can't
get it because they just don't know
enough about the financing. So, what
I've described to you now in just this
one class is probably more information
than most startup uh groups have in
terms of thinking about riskrewards and
and trade-offs like that.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Say that you're also a professor
here. So I'm wondering if like your
classes
and teachers more like healthare stuff
like that here at MIT or is that
something you have to learn outside?
>> So again very glad you asked that
question because I happen to be teaching
a class right now on healthcare
financing. It's called 15482.
Now for those of you who may not um be
able to take that class because of
conflicts or whatever that class is
actually online. It's part of MIT's open
learning library. So there is a version
of 482X that you can all sign up for.
It's free. Uh there's um you know an
archive version of it. So just check on
the open learning library website. It's
not part of OCW uh but uh open learning
library.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so the gentleman who started bio can
you just give like a rough outline of
like how on earth he did that from a PhD
to start.
>> Sure. So the first thing he did when he
graduated was he went to McKenzie a
consulting company and he knew a lot of
science and engineering but he didn't
know much about the industry. As part of
McKenzie's program they train they train
their uh hires to um learn about the
industry. So, you know, probably for the
first year, he shadowed a more
experienced biioarma consultant that
brought him into various different
companies and showed him projects that
they were working on and how he could
add to those projects by doing research.
Just like if he were a chemical engineer
doing research on, you know, better ways
of refining oil, uh he'd have to go and
read articles and then talk to people
and then do experiments. In that same
way, if you're in a consulting firm like
McKenzie and you're working on a project
like, you know, how should how should
Fiser fund their u uh vaccine program
for RSV? Well, what would he do? He
would go and learn about RSV. He would
read the journal articles. He would
figure out how it's being funded now. He
would come up with new ideas. He would
try to test them out by writing
different simulation uh examples to
illustrate what could happen. Those are
the kind of things that he did for the
first 3 to 5 years of his career.
At some point he learned enough about
the industry to start making investment
decisions like this company has got a
good bet because all the things that I
was studying about proper ways of
funding particular projects they're
doing it versus this company I don't
really want to invest because they don't
even understand how to fund their
internal pipeline. So at some point he
left McKenzie to join Third Rock
Ventures which is um a venture capital a
biotech venture capital company and then
he spent a few years there learning how
to make investments.
It was at Third Rock that he approached
me and said look I've been thinking
about rare diseases as well. I've seen
investments that Third Rock has passed
on because it's not a so-called platform
technology. it's only a a one-trick
pony, you know, one idea, one drug, one
disease, and and Third Rock thought it
was too risky. Would you be willing to
uh run some models with me to fund those
projects? And after we ran a bunch of
simulations, it gave him enough
conviction that this was going to be a
profitable venture that he was willing
to take the risk to try to do that. And
the first thing we did was we asked
Third Rock, "You guys passed on these
three opportunities, do you mind if we
take them? Can we invest in them?" Third
Rock said, "Be my guest. Go for it." And
what was not appropriate for Third Rock,
given they've got lots of other
opportunities that they're focusing on,
was a great um opportunity set for
Bridge Bio, this portfolio company. So
like anything else, it's a gradual
process where you learn more and more
and more and sometimes at some point you
learn so much that you are confident
that you know enough to be able to start
your own company.
>> That's very sure by the way it doesn't
mean it's any less scary. There is still
a scary moment where you know you you
learned all this stuff but still
quitting your job you know with a baby
at home and you know bills to pay that
that is scary but you know at some point
your confidence and your ability to um
you know get through that scary period
outweighs the u the wall that uh your
emotions put up.
>> Yes. I don't know what's like uh in
times of like crisis or when you
actually like need some type of drug or
like for example like um co needed like
the vacing
like too many people like I guess cuz
you talked about like the death and all
that stuff is that during those times
like like how is it adjusted I would say
or if you can
like that compared during those times
Well, so that's a a really important
observation uh because in the case of CO
19, we did have a valley of death and we
still do have a valley of death when it
comes to vaccines because the
profitability of the typical vaccine is
not very attractive. And so prior to
COVID, most big pharma companies were
actually getting out of the vaccine
business. Cancer was much more
profitable. rare diseases actually ended
up being more profitable than vaccines.
And so right before the pandemic hit,
there were only four big pharma
companies left that were still in the
vaccine making business.
And but once the vac once the pandemic
hit and we knew that it was going to be
bad when it came on US shores in March
of 2020, we knew it was going to be bad.
At that point, a lot of things started
to happen all at the same time. First of
all, philanthropy had been funding
scientific experiments for vaccines for
decades. In particular, the Gates
Foundation. They for years have been
working on a vaccine for malaria. Still
doesn't exist. By the way, we still
don't have a vaccine for malaria.
Believe it or not, malaria is probably
the single biggest killer around the
world. Not here in the US, but in
Africa, where malaria is a real problem
for many, many countries, and it kills
literally millions of people every year.
So the Gates Foundation had been working
on that for many years, funding
scientific research and it and funding
MADNA in particular among other
companies. And so once the vaccine hit
US soil, we were very very quick to be
able to collaborate with international
scientists to get the the the sequence
the genetic sequence of the particular
spike protein that we were going to
target with the various different
antibodies. So that process worked like
magic. We we had there was no valley of
death uh for that period of time because
the government stepped in and said we
got to do something otherwise lots of
people are going to die. For the very
first time in the history of the
industry, it took 63 days from the time
we sequenced the co 19 vacu
virus to when the first human patient
was injected with the vaccine candidate.
63 days. Typically, it takes 3 to five
years to create a vaccine.
It took us 63 days. That's an example of
what you're talking about getting around
the valley of death. The problem is now
that COVID seems like it's over. Of
course, it's not really over. You can
still get CO 19 as many of you will find
out in the next few months. Uh but it's
not as serious. We know how to deal with
it. We've got a number of drugs and
treatments and we recognize the various
different symptoms. So, because it is
not that serious,
people are more relaxed about it. And
what that means is the valley of death
is back. People don't want to spend
money on it. They'd rather spend money
on guess what AI, right? Let's put money
in open AI or Anthropic or uh you know
any one of these other companies. And um
that that that's that's a problem. So I
think that we need to worry about that.
That's one of the reasons why I'm here
today. Uh try to get some of you to be
excited about taking your ideas and your
toolkits and doing well by doing good.
you will really do spectacularly well
from a financial point of view if you're
able to succeed in fusion or in in drug
development devices and so on. But but
even more importantly, you're going to
feel really good about what you're doing
and you're going to actually help a lot
of people.
>> All right, I'm out of time. So, thank
you very much and uh have a good day.
[applause]