hello everyone welcome to today's
seminar it is my great great pleasure to
start the seminar Series this year with
our great guest Professor Barry rant
Barry is um jointly appointed between
the department of electrical and
computer engineering as well as the ant
linger Center for Energy and the
environment at Princeton University
prior to Princeton he was at iMac where
he was a principal scientist researching
the understanding optimization
Manufacturing ability of thin film solar
cells Professor rand's research is at
the interface of electrical engineering
Material Science supplied physics and
chemistry covering electronic and opto
electronic thin films and
devices uh he's authored more than 200
Journal Publications holds 25 us patents
and has received several Awards amongst
which are the 3M non- tenur faculty
award Dupont young professor Award DARPA
young faculty award onr young
investigator program award and the
Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation
experimental physics investigators
initiative award so before I hand it
over to Barry just uh a reminder for our
audience if you're here in person please
feel free to raise your hand to ask your
questions uh and those who are joining
us online you can type your questions
through the Q&A uh feuture of the zoom
webinar and I can help moderate the
questions for you so with that welcome
to MIT thank you for coming and we're
excited to listen to your talk thank you
faros
oh thank you for eating into my 40
minutes um so I'm going to tell you
today about some of the work that's
going on in my lab regarding interface
reactions between some medium and Hali
perovskites and in in a way to try to
understand two different phenomena one
is the phenomenon of degradation how
these materials break down over time and
the other one is to understand doping
and see if we are in fact capable of
either P or n type doping of these media
meaning controlling the electron or
whole population of these
semiconductors so let me start with a
brief introduction for those that might
not be familiar with metal Halli perov
skites I like to view them as this is
the unit cell the sort of tetragonal
system here but I like to view them as
has a series of these metal in this case
either lead or tin at the center o
octahedra with six of these apical
iodides or or halides in General on the
on the outskirts of it and then you have
this asight which is positively charged
which sort of has the right size to
scaffold this system and also charge
balance it to hold it together in this
three-dimensional octahedral Corner
sharing uh sort of uh Mantra and by
changing the or changing the metal you
can actually sweep the system's response
from the blue all the way out to the
near infrared and they're direct bandap
semiconductors so they're interesting
for all types of opto electronic devices
here's are some examples of LEDs and
lasers but the real success story has
been in in solar cells and this is a
little snapshot of the lower right hand
corner of enr's certified efficiency
chart and you can see that the
perovskite which sits here at 26.7%
is really just on the heels of Crystal
and silicon which is at
27.1% there and if you compare this to
other thinfilm Solar Technologies sigs
or cadel both around 23% or organic
which there are reports in literature
over 20% now but at least the highest
point on the chart here is just under 20
um really it it kind of puts them a bit
to shame to to have substantially higher
performance metrics at least on Day Zero
the issue with with perovskites and kind
of kind of what brings me here today to
talk to you about is not in their
initial efficiencies but rather in the
fact that those efficiencies don't hold
for an excruciatingly long period of
time for most Solar Technologies you
want that to hold for decade time scales
and that's indeed what silicon can do
but perovskites the best they've
demonstrated is somewhere in the
neighborhood of few thousand hours um
for degradation from its day one value
to you know a few thousand hours about
80% or so of that initial performance
and so when we talk about
degradation in my lab we've we've looked
at a bunch of different degradation
reactions and what we found is that the
the initiation right that first step
always falls into one of these two bins
first one being charge transfer and I I
kind of put this in in order of
importance so this is the first
important one the the most important
reaction that underscores the
degradation of these systems is some
kind of electrochemical or charge
transfer reaction and that's the one
that I'll spend most of my time here
talking to you about um and the
adjacency is an amine so lead can be
reduced you get this lead zero there's
there's still I think a lot of emphasis
about lead zero in the community I
deemphasize that um because I think if
you see lead zero you've pushed your
system so far beyond its limits that if
if that's your end end State I think
you're basically clinically dead at that
point so I I don't worry so much about
lead reduction anymore and I think the
primary lead reductant is an amine which
is actually the the the product of the
other main degradation reaction which is
an acidbase reaction or something
involving protons and so you have a lot
of Organo ammoniums in these systems if
it's deprotonated you can make an amine
and I think that's the primary then F
finally redox region for lead but I'm
not going to get into that today um the
other thing that can happen with am
meines and this is another uh adjacency
is a condensation reaction between
amines and form amidinium which also
spells a lot of problems for this system
structurally because I end up making
cations I like the most common one is
methyl formamidinium that are just too
big to fit in that perovskite lattice
and it kind of unfolds uh that system
leads to substantial strain and and
other things um but things like strain
things like ion migration I like to
think about them as consequences of one
of these two things and so these are
kind of the the original sin as it were
for Hali perovskite
degradation and here's a really simple
experiment that can be done in any lab
if I take a film of
aluminum um on a little piece of glass
and I dip it in methylammonium iodide
nothing happens but if I dip it in lead
iodide it gets completely corroded and
it goes away in seconds and what's
behind that is an electrochemical
reaction and this is a really
spontaneous one this is an obvious one
this is the one that we first published
six seven years ago now um sorry more
like eight years ago now um and so if
you have an easily oxidized and strongly
reductive metal like aluminum instead of
staying as pristine aluminum zero what
will happen is you'll have a metal metal
cation Redux reaction with lead 2 and
you will generate a lot of lead zero and
you'll generate a lot of aluminum 3 in
the process because uh aluminum 3 is has
a stronger electrochemical potential
than than than lead 2 to lead zero and
so that's the the end consequence this
is a very obvious one this is a
spontaneous one what I'm going to talk
to you mostly about today are less
spontaneous or non-spontaneous ones
these are ones that happen with the
application of stress either voltage
bias or light bias and we just published
a couple of weeks ago this perspective
in ACS energy letters and what we're
trying to do is go beyond ion migration
so ion migration is this often invoked
term in the literature of perovskites
but it doesn't really get to the core
and the Heart of what has happened yes
matter moves but what what mediates the
movement of matter the movement of ions
is actually some creation somewhere and
some Annihilation somewhere else and so
these are usually electrochemical
reactions and so behind ion migration is
some sort of electrochemical reaction
because they are the sources and the
syns of ions that end up
migrating and so here's a generic
framework for a device I have aaly
perovskite in the middle I have charge
transport layers on either side I have a
metal electrode on one side and usually
I have something like an an fully
oxidized metal like fto or I on the
other side and there are numerous things
that can happen I'm going to get into
these in the slides that follow um we
have uh potential bulk effects things
like you could have oxidation uh
reduction reactions forming interstitial
halides forming vacancies on the one
hand or you can have reactions on the
charg transport layer perovskite
interface and this could leech out
iodine or iodide which could then
ultimately oxidize metals and I can even
bring Metals into the into the picture
here and that's what we'll talk about
when we talk about doping in these
systems um and you know in order to make
progress here here's an example for the
one that I that keeps me up at night
which is interstitial iodide um and so
you know you have maybe a place here
where you can generate interstitial
iodide and halide vacancies you could
also have bulk generation you have bulk
Annihilation that's basically what's
known as self-healing basically these
prod these reactants or in this case the
products of this reaction are new newly
formed reactants to reform the
perovskite lattice and I can have
annihilation of these uh vacancies and
interstitials to join the lattice again
and so and that's all mediated by things
like generation Annihilation and mass
transport either drift or diffusion of
these interstitial ions this is this is
an effect the ion migration equation but
it needs to be merged with the the
equations of semiconductors continuity
equations Pon equation and so I think to
make progress we need to define the
reactions that happen the ones that are
most important and we need to develop
models that incorporate and merge these
chemical reactions with well-known
wellestablished semiconductor physics uh
equations and by kind of merging these
we can make a full assessment and a full
model in a mixed ionic electronic
context to better understand the
behavior of these
semiconductors so I'm going to show you
an example of an iodide redo cycle and
something that it does and and one thing
that we've established in my lab is that
iodide oxidation is the first thing that
happens which allows for Halli phase
separation so if I have a system that's
now a mixture of halides let's say a
mixture of iodide and bromide the
initiating step of redistribution of
this lattice is basically to create a
lot of vacancies so that stuff can move
around and the thing that creates that
vacancy is iodide getting oxidized
leaving the lce and now stuff can move
about ion migration can happen and this
is fully reversible you can go back and
collapse to the nearly well you know
well mixed uh AB mixed Halli system and
so here's how it works I have an anode
and a cathode anodes on the left
cathodes on the right and I have a
well-mixed x equals .5 uh halide system
in between if I put an anodic potential
on this so a potential difference
between the anode and cathode the as I
mentioned the first thing that we can
expect is iodide can get oxidized so
holes basically um oxidizing these
surface the ones on the left here iodide
atoms they leave the lattice they make
interstitials and now we have an
interstitial potential uh sorry an
interstitial diffusive gradient that's
going to cause interstitials to move to
the right we also have a field between
the positive anode and the negative
cathode that could also allow migration
of these interstitials toward the right
so whether it's diffusion whether it's
drift
uh you can think about it as you will
you also now have vacancies and these
vacancies will also be able to diffuse
and those vacancies are effectively
allowing bromide to net move toward the
left right because the the left the left
side is where iodide gets
oxidized and now I have a lot of
vacancies that have moved to the right
here and the electrons can reduce the
iodide so this is the closed circuiting
of this electrochemical cell they can
re-enter the lattice as negatively
charged iodide ions and the net result
is I have an iodide enriched cathode and
a bromide enriched anode and if I test
this experimentally we can see if we get
with if this hypothesis is true and so
we have a device here we have nickel
oxide on one side and we have C60 BCP
gold on the other side um initially we
can see the iodide the bromide and the
Le and the lead are all well distributed
vertically in this system and if we
forward bias the system meaning the top
is cathodically biased the bottom is
anodically biased that's my forward
biased situation you can see that the
iodide after some time here has
collected at the top the cathode and
bromide has collected at the bottom the
anode lead remains well distributed so
lead has little or nothing to say about
this it's the kind of scaffold that's
holding this whole thing together if I
flip the biasing and now the top is my
anode the bottom is my cathode you can
see the reverse situation has presented
itself the bottom has become enriched in
iodide depleted uh at the top the top
has become enriched in bromide and
depleted at the
bottom and so this kind of draws this
picture of an electrochemical cell
initiating by iodide o iodide redox
oxidation on one side reduction on the
other
and so this is the way we can sort of
schematically draw this we have our
anodic reaction which is iodide
oxidation and we have our cathodic
reaction which is iodide reduction and
all mediated by electrons and holes and
Hall vacancies on this lattice it's a
very simple closed form
situation now what if we do something
like we change out our electrode so
instead of gold which is a relatively
decent um anode in the presence of
iodide it's not readily etched by iodide
if we change it out with silver again we
have the situation where initially our
our system is well mixed iodide and
bromide and Lead they're all evenly
distributed if I forward bias this
device so silver is my cathode then I
get the same situation iodide is
enriched at the top bromide is enriched
at the bottom it all behaves very
similar to my gold situation but now I
reverse bias the situation and silver is
now my anode so what happens is silver
is more easily oxidized than iodide and
so I have effectively interrupted the
iodide redo cycle and if I've have done
that then if you believe me that iodide
redo iodide oxidation is at the core of
halide phase separation and
redistribution then because I've
interrupted iodide oxidation I no longer
have halight phase separation and that's
what I see iodide and bromide are all
both well distributed and equal to that
of the lead component and as a
consequence I'm actually bringing silver
into this system so silver is now
entering the lattice um as a consequence
because something had to had to have
gotten oxidized and in this case it was
silver and does anyone have a guess what
got
reduced remember I talked about doping
who has a guess what got reduced in the
process of pulling because remember redo
reactions they always have to happen
close close circuited you don't just
matter doesn't like being charged that's
why we have lightning to discharge stuff
but what got reduced when I oxidized
silver and brought it
in I think I heard someone Mumble it
this the Prof guite so the profy got
ended every metal cation that enters
that system the pery gets ended and so
that's going to that's my that's my f
the final part of this talk so I'm
trying to bring it around at the end but
remember this because this will come in
and be important when we talk about
reduction and doping the perov
guite okay so here's the situation here
when my silver is a cathode it's just
the same I have anodic and cathodic
reactions that involve iodide but when I
have silver as an anode now instead of
iodide getting oxidized it's silver that
gets oxidized and I end up creating all
these silver uh interstitials and that's
what is is sort of taking over when I
when I oxidize the
system and so this is only an issue for
mixed Halli systems at high biases right
like we don't have to worry about iodide
oxidation in pure iodide systems do
we yeah we do okay so let's let's talk
about it so we definitely have to worry
about it even the absence of bromide um
here's a schematic diagram showing the
kinds of things we need to be concerned
about and I I just want to impress upon
you lead reduction is not in this
slide because I don't really worry about
lead reduction anymore I don't think
that I think that is not something that
really is important to this system when
again when lead is reduced you you've
pushed it way too far and so this is
taking the archetypal methylammonium
lead iodide I need to worry about at the
anode I need to worry about iodide
oxidation when I have a whole transport
layer I need to be very worried about
the fact that it can react with oxidized
iodides we'll get to that in a moment
and then the reduction reaction I need
to be worried about um ma reduction
methylammonium being reduced in which
case I've have destroyed the system
start total Destruction but I also have
to be worried about gold oxidation when
I make triiodide which I will make in a
whole transport layer triiodide is very
easy to make in a whole transport layer
and triiodide is an especially fantastic
gold eent and so I need to be worried
about gold oxidation and gold reduction
at the fto interface where it's
cathodically biased and so let's look at
the voltage biased thresholds for these
different
phenomena so what I'm showing here are a
little hard to read but these are
cross-sectional Toof Sims
uh
um I don't know what you call them
rograms I guess
um depth profiles thank you Tonio um so
what I'm looking at here is the the
profile for gold as well as in the dash
lines the profile for tin which is
showing me where the fto perov interface
is that's what the dashed ones are and
so the gold what we see is that 6 volts
7 volts it's not enough to have any gold
in the system there's basically no gold
and then at some point I've what I've
done is I've effectively pile drived the
gold to that gold fto interface but this
was just the remnant of what we had
scraped what we had neglected to get off
when I when we peeled off the gold
contact and so you see some gold that
shows up here but now when I go to 08
volts 09 volts one volt you can start to
see massive amounts of gold in this
system if I add a spiral layer on top
you can see that I need to push it a
little bit higher and that's basically
because of the voltage drop on the
spiral layer but these are still
shockingly low voltages 1.3 volts 1.2
volts and I'm able to start getting
substantial gold signals that enter this
perov SK so these very low
electrochemical thresholds for gold
oxidation in the presence of triiodide
which if you're oxidizing iodide you're
making
triiodide and for those that would
prefer to see this in kind of a real
space image if you take a system you can
see gold entered and then when you
remove the bias it will actually get
reduced again and you have these gold
colloids that form inside the perovskite
system and it's hard to see here because
we just took a little slice but we know
from XPS profiling if you wash off all
the perov skite there's gold that has
plated out at the at the oxide interface
as
well so I mentioned about Spyro that's
that's the well-known sort of whole
transport material in perov skite solar
cells and these systems there have been
numerous observations in literature of
iodine just soaking these these htms but
what dictates this infiltration is
actually the fact that when I have a
shallow homo system like Spyro and the
shallowness basically needs to be
shallower than 5.4 EV I have loads of
electrons at relatively low potential
and those electrons are capable
of reducing iodine and therefore getting
pooped um as a result of exposure to any
oxidized iodide if I have a deep homo
system I don't get a lot of this
infiltration because those electrons
just don't exist at relatively shallow
potential and here's an example of
iodine in Spyro so I want to draw your
attention to the
lead um carbon interface here this one
between orange and blue you can see
there's a pretty abrupt interface
between those two profiles between
methyl L iodide in Spyro look at how
much iodine has just soaked into this
system and that's just spontaneous upon
spinning Spyro on top of an iodide
perovskite substantial amounts of iodine
leeches in and if I put a bias on this
thing go to 6 volts not much happens 7
volts look at my iodine signature it's
gone up 8 volts it's gone up even more
and if I put this back in the temm after
1 volt for 20 for 12 hours you can see
this zone of I infiltration has expanded
and so iodine that gets oxidized will
readily enter and dope and you make a
very high a very pooped Spyro at this
interface and as such it kind of makes a
really nice Omi contact it's a great Omi
contact um but it also has its other
drawbacks as well because I now have
this this possible bath and source of
triiodide which is
dangerous um we've measured iodine
diffusion rates basically the same way
that a calcium test works so calcium is
a good test for uh IOD uh sorry oxygen
or humidity we've basically taken the
calcium test which which uh basically
you're looking at how much time it takes
for calcium to be oxidized and rendered
uh insulating in the presence of oxygen
or water and we've just ported it over
to iodine and so silver is a good is a
good one because silver doesn't care
about the presence of oxygen in water
but iodine will quickly render it in
insulating and so we can measure the
amount of time it takes to upon exposure
to an iodine ambient for that silver to
be uh decommissioned to be rendered
insulating and non-conductive and uh
taking two examples here here's poly tpd
shallow homopolymer you can see it
renders UNC conductive within 200
seconds and pvk a much deeper
homopolymer and you can see it holds on
substantially longer and you can fit
these transients to understand the
diffusion Coe ience in these systems or
iodine permeability as it were and what
we see is that shallow homo Organics
whether they're small molecule whether
thermally evaporated whether they
polymers um spin coated anything that's
shallow you have quick diffusion of
iodine anything that's deeper and you
have much slower diffusion and this
energy around here is what we associate
to this iodine I triiodide iodide redo
couple it's going to be somewhere in
here and that's kind of where we see
massive transition from Fast re Redux
mediated iodine transport to much slower
redo mediated iodine
transport and unfortunately I put a gulp
here the methylammonium Le iodide or or
any iodide perov skites its homo energy
sits right here so if I want a whole
transport layer that's capable of
injecting or extracting holes from the
perovskite it's also unfortunately
capable being doped by iodine and being
this sort of uh readily uh mobile uh
circuit for iodine
transport to close this picture we can
see that iodine also dopes these shallow
whole transport layer organic so we can
see that the Delta I the change in
current upon exposure is huge the
shallower the homo I have because I'm
effectively doping it uh better and
therefore the conductivity goes up to
finally close that Loop using perovskite
as the iodine source so if I have this
stack here and what I'm what I'm
checking here is the conductivity of the
organic Bridge we can see the same Trend
so if I irradiate the perovskite and
then I shut off the irradiation what
happens is the I can measure the
transport of the organic which in the
absence of light is way more conductive
than the perovskite the perovskite is
very photo conductive Ive but actually
in the dark it's very insulating and so
I can actually look at the transport in
the organic and I can see the same Trend
iodine is leeched out from IR radiation
photolysis of the perovskite and I can
see this change in conductivity in that
organic whole transport
layer okay so um I still have some time
here so what happens when iodide is
oxidized so we unfortunately figured out
that there's also a Catal IC cycle that
can go on between iodide oxidation and
the organoammonium
cation in the hybrid organic inorganic
perovskites and it goes something like
this if you have your um halide
perovskite then I at some point will
oxidize iodide any oxidized iodide in
this in the presence of other Lattis
iodide will basically make triiodide and
fortunately as I'll show in the next
slide triiodide is a strong enough base
to deprotonate either formamidinium or
methylammonium in the case of for
amidinium I break it down into hcn and
ammonia in the case of methylammonium I
break it down into methylamine and um
the uh the subsequent hi is the final
product and then I make hi3 this is not
a very stable product and So eventually
I make hi and I2 and I2 in the presence
of more iodide I just make triiodide
again and so I have this unfortunate
catalytic cycle only one has to happen
and it just keeps going and yes this one
will actually make if I if I do this in
the presence of methylammonium I will
see lots of lead zero and that's because
of this amine which is a reducing agent
toward lead and so you will see lead
zero upon this catalytic reaction if you
have methylammonium
around so here's what happens if I have
Fai and and I put a little bit of iodine
in the solution I will make fa
triiodide and that induces the formation
of this type of species here which
basically forms a six-membered ring
encompassing the formamidinium cation
and triiodide and in the case of
methylammonium it's effectively uh in
both cases they're hydrogen bonded very
strongly hydrogen bonded and
unfortunately so strongly that uh with
time this leads to the the the breaking
of this complex into uh the constituent
components that I showed you this
ultimate
deprotonation and unfortunately for fa
when I deprotonate it it's complete
degradation the B the products that fa
deprotonation forms cannot reform form
aminium with methylammonium
actually if I make methylamine in hii it
there's a pretty strong push toward
reforming the methylammonium but not in
the case of fa that's
that's a one-way Street to to being
degraded so we asked the question if we
could stop this cycle and the the
effective the the most effective means
that we saw was could we put something
here something there that could act as
an iodine reductant so if iodide is ever
oxidized could it just interrupt it we
know there's one silver not a good one
because we don't want silver entering
the lattice maybe there's another system
that we could use as like this
intermediate to if any Ox iodide is
oxidized maybe it will push it right
back to
iodide and we drew inspiration from
actually biochemical processes
where thols are uh pretty good reducing
agents and what we wanted to do was
actually uh see if we could use thols to
reduce iodine and then make the
disulfide compounds and therefore
interrupt this catalytic
cycle and as as one thing that I want to
show you just because it's nicely
drawing out from what I what I showed
you a few slides back if I take a system
like Spyro with an iodide perovskite I'm
showing here again that iodine can leech
into the spiral layer you see this black
Trace is the iodine that has really uh
infiltrated the Spyro and if I put this
thol between Spyro and the perite you
can see that the iodine and Lead traces
follow each other very well and that's
because it's actually holding back the
iodide from being uh infiltrated because
it's never actually getting uh
oxidized without being just reformed
into iodide through the action of this
thol
compound it doesn't appear to compromise
the performance of the systems which is
good um it it might improve it but
statistically let's just say it doesn't
HT it which is already a good thing and
this is really just a vanishingly thin
coating of this thol compound which we
only tried three of them um whether this
R Group is methoxy or hydrogen or
Florine um it appears to sort of
preserve the performance of these
devices which is which is great um if we
look at the the stability we can see
that a few of them particular the either
the
fluorinated um the fluorinated compound
um or the methoxy compound are pretty
good at preserving the stability even at
85c which uh some of the these
cross-sectional analyses show really
allows iodine to permeate that spiral
layer but some of these Fales kind of
hold that permeation back and therefore
hold some of this degradation
um back as well and I think a lot of the
Spyro uh instabilities thermal
instabilities I know there's been some
work from mji Bend's group on this I
think a lot of its sources from iodine
infiltrating that system and interacting
with some of the other uh stuff in the
spiral layer so maybe one one solution
might be remove some of those additives
another solution is just don't let
iodine to enter it in the first place uh
and maybe doing both is is the sort of
better solution uh but I to my knowledge
that hasn't been attempted what we've
done is we've looked into trying to
replace Spyro with other compounds and
in this case we took this pretty
well-known whole transport layer from
the OLED field and it's readily doped by
Molly oxide it's also readily doped by
iodine but if we if we co- evaporate
this compound empty data with Molly
oxide we strongly P do it and we also
increase its its density and uh the
action of sort of pre-doping it with mly
oxide really holds back a lot of iodine
if you look at the Spyro system up here
you can see that the reason why it's on
the top of this waterfall plot is
there's so much iodine that's in that
system and you can see after analing a
lot more of it but if I take something
that holds back iodine in this case this
this composite of empty data and Molly
oxide you can see that it manages to
keep in check the iodine in that whole
transport layer and as such it can
really withstand substantially more
stress at higher temperatures so 60c
isn't enough to do much but 70c is
already enough to absolutely uh destroy
the Spyro the conventional doped Spyro
system and uh I I think that has a lot
to do with with iodine oxidation and and
infiltration into these
media so what about doping this is the
last part of my talk here um that should
be easy right as just a reduction
reaction um and ideally it's an
irreversible one and this this is one
nagging issue this
irreversibility um because perovskites
do feature ion migration and those a lot
of ions will just come in and change the
they'll kind of be be a sort of anti-c
correlating species to if you want to
affect change say dop it something else
will come in and just stymy that that
potential uh reaction and this is a lot
this has to do a lot with with our lack
of substantial success with doping per
op skites in general um the way we
started down this path was with using
molecular oxidants this is a well-known
one this Molly tfd compound strong
oxidizing agent what we see is that
putting this on the surface does in fact
make a much deeper work function but you
can see the conductivity of the system
is basically unchanged and so what has
happened with such a system is I'm
doping it but I'm just doping the
surface it's not doing anything to the
bulk properties of the perovskite and so
the picture I can draw and you can see
the the bulk actually the the XPS shows
uh even the core levels are shifting not
just the work function but everything is
really shifting so the system the
surface is really getting ptype doped
but it's not infiltrating the bulk and
so it's just a surface doping
nevertheless you can make a really close
analogy with a type of early silic solar
cell the the the screen printed aluminum
BSF solar cell back surface field and
the back here is basically p-doped and
it does promote whole collection so
devices are are actually aided by
putting a little p dooped back surface
on an nip type structure it's not it's
not necessarily a bad thing but it
doesn't really get to the core of of
true doping so then we tried using
cesium Le bromide nanocrystals see if we
could dope those through
electrochemistry the way this works is
pretty simple you put your cesium Le
bromide nanocrystals on a Surface in
this case I you immerse it in an
electrolyte uh in this case I think it
was uh
tea I forget pf6 I can't remember the
the counter C the counter anion um but
you inject electron from the I electrode
and every time you inject an electron
you attach one of these uh bulky
ammonium cation to the surface and
that's electrochemical
doping we were very careful not to go
beyond the electrochemical stable window
in the case of cesium Le bromide for us
that was about minus .9 volts to.5 volts
if you push Beyond it you see all kinds
of electrochemistry unfolding and you
are reducing lead you see lead zero in
the system you are evolving bromine um
so that's not a good idea but if you
stay within stabil the stability window
you can see a sort of nicely reversible
cycling and you can get real change here
you can get work function to the tune of
of shifts half more than half an EV um
and it's also seen in the core levels
not just the work function this is work
together with antoan Khan who's an
expert on electron spectroscopy and dop
and you can also see changes to
conductivity so you could see about a
factor of 20 increase in conductivity
when I end do the system and that was
that was coming together with an
increase in pl we said oh this is great
this is going to make this is going to
allow us to make a great led a great
laser diode we've end oped this system
um the pl got brighter that's great and
unfortunately also the lifetime got
longer and that's inconsistent with radi
creative re combination if I'm doping
this system if I'm adding electrons to
it free electrons to it my lifetime
should go down when my PL goes up but we
did not see that we saw that PL went up
and lifetime also went up and so what we
what we suggest it's hard to know but
what we think is that the injected
electrons are actually filling traps and
our increase in conductivity is actually
more or less an increase in Mobility
because we're basically making the
system a better electron transporter
we're not actually
adding free electrons to that system so
back to square one it's really hard to
dope these systems um so we went back to
this device and we thought more about
Metal
infiltration and we wanted to see if
every time a metal cation enters this
lattice do I actually end do it is that
the other side of the redox
equation we uh got the aid of leor
chonic at the white Institute in Israel
they did some density functional theory
on a gold interstitial and what they
found was that the gold interstial
transition level sits somewhere in the
conduction band in other words or and
right at the edge in other words if you
do have a gold plus
interstitial it should come along for
the ride with an electron that should be
the kind of stable state of a gold plus
interstitial and the the the the system
will ALS also end up changing the the
iodide transition will also go from
minus to plus and that'll come along for
the ride as well so you're going to
change the interstitial population of
iodide but you also add electrons to the
system and that's basically coming along
with the change of fmy level will shift
my interstitial population of iodide
from maybe some plus some minus to the
primarily minus along with free
electrons in the system so that's what
that's what their calculations indicated
and so we conducted these
very very simple uh tests this is
looking at current as a function of time
for different step UPS in the voltage
and what we saw was that initially we
had reasonable conduction and we thought
this was initially ptype conduction the
familyy level that we typically measure
of metal methylammonium Le iodide on fto
the familyy level sits slightly in the
ptype range and so it's consistent with
some kind of ptype hold dominated
conduction initially and then as a
function of time you can see that
eventually the conduction goes down and
I go through this plateau and we think
this is where you're basically
compensating that semiconductor so had
an initial hole population every time I
inject an uh gold interstitial I also
inject an electron and that is
compensating the system it's becoming
basically insulating you can see my
current falls off and then eventually my
current comes back up when I achieve n
type doping and that was consistent with
uh the the impedance analysis that we
did as well uh so this what we think is
happening you have initially ptype
conduction then the system becomes
compensated and then eventually you get
an N type medium and the
photoluminescence that I show that that
I'm not going to show here also agrees
with this we get PL that uh sort of goes
down when I enter this compensated
region when bimolecular recombination is
really bad right when I have almost no
electrons or holes around you see that
that uh low in conductivity is also
Associated to a low in
PL and so in conclusion um I I I would
really encourage you to treat perovskite
devices as electronic devices and
electrochemical cells in order to go
beyond the term ion migration and really
try to understand these systems at their
core um and stabilizing and doping these
materials presents a major challenge but
I think if if if we can adopt in Earnest
this type of approach I think we can
make some some real change and and
progress um with that I'd like to thank
the some of the agencies that helped
fund this the department of Energy's e
wing as well as the Office of Naval
Research and finally thank you for your
attention thank you thank you
very thanks for a great talk so we have
time for few questions uh if you have
questions we have microphones we'll pass
them around and and online if you have
any questions please type your
questions um I'm going to take you up on
the second point there uh or no the
first point there that they go Way
Beyond um ion
migration um 50 years ago I did a lot of
work in Al halides not profes but Al
halides
trying to uh dope them with excess
hallogen and that was done principally
with potassium iodide dope with iodin
under extremely high
pressures and one gets the same um
intertial type populations that one does
with the radiation of alkal halides and
what that shows is that the um the
iodine um in this case um uh binds with
the cat the annion at the annion sites
and forms
molecular interstitials so your I3 minus
actually uh is uh really uh a um an
intertial which is actually attached to
lce ion and yes it's essentially split
interstitials round aat ofite um also
the system generates um cation and
annion
vacancies uh and um these and that's
because of the pressure of the iodine
what happens is the interstitials
actually can occupy um at whatever
temperature um this is this is done at
um annion and cation vacancies it's a
way of actually stabilizing that
interstitial population um which leads
to the form of dislocation Loops which
in fact are found in the potassium
iodide which has been heavily doped with
iodine so what I'm suggesting here is it
not only goes a long way Beyond ion
migration but it gets into the realm of
extremely complex defect structures in
ionic systems and I think you have to be
aware of this um you can try to identify
the species but you can only really
understand the species of defects you
have in the system which also can lead
to the transport phenomena you see um if
you think about the reaction with the uh
Cs and anions and other defect
populations in your perovskites it's a
very complicated system and uh uh but
and I resonate with your first point
there but I think it has to be done
there has to be a lot of defect
spectroscopy done here to really
understand um what's happening in this
system it doesn't change the calculus of
what you know charges transport and so
forth but it does change the way you
think about the diffusion of these
defects a lot I'd like to pick your
brain about what type of spectroscopy
would be you know identifying these
defect levels because they are six seven
orders of magnitude below the lce sight
density epr is one of them of course and
and and there's been some work done with
NMR of course as well see um um I don't
know if these are transparent at all but
um in any in any uh wavelength between
infrared and
UltraViolet and if if they are you can
actually do some color under
spectroscopy but my guess is you may not
be able to do that yeah yeah I think one
of one of the main concern one of the
main issues not concerns one of the main
issues with these systems that they tend
to actually be relatively defect immune
which means
means non-native species or native
defects don't tend to occupy electronic
sites within the Gap so they tend not to
be visible and your your primary
exitation event is still that of the Gap
and and and that's kind of what makes at
least in in our experience direct
measurement Elusive and so we've had to
turn to close to the conduction or
veillance bands yes okay yes yeah and
that has made for us at least direct
measurement Elusive and then we've sort
of had to just kind of interpolate it
okay good yeah I have other
questions
questions okay Barry maybe you can
comment on your choice of the thile
molecule and you mentioned you've tried
three two three of them what goes into
selecting the right material you
know it was so we worked together with
Jeff Schwarz now in ameritus faculty of
chemistry and he wanted something that
was uh relatively thermally stable you
know wouldn't it wouldn't it wouldn't be
a liquid at room temperature it be a
solid at room temperature and also
relatively small so that it wouldn't be
this big uh sort of insulating monster
between the transport layer and the
perov skate and we decided and we also
want it to be commercially available so
we decided on these compounds as being
kind of like a neat compromise and there
was also rather synthetic differences in
them like the art the AR could be
swapped out again commercially there has
since been some work we tried we tried
alkal thyes we those are obviously
readily commercially available but they
we didn't have much success with them we
think they just make a relatively large
insulating barrier and the the
processing window for those to be
successful might just be very small but
the there was recent work from Alex
Jen's group at Hong Kong where they
where they found a thol that you know I
think works better than the one that we
showed and they and they they ascribe
the success to a similar thing it kind
of mediates iodide oxidation um sort
interrupts it I would say it reduces it
back and I I we haven't tried that one
in our lab but I'd be curious to attempt
that one because your I mean the catalog
of thols is enormous enormous and so it
would be it's very challenging to try to
identify uh which one to use
great any questions from the
audience sure any questions online okay
if not we do have a reception let's
thank Professor rant again thank you
all thank you Barry so we we're going to
have a reception so so please stay back
and Professor Rand will be here to
answer any questions you have or if you
want to talk one onone