The AI and rationality course that we're
[music] teaching uh examines really the
the the value of thinking about
machines, complicated computer systems
as if they were rational. That is the
way we think about humans. And so we
think about humans, each other, as if we
[music] have beliefs about the world,
about as if we have desires what we
would like to have be true. [music]
And we think of a rational human as
taking actions that will achieve their
[music] goals. And so uh in the class we
think about how can that be a helpful
view for building AI systems. Um and we
can think of it as a helpful view
[music] for talking about AI systems. We
can also think about it potentially as
inspiring an engineering approach to
building such systems.
>> I think there's two two places where
philosophy really interacts with
computing. One is about the nature of
rational agency and what it is to have
beliefs and desires and to be an
autonomous intelligent agent and have a
mind. Uh the other is ethics where we're
concerned about the social impacts of
these technologies that are changing our
world really quickly and we want to
think through how should we design
systems to achieve good outcomes and
avoid harms and risks.
>> And I think it's important when I work
with students who study machine learning
or robotics that they step back a bit
and examine the assumptions that they're
making. So often a technical field will
just make a bunch of assumptions and not
even state them and everyone operates
under assuming that they're true. But in
many cases they're not so warranted. And
so thinking about things from a
philosophical perspective helps people
back up and understand better how to
situate their work in the actual
context.
>> I think I'm probably an unusual student
in this course because I actually don't
do AI or philosophy. [music]
Um actually I do cognitive science. So
my main interests are in human
intelligence. [music] Um but a dominant
paradigm in my field is to what extent
are humans rational [music] and I think
to really understand how to engage in
that question you sort of need to
understand what it means to be rational
and I think philosophy [music] and AI um
have ideas about the fundamentals of
rationality and machine learning
algorithms are attempting to build
intelligent agents to [music]
um act rationally in the world. So I
wanted to have that interdicciplinary
[music] perspective to understand my own
field. I think what surprised me the
most about this course is [music] that
uh the math and the logic off of which
um all of this machine learning theory
[music] is based off of can lead to
machines taking actions that [music]
seem irrational, right? We're kind of
taught that math and logic are like this
[music] kind of golden standard or
truth, right? It must be um that if
something is mathematically or logically
consistent or correct, it must be
rational. But this class showed us a
variety of examples where [music] um at
least humans don't behave uh in
consistency with these mathematical and
logical frameworks. So other uh choices
of action seem more rational to us. And
then we open this whole can of worms as
to whether is it humans that are irr
irrational? Is it the machine learning
uh system that we designed irrational?
Is it math and logic itself? um and the
different implications of different
definitions of rationality.
>> When we're thinking about ethics and AI
technologies, I think there it's hard to
give a a sort of quick answer. And the
part of the reason is that AI is
extremely broad. It goes well beyond the
sort of you know chat GPT paradigm of
large language models with chat bots.
It's it's in our cars. You use it when
you use Google maps whenever we've got
uh you know facial recognition
technologies. And each of these
technologies is going to raise very
different issues. So if you're thinking
about automated hiring tools to decide
who to who to hire for a certain job,
you might be concerned about bias
against certain demographic groups. If
you're thinking about facial recognition
technology, you might be concerned about
privacy and surveillance. If you're
thinking about a chat GPT sort of
technology, you might be concerned that
it doesn't spew out racist content or
advise people in how to commit crimes.
So each of these different technologies
is going to raise a a very different set
of ethical considerations.
>> Given that the rate of progress in AI
and related technologies, it's
impossible to teach students what
they're going to need to know 5 years
from now at the basic level. So what we
need to do is give them the tools at a
higher level, the habits of mind,
[music] the ways of thinking that will
help them approach the stuff that we
can't really anticipate right now.
>> [music]