hello everybody and thank you so much
for coming today my name is Daphne and
I'm the CEO and co-founder of hereon AI
and I believe that companies like yours
with all of your resources affect change
on a global scale every single day but
are those resources being utilized as
effectively as they possibly could be
what if I were to tell you that in the
next decade 75% of accountants plan to
retire who here relies on accounting
professionals I know that I do so this
is actually going to leave a really
large gap in business analytics and so
let me give you a quick example my
friend Steve he is a VP at a Fortune 100
company he oversees about 200 staff and
a $500 million budget and even Steve is
having issues generating reports for a
quarterly meeting Steve is already
seeing turnover in his financial
analysts and accountants and because of
this it's now taking Steve about four
months to generate reports that should
take less than a
week with Steve uh he has over a dozen
people that work with him and what ends
up happening is he gets about a 5inch
thick binder with 150 different tabs and
this all culminates with the CEO flying
in a 100 senior Executives coming to the
table they go line by line through these
documents to make decisions about their
company does this sound familiar to
anybody
here and even after all of this it's
still still takes a lot of time to
actually Implement these
decisions so I know that I was like
Steve when I was in my first company I
was generating literally gigabytes of
data to try to understand the health of
my business the health of my clients
businesses and it was taking too much
time and I have a PhD in this stuff and
because of that I decided to do what any
Sayan person would do and I built my own
platform uh this platform was the point
of it was to expedite my uh analytics so
there was a client portal clients could
sign in and within seconds they would be
able to see how things were going with
their business based on the services
that we were
providing today we call this Heron AI
Heron AI is able to connect with over
150 different sources including Legacy
systems that you may be using one other
benefit of hereon AI is that we actually
have the ability to analyze clean and
visualize Excel data and this can be
done in under five
minutes on top on top of that when we
are able to ingest the data we have a
proprietary method that cleans your data
whether it's from an API or from an
Excel sheet from there it will analyze
that data also using proprietary methods
and then it will be able to geniz uh
generate customized dashboards and also
reports and this is now all done within
five minutes versus several
months so Steve decided to switch over
to use here on AI he connected some of
his leg software his Excel he was able
to connect that basically 5in thick
binder and what he was able to get out
in less than five minutes was not only
entire dashboards that he could now
utilize to track how things were going
in his Department he was also able to
get some action items that were telling
him where were his dependencies where
could he diversify his income were there
certain accounts receivables that he
really needed to be paying attention to
and the best part of this is that it he
could sync his data at any point in time
and these action items would update so
that as he progressed as he worked
through these action items now there
were new ones so that he could continue
to grow and focus on value
creation 81% of Corporations still
utilize Legacy software and still
utilize Excel today I know that I
absolutely do and I'm sure that there
are some people in this audience who do
as well if you're like me if you're like
Steve you really want to get more
insight out of this information this
super critical information that you're
spending a lot of money and time
collecting currently we are looking for
poc's we are uh fully developed and
we're about to be stocked to uh
compliant we also are about 16% more
accurate than the leading agentic
software in the market because of some
of the proprietary steps that we take
and so if you are somebody on this
screen or maybe even in another industry
please find me and come talk to me I
would love to talk to you about how here
on AI could help Drive some value
creation and growth for you thank you so
much and have a great day