So this is the second day of our of our
little unit on random walks on groups.
And the first day we introduced it. Um
and uh the second day we'll describe
some of some more modern stuff. And the
second day will be a little bit more of
a survey. I won't prove everything. Um
but I'll try to um uh and in the second
day we'll see how it connects to
projection theory.
Okay. So first let's recall what we're
where we were talking about
[Applause]
Okay,
so we have a finite group G and then we
have a probability measure on G
and we have an operator T mu. T mu of F
is F convolved with mu
and so this is like a does a step of a
random walk. So if f is the probability
distribution at some moment then you
make a step of the random walk end and
then t muf is the new probability
distribution.
Okay. Um so t mu of one is one the
constant function one and t mu maps the
functions of mean zero. So these are
functions whose sum to zero or have mean
zero. It maps it to itself. Um and sigma
1 of t mu is the largest singular value
of this.
Okay. And we saw that sigma 1 of t mu is
related to the mixing behavior of this
random walk. So um we always have that
sigma 1 of t mu is less than or equal to
one and uh actually we don't it's a
positive number and and sigma 1 of t mu
is strictly less than one then that
gives some kind of mixing of the random
walk we made that precise last time
okay um next we focused on the group
SL2FP PE
and one one special feature of this
group came from representation theory.
So we had a proposition that
um if you have a representation of this
of this group.
So that's a unitary
representation and let's say it's
non-trivial.
Then D has to be pretty big.
Okay.
And we use that to prove a mixing
estimate. mixing estimate says that if
mu is a probability measure on on this
group
um then sigma 1 of t mu is bounded by p
^ 2 * mu l2
for example if a is just a sub a subset
of sl2 fp then there's a uniform measure
on a Mua
and it's straightforward to check that
it's L2 norm squared mu aa L2 norm 2 is
1 over the size of a.
So a corlary is that if a is
significantly bigger than p^2 then the
random walk using a mixes rapidly.
So correlary
if for instance a is bigger than p to
the 2.1
um then
then sigma 1 of ta so I'll write ta it's
an abbreviation for t mua sigma 1 of ta
would be smaller than something like p
to the - one10th so it would mix quite
rapidly
okay so this is this is a nice
proposition and it's kind of sharp of
its type because if the set A is a
subgroup of SL2FP
then it the random walk will not
generate will not mix at all and there
are subgroups or easy subgroups that
have size around P^ squ so we can't we
can't do better than this
so remark
that this corary is sharp
uh because there exists
H a proper subgroup
size of H around P square. So for
instance, H is the upper triangular
matrices. Yeah,
>> if you had for a different group a
similar proposition where you can lower
bound the dimension of the of a
non-trivial unit, could you also use
that as an upper bound for the sigma one
for that group?
>> Yeah. So the question is if we had an
analog of this proposition for some
other group say SLDFP
um then could we do this whole story for
for all these other groups? Yeah, you
could. This is that's all that we've
used so far.
Yeah. Okay, cool. Um okay. So then also
last class we stated an old theorem
which goes rather it's older than this
proposition but it goes rather it does
not obviously follow from it.
So theorem this theorem is essentially
due to Selberg um although he didn't say
it in quite this way. Um so here a so we
pick okay so a is a particular list of
generators of sl2fp.
[Applause]
Okay. So this is perhaps the simplest
set of generators of sl2fp but is also
somewhat special in a way we'll talk
about when we talk about the proof.
Okay. So then the conclusion is that
sigma 1 of t a is less than 1 minus c
where c is positive and c is uh this is
true for every p. So c does not depend
on p.
So these all mix uniformly fast.
Okay. So this theorem is not an
immediate corlary of this proposition
because this is a much smaller set. Um
and uh okay so today there are a couple
of goals in in this survey. The first
goal is to sketch a proof of this
theorem in which this proposition plays
a key role but we'll see some other
ideas and a second goal is to discuss
what happens if you replace what was
special about this generating set at all
and what happens if we replace it by
some other generating set.
Okay.
Okay. Um,
cool. So, the first proof was due to
Selberg basically, but um, that proof
was quite difficult. It used the an used
a bunch of stuff including the remon
hypothesis for curves over finite
fields. Um, we're going to uh follow a
later proof
which is due to Sarnac and Shuer and
perhaps simplified or adjusted a bit by
by various people.
Okay,
cool.
Um, all right.
So, this set is uh symmetric, meaning
that uh if you if a group element is in
the set, so is the inverse. Um, and so
we could say that mu is symmetric
if mu of g is equal to mu of g inverse
for every g and g.
And um t mu actually is it's a bit nicer
if mu is symmetric. Um and here's why.
So remark mu is symmetric that is
equivalent to saying that the operator t
mu is symmetric as a matrix.
And so because so if you think of T mu
as a matrix then it has a g1 g2 entry
and the g1 g2 entry is mu of g1 g2
inverse. So if you switch these you're
taking the inverse of that and uh if mu
is symmetric that doesn't matter. So
it's a symmetric matrix.
Okay so that's nice because a symmetric
matrix you can diagonalize it and
instead of just having singular values
it has igen values. So once tu is a
symmetric matrix then the first singular
value of t mu to the k is the first
singular value of t mu to the k.
It helps to have a blackboard to sit.
Okay. And so that suggests a this is
helpful. This isn't true for
non-ymmetric matrices but it's true for
symmetric matrices. And it suggests a
strategy of how to get a handle on sigma
1 of t mu. So we can say the following
thing. Um
so we have sigma 1. Yeah. Let's also
think about t mu to the k. So t mu to
the k of f is f convolved with mu and
then convolved with mu and so on k times
uh which is f convolved with mu
convolved with itself k times.
So that's an operator of our type but
with a new measure. The measure is mu
convolved with itself k times.
Okay. So therefore sigma 1 of t mu to
the k sigma 1 t mu to the k
which is sigma 1 of t mu to the k. Uh
so if you try to explain this without a
blackboard, you have to have really
good ability to invoke things with your
voice.
All right.
Okay. So mu might be um the uniform
measure on this set of four elements A.
And if we apply this proposition
directly to that set of four elements,
it gives us nothing. But we can use this
and then we can try to apply the
proposition to mu to the k.
Um so if we put together what we have
can make the following corlary. Um sigma
1 t mu to the k. So okay so this is if
mu is a probability measure
on SL2 or fp
um then
sigma 1 of t mu to the k it's bounded by
well this thing and for this thing we we
can apply our proposition here
so we get
p ^ 2 * mu 2 * k L2.
Okay.
Um so the original for for the original
if you take the subbook measure a then
for the original mua um this thing would
be much too big to be interesting. But
perhaps we could find a high power k
where this L2 norm is actually smaller
than 1 over p^2 and that would give us
an interesting bound.
Okay,
cool. So, so all of the stuff that we'll
that we'll talk about today is based on
this corollary. Um, so we can think
about it like this. You start off with
the probability measure mu. We want to
know if does it get really evenly mixed
if you convolve it with itself a lot of
times. And what we'll see here is that
maybe if you convolve it with itself a
bunch of times, it will get
fairly well mixed. Not spectacularly
well mixed, but just fairly well mixed
to guarantee that this L2 norm is
smaller than 1 over P^2.
So if if it manages to be kind of
roughly evenly distributed around P to
the 2.1 elements in this group, that
would be good enough that this would be
less than one.
Once that happens, we can use this
correlary and we can bound sigma 1.
And once we bound sigma one, then we'll
see that that in turn tells us what
happens as we keep mixing. Then we'll be
able to say it gets really very well
mixed at some later time.
Okay. Okay. But how can we so how can we
bond this? How can we approach uh show
that that mu tensor k is is decently
well mixed fairly well mixed. Um okay.
So there are two different um approaches
that we'll talk about today. What so one
approach which is special for this
theorem involves either um
uh let me say it involves lifting to
SL2Z
um andor it involves hyperbolic
geometry. I'll describe it in a couple
of different slightly different ways.
Okay. So first let's talk about lifting
to SL2Z.
Okay. So if you reduce mod P it gives a
group homorphism from SL2Z to SL2F.
Okay. Um
so let's suppose that M is a probability
measure
on SL2Z
and mu is the push forward pi P of M. So
that's a probability measure here.
And this setup with group homorphisms
commutes plays nicely with convolution.
So um if I take the push forward of m
convolved with itself k times I will get
mu convolved with itself k times.
Okay, so one approach to try to
understand mu convolved with itself a
bunch of times is to first try to
understand m convolved with itself a
bunch of times and then try to
understand what happens when we perform
this push word.
Um okay
cool so here's our plan
study
m convolve with itself k times to the
push forward operation.
Okay,
so this is a a reasonable strategy
because of the fact or to the extent
that we feel that SL2Z is easier to get
our hands on than SL2FP.
Um, okay. And there is a there are a
couple of reasons that SL2Z is easier to
get our hands on than SL2FP.
Let me call this um good features
of SL2Z.
Okay, we won't necessarily use all of
these but let me mention them. So the
first feature is that SL2Z
is virtually free.
So what virtually means is that there is
a subgroup H and SL2Z
which is a finite index
free subgroup.
So in general if you say that a group is
virtually blah it means that there's a
finite index subgroup which is blah.
Okay. So it's pretty close to being
free. That's not true at all for SL2FP.
So you take SL2FP, take the simplest
generators you can think of. Try to
write down all the relations.
Not super easy. I I don't personally
know how to do it, although I think
people know how to do it.
Okay.
Um Okay. Number two,
SL2Z
is uh sort of sitting sitting inside of
SL2R.
It's kind of a discrete approximation of
SL2R. So it's pretty closely related to
a league group.
This is what we'll actually use.
Okay. And number three is that SL2Z
um acts nicely. This is maybe I should
call it 2B. It's quite closely related
to two. um it acts nicely on the
hyperbolic plane.
So recall that the isometries of the
hyperbolic plane is PSL2R.
So SL2R it's basically SL2R not quite.
Um so SL2R acts by isometries on the
hyperbolic plane and SL2Z is sitting
inside there. So it acts by isometries
on the hyperbolic plane.
um and that action is is captures a lot
of SL2Z. So you can also use this to to
help understand SL2Z.
All right. And so all three of these
things are much more complicated for
SL2FP.
Okay.
[Applause]
Um
all right so I I don't so the one of the
things I won't completely prove is some
thing about about doing convolutions on
SL2Z but I want to give some intuition
and rough statement about it. So
intuition
about
convolution
on SL2 Z.
Um so as a warm-up I want to think about
convolution on Z.
Okay. So let's say new is a probability
measure
on Z and I take new convolved with
itself k times. So new is some fixed
simple probability measure. Uh maybe
let's take new new of x is a half of x
is plus -1 zero otherwise.
Okay. So what happens when we convolve
it with itself K times? Um well the
central limit theorem tells us that this
thing is almost a Gaussian.
Gaussian also closely related to the
heat kernel on R.
Okay. So in analogy with this um what
might we hope to happen when we take a
measure on SL2Z and we convolve it with
itself alpha that uh so you might hope
so we have M measure probability measure
on SL2Z.
So you might hope to have some kind of
um central limit theorem for
matrices and it would say that M convuls
with itself a lot is sort of like
the heat kernel which needs to be
defined
on SR2R.
Okay, so this seems like a natural thing
in the intersection of probability
theory and matrix theory and has been
studied although I'm not an expert on
it. Um but CF work of first invogue
and
okay um so I believe that I know roughly
how it works out although I don't have a
precise statement but um let me tell you
roughly how I think it works out and
then we'll see how this would be helpful
to understand SL2FP.
Okay, so first of all, we'll have some
kind of balls in SL2R.
So BT
is the set of matrices A B C D in SL2R
with the property that A2 + B^2 + C^2 +
D^2 is at most R is at most T^2.
Okay. Um, so this is some sort of rough
some sort of notion of a ball in the
group SL2R. Um, you could imagine a
fancier notion where you start with the
Lee algebra and you put a ball in the
Lee algebra and you take the exponential
map and that's probably a better thing
to do than this. Um, but this is a very
lowbrow definition and it is sort of
approximately describes balls.
Okay. And then if we're interested in
SL2Z, we would take the integer points
in this BT of Z. That's defined to be uh
BT intersected with SL2Z. So these are
integers.
Okay. So for reference um what is the
cardality of BT of Z? So little lema
cardality of BT of Z is roughly T ^2. Um
sketch
um clearly choose
a and d
minus tt. So that's t² choices.
And then we have to solve b * c is a * d
minus one. I think I did that right. So
here you know sl2r determinant is one.
So a d minus bc is one.
Okay. So we have this integer of size
around t ^2 and we want to know how many
ways are there to factor it into two
integers of size around t.
Um okay so um
so not every integer will factor like
this. It could be prime but mostly they
will factor like that. And how many ways
will they factor? Well not too many ways
by most t to the epsilon ways. So, so
number of choices
for B and C is on and the order of so
the level of our back of the envelope
computation there should be about T^2
group elements in
all right so there's a vague statement
that if you fix M then MAR to the K is
roughly
equidistributed
on the ball of radius t
for t around exponential of some
constant depending on m * k.
So it's not stated precisely but this is
roughly what I think the central limit
theorem should say in SL2Z.
Okay.
In a little bit we'll do the hyperbolic
geometry point of view where I'll be
able to state things a little bit better
if we want.
Okay. Okay. So that's step one of our
plan. Study what the convolution looks
like in upstairs in SL2Z.
And next we need to think about what
happens when we project from SL2Z down
to SL2FP.
Why don't we pause there actually? I
mean I uh so I did some things not
completely precisely but let me see if
people have any questions or comments or
bothered by things.
Yeah,
>> question about kind of the link to the
existence of heat kernel that
like the heat kernel and R and in
general kind of uklidian looking spaces
is kind of closely related to the forier
transform but in a nonian group is there
anything analogous to that that sort of
makes this some sort of heat kernelish
thing work?
>> Yeah. So the question is um
how does the heat kernel work in a
nonabelian group? Um let me punt on that
until we get to the hyperbolic space
version and and we'll talk about the
heat kernel there which is a little bit
easier for at least for me to make it
precise. Yeah. Okay. So let's do the
second step where we pass from SL2F from
SL2Z to SL2FP.
Okay, so remember our setup that M is a
probability measure
on SL2Z
and then mu is the push forward of M.
It's probability measure on SL2 FP.
Um, also let's mention that gamma P
could be the kernel of pi P. So that's a
normal subgroup
of SL2Z
and it's gamma P is the set of A B C D
in SL2Z.
So that um
a d bc is congruent to the identity mod
p.
Okay, great. So now our goal is to
understand the L2 norm of some
convolution of this. And here's a cute
trick
um little lama.
So if mu is symmetric
so for instance if m is symmetric
um then
mu tensor k l2
is mu tens or 2k of the identity.
So here's the proof. Uh let's start on
the other side. Mu tensor 2k of the
identity is well mu tensor k convolved
with sorry I was saying the word tensor
that was not the right word I mean
convolved mu convolved k convolved with
mu convolved k
the identity
so that's the sum over g in our group
mu convolved k of g mu convolved k of g
inverse that's how you convolve two
functions
But what's nice is mu is symmetric is
that these are the same as each other.
So we just get the sum on g mult k of g^
squ.
So that's equal to that.
Okay cool. So that's sort of convenient
because now we just have to estimate
this one thing.
Um and mu convolved 2k of the identity
is if we that's that's something that
lives here but we can relate it to
something that lives here. It's the sum
g in gamma p of m convolved 2 k of g.
So in other words, we want to know how
much mass what what is the measure using
this m measure m involved 2k what is the
measure of the subgroup gamma p.
All right now m convolved 2k is
approximately evenly distributed on some
ball. So um by the vague statement
this is sort of equivalent to estimating
what fraction of the ball is in gamma P.
So we have some big ball in our league
group. What fraction of it is in the
subgroup gamma P.
Okay. So remark
the index of gamma p is the cardality of
sl2fp
which is around p cubed. So if this were
sort of evenly distributed um then you
would expect this quotient to be about 1
over p cubed.
Okay. And that's basically true. And so
here's another lema.
Um,
BT intersected with gamma P is bounded
by T ^2 over P cubed, which is also like
the size of BT of Z
over Q cubed.
So it is pretty evenly distributed.
Okay.
All right. So here's the proof.
So we're looking for
a b c d where each entry
is size smaller than t and they're
integers.
And we want
um this to be congruent to 1 0 0 1 mod
p.
Okay. So first of all let's try to do a
back of the envelope calculation.
Um
so there if I don't if I erase this
congruence condition then I'm just
asking how many integer points are there
in bt and we said before that's about t
^2.
Now I'd like a to be congruent to one
mod p. So maybe I should divide by p for
that. And I'd like b to be congruent to
zero. So maybe I should divide by p
again. And I have four conditions. So
maybe I should divide by P4 times P ^2 /
P 4th.
Is anybody suspicious?
Okay, so that's the wrong answer. It
should be closer to t ^2 / p cubed. And
the reason that that was not really okay
to do is that those four conditions are
not independent of each other. We
already know that a d minus bc is one
because we're in um okay, I didn't write
this properly. This is supposed to be in
SL2Z,
which means that AD minus BC equals 1.
Um, and I think that probably implies
that once I have three of these
congruence conditions, then I would get
the fourth. Okay, but it also brings up
the point that I should shouldn't be too
fast and loose. Uh, that it's it's not
super obvious that all of these things
are independent of each other.
Um, so there is actually a kind of
algebra trick to make this work.
that allows us to keep things more
independent of each other. And here's
the algebra trick.
Okay, so um B is divisible by P and C is
divisible by P.
So P divides B and P divides C.
Therefore P divides BC
and BC is A D minus one.
So sorry P ^2 divides BC
and so P ^2 divides a D minus one. These
are equal to each other.
All right. Similarly P + 1 divides A
uh sorry P divides A minus one.
A is congruent to one mod P and P
divides D minus one. So p ^2 divides a
minus1 * d minus one.
All right. The leading term here is also
a * d. So we can play these off against
each other and we conclude that p ^2
divides a + d minus 2.
All right. Now let's start choosing
things.
So we're going to choose a and um a has
an integer of size at most t and it's
congruent to one mod p. So I have less
than t over p choices.
Next I'm going to choose d.
I've already chosen a. So I now know the
value of d modulo p^2 because of this
sneaky algebra trick.
So I get at most t over p^2 choices.
This was only really okay if t is at
least p ^2. So let me say t is at least
p^2.
Okay. And now once I've chosen A and D
uh now I I have to solve for B and C.
And I forget about all the congruences
just like above at most around one
choices.
And so now they're less than one choice.
Choose B and C. And that's because BC is
A D minus one as integers.
Yeah.
>> When you're saying there's kind of at
most one factorization of a minus one,
would that actually be a log of
being precise the number of factors?
>> Yeah. So the question is how many
factors are there of a number of some
size? Um and it it is a little super
constant. It's actually so if this
number has size n, it's actually more
than log n. It could be potentially
could be worse than that, but it's less
than n to the epsilon for any epsilon.
And um and that's what this symbol was
supposed to mean.
>> Okay.
Simples being slightly different
versions of equality.
>> Yeah.
Okay. Um,
so any other questions or comments about
the lema?
Okay. So, so those are the ingredients
of the proof of the Sarna proof of
theorem one. All the ingredients are
rigorous and precise except for the
vague statement about how random walks
behave on SL2Z. And if you if if we're
willing to believe that, then we can put
them together and prove theorem one.
[Applause]
Okay. So proof of theorem one.
So m will be m a for this set a on sl2z.
Um then by the vague statement
mvolves k times is roughly
equidistributed
on bt where t is around x of some
constant time k.
Okay. So now we will choose
k. So we'll choose t to be a little more
than p ^ 2 so that we can use the lema
at the end which means that k is around
log p. We take around log p steps and
after that m convolved k is roughly
evenly distributed on a ball of size t p
^2.
Uh okay um and I guess we can here we
can put 2k I guess. So then m 2k of
gamma p will be around bt intersect
gamma p over bt
which is smaller than like e to the
minus3 by our lamma. And here we're
losing a little power. So if I wanted to
be more clear about what I was saying it
would be something like uh something
like this.
Okay.
Therefore,
mu tensor k l2^ 2 that's the same thing
as m tensor 2 k of gamma p. And so that
would be around pus 3 + epsilon in
particular significantly smaller than
pus 2.
Um and then we use the correlary
that gives us a bound for for this
and we get that sigma 1 t mu is less
than 1 - c right is independent of p
Okay, let me tell you just briefly about
the hyper hyperbolic geometry point of
view and then we'll switch to other
choices of generators.
Okay. Hyperbolic geometry.
All right. So we mentioned that SL2Z or
SL2R acts on the hyperbolic plane H2.
Let's say that X of P is H2 modulo gamma
P. So X of one is the hyperbolic plane
modulo SL2Z
and X of P is a cover of it.
X of P is a cover
of X of one and the group of deck
transformations
is SL2FP.
Okay. So I'd like to try to make a
picture of this. So x of one is not
quite a manifold, but it's not super
important for this except for being a
technical irritation. So I'm not going
to try to draw that. Um, so it is
uh almost a non-compact manifold of
genus Y. It looks sort of like this. The
non-compactness is annoying, but it's
maybe important.
Um, so then X of P is a cover of this.
So, it's going to look
sort of like so.
And it I guess it has a cusp for each.
Yeah, it also has some cusps. Not sure
exactly how many.
And this is a cover. Um, so how to make
that look nice?
Well, you could kind of chop this into
fundamental domains
and then each fundamental domain is a
bjection onto x of one. And if you do
this nicely, so then the different
fundamental domains, they correspond to
the group of deck transformations, which
is SL2 of FP.
And if you do this nicely, you could put
like a dot in each fundamental domain
and you could put an edge if the
fundamental domains um touch each other.
And the the graph that I just drew would
be the uh k would be a kaly graph
of SL2FP.
So the geometry of these two dimensional
surfaces is closely related to the
geometry of SL2FP.
Okay.
So then uh we would talk about the
spectrum of the lelassian
on x of p
our subject of study and um zero is in
the spectrum. So the plashion of a
constant function is zero
but after zero there's a gap. So if this
is the real lang and here's zero that's
part of the spectrum but then there's a
gap and this is called lambda 1 of x of
p and the rest of the spectrum lives
here
is contained in
okay so that's what lambda 1 is the
smallest nonzero part of the spectrum
All right. So the theorem that Selberg
actually proved in the 1950s
is that lambda 1 of x of p is at least
for all.
And the conjecture
is that lambda 1 of x of p is at least a
quarter maybe minus little o of one. Not
sure if you need it but certainly if
somebody proved that that would be a big
deal uh for all.
Okay, this that may not look immediately
that it matters very much. A quarter is
a significant number because it's lambda
one of hyperbolic plane. So I would say
it matches that
anyway. So this is the theorem that
Selberg actually proved. With modern
techniques, it's not that difficult to
get from this theorem to that theorem.
it's much more difficult to prove either
one of them.
Um,
okay. Instead of the random walk, we
could use here the heat flow
on X of P. And there was a question
earlier like what what is the heat flow?
So the question earlier was what is the
heat flow on SL2R?
But the analysis question here is what
is the heat flow on this hyperbolic
manifold? Um well you can think of it as
solving the heat equation.
So the heat equation would be del t of u
equals lelassian of u and the lelassian
okay would take a while to write down
but it's a it's a second order
differential operator on your hyperbolic
manifold.
All right.
Um okay and the solution has a formula
using the using a heat flow operator. Um
so that so let's say so u of dot comma t
would be ht of u. So this is now an
operator ht which plays the role of our
operator t mu or t mu to the k.
Okay. Um
so everything we talked about with like
a little bit more analysis and PTE to
set things up everything we talked about
applies here. So for instance, SL2 of FP
acts isomemmetrically
on X of P and therefore it acts on the
igen spaces
of H of H2
they have multiplicity.
Um and also you can do lifting.
So ht tilda is the heat operator
on the universal cover the hyperbolic
plane and then ht of x1 x2 is the sum
over g and gamma p of ht tilda x1 tilda
gx2 tilda.
So in other words, the the new heat
operator is take the heat operator on
the hyperbolic plane and push it
forward.
And that follows basically because that
this is a local equation. So solution to
the heat equation, you pull back, you
get a solution to the heat equation.
Uh okay. Um and ht tilda the heat kernel
on the hyperbolic plane it has an
explicit formula
and that's the equivalent that's plays
the role of the vague statement.
Okay.
So this hopefully is a dictionary of
most of the elements of our proof that
they they all have natural analoges for
this hyperbolic surface and the one that
was most troubling has a less troubling
analog or the one that you know was not
stated precisely would have a precisely
stated analog. Okay. So without doing
all the details, if you then translate
the proof that we did into the setting
of hyperbolic surfaces, um then that
would give a proof of a theorem like
this one with a constant that's not
quite as good, but usually it doesn't
matter. Yeah.
>> Question about the heat flow. Since the
uh spaces x of p are not compact, does
there have to be some sort of like decay
condition to make the heat flow
spaces?
>> Yeah. So the question is since X of P is
not compact should we have some kind of
decay condition to make the heat flow
work? Yeah, I think the answer is yes.
So these spaces have finite area. So
it's not as bad as it would be in some
other settings. But I think we should we
should say something about the solution
not going crazy near infinity.
Yeah.
Okay. So this is the end of our
discussion of the Selberg theorem for
this particular set of generators. So
take a moment to see if you have
questions or comments about it and then
we'll explore what would happen if we
didn't have that particular set of
generators.
Yeah. Anything on people's minds?
>> Yeah.
>> Can you give some intuition why the uh
the support grows exponentially?
>> Yeah. Okay. So, the question was if we
go back to um
we we thinking about we had a
probability measure on SL2Z. We convolve
it with itself a lot of times and then
we discover that the support it's
roughly evenly distributed on a ball of
size t but t grows exponentially with k.
Okay.
Yeah. So this is a a kind of different
behavior from what happens on the real
line. Uh let's talk think about what's
going on. So m let's say is just evenly
distributed between a few matrices.
maybe the matrices in the Selberg thing.
So now I'm going to take K of those
matrices and I'm going to multiply them
together. Now if I multiply K matrices
together, the biggest that the entries
could be at the end is exponential in K.
On the other hand, you might wonder is
it really that big or is there some
cancellation?
Like suppose I had one by one matrices
and I had a measure that 50% I was a
half and 50% it was two. Take K of those
and I multiply them together. What would
happen? Well, there'd be a lot of
cancellation. There are a lot of
cancellations between the 1/ halfs and
the twos. Uh it would get clearer to us
if we took the logarithm of everything.
Um and the size of that would actually
end up being exponential of the square
root of k.
So the 2x2 case is different from that.
Uh the actual size of this is typically
exponential in K. There's not as much
cancellation of that kind.
And um let's see what how can we get
some intuition about that. Uh
>> in some sense because of the virtual
so
this tells you that the group kind of
looks like a
>> Yeah, it's a good comment. So the
comment was uh SL2Z is virtually free.
So it's not very likely to to sort of go
out in SL2Z and then come back. And that
that's a related fact. Yeah. Yeah. So
the the it's also related to hyperbolic
geometry. So you do a random walk in the
hyperbolic plane. Um if you take S
steps, you'll typically be around a
distance s from the origin. And that's
because the hyperbolic plane is sort of
branching out. And so at every moment,
you're not equally likely to be going
back towards where the origin or away.
You're kind of threequarters of the
directions are away. And that's what
life is like inside of the matrices.
Yeah, great question. Anything else on
people's minds?
All right.
So,
[Applause]
so let's look back at this uh Selberg
theorem now that we understand it
better. And we had this particular a
listed here. Um what did we really use
about a what was special about a
>> Yeah,
>> we used the fact that it was a
generator.
>> Yeah. So, we use that it's a generator
of SL2 of FP. Um, and what I'd like us
all to think about is if we had any set
of generators of SL2 FP,
do we think that this would still be
true? And do we think that this proof
would still work?
I'll write that down while you think.
So question
can we replace
a
by any set
of generators
of SL2.
Yeah,
>> at minimum they need to be symmetric,
right?
>> Um, yeah, let's say they're symmetric.
>> Let's focus on the symmetric case. That
made things technically easier and I
would be happy with any symmetric set of
generators. Yeah.
>> Does the set of generators still need to
be kind of at least close to virtually
free?
>> Does it still need to be close to
virtually free?
Yeah, that's a good question. Um, so, so
although I mentioned being virtually
free, we didn't actually use virtually
free in the proof.
Um, that was sort of for intuition,
but we used something in the proof.
Yeah. Well, it's Yeah,
>> they're conjugates their own powers or
something like that, right?
Oh, they're conje
So the comment was these guys are
conjugate to their own powers. Yeah. So
that's important but we didn't use that
either. So we we in when we proved that
every representation of SL2FP is big, we
considered these elements and we use the
fact that they're conjugate to their own
powers. But once we knew abstractly that
every representation of SL2FP is big, we
just used it as a black box.
Um, so it's not important that these
elements in the statement of cells
theorem are the same elements we used in
that proof.
Yeah. Good. Okay. But well, so one part
of the answer is that we used
that A uh is a set of generators
of SL2Z.
Okay, so in the proof where we lifted
things to SL2Z, we took this set A, we
lifted it to SL2Z, and then we did a
random walk on SL2Z. And we needed to
know that that thing was kind of evenly
distributed. And the only way we could
hope for that to be true is if this was
a set of generators of SL2Z.
>> Yeah. like are there any even
straightforward kind of sets of
generators of SL2 of FP that would not
be generators of SL2 of Z
>> right okay so the question is um could
it happen that we have generators of
SL2FP but they don't generate SL2Z and
um the answer is yes that happens fairly
commonly um and let me show you
an example
um Okay.
Yeah. Okay. So, here's an example. Uh
maybe we won't prove everything, but um
let's say that a k a no I used a
different letter. A um M is the set of 1
+ or minus M 1 0 and 1 + or - M 1 0.
Okay, so this is still a set of four
elements size of a = 4. And if M is 1 or
two, it generates
SL2Z.
But if M is at least three, it does not
generate does not
generate
SL tubes.
On the other hand, for every M, for all
almost every P, so for
all but finitely many P.
Um, this AM generates
SL2 of FP.
All right. So, why does this happen?
All right. So, notice that that this guy
is one 011
to the plus or minus m, right?
So if if we so we assume that these guys
generate SL2Z, it's not that hard to
show. Take a word in these guys,
it's only included in the group
generated by these guys if it has a
rather special structure that um you
know each each letter is raised to the
plus or minus n power. So maybe m is 10.
Okay. So now it's clear that most words
do not look like that.
Um now it's not immediately clear that
we don't have the whole group because an
element in the group might be
represented by many words. Um but we had
we mentioned before that there has a
finite index subgroup which is free. So
there are not that many ways to
represent most words. Um so so um so you
know this tiny subset of the words we
don't expect it to cover very much of
the group.
Okay. Um, and life is different in
SL2FP. And a little later we'll talk
about who are the subgroups of SL2FP,
but there aren't a whole lot of them.
And once you have enough elements that
they're not trapped in a subgroup, then
they must generate the whole group.
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
So there there are other choices of
generators for SL2Z. Any choice of
generators would have worked fine in our
argument. But it's actually quite common
that you have some generators for SL2FP
that they and they don't generate SL2C.
Okay. In this case, our argument um
doesn't work very well.
Let's say that GM is the group generated
by AM.
This group is a lot is a lot harder to
understand than SL2Z.
So for instance, if you were to give
write down a matrix and then you'd like
to know is it in GM? Like that's not
super easy to figure out.
Um SL2Z are all the integer matrices
where the entries satisfy the equation A
D minus BC equals 1. um whether or not a
matrix is in this group does not have a
simple criterion like that. As far as I
know, the best thing well I I don't know
anything faster to do than to take the
generators and multiply them together
different ways and see if you get this
matrix. Yeah.
>> How close is GM to gamma M? Like are
they have anything in common? Because at
first it sort of looks like things
congrent to the identity mod,
>> right? So GM is a subgroup. So So okay,
so the question was how close is GM to
gamma M? Remember that gamma M was the
subgroup of uh matrices in SL2Z that are
congruent to the identity mod M. So
these guys are congruent to the identity
mod M. So therefore, GM is a subgroup of
gamma M. Um however this group has
infinite index
um in SL2Z
for M at least three
whereas gamma M had finite index because
it was the kernel of a map to a finite
group.
So, gam gamma m which is not which is
already not a super easy thing to
understand if m is large. Um uh this is
um well okay objectively this is a
smaller group than gamma m and
subjectively I think it is a harder
group to understand than gamma m.
Okay. So this whole method has not
really worked and in fact it goes in the
opposite direction. Um so namely
we for for for generators of SL2Z we
first understand SL2Z really well and
then we can use that to understand SL2FP
with those generators. Um with situation
like this the there's some progress and
it goes first you try to understand
SL2FP with those generators and you use
that to try to understand G of M. So
there's actually a big literature now
about these groups G of M and first you
try to figure out things about SL2FP
with those generators.
Okay, so um there is uh okay so so
that's one part of the answer to this
question and what we said so far is that
our proof doesn't usually work for other
sets of generators but that's not an
answer to the question whether the
theorem is true and as far as we know
the theorem may well be true so there's
a conjecture you take any set of
generators of SL2FP you just always have
a spectral gap
that's not proven yet but there's some
significant progress and I'm I will tell
you something about
>> what's the equivalent uh spectral
statement
>> what is the equivalent spectral
um
okay so if you take so I'm not sure if
this is your question but let me say
something and then okay um so so if we
take another set of generators here we
have a different operator And we can ask
what is sigma 1 and so on. But so I
think you were wondering is if we took
another set of generators there would
that be related to the spectrum of the
plashion of something? Is that a
question?
>> Okay. Um
okay so not not as far as I know. Um,
and so you so you might say, you know,
this theorem is great because it
connects to this hyperbolic geometry and
it tells us something really interesting
estimate for the spectrum of some
surface. With other generators, maybe it
doesn't exactly do that. Um, but on the
other hand, it says some interesting
stuff about this group, which is
interesting in some other problems.
Okay.
Um, yeah, let's leave that.
All right.
Um, all right. So, suppose we're just
given any set A inside of SL2FP and we'd
like to figure out if there's a spectral
gap. One thing that we know could go
wrong is that A could be contained in a
subgroup.
So, if A is contained in H, which is a
proper subgroup,
then sigma 1 TA is one.
All right. So, so that's elementary to
see. But in order to really use this, we
would actually it helps to know what are
all the proper subgroups. Um, so let's
talk a little bit about the
classification
of subgroups
of SL2FP.
Okay.
So, um the classification was done by
someone named Dixon in 1901.
And it's not that hard, but it's not
that easy either. Um, and uh, I was a
little surprised to learn that if you'd
like to classify the subgroups of SLDFP,
that was only done, first of all, it's
only done approximately and it was only
done around the year 2000.
So some of these problems actually are
are really pretty hard.
So done by Dixon in 199.
Um, okay. Well, let's think of some
subgroups.
We could have the diagonal subgroup,
which is typically called T for Taurus.
There's this guy. We have the upper
triangular like unipotent subgroup
like that. Um, let me put a little knot
here.
And we have the more general upper
triangular guys which which
have
Okay. Now if you take a subgroup group
group you can conjugate it and you can
get another subgroup. So you can
conjugate all of these.
Okay. And so let me write B that means a
conjugate of B 0.
Okay. So those are a bunch of subgroups.
Those are the only ones that I was able
to think of without effort.
Um there are a few other sort of small
subgroups like for instance the
apparently the icosahhedral group
appears in SL2FP for some PS. Um and the
statement of the classification is a lot
easier if we don't say exactly what
groups appear but just kind of roughly
and ignore small groups.
Um so so there's a theorem about this
and the rough theorem would say if H in
SL2FP
is a proper subgroup
um then there exists a oral subgroup B
one of these guys and um B intersect H
is a large fraction of H.
So this C bigger than zero is a
universal constant.
So more or less H is in H is not quite
in B, but almost all H has a very large
part that's in B.
Okay. And B is a conjugate of B 0. And
the fine print is conjugate of B 0. um
conjugated by
not necessarily someone in SL2FP, but
maybe the maybe the matrix you conjugate
by might involve the algebraic closure.
I think it's fine.
Okay.
Um, now let's make a remark. The analog
of this is not true
for SL2FQ.
Q Q is a prime power. Um, because SL2FP
is a subgroup of SL2FQ,
but SL2FP is not contained in any like
upper triangle or something.
Um, so the analogous there's an
analogous theorem for SL2FQ, but it
needs to be stated in a little bit
different way to take account of the sub
fields.
So this may already start to remind us
of something that we've seen that
projection theory is different over FP
and FQ.
Okay.
Um
okay so now I can state uh the second
main theorem that I wanted to say about
random walks on groups which is a
generalization of Selberg's theorem and
it allows to take any set of generators
where it's not trapped in a burell
subgroup
but it requires a little quantification
which is perhaps not quite as strong as
one might fantasize about.
All right. So, um for every epsilon
bigger than zero, there are a couple of
positive constants.
um
every P um okay so if I have a subset of
SL2FP
and the subset is not contained in a
burell subgroup and also it doesn't
concentrate too much in a burell
subgroup so for every B or
if I take A intersected with B this is
at most um
uh p to the minus epsilon size of b and
with this small constant.
So a smallest sorry size of a
so only a smallest fraction of a is in
this burell subgroup
and it's a p to the epsilon kind of
fraction where you you that's a pretty
small fraction you might hope to do a
little better but anyway that's what it
says. Um, and here I wasn't positive if
it so I'm when I proved it I needed to
say co-et but I'm not sure if it's
co-set or subgroup anyway. So if it
doesn't concentrate in something closely
related to a subgroup um then it
expands. So that then it has a mixed
sigma 1 of TA is less than 1us.
Okay. So up to a little bit of
quantification
you know if a set if if a is contained
in a boral subgroup definitely we won't
have a spectral gap and if a is doesn't
intersect a burl subgroup too much then
we will have a spectral gap. It's almost
if and only if although you might hope
to improve this a little bit.
Okay
so this is kind of its own story to talk
about. So since we're almost done, let
me just make a a couple of highlevel
comments about it. Yeah,
>> it's a burell subgroup.
>> A burell. Yeah. So I don't know why so
burell is involved in this. A burell
subgroup is these guys. B it's the take
an upper triangular matrix that that's a
burell subgroup or conjugate that.
Okay. So one comment about this theorem
is that it you know we had better know
this theorem better know something like
this.
Um
and
so what the first part of this theorem
is to prove that if you don't have a
spectral gap then there must be a subset
that's kind of approximately a subgroup
that intersects a a lot.
We don't have a spectral gap. There must
be a subject subset that's kind of
approximately a subgroup where maybe a
convolved with itself many times is
heavily concentrated in this approximate
subgroup.
Okay. And that's a a very nice argument
and it uses it turns out to use the
tools from additive combinotaurics. It
uses like bality gowers and things like
that or in a non non-commutative
version.
Okay. Then the second part of the proof
is to say is kind of a robust version of
this theorem. This is a classification
of actual subgroups. We want to make it
a little bit stronger and have a
classification of approximate subgroups.
Um so not only any actual proper
subgroup would have to intersect a
burell subgroup a lot but actually any
any kind of approximate subgroup. So any
subset where when you multiply it by
itself two or three times it doesn't get
very much bigger. um the only way that
can happen is if your um is if your
subset heavily intersects a burell
subgroup.
Okay. Now that second part you'll notice
is not true over FP
is not sorry is not true over FQ.
Um, and so the second part was we'll
draw on some product theory and our our
like theorems that we worked very hard
on that give a projection estimate over
F over FP that's not true over FQ. We'll
need that.
Um, okay. And so I I think this is a
nice example of how those, you know,
those theorems are only an epsilon
improvement on a trivial estimate where
epsilon is very small, but it still is
meaningful. There's an important
difference between epsilon being zero or
not zero. And they're used to prove kind
of an, you know, this c of epsilon is
pretty small. But um um but there's
there's a just a really important
difference between whether you had zero
here, which is like a completely vacuous
statement, and whether you had one minus
epsilon, which even if epsilon is a
small constant, is a qualitatively sharp
statement about um about how this random
walk mixes.
Okay, cool. So we'll talk about more
more about those things on on Thursday.