Technology isn't what you think it is.
We all use the word technology as if it
meant the same thing to all of us. But
are you sure we all mean the same? To a
researcher, technology is what's on a
research paper. To an engineer, it might
be a prototype or a system. In
government and in the military,
everything hinges on requirements.
Investors seem to associate technology
with industries and valuations. To an
office worker, it is the stuff we do
with computers, information technology.
In MBA programs, the word is used as a
synonym for product. This leads to many
comical situations. For example, at MIT,
enterprising researchers in engineering
or science will describe what they've
invented to business students, hoping
that these students will get it and will
solve for the product to build.
Meanwhile, the same business students
eager to work with technologies are
hoping for the precise opposite. That
the researcher will have figured out the
product already so they can wrap a
business around it. They all use the
word technology, but they mean different
things. And they each hope that the
other party will have done the work of
figuring out where the technology fits.
The same happens when government
agencies in science and technology seek
sponsors to commercialize ideas or when
the military seeks to transition
technology to operations. In the new
mindset, we think about technology
differently. It is neither the product
nor the paper. Technology creates
options. You can reshape technology.
This should be obvious, but often it
isn't. Take lasers for example. Today
they're used everywhere. In
presentations, to carry information over
long distances, barcode readers,
military, computing. We know the laser
is good for many things. But years after
he invented it, Dr. Mayman still called
it a solution in search of a problem.
This is why thinking in products leads
to paradoxes. Sure, you could interview
users for the first laser, but who are
they? We all hope that something about
the technology will tell us what it is
good for and what to use it for. But the
fact is that at the start, nothing is
new or obvious. To go from that first
hunch or paper to impact, you're going
to have to work on and reshape what you
start with. Technology gives you
options. It is malleable. It can be
reshaped. Here are some examples of what
I mean by creating options. These
examples come from the work of students
in our MIT class and they show how one
technology has led to unexpected uses,
sometimes more than one. Jeff Grman's
laboratory developed a powder that
stored heat in the cold. It was meant to
help increase the efficiency of solar
energy concentration plants. Students in
the class determined that if laced in
fabric, the same technology could help
create selfwarming high fashion
clothing. They took the technology from
energy to fashion. Another example, Joel
Dawson's lab invented a new kind of
circuit that increased battery life by
about 10%. At the time, the prevalent
phone was the iPhone 1. Students in the
class found out how to adapt the
technology to manage energy in the
telephone network instead, where it
saved millions and end up founding two
different companies from the same
technology. Both companies were
eventually acquired by large
infrastructure equipment companies.
That's one technology, two companies.
These examples are from my MIT class.
And so they may lead you to believe that
you need a technology to start. So let
me give you two examples involving
technologies born out of repurposing
other knowledge. The first laser emerged
out of a pet project in an industrial
lab and it was produced with parts
ordered from a catalog like a
photography flashlight or a ruby crystal
cut to order. Nothing was new.
Everything was repurposed. Early in my
career, we created a company to locate
cell phones in case of emergency. The
problem to solve came to us from a new
regulation from the Federal
Communications Commission. We invented
an artificial intelligence technology to
solve the problem. However, the
technology was inspired by a chemical
engineering thesis. Students often come
into class expecting to find the ideal
use for one technology. They learn to
appreciate that one technology creates
many options. This means that technology
investments are made risky not by the
technology itself, but by how we try to
narrow technologies down to one obvious
use. So do not narrow it all to just one
use. Challenge yourself to find those
options. There are ways to do it
systematically. In my class, students
start with keeping at least three
options open. Having options is
convenient because, as you'll realize in
the next video, real world problems are
interesting because there are many ways
to chip at them. That's how technology
gets you to solve problems.
[Music]