The following content is provided under
a Creative Common License. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Um, welcome back. Uh, thanks for not
dropping the class yet.
>> Oh, I got to do that right now.
>> Funny you mention that.
Uh let's see. Uh just a reminder
actually the one big reminder for folks
who weren't here on Friday is that we
swapped around Friday and Mondays 17th
and the 20th have been swapped.
>> Yeah.
>> In terms of readings and what we're
going to do in class.
>> Yes. So, uh we're still going to be
playing the games on Friday on Friday.
Uh but uh the brainstorming activity
that we have scheduled for Monday is
going to be on this Friday instead. And
and then we can flip around otherwise.
So um I want to manage to get through
the readings.
Uh cool. Uh let let's see where should
we start? Um so there was D Church
article which was on Gamma Sutra and uh
if if you're familiar with Gamma Sutra
it's or if you're not actually it's a
fairly
well read news and industry sort of
industry news blog for uh for the games
industry but largely the digital game
industry. Um that particular article I
think was originally written not for the
website but for the magazine that the
associated company publishers for the
game development magazine uh and Doug
Church is actually an MIT alum uh
him and the other article that was read
Mark actually MIT alums so that's one
thing
um so Dr. proposes a a set of tools.
Anyone remember what they call the
formal?
>> Yeah, the fat.
>> Yeah. Um so and and uh uh framework
which is
>> m
>> Yeah. Mechanics.
>> Yeah. Um and we kind of kind kind of
covered mechanics and dynamics on uh uh
on Friday and today we have a little bit
of time to talk about aesthetics. But
the reason why these two essays were
kind of put right next to each other was
NDA is an example of what uh Duncan was
describing for design. Um in fact at the
time when NDA came out it was pretty
much the only one that caught on. um
everybody all the problems that Doug
Church lays out in his article about the
problems that we don't have a vocabulary
that consistent vocabulary to talk about
our craft and thus we can't actually
improve on it. Um and thus we need some
some formal tools to uh that that
everyone uses. Uh unfortunately not much
has caught up um MDA being one of the
few that has um because it you know for
a number of different reasons. First of
all, it it actually is a is a useful
framework. You know, you can think of
many many ways to formally look at
games, but from a designer, you need to
to to think of something which you can
actually apply to help improve your
games. And MDA actually gives you a uh
uh a reason why design is hard, you
know. So, if nothing else, designers
like it a lot because it says this is
why my job is hard. Um,
and the reason being you get to control
the mechanics, but that's not what
you're going for. You're not going for
really interesting mechanics. They're
really they're going for a really
interesting aesthetic. They're going for
a fun, engaging play experience. There
are Mark uh uh in the MDA paper this
eight kinds of fun. And I've asked him
about this when he gave this
presentation here in in MIT. Those eight
were not meant to be comprehensive. they
they were meant to be. These are the
eight that I could think of at the time.
Um and the and Idos had I have a list
somewhere where Idos has like a full
page of different kinds of fun. Um now
different kinds of experiences that
people are trying to get out of playing
the game. That's what a game designer is
trying to get. The only problem is that
the game designer doesn't actually
control that experience. The game
designer only gets to control the
mechanics.
Depending on what company you are, maybe
you have the title of game designer, but
you're also in charge of the art. you
know, you're also you're actually also
the lead programmer. It's possible uh
that you also have more control over
things than just the mechanics, but most
designers mechanics is where is what
their job scope is. Um so they they
write the the the the rules, the rules
interact in some sort of like
ridiculously hard to predict way and
then you get the experience of playing
the game with the aesthetic and you hope
that's what you were going for. It
usually isn't. and uh and you you know
and then you make a change to the
mechanics try again and the nice thing
about that is that that works really
well with iterative design. Um in fact
without iterative design it becomes
really hard to control this entire
process because basically um you're
you're two orders removed from the
experience that you're trying to create.
It's like, you know, um trying to draw
on a piece of paper where uh not only
can you not see the paper that you're
drawing on, uh you're also, you know,
controlling the brush or the pencil, you
know, tied to a stick or something like
that life of it. That's kind of what
being a game design is like. Um
so, so that's the experience of the game
design side. Uh you get to control the
mechanics and you're going for some sort
of aesthetic. And on the other side, the
player is experiencing kind some kind of
aesthetic and you know, and they can
sort of work their way back. Um, you
know, it's like, I'm getting this kind
of experience. Um, why am I getting this
kind of experience? You know, if you got
a particularly insightful game player,
maybe you're taking CMS 300,
introduction to video game, and you're
analyzing games. Um, and you're trying
to say, how did we get here? And, and
you know, if you're taking this class,
you're going to be doing that a lot. You
know this game, Heroes Might Magic 3 for
instance, you know, you know, uh has
give me a particularly, you know, a a
sensation. Describe a sensation that you
got when you were playing that game that
that you recall
>> strategic, outsmarting, playing friends,
outsmart them.
>> So, so, so it made you feel smart. It
made you have to think really really
hard and everything. So and then you
think about what dynamics might have
resulted in that you know what what sort
of
>> fog of war
>> huh f fog of war you have to figure out
what what is behind the areas you can't
see. Yeah,
>> but there's some information that you
can see that may give you clues. And
then you know might actually be be
already a mechanic. But you know the
idea of there is information that you
can deduce even though you can't
actually see it. And there's some
probability
of getting it right uh based on your
experience with game. Fall war being one
to uh one one game mechanic that gets
you there. So you can sort of analyze it
backwards and uh figure out okay that's
one thing for war gets you. Sometimes
fog of war just confuses people, right?
That there could be anything behind this
corner. I mean, technically Final
Fantasy random combat system is like fog
of war, right? I don't know if there's a
random encounter here. I will walk into
it and then oh look, there's slime
slimes at Dragon Quest. Um, Final
Fantasy 10 slimes, I think.
>> Were you in Final Fantasy?
>> The Square Enix version is complet.
>> Mhm. FL. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You are
fighting cake.
Um but there is actually a problem.
Actually I I don't need to write this
down that there is a problem with um
well it means no problem. There is an
issue that I have with formal abstract
design tools and come to the word
formal. Um Doug Church uses it
specifically to say well it should be
sort of serious business right? You know
it's formal with a capital F. We're not
talking about how cool this game is. You
know, we want to be very precise in our
vocabulary. We want to be um you know,
we want to treat it like this because
that's capital that's capital B.
However,
that the other assumption with the word
formal comes from formalism. You you are
thinking about the form of the game in a
way that if you were trying to apply the
same technique to talk about art, you'd
be talking about the form of visual art,
you know, the form of cinema. Um and uh
and that is actually a fairly narrow way
to look at something which at a topic
that's as broad as a game. Um you are
you know it is as if
as if we were trying to analyze
something like like life heroes might
have met and completely ignoring your
the fact that you were playing it with
friends from French class. You know that
would be an example of well that had
nothing to do with the game. Well,
actually, it probably had a lot to do
with how you experience the game. Um,
you know, uh, you know, playing that's
the rules of chess. There's, uh, and and
you could just look at the game based on
this rules of the rules of chess. You
could also look at the history of chess.
You could also look at who you're
playing it against. Are you playing
against random person or against a dad?
You know, uh, big difference. Uh, uh, or
in my case, my mom. Um, are you uh, you
know, playing it in a club? Are you
playing it, you know, against the chess
master in in the cupboard square or
something like that? Um,
uh, what what does this game mean? I are
you using the game metaphorically in in
speech or, you know, just saying and and
and I had, you know, and and my opponent
was in a checkmated
uh, position. does it necessarily mean
that you were playing chess with your
with with someone someone else in order
to get that point across. Um there's a
whole range of different ways that you
can look at games even as a game
designer that isn't specifically
formless that isn't specifically just
look just looking at the form of the
game. Um
just understanding what context people
are going to be playing the game in for.
So for a lot of the games that you guys
are going to be designing this semester
specifically uh in this class, you know,
you have to think about the fact that a
lot of these games are actually going to
be played by your instructors uh are
going to be played uh in a setting very
similar to this by your colleagues in
this room. Um are probably going to end
up being tested by dorm mates, you know,
fraternity f uh friends, uh folks around
campus. And all that is going to heavily
influence the kind of game that you
make. Um,
now for for better or worse, you know,
you are pretty much making a game for an
MIT audience. And we're trying to change
that a little bit uh for the last
assignment, but uh keep in mind that,
you know, you have to be uh that that's
not necessarily every single game that
you're going to make in the future and
that shouldn't be. But knowing that you
can try to cater to the audience that
you've got for every round. um that has
very little I mean in some ways this is
going to affect the design decisions
that you make in your game. What will be
perfectly acceptable to a uh a
competitive MIT audience might not be
perfectly acceptable to your average
board game buyer in Target or something
like that um and vice versa. Um, and so
what may be a perfectly engrossing game
mechanic, dynamic, aesthetic experience
that you will get, but just by looking
at a formal aspects of a game, you know,
this this will be really cool if you
understood the mechanic, played it out
in the way that create a desired dynamic
to give you the aesthetic experience.
But if you're if you don't understand
the context that you're playing the
game, as an example, then uh your player
may not even get that part. Your players
may may may look at your game say this
game is not for me. Yeah. Uh and just
walk away. Um it might mean that uh you
might I I'm thinking of things like uh
we we just had this discussion over
lunch about social games that you find
on Facebook for instance. Um and a lot
of social games I might have already
made this point but it has been argued
that social games aren't all that
social. All you do is really beg and
spam your friends. Uh that's the whole
point of playing. But in many ways, it's
also saying to your friends, we're kind
of doing the same thing. You know, we
may be separated by time and separated
by distance, but we're all doing the
same thing. And we we could be playing
this game. We could be talking about the
show that we that that that that we are
watching in our own apartments, but then
we get to discuss it. But in many ways,
this is just me telling you we're doing
the same thing that we're part of the
same group. And that serves a function
that has almost that that really doesn't
have anything to do with the formal
analysis of how a game mechanic works.
Um but it's still incredibly crucial to
the popularity of these games. So uh so
that so so so keep that in mind that um
even DJ makes this point but I think a
lot of uh designers actually kind of
ignore that when they read his his essay
that it's only one set of tools. the the
formal tools are only one set of tools.
Even uh there are tools uh at looking at
games culturally, personally
um uh and uh and other things that that
that that you may get in this class and
in classes like like CNS 300 um uh that
that that will affect it how people
experience the game and how much
pleasure that that they're running at
the game to understand whether your game
is doing what it does, right?
um that aren't that don't have anything
to do necessarily with just by looking
at the self-contained system of the of
of the game.
Just as a side note, um how many of you
folks have heard of the narrative versus
nudology debate?
How many of you are sick of this? Okay.
Okay.
Um, don't you I'm I'm sick of it too,
but I bring it up for one reason that I
there is an interesting case that if you
actually look at narrat marintology as a
study and nudology as a study, they're
both formalist studies. And in fact,
they're more accurate than more more
precise. They're both structuralist,
which is kind of if you look at at at at
philosophies, it's kind of a subset of
formalism or at least a more recent
version of of of it. They're both
basically focused on these are the
elements of this art form and this is
how they interact to produce some sort
of effect. Um, and all that matters is
what's contained in this art form.
What's outside this art form doesn't
matter. That's what narratology does for
stories. That's what dudology does for
games. Um, and uh, that's in fact
probably why most people who study games
have kind of walked away from from from
ludology because it's not that
interesting to just study what's inside
the system. People want to see what's
outside. Um, and uh, so when you compare
structuralistic and structural
structuralism wins, that's that that's
one case. Um, and uh, you only have a
and and you may not realize that you're
actually looking at your game through a
very very narrow lens. So try to broaden
the range of tools that you've got. You
know, this this class is going to give
you a small set of them. Uh and it's not
by by any means the beyond and all of
every single way that you can look at it
at at the game. And again, they're not
they're not just restricted to the tools
that we're specifically teaching you in
this class. So keep so keep looking out
for new ones. Um
>> let's see.
Any questions so far? That was my rant.
10 10 minute rant. 15 minutes. Okay. All
right. No more ranting.
All right. We have a uh activity and do
you want to run through?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um Okay. So, I'm going to
pass around. This is um my crappy race
game. So, you're going to need one one
copy per pair. Um, there's also some
nifty set of dice. You need one copy per
or one dye per character
on
I just aside.
>> And then um each person is going to need
three of these poker chips. It doesn't
matter what color. So just grab three.
>> Um, and then you're going to need a
marker to indicate yourself. And I
recommend just grabbing any
[Music]
>> copies.
You only need one per
Jason.
>> So,
>> one d for every two people.
>> Yeah. One of the six-sided die for every
two.
>> And then you need markers for yourselves
and then bonus markers. And that's what
the poker chips are for.
>> So, keep the keep the poker chips
circulating.
>> Three per person.
>> One piece per person.
>> Okay. You can use coins. You can use D
likeid
paper. Whatever you want.
I'm a maker with a penny and a crown.
>> So, we have three of these.
>> Most people.
>> How many? Take that.
>> If you need markers for yourself, you
can try one of the multi-sided
polyhedral.
[Music]
>> Okay. Okay. What now? have what now?
>> Okay, I should have used this.
>> I'm more well versed in the person.
>> I can see defeat.
>> Is that even correcting?
>> I think you're going to have to die.
>> The direct.
>> Okay. So, can everyone hold for a
second? So, what we're going to ask you
to do is just play through this game a
couple times. Um, then we're going to
come back and kind of apply the MGA
framework to the game itself and then if
we have time, I think we're going to
spend some time tweaking it. Yeah. Okay,
cool. So, we'll interrupt you in
probably
>> uh
actually 10 minutes. It's a pretty
>> uh Okay. So, I mean
>> this is sort of on the fly.
>> Yeah. So, so what we what we kind of
like to do is hear about I guess we'll
just go around the room in pairs and you
guys can talk or do you want a minute to
talk to apply MTA to this and kind of
something so I'm not like calling on you
on the spot.
>> Anybody wonder what how they felt what
the aesthetic of this game?
>> There is none.
>> People were pretty loud for their
crappy race game.
>> It felt competitive.
>> Well, the thing is it's like very simple
aesthetic. So, so in the paper they say
you're going to go straight like the
player should be using the aesthetic,
but here you go straight to the mechanic
and you're wondering about it.
>> Yeah, I mean the you definitely is easy
especially for board games because the
mechanics are written down right in
front of you is really judge. But how
did you feel while you were playing
this? I
>> think there was a there was a sense of
tension. There was maybe a sense of
brinkmanship perhaps.
There was a a sense of
um I mean
like there was the intellectual
challenge of working out like like is
there really a meaningful decision to be
made here
and if there is like what is what is the
correct decision?
>> Um
>> so so so just put put opinion in the
mind of like can can I optimize this?
Yeah. Yeah.
>> Especially for this crowd. I think this
is immediate.
Can I figure out what's the right way to
play this?
>> And and I know you tried to figure it
out.
>> I think I think he I think he correct.
>> He figured it out.
>> Yeah.
>> So, what's So, is there an optimal way
to play this game?
>> Yeah. Okay. So, if you're losing, you're
going to if you keep putting tokens
down, you're going to lose anyway. So,
you want to be rolling in order to like
increase the variance. Um, and if you're
winning, you want to be putting tokens
down in order to remove the variance.
You can imagine it as like a
distribution. Whereas, if you're like
below uh if you're like below the
winning line, you want to like widen it
out as much as possible. So, as much of
that distribution is above the winning
line. And if you're above the winning
line, you want to be as narrow as
possible. So, you stay above the
winning.
>> So, your strategy is basically based on
what's what's the current state of the
game.
>> Yeah. until like the last turn where
obviously you don't want to put a token
down if you're two from the end. Um like
as long as no one can win on this turn.
If I'm behind him, I'm putting down a
I'm rolling the die and if I'm ahead of
him, I'm putting down a token.
>> Did anyone like prefer a strategy before
you started thinking about what was the
best or
>> So I was too lazy to use a token, so I
would just keep rolling.
>> That's right. That's and that but that's
also part of the aesthetic of it, right?
It's like you just happen to prefer.
>> Yeah. Well, in the first six spaces, I
mean, you should have got the average if
you were all the same. If you put the
token down, I personally like being
conservative.
>> True.
>> See, and so that's
>> Sorry. Go ahead.
>> That is more exciting because it does
different things.
>> The token the illusion that you're
actually
>> Did anyone like get to a situation where
like really far behind and just like
caught up?
>> No. quickly.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. Like the actual difference, one
of the things that you do get in this
game is sort of perceived distance
between players is actually, you know,
not that not that far. If what if if the
one behind actually has has to do with
it then uh I think people refer to this
as the American Gladiators effect.
>> Yeah.
>> Um you know how like American Gladiators
you uh uh actually is this your example
that I'm stealing here?
>> I don't remember.
>> Okay. Honestly,
>> this someone's example that I'm stealing
but
>> I think it's in the book at some point
but I think we had applied it to
>> Yes. Yes. Uh well, I'm crediting someone
for this, but
I wish I
citation. Um so yeah, uh the the the
basic idea being you know if who's who's
seen American Gladiators or um
>> it might be too old.
>> I've never heard I don't know what it
is.
>> Okay. Okay. Um there also a number of
different like Japanese game shows which
are kind of similar.
Did you guys seen Japanese game trips?
>> Yeah. The basic idea in American
Gladiators is that it's basically an
obstacle course where the obstacles are
uh h happen to be kind of these like
athletic dudes and women who have um who
are either pummeling you with buffer
sticks or like shooting tennis balls at
you gun and stuff like that. And you
basically have to get from the beginning
to to the end faster than the other
teams. Actually faster than than the
other players. So, it's two regular
dudes, a bunch a whole bunch of athletes
who are throwing things at you.
Every time you get a kid, you have to go
back a little bit. But the thing about
the the thing about American Gladiators
is that so you have this long obstacle
course. In fact, this was one of the
events. This was always the final event
of the entire uh of the entire TV show
is that um you will you will have two
people doing the same course. They would
have to climb up a wall and then they
will have to go down um uh flying fast a
net. Yeah.
>> But it was it was like a cargo net
specifically. So it was really difficult
to climb up it.
>> Yeah. It's like this big webbing kind of
thing. If you ever try and it's like
climbing the rigging of a ship, right?
You know, it's like really really
difficult your feet.
So what happens is that you know you if
you have two people who are really
really far apart one one person way
ahead and that person starts climbing
the cargo net it takes that person
forever to get to the end of the car
coconut because climbing up cargo net is
really really hard no matter who you are
that gives the person behind plenty of
time to catch up uh and start climbing
the cargo net. Um but then that the
person who wasn't the lead in the first
place hits the zipline and all of a
sudden there's a huge increase of
distance. Um so that this whole idea
that they never really were all that far
uh they they never really changed their
position for most for most uh uh
gladiators games. They the the winner
has already been decided by that point
because first person who reaches the
cargo net tends to win to tends to win
the match. But it looks like the lead
just shrank because suddenly you got
both of them in one camera shot. Um, and
then you get that huge huge relief that
that Mark likes to call that dramatic
tension, which I think is a better
description than his other term for the
same thing, which is drama, because it's
not drama. It's just tension release. Um
but uh but that's an aesthetic, you
know, going for that aesthetic of
tension and coming up with a game that
makes you feel like a price is closer
than it actually is or you know uh or
allowing someone to close the gap really
really quick quickly because as many of
you have pointed out these things
probabilistically mean exactly the same
thing as a di um
let's see um so that's you know but the
the the ability to, you know, increase a
for for a gap to to to open up and then
to close. That's actually a dynamic
that's actually a result of a number of
different rules that are in this
particular game. And um it's not written
down that that's going to happen, but
it's pretty much going to happen if you
have two people playing those particular
strategies. And it's one thing that
happens pretty often. Um so yeah, that's
so that's one to keep in mind. Um
What are the constraints that you're
seeing uh in the design of this game
here? Like like what what was this game
what what does this game have to do in
order for it to be a viable in-class
exercise?
>> Fit on a sheet of paper.
>> Fit on a sheet of paper. That's a huge
one actually. Uh because first of all
limits how many spaces you've got
assuming everyone's using like something
this size or a coin or something. Uh,
>> you mean you can I mean you can laugh at
that, but that's literally how it went
is I wanted it to fit on a sheet of
paper and the spaces had to accommodate
a die. So the number of spaces is a
result of that.
>> So 12 was an accident.
>> Yeah,
but you probably could have fit the
square, but you know some margins.
>> Yeah, it's hard. Um,
see the rules have to fit on one sheet
of paper as well. So the rules can't be
that complicated.
>> Yep. Um most of these rules are single
sentences for the most part. Uh it's
just that because the college are so
small they look really much complicated.
>> Um
>> it had to be quick. It had to work for
10 minutes. Uh in fact it had to work so
that you could get a few games hopefully
through within 10 minutes. Anyone only
managed to get through?
>> Yeah. Okay. that being really hard.
>> So, so different aesthetics.
Um so you know this this game tries to
get it like really really tense but you
know obviously the decision that you're
actually making in this game you know is
minimal that you you do get to to say
well if you are already losing then
there's really only one r one one one
rational thing to do but if you were
playing this game as Jason recommended
if I was playing this game against
myself you know there really is no
optimal strategy I could pick two
different strategies for each side and
because then who plays first basically.
>> Yeah.
>> Person who plays first is by default on
on average. Um
and depending
game but one
>> I'm bad at rolling dice because if
you're rolling out right you could it
could be bad.
>> So um I would like actually folks to uh
try mixing this up a little bit. You
know pick a rule in here any rule uh and
uh and alter it. you know either you can
do things like adding more squares you
can change the movement chart uh
one idea that I had and someone who's
taken probability more recent than me
which is uh what happens if you use the
high of two dice rolls instead of just
one uh you know because dashing just a
probability and uh play around with that
um see what that feels like and uh and
if that feels just boring
cash need something else. So, um we've
got 15 minutes.
>> Yeah, it's reasonable.
>> Yeah. And then and then you know and
then you'll tell you'll tell the class
about what you changed and how that
changed the feeling you made.
>> Cool.
>> So, every two people uh uh work with the
the team next to you, explain how your
game how your version works uh and have
the other group play it. Um and what and
what I'm going to do after every um and
vice versa and what what what we're
going to do once everyone's done this is
you tell u you will have tell the class
what you felt that game well the the
other group's game felt like. So let
someone else figure out what your game
is.
>> Cool.
>> So uh does uh any team want to just go
first describe the the other teams? Um,
>> okay. That's studying with you.
>> Do you want to like describe the rules
they changed?
>> Uh, sure.
>> Just like So,
>> uh, the the the main change in this
version was that it's modular, so you
have to land exactly on the end or
otherwise you wrap around.
It it changed the aesthetic a lot
because it stopped being like a race
against your opponent and it became more
of like a a trying to figure out how you
can use your tokens to like precision
just hit the end.
>> Very mathematical. like uh methodical
you just like you decided whether or not
you're going to stock those things give
you more like winning squares and then
you just waited until you landed on a
winning square.
>> So you get into this computational
model.
>> Yeah. It's not it's not as like
competitive.
>> So one of the discussions we had was if
you had three tokens you would just get
to the end because we made our token so
you move four spaces.
>> Okay.
>> But I just realized you have to do the
die roll after that.
>> Yeah.
>> So automatically
>> Oh yeah.
>> Okay. Anyway,
uh let's see.
>> Yeah. So, they had a really creative
rule where they had a a d10 here. So, if
it goes from 0 to 9 and you roll it
under a cup and that's the number of
spaces away from the end. So, from 0 to
9 that the winning point is okay.
>> And in your turn, you can either play
normally or you can check to see where
the winning point is. If you've won,
that triggers you winning, but you
cannot win until you physically check
and confirm that you've won.
So, it eats up a turn, but it could be
that after one roll like or two rolls of
two and if this was a nine, you've won.
And and so there's there's and that was
a lot of fun basically because we had
yet figured out the optimal strategy,
but it was just fun. Yeah, it was.
>> So, so what's it feel like when you're
like when you're trying to figure out
what you're going to do? He's beat me by
checking when it was far away and being
lucky.
>> So if you don't check, you have to reach
the end to win. So you have to check
usually anyway in that game.
>> So So one thing we wish I had in mind
when we were thinking about the rule was
that there ought to be information that
you can get from how your opponent
reacts after they look under the cup. So
like if they then go and start rolling
again or what have you or they then like
stop file shift some I don't know.
>> Well I mean obviously
>> but there must be an abil some way that
you can get leaked information from
their behavior which makes it kind of
interesting in a different way.
>> If you have already seen the cup and you
get past the point do you have to check
to win?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. There are we there are two
different variants. One way you didn't.
>> Oh I see.
>> Well you don't have to check the second
time. If you check the first time then
you pass it. You win.
>> So that's one way of playing.
>> Okay. So the person who checks could win
even if both of them have passed the
point. Am I understand?
>> Well, so if he's the first pass a point,
the way that we're doing is if if you
don't have to check to fit to win. So if
you just need the knowledge of what the
end point is, then if he passes it
first, he wins. If when he checks both
players are at that spot, then it's a
tie.
>> Okay. Um, but since it's a sequential
game, it's impossible other than at the
moment of the check, if both players are
at the same spot, it's impossible for
them to hand out at the same time. So,
that's not really an issue.
>> What if I check and you're past me and
you have passed the checks part?
>> I don't win.
>> Okay.
>> I never checked. So, as long as I don't
know, I don't win.
>> That immediately makes me think of a
different variant. Okay. Okay. Cool. Um,
so what they did was they had it they
introduced a couple new rules. The first
rule being that the person who rolls
first on their first turn, they cannot
put down a token. So they actually have
to roll. The second rule is whenever you
roll, if you have a bonus, a token on
the stockpile, you have two options
after you roll. One is you can take it
off and move two spaces like normal. The
second is you can choose to make that
block impassible. And so what this does
is you cannot your opponent cannot land
on that block. If they are already on
that block, they get pushed one uh block
back. If they are behind it, they and
they roll and they move to that block,
they get pushed one block behind it.
>> So they're changing the map while you're
playing.
>> Yes.
>> And and how that feels while you're
actually playing.
>> We didn't actually use that much.
>> It felt like a rule.
I felt like the penalty for the impassel
block should have been more because if
you land on the block that they're on
and make them move back one, that token
would otherwise have made you move
forward too.
>> So, it doesn't really reward you for
that. I feel like if it had if it could
have been really awesome uh if the
penalty was like significantly more
severe because it's hard to like get in
front of them enough
>> to actually make a block impassible and
have them land on it later.
>> Um
>> Oh, all the way back or something.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, exactly. So yeah, you know, try
multiplying it by two and see what
happens.
>> You just go too forward.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And then you're not always
going to land on it.
>> Yeah. If if if you're like hm that
should have changed the game play, but
that didn't one the one one one of the
tricks in chapter one was, you know,
just multi just make it bigger and see
what happens. you know, if nothing else,
it will it will just give you more
information on you know, whether you
should be spending any more time with
this direction uh or whether it uh you
know, it really isn't going to affect
the way how people play because people
don't end up caring a lot. Uh so the
rule of two is just like multiply
something by two or half it by two and
see what happens. Um obviously hopping
by two will not take so long. Okay, who
else?
So essentially they had these tokens as
powerups
>> and you would never actually take them
off to move more spaces. You would just
keep adding tokens and you could roll.
So you could spend one turn to put a
token on
>> and then uh consequent rolls you could
essentially say I have n tokens. So
therefore I roll n plus one dice and
subtract n.
>> N + one dice. So I have three tokens.
>> You roll and then you roll a dieice for
each token you have and then move back
one space for each token you have.
>> Interesting.
>> So it moves your average and your
maximum up each time.
>> So you could add tokens to power
yourself up.
>> And you could also remove tokens to take
away tokens from the other guy, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So we never actually did it wrong.
Oh, one thing we didn't realize with uh
they I guess we forgot to go over the
fact that uh you don't take out all the
tokens when you do your special move.
They stay in there
>> because mathematically speaking, if you
take them all, it's just mov
uh well that that that's an important
object lesson in how to explain your
rules to people, but you know uh how it
feels there. Uh, it was it made my mind
tired being like n + 1 minus n blah blah
blah. But it was interesting. I actually
used it. Like before I said that I would
only use the D, but this time I actually
use token.
>> And what happens when you actually use
the token? Was it like yes or
>> like I said like the math made it too
hard for me to actually
>> Oh, something happened.
>> Okay. Well, it made you use the tokens
uh as opposed to
>> interesting. Okay, cool. Who has any?
Yeah. Jason.
>> Uh, so the rule that they gave was that
if you are behind the player, by by
behind they mean if your token if if
your piece is like behind the other one,
not like
>> in losing second place,
>> right?
>> But but not in the imaginary sense. in
the well whatever
>> if you're physically if you're
physically behind
>> if you're if you're physically behind
them then when you use a token you get
to move one extra space in it.
>> Okay. Uh if you can't if you use two
tokens you end up getting like one.
>> So how so how that feel?
>> Uh it actually changed the strategy a
little bit because you know in the
beginning you basically don't want to be
the person who moves first because then
your opponent can just use all their
tokens and get a lot further ahead of
you.
>> Oh, I see.
>> Interesting.
>> Okay.
Maybe you want to stockpile tokens and
then wait for the other player to get
ahead of you so that you can reuse them.
You can
>> then you just sit at the start line with
three tokens.
>> But then you're forced to roll.
>> So pretty much the person can go second.
>> So that's actually a negative feedback
loop uh uh which we'll get to I guess in
the next class. But you know the the
whole idea being if there is a gap
between players and you have game
mechanics that specifically are designed
to narrow the gap uh those are negative
feedback loops. You know pretty much
>> Mario Kart has
>> Mario Kart blue shell is the other
direction right is to knock back the the
the person who's leading rather than
helping you catch up. Um but actually a
lot of Mario Kart's mechanics are
basically designed trying to reduce the
lead. All right cool. Um who has it on?
>> Yeah. Um they added one rule keeping
everything else equal. They added a
second die and then the way it worked
was you arbitrarily assign people odd or
even numbers and then you roll to see
who would go on that particular turn
>> and then that person whoever it was
assigned to would play and then you
would roll again to see who went at the
next turn and so forth and so forth.
>> How feel?
I got I got I got bad memories with
Mario Kart. It's like what again?
>> Boy like I I
many mechanics I just described as very
Mario Kart like phenomenon.
>> Well, Mario Kart is actually a
collection of a lot of fairly
fundamental mechanics. But you know
describe specific
>> I felt like like just rolling to see who
went like amplified
the sense that you were just playing for
luck.
>> So it it amplified a randomness
basically which which I actually detest
personally.
>> Well the original game
>> yeah that rule is like the initiative
rule in Star Wars miniatures and
Dungeons and Dragons miniatures. Um, and
like in that case where there's like
actual strategic decisions to be made,
then it's it's actually kind of cool
because it means that you never know
like whether you're going to be able to
capitalize on the position that you were
in at the end of the turn.
>> That's exactly I was going to say it's
like since we both know optimal strategy
for the original game just
>> if there was harder strategy.
>> So it almost becomes like a a gambling
game of chance.
>> Cool. All right.
They added uh different dice you could
roll for different effects such as if
you rolled the d20 you could uh go 10
spaces if you manage to get a 17 18 19
>> 18 1920
>> or 18 1920. Yeah.
>> Um and they added the d10 which also had
similar effects and the d8. So Patrick
and I pretty much experimented with well
he just rolled the entire time
>> and I experimented with rolling the d8
from the d10
>> and just choose which one you
>> get and you use the d6 as well. Why
would he not roll?
>> Why would he not roll?
>> Yeah, I started feeling impatient. Like
I I I would forget everything about Alec
and what he wanted to do. And every turn
I would roll the d20 hoping to get 18,
19 or 20.
>> By the way, with the d20, if you don't
roll any of those, you go zero spaces.
So that's actually
>> you could either win the game.
>> I would roll the d20 waiting to get 18,
1920. And not until I rolled the 1820.
Would I care where he was on the board?
>> You and you.
>> It's just you and you and the random.
>> I won like twice.
>> No, I won twice, too.
>> Equal chances,
>> which which was slightly different. I
mean, like what you described earlier is
that, you know, whe whether you're
behind or in front of someone changed
the way that you play in the original
version. This one now no longer really
matters anymore, right? It is just you
and the dice and and if the universe
loves you, you would just automatically
win.
>> Well, the intention was to have the D20
that if you were like way behind and the
other ones if you were only slightly
behind, but apparently that's not how it
is.
>> Well, we have iterative design, right?
>> Well, it's a great example of the
aesthetic you were going for, not
necessarily being the aesthetic that was
actually experienced. So, you know, uh
it's still a powerful aesthetic. It's
just a different thing that
>> um I'm going to skip to you.
>> Yeah. Sorry about that.
>> Yeah. Uh so their new rule was
um if you're physically ahead and you
roll a six instead of only getting
three, you go four.
>> If you're physically ahead and you roll
a six, you go.
>> Okay.
>> Exact opposite from
>> Yeah. So at first we tried playing it in
a similar way to how we did before and
it really felt like the person who was
ahead was ahead even more and it all
everyone rolling because as soon as you
roll you get a higher expectation value.
>> So so you are more you you prefer to go
for luck rather than the
>> So the problem is if you put a token
down
>> then they're guarante they roll at least
a one so you're guaranteably going to be
behind and then they have a higher
expectation. So, so but how how does it
feel? I mean, sure, mathematically that
that's what it means, but
actually
in play in the first game, I don't think
it actually came up at all.
>> So, and then in the second game,
I believe it did. And
>> yeah,
>> I don't know. It to me it didn't really
feel like it changed.
>> I don't know. For me, the entire time I
felt like the person who was head was
more ahead.
>> It would come up more if your board was
longer.
>> Yeah,
>> cuz you're only encouraged to stockpile
for the first few turns. But if you're
encouraged more, then you switch.
>> Even in games where no one rolled a six,
do you feel like it changed your
strategy?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. It changed
>> just it made rolling feel like a better
engineer.
So
>> which was the which was the point,
right? That was what you guys were
aiming for.
>> Yeah. The the alternate rule that we had
toyed with uh was that if you are ahead
and you put down a token, you have to
roll and if you get a sick, you have to
move one step back. So like a one in six
chance of there being a penalty for a
token because precisely what you
mentioned which is that when you're
ahead, the diamond strategy basically is
to reduce the variance. So you're
playing with stuff to make you want to
roll more basically.
>> So So okay. So,
>> so dynamically that uh that that tell
that that tell tells you ro more uh and
uh I think I would say aesthetically you
have the whole monopoly situation of the
person who's winning keeps winning. Uh
and that's you know there are times
where you actually want that feeling. Uh
especially when it came to the game of
of monopoly the whole point of the game
was huge financial imbalances and then
it's like wow I have no money and I'm
just going to keep losing money. That
was the point of the game actually.
That's why it's called an
>> the amusing thing with that is that the
person who's physically ahead might not
actually be ahead in terms of in terms
of absolute gameplay because he might
have the other person may have
stockpiled
>> right
>> uh tokens
>> and and we weren't sure whether
determining who was ahead by counting
the tokens in the equation or not was a
better game rule if we didn't have
enough time to test.
>> Give it a shot after test.
Um, the one that we came up with was at
first we thought it wouldn't change the
game at all, I guess, which is basically
instead of spending tokens to go forward
two steps, you spend a token to knock
your opponent back two steps
>> and change the
>> completely change the game play. I think
other people we tried it really
what happened is like you stockpile
first and then you knock people back and
so like you didn't go anywhere for the
first like 10 turns and you realize that
nothing was going to happen and we just
kept rolling the rest of the time.
Yeah, but but which is a completely
different way to play the game. Yeah. Um
that that that whole process of
stockpiling right in the beginning is I
mean sure we could have both started
with a stack of three each because
that's really what will happen three
turns in but this but the whole act of
like
>> you know that that felt really like okay
clearly you are setting up to kill me.
Could
you move the very start?
>> Huh?
>> Can you move?
>> No. No. But we we we had it so that it
wouldn't be any point spending it uh
when you were right at the beginning.
But but there was that whole arms race
feel that we didn't have any game. Uh so
uh we didn't but I mean it all it did
really was make the game longer.
>> Yeah.
>> But it felt mean. Okay. Um that's pretty
much it for today I guess. Yeah. So, uh,
cool. And we need the poker chips and
all the dice back, but you can keep the
game boards really fast.
>> Yes.
>> How long did this game take you to take
you to make?
>> Um, it took longer to make the board
than to make the rules.
>> I illustrated going on.
>> I know. It's a word document.