Hello, good morning, good afternoon.
Hope everyone's doing well. Welcome back
to 61200.
Um, today we are going to be talking
more about proofs. Um, we spent all of
last lecture going through twothirds of
our definition of a mathematical proof.
Um and the last term we haven't talked
about yet uh is logical deductions.
So we said that mathematical proofs are
built from are verifications of
propositions. We talked a lot about what
propositions are um using a sequence of
logical deductions starting from a base
set of axioms and we talked about what
axioms are. So finally we get to talk
about logical deductions. This is going
to be the heart of how we build and
construct and check our proofs. Um, so
this is where most of the proofing
happens inside of our proofs. Um, so
what is a logical deduction? Let's see.
So an inference rule,
let's see,
is a rule for combining
true propositions
to form
other true propositions.
For example, one of the classic ones and
one we've um we've talked about uh
briefly is called modus ponins.
And I'm writing this just to say let's
not ever use those words again. Um the
the concept is um is intuitive enough.
If we know P and we know P implies Q.
If we know these
then we know Q.
Yeah. If we know P and we know P implies
Q then we know Q. If I think and
thinking implies amming then I am. Um
very intuitive. Let's again never
mention this by name. That's way too uh
precise for our uh for our purposes. Um
there are some other famous ones like if
we know P implies Q
and we know not Q sorry not Q
then all of this implies all of that
implies not P.
This is sort of the opposite direction.
If we know P implies Q but Q is false
then P better be false as well. Um
here's another fun one. Uh if we know
that not P implies false
then that implies P.
Basically saying if P isn't false then
it's true.
Hopefully intuitive
but we have the tools to not just rely
on intuition here. We can verify these
statements are actual inference rules.
Uh for example by drawing a truth table.
Um let's do that last one just because
it's smaller. Uh let's see. So uh we
have our we have P and it has two
possible values.
Um and then we have our big old formula.
So not P implies false.
PNS imply P. I want to make sure that
this formula on the right is always true
no matter what P is. Um okay. Well, a
useful way to fill out these uh these
truth tables
um is to go sort of one step at a time.
And I like to do that by drawing
directly under the symbol I'm working
with. So like not P. When P is true, not
P is false. And when P is false, not P
is true. And I put that right under the
the P bar. So I know I'm talking about
the P bar. Now let's talk about this
implies. Does false imply false?
Yeah. Yeah, that's true. Does true imply
false?
No, that's the case we need to avoid for
implication. Okay, so finally um this
this implies is really this whole
parenthetical um clause there. Does true
imply true? Because remember this is
true and false here. Does true imply
true?
Yeah. So this implies in this case is
true. Does false imply false? also yes.
Okay, so the column that corresponds to
the whole formula is always true no
matter what. And that is how we verify
that this statement right here is always
true. This is one possible way to verify
that. Um these other um inference rules
and lots of other ones that we're going
to use in this class. You can also
verify this way if you wish. Please
don't like do this in the middle of a
proof. Let's just use these rules. um as
rules that we're familiar with. You
don't have to reprove them every time.
I'm just showing you that we have the
tools to do it if we wanted to.
All right.
Um in general, when writing proofs in
this class, um we're going to want each
step to be clear and logical. We're
going to want to use a valid um uh
inference rule.
Um but we just want to use it. Um, it
should be clear from your writing what
rule is being used, but you don't have
to call it out every time. Like modus
pollins, modus tolins, I didn't even
tell you what that second one means. Um,
just go ahead and use it. We're going to
have a familiar set of tools and
deductions uh when writing these proofs.
So just um if you use those or you're
doing something else that is clear
enough um use that. And if it's less
clear, explain it more. Um, of course,
you should be explaining your steps. Um,
usually you're relying on facts that we
proved before or axioms that maybe we
haven't explicitly written down yet. And
you should be identifying those. When
you're relying on something, tell us
what you're relying on.
Um, let's see. Please don't use what's
called proof by intimidation. Clearly,
this is true. This is obvious. This is
intuitive. Uh, in fact, I would strongly
recommend striking those words from your
mathematical vocabulary entirely. Um,
anything that is clear and obvious to
you, well, first of all, it might not be
clear and obvious to your readers, um,
who might be your graders, who might be
your peers. Um, and that can lose your
points, u, because you didn't explain
yourself fully. That can be demotivating
for whoever is reading it, like, wait,
this isn't obvious to me. Am I not as
smart as I thought I was? Um, and of
course, it runs the risk that the thing
you said is obvious is wrong. Um, in
fact, this is a common source of
mistakes because instead of proving it,
you just glossed over it. Um, the proof
is there to help you check that things
are correct and help you catch mistakes.
And if you're skipping the proof, then
you're skipping that redundancy. Um, so
things are never obvious, things are
never clear. Please explain it.
Uh
um I I mentioned last time that we're
going to take basically all of high
school math as our common set of axioms.
Uh the the one exception to that is if
we ask you to prove a theorem and you
say, "I know this from high school math.
It's an axiom. I'm done." That's maybe
not
um adhering to the spirit of the
assignment. If we ask you to prove a
statement that you already know is true,
please please go and prove it. Um, we're
asking you to think more deeply about
why it's true. Does that make sense?
Cool. All right. So, using these logical
deductions and things like them, I want
to talk about a couple very common proof
outlines.
Proof outlines. Oh, that's not a Q.
That's a U. about lines
for proving some of the most common
shapes that our theorems might take.
For example, if we have a theorem,
there exists a natural number n such
that n is at least 10 and uh n is prime.
Here's our theorem. There exists a
number that's at least 10 and is prime.
There exists a prime um bigger than n.
Can someone prove this for me?
Yes.
17. That's actually the same example in
my notes. Well done. Um proof
n equals 17. Is that a full proof?
I mean kind of. Yes.
if we one more time.
Okay. Um so the suggestion was we should
be going through all of the possible
factors of 17 and show that they're not
factors to to verify that 17 is prime.
Absolutely. Um that is something we
haven't done. Um also we haven't checked
that explicitly. We probably want to do
that. Um, but let me back up and let me
write down what the general proof
usually looks like. Um, let's see.
Proof. Oops.
We'll show that n equals fill in the
blank
works.
This n
is in the set we asked for. It's in the
natural numbers. In this case, we're
going to secretly be using 17. Um, so
it's pretty clear, but in general, it
might be less clear. So,
for reasons
and n is prime
because
reasons.
So this is in general how we recommend
writing a proof of a of an exists. If
you want to show something exists in a
set with a property, you tell us what it
is. You show us why it's in the set, you
show us why it has the property.
Pretty intuitive, right? Hopefully. I
know I just used that word that I said
we weren't we aren't supposed to use. Um
but this is sort of inextricably tied
with what this symbol means. In general,
there exists a natural number. To to
prove that there exists a number with
this property, you have to show me a
number with this property. That's the
most straightforward way to do it. Um,
and that's what this proof outline is
letting us do.
In this particular problem, we're going
to say we'll show n= 17 works. This
number 17 is a natural number because,
well, yeah, that I I don't know how to
convince you of that if you're not sure
of that. Um and n equ= 17 is prime
because and this is where we should if
we want to be super careful check all
the possible factors um it's not
divisible by two by three by four etc.
Uh Eric
I am missing n greater equal to 10 um
yeah we need to show that n satisfies
this whole property um and n is
prime and greater equal to 10 because
reasons.
All right. So more abstractly, if our
theorem is
um there exists X in some set such that
P of X holds, then our proof can often
look like um
choose X equals some specific value that
you have to put in. Um
then X is in S
because
big to-do there.
These are these are our to-dos
and p of x is true
because
to-do.
All right.
Similarly, what if we're asked to prove
a for all
theorem
for all numbers
x in the reals. So for all real numbers
x x^2 - 6x
is greater than -10.
So this theorem is about a for all not
an exists. Um when we're asking about
exists we need just a single example.
But when we're asking about for all
examples aren't enough. Remember last
time when we talked about n^2 + n + 41
being prime lots of times? Well it's not
prime every time. If we're trying to
prove a for all, we need to show it that
the property is true for every possible
choice of X.
And in general, let's see what this
outline might look like. So if our
theorem is for all X in some set, P of X
is true.
Our proof usually looks like this.
Proof.
Suppose X is a generic
element of S
then P of X is true
because reasons,
right? I'm think it makes sense to put
little question marks in there so we
know that we we have to figure out
what's going on. There we go. this first
line. Suppose X is some element of S.
Which element? We're not allowed to
know. We're not allowed to choose a
particular one. We need to prove that
this is true for every possible choice
of X. Which means in our proof, the only
thing we assume about X is that it's in
S. So you start by taking something in S
and assuming nothing else about it and
then going and and concluding the
property that we need to show.
Again, this kind of like
These might look very similar to you and
they are. Um this says everything in S
has this thing. This says a generic
thing in S has this property. Um the
difference is that suppose X is a
generic element of S or however you want
to phrase that makes it concrete. It
gives us a particular X to talk about.
So now we have something to use and talk
about and reason about inside of our
proof. Whereas up here, every how do we
approach every that that's a little
daunting. I I only know how to deal with
one. So this gives us one. It's called
x. We know nothing about it except that
it's an s. But at least we have the one
and we can work with it. So whenever you
see a theorem that starts with a for
all, your first line is almost always
going to be this in order to bring some
into scope that we can talk about. Sound
good? Awesome. So how do we prove this
theorem
proof? Let's see. Let's see. Um
suppose x is an element of the real
numbers.
Then let's see x - 3^ squared is greater
equal 0.
Um because all reals
have non- negative squares.
This can be a fact we're citing from
high school. We know how the real
numbers multiply to each other. All
right. Right. And once we know this um
let's see equivalently
this thing says that x^2 - 6x
uh is greater or equal to -9
which in turn is greater or equal to -10
as needed.
So we started with pick some element of
r without specifying which one. We ended
with the property we need is true. QED.
Sound good? QED by the way um is a
common way to mark the end of a proof.
It's Latin for quote erat demonstrandom
which was to be shown. So it's a synonym
for like as needed or um as desired. QED
all the same thing. All right.
Question.
Sure.
So the question was could we do this a
different way? Could we look at like all
the negative numbers and they behave one
way and then look at all the numbers
between zero and three or zero and six
or something and they behave a different
way and then look at all the rest. Yes,
absolutely we can do something like
that. That's called proof by cases.
We're going to talk about it next
lecture.
Um but for now let's move on to the next
common outline which is proving uh
implications.
If we have a theorem
that says P implies Q.
I mentioned we're going to be using
implies all the time.
And often theorems say if this then
that. If P then Q. How do we prove this?
Our proof often looks like
assume P
then Q is true
because reasons
again looks pretty similar to the kind
of thing we're talking about. But this
first sentence assume P assume P is true
makes things concrete. It instantiates
um the thing we're supposed to be
assuming. Um it gives us something
concrete to work with. We can now live
in this hypothetical where we know for
certain that P is true and then work
with it as if it's true because inside
of this proof for the rest of this proof
it is.
Assume P. Use that to show Q. Whenever
we're trying to prove an implication,
this is a common way to do it. Um this
is called a direct proof.
Um
we're going to see indirect proofs a bit
later. Um but there is a another common
way uh actually sorry before that um
let's do an example of proving something
um in this fashion theorem.
Um, if n is a multiple
of 10,
then it is even.
If n is a multiple of 10, then it is
even. We're proving an implication. N
multiple of 10 implies even.
P implies Q. So even without having to
think very hard proof
assume n is a multiple
of 10.
We know we're going to start with that.
Assume the first thing we know we're
we're going to end with the last thing.
Therefore n is even.
So question mark question mark question
mark.
Therefore, n is even.
And if we can connect the dots from the
first line to the last line, we'll have
our proof.
Notice, by the way, that was kind of an
automatic process. If the theorem is an
implication, then kind of this is what
our proof is commonly going to look
like. So, we can just write it down. And
now we have a clearer, more concrete
sense of the task we're supposed to do.
Starting from the fact that n is even,
we're supposed to derive the fact that
it's sorry, starting from the fact that
it's a multiple of 10, derive the fact
that it's even. So, let's go ahead and
do that. Assume n is a multiple of 10.
Um, what does it mean to be a multiple
of 10?
So, n is 10 * k
for some integer k,
right?
Um, but then n equ= 2 * 5 * k
and so it's 2 * an integer. Therefore,
it's even. There's our proof. We're
done. Just by identifying where we're
supposed to start and where we're
supposed to end, we were able to bridge
the gap. Sound good?
Nice.
So, there's another common way of
proving implications.
Um this is called proof by
contraositive.
Recall last uh last lecture we said that
P oops P implies Q
is equivalent to its contraositive
uh let's see not Q implies not P.
This right here is the contraositive
contraositive.
And so if we're supposed to be proving P
implies Q, sometimes it's more
convenient to instead prove not Q
implies not P.
And so our proof outline
um would say proof by contraositive.
So assume
Q is false. Assume not Q.
See assume Q is false.
Then P is false
because question mark,
right? Same as we did for for direct
implications, but we're proving this
implication instead. So assume not Q,
use it to prove not P. And let's see an
example of this
theorem.
Uh let's see. So for all integers n
let's see
if n^ squ is even then
n is even
for all natural numbers n. If n squ is
even then n is even.
Now automatically oh we're proving a for
all. I know how to write that proof
proof.
Suppose n is an integer. Now we have an
n to work with right we need to prove
this implication.
Um let's see. So
proof by contraositive
always nice to say what proof technique
you're using if it's maybe not as
self-evident as it might be. So now
we're indicating we're proving this
implication by contraositive. And once
we've said that both you the writer and
your audience the readers know what's
supposed to come next. Proof of
contraositive. So assume
this thing on the right is false. Assume
n is odd
because that's the opposite of n being
even.
Want to show
n squ is is not even. N squ is odd.
This by the way wts um want to show
this. This I find is really useful for
me when planning out proofs, thinking
about proofs, sometimes even when
writing proofs. Um, this is an indicator
that this is where I'm trying to go.
This is the end of our proof. This is my
goal. Um, and it signals both to you
that this is work that's left to do. Um,
it signals to your reader that okay,
great. We we agree that we're working
towards the right thing. So now let's go
and do it. Um, and also as you're
writing scratchwork and solving these
proofs, um, and maybe you get distracted
and have to come back later and you see
a bunch of statements on your page.
Wait, which of these statements did we
prove and which are we trying to work
towards? So, um, as I'm working on these
proofs, I really like to be organized
and say, we know this, we know that, we
want to show this other thing. So, I
know that we haven't proven it yet and
we want to.
All right. So proof a contraositive. So
assume n is odd. We want to show that n^
squ is odd,
right? Because that's that's what the
proof method tells us to do. And now we
can go do it. Okay. So assume n is odd.
Um so n is 2k + 1. That's what it means
to be odd for some
integer k. Then n^2 is 4k ^2 + 4k + 1
which is 2 * an integer + 1 which is odd
q e d. And just to be precise about it
2k oop sorry 2k^ 2 + 2k but two times an
integer plus one is what it means to be
odd. So we're done.
All right.
So, we have proven implication. We've
shown two different proof outlines for
how to show P implies Q. One direct, you
assume P, use it to conclude Q. Um, one
sort of flipped around. Um, assume not
Q, use it to derive not P. Uh, there's a
related proof technique called proof by
contradiction.
Now, in growing up, you might have been
told, "Don't use double negatives.
They're not as clear. It's always much
stronger to more directly say what you
mean." But sometimes in math, a double
negative isn't what we don't want to
avoid.
I think there were four negatives in
there. Got it right. Yeah. Uh double
negatives can sometimes work to our
favor. uh and proof by contradiction is
exactly
that technique as a proof outline. So
let's talk about what this does. Um
proof by contradiction. So theorem
P whatever P is proof by contradiction
can be used to prove anything you want.
You know sometimes sometimes it it works
sometimes it doesn't sometimes it's
nicer but it's not assuming a specific
form of theorem.
Our proof looks like this. Um let's see
um for the sake
of contradiction.
Assume P is false.
All right. Assume P is false. Then the
proof continues.
Then some other statement R. Any
statement R we want we get to choose.
Then r is both
true and false,
which is bad. That breaks math.
Propositions are supposed to be true or
false, not both.
Um, that's a sign that our set of axioms
is inconsistent. And remember, that's
the the one thing we don't want them to
be. Um, if something's true and false,
then everything's true and everything's
false. And and that's bad. let's not
break math. Um, which is a
contradiction.
Um, and then to to explain it further,
so our assumption
is wrong.
So, P is true.
So we started by assuming P is false. We
broke math. So the assumption that P is
false must be wrong. So if P is false,
it isn't true. Um now I put this last
sentence in parenthesis because it's
clear, it's clearer than if you leave it
out. Um, but if you're writing between
people that all agree on how proof by
contradiction works and understand
what's going on, then just including
this word contradiction at the beginning
and saying
uh what the contradiction that we've
reached is, that's usually enough. You
don't have to have that that summary
statement at the end if you don't want
it. Um, that's a matter of personal
style, but you should be saying right at
the beginning that you're doing a proof
by contradiction, and you should say at
the end what your contradiction is.
Does that make sense?
Cool. Um, yes.
Yeah. Um, that's exactly right. This uh
inference rule that we analyzed at the
beginning is exactly what's justifying
proof by contradiction as a proof
outline. Um, if not P implies that false
is true,
then P has to be true. That's exactly
what this is saying and that's what the
proof technique is doing. Very well
spotted. Thank you. Um, I meant to say
that and might have forgotten. So, thank
you for the reminder. Um, a couple other
things about this. Um, for the sake of
contradiction,
um, there are lots of other ways to say
that. You can just say proof by
contradiction and that's enough to
signal to the reader that you're doing a
proof by contradiction. Um, I've also
seen
block by way of contradiction assume P
is false.
Uh, I have seen that. I like it. I don't
use it as much because I don't think
it's as standard. Um, but it's silly and
I like it. Um, at the end when you find
your contradiction and you want to say
this is a contradiction, we've broken
math. We're done. However you want to
say that part. Um, I've also seen this
symbol equals x equals because it looks
like two arrows pointing at each other
contradicting each other. That's another
fun embellishment if you want. But now
that we've seen the proof outline, hey,
that looks like a smiley face. Um, now
that we've seen the proof outline, let's
use it um on a real theorem. and that is
that the square root of two
is not a rational number. So remember
this blackboard bold q is the set of
rational numbers of um integer divided
by non-zero integer the set of all such
things. Uh and the theorem is that
square root of two is not rational.
So let's prove it. Often when your
theorem has a knot on the outside, it is
not true that property. Contradiction is
a common way to handle that because if
um because our proof by contradiction is
going to say well proof by contradiction
assume
and again I want to emphasize the moment
we say this is a proof by contradiction
what we assume is fixed. There's only
one thing we're supposed to assume. The
outline tells us what we have to assume,
which is that the entire theorem is
false. That's the only thing we're
supposed to do. We should still say it
because we want you and the reader to
agree that the correct procedure is
being followed. You're assuming the
correct thing. So assume that this is
false. In other words, assume that
square of two is
a rational number.
uh is not isn't
do what I say not what I write.
Um okay and now let's let's keep going.
What does it mean for square root of two
to be a rational number? Okay. Um so
square of two equals a over b
um for some
integers a and b where b does not equal
zero.
And as we might recall from high school
math, we can always assume that a
fraction is in lowest terms.
Um, in lowest
terms,
so a and b
have no common divisor,
right? We can always reduce a fraction
to lowest terms. So let's take that
fraction already written in lowest terms
and let's keep going from there. Okay.
So a over b= 2 means a = 2 * b
means a^2 = 2 b ^2
which means a^2 is even.
And wait, we already proved something
about if the square of a number is even
then the number itself is even. It's
very convenient that we already have
that there. So since a^ squ is even this
theorem shows us that a is even
by the theorem over there on the
previous board.
Yeah.
Okay. What does it mean for a to be
even? So a equals 2 times some integer c
for some c oop sorry for some integer I
did it again c in the integers
right that's what it means for a to be
even it's two times an integer so let's
keep going let's put this back into our
formula
um so now this says that 2 c^ 2 = 2 b
^2.
Right? So this says that 4 c ^2 = 2 b
^2. We can divide by 2. This says 2 c ^2
= b ^2.
But now b ^2 is even.
And as we know by our by our lema over
there again b is now even
by the same theorem.
Yeah.
Okay. So,
A and B are now both even.
So, they have a common factor
of two.
I to be more precise, no common divisor
is greater than one.
um a and if a and b are in lowest terms
then there's no integer bigger than one
that divides both of them. But we just
found that two divides both of them. So
this is our contradiction. This
statement here contradicts this
statement here.
Right? We have a single statement that
we showed is both true and false.
So we've reached a contradiction and our
proof is done.
Does that make sense?
Awesome.
Very nice. Very nice. Um, let me take an
one more minute to talk about these
proof outline techniques in general. Um,
now these aren't meant to restrict the
way you're allowed to prove things or
restrict the way you're allowed to
express things. They're there as
scaffolds to make sure you're proving
the right things
um and to direct your thinking. The more
you can break down a proof into smaller
and smaller to-dos.
Um first of all, the easier it is to
make sure that your proof is correct. Um
and secondly, the the easier it's going
to be to think about those individual
tasks. Smaller tasks are easier to
handle than larger tasks. Um, also a
common mistake when writing proofs in
general
is when you're presented with a theorem
to dive right in. Why is this true? How
am I going to figure this out
without taking the time to realize that
actually what's going on in your head,
what you're trying to prove is not
actually what the theorem is asking you
to prove. And so that's just a bunch of
wasted effort and lost points on your
homework. Um if you had taken a few
minutes um or with practice a few
seconds to do these um standard
outlining procedures to figure out what
the structure of the proof is supposed
to be,
then now you know what the structure of
the proof is supposed to be and you can
spend your um your precious thinking
cycles thinking about the things that
you're actually supposed to prove.
uh and let me demonstrate this um that
with proof you can make this automatic.
You can make this fast. You can really
use it to help inform your uh your proof
writing endeavors. So let's say we have
a theorem.
Let's see. So
an integer n is foolish
precisely when
n+1
is barome.
What do these underlying words mean?
Absolutely nothing. But let's imagine
they actually mean something. Let's
imagine this theorem is meaningful and
we've been asked to prove it.
I claim there's a lot of progress we can
make in writing and structuring this
proof even before we go and look up what
these two weird terms mean.
So let's do that. Okay. So this theorem
we can we can phrase it as for all n in
z
n is foolish if and only if n plus one
is barome.
Excuse me. Um, now this sorry I would I
prefer to write it like this. FN if and
only if BN plus one. I don't remember if
we talked about if and only if on
Tuesday. Great. Let's talk about it now.
Um, so P if and only if Q
also written as P if and only if Q
um means that P and Q are both true or
both false.
um P and Q
both true or both false.
It means they're expressing the same
condition. They're they're true in
exactly the same times. They're false in
exactly the same times. So they're
logically equivalent. Um one way you can
define this like we we could just draw
the truth table like we did last time,
but also commonly Oops.
Um this is this can be defined as P
implies Q and Q implies P.
If P is true then Q is true and if Q is
true then P is true.
All right. Um and this if and only if um
implies in both directions this concept
is what we mean when we say precisely
when these are true or false together.
Sound good?
Okay. So, we have our theorem. Let's
prove it. Proof.
Okay. The theorem starts with a for all.
I know how to handle a for all.
Um
suppose n is an integer.
We want to show
fn if and only if bn plus one.
Right? That was that was one of the
first outlines we talked about. If you
have a for all, you introduce a generic
one and you want to show the property
for that n. Right?
Okay. Well, now we want to show an if
and only if which we know is defined
like this. So really instead of all of
that, we can be a little more precise
with it. We want to show
that f(n) implies bn plus one and
that bn plus one implies fn. And once
we've done both of those tasks, we will
have proved the ifolith.
Okay. Well, now we're trying to prove
implications. We know how to prove
implications. Let let's use a direct
method for each of these.
So assume
um fn is true. Now we want to show bn
plus one.
So these are sort of separate sections
in our proof.
In this part we are temporarily assuming
that fn is true and using that to prove
that bn plus one is true.
And now down here uh assume
instead
that bn plus one is true. And now we
want to show fn is true.
And now our tasks are very clear to us.
We need to show that if fn then bn plus
one. We need to show um in addition to
that we need to show that if bn plus1
then fn.
And now at this point, there's not
really much else we can do without going
to look up what these terms mean, use
their definitions, figure out why this
thing is true. But this is where the
interesting part of the proof happens,
where the unique part of the proof
happens, the part that's specific to
this problem. Um,
yeah,
and that's a lot of progress that we
made even before the theorem even makes
sense. So once you get better at this
task um the easier it will be to set
things up correctly and set yourself up
for success.
Questions on that?
Awesome.
All right. So the other main topic for
today, we talked a lot about proof
outlines, proof by contradiction. The
other main topic is proof by induction.
[Applause]
And interesting I didn't I didn't hear
the groan that I usually get. Um proof
by induction is one of those t one of
those topics that um some students come
in with the impression that it's
difficult um that it's hard to grasp. Um
and there are reasons for that. Um even
before telling you what induction is, I
can tell you that
it's kind of a shame that we have to
teach you induction so early. um because
we're in we're now in the process of
telling you that proofs are supposed to
be clear and self-evident and um and
easy to follow. And then we come to
proof by induction which has a weird
outline that has lots of things you have
to say in weird orders for some arcane
region like we're summoning an ancient
demon. Why do we have to say this in
that particular way in this place? I
don't know. It's confusing and it is
confusing and there's a reason it's
confusing that sort of the reason
induction works and the reason that um
that the proof is structured the way
it's structured
isn't explained in every proof
byinduction
because everyone who's writing a proof
by induction assumes that everyone who's
reading their proof by induction
knows what proof by induction is and why
it works. So every proof by induction
you see is completely opaque and makes
absolutely no sense until you know what
induction is. And I think that's why it
can be difficult to approach. Um what
we're going to talk about right now is
first of all before I tell you what
proof by induction is let's solve a
problem together that's sort of going to
lead us to the the why and the how and
the what of induction. It's going to
tell us what we need to do and what tool
we need to do it and then induction will
be there right at the end to say I'm the
tool for the job.
So here is a theorem
theorem
for all n and z for uh sorry for all
natural numbers n
1 + 2 + 3 + up to n equals n * n + 1 /
2.
This might be familiar to some of you.
There are lots of ways to prove it. You
can prove it by induction. You can prove
it by picture. You can prove it by
counting. There are lots and lots of
ways. Um, we're going to talk through
one particular way of making sense of
this theorem. And let's just go by
intuition. I'm not we're not doing
induction right now. We're just we're
just figuring out why this thing is
true. Uh, so first of all, let's make
sure we understand what this thing is
even saying. Um for example
um so eg when n equals 4 this is
claiming that 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 equals 4 * 5
over 2 which looks pretty good. This is
10 this is 20 over2. Yeah they're equal.
And we're supposed to prove this um this
kind of thing for every natural number
n. Yeah. Um even all the way down to
just n equals 1. eg n equals 1. What's
the sum from one up to one?
It's just the one itself.
One is the sum of one term. Um, and
that's supposed to equal 1 * 2 over 2,
which looks like it does
even down to n equals 0.
What is the sum from one up to zero?
That's weird.
Um, that is a little weird. Turns out we
can make sense of it. um in this in this
context. So another way to write this
is with what's called sigma notation
k goes from one up to n of k.
And you can think of this like a for
loop. You start at k equals 1 and you
write down the value of k in that case
one. Then you go up to k equals 2 and
write down the value. k equals 3 write
down the value. All the way up to this
part you go up to k equals n write down
the value. And the sigma says you add
all these together. Sigma is the the
Greek s for sum.
Um so this is notation for exactly this
sum from 1 to n. Um and by convention
and there are good reasons for this
convention. But by convention
the sum from k= 1 to 0 the sum of zero
terms of whatever you want in here. But
now we're talking about the sum k
is just zero. The empty sum is zero. If
you're adding nothing, you have a total
of zero.
And in that case, the sum the empty sum
is 0, which is supposed to equal 0 * 1 /
2. And it does. Hooray. This theorem is
true when n equals 0 and one. And four.
We verified three cases, which is a
pretty good 0% of all the cases we're
trying to show.
But it's a good start. So, let's see
how to continue.
[Applause]
So, we are trying to show that 0 = 0 * 1
/ 2. 1 = 1 * 2 / 2. 1 + 2
uh is 2 * 3 / 2. 1 + 2 + 3 uh is 3 * 4 /
2. I'll stop in a minute, I promise. 1 +
2 + 3 + 4 uh = 4 * 5 / 2. Let's stop
there for now. But we're supposed to
prove all of these statements. That's
what the theorem is asking from us.
And we can we can think about this a
little bit. Um, if we stare at this, we
can notice that on the left side, to get
from this to this, we're adding one. To
get from this to this, we're adding two.
It's right there in how this sum is
created. To get from here to here, we're
adding three. Again, we're just adding
one more term to the sum. Then we're
adding four. Then we're adding five.
Then six, then seven, then eight, and so
on. There's a very simple pattern that
explains how these numbers are changing
from one row to the next.
So, wouldn't it be convenient if the
numbers on the right side followed that
same pattern?
And if they did, it would it would make
a lot of sense, at least to me, that
since they start at the same number and
we're making the same changes to both
sides every time we move down a row,
that all the rows are going to be equal,
that the left side is going to be the
right side in every row. Yeah. So, we're
hoping
that that's a plus one and that's a plus
two and that's a plus three and that's a
plus4
and so on. These are question marks
because we don't really know whether
that's true yet.
Uh, so let's write down what we're
hoping is true. 1 + 2 + up to n is
supposed to equal n * n + 1 / 2. And
then the next row, 1 plus 2 + n plus the
next term, n + 1 is supposed to equal n
+ 1 * n + 2
divided by two. These are two
consecutive rows in our big list. And
what we were saying is to get from here
to there, we're definitely adding n plus
one.
We're just adding this one more term
over here. So is it true that to get
from here to here, we're adding n plus
one?
And we can check that. Let's see. Um, n
+ 1 * n + 2 / 2 minus n * n + 1 / 2.
Well, we can factor in n+1 from both
sides. That's n +1 *
n + 2 / 2 - n /2.
That's looking pretty good. That's going
to be n +1 * 2 over2 * 1. That's just n
plus one.
So our hunch about that pattern is true.
To go from the nth row to the n plus
first row, we're adding n plus one.
Yeah. So what we said earlier is true.
This pattern of add one then two then
three then four then five that we saw on
the left is recreated on the right. Add
one, add two, add three, add four, add
five and so on.
So, at least to me, this feels like an
explanation that should make sense and
an explanation that we should be able to
write down somehow as a mathematical
proof.
Does anyone have questions about this
idea? I haven't said anything about how
we're going to write this, but is the
idea clear?
Awesome.
Um, let's see.
So let's dig in a little more and see
what exactly we accomplished over there.
So this argument here on the right um
that we did over here, let me write down
a little more carefully what we
accomplished.
Um and it's going to look like this. Um,
if
1 + 2 + n = n * n + 1 over two. If
that's true,
then
1 + 2 +
n + 1 equals n + 1 n + 2 over 2.
because we just
added n + one to both sides.
You would also want the algebra work to
show that going from this to this really
is just adding n plus one. And that's
exactly what we did over there. I don't
want to write it again, so I just wrote
the word algebra.
Does it make sense that this is what we
accomplished?
If this row of our list is true, if left
side equals right side, then the next
row is also true. Yeah,
cool. So, let's put some notation to
this.
I'm going to say that
P of N is the statement. By the way,
this colon equals is a way that we'll
commonly say P of N is defined to be
this thing. So not only is it equal to
this, but this line right here is the
definition of P of N. So let's define P
of N to be the statement that 1 + 2 + up
to N equals N * N + 1 / 2.
So PN is a predicate. It's not a theorem
on its own. Uh what is a theorem
is that for all n greater equal zero,
p of n is true.
That's what we're being asked to prove.
That's that's just a restatement of our
theorem from the top board over there.
And now
what we accomplished over on that board.
Actually, I want a fresh board for this.
Um, that's going to be this board up
here.
What we accomplished is first of all we
proved
P of 0.
That's the the first line up here.
And then
um these these statements up here, what
that's saying is that PN implies PN plus
one.
So we proved
P 0 implies P1. We proved P1 implies P2.
P2 implies P3.
P3, I'll stop, I promise, implies P4,
and all the way down.
This is what we really accomplished on
these last couple boards.
But this isn't the theorem we're aiming
for, right? The theorem we're aiming for
asks for P of zero, oops,
and P of one and P of two and P of three
and P of four and all the way down. We
want to know that all of these are true.
These implications are are not what
we're asking for.
However, it kind of feels like this
should be enough, right? Because once we
know P of 0 and we know P of 0 implies P
of one then modus ponins we know P of
one and once we know P of one this
implication tells us P of two once we
know P of two pair with this we get P of
three then we get P of four then all the
way down we get all of them I don't know
how to write that yet but that's the
intuition that I have guiding this um
and so it really feels like if we
accomplish the left side we should be
able to conclude the right side. Do we
agree?
All right. Um and now we have the
principle of induction
which just says
what we wanted to say.
The left hand side of this table implies
the right hand side of this table. If
you know all of these, then you conclude
all of these.
So when we're structuring a proof by
induction,
we must prove everything here on the
left. That is our responsibility. And
then
everything on the right we get for free.
by the principle of induction.
To be more precise, principle of
induction says if you know
P of 0 and
for all n greater equal z, p of n
implies p of n plus one.
That implies
for all n greater equal z p of n.
So that's exactly what's written in this
table just in formula form. P of 0 is
this first one over here. And then all
of the PN's imply PN plus1's are all of
the remaining stuff. And it says if we
accomplish all of these then we can
conclude these.
Yes.
Good question. So is the principle of
induction a new axiom or is it just a
name for this this intuitive fact that
we have? Um in truth what it's really an
axiom about is how the how the natural
numbers are constructed. Um really what
it's saying is that if you start from
zero and then add one add one add one
add one add one um to infinity you will
hit all the natural numbers. That's one
way of thinking about it. But in
practice when we use the principle of
induction we're using it like this. Um
so yeah you can take it as an axiom you
can take it as following from the
definition of the natural numbers. We
didn't really go that far down in um in
defining our fundamentals. So we'll just
leave it like this. Good question.
All right. So we have the principle of
induction.
We know what it's accomplishing and why.
So how do we actually write using the
principle of induction? Let's actually
write this proof now.
And the thing to always keep in mind
when writing a proof by induction is
this table.
We are responsible for proving
everything on the left side and then
we're able to conclude everything on the
right side.
So the theorem that we're trying to
prove should be the right side and then
we're going to do the left side to get
it. So
proof by induction
um we need to say what p of n um let's
see p of n is defined as the sum
n + one over two same way we defined pn
um before
and we'll show
that
PN is true for every n greater equal 0
by induction.
So the first thing we're responsible for
is P 0. That's usually called the base
case.
Base case
want to show P of zero.
Well, P of 0 says that 0 = 0 * 1 / 2,
which is true. So, we verified P of 0.
Usually, the base cases are pretty
straightforward. Um, it's the inductive
step,
inductive
step that we need to watch out for. Um,
we we now need to prove this whole
thing.
And we usually write it like this. um
assume
n is greater or equal zero
and assume
pn is true.
We want to show pn plus one is true.
And notice what we just wrote is exactly
the unpacked outline for this theorem.
It starts with for all. So assume n. It
then has an implication. So assume the
left side. Let's prove the right side.
Right? The things we write when we're
doing a proof by induction are not
magic. They're just unpacking this.
And now we can do it. The next thing I
always recommend um when proving
something by induction.
What is P of N? What is P of N plus one?
I know we defined it, but I can't
remember what it is. I always find it
much more useful to write these things
down in context. So in other words,
assume
we're supposed to assume p of n. So
assume 1 + 2 + up to n = n * n + 1 / 2.
And we want to show PN plus one which
says that the next row
uh n plus1 * n plus2
over two.
All right. And just by following the
proof outline and by identifying the
things we're supposed to identify now we
have a very clear task in front of us.
Assume this row, use it to prove this
next row. And we've already done that.
We know how to do that.
Um,
we know that this thing equals that
thing and then this plus that equals
that because of algebra. This is all the
work we already did. And now we're
seeing how the induction outline leads
us to figuring out that that is the
right work to do. Did that all make
sense? Yes.
Great question. Does this have to start
at zero or could it start somewhere
else?
Um, yeah, it can start wherever we want.
Um, if if we didn't know that P of zero
really made sense, uh, and we wanted to
start at P of one, we absolutely could
have started at P of one as our base
case and then all the implications above
that. Just keep in mind that by not
mentioning P of zero, we didn't prove P
of zero and so we can't conclude it
either. But wherever we started and all
the implications after it um those fit
together um to give us the thing on the
right side. Um yes that's a slightly
more general form of the proof of the
induction principle. Um please go ahead
and use that version as well.
All right.
So let's do one more proof by induction.
Uh this is a really pretty problem. This
seems to be a mandatory problem for any
textbook on discrete math. Um, it's one
of my favorites. And here is the
problem. Which board did I leave on?
This one.
[Applause]
So, the story is like this. We have a
big old courtyard.
um subdivided into lots and lots of tiny
little cells. It's going to be 2 to the
n tall and 2 to the n wide. So imagine
like 64 by 64. It's a big old
checkerboard.
Um
I'm just going to draw 8 by 8 because I
don't have that kind of time.
And now we're going to take a single
cell
and get rid of it. Which cell? I don't
know. Doesn't matter. Um the question
is, can we then fill the remaining cells
with these LORs?
You might know the word domino. It's two
squares next to each other. It's a it's
a fun game. Um this is like a domino,
but it's three squares instead of two.
and it's in the shape of an L. So it's
called the L traumo. And the question is
can we fill all of this board without
that one missing cell
um using L trainos and nothing else.
So that is our theorem theorem
um a 2 to the n by 2 to the n board
uh without one cell without any one cell
can be tiled
with l prominos.
So that's what we're supposed to prove.
And let's see if I can set this up
quickly.
Um, yeah, that's all right. See if I can
get the glare a little different. Okay,
I do want to plug in. Thank you. I
always forget this in Zoom meetings,
too. Please share your screen.
Yes. All right. So, I I I laser cut some
toys to help us play with this puzzle.
Um, so we're supposed to prove that a
two to the n by two to the n board can
always be tiled with elmos. Here, let me
put something on there for you to enjoy.
Well, let's phrase it like it were um
like we were going to prove it with
induction because we are. So let's say
that P of N
is going to be
um a two to the N by two to the N board
without one cell without any one cell.
Doesn't matter which one you pick
can be tiled
with L's. Going to call them L's not L
trromos. And notice I kind of just wrote
the same thing twice. That often
happens. P of N is not our theorem. It's
the predicate
um which is inside of the for all that
is part of the theorem. So this is
really every 2 to the n by two to the n
board. Um so if p of n is this then our
theorem
is that for all n greater equal 1 p of n
is true.
All right. And now we need to prove
this. Okay. Um let's start with n equals
1. You can think about what n equals 0
means. It turns out it's true. Um but
let's start with n equals 1. So a 2 to
the 1x 2 to the one board. That's a 2 x
two board. Um and can you see the the
little um crosshairs in there? It's a 2
x two grid. And we're supposed to say no
matter which single piece no matter
which single cell we remove, we can
always tile what remains with these
L-shapes.
Anyone see how to do it?
Yeah. All right. I'm gonna put that
there.
Solved.
What if the missing cell was in a
different place? Like there. Yep. Okay.
Can still solve that. We're allowed to
rotate. So the 2 by 2 case isn't very
hard. Um, so let's keep track of our
progress.
P of one. Actually, I'm going to write
this as
the 2x two case. Not very hard. Let's
let's step it up a little. What about
the 4x4 case?
And say we're trying to avoid that one
cell. Well, we also need to solve it for
avoiding that one cell and that one
cell. We need to solve all 16 cases
because the theorem says it doesn't
matter which one you exclude. You can
always tile the rest.
Um, well, you can play around with this.
I have lots and lots of of pieces to
play with.
You can you can tell I had way too much
fun designing this thing. Um, and turns
out you can you can make it work. Um,
like this one. This is one of the 16
examples. Turns out if I put that one
there and then that one there and there
and there and there, then I've solved
it. I've solved this one out of 16
cases.
Um, but also it turns out it's not too
difficult to generalize from there.
Um, like if the missing cell is in
one of these four positions, then I know
how to do it.
If it's in one of these four positions,
then I also know how to do it. If it's
there, I can just put that there. If
it's there, I can put that there. If
it's in one of these four spots, can
still do it.
if it's one of these four spots can
still do it. So by looking at all of
those 16 cases combined, we now have a
way that can put that yellow cell
anywhere we want and finish tiling the
rest. Not a very
nice or clean argument, but at least we
did all 16 cases. So that's good enough
for now. Let's call the 4x4 case solved
for now
and move on. Um, and I want to emphasize
this is actually a key moment in this
proof.
We just solved the 4x4 case by looking
at all 16 cases and showing that they're
all possible. I want you to hold that
deep in your heart that we have solved
4x4. Any 4x4 you ever see with a single
missing cell can be tiled.
Yeah.
I want you to hold that deeply in your
heart and then not worry too much about
how we did all the 16 cases. Just know
that it's true. Are we comfortable with
that for now? 4x4 case is fully solved.
Let's move on to 8 by8.
We have an 8 by8. There's a single cell
we're trying to avoid. Maybe it's there.
Um maybe it's over here. Let's leave it
there. I don't care. Um what we're
really looking for here is sort of a
generalizable method. I don't want to do
64 cases and in the 16 x 16 case I don't
want to do what is that 256 cases.
Please don't make me. Um we want a
generalizable process that we can that
we can use to solve every board size.
Um and here is a cool idea that works
nicely. Um
so first thing we're going to do, we're
going to we're going to shift our
perspective. This isn't an 8 by8 board.
This is for 4x4 boards.
All right.
And now um let me just make this one
purple for now to remember that that's
the special one. We cannot move that
one. However, remember we we have solved
the 4x4 case. So like if we if we're
missing a cell somewhere in this
quadrant and missing a cell somewhere in
this quadrant and missing a cell
somewhere in this quadrant,
but now we just have four instances of
the 4x4 problem. We have four 4x4s each
missing a single cell. And we know how
to solve all of those, right? So, we
know how to solve all of the red that
remains. Unfortunately, we're not
actually allowed to use these individual
cells. We're supposed to cover
everything with our L-shaped tiles.
Um, but remember, doesn't matter where
we put these yellow ones. Anywhere we
put this in here, we know how to solve
that quadrant. Anywhere we put this in
here, we know how to solve that
quadrant. The purple one was the one
that's given to us. We're not allowed to
move that. Um, but the next clever idea
is what if we put the yellow ones right
there and then think of them as not
three individual cells, but as an L in
their own right. No, there we go.
So now this is going to be our key idea.
Um, if we're trying to tile
everything except the single special
cell, step one, think about it as four
separate quadrants. Step two, put an L
right in the middle, directly in the
middle, to make sure that each of the
four quadrants is now missing one cell.
Yeah.
If this initial cell that we're supposed
to avoid is somewhere else, well, then
we just put the L to touch the other
three quadrants. So, we just rotate it
this way instead.
And once again, every single quadrant,
all four quadrants are missing a single
cell to really drive that home.
Let's see. Uh, we have this shape here.
That's a 4x4 missing a corner. This
shape here is a 4x4 missing a corner.
Here's a 4x4 missing a corner. Here's a
4x4 missing that initial cell. So we
have four separate problems where if we
can solve the four orange cases, we'll
be able to piece them back together to
form a solution. And this is why we
stored that deep in our heart. We know
we can solve 4x4s with a cell missing.
So we know all four of these orange
quadrants can be filled.
So we already know that this bigger
shape can also be filled.
So we're done. No matter where this one
started,
um, we can do this thing. We, we put
down the cross, we put the L in the
middle. Now we have four quadrants, each
missing a cell. We invoke the 4x4 case.
And now we've solved any 8 by8 case
that's given to us. Does that make
sense?
So if we believe that we can solve every
4x4,
then we also believe that we can solve
every 8 by 8. Yeah.
And this keeps going. If you instead had
an 8 by8, sorry, if you instead had a 16
x6, you can do the same thing. Draw the
crosshairs, put the L in the middle. Now
all four 8 by8 quadrants are missing a
single cell. Invoke the 8 by8 case. Um,
we can even see that here.
Go away webcam.
Um, so here here is a 16x6 with one cell
we're supposed to avoid. So let's cut it
into four quadrants and put an L right
there in the middle. Now we should think
of this as four separate 8 by8s each
missing a single cell
and we trust in our heart that we have
solved the 8 by8 case. Right? Don't
worry too much about how we solved it.
Just be confident that we solved the 8
by8 case. Um that there is a way to tile
each of the 8 by8 corners. Um so now we
can piece them together to form our our
16x6 solution. And now it's all it's all
L tile tiles and we win.
So this is the idea behind this proof uh
that we're that we're able to show
that PN
always implies P of N plus one. If you
can tile a 2 to the N by two to the N
missing one cell
then you can tile Oops. Then you can
tile a 2 to the n plus1 by 2 to the n
plus1
missing a tile using our strategy of
taking the 2 to the n plus1 by 2 to the
n plus one
and cutting it into four quadrants
of 2 to the n by 2 to the n. Put an l in
the middle. Make sure each quadrant is
missing a cell. Invoke the the inductive
hypothesis.
That was a little sketchy. Um I didn't
write this down carefully. uh you can
check the lecture notes later if you
want to see this written down a little
more carefully but that is the core idea
um and the problem I want you to see
there's one more thing I want to mention
before we go um so I I kept saying store
it deep in your heart that we've solved
the 4x4 and then use that to believe
that we've solved 8 by8 um believe that
we solved 8 by8 in order to believe that
we've solved 16 x6 but sometimes belief
isn't quite enough and you really want
to actually run this algorithm. Um well,
for then all all you have to do is um
when you h when we have the 16 x 16 and
you break it down into 8 by8s. Well,
let's actually remember how we solved
the 8 by8s. We did that by splitting
them up into 4x4s. And then turns out
you can do the same thing and split the
4x4s into 2 x2s. So now each 2x two is
missing a single cell, but a 2 x two
missing a single cell is just an L. So
it's all L's. And then we just recombine
uh reverse what we did before. And now
we've tiled everything and we're done.
And that's the algorithm. Thank you so
much.
[Applause]