Hello everyone. Good afternoon. Uh my
name is Yael Weiss. I'm the CEO of a
company by the name of Mazi Therapeutics
and I'm here to introduce the speakers
of the next session. You guys have an
advantage over me because you probably
know the speakers better than I do. So I
decided to go beyond the small intros
that I got and look at people on the
online. And Nile, Dr. Nile Lennon, he uh
is obviously the dawn of the labs here
at the Broad. He needs no additional int
introduction, but can I see your hands?
Can you go like this, please? So, I
looked him up and his ex profile, he is
holding his hands like this. Now,
there's nothing on them, but it says
science rules,
right? He hasn't posted since
2021. So, that's that's actually a plus,
but that's what his profile shows. So,
science rules, guys. Dr. Nile Lennon.
Oh, thank you.
All right. Um, thanks for that intro.
That's great. I didn't even know I still
had a profile, so maybe should delete
that. Um, all right. Uh, so this is
going to be very different than probably
the last couple of talks. I'm not really
going to talk
about specific sort of biological
disease stories, per se. This is really
kind of technology nerd update. Um and
and maybe just for folks who may be new
or maybe come in from out out of town,
just to kind of say a little bit of
background. Um first of all, what's this
logo? Who is this group? Why have I got
the wrong clicker?
Um do I have the wrong
clicker? Do you have the other clicker?
You're bringing it home. You got the
right clicker. All
right. Gotcha.
Perfect. Hey, it worked. All right. Um
we'll hide this one. All right. Um so
just in case you haven't sort of you
know been here for 20 years like I have
um you may be more familiar with a group
called broad genomics platform and so
that essentially has been the group that
operates the sequencing technologies at
the broad institute um since its its
formation I mean it was called other
things it was sequencing platform but
basically where the big sequencers live
um that's the broad genomics platform
about 10 years ago um actually you know
David Uler was the executive sponsor and
I led a project to build a clinical lab
at the broad. So that is essentially a
clea certified um entity that allows us
to do testing under clea regulations for
projects that want to be in that
translational space maybe as a research
study but want to do return of results.
Maybe is a clinical trial but wants to
be able to have an auditable quality
system or actually wants to do
diagnostics. And so we created a new
entity back in the day. It had a
different name to begin with. I won't
even say it. It was unhelpful. Um uh but
it's a wholly owned LLC of the Broad
Institute that that operates our
clinical um license. Now it's called
Broad Clinical Labs. Um and our lab
director is Heidi Rem, who most of you
will probably know. Um so for all
intents and purposes, you can think of
the two things synonymously. Broad
Clinical Labs doesn't have any
employees. It's essentially Bro Genomics
platform, but Broad Clinical Labs is the
entity through which we do two things.
One is any clinical work that's
regulated um and two any external work.
So if a pharma company wants to work
with um us for you know genomics project
they actually contract with broad
clinical labs um even if they're doing
research work. So it's just sort of it's
our external facing um sort of brand to
the world. But for all intents and
purposes, if you're at the broad or in
the broad community, it's the same
group. All right. Um Oh, something has
changed. So, you know, um when I joined
20 years ago, um the sequencing group uh
was a few blocks from here in 320
Charles Street in that lovely old
building that housed the sort of human
genome project uh labs. Um we are no
longer there. We have moved all the way
out over here to Burlington,
Massachusetts. Um, which is about 14
miles from here. Um, um, so for most of
you that isn't a big deal. It doesn't
really make too much difference to you.
Um, this little green circle is where I
live. Um, so it's actually exactly the
same distance, but to drive to Kendall
Square it takes me 45 minutes and to
drive to Burlington takes me 15 minutes.
So for me, it's an improvement in
quality of life. Um, it's actually an
improvement for quality of life for the
people who work there, too. We actually
built an entirely new building from the
ground up. Uh, it's a beautiful
building, 145,000 square feet of new lab
space, customdesigned for a sort of
modern genomic center and clinical
testing laboratory. And we have about
200 people who work out there. And so,
if you're ever in the Burlington area,
please feel free to uh swing by. It's
like any other broad building. You can
come in, you can find a hotel space, you
can work. We have 40 meeting rooms that
are not booked most of the time. Um,
so anyway, so that's where we're at if
you're ever looking for us. Um, but I
also want to point out that now rather
than sort of just running sequencers, we
actually do quite a lot of things under
the umbrella of um, GP and and BCL. Um
so obviously we run a lot of sort of the
you know genomic assays that many people
will use um genomes and exoms and RNA
and you know single cell sequencing and
all that kind of stuff and we have
versions of those things that have been
validated for clinical use as well. Um
we we run microbial whole genome we have
you know we have all sorts of fun stuff.
Um but we've also now got um things like
um patient engagement um capabilities.
So the count mein group which was uh you
know for folks who've been here a long
time originally um sort of initiated by
um um Nick Waglay and then and Corey
Painter as a way to enroll directly
enroll participants into uh research uh
and then became sort of its own sort of
spinout entity from the broad has kind
of rejoined the broad and now sits
within uh the GPCL uh group um
and so and I'll talk a little bit more
about that in a Second, we also have
things like, you know, if you have a
research study where you actually want
to directly enroll participants, we can
directly send saliva kits to people's
homes and receive them back. And so we
have thing capabilities like that. Now
um we also have if you if you work in
the Kendall campus um the um molecular
development lab MDL methods development
lab MDL uh run by Aziz Alavage and
that's sort of like hardcore molecular
R&D type work. And so many folks work
with Aziz's team on sort of, you know,
novel methods if you need to sort of
figure out, you know, ways to construct
things. So they work sequencing wise if
you're interested in isoforms. There's
lots of things that Aziz's team works
on. And they sit on this campus, but
they're part of the GPCL um group. And
uh recently just at the end of last year
we also um uh brought in uh Victoria
Puppik who is um a Schmidt fellow who
now leads our computational R&D team as
well and so she's really um developing a
lot of sort of machine learning methods
in um you know things like calling
structure variation and other uh things
as well. So we have that capability as
well. And sort of a new thing that sort
of hasn't been sort of fully formally
rolled out yet, but some people know
about is we are actually starting to
build out cell services um cell factory
services. And so that means now you know
we've actually stood up um cell culture
and the ability to do very large scale
cell um processing at in Burlington. And
this is really in service of what you've
been hearing sort of the you know
massive explosion of this idea of using
perturb seek and other um methods to do
largecale discovery uh in cells and we
see that as a very very large growing
area. There's programs of the cell.
There's a whole bunch of people now
planning out very large cell programs.
And so we're moving from individual
experiments which are sort of hundreds
of thousands to millions of cells into
billions of cells. And that's something
that a platform is really set up to
actually do really well. And so we're
we're actually just kicking that off
now. And so that's going to be an
exciting area in the next few years. All
right. Uh just on the CMI just for for
rare diseases specifically, it can be
useful. So having knowhow a team who's
been doing it for years uh independently
but um how to actually set up studies
how to develop enrollment strategies to
actually then operate those outreach and
enrollment to have software to support
online consent and enrollment into into
studies the backend infrastructure to
send out kits for sample collection
directly to patients and participants.
have those come back have your your
molecular data generated and then
submitted to whatever cloud environment
you're actually going to do your
analysis in. So this has of course
powered uh many of the projects that me
people know there's been over 20 studies
done at um with the count me in group
including the rare gems project at
project angio saroma many rare cancer
projects as well so this idea of
connecting people directly allowing
people to enroll around the country into
these studies is very powerful and and
we're working really hard to try this
into like a sustainable sort of uh
business model that we can that we can
run and offer offer to people to come
work to work with us. So, we're not
just, you know, send us your DNA and
we'll take it from there, but like help
us enroll the actual community that you
need um to power your study. All right.
Um so, just to get technical and nerdy
then for a little bit, there's going to
be a couple of updates that you you may
not care about or you may not think
about a whole lot, but I wanted to let
you know what's been happening in
genomics technology over the last six
months to nine months, just so you're
all aware. um uh lots of things use
short read sequencing. So you know you
again oh I should I didn't mention in
the other slide. So the bro technology
space is also part of um GPB um BCL and
that's for groups you know on main
campus who want to walk up and use a
benchtop sequencer there's tons of
technology in Trish's space at the broad
technology space um and that's another
um sort of service for the group. If you
need the big big sequencers or you need
like the highest amount of data for the
lowest amount of cost those are the
things we actually operate out in
Burlington. The latest version of those
for Aluminina if you're if you're
interested is the Nova X. Uh we have
like 15 of them. Um so we run them a
lot. Um we did a 100,000 genomes last
year. Um I think a week ago we crossed
750,000 human whole genomes done over
all time. Um so we have a lot of
capacity to sequence. Um now um so the
one thing about these machines allows us
to keep trying to push that cost down.
So it makes it feasible to do whole
genome sequencing. um and continuing to
support all kinds of input uh materials
for those. So hopefully, you know, the
path of genome sequencing costs going
down will continue. Although I will note
that companies like Aluminina have
started issuing notices to saying
because of tariffs, we're increasing our
prices. So hopefully that'll change next
week because that's about the new cycle.
So all right,
um Dragon. So if you care about data
processing and secondary analysis um you
may be surprised that as a default we
actually give people who do whole genome
and exo sequencing with us dragon align
data. So this is a a company that was
purchased by aluminina and is now
integrated into their sequencers but
also as standalone servers. Um we've
partnered with them and had a
collaboration agreement with them for
many years. So if you send samples for
sort of default genome exom sequencing,
you'll get this dragon 3.7.8 aligned
data. Most you may not care about that.
The reason it's that version is that's
the version we all collectively lock
down on for the all of us research
cohort. So the 500,000 genomes or so
that are in the all of us data set are
all aligned with that data with that
version of the aligner. And so that's
sort of the default research version
today just so people can if they want
and are able to do sort of co-analysis.
At some point hopefully somebody will
solve the problem of alignment version
specific joint calling and then we won't
have to worry about what version we're
running but right now we do. Um I will
point out that if you send a sample for
a clinical whole genome you actually get
a very different output from the
secondary analysis pipeline. It's a
later version of the Dragon 436. Um, and
what that means actually for those users
who do get that is that we've been sort
of diligently working away at validating
the outputs from secondary analysis so
that they can be used in clinical
research and for clinical reporting. So
from our clinical genome today obviously
short variants but also CNVs and SVS
certain types are validated. We've also
um done the sequencing and are in
process of writing up the validation for
repeat expansions, specific repeat
expansions. We've got um SMN calling
validated and we're working through the
other um difficult genes. Um so Dragon
and the Luminina team and us have been
collaborating on sourcing clinical
specimens and running them and modifying
the methods to improve their ability to
um call in these um traditionally
difficult genes um that are clinically
meaningful. And so there's a host of
those that we're sort of working our way
down through. We also you also get PGX
um star al calling um out from the data
as well, although we don't include that
in our clinical reports today. So
contact us if you're interested in
different types of um secondary
analysis. Um blended genome exom is
something that we developed with um Ben
Neil's team and the Stanley Center for
their large scale GIWAS studies. Um it's
a lowcost uh version. It combines
basically exoms and low passhold genome.
So if you want to do rare variant
monogenic discovery in the exom region,
but you also want to do essentially
imputation um across the rest of the
genome, it's a it's a good balance
between sort of um performance and cost.
So for research purposes, if you have a
large scale study at the broad, it's
like a $99 assay. So it really replaces
what you might have done with a
genotyping array and a and an exo in the
past, but it has the benefit of not
being essentially biased to the content
of a genotyping array. Um, and now we've
made a clinical version of it. The
clinical version has deeper exome
sequencing. So you have sort of that
typical standard of being able to call
monogenic variants in the in the coding
region. And we're actually using that
now with partners. Um so um MGB Matt
Lebo's team at MGB in the in LAR from
molecular medicine just launched a a
suite of uh polygenic risk scores um
developed by Praep's um team um using
the clinical BGE as the data source
behind it. We are also directly doing a
clinical trial with Jason Vassie and the
and the Boston VA on prostate cancer
risk um where again you can look at pro
known prostate um cancer monogenic risk
in the coding region and then from the
low pass we do an imputation on a a
prostate um polygenic risk score that
was developed in the million veterans um
program and validated in the all of us
um data
set. All right, completely different.
Um, so you may or may not have heard
about this. Um, it was mentioned at at
ASG last year. Um, so this is an
aluminina, a new aluminina prep type.
They called it constellation, the
marketing name constellation. Um, but
essentially what it is, it's a way to
create linked read data from short
reads. So not long read data, but
spatially linked read data from short
reads alone. Um, and the kind of cool
techy part of it is essentially what you
do, you take your DNA, if you have good
quality samples, you can do a high
molecular weight extraction. That'd be
even better. And we actually just like
load it directly on the flow cell. You
don't do anything else to it. You don't
fragment it. You don't adapt it. You
don't do anything. You just load it on
the flow cell. So, for one thing,
there's no sample prep. So, that's
different and cool. What it actually
means is that on the flow cell, so what
they've done, it's a tech they had for
many years and they couldn't really
figure out what to do with it, but
essentially in the wells on the surface
of the flow cell, they've essentially
modified a um a a tagmentation um enzyme
that if you sort of layer a a DNA, a
molecule on top, you know, I have this
kind of hungry hippo thing in my head,
like it sort of reaches up, grabs a
piece of DNA, tagments it, adapts it,
and clusters it inside the inside the
well. It doesn't do anything and so it
does that um it doesn't do anything else
different really. So you're still doing
short read sequencing after the fact
after you do cluster generation. But
what you end up with is actually then
when you look at the data because new
aluminous flow cells are not a random
lawn of oligos like they used to be.
They're an ordered array of of
essentially sort of wells. You can look
at the read data and then you can look
at the spatially adjacent read data and
say, "Huh, based on mapping, this one is
more likely to have come from the same
molecule that was laying on top than
not, right?" And so you can use that
model to essentially recreate links. And
what it does is means that you can
create now confident sort of phasing and
linking of of short read data into long
read contigs, which really helps with
things like mapping. So if you look at
like clinically meaningful difficult
genes like stericylin, PMS2 these other
genes um where just in short reads alone
you would always get this dropout
because of homology when you start using
linked information you could actually
confidently link and place those reads.
So you essentially recover coverage in
these traditionally difficult regions.
So that's kind of cool.
Um um there's a lot more data, a lot
more genes we've looked at, but just to
summarize, if you are if you have sort
of high quality DNA going in and you can
do a high molecule extraction, we can
actually fully phase almost all the
genes um with short read data. That's,
you know, we never could do that before.
So that's cool. Um and you get these
quite large, um phase blocks. And so
you're actually, you know, you're
getting like
um um recreating sort of up to like 40
KB chunks in the genome. So that's um a
really interesting application. We've
run clinical samples on it from
difficult genes and shown that we can
confidently call them. It doesn't impact
your short read um performance. Um so
the big thing so it's not commercially
available yet. So we're working through
in a collaboration to like run new
samples through it, understand its its
um utility. Obviously with Victoria's
team, we're collaborating to see how can
we leverage this for better structure
variant calling from short reads alone.
The one thing we don't know yet is like
what will it end up costing. Um so if
you've been sort of paying attention,
the one thing we can't do right now is
barcode because you've taken your DNA,
you've just loaded it on the flow cell.
So you can't multiplex. So right now the
cost would be whatever the cost of one
lane of sequencing is, which has come
down a lot, but it's still like $2,000.
So that's not great. So Aluma is working
on ways to like figure out what it
actually could cost. So that's um but
it's a really interesting way. It sort
of gets you partially like a lot of the
things you might have traditionally done
long reads for, but not everything. But
so that's one thing that's new that
people might be interested in. Um,
talking of long reads, you know, PAC
Bio, we still have 10 Revio instruments
that we can run. Um, PAC Bio has least a
new chemistry for those recently. It did
reduce the input requirements. So,
that's good. That can often be a barrier
to using long reads. Um, increase the
yield. It allows us to lower cost. It's
still two to 3x more than a short read
genome, but they are continuing to sort
of, you know, promise that this cost
will come down and it at some point in
the future could be on par with a short
read genome. So, we'll see. Um, we are
actually doing a clinical validation of
the Revio now and so that we will have a
clinical grade sort of genome from um,
Revio for those translational studies
for clinical research as well. Um just
on that just to point out one thing
we're doing as a collaboration with PAC
Bio and Wendy and and Alan Begs at
Boston Children's is a study to
understand the impact of doing long
reach sequencing on rare disease cohorts
uh within BCH. And so um we've actually
run over 600 um samples from um the
aggregate sort of consortium within
Boston Children's of rare disease and
orphan diseases um across a range of
different sort of um clinics. Um and you
know some of these are legacy samples
some of them been around for quite a
while. So performance is has been up and
down across the cohort. Um some of them
we were able to get fresh material from.
Um but we've been able to get you know
about over 20x uh genome coverage in
general from all of these cases. Many of
them are trios. Um almost all of these
will have already had short read
sequencing and you know are still sort
of unsolved and so analysis still
ongoing but the different investigators
have been reporting back and so we're
seeing about a 15% of cases having new
findings when you look at this long read
data as well. So, so we'll see, you
know, this uh is
15% good. Is it good enough to justify
doing long reach sequencing on on cases
like this? Um, and you know, how that
all will all play out um when
constellation comes out, we'll see. But
this has been uh really good to at least
get new data to uh Boston Children's.
All right. Um, quickly, last one or two
slides. Um you may have heard about this
uh announcement uh earlier this year. Uh
RO um the giant pharma company and
diagnostics company has been investing
for actually has had internally for many
many years a program to develop a
sequencer and they finally launched it
or at least announced it um earlier this
year. It's the um sequencing by
expansion um method. And without going
into the technical details, there's a
preprint and stuff with a lot of detail
if you want to go into it. It's kind of
interesting. It's a nanopore sequencer
or at least the detection module is a
nanopore. Um, but the big difference is
in how they do essentially the prep and
I kind of like to call it the pool
noodle method. And so what they do is
essentially they have a expandimemer
um chemistry which takes your DNA
template and essentially for every
nucleotide labels it with these really
large macroolelecules and then allows
you after you've labeled it to cleave it
such that essentially you break the
nucleotide bonds but you've got in
between them these giant pool noodles.
And so the point being when you run
something through something through a
nanopore it goes really quickly. And so
most of the error modes in nanopore
sequencing come from the the rate of
sort of things transver traversing the
pore and the signal being so small from
nucleotides which are really small. But
pushing pool noodles through the
nanopore is a really big signal. And so
it actually allows you to get much
better signal to noise and and then
recapitulate that. So um so what they've
built is a system to actually leverage
this um which is like a lot of
complicated chemistry to make it work um
but it's massively fast and so you can
do a rapid duplex um run and get about
600 gigabases in one hour which is four
times faster than we can get on the Nova
X and and so and to put that in context
like the actual like if you just did had
a library ready to go it's about 20
minutes of sequencing time for a whole
human genome. um for 30x like that's
kind of crazy. Um we've been testing it
uh as a fast clinical um option for
sequencing and we've been able to get a
trio analysis done sample two variants
in seven hours from everything from
sample collection to variance in about
seven hours. And so obviously we're
really interested in where this can go.
Um, we've also been doing some some work
on on what could this mean for single
cell work. Like it produces a tremendous
amount of data. So that's a very new
technology. Um, and we'll, you know, be
collaborating with them over the next
few years as well to see what we could
do with that. All right. Uh, last slide.
I think just to point out, there's lots
of other things that I haven't had time
to talk about. Um, there's proteomic
assays that that people are now running.
We're running for the all of us program.
I'm running for other things to generate
large data sets for uh plasma
proteomics. Um there's also a new RNA
product um that we've run on 10,000
samples for the all of us program as
well which is a total RNA uh method with
globe and ribosomal depletion that just
gives you a tremendous amount of sort of
um RNA information um and is lower cost
than what we've been doing traditionally
as well. So um I think with that I'm
wrapped up but there's lots of stuff
that we do with the platform. So, if you
ever have any um issues, just email us,
find us, come out to Burlington, visit
us, stop off at the mall, have lunch,
come over. Um and we're we're here to
serve the community. So, please feel
free to reach out to us. Thank you, Dr.
Lennon. Very important in this age of
genetic diagnosis. And I do have some
questions for you for
later. So, our next speaker is uh Arya
Ralph. Where's Arya? Hi, Arya. Uh Arya
um is obviously a very talented MD PhD
candidate in the Batya and Sebetti Lops
and she is the recipient of the
inaugural ladders to cures accelerator
award. She's also a Renaissance woman.
She swims, she plays the saxophone and
she sings. So Oh, impressive.
Today she will talk to us about
harnessing cell type specific gene
regulation for targeted gene therapy.
Okay. Thank you so much y'all. Um it's
wonderful to be here and to be with you
all. Um as was mentioned I'm an MD/PhD
candidate uh in the Harvard MIT MD PhD
program uh pursuing joint doctoral work
between Paris's lab here at the Broad
and Sanga Batia's lab at MIT. Uh and
today I'm excited to share some of our
work towards developing novel cell type
specific gene therapies.
So to start, our genome is composed of
just four bases, A, C, T, and G. And
with different combinations of these
bases, our genomes are able to
accomplish this huge range of functions
needed for our body to
work. But it's interesting uh while
there are tons and tons and tons of
combinations of these four bases,
natural evolution has only explored a
small fraction of these. And we can do
the math to see that that's the case.
For a genome of our size, which is three
billion base pairs long, uh there are
four to the three billionth possible
configurations of a genome of our size.
But looking at the human genome, we
realize that less than 1% of these
configurations have actually been
explored. Uh and so the question is why?
And what's in that missing
code? Evolution works via two key
forces. We have mutation and then we
have selection. As our cells divide
throughout our lifetimes, um, errors or
mutations accumulate, uh, and the
beneficial ones rise to high frequency
via the process of
selection. We can imagine evolution like
a hiker in a mountain range, a step
forward that our hiker takes as a
mutation. Uh, and beneficial mutations
take the hiker higher along the
mountain. But the problem is this. When
our hiker or evolution is standing in
this mountain range, it doesn't know if
that the path that it's on is the one
that's taking it to the highest possible
peak. And so it's easy to just follow
the path and line wind up on something
that's suboptimal, not actually the
highest peak in the region. We can get
stuck on those sub-optimal peaks because
we can't actually see where we're going.
And so it's for this reason that
evolution has only explored a tiny
fraction of what's possible with the
number of configurations we have. Uh we
can't see where we're going.
There are many many peaks that are left
to be unexplor left to be explored
though from this unexplored space and so
it's in this uncharted territory that we
might discover new functions for our
genetic code that we haven't found
previously things that we can do that
will give us new options for gene
therapy in this synthetic
DNA while I was a medical student on the
wards at Mass General I was really
fortunate to work with fantastic rare
disease patients and their families and
something that struck me during this
process was that if we could find ways
to more specifically target the cells
that are at risk or diseased in these
cohorts, we might be able to offer more
promising
therapies. Most of the DNA in our cells
is actually regulatory, turning genes on
and off uh as opposed to coding for
proteins directly. One type of this DNA
called cis regulatory elements or CRE
are prevalent and we can tune our CRES
to give different levels of gene
expression. Uh give higher levels of
genes uh make our genes active in
specific cell types so on and so forth.
We can learn the rules of this
regulatory DNA and maybe if we can build
around them we can design new
therapies. Achieving this vision for
rare disease therapeutics requires
building the right team and I'm very
fortunate to be part of a great one. Uh
as I mentioned I'm in the SEI lab and
the Batia lab. Um and party sibi's lab
is a computational genomics lab. This is
where we're going to be able to design
the right CRES. Uh Sitabatia's lab
focuses on nanotechnologies and this is
how we can focus on getting our CRE to
the right place. Uh and so together this
is how we can achieve this next
generation of rare disease
therapeutics. Our lab has come up with
ways to design CRES that work in
unprecedented ways. This work has been
led by Sagosai and Rodrigo Castro. Uh we
use an experimental assay called a
massively parallel reporter assay or an
MP to test hundreds of thousands of CR
at once uh empirically. And this allows
us to describe the genome's regulatory
grammar uh just with a simple
experiment. We can use computational
methods to then explore that data
further and design sequences that act
even better than the ones that we find
naturally.
Diving more closely into that method, uh
we start with a DNA library of our
putitive CRES. We tag these on to
fluorescent reporters like a GFP. Uh and
then we can transfect those into
different cell lines of interest to
obtain activity readouts of the
expression of our reporter. Uh and these
numerical scores can be used to fuel
computational exploration. So the
experiment I've showed here, we did it
in blood, liver, and neuronal cell
lines. Our experimental data can be used
to train machine learning models uh that
learn the regulatory grammar of the
genome. So we can hone in on what parts
of the DNA sequences are actually
contributing to DNA activity. Here we
can explore why a certain CR might be
cell type specific, why one might be
more active, uh and how we might be able
to modify these sequences to gain
functional advantages going forward. So
our predictive machine learning models
here are giving us a bird's eye view of
that fitness landscape or mountain range
that I mentioned.
We can then computationally explore the
remaining sequence space that there is.
And so we can take this predictive map
and use generative artificial
intelligence models to design sequences
that are better than before. Uh and
here's how this works. We start with a
set of sequences, maybe a batch of
random
sequences. We pass those to our
predictive model which already knows how
MP works and knows what the readout from
an experiment might be. And we feed that
prediction into a generative model which
can update our sequences so they reach
the highest predicted possible activity
for any user specified task. So
something that's more cell type
specific, something that's more active,
what have you. We can validate these
results using a massively parallel
reporter essay. Again, taking things
back into cells and observing the real
biology at hand. And then we can even
continue the cycle modeling uh and going
forward from there with active learning
processes.
When we test our computationally
designed sequences in vivo, we have some
really promising results. Uh this is a
striking figure from a paper that we
published last year uh in nature showing
that when we take our neuronal specific
CR and tag it onto a reporter, we can
achieve brain specific expression uh in
an embryionic mouse. So we're very
excited about this, but there's a lot of
work that remains to extend from the
these early results towards new cell
types and more importantly therapeutic
applications. uh and this is where the
work with the latter secures initiative
comes
in. So we think that with the right CRA,
the right vector, we might be able to
build fitforpurpose gene therapies that
exploit our genome's regulatory code to
cure rare diseases. The first challenge
that we've tackled with L2C uh is this
idea of optimizing cargo space. As this
group likely knows well uh in gene
therapy vectors, viral vectors,
nanoparticles, etc., size is everything.
And so the framework that I showed you
previously is actually to design
enhancers which are positioned upstream
of the promoter that actually drives the
transcription of genes. Uh but together
this complex works to initiate gene
expression. But what if we could
restrict the range of sequence that
we're actually actually optimizing. So
it's optimally small uh and can be
inserted just with the gene of interest
so that we don't have this 200 base pair
enhancer a linker sequence and all sorts
of other stuff that might interfere with
the size carrying capacity of our of our
vector here. Uh and so we've been trying
to leverage this framework that I showed
you to design minimal promoters. To do
so we've designed an MP library that
takes in a lot of design facets of what
we might think comprises a minimal
promoter. So things like what are the
highest predicted transcription
initiation peaks uh what are known
promoter motifs and a couple other
methods here and we're testing those in
a few cell types uh K562s HEP G2s and
HEC 293 so it's blood uh liver and
kidney and the reason we've chosen this
system is that it recapitulates a
classic uh therapeutic evaluation system
for human ariththropotin or EPO uh and
the reason we think EPO is interesting
is that it has a number of physiological
ical effects that we might be able to
exploit for later validation of this
pipeline. Uh so a little more detail on
EPO. It's a regulator of the oxygen
carrying capacity of the body. Uh it
acts on ariththroidid progenitors in the
bone marrow. Uh is produced primarily in
the kidney and then has some secondary
production also in the liver. And so in
our cell types, if we can engineer
specificity for promoters that act in
these three different tissue types,
organ types, then we might be able to
see them with EPO as a readout. uh and
more interestingly for rare diseases,
EPO deficiency can be congenital but
also has this tie to common diseases
which I think Raj touched on earlier
where you can actually have acquired EPO
deficiency as a result of things like
chronic kidney disease. Uh so this is an
aspect of that nodal biology we've been
talking about. And so we're going to
test our theories in the ecosystem using
a nanoparticle lipid nanoparticle uh
containing our promoter gene construct
delivered to each of these three
different tissue types in invivo mouse
models. This work is being done um in
collaboration with Savin Patel and the
Batia group. Uh and so we're going to do
two primary assays once we have these
designed promoters in hand. The first is
a pharmacocinetics based assay where we
do elya um from human arthropotin
expression in mice. Uh and the second is
looking at specificity with whole organ
imaging with our GFP and then eventually
also single cell readouts to see exactly
where our constructs are going and where
they're being
expressed. But more broadly this idea of
a minimal promoter can be extended to a
whole host of rare diseases. And this is
the framework that I want to share with
you today. Uh while this minimal
promoter work in these three cell types
is exciting. We think there's a whole
more whole bigger world that's there to
be explored uh in many many cell types.
Here in the L2C grant we're focused on
three which are skeletal muscle, cardiac
muscle and smooth muscle. And we think
there are a lot of exciting applications
here. And so to close I will share a
couple of
these. The first is something that is
likely familiar to many in the rare
disease community and I think our next
speaker will be touching on this a
little bit too. Uh Duchens
musculardrophe. Um so it's caused by a
mutation in the distrophin gene and has
de devastating effects on muscular
tissue and also systemically and so
there are a number of offtarget effects
that are actually caused by the existing
gene therapies on the market for DMD
which either aim to deliver distrophin
natively or edit the genome itself. Uh
we think that if we can target muscle
cells specifically with a muscle
specific promoter and enhancer we might
be able to ameliorate some of these
which would be very
exciting. And beyond enhancing existing
therapeutic applications, we think our
CRES uh could lead to novel therapeutics
in and of themselves. And one exciting
disease that we're thinking about here
is hereditary hemorrhagic
talangjectasia, which is a bit of a
mouthful uh but we can just call it HHT.
Uh HHT is caused by a loss of the
endogen protein, which is a structural
protein in blood vessels and has a
number of devastating effects, strokes,
anemia, heart failure, hemorrhage. uh
and if we can deliver endoglen natively
to smooth muscle cells we might be able
to prevent these and that's very
exciting as well uh we can conceive of
this cell type specific CR that we can
use to drive increased expression of
normal
endogllin and so to close I just want to
come back to this framework that we can
use high throughput experimentation of
any kind combined with computational
optimization to drive cell type specific
therapies or any sort of therapy uh that
can't be optimized by natural sequence
alone. Uh this is the kind of framework
that's going to allow us to move beyond
the biology that we see to the biology
that we create. Uh and I'm very grateful
to be part of the team to to do this. Um
and so I have to thank several people uh
primarily my PIs Partisan Singita but
also Sager Savan Brian a rotation
student who just finished up with me uh
and everybody listed above and happy to
take any questions.
Thank you. We'll take questions at the
end.
So our last speaker um is Dr. Michelle
Ren Renarajin and um she scrubbed her
online presence while I was looking to
find anecdotes about her and only
professional things. So she's um where
is she? right here uh an
endocrinologist, an MD uh scientist,
physician, endocrinologist and
geneticist working on autoimmune
diseases and duchen musculardrophe and
her the title of her talk is
[Applause]
dysfun um and also new in the world of
being a PI and so Um, I'm not going to
talk overly specifically about our exact
letters to curious accelerator project,
but kind of going to talk more broadly
about the way my lab is looking at
taking on Duchenne. Um, and very
selfishly doing this because we're quite
eager to find people to join our team
both in the lab and also as
collaborators. So, I'm happy to talk to
anyone um
afterwards. Um so the distrophen protein
is a um large muscle regulatory protein
um that links the is there pointer? Oh
um that links the actin cytokeleton to
the muscle cell membrane um and
nucleates a large membrane bound protein
complex in the muscle cell nucleus
that's critical for maintaining muscle
integrity um particularly in the face of
muscle contraction. Um the DMD gene um
is the largest gene in the body at 2.4
four megabase pairs. It's on the X
chromosome. Um, and the protein product
is about 3600 amino acids, um,
comprising 79 exxons. Um, in duchen, um,
as I'll talk about in a bit, there's a
number of different mutations, but the
most common mutation is a large deletion
of one or more exxons that leads to an
out that leads to an out of frame
transcript. Um, and this in turn leads
to transcript instability and loss of
protein expression.
The consequence of this transcript
instability is quite dire um and causes
the disease duchen musculardrophe or DMD
um which is a progressive terminal
disease with no known cure. Um it
primarily because the gene is on the X
chromosome almost exclusively affects um
uh boys um but begins with ongoing
cardiac and skeletal muscle damage
starting at birth. Um this results in
the loss of ambulation somewhere between
the ages of 9 and 15 um due to diaphragm
weakness the need for non-invasive
ventilation in the late teens and
ultimately death from cardiac failure
somewhere in the late teens um into the
20s. Um however despite this really dire
course the disease trajectory is
modifiable. And so if we look just at
cohorts that are born at different
times, if you compare a cohort of
patients born before 1970 to those born
between 1970 and 1990 or after 1990, you
can see a clear shift in survival. And I
just want to emphasize that this is not
from a therapeutic intervention. This is
advances in clinical care. Um, so there
is reason to believe that effective
therapies could actually push this curve
out much, much farther.
Um, so something I hear all the time
these days is, "I thought I heard about
a cure for DMD." And so while there have
been many new drug approvals, I want to
emphasize that none of these are really
curative. Um, standard of care is
highdosese corticosteroids, there is an
approved microistine gene therapy that
was mentioned that's available for
patients above the age of four. Um, but
a huge issue with this is naturally
existing immunity to the viral vector
that prevents safe and effective
administration of this drug. There are
significant safety concerns and I think
it's fair to say that at this point the
durability and benefit of this drug have
been quite
disappointing. Um there are mutation
specific exxon skipping therapies that
are available for three quite common
exxons. These result in very minimal m
muscle delivery less than 1% of um
normal levels of distrophen. And while
there are ongoing trials with better
delivery mechanisms, these only target
the four most common exxons in this
disease. Um there's an HDAC inhibitor
that was recently approved. It may
prolong um ambulation but likely with
some effects on the bone marrow that are
manifest as
thrombocytoenia and many additional
drugs are ongoing or expected in
clinical trials. Um but I just want to
emphasize that it can be a very very
long time from proof of concept in the
preclinical space to getting a drug into
patients. So lined up against the life
expectancy of someone with duchen. If we
look at the most recent approvals for
gvenatin HDAC inhibitor
um the approved microistrphan gene
therapy and a novel steroid you can see
that the timelines here are just far too
long for anyone living with this disease
today. And many of those challenges
occur because DMD is really a microcosm
of the challenges of rare disease
therapeutic development at large. Um so
the diagnosis is late. We know there's
damage occurring at birth. Most kids are
diagnosed even today between the ages of
four and five years old. It's a very
large gene and a very large protein. And
this has implications for delivery. It
also has implications for the kinds of
mutations we see. So thousands of
different mutations have been
identified. Um and all different kinds
of mutations. So 60 to 70% are large
deletions. We also see um nonsense
mutations, other point mutations um and
large duplications. And also compounding
those many different mutations is um a
substantial amount of disease
heterogeneity that makes it really
difficult to run effective clinical
trials. Um the target tissue is vast and
I think like many rare diseases the
commercial incentives which do exist for
some mutations with duchen leave many
many people out. Um so the objective of
my lab is to accelerate distrophin
restoring therapies for every living
patient with DMD. And just to emphasize
what we mean by that, um, we're agnostic
to
modality. Um, we want to treat every
patient regardless of their mutation,
regardless of their ability to walk, and
regardless of their neurocognitive
ability. And we really want to focus on
living patients. Um, so I just flew back
yesterday from ASGCT. I can tell you the
future looks very bright for kids born
with this disease in 2050, but those
solutions might not be available to kids
living with this disease now.
And so we've taken this on by first
focusing on mutation specific approaches
for rare exxons um developing biomarkers
that might be able to truly track
trajectory um and and focusing very
deeply on seropositivity and AAV. And I
should step back and say when I say
we've taken this on we are really at the
earliest steps of of all of
these. Um so exxon skipping um is an
approach to try to restore a
distrophin-l like protein um in patients
with DMD. And so the way this works is
if we look at full length distrophen in
a patient with a mutation we have an out
of frame mutation um an anti-sense
oligouonucleotide that prevents um
splicing of the next exxon can restore
the reading frame and produce a
distrophin with an inframe internal
deletion. And we have substantial
evidence from human genetic studies that
that demonstrates that these internally
deleted distrophins can be quite
functional. The challenge of this
approach is that 40% um of skip
amendable mutations are not in existing
pipelines. Um so I've just listed um
five different companies that are in
clinical trials in this space and what
you can see is that they're focused on
five um mutations. So how do we think
about getting to these non um
non-commercial exxons? Um so the first
thing we wanted to think about are what
are the slow steps in the process of
getting an exxon skipping drug into the
clinic. And one of the first steps that
is still extremely slow is the way in
which we find targets. And so currently
um predictive models are not as great as
we would like. And so most um ASO
targets are found by tiling um
overlapping anti-sense oligos across the
region of interest. So you start out
with hundreds of oligos tiling your
exxon in the flanking sequence. Um
identify the top constructs, make more
oligos, and then um do a secondary
screen of sort of the best fits. If
you're looking at just one exxon, this
is probably the best way to do it. But
if you're looking at 79, suddenly the
scale becomes very very difficult. Um
and so we've launched a collaboration
with Sylvie Ruskin where we're hoping to
both employ higher throughput screening
strategies for target finding and also
feed that into models for predicting um
optimal ASO targets with the hope of
just getting much better predictions and
so that we're actually screening closer
to 10 oligos per exon rather than
hundreds. Um we're also working very
closely um with patient advocacy groups
um parent project musculardrophe in the
hope of trying to build some long-term
bioreositories that will facilitate
mutation specific approaches both for
anti-sense oligos but also in the future
for things like editing um potentially
even large insertions in the
future. Um a a big question about this
these sorts of rare approaches is c can
we rapidly show efficacy in a single
individual. So I mentioned that the
clinical course of DMD is heterogeneous.
And so what I'm showing you here is the
the standard scale um for measuring
motor ability in these children. It's a
17point scale called the Northstar
ambulatory assessment. And I'm showing
you this scale over time. And each gray
line is an individual
trajectory. So you can create an average
trajectory, but you can see that there's
substantial spread from that average
trajectory. Um, Franchesco Moni at UCL
has done some really nice work trying to
extract different classes of disease
from these trajectories. And you can see
that here where the individual
trajectories are covered by class. And
now the averages for these individual
trajectories look quite different. But
if we focus on sort of the earliest ages
here, you can see that there's
considerable overlap and you need quite
a bit of time to actually see trajectory
separation. And this is kind of
reflected in our in our current clinical
trials, right? So we typically sample
patients who are in the four to seven
age range, follow them for a year, look
at the average change in baseline in
placebot treated versus drug treated
individuals um and sort of hope that
you've um randomized enough people that
you actually have comparable
populations. But of course with a rare
disease and a small trial that
randomization is often biased. And so
what we would really like is we would
like to take have some sort of baseline
measure that we follow patients in a
run-in period treat
um and then be able to say this is this
patient's projected trae uh expected
trajectory and this is what we're
actually seeing. And so ideally we want
to be able to much quicker say this
individual patient has switched their
trajectory as a result of this disease.
Um and so again we're just beginning to
explore these but really looking at um
non-invasive markers of tissue damage
using self-free DNA based approaches um
and extracellular vesicle analysis as
well as wear wearablebased approaches to
measure motor function that we think
will be more accessible to the full
range of ages and the full range of
cognitive ability um in this
disease. All right. And so the last
thing I want to talk about is
seropositivity and AIV. And this is
actually something that's a bit bigger
than my own lab but but really grew out
of the ladders to cures accelerator. And
so I wanted to give an update on where
that's been. Um so currently the
standard for gene therapy is
adnoassociated virus. Um and while many
of the um AAV viruses that are used
might have been were isolated from
either humans or animals, many of these
viruses circulate in humans and so most
many people have antibodies to these
viruses. Um and so if we look in DMD at
the AAV capsids that have reached the
clinic, AAV RH74 about 14% of patients
have antibodies to this vector. Um AAV8
um 44% of patients have antibodies to
this vector. AAV9 32% and SLV 101 is a
new capsid that's expected to have
similar immunogenicity to AAV9. So we're
excluding quite a lot of patients who
cannot get these vectors because their
antibodies would neutralize the vector
preventing an efficacious effect and
then potentially also lead to safety
complications. Um and so last November
um we sponsored a meeting or ladder to
cure sponsored a meeting along with
parent project musculardrophe here at
the broad focused just on this topic.
Um, and a as a result of that meeting,
we formed the all-in AAV consortium,
which now has representatives from over
13 AAV companies as well as 13 different
academic and nonprofit institutions with
the objective of accelerating safe
clinical trials of AAV gene therapy in
cerositive patients. And so at the
start, we're aiming to really advance
diagnostic tools um such as universal
standardized antibbody testing and also
fill scientific clinical and knowledge
gaps and create a um create a structure
for standardized protocols for
evaluating complications and emphasizing
the need for sharing that data so that
we can all share information to develop
safer therapies.
Um, and so with that, um, I'll just
thank my lab who's here. Um, some really
wonderful collaborators who have helped
us get this off the ground. Um, and I
just want to issue a a big thanks to
Anna Grea, Julian Shaw, and the LTC
Accelerator. Um, generally people don't
advise you to change fields when you
start a lab, and so it was really
wonderful to have some really early
support from this
group. Thank you.
Do we have time for questions? So, Nile
and
Ara. Uh, while people are lining up, I'm
sure you have tons of questions. Line
up. Line up. Uh, I I'll start maybe with
a couple questions to the speakers. So,
Nile, I all these amazing novel
sequencing technologies. What would you
recommend clinicians to or patients who
had a genetic test done in the past and
it was a either a panel or an exo and
they didn't have a finding would you
recommend to them to come back and have
a
retest with a whole genome? Yeah, I mean
I think working obviously with
their you know physician geneticist
genetic counselors um and whoever sort
of looking at their data but I do think
if you know people have had gene panels
certainly it's a reasonable you know
time to go back and do whole genome
sequencing
um you know some of the newer things are
not going to be available yet
for that kind of reanalysis or reflex
testing but um but but yeah but you know
as the technology advances every couple
of years, it's probably worth a
reanalysis for sure. Thank you. Um Arya,
can I ask you, you talked about cell
specificity for your promoters? What
about level of expression because in
some disorders it's very important not
to overexpress just as much as not to
underexpress. How do you see your
promoter's position for that? Yeah. Uh
we we view our framework as being highly
customizable to any level of user
specified tasks including level of
activity or expression. Uh we think we
can use our framework to design things
that are exquisitly tunable, exquisitly
specific. Uh and also the opposite. We
can design things that are robustly
active or tunable across cell types as
well. Thank you. Hi. I have a question
for Nile. Um, I'll fully admit that I
have taxed the patience of all your
project managers when I submit three
samples from one family. I feel like,
you know, it's, you know, you guys are
so used to like thousands, hundreds of
thousands of samples that like you
immediately know you're losing money on
my 80 emails that it'll require. But
I'll say that the one thing that's been
really exciting is that you have this
platform called Seeker for someone like
me who doesn't do this sort of
computational analysis to take the
sequencing data and identify causal
variance with just like a graphical
interface. But I think the support for
that has been spotty at times and I was
curious if you're going to expand those
things or even like have a specific
project like workflow for just these
like kind of three, you know, three
samples from one family sort of
projects.
Yeah. So, so to your first point, so
certainly for things like whole genome
sequencing, the whole point is, you
know, we try
to get kind of operational for a second,
the when you have like 15 giant machines
like that, it's like running an airline,
right? So, if they're not running,
you're losing money. So, we our whole
point is like we try to like keep them
full, keep them go go go. Um, and we do
that by aggregating tons of demand
across all kinds of research and
translational work. But the whole point
of doing that is if you can run keep
them full, you can run them efficiently
and try to keep the cost as low as you
can. And for anyone who comes with a
standard like a genome test, one sample
is totally fine because it's standard
like it's built to just fit into the
exact workflow where small sample
numbers become an issue is more when
it's a bespoke assay and where you have
to kind of burn a whole sequencing run
where you get charged the same amount
from aluminum no matter what how many
samples we run on it. And if we can't
aggregate that's when it starts to
become expensive. So the operation is
really designed even though it so it
shouldn't be intimidated that like it it
runs lots of samples small numbers of
samples using existing assays. It's
totally totally good for that. the
second part of the question. So
interestingly, so Seeker um really, you
know, we can't claim um sort of credit
for that sort of you know, Heidi's team
and O'Donnell and and and the rare
disease team who've really kind of kept
that u built it, developed it, kept
iterating on it for the purpose of sort
of this sort of rare disease research.
Um and so this is where we have to make
sometimes make hard decisions. So,
Seeker is built as a research platform.
Because of that, it doesn't have some of
the things you would need to run it as a
clinical platform. So, we can't validate
it for our clea interpret. So, we don't
use Seeker to sign out diagnostic tests.
We use other thirdparty software just
because they've been built specifically
for that purpose and they have, you
know, lock down software and live in in
secure locations and all that kind of
stuff. So Seeker has remained the tool
that's super valuable, but also because
it was built with this kind of discovery
research mode in mind. The input to
Seeker, which actually is more of the
issue that you brought up in number one,
the input to seek is a joint call set.
Seeker doesn't take a single sample as
an input. So that's a that's also a
limitation in using it in a clinical
workflow where you kind of want to be
able to run your entire end to end with
one sample or one trio um rather than
create a joint call set to load into the
seeker environment. Um so that's so so
again it's sort of used in a different
part of the community. It's not part of
our clinical workflow that our team
runs. Um the second part about sort of
maintaining and continuing to develop it
is a completely different kind of worms
and that's all about how do we fund
software maintenance and development and
investment at an institutional level and
that's really tricky because
unfortunately you know again our mission
is to try to keep the cost down as much
as we can because the community and the
marketplace assumes a certain amount of
like low cost to run things which means
there's not a lot of extra like
contribution in every sample to to
invest in certainly homegrown suffer is
really expensive and that becomes a
really a challenge.
I had a question for Michelle. So um
correct me if I'm wrong but my
impression from that AEV symposium the
one you were referring to was that
serositivity was more of a concern for
efficacy and not for safety. And so what
I was wondering, you know, okay, we can
have this symposium with all of these
companies, but if it's not effective,
what does the sharing of the data like
ultimately accomplish? And maybe I'm
naive about that. Yeah. No, I think
that's a really good point. I also think
safety was sort of under discussed at
that symposium. Um I would argue I think
there are some safety concerns, but I
agree that that was the consensus that
day. Um I think um so sort of two
concerns, right? So the presence of
antibodies binds capsid prevents capsid
from reaching the target tissue. That's
the concern for efficacy. Um the safety
concern is that you have you know one of
the big safety issues that has been seen
with gene therapy is thrombotic
microangopathy. Um and so the concern is
you have lots of
which presumably through classical
compliment activation. So you have lots
of antibodies, you have lots of capsid,
that combination leads to antibbody
mediated activation of the compliment
cascade and then ultimately TMA. So the
presence of antibodies can cause both of
those things.
No, no one is intentionally dosing with
some exceptions antibbody high patients
currently. It's actually an exclusion
criteria for most of the clinical
trials. Um so the idea of the consortium
is actually what do we need to do to
mitigate both the safety and efficacy
concerns so that these patients can get
an efficacious gene therapy. So we're
really thinking about things like
combining capsid evolution with immune
modulation strategy. Um it just gets
very tricky because um preclinical
models don't fully capture some of that
safety risk. It's just quite a leap to
get from something working preclinally
to the clinic in this setting where we
don't we don't have data to really help
us understand what's going to happen.
So Michelle, if I can follow up on that
because we are starting a a neurological
gene therapy program now in neurology,
we do not exclude zeropositive patients.
We do sample but we do not exclude but
what we did find is that the
imunosuppressant protocols are so
different from one protocol to the
other. So will your consortium be
looking at different protocols and
making recommendations based on past
experience? Yeah, I think one of the
things we realized is there different
protocols in every trial but also like
different data is being collected and
shared from every trial. So it's really
hard to learn about immune modulation
protocols in that way. Um and so part of
the initial focus is actually like
setting sort of standardiz standard
guidelines for like what should be
collected what should be released so
that we can try to understand what's the
effect of these including neurological
disorders as well or only uh no it's a
cross disease okay and I'll also add
like similarly one of the things that
happens is when an adverse event occurs
um frequently it's just people are
reaching for whatever they can uh that's
immune modulatory. Everyone does
something slightly different and it's
really hard to know did you need all of
those drugs. What do those drugs do? How
does one protocol? So that's the other
thing where I think it's really hard in
the moment where a clinician does not
have the information they need until
after the fact, but maybe we can at
least retroactively try to learn from
some of these events. That's great.
Thank you.
a question for now on the constellation
to us. Um can you share any preliminary
data on performance calling repeats?
Yeah. So the so the interesting thing
about constellation moment we have
access we got access to it over the
summer last year I think.
Um currently it's like a prep method and
then the analysis to like get the links.
What we're working on now in
collaboration with Lumin is like they
haven't like we haven't built any
special callers yet on outside of small
variants to um to like really leverage
linkage information. So that's actually
what Victoria Popek who has a a method
called Q which was actually originally
um built to handle there used to be a
method called from 10X that created
linked reads. So it was actually
developed from that. So we're applying
that to this data type to do a lot
better on structure variation. I don't
think we have any repeats. We have a So
one thing you can do you can actually do
collocation plots that looks almost like
a high C plot where you have sort of the
and you can see you can physically see
things like um structure variance in it
that way. But um the actual like callers
are still in development and then we'll
run the repeat expansion samples through
to see how how we're doing on there.
It's not going to be like the links are
a couple of KB apart. So you're not it's
not like you know it's not it's not the
same as a long read that way.
So I wanted to ask a question um also to
be provocative and to maybe see if that
spawns any conversations during our
coffee break and later on today. Um just
it relates to all the discussions that
we've been having and maybe um it was
inspired a little bit by a comment you
made Michelle. So two things and you and
I have already uh talked about this and
uh Janet Woodcock and I had talked about
it and I introduced her to you. This
idea of like randomized control trials
in rare diseases may not make a whole
lot of sense. You you touched upon it
and the idea that each patient can serve
as their own control if we have enough
understanding of trajectories and the
right biomarkers to guide us. So that
was one thought that I just wanted to
throw out there and see if you or anyone
else has thoughts on this. The second
even more provocative idea that comes
out of um KJ's example yesterday and
there's been a little discussion about
this is what if we treated programmable
therapeutics you know what Arya and all
of us you know eventually you know want
to develop as surgeries you know you go
into a surgeon and you know you get you
get a procedure and you know it's not
like there's like a randomized control
trial for every you know sort of
procedure you know that you're getting
or any device that is deployed to get
like a stent a coronary stent for
example right so we sort of have an
understanding of the fact that there's a
consent for that to happen for this
individual patient. And what if a
programmable therapeutic could be
approached in the same way for two or
three or 10 patients so that it becomes
like a very sort of personalized
programmable therapy for uh that
particular mutation. Is that something
that we can imagine uh sort of in the
future? I know it's these are all big
topics and very provocative. Just uh
throwing the ideas out there for people
to consider. I don't know if any of you
would like I don't want to put you on
the spot, but I just want to see if you
have ideas and then maybe we can take it
into the coffee break as well for
discussion. Thank you. Yeah. Well, Anna,
I can certainly take the second
question. Um, as an aspiring future
surgeon, I the same things that attract
me to the field of of surgery, the idea
of being able to work with individual
patients and come up with customized
solutions that are creative and in the
moment are what drives me to work on
gene therapies for rare diseases. You're
right that we should be treating
patients as individuals. uh but more
importantly that we should be treating
biology as individuals and I think the
ideas of doing randomized control trials
for rare diseases inherently um
deconvolve those two things. We should
be treating patients as who they are and
their biology is what it is.
Programmable therapeutics enable us to
do that versus the suite of medicines
that we have at hand right now which do
do not treat patients as individuals. We
treat patients as cohorts. Um so maybe
even in the future and this is
potentially even more provocative uh we
can get rid of the randomized control
trial altogether even for non-genetic
therapies and think about uh what what
medicine uh might mean when we evaluate
each patient individually. For now
though I think the RCT is great just to
clarify but
I have so much to say about it to start
with.
Um I think now today today is one thing.
The future is different. Today when you
come to a surgeon and they offer you
some kind of surgery, you Google it. You
want to see what the outcomes are, what
others have experienced. And when there
isn't data, it's very hard to make
decisions. And not everyone sits at the
Broad Institute. Some people are farmers
and other professions. They're not as
understanding as we are. and they will
not have the right information to make
decisions. So, how do we collect that
information? I think that's a really
important point. Um, and yes, there are
individual patients that have individual
mutations, but there are a lot of
patients that have similar mutations.
And again, how do those who know less
about it access these amazing new
therapies that are being offered here?
Um, I also have like lots of thoughts on
all of that. Um I I mean I think you
know I agree that I don't think
randomized control trials for rare
disease are necessary or should be
necessary particularly when we're
talking about progressive fatal
diseases. Um uh so you know one of the
examples that's come out of Duchen is
it's actually a lot of the trials are
run to one-year motor end points and
that's actually probably not enough time
to separate disease trajectories.
I think almost everyone is in agreement
that a three to fiveyear placeboc
controlled trial in a progressive
terminal pediatric disease is not
ethically acceptable. Um and so I think
we have to start figuring out ways to I
agree like we need data but we need to
start figuring out ways to like I think
be more creative with natural history to
develop biomarkers with sort of
correlative functional endpoints and to
actually try to get away from that. Um
because I think unless you have an
endpoint to your randomized I'm an
endocrinologist so I'm used to six-month
hemoglobin A1C as a randomized control
trial for full drug approval right we
don't have that in rare disease and in
the absence of something that fast and
robust I don't think you can ethically
maintain a placebo arm
also I think we're a far far ways away
from this time but there is so much work
going on to do artificial intelligence
based modeling um for digital twins and
what have you and we could conceive of a
world where we do RCTs and uh clonal AI,
you know, populations. Don't think we're
there yet, but that work is is
ongoing. Coffee break until 3:20.