what does my t-shirt
say that's what I like enthusiasm right
this is solid carbon dioxide dry ice its
temperature is -78° C it's very cold and
I'm going to dump the hot water in here
the hot water vapor hits the cold air it
condenses and then gets to the same
temperature it it disappears right what
I'm going to do now is Take the bucket
of dry ice put the dry ice right in
there
I can't even see
it condensed water vapor is what we see
we see the fog is
moving downward why because the
condensation is taking place on the
carbon dioxide gas which is denser than
air right for more MIT moments from MIT
open learning like subscribe or follow