welcome back after the summer to um our
colloquium series which we're very very
excited to start off here with Dave Bly
um so as you know you know you've seen
like talks here where it goes either
from machine learning into important um
biomedical applications or the other way
around from applications to actually
developing foundations of machine
learning and today uh we're definitely
going to be more on that route um and I
know Dave will also tell us how this can
also be applied and give pointers to
different things that are also ongoing
or that have motivated the type of work
that he's going to talk about um so I'm
sure we all know Dave blee um so he's a
professor in statistics and computer
science at Colombia um university got
his PhD in Berkeley um and then was at
Princeton for some years before moving
to Colombia has um had a lot of
different Awards um particular a lot of
test of time Awards which I find always
like very impressive at newps at icml k
and you know Simon's investigator fellow
of the IMs etc etc um so his research is
mainly um in the field of ban statistics
um and machine learning and really
thinking very heavily about you know
starting from many different types of
applications and then going to really
principled methods um I'm sure we you're
all familiar with a lot of work in topic
modeling um and then now more and more
also in causality and that's what you're
going to talk about today on
hierarchical CA pule models so I'm very
very excited to see that so thank you
Dave for being here and very excited
about your talk thanks thanks Caroline
thanks so much for inviting me um yeah
I'm uh Dave blly I'm going to talk about
hierarchical causal models and thanks
for such a nice introduction um I
remember I did win a test of time award
for work I did when I was a postto and I
called my postto adviser John La I said
good news we won this test of time award
for our paper and he said you know what
that means Dave it means you're old
um anyway he was right and that was a
lot of years ago so um I want to talk
about hierarchical causal models and I'm
going to I'll I'll I'll mention biology
I know you are all focused on biology um
but the tutorial example is going to be
more in the social sciences but
hopefully it will still help you um
understand the idea and you'll see the
connections to the kind of questions
that you want to answer so let's just
start with a question suppose you are a
superintendent of schools there's a
bunch of schools in your district and
you want to know how tutoring affects
test performance okay so people in the
different schools they get different
numbers of hours of tutoring and then
they all take a standardized test and
here are some different schools in your
district and you want to know how
tutoring affects test performance uh in
this uh in this world um your data
you're the superintendence you get all
the data you want your data is the
average tutoring hours and test
performance for many many schools okay
so each of these schools you get the
average number of tutoring hours at the
Springfield Elementary School average
number of tutoring hours here at I guess
is my wife's High School average number
of tutoring hours at my high school and
at um uh The Buffy High School and um
then you get the average test
performance of the students at all these
schools now here you're going to draw a
causal graphical model because you're a
pretty sophisticated superintendent and
um and so here's the model you would
draw where you have average tutoring
hours average test performance and you
want to estimate the expectation of
average test performance in a world
where I intervene on tutoring hours and
set it equal to H right that's when you
mathematically ask what we mean by a
causal inference we're asking a question
about an intervention so there's their
your intervention I'm going to give
everybody 10 tutoring hours H is 10
what's going to happen to test
performance what's the expected average
test score if I set the average tutoring
hours to H now the problem is there an
unmeasured confounder in your graph okay
so for example the school's budget some
schools are are well funded some are not
affects both how many tutoring hours you
deliver but also is going to affect the
general quality of the school and so
affect the test scores as well okay and
you don't have the school's budget in
your um in your data I mean you would if
you were the real superintendent but
let's say you don't and there might be
other Compounders too and so if you know
about causal graphs you can see from
this graph that the causal es demand the
expectation of average tutoring hours in
a world where I intervene sorry
expectation of test performance in a
world where I intervene on tutoring
hours is not identifiable you can't even
if you had an infinite number of schools
you'd never be able to figure it
out okay but what if we observed the
students themselves within the schools
okay so we observe not just the average
number of tutoring hours in test
performance but we get to know each of
the individual people's uh number of
tutoring hours and test scores for all
the different schools
okay then it turns out we can estimate
the causal effect of tutoring hours okay
this is well-known stuff um but we're
going to generalize it um and so let me
just show you
how so here is now a new causal model
this is the subject of today's talk this
is a hierarchical causal model it's a
causal model with an inner plate inner
plate this box means replication of
variables inside the main unit of
analysis um and in this case it's
students nested inside schools okay so
here I have my compounder but now
instead of average tutoring hours I have
ai J the number of tutoring hours that
student J and school I received and Y IJ
which is the test perform performance of
student J in school I and I still want
to measure the expectation of test
performance in a world where I intervene
on tutoring hours
but um now now I'm going to show you how
you can estimate that causal you can
identify that causal estimand even
though there's still the an unobserved
confounder and what's important here is
that the unobserved confounder is at the
school level budget okay so this
unobserved confounder is the same value
for all the students in each school okay
um but just this kind of graph is what
we're going to be talking about
today all right so let me first just
show you how you can identify it so um
um first we'll write the intervention
expectation of why in a world where I
intervene on tutoring hours as a
um conditional given the unobserved U
okay so this is just backd door
adjustment where I condition on the
unobserved confounder expectation of Y
given aals H and U equals u p of U du
this is back door adjustment to get at
this es demand and
um don't worry about the fact that we
don't observe it yet and now I'm going
to approximate that integral with Monte
Carlo so I take an average over schools
of the expectation of test performance
given H tutoring hours and U equal to UI
the budget of that
school and the and here's the here's
where we can do what we couldn't do
before even though we don't observe you
UI itself we don't know the budget of
each school we can estimate this
conditional expectation
without explicitly observing it okay and
all we need to do to do that is take the
data sets from each school so here's the
let me see where is that here's the data
set for school I it's for each student
how much they were tutored and what
their test performance was we take that
data we fit some kind of model of
expectation of Y given tutoring hours
and notice that when I take the data set
from Springfield Elementary and I take
all those students I estimate that
regression function let's say it's a
regression then essentially in that
regression function U equals UI for
whatever the budget is for Springfield
Elementary even though I never really
observed it right it's always going to
be equal to that for that for all those
students and so I've effectively
estimated this conditional expectation
from each of the schools data sets Okay
and since I've gotten that right you hat
I is a regression fit to each to school
I and I have a regression fit to each of
the schools I then substitute that in
for my expectation of Y given AAL H and
U equal UI in my formula here right here
I here are my fitted regressions for
each school I take the average of those
fitted regressions evaluated at H
tutoring hours and Presto I've
estimated this expectation even though I
didn't get to observe those budgets okay
is that all clear
good so here we just ran it as a
simulation just for no other reason than
to make the slide and so you can see
that it's um uh it's accurately
estimating the treatment effect um even
though it doesn't observe the budgets
okay whereas if I just ran a naive
regression of the schools on on um of
the tutoring hours on test performance
in the simulated setting I'd be biased
because of those
budgets okay
so what happened first of all I want to
emphasize again what I just showed you
has been well known for a long time um
but it was just a point of curiosity for
us that
somehow in this flat model we could not
estimate this Interventional expectation
it wasn't sorry we could identify the
Interventional expectation um but in
this hierarchical model when I when I
expand these aggregated variables into
the per student values I can identify it
and so what I want to talk about today
is what does it mean to take a causal
model and add hierarchy if I have data
sets like that and how can it help me
with causal inference okay and so just
to speak for a brief moment at a high
level the idea is that this kind of
causal structure this kind of
hierarchical structure might appear in a
lot of different applied settings in the
social sciences we see citizens within
States and we might have citizen level
variables about political preferences
and things like that and state level
variables about things like Bud budgets
and laws that might be confounding our
inferences about how some variables
affect others in biology which you're
interested in here many of you we have
cells within patients right cell level
variables might include genetics and
drug efficacy and patient level
variables might include things like
disease status or demographics and these
also might confound our understanding of
for example a drug on um on the patient
in physics and chemistry in many
different settings we have this idea of
data nested into groups and maybe even
nested further below
that okay speaking just from the
methodology perspective in basian
statistics and applied basian statistics
we have long enjoyed the benefits of
hierarchical modeling okay most applied
basian statistics papers nowadays are
about some kind of hierarchical model
where there's multiple groups of data
and the benefits of hierarchical bays
and of empirical bays are all about that
idea that idea that when I have multiple
groups of data and I estimate something
about them simultaneously I get a
benefit and so what we were trying to do
in this work is to understand you know
but so sorry but causal graphical
modeling has really only considered flat
models has never really contemplated
this idea of nested variables inside
units and so we are asking the question
you know can we enjoy some of the same
benefits that basian statistics enjoys
but via multi-group VIA multi-group data
in the in the context of causal modeling
and that's what this work is about
okay I will say one thing about
biology so I can't talk about it today
but if you want to invite me again I'll
talk about it
then um as long as you saw this talk
first um but the applied project that
we're working on using these ideas is
about understanding the effect of te-
cells on immune response okay and the
idea is which I learned from my
excellent co-author here Eli Weinstein
um each of us has a distribution of te-
cells in our bodies and it's called the
repertoire and the question we want to
ask is if I injected some other types of
te- cells into my body how well would I
protect against some new disease okay
and what is the causal effect of the
repertoire of te-
cells I feel nervous Speaking In This
Crowd about this um what what is the
causal effect of the repertoire of te-
cells on my um disease outcome
okay and and again the I'm going to
today talk about the kind of
mathematical basics of of the tools we
use to to solve this problem but this is
the kind of application that we have in
mind and that we're working on
now
okay again this idea of causal inference
from group data is an old idea it it
appears in lots of different settings
and today what I want to talk about is a
graphical methodology for causal reason
ing about group data how can we think
about it graphically and what kind of um
identification and estimation falls out
of that way of
thinking
okay so now we'll get into the
details to talk about this idea of
hierarchical caal models I'm going to
have three motifs three small little
graphs that we're going to be uh
studying
one we call confounder this is the one
we just studied where I have a a is
always going to be like a treatment Y is
going to be an outcome I have a
treatment to an outcome but then there's
this what we call a unit level
confounder you like budget we're going
to have this one called interference and
confounder where a goes to this unit
level variable Z the whole collection of
A's goes to Z and Z also affects the
outcome that's called that's a certain
type of interference not a general
interference but a certain type
um and then we're going to have what we
call an instrument graph where there is
now this Z variable which is an
instrument again nested inside of the
units many Z's Z goes to a it's not
affected by the confounder and a goes to
a unit level outcome okay we'll talk
about these throughout the
talk in each of them we're going to
consider the effects of a soft
intervention so just to remind you when
you intervene on a variable in a causal
graph what does that mean mean you
clobber the arrows going into that
variable and replace them with whatever
it is as determining that variable in
your intervention okay and so we're
going to intervene on a and all of these
and kind of almost necessarily we're
going to consider a soft intervention
where
we are going to replace the distribution
of a with another distribution called
qar a
okay now that could be a hard
intervention it could be that we say
everybody gets two hours of tutoring or
it could be that there is a distribution
of tutoring hours that we're imposing on
everybody equally at random everywhere
okay um that's called the soft
intervention P of Y in notation do a
comes from qar a all right and you can
see in all these graphs I removed the
arrow from U to a and replaced it with
qar a what we're going to think about is
we observe here passively
but our goal our inference goal our
estimation goal is to understand what
would happen if we did this okay in the
future right so there's kind of
counterfactual inference which is asking
what would have happened had I done that
given that that didn't happen but that's
so takes so long to say that we could
never give a talk about it and so we're
going to rather ask if I took my data
from the schools but then I made a
change and I gave everybody two hours of
tutoring what would happen then yep good
but but but not that we are going to do
this yeah we we're hypothetically
imagining it and then it's a
philosophical question that we won't get
into whether or not you can only
consider interventions that you can
really do but certainly people will
argue about that as well as every other
aspect of causal
inference
okay so let's first talk about this
confounder graph so remember schools are
units so the nplate are units students
are subunits that's the mplate
and the variables AI J tutoring hours
for student J and school I Yi J Test
performance for student J and school I
and UI for example budget for school I a
unit level confounder and the
intervention how does the distribution
of tutoring hours affect test
performance this is the example we've
been going
through now in the second graph
interference and compounder the variable
Z is a unit level descendant okay or we
call it interference and so for example
you might imagine that you know there's
a school here and um here are all the
students in the school and some of them
get tutoring and some of them don't but
then when they go out for recess as
students do they all discuss what they
learned during the day and so the
students that got tutoring are going to
tell the students that didn't get
tutoring all the cool stuff they learned
about math and things and um then that's
going to affect everybody's performance
on the test okay so that's called
interference where the treatment on one
student um affect is going to influence
another student even who didn't get
treated okay and that's called
interference okay um and finally in the
instrument graph the outcome variable y
notice is now at the unit level okay so
this is something about a school so for
example whether or not school I is
listed in a published list of top
schools and there's a new subunit
variable Z J which randomizes the cause
the treatment AI J for subunit J and
unit I what that means is that zi is
some kind of random influence on the
treatment variable AI J and notice it's
unconnected from UI so for
example if each School randomly
distributes coupons for tutoring to make
tutoring 50% off um and does so with
different distributions in each school
that would be an instrument that would
be a z now you might think oh
instrumental variables is solved but not
in this
situation and you'll see that we'll do
it with different kinds of assumptions
than normally used with instrumental
variables
okay with those three
motifs I'd like to get into the
nitty-gritty details of these
hierarchical causal models and so the
road map for the talk is to so
um if you're familiar with causal
graphical models there are these um
different levels of causal graphical
models and so first what we're going to
do is discuss what is hierarchical
structural equation model is what a
hierarchical causal graphical model is
and then discuss how to perform
identification in a hierarchical causal
graphical model how to do estimation and
then I'll just show you a kind of a toy
example with a real data
set okay so we'll begin with
hierarchical structural equation models
and hierarchical causal graphical models
and really we're just following along
the path the intellectual path of pearl
with hierarchical models with
hierarchical causal graphical models
rather than flat
ones okay so just to you a quick review
what is a structural equation model so a
structural equation model um it's before
Pearl but Pearl this is Pearl's
formulation of this idea each node is a
deterministic function of its parents
and some independent Noise Okay so this
is a flat model we have x a and Y and
it's a square which means it's a
deterministic function it's a
deterministic function of its parent so
a is a deterministic function of X and
some R independent noise
variable gamma okay and you can write
down a a schedule of equations to
describe a structural equation model so
here gamma X gamma a and Gamma Y come
from some distribution they're going to
be independent I guess I didn't make
that clear in this notation and then now
you see the variables have our
deterministic functions X is a
deterministic function of its noise a is
a deterministic function of X and its
noise and Y is a deterministic function
of a and x and its noise okay these are
all just
functions okay the idea behind
structural equation models when you're
building out your causal graph is that
you require a deterministic function
node an endogenous node for any variable
that affects two or more others
otherwise it can be thought of as a
noise
variable now again following Pearl's P
this is just Pearl again Pearl now takes
these structural equation models and
uses them to Define what he calls a
causal graphical
model and the idea there is to integrate
out the noise so integrate out the
random noise to produce random variables
instead of deterministic variables okay
and this looks familiar to you this is
just a probabilistic graphical model it
inherits all the properties of a
probabilistic graphical model here I
have X going to a a going to y y coming
from a and
X it defines a joint distribution of x a
and Y that factorizes using these
factors but because it came from the
causal model the structural equation
model it can tell us something about the
world of interventions that's the idea
and it's there's nothing magical here
we're assuming it came from this causal
struct the structural equation model and
that's what's giving us that power to be
able to predict something about an
intervention in the world through this
causal
graph okay but this just when you see it
in papers is a causal graphical
model looks just like a graphical model
if you saw it in the street you would
think it's a cause it's a graphical
model but if you have the secret
knowledge that it came from a structural
equation model you know that you can
make predictions about interventions
with this that's the
idea so now we have our
question how do we take our situation
where I have replications inside of a
plate and and think about a a structural
equation model in that
context and here there's an important
detail unlike classical structural
equation models for every subunit level
variable we're going to include two
levels of
Noise Okay so this is so here's the
model you write down on your whiteboard
when you're thinking about how the the
thing works that you're trying to figure
out and this is the corresponding
structural equation model and what's
different about this from a typical one
is that this variable here AI J it
doesn't just have one noise variable
going into it but it has two it's got a
subunit level noise variable Epsilon IJ
and a unit level noise variable gamma I
okay and the idea behind this is that
the subunit level noise Epsilon here
captures variation within the subunit
variables right in in Springfield
Elementary different students get
different amounts of tutoring and that's
and that's captured by the randomness in
epsilon within Springfield Elementary
okay but the unit level noise captures
variation among collections of subunit
variables Springfield Elementary and
Sunnydale High School have different
distributions of tutoring hours and that
difference in those distributions is
captured by gamma does this make sense
okay and so to go from the thing you
wrote on your whiteboard because you had
subunits Etc to a structural equation
model because you want to reason about
it causally you need to think about
these two levels of noise for the
subunit variables that's one of the
[Music]
nuances okay and then the schedule of
equations looks similar right I have my
noise variables I have my subunit noise
variables and everybody is a
deterministic function of its noise and
its parents
question one perspective on this could
be that you unroll this hierarchical
model and flatten it in some sense and
would that be equivalent to this except
where those errors now are now
decomposed into these two different
kinds of noises or is that a difference
are missing
well I'd have to think harder about the
answer to that question to answer it
well but I suspect my instinct is the
answer is no it's not the same as just
unrolling it if you unrolled it you
would not necessarily say oh I might put
this gamma
here the key thing is if you unrolled
this you would and then and then read
pearls excellent book the primer the
causal inference and statistics
primer um if you just did that then you
would only put these epsilons in you
would miss this gamma but the gamma is
important because the because that's not
respecting differences between
schools
yeah I was just going to maybe say I
think if you made a latent variable for
gamma and unroll it then maybe it would
be equivalent yeah you could do that our
point in in in making this kind of part
of the translation process from this
picture to the hierarchical structural
equation model which is too many
syllables is that is that this is a
picture you might draw when you're just
thinking about how do variables relate
to each other you wouldn't necessarily
put a latent variable there but but it's
implicitly there and actually I'll have
an ex I'll give an example for what this
might mean kind of intuitively in a
second question that the two different
the different noises are
independent yes they are independent yep
okay there's the schedule and so you can
see it looks real similar to the before
but now I have two sources of noise but
notice that Yi
J for all the students in Springfield
Elementary just make sure I know I'm old
as I mentioned so that's the Simpsons
school okay that's what we had there
before for all the students in
Springfield Elementary they all share
the same value of gamma iy right so
gamma gets chosen once and then all the
students in Springfield Elementary share
that gamma in their in their um
structural equation but each one has a
different Epsilon right some students do
better than others and in Sunnydale
That's The Buffy one all the students
share the same gamma again might be a
different gamma because it's drawn once
for that one but each one has a
different
Epsilon okay um so now to the
interpretation the noise variables
represent hidden causes that are not
confounding okay this is the idea behind
these noise variables they might they
they reflect variation that's not
confounding in the variables that you're
modeling and the intuition is that the
the sub unit noise just represents that
there is non-confounded variation among
students inside a school the unit level
noise on subunits reflects hidden causes
at the unit level right so for example
there might be a good teacher at
Springfield Elementary right that's
gamma everybody benefits from that good
teacher oh this is the Y variable so
there's the good teacher everybody
benefits from that good teacher in the
same way and um it's not that that good
teacher is at a student level and
whereas a student in another school does
not benefit from that same good teacher
okay that's the
idea Okay so we've got the hierarchical
structural equation model that's really
the basic material of this idea now
let's play the same game that Pearl
plays to create causal graphical models
and we'll integrate out all this
noise okay so first we're going to
integrate out the unit the subunit level
noise and you can see we have a little
graphical model for the subunit here
right we just did the same thing that
you do
classically but now we're going to
integrate out the um unit level noise
all right and now something interesting
is going to happen speaking of latent
variables so what just
happened when we integrated
out the unit level Noise We produced
these new variables called
Q which in the superscript shows you
what so I don't know how to explain this
let me just think about
it we can think of this subunit as being
a little graphical model right P of a p
of Y given a for school I all right and
when we integrate out the unit level
noise what we're doing is we are
producing new random variables that are
the factors in this graphical model
right this is p of a Qi of a for school
I this is p of Y given a for school I
okay that's what we're doing when we
integrate out the unit level noise the
unit level noise is affecting the
distribution of the subunit variables
and so when we integrate out the unit
level noise we have to make nodes for
that distribution and those are random
distributions because every time I make
a new school I first choose Q of a then
I choose Q of Y given a and then I let
the students get tutored and stuff
okay um
notice that's one thing to notice so
these are these Q variables are
important and also notice the how
connectivity changed so we had this unit
level variable
XI when we integrated out gamma I it
became a random variable but it was
connected to school performance however
because it's a unit level variable it's
only a relationship to test performance
sorry I said school performance I meant
test performance its only relationship
to test performance is through the dist
distribution of test performance for
that school and so the
connectivity X goes to q and Q goes to Y
these subunit variables are only ever
going to be connected to factors in the
subunit make sense okay and I'll show
you the algorithm for how to connect
this up uh
later all right and so now we have our
hierarchical causal graphical model
where we have these new variables Q
which are distributions drawn from
distributions of distributions okay this
is a distribution over distributions of
a this is a distribution over
conditional distributions of Y given
[Music]
a okay put differently they lie between
the unit level variables and the subunit
variables and again oh that's another
thing to notice they do not inherit the
connectivity of the subunit variables
that's also important so whereas a is
connected to Y excuse me qia a is not
connected to Qi y given
a okay and in the paper you can see a
derivation for why this all
happens all right so here is the
graphical algorithm for turning a
hierarchical structural equation model
into a hierarchical causal graphical
model for each subunit variable form
subunit level random variables and
remove the subunit level noise that's
easy that's just the same classical
thing just applied to the subunit for
the regular unit level variables like X
form unit level random variables and
remove unit level noise that just gave
us the X as a random variable
there and then for each subunit level
variable form unit level variables for
the factor V given its parents that's
where we make these Q variables
disconnect the unit level variables
from the subunit variables and then
connect the unit level parents of VI to
these Q's all right so this is now a
thing you can follow to turn
your hierarchical sem to a hierarchical
CGM okay so I'm not going to go through
it in that much detail but I'll just
show you so here's the thing you draw on
your board because that's the problem
you're solving and now there is your um
hierarchical sem corresponding to that
graph and now here is the corresponding
hierarchical causal graphical model
again you can see that whereas there's
an arrow here there's no Arrow here
that's going to be important for
identification here's the interference
graph here is the corresponding
hierarchical causal graphical model
where you can see some interesting stuff
happened with z and the q's
okay here's the instrument graph and
here's the hierarchical causal graphical
model you can see we have a Q for Z
that's disconnected from everything else
Q of a given Z here and some interesting
things happening with how it's connected
okay so that's
the that's the work you do when you draw
your assumptions like this with a
subunit and to go to something like this
which I'm calling a hierarchical causal
graphical model the next thing we're
going to do is try to figure out how to
identify causal effects in the context
of these of these causal graphical
models and you'll see it's going to be
um not that tricky there are assumptions
about the way that y depends on this
collection of A's and in particular it
needs to sort of exchangeably depend on
it it can't be that y depends on the
First Student in and the third student
and the ninth student it has to be that
if I saw these A's in different order I
would have the same distribution of Y
that's crucial all right so now let's do
identification and estimation just to
remind you um
if I'm sitting with a causal inference
problem I've set up a a graph that
that's my world and um the first
question I have is can I identify the
causal estimate so I set up my graph I
write down the effect of the
intervention as some kind of expectation
like expectation of Y do
QA and then I ask if I can identify it
meaning if I had actual access to the
Joint distribution under that that um my
causal graphical model represents if I
had access to that joint distribution or
equivalently I had infinite data from
that joint distribution could I then
figure out what this causal s demand is
and the premise is that if you can't
which sometimes you can't then there's
no hope in trying to estimate it from
finite data you're you're
sunk if you can then often that formula
for how to identify the causal effect um
leads you to an algorithm for estimating
it from finite data by estimating the
various components of that formula so
putting the causal s demand in terms of
the observational joint distribution is
what identification is
about okay so I just said this we're
writing an Interventional distribution
in terms of the observational
distribution so for example using the
due calculus Pearl's due
calculus is one way to get at
identification
um and again I said this earlier we're
going to consider a soft intervention on
a where we intervene on
a with this qar but now in our new model
that has these Q factors in them that's
just replacing this q o sorry this Q
factor with qar a okay so there's my
intervention this is my observational
distribution this is my intervene
distribution and so what we're going to
do is devise a graphical procedure for
doing identification these hierarchical
causal
models
okay so here's my confounder graph I
turned it into a structural equation and
a causal graph and I got these Q
variables and so
on here's my es demand the expected
performance in the world where I
intervene and I set everybody's tutoring
hours to be drawn from qar a so I'm
going to write that down in this way
expectation of mu of Q of Y
in the world where I intervene on QA
now let me explain this notation mu of Q
of Y is equal to the expectation under Q
of y a marginal distribution over test
performance of Y and Q of Y is the
marginal distribution of test
performance inside the subunit all right
so Q of Y just equals this integral QA
of a qy given a DA right that's just
probability and um but to be clear this
is the marginal distribution of test
performance within a school
right that's why it's capitalized here
it's random okay so this is an
expectation across schools and this is a
random marginal distribution of test
performance in a school in other words I
don't know I'm going to pluck a school
from my from my collection of
schools and it's got some distribution
of tutoring hours and it's got some
relationship between y in tutoring hours
and what I'm looking at is the marginal
distribution of test performance in that
world okay that's just this make sense
okay and so this expectation of Y this
is like a little iterated expectation
it's a
little complicated way to write it but
that's all that is
really what I want you to notice is that
this s demand is only a function of Q
variables Q of Y is
this
marginalization and I'm intervening on
on
QA okay so this is just something about
Q
variables So In classical
identification analysis we take n to
Infinity we imagine the number of units
goes to Infinity for hierarchical causal
models we're going to take both n and M
to Infinity so we're going to ask can I
identify the causal effect if I had an
infinite number of schools and each
school had an infinite number of
students and what that means is that
these Q variables are effectively
observed right if I had infinite number
of students in each school then I don't
need to worry about subunit about
variation of of uh students within the
school because I've seen an infinite
number of students I can tell you
exactly what the different Q factors are
going to
be so we call this graphical approach to
identification collapse and augment all
right and what's going to happen is
we're going to do this thing it's going
to result in a flat causal graphical
model a classical one that's going to be
equivalent to the HCM in both pre and
post intervention distributions and then
we do identification in that model okay
so first what we're going to do is we're
going to what we call collapse the model
we write the model down in terms of
these Q variables so there's my
confounder and I remove the subunit
variables because I'm imagining an
infinite number of students in the
schools all right and so you can see now
already what happened I made my Q
variables excuse me
and um I'm they are effectively observed
because I saw an infinite number of
students but remember I did not preserve
that connectivity between them right
that went away so that's going to help
us
okay but the second step this is in
terms of QA and qy given a but our
causal es demand is in terms of qy which
was this integral and so I'm going to
add qy which is a deterministic function
I'm using double arrows to denote that
of QA and qy given a
all right so that's collapse and augment
right so now this is my graphical model
that I want to try to identify the
causal effect of intervening on QA on
qy all right and so again here's my
causal s
demand and this if you know graphical
models you can see is easy to identify
with backd door adjustment qy given a is
I need to condition on that and
marginalize it out and then I can get
the distribution of qy in the world
where I intervene on
QA okay it's p of qy given a p of qy
given qar a and qy given a dqy given a
all right this is an Interventional
distribution this is all about the
observational distribution okay one
Nuance here is that P of qy given qar a
and qy given a is essentially a Delta
mass at the right qy given a that when
combined with QA gives me qy all right
it's a little funky
but but it works out
okay all right at a higher level the
point is this I took that hierarchical
model I turned it into this flat causal
model this flat causal model ows for
identification of the effect of QA on
qy that's
it we took that identification formula
we ran a little simulation just to
demonstrate that it works and you can
see as we see more and more data in
terms of number of units and subunits we
get closer and closer to the true effect
whereas a naive regression is going to
be biased the theory already tells you
that this is true but this is just a
demonstration
so we're going to now play that game
with the interference graph so when we
collapse the interference graph the Q
variables are going to attach to the
mediator there is the there is the
collapse graph for the interference
graph again I got my Q variables for the
different factors in the subunit but
they attach to the mediators right and
again the intuition if more students
receive tutoring QA then there's going
to be more classroom discussion
Z and that class classro discussion is
going to change the conditional
distribution of scores how much tutoring
affects my
score we're going to augment it we add
qy and
um now these Q
variables all right so we're going to
augment it qy and and this is the graph
um
good now again we have the same cause of
L demand the the the effect on qy of
interv meaning on QA now it's going to
get a little
hairer we write that down in terms of
again a point mass at the marginal now
times the change in qy given a by that
intervention and
this the change in qy given a based on
the intervention on QA can be can be
found with what's called front door
adjustment I won't go into the details
here if you're familiar with it that's
great you just saw an application of
front door adjust
if not you can read about it in in
Pearl's work um it's another way to get
at the intervention distribution using
terms from the observation distribution
that's all that's
important and that we can do it here
whereas we couldn't do it if we had
already aggregated the
data again a simple simulation to show
you that it's doing the right
thing the instrument graph this is the
last one is
again the es demand is expectation of Y
do a but now y remember is at the unit
level this is like is the school in a
published list of top
schools here again we collapse and
augment the
graph it's a little special in that the
augmentation is on the treatment
variable right because we QA is a
function of qz and QA given Z and QA
given Z and qz only affect y through QA
okay identification now comes from backd
door adjustment and what this shows you
is that in this graph you can do
identification without the usual kinds
of assumptions that instrumental
variable analysis requires right the
details are in the paper about
that okay and again here's a simple
simulation just to confirm so what we're
doing by the way in these simple
simulations is taking the identification
formula in this case it comes from back
door adjustment and just doing
the dumbest Monte Carlo estimates of
each term and then estimating the
distribution or expectation through
that okay that's the slog of the details
of this
idea the main point is you might be in a
causal inference situation where you
have subunits inside units if you are
you can reason about that that by
thinking about random distributions of
subunits inside units and those random
distributions won't necessarily be
connected in the same way as the
subunits were and that could be that
could open the door to causal inference
where it was otherwise unavailable from
aggregated data that's the
punchline so as a sort of real world
study I say sort of because this is like
the digits of hierarchical basian
analysis um we looked at the old data
from the eight schools all right and
actually this data is about it's a
coincidence test performance and um
tutoring hours and this data has become
a staple of hierarchical basian modeling
and the idea behind this data is to
estimate the effect of test preparation
on the SAT verbal which is a
standardized test I say it's a
coincidence because we use that example
just to work out these ideas and then at
the end we thought oh let's look at
eight schools and then it turns out
eight schools is about that example okay
so here's our here's our variables XI J
is the previous test store for student J
aij is tutoring hours Yi J is um sat
performance and you know one thing you
can do is imagine there are no causal
issues that this is just everything is
fine okay and now you just look at a big
average okay and and and that's not even
hierarchical base that's just taking the
raw data and calculating a big
conditional average of Y given a and X
now you could imagine in the eight
schools example that there could be unit
level by the way eight schools means n
equals 8 okay you can imagine in eight
schools there could be unit level
confounders that affect both treatment
and outcome all right and in and Eli
looked at the original 1979 paper found
this quote where student interest far
exceeded the program's capacity a larger
number of students went into the control
group than in the treatment group okay
what that means is that there's some
hidden variables here that are affecting
distributions of tutoring hours and of
course performance because there is
student interest right you can imagine
in schools where people are interested
in tutoring they probably are doing
better on the test I mean I'm not an
expert but that's you can imagine that
um what's interesting I thought just
historically is that when you run
through our methodology with this graph
you get back classical hierarchical
basian modeling right which means that
doing the classical hierarchical basian
modeling thing even though it's not a
causal thing is gives you the same
algorithm as imagining a causal graph
with this unobserved confounder I
thought that was kind of
interesting now could there be
interference turns out that class size
the class size of the tutoring hours of
the tutoring class depends on school
size um as well as of course treatment
and affects the score Yi J right so this
is another case of
interference and so we reanalyze the
eight schools data using this
hierarchical causal graph and what we
found is that if you imagine and there's
again a quote I don't have it in here
from the paper saying that class size
could really be a thing um you find that
whereas the paper found a small positive
effect to tutoring the uncertainty about
it uh when you think about the
possibility of interference uh goes up
and you can't you can't conclude that
there is any um good effect for tutoring
on Sat performance again I'm not
suggesting that this
is any kind of new result in
educational data analysis rather that a
way to use hierarchical causal models in
a real world
setting okay so in summary nested data
and hierarchical models are a main stay
of Basi and statistics but today I told
you about how to think about nested data
in the context of causal models the key
idea the nested data produces a flat
model of distributions that if you see
many many many students you've
effectively observed and now you can
reason about those distributions but it
doesn't inherit the connectivity of the
original model which can open the door
to identification and
estimation there's lots of things you
can imagine doing different applications
I mentioned the tel application that
we're finishing up now you could think
about using this in the context of
multi-site experiments you can think
about about all different kinds of
places where you have many
related groups of data a causal
inference question that you have about
all of them and where this could help
you deal with some of the unobserved
variables that are lurking in those data
sets as I mentioned we did the most
naive silly little estimation algorithms
using Monte Carlo but I enjoy doing
basian inference and so you could
imagine and this has random
distributions in it and so you know one
thought would be to think about basian
nonparametrics which is all about how to
do basian analysis on random
distributions in the context of these
hierarchical causal models or other
better estimation algorithms and then
another question is is this method
complete in other words um Can it always
find c can the algorithm for deciding
whether or not it's identifiable always
find out that it is identifiable if it
is this is a theoretical question that
we have not answered if if you're
interested there's a paper on the
archive that's it these are the extra
slides thanks very
[Applause]
much thank you very much Dave
wonderfully explained talk okay so
questions I'll try to run around and
also if you can um come to the mic as
well um I was wondering about
measurement noise in the observed
parameters at one point you said all the
noise we observed is the result of
hidden causes but it could just be
random sampling and measurement errors
which is I think a lot the case in some
of the data sets we look at and yeah it
seems like especially if the
differences and the causal effects could
appear smaller for variables that have
more measurement noise and that sort of
thing and is it still possible to
identify cause effects in those so I
think the answer to your question is
that that um
you know I I told you earlier I'm a
little allergic to the philosophical
stuff but the you know I think the
answer is that the subunit level noise
is measurement noise right so that could
be seen as a hidden cause the hidden
cause is some crazy stuff that you know
a genius could figure out was there is
creating noise in my subunit variable or
maybe it's innate Randomness I'm not
sure that's why I said it's kind of
philosophical um so that's where
measurement noise would live now can you
still
identify I made a big assumption here
which is that you have an infinite
number of subunit variables I a question
here I should added to this list what
are the finite sample properties of
these estimators right this is the this
is the an important question it seems to
me the measurement L does not affect the
other variables it's just what you
observe again yeah that's right so
that's why it would be in like the let
me get my guy that's why it would be
like if there's an Epsilon here in the
in the structural equation model right
that the randomness in AI J is because
of measurement noise for example that's
the idea that's where measurement noise
would be modeled in this situation and
indeed thought of as unconfounded it
doesn't connect to anything else it just
connects to AI J but of course if you
see an infinite number of these subunits
then all that measurement noise is
washed out except that you of course
don't so that's why it's an interesting
question to ask one what are the finite
sample properties but two even
theoretically how do I think about
more subunits like we were talking about
at lunch more subunits versus more units
y good
question yeah uh so I have a question
about the the error bars and uncertainty
so towards the end you mentioned this so
one question I guess is how do you
compute these are these um uncertainties
over the identified model or the
randomness for an experiment are both
and why was it that in your model uh you
had error bars that weren't overlapping
with the truth for small samples should
we expect those ER bars to overlap with
the truth but just be really big when
you have small samples is there a bias
yep
so I need to check the paper but my
memory is we did simple like
bootstrapping to get airor bars here so
this is like estimation air bars um and
the reason that you see in so and again
these identifiability results are for
infinite numbers of subunits and units
so when you're in a finite sample
situation where there's you know 10
students in a school and 15 schools you
are there's going to be bias and so
understanding this of course is a good
open question do you think there are
ways to have a bigger error bar on the
left a bigger one yeah I mean it's it's
too small right oh this um
yeah I'm I'm not sure yeah um there's
sort of two kind of data settings I'm
sort of thinking about that I think
maybe are related but not exactly the
same as your school example um and
they're basically the same one is time
one is space so you can imagine um sort
of Time series data where the hierarchy
is maybe not so well defined such as uh
which school but maybe I want to say do
I time average over a year over a minute
and you know many minutes mapped to an
hour many hours mapped to a a day and so
on and then same thing maybe more close
to what people work on here like spatial
data um I maybe have some sort of
confounding on the scale of tissues
which is maybe like centimeters and then
uh individual cells and so on and I was
wondering if you could speak
to um I guess this question of searching
for the
correct uh hierarchical level upon which
to separate your data that's a good
question yeah so let's just get a graph
up right so um
so you're you're highlighting
a assumption I've been making this whole
time right which is some kind of
exchangeability assumption the schools
they're all exchangeable with each other
and the joint distribution of the school
level data doesn't change if I if I put
the schools in a different order in that
joint distribution you know now
spatially right we could add a node here
which is the lat long of the school and
that affects everything and then
essentially you've got conditional exch
you know conditional on that it's
exchangeable and so everybody's happy
right you've found enough variables to
make it conditionally exchangeable to
make it
exchangeable um so one question is what
if you can't find variables to make it
exchangeable or what if they are
organized in a Time series where there's
something latent that is drifting and we
haven't thought about
that theoretically I think these ideas
could be extended to that situation but
I would know quite how to do it in front
of all of you
um but certainly the the case where you
can you can find variables that you can
can condition on to make it exchangeable
and that variable could be time stamp
too right space and time is all the same
so um you could do it that way your
second question is about what level
to hierarchical eyes yeah I'm kind of
like thinking like you know centimeters
mapped to millimeters mapped to
micrometers right I see so like another
other words if I have if if I have
groups within groups within groups at
finer and finer scales or do you mean
even just what scale to think about the
data at it seems like your model is sort
of mapping out exchangeability with
respect to different types of
confounding so there seems to be maybe
you're concerned about confounding
relative to tissue type you would want
to um sort of group things at the level
at which tissue type kind of doesn't
vary kind of with the schools whereas
then if I was worried about removing a
signal with respect to I don't know some
other that happens at some other length
scale I could pick
the I see what you mean like I I don't
quite know how to answer the question
but you're saying that somehow the the
definition of the
subunit
is relative to the definition of the
confounder in a sense yeah so maybe with
schools I could have broken It Up by
classrooms right yep okay so which one
do I do right yep um yeah I I you know
my hunch is that there's something to
say about
that and that you could do it
yeah that's my hunch yeah I agree with
you it's it's very interesting it's it's
it's related to the idea of like at what
level do I want to model things and and
you're right it relates to
exchangeability but here it relates to
where can I model things such that when
I know the distribution of that I'm able
to unhinge
identification right it's good yeah I
think my question is related to the last
one actually because because I guess
when you have this hierarchy of
hierarchies or something like in
principle you can have other levels of
confounding and you could add on to this
like have a deeper
hierarchical causal graphical model I
suppose right um
so in principle I guess you could do
that but that's I guess where the finite
sample stuff becomes relevant because
you you only have only so much data
right and then the the more you add
these levels I'm trying to understand
when does it start hurting in some sense
to to do that I mean I think that also
that has to do with in the previous
question about where the confounding is
kicking in so you know if these schools
were all in different countries for
example there might be and and and there
might be subgroups within the groups and
those subgroups might enjoy not enjoy
might involve confounding at that
subgroup level and so um you might want
to model it at that point
too or it might be that going deeper
down maybe maybe this is countries and
these are School averages there is no
confounding and so there's no point in
doing it but that you're right that
would also be interesting from a finite
sample perspective like if there's no
confounding I imagine aggregating the
data and modeling it is better right and
so maybe making that precise would be
interesting yep
one question and then we can take other
questions after I mean this will be
quick because I essentially was asking I
I was curious about the same thing as
him but I was just curious uh presumably
this process generalizes to several
levels of hierarchy but I was curious if
you know anything about the trade-off
between like increasing the levels of
hierarchy in terms of how much it helps
you like be able to make better causal
reasoning versus how much it requires
you to have like more data at each level
yeah I mean I think that you're right
that that relates to the answer to the
previous question probably if if if
there's no confounding or issues if
there no causal
issues below this level probably it
hurts to break everything up
um and so maybe you want to aggregate at
the highest level possible such that
there is no confounding issues or no
identification issues would be a more
General way of saying it um these are
these are good points you're all making
I know there are more questions but
maybe so that others can leave since
we're already over time we'll just have
them come up to you direct yeah so thank
you so much thanks