So last time just quickly recall we
looked at a function on some interval
into R.
We looked at uh a partition P. So here
we have the interval from A to B. Then
we have a partition x0
x1
up to say xn.
We looked at uh mi which was the soup
on this little interval here from x i
minus one to x i of f. We looked at
little mi which was the in
f here was bounded again
uh and in on the same interval x i minus
one 2x i
and then we looked at the upper and the
lower sum. So we looked at the uh upper
and lower sum
with respect to this partition. So this
here was the sum of mi and then delta xi
and the lower sum
for this partition which was the sum of
this small mi delta xi where the delta
xi was the length of this these little
intervals here
like that. Right? And then it was reman
integral. Then we looked at the the
lower and the upper reman integral.
So we looked at the
upper and lower reman integral.
This here was now the in
of uh these upper integrals
over all partition and the lower one
that was the soup.
of the lower
sums
over all partitions.
And then we said that f is reman
integral
uh if if those two numbers are the same.
If the upper one here which is always
big or equal to the lower one if that is
actually equal to the lower one the
lower reman integral right
and and if this is the case right so if
this here is it's it's reman integral if
and only if these two numbers are the
same in that case we wrote for this
common number we wrote just the uh we
wrote it as as a reman integral
So now
there was this parallel to things we've
done before. There was these algebraic
rules for that we talked about at the
very end. So what were there th those?
Uh if you take a function
that is reman integraable
uh and you take c is a constant.
Then uh then the product here is also
reman integral
and the integral of the product is just
product function is just the product of
c with the uh with the reman integral of
f. Right? So that was one.
two is that if you have a second
function, so in addition to f, you also
have a g and they're both reman
integral.
Then the then the sum here is also reman
integral
and the integral of the sum
is is equal to
uh from a to b is equal to the sum of
the remman integral.
Let's prove this one here.
I won't prove the first one, but let's
prove the second one. Right? So, this is
true.
Now to prove this, let me remind you
about one of the one of the uh one of
the lemas that we had last time that we
was talking about that this was a useful
lema to determine whether a function was
remman integraable. So, so recall this
from last time
that uh you have the following lema
that um f again is bounded. So f is
reman integral
if and only if
uh for all for all epsilon greater than
zero there exist a partition of this
interval here such that
the upper sum which is always bigger
uh than the lower sum
this one here minus
the lower sum. So this number is always
positive. But if for all epsilon
you can make this difference here
smaller than right you can find a
partition so that you have that to prove
that last time.
So now let's go to the proof of this.
So proof of true.
So since so uh given
given epsilon greater than zero
since uh f here is reman integral
then there exist a partition p1
um such that
the
upper
sum
minus the lower sum
is less than epsilon / two. Right? This
is because the function f was remand
integraable. And likewise
likewise
likewise since G is remman integraable
so there exist
uh exist
a second partition
P2. So that uh for G you have the same
thing
for G and P2. Sorry this is G.
this upper sum minus the lower sum for G
with respect to this second partition.
This here is less than epsilon / two
right now.
So now you let P here.
So now let
let P be the partition
that
has all the dividing points
uh points
of P1 together with
all the dividing points
uh of P2, right? So, so it has it has
the partitions that are in either one of
the two, right?
Or both, right?
And so now we know that so this is means
that so so P here is a refinement
of both
P1 and P2
right so this means that actually when
you're looking at this if you're looking
at this upper
sum minus this lower sum. Remember that
if you go to a refinement then this hair
goes down and this hair go up. So it
means that this difference here will be
less or equal to what it is for for P P1
and this was of course less than epsilon
over two. That was how it was chosen.
And similarly, if you're looking at the
upper sum for G
with respect to P, P here is a
refinement of P2 also. Right? So this
means that you have that this difference
here
is less or equal to the upper sum of G
with respect to P2 minus this lower sum
with respect to P2 and that's less than
epsilon / two
right but this means now that if you now
take the so now if you take so now
[Applause]
So now if you take the an interval here
of uh this is from x i minus one to x i
if you're looking at this sum here you
had to be a little bit careful here
right but if you're looking at the sum
on this interval right the sum here is
less are equal to the soup of what f is.
This is you know this is on on on this
interval here right on this interval
this function here is less than the soup
of f plus the soup of g on the same
interval.
Right?
And it's of course bigger equal to
what it is the in
of f plus the in of g on that same
interval.
Why do I say you had to be a little bit
careful is that the in of the sum could
be strictly larger than this and it
could be strictly less than that. Right?
But you certainly have this statement,
right? But just thinking about if if f
and g was the same up to a sign, right?
If g was like minus f, right? Then the
sum would be dead zero. But you know one
of the function may be negative on this
interval and the other one was positive
right? So, so you see for the sum here
could be dead zero but these two numbers
one would be positive the other would be
negative right but you certainly have
this inequality right and so of course
this implies
that the on this interval the soup of
the sum here
is less than the soup
of of of
the the sum of the soups
some of the soups on the same intervals
and and likewise
uh for the in right.
So you have this thing here and you have
that this thing here is clearly bigger
or equal to the in of the same function.
So which is the sum of the two on this
interval here.
And that is of course bigger than than
than this sum here.
Right?
So, so this here this number here right
you see this here is like m i for the
function f right this is what this
number is right and this here is like
this number here is like capital m i for
the function g right and this here this
here is like little this here is like
little m i for the function f and this
number here is little m i for the
function g. So what we have here is
that's uh mi
for f plus sorry let me let me write it
uh
let me write it over here.
[Applause]
So what we have is that we have little
mi for the function f plus little m i
for the function g is less or equal to
little m i for the sum
which is of course less than soup of the
same sum on the same interval. So this
is this
and that's less or equal to the soup of
f on that interval plus this here of g
right so you have that inequality
but now you see that this means of
course that the contribution so if
you're looking at this upper
sum for this
This upper sum for the sum of these two
functions
with respect to P
this here the contribution you get is
for the upper you get this and for the
lower you would get
you get this here times the length of
the interval right
so this is
so again so what you get from on that
little interval the contribution you get
is like m i f + g
um times the length of the interval.
This is this minus m i f + g times the
length of the interval. This is the
contribution that you get here from this
interval from this little interval.
Right?
And because this number here is less
than that then this here is less than
uh m i f plus m i g time delta xi
minus
and then this thing here you see this
the spread between these two here bounce
the spread between those two. So this is
less than m i f plus m i little m i g *
delta xi
right so right and now you're summing
over everything right so this means that
this thing here is so this and you and
if you just split this here this sum
here you can just split that into two
parts the mi
times uh delta
X I minus little MI F * delta XI and
then plus
um capital M I G delta XI
minus little M I G delta XI right so
when you're summing these up
you get uh U FP
that's from this here. What when you're
summing these up UM FP minus sorry L F P
right when you're summing these up then
you're getting U G P minus uh L
f L uh G P
right?
And so what you get here is
again when you're summing it up this
here
gives you when you sum this up then you
get this. When you sum this hair up you
get that. When you sum this up you get
that. So summing everything up you get u
f + g comma this partition minus l f
plus g with respect to this partition is
less or equal to u f with respect to
this partition minus l f respect to the
partition p plus uh u G P minus L G P
right so you're getting that right
and this thing here
it was a refinement of the partition P1
so this spread here is less than what it
was for P1 so this here is less than
epsilon over two and likewise this here
is a refinement of the partition P2 so
the spread here is less than what it is
for P2 two. So you're getting this and
so this here is epsilon, right? And so
this gives you the partition and so
there's two syncs, right? You have to be
careful with that, you know, for one
function you get one partition. For the
other function, you get another
partition. So you're looking at the at
the sub partition that has all of the
dividing points of both of them. And the
other things you had to be careful is
about and that was embedded here it was
uh but it was actually more clearly on
one of the other board is that when
you're looking at two functions and
you're looking at a little interval and
you're taking like the soup of the two
of the sum then that's bounded by the
sum of the soup but it's not like equal
to the sum right you know and likewise
for the in right yeah
I mean, so the there's not uh but the
reason there's not is that once you have
this sort of general framework, you
wouldn't really get back to the
partition actually. So you know if it
was I mean yeah I mean you know once you
sort of have this solid foundations
then you just write uh I mean you just
write the integral fine yeah and and so
so so just to just on that note right
this dx this is right so it's it's so
this here
Um
[Applause]
um
this here is uh right this here is like
uh is referring this is like a giant s
right so it's referred to summation
this here is of course a d and and and
delta right is a Greek letter for d and
so this here you should think about this
here is referring to sort of some sort
of limits of these uh delta xi.
Okay. So, so that was uh let me just uh
talk a little bit about uh the other two
um uh rules. So one of the other one is
one of the other ones is that if you
take two functions
f and g again.
So you have so number three here was
that if you have f and g they are both
integral on this interval here
and uh f here is lesser equal to g then
it implies that the integral here is
lesser or equal to
the integral
of g
and that's I won't prove this. sort of
in a way I mean maybe I'll just say
words right that if you take a partition
then of course you're looking at some x
i minus one and x i some interval like
this
and so if you're looking at the function
f and you're looking at the soup of the
function f on this little interval well
then obviously
this soup here is less than the soup of
of of just because you have this
inequality everywhere, right? And so
this means that the and likewise for the
int and so you see that it's kind of
this inequality
you have to you know of course make it
nice into a mathematical proof but this
inequality will seem kind of obvious
right?
Uh
let me instead try prove uh that if you
split the interval up into pieces
uh then you can just sum the pieces.
So this is the following.
So, so again in the notes which I
haven't I forgot to post but I I will
post I guess these are posted because
these is from from these are things we
didn't quite do yet last time. Uh and
but but the proofs
of all of these four here also the one
in particular like the one this one here
I didn't do now. Uh they are all the
proofs are all in the notes.
So number four here is that if you take
a function and it's integraable on some
interval like this, it's bounded always
bounded
and you're looking at the integral here
of this function
and C here is C is somewhere between so
C is lying between A and B.
Well then actually um and then actually
let me just before write down this then
the function here if you thinking about
restricting the function to the smaller
interval from a to c it's also
integraable there
and likewise uh if you restrict it to
the integral
from C to D to B then it's also
integraable here. So it's integral
integraable on both these sub intervals.
And
and you have that the integral here of f
is dx
is equal to the sum
uh of the integrals
like that. Okay.
And so now why is this the case?
So
so this is just because if you take
So let's see. So
Right. So now let's try to prove then.
So
right so if so I want to look at the
um right. So, so let me first let me
first prove that if it is integral here,
it's also integraable on these two sub
intervals, right? And then once you know
uh through um in that proof, we will
also see uh what that sum is equal to.
So I again use this lema from before
that all I do need is to for a given
epsilon I need to find a partition. So
uh so that the spread between the upper
and the lower sum is um for each of
these two is bounded by epsilon. So
given epsilon
uh we since
f here is integraable
on the integral from a to b.
We know that there exist there exist a
partition p such that
the uh upper sum
[Applause]
uh minus the lower sum
is less than epsilon.
Now I then I look at a refinement. So
here I have A, here I have B and and
here I have C. And then I have some
partition
but it's a partition may not have C as a
dividing point. Right? So I'm looking at
so let's
let's uh
let P star
uh be the refinement
[Applause]
that
in addition
to all the dividing points.
uh of P
also
have
C
as a dividing point.
Okay, so it has one more dividing point.
I mean of course it may be that C was
already there then you don't then then
this partition is fine right
and so now of course now the thing is
that once you have that well first of
all you have this is refinement so you
still have so you may as well just think
so so you have this inequality so you
have that u of f comma p star
is minus l of f p star is is also
strictly less than epsilon, right? This
because it's refinement of B.
And so now you're looking at at the
piece. So this thing here but this thing
here this thing here is just equal to
this here is simply equal to u uh f of p
star
intersected with
a c
plus
u
p
u p star intersected with the interval
from C to B. Right? By this here, when
I'm taking the position partition and I
intersected with the interval, I'm just
thinking about the the part of the
partition that is dividing this interval
up. Right? So you have this and likewise
this thing here
is is the sum this one here is the sum
of the partition the lower sum the sum
of the two lower sums
which is this
A to C
plus
L f
P star
of uh of C to be
like that. Okay.
And so this of course means that so now
you can split this up and you can divide
right. So you have this is equal to this
sum. This here is equal to that sum. So
you can just rearrange it so that that
the upper sum. So you have so this means
that this whole thing here is equal to
u f p star
intersected with a comma c
minus and then I take this one here
next. So, uh, L
F P star intersected with A C.
And then I take plus this one here.
And then I take the last one, which is
this one here. And it's again it comes
with a minus sign. So, minus L.
F P star
uh intersected with
C V
like that. Okay. And but each of these
things here this here is is is non
negative. This here is non negative.
And you see the the sum of these two
numbers is bounded by epsilon. just
means that each of them must be at most
epsilon, right? Yeah.
>> Explain what you did to break up into
>> Okay. So,
so I have
I have here the interval.
Um
I have here the interval from A to B.
Um here I have C
and the star partition is the one that
has all of the dividing points of the
original partition P and then also C. So
the partition looks like this.
Maybe this here would be the partition.
And now I'm thinking about so the the
sum here in the the sum from the star
partition it would look like this and
I'm summing over all I right but I can
look at where I'm summing over just
those interval up to here
right I can look at where I'm just
summing over this interval and then I
can look at where I'm summing over those
interval Right? And so that's what I
mean. So this here is now where you're
summing over all the I but but you can
also just summing over the eyes that are
lesser equal to C and the eyes that are
you know in this range right okay so
that's
okay. So, so this here proves
this here. So, what this prove is that
if you take uh this function
and is integraable on this interval
and you now restrict it to either of
those, they are also integraable. Right?
That's what it actually proves. But it's
easy to see that uh that it it also with
a little bit maybe I'll leave this for
you. Uh but it but that that through the
proof we also get that this sum here
will have to be equal to the sum of
these two right but really what I
technically speaking proved was just
this part here. Okay.
But again the it's the all of the
details for this are in the in the
notes. Okay.
Um now the next thing I want to Okay. So
yeah. So I I I I will um let's talk
about one other uh one corner of this.
So it's the corner really not of this
fourth property but on the third
property.
So the third property was this wheel.
So the third property was this property
here over here. So I want to talk about
a corate of this one.
So now I have a function. I'm assuming
both the function and the function that
is the absolute value. So the function
that's absolute value means that at each
point instead of looking at f ofx I'm
looking at the absolute value of f ofx.
This is the function. So I'm assuming
that both of these functions are reman
integral
on this integral from a to b.
And then the claim is that the that the
integral here of f is lesser equal dx
sorry
is lesser equal to the integral from a
this is a very ex this is
very simple inequality but extremely
useful. So this is the claim right. So
I'm already assuming that things are
everything is remman integraable. So I
don't need to to prove anything like
that. I just need to establish this
inequality. And so to do that I'm just
looking at f. Well f is less or equal to
the absolute value. If f is positive
it's equal to the absolute value. If
it's negative this here is non negative
anyway. So so so this is clear. This is
clearly for all x.
But it's also clear that if I take minus
f you see this is also less than this
right
but now taken together so those two
things
so now the first one so
so let's say star here and double star
here
it's just star here
plus properties three from from over
there. This just give us that integral
of f from a to b dx is less or equal to
the integral of the absolute value.
Right? This is from star and tree. But
if we take double star here
+ three well then we have that
uh right so this here so we have that
the integral of minus f dx is less or
equal to the integral
like this
right but this one here is you can just
think about this here as minus1. This is
like minus1
times this function, right? So minus one
just comes out. That was like number
one. So this here is like minus1
times the integral from a to b of f dx.
But this is of course the same as minus
the integral from a to b f dx. Right? So
you see that so this here so this so the
second here implies that minus the
integral from a to b f dx is less or
equal to this thing here
right and so now you have this thing
here and that thing here and so together
it just means that the absolute value of
this is bounded by this
And so that's really this column. Okay.
The next thing I want to talk about, so
this is how to evaluate integrals,
right? And so there you have this the
fundamental theorem of countness.
And so we give two versions of that.
So
how to evaluate
uh integrals.
And so this is the fundamental theorem
of calc.
Okay. And now what does the fundamental
theorem of calculus? So let's skip
version one.
So version one,
version one is that if you take um uh if
you take a function uh f
and f here is continuous
uh and you're looking at the integral.
you're looking at so you have a function
I don't really think about it as two uh
as two versions
uh but but but uh the the version uh um
but but but I divide it into two
versions here so the function if f is
continuous say on the interval from
on this interval here and you define a
function f ofx
which is the integral from a to x of f
of s
ds.
Right? You see for each fixed x in the
interval here,
well, if you're thinking about the
function little f, the little f was
continuous on the whole interval. So
it's continuous on, right? So f here is
continuous on the interval from a to x,
right? So it's when you restrict it,
it's still continuous.
So this means that it's integraable,
right? And so this here gives you a
number, right? And so for each x, you
can think about this number here. So
this gives you a function capital f,
right? And the claim is that that this
function here. So the claim
is that the function capital f defined
this way
is is differentiable. So capital f is
differentiable
and the derivative of this
uh at uh at x
um is is uh is little f of x.
And maybe I'll just Yeah. So that's
that's the claim.
Okay,
let's try to prove that.
So let's look at let's try to prove
so we want to prove so we want to prove
that this function so so we want to
prove
to so want to show
uh want to show that
fprime
exist right
uh at say at x0 right if you want to
prove that it exist
then you need to look at the difference
quotient
so we need to look at this difference
and we need to prove that this thing
here has a limit as x go to x0 right so
x0 is fixed and you want to prove that
it has a limit
Let's um
so in order to estimate this let me just
let me not uh divide first let me just
look at what this difference here is
right and then afterwards I'm going to
divide by x - x0 so if I'm looking at
this let's for the sake of arguments
assume that x is bigger than x0 of
course I need to also see when I'm
approaching x0 from the other sides,
right? But but but the argument for that
is similar. So I just assume that x is
bigger than x0.
Well, this difference here, well the
function, so this function here, the
function here, so let me just write it
over here so I have a little more space.
So this difference here where the
function this here is the integral from
a to x f of s ds and this thing here is
the integral from a to x0
f of s ds right
but this first integral here I can use
this fourth rule that I maybe don't have
anymore. But it the fourth rule is
saying that you can split it up a
integral you can split it up. So here if
you have a you have a then you have x0
and then you have x. If you want to
integrate little f over this it's the
same as integrating over this plus the
integral over that. Right? So I do that.
So this one here I break into two
pieces. I integrate from a to x0 f of s
ds and then I take the second piece
which is from x0 to x
and then minus the integral from a to x0
of f of s ds.
Okay,
but now you see that this one here
cancel out with that, right? And so this
difference is just the integral from x0
to x f of s ds. Okay.
So
so so
what we have is
we have that this difference here f of x
- f of x0
We know that this difference here is
equal to this integral here.
Now let me use this to bound this thing
here from above and bound it from below.
You see this integral here, this
function here. So this function here if
you're looking at this integral here
sorry for f of s ds
well this function here is
is smaller
than the max right the function is
continuous so max and soup is the same
the max or soup whatever you want on
that interval right so this thing here
is less than than the integral of
um if you will x0 to x of the soup of f
on this interval here,
right? But this is just a constant,
right? And so this here is just uh this
is just like the soup of the function on
this little interval
times, right? So this constant. So this
just pops out and then it's just the
integral of one on this. But that's just
the length of the interval. So it's this
here times the length of the interval.
And the length of the interval is this.
Right? So this thing here is less than
that. Right?
Likewise this function here on this
little interval is bigger equal to the
in. So this is bigger than
right than if you were just integrating
the in of the function on the same
interval.
But the in and is this is just a
constant. This pops out. So this thing
here is just the in
of the function on this interval here
times the length of the interval.
Okay, like that.
Okay, so now I can and remember that
this here was equal to the difference,
right? So now I can just record this. So
what I have is now
What I'm interested in is in the
difference in capital f. So what I'm
interested in is of course I really want
to look at the difference quotient but I
can do this in just a second. So I'm
interested in the difference of the of
the function at those two points. Right?
I know that that difference is equal to
that integral here and that integral is
bounded from above by this and below by
that. So I just write I can now just
write that this difference here maybe I
should write it so I have a little more
space somehow f of x minus f of x0
the difference is bounded from above by
this thing here the soup of f
on this little interval
time x - x0
and it's bounded from below
by the in
on that same interval
times the length of the interval.
Right?
So now now we can go to the different
function because we just divide by x -
x0 on both sides. x is bigger than x0.
So you have this in here. So you have
this difference quotient here. And
that's what we want to show has a limit.
And now we have that this is less than
soup of f on this little interval here
and it's bigger equal to the in
of f on that same little interval.
Right? But you see that as x here
but now you have
[Applause]
now you have that as x go to x0
right so
so now as x goes to x0
right the values
and not just the value at x but actually
in this whole interval here the values
goes to the what the values is at x0
right so you see that this here
this the right hand side here goes to f
of x little f ofx0 and the left hand
side go to little of f of x0 right so
this means that this thing is squeezed
between these two numbers that goes to
the same number. So this difference
quotient also goes so this difference
quotient here
goes to
f of x0 right because it's squeeze
between those two numbers that converge
to the same number namely to f ofx
little f of x0.
So this here proves
that it's but technically speaking I
only did it where I'm assuming that x
was bigger than x0 if you if you let so
you also need to check when x is
strictly less than x0 and it's
converging to x0 from below
but with trivial modification the same
proof works so and and and that's done
out in the notes so I to not go through
that.
Okay. Now let's talk about so this is a
second version of the fundamental
theorem of calculus
right and so I mean again you know you
wouldn't really eventually kind of think
about it as probably as two different
versions but but but there sort of
slightly you know it's it's two two
things about the same stuff
but uh second version here. So I divided
into these two versions. So the second
version. So
so again fundamental thermal calculus
version two.
And so this is the following
that you take a function uh f that is
def you know and is f is defined on some
interval from a to b
into r and f is differentiable.
So this here exist
it's differentiable at each point
and uh and um uh f here this little f is
reman integral
and then the claim is that um
that f of b minus capital f at a is the
integral
from a to b of uh of little f of x dx.
Okay, so that's a claim, right?
Um,
all right. I wonder if I should just
skip that.
Uh I did that I did the proof uh for for
this out in the notes also. So maybe
I'll just skip that.
Um
and and then
uh
okay so now but let me look at an
example where I'm applying it.
Um
and so I have uh I'm looking at so
suppose I want to compute x from 0 to 1
dx
suppose I want to compute that
and so in this case I could look at So
if I sort of want to apply that version,
I could think about suppose I'm looking
at f ofx equal to uh x ^ 3 over three,
right? Suppose I'm looking at this.
Well, if I'm looking at this function, I
know that capital f of x is equal to the
derivative of this is just x,
right? So this say and x squ is now of
course it's continuous so it's
integraable right so this means that uh
by the second by the by this second
version
uh of the fundamental thermal calculus
Then we have that uh that f of 1 minus f
of zero
is equal to the integral right of of the
derivative because the derivative is
integral. So 0 to 1 of of
x dx, right? But this here is now just
evaluating
this function here. So this here is/3
minus zero. So this original integral is
a third, right?
Okay. So,
so the next thing um right so the next
thing I want to talk about is
uh uh improper integrals. Okay. So this
here concludes this here was stuff I
actually had from the previous lecture.
That was why I skipped a couple of
things. But but um
um but yeah, but the details uh for for
the things I skipped is in the notes and
the things I skipped is very similar to
things I went through here anyway.
Okay. So now let me look at improper
integrals. And there's a couple of
versions of this. So we will look at two
version of this. one is where the
integral where the integral is. So we
look at so improper integrals.
So I'm going to look at two versions. So
two versions.
uh version one is where the integral is
unbounded. The integral
is unbounded
and the second version is where the
function is unbounded.
Okay. Now in the first version
then you take uh you uh looking at a
function
uh f
and this function is uh integral. So f
here is integral
uh from a to b
uh for all
uh so so a here is fixed
but it's integral for all uh b bigger
than a so a is fixed so a here fixed
and it's integral like that Okay. Then
what we want to what we are interested
in
so again if you're thinking about the
integral as a kind of think about the
integral as the weighted area.
So and weight just means that if the
function is negative in a stretch then
the area there will count with a minus
sign. Right? So uh this here is so what
we're interested in is we're interested
in
making sense of the area the weighted
area below the graph where we go all the
way out to infinity. Okay. And so this
is you know does this make sense?
So this is this is in this case the
improper integral. It's improper because
it's not a bounded integral. Right? And
so yes, if yes if uh this limit here
of um a to b if this limit here of f of
x dx if this limit here is b goes to
infinity exist
then we say
we say
that the improper integral here from a
to infinity of f ofx.
We say that this here exists and is
equal to this limit.
Okay.
So this is one version of the improper
integrals and the other version is uh
the other version of the improper
integral is the following
um
um so the second version.
So this is where f here is unbounded.
In a minute I'll look at examples of
both things. So the function is
unbounded. So it's defined on but f here
is supposed to be integral on say a to b
right sorry a uh supposed to be integral
from
um it's supposed to be integral from c
to b
uh for all
c
bigger than so see See here C is bigger
than some A and less than B. So think
here about
here you have A
here you have B. So A and B in this case
are fixed
but the function is not bounded. It's
not maybe even defined at A. Right? It's
not really defined at a but it is but if
you but it is integral on if you go
anywhere strictly to the right of a then
it is integral on this interval here.
And so if if this limit so if
this limit here as c goes to a the
integral from c to b of fx
dx if this limit here exists
then we say that this improper integral
from c to b sorry a to b of f ofx dx
this is a improper integral because the
function is not bounded on this whole
interval. It's not even defined at at at
a. If this here we say that this thing
here is equal to this limit as c = to a
of c b f ofx
dx. Okay.
And so you know you the improper
integral actually often appear in
things.
Okay. So let me look at examples of
this.
So I will look at example of this and I
will look so again there's these two
versions where the integer is unbounded
or the function is unbounded. Right? Of
course there's all kind of variation of
this. Right here I looked at where the
function was unbounded to the left or
you could do the same to the right. It
could be this interval here. this
interval
in the in the uh the where the interval
was unbounded you I'm talking I was the
ex when I I explained what it means I
did it as if the interval was unbounded
to the right but of course you can also
look at unbounded to the left or you
could even look at where it was
unbounded both to the right and to the
left Okay,
but let me look at some examples.
Um
and so the first example
again the first two examples would be
where the interval is
uh unbounded.
So the first example here
is uh where the interval is unbounded
and we're looking at uh the interval is
1 to infinity and we're looking at the
function uh f ofx
= 1 /x
right
and I'm interested in.
And the question is, does
the improper integral
this here of 1 /x^2 dx does this exist?
That's a question, right?
And so you we use the fundamental
theorem of calculus to determine that.
We observe that if you're looking at f
ofx
which is 1 /x
then the derivative here
is uh of this function here this is 1
/x
okay
so this is what we observe so therefore
it means that if you integrating from 1
to b of 1 /x^2 dx
this thing here is the same as f of b
minus f of one.
Right?
And so using this and we know what f is
you have that this is minus
uh minus sorry 1 over b and uh no sorry
yeah it's minus one over b. This is what
you get from this. And here you're
getting one plus one like this, right?
And so you see that this thing here as B
goes to infinity this here converts to
zero. So this converts to one. So indeed
this improper yes
is our answer and and what it is equal
to.
Why? because it converts to one,
it's equal to one.
Okay, so again, if you're thinking about
it, it's sort of a little bit like what
we did for series that you're summing
infinitely many numbers. So here you're
looking at something and you're looking
at the area, but the area actually is
finite even though it continue on
forever.
Um
h so that's one version of it. Suppose
that instead of 1 / x^2. So one over the
property that the function 1 /x^2 has is
that it go really quite fast to zero. As
x go to infinity 1 /x^2 goes really
pretty fast to zero. Suppose I look at a
function that does go to zero. But if it
doesn't go to zero, right? If the
function doesn't go to zero, right? And
if we were kind of let's say that it's
was staying above a certain line well
then the area below the graph would of
course be larger than this thing and
that would be infinite. So it's not
going to converge right? So so it will
have to kind of go to zero in some way.
Um so example two I'm looking at another
function still goes to zero again the
interval is the same from one to
infinity and the function is now this
time it's one of x
still goes to zero so maybe it has a
chance let's let's see
if you now take the integral from one to
x of uh 1 to b sorry of uh of 1 /x dx x.
Well, again, you use the fundamental
therm of calculus. If you're looking at
the function f of x = to log of x, the
derivative of log
is 1 /x.
Right? So, this thing here by the
fundamental theorem of calculus, this
second version of fundamental the
calculus is f of b minus f of one.
And that is log of B minus log of 1. Log
of 1 is zero. So this is just log of B.
But as B goes to infinity, this here
actually goes, it's not bounded. It tend
to wander off to infinity. Right? So
this improper integral here, this one
here
does not exist.
Right?
It actually it's like the area below
this function here would actually be
like infinite. Right?
It does not go to zero fast enough.
Okay?
So that's examples of the where the
interval is unbounded. Suppose that we
look at examples where the instead of
the interval is being unbounded the
function is unbounded.
So let's look at some example of that
suppose you take so now
suppose you take the interval from so
the interval is bounded but the function
is not bounded
is sorry the function the interval is
bounded but the function is unbounded so
I'm looking at first f ofx X = 1 /
of X as X go to zero
square root of 0 X goes to to zero so
this means that one over it goes to
infinity so this function is not bounded
but if I'm now looking at so I want to
look at the improper integral where I'm
taking this function the function is
blowing up as I'm going close to zero
right blowing up like that and I want to
I want to see does this here does uh
this improper integral here
does this exist
right that's a question
uh and so in order to figure that out I
use the fundamental theorem of calculus
again so if I take the function
if I take the function function uh f(x)
= 2 * x
and I now take the derivative of this
then I get 1 / of x
and so this means that um so this means
that if you now look at Um
so this means that if you're now looking
at the integral here
uh of um
uh right this integral from a say to one
of 1 / x a strictly positive dx X.
This thing here is capital F of 1 minus
capital F of A. And so capital F was was
this function here. So this is two I
two
one that's one. So it's two minus
uh 2 square of a. But now as a goes
to zero this here converts to two.
Right? So this improper integral exists.
So yes,
this one here exist
and is equal to two.
Okay,
let's look at one uh one last example
uh of this
um
And so this is another example where the
function is so again you know uh in in
in this sort of example the function was
unbounded. It's blowing up.
It's going to infinity but the area
below the graph that's what we
calculated is still actually finite.
Right? But what if the function is
blowing up faster than this? Right? So
this is an example like this. that if
you take uh this it's again the interval
from 0 to one and the function is now
now it's going to infinite faster as x
goes to zero. So this is the function
and so now we want to we again asking is
does this does the improper integral so
does this improper integral here
exist
and uh let's see if it exist or not. So
we use the fundamental theorem of
calculus again we observe that the
function f ofx equal to log of x that
the derivative of this function is just
1 /x. So this means that if we integrate
from a a is now again strictly positive
strictly positive.
So if you're looking at this integral
here,
this here is because of the second
version of fundamental theore calculus.
We have that this here is f in one minus
uh f and a.
And this thing is now log of one that's
zero
minus log of a. Uh log of a is uh right.
So log of a so it's like that.
And now remember that log the log
function here the log function looks
like this
right this is the log function.
So you see that as as you go towards
zero here this number here goes to minus
infinity so this here goes to infinity
right so it doesn't converge right so uh
so the answer is no
okay
and so the very last thing uh I want to
talk about is just I'll just give you a
definition. So this is arc length.
So uh suppose you take a curve
in the plane.
So suppose that I have a curve in the
plane.
So gamma of t
this is a curve so it has in the plane
so it means that it has two coordinates
is called gamma of s I think that's what
I did in the notes
uh
so this here is the curve
and uh and I'm assuming that f and g are
differentiable
and the derivative here
are continuous.
So suppose I have such a curve and s
here is running in an interval from a to
b.
Then the length of the curve is by
definition the integral from a to b of
square root of uh f prime
of s squared plus g prime of s squar
d s. So this is this is the length of
the curve. Maybe I'll talk a little bit
more about that next time.
Okay. So, I'll stop here. So, and I'll
post the the notes. Uh,
any questions?
Okay.