Hello everyone. Uh my name is Dina
Kitabi. I'm professor at MIT. Um I'm
very happy to welcome you here at this
conference. I just before getting into
the technical material I uh I just
walked from the main campus uh here and
of course I noticed the protesters
outside
and I don't know which companies are
involved in this conference but I want
to emphasize one very important thing to
me and all the researchers who worked on
this project is that we insist that
everything that we do is for helping
people particularly in healthcare act
and these invisible technology are not
used to harm people in any way.
Thank you very much. So now let's let's
get to the technical material.
So as you can see from the title of my
talk, beyond wearables, the rise of
invisible health tech. Now I want to ask
you by show of hand, who is wearing
wearable in this audience?
Okay, like significant subset. Now I
want you to look at each other. Look at
my audience here and what do you see? I
can tell you what I see. Healthy people
mainly like everything here looks great.
You guys are not the problem of our
health care system or health care like
in any modern society. You are taking
care of yourself. you are like trying
your best to like follow your health
through wearables and variety of things.
He is the reason why our health care
systems have to pay about $5 trillion on
healthcare. This is my grandfather.
He's old and sick. He passed away now.
But it is people like him who are like
that we need to take care of. And people
like him don't wear wearables.
In fact, there are many studies that
show even people like us, even you guys
who are wearing the wearables, like when
people are feeling sick and like really
unhealthy, they stop wearing the
wearables. The last thing on one's mind
is that I'm really sick today. I have to
wear my Apple Watch and by the way, I
have also two charges to make sure that
the data is there. So how can we monitor
the health of the old and the sick the
people who really need health
monitoring? That's is the question that
we ask. Now imagine with me if there is
something a device that looks very much
like your Wi-Fi box that sits in the
background of the home and analyzes the
wireless signal that bounce off people
bodies and be able from that to get your
breathing, your heartbeat. When you
sleep, it knows that you are sleeping
and it knows like the difference between
REM when you dream versus like sleep
versus deep sleep. It can monitor motion
and even EEG even the brain waves that
uh follow the the the evolution of the
uh of the u nervous system. It can do
that and from that it can get biomarkers
of diseases and drugs.
That might sound science fiction, but
this is exactly what we do. We have a
device that we call the Emerald device,
and it can do all of that stuff because
you guys, as you are sitting here, you
are swimming in a sea of wireless
signal. All of those electromagnetic
waves as they bounce of your bodies,
they carry information about the pulsing
of your blood, your respiration, your
movements, and even indirectly about
what's happening inside your brain. And
AI can extract with the proper custom
neural network can extract many of these
pieces of information. So I'm going to
show you a few demos and I'm going to
start from one of the earliest result
that we have here. So this is one of our
offices. You see one of my students
standing here. Now the device is not
even in the same office. It's going to
monitor him from behind the wall. You
see a red dot on the side. Now I play
this for you and you can see as he walks
the red dot is tracking his movements.
He doesn't have wearables on his body.
It's purely because we analyze the
wireless signal as it bounce on his body
as he moves without any wearables, no
cell phone, nothing.
Okay? And everything that I show you
today is quite accurate. It's compared
to the gold standard for measuring that
physiological signal and we have
multiple publication that I encourage
you to look at. So I told you that this
is one of our earlier results. Let me
show you what we can get today. So you
can see these like skeletal figures. So
we can get this is what the wireless
device get the full stick figure of how
the person is moving and what you see on
the side are the people inside the room
just for you so that you can see what is
happening. So when I play this he's no
longer a dot on the floor map. You can
see that he's sitting. When he stand up
you can see that he's standing up. when
he moves with the right foot, you see
the right foot, it's the left foot. So,
we can monitor these stick figures in
the home. If somebody who has like motor
symptoms like in Parkinson's, inexia,
an Alzheimer patient who forgot what he
did today. So, we can have continuous
monitoring of what people have as stick
figures without looking at details of
what they are, how they are dressed and
all of that stuff. And again, everything
that I'm showing you here is compared to
the gold standard showing that it is
highly accurate. Motion is not the only
thing that we can get. When you go to
sleep, your brain waves change and you
enter different stages. Awake, light
sleep, deep sleep, and REM, rapid eye
movements, which is the stage in which
you dream.
These sleep stages are important for any
like person who has sleep disorder. But
actually sleep is a platform for almost
all diseases. You name it from Alzheimer
to depression to everything. So if you
want to understand diseases, we need to
understand sleep at a deep level. Today
if you want accurate sleep staging, you
send someone to a sleep lab. This is the
MGH sleep lab. And you can see what
happens to those people.
You can see he's not happy.
So they ask you to sleep like this. Let
me show you what we do.
So this is our device transmit very low
power wireless signal analyzes the
reflection using AI
and spits out sleep staging. This is
something called the hypnogoggram. It
tells you how the brain is moving
between different sleep stages from
awake to light sleep to deep sleep to
REM and again and with sleep cycles. As
you can see this is what you get when
you send someone to the sleep lab at
MGH. And we can get it as you can see as
a person sleeping in their home without
anything on their body. And sorry let me
just go back and we have many
publication that compare it to the gold
standard. Now I know many of you for
example may not be getting like sleep
like from URA or from uh the Apple
Watch. In fact our results show that
this is more accurate and achieve higher
accuracy than the wearables
at least for the one that publish
results on on their performance. Of
course, there are many that we don't
even know what's the the accuracy.
Okay. So, this person is sitting like
you. What you see on the screen is his
inhales, exhales,
and uh we told him to hold his breath.
So, stop breathing. And you can see the
signal stays at a steady level because
he exhaled and he did not inhale.
Again, everything is compared to the
gold standard FDA approved devices. I
want to show you the most recent uh
result that I'm very very excited about
which is EEG the brain waves and here
I'm showing you an example. So this is
the EEG but during sleep. This is not
the EEG when you are thinking about a
particular problem but this is the EEG
during sleep. It is uh you can see the
ground truth EEG of the person. The
first row this is an Alzheimer patient.
He's a male 83 years old and you can see
the AI generated EEG for him with our
neural networks.
Quite accurate isn't it? But I mean this
is one person. We have repeated these
results for 20 20,000 different
individuals and with mean error that is
less than 7%.
Now once you have data about like
physiological signals you can start
asking questions about diseases and
drugs. So for example, what you see here
is uh the first result is can we detect
Parkinson from just like the the the
wireless signal and the breathing of
someone during their sleep and you can
see like very high accuracy. This is
published in nature medicine and today
we are working on other diseases like
Alzheimer and you can see our results
already from one night of sleep that
could be obtained purely from the
wireless signal we get like about 80%
accuracy on detecting whether someone
has Alzheimer or not and what's very
interesting to me also because we are
facing a pandemic of mental health we
can actually detect anti-depressant
effect on people so today mental health
is something that we don't have very
concrete and objective measure. We ask
people how do you feel? Now we give them
a drug. How do you feel? But imagine if
we can actually measure the change that
anti-depressant have and from that
detect whether somebody is taking
anti-depressent or not and that's the
last A-axis you can interpret it as
accuracy. A is interpretable as
accuracy.
I want to say a few words about how it
works and I'm going to use EEG as an
example and this is very very high
level. Okay, I want to remind you of
something that you all know like uh gen
AI for text and images. So you know
today that you can give a generative
model uh a a text prompt and it can
generate an image for you. Daddy for
example would do this. So you can say oh
generate for me the an image of a corgi
playing a trumpet and I will generate
that for you. Now the thing that you
have to notice in these gen AIs is that
there is consistency between the text
and the image that is generated. How can
we use that to generate physiological
signals? So here's what we do again at a
high level. So we say instead of prompt
that come from text now we can take the
prompt from the wireless signal that
bounce off someone and say look I want
you to generate the EEG for this person
given that this is a wireless signal
that bounce of their body and it can
generate the EEG for them.
So as we are speaking here these emerald
devices are used with real patients in
real clinical trials. We are deployed
with patients who have Parkinson disease
Alzheimer ALS Crohn's lupus FSHD
syndrome etc and also depression or
mental uh issues.
So I want to show you quickly two
results that are more related to
diseases and drugs like what we call
biomarkers for diseases biomarkers for
drugs. So I'm sure all of you guys have
heard of the disease Parkinson's correct
I mean Parkinson is a neurogenerative
disease. It is the fastest growing
neurodeenerative disease in the world.
It is the second most common
neurodeenerative disease after Alzheimer
and what happens uh is uh basically we
notice Parkinson typically today due to
the tremor and the stiffness of motion
and but the problem is that by the time
someone get tremor and stiffness the
disease has started already 10 years ago
in their brain and the neurons the
dopamineergic neurons are responsible
for parking Parkinson disease already 50
to 80% damaged. So by the time these
motor symptoms appear the the neurons
are 80% damaged. So what can we do? How
can we like this is very late to detect
a disease. So what we wanted to do is to
detect the disease without any motor
symptoms without any tremor without any
stiffness. When people sleep all of that
stuff disappears.
So can we detect Parkinson just from the
breathing of someone?
And what we did is we took the
respiratory signal. We know that we can
get this very easily from wireless
signal in in the in just like a device
that looks like Wi-Fi box in the home of
the person. We uh designed a neural
network that answer two question. Does
this person have Parkinson disease? And
if they do, what is the severity of
their disease according to the gold
standard? Let me show you the results.
So this is something called the rock
curve. If you haven't seen this style of
curves before, not important. The
important number is that AU there. So
this curve has specificity on one axis,
sensitivity on the other axis, but the
AU you can interpret it as accuracy. So
this shows you that from one night a
forless signal with an accuracy that is
about 90% I can tell whether this person
has Parkinson's or not. No questions
asked, no movements, nothing. And it's
not just about the wireless signal, but
what's good about the wireless signal is
that it gives me respiratory signal very
accurately. But I can also like if I put
a breathing belt on them, I can do the
same thing and detect from that whether
they have Parkinson's or not. Now this
is very important because no like med
medical expert today can look at
someone's breathing and say oh they have
Parkinson's no they don't have
Parkinson's we don't have that ability
so we can push medicine to a new level
and now the natural question to ask okay
can I actually detect Parkinson before
it is diagnosed by a doctor now of
course for this uh study like the other
study here we had uh you see we had
about 7,000 individuals. This is a very
large study that we show that it's we
are very accurate. But of course, like
studying whether somebody is going to
develop Parkinson later, that's much
harder. How are you going to find people
who eventually developed Parkinson's? So
we we found a data set that has
respiratory signal on two visits and uh
in the first visit people came they we
they recorded their respiratory signal
and their sleep. on the second visit
that happened six years later they came
again and a small subset of those people
when they came again they said now I was
diagnosed by Parkinson so they were not
diagnosed by park with Parkinson uh in
in the early visit but six years later
they came and they had a diagnosis of
Parkinson so we don't know exactly when
they got diagnosed but in like later
than this first uh visit so we looked at
the first visit when they did not have
Parkinson or at least they were not
diagnosed. And these are the blue guys.
So you see the orange line like the the
machine learning already is saying look
this these blue guys are very different
from the red guys who never developed
Parkinson's. I think actually they
already have Parkinson's.
So of course this is an initial results
we need to get like in medicine you
really want to have a large data set and
repeat these results to be sure like
about the specificity and the
sensitivity. But this is very promising.
It's telling us that we can screen very
easily from thin air for who is going to
have tendency toward developing
Parkinson's.
Mental health is very important and one
of the issues with uh mental health is
like for example in depression of course
anti-depressant are prescribed but many
people are non-adherent with their
anti-depressant or after some time like
they take the anti-depressant and they
think that they are fine so they stop
taking it and that causes relapses and
in some cases actually suicide.
So it's very important to make sure that
people are adherent with their
anti-depressant. Now if you are going to
to ask someone who just like decided not
to take their anti-depressant are you
taking it mean they might say yes I mean
just I mean basically non-adherent
people and they decided not to be
adherent or they are not adherent for
some reason. So ideally you want to have
a test that is very easy that can tell
the doctor okay pay attention to this
patient remind them check on them
because that is dangerous if somebody
particularly severe cases who are
suicidal
so how can we check so I want to remind
you of that hypnogog the sleep so this
is the sleep in a normal person and I'm
going to use this to explain to you like
how sleep is changes when somebody takes
anti-depressant so this person is not
taking anti-depressant and you see on
the x-axis is time on the y-axis is the
sleep stage. Uh this person went to
sleep slightly before midnight. This is
sleep onset. He moved to light sleep and
then he moved to deep sleep and then REM
which is the stage in which we dream.
Now I'm sure you heard that sleeps
happens in cycles. So every cycle either
end with REM or with the person being
awake. So here you see four cycles. The
first three ended with RAM. The last one
ended with a person waking up.
So let me show you how sleep looks in a
person particularly how RAM like for
example here if we just look at the RAM
and we set everything else to zero just
look at the RAM architecture and I stack
many nice one after other one after
other and let me show you what happens.
So here is how this this is in a person
who is not taking anti-depressant. So on
the x- axis zero means sleep onset and
the x-axis is time since sleep onset
since they went to sleep and on the y
ais is many days and nights st st st st
st st st st st st st st st st st st st
st st st st st st st st st st stacked on
top of each other zero means no RAM any
color that you see means RAM okay so
what do you see you see something very
much like the sleep architecture like
there are cycles and the cycles are
ending with RAM but the last cycle the
person can wake up so not nec
necessarily that it ends with RAM.
So this is what we know about people who
don't take anti-depressant. Now let me
show you an example of a person who
takes anti-depressant.
So without even me telling you what's
going on, I mean immediately it's very
obvious that the first REM cycle got
knocked off.
But this is requires us to put so many
nights and stack them on top of each
other. So now we can go and say okay AI
can you help us can you actually from
one night tell me whether the person is
taking on their anti-depressant or not
so that I as a physician I can react
quickly I don't waste six months to
figure out that they are not taking
their anti-depressant
and so what we did we took respiratory
signal again and that could come from
the wagless signal from thin air in the
person's home but also could come from
breathing belt I mean that's The point
is to be able to get correct respiration
and then we transform this like we have
LLM inspired model that give us an EEG
representation and from that we can ask
is this person taking anti-depressant or
not
and here is the result. So this is again
similar to the curve that I showed you
before on the x-axis specificity
sensitivity again the number that you
have to worry about is the AU from a
single night of data I can tell from
thin air from the wireless whether this
person is taking their anti-depressant
or not
with an accuracy that is 84%.
Now let me show you two example. One
person who was not taking
anti-depressant and started
anti-depressant in the middle of the
first figure and another person who was
on anti-depressant but the doctor
started tapering their anti-depressant
so taking them off the anti-depressant
and you can very clearly see that the
the on the yaxis is the the score from
our AI model and you can tell that the
model is able to detect when a person
started taking the anti-depressant and
when the other person was tapering in
the anti-depressant
and that is allow us as I said earlier
50% of patients have adherence problems
and in the worst case it can end up in
suicide but also even when it hopefully
doesn't end up that way but it has a
risk of relapsing to depression and
hospitalization
and this can help doctor monitor that
I want to end with our vision basically
today we all use and are very familiar
and but foundational model of text and
images. So I'm sure all of you use like
chat GPT the GPT model is foundational
model of text and you use probably Deli
and Sora and many of these models that
try to incorporate also images and
different modalities. So what we want in
my group in my lab what we design now
foundational model for human physiology
imagine if we have models that can
actually understand EEG understand
respiratory signal understand uh like uh
pulsing understand all of that stuff on
their own it's not about like just
looking at what the medical literature
tell them because the medical literature
tells us only about what doctors already
know. But I just showed you things that
doctors don't know. Doctors don't know
how to extract from breathing whether
somebody has uh Parkinson's or not. They
don't know whether like someone from
their respiratory signal also whether
they are like taking anti-depressant or
not. So this new foundation model will
push the limit the envelope of our
understanding of medicine and cannot be
taught just from textbook on medical
stuff. It has be it has to be taught
directly from our physiological signals
and a foundation model that for human
physiology means a model that can
understand our physiological signals so
that with a small tuning its
representation can be used for many
tasks. the same way as you use like chat
GPT not just for generating poetry but
for legal stuff and you can use it for
uh like uh mass you can use it for code
so it applies to so many different
domains so can we have a physiological
foundation model that looks at a human
physiology and can be used for many
downstream tasks like for Parkinson for
Alzheimer for ALS for CHF for uh
anti-depressant for anticolinergic and
we are working on this model. We have
very promising initial results that show
us that we can actually apply this model
and achieve high accuracy on so many
tasks that span neurological,
respiratory, cardiovascular and
metabolic.
And with that I want to leave you with
this vision of the future. Imagine if we
can have like the same way as we have
today like a smoke detector in every
home. It should be that every home that
has a chronic disease patient. In fact,
every home that has somebody like we
should like take care of the health of
the resident. So imagine a future where
every home at least every home which has
a patient has a an an emerald device
that continuously monitoring the health
of that individual. applying these
foundational model and extracting
information about diseases and therapies
and be able to inform to talk to the
person because now we can easily have AI
that can talk to people, talk to the
doctor and inform them about how this
person is health is changing and help
personalize health care and improve
outcomes.
I think this is a vision our vision of
the future. We hope that you uh help us
and work to with us towards improving
the outcomes, personalizing healthcare
and moving from a like a system that is
reactive. It waits until we have a big
problem, we end up in a hospital to try
to help us to a system that is
proactive. It is looking forward and
being able to predict that we are going
toward an exacerbation and help us
before we get to the hospital to avoid
that. Thank you very much.
>> Do we have time for questions?
>> Okay.
Any questions?
Oh, how does a device separate data when
there are multiple people in the room
when it's tracking motion sleep? So, I
mean similarly to how like in driver
glass car like you you have this like
rotating laser and it can separate
individual in space. Similarly, wireless
signals has the ability to separate
individual in the space. And then we
have a machine learning model that
focuses on on the patient and ignore
signals from like other people or like
also dogs and cats. Many of the homes
have pets including mine.
Uh so how much data is required to
develop such a functional uh
foundational model? Should all HC
companies develop their own? How much
data? I mean basically this this is very
early question to ask. I mean at this
stage the more the merrier. I mean
similarly like we basically we are able
to to be to get with uh hundreds of
millions of tokens some initial results
but of course as that get bigger and
bigger we hope that the performance also
will get better similarly to how we see
that in text and images. what is
negative impact of living amongst this
high RF and any if any uh so basically
we all are comfortable having Wi-Fi at
home and I think Wi-Fi if you compare it
to any clinical trial I mean they the
Wi-Fi and having Wi-Fi is probably the
largest clinical trial on earth and
there are no uh basically proven reason
that wifi has any bad effect and if you
are comfortable with Wi-Fi let Let me
tell you that this device is 1,000 times
lower power than Wi-Fi. So, it is at
least as safe as your Wi-Fi at home.
Does the wireless signal uh being used
comply with each country radio wave
related laws and regulations? For
example, is there is there no radio wave
interference? Yeah. So, yes, it does.
This is the the type of technology that
we are using here is called ultra
wideband technology. This is a standard
technology. It is under uh like the FCC
has standardized it also the European
countries and everywhere. Basically
these are standardized technologies. Uh
and they are basically designed ultra
wideband is designed to not interfere
with other technology like Wi-Fi and
cellular and also to be resilient to
interference from other technologies.
to what extent is this kind of health
tech likely to drive pricing models for
health insurance and healthcare. So
that's very interesting question. I mean
my my problem with the health care
system is that it is all the incentives
are in the wrong place. In fact, and you
there is kind of like the the the cost
is spent in most of the time on like
bureaucracy and documentation that
basically the health insurance want to
like push the cost on the providers and
by adding documentation then the
provider increase the prices because now
they have to like pay put so much time
on like their staff doing the the
documentation. So I think the the main
as a researcher my interest is how we
can have health care that is minimize
the the the cost to the individual make
it as widely available and better than
existing healthcare and how we can
design the technology. But at the end of
the day there are policies around that
and that also we have to take care of
that so that we ensure that our health
care system does not put policies that
increase the cost on everyone.
Can this device be used to predict the
onset of cardiac events such as
eskeemia? uh so we haven't trained this
device on this kind of situation because
basically
in in the current state I'm more
interested in chronic diseases on one
hand because chronic diseases are the
bigger problem and also it's much more
natural to monitor them over time and be
able to avoid problem if we can detect
things earlier. So basically before
something happened like I I'm I'm less
like looking at can we detect someone
who is like when a heart attack occurs
and I'm I'm more interested and can we
detected like when when they are moving
toward like they have a chronic
condition and the chronic disease uh
condition is exacerbating also we we
kind of focus so far on more of like uh
neurological diseases, respiratory
diseases and autoimmune diseases because
with uh Fitbit and Apple Watch there is
a lot of work on cardiac things. So I
think there is a gap much bigger on the
neurological and immune uh related
diseases.
I see that I run out of time. Thank you
very much. Very nice talking to you.