often times in applying the
probabilistic method we'll need to
understand whether a certain random
structure typically have a property that
we're looking for in this video we'll
look at one such property and understand
how to analyze whether a certain random
graph have the property of containing a
triangle with high
probability the object we're going to be
looking at today is the a r random
graph commonly referred to as
GNP and this is the graph consists of
placing n
vertices and for each pair of vertices
we put down an edge between them with
probability P independently for all
pairs of vertices
in other words we flip a biased coin
that comes up heads with probability P
independently for each possible Edge and
put down the edge randomly as such this
is a random graph it's a random
structure it's a random object and we
would like to understand various
properties of this random graph and the
property that we're going to look at in
this video is the following does this
random graph typically contain a
triangle
in the rest of this video we'll be
looking at p as a function of n so p is
allowed to change depending on
N we denote this dependence by a
subscript but out of convenience will
drop the subscript for the rest of the
video okay so GMP does a typically
contain a triangle well by typically I
mean the following mathematically
precise meaning
typically means with probability that
approaches one as n goes to
Infinity so the statements we're going
to be looking at are ASM totic as n
becomes
large the main theorem that will prove
in this video is the following well
there are two
statements I've conveniently labeled
them Z zero and theem
one theorem zero sometimes referred to
as the zero statement is the statement
about not having any triangles having
zero
triangles and it says that if n * P
remember p is a function of n p is
allowed to depend on N if n * P
approaches zero as n goes to Infinity
then this random graph GMP is triangle
free with probability approaching one as
n goes to
Infinity in other words with high
probability this random graph does not
have any
triangles this makes sense in that this
graph is pretty sparse when p is small
right so this statement basically says
that P is much less than 1 / n in terms
of the growth rate so when p is very
small you expect not so many edges and
it turns out that there's not going to
be a triangle typically in this random
graph the second part is z and one the
one statement and it's says that when NP
approaches
Infinity again p is a function of n then
this random graph GMP typically contains
a triangle I.E it contains a triangle
with probability that approaches one as
n goes to
Infinity so if you have a high Edge
probability then typically you expect to
see triangle in a random instantiation
of this random graph
GNP one way to summarize both statements
is the following one/ N is a threshold
for the property of containing a
triangle to interpret the sentence
imagine if p is much larger than 1 / n
then we're in the theorem one setting
then the random graph typically contains
a triangle whereas if p is much smaller
than 1 / n in the sense of being in the
Zer zum zero setting then typically the
random graph does not contain any
triangles so 1/ N is a threshold
depending on whether the edge
probability p is much larger or much
smaller than 1 / n we expect very
different behaviors from the perspective
of whether the graph contains a
triangle this type of statements
are widely studied in combinatorics in
probability and understanding how to
establish and prove these type of
statements are some of the bread and
butter of probabilistic
combinatorics so in this video let us
prove the statement in this
box let's start with the easier
Direction which in this case is the
first statement uh theorem zero so let's
prove theorem zero
we're looking at triangles so let's
define a random variable X to be the
number of
triangles
in the random graph
G&P we can compute the expectation of X
with not much difficulty because by
linearity of expectations there are n
choose three triples of vertices and
each triple forms a triangle with
probability P
cubed we see that this quantity here is
on the
order of n cubed P
cubed we get to drop constant factors in
this ASM totic estimate now when NP goes
to zero as n goes to Infinity n Cub P
cubed also go goes to zero so this
quantity is little o of one it's a
quantity that goes to zero as n goes to
Infinity let us now apply maros
inequality
we explained and proved markov's
inequality in a different video by
markov's
inequality we find that the probability
that X is at least one
is at most the expectation of
x divid
one and from earlier this quantity is L
to O of one all right so the number of
triangles is typically small in
expectation so it's small in expectation
and therefore the probability that
there's at least one triangle goes to
zero as n goes to
Infinity right thus
the previous statement is
equivalent to the statement
that the probability that there are zero
triangles approaches one as n goes to
Infinity
okay but this finishes the first part of
the
theorem in the first part The Edge
probability is very small and so the
expected number of triangles
is goes to zero as n goes to infinity
and by Mark of inequality we see that
typically there should not be any
triangles in this random
graph let us now move on to the second
part in the second
part namely theorem
one if
we use the setup that we had earlier we
see that the number of triangles in
expectation goes to Infinity as n goes
to
Infinity however this does not
immediately imply that X is typically
positive because it could be the case
that X is still typically zero but is
very very large a
diminishing fraction of the time
and in that case we will still be able
to have the statement that the
expectation of X goes to Infinity well
it would not be true that X is typically
positive so we'll need additional ideas
to establish that X is typically
positive and what we will do is to use
the second moment
bound to show that X is
typically close to its
mean so the x is very concentrated
around its
expectation and in that case having
expectation that goes to Infinity we
then imply that X is typically positive
so let's carry out this
idea let's consider the
following
probability we see
that
the probability that
X is equal to zero okay well if x is
equal to zero and here x is some non-
negative quantity
then this statement is equivalent to the
statement
that
X deviates
from its mean in the downward Direction
by minus the expectation of X okay so
this is the same as X less than equal to
zero but X is always non- negative so
these two probabilities are equal to
each other
we can
then relax the event
inside as
such again noting that the expectation
of X is always non-
negative okay now we apply chapy shifts
inequality
okay so in this step we can apply chabby
shfs inequality and you'll find an
explanation and proof of chabby shfs
inequality in a different
video which allows us to conclude that
this probability is at most the variance
of x divided by the expectation of X
squar all right so what have we learned
from this
calculation let me State a
corollary
if the expectation of
X is much smaller so if the variance of
X is much smaller than the square of
expectation then the right hand side
goes to
zero as then goes to Infinity which then
implies X is
positive with high probability meaning
that this probability that X is positive
goes to one as n goes to
Infinity okay so this is the conclusion
that we will use to establish theorem
one
X still the number of triangles will be
able to write in the following way X is
equal to the sum over all triples of
vertices the following quantity x i j x
i k XJ K where we Define this x sub I as
follows x sub i j is equal to 1 if J is
an
edge and zero if i j is not an
edge the vertices are labeled
by numbers one through
n okay so you see this sum which is
indexed over triples of
vertices each term is one
if these vertices i j and k is a
triangle and is zero otherwise so this
is the number of triangles in the graph
and let me
just because it will make the notation a
little
easier rewrite this quantity as such
here T ranges
over all
triples of vertices so onward the
triples of
vertices and X subt is this term so we
can rewrite this term as just a
single a single variable x sub IG
JK to apply the corollary we will need
to get some estimate on the variance of
X and we'll do so through co-variance so
as a reminder the
co-variance of two random
variables say Y and Z is defined to be
the expectation of y * Z minus the
expectation of
Y times the expectation of
Z in particular if y and z are
independent random variables then their
co-variance
zero and the
variance of a random variable X is equal
to the co-variance of X with
itself okay so let us
compute the variance of x x being the
number of
triangles we can rewrite it as a
covariance of X with
itself here x we can write it as a sum
of various terms indexed by triples of
vertices
okay I'll use T for the first index in
the first sum and T Prime for the
indices in the second
sum the nice thing about covariance is
that it is a bilinear function if you
split Y in this covariance of Y and Z if
you split Y into a linear combination
various sums then you see that the
dependence in this formula is linear on
splitting y so you'll be able to write
the
covariance correspondingly as a
sum so given this covariance of these
two sums we can
distribute this
quantity
and write it as the covariance Over All
pairs of triples T and T
Prime the coari of x sub
T against X subt
Prime
okay now we need to understand this term
the co variance of X subt against the co
variance of X subt Prime to towards this
end let
us think about what happens to this ter
right so let me do a side
calculation from the definition of
covariance we see that this quantity
equals to the expectation of x subt x
subt Prime minus the expectation
of x subt times the expectation of X
subt
Prime okay there are a few cases that we
need to
consider
first x t and t Prime are two triples of
vertices and they could be in various
positions the coresponding full
triangles could be disjointed or they
could overlap and we need to consider
all of those
possibilities now before doing those
cases let's observe that this quantity
here if you have for
example T and T Prime
being in any number of configurations so
these are the vertices of T and this is
the vertices of T Prime for instance
right so they could share some edges or
they may overlapping some
edges but no matter what the
configurations are
the first term always equals to P raised
to the number of edges
contained in the union of T and T
Prime so in in the complete graph right
so what I mean here
is the
following so here's P raised to the
number of yeah so P raised to let me
still write it this way and and then
we'll see some specific
examples and minus P raised to the
number of edges in T and P raised to the
number of edges in t Prime so here uh
the exponents will correspond to the
number of edges in the complete graph
Spann by these vertices T and T Prime so
let's look at a few different
possibilities the first is if
the two triangles T and T Prime do not
intersect in any edges so the number of
vertices they intersect is at most one
so the two scenarios are the one that I
just drew and if these two triangles
are even disjointed in their vertex set
so then there's no Edge
overlap in which case the edges right so
the V random variables that correspond
the edges of these two triangles because
they are independent of each other so
the covariance should be zero and indeed
in the first term here you have P raised
to the^ 6 and then minus P cubed and P
cubed and so in this case this Co
variance is
zero in the second
case when these two triples T and T
Prime overlapping exactly two vertices
well here there
are um the union of these two triangles
so I think I misspoke earlier so by this
notation I really mean viewing t as a
triangle and T Prime as a triangle and
looking at the union of these two
triangles so the union of these two
triangles have five edges so that's the
number
of terms here dismissing repetition in
the first first first term the number of
fact the number of
factors and then
minus the later two terms
are both P cub and P cubed
okay
finally if T and T Prime are identical
then the number of edges in the first
term is 3 minus P cubed P
Cub okay so recall that P is some
quantity that goes to zero as um well it
doesn't have to go to zero but you know
we uh
p is some quantity that um you know for
now you can think of as going to zero so
that the first term is always
dominant even if p is constant up to a
constant Factor still the first term is
is
dominant okay so let us now continue the
earlier convers the earlier computation
and we see that this sum is equal to the
following there are uh we need to think
about
how each of these cases can arise now
the first case contributes zero to the
sum so we don't have to worry about it
the second term the second possibility
contributes the following it
contributes n choose two but we need to
count how many different configurations
can we have like this where you have
these two you know the the red and the
blue triangles overlapping by an edge so
this n choose two for the two
overlapping vertices and n *
nus * N - 2 * N -
3 for the remaining
two
vertices and in this case we have P to 5
minus P to
the
6 okay and then the third
possibility and choose
3 time P cubed minus P to the 6
power
okay this is some expression and we only
need to get some bounds so we can play
around with astics and not think about
constant factors so we'll basically
ignore the constant factors and do an
upper bound so up to a constant Factor
so Big O the first term here involves n
to the 4th
P fifth power okay so we can ignore the
the the negative contributions they they
don't matter for this
calculation and then the second term
here is n
cubed P cubed and most on the order of n
cubed P
cubed
and Okay so under the hypothesis that NP
goes to
Infinity both these terms are little o
of n to the 6 P to the 6 okay so that's
something that one can check from the
from the
hypothesis
thus the variance of X is little o of
the expectation of x^
s and so by the
corollary of CHF
earlier we see
that with probability approaching
One X is positive so that there's
typically this random graph contains a
triangle and that finishes the proof of
the second part this theorem one right
so to recap
we
showed that 1 / N is a threshold for the
property of the random graph GN P to
contain a triangle so that statement has
two parts the first part is that when p
is quite small it's much smaller than 1/
n then typically this random graph does
not contain a triangle and the way we
establish this fact is by showing that
the number of triangles not X the number
of triangles has expected value going to
zero and thus by Markov
inequality this number of triangles is
zero with high
probability the second
part where P now is much larger than 1 /
M here the expected number of triangles
goes to Infinity as n goes to Infinity U
but that alone does not allow us to
conclude that the number of triangles is
positive typically
instead we'll need to apply a second
moment argument to show that the number
of triangles is typically concentrated
around its mean and that was a
calculation that we did this was a
second moment calculation namely
understanding and Computing the variance
of this random variable and showing that
the variance is much smaller than the
square of the
expectation from which then we can use
chabby shf inequality to deduce that the
number of triang go is typically
positive right and combining these two
proofs together we obtain this threshold
statement now what we just showed is a
important but fairly basic application
of using probalistic methods to
understand typicality statements and
these types of uh statements and proof
techniques are quite ubiquitous in
studies involving the probabilistic
method and Beyond and there are much
more difficult results of similar flavor
but they involved much more Advanced
Techniques and what you saw here is
simply a taste of what such a statement
and its technique could look like