I want to distinguish comparative
advantage from just the term advantage
or what we call absolute advantage.
Let's think about LeBron James mowing
his lawn. Let's assert LeBron James is
the best person at both mowing his lawn
and playing basketball. He has an
absolute advantage in both activities,
but he has a comparative advantage in
playing basketball. A billion to one
comparative advantage in playing
basketball. Mowing lawns, he's maybe
five to one. He's certainly better than
me at mowing a lawn, but is he more than
five times? Could he do it five times
faster than me? Probably not. So LeBron
James has an absolute advantage over me
in basketball and lawnmowing, but his
comparative advantage is basketball.
LeBron James should specialize in
basketball. Let me mow the lawn. It's
all about comparative advantage. It's
what are you relatively better at. For
more MIT moments from MIT Open Learning,
like, subscribe, or