Good morning everyone. So hello I'm uh
Ching. I'm a postto ashme center and I
have the honor today to introduce you to
Emma Landberg. Uh Emma welcome. So Emma
has been a professor at KDH Royal
Institute in Sweden and where she
created and served as director of the
cell atlas part uh part of the human
protein atlas and the cell atlas images.
You already see a lot actually yesterday
uh through the talks of uh of the
speakers. Um so Emma moved to Stanford a
few years ago and is now also serving as
associate professor at bioengineering
and pathology department. Uh so where
she is really using deep learning to um
utilize all the data we've generated in
the proteomics and imaging to advance
the modeling and understanding of
spatial temporal organization at
cellular and subcellular level. I
personally had the honor of
collaborating with Emma like a few years
ago. Best experience so far and even the
8 a.m. meetings are so enjoyable I have
to say. Um, and kind of like Emma has
been pioneering on the science side, but
also like the way we actually do
science. I might need to put a spoiler,
but she has hosted two KGO challenges
and also Oh, three, I'm sorry,
correction. Three Kaggle challenges and
also like most amazing like
collaborating with video gaming company
and really allowing every single person
to be able to contribute to science.
Well, I can go on on telling you how
amazing like Emma is. And before I take
like put out more spoiler alert, Emma,
please take away. Thank you. That was a
very sweet introduction. Thank you very
much. She's amazing by the way. I've
enjoyed working with her. So today I'm
going to talk about well what we've
basically we touched it many times
yesterday. So how we can use spatial
predomics to to do cell modeling and
we've been talking about virtual cells
and can we use AI to model cells for
example. And I think this is a very
interesting field and I I do think that
at some point we're going to be able to
do it. Um but and I've had the pleasure
of working with the Chan Zuckerberg
initiative last year and we organized a
series of workshops and really discussed
this topic more deeply which ended up in
a perspective paper where we discussed
if we build virtual cells what what
should they be able to do what's needed
from the community how would you
possibly build these cells and such but
I I just want to point out that a key
challenge will be to connect the scales
as we all know and as we've discussed
already from molecules to cells, from
cells to multisellular system and this
is not trivial and I will focus on how
we can do this at the subcellular level
in my talk today and I would argue that
protein data will be key for AI virtual
cells because proteins are the building
blocks of human biology. They execute
most of the functions that we have in
cells. uh transcripts do not and cells
are 3D systems consisting of nested
functional units and we really want to
understand this structure and we also
know that there's a lot of moonlighting
activity or pleotropic effects that
arises at the proteium level that is
very hard to predict from the sequence
level. I would also argue that images
will be key for AI virtual cells because
they're so rich in information related
to structure and morphology. They c can
capture both spatial and temporal
scales. again trying to to meet that
critical gap of how do we bridge the
scales in virtual cells and I also think
it's very cool to think of microscopes
as opportunities for developing
autonomous instrumentation and very
like it well tight systems for lab in
the loop experiments. So with that
little backdrop I'm going to get to my
my talk for today. So at first I will
talk a bit about the work that we've
done to map where proteins are in our
cells and then I'm going to give you
some different vignettes of how we're
trying to model cells off from this
data. So uh the interest of my lab is
really to measure and model the spatial
temporal subcellular organization of the
human proteome with a goal to understand
how variations in protein distribution
can fine-tune cellular function and also
how misloization can lead to disease.
and we've been doing uh this type of
work for a long time and we're very
proud producers of the human protein
atlas project where I'm a co-director.
So this project is um it's been going on
for 20 years now and it's an open
project and we've generated antibodies
for the majority of all human proteins
that we can deploy in a variety of
assays to map where proteins are
expressed. Uh if you haven't checked it
out, you can find it at
proteinatlas.org. It's fully free, no
registration needed. And it's actually
we're gaining more and more traction. So
the number of users increase every year.
Right now it's about 2 million users uh
per
year. And and I should say we have
nowadays one update every year. So the
next update with new data is coming in
October this year. And the key data in
the protein atlas is images. We have
about 20 million images that either are
very classical like no fancy imaging
right now uh immunisttochemistry to the
left that shows protein expression in
cell types of most tissues of the human
body or confocal microscope images that
shows the subcellular uh expression of
proteins within cultivated cell lines.
And today we do work with both of these
image data sets but today I'm going to
focus on the subcellular aspect of this
image collection. So the images have
been generated over many years very
systematically with some reference
markers. So we have dot nuclear staining
a staining for microtubils a staining
for ER. So this makes it possible for us
to kind
of orient ourselves in the cells and on
top of this we've used our in-house
generated antibodies to localize most
human proteins one by one. So CD44 would
look like this. And let's see if the
pointer works. Yep, we can see that it's
expressed at the cell membrane plasma
membrane of this cell. If we see an
image like this, we'll say that this
protein in green is localized to actin
filaments. Everything has been manually
annotated over the years. This protein,
we see these two dots here. That's the
centrosome and so on. So, we've we've
done this for a long time. When we
published the first paper, the
subcellular map of the human proteome,
we actually provided the first evidence
for localization of that protein for
over half of all the human proteins. So
it's it's very basic information but
still very valuable if you want to
understand protein function and I I'm
not going to talk about that today but I
do want to say that in the last release
we added some new data that we've been
working on for many years where we've
actually localized proteins to the
primary celium which is a very
interesting cellular structure that is
involved in a lot of different diseases
and also been linked to diseases like
obesity and autism but uh that's for a
different talk but happy to chat about
it uh in the break later if someone is
interested.
So some of the key findings
that still fascinates us is that here
here you can see kind of the classical
organels. This is a protein in the gyrad
is in mitochondria and so on. But we
find a lot of proteins that are in
multiple compartments as you can see to
the left here. This protein is on the
cell surface and in the nucleus. And
most proteins execute their function by
interacting with other molecules. And it
is likely to assume that the potential
interactors in the nucleus and the
plasma membrane compartments are
different. So it might be so that this
protein is performing two different
functions in these two different
compartments. The other fascinating
aspect uh is of course when we see
variability single cell variability this
protein is expressed at low level in
this cell at a high level here. It's
actually a cell cycle protein. Uh so
this kind of hint at some kind of
temporal dynamics. So even though the
images are static, we can still assume
that there is sometimes see signs of
temporal dynamics. Most often it doesn't
look this clean. Most often it looks
something like this. So this is actually
a very wellstudied protein. It's enolace
one and we know that it has different
functions in different compartments. So
these are all you know it's a cell line
all genetic kind of even
transcriptionally very similar cells.
But if we look at this protein they're
very different. Enolace one performs its
glycolytic canonical function in the
cytool. It controls gene expression in
the nucleus and on the plasma membrane
that you can see here, it's actually
functioning as a plasmminogen receptor.
So these cells, even though they're
genetically and transcriptionally highly
similar, present very different
functional capacities just by changing
the amount and the location of this one
protein. So we're not interested in
inlay one. We're interested in this at a
systems level. So how common if we look
at the entire proteome, how often do we
see this? So we've been able to show
that close between 50 and 60% of all
human produce proteins localized to
multiple compartments. And I would maybe
I would I dare to say that I do believe
that a lot of these proteins perform
dual functions. And there's a lot of
unknown biology in there. Um and about
20% of all proteins show signs of
temporal dynamics. And I think this
number is still an underestimate. So
probably it'll get higher. So with with
these conclusions, I would want to argue
that I don't think that we can build
good models of cells unless we take this
spatial proteome information into
account because otherwise we're missing
out on so
much biology basically. So how can we do
that?
Um I want to present three different
vignettes and the first one is just can
we can we make use of a very simple
metric which is cell shape to try to
understand all of this because we have a
a great image collection but it's one
protein at a time. There's still no
technology so that we can multiplex
10,000 proteins and visualize that in a
single cell. So can we use different
computational frameworks to try to
aggregate the data basically? So one is
to to try to use shape modes and this
has actually been a very fun
collaboration with Susan Rafalski
sitting there and Matthew Vanna at the
Allen Institute. So we've constructed an
interpretable shape space to study the
human proteome and we've then mapped all
of these proteins that we've measured
onto this shape space and these are some
of the cell lines that we've been
working with. So I just want to show
that they are of course they look very
different. we have more epithelia or
fibroblast like cell lines and there's
also some blood hematopoetic cell lines
and so so we use the same framework that
Susan and her group developed and showed
in her I think she briefly showed that
nature paper uh on her slides. So
basically we start by segmenting the
cell in the nucleus and then we
basically trace the contour here and you
get this wavelike pattern and then we
perform a fourier transform so that we
get these coefficients and then we do uh
dimensionality reduction and then we
reconstruct the cell. So we get the
average cell shape and then we can walk
along do a standard deviation walk along
the PCs to see what the shape mode
variations
are. So if we do this uh in these plots
you can see what how the cell shapes
change in the different this is PC1 PC2
PC3 etc. And these are, of course, they
don't look like the real cells, but it's
basically the this is basically based on
the assumption that cells have very
complex shapes, but maybe they're made
up of a a series of common shape mode
variations that we can combine. So, uh,
for example, here you can see all the
different cell lines that we tested. You
see the average cells look pretty
similar in shape, but different in size,
slightly different. Uh what is very cool
though is that the shape modes are
highly conserved and basically exactly
the same for all of these cell types
even though they're different. So we
have like the size length changing the
size and the polarization changing the
nuclear positioning the width versus
length and kind of center of mass shifts
and things like that. So now when we
have these shape modes can we then map
proteium protein data onto it and does
it make sense? So we've tried doing this
for comparing cell shapes, organal
shapes, pathways, single proteins and I
will take you through some of that. So
first of all when we map the protein
expression we ended up using a
deformation field. So basically we we
deform the real cell staining into this
average cell shape and then we get we
can do that for let's say pick 200
nuclear proteins and we average them all
and then we get this average nucleoplast
staining in a given cell shape. Same
thing for the mitochondria. So it
becomes of course very diffuse because
it's the average. But we still see
different patterns for all the different
organels. So what we can do then with
these different patterns that we is that
we can correlate them and see how do the
different organal organal distributions
correlate in different shape modes. So
thinking of what Jennifer talked about
yesterday. She showed beautifully
beautifully with her cryo data that the
the correlation between organals is
highly conserved and we're actually
seeing the same thing. So this is in one
of the cell lines, the Utoos cells. We
see this is the correlation between all
the different organels. And of course it
makes biological sense like the nucleol
like correlates to the nucleus and so
on. Uh but what is very cool is that
when we compare the extreme and this
correlation looks slightly different for
different cell types. But when we
compare this correlation in the standard
cell shape and the extreme versions, we
compare the the round cell to the
elongated cell for example or the the
yeah we can see that this correlation is
highly conserved across all these shape
modes even though it's slightly
different for the different cell types.
So that's good. That means that we
should be able to like this structure is
preserved and it means that maybe
there's some kind of generalizability
lying in here when we think about
virtual cells too. Uh and then we
thought about what if we try to enrich
for look for variable proteins and see
if we can find certain proteins or
pathway that are enriched in certain
shape modes. So we did this and here you
can see how different proteins are
expressed in the different PCs the
different shape modes and we found over
500 proteins that vary significantly
through shape space. A lot of them are
cell cycle proteins of course but many
and they enriched pathways are
interestingly related to both cell cycle
metabolic and signaling
processes and we can go even further and
start to look into really like fine
grain things. So as an example I'm just
showing we we had a cell cycle marker in
a big image data set. So we said let's
look at cells in in one cell state.
Let's look only at G2 cells and then we
compare round cells versus elongated
cells in G2. Do they show any difference
in protein expression? So when we
aggregate this data of of differentially
expressed proteins here, we see that
they actually we we see different
pathways expressed and it seems like the
round cells are really focused on
oxidative phosphorilation and seem to be
preparing for division whereas the
elongated cells show enrichment for
pathways that relate to lipid metabolism
and migratory uh patterns. So maybe they
are actually preparing to migrate and
not directly divide. And of course we
can go back to the proteins that kind of
contributed to this enrichment and see
that these are the cells that we can
classify as round cells and elongated
cells. And yes we can actually visually
also observe this difference difference
in expression but it is a lot easier to
interpret in this aggregated shape
space. So in total uh in summary uh we
believe that these interpretable shape
space are very it's a very useful
pipeline maybe not the right tool to
build a virtual cell model but I think
it's a very good good pipeline to
understand your image data sets let's
say if you do an optical pool screen and
you want to see how do my population of
cells change for example it's it's a a
great pipeline to just understand the
baseline of cell distributions that you
have and if you have any significant
shifts in this space. I didn't talk
about it here, but we can also do this
at the protein level upon drug
pertubation. And then it turns out that
it's very helpful to stratify the data
into shape modes before you start to
look for significantly uh affected uh
proteins as well. So with that, can we
besides aggregating the data like this
can we think about building spatial cell
models and what could that be? What's
the best spatial model we have right
now? probably gene ontology cell
components still some kind of
hierarchical cell structure. So can we
use our data to build something like
that? And uh we've uh worked recently in
collaboration also with the transber
initiative to build subscell. It's a
suite of self-supervised deep learning
models uh for florescent microscopy. And
what we wanted to do here is to build a
model that can both classify patterns,
embed spatial patterns of proteins, but
also understand morphology of cells and
phenotypes because I think those are the
two main use cases like drug
pertubations, crisper
pertubations and also localization of
proteins. Uh and of course we want to
have a model that can provide us
insights to biology beyond what we can
kind of perceive with our eyes. And the
hypothesis here is that we can while our
data set is not the largest in terms of
number of images like the jump data set
is big there are some massive data sets
out there but it is the most diverse
data set when it comes to patterns
because we don't only have five markers
we have all human proteins. So we
thought that even if this is a smaller
data set, we can still it's still a
pretty big data set but we can build a
broadly useful microscopy vision model
and hopefully this model will have
learned to pay biologically relevant
attention because we've trained it with
images of all intracellular human
proteins or less. So uh this is the
architecture that we ended up with. It's
a bas it's a vision transformer
basically with three different uh losses
and tasks. So it's a reconstruction task
which is great for usually great for
building models to classify morphology.
It's not great. Those models aren't very
performant when it comes to classifying
some cellular patterns though. So that's
why we added also two different um
contrastive functions here. One focused
on on the cells and augmenting it and
one focused on on different proteins and
making assumptions that it's this
protein is more likely to have a similar
pattern in a different cell line than
compared to a completely different
protein for example. So we're making
some assumptions about biology here and
I will show you the results for our top
two best models. So we first of all test
them on two very like the two tasks that
we want to do pattern classification and
then phenotype classification. And here
we just use can we classify different
cell types. A very simple tasks and we
compare it to what we consider to be
state-of-the-art model models the um
dino for cells model and then also what
we call best fitting. So this is the
winning model from one of our previous
Kaggle competition which is a supervised
model and basically our models
outperform the state-of-the-art in both
of these tasks. So that's a very good
starting
point but we also want to go beyond what
the human eye can do. So in order to
test this we try to predict pathways
from these embeddings and also predict
protein protein interactions. And of
course we're perform it's performing
better than the other models but it's
it's very hard to predict pathways only
from microscope images but we can
actually predict start to predict
protein protein interactions pretty well
and also outperforms the other models
here. Uh we then started to analyze the
attention to kind
of go back to our hypothesis was it
useful to train on the protein atlas
data and we were so surprised when we
saw these these uh the patch attention
generated by well in in the transformer.
So these are all the different attention
heads and if you look at these images it
almost looks like imunostating or or
different organels. Attention head four
clearly only pays attention to the
nucleoli. Attention head seven looks at
this region on one side of the nucleus.
Attention head six has kind of more
membranous general all membranes in the
cell type of attention. And let's see
attention at 12 looks at the plasma
membrane. So it's kind of cool that the
model has taught itself to look at
regions in the cell where we know that
proteins are distributed and we believe
that this these are biologically
relevant regions and that's maybe why
the model has good
performance. And if we also look at the
correlation of the attention to the
different tasks that we're trying to do
and these are just a lot of different
cells where we've a lot of every dot
here is a cell and then we just link the
attention to uh the different cell lines
and also the different protein
localization locations. We can see that
these are really encoded orthogonally
here. Right? So the model has learned to
think about both morphology and location
of proteins without confounding them too
much. Which means we were very excited
about this because this means that we
can start to maybe compare protein
distribution patterns in cells that have
very different morphology which has been
very hard to do
before. Uh besides that we wanted to
test this model
on other data sets. No no fine-tuning
here. We just test it exactly as is. So
we tested it to on the open cell data
set which is a data set with just pure
markers two markers and it it
outperformed the model that was
specifically trained on open cell. We
also tested it on a bridge to AI data
set that we've generated but this is a
new cell type that it hasn't seen in
training and it's also drug perturbed
cells. So we were able to show that we
can bring all of these drug perturbed
cells and other cells into a joint
embedding with this model and we can
identify relocizing proteins upon drug
perturbation in this embedding space.
And then what we were most excited about
is that when we even apply it to the
jump data set which is images of quite
different resolution and such we can
actually outperform the existing models
that were trained on jump in tasks like
mechanism of action prediction. So again
we believe that this is because the
model has learned to pay attention to
biologically relevant regions. And of
course we're excited to start to
fine-tune the model for some of these
tasks as well. But with that in mind,
we're pretty confident that this is a a
robust model for embedding cells from
microscope images. So what can we do
with that? Can we embed all the images
from the protein atlas and start to
build some kind of graph that looks a
bit like the geneontology cellular
component? And yes, we can. This is the
graph that we get if we we build it from
all the human protein atlas images.
You'll have a hard time to read the
labels here, but this is the cell. And
then we do just hierarchical clustering.
And you can see that and the the labels
here are from either go cellular
component at the bottom layer is from go
biological process. You see we get the
nucleus the cytoplasm and then that
splits up into like the cytool the
endommembrane system and m and filaments
and and deeper and deeper. So basically
it recap recapitulates what we know
about biology and how the cell is
organized. But then when we start to get
down to this level we're seeing clusters
that we couldn't have annotated by eye.
And this is where it's interesting to
start to inspect them. So for example,
here we see a cluster
of proteins involved in translation
ribosomal proteins. We could not have
annotated that. Uh I also really like
these clusters. So it's it's a subsplit
of a nuclear of proteins localized to
the nuclear membrane. And when we look
at the proteins in these different
classes, one of them is structural
proteins that are involved in
maintaining the structure of the
nucleus. One of them is protein involved
in export from the nucleus. One is
protein involved in import to the
nucleus. Uh so so it's it's very cool
that we're starting to see these
functional differences that we could
never ever have annotated by ice. I do
think that these models capture
information that is relevant to
understand biology and this model uh as
a collaboration with CCI it's available
on their virtual cell modeling web page.
And there's also a demo where we use
this model to understand how SARS KV2
relocizes protein upon infection.
But with that uh even if it's it's nice
that we can have this graph of cells,
how can we go beyond like there's a
limit to the resolution in our images.
It's confocal microscopy. How how can we
try to go beyond that down to kind of
protein protein
interactions and uh how can we improve
the spatial precision of these cell maps
to true complex level and this is uh the
project that we've been working with UA
on. So it's been basically two
publications and we had the most recent
one now in nature two weeks ago. So this
is from the newer newer paper. So the
idea here is that maybe we can build
such an hierarchical map if we integrate
two types of spatial data. The image
data that describes the global
distribution of proteins in a cell and
the protein protein interaction data
that describes the local distribution of
proteins in in the neighborhood of any
given protein. And we can use machine
learning to to integrate those data
types and build a hierarchical model of
the cell. So for this we used the UTOS
cells and all our images we've generated
and then uh Steve Giggy and Ed Hutlin
here at Harvard uh generated protein
protein inter interaction data. We're
still limited for data. So this is not a
protein wide map. This is only 5,000
proteins and we're limited because of
the lack of PPI data. So if anyone is
interested in generating protein protein
interaction data at scale that would be
incredible. Uh so what first thing that
we do is of course that we we embed each
data type alone with our machine
learning models and a node to graph
model and then we bring these embeddings
into a joint embedding space. And then
here's the joint embedding space. We can
of course start to look at it and see
that yes we're keeping all of these kind
of clusters that resemble organels. And
if we go further in we can also again
start to see these clusters that are
more biologically refined probably
driven by by the protein protein
interaction data. So there's definitely
biologically relevant information in the
structure of this embedding. And what we
also do then is that we use this trick
that actually works pretty well that we
calibrate the size of
the of clusters
to basic this is a bit complicated to to
describe. Basically it turns out that
the size of any structure in this
assembly correlates very well to the
number number of known proteins in that
structure. So the size of the gold
chapatus according to literature and
structural studies corresponds to the
number of known proteins in it. We get a
pretty nice linear correlation there. So
we use this linear correlation in order
to be able to estimate the actual size
of systems that we can identify in this
embedding. And in this embedding we can
do hierarchical clustering and build a
similar map to the one that I showed you
before. There are some differences here.
Proteins are allowed to be in
multiple nodes for example if they
perform multiple functions. Uh and as
you can see we have all these major
organels but then we have a lot of the
smaller kind of systems here driven by
the protein protein interaction data. In
total uh we identified this is nearly
300 different cellular systems. All the
yellow ones are known in geneontology
and literature. All the purple ones are
new. We've spent a lot of time
validating that they are indeed real
systems but that was more described in
the first paper. So I'm not going to go
through that now. Instead, I'm going to
focus on how we can use these maps and
to do better functional genomics and
better understand
biology.
So, for
example, here is an interesting system,
the rag regulator complex. It's known,
we have a structure for it, but we found
two additional proteins in this system.
Okay, how can we validate that? So here
we worked with Andre Shali at UCSF to do
structural modeling and he showed that
these two additional proteins bor S6 and
ITPA can actually bind to the known rag
regulator complex in this way. So
basically these systems can be used to
guide alpha fold and kind of structural
modeling principles and it would be kind
of cool to think about folding
everything with everything using these
maps as a kind of scaffold to reduce the
search space.
Uh so that's one way you can use this
map. Another way is that we use this map
to to uh use as assemblies as
convergence points for pediatric cancer
mutations. So here we took very big
pediatric mutational data sets that have
been published and when we map it onto
these assemblies, we identify that
there's there are certain systems that
are consistently disrupted in certain
pediatric cancers that were not
discovered in these initial papers
because the mutations might be hitting
different genes. But for example, these
genes are often involved in collagen
biosynthesis or in this nuclear complex
associated pores. So it's also a way of
using just aggregating data on top of
it. Uh a datadriven cell map. Basically
what we also did uh which I think is
interesting, we were able to propose
function for 46 proteins that have no
known function and we were also able to
suggest additional secondary functions
to 951 proteins using a guilt by
association principle uh by just as
these assemblies. So this map is
currently being uploaded into the EBI
complex portal and we hope that people
will use it. I and I personally think it
would be very nice to see more
datadriven cell maps like this that have
not been biased by our assumption of
biology and how biology should be and I
think it would be very interesting to
have maps for different cell types as
well so we can understand how much
rewiring there is in a cell between
different cell types. So with that end a
very very very short ending. I also
think that this is cool but the image
space is even cooler. I kind of want to
pull it back into the image space again
because again it's interpretable. It's
close to the bench and it's a place
where we can do a lot of validation
experiments and this is where we think
about generative models as kind of
virtual microscope. So at some point we
also want to go towards that lab in the
loop where we well predict what a where
a protein would be or a pathway which
pathway is affected where would this
protein be which experiment can we do to
validate it and then do that experiment
in the microscope and then we want to
generate synthetic images to do so. So
we've trained models that can generate
very realistic images denovo. We've
trained organal specific models that so
inputting these different organels we
can generate images of the other
organels for example and we're also
training a model uh with the aim to
basically build a synthetic image that
multiplexes all human proteins so that
we can bring these maps back into the
image space. But for many many reasons
this is a difficult task and I I don't
think I have time to talk about that
now. And of course in the end ultimately
going from sequence to image would be a
goal but there's a lot of of problems to
solve before we're there and we probably
need a lot of additional data types to
do that well. And with that I'd like to
thank my group and uh thank you and
happy to take any questions.
[Applause]
Hi very nice talk. I was wondering for
the protein interaction prediction um
can you actually predict like real
interactions versus uh collocicalization
into the same compartment? Yeah. So what
we did in that plot is that we of course
what we can predict in the image space
is probably collocicalization but that
has a pretty good correlation to
interaction. So when we compare it with
it we we tried to predict the string
score which is a likelihood of
interactions. So we we can predict the
string score pretty well, but of course
it's not going to be Yeah, we can't do
anything beyond the resolution of the
images.
Oh, just a follow-up question. Have you
tried to look into like co-evolution of
those proteins that you predict to be
interacting together? If they
collocicalize and they interact, you
might see co-evolution signals.
Sorry. Sorry.
um like have you tried to look into
co-evolution signals of um those
proteins that you predict to interact
since they are localized the same place
and interacting and maybe with um yeah
multiple sequence alignment for alpha
you can explore that a bit. Yeah. Yeah.
That's a very good question. So to uh
what we've done we've done a lot of
things there but then we realized that
there's a lot of papers that just
predict locations from sequence
mitochondria. It's described as a solved
problem in literature and it's actually
not solved. I didn't present that here.
So we've spent a lot of time uh making a
better benchmark data set than what the
community has used uh that is highly
validated not only protein plus data but
other like three sources two sources of
experimental validation and when we
apply and that benchmark data set is
also balanced with all locations and
balanced in terms of sequence features
and when we apply the best models today
on predicting location on that benchmark
they all perform very well. they perform
pretty okay on nuclear cytoplasm and
some other locations but certain
cellular compartments they can just
never predict. So I think that this is
where we need more information than
amino acid sequence alone. We probably
need regulatory regions, UTR regions. Uh
we can have also been trying different
protein embedding models. Some of them
work well if it's like a long intrinsic
disorder region. It might work well in
predicting some locations, but certain
times it's just one amino acid that is
changing and most models don't capture
that. So I think that like it's nothing
that my lab will do but I think it will
be very interesting to start to think
about location as one of the features
you want to predict with protein models
and when you design molecules and new
proteins maybe not only design the
protein with a a certain function in
mind but also with a certain location in
mind because there are certain classes
of proteins where that location really
matters for its function. Awesome. Not
really an answer to your question, but
so when you look at your new ontologies
that you're finding, do you also find
places where you want to where your your
model or your data wants to change the
tree structure? Because over the years
predicting protein function, a lot of
people would do that work complain that
that tree is not always right, I guess.
Yeah. I think I think that the high
level tree like the organels are are
pretty robust and right. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Down there I think there's a lot
of rewriting to do. And I also think
that we're still a bit data limited
because when it comes to like below the
the miso scale where you have a lot of
face separated systems and things like
that, we're probably going to have to
build sequence image models to really
capture that. And I'm guessing that
we're going to see a lot of shuffling in
these ontologies when when we do that.