I was became interested in um uh
the Apollo space suit in graduate school
and um it had never really been written
about in design terms and the the story
that I became obsessed with and spent um
uh many years writing about um was
really a story of uh at multiple levels.
At the first hand, um, at the first
level, it's this amazing story about how
this tiny division of what was then
known as the Plex Broad and Girdle
Company beat out a range of military
industrial contractors, more traditional
military-industrial contractors to build
um, uh, to really sew the Apollo space
suit that walked on the moon in uh,
1969. Um, and then secondly, it's a
story of this remarkable object. The
Apollo spac suit ended up having 21
different layers of fabric, each of them
with a different purpose. And um you
know, if uh uh what that means is it was
really a kind of um uh object that had
as much in common with the skin of the
person that it protected with all its
layers uh as it did with the larger
military-industrial um complex really of
of which it was a part. And so it's a
really interesting object at the
intersection between man-made systems uh
or technological systems and and the
system of the human body. And it really
um has as much in common with each of
them um uh uh and uh or has essential
qualities in in in common with each of
those uh systems. And so for me it was a
really interesting um not just a really
interesting object but a really
interesting object around which to work
through uh a lot of very important ideas
about resilience, redundancy um uh
designing with natural systems instead
of against them. All all of the ideas
that that uh uh my own design work tries
to work through at the scale of
buildings and at the scale of cities and
ecologies. So there's a a direct um link
for example between the ideas in spac
suit and the ideas that I've tried to
bring to uh urban design in the context
of designing for climate change. So
we've already talked about how what a
contributor um uh architecture and the
building of cities is to the production
of greenhouse gases and the causes of
the climate crisis. But it's also the
case that cities are at the um uh really
at the front line of the effects of the
climate crisis. coastal cities in
particular um uh but also cities as
they're affected by wildfires and other
um uh natural disasters which are um not
natural because they're really amplified
by man-made climate change to produce a
real threat to our cities and and and
landscapes. And so in terms of thinking
about how cities can be more resilient
to the effects of climate change um for
example flooding in San Francisco um uh
I think it's really important to think
not just in terms of um big singular
pieces of infrastructure which is how
we've traditionally thought about uh
protecting cities for example from
flooding um and instead thinking about
giving uh a city something that much
more resembles the immune system and the
human body. lots of different pockets of
defenses all of which can organize
together. Um but when one tiny part of a
natural system um of a resilient uh
natural system fails the whole system
adapts and compensates for it whereas
when one part of a dam fails the whole
dam is uh is useless. So I I bring a lot
of these ideas from thinking about the
history of evolution um uh uh the the uh
evolution of natural systems which is a
big part of the kind of intellectual
piece of the spac suit book to really
thinking in very practical terms about
how we can redesign cities to better
accommodate the effects of climate
change which are already coming and
which will only increase in the next uh
decades. So the project we're talking
about in in San Francisco and that we've
adapted to different settings settings
is a is a real example of that because
uh uh in the context of San Francisco,
we were looking at storm water drainage.
Um so of course San Francisco uh uh gets
the same amount of average rainfall as
other cities in the United States, but
it tends to come in kind of mega events
um uh uh which can cause um tremendous
flooding throughout the city. At the
time we were doing that project um 10 or
15 years ago, the city was looking at
expanding the storm water system to
better accommodate flooding. But what we
showed was if you took these 1500 um uh
sites throughout the city which which
were very well situated to do this work
and created in each of them a kind of
temporary storm water um uh uh holding
system which you can do which um you
know just looks like spongy green stuff
that holds the water before it and and
slowly lets it into the um uh uh sewer
system over time. Not only did you not
need to increase the size of the pipes
under underground to accommodate the
increased flooding, but you created a
system that um you know if one uh if one
microite fails, if another site fails
and and doesn't uh hold water as well as
it should, it's okay because the system
as a whole um is very resilient to
failure. Whereas if you have a single
pipe draining everything under the
ground, you have one blockage in that
pipe, the whole thing doesn't work.