Our rounding out our presentations today
is nine diagnostics with AI powered
nanoensor technology for precision
medicine and monitoring. Welcoming CEO
and co-founder Freddy Wyn. I just want
to thank the ILP and the startup
exchange for having us today. So my name
is Freddy Wyn. I'm a physician scientist
engineer by training but I'm the CEO
co-founder of Nang Diagnostics where
we're really trying to work on
determining treatment effectiveness
discovering new biology using our AI
enabled nano nanoensor technology cancer
diagnostics and biotools are evolving
towards really more comprehensive
profiling across the R&D and
manufacturing pipeline as you've heard
throughout all the talks today but some
of the challenges are there's still
limited biomarker insights which really
slows that real-time feedback that we
can use there's been poor stratification
has been driving the drug development
failures and there's fragmented data
that really undermines the promise of
precision medicine and current
diagnostics and tools that are being
used are slow, expensive and hard to
scale. And so up until now we've largely
been limited to validate biomarkers. But
at nine diagnostics now we can unlock
insights from unknown biomarkers and
contextual clinical patient data. And we
combine all of that together to create a
new signature fingerprint using the
technology at N Diagnostics.
How does our technology work? It's based
on sigma on carbon nanot tubes which you
heard about earlier from Angela
Belchure. Um but what we now can do to
it is surface chemistry that allows us
to introduce quantum well defects to
those carbon tubes and really get a
variety of types of carbon tubes. And
then we wrap DNA sequences around it to
provide that binding sensitivity and
specificity around of the of the sensor.
And we can detect everything from large
proteins down to small molecules. But
now you can see with all these or all
these um excuse me access of variables
uh we can have an unlimited uh s library
of nano sensors and then we mix our
sensors with uh a patient sample right
now we use plasma uh proteins is what
we're looking at. So looking at the
plasma layer uh we don't need any extra
sample prep and then we uh look at it
through a high throughput near infrared
fluoresence uh
system and once we look at that
interaction we really can create these
signature fingerprints and then we start
incorporating the clinical data from the
patient including their medication
history their coexisting diseases their
migraphics information social
environmental factors and then really
develop that AIM ML model and disease
state
classification some of Our earlier data
has been on developing screening
diagnostics. One has been for high-grade
serious ovarian carcinoma. The second
has been in differentiation in the brain
cancer space. And you can see even with
these two early validation studies, uh
we've been able to develop assays with
sensitivities in the 80 mid 80 to upper
80% as well as specificities in that 95
98%. And all only needing about 200 in
the first one 269 samples. The second
one only 690 samples of to use and
really a relatively short development
timeline in terms of only 3 to six
months. And so some of the more
interesting and newest data that we have
is that we've been trying to figure out
well we can detect known biomarkers but
also unknown ones. So how do we
determine what those unknown ones? So
we've been developing the pipeline for
determining what those proteins are. So
from our most recent early brain cancer
work right now we've been able to
identify 37 proteins that our sensors
responded to. And these are known to be
associated with the tumor cells
themselves the tumor micro environment
as well as the systemic immune
inflammatory response. So that really
allows us to do simultaneous detection
identification of relevant unique
biomarkers without knowing what those
proteins are ahead of time. And so
that's really going to allow us to lead
to new discovery and new biological
insights and better understanding of
what treatment response
works. In terms of our technology, we
use small volume samples. Right now, we
can use just 300 microL of the plasma
layer. Um, but we're working on trying
to get that smaller. We can create these
unique signature fingerprint profiles.
We have a rapid assay development time
of only three to six months. And it's a
very cost-effective and rapid testing
technology. currently less than $5 per
sample in a research environment, less
than five minutes to run per sample and
can continue to uh develop reliably high
sensor performance. And so the way that
we work with our partners is through a
code discovery process to build
processing local technologies or invitro
diagnostic tools uh where we bring the
AI enabled nanosensor technology. Our
partners bring the bio samples, the
contextual data together we build these
high performing assets that can provide
that actual insights that you're looking
for. Here's an example of how we've been
working with one of our other academic
partner at UCSF in terms of trying to
think about endotyping to treat. So now
really moving the paradigm towards how
do we classify patients based on what
they're most likely to respond to as
opposed to purely on the screening
diagnostic side. And nine diagnostic
aims to transform the R&D value chain to
achieve that acceleration process reduce
risk and proves the sex risk. Right now
we're focusing on the discovery, the
translational science and the biom biio
manufacturing part of the pipeline.
So at 99 we're trying to make smarter
decisions across the R&D and
manufacturing pipeline
uh and through by developing a high
throughput proteomics and metabolics
platform technology really for rapid
biomarker discovery and response
readouts. Our team has had 20 years of
experience in this space over 20 plus
patents have been filed in the nanom
materials nano technologies place and uh
this is now the fourth startup that's
spun out of my co-founder Dan Hiller uh
who is also an alum for MIT as well. So,
thank you so much for your time.