That is a tough act to follow. Uh really
thank you so much for sharing your
story. That was really amazing. Uh so
there's a lot of opportunity to do some
great science. Uh and we're going to
hear uh three wonderful talks uh in this
first session on next generation
screening technologies at scale. Our
first speaker is Gabe Griffin. Uh Gabe
is a physician scientist at Dana Farber
and a member of the Broad Epigenomics uh
program and he's going to talk to us
about his work on cancer amunotherapy
and understanding how to make it work
better. Gabe, take it away.
Uh there's a lot of really important
work that we can do in the rare disease
the rare disease area. Uh the particular
topic that I'm going to speak to you
about today is is a collaborative
project uh we're doing that is
attempting to harness functional
genomics and machine learning for rare
cancer research and particularly to find
new drug drug targets for rare
cancers. And I'll just say at the outset
this project is a collaboration uh with
the ball lab here at the broad
institute. Uh that lab is run by Dr.
mybball shown at the top here and a lot
of the work that I'll I'll speak about
was also led by Dr. Lauren Wickstrom who
I believe is is here as
well. Okay. So the talk is organized
into three
categories. Our goal is really to find
new drug targets for rare cancers as I
said. So the first part will be why rare
cancers? Why should we care about rare
cancers? The second part is what are the
challenges of drug discovery in this
area and then the third is what is at
least our proposed solution to these
challenges. What is the strategy we're
taking? Okay. So for the first point,
why rare cancers? So, if if you'll bear
with me for a moment, I' I'd like a show
of hands from the audience of anyone who
has been either personally impacted by
cancer or had someone in their immediate
sort of world impacted by cancer,
whether it's a a family member or a
friend or a
co-orker. Okay, so it's a a fair number
of people. You can keep your hands up if
you don't mind. And so, I'm going to cut
cut this group in half. So, anyone who
was born on an odd numbered day, you can
lower your hand. So if if you were born
on an even number day, you can keep it
up. Okay, great. And I'm going to cut
that group in half one more time. So
anyone who was born from January through
June, you can lower your hand. And if
you were born July through December, you
can keep your hand up. Okay. So I
there's maybe 10 15 hands still raised
in the audience. So what what am I
getting at with this? The point is that
uh among all cancers okay while an any
any individual rare cancer might be rare
among all cancers rare rare cancers come
come together to comprise about 25%.
Right? So about 25% of everyone who
raised their hand initially has been in
some way affected by a rare cancer.
Okay. So they they impact they impact
all of us.
The formal definition of a rare cancer
maybe isn't that important, but it
generally uh means cancers that affect
uh about 40,000 or less new people per
year or 15 per 100,000 cases uh per
year. What is the challenge of studying
rare cancers? Well, fewer patients means
it's harder to test possible therapies.
Uh it's harder to get samples for re
research. It's harder to get funding.
sometimes it's harder to make
progress and this problem is
particularly acute in the field of rare
uh pediatric cancers. So in effect every
pediatric cancer based on its incidence
is considered a rare cancer. And so you
can see the numbers in terms of cancer
diagnoses and cancer deaths uh uh on an
annual basis in in uh individuals uh
less than the age of 19 here.
But these are all kind of statistics and
I think especially following the last
talk I think maybe one of the most
critical things to remember especially
from sort of a physician scientist
perspective or perhaps from a patient
perspective is that cancer always
affects an individual person uh with a
family and they don't choose to have a
rare cancer they just have their cancer
and so I think it's important that we
take these cancers seriously for study
and therapeut therapeutic development
like we would uh anything else so I
think that that kind of relationship of
uh you know an individual patient is
highlighted in this statue here. This is
actually a statue of Dr. Sydney Farber
who helped start the Dana Farber Cancer
Institute and uh one of one of his early
patients who was nicknamed Jimmy. He was
a boy who was diagnosed with a rare form
of blood cancer. This statue actually
sits right outside the the laboratory
building, the Jimmy Fund building where
our lab is. And so, you know, walk past
this statue essentially every day on the
walk walk-in from the parking garage.
And, uh, so, you know, really serves as
a a source of
inspiration. One of the key discoveries
that Dr. Farber made, this is, you know,
back in the in the 40s, was that, uh,
cancer cells depend on this nutrient
folic acid for their group, for their
growth. And if you could use a drug that
targeted that pathway, antifolate drugs,
at the time it was called aminoptrine,
you could actually kill their cancer
cells, in this case blood cancer. And
ammonoptrine is really the the
predecessor of this drug that's widely
used now called
methtoresate. And in this remarkable
story, Jimmy was treated with this drug
uh when he was a kid. He was cured uh
and he, you know, lived to the ripe old
age of of being a grandfather. And
there's this beautiful photo from 1998
of him with his his grandkids. His real
name is In A Gustoson. He was originally
from Maine. So I think really
transformative
uh potential for individual people for
for cancer research and and particularly
in rare
cancers. Okay. So what are the
challenges of drug discovery in this
area? How can we make progress uh
similar similar to what I just showed?
So I think at in kind of the early days
of cancer research and and drug
development, there was this sentiment or
perhaps a hope that cancer would be a
single disease and that we would find a
single magic bullet that would work for
if not all patients, most patients. So
that was really a dominant aspiration or
hope in the field. But as as we've
realized in decades since uh cancer is
in fact many many different diseases.
This is one of the challenges of
developing cancer therapies. You might
find something that works very very well
for a particular disease but it won't
work at all for something else. So
really what we need is many many
different magic bullets. Some people
have even described like a magic shotgun
approach where you you really hit uh you
know an indiv an individual patients
cancer with with at least one or several
targeted
therapies to highlight this development.
So in Jimmy's time there were two major
types of acute leukemia or this acute
form of blood cancer. uh they were
broadly categorized into acute leukemias
that had differentiation like myoid
cells or differentiation like lymphoid
cells. There were basically these two
big categories and uh you know this is a
field that's near and dear to my heart
in my clinical life. I I uh study or I
help diagnose patients with blood cancer
and this field has evolved tremendously.
This is, you know, not meant to see the
details here, but this is just meant to
highlight all the many different
categories of acute leukemia that exist
today. There's B acute leukemia, T- cell
acute leukemia, myoid leukemia, and
they're all defined largely by very
distinct genetic drivers, many of which
are are anogenic gene fusions, and we'll
talk more about that. So, there's just
incredible diversity of drivers within
within even just this one disease.
Luckily there has been uh you know
despite this diversity uh enormous
success in the development of targeted
therapies uh for many of these diseases
over the years highlighting just a
couple here. One example is chronic
myoid leukemia or or CML. It's driven by
this encogenic driver BCR able. There
was a tyrrosine kinase inhibitor a
matnib or glevec that was developed for
this FDA approved in 2001 and this is
basically transformed therapy for these
patients. Uh a couple other examples
here uh targeting other uh particular
you know fusions in blood cancer that
have been developed. Now one thing
you'll you'll notice about these is that
these are all the mechanism of action of
these drugs are all ty tyrroscen kinace
inhibitors. What that means is that
these drugs are targeting an active
site, an enzyatic site, a kind of
conventional druggable site on these
encogenic fusions. That's one of the
reasons these have been these have been
possible. So why not just use this
strategy for all other encogenic fusions
and we can we can cure all rare rare
cancers. Well, the problem with that is
that many key drivers of rare cancers
and many encogenic drivers or encogenic
key infusions actually lack conventional
druggable sites. They lack enzyatic
domains and so they're kind of less
straightforward from a drug development
standpoint. You don't necessarily know
where to design your drug
against. Here's one example of that.
This is an example of an MLL or KMT2A
gene fusion that drives certain subtypes
of acute leukemia. On the top is what
the wild type protein looks like. So
this is a lysene methyl transferase in
its sort of wild type physiologic form.
And the enzyatic domain, the histone
methyl transferase domain is shown all
the way out here at the C terminus, the
set domain. In the fusion protein, the N
terminus of wild type MLL is retained
and then there's a break and one of
various gene partners can come on the C
terminus and this essentially causes the
loss of this enzyatic domain. So this
kind of conventional approach enzyatic
targeting disrupting an active site
won't work for an MLL fusion
protein. Okay. So what what can we do?
How can we go after this? Well, MLL is
actually a beautiful example uh in large
part due to a lot due to work that has
has been done um locally. There's been
enormous therapeutic progress in this
area and a key insight was the discovery
that MLL fusion proteins actually form
encoenic protein complexes and that's
illustrated here. So the you can almost
imagine the fusion protein acting as a
scaffold for recruiting all these other
transcriptional regulators including
this protein menin and that encoenic
transcription complex finds target genes
that are critical for promoting the
leukemia. So if somehow you could
disrupt this complex you would prevent
activation of these leukem leukemagenic
genes and uh potentially cure patients
leukemia.
So that has been an enormous success
story. So there's an inhibitor actually
several different inhibitors of of this
protein menin which these drugs in
general uh disrupt protein protein
interaction between menin and this
ankcoenic fusion uh the MLL fusion and
disrupts uh its ability to activate
leukemagenic genes and is very effective
in MLL rearranged leukemia. So I think
there's a nice paradigm here for
thinking about how to drug encogenic
fusion complexes in a way that doesn't
require you know kind of a conventional
enzyatic inhibition approach and of note
this uh MLL inhibitor revanib received
FDA approval recently in
2024. Okay. So how can we build on this
kind of paradigm of of menin inhibitors
for MLL rearranged leukemias and extend
it to other leukemias and other
encogenic fusion driven rare
cancers. That was really the or origin
of our of our work and collaboration.
This is just a summary. I won't go
through all the text but basically the
targets that we're that we're interested
in are ankcogenic fusion proteins in
rare cancers. Our hypothesis is that the
ankcogenic fusion proteins form these
complexes that are critical to cancer
growth. A additional hypothesis is that
if you can disrupt those those
complexes, these will be targetable
effective dependencies for rare cancers.
And the objectives of our work is really
to define the functional interactors of
ocogenic fusion proteins in rare
cancers, but to do this in a way that is
really scalable and costefficient. So
perhaps to accelerate this this process
beyond kind of conventional
approaches and to do that our strategy
is to integrate some of the high
throughput uh technologies scalable
technologies that have been developed
over the last you know decade and
beyond. uh first in functional genomics
that's what my lab really specializes in
doing crisper screens to you know
identify new new therapeutic targets and
then also uh structural modeling of
ankcogenic fusion proteins using some of
these just revolutionary computational
structural biology tools that have come
out uh in including things like
alphafold putting these two together we
want to uh prioritize new drug targets
for ankafusion positive rare
cancers okay so in the subsequent slides
just have a few more slides ides uh to
show our progress so this far in this
project. We're going to I'm going to be
using the MLL ankcogenic fusion in
leukemia as kind of a benchmarking
control for our method development and
for illustration
purposes. Okay. So this step one of our
method is to identify cell lines from
the cancer dependency map that was
generated here at the broad institute
that have a functional dependency on a
given agogenic gene fusion. So in this
particular case we're looking at all of
the depth map data. All each each dot
here is a cell line. Okay. And then
we're looking on the x-axis of the
effect of knocking out one component of
this gene this gene fusion ml or
KMT2A. And you can see that uh cell
lines to the left. These are cell lines
that die when you knock out that
encogenic gene fusion. These indeed are
in highly enriched for leukemia cells
that harbor this this encogenic chain
fusion. So it's a way essentially of
identifying cell lines that have a
strong functional dependency on this
encogenic chain fusion. So we collect
all
those. Next we then identify among those
cell lines selective gene knockout
dependencies that are really unique to
that particular encogenic gene fusion.
In other words, these are genes that if
you knock like other genes that if you
knock them out in that cell line, the
the cancer cells will will die as well.
And so that this is a this is a group of
those that come out of this kind of
analysis.
And what you can see here is that this
approach in a kind of unbiased way also
finds menin this known interactor of of
MLL alcogenic fusion and a known drug
target uh in this in this context. So
the hypothesis would be that there's
probably other uh members of an MLL
fusion protein uh complex that that are
included in these in these
codependencies.
So the question then becomes well how
you know given this this list of of
codependencies say we took the top 50
from this how can we
then associate them together are they
all just random genes or do they
actually you know come together to form
true true fusion protein
complexes. So h essentially how could we
group them into little little
subgroups? So one one strategy is to use
an approach like uh string databases.
These are beautiful databases that have
been kind of built on the top of all of
the literature and published data that's
come out over over the decades. A lot of
it experimentally informed where people
have you know pulled down particular
proteins and done things like mass spec
to find what the the protein interaction
partners are. This is a great starting
point and you can see that even uh you
know in string you can find uh
interaction networks that involve men
mll and some of the known known encoenic
fusion partners. So this is uh you know
one starting point for doing this but
this this method is also somewhat
limited by the fact that you know for
this this database is populated by known
information or published information.
And so it would also be nice to to
complement this with a way that sort of
a strategy that can associate proteins
without any reliance on published data
or uh perhaps you know uh you in a
context where maybe a protein hasn't
been studied before. How could you how
could you approach that and this is
where alphafold comes in and this has
been the work largely led by uh uh uh
the kickball lab. So you can use uh you
know in short alpha fold can allow you
to predict the structure of a protein
just from its primary protein sequence.
And there are new newer versions of
alphafold that can also allow you to do
protein protein interaction modeling to
potentially identify protein protein
interaction surfaces that could be could
be druggable. So we uh took all of those
codependencies and then without any
prior knowledge about them other than
what what AlphaFold could teach us, we
tried to do pair-wise interactions
between all of
them. And what's shown here is the
result of that. So if you do pair-wise
interactions between all of these
individual codependencies and the MLL
fusion protein, this is what you see uh
kind of gratifyingly men. So this
established target is at the top of this
list. It's the fourth highest sort of
confidence predicted uh interaction with
with the MLL encogenic fusion protein.
And so this really gives us confidence
that this type of strategy if applied to
other uh encogenic fusions could
identify, you know, meaningful um
meaningful
PPIs. And uh just to drill down on this
a little bit further, this is this
beautiful representation where there's
uh the menin protein in tan and there's
this men and interacting peptide of MLL
which is an aqua and then a bunch of the
uh individual uh uh contact points
between these two that were identified
as as of high competence by Alphaold.
And so it can really help you even get
down to the molecular level or
structural biology level to find you
know interaction surfaces that you could
then exploit for for drug
development. Okay. And then the last
step uh once we have these structural
computational models with all these PPI
surfaces uh predicted then the question
becomes well how can you validate their
function and this is where we bring back
in or circle back to the function
function genomics approaches integrating
base editor tiling munogenesis of
encogenic fusions where we're basically
introducing point mutations across the
entirety of a fusion and testing the
functional effect of that in high
throughput screens. And once we have
that data, we can then integrate that
with the structural predictions to
nominate candidate drug binding sites.
And so this is an example of doing this
for for the menin uh menin protein where
we uh this is actually re reanalysis of
published tiling data from this
reference uh for the menin protein and
you can see that there are a number of
resistant hits that come out of uh this
screen. These are basically mutations
that prevent men and inhibitor effects
in these cells. And then you can then
plot those uh resistant sites onto these
structural predictions that we've had
that we've generated and find um that
indeed these sites affect known drug
binding sites and kind of make sense
from a structural
standpoint. Okay. So the next steps for
this is to develop this general approach
now that it seems to be working in this
positive control or benchmarking
context. Develop it as a scalable
workflow to identify novel interaction
sites in additional or potentially all
agenic fusion positive cancers that we
have some functional uh dependency data
for and we're specifically focusing our
efforts now on leukemia or blood cancers
and also increasingly now in pediatric
saroma. Okay. So with that, I'll stop.
Acknowledgements uh to folks in my lab,
Jada Coffee and and Annie Chen, and then
also in the BAL lab, uh Dr. Lauren
Wickstrom. And also thank you to Guiam
Pon Montan from Broad Cott who's been
excellent structural biology uh
collaborator and also to the ladders to
cures accelerator for pilot funding for
this project. Thank you very much.
Okay, as Jillian mentioned, we're going
to do a Q&A after all three speakers.
So, I'd like to welcome up our next
speaker, JT Neil. JT Neil is an
institute scientist here at the Broad.
He is the director of systems genomics
in the metabolism program and part of
the Novo Nordisk Center. And yes, I just
memorized that right now. JT, take it
away. Perfect. All right. I'm really
excited to be here representing our
team. I'm gonna actually stand out here
because they don't build these podiums
for people of my stature. U so uh the
our our our project is called rapidly
identifying drugs for rare disorders by
pulled imagebased profiling. Uh I'll be
giving the talk today, but uh I actually
am co-leading this project with an
carpenter who's here at the Brook. So I
don't think I need to convince really
anyone in this room that therapeutics
are a major unmet need for rare
diseases. And uh as you all are aware
rare diseases collectively are not rare.
Uh as many as 30 million Americans or
nearly 10% of people in the US are
affected by a rare disease and they
cause over a third of deaths in the
first year of life. So this is really a
heartbreaking medical
problem. Additionally there are
thousands of these diseases perhaps as
many as
10,000 and there are approved treatments
available for 5% or fewer of these. So
this is really a huge clinical gap that
needs to be
filled and part of the reason this gap
exists is because drug development uh
canonical drug development denovo drug
development is both incredibly expensive
and incredibly slow. So uh we can take
anywhere from 10 to 17 years to develop
these agents from scratch and it can
cost over a billion dollars. Now, this
makes rare diseases not a particularly
good like commercial candidate because
unless we can figure out a way to
aggregate patient populations, there's
no way for drug companies to recoup this
money. Plus, people are suffering from
these diseases all the time and we just
don't have the
time. So, we and others actually many
others in the rare disease community
have come to rare uh rare disease drug
repurposing as a promising approach to
treat these disorders. So in drug
repurposing, we are identifying new
therapeutic uses for drugs that have
already gone through some level of
testing. Uh it takes advantage of some
of these early pipeline steps that fail
out many earlyphase compounds. So things
like solubility, stability, selectivity,
um and potency. But most crucially,
these drugs have already been proven to
be safe in humans. And so this means
that there uh the timeline to get this
drug into a patient can often be much
much faster and at a pretty dramatically
lower
cost. Well, if you're interested in
doing drug repurposing, the Broad is
really a wonderful place to be because
we have one of the world's best
collections of drug repurposing
compounds in a resource called the drug
repurposing hub. The drug repurposing
hub is a very very large collection of
compounds over 7,000 that sort of span a
range of uh clinical phases um and a
large number of targets and mechanisms
of
action. Um and importantly it has over
2400 FDA approved drugs. Um so a really
really great resource first inclass for
someone who wants to run screens trying
to identify uh drugs to repurpose for
rare disease.
But we're still facing a pretty big
challenge and that is that these rare
diseases are incredibly diverse. So
there's something like 5,000 rare
mandelian diseases where we know a
genetic cause. We have a genetic anchor
and thousands more where we don't. And
these diseases affect dozens of unique
cell types and organ systems. And so, as
Anna alluded to this morning, many of us
in the community are trying to find
these nodes or these um handles by which
we can we can reduce the complexity of
this problem. Um so, can we identify
some sort of common mechanisms that
allow us to have an entry point? And it
turns out actually that protein
misloization is is a is a mechanism
that's common to many rare diseases. So
I'm showing you here a figure from an
elegant study uh from Anne Carpenter in
uh here at the Broaden and Miko Typola
the University of Toronto uh in which
they screened a very large number of
rare coding
variants uh and so they overexpressed
these as proteins and what they observed
is that these and they're tagged with
flag tags so you can see where they go.
Uh and what they observed is that many
of these uh proteins are misloized so
they end up in the wrong part of the
cell. So for instance, you know, if it's
supposed to be in the gold, it ends up
in the ER or vice versa. This happens
often along sort of known uh secrettory
route within the cell. Um, and that
these things also tend to fall in sort
of patterns of misloization shared
between uh, you know, some of these
protein variants. And it's not all that
uncommon. 16% of all the variants they
test have one of these misloization
defects. And intriguingly, the degree of
misloization is often associated with
the disease severity. So the amount of
protein that's in the wrong place can
lead to more severe symptoms and earlier
onset of disease. So this leads to a
really tantalizing question. What would
happen if we could move some of this
protein back where it's supposed to be?
Well, it turns out that we actually
don't have to stretch our imagination
all that far because correcting protein
localization is a proven therapeutic
strategy. So probably the best example
of this is in cystic fibrosis. So the
CFTR protein uh chloride ion channel
that's supposed to be at the membrane.
Uh in cystic fibrosis inducing mutations
like CFTR delta508. You see here we have
diffuse
staining. Uh but the it turns out that
if you treat with Vertex's drug
lumicapater you can actually drive some
of this protein back into the membrane.
And when you then combine this therapy
with ivacater which enhances activity of
this channel you can actually achieve s
significant therapeutic
benefit. Uh and this this has been
observed for other cases. Here I'm
showing you pgeria and lamina a um which
I I think many of you are probably
familiar with uh in treatment with the
agent
lunafarnib. So our goal really is a
pretty simple one and that is can we
identify new drug repurposing candidates
capable of correcting protein
misloization in rare disease. Um pretty
straightforward. So step one, identify
the pathogenic phenotype. So here we
have a very clear screenable phenotype.
That is the protein is in the wrong
place. We are combining that with a
little bit more um complex phenotype. So
cell profiling with cell painting. And
then we just want to test drugs, screen
drugs to see if we can reverse reverse
this phenotype. So can we make unhealthy
cells look more like healthy
cells? So this is pretty simple as I
said. Why has this not been done
already? Well, practically speaking, uh
it's actually quite difficult using
traditional screening methods because
there are if for instance you wanted to
screen all 7,000 drugs in the
repurposing library against just our 250
variants, you're talking about 1.75
million individual experiments plus
controls and
replicates a measly 600,000 if you just
want to do your FDA approved drugs. And
we're not afraid of scale here at the
Broad, but this gives us
pause. And this is because we're
screening these phen phenotypes
optically and that means that we have no
way of taking these variants and pooling
them together because then we wouldn't
know which cell had which one.
Thankfully, we're not held back by this
any further because of a technique
developed in Paul Laney's lab called
optical pulled screening a few years
ago. What this enables us to do is to
put unique barcodes onto each of our
disease variants, amplify these
barcodes, and then sequence them
directly on a microscope using aluminina
chemistry. You'll hear more about this
in Matt Brown's talk after mine. Here's
what it looks like. So, we can sequence
uh on a microscope over sequential
cycles. Each one of these dots is a base
and the barcode. And so, through
sequential cycles, we can figure out
what the barcode is, what cell has what
variant. This now enables us to put them
all together into one big experiment.
And we've spent uh the last few years,
my lab working with Paul's lab, Ann's
lab, and some collaborators at Calico to
really platformize this. So this is the
essence of our L2C project. Um we want
to take our 250 disease variants along
with a 100 uh of their wild type
partners, pull them all together and
apply a compound from the drug
repurposing library. We'll collect
variant localization and cell morphology
and combine that with optical variant
barcoding to enable us to assess
compound effect and assign a variant to
cell. So this is a huge increase in in
throughput. So here for uh screening a
100 drugs if you did it the oldfashioned
way it would take 35,000 experiments. We
can do it in a 100 experiments.
So our aims are were to build and QC a
barcoded library of these 250 disease
variants and their wild type controls,
capture protein localization and paired
cell morphology using cell painting uh
for both the normal and the disease
associated variants and then to screen
100 FDA approved drugs against pulled
variants to identify potential
therapies. We're making good progress to
date in the first year of of our our
project. So, we've finished building the
library and we've qced it. We've
optimized all of our uh screening
culture conditions, staining, incencing.
We've carried out a pilot cell coverage
study to let us know how many uh times
we need to see a variant in a cell to be
able to identify hits. And actually, as
we're here in this room together, uh
we're carrying out a pilot screen in
which we're screening four drugs from
the repurposing collection against our
100 disease uh collection. and we hope
to read that out next
week. So, of course, it's it's worth
spending a minute to ask how we're going
to think about hits that come out of the
screen. We have no illusions that we're
going to take a primary screening drug
and put it into a
patient. So, uh we're screening these
all in singlicate to begin with, one
high dose and one well. These are pulled
experiments. Uh and so we think this
helps alleviate some of the batch
effects you would normally see in a RAID
drug screening. Um, but any hits we
find, we're going to take back and
reconfirm in eight replicates across
eight doses to build a dose response
curve. Any hits from this secondary
screen, we'll take into a tertiary
screen that will be in a cell type. So,
we're screening only in a single cell
type. I should have said helicotto
cells. We will then take those compounds
and screen them against that variant uh
that variant pair now in a disease
relevant uh cell line. So, be it neurons
or endthelial cells, whatever is
appropriate for that condition.
And then we're going to take this back
to the rare disease community. We're
going to bring it back to the latter
ladders to cure uh community and we're
going to um disseminate these data
through traditional um venues,
publications and online portals and the
like. Work with gap bridging
organizations like ENCATs and every
cure.
Um and then engage other rare disease
researchers to see if we can motivate
further experiments be they in vitor or
in vivo as well as engaging clinicians
where uh we have promising candidates to
see if we can move into clinical trials
or potentially even consider
compassionate use exemptions uh for
cases where there is extreme great
evidence and extreme need. And then we
hope of course that through screening
these multiple mechanisms, we'll be able
to identify shared nodes that might
allow us to aggregate diseases into
shared classes which might make them
more um interesting candidates for drug
companies to want to develop drugs
for. And and before I wrap up, I I want
I want to take a moment to uh especially
thank Anna and Jillian and the rare
disease uh community and latter secures
here at Broad because um this work is
really really hard to get funded and we
have been trying to get this uh this
project funded especially an has been
trying to get this project funded for
years and uh the pilot funding that
we're using here through ladder secures
as one of the initial projects is
enabling us to generate not only key
proof of concept data but has given us
momentum and that momentum we have
actually used now Ann and I are are in
the early stages of of forming uh a
industry uh collaboration a consortium
the Vista uh consortium that will begin
the first process of scaling this effort
now from 100 drugs to 500
drugs and uh so this is this is not
finalized uh keep your keep your ears
open but we have two pharma partners
already that are very very excited about
what this data set could could mean. And
then of course in the fullness of time,
you know, this genetic discovery is
ongoing and large projects including
ones like uh the one that Ann is
currently leading are going to discover
more and more of these cases. Uh and so
in the fullness of time, of course, we
have the bold vision of being able to
screen all of the broad drug repurposing
library against thousands of rare
diseases uh to find new medicines for
for the patients who need them most.
So with that, I'll thank the people
who've done the work in my lab um in
Miko Topal's lab at the University of
Toronto, especially my partner in crime
and carpenter and the Broad Imaging
Platform uh and and Paul Blay's lab. And
then obviously huge uh thanks to the
latter secure scientific accelerator for
making this possible.
Hey, thank you so much JT. Our final
speaker of this session is uh Matt
Brown. Matt received his PhD uh from
Mayo Clinic. Uh he then came to Anna
Greer's group uh to do his post-doal
work where he's also an awardee of the
Broad Ignite Foundation. So Matt, take
it away. Thank you.
Uh yeah, thank you John for the really
nice introduction. In an interest of
time, I'll try to uh get everyone to the
the coffee break as soon as possible.
But I'm really excited to uh share our
work today about uh using multiplex
optical optical cooled screening uh for
uh proteinopathy uh therapeutic
discovery.
Um so for a long time I've been
interested in how um how the kidney
works and specifically how ep uh kidney
epithelial cells uh which line the
nefron or the kidney's functional unit
uh function to transport solutes and
waters across the apical and basil
basilateral membranes of the kidney. Um
these epithelial cells uh do this uh by
tra by moving uh transporters uh and
other accessory proteins uh to these
membranes and they do this uh through a
pathway called the secrettory pathway.
Um in these cells uh these transporters
need to be uh synthesized in the ER uh
processed in the Golgi um and then moved
to wherever they they need to function
within the cell and then eventually
they're degraded uh using lysosal or
proteosomal mechanisms.
Um however mutations in protein cargos
um such as muk one or urodulin or
disruption of the secrettory pathway
itself um can lead to proteinopathies in
a in a number of rare diseases in the
kidney and in in a number of different
organs. Um and previous work from our
lab um has identified disregulation um
in a kind of a nodal mechanism um uh
called these T-ED cargo receptors. Um
and these team cargo receptors live um
in the space between the ER and the
Golgi and they and they function to move
proteins uh between these two between
these two secretary organels. Um and
disruption of this pathway again uh
leads to kind of uh proteinopathies in a
number of tissues such as the kidney uh
the eye um and the brain. So really um
our central question um is what factors
and genes uh control the efficient and
quality production of proteins and can
this teach us something about the
pathogenesis of of proteinopathies.
So in order to do this uh we we kind of
again uh as JT alluded we took a
approach developed by the Blenny lab
called optical poolled screening where
uh we can take a epithelial cell line
that is expressing cast 9. Uh we can
infect it with uh guide RNAs that uh
disrupt or knock out uh the entire
genome. um we can subsequently sequence
these guide RNAs to demultiplex uh which
uh cells got which knockouts and then we
can subsequently integrate this with
with uh iterative imaging to basically
mark or track uh both our secrettory
organels as well as nodal proteins
associated uh with the development of
proteinopathies. So in order to do this
at a at such a large scale uh we made
some key changes uh to the to the
initial protocol developed by the Bliny
Lab uh that kind of allow us to scale
up. So we optimized our optical poolled
screening approach uh for compatibility
with all commercial highcontent
screening automated microscopes that
really can empower the next generation
of optical pulled screening. Uh we also
increase throughput by uh integrating
the protocol with automated plate
loading uh and handling uh systems that
again can empower drug screening and and
kind of uh then um and so on. And
additionally we can compress the screen
by increasing surface area uh that we
screen by up to 30%. And and all these
things together uh allow us to scale up
poolled screening for therapeutic
discovery. So just a kind of a a brief
kind of pause here. Um this doesn't
happen in a vacuum. There's a lot of
people to thank for this work. Uh this
was this project was co-led by a really
talented BBS PhD candidate Brianna
Silverman um and a research associate
Jennifer Chen as long as collaborations
with C dot uh the GPP platform here at
the bro genomics platform and then a lot
of uh collaboration and advising from
both uh JT's lab and uh Paul Bane's lab.
So just a kind of a kind of a quick
aside on uh on how we do this INC2
sequencing and and and uh kind of some
of the quality of this new
platform. So as GT alluded uh INC2
sequencing of guide RNAs is a cyclical
process where we read out uh the bases
one by one. Uh you can kind of
appreciate over 15 cycles of institutu
sequencing. uh we can kind of
demultiplex an individual guide RNA um
using two channel uh chemistry which is
a kind of an evolution from the original
protocol. Um if we compare this uh
compare these INCU readout guide RNAs
compared to our kind of ground truth our
next generation sequencing data which is
on our x-axis
um and then our institu sequencing
results on the y- axis you can see a
high correlation between uh between our
guide RNA distribution suggesting that
we're accurately uh reading out our
guide RNAs. Uh similarly if we look at
our our overall library skew we see high
concordance between our next generation
sequencing results our incitu sequencing
results and then our guide li guide RNA
uh li library library
input. Um when we look at overall
distribution of of number of guides
we're capturing per gene uh we're
consistent with other genomewide uh
other genomewide screens where we're
seeing around a thousand cells u uh
knocked out per per gene.
So kind of diving into uh to the to the
meat of the of the story uh how are we
how are we changing the secrettory
pathway and which which genes and and
and factors control the processing of
proteins. So uh using this kind of
iterative and kind of uh massively
paralleled approach we can actually
track the entire secrettory pathway um
across the entire genome. So we can uh
iteratively stain organels starting from
the ER all the way to uh the loome as
well as these nodal pro these nodal
t-med proteins that are key nodes in the
development of proteinopathies.
So u if we kind of delve into the data
and we look at specific uh specific
aectors of the secrettory pathway uh we
can observe that uh positive controls
are our top regulated downregulated
guide RNAs for key organel markers. So
for example on the on the x-axis here I
show transgi contrast and you can
observe that the top down reggulated
guide RNA is the guide targeting the
transolgi. uh we can visualize this um
in individual cells and again you can
see cells expressing guides targeting
trans gulging 2 have an absence of of a
trans golgi signal.
If we do pathway analysis of the genes
that of the guide RNAs that are uh
downregulated uh that downregulated
transgal they enrich for pathways that
are essential for Golgi function such as
ER to GGI transport uh retrograde
transport and GGI organization. So again
just highlighting the quality of the
data. Um and because this is cyclical
often people ask you know do we can we
reproduce this data across different uh
imaging cycles. So if we look in cycle 3
for example and we look at uh the the
COP 2 vesicle marker SE 13 we can see
that our top down reggulated guide RNAs
um encode for both SE 13 and SE 31A
while we see knocking out for example T-
proteins which live in this space
actually uh we see compensation of sect
13 which is kind of a nice positive
control again you can observe this uh at
the kind of the individual cell level
and then the lastly Again, we can go all
the way to our final cycle, our sixth
cycle of iterative imaging. And again,
you can kind of observe the same thing.
We're knocking out Cal Nexin, uh, which
is our marker for the ER, uh, is the
topmost downregulated U guide RNA. So,
these are all great, uh, positive
controls. Again, if you look at
upregulated guide RNA, again, it it's
kind of the who's who of things that
regulate the ER.
So what else can we learn from this data
and how can we connect it to uh kind of
the understanding of
proteinopathies? So uh we can kind of
start to understand how organels work
together and how this process again um
how organels work together and how
disrupting part uh of the signaling
between organels um can regulate the
secrettory pathway. So uh kind of a
classic example is uh the interaction
between lysosomes and autogazomemes and
the formation of
autolymes. So if we if we kind of uh
create a a dot plot of uh things that
change p62 or autofagosome uh intensity
and lampum or loome intensity again we
can observe that knocking out uh the
gene encoding p62 is our top down
reggulated uh guide RNA for p62 and lamp
2 for for lamp 2. Um and then we can
observe again like we can observe shared
mechanisms of regulation where um
inhibiting uh the VATPH complex or
knocking it down uh can both activate uh
P62 levels um and uh lysosal levels and
this is kind of concordant with u the
inh the small molecule inhibitor
bofalomiain. Uh similarly we can observe
unique regulators that specifically
target uh one organel uh and should have
no effect on the other. So uh kind of
our one uh nice example of this um is
the our regulators of lipid trans lipid
transfer from um the ER to nent
autogazomes. So by knocking down uh
members of this pathway we can activate
uh autophagy while not changing looal
intensity. So if we zoom out a little
bit um and we look at multiorganel
disruptors. So, so uh genes that disrupt
multiple parts of this process, we can
actually uh start to cluster genes into
known pathways of biological function.
So, for example, we can observe uh
organels or guides that um disrupt
multiple organels and that encode for
again uh the transport of proteins early
in the secrettory pathway uh between the
ER and the Golg. Similarly, we can
observe uh clusters encoding for uh
genes encoding for transcriptional
regulators as well as uh ER stress or
ERAD pathways suggesting that again
there is these shared nodes of of
regulation of this pathway um that are
important in in the in the regulation of
of protein
transport. So, if we take a really a
really big uh zoom out and we think of
the 3,000 causitive genes associated
with monogenic rare diseases um and we
and we kind of analyze which genes
disrupt this pathway, something is
pretty remarkable we find in the fact
that almost 15% in 15% of of of these
genes uh actually in our kidney cells uh
result in disrupted organeller uh
morphology suggesting that these genes
really uh loss of function of these
genes uh truly um can disrupt this uh
this secrettory pathway and this can be
kind of an a shared uh node for uh for
therapeutic discovery. So I'm just going
to share with you one kind of case study
and how we can use this approach to
understand nodal mechanisms of
proteinopathy pathobiology. So previous
work from our lab um has shown that uh
T-ds uh are kind of a a known process by
which uh misfolded proteins are are are
entrapped in the early secrettory
pathway. Uh these team proteins exist in
uh co-regulated homo ilyic and
heterolygumeric protein complexes.
Um and if we look at the expression of
of for example team at nine one of the
of the members of this complex you can
see that is that its expression is
codependent uh with other other other
members of this of this family.
Um if we can uh recapitulate that in our
screen where we can uh when we look at
T-M protein levels by knocking out T-MA
9 or team at 10 we can recapitulate what
we see
biochemically. Um similarly at the whole
genome level uh we can observe by
knocking out uh uh team 10 9 2 and 7 we
can observe a significant decrease in
team 9
levels. And this in this uh complex
family are are highly dependent um
across the board. Um they exhibit uh
both co codependency um and compensation
for for one another. So again uh this is
a nice kind of model where we can
identify novel regulators of for uh for
therapeutic discovery that are
potentially specific to to uh one uh
complex.
So uh for example uh we can we can look
at team one uh levels uh in cycle three.
Uh you can see that uh team one knocking
out team mode one biochemically uh as
well as knocking out team nine and team
10 uh reduced protein levels and we can
kind of observe that um in our screen
versus when we knock out team at 7 we
actually see this huge compensation of
team one again s further suggesting that
there's kind of co-regulation of this of
this protein uh family. So when we when
we put all of our data together, uh we
can observe kind of overall complex
regulators uh that we can potentially
target um to to more selectively uh
target this nodal pathway. Um if we just
look at just non- selective team complex
regulators, it's again what we would
expect in terms of things that alter
protein transport, eroggi transport and
and so on. Um and then I'll just leave
on uh this one point
that we can start to now use this data
to identify uh kind of spec more
specific uh genomic targets uh that can
be therapeutically relevant. So previous
work from our lab has shown that uh
removal of team 9 uh a small molecule
that removes teammed 9 uh can kind of
resolve um resolve several
proteinopathies in the eye and the brain
and the kidney. Um now we can start to
use this data to to target uh more
specifically uh potentially upstream or
downstream uh in this pathway um at the
genomewide
level. So I just want to thank again our
lab um my co-lead on the project Brianna
Silverman um in and then our
collaborations with C dot uh genomics
perturbation platform um and then ladder
secures and border for funding the
project. So, thank you.
Okay, thanks so much. I'd like to ask
our speakers to come up. Uh, so Gabe,
JT, and Matt. Uh, in the interest of
time, uh, we're going to close the
session here, but if you want to come
ask questions. We'll have a little rat
pack of nerds right here, so come up and
talk. Uh, please come back at 11:15, uh,
to kick off our next session. Thanks so
much.