Modern warehouses are adopting an
increasing level of automation and
technologies to manage the complexities
associated to the growth of e-commerce.
Some of the most relevant technologies
that these warehouses are including are
related to robotics. For example, the
automated storage and retrieval system.
If we focus on warehouse robotics, the
global market reach in 2024 $25 billion
and it's expected to reach $50 billion
in the next 5 years. the integration of
technologies like the internet of things
devices, sensors, computer vision or
advanced artificial intelligence systems
is what really can unlock the potential
of highly automated warehouses. Find
your MIT moment. Visit learnmit.edu.