thank you everyone for joining my name
is Ana Maria and I would like to welcome
everyone to our renear speaker series
hosted by Latin xpro um I'm especially
excited to be hosting today as we are
going to start our Hispanic Heritage
Month and part of this initiative is
part of our our mission to build a pring
Community among Latinos and allies in
science while also empowering the
members of our community uh we hope that
through this program we highlight the
incredible work that our researchers are
doing both here at the broad and Beyond
as well as um hopefully fostering
collaborations with between the speakers
and people that are joining the talk and
also provide um opportunity for
networking uh we hope that by showcasing
these accomplishments of these
individuals we can provide um a platform
for people to learn about the research
that Latinos are doing and also try to
show and inspiring rols for under
repesentative groups in science our goal
here is to cultivate ful connections and
promote groundbreaking research as well
as celebrate the richness and diversity
of our community um so thank you again
for joining us or this do um and I hope
um you keep joining and also please
share um the speaker series with
everyone we from your network we Host
this every month um so now I leave it to
my colleague Ricardo who will be
introducing our speaker for today Ren
thank you for
joining H thank you very much Anna so
it's my pleasure to introduce Dr Ruben
Cordo
um he's a post Aral scientist with
fisheries and oceans Canada and he
explores aquatic ecosystems from Arctic
freshwater habitats to Coastal Marine
environments he'll discuss how factors
like glaz field history predation
aquaculture impacts species and
distribution and Community interactions
across these diverse ecosystems this
talk offers a glimpse into the complex
Dynamic shaping Aquatic Life from
historical climate events to modern day
environmental changes don't miss this
opportunity and take it away
all right thank you very much uh let me
see how this
works okay so first of all um I want to
thank Ricardo and Anam Maria for this
amazing invitation and thank you all for
attending this presentation name
exploring aquatic e ecology H in size
from fresh water to marine
ecosystems all right uh so in this
presentation I will start briefly with
my background and then I will describe
my work starting with the uh the work
that I develop in my masters followed by
my PhD work and then finishing with my
current project as a postdoctoral
research at fisheries and oceans
Canada
okay okay so I'm from a city in Bogota
called Colombia called K uh which is
located at the border with Venezuela um
and after
sorry having some issues okay then after
high school I moved to botan uh to study
biology at the univers the University
alandz where I joined the lab of
Professor Emilio Ri so in this lab I did
my undergrad and Masters working at the
total Lake which is a high mountain lake
located at more than 3,000 meters of
elevation here I analyze uh for my
undergrad the levels of electrification
by measuring phosphorus and nitrogen
concentrations and for my masters uh I
analyze the levels of heavy metals in
fish tissue because this area is the
largest producers of rainbow trouble for
human consumption So eventually I moved
to Canada where I studied a second
Masters at the University of Toronto and
H the first analysis that I will present
which is called H geographical history
of aquatic insects in Northern Canada so
this work was made under the supervision
of Professor Douglas
Cory so the Arctic is one of the most
fragile ecosystems in the planet and is
under great threat since effects of the
climate change are stronger in this
region organisms in these ecosystem are
highly adapted to EnV extreme
environmental conditions however they
can be affected by fast changes of those
conditions and studies on species from
northern Canada are necessary to assess
assess and compare how much impact
climate change is having in this
environment so this motivated us yeah so
this motivated uh the northern
biodiversity program which was an
initiative between researchers from Mill
University and the University of Toronto
to document changes in the Northern
arthropo
Communities so first let's review the
climatic history in North America and
the impact of the glacial periods during
the last 1.6 million years which is
known the as the place toin huge glacial
advances and retreated several times
over North America so here we can
observe the global temperature fluctu
fluctuation during the last 500,000
years and the multiple glacial and
interglacial periods the GLA the last
glaciation period uh which is called the
Wisconsin started about
75,000 years and the last glacial
maximum which cover most of uh more than
half of North America Ur about 22,000
years so this animation uh this is an an
animation that shows how the ice R in
North America since the last GLA maximum
and we see that initially uh the
beringia was exposed and Ice free acting
as refusion from where organisms from
bacteria to animals started to
recolonize the new ice free
land so we can observe that at the end
Binga the Binga land disappear and
that's what separated North America from
Asia all right so my study was focused
on aquatic insects from the orders EOP
copter andopa for several reasons for
example they are the base of the food
Change in these aquatic environment
environments they are also WID spreads
across Northern Canada including the
Arctic archipelago they are easy to
collect and preserve and they are
sensitive to environmental changes which
makes them good
indicators so the objective of this
study was to evaluate the influence of
the last glaciation on intraspecific
structure on within this species so we
wanted to determine if there is evidence
that widely distributed species of
aquatic insects survived during the last
glaciation in two or more refugia for
example beringia or the Southeastern
refugia the hypothesis was that
populations of widely distributed
species that exhibit both genetic and
geographical structure originated from
two or more glacial
refugia so to collect the specimens uh
we went to these areas in in in Northern
Canada uh us standardized Protocols of
sampling on each side and or thing
collected in four sites per echor region
that they were the Boreal the subarctic
Antarctic to cover East and West
Canada for the specimen identification I
use a co1 barcode approach which is
which is a very simple but efficient
method to obtain a reliable genetic
identification of
species all the sequences were
contrasted in the Gin bank and Bol and
that database to obtain their
identification and then used to
construct the philogenetic Trees of each
groups but how we can differentiate
species with genetic and Geographic
struct okay so in this example we can
see that this mayfly species shows
multiple individuals with a clear
genetic structure but not a geographical
structure while for disorder species we
observe both the genetic and
geographical structure and the
populations from Eastern Canada is
different from the population from
western
Canada okay so for the results I
generated I I obtain Bas on philogenetic
treats for each order inop Tropa and
plopa and I could identify 18 species
spread across East and West
Canada so from those uh uh species
widespread seven species show both the
generic and geographical structure as uh
this um figure is
showing and in addition um we calculated
the Divergence
time and for six species uh we observed
a similar range of Divergence signs uh
suggesting a common event that matched
with the duration of the last glal
period while for only one species that
Divergent that Divergence time was
earlier and apart from that the genetic
distance between the East and West
population of these species suggested
instead that they were two different
species and um that the classification
generate this spean event so the main
conclusions for this project were that
um I obtained evidence of the species
with genetic and geographical
structure um the Divergence time allowed
to detect the effect of the L glaciation
on aquatic insect
populations uh we found evidence of a
species occurring in different fuia
during the last glacial
period and finally I found also evidence
of ESP speciation H due to glacial
isolation so for this work I want to um
thank my supervisor D Curry all the
people in my committee uh the northern
biodiversity program and the people in
my
lab okay so now I will talk about my PhD
project at the University of Toronto but
this time with Professor Don Jackson uh
this project was called parents of a
species cooccurrence a species pairwise
approach so the great ecologist Robert
MacArthur stated that eological patterns
are only interesting if they are
repeated they might be repeated in space
or in time and they might be repeated
from species to species so as
introduction one central question in
ecology is how natural communities are
structured and among the different
approaches used to address this question
the species currence analysis have been
a prevalent subject that goes back to
the 1940s with classical studies that
analyze currence parents across multiple
communities however it was the Assembly
of a species Community by diamond in
1975 the publication that spark an still
ongoing de debate about whether natural
communities are structured by determined
rules in this publication Diamond
concluded that competition was the main
mechanism structuring be communities
which was in agreement with influential
contemporaries studies that also propos
competition as the most important
mechanisms structured in those
communities Diamond also mentioned that
competition generates the Forbidden
combination which means species that
exhibit a pattern of segregation or
negative cooccurrence one example of
this forbiding combination was observed
between two species of Coco doves which
never cooccur in the same island as as
is observed in this map so Diamond
attributed this segregated par to the
strong competition between those species
for similar
resources however Diamond's ideas were
challenged by Conor and simlo in 1979
who argued that the effect of
competition was typically assumed
instead of being properly tested and
that the community should be analyzed
entirely instead of selecting only the
species pairs that exhibit these
forbidden combinations and for this they
proposed the null model as equivalent of
the N hypothesis to test competition as
main factor in natural environment
so the species currence analysis has
been an active field since and
subsequent studies of species currence
have produced important advances in this
area like development of Robos metric or
reliable randomization methods that
allow to find evidence of nonrandom
structor in natural communities however
most of those stories have used the same
approach that consisted in analyze the
identity of the entire Community
ignoring individual species SPS
Association that can provide important
ecological information so we went from
one side to the
other so for example let's suppose that
one pair of species species one and two
exhibit at large segregation value while
another pair of species three and four
have a large a large aggregation value
but when these values are added up they
can cancel each other out producing a
new cooccurrence uh value that is non
different not different from random
hiding the actual eological relevance of
those species pairs
however if we analyze individual species
SPS we can determine which part are
aggregated segregated or randomly
Associated which increases the Insight
of the community structure and open
questions about ecologically relevant
species so general question of my my
thesis was how does our understanding of
community structor improve from the
classical approach the whole Community
to the individual species per wise
approach the objective was to test
ecological hypothesis related to
patterns of association between species
the signal of biotic interactions and
the influence of biotic and atic factors
using a species wise
approach so I divided my thesis in three
data chapters that I intend to go H
quick uh so in chapter one I assess the
community structure
consistency of Association parents and
Community assembly Theory using a
species wise approach in chapter two I
aim to determine the influence of
habitat side on the on these species
Association patterns and in chapter
three I wanted to determine the
influence of biotic factors like trait
on the species Association
parents so in the first chapter I
intended to determine whether and how
species currence pattern are structured
analyzing Fish Lake communities this
imply to determine their direction as
well as their magnitude and
consistency in addition I tested whether
ecologically Related Group of species
like compar species that share habitat
requirements or Predator PR exhibit
currence pars expected by Community
assembly
Theory so for this chapter I use the
database of the Aquatic habitat
inventory which is a program of the
Ontario Ministry of Natural Resources so
these database contain records of
incidents of 99 fish species distributed
in almost 10,000 legs
grouping 144 tary water Chase as is
shown in this map of
so in this study each water shed
represented one community that was
analyzed individually using a species
per wise not modal approach to obtain
the Cs scores which indicate the
segregation level between each spes
pairs with the obtain scores I obtain
also the standard effect sizes which
represented the cooccurrence value sorry
um and then for each species pair I
compar the standard effect sizes or the
currence levels across all the water
Shades they they occur to determine how
consistent was H or was the the pattern
that they show and in addition I
evaluated assembly hypothesis within
ecologically related groups of species
competitors prator prey and Spees with
similar habitat requirements okay so for
the first part the whole Community I
analyzed a total of 76 fish species and
I obtained the association value for 78%
of the possible species paars in this
figure the values of a standard
effect size on the right side indicates
a consistent segregated pattern or Spees
that that Cur less than expected by
Chance the values on the left side
indicate a consistent aggregated pn or
species that Cur more than expected by
chain and for species pairs with
confidence intervals Crossing zero the
par was considered not different from
random so overall I detected consistent
Association parents in 48% of the total
observed species pairs of which 27% were
consistently segregated and 21% were
consistently aggregated so in the second
part the hypothesis of community
assembly predicts Association pards
expected for group of species
biologically related so among the
processes expected to lead to
segregation pars I focus on competition
and predation for example it is
suspected that closely related species
that compete stronger for similar
resources exceeding a consistent pattern
of segregation however if the
association pattern is not consistent or
is consistently aggregated Instead This
Could indicate that competition is not
strong or other processes are more
relevant the same consistent segregated
pattern is also expected for predator PR
species when predation is strong however
other factors might also contribute uh
to segregation pars like habital
filtering or different Geographic
Orin and among the fact lead into
aggregation Parn I focus on the share
habitat
requirements so I analyze the
association pars within the centrar
family which is composed by bases and
Sunfish Sun fishes sorry H the members
of these families are predators and Ur
in similar habitats which according to
assembly Theory should generate a
pattern of segregation due to strong
competition for similar resources but
instead the results of the analysis
between the small modb and other species
of this family show consistent
aggregation parents and the same parent
was observed between the other members
of this family which suggest that
competition is not strong enough to
generate segregation at this
scale now for the species with similar
habitat preferences I analyze the
association pars of fish that require
cold water and the results show the
expected um consistent pars of
aggregation indicating the strong effect
of this mechanism on this group
last I analyzed the cooccurrence pars
between pre species like Minos and top
predators of these systems like buses
and Northern Pike and I detected a
consistent segregated pattern between
each prey and pror so this analysis H in
addition allowed me to determine what
prey was more segregated by the
Predators and we can observe that the
stronger effect was observed on the
northern red valy days and besides I
could detect also which of the top
predators gen
the strong segregation effect on the
praise which was the northern
pike so the conclusion for chapter one
were that the species per wise approach
provides an assessment of the overall
community and allows testing a specific
patterns on their ecological relevance
this is because by pulling all the
currence values as in the classical
whole Community approach H result in a
strong negative and a strong positive
relationship canceling each other out
with the wrong conclusion that the
community is a structor not different
from
random uh also species currence analysis
can produce robust information about
observe patterns that are repeated
across multiple independent units in in
our case where they waterers sheds in
large scale Geographic
areas and finally at the scale
considerer in this study I found
evidence supporting predation and
habitat preference as a stronger
mechanisms in structuring fish
communities than
competition okay
so moving to chapter two here I wanted
to determine the influence of habitat
size on the coor SPs so among the
environmental factors area and
specifically the species area
relationship has been considered one of
the few laws in ecology and it has been
one of the longest analyzed and most
frequently demonstrated in nature so
here we see a classic example of this
Parn detected by MacArthur and Wilson on
Caribbean island where the richness of
amphibians sound reptiles increases with
Island
area studies evaluating the influence of
area on a specific rich on a species
richness has also been applied to Lakes
this is because Lakes are considered
analogous ecosystem to Ireland due to
First the clear area delimitation as is
observed in islands in the bismar
archipelago or lakes in
Ontario and second elevation in island
in Islands uh is related to Habitat
diversity which allows for example in
Plants the establishment of different
communities along an altitudinal
gradient this factor is analogous to
depth in Lakes which generates habitats
with different characteristics that
allow different type of communities so
area and depth influence the
distribution and richness of species and
has been um um tested several times
however it is still not clear how these
factors can influence the Cur par in
fish
communities so the general goal of this
chapter was to determine whether and
how a bior factors related to Habitat
sitze like Lake area or dep influence
the species currence
pars so to determine the effect of uh
habitat sites on species currence I
group adjacent ter water sheds with
similar species composition in two
different regions in Ontario this allow
me to increase the number of flakes to
gain more statistical power because we
analyze more than 1100 Lakes per region
is still controlling for biogeographic
influences so um I will skip the methods
here and we can talk later about them
but basically I use our randomization
test to determine significance between H
Lake area and depth categories and
individual species per currence
values so in the second part I wanted to
evaluate the effect of area and DEP in
group of species that potentially
interact like prator preise or species
with similar habitat requirements like
cold water
fish and for this I use a met analytical
approach to determine the whole effect
between one single species with the
other species in the
group so in the results across all
species SPS I found that both factors
area and death in both regions Central
and Western exhibited highly significant
differences between the observed and
expected distribution of sensor slope
indicating a strong influence of habitat
size on the currence par now for the
group of prator prey I analyze the
currence values between each prator and
each prey and I detected significant
differences between the categories the
categories which indicate the strong
influence of Lake
Area um in this group so in this Forest
flood we can observe that the strong
negative currence effect in the smaller
Lakes okay legs like legs with less than
hectares is significantly decreases in
larger legs indicating that species
segregated in a smaller legs can Co can
coexist in larger
legs now for the group of cold species I
found no significant differences in
currence values across the death
categories however uh we can observe a
tendency for these species to be more
aggregated in deeper Lakes so in
addition we observe the lack of
Association parents in the smaller
category which indicates the strong
environmental filtering for these
species in shallower and warmer laks so
this result suggests that when Lakes
reach a minimum required dep these
species T to cooccur
positively so the main conclusions for
chapter two were that habitat size does
exert a significant influence on the
species Co
corespondence um in the group of PR or
pre species segregation effect was
reduced when area
increase and it is important to
recognize how habitat characteristics
reveal ecologically relevant information
that might be concealed when these
variables are not
considered now chapter three about the
influence of species traits on
cooccurrence parts so biotic
interactions have been recognized as
important factor structuring communities
and the magnitude of those interactions
can be related to the degree of similar
uh of similarity of species in their
traes the trade based approach have been
employed to predict community structure
by assessing whether the parents observe
can be expained by the proposed
mechanisms for example species with
similar traits are Ed to compete
stronger due to more resource overlap
than species with less similar
trait so among the species traits body
size have been recognized as major
influence on the strength of species
interaction particularly in aquatic
ecosystems as the structure of this
community can be determined by the pr
size range that a predator is capable of
consuming another important trait is the
temperature preference which has been
observed to influence the community
structure by selecting or restricting
species from various locations for
example plant communities adapted to low
Mountain Versus communities adapted to
high mountains or cold versus warm um
water fish
assemblages trophic level is another
important trade that has been used to
define the position of species in the
food chain and it can be used as well to
identify potential competitors or
species involved sorry in Predator
interactions so in this chapter I
intended to determine whether the
mentioned traits can explain the
co-parents obtain for all the species
Pairs and whether the signal of biotic
interaction can be
detected okay so I intended in this
chapter to test four hypothesis don't
worry I'm going to go uh quick about
this so the first hypothesis is that
across all the community or in general
the trade values are significantly
related to the concurrence pars across
all the species
pairs hypothesis two is for body size
and I expected a negative and
significant relationship between body
size dissimilarity and currence pars if
the signal of competition is strong this
is because species with similar body
size tend to compete stronger and
segregate each other but the segregation
level can be reduced when the
differences in body size increase
or alternatively a positive and
significant relationship if the signal
of predation is strong and this is
because species with similar different
body size tend to have a prator PR
relationship and segregate each
other uh hypothesis 3 is about
temperature preference and for this
trait I expected that species pair pairs
having more dissimilar temperature
preferences exhibit more segregated
parns due to environmental filtering
while aggregation is expected for
species with similar temperature
preferences and for hypothesis four
about tropic level very similar to body
size I expected a negative and
significant relationship between trophic
level dissimilarity and coorp parents if
the feral of competition is strong
because species with similar trophic
levels tend to compete stronger and
segregate each
other and uh the segregation level uh
can be reduced uh when differences in
trophic level increase or alternative L
A positive and significant relationship
if the signal of predation is strong
because species with different tropic
levels tend to have PR PR relationships
and segregate each
other all right again so to summarize
the methods I perform a series of
multiple regressions and permutation
tests between the concurrence values and
the trait to determine the significant
effects we can talk about this later if
you uh have some questions so the result
for hypothesis one um including all the
trait and the randomization test for all
the species pairs show significant
relationship between the currence value
with temperature preference and tropic
level but not with body
size for hypothesis 2 the result for
body size dissimilarity at currence
values shows a negative quadratic Trend
although this relationship was not
significantly H was not significant
according to the permutation test
indicating that body size dissimilarity
do not predict Val of cooccurrence
between
Spees for hypothesis 3 we observe a
positive and significant linear Trend
between temperature preference and
currence values indicating the strong
influence of environmental filtering
that means that species with larger
differences in temperature preference
tend to be
segregated and finally for hypothesis 4
I obtain a positive and significant
relationship for both the linear and the
quadratic term of trophic level and the
currence values which suggests that
species with larger differences in
trophic level tend to cooccur negatively
however um here the signal of predation
uh is observed while the signal for
competition was not clear corroborate
corroborating previous uh
results right so the main conclusion of
chapter three um I detected significant
Association pars between the predictor
and the response variables which
indicates an overall influence of the
the traits on the currence
pattern temperature preference was
highly associated with the currence
values which indicate a strong influence
influence of environmental filtering in
in the structure of these
communities trophic level was
significantly uh or significantly
influences the currence values and
species with different trophic levels
tend to segregate each other the signal
of predation was detected here but not
the signal of competition
and finally contrary to expected uh by
Theory body size was not significantly
related to the currence par and so the
this trait cannot predict interaction
between
species so in this part I want to
acknowledge I want to thank my
supervisor Don Jackson and the members
of my committee and all the people from
Jackson lab and yeah like all the people
that made possible this
journey and last I present the current
project that I'm working on as a
postdoctoral researcher at the DFO
Department of fisheries and oceans
Canada about the effect of shellfish
agriculture industry on SO planton size
distribution in several Coastal ements
in Canada here Ruben would you like to
take a question about the last section
or would you like to keep them for the
yes if um I don't
know uh so we have a question from irn
jungar uh if competition wasn't a big
factor why did competing species
consistently aggregate rather than just
being
random I mean we need we need to
understand that I am analyzing at the
level of the lake right within the legs
there are many habitats that they can
they can uh where competition can be
important we we need like a more
experimental and this experiments have
been performed for like a years showing
that competition is very important but
at this level competition doesn't show
didn't show like a clear signal while
predation did so that's that's the main
difference it's not that competition is
not acting it's not acting at the the
level that I um
analyze does it make
sense yeah I believe so I didn't have a
followup or I didn't see a follow-up
question okay we can we can talk about a
little bit later but yeah sure that's
that's the main reason it's just the
skill that that I was
analyzing so um again so the shellfish
aquaculture in Canada um is an industry
that has experienced substantial growth
in the since the 1970s and today is a
Threading industry producing millions of
metric tons of food meeting not only
domestic but International demand and
expanding across coastal zones
highlighting is its economic importance
however as this industry spans the focus
of ecological he studies has
increasingly shifted toward
understanding of the interaction of this
activity with surrounding habitats
specifically analyzing the effect of
higher on higher trophic levels and
local clonic
communities so shellfish uh feed mainly
on plantonic organisms and the high
density of shellfish produced by the
aquaculture activity generates different
effects on the local activ local habitat
and organisms one major effect is the
greasing pressure generated by the
shellfish on higher trophic levels for
example experimental studies found a
significant effect of the shelfish
density on the development of lobster
laral stages and because the strong
competition excerted by shellfish on the
microp planton resource lur lar exposed
to higher shellfish density exhibited
lower development and
survival but how is the plantonic
community structur so basically the plon
is composed by two main groups the
phytop planton and the S planton phytop
planton is composed by the primary
producers the organisms transforming and
storing the solar energy accounting for
most of the smaller size fractions like
the Pico and nanop planton and a studies
that analyze impact of shellfish grazing
pressure on this group observe that the
smaller phop planton fractions that
cannot be filtered by shellfish exhibit
an increment in abundance compared to
the larger H fractions more intensely
Gra
the other group is the so planton and
these organisms are the main component
of the larger size fraction of planton
like the mesos planton which is the
focus group of this study so let's
briefly review the importance of this
group the mesop planton fraction has two
main key characteristics that makes it
an interesting study system first it
plays a fundamental role in Marine
ecosystem by acting as a critical trophy
lean facilitating the energy transfer
from the primary producers or phop
planton to higher levels that includes
um or Bol and other Fisheries Target the
species and second so plant exhibit a
high degree of environmental sensitivity
due to their physiological adaptations
and life history strategies making them
highly responsive to variation of
environment conditions like temperature
salinity and nutrient concentrations so
given these attributes many
researchers have advocated for the
establishment of enhanced monitoring
programs to facilitate the early
detection of ecological impacts
especially in our current scenario of
climate
change but although several large scale
programs have been established to
monitor long-term changes in Marine
health there is still a scarcity of
monitoring program specifically designed
to track the continuous effect of
aquaculture on plantonic communities so
this motivated the initiative of the
aquaculture monitoring program by the
DFO which aims to track H and analyze
changes in the structure of plan plon
communities to develop strategies and
conservation
policies so we have seen that the mesop
planton plays a key ecolog ecological
role as linked between primary producers
and higher trophic levels and is highly
responsive to environmental changes as
well we know that shellfish aquaculture
has a range of effects on these
plantonic communities and although these
effects have been evidenced by
theoretical and experimental analysis
still significant gaps remain
specifically concerned in the long-term
consequences of this interaction in
natural environments both within and
Beyond Bay scale
context so then the goal of the
aquaculture monitoring program is focus
on the long-term sustainability of the
shellfish aquaculture industry the
general objective uh of the is to track
changes in the coastal ecosystem by
absorbing alteration in the structure of
supp planton communities in presence of
shellfish Agriculture and provide
managers with robust and reliable data
to make more effective conservation
policies specifically we focus on
determining the level of variation in
the mesos planton size structor
generated by three factors the station
or location within the bay which is
related to the morphological
characteristics of each Bay tie level
which is related to the replacement of
Grace individuals by by water exchange
and the day of sampling which is
associated with a stasic events like
rain or wind in addition uh we also aim
to determine the seasonal variation
pattern in the mop planton side fraction
by comparing monthly samples associated
with the local water temperature
gate so to address this objective the
team collected planton samples in
different Bays with presence of
shellfish aquaculture across several
regions um including Newland the
maritimes Gulf of of Stan Lawrence and
the Pacific as is observing the map at
each Bay the goal was to sample in three
different locations or stations for
three consecu days and each day there
was one sampling during high tide and
another sampling during low tide so
these samplings were collected during
the Summers of 2020 and 2021 and in
addition H monthly samples were obtained
at TH arm Bay in Newland from June 20 uh
2021 to July
2022 after the samples were obtained and
preserved uh we used the microflow C
methodology which generates a measure
microscopic individual images to obtain
18 parameters
related to body size for each collected
individual so we selected the biovolume
prolate esid we're going to call it
biovolume because this parameter
accounts for the organism's shapes and
and surface area in relation to its
volume and for comparative Purpose with
reason
studies so the team aimed to collect and
analyze planton individual which sizes
about 30 micrometers but for this
analysis I include only the individuals
of the largest fraction size between
250 and 2
mm
okay so in the results uh we obtain more
than 500,000 individuals bi volume
values across the stud base and we
generated this viol flot to visually
detect differences in the bio bi volume
distribution of mesop planton across the
different base this figure um shows uh
the different size distribution across
the analyz base indicating that Bas are
not homogeneous in their so planton size
structure so to quantify the by volume
variation we obtain the cumulative
frequency distribution of each samples
and they were compared perir wise to
calculate the maximum variation between
those samples associated with the
analyze factors for example this figure
shows two cumulative frequencies from
two
samplings H comparing the effects of
Tide so one sampling was made in high
tide and the other one made in low tide
and we compare that and exhibit low
variation and we quantify that Vari by
calculating the maximum distance using
AOG test which in this case shows about
7% of variation between these samples
indicating a low effect of type while
for these two samples in the right we
see a greater maximum distance of 35%
between those samples indicating a
greater effect of these factors then the
maximum distance from all the
comparisons related to each factor TI
day and station were pulled to obtain
the Vari generated by each factor at
each
Bay so here we can see the result for
the station effect and in general we
observe a low bio volume variation
across the base with exception of some
pets where the variation between the
stations show shows a median of 23%
indicating a potential effect of this
factor in this
Bay similar results were observe for the
tide effect with low values of variation
detected for most Bay as well we can see
here the higher variation in s Peters
Bay with around 16% but still indicating
a weak effect of this factor in the B
volume
variation and the factor day shows
similar results than the previous Factor
but the variation level Associated to
this Factor was much larger for some
Peters than the other base with around
35% of variation When comparing samples
from different
days finally we pull together all the
variation from the three Factor and we
observe the overall small V volume
variation across the compare base as
well with some Peters showing the
largest overall variation a potential
explanation to this variation in some
Peters might be related to the higher
proportion of area used for shelish
aquaculture in this Bay which is around
40% of leas coverage compared to the
other Bays however we are still H
testing this
hypothesis so now we focus on some
Peters which is the B with higher
variation and we determine the amount of
variation H between the the categories
of each factor and this figure shows
that the factor day for example the
higher variation was observed between
day one with days two and three and for
the for the factor station uh the
largest variation the largest
differences were observed between the
outer station with the mid and the inner
stations and the level of variation due
to TI effect was lower than the other
Factor
so we also generated this nmds which is
a nonmetric multi-dimensional scaling uh
it's an ordination plot and this plot
allows us to see um a separated group of
samples from the other Station group by
the red Dash um ellipse apart from the
other stations and also we observe and
the green ellipse the samples from day
one group apart from the other uh days
now we wanted to test the significant uh
Factor effects and for this we perform
linear mix effect models comparing three
quantiles of each sample distribution
with station and Tide as the fix effect
and they consider as the random effects
so the results show significant
differences for the station across the
three quantities between the outer and
the middle stations and between the
outer and inner station we observe
significant differences at the larger
biolume conle
for the random effect day the model um
results show highly significant
differences across the three quanti
indicating a strong effect of this
Factor representing stochastic events
the factor tide and its interaction with
the station show no
significance so finally to determine the
seasonal effect we analyze H monthly
samples collected between June 2021 and
in July
2022 and we obtain the bio volume
fraction distribution for 13 months and
as expected we observe significant
differences in the fraction distribution
across across different months so in
general we can see AB sortal par where
the largest V volume media values were
associated to the colder
months um the temperature Trend can be
tracked with the red uh dash line and
the temperature values in the right ya
AIS and finally our regression analysis
between the medium biolume and the mean
temperature show a negative significant
relationship supporting this
part so the main
conclusions um of this work are that in
general we observe a low variation in
the v volume fractions distribution
between samples related to the factors
analyzed with a higher or like an
exception observed in some
pets contrary to expected the factor day
of sampling which we thought that it was
not like important related to EST
stochastic events show more variation
than the type level or the
station the higher variation observed in
some Peters might be potentially related
to the more intense shelfish aquaculture
develop in this
vein the seasonal pattern showed that
colder months exhibit greater abundance
of larger mesop planton individuals and
as a general conclusion long-term
monitoring programs are fundamental to
track changes in the size fraction
structor of plantonic communities which
is the foot of the shellfish industry to
ensure the sustainability of this
growing and necessary activity so with
this I want to thank the P of this
project uh also the members of the F lab
here at the housei University to all the
members and collaborators of the team
again thank you uh to Anam Maria and
Ricardo for this opportunity and thank
you all for your attention and I'll be
happy to take any
questions awesome so thank you very much
Ruben so first thing is that we have a
short survey so if you can please fill
out the survey because your feedback is
very valuable and we're gonna open the
Flor question so Irwin also had another
question but why aggregate rather than
being random or negative and that was
from the end of the first section I
don't know Russell can we get Irwin on a
mic maybe he wants to have more of a
discussion up to Irwin but if you can
start by answering the question and IR
Irwin can let us
oh there he is
yeah uh hello can you hear me yes yeah
I'm referring to a slide that was right
at the end of the first section where
you showed the competing species uh
tending to aggregate this ones I can't
see your slides sorry oh sorry
yeah right so if the species were were
okay competing the original hypothesis
was that they would segregate and I
understand you said that at this at the
level you're looking that was not strong
enough to
detect but if that's so I guess I would
expect that what you'd see is sort of
random whereas what you're seeing is
consistent aggregation rather than
neither so why are they consistently
aggregating well they they are still
like a all these species they share uh
similar habitat requirements so um in
the paper where we connected these ideas
to like saying that this is this uh
factor is was stronger than competition
organizing the the structure of these
communities at this level right okay so
again so again so if we if we go deep
inside the lake we are going to see that
areas uh where like a I don't know the
small M BS is is the largest of these
interets were like a present like in
like around that area in the lake L
within the lake uh there is not going to
be any other in tret especially the
small ones but we are like just checking
the present substance across in the
entire
Lake that's that's that's the the main
reason why um competition was not
observed the
signal okay thank
you yeah so please feel free to post
questions so I had a question actually
so in your first section you said
there's like a 8% difference between the
species is that like what is um like how
do you measure is there a cut off for
species Divergence or um according to
the co1 papers since the beginning they
they the their agreement was like around
2% and that's based using like a
molecular and also morphological data so
when when when a species is about four
or 5% is considered to different species
populations show that amount of genetic
Divergence they are considered to live
species so in our case we observe like
all the species were below that uh
threshold uh
here here for example this species is
less than
two or like around two this is way less
than one but here we can observe the
that the genetic distance is 3 + 4
that's almost 8% so so yeah that that
started to to uh indicate possibly it's
two different species and the speciation
event was because they were separated in
the beringia and the southern planes
F so it's um have you seen indication of
not just like geographical distribution
that changes speciation but maybe like
they go to different like niches
ecological niches
that was I mean like I'm pretty sure
that there should be like a evidence for
that but that I I didn't I didn't delve
into into that part we're just focusing
on this big scill and and have you seen
a lot of molecular changes without many
like um morphological changes or is it
both have to be in coincidence to Define
a species I mean like this this species
is still consider one species in North
America so I don't I don't know if like
if there is like a
taxonomies this group I invited to to
dig into this part because it's very
interesting how um these PES they look
similar they they they are occurring
similar habitat so is is the differences
are not uh I'm not very clear so yeah
yeah so uh I just going to ask one more
time if anyone else has questions please
feel free to ask um otherwise we're
coming up against the
hour so once again I'd like to thank
Ruben for doing this talk for us we had
a lot of interest from a lot of
different types of people at the bro
which is really cool so we had uh you
know some people who were super
interested in evolution so that was
great so thanks again and beend
it thank you everyone