our third and final company presenting
is Butler Butler is offering iot
intelligence for indoor movement and
well-being uh Butler is an MIT media lab
spin out and so introducing CEO and
co-founder for Butler hunga Deng hunga
Deng is an award-winning innovator and
computational designer and created the
field of responsive context aware AG um
architecture among his many
accomplishments and experiences HHA is a
former researcher at City Science group
MIT media lab welcoming now hunga to
speak on
Butler thank you so much for inviting me
I'm H co-founder and CEO of Butler my
background is boosting architecture and
computer science I have my degree at
Harvard University for computational
design as SP the company off MIT media
lab 2019 on L with my labmate at the
media lab City Science group so since
buing isar Brad and but it's my pleasure
to introduce what we bu here at
berer our mission is to build the worst
most scalable privacy friendly people
sensoring platform transforming how
spaces responds to people so it's this
tiny wireless sensor insto in second
helping business to make smarter
decisions from improving operational
efficiency into life-saving use
cases with SP the company off on media
lab 2019 the slce used to be two rows of
PhD from both MIT and Berkeley I call
the complete nerdy marriage of the
technology we launched our V1 sensor in
2022 so three years in we become a c
leader in the smart building occuping
sensing space particularly in workplace
and we are emerging to be the leader in
house care selling
too so now it's definitely a little bit
bigger group than just my labmates we're
strong team of 60 plus teammates and
have offices in San Francisco Boston and
Tokyo bottom right and we deploy our
sensor globally uh in the past few years
we already deploy 207 sensors covering
40 million square feet for largest
Enterprises in the world you might can
recognize from the picture here some of
the top Fortune 50 campuses and we have
recently complete our first full campus
implantation for Senor living in Sweden
hamsa City for to buildings today my
presentation will cover both office use
cases and Senior Living use cases in the
smart Ming smart cities
environment so in the past decades it
have only been two type of sensor detect
people scale well in the CI and cities
and also buildings once the motion
sensor on the right it does not really
sense people any Movement Like a puppy
like tricker or during night time in the
building it turn the lights off and
leave you in the dark with the move and
you have to make a dance like this to
turn lights on and other accurate
alternative is camera on the left but
camera intrude people's privacy so no
one wants a future where camera camera
fly
everywhere so we design something right
set in between it has accuracy of a
camera but without privacy sensitive
information they also F out the puppy
we're the first and only sensors that
can only use surface temperature to
sense people's location body posture in
real time and wireless with multiple
years of battery life it's really not
eyes it's a nerve cells that that feels
the use of the space and understand what
users
need so the version of fut I believe in
with AI is spatial intelligence
buildings is the world's largest user
interface with six actually 7 billion da
active users now and finally reach their
potential with Anonymous user data we
provided we capture over 1 billion data
frame daily with with just 207 sensors
so this is just a tiny drop of water to
transer bons of square feet of a space
into of the word into space that can
understand individual needs from space
efficiency use cases to life saving use
cases
so our first Fe market like I mentioned
is office based this UI is a littleit
old but data is very representative
workplace managers never know there are
hundreds of leads being used through the
badge data this was a public company San
Francisco office and the global warpless
manager in Canada was very proud of
office design from The Bash data they
design for 25 people and there's 25 bass
STP every day so she was very proud of
it until she install Butler and find out
what actually happened so they do their
morning stand up and then they have
lunch and at 1: p.m. people EMP the
office so they were just there for the
free
launch that's the crew reality so the
real estate team is a small team that
makes hundreds of lead decision two
people team as a public company probably
manage 50 to 200 Lees they really need
the visibility into the this data this
data otherwise they might just end up
with 10% which is potenti
at minimum four to five leas people just
came in for free food and completely
wasted um off the space uh and this is a
few million dollars of the leads at list
um and Senior Living side might be
certain rooms that never got enough
resources and that's not just money but
people's
life so you can manage those data and
also see through like stock ticker you
can also
take the data we provided and then use
our AI Prof platform to suggest new
design based on the sensor data of the
office usage you can see even the colors
matching here off the rendering uh AI
suggested so we have buil many
integration for building controls from
Smart cleaning also to awag um to life
saving nurse cost system and many of the
building automations can lead to carbon
reductions
so in loving side of use case besides
body posture and location recognition
fall detection the most important thing
actually fall prevention is the biggest
uh value add so in this deployment each
room is covered with three sensors to
understand patient
movement an alert nurse when they're all
of bad in night time and no Motion in
the daytime so this is more of near real
time prevention features so you have a
few second to a minute to detect and
respond and prevent a a potential
incident we also can do daily analytics
number of time going to the toilet to
get to guide and diagnose unary tract
infections UTI which is a top emergency
in senior living and also lead to
reduction of fall if provided uh a
prevention early prevention to prevent
the UTI so you can see this specific
room have increasing visit off the
toilet you can also summarize Daily
Report through our customiz GPT using
our sensor data instead of manual
logging so one day when you're walking
into any buildings when you look up you
sort of see
berer that's all
my thank you so much appreciate it and
fantastic really interesting stuff
you're doing um you mentioned it briefly
um but would love to dive into it since
we have the time what the sustainability
benefit of the sensors
are so as I mentioned there's like a
dozens of integration we do with our
sensor data from what you're just seeing
a little bit the ACTA control from
number of users in the building to drive
like um turning on and off atra um this
wasn't a thing that could be done from
traditional motion sensor CU you cannot
wave a hand and control and turn on the
full rooftop machine so you have to Bas
on the trends of people which is the
definite number of people using the
space right and you cannot use like air
quality because it's aftermath usually
it's already like really high CO2 and
then like crank it up and it's not part
efficient at all so that's just one use
case we also have like smart cleaning if
you nobody is using um the the toilet uh
there's both spectr sometime in the in
the airport you see really really dirty
like toilet right you see those tablet
you have to like say really really
unhappy with that and someone came in
but like through like usage data you can
also Drive smart cleaning automatically
and in a lot of cases nobody was using
it and then they were regular cleaning
this is also operational efficiency uh
Improvement and also operation cabin U
reduction in terms of operating the
buildings and then respectively uh so
from
utilizing just the sensor data for Real
Estate footprint planning you can reduce
use um six tens of CO2 per employee to
roughly like a 2 uh 2.51 like which I
just showed just now and then like from
at control we can reduce another 0.3
tens of CO2 per employee we have a paper
around it and also one a word like uh
was uh in the recent competition from
word economic Forum in San Francisco wow
well congratulations for that and I can
definitely see how the recog was well
deserved um well thank you hunga really
appreciate you joining us today and to
all the companies that presented um as
part of MIT startup lightning talks
today now I'd like to turn it back to
our fearless leader throughout and my
colleague Graham wrong who will close us
out today for this webinar with his
final remarks