why MIT son's andan capson project is a
Perfect final assignment according to
students it's a fun learning stud you
learn a lot of new stuff in a very short
span of time you learn how to deal with
business problems develop soft skills
and you're also learning so many new
technical Concepts in applying them to
real world scenarios it's a great
opportunity to put your hands on the
real world problems and the real world
challenges that comes when applying dat
science you get to work with the company
talking with different teams and getting
to know the core business value that we
will be generating through our project
yeah it was a very good experience