[CROWD CHEERING]
SANJAY SARMA: I can't
think of a single person
to have impacted the
field of robotics
in design, in undergraduate
education, as much as Woodie.
WOODIE FLOWERS: The real
danger isn't this thing.
ELY SACHS: Woodie
truly was a visionary
in the field of education
and also many aspects
of what it means to be human.
MEGAN SMITH: So he
always instilled
this wonderful sense of kindness
and community and collaboration.
WARREN SEERING: There
was really only one thing
that mattered to him.
It was all about the
students and what they should
get from the MIT experience.
He lived for that.
DAVID GOSSARD: Woodie was no
stranger to simply building
things from scratch.
To him, that's what engineering
was or what it should be.
So as soon as he was given
a course, his view was,
I'm not going to be
making them do drawings.
I'm going to-- they're going
to build something, by gum.
SANJAY SARMA: When MIT
was established in 1861,
it was designed as a
technical university.
And over the years lectures have
displaced the hands-on stuff.
And Woodie brought it back.
WOODIE FLOWERS: The
thing we have to do today
is get the task over--
DAVID GOSSARD: He took
over a course, 270,
at the time deadly dull.
Their idea of design
at the time was
to draw drawings of
parts of designs.
Woodie had a different idea.
WOODIE FLOWERS: Ready?
Get set!
Go!
[CROWD GROANS]
DAVID GOSSARD: It
was a terrific idea,
which was to give
the entire class, 100
students, a kit of materials,
a common goal, which
was to build a machine to climb
a hill or pick up golf balls
or whatever it did, and
make a contest out of it.
DAVID WALLACE: He
really thought,
let's think of this almost
like a sporting event.
And so we do this competition,
and we're competing.
But it's this joyful thing that
everyone wants to be a part of.
[CROWD CHEERS]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID GOSSARD: It was
a phenomenal success.
The kids loved it.
The faculty loved it.
The Institute loved it.
And over a period
of years, it became
I think it's fair to
say, an institution.
WOODIE FLOWERS: This is an
interesting circumstance.
MARIA YANG: It's hard to
understate how important he
was because there was a long
period of time in engineering
education where
everything was much more
physics and theory-focused,
and he made it practical.
KRISZTINA HOLLY: He
created these environments
and these circumstances where
the students would succeed.
NEIL PAPPALARDO: He represented
one of the very first faculty
at MIT who focused on teaching
kids to design products,
to design processes that
had never been made before.
SANJAY SARMA: You know, other
schools had heard of this
amazing contest
in the early '90s.
And they all tried to do it,
but there was something missing.
There's some magic missing.
And they found out afterwards
the magic was Woodie.
MEGAN SMITH: He innovated
on innovation itself.
And--
--you learn so much about
just how to design things.
I mean, you know--
you know everything.
And you just learn all that
kind of stuff that's going to be
awesome for when we're--
when we're real engineers
in the field.
DAVID WALLACE: And so
he really brought it
together as this iconic entity.
And then ultimately
that idea, that model,
has been adopted by Hearst.
DAVID GOSSARD: Between
Woodie and Dean,
Dean Kamen, a very prominent
and important inventor,
there emerged this idea.
Why don't we do what you're
doing at MIT for high schools
all over the state or
all over the world?
And lo and behold,
FIRST Robotics was born.
KRISZTINA HOLLY: The
impact has scaled,
has just replicated across the
country and around the globe.
WOODIE FLOWERS: Learn to compete
like crazy while treating others
with empathy and respect.
KRISZTINA HOLLY: He came
up with this term "gracious
professionalism."
And we can't always
win all the time,
but we can always be
gracious professionals,
how we act as human beings, and
how we relate to each other.
And that's really
what Woodie taught me.
ELY SACHS: He fought.
He went against the grain.
He took risks to make his
type of teaching real.
WARREN SEERING: He
worried about the future.
And he wondered what he
could do to make it better.
DAVID WALLACE: And so it was
never "we've got it solved."
We can always do better.
WARREN SEERING: He was the role
model for all of us at that time
because he was "the dude."
He was the one that
we all looked up
to and tried to emulate.
DAVID GOSSARD: He
impacted everyone's life.
He was a force of nature.
He was larger than life.
And yeah, I miss him.
DAVID WALLACE: I'd
like to say thank you.
You helped form me as a
person and my own path.
For sure, I miss Woodie.
DAVID GOSSARD: He
revealed unambiguously
that design, building
things, was fun.
It was arguably the
essence of engineering.
There was joy in it.
[CROWDS CHEERING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]