so that will wrap up our program but
before we adjourn just one more thank
you to our sponsors CP group true
digital Sam Cement Group Bangkok Bank
bapon and much appreciation to Dr tarret
Mr joke from True digital for their
terrific support and to mrwan Lee from
MIT corporate relations for his hard
work and guidance and with that it's
time for everybody to enjoy the
networking reception outside I hope
you'll enjoy the refreshments have some
good conversation with the program
participants and colleagues and on
behalf of MIT corporate relations and
its industrial liazon program it has
been an honor to host the program today
capping off 25 years of my association
with our friends here in Thailand thank
you
[Applause]
what