we have seen I would say three sets of
tools applied to the problem of
projection theory. So at the beginning
of the class first we talked about like
double counting and then we talked about
methods from 4A analysis and then in the
last week we started our our third set
of tools which are tools from
combinatorial number theory. Um so um so
this week we're going to finish our unit
on tools from combinatorial number
theory and projection theory.
Okay. So uh the the goal for these two
weeks
is this projection theorem of banan cats
and tao and it takes place over finite
fields and the cool thing about it is
that it distinguishes what's true over
prime fields from what's true over other
fields which none of our previous
methods could could distinguish.
Okay,
so this is our goal
says that if x is a subset of fp^ 2 and
it has size p to the sx, you can think
of sx sort of like a dimension and sx is
in between zero and two. So it's not too
tiny and it's not everything. And we
have a set of directions in FP.
set of directions has size P to the SD
and it's not too tiny.
um then if I take the maximum over all
of the directions of the size of the
projection in that direction so at least
um so the square root of x that so far
that's not difficult to do um but then
plus times a little bit more time p to
the epsilon I'll call it epsilon p to
the epsilon so this epsilon
depends on these dimensions but it's
positive
Okay, so that's our goal and it's
significant
that this would not be true in other
fields. So this is false
in um f q^2
if q= p^2.
Um and the example is
that x is fp^2 and d is fp.
And so then this thing is always fp.
Okay,
cool. So, even though this epsilon is a
really tiny number, which we could make
explicit if we worked hard, but we would
then be disappointed. Uh, even though
it's really tiny, um, this theorem is
qualitatively an important improvement
and it it has lots of applications. This
and the version overr have lots of
applications and almost everything in
the rest of the course would will be
based on that kind of whatever most of
the directions we might go in.
Okay.
All right.
So last week we introduced combinatorial
number theory and sum product theory and
we proved a theorem which is in this
direction.
It's kind of the special case when x
happens to be a product set a cross a.
So our theorem one was last time if A is
in FP
and the size of A is P to the S A
and D is a set of directions in FP.
Uh and size of D is P to the SD.
Um then if you take the maximum t
of a + t * a which would be like pi subt
of a cross a then that's at least um the
size of a * p to the epsilon 1
that's a little bit bigger and this
again would be false in other fields. So
if if if our field had a sub field, you
could choose these guys to both be the
sub field and this would stay in the sub
field.
Okay, cool.
All right, so uh our goal today is to
get from here to there.
And we were talking about it last time
and I wanted to So at first this looks
like a very special case. Um I'll try to
argue that it's only a little bit
special case and we'll see what what the
issue is.
Okay.
Um, so let me call this an attempt
at BKT
using uh theorem one.
Okay. So we're going to do a proof by
contradiction.
We're going to say epsilon is very small
and it's to be decided.
And so then we'll assume
that pi t of x is less than x * p to the
epsilon for all the t's in d. So proof
by contradiction. So we can assume that
um and also without loss of generality
we can suppose that zero and infinity
are in our set of directions d. So in
other words we include the horizontal
projection and the vertical projection.
So then we can make a set a so that a *
a contains x and x is most of a * a. So
the set A is pi 0 of X union pi infinity
of X or the size of A bounded by size of
X to the half * P to the epsilon
and and X is contained in A * A.
Okay.
[Applause]
So x is a big subset of a product and we
can apply theorem one to our product.
[Applause]
So theorem one tells us that the maximum
t and d of pi t of a * a is big
[Applause]
and even bigger than that. So it's this
is this could be epsilon 1. Um and
epsilon 1 is much bigger than epsilon.
So epsilon one came from a theorem
that's already proven. It's some number
and we get to choose epsilon as small as
we like. So we choose it much smaller
than epsilon.
Okay.
But this is not yet the
projection theorem that we're aiming
for. And the issue is
we would like pi t of x to be big.
So the issue is maybe pi t of x
is much smaller than pi t of a cross a
even though x is is a big chunk of a
cross a.
Let me make a picture of this enemy
scenario.
So here's the end of the scenario.
[Applause]
All right.
So there's a set X
which has a small projection.
So we're going to be doing a projection
say in this direction.
projection at x is small.
[Applause]
Okay. And x is a big portion of this
larger set a cross a.
So in blue we have a cross ax.
And when we project that down, then we
see
a lot of stuff.
Pi t a cross a without x. So we're
worried that we may be so unlucky that
even though pi t of a cross a is quite
large and even though x is a big chunk
of a cross a, nevertheless pi t of x is
small. We're worried about that.
Okay, so that's where we left off before
vacation.
And now what I'd like everyone to do is
to try to think of an example where this
happens. Does this ever actually happen
that inside of a cross a you have a
large subset x and the projection of x
is small even though the projection of a
cross a is big?
Can you think of an example where that
actually happens?
>> Yeah,
>> you could choose X to be like a
diagonal.
So like all the values like guess I I is
in FP,
>> right? Okay. So,
so here's an example. So X, so X is
going to be contained in A cross A. X is
the set of all A comma A
and A cross A. And so then if I take the
projection
um I guess in the direction minus one of
X I just get zero. A minus A is always
zero. So this is extremely small. Um
okay but in this case this X is quite a
bit smaller than the whole A cross A.
So let me make a more pre uh precise
question. Um
so let's say a has size n
and x is a subset of a cross a and it's
really quite big. So I'm going to say x
is bigger than well we're going to call
it for now k inverse time n^2. Um but
then maybe k is order of n to the 1
over,000.
So it's really a big portion of a cross
a
and
pi t of x is like way smaller
than pi t.
We could make that more precise too if
we wanted to.
And that that's the situation we have in
our attempt, right?
A is only a bit bigger than X. And so
um let's say the size of A is N. It's
just the definition of N. And then X
would be bigger than like P to the minus
a few epsilon
size of A plus. So it's really a a good
portion of that.
Okay.
Right. So, could it still happen that
the size of the projection of X is way
smaller than the size of the projection
of the whole thing?
>> Like can you like pigeon hole principles
like the fibers of the projection cross?
>> Yeah.
And that like if X is big enough, you
know, it has to be at least
some nice number of those,
>> right? So the suggestion is we can look
at all of the fibers of the projection
of A cross A and then we should pick X
to be the union of of the big fibers.
Yeah. Yeah, that's right. That's right.
So in this enemy scenario, there have to
be some very big fibers and some much
smaller fibers. They have to be kind of
different from each other.
Yeah.
Um Okay. But let's see if we can think
of an example where this happens.
That should erase
some space.
Okay. So, um I just going to continue
below the line here.
Okay. So first of all, can we even think
of an example where the projection of of
X or something would be small at all? Um
so so an example um maybe X could be the
numbers from one up to N cross the
numbers from one up to N
and then pi 1 of X is pretty small
would be basically introduced from one
up to 2N.
So this would be quite small.
Okay.
Um,
so you could make you could make this a
so x would be all of a cross a. Then the
projection of a cross a would be small.
But you could also inflate a to make it
bigger than that.
So we could take a to be the integers
from one up to n union a tilda.
Maybe the size of a tilda is also n but
a tilda is unstructured or random.
[Applause]
Okay. So now if I take
pi 1 of a cross a,
it's at least as big as pi 1 of a tilda
cross a tilda.
and a tilda has nothing to do with
numbers from one up to n. I could build
some set where that's big.
Okay, but pi 1 of x
is only around n.
So there could be a big gap between
these guys.
Um
but this example is not so not such a
problem for our strategy because in this
example we just should have chosen the
set A smaller. We'd like a to be we
could we could choose a as we like. We
could choose a smaller set a so that a
actually with the smaller choice of a
just these guys x would be a cross a and
then we would be happy.
Okay. So the key to the proof of uh of
banan cat's tao is a theorem from
cominator. It's called the balog sum
gowowers theorem and it says that this
example is pretty much the only way that
pi 1 of x could be much smaller than pi
1 of a cross a.
Okay.
[Applause]
All right.
This is called the balag seme gow
theorem and it's uh another of the kind
of uh central tools in the toolbox of
additive combinatorics along with the
plunicarusa inequalities that we talked
about last time. All right. So it says
if a and b are contained in an aelion
group and they have size at most n
uh and I have a subset of a cross b
which is significant.
It's a significant fraction
and the projection of this subset in
some direction is small.
So, so here I want you to imagine that K
is a lot smaller than N. So this is a
big chunk of all the pairs A and B. And
the smallest this could possibly be is
around N because if you just fix one
element of B, you'd have around N
choices for this element of A. So that
would already give you a round N here.
So this is almost as small as possible.
And then the conclusion is
it's not necessarily the case that pi t
of all of a cross b is small. We just
saw a counter example to that. But we
could find big pieces of a and b so that
the projection of the big pieces is
small. So then there exists a prime and
b prime which are subsets of a and b. A
prime and a b prime and b. So that um
I'll say x prime is defined to be a
prime cross b prime intersect x
and x prime is still a big fraction of
n^2.
So k to the minus some constant power
time n^2
and if I take pi t of a a prime a prime
cross b prime that is less than k to
some power* l.
So this is small.
So in this example here
where a was like this, this part here
would be the a prime and it would be
symmetric in the a b prime and a prime
would both be this.
Okay, take a moment to digest that
statement and see if you have questions
or comments.
Okay.
Um so we will prove this probably
starting later today but but most of it
next class. Um but for the rest of this
class we'll explore uh explore why this
is useful and in particular we'll use it
to prove the projection theorem. Okay.
Okay. Um,
[Applause]
all right. So let's do the proof
of the Borgan textile projection
theorem.
Okay. So let's say epsilon is small to
be decided. We're going to prove there's
some small epsilon where this is true.
And I'm going to write I write C less
than tilda tilda D. It means that C is
less than P to the big O of epsilon * D.
Okay.
And now we're going to do a proof by
contradiction. So we can suppose
pi t of x
is less sim less than or equal to p to
the epsilon * x to the half for all the
t and d.
Okay. Um without loss of generality I
can suppose that zero or infinity are in
my directions and I'll take a to be pi 0
of x union pi infinity of x.
And so now I know that x is a subset of
a cross a.
Um I'll say a size of a could be n and
that is tilda tilda the square root of x
up to some powers of p to the epsilon.
Okay. And uh therefore x is greater
tilda tilda n^ 2. So x is a big fraction
of all of a cross a.
Oh,
next um I choose some other t1
in D and I know that pi t1 of x is less
than tilda tilda n.
Okay.
And so when I once I know this the
bality gowowers theorem tells me that it
this comes from a product a prime a
prime cross b prime. So sarity gow
theorem says
this a prime and a b prime and b and x
prime is the part of x in this product a
prime cross b prime. So first of all, x
prime is still quite substantial and pi
t1 of a prime cross b prime is small.
And this means in other words that a
prime plus t1 b prime is small.
Okay.
And this here is
um
this information here we c uh is is is
is strong in a helpful way that's
stronger than this because here we can
use the pluna rou inequalities.
So once we know that a prime plus t1 b
prime is small then plunicar rouia
inequalities tell us that lots of other
things are small. So for example a prime
plus or minus a prime is also small. Um
if I wanted to
uh I could do a triple sum a prime plus
a prime plus a prime is also small dot
dot dot. You could do the same with B
prime.
Okay. So,
so now we have see that A prime and B
prime have a lot of structure.
Have a lot of structure. And actually,
I'll use the word symmetry.
All right.
Right. Okay.
Okay. So I actually I'll draw you a
picture in a minute of how I visualize
this and why why I use the word
symmetry.
Okay.
So next
[Applause]
so I have to make space I'm going to
erase the statement of the theorem.
We're going to try to prove that one of
the projections of x is big.
All right.
All right. So now have a lema. It says
if I have a subset y and a prime cross b
prime, the subset we're going to care
about is just x prime, but the lema is
more general. Um, okay. And um a prime
and b prime have these nice properties.
So I'll just copy these two.
So a prime + t1 b prime
is small.
A prime minus A prime is small and and Y
itself is is is fairly large
although I don't need to write it in the
statement.
Um then
pi t of y so this is for any t so t is
just anybody in fp different from t1.
This guy is bigger than tilda tilda
y / n^2
times pi in a different direction
t over t1
of a prime cross a prime.
Right? So we have a
the biggest y could be is it could be
have size around n squ in which case
this would disappear.
And so I say if we have a large subset
of a prime cross b prime then the
projection of that large subset y is
bigger than the projection in a related
angle of a whole product a prime cross a
prime. This is good for us because we
can apply theorem one to this.
Um and um this is
uh this inequality kind kind of ruling
out the enemy scenario. We're ruling out
the possibility that there's a big chunk
of a prime cross b prime that got
compressed even though the whole thing
didn't.
Okay, let me put over here some uh
intuition.
So my intuition is
that a prime cross b prime is very
symmetric.
And so let me draw an exaggerated
version. Suppose that a prime cross b
prime just looked like a lattice.
Okay.
And inside of there we have some
substantial but kind of unstructured set
Y.
All right.
So if there were some angle where the
projection of Y got compressed a lot. I
claim that compression of the the whole
lattice should get compressed a lot.
Why? Because the lattice is symmetric.
So I can cover the lattice by some
translates of y and if each of those
gets compressed a lot then the whole
lattice should be compressed a lot.
So
recover
a prime cross b prime by a few
translates of y.
And then we would get that the
projection of the whole thing
should be bounded by a few times the
projection of y.
Okay. So now let's carry out this
intuition. We are going to cover y uh
cover a prime cover something uh by
translates of y.
Okay.
Um
so let's consider
y + t1 t2. These are some translates of
y set of these guys
where t1 is an a prime cross a prime
minus a prime and t2 is in um this
slightly weird looking thing
there.
Okay. And so these are a bunch of
translates of y. And these translates of
y
cover uh
cover somebody a lot of times. So for
every um
every y1 y2
let me do it this way. So for every a1
a2 in a prime cross a prime and for
every y1 y2
in y there is a unique t1 t2 which is in
this list.
Um so that uh a1 so that y1 y2
plus t1 t2 is a1h.
So this is easier to prove than it is to
write down.
Just solve for t1. t1 must be y1 a1
minus y1. And uh and these these guys
both live in a prime. So t1 is in there.
Um and uh
um ah
wait
yeah sorry. So this is going to have to
be -1 over t1 a prime.
Okay. Now how does y2 work? um for every
uh so t2 is going to be a2 minus y2
and the uh
the a2
lives in b prime and the uh
Um
yeah.
So the a2 lives here and the um y2 lives
here. So the difference lives here where
it's supposed to.
Okay.
So So these translates
of y
cover a prime cross -1 over t1 a prime.
They cover it
y times.
I cover each point in here y times
because for each point in here I have y
norm of y cardality of y choices for
this guy and then uh there's one one in
translation a set of translations that
that lands here.
Okay, does this sentence make sense?
So we have rigged it that we've taken a
bunch of translations of this set y and
we have covered a nice uh product many
times and the product we actually could
have arranged the product to be a prime
cross b prime that would have been a
little easier than what we did but we
have arranged that the product that
we've covered is a prime cross a um
dilation of a prime and that's a little
bit better technically because it's
going to be closer to theorem one.
Okay. Now notice that this guy is small
by hypothesis and this set here is also
small. This is uh just a dilate of this.
So these sets are small. So we took a
few translations of Y and we covered
this um product many times. And that
means that at least typically each of
the translations was covering a lot of
the product.
Okay. So that matches this intuition.
So then we can say
that pi t of a prime
cross -1 / t t1 a prime
that guy is bounded by um
okay so
um so we're going to take
a prime minus a prime times um
a prime plus t1 b prime. This is how
many copies of y we took. For each one
of them we have a projection. So that
has the size pi t of y.
And after doing that we've covered every
point here y times. So we have this guy.
Okay. These are hypothesis bounded by n.
So this is n^2 over y
pi t of y.
And that's basically our final
inequality. Put the pi t of y by itself.
Pi t of y is greater tilda tilda y / n^2
times the size of this thingy which is
equivalent to
pi t / t1 a prime cross
Okay, take a moment with that.
Okay.
Um, so now let's finish the proof of the
DK theorem.
All right.
[Applause]
So, we would like to estimate the
maximum t in our direction set of pi t
of x.
That's at least
the maximum t in our direction set of pi
t of x prime.
We're following up from over here. And
here's x prime, which is a big chunk of
a prime cross cross b prime.
Okay. And now we can apply our lema.
So the lema says
that is at least as big as the maximum t
in our direction set x prime / n^2. And
then we have pi - t / t1 a prime cross a
prime.
Okay. Now x prime we already determined
has size about n^2. So this factor
disappears.
And now we are looking at projections in
many different directions of a prime
cross a prime. That's exactly the thing
that theorem one told us about.
So by theorem one
this is now greater sim sim n times um p
to the epsilon one
and that's the proof.
So one of these is significantly bigger
than
the square of x * p to the epsilon
Okay,
let me put up on here a little summary
of what we did and then uh and then I'll
let you look at the
look down from above at the whole thing.
So we're trying to get from theorem one
to theorem bkt.
And the enemy
was that we have a set x in a cross a
where x is around the same size as a
cross a but
the size of a projection of x is uh much
smaller than the size of the projection
of a cross a. That's our enemy.
And we learned two pieces of wisdom
about this enemy. One in the BSG theorem
and one in the lema.
So wisdom one in the enemy situation
um X lives in a smaller product
and the projection of the smaller
product.
So this the projection of the smaller
product
well it doesn't live in that but it has
a so the enemy situation implies that X
intersected with the smaller product is
about the same as X. So a good chunk of
X lives in a smaller product and the
projection of the smaller product is
about the same as the projection of X.
Okay. So then we look at that situation
and the second piece of wisdom was that
if uh the projection of a smaller
product of a product
um
if this is small
um so if this is around
the smallest it could be would be one of
the factors for one t1 then this product
becomes very symmetrical
and Then the conclusion is for any
subset X prime in the in this thing
which is substantial
[Applause]
then
the projection of the subset actually is
around the same as their direction the
projection of the whole product.
So the enemy situation can only really
happen because X was mostly in a a
smaller product that had a small
projection
and this situation is very symmetrical.
So if a smaller product has one small
projection then when you project it in
other angles then um the projection of a
big piece of it can't be way smaller
than the projection of the whole thing.
All right.
So, the whole story is on these boards.
Uh, take a take a couple moments to look
it over.
>> Yeah.
>> Have a question. So, should it be the
case that the a prime there depends on
t?
>> Okay. So, the question is whether a
prime depends on t.
Um, so let's see where a prime appeared.
So we have uh our set with many small
projections
and um okay and then in particular the
t1 projection is small and so the balag
summarity gow theorem says there's a
prime and a and b prime and b so that
the t1 projection of a prime cross b
prime is small and this a prime depends
on t1
>> right
>> now later we're going to look at pi P of
X for other T's. Um,
one could, I guess, apply Boxed Gowers
again to those other T's, but that's not
what we're going to do. We we use T1 to
find A prime and B prime. And then we're
going to run with these same A prime and
B prime even when we look at other T's.
What did we learn? Once we have this one
small projection, we learned uh Alex Gar
told us this and then we learned from it
some other stuff. So that what we
actually used is this.
So we so we then we use this stuff. So
this is telling us that a prime cross b
prime is quite symmetrical and that's
what's helpful in the second part.
>> Good. Other questions or comments
don't we know that it's also kind of
Yeah, the question is why don't we know
that a itself is also kind of
symmetrical? That might depend on
exactly what we mean by symmetrical.
But um an important thing an important
way that a prime is better than a is
that at this moment um
a prime minus a prime is small. And we
didn't know that about a. A could be,
you know, you can think of A prime as A
as being A prime plus some garbage and
the garbage minus garbage is is not
small.
Why the the epsilon
>> like the epsilon is different between
the two because
>> of the a prime plus minus a prime has
like
there's like a hidden factor there
right?
>> Yes.
A prime plus minus a prime here there's
a hidden factor which is p to the order
of epsilon
>> and you're right it's very important
that the epsilon is different between
the two theorems. Um
so epsilon one is the epsilon in theorem
one which was already kind of small if
we had unwind the proof of theorem one
and then in theorem bkt there's an
epsilon and the epsilon and bkt is way
smaller than the epsilon one and the
reason we need that is um okay we
started with this where we have a factor
of p to the epsilon then um we did some
stuff most important stuff is bsg so bs
SG will lose like there'll be like a
factor of 10 epsilon here uh that comes
out of the proof of balm gowers. So here
the these these things will be something
like p to the 10 epsilon if you did them
carefully and then you go along and
we're following our proof. So here
there's um we did a little bit more work
in the proof of the lema. So there's p
of this is hiding a p of 10 or 20
epsilon
and then but here we have a gain of p to
the epsilon 1. So the p to the epsilon
one needs to dominate the p to the 20
epsilon that we lost at various steps in
this process. So epsilon should be like
120th of the size of epsilon one.
Yeah. So we have to do a whole sequence
of clever things to prove briang cat's
ta theorem and each time we do something
clever our epsilon gets smaller by a
factor of 10 until you know we're so
clever that we really can't see the
epsilon.
Yeah.
>> Is there a conjecture bound for what
possible epsilon could be?
>> Ah, that's a great question. Yeah. So,
the question is, is there a conjectured
bound about the right epsilon? Um
um yes. So, yes. So the conjecture so
we're working right now over finite
fields and the conjecture is that the
worst case is a lattice
and we wrote it down let's write it down
again but we we wrote it down at the
beginning of the course um
okay so I think we're moving on I'll put
it here
[Applause]
okay so suppose we have x
which is a subset of ft^2 squ and then
we're going to take the maximum t and d
pi t of x. Um, and this is bigger than I
think it was d to the half x to the
half.
Um,
maybe you should check it. I don't
remember these. I don't quite remember
these off the top of my head. So, I
think
And the way to remember it is that the
example is that X is a lattice
and then D is the set of rational
numbers of small slope.
Right? That was the case where the pro
the case that we've seen so far where
the projections are small. So if you
compute with this you can check whether
this is true or whether it needs to be
modified a little bit. And then if you
rewrite it in the language of BKT it
gives you an exact formula for epsilon
right and that is a wide openen problem
um over FP but the version over R has
been proven and and uh um I'll try at
least to say to say at least some of the
main ideas of the proof in the in the
class.
Yeah.
Okay. Um
so the the ideas that we've just been
talking about when um going back and
forth between whether a projection of
the whole product is small whether a
projection of a big chunk of the product
is small um that is a theme in additive
combinotaurics and I want to describe to
you some of the other key words and
ideas behind that theme to to flesh out
the lecture and see how it I don't know
how it fits in in general.
Um,
[Applause]
all right.
So section is called additive energy
versus the size of a plus b.
So these are two points of view about
measuring the additive structure
involved when you add um numbers in a to
numbers in b. This one we've already
met. Let me tell you what additive
energy is.
So definition
if A and B are contained in an Aelian
group
the energy of AB
is the number of quadruples
A1 and A2 are in A. B1 and B2
are in B. So that a1 + b1 is equal to a2
+ b2.
So if you add numbers from a and b, how
many coincidences are there? Does it
frequently happen that you get the same
number?
So another way of thinking about it is
we could say r a b of z. the number of
representations of Z as a sum somebody
in A and somebody in B. So this is the
number of ab
+ b is z.
And the additive energy ab is also equal
to the sum over z r a b of z squ.
So if this is large it means there are a
lot of numbers that can be written as a
plus b in many different ways. There are
many additive coincidences.
Okay. So um
so for reference if a and b both have
size n
then think about how big or how small
the additive energy could be. it's at
least n squared. Um that happens if so
there are n^2 obvious solutions to this
which are a1 equals a2 and b1 equals b2
and um if if you have kind of a random
set of integers or random subset of a
big group those might be only the the
only solutions. So here we have only
trivial
quadruples.
Okay. And energy is at most n cubed
because once you've picked three of
these, the fourth one is determined by
this equation. So there's at most n
cubed of these additive quadruples. And
um
and this happens if a= b equals a
subgroup of z.
A and b are a subgroup of z. Then
there's always a choice of b2 you can
pick to solve this equation.
Okay,
cool. So having large energy is sort of
having a lot of additive structure. And
before we were sort of thinking that if
a plus b is small then that would mean
there's a lot of additive structure. Um
how are those related to each other?
Okay. Um, so there's a lema
that says a * b a ^2 * b ^2 is at most
the size of a + b times the energy
between a and b.
And this is uh the proof of this is just
Koshy Schwarz.
So if I add up on Z R A B of Z
I get the size of A times the size of B.
This is by double counting. So every
time I add somebody in A and somebody in
B I get some Z. I add this up I get all
the pairs.
So now
uh a * b is the sum z of r a b of z and
in this sum I only need to count the
guys in a plus b because if z is not
cannot be written as an a plus b at all
it means that this was zero.
Okay, now I koshi Schwarz.
So I'm going to write it as the sum or a
+ b of one to the 12 and the sum r a b
of z squared to the 12.
Okay, so that's the size of a + b to the
12 times the energy to the 12.
That's the per.
All right. So we see from this that if
the if a plus b is small then the energy
must be large. You know we could bring
the a plus b over to the other side. So
people usually write this the energy is
at least a 2 * b ^ 2 over a plus b.
So for instance, if a and b have size n
and a plus b is almost n, then the
energy would be at least around n cubed,
which is as big as it could be.
All right? So a + b small
implies
that the energy is large.
Now, do people think you can go the
other way? If the energy is large, does
that imply that a plus b is small?
>> Good. No, because you could have some
garbage.
Okay. So energy
of a large
does not imply that a + b
is small.
Uh the example
is that a = b equals numbers up to n.
Somebody with a lot of additive
structure union some garbage.
Good. Now if you look at the definition
of the energy, if I add some extra
elements to A or to B, it can only
increase the energy perhaps not very
much. So the energy of this example is
at least the energy of this example
which is large.
On the other hand, the garbage can make
this a lot bigger. And this is basically
the same example that we've been
grappling with all class.
Okay,
cool.
So now
we'll leave that up.
Right.
Okay.
Now if the energy of A and B is is small
that implies that the size of A plus B
is large. That's just the contraositive
of what we wrote before or you can see
it from this formula. If this is small
then this one must be large.
Right?
Okay.
Now
um
right
now suppose I have a set x in a cross b
and I look at pi 1 of x right. So
remember that pi 1 of a cross b is just
a + b.
So when I take pi 1 of x it's sort of
like a plus b. But I don't take all the
pairs. I just take the pairs in x.
Um
and um
um
so if even if pi one of x were small,
if x was a large set and pi1 of x were
small, that would still produce a lot of
energy.
um because that would still be um a lot
of numbers a bunch of numbers Z that
have many representations of A plus B.
Let me just write it down. U okay so
yeah. So, so actually so let me recall
that
a + b large
and x being a big fraction of of a * b
that does not imply that pi 1 of x is
large and this is again the main thing
that we were struggling with but with
energy this is true. So, lama um
check exactly what it says.
So lema um x is less than or equal to
p1 of x times the energy of ab.
So if the energy is small
um then pi1 of x is pretty big for every
subset x or every large subset x.
The proof is the almost the same as the
previous proof.
So proof rx of z is the number of ways
of writing um a + b equal to z where the
pair ab is an x and that's smaller than
representations of z is a general sum of
somebody a and b because we're only
taking a a portion of the of the sums.
Okay. So now x is the sum um on z of rx
of z.
And here in this sum we only have to
take z's in pi 1 of x only have to
consider those z's that can be written
as the form a plus b where a and b are
in x.
So now we can koshy schwarz this and we
get the size of pi 1 of x^ the 12
times uh a kind of energy thing which is
smaller than the standard energy. So we
have the sum rx of z ^ 2 to the 12
that's smaller than the sum ra of z ^ 2
to the 12 which gives us the energy.
Okay, cool. So to summarize,
having small energy implies that the
subset is large, but it's stronger than
that and it also implies that um that pi
1 of x is large for all substantial
subsets of a cross b.
So it's stronger in a way which is
exactly what we need in our discussion.
Okay,
so that suggests
a better version of theorem one that we
could have tried to prove.
Um, let's erase this lema.
So remember theorem one said that if we
take the projection of a cross a in many
directions, one of them has a large
cardality.
But we could have proved could have
tried to prove something stronger that
one of them has a small energy. Let me
write it down. It's true and it's a
theorem.
Theorem two
says
um
right so if a is a subset of fp size of
a is p to the s a z less than s a less
than one
d is in fp size of d is p to the s d 0 z
is less than sd
then
um I'm going to consider all the
directions and pick the best one. And
instead of looking at at the size of a
plus ta, I'm going to look at the energy
of a comma ta.
And I'll take the minimum over all the
t.
Okay. So the biggest this energy could
be is p to the 3 sa. It's the maximum
possible energy.
And we're going to say it's a little bit
better than this.
Okay.
Now because of this lema we
automatically get not only a lower bound
on pi t of a cross a but we get a lower
bound on pi t of any big subset of a
cross a. So this would automatically
gives the BKT theorem.
So in fact this easily implies a strong
version of the BKT theorem which I think
was also proven by BKT.
And it says
that um
uh so
x is p to the sx and d is as above.
So not only you can say
the maximum t and d pi t of x is large.
So this so that that's the regular
theorem
and this follows from theorem two and
using our lama
but we could say that um uh
that there so this is true but even
better
there is some t and d so that
[Applause]
if y so if y is a subset of x and it's a
substantial subset of x.
Um then
uh pi t of y is big.
Okay. So the proof from here to here is
you know we observed earlier that uh we
can reduce to the case
wow. Okay.
Yeah, I guess I should say using ball
ready gowers, we could reduce to the
case where x is a big subset of a cross
a and then y is a big subset of x. So y
is a big subset of a cross a and then
you use the energy bound to get this.
Okay.
Um so let me say
proof of theorem 2 plus bkt2
are similar to what we did in class
and so they could be they're good
optional exercises uh or they could be
some some pieces of it might be required
exercises.
Okay. Um,
cool. And I thought I should mention
this. One of the things that Pablo
impressed on me when we were talking
over the vacation week was that
this slightly stronger version is is is
very is important in applications. Most
of the applications actually depend on
being able to say this slightly stronger
thing.
Okay.
Okay. So now you might think you might
ask yourself um
maybe energy is actually a better thing
to be talking about because a bound for
the energy is is kind of stable under
taking large subsets.
And so maybe we should have been talking
about energy all along.
And it's reasonable to ask if you take
our proof of theorem one and you just
try to change all the cardalities to
energies, could you adapt it and prove
theorem two instead?
Okay. And you you can't do that. Um and
it's a good moment to recap the main
idea in theorem one and also sort of uh
a way of reflecting on the different big
tools and how they're related to each
other.
All right. What should I erase?
Maybe now I can erase the BSG theorem.
[Applause]
Um,
okay. Actually, before I erase the BSG
theorem, let me make a little comment
about it. So, it's of it's there are a
couple of closely related forms of the
theorem. And another way I often say it
is that if the energy of AB is large
then there must be A prime and B prime
so that the cardality of A prime plus B
prime is small
maybe I should yeah
maybe I should me put it here.
So theorem the SG variant
this is the the way it's most commonly
said so I would be a bit remiss not to
show it to you. So if A and B are in the
group
and let's say A and B have size at most
N
and the energy of AB is large
um energy of AB is greater than K
inverse N cubed
then it may not be the case that a plus
b is small because of the example with
garbage but we can get rid of the
garbage. So there exists a prime in a
and b prime in b so that um
uh a prime
a yeah so that they are substantial. Um
so a prime and b prime are greater than
or equal to k to the minus order of 1 n
and
a prime + b prime is less than or equal
to k to the order of 1.
So if we there's we can locate the
correct structured parts then their
subset is small after we remove some
garbage.
Okay.
[Applause]
All right. So now let me remind you of
one of the key ideas in the proof of
theorem one.
key idea
in the proof of theorem one.
So the key idea was based on the plume
corusia inequality and it was an idea
that I called contagious structure.
So it said if a + t1 a is small
and
a + t2 a is small
then
a + t1 + t2 a is also small.
Not quite as small but still pretty
small.
So this was the key thing.
If um a plus a if a plus ta is small for
a bunch of t and d then it would have to
be small for an even bigger set of d by
adding d or by multiplying d or by
taking negatives and then there would be
a huge set of t's where a plus ta was
small and then that contradicts basic
double counting.
That's the proof. Okay. So what if we
tried to work with energy throughout? So
instead of trying to prove that a plus
ta is big, we're going to try to prove
that the energy is small.
So we're doing a proof by contradiction.
So the the analogous question would be
if the energy between a and t1 of a is
large
and the energy between a and t2 of a is
large.
Then does that imply that the energy
between A and T1 + T2 A is large.
Okay, the answer is no. uh and it is the
same issue that we saw before that when
the we say the energy is large it means
there's at least a piece of A and a
piece of T1A that are very friendly with
each other but it doesn't have to be all
of them. So one piece of A must be very
friendly with T1 A and one piece of A
must be very friendly with T2A.
But those could be two different pieces
of A. And in that case we can't really
learn anything more. Doesn't mean
there's any piece of A that's friendly
with both of them.
So here's the example. Answer is no.
Here's the example. So a might be the
numbers up to n union t1 times the
numbers up to n union t2 * the numbers
up to
okay
so then uh t1 a be t1 numbers up to n
union dot dot dot t2 a this t2 numbers
up to n union dot dot dot.
So these two guys are very friendly. Not
just because they're the same as each
other. Not everybody who's the same as
each other is friends, but because they
have uh they're have a lot of additive
structure.
And therefore
this guy is large.
And
uh these two guys are very friendly
and therefore this guy is large.
But there's nothing going on with T1
plus T1 and T2 are totally arbitrary and
T1 plus T2 we would not typically have
this large.
So
all right
if a T1 + T2 a is typically small.
Okay,
cool. So, it was actually kind of
crucial in our proof of theorem one to
talk about the cardality of the subset
instead of the energy because in that
setting we have the Pluna Roua
inequalities and we get a great deal of
structure from a single subset being
small. We get lots of other things.
On the other hand, it is nice eventually
to get to theorem two because theorem
two is stable if you replace the actual
product a cross a by a subset which is
almost all of it.
So energy so so both so both looking at
cardality and looking at energy has it
have have good features. Energy
estimates are stable undertaking subsets
and the cardality estimates have this
contagious structure thing. Those are
both very helpful.
And so um
uh okay and um and bal
this is important
because
uh okay even though having a big energy
is not synonymous with having a small
subset balm gar says they're very
closely related and so by using balag
samuris you can often get the best of
both world worlds so if you were to
pretend that you could have all the good
features of of an energy bound and all
the good features of a cardality bound.
See what you could prove. Very often you
can prove those things by using
balacrated gowers to move back and
forth.
And Pablo gave the analysis seminar a
few weeks ago and he gave an overview of
recent developments in projection theory
and he made the claim or suggestion that
this theorem might be one of the most
important or most used theorems in math
in the last several decades.
It was a It was a little provocative.
I thought it was interesting. Uh and I
have gradually been appreciating it uh
more and more. I'm learning about it. Uh
anyway, I would gradually appreciating
it more and more. Um and um yeah,
probably as we keep going, we'll see how
this keeps being important.