First of all, thank you for having us
all here today. Um, this is fantastic.
It's an awesome opportunity. Um, anybody
want to guess how you pronounce our logo
or our company? Visible. Visible. There
you go. Awesome. Love it. Um, speaking
about visibility, um, who would guess
how many engineering leaders actually
know how to measure their organizations?
Yeah, that's a tough one. My name is
Chad Upton. I'm a co-founder of Visible.
I'm the COO. And um I'm really excited
to share that we have built a platform
that helps engineering leaders shine a
light on what's actually happening in
their engineering
organizations. Um the truth is we're
absolutely drowning in disconnected
tools. We have all of our AI agents now.
We have all the SDLC's. We have DevOps.
We have everything that's out there
everywhere. And uh we have cheer for
tickets, Slack for comms, um what else
we got? GitHub for code, those kind of
things, right? And so hours vanish just
trying to answer status updates. If you
look at how many requests, how many
Slack messages you get? Hey, when was
that last release? When was that last
P1? All of those kinds of things. You're
constantly looking at where do I go to
find this information? And now we have
AI. Are we using it enough? Is it being
adopted? Can we measure the impact?
These are all areas in which Visible is
focusing. But honestly, it's crazy that
we're in 2025, and we still don't have
this problem
solved. Um, projects stall, teams fall
behind, and millions of dollars vanish,
and refactors and
delays. 71% of IT projects fail. 50% of
those are because of fail of poor
execution.
The result, I think most of us know this
answer, wasted budgets, crushed morale,
and missed market
opportunities. Um, so why hasn't it been
solved? Well, most of the other teams
out there and competitors that we are
going against, um, they're really,
really focused on collecting your data
from all of these tools. That has been
the theme for the last 2, three, four
years. Um, Visible instead has been
laser focused on connecting your data.
We built an ontology model that weaves
all of your data into a single knowledge
graph. This helps us connect the why to
the how across all your tools. Once we
do that, we use the power of LLM to
translate natural language questions
into queries and then we enrich the
responses giving you clear insights on
what is actually happening inside your
organization. But as we've all talked
about today, we're all focused on saving
time, that endless parade of status
updates. Why did we what did we really
release? you know, um, are we tracking
on track for Q2? We spend countless
hours every week just responding. And
don't even get me started on how many
other people I have to bother to answer
some of these questions, right? I have
to go to other engineering meeters, QA,
other teams, those kinds of things. So,
it's not just
us. And unlike some of the other ones
that are here that are um much further
in their journey, we're very early.
We've spent countless nights and
weekends um building this product and
we're actually starting to see real real
traction in the market. Um we started
working with Matt at Defiance AI and he
is a basically a consulting type firm of
what they do there and we've unlocked
data connecting all his tools together
that he's now able to get rid of
spreadsheets and manual data crunching
saving hours every week. Um I think it
translated to something like six hours
per manager.
So, for a company company that's called
Visible, um, why haven't you heard about
us? Because we've been pretty invisible,
unfortunately, which is kind of ironic.
Um, we did the really hard part first.
We wanted to build a product we knew we
would actually use. My entire founding
team are almost all product and
engineering. We know this space very,
very well. Um, now we're ready to focus
on our go to market. So, that's kind of
why we're here talking to everyone else.
Um, we're expanding and we're looking to
bring 50 to 100 pilots over the next 12
months. We want organizations that crave
real time analytics, operational
narratives, and a clear competitive
advantage in software
engineering. And so, right now,
engineering is at a very critical point.
AI is disrupting almost every single
vertical we have out there. Teams
without deep operation visibility are
left to
guess and those with it are going to
start pulling ahead. We built visible so
you're not left
behind. Thank you.
Thank you Todd. Any questions there?
So, I'm not quite clear when you say
metrics, are we talking about like stuff
like cycle time
and all like um velocity and all that?
Those are the um it's so funny you say
those. That's what the industry has been
using to measure our teams. Dorometrics
is kind of like our baseline today. And
if you ask anybody today, what do you
use Dorometrics to actually measure or
have you actually done anything with
those that's actionable? The answer is
probably no. So um instead what we've
done is connecting to all these tools.
We pull every single event that happens
either web hooks, your GitHubs, your
selects, every comment, every commit
message, everything that you do across
all these and then we combine them in
that model. So then you have a interface
to query to ask anything you want. But
we've built simple use cases for you to
say what were our key deliverables for
this team for the last 30 days and it
gives you a chat GPT type narrative that
go that comes out and gives you
everything that you need to know so
you're not having to be a data scientist
to understand the metrics you're looking
at. Great question. Anyone else? Yes
sir.
One other
very simple one. I'm assuming your
system requires a cloud connection,
right? It does. Yes. Um assuming most of
your tools are in a I mean today it
does. It probably wouldn't doesn't have
to necessarily. Um if your code is
stored in a local private GitHub repo,
for an example, we could probably get to
it.
You don't need any
AI. Okay. It could it could be hosted on
premise completely.
Um, yes it could be. We could deploy it
anywhere if we had
to. Great question. Thank you, Chad.
We'll um move on to the next startup,
but of course you can thank you very
much. Further with all of them.