then the next speaker is uh uh UNM
a uh he's a uh uh he's the Chipman
Career Development professor and an
assistant professor in the department
Materials Science and Engineering at
MIT he completed his post uh trainings
at UC ble and uh his PhD at Stanford
University uh his research group works
at the next Nexus of
electrochemistry uh condensed matter of
physics asart sciences and the data
science to develop materials and device
for Next Generation energy storage
uh and Computing and Mining Technologies
uh he uh prior to his PhD he conducted
research at IVM and R
rosos National Laboratory for two
years
uh he uh Professor AET has been
recognized by one of the uh talented
12 by candre
news uh both fellow by MIT and the Mir
fellow and the
presidential uh presidential fellow by
UC B uh I think
he he's he will introduce and discuss
both short and long duration energy uh
St you so you
today is this
okay so please welcome
uh uh thank you kg for the kind
introduction uh good afternoon everyone
um K I'm very happy to be the last
speaker of today I heard that's an honor
to be the last speaker and I'm very
happy to be doing that uh so today I'm
going to tell you about innovating
materials and chemistry for the green uh
transition I'm going to start uh this by
telling you a story uh the story starts
in West Africa Mali so in Mali in West
Africa in the 1980s the locals were
looking for underground water it turns
out at that side there was a rock that
has been reacting with the with water
for God knows how long converting the
water to hydrogen and this guy who has
been who are digging the the well he was
smoking while he was digging not knowing
that there's hydrogen underneath his
feet and there was a boom an explosion
that took his life of course this is a
very sad story but this incident where
where later on people went back to this
site to identify that indeed there has
been hydrogen production from this inent
we learn two things at least I take two
takeaways from this incident the first
one is the Earth can be source of
hydrogen and the second one is the Earth
can be a factory to make clean
fuels so as you know there are several
ways in which we have been producing
hydrogen the most convictional one is
the black hydrogen where we are
converting methane to CO2 and hydrogen
this has been the method of making
hydrogen for the last 100 and more years
and in the last few decades there has
been emerging ways of replacing this
carbon intensive method one by putting
back the CO2 into the sub surface
another one by doing what's called Green
hydrogen where you are using wind or
solar energy to break water into
hydrogen but the UN emerging you know
form of hydrogen production is called
geological hydrogen and this is what
discovered in Mali so uh if you compare
the CO2 emission and the cost of this
form of hydrogens you can see that the
gray hydrogen which is the incumbent
method for making hydrogen is very high
in CO2 emission but very low cost
however the GRE hydrogen has a lower CO2
emission is very very expensive we're
comparing a $7 per kilogram of hydrogen
with a $2 per kilam of hydrogen so we
have a huge challenge to bring this cost
to be competitive with the incumbent
method however the geoh hydrogen is
bothos low in coast and low in also CO2
emission that's why it's a very you know
a promising Pathways to making hydrogen
and if you look into how this is
produced it TS out that this rocks must
contain iron the iron in The Rock has is
a one that interact with the water where
the iron is oxidized while the water is
reduced to from hydrogen so basically
you are forming a rest rest while you
are converting H2O to H2 and if you do
back of the envelope calculation to
quantify how much of iron you have in
the subsurface that is accessible to you
know the surface of the Earth you found
out that there is in a hydrogen that
will supply all our energy needs whether
it's Transportation industry or
residential for the next
250,000 years of course you know being
able to extract this will be challenging
by itself but the promise is there and
there are two ways in which we can
obtain this hydrogen the first one is
was what we call the passive one this is
similar to doing oil and gas exploration
where you explore where you have
hydrogen you go there and exploit it and
this way you can produce up to 20
million of hydrogen per year the other
one which I will discuss more in a few
seconds is called stimulation where you
don't depend on the Earth but rather you
stimulate this
reaction as a result this from hydrogen
is called the new Green because of the
low Co emission and also the the low
cost of its
nature so the passive hydrogen the one
where you explore and you know extract
from the subsurface it's it's now almost
an emerging and a m maturing sector
where we have a lot of startups all over
Europe us and Australia trying to
extract this hydrogen and next time you
are on a plane if you are looking down
in the Jung underneath the plane if
there's a jungle and if there is like a
circle in the jungle that might be a
region where we have hydrogen because
that area is not favorable for the
growth of
trees but what is interesting for me and
what my lab works on is called
stimulation in this case what the
technology will involve the following so
you'll have two bore holes where in the
first bore hole you inject water and
catalyst so in the passive one you
depend on the earth to do everything for
you but in this case you only look for
where the rock is and once you know
where it it is you with with the first B
hole you inject a water a catalyst or a
pH that will stimulate the
reaction produce the hydrogen and you
can collect the hydrogen with the
X2 that's what we call the stimulated
hydrogen
production so this system though hasn't
been explored for a long time we know
about the passive one but this the
stimulation is a very New Concept and
the reaction by itself is very very slow
in rate and very low in yield it's a
geological reaction that takes
geological time scales so what you want
want to do is to find ways in which we
can optimize the reaction parameters to
increase the yield and the rate to be
economically feasible so in my lab we
approach this challenge in three
different ways at different LS scale in
the atomic lenss scale we're trying to
understand what is happening at the rock
water interface knowing the mechanism
will allow you to control the reaction
kinetics and thermodynamics we also want
to know what happen to the rock it turns
out that the rock expanding volume
during this reaction leading to some
cracking what we call chem mechanics
chemically induced mechanics so we're
trying to apply some Advanced x-ray
techniques to understand the phase
transition and the mechanics of this
rock uh reacting with the water and
finally we have a customade reactors
which are a very high in temperature and
a very high pressure that simulate the
subsurface heat pressure allowing us to
manipulate physical and chemical
parameters to optimize this reaction
yield and reaction rate so in the lab we
you know collected rocks from different
parts of the US from California from
Oregon uh from Minnesota and so on and
so forth and within our reactors that
simulate the subsurface heat and
pressure we try to see how can we
increase the reaction kinetics and as
you can see in the black curve is what
happens when we just have The Rock in
the water with no optimization and the
y- axis is the amount of hydrogen you
are producing per time you can see that
in the black case where you don't have
any optimization you can't wait for
hours days even years and there's no
almost hydrogen production again this is
a geological reaction taking geological
time scale however if you optimize this
reaction by adding some Catalyst you can
see you can enhance the reaction rate by
almost 300 times if not more and this
production rate and production yield is
economically feasible if it scale up
toward this
production so this is very interesting
one and we have the record rate right
now for this production of hydrogen from
the Rocks but we went on and expanded
this concept where we asked okay in the
previous case we trying to convert water
to hydrogen but now can I generalize
generalize this reaction and take any
molecule X and convert it to Y where Y
is a economically valuable chemical to
begin with we look into ammonia for for
two reasons the first one is hydrogen as
a very small molecule as you know and
even if you make it in the subsurface it
might be very challenging to be able to
collect it store it and transport it and
it's very very also expensive to
transport and there's no infrastructure
to be able to transport hyrogen except
you are near o refinary sites the second
problem we're trying to see is you know
ammonia by
itself as a very important chemical and
so the goal therefore is can we actually
tune this reaction mechanism by which
now we want to make ammonia from water
and a nitrogen source that can be N2
from Air it can be also
nitrate and like I was saying ammonia is
the most produced chemical in the world
it's also the highest CO2 emitter even
though we know amonia to be very
essential for fertilizers now there are
emerging ways in which we are trying to
use ammonia to run turbines and engines
for application in industry and
transportation so this growth is
actually expected to be two by two times
or three times more production in the
next couple of
decades and the incumbent way to make
ammonia as you know SCH Hab and if you
look at this reaction what we have is we
have N2 plus
hydrogen at a very high heat and high
pressure to make ammonia surprisingly
the 80% of the CO2 production from Hab
bush is not coming from burning fossil
fuels to actually power the
reaction rather is coming from the
hydrogen we are using which is produced
by STEM reforming which also by itself
is a carbon intesting process so now if
I actually find a way in which I can
supply hydrogen to this reaction by
using geoh hydrogen that has a low
emission then I might be able to solve
this 80% dependency of the CO2 coming
from the hydrogen in addition if you dig
in the
subsurface the Earth is also hot it also
have high pressure and this is a profile
showing you how the pressure and
temperature is changing as you dig into
the subsurface so maybe maybe the Earth
can also provide this required heat and
pressure not only I can have a geoh
hydrogen as a clean form of hydrogen but
maybe I can also use Earth as a factory
to supply The energy needed for this
reaction and that was the high moment
for me about a year and a half ago so we
went on file pent and then we to the lab
to see if it actually works so the idea
is the following so again you have a two
ble system and the first B holes you
will inject a water and an nitrogen
Source along with a catalyst or a pH or
atives that will increase the reaction
kinetics and yield once you inject it
you will have reaction with the Rog
where you from the ammonia and in the
second wh you collect ammonia and once
you do that you have a separation system
system that will provide the ammonia
ready for transportation for a place for
use for a place in demand and as you
know ammonia is easier to lufy it's
easier to transport and the us only we
have about 5,000 miles of ammonia
transporting pipelines and almost
nonexistence for hydrogen unless you go
to Gul of Mexico or Gul of America
depending on how you call it and um and
also uh we have about 10,000
terminals in the the US to transport
also import ammonia in the future we
might also export to other world from
the US so it's a very mature technology
we also have a community market to
exchange ammonia but almost n existance
for also for hydrogen and this is why we
believe that ammonia is a NM solution
compared to hydrogen for for the because
of this maturity in all
sectors so this is the result so again
we have the Rocks we injected the water
Plus source of nitrogen and we see a
clear NMR nuclear magnetic resonance
Spectra showing that we are indeed
forming ammonia from The Rock and I
collaborated with people who are expert
in oil and gas who actually know how to
D operate and in fact this the scale up
requires basically existing mature oil
and gas techniques and we calculated
what would be the cost of producing
ammonia from this method if you take
into account the cost of the drilling
the operation CeX Opex but also the cost
of water Catalyst and source of nitrogen
we found out that the cost of production
of ammonia is actually comparable with
Hab Bush as you see on this table so
what you see in the first one is Hab
Bush about 4400 per ton that is before
the Ukraine Russia War but right now
it's about $700 per T per ton and our
estimation is is is is is is competitive
if not cheaper to am H bush process in
addition the biggest win we have is that
there's almost no CO2 emission except
the CO2 you'll be emitting when you are
Drilling and also when you are
separating the fluid as you col after
you collect it so this work is now
published in June just two days ago in
fact you are the this is the first time
you know sharing the work so I'm very
happy to to be here to share the work
with you after the work is published so
you can go to the Jew um uh jeel Jewel
journal to look at the paper and also we
have a lot of uh you know uh press
coverage um and uh that you can learn
learn about about this technology so now
we have demon this idea in the lab the
next step is to see if you can actually
commercialize it and scale it and to see
if actually works so for this I
co-founded a company called Addis energy
joined by you know seasoned oil and gas
expert Michael and Charlie and also my
colleague atmin Chang who who is a seral
entrepreneur so we have you know you
know we have raised capital from arpa
from the venture capitalist we have a
lab space in the Boston area and the
next year we're trying to acquire land
and then do the first um pilot scale for
this
technology so now I told you so far I
have been telling you about hydrogen and
ammonia and these are chemicals and
which they allow you to store energy for
a long long time and therefore they are
called you know long dur energy storage
what I'm going to do in the the last you
know few minutes of today is are the
technologies that are valuable for Mid
and shortterm energy storage compared to
the chemicals and this is namely
batteries so in my group along with you
know creating new ways of making
chemicals we also looking into making
new
batteries um that can be useful for Mid
to shortterm uh duration particularly
we're trying to work on high capacity
high high energy density sodium ion
batteries made from abundant materials
the question is why sodium batteries
right because right now we have a very
much technology L batteries that we are
enjoying the benefit of off here here
are the different reasons why S battery
the first one is the the material cost
is very very cheap so the cost of
materials for sodium battery is about
$40 per kilowatt hour however it's about
$100 per Kow hour F batteries in
addition you can use sodium manganes and
iron as compared to lithium Nik Cobalt
which are critical minerals which we
have significant supply chain constraint
so we can solve this problems of supply
chain but also making this environmental
sustainable elements than the lithium
cobal and the N by using sodium manganes
and IR for a given lithium mine there's
about thousand times more sodium so
sodium is very very abund for example we
can use aloni versus copper as current
collector and another benefit of the
cost and also
sustainability you can operate them in
extreme cold condition much better than
batteries so if you want to drive your
car in Siberia or or Canada it's easier
to do that in with sodium than the
lithium batteries and finally fast
charging is much easier to do with
sodium than the lithium
batteries so the goal is to actually mat
the technology toward this having
competitive battery that with lith
batteries which are cheaper in cost but
also made from abundant materials
and here is you know on the top um left
you are seeing the cost of lithium and
sodium as you can see the lithium cost
is growing
exponentially to look at the sodium cost
you have to squint your ice because very
very very small on the left side on the
right side you can see that right now
our phones and cars are filled with Nik
and Cobalt however Nik and Cobalt are
less abundant more expensive compared to
manganes and iron which are the opposite
and finally unlike other in upcoming uh
battery technologies St batteries
actually can be scaled up by using
lithium battery scal technology so
there's no reinvention of the wheel
toward the scale up the the current
scale up process can be adapted for
sodium ion batteries unlike other ones
which require innovation of new scale
Technologies however if you look at the
cost of a given S battery most of the
cost is coming from the cathode so as
you know in the battery you have the
cathode you have the anode and you have
electrolyte are the three parts of the
the bodyy material the most expensive
one is a cathode therefore innovations
that will make S battery to be
competitive should come from development
of C materials they are the most
expensive one and the most challenging
one to
address and so far there are three class
of materials we have been studying in
the field toward this you know making a
cut material this include layer oxide
very similar to what we have been using
lium batteries Persian blue analog and
poly anons here you can compare the
energy density both the volume and the
gr gram based energy density of the
three class of materials you can see
that the layered oxides have the highest
energy density compared to pan blue or
polyon and therefore if you want to
develop battery to be competitive with
the batteries we have to you know
develop one based on lexide in my
opinion compared to the PBA or the poly
anal if you look at the current you know
landscape for sodum B commercialization
like I was saying you know this is a
very upcoming technology we don't have
any I guess maybe there's one giga
Factory in in megaw Factory in China but
there's almost no mass production of s b
yet but there are several startups in in
Europe in the US and also in Asia trying
to develop C
batteries however what is lacking right
now in my opinion is the following the
first one is uh the first one is most of
them are made from polyan and PBA not Le
oxide so we want to have Technology
based on L oxide and those with L oxide
have significant amount of nickel in
them so we want to develop L oxides that
are free in in Nick and Cobalt
and mature in terms of energy density
and cycleability to be able to compete
with the batteries that's what's missing
missing in the current large scape of
upcoming s b commercialization and
that's why my group's trying to tackle
this this problem by developing Le
oxides that are based on manganes and
iron so now that being said what is the
challenge the challenge in doing this is
the following normally sodium is heavier
compared to lithium so the energ density
is lower in sodium than the lithium in
batteries to compensate for that one you
should be able to charge your system to
high voltage that way you can get more
energy from the Sol batteries to be
compe competitive with the in batteries
so the idea therefore is pushing the the
charging voltage more than what we do
currently but there's a problem with
that so currently what we do is we
charge the our batteries to a low
voltage quote unquote and as a result we
have a very reversible kind of cycling
doing charging and
discharging but if you want to push this
and Achieve high energy density that
means you increase the voltage that
could give you high energy density
however the problem is you will lose
Incycle ability when you do that so
pushing the system to a very high
voltage will induce disorder in the
material giving rise to loss in voltage
and loss in capacity so that's the
problem we're trying to solve if we
solve this problem then we could achieve
H density system that are reversible
into thousands of cycles that can comp
compete with batteries so my group is
trying to solve this problem I would say
this is the billion dollar problem in
this industry so the first approach
we're trying to do is we're trying to
design three different type of methods
to make new materials that can overcome
this challenge
the first design principle is to be able
to control or manipulate the structure
namely we trying to engineer the defects
in the material that way we kind of
prevent a disorder in the M disorder in
the material when when you are charging
and discharging so by introducing
defects in the material like for example
in this case we have showed that we can
actually achieve a very high capacity
and energy but with a very small loss in
voltage if you remember in the previous
plots we have very high voltage normally
about one volt but using our design
principle we narrow down this one VT
loss in loss in voltage to only a 40 Mt
loss in voltage and here is comparing
the loss in
voltage with different materials and our
material shows the lowest voltage loss
upon cycling compared to other existing
sodium and lithium oxide
systems so therefore the first principle
is to engineer the defect in structure
to penalize the disorder and stabilize
the material upon
cycling the second design principle is
the chemistry our predict table is reach
in Elemental type uh compositional
diversity as there is huge space of
materials we can explore so we're trying
to understand how each element affect
the material chemistry and its property
by manipulating the compositional space
we trying to find compositions that
allows us also to narrow that loss in
voltage for example in this case we have
show that by doping a small amount of
dopant into a given material we can
lower the voltage loss and we can lower
the material Disorder so the second
design principle therefore is to
manipulate the chemical composition
space while the first one's the
structural uh
engineering and here you can see one
example example of you exploting the
compostion space to avoid this loss in
voltage and finally the third design
principles to combine both to create new
structures new materials which have
defects in them that control but also
with elements that can optimize the
material stability by doing this we
generated over dozens of new
compositions which uh compositions that
have also the lowest hisis in the
literature and here's example of a
structure that stabilized what you see
as a black dots are the TM image of the
defects in the material we control by
manipulating our heat and pressure
during sentences allowing us to prevent
disorder and achieving a very low loss
in capacity and voltage to recycling and
all these three design principles which
are published across several papers
showed that even though we have this
biggest problem of his loss of capacity
and voltage upon cycling to high voltage
which is caused by the
disorder by applying our design
principle we were able to solve this
issue and we are creating new structures
new materials that allows us to achieve
this so with that I would like to
conclude and uh thank you know the lab
members who who are you know doing the
real work uh particularly you founda uh
who led the GE ammonia work and Hugh SMI
and Shan who led the sodium battery work
and also our funding sources and uh
National facilities which we have been
using to understand the mechanism behind
this uh uh principles in in in both
ammonia and batteries thank you so much
for your uh for for your attention I'll
be happy to answer your
[Applause]
question yeah
so yes okay sure so the question is
what's your anticipated time frame for
Designing new principles for
developing uh manganes and iron reach
systems so this is what we are doing
right now the three example that I gave
you are actually you know examples of uh
design principles to make manganes Rich
iron rich systems in fact in most of the
examples we have no nickel and no Cobalt
in this in the structure so we are
already making a progress um but of
course there's more to come before
commercialization the second question is
is it good idea to build infrastructure
for hydrogen in areas where Ultra mic Ro
is visible on the surface or is better
to extract orange hydrogen by drilling
deep near conception sites very good
question so alic rocks are the Rocks we
are using
and the word Ultra mfic means high in
iron and high in magnesium maic um and
they are so these are the Rocks we are
targeting um I wouldn't the first part
of the question is about building you
know infrastructures near the sides
where we see this rocks on the surface
and I would say no because those rocks
on the surface are already oxidized are
already rested even though they contain
iron the iron is not in the pl two state
so PL to Valance state so oxidized to
plus three or plus4 so if you you know
pour water on it there's no more
arresting that will happen so I would I
would say that won't be economically
feasible because of the fact that it's
already oxidized the second question the
second part of the question is uh exact
origin exact the hydrogen near
conception site so that question has two
parts so because because there are two
ways of orange hydrogen there's a
passive one and stimulated one the
passive one you don't have
aay on where it
exist so even let's say your conception
s is in too but the passive one can be
on Osaka right so you don't have a say
where the natural hydrogen exists so
from that point of view if it happens it
would be amazing if you are lucky to
find that one but what we found so far
is that this industri startups are
finding hydrogen in a remot place from
where there's a
conception nature governs that one but
if you the
stimulation now you have more control on
the chemical reaction in kinetics and
then it makes sense yes to build you
know those facilities near uh conception
sites so yes for stimulation no maybe
not for the the passive one because you
don't have control over over over
weights produced or weight
available good
question the other question is um sodium
batteries t to have less in density uh
do you have ideas on how to
use uh ins say Bel from linking them
together linking them together let me
try to answer this question in the way I
understand them so the First on yes it
has lost energy density because the
sodium is heavier and that's why I said
earlier that to compensate for high
heavy mass of the sodium you have to
charge to high
voltage that way you can get more energy
and the density become also scaled up so
that's what that's the bottom leg which
we trying to address so therefore if we
achieve if we achieve what we a aim at
in which we are charged to high voltage
and have energy density maybe in that
case the energ density can be comparable
to batteries but if
not there are some metods in which
people are proposing to use them in
hybrid form so for example catl the big
Chinese company that makes a battery
they are proposing to use sodium battery
and together in one car so maybe that's
what you were saying in terms of linking
them uh together so yes and those are
actually because they are linking them
in C case because they they are using
what's called Persian blue analog
material so if you are using Persian
blue analog material nominally you have
a very low energ density but if you have
L oxide then you don't have to hybridize
them with batteries so yes in the case
of PB and
polyon and I would say for oxide I I I I
argue that we should aim for making
independent battery that can actually
deliver high density by charging to high
voltage do you think it's feasible to
construct a small scale production site
to generate hydrogen in a safer way
um I believe so
um so for example you know in a steam
reforming right now in Steam reforming
we are doing that we are producing
hydrogen a safe way um by converting me
to hydrogen so in the case of uh orange
hydrogen or white hydrogen
um I believe so but you know this is a
new technology right and we will face
new challenges as we kind of explore
them and develop them
so uh there might be some challenges but
I believe it be possible because if you
look at
history H in h in bch in the early uh 20
20th century when they came up with this
ammonia synthesis from N2 and hydrogen
there was no metall
energy there was no high temperature
vasels there was no pipeline
no welding technology at that time so
going from the idea to now having Hab
bush plant was almost
impossible but then they develop all new
technologies for Metallurgy welding high
pressure reactors separation system all
of those things so I I believe that we
might face similar challenges but we can
learn from existing technologist to
adapt them into this into this new
technology and two areas are geothermal
heating and mean extraction which are
already doing subsurface operations so
we're trying to learn from them to do
this in a safer way in the decade in the
years and decades to
come good question so the question is
would it be possible to use MLA uh
approach by Professor C to discover new
compostion structures definitely um you
know this is a rich compos space and
something talk about in my group is
actually we have auton I met with some
of you today and yesterday we develop
High to put methods in the lab which are
robotic systems that can make new
materials and test them for S batteries
and these are also powered by some AI
machine learning algorithms that explore
their face of space and you know suggest
new composion to try so definitely
that's true and we are trying to also do
the same in our in our group which I
didn't show today because of time
very good thank you very much thanks so
much thank you