So we've reached the end
of our plenary program.
And [? Katerina ?]
and I would like
to take just a couple
of minutes in closing
to express our gratitude
to the people who made
today's symposium possible.
So this morning, Sally
thanked a lot of people.
We would, of course,
like to thank her.
Thanks, Sally--
[APPLAUSE]
--and also Dean Anantha
Chandrakasan and Dean Nergis
Mavalvala.
The commitment of
Sally and Anantha
and Nergis to advancing our
understanding of biology
and human health through
interdisciplinary collaboration
is the driving force behind
the HEALS collaborative
that we're launching today.
So today's symposium would
not have been possible
without our multitalented
planning committee.
Their names are listed here.
You saw many of them
on the stage here today
or running breakout sessions.
This is the group that took
the charge of the deans
and turned it into a day of
exciting MIT research highlights
from all across campus.
So we're very
grateful for the ideas
and the enthusiasm
of the committee that
brought the event to life.
[APPLAUSE]
And, finally, a
huge thank you to
the amazing administrative,
technical, communication,
safety, transportation,
facilities staff
who worked tirelessly to
ensure a successful event.
[? Katerina ?]
and I particularly
want to thank Marsha Warren,
who's lurking here somewhere.
Thank you, Marsha.
She's been keeping us
organized from day one.
We never could have
gotten here without you,
so thank you so much.
So while the formal part of
our day is coming to an end,
the discoveries
do not stop here.
We invite you to
continue the conversation
and explore the amazing work
of our students and postdocs
that really drive the innovation
at the poster session that
is set up right next
door in the tent.
This is your chance to connect
with the brilliant minds
directly.
And I promise it will feel like
a treasure trove of discovery
and exciting research.
A special thank you
for the poster session
goes to Iain Cheeseman, a key
member of the committee also,
and Katey Provost
and Tia Giurleo.
It is incredible how much
work they put into it.
I really underestimated
how many hours.
Very, very, very big thank
you, their dedication
made this exciting
opportunity possible.
And thank you all
again for being
part of this vibrant community
and bringing your curiosity
to this wonderful day.
Let's celebrate the future
of health and life sciences
and continue to push the
boundaries of what's possible.
[APPLAUSE]