You live in my dreams, you're beautiful, you
shook me and left, you wait for me, wait for me, I'll pray for you, you
move me, your meaning can
exist in our language,
open up time, if you can, then yes, if you have the heart, I'll
draw you out.
Dad
[music]
Little kid, don't touch the ground,
you're
really out of it.
I believe that the faith and prayers of your heart are what make your prayers come alive. I have
never doubted my faith. I am thirsty and
cold. This is
my movement. Your meaning.
Open the time where only we can exist. If I can do that, then yes, I will
draw myself.
[Music]
For you
[Applause]
The book will give you a rough idea,
but it will
really give you the book in front of you
.   I'm
looking for you every time from January to December.  If we truly match, not for money,
our 13th month will be fulfilled and we will come together in four
seasons. I
can't do it, so I miss you. Spring has come and your eyes have become snow. We have made
each other feel touched.
Yeri
[music]
[music] It's hard to
give up on the baby.
How can you give up your mistake there?
[applause]
[music]