[music] I'm Carara Miller.
>> And I'm Rob Zmer.
>> And from the MIT Energy Initiative, this
is What If It Works, a podcast looking
[music] at the energy solutions for
climate change.
[music]
Today, a scientist who knows that coming
up with tech that's going to rock the
world is [music] not easy.
>> If you can't beat the existing
state-of-the-art, you don't you don't
get to play. full stop. And and so
you've got to offer something above and
beyond what exists today. Otherwise, you
should go home.
>> And remember, says Asha Gun Henry,
rethinking energy tech and rethinking
[music]
tech we might be a little more familiar
with. Those are two very different
things.
>> You could look at, for example, iPhones
as [music] a consumer technology and you
look at how quickly iPhones took over
the market. It's very enticing [music]
to want to think that energy
technologies could proliferate that
quickly and you know it's the right
solution so everybody's got it a year
later. It doesn't work that way.
>> Henry [music] argues that one place
where we definitely need something
beyond what exists today is in energy
storage. And even though there are lots
of competitors in that space, it may not
always be that way. [music] there likely
will be a single or a very small handful
set of approaches [music]
that end up really dominating because
they meet the needs the best and many
other things will fizzle [music] out and
so you know I put so much time and
energy into fourth power because I think
it's going to be one of these key
winners that ends up out there in the
end
Henry believes that when people imagine
what the energy transition looks like
they frequently make a central mistake
They forget how much this is a physical
problem. A problem that largely is about
big heavy stuff scattered all over the
world.
>> When we think about the future energy
system and what it will take to get from
where we are today to what the future
energy system will look like, there's a
lot of new hardware. This is not a
software problem. This is although there
may be software solutions that help
along the way that make things more
efficient that do things better and more
safely etc. At the end of the day there
is a need to physically change the
infrastructure that we use to convert
energy from one form to another and
deliver it where it's going to be used.
>> Henry notes all you have to do is glance
back at the past to see how this sort of
transition has played out before. When
you look at the various histories of
different technologies and
look at the time scale it has taken for
humanity to switch fuel sources like
from wood to coal and from coal to
natural gas. You know it's typically a
50 to 100year time scale and developing
a new set of hardware is also you know
order 10 10 year time scale uh to just
develop the technology itself. But if
you don't feel like we've got a half
century or more to figure this one out,
what do you do? Henry says relying
purely on capitalism may not do the
trick.
>> If you're waiting on the natural driving
forces in a market to take up a new
technology and start using it, that time
scale may be far too long, much longer
than than we have. And so at the end of
the day, what I think, you know, my
perspective is on the field is
we only get, you know, pretty much one
shot.
>> So how do you take that one shot? Henry
says you've got to go big. We basically
have to parallelize everything and
[snorts]
try every idea that we can think of that
has merit and try to get to whatever the
cheapest most effective technologies are
as fast as possible so that we can
minimize the total cost of deployment.
The the deployment cost is really where
all the cost is and so you know it's
like why not spend an extra 1% to save
90%. And there are examples of
technologies where investment resulted
in plummeting costs like wind for
example or photovoltaics to capture
solar energy. So those are great
examples where you have a technology
that call it 30 40 years ago was uh kind
of laughably expensive compared to the
existing infrastructure but over time
has now overtaken in a sense and become
you know one of the cheapest sources of
electricity on earth is one great
example where we got 10x from kind of
economies of scale and sub and you know
sequential u iterative development for I
think storage is another place where
there are ideas. There's a, you know, of
course, my company is pursuing an idea
uh forth power that is uh 10x cheaper
than the current state-of-the-art.
Um and I think there this is an area
where you see potential options where
you know as as uh Bill Gate Bill Gates
like to call it the green premium um
meaning how much more do you spend to
get the clean technology compared to the
existing technology. This is one of the
really uh rare cases where you have an
opportunity to possibly get cheaper than
what we use today like natural gas where
if you pair uh these really cheap energy
storage technologies such as the one
we're p pursuing at fourth power um if
you pair that with renewables you get to
essentially a a high capacity factor
fully dispatchable renew you know uh
renewable energy power plant that is the
same or lower cost than natural gas and
and
>> so what's the technology?
>> Oh, [laughter] how does it work? Yeah.
So, uh so so the the key point here with
Fourth Powers technology is we made a
pretty radical departure from normal
energy storage. So when you say the term
battery, typically people mean an
electrochemical battery, which is one
that has an electrochemical reaction
going on inside. Um and
what we decided to do differently is
instead of storing energy
electrochemically, we store it
thermally. And the premise of this is
that storing energy thermally is about
10 to 100 times cheaper than storing it
electrochemically kind of from just from
a fundamental basis. So we started by
storing the energy in a different way.
There's a big trade-off you make though
when you store energy thermally is that
you then need to convert it back to
electricity and when you do that you
lose call it roughly speaking about half
of it. And so you you end up wasting
some energy and for a long time this
concept of going from electricity to
heat back to electricity would have
sounded absolutely stupid. And the
reason it would have sounded stupid is
because we go through great pains
already in the current energy
infrastructure to convert heat to
electricity the first time. And when we
do that, we lose more than half of it.
And that's a big waste. Um, and so we
put great effort into trying to retain
and convert as much of that energy as
possible to the final form we want,
which is electricity. Um, so the idea
that you're going to now go back to heat
only to pay the penalty a second time
would sound like we used it's so bad we
used to call it a thermodynamic crime
actually [laughter] that it's a a crime
against thermodynamics to go back to
heat only to do it to pay the penalty a
second time. Um, but there's there's one
main reason to do it and the only reason
to do it is because of cost. Meaning
storing energy thermally is so cheap
that it actually makes sense to waste
some of the energy along the way uh and
pay a factor of two hit on uh efficiency
to get an act to get access to an order
of magnitude lower cost.
>> So explain this to a non-scientist for a
minute. You reference the fact that
generally initially when we get
electricity there's a creation of heat
and I assume that could be like a coal
powered plant would be that right you're
getting heating things to very high
temperatures and out of that you're
powering the plant and powering your
city or your town right
>> yep
>> okay so in what you're doing what is it
that you're heating up I assume things
are going to very high temperatures what
is getting heated up what does that look
like and should people be concerned
about like that level of heat and
>> yeah so so to the first question of what
are we heating up um what we are heating
up is graphite blocks so graphite is
essentially you can think of it like
pencil lead
>> that's how I think of it [clears throat]
>> and uh it's a very inexpensive yet very
refractory material when we when we say
refractory it means that it's maximum
temperature that it can remain solid lid
is a very very high number. Very very
high temperature.
>> Okay. So it kind of still looks like
graphite. It's not melting all over the
table sort of thing. No. Okay.
>> Yeah. At atmospheric pressure, carbon
doesn't form a liquid. So it just
supplimates when it gets hot enough. And
so graphite can be used beyond 3,000° uh
Celsius.
And so that is the main thing that we're
storing the energy in. What's unique
about the system we're developing and uh
commercializing at Fourth Power is that
there's another material we use that
that allows that system to have some
really unique features which is uh
liquid tin. So we use liquid metal which
is essentially the same metal you see in
solder. I don't know if you're familiar
with soldering.
>> Sure. Sure. Sure.
>> If you solder two wires together that
liquid it melts at a very low
temperature, the same temperature you
can get a soldering iron to. Uh but
what's amazing about that particular
element on the periodic table is its
boiling point is is 2600 degrees C. So
it has a huge range where it remains
liquid and doesn't boil. And so we
exploit that. And so we use that liquid
to actually move heat around in our
system. And what it allows us to do
ultimately is is two major things.
Number one, it allows us to decouple
energy and power. So a typical let's say
lithium ion battery it's kind of made
like a fruit rollup of materials that uh
are want to interact with a separator in
between. In our case when we've
separated power and energy what I mean
by that is our system has separate
components that do the conversion of
energy from one form to another and it
has one component that is storing the
energy which is the graphite blocks. So
if you now and these things are
physically located in different places.
So, if you now wanted to increase the
amount of energy you're storing, all you
have to do is keep adding more graphite
blocks to this big very large structure
we have of graphite blocks. And so, you
can do that independently of changing
any of the power hardware. And this is
really attractive for utilities.
Utilities are our customers at Fourth
Power. And it's really attractive for
them because, [clears throat]
you know, they have to size the energy
storage that they want to use on their
grid. Maybe they want a battery that can
output for 10 hours. It's projected in
the future their needs are going to
evolve and they're going to need 20
hours and 30 hours and 40 hours. And the
the n the duration of the need of
discharge is going to extend as more
renewables and other things come onto
the grid. And so we have the ability to
actually grow with the grid and evolve
with the grid where we could install an
initial fourth power thermal battery.
Let's say it's a 10-hour battery and
later the utility could decide, you know
what, we really wish that that had was a
20 20 uh hour battery and you can
augment it and retrofit it to just add
more storage. And the addition of more
storage is only like 20% of the cost,
the original cost. So it's a very small
increment to now keep adding on and
tacking on more storage to change the
duration. So that's one of the key
features. The second key feature with
the liquid metal is uh power density. So
it allows us to shrink the total amount
of hardware you need in order to make a
system of a given power rating. And
ultimately what this does is this cuts
the cost low. And so this is how we get
our cost really far down is by
leveraging the liquid metal as a medium
that can transfer a lot of heat with
very little equipment.
>> So you're saying basically you you just
put more metal in the pot.
>> Well, I want to be careful because you
said metal. So we're using we're using
metal to transfer heat, but you put more
graphite blocks in the pile in order to
get more energy storage.
>> And then how much of a gamecher? There's
sort of two twin questions. One is how
much of a game changer do you feel like
this is? And then how hard slash I mean
you're obviously a professor. You're
kind of an an entrepreneur here too.
How hard or easy is it to launch this in
a big way to get it to be widespread?
Our technoeconomic models show that this
is this is quoteunquote the gamecher in
terms of being able to proliferate
um storage onto the grid in a
cost-effective way that will allow us to
transform the grid and decarbonize you
know very very deeply if not fully. Uh
it's a platform technology you can do
multiple things with it. So taking in
electricity and outputting electricity
is the number one target market we have
for starters. But one of the amazing
things you can also do with it is you
can take in electricity and output heat.
And so heat is another application where
there's big energy needs. And because
our temperature is so high, we can
basically service any application on
Earth that needs heat. Um, in addition
to that, there's another feature where
you can you can actually bring in fuel
and because you can uh react fuel to get
off to give off heat, you can actually
charge it up with fuel rather than
electricity. And so this third uh way
that you can utilize it allows you to
really use it as an ultimate backup for
the grid and keep the grid going kind of
under all circumstances. So from that
perspective uh we think it's an absolute
gamecher right now. We are in the
process of uh we've built some very
large scale uh accelerated life test
rigs um at our fac at a facility we're
working out of
>> meaning rigs that they're used to test
how long these things will live.
>> Yeah. I call them rigs because they are
not the full system fully integrated. Um
they are subsections or subsystems of
the full system that we are testing for
longevity um and and operability. Um and
then the second thing that we're doing
is next year we're building a fully
integrated 1 megawatt hour system um at
the at the same location. And so once we
do that uh that'll uh we expect that
that'll be a very large value inflection
for the company to show all this
full-scale hardware working together. Um
that's I would say the primary challenge
in front of us right now and it's it's
it's largely one of I would say timeline
because we we built the entire
technology in my lab before we spun it
out before I spun it out and um and so
I'm confident that it works right. It's
not really going to be a surprise that
it works. What's really the the new
thing to demonstrate is that it works
when you now scale it up. Meaning the
components that we're using are not
small anymore. Now they've got to be
lifted and hoisted into place with
cranes. And these are the same kinds of
dimensions you're going to see in the
full scale product. Uh and so you derisk
a lot of the risk associated with
scaling up all in this one demonstration
we're doing next year.
>> So the temperatures are operating. What
sort of efficiency are you getting from
the device? And how does that compare
with the efficiencies of batteries that
people are developing that they also
claim can be very low cost and very
large scale things like molten metals
and so on.
>> Yeah. So most of the technologies that
I'm aware of that claim anything even in
the realm or approaching the cost that
we claim are all making the same trade
which is they get to lower cost by
trading efficiency. So, typical lithium
ion batteries are greater than 90%
efficient. And all the battery
technologies that get to like well below
$100 a kilowatt hour are all trading
efficiency and are closer to like 50%
efficiency or 60% in that range. In our
case, for our fourth power thermal
battery, the target is to get to 50%.
And all of this loss is really dictated.
I didn't I didn't actually finish
explaining how it works, but you know,
the entire system is extremely hot. So,
the nominal operating temperatures are
between,900°
C and 2400° C. To put that in
perspective, 2400 degrees C is about the
same temperature as um an incandescent
light bulb. It's about the same it's
about half the temperature of the sun.
Um so, there was an earlier question you
asked about safety. Um, so that's
usually the example that I give for
people like everybody has actually been
a couple inches away from something at
2400C which is which is a light bulb
filament. Um, so it high temperature
inherently on its own is actually not
dangerous. Typically what is is
dangerous is high pressure which is what
can lead to explosions and mechanical
failure. Um, you know what makes a light
bulb safe is the fact that it's got the
bulb around it. Right? So the point is
that there is a barrier between your
hand being able to try to touch
something at 2400C. And the same is true
for our system. There's an entire
warehouse built around the system
[music] that prevents anyone from being
able to walk up and touch or even see
any of this glowing white hardware.
[music] And this is where the moniker
came in the in the news calling it sun
in a box. [music]
>> [music]
>> You've talked about the notion that
climate change itself is a big enough
problem and also the the sort of
transition that has to happen is a big
enough problem that it's really
government scale money. Now in the US
currently we don't really see the
government investing huge amounts of
money. So how is the private sector
doing? I mean that's I assume who's
coming in and saying like okay let's
take a look at these batteries let's
implement them how's that going
>> it's slow um and and I think this is I
think a a principle
uh I I call it a fundamental problem
that we have which is I think there is a
assumption on the part of of um
you know we look at different
technologies and their proliferation
particularly things that don't require a
lot of hardware. You could look at, for
example, um, and iPhones as a as a as a
consumer technology. And you look at how
quickly iPhones took over the market.
And there's a a very uh it's very
enticing to want to think that energy
technologies could proliferate that
quickly and, you know, it's the right
solution, so everybody's got it a year
later. Uh, it doesn't work that way. the
the physical amount of hardware that has
to be deployed is so large the time
scale is just much longer and so the
main concern I have about uh the rate at
which we are moving is I think that
there's an assumption built into the
idea that you're just going to build
some cheaper solution and it's going to
get proliferated fast enough and and and
that assumption is that the rate at
which business or um the rate at which
the market will take up a new technology
technology that even at its maximum
speed is is actually fast enough to meet
the the goals that we have for the
climate. And I think that that
assumption may not be correct. That in
order for things to move fast enough,
there has to be like an external driving
force, something else that causes things
to happen much faster than they normally
would. And I generally label forces of
that nature governmental in nature.
Meaning it's it's got to be a collective
decision on behalf of humanity to
actually take some steps that will
actually either deincentivize
the emission of CO2 or or promote the
the its replacement so that you can
accelerate its decommissioning. And this
is actually an important point I want to
I want to point out because I've I think
I've probably said this publicly before,
but I love to to to highlight this point
because I think there's a big misnomer.
Um, building renewable energy on its own
actually doesn't solve climate change.
Um, stopping the use of fossil fuels is
what what stops climate change. And
those are two actually very different
things. Um, you know, I I'll use the
analogy of um let's say someone that is
uh [laughter]
uh physically unhealthy for eating a lot
of unhealthy foods, right? And it's like
you add some salad into their diet and
just adding salad doesn't actually keep
them from being unhealthy if they still
eat the unhealthy food, right? So, so at
the end of the day, we have to somehow
either deincentivize
uh the emission of CO2 or or incentivize
things that can can decommission those
assets quickly. And um and that's
actually what what stops climate change
is is is stopping the emissions of CO2.
So, um, to your point,
I think that
it's not it's going slow. I think that
if you talk to folks that are part of
the intergovernmental panel on climate
change, they they're very they're
they're watching the problem closely and
and we have not yet hit the turnover.
Like we're we have we have not yet like
decreased the amount of CO2 we're we're
emitting. We're actually we're still
increasing every year, right? So, we're
like business as usual is still
continuing and we're still it's still
getting worse. Now, here's the key point
just to tie this back to what I just
said.
>> The amount of renewables on the grid is
going up.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, like there's actually been a
significant amount of renewable
deployment and yet the CO2 emissions are
still going up.
>> I think China is a great example of that
where they build coal fired power plants
and renewables are taking off. Like two
things can be true at the same time.
It's not like you have to choose,
>> which obviously not good for climate
change, but solar power can be spreading
like crazy and you can be building coal
fired plants if you're industrializing
and so on.
>> Absolutely. And this this to me just
further underscores the main point I
want to make about storage being
arguably the single most important
technological problem we have to solve.
Because storage is really what enables
you to not have to build the coal plant
across the street from the solar plant,
right? Like what they do now is you
build a big solar field and then you put
a natural gas plant across the street to
to back it up. Um [clears throat] and
and energy storage has the ability to to
take the place of that backup gas plant.
We have plenty of excess capacity of
like power plants that sit idle and
don't output their full capacity. We're
not we're not lacking in total energy.
We have a we have a timeshifting problem
where the energy we want is not
available when we need it. And that is
cheapest and most effective to to uh
solve with with storing what you have
rather than just constantly building.
You know, I told someone um an analogy,
[laughter]
you know, um
it's like imagine you have a a grocery
store that supplies food for a caterer
and the caterer um is expected to
deliver their food at the event on time.
And if the caterer is late, you don't go
and then say, you know, we need to build
more grocery stores, [laughter]
right? the caterer actually just needs a
place to store the food uh so that they
can actually deliver on time and and
make sure that they can buffer buffer
the food, right? And so um that's kind
of the problem we have and right now
it's kind of you know when you have a
hammer everything's a nail. Uh the
commercialized technology we have
available to us is to build more gas
plants and so that's that's what that's
what we're we're we're doing. Um and we
are trying to change that by offering
storage as a as an alternative that's
cheaper and faster.
>> What sort of time frame are you working
on at at fourth power?
>> Yeah, given given where we are today, I
would say within within 5 years, you'll
see uh first commercial operating
systems. Uh so we're targeting the 28 uh
2028 to 2030 uh time frame for first
wave of initial deployments. Uh so we
have the first system integrated system
that we're looking to build next year in
2026. After that is then a uh pilot
system uh that will be fielded uh
outside
um working directly with the utility
that is effectively 10 times larger. So
about 10 megawatt hours in size and then
the system right after that and call it
the 2028 to 2030 time frame would be a
uh commercial operating system that is
um another 25 times larger in terms of
uh power and energy.
>> I just wonder when you think about
putting on your hat of realism and
thinking about uh storage which is
something you care a lot about and are
working on. Play it out for us for the
next 5 years. What do you think is going
to happen when it comes to storage? And
as you said, like that's just such a
seinal thing in thinking about
transition and and it's such an
important problem to solve. This is
something that I I think I have a
different opinion on than than many
folks, which is um I think there's a
natural tendency when you look at other
areas of technology to assume that there
is going to be this plethora of options
of different types of technologies that
will all have their special role to play
and do different things. Um I could be
wrong. It may it may turn out to be that
way, but I I think the problem of energy
storage is so kind of straightforward in
terms of what value needs to be given to
the grid that you may see a single or
maybe two technologies kind of win out.
And the
the correlary I have for this or the
analogy I have for this is just look at
the existing power infrastructure.
There is a single technology we use for
transmitting electricity. [laughter]
There is a single there's two there's
two different types of power plants we
build. There's there's the ranking cycle
and the braen cycle. They won out. They
beat the auto cycle. It be like
everything else. It's it's a monopoly
there. There's like a handful. Now,
there's many suppliers. You can have a
diversity of different I'm not saying
there's a single company that will win
but there likely will be a single or a
very small handful set of approaches
that end up really dominating because
they meet the needs the best and many
other things will fizzle out and so um I
think you know I put so much time and
energy into fourth power because I think
it's I think it's going to be one of
these key winners that ends up out there
in the end
>> and I it makes so much sense to me
because also you need to be able to
train people to build a certain way and
if you're like well there's six
different things on the menu [laughter]
that's a complicated menu but you know
if you just say like we either do it
this way or this way that's a simple
menu you can train people it's it's it's
easy to replicate I feel like
>> yeah there's there's so many aspects of
like consumer technologies and the
expectations around consumer
technologies that do not port over to
energy technologies, you know? So, like
for example, uh I'll just stick with
cell phones, right? Like, you know,
Apple invented this multi-touch screen
and it pretty much took over and you got
a variety of different flavors, right?
And it's being used on iPads and all
kinds of other stuff. Um, you know, when
you look at,
you know, as I mentioned, power plants,
there's like basically two two
inventions. If you look at cars, we all
use the autocycle. You mean there's like
a bunch of other thermodynamic cycles
for like making engines and no, we don't
use any of them. [laughter]
Um, if you look at heating and cooling
and refrigeration, right? Um, we use the
vapor compression cycle, it's like over
a hundred years old and it's still the
best. It's still the thing we all use.
It's a single technology that's winning.
I mean, and there have been a number of
other technologies that have been
proposed. It can't compete.
>> But so incumbency is always a problem.
And it it's part of what you're talking
about here, I think. I mean, with with,
you know, silicon PV, this is a
technology that's 70 years old, at least
in the 60s since it began to be
commercial. It's not the most efficient
solar technology you can think of. It's
got all kinds of disadvantages. But one
way or another through either government
incentives or just ease of manufacturing
and strategies that governments like the
Chinese government adopted for example
of bringing it to scale and subsidizing
it. It has reached such an enormous
scale of deployment and along with it
the whole ecosystem of power electronics
and battery systems and ways of thinking
and it's reached such giant scale that
it's very hard for better technologies
to overtake it. That's also true some
would say of lithium-ion batteries that
have reached this enormous scale now and
and better alternatives just can't
possibly get there. What do you do about
that? I mean to some extent what you're
suggesting is that your technologies are
so super fantastic that we should
implement them and and the government
should subsidize them and then they'd
become incumbents and we'd have the same
problem. We sort of
>> get in the way of of creative
destruction that could lead to another
generation of technologies.
>> I think you're right and I think that's
the position that myself and many
technology developers and inventors we
operate from. If you can't beat the
existing state-of-the-art, you don't you
don't get to play. Full stop. And and so
you've got to offer something above and
beyond what exists today. Otherwise, you
should go home.
>> And so
>> it's an enormously high standard.
>> It's not the end point that you have to
match. It's today's performance and cost
that you have to match. Incredibly hard.
>> It is. I mean, this is why, you know,
like I I said very much earlier, right?
I really think we should be lauding and
celebrating and and in some way like
really commemorating and rewarding
everyone and all the various people that
worked on um bringing wind turbines and
PV to the cost that they're at now. We I
I remember I still remember in 2011,
you know, we had a term that we used to
throw. We used to call it grid par.
We're like, when the cost of PV gets to
a dollar a watt and it's like the same
cost as a turbine, it's a big deal,
right? And we got to grid parody and
then we passed it. It got even cheaper,
right? And we celebrated at that moment.
That celebration to me should still
continue. It's it's such an amazing uh
feat to have brought a technology like
you said from you know a hundred times
more expensive than the state-of-the-art
to to being half the cost of the
state-of-the-art and and to displace it.
That happens so rarely in in in energy
um that that it definitely needs to be
uh respected and and praised and you
know we are trying to do the exact same
thing in storage. I mean, storage is
storage is a bit different because there
isn't really a widely proliferated
um state-of-the-art already. You know,
the form of energy storage we use today
is basically leaving fossil fuels in the
ground. Like we we have like one-time
use storage. So, it's like it's all
stockpiled in the ground. We draw from
it. We use it at the rate that we want.
Um but there isn't really a rechargeable
form of storage above ground that we
that has been widely proliferated.
lithium-ion batteries are are working
their way out, but they're limited on
cost and so they're going to very
quickly push up against a ceiling um you
know in terms of how much deployment is
going to happen due to cost. And so we
are trying to prep for the second wave
and come right behind them with with
something better that's much cheaper.
[music]
>> I feel like we need to have this
conversation in 5 years to see where
things are.
>> Yeah. Asha Gun Henry, thank you so much.
This [music] has been great.
>> Thank you for having me.
>> Thanks, Ashen.
[music]
>> What if [music] it works is a production
of the MIT Energy Initiative. If you
like the show, please leave us a review
or invite a friend to listen. And
remember to subscribe [music] on Apple
Podcast, Spotify, or wherever you get
your podcasts.
You can find an archive of every
episode, all of our show notes, and a
lot [music] more at
energy.mmit.edu/mpodcasts.
And you can learn more about the work of
[music] the energy initiative and the
energy transition at energy.mmit.edu.
[music] Our original podcast artwork is
by Zitler Design. Special thanks to all
of the people at Mighty and MIT who make
this show possible.
>> [music]
>> I'm Cara Miller.
>> And I'm Rob Stoner.
>> Thanks for listening.