Let's start with looking at the standard
definition of money. So money is a tool
that helps us to measure value. It's a
tool that allows us to [music] um
exchange products and services and it's
a tool to store value. But then the
question is what is the value? Where
does the value come from? [music] Money
today is fiat money. So money is not
backed by physical values like gold but
money is backed [music] by the
government and issued by the central
bank. So the value of money has to do
with our trust in the government, our
trust in [music] the economic system.
Money um is basically a legal construct.
[music] So money sits at the edge
between our economic system and our
political system.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.