okay let's get started let's get this
world world we're moving on uh this is
week four so we're on topic four they're
not always going to line up so neatly
with a week but as long as we can do it
just makes the mind a little better and
week four is about equality equivalence
in intervals
um so uh first thing
first any questions on problem set three
those who have started working on
it yeah one of the
scores was behaved weird when I was yeah
anyone else see anything weird about
10.7 did you show the score um yeah I
showed the score I counted the number of
notes and then I actually
like or maybe I'm not thinking of 10.7
then if if it didn't immediately got
like three times as many notes when I
did score analysis but it didn't have it
on any the pieces but I actually
physically counted them my hand
interesting look look at that one show
doesn't show the entire score yeah show
doesn't yeah show doesn't show the
entire score in Jupiter uh that's a
feature um thank you for for reminding
me that's a feature in um in Version 9
which was supposed to be released before
the beginning of class but we found bugs
in that where you'll be able to look at
the other Parts yeah yeah 10.9 is a
longer uh one of the longer scores thank
you thank you one of the other scores
has something uh a little bit different
to about it that's worth looking at cool
um yeah yeah so uh especially if you
don't um if it doesn't seem to conclude
with a a nice authentic Cadence or
something like that then probably not
and actually for anybody um nice I don't
have any prizes I didn't bring any um
Candy or anything say 66.6 one we're
working on does it end with an authentic
Cadence or something else that'll be an
interesting point when we get around to
automatic Roman numeral analysis uh
which we will get to later that that the
preview I think that's P set seven it
might be P set eight that's the other
one uh and I'll give you some notice in
advance that's the other pet that um
that takes a little bit more time though
that one's uh you have a group for that
okay um great uh you all watched I can I
can see most people are doing very good
job of keeping up with videos and things
uh this weekend by the way you won't
have any um you all need a break from
that definitely um but uh most people
keep me up with videos anything about
the sound discore the thing I had hop to
get into class but that we instead uh
watch me not blabber live but blabber on
video um anything about that there were
some really cool uh other examples
anybody want to share theirs U on there
that one that one I did give sometimes
just one to two words feedback but what
what were some of the things that you
could
use what are some of the steps do you
remember in going from um an audio file
to audio to uh score what was some of
the things you needed to
do frequency analysis what's that
frequency analysis good good more toward
the end the beginning toward the
beginning okay so somewhere over here
with frequency analysis
y pitch connections what what did we
mean by that just I guess that's
technically analing the not
are What notes are being produced what
notes are being produced in the
frequencies yeah what's slightly
different about frequency you you I
think you started to say oh that's
actually the then you're like no it's
not actually the same what's the
difference between frequency analysis
and
um pitches musical
pitches what's what's the thing we need
to do M I guess some like pictures or
notes they have multiple frequencies
like overtones so they try to analyze
that and create like instrument yeah
yeah when you play a really low
note you can hear some of them
especially if I take um one of the
[Music]
notes and you
get rid of the really low frequencies
you
can start hearing the thing if you ever
are writing a piano piece and you need
some bells in the background that's
always a good
trick just okay um not too many
composers writing for piano and wanting
Bells um okay so good so we have um yeah
so we're we're taking out the harmonic
spectrum and uh we're getting the
pitches and things from that what's
what's the by product if we're thinking
of like nuclear fion we have all these
energy and we have this Radioactive by
product what what do we learn when we
strip out the overtones what might we be
able to learn um and get down to the
frequ to the notes
themselves if you do that with a whole
bunch of
notes or a whole bunch of sets of
frequencies think it it was already said
but wasn't super explicit the word
already appeared um in what M
said take a take a stab what what are we
talking about when we're talking about
overtones and and
harmonics are they always the same yeah
Vanessa
you don't necessarily want to consider
you're considering the individual
pitch kind of present for all of the
different like individual pitches that
You' be playing so you need to determine
when that's something that you should be
paying attention to as opposed to like
if it's in a chord or not yeah super so
chord chords definitely an issue problem
we'll leave that offic up what if we
just follow up um are does every D that
you analyze let's say d octave 4 does it
always have the same overtone Spectrum
no what what determines the
difference it's okay great John the
instrument the instrument yeah so I said
this this was there so one of the things
while we're going from frequency I
should have had something up here while
we're going from frequency to um to
pitches the byproduct is we determining
what instrument is being played so we
have that good what are some other other
parts of it that um of the of the
process that we
remember Hannah the duration and Tempo
the duration and Tempo great does
duration tell you the tempo or does
Tempo tell you who votes duration tells
you the tempo who votes Tempo tells you
the
duration who votes something else
something more complex yeah you could
also have raised your hand on both of
them there's kind of that weird feedback
loop that you can't tell the tempo
unless you have a whole bunch of
duration
but then the temple will also tell you
something about you is that a quarter
note so you second duration good any
other parts that stood out
from what what what somebody else's
people give great great examples of
something that you could once you think
you have a score once you're at some
part you could use something from music
theory or history to bring
back I'm going to put you on the spot
cuz I remember yours was very good I
don't remember what okay
good there y all y all do your work
early in the weekend and it's out of
mind any anyone want to make
up think yours was on articulations was
it not spato oh perhaps yeah that you
could find that there's go ahead what oh
no I just going to say that like
sometimes you might hear it as like a
lot of notes I followed by like short
rests and not
um but then based on the piece or style
you might go back and mark it as yeah
yeah based based on based on having a
whole bunch of notes that always have
this you large amount of rest you might
say spato or staccato or something or
the notes are all running into each
other you might say this is legato you
might get out slurs things good any
anybody
else either remember theirs or something
else come to mind
um trying to trying to remember there
were there were at least three that I um
that I've never seen uh that I never
thought of that I was like Wow and then
then about seven more that I'm like
we're on the same wavelength with each
other okay I we come back to that later
what one of the things you'll find um
the end of problem set three asks you to
write your own question right it asks
you hey if you had a whole bunch of cson
based on the tools you have for
statistical analysis what kinds of
questions you could ask and it doesn't
ask you to answer that um but you're
going to find um that as the semester
goes on those become bigger and bigger
parts of the problem sets taking more
time you'll be asked to pose your own
question and answer them and um both the
quality of the answer but also the
interest or the the you know of the
question becomes really important and
why why is that important what are we
going to do at the end of the
semester we're going to pose our own
question and try to solve it right and
what what do researchers do in the world
for the most part they pose an
interesting question and they try to
solve it so we're going to try to make
it so by the end of the semester you're
not just students who are who are given
an assignment to do but also posing your
own your own questions and so you'll
you'll probably get sick of the fact
that I'm asking you to document uh write
doc strings and all that stuff in your
problem sets now and at first it's
pretty silly because I'm asking you
specifically to do you know one task um
but um you know but then as it goes on
the more and more complex problems
you're going to be making your own sub
problems uh pet 4 is the first one where
I suggest that you might write some
helper functions that won't be graded
it'll be the first time where I think
you probably shouldn't try to solve
everything right in the answer um and so
you you know that's a good time to
practice doing that type of
thing anything else before moving on to
the third little topic um from from the
uh weekend discussion music
XML any thoughts anybody um watch the
interview with Michael Gooden take away
anything you want to share
he's gonna drop into this class um in a
couple weeks I think uh he's visiting
campus uh I think it's is yeah go ahe I
think one thing that I kind of took away
from the deal was just how much effort
goes into like creating something and
then trying to like nor sure it's like
survivability into the future like how
much of your own effort has to G to
advocating for something when there's
nothing to be doneil yeah yeah so he did
this huge he said you know well I came
up with this format and then I had to
Market it and I don't know if everybody
knows finale and sellus some of you all
know Muse score and note flight and
things flat might be the things you know
now as much but yeah th but those were
the two big leaders and he just felt
like if he couldn't get one of them to
use his product he might as well not
have made it and then just going around
trying to um trying to make more and
more and more um things out of it and
it's been a super successful uh Legacy
uh Michael good finally retired from
running the U music XML spec from from
taking charge and making sure it was all
working after doing that for uh what was
it 20 24 years of doing it um but he
finally found some poor schmuck to take
on that uh role and agreed to do it for
the next couple years um he also
mentions in the the something called uh
mnx which is interesting um that it's
really beginning to uh pick up some
steam and so what music XML was
primarily about if you recall it was
about trans you have data in one
application and you want to get data in
some other application and you don't
want to convert it down to MIDI and lose
spelling and lose all the things about
Tempo estimation and beat and spato and
and all these other things you want to
transfer over into music exml was really
great is really really great for
transferring documents things but once
you get it into your application uh
almost every application you use has
some sort of internal memory
representation right you've you've coded
things that you store oh I I'm going to
store the name here as a string and
somebody else's well I'm storing it as
an array of characters so I can
manipulate it you know whatever it is
everybody has a different representation
and music XML was not good for that that
wasn't what it was designed for but now
more and more people uh want that and
they want something and so uh M andx
something like music notation next or
something the X doesn't really mean
anything the next format was coming out
and the encoding format the final
decision on that it's going to be
entirely Json based do who has heard of
Json should who is not feels okay yeah
so it's the the data format interchange
format originally for JavaScript that's
what the J JS stands for but now used by
almost every language um it's sort of
where XML was 20 years ago that this is
the thing that everybody knows that's uh
the thing now and so trying to figure
out exactly what's going to how it's
going to work but um but this is pretty
exciting things that that the next 20 25
years 30 years of music notation was
finally decided uh
yesterday so that was uh that's pretty
good it's it's an exciting exciting
world and if you get very into notation
and representation and things you can
jump onto the GitHub repository and
start saying you know no if you
represent a cordian symbols in this way
it will never be useful for what I like
to do with a cordian it doesn't have to
be that esoteric it could even be on
octaves the question is uh we all like
writing things like pitch
C4 something like that but um boy you
know should it be should it be like uh
name c and
octave four and therefore you have one
less thing that you have to convert from
a string to an INT there and so that
when you get so that your program won't
CR crash on octave -2 or whatever
happens octave 10 all the things that we
always uh forget to do so anyhow that's
what's been happening uh a little bit in
the
world okay let's get to the main um
topics today um let's start with the
concept of equality what's it mean for
something in music to be equal to
something else what's it mean what does
it mean for two notes to be equal I'm
going to uh we're a little bit less um
sort of less uh I don't know vigorous
today than um than we have in the past
so I'm going to I'm going to call on uh
some people just because there's not
really a right wrong answer on this um
the first person I'm going to call on is
Jason then I'm G to call
on
uh then I'll call on
Hannah then uh Paul so what what would
you say means for two notes to be uh
equal I guess abstractly maybe just
thees are the same and durations are the
same okay so pitches are the same least
s pitch
same
duration the
same what do we mean by pitch is the
same abstractly mostly like if you
really want to compare the quencies like
the overtones and stuff that might cause
some issues so I guess abstractly
just maybe going down to MIDI is a
little too simple but
like just name and accidentals okay
great the
name and accidental are the same this is
by a very good definition so so we could
completely go with that and do you want
to um change anything go with it um I
was going to say something really
similar probably also consider the
octave so
octave has to be the
same um anybody else want to jump in you
want I would say that the you wouldn't
say that the accidentals have to be the
same
so what give me an example of of
something that that would be the same
without
umat
dlat and and C sharp great so in this
case not only is The Accidental
different what else is different the
name good so what what can we put
instead for that
what what what what do we call what's
what's a representation that allows
these to be
equal the uh pitch class what you might
be thinking of yeah pitch
class or pitch class plus octave what's
another uh thing that encodes pitch
class plus octave heard this four-letter
acronym used a couple times
John I was going to say space but it's
not four letter it's not four space
space is good yeah Adam mid midi so it's
midi
number good so we could do this
so so when you turn in your homework for
your tonal Harmony class and it says F
major 5 to one write this and you put
in
uh and you get it wrong marked Wrong by
your teacher that that wasn't 5 to one I
think I got no that's definitely well
that wouldn't be 5 to one anyhow that's
one I'm looking for um
do do all of these notes have the same
midi number
as good so um so maybe we don't want to
go with that because there's there's a
place where your teacher says it's wrong
right on the other hand what are the
consequences of that of of not saying
that M uh are these two notes the
same of course when I do this it's
always a trick question what do you
think the answer should
be yes but we already said we're we're
not going to count that the same and I
played a C and A B Sharp you all you all
knew that right I conceptually flipped
the inharmonic between the two so um so
Okay so we've L worked ourselves into a
real bind I think this is a useful
exercise but the answer really comes
with uh we don't really really know and
we can Define different cases where uh
where we use the words we don't use the
word equal too much but let's say the
same the same
um if I yeah go ahead I just had a quick
question about like what what cases
would this like the the details of the
meaning of musical equality
really uhhuh great we're about we're
about to get into that what what cases
let's we'll open that up as as a topic
to to think about there I can I have
some in my head and it's going to be
your your one one slide ahead of me but
um but maybe um Everybody sing sing this
with
[Music]
me well the men's Sayang with me but the
woman
didn't unless we have and a saying
seeing this doesn't include the
octave right so it um but
also uh we we can think of a lot of
different things that might be slightly
different with each other um we can also
say that here are two
notes bom
bom are they the same yeah in some ways
but also no the first one was on beat
one the second one was on beat two there
might be cases where we want to not just
consider the duration which we didn't
even talk about because I already began
this semester with the trick question of
how many notes we remember that good
good good I'm starting to see smiles and
things uh and not just you know scared
calling me but uh yeah but but not only
uh duration but we might also consider
the what beat it's on that we might not
consider that to be the
same um so there might be different
cases like that uh here's an example
from uh one of these oops well it's even
more complex than I expected it to be
without that um great who's who is my uh
uh designated tell Professor when he's
projecting without projector that's all
of you right you'll all you'll all take
it on yourselves to say in safe time
good um so this is one of these weird
experimental pieces from the 60s and 70s
and things called beru by a composer uh
who's a Dartmouth professor of
philosophy actually uh Christian wolf uh
friend of John cages and this is a
typical things it's in a whole bunch of
movements but very famously for me is
um the opposite of equal uh is the
instructions for number three each
player is to make about 400 511 sounds
each sound different in some way and I
remember uh talking with uh Professor
wolf um he was sort of a guest speaker
in one of my composition classes once
and he was talking about the
interpretation that this part uh
movement ended up being one of his
favorite ones watching it performed to
see what people
did and in one case a player had a
bucket um and then had another bucket
filled with water and took an eye
dropper and dropped one drip of water
into the other bucket and hit it drop
one hit it drop one because the
frequency would change and after 500
changed a lot and so he
thought the the composer was saying Oh I
thought this was very interesting and
other people did all kinds of things but
as you can imagine uh you get your piece
played with a larger Ensemble and some
people are really really into this kind
of music I can find it if you've never
performed a piece like this uh don't
knock it till you tried it it always
sounds kind of I won't enjoy it then you
then you go and do it and you with all
your friends and you're and you're
trying to follow these instructions it
can be quite quite wonderful but there's
always somebody who's not going to want
to do it and it said there was I think
it was it was a trombone player who just
sat there b b b b and the composer only
came to the performance not any the
rehearsals and he said he got so furious
at first because the only thing the only
constraint he put on him was on on the
performer was that each note had to be
different in some other way and so the
only thing you can do anything you want
choosing not to and he said but of
course it's 51 notes so I had a long
time to think about it and after a while
I began to really really like what he
was doing because every one of them was
different because first it was a bot out
of the blue then it was a Bop that had
been preceded by a Bop then it was a Bop
that had been preceded by two other ones
and the one that you hear in the 100th
time is very different so this is all to
say that we um we can think of equality
in many many different ways and that
there could be different cases where you
want to do something different than the
other um let's go ahead and start a
Jupiter notebook you guys are seem to be
pretty fast at getting this and we want
to figure out some um definitions of
equal that music 21 has used but um just
only to think of what kinds of
assumptions were built into the system
even though or not um you could have
just about any one so I'm over here and
how do we just just to review how do we
test in Python that X is five equals 5
assert what's that just shout it
assert
x five
no um no what what
what if you were doing it an if
statement what would you do if
x equals equals 5 good good yeah problem
is I have to remember where my trick
questions are and where we're going to
the uh the real ones so you can do it
good
um and Python's a little bit interesting
that we can create two mutable arrays
we'll say a is 3 comma 4 B is 3A 4 does
a equal
B yes
remember you say yes no we can hit shift
enter and get it this case yes let's um
I think I can do this up here without
anything going can I make this any
bigger yep I can uh let's do this in
JavaScript let X =
3a4 let y b = 3A 4 AAL
B
false so two very well often used
languages both kind of scripting type
languages first time I've shown my
console in a while
um that yeah that end up with very
different results on that let me just
make a note for myself to make sure to
do
that
yeah this is by the way one of the first
mistakes I always make when switching
over to JavaScript now python has the
second equality operator so there's
equals equals and
there's is yeah
so a is
B
false so um do X is
five yes or
no you get all kinds of warnings now if
you're on a new p saying that's not
really a great way to do it that's not
really a great way to do it hey stop
doing this Michael stop doing oh but
yeah it's true so um various things but
if we um so x = 5 yals 5 x is
y true actually it's very odd there's
all these weird things that happen so
you'll find that um that there other uh
things that that come up um quite often
that are all the choice that somebody
made um at some point to do it so let's
do music
equivalence Ops um from music 21 import
note is that big enough no it got
smaller and here's something I'm going
to that I am going to do when I'm in
class n equal note. note capital N
equals note. note and notice I'm not
calling it what I'm saying is the
variable capital N can now be used as
the class note. note so I can do things
like uh n
C4 do show and same as anything else I
probably should of call that and works
the same so
let give everybody a second to catch
up I'm going to create two of those C4s
I call it C I'll call it
C2 and what do you hope that the answer
on this
is
true by the way I did I am running music
21 Version 9 and you all are running
version 8.1 or 8.3 or something like
that we changed a few equals things so
if something up here is different from
yours shout out and I'll try to remember
if that's a place we change it but I
don't think we'll get too much into that
good so so two notes that the same are
there let's call C3 equals and an O the
same note an octave higher so go and
type that
what do we
hope yeah could if you're all ever
behind
uh so false they're not not the same
operation does the duration need to be
the
same so let's just remember that c is
the same as C2 let's say
C2 duration quarter length
equals 4.0 what's what's the anyone
remember what's the default quarter
length in music
21 one that's why it shows a coordin
note so we'll make it four which is
what whole not good C is the same as
C2 false so so good we some a lot of us
have the same um sort of intuition as as
each other maybe that's bad maybe that's
group think um so does anything thing
make an object the same we'll say
C4 equals we'll create another in this
case C4 is
C4 C equals
C4 what
about um C here's something you probably
haven't seen LC equals
hello we can
show hopefully that should work
and c4's
lyric I don't know what what's a
favorite language French we do
bonjour does C equals C4
now is that the same on
yours so we've decided the we the music
21 Community I don't can't remember if I
decided this one or not but I'm living
with it that the lyric
does is not an essential part of the
equality of a note that two notes can
have different lyrics but still be the
same thing um where all Yankovic has
been working on that for a very long
time right you can do the same song
Different lyrics still the same
song
um okay well let's let's do this
one BS uh not for barsh let's create a
BP and but oh if I want the same note
let's let's see how um how anal your
your music theory teaching was if I want
the same note as C for sorry C4 in as a
b what's the
octave four four three four well first
let's let's create bar
4 and by the way this is one of these
things I think that there's a lot of
consensus on this but not unanimity so
somebody might have taught you something
else but the octave
number refers to the letter name and so
when you put lots of Sharps on it even
though this this is the same note as C
five five it's still in octave 4 because
the B is an octave four these are all
weird things so we want BS well we can
say pitch.
octave equals 3
now guess should be the same note oh I
just slipped it should be the same note
uh as as C Shar right so if it's the
same note or C natural so if it's the
same note then these two should be equal
right and they are
not so how do you work in a world where
um where you want this to be equal one
way you can do this um a nice thing
about a lot of languages like python is
um you can Mony do something called
monkey patching so we can just create a
new equality thing uh return whether or
not um. pitch. midi equals b. pitch.
midi who's
um
um idea and then we can say that n which
is the same as no do
notes it's special thing that you run
uncore EQ which is run anytime you check
equality equals new EQ so now anytime
there's want to do equality we can check
that so we can do um this is Si I use
German when I need to do things uh e
Shar equals that and F is our normal F
now we can see is e Shar the same as f
yes just before I do do it you will
create things like this all the time to
deal with your um definition of equality
do this much less often because I'm not
even sure if note doow will work anymore
or if there's other things there yeah um
what did you say about um like the B sh
um 4 going back to C4
so so that um the this definition of
octave which I used quite a bit has the
notion that the octave defines a range
of sort of Staff spaces so if we're in
trouble
cleff this is
all octave
four October 4th it doesn't matter how
many flats or Sharps you put down
anything anything that's written on
those staff spaces in shovel cff will be
octave 4 so in this case writing B Shar
4 would be pointing outside of the St no
so so B you first see okay I want octave
four and then I want the B and octave
four so it's going to be this one so B
Sharp would be this
one even though the C in octave four is
down here so so but but like if you play
the B 4 in this it would still sound the
same as so C5 a C5 yep
great like I said you could probably
find somewhere someone who's not using
that definition and you can definitely
find a lot of places where this has not
been uh well defined um in a lot of
textbooks but yep any other questions on
that um we can try certain things are
um meter time signature anyone play this
play this 34 the same as meter uh this
is why I abbreviate these things time
signature
68 copy all
that
oops yes it's exactly the same if you
don't import meter they're both an error
from music 21 import
meter so it's not just based on the
duration of the meter you can try to
figure out there's some ways that you
can Define time signatur such that they
um they might look the same but do
different is um 2 28 + 38 the same as 38
plus 28 and so
on any other questions on um oh and even
in this case by the way that where we've
redefined to be midi is um here I'm
going to put this up here so it's next
to it uh
Eis is f false yep
that supposed to happen I think that
might be one of the places that um was
fixed in version eight in version
nine yes so that was changed in version
9 I think that I remember that was
sometime over um over the holidays I got
an urgent call from somebody who was
like ah I needed this to work and it
didn't okay so that's that's good
there's a lot of things there are still
up in the air and um and they're all
things that people can debate so equal
isn't equals kind of slightly arbitrary
in this case um play it but um let's
let's do one um exercise it'll take
about five minutes to do um either get a
blank document you can probably just jot
it down also in Jupiter or it's kind of
more fun with a blank sheet of paper or
something and you're going to hear a
shakon which uh is a theme that repeats
over and over and what I want you to do
is um there'll be some letters and maybe
don't try to count the number of
measures say like just before a or a
little bit after A or B these rehearsal
letters and want to find out where you
hear the shakon theme each time it
begins at the beginning so you all get
that as a as a freebie but I want to try
to um do and then if it's the shakon
theme but transformed what's transformed
about it
anybody know that piece before played it
a few people anyone playing it right now
believe it's on yep it's on the wi
ensemble's next concert I saw that
around great so if you like it's a great
piece um one of uh hols greatests maybe
after the planets things but one of one
of his wonderful pieces so about how
many did people
find tell how many you find seven or so
seven or so
about pretty much like there the whole
time it's there the whole time good
anyone find a place where it
wasn't what's different on the second
entrance John good
theyed so it's when harmonized so
something can be a thinge can be the
same thing
but harmonized what else is different
everybody
yeah it's what the instrument that plays
it the instrument that plays it
[Music]
good I always think that one the
clarinet's going to enter it but then
somebody other one does what else has
changed remember where it started yeah
the Dynamics good so Dynamics we
consider something sometimes to be the
same sometimes not if the Dynamics are
different now we're back to a very low
octave which we weren't in every time
[Music]
what's different this time duration
duration or we could say spacing between
the two right because the the duration
hasn't really changed but so that's
another thing that we might think of as
the same but
different register instrument
again so um I'm going to fade it out for
a little bit so that we can uh St so all
of these things that we wouldn't say
it's they playing the exact same music
right but we're saying in some sense
they're playing the same thing as before
and we'll get one more uh coming in up
in just a little
bit this is very beautiful anyhow
[Music]
what's
here do anyone hear the theme
now
nobody Hol seems to think that the theme
is still playing here so he doesn't yeah
it's like the concept other the theme
still there is just kind of more major
theme little bit more Majoris theme yep
going yeah is it inverted is it
inverted what do we have here
[Music]
inste
done so it's an
inversion is playing something upside
down the same as playing it
depends it really really depends if I
say let's all sing happy birthday let's
see if I can do this and you all go uh
Happy Birthday to uh to how was it going
to you you like okay you just ruin my
birthday right right so it's not always
the same yet there are some places where
composers think of it as the Same by the
way if you don't have that one of the
things nobody said was it's the same
when the rhythm's the same if nothing
else right John John John John John John
John John so it is even still the same
Rhythm even if it wasn't um perfectly if
it wasn't fully inverted but yeah so
things that are sometimes we want to
consider the same and sometimes we don't
we don't tend to call them equal very
much we tend to say that they're
equivalent and there equivalent in some
way or what we'll often use I'm putting
this up so somebody might put this back
down um is that they're equivalent under
something so
um let me uh take something that you
might know uh right now just looking up
there it's a very musical we just did a
follow of John Cage in the time right
now is
that anybody prefer that
time what's what's the equivalence
here how how is it that that some people
might say especially if I put that on uh
that these two are equivalent but let's
let's get rid of that for
now yeah 12
hour 24 hour
yeah so 12h hour can can each time in a
12h hour in a we could call it an AM
PM um world has an equivalent in a
24-hour you could call it military time
whatever you want to call it world so
that there is an equivalence that allows
the mapping back and forth between them
not all equivalences allow a perfect
mapping good
mathematically what do you need to do
if you're at
[Music]
25 p.m. what do you do to convert that
to 24-Hour
time 12 at 12 good and what do you do if
you are at
14:05
p.m. and you need to do it you can
subtract 12 or you can think of it as
mod mod yeah is it mod 12 or mod 24 both
happen to work both happen to work do
they no 24 doesn't work because uh 20
2350 okay yeah but in that case it works
in this case it yes in this case it
works yes good always always solve for
the most specific case you can no of
course well no we'll try solve for the
most General case so mod 12 there's some
um other little thing that you have to
do on this uh right if you're at uh
1205 uh
PM let's see yeah in that case no I
can't remember anyhow there's something
off by one errors don't follow don't try
to figure them off at the but there's
this particular case where if it equals
zero you're going to want to add 12 so
it's sort of uh mod 12 plus I I can't
remember you'll you'll figure it out I
know how to do it in music and stuff so
let's think of some equiv musical
equivalence classes one of the ones that
we've put up here and so one of the
reasons we debate a lot about equals is
that equals is trying to uh create a set
of equivalence classes once and for all
this is better I'll keep this more
Center just um
so here's a
particular thing that we can debate
whether or not they're equal music 21
has decided that they are not but that
could be debatable but we I don't think
it's debatable that there is some form
of equivalence between these two what do
we want to call that and inharmonic
equivalence
good
inharmonic
equivalents they are enharmonically
equivalent somebody tell me if I got my
e and A's right yeah did this time um we
can also sometimes say they're
equivalent under spelling under um under
lack of spelling or say equivalent with
spelling good what's another equivalence
class that we're we're going to go
really fast so so let's start start
thinking what's what's something else
that we might sometimes think is
equivalent we said
inversion sometimes but often not good
what's another
in duration duration sometimes we don't
care how long two things are
good key ooh that would be good great I
heard another one just tell octave
octave I should have chosen the one
without staff lines twice as much space
keep going everybody what's that
instrument instrument
yeah sometimes
it sometimes it doesn't matter what
instrument is playing we'd say it's the
same thing and sometimes when you hire a
musician to perform uh at your wedding
and they show up with an accordion and a
bag pipe it's not equivalent right good
what other things that that we might say
context what's that Contex context what
uh no too broad too broad we'll have to
good good idea we uh give me one context
that might be like where you're coming
from where you're going to where you're
coming
from coming
from from going to so the same song is
the same under equivalent of car stereo
versus home
right it's interesting that that we
might think um give me a context we're
listening to the same song uh in your
recording studio versus uh or or at home
versus your car might be a
difference the same song might not be
equivalent under that if the car has
police sirens in it if the car has
police sirens in it good I was thinking
uh if you're trying to to uh mix your
composition for submission right does it
does it matter if you're listening at
home in stereo with your very nice
headphones is it the same piece as if
you were um you know let's hope you're
not doing while driving you're in the
passenger seat but you're doing it on a
noisy road yeah so the amount of
background noise might be a context that
changes whether or not you think this
piece of music is the same yeah like if
you're looking at a pitch like what the
cord is coming yeah I knew that I knew
that I knew you met that but uh yeah so
uh
preceding seeding versus
following
good other things this this have been
super
great yeah articulation articulation
good articulation good shout some more
Tempo
Tempo the same piece is the same piece
if you uh rush through it right some
sometimes s not but yeah good anything
else we can keep thinking of more I
don't want to use them all up because I
think we're going to be asked to come up
with at least uh one that's there great
um so this is this is really really good
you're going to be reading
um yall got to be
faster y'all going to be uh reading
another section from this book by
Dimitri Tacho um a geometry of music
and um a second part of chapter 2 which
you read uh earlier when we were talking
about those um flipped inversions with
the mirrors and he defines Five Points
of inversion or five equivalence classes
that we think of quite often in
music uh and and he gave them the the
ordering isn't the greatest ordering in
the world except it makes it very easy
to remember optic and I'm going to add a
sixth one Cu uh I I think it's very
important too um the octave quite often
we don't care we the two musical
elements two chords to be the same if
they're in different
octaves right or two two notes the same
note or equivalent note permutation what
do you think that
means out you have a cord version of it
perhaps you want to consider them the
same yeah so we have you have an
inversion of the chord you might
consider it the same you might the order
that goes only that would only work if
you also have octave
um let me
[Music]
um is there some way that those are the
same
they're both if I so the first note was
C they're both
arpeggiated C major Triads right you can
hear hear that does it matter sometimes
it matters if well you're arpeggiating
it up and it matters if you're ping it
down if you're doing your theory
analysis does that matter if you're
trying to put a cord no so sometimes on
the other hand if you take uh let's
stick with happy birthday I'm going to S
happy birthday to you but I've I've run
it through my python scramble thing I'm
going to do um every note in a different
order we would not apply that
equivalence class to that place so
permutation um is something that quite
often when we're just analyzing the
cordal structure of a measure we don't
really care what order the notes come in
we just want to see what are all the
notes in the measure and then figure out
what chord it might be so the
permutation transposition when us who
shouted key is that yeah John were you
thinking
of of that the same piece in two
different Keys could be yeah that and
just saying like oh I mean is kind of um
synonymous to an harmonics if you're
like G flat major okay yep also great
but sometimes it it doesn't matter
actually what key you're in if you're uh
if you're a singer and you show up and
people used to be able to pianist
accompanies uh collaborators used to
really know how to do this and stuff
you've been practicing all uh all week
in G major and the the singer comes to
the concert and says I I woke up with a
scratchy throat can we take it down to F
today and they play and you're still
playing in some ways the same piece so
the the transposition might not matter
in some cases in some cases it really
matters one place it really matters is
um if you're playing the viola in the
orchestra and you choose to transpose
and nobody else does I think people will
notice right right uh so transposition
again these are all equivalence classes
I I didn't do a good job of this in
other years of lecturing so I want to
say now these are things that in certain
contexts make sense to apply and in
certain contexts do not make sense to
apply and so transposition is one here
uh inversion we've already talked about
in some cases it makes sense to apply
and some cases it doesn't want to say
there are two different um a number of
different definitions of inversion and
that's actually one of the things
happens one is something that we call a
tonal inversion where you
um
say no tonal I'll put it in the key
signature something like that instead of
going up four notes we go down four
notes and then go down one more note so
um in this case it's exactly the same
let me go um let me keep going up
here ah I have to go one more note up
assum these go
here eventually you get to a point where
this is a half
step and this is a that was good to L
lines whole step um in a tonal inversion
you just care that you went up a step in
one and you went down a step in the
other if you went up four steps you
don't really care if it's a perfect
fourth or whatever in uh an atonal or
post tonal or non-tonal thing we would
really want to make sure that where did
I screw up there has to be some place
because because this this is an octave
up I'm pretty sure if you go up an
octave you end up going down in octaves
your first series of notes in the second
the right hand
one ah uh so that's a sorry I'm now I'm
in a postal world so now I need to write
all my accidentals I oh there it is
that's the whole step and so that would
have to be the half whole step whole
step and there right yeah so uh so those
are the two kinds of inversion that he's
talking about um and sometimes it makes
sense sometimes it doesn't if you listen
to the music of um the the post tonal
music of the early 20th century uh they
use inversional symmetry a lot and so if
you're trying to figure out oh how does
this relate to something I heard before
almost always try well is it the
inversion of it um and there's here some
cool things that um here's here's uh
four Triads you might know them by name
um not you don't need to know the name
but what type of Triad are
they shout it
up ma yeah
major
minor
and a
augmented diminished um so there's four
different
Triads major minor augmented diminished
a lot of people think that major and
minor have more something more in common
than the other two
because this goes what's up a major
third up a minor third if you start
instead go the opposite way and you
start here and you go up a minor third
and then you go up a major third you end
up with a Minor triad so the Minor triad
is the inversion of the major Triad and
therefore they both have the exact same
interval content they both have a ma
minor third a major third and a perfect
fifth within them whereas an augmented
Triad
cannot be inverted to become a
diminished Triad
or to become a major or minor Tri so
they don't have an equivalence class
between them so this comes up often
last
cardinality sometime how many notes
there are sometimes it matters SI as it
doesn't
[Music]
versus some ways the
same also if you put it together with
octave and cardinality I'm not going to
run over there again I need to put my
keyboard here a four note Tri major
Triad c e g c now you say that octave
doesn't matter so now it's c e g and a
second C here and now you really want
cardinality not to matter if you want to
say is this the same as some other C
major
Tri um and the last one I think's really
important uh Demitri taso comes from uh
a slightly different practice world is
that he just assumes that spelling
equivalent or we call midi equivalent or
enharmonic equivalent I should have
called it enharmonic but I can't figure
out a way to make an e into the optic um
uh acronym offf so that does does n
harmonic equivalent does spelling matter
and uh one of the things in his world
which is very different from music 21
but in problem set 4 you're going to be
working in the world of optic of
geometry of music uh the spelling
equivalence is always
assumed yep
poetic
p p o oh yeah but then I would have to
rearrange his yeah no that's really
really good there's another one uh um
you know that we can start putting in we
can start thinking of tomber equivalents
we often think of that all these other
things that you wrote up there but these
are the ones that um will give you the
most hard time on the next
problem uh let's there's not time so
we'll um end this up uh end a little bit
early for the first time in a while uh
cool we'll get to um working with
intervals next class and filtering
streams thanks everybody