some fantastic presentations have
already uh been put in front of you
today you've seen some really insightful
kind of uh work with AI and how it's
kind of evolving um it's now 4:00 in the
afternoon you're probably a little bit
tired um I'm going to try and keep you
awake uh for that last kind of stint I
know you're probably thinking to
yourself how am I getting home uh what's
for dinner what uh what's in the fridge
um but I mean I couple of little things
I know I have a weird accent I uh I come
from I'm I'm Irish by by birth and I
know I speak at a million miles an hour
and I know with this particular topic I
get very very enthusiastic so please
forgive my uh somewhat some somewhat uh
immature excitement as I go through this
when I get very excited about certain
elements of the conversation but
hopefully what I'm going to do is I'm
going to Showcase some really really
interesting ideas that can make you
think about where the future is headed
how AI is shaping real estate
specifically and how AI is supercharging
this incredible concept that is digital
twin and you know we're going to look at
some of kind of a number of different
aspects from that and hopefully what I'm
going to do is I'm going to kind of get
you on my side to to get you thinking
about how this potentially is one of the
most important Concepts in the in the
Realms of real estate going forward
digital twin technology itself is really
starting to revolutionize and has been
revolutionizing a number of Industries
for for quite some time now even
including real estate by really
providing uh virtual replicas
essentially of physical assets we're
going to kind of go through that in the
in the next few minutes and these
digital models are really what they're
doing is they're integrating real-time
data and historical data to really kind
of reflect that the physical counter H
kind of components within a specific
system and hopefully this presentation
what we're going to do is we're really
going to outline how the future of
digital TW digital twin technology is
really going to impact specifically the
the real estate sector so just to begin
with just introduce myself my name is
James Scott I wear a number of different
hats here at MIT um I was research
scientist I'm direct I mean I really
helped facilitate a number of the
industry relations over at the center
for Real Estate now and on top of that I
also am the director of the real estate
transformation lab what that is kind of
quite simply is what we try to do is
take the 40 now years of Real Estate
research and understanding that has
taken place within the center with mit's
technological prowess and understanding
um to merge that bring them together and
create a research platform that can
really start to understand this
digitization that's taking place across
the built environment and we do that in
a number of different facets with a
number of different research verticals
but primarily what we're always doing
above everything else is always trying
to understand what are the newest
products processes and technologies that
can really make a difference and so
that's kind of really I as as my wife
continues to tell me when am I going to
get a real job because it's one of the
most fun things anyone can actually
really get to do as
well um so over the course of this
conversation we're going to look at what
a digital twin is I'm going to assume
that numerous people know what it is
within the room but we're going to bring
it down we're going to start at the
start for everybody we're going to
quickly kind of De delve through that
figure out what it is the concept itself
understand the kind of the
classification system examples of what
it exists out there in the real world
and then finally its applications to
real estate and how AI is really driving
that forward over the course of the next
few
years so what is a digital twin these
are kind of two um I remember when I
went back researching this number of
years ago uh I think I stopped at about
37 different uh specific definitions of
Digit Twi there is no specific
definition out there these were just two
that I kind of enjoyed when I was
putting this together um a virtual
representation of a real world entity or
IBM how they classify it it's a digital
twin is a virtual representation of an
object or system that spans its life
cycle really great kind of definitions
and then but there's literally hundreds
of them out there but really all it
simply is is a dynamic ual
representation of any real world system
out there that utilizes now this is the
really important part real time and
historical data and so often times when
I ask in class when I ask them at the
start of what's a digital twin I usually
get the same three answers within about
12 seconds
Bim building management system
matterport they're not wrong but they're
just they're not necessarily right
either the difference between what a
really a digital twin is compared to all
of those other things is that the data
that's fed into it is live all right
like a matterport situation or a Bim
situation the data is static it stays
there and while you might see animations
taking place within that ultimately the
data doesn't actually move the
difference with a digital twin is that
that there is a live feed of data into
it at all times giving you two elements
a upto-date understanding as as of this
moment in time of what's taking place
within that system but most most
importantly and probably of the most
value is that it allows for forecasting
and scenario modeling within that system
as well and that's the real value part
of all within any all of this um there's
there's numerous different ways that
people kind of portray this in numerous
different systems with think collecting
the data generating the data and then
simulating it in through different
phases I actually bring it down to all
like I mean while we showed earlier
maybe 10 this is six I bring it down to
with real estate I often bring it down
to three simple phases all right there
is the data there is the representation
or the imagery that kind of takes place
within that and then from that what you
have is the analysis that's taking place
over here in the kind of the in the
third quadrant or the third the third
component of a triangle as
well uh digital twin Is Not A New
Concept and by the way again I'm hearing
my voice move quite fast here so if
please forgive how the speed at which I
want to try and get through all of this
but it's not necessarily new all right
the concept itself was really developed
back in the 60s with NASA all right they
started using the this basic twinning
concept to create physically duplicated
systems on Earth when they were running
missions in space right because
obviously they needed to run scenario
testing on the shuttle when it was in
orbit and they couldn't do it when it
was in orbit and then from that the term
digital twin itself was really first
mentioned in 1991 by David glenner in
his book mirror world and then from that
what you had I think about 2002 you had
Michael Greaves over in Michigan and he
formally formally introduced the concept
of digital twin in the context of
product lifestyle management and his
work has really laid the foundation for
modern understanding of digital twins
out there in the manufacturing world as
well um the adoption of digital twin
really started to gain momentum though
in the last we'll say 10 15 years and
what drove that was of course the
advancement in AI capabilities the
advancement in data computational
computational power and of course the
proliferation of that wonderful fabulous
thing called the internet of things and
then really what happened we had that we
had a number of different people over
the the last 10 years like John Vickers
at NASA who really popularized the term
digital twin and the technology began to
really be recognized as a strategic
Trend across a number of different
Industries just a couple of quick
examples in the real world Rolls-Royce
intelligent engine has been around since
2018 this service utilizes digital twin
of a motor engine and performance of of
flight engines and what it has done it
has facilitated an improvement of the
lifespan of a flight engine by 1.5 times
of course we can't go anywhere these
days without talking about Nvidia and
digital twins of their factories have
allowed
manufacturers um to to model and to
simulate and analyze and optimize the
production process without a need for a
physical protot prototype within their
particular plant and a specific company
uh wistron a leading Electronics
manufacturer was able to achieve a 51%
boost in worker efficiency and 50%
reduction in production process times
using this particular solution as well
Volvo trucks another one that used this
really really well within their Super
Truck 2 concept vehicle and of course
what they've achieved there is in
running the scenario modeling instead of
actually using specific prototypes we're
able to facilitate and succeed in
reducing drag by 50% over the previous
iterations as
well I love this quote the power of
digital twins is the ability to
visualize multiple different data
sources in a single model I love that
because it outlines the power what what
it can achieve this ultimately is what
we're all trying to achieve within the
the process of formulating a digital
twin but unfortunately it is also its
greatest challenge as well we'll talk
about the challenges as coming over the
next few minutes as well just some kind
of like mean conceptual ideas
classification digital twins are
classified in numerous different ways
depending on who you're talking to what
industry you're in and the most common
probably is by scale either through the
component level asset level systems um
think about it in a number of ways like
let's say a component level might be a
HVAC system with a bin a building or
even maybe a plane engine asset level
would be the building itself or a plane
if I'm using the the two different
analogies beside each other a systems of
assets might be a portfolio or
particular real estate and then a
multistem might be a smart city mean
environment out there which encompasses
numerous different elements of uh
digital twin
technology there has been of course vast
investment in this in in recent times
with the forecast for 2025 even
predicting sust substantial growth in
the adoption of this technology across
multiple Industries with somewhere in
the region of about I think $13 billion
invested last year and about 17 billion
on track to kind of investment in this
year with but that's not the really
really incredible statistic that's up on
the board 250 million or north of it I
mean by 2031 that's where that the
industry is seeing this kind of move by
in a very very short space of time as
well this is a technology people that
really see the true value of in a very
kind of
in multiple different
facets so going back to what a digital
twin is as I outlined before it is the
historical and real-time data coming
together to formulate different concepts
as well and they really complement each
other and provide really comprehensive
view of the assets past and present to
ultimately utilizing AI technology to
predict future behaviors and how they do
this and how they correlate it is
through a number of different Ventures
first is through the Baseline of trend
analysis
historical data really provides a
baseline of past performance and Trends
which is essential for understanding how
an asset has behaved over time and this
information is it's it's crucial for
identifying patterns and anomalies when
comparing to real-time data predictive
modeling which is an offshoot of
artificial intelligence in itself what
happens here is by analyzing historical
data the twins themselves can build
predictive models that anticipate future
events or failures
through simulation and scenario testing
the historical data allows digital twins
to simulate various scenarios by
understanding past conditions and
outcomes when combined with real-time
data these simulations can really be
adjusted dramatically to to can really
reflect the current conditions or State
of Affairs within a specific asset
providing a far more robust and
adaptable model as well you have of
course AI machine learning Within
digital Twins and that utilizes this
both both the historical and real-time
data to improve decision-making
processes you have synchronization and
validation which again using the
historical data helps validate the
real-time data providing a reference
point for comparison and ultimately
that's probably one of the biggest
issues that has taken place within the
real estate industry in the last few
years we'll talk about that in a few
minutes where that is kind of stand from
but overall the integration of
historical and real-time data in digital
twins really enables a far more holistic
IC understanding of the asset itself
leading to hopefully somewhere in their
really far better improved decision-
making and operational efficiency as
well so how is AI and digital twins
really kind of making this better well
AI is really driving and revolutionizing
the digital twin by
enhancing not only the data collection
but also the integration process within
a particular system as well and through
AI sensor Technologies they're really
helping facilitate digital twins to
gather enormous volumes of realtime data
within the physical world these sensors
you know can include far more complex
ones like computer vision cameras or iot
devices as well as more conventional
ones like you know simple ones that we
see I've seen for a number of years like
temperature and pressure sensors and
then through using AI algorithms this
data is interpreted it's filtered
processed to make much more useful and
create far more actionable insight
within that system as well enabling the
digital twin really then to to integrate
the data from diverse sources and and
and and different components you know
and a far more seamless capability as
well so if you were to take for instance
a smart city or of a digital twin and
take all of the different data from
traffic cameras or weather stations or
even social media feeds to analyze in
real time to then formulate in situation
to optimize something quite complex in
traffic flow patterns but let's add in a
little bit of in issue with adverse
weather conditions as well well then we
have a system where ai's ability to
process all of that very difficult
unstructured data such as texts or
images really helps facilitate and
enriches the digital twins understanding
of its surroundings around
that
um because we're in iot devices just in
case anyone just what that is and what
they are quite simply is iot sensors are
really just physical devices equipped
from different sensors that capture data
from the the the physical
world and these centers can measure
extreme you know a wide range of
perimeters including temperature uh
humidity pressure space optimization
presence vibration lights and anything
you can really think of at any given end
time and all of this data is then
collected by these centers is really
creating an accurate up-to-date
representation of what's taking place
within a
system so within the Realms of real
estate what does that mean what is a
digital twin capable of doing well
really a digital twin can provide kind
of two two two really valuable um
elements it can provide a transformative
solution really in the development and
the operations of a building or a built
environment situation itself as well and
what it does is it can provide a a a
virtual representation of exactly what's
taking place in an up like I mean at
this moment in time within a particular
building or a city and then far more
importantly what happens is that it
allows for that forecast and scenario
modeling to take place within that
system so let's take a building for
instance how
would we've never really been able to
have an R&D situation for our buildings
we've never really been able to do that
because it simply it just it costs too
much you put a new system in you can't
just take it out because you don't like
it or it's not not working at an optimal
level what happens now with a new kind
of dynamic situation of digital
technology that would allow you to
better understand
how a new HVAC system would cope and
operate within a system what would a new
space optimization configuration within
a building look like and how would the
asset react to it what would happen if a
new heat pump was installed within the
building what would the reaction be what
if one of the
new
helpful um AI enabled HPA systems that
could can transpose the cold air from
one floor into the cold air down into
another floor that needs it without
actually utilizing or producing any
other cold air within it to really
utilize all of the different elements
within a space that's when we start to
see real value within the real estate
industry across different buildings and
ultimately what we're trying to achieve
is to help facilitate a situation that
the highest and best use of all of the
space within that is getting
utilized some examples that are right
there in the real world one of my
favorites that has been around for quite
some time has been Nan young Tech
technology University in Singapore this
is a 50 hectare special purpose uh built
campus that has about 8 to n years into
a 10-year buildout and they've been
focusing on trying to create a a digital
twin for that entire time and they've
they've really seen and yielded
incredible results in some ways I mean
with a 31% reduction in energy
consumption however I want to be fair on
this a lot of that was through trial and
error as well it wasn't just automatic
straight off the bat some other ones um
the uh inam uh city in in Korea have
done some fantastic work um with one of
the ones that they've built out with
fire response traffic control but one of
my favorite Parts is the realtime
monitoring system response to Rising
mosquito born diseases which has been
extremely helpful within that particular
twin and of course Singapore as well
which has really been at the Forefront
of developing and and implementing an
urban digital twin um uh for for a
number of years now since 2014 their
smart Nation uh initiative this has come
with Incredible successes but also has
really shown us what the real true
challenges are for digital twin we've
seen a numerous different companies come
and go within this initiative Bentley
systems been part of it and have left
but the challenges themselves you know
have been really um instrumental in
helping other people better understand
that through the standardization of data
and the complexity that comes with that
as well as the implementation of a
number of different systems out there to
Showcase where where things can go
wrong
um one of the kind of one of my favorite
particular twin projects that has taken
place here in the United States is what
is a video clip that I'm just going to
show next um I'm going to use a video I
apologize but I just cannot I can't use
my words I'm not a like like I feel like
I'm talking to my son all right I can't
use my big boy words in order to to just
describe how fantastic this next project
is this is put together by Brookfield
asset manager one of the largest office
owners and and re
real estate owners here in the United
States along with Willow which is a dzel
twin technology here in in the United
States and Microsoft aor I just kind of
give you kind of a quick bit of insight
with this
one Willow twin is a digital replica of
exactly what the building is made up of
all the security scalability Cloud AI
technologies that Willow leverages
inside of the willow twin are a
fundamental component inside of the
Azure digital twin stack it's comprised
of the architectural drawings the
heating ventilation and air conditioning
systems the building automation system
occupancy sensor networks all of the
equipment that goes into the building
there's over 40,000 data points and we
can look at all of these systems
together in real time and understand how
one is affecting the other and respond
to
that that's one of my favorite kind of
visualizations of this that particular
technology that's one Manhattan West
which is basically the first building
you hit when you come out a pen station
going towards hoods and yards it's a
phenomenal building just to see it and
just as a building in itself but the
project that they've been working on
there has really kind of led the way for
a lot of digital twin understanding and
quite simply that video is three years
old and it's only now that they're
starting to really reap the benefits of
all of the implementation of all of the
systems that they built into it so with
that what this what does this all mean
what is the the impact of digital twin
which is an a enable technology on real
estate what does it all mean for for for
our cities and for our buildings and how
what are the true benefits that we're
able to to kind of De Garner out of this
particular technology well first and
foremost at a city planning level
digital twins will enable far more
efficient and sustainable Urban
Development planners will be able to
essentially simulate various scenarios
and assess the impact of new
developments and optimize infrastructure
planning and that's extremely helpful
you know across different cities even
across the way here with the the new
with a we have a incredible site across
the way here that that MIT built and the
team at the city science lab but Kent
Larson team have done an incredible job
in creating their their own virtual
representation of that and that's all to
help facilitate a better understanding
of what of trying to ensure that
everybody gets the most out of new
developments going forward and from that
all right cities then can create
detailed virtual replicas to help
facilitate with their management now
there are no number of different kind of
iterations of this across the the US
that have been utilized but one of my
favorite ones is Lake Nona down in um
down in Orlando in Florida Lake non is a
a 7,000 acre master plan development
it's a it's a monstrosity it's the like
if you know the Irvine Company over in
California it's one of those ones in
fact this is their small one they have
one next door that's closer to 22,000
acres to be developed but they've
started building out in the last three
years a digital twin within their
Community as well using
Google Map API GIS parcel data building
topography data uh pedestrian traffic
flow um occupancy level iot within the
spaces um traffic uh heat maps all of
them to create one of the most really
fantastic digal twin platforms that I've
seen for an entire Community here in the
United States and it really is a
fantastic product that they that they
have um some of the low hanging food of
course improved maintenance and
operations one of the most immediate
benefits of digital twins is of course
predictive maintenance and you know I
when I showed this sometime people
always go but we've seen that with IBM
Watson for you know four or five years
ago on on a Super Bowl ad nothing really
came of it well it nothing really came
of it because it kind of goes back to
that situation that I was talking about
earlier with historical and real-time
data we thought we had the historical
data but we really didn't we didn't have
a standardization and it's probably
taken till now to get the data to a
level that we can understand it utilize
it Benchmark it then from that make
better decisions from that as well and
then this can really help facilitate
analy and and create a pro a proactive
approach that of course will reduce the
downtime within spaces save costs and
ultimately add value to uh to to uh to
real estate
assets
um datadriven
decision-making digital twin of course
will provide a wealth of data that can
be analyzed for insights and Trends and
helping Property Owners make much better
strategic decisions and plan for the
future the office Market's not exactly
in the best place it's ever been right
now this is the exact type of technology
that can help facilitate owners and
operators with understanding what's
needed what's necessary and what the
true value is of trying to get the the
the best value out of what what assets
they have at this moment in time and it
can ultimately only be be a a a really
true value add for them I canot have
this conversation without sustainability
and
decarbonization for the real estate
industry this is the elephant in the
room we have incredibly
complex regulation coming down the
pipeline with local on 97 Berto here in
Boston it's only going to get more
bigger and stronger over the course of
the next few years as well well digital
twin technology can play a crucial role
in sustainability efforts by identifying
he eting Cooling and efficiencies within
spaces generating detailed energy usage
statistics and more importantly where I
think the true value is is helping
facilitate informed targeted
retrofitting capabilities within spaces
that have been underutilized or have may
be defunct depending on certain demands
at this point in time and this of course
will help reduce carbon emissions that
align with all of these uh global
climate change uh regulations that are
coming down the pipeline
where am I Facilities
Management Facility management companies
are really leveraging digital twins to
help facilitate and optimizing building
performance um and reduce of course
their operational costs this is always
going to be of importance within the
real estate industry from an investment
perspective and by integrating iot
devices and data analytics facilitated
and driven by AI technology these
digital twin will really help provide
the insight and help create a far more
comfortable
um and an environmentally responsible
workplace for anyone within the space as
well they this is probably one of the
biggest markets for digital twin and
real estate and they can use it to
analyze the building performance um
optimize operations and create the best
possible space for the people that are
within that within that
environment of course collaboration
stakeholder engagement again a very
useful tool helping to
to really help facilitate collaboration
among stakeholders by offering you know
a real true understanding of a real-time
platform for interaction for those I
can't show it here but for those of you
who who get a moment please take a look
at immerses project down in Tampa with
their Water Street project this is an
incredible interactive model that
integrates both massing and analytics
into One Singular interactive tool to
that's been presented in a realtime
projection of the of this particular
development with Incredible different
elements of data that have come together
to Showcase this this project this
project to all of the different
stakeholders within
it
now everything I've just said here
digital Twin's amazing it's going to
change the world this is a simple easy
as got to use it it's going to change
everything but that's not simply the
case the media coverage of digital twin
over the last few years has been
extremely positive but if you look at
all these these headlines This Is 2020
2021 digital twin has been as a concept
in real estate has been around but has
it fundamentally really made a
difference or made a change
within within real estate absolutely not
it has come across significant
challenges but why I mean do I still
believe in it do I still think that it's
a a gamechanging technology absolutely
through the evolution of AI capabilities
generative AI capabilities and more
importantly facilitation of the data
which we didn't necessarily have before
this is only going to get stronger and
it's only going to get better there's
been significant barriers to adoption
the difficulty of course in measuring
and demonstrating a return on investment
with any new technology is of vital
importance for any particular uh
industry but but but real estate are
probably one of the hardest people to to
really get on board behind this the
likes of what you saw with Brookfield
that's they are they're an outlier
they're a team that's really taken a
chance they put a lot of effort a lot of
money and a lot of time into creating
something new and something Dynamic but
they do believe that they're now
starting to see the the True Value at
the end of that and in the next few
months what you're going to see coming
out of that project is really quite a
standard some of the some of the levels
of of um of of efficiencies that they've
been able to create with
it um another issue is
interoperability which has been one of
the biggest CH uh challenges in
utilizing this technology because of its
ability of different platforms different
data providers to work closely or
together or seamlessly and this
ultimately requires a huge amount of
standardization and collaboration across
an industry
but because ultimately how data is
constructed how it's pared how it's
synthesized how it's gathered is
different depending on City environment
software building and anything else but
we've actually had a number of different
initiatives across Europe and here in
the United States trying to facilitate a
common digital twin language a HTML if
you will for digital twin technology or
even a a dtml is how they try to
describe it and that's something you're
starting to see a lot more kind of in in
in
process of course the cost and
complexity The Upfront cost of
implementing this technology is
significant and that's you know it's not
everybody it's not going to be this is
not for your average real estate owner
at this moment in time but that's not to
say that in a couple of years that this
won't be part and parcel of every single
operation out there just like we've seen
with liar technology over the last few
years the cost of iot sensors the cost
of the the the analytic capabilities
behind that is coming down significantly
to a point that this will be mainstream
in a not too distant future
so with that digital twin technology is
really you know it's really starting to
revolutionize certain aspects of
commercial real estate by really
facilitating and enhancing the improved
management and operations within a lot
of the systems to help obviously support
sustainability efforts um improve
marketing and create the best possible
efficienc efficiency levels within a lot
of
organizations and as the as the industry
starts or continues to embrace
this digital transformation I have no
doubts that digital twin will play a
crucial role in future proofing a number
of real estate assets and driving
Innovation um everything I've said to
you here is not necessarily coming off
the fence a lot of you've seen this
before you've you know you've you've
seen certainly the concepts before but
for me I'm going to just kind of I'm
going to give a little bit of my own
personal opinion on this which is always
very dangerous and a room like this here
but ultimately probably one of the
biggest issues we've seen in trying to
push digital twin technology forward
especially in real estate has been
implementing the data with the the
visualization component and if I were to
actually say it I mean going forward I
don't necessarily believe that is
ultimately even necessary what we
probably need really need is just a
digital integration platform that can
take the data can analyze it and then
from that with the power of generative
AI really just help facilitate from with
the decision- making of the The
Operators or the property managers and
facility managers to tell them exactly
what to do to take the data that they
have generate a very simple report and
from that let them go and do their work
and that's probably what we're going to
see in the not too distant future if if
that we're not already seeing it this
year alone as well and that's probably
this the kind of the lwh hanging frood
value within all of this
but the history of digital twin
technology really reflects a journey of
innovation and adaption and when you're
talking about something like things like
with Innovation and adaption things do
take time there is a struggle there is a
there is a sort of a a moment where you
kind of have to step off the cliff and
kind of embrace it and take it all and
ultimately we're starting to see people
start to do that and more importantly
see the benefits with that as well and
so the future for this particular
element within this industry I think is
extremely uh extremely bright and we're
going to only see more of
it um so with that thank you very much
um if any of you you didn't hear a word
I said and I was speaking way too fast I
apologize but uh I'd love to have some
questions um if you uh if you have any
oh wow we we've loads of
[Applause]
questions
um yeah answer the sure question okay
I'm going to pick the easy ones the
sports ones okay okay is digital twin
better than smaller methods that use
less data how does it differ in terms of
cases and
accuracy
um smaller methods that use less data
well for me when and I'm I'm going to
infer that the question is like I mean
different components within a different
or a of a building so a smaller method
might be utilizing the information or
data of a HVAC
system or understanding the Energy
Efficiency of of a particular space or
the space optimization they're all
fantastic and they all work really well
but why not put them all together
because when you put them all together
you have a far better understanding of
what's taking place within your space
and so it's not a case of whether one is
better one as the other or than the
other I think it's a necessary Evolution
that you put all of these things into
one into one product to give you the
best understanding and from that what
you can do is make the best decisions
possible with not just your building but
with your portfolio of assets because
you need to have all of these things
together because they're not mutually
exclusive right like if you decide to
reduce your budget on a HVAC system and
It
ultimately you know it cranks out on you
in the middle of winter or during the
summer when people need it the most it's
going to affect your occupancy levels
it's going to affect the tenant within
it it's going to affect the wellness the
health the people that utilize the space
so the information you get for one
system is good but more information is
always better it gives you a far better
kind of train of insight within that I I
think I've answered that
question
um do you have some figures about Roi of
such Technologies with real estate cases
well I gave one that we had up on the
screen there was n young technology
University like mean through their
campus there have a 30% reduction in
operation or sorry with energy energy
usage I think that's probably an unfair
example because they've they've utilized
a trial and error scenario in lots of
respects of how to figure out which
works and what doesn't work the data
that will come out and like I can't get
into it just it's it's not it's not time
for it to be released but the
information that will come out from one
Manhattan West in around November or
December when that report is released I
think will be of
significant uh to to the marketplace
where they have a much better
understanding of how how valuable this
is and essentially all of the parameters
I'm not giving too much away here but
all of the things that they've
ultimately tried to achieve or they
thought that they would hit they with
the exception of maybe one and they were
off by maybe 1% they they they've hit
all of their targets so this is
something that can really help
facilitate a true reduction in energy
and one thing I can talk about is I know
that over the course of the next 10
years it'll ultimately save them
somewhere close to about $60 million in
operational
expenses
um how useful could digital twins be for
evaluating potential damage to a
building from things like fire flood
wind I think like I mean a number of
different um insurance companies already
looking at this um to better understand
it um
but the problem with this is you have to
ask what's the true value like I mean if
a building is damaged by fire ultimately
it gets demolished like I mean it
doesn't matter what a digital mean it's
more trying to Res if the resiliency I
think is or maybe that is the question
if the resiliency of certain materials
and the resiliency of certain components
within a system that can help probably
better understand it how a sprinkler
system might work or how it might curate
a situation to create the as less as
little damage as possible in one of
those horrific situations I think is
where this would go and there's
absolutely you know it will be of course
immense value um I know one of the the
ILP members is FM Global there's anyone
FM Global members in the audience but
like they have yeah you guys have a
campus stand in Rhode Island where you
kind of do that you do it naturally you
don't need a digital twin yeah
yeah
um
okay anyone anyone I want to ask a
question from the audience put their
hand up anyone feeling brave enough just
got a feel bad just picking questions
out off
offline make this a
classroom yes sir
look some
experiment uh we found that
sometime the question is CL close to the
business situation we are in the finance
security not a real estate yeah how you
advise Beyond this real estate which
have a building concrete you can see
heat pipes you can you can feel it but
in a more Finance or other let say
retail type of
Industry so
I'm going to try I'm going to try
to yeah so I think he's asking
me the physical components of a digital
twin allow it to be kind of assessed
quite a little bit more simply but can
you transfer that particular technology
and an understanding to other elements
like retail scenarios or financial
modeling I for me I don't think that's
what a digital twin is because for me a
digital twin is a 3D virtual
representation of a physical system or
physical asset what I think you're
talking about and we have numerous
different kind of variations of it is a
not of a lot of Quant analysis that
takes place on on on Wall Street already
I I mean with different components in
retail we have it in understanding the
power of the consumer be it uh
walkability space and there's a there's
a really interesting team at there
called
Pro know Placer Placer that really help
better understand all of how how how
people use the retail space how much
they're buying how much they're buying
around different environments so I I I
think there's an awful lot of
AI powered analysis systems that are out
there but I don't necessarily I wouldn't
consider them a digital twin because for
me I think you need to have a physical
component to it to be to be considered
that that digital
twin anyone
else yep so um it's two question one is
of you only get one no no no no no howly
do you need to
start so great great question well I'll
come back to you let me let me answer
we'll do them in Parts all right so the
earlier you put it into the system
obviously the better all right I mean so
a lot of buildings that you're going to
see can constructed over the next few
years are going to have that componentry
that capability of iot sensors powered
and that optionality to integrate new
systems within the building
automatically and that will be from the
evolution of even Bim systems themselves
as well where you will probably see a
situation where they'll take the Bim
construction people have used Bim before
that Bim virtual representation of the
space and utilize and funnel in the data
to give them that capability of having
an understanding from an operational
component going forward
trying to do it with an older building
we've seen it happen but it's it's
harder it's like everything it's like
with this trying to create a new
sustainable sustainability effort within
an older space it's just harder because
they weren't built with that purpose in
mind and of course you know the team
that comes up with been able to do that
with an older space well look at mean
they're not they're going to be flying
in on a private jet the next time that
they come all right because that's
that's that's where the real money is
it's you know it's great to be able to
implement these within new places but
ultimately if you can do it with the
majority of older stock that's out there
that's that's the game changer that's
the ultimate where we're trying to go so
my second
question is who are the decision makers
that it seems to me that once you're
already's
decision or
is oh you've just you've opened up a
whole kind of worms there haven't you um
so just ask the question again who the
decision maker
for who do you talk to to make sure are
you talking about to implement it or to
take the to take the the the Insight
that it provides and then go and do
something with
itel yeah
that that's probably a corporate
question to be fair but I'm going to try
I'm going to try and give a little bit
of an answer to it there's a number of
people that are involved with the
process like with anything right when
you want to implement a new software a
new structure but the important part and
this kind of is a big Fear Factor for a
lot of people because one of the big
issues with adoption for digital twin is
of course the facility manager the
property manager the asset manager they
see a technology like this here and it
scares them because they think hold on
I'm going to be out of a job very soon
because this is going to take over and
automate all of the systems in
process that that's not how we see it
all right what we see is that this
provides the ultimate insight into
what's taking place within the space so
that that decision maker whoever that
person might be that utilizes this can
make the best decision possible and give
them the foresight and actually if I'm
going to go further I love given my
opinion because it causes far more
arguments than anything all right it we
have had that in the real estate
industry for a number of years and this
goes back to the that first question the
smaller iterations of data that are
available out there the problem with the
real estate industry is they've actually
been inundated with so much data and so
much Insight that they forgot who their
target Mark that person that's using is
and with the greatest of respect they
didn't go to MIT they didn't go to
Harvard they didn't go to Princeton they
people that work in the real estate
industry for 20 30 years and they see
you know lines of code at the top of a
an interface with pie charts and graphs
that are showcasing the optimization of
certain of their Chiller system or their
or their heating system and they
ultimately don't know what to do with it
and so they have no real kind of
pragmatic way to take it but that's
where gen C comes in all right so let's
say we have that in front of the
individual and you say push the button
we don't necessarily need the virtual
representation we just have a
simple interface with all of the
systems coming into play and you say
generate report all right and it
generates three very easy to read
paragraphs that anybody can understand
and from that they can make decisions
boiler number two is running at optimal
levels boiler number four looks like it
could do with a service because it's
overheating at certain times during the
day all right literally it's writing it
out for the person so they can take it
and they can use it and make it work and
that's the missing step for a lot of
this it's why we haven't had a lot of
the adoption with a lot of prop tech
software and a lot of prop Tech products
because ultimately that last step didn't
really take place but I think ai's
capability specifically jni is
ultimately a huge missing link for the
the the the property managers and the
facility managers who can ultimately now
use this data at a far more efficient
level okay I'm I'm out of time I've got
to leave you've had enough of me listen
thank you so much