I have the best honor of the day to
introduce our our first Speaker uh
Professor varasi I'll say Professor
varasi is one of those cases in
which I really urge you to keep an open
mind he has an impressive resume an
impressive book of past
accomplishments but what you'll see here
today is opportunity to do new things in
the future Professor
[Music]
ver all right thank you so much uh can
you all hear me good morning everyone
and uh it's a honor to be here uh I'm uh
uh I love Japan it's great to come back
and uh I hope to uh for some good
collaborations and uh connections today
uh so let me tell you what I do in my
lab my lab uh we work on Advanced
Materials and interfaces apply to a
whole range of different uh Industries
because interfaces are ubiquitous and
and they are everywhere uh we've been
able fortunate to work across the energy
water biomedical and Agriculture and
other uh other areas so this is a very
busy slide but shows uh the things that
I've dabbled in in my career starting
from uh power plants all the way to um
uh energy industry to biomed and uh
Aviation as well as Agriculture and a
lot of my works today uh these days have
been focused on uh sort of
decarbonization to uh to
healthcare um so this kind of gives you
uh an idea of the uh areas of work that
go in my lab uh starting from uh energy
all the way to uh biomedical work and
along the way we use our expert in
materialss uh manufacturing and scale up
and and so
on um uh so again a busy slide with uh
with a lot of these areas and I uh am
happy to interact with you after my talk
I'm not going to be able to go through
all of these today but we'll give you uh
sort of a uh teaser on on some of the
work that has been done and some of the
things that we are working on uh so
let's get started with thinking about uh
the CO2 problem you know it is a
gigascale problem right there is
gigatons of CO2 uh that we have put into
the atmosphere since we discovered fire
we've been putting CO2 into the into the
atmosphere and that's causing problems
and we need to be able to solve this but
solve it by actually creating some value
to the uh to at the end and so if we
look at uh where we are uh to where we
should be we should be removing gigatons
of CO2 that means uh it's a big cap aex
as well as an Opex problem and our
efforts have been looking at how to sort
of overcome both of these challenges on
the other side of the story is
Renewables for Renewables to become uh
effective you need storage and you need
storage that is safe because you need to
be able to put gigawatt hours of storage
out there and to be able to do that we
need something that um is both uh safe
sustainable and can be manufactured
anywhere and and I'll talk about about
some inventions in non-lithium and non-
Cobalt and nonflammable batteries that
we are actually commercializing through
a company of mine called alsim
Energy and uh so uh again kind of
straddling this going from capture to
Circular e economy to some
biomanufacturing if I'm able to get
there we'll discuss some uh things that
we have done in this space um uh in the
biomedical space we've been working on
bio interfaces to delivery to enhancing
biom manufacturing and I'll highlight
two projects uh one that's kind of
completed uh working with the Gates
Foundation we've been able to come up
with new ways to inject High
concentration biologics these are
sometimes as viscous as thousand times
the viscosity of water and we we've been
able to show that we can inject them
through a regular syringe needle kind of
a system and so uh this is a huge Market
apart from vaccines you're looking at
all kinds of uh all kinds of uh um areas
uh starting from uh uh cancer to to
cardiovascular to others where uh where
biologics are becoming very important
and I I know Stacy is going to talk a
lot about that in the next uh talk um
but I think what we have done here is
really democratize access to healthcare
by creating a platform where we can uh
do this and uh give a lot of freedom to
drug formulators and so on uh another
project that you know currently going on
in the lab is looking at early detection
of ovarian cancer um ovarian cancer is a
killer Disease by the time it's you know
one it's detected you're already stage
three and can cause really a big impact
you know essentially there is you know
uh it's pretty much um a very difficult
decision at that point by the time it's
detected so what we are trying to do
here is based on some of the work from
our amazing collaborators who have found
that ovarian cancer originates in uh in
the pH opan tubes and not the ovaries we
looking at ways to do early detection so
that there could be opportunistic uh
surgeries that could remove of the
Fallopian tubes and thereby take the
risk of cancer to zero and all of this
involves some very interesting uh
interdisciplinary research and in my
group we do a lot of interdisciplinary
work we've been fortunate to learn a lot
of new things um because we work at the
interfaces of matter and uh so that
meant you know working on thermal fluids
to electrochemistry to soft matter
matter and then always think about
Manufacturing in scale so we can take
our ideas to to Market so this kind of
gives you a road map of how I think
about research in my lab where we you
know establish a business case first
talking to people like you and then sort
of go bring in our expertise and create
a focused R&D effort in the in at my lab
and then sort of that leads to some
pilot scale work and all the way to
commercialization and so uh over the
past decade we've been able to
commercialize a number of Technologies
uh starting from a company called liquid
Glide where we able to uh create a
hypers slippery surface to which nothing
sticks and we've been able to take that
sort of to uh to Market through uh some
consumer packaging work as well as some
biomedical work now and then uh we have
infinite cooling where we are able to
capture the plumes and create a lot of
value to power data centers and other
cooling areas and uh my co-founder and
former student Maher damak is here who
uh will be talking about this uh also uh
later this today uh Alim energy is this
non-lithium nonflammable inherently
non-flammable Battery Technology for uh
for energy storage uh and then if I have
time I'll get to axen where we are
reducing they amount a pesticide spread
and creating value to both Farms as well
as the chemical companies to do better
formulations of their pesticides and so
on and coflow medical was what I just
discussed which was the uh High
concentration biologics injectability
design uh so I'll start off by looking
at efficiency improvements and then talk
about decarbonization and and other
topics so I started off looking at the
energy area looking at U you know the
mundane steam cycle which has been there
for now more than what 100 years to
really convert uh you know a chemical
energy into electricity by using a cycle
which we all know very well you know
take water boil it from Steam uh Steam
does work on a turbine and then you
condense it back and come back uh and
complete the cycle but there are a
number of big efficiency problems
whether it's on the turbine interfaces
or heat exchanger interfaces which is in
a condenser a boiler and uh we have we
have uh sort of solved these problems by
designing uh interesting surfaces uh in
this case you know we've been able to
make surfaces that can bounce off liquid
thereby prevent formation of films on uh
on these turbine blades and that has led
to significant efficiency gains uh we
have taken these ideas to other topics
uh here we've shown how we can do
condensation or understand condensation
at a micro scale or freezing at micro
scale and then develop surfaces that can
even sort of uh be slippery to something
as sticky as a crude oil right in this
case uh or other kinds of things and
I'll I'll talk more uh in detail about
this uh so here are some other examples
where we've shown the that we can uh
improve or change the surfaces to shed
liquids as droplets while condensing
them on surfaces so you prevent sort of
these films that are forming uh and
reduce uh heat transfer and thereby
increase the heat transfer efficiency
you can make filters that are uh sort of
um preferentially wetting to one phase
in this case oil uh as you can see here
and then uh water basically um doesn't
pass through so you can look at it for
oil water separations here we made some
photo thermal materials that allow us to
convert the incident light into Ambi
into a temperature increase on the
surface thereby using the sunlight to
you know uh to effectively deise a
surface so I I sort of focus on on one
aspect of these surfaces which is the
ability to kind of uh uh sort of shed
extremely viscous uh materials uh we you
know we are all surrounded by viscous
fluids which include you know if you
have um in the morning you would have
brush your teeth you would use a
toothpaste imagine all the toothpaste
that's left behind to uh to maybe uh
condiments to even in healthcare where
you have uh catheters and others which
uh basically um cause blood clots and
things like that so this technology the
idea was uh seems simple but you know
seemingly seemingly simple but has a lot
of interesting uh uh uh Dimensions to it
uh so we have a what we do is we Infuse
liquids into a porous or into a textured
surface and uh the liquid is held by
capillary and other kinds of forces
intermolecular forces and that allows us
to create highly slippery surfaces for a
variety of liquids uh so we use uh
thermodynamic platforms to really uh
come up with uh the design of our
materials but it fundamentally sort of
changes the Paradigm on when you think
about Coatings and surfaces you don't
have to stick with a solid film you have
now a composite of a solid and a liquid
that gives you amazing new properties
right so if we take uh for example uh
packaging packaging there's a
significant amount of wastage uh and
because of that way so a there's wastage
uh so you put energy into this to make
uh these product and a lot of that
product is left behind but also you have
uh to use a lot if you're going to
recycle it and if you take take some of
these p packaging and you throw it in a
recyclable bin it doesn't mean that it
it will get recycled because of the
leftover product you had to clean it out
and that is leads to a significant sort
of a water consumption as well so when
we developed this technology and we went
to the Press you know the hasn't been
guilty of assault on a ketchup bottle
but has technology finally caught up
with ketchup look at that thing slide
amazing oh my God our long National
nightmare is over mechanical engineering
students at MIT have come up with a
super slippery coating that makes
anything from ketchup to mayonnaise
practically leap out of a bottle coated
with a stuff they call it liquid Glide
even Tony Soprano would be beholden to
these
students look how annoyed Tony gets at
the dreaded ketchup clog and if col us
that's talking
homicide liquid Glide let it slide no
more bangging with shoes guess we all
been in that in that space uh and so uh
you know actually all of this started
when my wife was trying to get honey out
of a bottle and she said why don't you
solve this problem and uh so you know
there's always we are always looking for
problems to solve and uh it always
motivates us to come up with solutions
that may not be easily you know you
can't think of that and that's kind of
why these forums are very important
where we can learn what are some of your
key challenges right uh so this stuff we
then took it to apply to all kinds of uh
products um and this is peanut butter
you know which is very sticky and uh
we've been able to make like a uh
squeeze bottle for this but we've taken
this and you know it took some years to
take that idea and then think about how
do you scale how do you work with a
customer but at the end of the day we
have been able to commercialize it with
Colgate uh to make the world's first
zero waste and also fully recyclable uh
toothpaste packaging right uh and this
could be applied to a whole range of
things we uh well we got a good uh press
from Trevor NOA here uh ended up on
colgate's annual shareholder report but
we are moving this to other products
such as consumer package such as uh um
Cosmetics or skincare products uh as
well as to uh to other kinds of things
uh which inspires new kind of packaging
this is you know um cream cheese and
typically it's in a jar it's in a tub
and we have to use some sort of a uh um
you know you had to use a knife and a
fork and it's can be sometimes annoying
but you can you know directly uh put it
onto onto your bagel here so it's kind
of transforming uh packaging uh and when
you think about um uh you know postco
world you know if you have large tubs
and you're a cosmetic and you're putting
your hands in it it can be very icky or
very sanitary so we can do this uh
directly into a into a dispensable uh
kind of a bottle and and things like
that so overall you know you can get rid
of all kinds of uh uh clutter in
packaging which leads to a lot of
landfills and and down down side effects
and you can actually make very
minimalistic and very elegant uh
packaging uh we have taken this to
looking at things like U manufacturing
of the same products and improve yield
losses um and applied this to uh Even
Flow batteries where if you want to
increase the capacity uh your flow
battery electrodes get very very wiscus
and they don't uh they can't actually
flow anymore and uh here is an example
where we able to using such surfaces
create some interesting flow battery
kind of uh
configurations yeah one can use these to
prevent ice buildup uh and you know the
applications are endless you can prevent
for example fowling whether it's
biofouling or whether it is uh scaling
and so
on uh we have also taken this to
biomedical products here is a catheter
where we can prevent uh formation of uh
blood clots and be
anti-thrombotic uh we have also taken
this to space stations where we can uh
prevent bofilm formation uh and this is
actually a uh the astronaut trying this
out in the space station showing that we
can actually prevent biofilms and redu
and create strong antimicrobial kind of
uh surfaces and that allows for
improving astronaut Health like you
don't want them to get sick or you know
if you have any parts that can actually
uh lead to failures because of biofilm
formation in space you know you're not
you don't have a Walmart next door to go
and pick up a extra part so uh these
kind of surfaces become very very
important uh to to to maintain both
equipment as well as to uh to to ensure
astronaut health and so on uh another
application that we have uh that we have
uh developed here is uh applying this to
ostomy patients so if your um an ostomy
patient has you know they basically
colon or things are taken out so you
have to use a bag and sometimes you know
uh when the stool comes out it can push
on the bag and can everything come out
and essentially a lot of the osty
patients uh it's a very it completely
affects their lifestyle and um you know
it it can put it can take people into
depression
so what we have done here is make a new
product which is a coating that we can
we or or a product that put we put into
osty bag and when you rub it you create
this coating and when the stool comes
out it can easily fall in and therefore
you don't have those kinds of problems
and it's really having a great uh impact
on uh on a lot of the folks are using it
and they uh and I'm you know I always
feel very uh honored to see uh some very
positive feedback from all of them
saying that this has been a lifechanger
uh uh so you know we can uh we we we are
imbuing this with antibiotics we are uh
and trying to solve a number of other
other problems um I um uh so I'll switch
gears and talk about some uh water
capture work which actually Mahir is
going to go through but what we have
done here is taken um U the water that
comes out of this cooling towers as
plumes and we are able to capture this
so I will I will leave it to my ha to
discuss this because this is a a very
very important uh kind of a uh
application because cooling is becoming
a huge bottleneck for many Industries
whether it's power plants or data
centers uh or uh HVAC and other things
and we have some very innovative
solutions that are at scale have been
deployed now and uh and Mah will discuss
those uh as as he comes up in in couple
of talks from now uh we have taken some
of the ideas which we developed with
infinite Cooling using electrostatics
and looked at how we can prevent for
example dust formation on panels solar
is is expanding uh a photo takes are
growing rapidly but a big uh show
stopper could become formation of dust
something as mous dust accumulating on
these panels leads to a big efficiency
loss if you don't clean the panels uh
within a week you could be losing a
percent or a 2% and then um you know
sometimes when you have a dust storm
like if you're in a desert which is the
ideal place to put the panels you can
lose almost 30% of your uh Power uh so
here you know what we have seen in the
lab we sort of recreated that problem
right where you you have a dust of
course you you're blacking out the panel
and uh uh the waste that are cleaned
today are using water which has to be
demineralized and very clean and it's a
huge Opex cost uh and you're in the
middle of a desert where you need to get
such clean water right and then uh if
you go to dry scrubbing you scratch the
surfaces and that say leads to
irreversible damage so uh this is you
know if you don't solve this it's a big
a big sustainability issue for solar uh
and so our goal has been to create
waterless ways or contactless ways to do
this and as we were experimenting in the
lab trying to use some charge effects we
found some interesting new phenomena
where uh we found that by electrostatic
induction we were able to get the dust
particles to sort of repel off of the
surfaces and as we dug more into it we
found that you know all these particles
made out of some level of silica and
that able to absorb a little bit of uh
uh water films and that allows us to
then use electromagnetic induction to
actually um um repel to charge the
particles as the land on the surfaces
and can be removed so we have shown that
you know we've taken a made a prototype
where we can uh you know put it on a
robotic arm and sort of move things
around and take uh the dust off of these
surfaces so we are looking at scaling
this technology and then uh really
implementing this so that you know the
water footprint of solar as well as
other Opex cost could be
reduced so let me jump into my next
topic which is my recent passion which
is to solve sort of the carbon uh CO2
problem and as I mentioned um this is a
problem of scale really because uh you
know you need to be removing gigatons of
CO2 and the way to do this is of course
taking care of Point sources taking care
of also the atmosphere because there's a
lot of CO2 out in the atmosphere so
we've been looking at both Dak and dock
uh systems which I'll discuss today and
then uh you know also valorizing that
CO2 so that at the end of the day there
is a useful product and so if you take
the CO2 emissions a lot of this you know
of course it's in the ambient but it's
also uh partitions into the oceans
oceans take up about 30% of the CO2 it's
the biggest contactor there is with the
atmosphere right and so what we have
here is as the oceans take up the CO2
you have uh essentially the pH of the
oceans oceans are acidifying and the pH
is decreasing as you can see and even a
small change there it may not seem like
oh I'm going from 8.5 to 8.1 but that's
huge because this is a logarithmic scale
and this is leading to unwanted effects
for example corals are getting affected
or marine life is getting affected and
then we have hard to uh hard to
decarbonize Industries such as Aviation
or shipping and others so how are we
going to do this and do this fast and do
this in a way that we can have an good
economics uh as well with it so those
are the kind of problems you're trying
to address and this is a simple example
of shipping a runof-the-mill ship like
50 megawatt kind of engine could be
emitting as high as 500 or 600 tons of
CO2 per day right and so we and there's
IM more timeline here of reducing
emissions by 50% so you're looking at
new ways where you could retrofit onto
the ship's exhaust and directly do the
capture and in this process we've been
thinking about integration and
integrated approaches if you take
traditional ccus you're taking capture
and when when you're doing capture you
know uh the capture is not uh uh is is
thermodynamically favorable because you
have sorbents that can absorb CO2 but
then the extraction of CO2 from the
sorbent is costly and then after that
you know conversion can be a lot more
expensive both in terms of capex and
Opex so what we've been doing in my lab
is uh to really integrate processes so
that we can go directly from capture to
conversion and uh like I said we work
with uh no matter what the source is uh
we we've done work with Point sources
where you have a higher concentration so
easier to separate the CO2 two oceans
where the concentration is maybe 4%
similar to what happens at a gas turbine
exhaust to air which is 400 PPM 100
times less than uh that and then upcycle
it and create uh value products such as
fuels or um other chemicals uh and and
so
on um so I'll highlight few efforts that
are going on here we uh are taking uh
some of the uh our ways to capture these
uh is using uh sort of the goal is to
reduce capex so using again the the play
on surface area and improve the uh
capture efficiency and then uh you know
uh We've invented a technology to
capture Mists which uh which we'll
discuss in Mah's talk in in a few few uh
talks from now and then we have some new
electrochemical conversion techniques to
convert that back into products and then
we can regenerate our sorbent and kind
of put it back so that allows us to take
uh uh Towers like this this is a a
postcombustion
PCS capture called Petrova plant which
is huge almost the size of a skyscraper
and um one of my uh thoughts was like
why is it so why do you need such large
capex especially when you're using
sorbents into which CO2 solubility is
pretty high and the reason for that is
there's not as much interfacial area
available to you and that's because some
of these films are only 600 microns
thick and now if you take this and make
finer droplets you can go to much higher
surface areas and then you can
essentially uh get you know 100 fold
Improvement in uh in the capture
efficiency and uh you know we've
developed electrostatic ways to capture
The Mists which uh allow us to uh do
something like this so I'm going to
steal a little bit of Mah's Thunder here
uh so this was in Mah's PhD thesis uh
where we have used plumes like this and
when you apply an electric field you
capture these uh these Miss and we are
able to then uh essentially not have
emissions so if we use something like
this we can redesign completely from
scratch how we put together a absorber
and what kind of drop sizes and
distributions we need that allow us to
do this capture better and we can
significantly reduce the uh the the
capture uh sort of the the tower sizes
and so on and thereby reduce capex
significantly this also could be used
for DAC processes because uh significant
cost here is in the uh contactor and the
absorber costs and um uh like Mah will
describe we have already scaled up this
these kind of systems and therefore we
are very confident that we could apply
this technology and really take it uh
take it for forward into into the market
and those are some of the efforts that
are going on in the lab I'll switch
gears to another topic which is U uh on
the Marine
CO2 uh like I said uh the oceans are the
biggest contactor the capture is already
done for you so you don't have to build
a tower to do the capture but uh now
it's how to take the CO2 out of the
oceans in a efficient manner uh the
concentration of CO2 is about 100 times
more than in air so that's about 4% you
know similar to the exhaust of a gas
turbine output so uh which is kind of
mindboggling that you're putting so much
CO2 into the oceans and it's only going
to increase and the potions are amazing
you know they they are able to kind of
self-heal in a way they have this
buffering system that takes in the CO2
right and forms carbonic acid and the
carbonic acid Spates as bicarbonate and
carbonate ions as the ph and it's a pH
mediated equilibriums as a pH decreases
what we see is more of the bicarbonate
and that's also why it's having an
impact on sea life because they use
carbonate ions to form shells and other
things so what we have come up with is a
all electrochemical just using
electricity as a input right we take the
ocean water using this reaction we
protonate that and thereby uh uh move
the equilibrium to CO2 aquous and which
can be then removed from the uh from the
system and now we have another cell
where we deprotonate and thereby real
alkalize and put this thing back so the
real alkalized water essentially can
capture more CO2 or could be used as a
Val stream for example in aquaculture
and other sort of areas and um uh we
have some of the best energetics in the
world uh because we uh this system
operates almost like a battery right so
we are taking putting protons here and
taking protons out from this side and
then there are no membranes we don't
have any waste products or waste
chemicals so it's a very uh uh you know
I'm very excited about this technology
and we're looking at uh scaling this and
then being able to apply this in real
world application ations uh
soon uh the economics works out also
well uh we this is just including our
electrochemical cost we at a54 per ton
of CO2 and then we uh have have now come
up with new ways to extract the CO2 in a
vacuum free manner or use the CO2 Waters
in a way to do direct conversion and
this allows us to apply this on Offshore
platforms in shipping or in desalination
plants and various places where you're
already moving ocean water or Fisheries
for example I know Japan has a lot of
aquaculture business uh as well right so
uh this is what's happened right with
ocean life pre-industrial revolution you
have uh enough carbonate ions for these
shellfish to form uh the shells but as
you go into now a lot of the uh because
of the decrease in the pH a lot of the
uh uh uh uh DIC or the dissol in organic
carbon is in a bicarbonate form making
it difficult uh for the shellfish to
form shells and actually uh in in the us
alone you know both on Washington as
well as in Gulf of Maine uh there's been
a significant impact people have to
treat their ocean waters now with care
with way to neutralize and be able to
use it for their hatcheries and and
other things uh the shellfish Market is
about you know close to a billion
dollars in the US just in in Washington
alone you know there's been1 10000
million loss because they are not able
to the Washington oyster economy was
affected because of the acidification
kind of issues so we uh we have been
continuing to uh um sort of uh make
strides on the technology development
and we are recently uh working with
University of Maine we have a new
collaboration where we where we are
scaling this and applying this to this
aquaculture uh systems uh if you look at
CO2 removal Market it's a huge Market uh
but in the shellfish aquaculture which
is also a big Market but the value of
really dealing with the CO2 problem is
immense because you know it's both
affecting Coastal communities their
economy as well as you know they are
actually using chemicals to buffer uh
and having to input you know materials
and cost to buffer the ocean so we can
really come in as a good economic uh
gain here as well for these uh this
industry and so yeah we have some uh
current work that's going on where we
are scaling our system into a modular
stuff that could then be uh taken uh
forward I think I have few more minutes
uh and I will uh wrap up soon but uh so
you get all that CO2 what do you do with
all the CO2 right how do I then take it
and make value with this thing um and so
one of the approaches we've been looking
at is uh electrolysis of CO2 right so
you take uh the CO2 and uh we can uh
basically uh do electrolysis and create
high value products and uh again
technoeconomics we always do
technoeconomics as we go along with the
science so that we know that we are you
know approaching the right market and we
can then accordingly engineer our
systems and one of the products here is
ethylene which has a significant market
and a big contributor to uh emissions
and uh to be able to make this work a uh
one needs to be able to do this at very
very high current densities if you are
at low current densities which is a lot
of uh the work is it makes it sort of
difficult to commercialize these kind of
systems so what we did here was uh we
took uh existing uh gas diffusion
electrodes where CO2 comes in here
interacts with the electrolyte and forms
uh the products we can then essentially
uh uh there's been a major challenge
where if you uh have high you need both
High conductivity and high
hydrophobicity because if you have high
conductivity and and don't have the
hydrophobicity the electrolyte can just
get into or flood this gas diffusion
layer thereby adding a big mass
transport resistance but if you have
something that's hydrophobic like Teflon
then it's not conductive and the
electrons have to go through a very thin
uh region thereby creating a huge omic
losses so uh so we kind of uh created
kind of Best of Both World scenario by
uh creating a hierarchically conductive
gas diffusion electrode that allowed us
to then uh really sort of
uh both uh reduce all these omic losses
and also make a tunable way to both make
U you know carbon monoxide or uh
ethylene or have a combination of these
kind of uh materials or these kind of
products and so we've been able to show
high faradic efficiencies uh and also
high efficiency towards uh ethylene and
scale uh this uh reactor so that it can
then be modularized and scaled to
Industrial sort of applications and this
is kind of where we ended up a lot of
the literature in the space is at low
small sizes but as you scale this there
are a lot of challenges and I think
that's why you know thinking about scale
as you're doing science is uh is very
very
important uh we also do another Pathway
to capture CO2 using biological uh uh
approaches here we use in this case
algae and created sort of
photobioreactors uh and these photobio
reactors use light as an input and the
algae and they're very extremely
efficient effent more efficient than
trees to uh to move the CO2 and and be
sequestered uh so what we do here is uh
for example a kilogram of algae can
consume up to 2 kilog of CO2 and then
you can create value products like
omega3 and food and so on and a big
challenge in this space is biofouling
and we have uh Tre uh used uh various
other surfaces where we can create a
surface that is uh negatively charged
and algae surfaces or algae cells have a
negative charge and thereby can prevent
you know um prevent sttion of these
cells and and keep these bioreactors uh
clean
um so I'm going to switch gears I think
I
have what one minute okay so I'll do uh
in one minute I'll just talk about the
Battery Technology uh so uh with
batteries the uh like I said the key
challenge here is is U um flammability
you know as we go to uh storage you know
when we when you have a when you have a
lithium I mean I'm sure all of you know
what batteries are right so you have two
electrodes anode and cathode and then
you are using some sort of a uh ion that
moves shuttles back and forth and you're
storing uh storing charge and thereby
storing energy uh in that in that form
if you're taking your iPhone it has a
lithium cell which is fine it is a very
low uh low low capacity so but then you
take the same material and go to um
stationary storage where you're going to
megawatt hours and lithium is explosive
so that has led to major problems uh
while lithium is a king but when you go
to these large applications can lead to
significant uh fires and so on this has
happened recently in many places and um
this uh can be catastrophic because when
these uh things go off um just because
lithium can be very explosive here you
know I'm showing you I think this video
is probably not working but if you
puncture a cell it can blast off and uh
and the fires that you're getting emit a
lot of lot of fumes that can be very
dangerous so uh so that has led us to
really think about uh new kind of uh
approaches where we are doing
non-lithium uh and non flam in
inherently non-flammable batteries uh
through this uh through this company of
mine alsim uh energy and what we have is
a mixed metal oxide where we use uh both
sort of a manganese based cathode and a
metal oxide based anodes and we are able
to uh develop these cells uh here we are
going to put out 3.4 megawatt hours per
40t storage container and this should be
out sometime in 2026 so we are uh we we
have commercialize this technology and
along this path uh this can also operate
at high temperatures for IC and others
and then we are going to the next one
which would be at 6.8 megawatt hours per
40ft container applicable to shipping
and other uh Marine sort of
applications um and I'll just uh quickly
end uh by showing how this technology
works as you can see you know people
here in the in our uh in our our company
are assembling cells in open air if you
are a lithium cell you can't do this you
need a glove box so it allows us to man
uh do uh simplify Manu ufacturing
drastically uh we had a 500 kilowatt
Proto plant and now we building a
megawatt plant and from a point of view
of how this could be applied we could do
all kinds of ways to do the discharge it
is software configurable uh some
utilities want to be able to do 12-hour
cycle maybe 4our cycle uh we can easily
do that because a material allows this
we could do c uh we have a co4 discharge
rate we are trying to get to CO2
but this allows us to then uh really
choose what discharge rate you want for
what power you're going to do and then
what kind of a capacity there will be
and so at the moment we are on parity
with the with the on the levelized cost
of storage with lithium at a container
level right because we can pack more
cells uh and and uh we can also uh be
efficient with the land uh that uh one
could use um essentially we can do this
at a at a much smaller uh land footprint
so I'll pause here uh we have a number
of applications from utilities to uh to
Data Centers to others where storage is
important and if you're a chemical plant
you can't put lithium there because it
can be explosive and has all these uh
safety risks but this Battery Technology
can can readily be
applied thank you very much I'm happy to
address any questions uh
all right so the question is how do how
long do the liquid coating last we can
make them
um last as long as you want I mean
that's right so we um we we for example
some of the products that I showed you
we designed it for the shelf life
of the of the product uh we could also
replenish the coating as this is
happening so in a way it could have you
know as long a life as as one as
application might
me okay the surface engineering can stop
formation of blood clots and biofilms is
it also effective in preventing
rejection of biomaterials for
implantable devices uh yes so one could
actually do that as well uh we been
looking at ways to reduce protein
absorption and other things so yeah I'm
happy to discuss more if you tell me
what your biom material
is how can you find such a fitting
market for your technology do you
aggressively speak with industry people
is there a particular industry you're
looking to engage that's a great
question and that's why you know I came
all the way here to talk to all of you
uh so you've seen a flavor of what we do
uh talking to Industry is key because
the the problems are there right I can
sit in my office and imagine all kinds
of problems but that may not be real
though you know we do uh we we we we
want to look forward and think about
what could be but at the same time I
think there are critical bottlenecks
that if Sol could lead to uh could lead
to breakthroughs and I think you know
one uh area that I can I can highlight
is uh in the in this agriculture space
that I was looking at when I was at USDA
I gave gave a talk almost 10 years ago
and said okay what is a wish list of
problems that you want me to solve these
are my skills and they talked about
pesticide uh runoff and that led to
actually this company uh that is solving
that problem today and we deployed this
technology now in 65,000 acres in the US
and reducing the amount of pesticide
footprint but I'm happy to discuss
across you know Carbon capture to energy
to biomedical what could be some of the
interesting areas that you are looking
at interesting topics what bottlenecks
you might have and uh you know we can
bring some of our expertise to bear and
I can tell you if I can solve it or not
uh and uh and and and potentially come
up with ways to uh think about how to
scale and commercialize these
things all right so can carbon
deposition during CO2 capture due to
chemical reactions be prevented by
applying magnetic fields or coating
Technologies to create a protective
barrier
beforehand
uh so I guess you know the the point
here is uh I I'm I need to understand
this question a little bit more but I
can broadly kind of say that in the
absorb Towers you want best sorption
into your sorbent and most often you are
limited by surface interfacial area and
the reactivity of your sorbent for
example if I take hydroxide Solutions
which are a aquous you know less I would
say more benign than most other sorbents
uh you want High hydroxide concentration
to absorb that CO2 and then when you
want to release it you want to go back
into slightly more acidic regime where
the CO2 can go from carbonate back to uh
the CO2 aquous form and so in all of
these yeah interfacial engineering plays
a very important role so I'd be happy to
hear what your specific uh you know
challenge here is and can thereby you
know see what the best way to address
that is liquid light technology
applicable to extremely large surface
areas as high-rise buildings cars trucks
what level of constraints okay that's a
that's a great question we always
thought about you know can we quote the
bottom of the ship right so that you can
prevent biofouling or quote large areas
I mean it is it it can be completely
done it's uh you know all it comes down
to is what's the business case and what
is the customer willing to pay for for
what is the kind of the benefit right uh
is it easier for someone to go and clean
is it easier to have a robot do that
versus you know is it better to put in a
coating so I think it it's more of a
technoeconomics issue than a technology
issue we can scale and it depends on uh
what the application is and what is the
cost benefit
all
right thank you very much uh