Erica Hodes I'm the associate director
of Corporations uh what that means to
you is that I am the main person
responsible for making sure that we have
a really exciting slate of Capstone
projects every year um that you can
partner with companies on um and I'd
also like to introduce my colleague
Jordan LaVine who is a lecturer in
operations research and statistics and
partners with me on Capstone by Leading
you through the entire project uh
through our Capstone Force um we will
both be kind of contributing to we talk
about in terms of hstone process and
projects um but for now I'm going to
turn it over to Jordan to give you a
quick overview thanks Katherine or Erica
and um Katherine uh you want to go
ahead okay so um we're going to discuss
uh sorry the Capstone over Capstone is a
critical part of the curriculum um the
fall semester is focused in academics
and you will have a
uh robust slate of analytics classes in
the spring the uh along with the number
of electives one of the core components
is our Capstone um you will be given a
real world business and uh business
analytics and data science problem so
specifically what that means is Erica
and I right now uh for our next class
um or for 2025 are in active dialog
with our partner host companies and we
are making sure that what they bring
forth in terms of both data but also the
problem set is useful to their their
leadership their executive leadership so
um in this CL in this program I think we
did do a great job of just uh not being
too theoretical ensuring that what you
work on will actually impact the real
world our construct is teams of two with
a faculty advisor so you will meet with
me weekly you'll have a partner and
you'll also have a faculty adviser to be
uh prepared to provide you technical
advice so this is not a um this is not a
solo Evolution you are well supported
and um part of a team and um timing wise
we match in January which is during
something called IAP at MIT and you are
part-time from February to May at
approximately 10 hours a week so you can
balance your academic electives and then
full-time in the summer and we um we
make sure that you do something what we
call uh Advanced analytics so doing
descriptive analytics is not enough you
we will make sure that in the scope
there is some aspect that is predictive
uh machine learning or there's an
optimization aspect of it or lately
we've been picking up generative AI um
Elements which has been pretty
interesting
and Katherine if you got if you want to
go to the next
slide so here you see uh some example of
our partners we hope you recognize um
some of these brand names so
um Coca-Cola probably you recognize um
if you uh and Nike are probably the two
Global brands that stick out um if uh
United States based uh firm so Comcast
is is one of a handful of of major
providers of media cable TV in the
United States um and then we have a
number of startups included so we will R
we will majority work with large Fortune
500s but we also engage uh smaller
companies and we are mostly industry
agnostics so here in front of you you
will see uh you'll see projects ranging
from
retail uh consumer packaged Goods
technology and
media
Insurance um but you also will see
nonprofits so like the city of Boston um
or the United Nations and uh what I love
about these projects is you can
potentially work on a project and
actually see the um
implementation uh just as an examples as
I'm looking at this page on the right
hand side you see CVS in the middle
that's um
it's one of two or three uh retail
Health Care firms in the United States
and we had students and they'll they'll
teex they'll send text messages to their
customers and we had students work on
that the texting and so you know as a as
a patient or consumer of CVS I um I saw
the text messages that essentially was
um derived from students work Erica any
um you know over the past four years do
do you have any favorites on this list
oh I don't think that's fair
um I will say you know the the okay I'll
answer that the favorites are the ones
that come back year after year and build
on their work um so I think you know
when I'm when I'm looking at this list
Comcast Accenture fizer um a lot of
these companies have started off with us
when we were a really small program and
have continued to iterate various
problems that they have knowing that our
students are capable of giving them the
solutions that they need um so we have a
really high retention rate as I think
Jordan already mentioned but there's a
lot of value in building long-term
relationships here and they also tend to
hire our students um and so I think that
that's a really exciting way to think
about partnership so I um I I call it
the Congo line I I don't have a better
explanation it's kind of you know maybe
I'm showing my age I I don't know but uh
the metaphor works so Eric I mentioned a
few but also like CAC CGM thermofisher
scientific that they'll sponsor and then
they'll hire and then the individual
that they hired will then be the manager
or the program leader for the next
Capstone um and we see that as highly
synergistic as um I mentioned you this
isn't you don't do this alone you do
this as part of a team and it's pretty
it's pretty cool when you then work with
a company and you're working with former
um Mand students or Alum of the program
who who are best uh able to assess your
your calibration and skill set and and
position you for
Success um Katherine wanted we go ahead
and move
forward so timing um we have this down
to a science we feel very good about it
uh Eric and I have been doing this for
four years programs done it for maybe
seven or eight um I'm estimating maybe
200 plus projects so we feel very very
good about how this process plays
out um as I mentioned in the fall so um
September to December and you'll if you
enroll um orientation is actually in
August but the the core fall semester is
uh is analytics
coursework um you will do some prep but
really we try to keep you focused on
your
academics in January uh which is a
special session as I mentioned I AP at
MIT you will uh you and your partner and
and you choose your partner by the way
um we stay out of the partner choosing
process uh by December we'll ask you to
pair up we'll help kind of guide it but
as I said for the most part we stay out
of it um January you will will kick off
cap Zone you will work on your uh
messaging to the companies we'll conduct
something called pitch day where the
companies come to MIT campus it's it's a
lot of fun it's my favorite event for
the process um you will hear the
companies and their plans you will then
have the opportunity to interview
with uh a number of companies we'll
organize that and you'll also get
coaching from uh one of our colleagues
um in career development on how to best
present yourself we'll then release a
match um usually in the beginning of
February uh there's absolutely an
algorithm that we use because this is
the MIT applied business analytics
program um Eric and I actually conduct a
class in January where we show you uh
underneath the hood of the algorithm and
then Springtime you are at 10 to 12
hours per
week um you will be taking electives and
um you will you'll have a Capstone
course so that's about 60 to 90 minutes
with me once a week and the goal in the
spring is to get you oriented to the
company to the problem statement to
their lexicon to their line of work and
ensure that you have data so that you
are positioned to join the company in
June at 40 hours a week um your
geographical location is is dependent on
the company so preco we were very rigid
on um being on site and co uh presented
us with the opportunity to learn and
understand
um uh remote
um support and now essentially it's a
company by company thing during the
pitch the company will will will tell
you where they want you to be and then
as we're working through the Capstone
class in Spring I'm going to ask you for
a series of Milestones that I think
we'll see in a second and and one of
them is to be very clear by the month of
March on where you're going to be in the
summer so um as I said we've done a lot
of these projects at this point we're
pretty good at making sure that we
enable you to have a constructive
dialogue and discussion with your
companies um so your best position to
support them that might be full-time on
site at the company that might be fully
remote uh we will position you to have
that discussion
um and of
course mid August the end of August you
will come back to campus and present
your work as part of the capson Showcase
and um what's pretty interesting is it
overlaps with orientation so the
incoming students get to see what the
final product looks like um and so you
get a sense of what uh where this where
this effort leads to um respect to
process Erica am I missing
anything no um but there did come in our
most popular question uh which is how
does the matching process work uh
everyone asks this multiple times
throughout throughout the admissions
process and once you're on campus so
happy to give a quick overview of that
um as Jordan mentioned we have an
algorithm um but that's not the whole
answer right so the thing that is
important for you to understand is that
it is mutually ranked uh and equally
weighted so when you meet all of the
companies and see all of the projects
you and your teammate will rank all of
them from one to presumably 40 depending
on how big our classes you will then get
match of 10 to 12 interviews from that
initial ranking so you will only
interview with 10 to 12 of those
projects after you complete those
interviews you will rank them again
right for your top 12 uh or for from 1
to 12 and then those companies that you
interviewed with will also rank you and
we then use those two data set that's um
to run a matching algorithm so the
companies do not have greater preference
you do not have greater preference
there's some Nuance in there that we
talk about in January once this process
is kind of in ongoing um but that's the
that's the C of it is that there you you
have a say and so does the
company and um and yes we're Al we're
often asked this question um I think the
key point on top of all this is Eric and
I our objective is
um is is synergy and
sustainability and thus we work very
hard to establish a transparent process
and one that gets the students excited
gets the companies excited ensures the
companies keep sponsoring into the
future and and and and hopefully guides
the companies to hire um and then
ultimately we want the alumni to come
back and sponsor so uh we recognize the
gravity of the match and we take it very
seriously um and we will spend a good
amount of time helping you understand
that this is a multifaceted um Evolution
with a lot of different
stakeholders absolutely uh we also have
another question here um if a company
requires students to be on site will
there be funding to help with temporary
location uh yes so the company pays a
fee in order to participate in the
Capstone projects um and that fee
largely comes back to you in various
ways one of those is with your summer
tuition but the other is through a
travel reimbursement um so every student
will get a baseline level of support
throughout the summer um but there's
also travel specific reimbursements that
we provide we have companies in the west
coast we have companies in Germany and
other places in Europe um so we do
understand that that is that is a factor
in terms of how we match and how excited
you are about the company itself um so
there is financial support
there and next page
Catherine thank you okay um topics uh
I'll briefly touch on these um I'm not
going to go into too much depth uh we
just published a article in MIT SL ideas
at matter Katherine if you would uh
please drop that on the
chat um I'm going to work through these
uh Accenture so this one was fascinating
um
we were still working on it actually but
the concept
was can the students and they did this
can they
enumerate which jobs in the global
Workforce will be impacted by generative
Ai and that product is the the the data
product they built is being used by
centure a global management consulting
firm to advise and guide their
clients
um the sigma case this was pretty
interesting
um we were able to identify prescription
routines of
physicians in treating depression and
the students were able to essentially
enumerate or quantify the an observation
that Physicians tended to
use the prescription option that was
best for the general population but was
suboptimal for the
individual and so they did a a great job
getting the data in place presenting the
the problem statement in a way that
clinicians could understand it and then
creating an algorithm that would uh lead
to a personalized recommendation as
opposed to a generalized population
level recommendation dig Sporting Goods
um this is one of my favorites of the
year um just because but whereas the
signal signal use case that I just
talked about with um uh prescription of
of depression products it requires a
very high level of um accuracy for for
obvious reason Dick Sporting Goods uh
sought to use generative AI to send
custom emails where the stakes are a lot
lower and so you can have a higher error
rate Dick Sporting Goods they refer to
their customers as athletes and they
want to generate um uh you know the
specific email to the athlete
so uh Erica is a runner um and so
ideally you would send a promotional
email to Eric on running I I don't run I
I'm allergic to it um I do other things
like watch sports and so I um I want to
get the emails about uh about being a
college football fan
um thermal Fisher Scientific uh was
pretty interesting uh the students were
supporting something called the sales
and operation planning
process um which is pretty routine
however the students were able to apply
uh novel analytics methods in the
thermofisher scientific environment so
they actually got like a a 2x4 for
improvement on their on their
predictions from six month forward and
then um UNICEF is a United Nations
entity and their focuses on how to
allocate scarce resources specifically
vaccines in the in West and central
Africa and the students um problem
statement was pretty fascinating and
that they were operating with very
sparse data um and so they to get very
clever in their their techniques and
methods to help guide um well it's
ultimately a political process the
allocation of vaccines um in in a
limited environment a date
environment uh Katherine go ahead
please so um every year uh we
select around 10 projects to present at
our Capstone showcase so the Capstone
showcase as I mentioned the end of
August you'll do a poster session and
we'll have about 10 teams actually
present um we have a global feed so your
parents can dial in or your friends
which is always a lot of fun um and this
year we elected to have two winners one
was from a startup called cognit and one
um is a product in support of wiser
fizer at fizer the pharmaceutical
company cognit um is in the business of
simplifying business operations and
processes for insurance companies
and the team leveraged generative AI
to uh
read PDFs free form
PDFs um thus uh just enabling cognit
startup to be a lot more efficient and
faster in their support of their
insurance company
clients and then fizer um is one of
these companies where we have the Congo
line going so uh we f has been hiring
for years and the student
team um were able to uh leverage
generative AI to um analyze uh how
scientists within fiser do their analyze
what scientists are doing at fiser and
support them to communicate better to
get their drugs to Market faster um so
both these projects were selected
because uh one they are using or did use
fairly novel and new methods but both
had almost immedate impact in in their
um company environments which we thought
was pretty
impressive Katherine if you want to go
ahead um so we have a couple frequently
asked questions how to cstone teams get
chosen I I briefly mentioned that um
you're going to choose your partner in
December
and by then you will you will know the
cohort um and then we in January as as
we said there's
a uh fun process that starts with pitch
starts with your preparation has a pitch
day has you H we'll have you doing a
number of interviews and then we'll have
the match um Erica touched on the
matching process we can come back to it
if there are following questions um to
Capone companies hire us uh our numbers
are about 25 to 30% of our stud students
go to Capstone
companies um that
number uh we'll see how it fluctuates
but it it's a number that we We Stand By
and are pretty proud of um and then can
we suggest a company for capson
absolutely if you know anybody who would
consider sponsoring uh by all
means send Erica or I an email and we
will take it from there um Erica do we
have any other questions in the in the
chat you um so here's one that's asks
what are the most used tools when
working with the companies for the
project uh python Excel Etc um the
answer is yes all of them uh and when I
say that I'm I'm mostly saying that you
will you will know how to use what the
company wants you to use um so they may
be working in R they may be working in
Python um certainly you will be using
Excel in some capacity um there will be
some data visualization you will be
working in various forms of class
because they are largely not going to
let you download their data uh straight
to your laptop so you will adapt to
whatever they are using you will be
equipped to do that by the time January
rolls around um and Jordan feel free to
add anything yeah um so it's a great
question um my my top level answer is
that uh you know to Echo ER you're going
to do what the company needs you to do
and you're going to be in the tool set
they want you to that's said you're
going to have plenty of time to get
ramped up and so like first order thing
for me is always the problem statement
what are you working on why are you
working on it um Eric and I'll make sure
you have that preliminary answer but
once you get match it's going to be on
you to really spend time on the problem
statement that's baked into the
curriculum then you're going to need
credentials so the companies might send
you a laptop or they might give you
Cloud access um and we'll there's time
for that
and then you're going to start
visualizing their data and in our first
our second milestone I just I just want
to hear or understand that you can
interpret their data appropriately and
so I don't really need use of tools
until like April or May uh because we
have a lot of time up front and it it's
I I love the process I I didn't I did
not create it I inherited it and I think
it's wonderful nice long slow Runway
before you really have to take off
um and that said I track where each team
is every week and if your credentials or
access doesn't come through I I'm there
to work through that with you and your
company to make sure you get back up to
speed so um things are deliberate and
slow up front and then once you actually
will have a requirement to start
leveraging a tool set which you will um
you will know that and you will have the
time to uh to learn it and be
ready great thank you uh next question
is do we have access to mock or sample
interviews between student companies
during the matching period um you will
have a lot of practice interviewing uh
there will not be specific examples of
what the companies ask you because all
companies conduct these in their own
sort of unique ways um but our Career
Team uh through the career office does a
really thorough job of preparing you to
answer the types of questions that most
of the companies are asking and we spend
a great deal of time in January but even
prior um making sure that you have
plenty of practice and plenty of
practice interviewing as a team because
that's a a unique experience for for
most of the
student uh the next question and you're
gonna probably do 10 interviews and so
the first one is going to be
stressful and the 10th one is going to
be less stressful every interview in
between uh you start to learn so this is
one of the features of the program uh
that I also think is just excellent in
that this is a uh I don't want to say
Force but it it's it's a milestone in
which you execute the process of
interviewing it you do it with a partner
you get feedback and it's it's not in
the live environment that you're going
to face in the summertime when it's time
to go get a real job
postgraduation uh next question is what
kind of deliverables will be asked of us
to submit internally for the sake of the
class or is material primarily going to
be shared through continuous update
meetings with faculty and you
Jordan so we have five great question um
we'll cover it in depth but we have five
Milestones that are standard um the the
first Milestone is Administrative nature
it's a project Charter just to make sure
that you and the company have a very
clear understanding what it is you'll be
doing uh it's not set in stone but it's
a good marker second m is exploratory
data analysis the third Milestone is um
is before you go off for the summer
where it's my ability to make sure that
you have a good plan the fourth
Milestone is a
um uh kind of dry run of your mil your
Capstone showcase and then your fifth
Milestone is the Capstone showcase there
are a couple deliverables with the
Capstone
showcase uh one is company specific and
that's like a 30-page report due to the
company we'll have company confident
confidential data nobody sees that
except for me and a faculty member and
then you'll have a
poster um and a presentation that will
have to be reviewed by your company will
be released into the public domain um so
I I try to be as hands off as possible
and let you do your thing with your
companies um but I do need I do need to
build a track progress so I have these
five milestones in place so I can make
sure that everybody's moving at the
right
pace thank you Jordan
uh let's see so do students come up with
the Capstone project topics if we do
does it go through an approval process
um so no you don't um the companies
themselves will bring us a use case um
and in some cases you know will work
with us pretty closely to come up with
their use case uh particularly if
they're new to the process um they will
kind of work extensively with us upfront
to make sure that their project proposal
makes sense for the type of analytics we
want the students to be doing um as well
as things that are attainable for a
student cohort within the seven-month
engagement of the project um so no you
never are the one coming up with the
Capstone topic itself um that said
projects will be influenced by you
throughout the course of it so what the
company comes to us in January and
proposes may end up looking very
different by the time you present it in
August uh and that's normal and we like
that and that is an expected part of
doing business and so there was a sort
of secondary question that's related
which is have there been any cases where
a student or company switches projects
Midway through um we're never going to
switch teams Midway through but you
might find that the project has pivoted
based on the availability of the data
Maybe the question you thought you were
going to be able to answer turns into a
different question um maybe the
priorities of the company have changed
and they are pivoting to a slightly
different topic all of those things are
stressful potentially but perfectly okay
um and that is one of the reasons Jordan
and I are here to make sure that those
projects still end up being
successful um so that's that's kind of
the the large answer to that obviously
there are you know different things that
happen every year that we deal with as
they come um but we do expect that that
the question that a company comes with
may not be the answer that they end up
with at the end
um let's see here oh there's a lot of
questions coming through okay what
programming language do we need to
master in the mband um most of our
students are coming in with some
experience in coding um regardless of
language we're actually fairly agnostic
to it you will learn Julia while you are
here um you are going to be expected to
be able to be competent in SQL and
python andr
uh right couple questions left um is the
interview conducted as a team or alone
and is the ranking selection for the
companies done done as a team or
individually everything is done as a
team um for the purposes of the Capstone
project so you will you will get to know
your cohort really well um in the fall
and you will do some Project based work
with them so you should have a good
sense of who you work well with and that
will influence who you decide to team up
with um your interviews are conducted as
a team your matching is done as a team
so you are a package deal as far as the
companies are
concerned uh and then our final question
in the chat right now is when companies
propose Capstone topics how many topics
does each company typically provide this
varies um the vast majority of them
simply propose a single project and and
host a single project um we have some
relationships with companies that are
hosting more than one project and we
have some very select companies that we
trust really because of a long-standing
relationship that will propose any
number of topics and either let Jordan
and I choose the best one or propose a
couple of topics to the students and let
them choose the best one or or the one
that they're most interested in so it it
varies but the vast majority of
companies are proposing a single topic
that we then refine with them to make
sure it's appropriate for our student
uh just to confirm on the language
question is this a prerequisite for the
program or can it be learned during the
fall period um to be perfectly Frank if
you don't have a any coding experience
you may not be a competitive candidate
we have about 1,800 applications every
year and we seed a class of 80 um every
single one of those 80 students had at
least some programming experience before
they came here um that doesn't mean you
have to be fluent in any of them we care
a lot more about your hard math so your
linear algebra your
statistics um but we would expect you to
have at least dabbled uh in in learning
at least one coding language before you
get
here and those are the open questions
that I
have and I will just add on for folks we
will have a application overview and
tips for the business analytics program
on November 25th that also will be
recorded for those who can attend live
so um we'll go into more in depth those
questions are on coding and letters of
recommendation at that time but
definitely um we have a few more minutes
about 10 more minutes so take advantage
of having Jordan and Erica here please
do uh put your questions in the chat or
Q&A I can I can talk
um
so chat GPT um unveiled itself to the
world in what December of
202 um so for the 23 cycle we had two
companies do generative AI use cases
which was which is pretty interesting
because you know they turn around quick
if that gives you a sense of speed so
right December of
22 um am I am I thinking properly or
maybe maybe was end of fall of 22 but in
a couple months we had two companies
that said okay let's do generative AI
use cases they did they were
successful last December then we were
looking at the slate and we had 10 of 40
um and that felt high but those tended
quite well um which uh Captain dropped
that article and you can see a quick
synthesis um so we'll see we'll see how
fast the technology is changing I still
I think that the majority of Scopes next
year um that so January so in a couple
months January of 25 I still think are
going to be the traditional data science
pipeline use cases I would imagine for
your class we're going to be majority
generative AI um but it's all TVD um and
I say this one to just give you a kind
of pulse check of how the world's moving
um but also to emphasize the point that
we will we will stay agile and adaptable
to the need needs of our host companies
and if they have a desire to experiment
with generative AI we'll do it on the
condition we understand the influence to
the business and the the profit and loss
statements and their in their key
financials right we have a couple let's
see all right how does matching work um
so we talked on this a little bit it's
mutual uh so the companies rank the
teams the teams rank the companies there
are two rounds of that one pre-interview
one post
interview um and both sides are equally
weighted so we run an algorithm to match
you that does not give you preference
but also does not give the company
preference so it's it's pretty evenly
weighted we've had good luck with it um
generally speaking both companies and
student teams are overall happy with
their match um we don't guarantee
anything to either you or the companies
so anyone you interview with is fair
game you might get matched with them we
expect that you'll be fine with it um
and we expect that even if you're not
fine with it you will adapt and become
fine with it because some of those
projects end up being the best
projects
um so that's how that works let's see uh
what were markers that have shown up in
very successful Capstone projects
Jordan um
yeah um good question it's it's whether
an executive like really cares usually
that that's my answer it's it's whether
or not we'll get the business unit
president focus on on what's going to
happen um it takes a lot to get there
and that's usually with our repeat uh
caps on house
um
alternatively robust and available data
is also prerequisite to a very
successful Pro and that's something we
work on to make sure that's the type of
data you
get thank you uh what has been the most
exciting memorable project you've seen
so
far there's a lot
um I think the ones for me it's the ones
that get implemented really quickly
right so that fiser project we did this
year the BMW project um about defect
detection they that where they're
transferring the code and it's getting
implemented right away as part of the
business strategy for me those are
always the most exciting um there's
always really interesting analytical
work to do um but because we're an
applied program I think for me it's the
ones where the compan is so excited
about the work that the students did
that they're like going back to to their
decision makers and and getting it done
um and there's there's there's honestly
no shortage of those which I think is
really cool
uh roadblocks that students run into um
so Jordan mentioned that some of the
best projects are the ones with readily
available data uh roadblocks would be
something where getting data is
challenging for one reason or another
right either that's jumping through
administrative Hoops to get it and you
get it really late or the data that the
company thought was going to be
available simply isn't uh there was a
memorable project where the company was
prepared to get give data to the
students they had a different data
breach and got very skittish about
sharing anything and so the whole
project had to Pivot and it still ended
up being successful but that was
certainly a road
blook um others I think would be you
know a Mis mismatch set of
expectations uh of what the students
deliver at various points um but those
are things that are very common and we
work through fairly
quickly um I think data availability is
probably the biggest frustration for
students um particularly early on when
they kind of expect to just kind of be
handed data sets as they've been in the
fall right in the fall you're doing a
lot of cour work you're getting handed
very clean data sets um and that's not
going to be the case in the
spring
roadblocks um you know we've had some
kind of regulatory problem statements so
uh we're try to analyze like the effect
of third party cookies going away that
one got a little complex um but
generally speaking these projects we
have a good process and we have a good
flow and sometimes in the spring we'll
have a couple teams that aren't moving
as fast as the rest of the cohort
because of uh administrative issues and
the students can get very concerned uh I
try to make sure I spend time with those
teams and help them understand we'll
work through it um but sometimes
administrative things hold up the
project and part of that's part of life
uh and thus you know learning how to
adapt and kind of go the flow um and not
getting not emotionally reacting so you
know being so concerned is part of it
but that that's that's why that's why
we're here that's why Eric and I are
here to support you through this
yeah uh can we share any information
about the list of companies for the
class of 25 or 26 uh no but thank you
for asking uh do we see any difficulties
in securing spons because of the
academic downturns in recent years uh
we've already we've already kind of gone
through this in the sense of Co really
did a number on companies abilities to
engage in the type of way that they
engage with us um so we've weathered a
number of economic downturns already um
and we have strategies for making sure
that we still come to you with a slate
of really excellent projects um so yes
it's it's part of our job to anticipate
those those difficulties and to figure
out how to Pivot around them um but
certainly there's always there are
always challenges some of it's not
economic some of it has has to do with
with other things um but we have never
failed to deliver a really great set of
Capstone projects uh and there's no
reason for us to think that 25 or 26
will be any
different um we have maybe a minute or
two Katherine is there a way to identify
like the last question
yeah I can start typing some answers to
some of these yes I know we are now
getting a bunch in here
um from experience maybe this is a good
one to end us with what teams were able
to Excel and overperform in their
projects
the the the ones who know how to walk
and chew gum at the same time um we are
we are the applied business analytics
program uh there's got to be focus on
the business and stakeholder management
and understanding what the purpose is
and the why and then we're searching for
a distinctive analysis of data sets um
it's easy to go to business and kind of
keep things basic it's easy to go super
technical and forget about the business
so the uh the ability to walk the line
is what uh what we're all about on this
program