living in the world you must have
concern for the future if you care about
it and I think if you want to predict
the future and want to know if it's
going to be positive or negative the
best way to do it is to shape it so I
think my biggest concern would be making
sure there's responsible use of certain
Technologies I'd say AI is a huge
concern for me I think it's only as good
as the programmer it's only as good as
the user it's only as good as the prompt
and I think what I'm really concerned
about is how Schools traditional
schooling private schooling goes about
teaching students about this new
technology for more MIT moments from MIT
open learning like subscribe or follow