I'd like someone in the audience to uh
let me borrow from them a real $1 bill.
I'm going to soak it in this clear and
colorless liquid which looks like water.
So, here is the dollar bill on fire. Or
is it?
>> Dr. Shakashiri soaked the money in a
solution of water, rubbing alcohol, and
a little bit of table salt. When he puts
the money in the flame, the alcohol
burns, reacting with oxygen, producing
carbon dioxide and water and heat and
light energy. So, why doesn't the bill
burn? Alcohol is evaporating off the
bill, turning into a gas and burning.
So, those are the flames that you see.
But remember that the solution is 50%
water. The water is evaporating much
less quickly than the alcohol, staying
in the bill [music] and preventing the
paper from burning.
Find your MIT moment. [music] Visit
learn.mmit.edu.