Welcome everyone. Welcome back. Um so uh
today we'll have a treat of you know
we're we're here in this um in this
colloquium uh where we've been at this
intersection between machine learning
and biomedical sciences really going
both ways. Um we'll actually be talking
more about applied mathematics and and
uh biomedical sciences and how to think
about foundations um in applied
mathematics in particular and topology.
um and then really motivated by you know
particular biological questions and
really going both directions. So from
biology to foundations and then from the
foundations back to um biological
questions and so I'm very excited to
have Katherine Hess here um from EPFL.
Um so she got her PhD in algebraic
topology actually here at MIT. Um so um
and then held positions at the
University of Stockholm, NIS and Toronto
um before going to EPFL where she's now
professor of mathematics and life
sciences. Um so her research uh focuses
on um algebraic topology and its many
applications primarily in the life
sciences, a lot of neuroscience
applications um but then also some
applications in material sciences um and
she has for example developed um a lot
of topological data analysis methods um
that were used for high throughput
screening of nanoporos crystalline
materials as well as and I think we're
we'll hear uh probably a lot of that
today the classification of neuron
morphologies and also neur eneral uh
network
dynamics. Uh Katherine has been highly
recognized for her work. Uh she was
elected to the Swiss Academy of
Engineering Sciences, was named fellow
in the American Mathematical Society as
well as the Association for Women in
Mathematics, etc., etc. Um so I'm very
excited that Katherine is here as she's
enjoying her sbatical and um came to
visit us during that time. So I'm very
excited to have you here. So the floor
is all
yours. Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Caroline. Thank you
for the invitation. Thank you to
everyone for being here. It's a great
pleasure to be here. I've really enjoyed
the time that I've spent at the Schmidt
Center so far. And I really look forward
to the coming days as well. Please feel
free to make appointments. Stop by. I'd
love to talk with people. That's what
I'm here for. Char recharging my uh
research batteries after four years of
being an administrator.
So I'm really eager to hear about your
ideas, what research you're doing, and
any ideas that my research inspires in
you. So today I'm going to talk about a
project that was led by uh one of my
former PhD students, Kelly Mags, and one
of my current PhD students, Marcus Ysef,
together with some people who are from
the life sciences at EPFL or life
sciences at the University of Loausanne
and now Heather Harrington for whom uh
Kelly is a posttock in Dresden at
NPI. And this is research that goes back
to the the roots of Kelly's thesis
project. So he was hired on an
international training grant from the
European Union which uh was all about uh
cancer biology and uh innovative methods
of doing cancer biology. And his
specific project was to think about how
the the menstrual cycle affects gene
expression. And so we're really looking
for topological tools for understanding
the cyclic behavior and gene expression.
And it really took until basically the
last year of his thesis to have the
right mathematical tools in place. And
so this what I'm going to be talking to
you about today is really this project.
What kind of mathematics goes into
understanding slick behavior of gene
expression? So what kind of challenges
are we talking about? So when he
actually when I first started thinking
about this kind of data, it was before
there were even single cells. We were
thinking just about ordinary RNA seek.
And now I'm going to be talking about
like what sort of problems can we tackle
in with related to single cell data that
we for which we can use tools from
topology and
geometry. So the first pro thing I want
to talk about is identifying cyclic
processes. So we're interested in
processes that are going to loop back
going back to homeostasis for example.
And so what are the steps that go into
our method for identifying such cyclic
processes? So we're going to use tools
from topology specifically something
called persistent coology which is a
tool from topological data
analysis and the pipeline we can develop
pipeline to detect and compute
statistically significant the
statistical significance sorry of
circular structure in such single cell
data. So we not just detect it but say
okay what is it really significant what
we're detecting there and how can we
justify it. So the tools we'll be using
are from topological data analysis. So
I'm going to explain these pictures
here, but basically we're going to have
a signature of the data that looks
something like this, which is called a
persistence diagram. And you see this
point here is pretty far from the
diagonal. And that turns out to give us
some notion of statistically significant
cyclic processes. And I'll explain in
more detail how that works.
The other type of problem we want to
study is okay once we've identified
these cyclic processes and we can say
sort of where in the process the
different cells are we'd like to see
something about which genes are actually
involved in these processes and in which
order are these genes activated through
gene cascades. So what we're going to do
is now use geometry, another kind of
mathematics to really analyze the
dynamics of the gene activity in these
cyclic processes. And we're going to
look at this by looking at the embedding
of this circular structure in trans
transcripttoic phase space. And so what
we'll end up with in the end is a
pipeline for estimating both cell and
gene phases from circular structure. So
we're going to have some sort of matrix
that's going to tell us about which
genes are leading which other genes. And
from that we'll be able to sort of see
the different phases and amplitudes of
the genes as we go through the cyclic
process. Be able to say oh gene I is
leading gene J which is leading gene K.
So that's the basic idea and I'll
explain in detail how we actually get
there. I'll provide some validation type
results on both synthetic data and
well-known cell cycle data and then look
at some experiments we've done with
different kinds of androgen receptor
silencing. So the philosophy that we
have is that if you look at the
epigenetic landscape, this is Wington's
famous epigenetic landscape that the
topology and geometry of this landscape
which is some sort of geometric object
actually has biological meaning. I don't
think that's very controversial. But how
do we go about measuring the topology in
geometry? Well, if we think about paths
in this landscape, we can think of this
as really corresponding to developmental
trajectories, right? As a cell evolves,
its gene expression evolves. And so you
can really think of that as some sort of
developmental trajectory. Now, in
particular, if we have a cell that
starts looping around in this landscape,
then that's really some sort of cyclic
process that we're seeing.
Now what turns out is that top
topological features of spaces. So
topology is about the essential shape of
a space not having the sort of scale
invariant and continuous deformation
invariant and that that gives us a sort
of stability to these features that we
detect and that provides us with
robustness for the signature we're
detecting in this way. And then we're
going to think of single cell data as
really providing us with a finite sample
of this landscape. we sort of figure out
where the cells are moving in this
landscape by looking at some sort of
finite
sample. Okay, so let's focus for a
moment on circular enrichment. We're
going to talk about the methods here and
then we'll see how to apply them
later.
So suppose we have some single cell
data. What do we do with it? Well, the
first thing we're going to do is define
find some sort of hallmark gene set. say
in the context of the particular problem
I'm considering which are likely to be
the genes that are important because
it's very hard to analyze genes in a
20,000 dimensional space we want to
restrict to something where we have a
greater chance of actually being able to
analyze the data in a reasonable way and
so we say okay if we're thinking about a
particular kind of problem then we
should restrict to maybe these 100 genes
or these 200 genes or something that
makes it easier for us to detect the the
circular structure we're looking for and
gives us some interpretability in the
bargain. From there, we're going to
simplify even further. We're going to
project onto the first K PCA
coordinates. Often in the calculations
we've done, K equals 5 turned out to be
a good answer. That's more of a
um not something that's mathematically
justified, but it's worked so far. It's
an engineering type
solution. And then from that, we'll
compute what's called the
one-dimensional persistent chromology of
this point cloud. So what we're getting
is a a bunch of points in some sort of
usually five-dimensional space. We like
to say what kind of structure are we
detecting there? We're going to use the
tools of persistent coology to detect
these circular structures. And I'll
explain
how. And then we have a way of
associating the of detecting whether or
not the circular structures that we've
noticed are actually relevant, actually
statistically significant by associating
to them some sort of score which is
called a ring score.
And then we can evaluate the statistical
significance of these ring scores
uh which will tell us something about
whether the circular structure we've
detected actually is meaningful and
worth evaluating from a biological point
of
view. So how do we get from point clouds
to what we need to use which are called
persistent diagrams. So we'll do an
example in in more detail in a moment.
But the basic idea is if we have a
collection of points in some
lowdimensional space. We if it's just a
collection of finite points, there's no
particular topology or geometry that
comes out. But we'd like to say well if
we have these collections of points
here, it looks like we have two circular
structures. Is there some rigorous way
we can say that? So using the tools of
persistent coalology or persistent
homology from topological data analysis,
it gives us a way of making rigorous the
argument that we have two circular
structures here. This idea of taking
little balls around each one of the
points and slowly growing the
radi sort of more complex geometric
structures arise. We see that once the
balls are big enough that we have two
holes in the center here which is giving
us circular structures and if it grows
even more then it all fills up. So what
we can do as the radi of the balls
increases is we can say okay at what
point does such a structure arise and at
what point does it disappear again. So
on the one hand we can compute what's
called the zero homology which is just
counting the the connected components or
we can look at the appearance and
disappearance of these sort of circular
structures which is what we call the
first
homology and then you can graph this
here by saying at what time at what
radius rather is this structure born?
What radius of these little balls is the
structure born and at what radius do
these things die? Does it all fill up?
And so we could plot points time of
birth time of death like this. And
looking at the distance from these
points to the diagonal here gives us
what's called the persistence of the
feature. So this particular feature here
corresponds to a persistence of one.
This feature here gives us a slightly
shorter persistence. So what we look at
is a difference between the death time
and the birth time. And what we're going
to do is as in this image here, we're
going to order the death and the birth
time from longest to shortest like this.
So we're going to go from a collection
of points by this method to now a
sequence of non-gative numbers like
this. And from this this sequence of
numbers will be able to tell us
something about the significance of the
features that we've detected
there.
Okay. So let's look at an example. So
here we have some collection of points
in the plane like this. And I'm going to
slowly grow these little balls that are
centered around each of these points. So
here we're supposeding the balls of
radius.3. We grow them a little more.5.
And we start to see different structures
emerging. There's a little circular
structure. The idea is that you're going
to add an edge between two points.
Anytime the two little balls intersect,
we grow the balls a little bit more. We
see this circular structure still here.
We see a hint of another circular
structure that seems to be on its way to
being developed. And we get to 0.9 and
all of a sudden you see this nice big
circle here. This is looks like some
sort of more significant circular
structure that's showing up. And we'll
say, okay, this is some sort of critical
threshold radius, critical radius for
these uh around these ball for these
little balls at which we see something
that seems to be a really important
feature that's coming up. What we want
to do is study this collection of points
and edges that we get this way that we
can study using the tools of algebraic
or combinatorial topology. If we
continue growing these balls like this,
then it starts filling up more and more
until at some point it's all filled up
and there's no more really interesting
topology in the
picture. So what are we going to do in
this case? We're going to go back to
this critical radius of 0.9 as we had
and we're going to find a way of
encoding this circular structure by
what's called a one co-chain. So if we
assign a real number value to each of
these edges here, we can assign a real
number value in a way that gives us u
just a function from the set of edges of
this structure. So we're looking here at
the collection of points and
edges coming from the intersections of
these little balls. And we want to
define a function from the set of edges
here to the real numbers. And so this is
actually this set of functions from ed
from the a set of functions from the set
of edges to the real numbers actually is
itself a real vector space. And we can
make a specific choice of an element
there that encodes this circular
structure. There actually infinitely
many equivalent ways of choosing this
encoding and in the end we'll find I
will provide you with a way of making a
specific good choice of a way of
encoding this structure by a particular
choice of a function from the edges to
the real
numbers and so this vector space here we
call the vector space of one co-chains
that's just the mathematical language we
use on this set of edges you have there.
So this is the a standard way of
encoding this kind of circular structure
that shows
up. And so now if we go back to our
persistent diagram where recall that we
looked at the the actual persistence we
look at the difference between the death
and the birth and we've ordered them
from largest to smallest.
Then what we can do is associate to a
sequence like that of
persistences of p a certain score where
we take this first persistence this
longest one and we subtract from it the
sum of the other persistences where we
divide the p1 by two p2 by four and so
on because somehow the shorter the
persistence the less significant it
should be somehow saying how important
is this feature that's picked up by this
zeroth persistence compared to the other
ones and that's what we'll call the ring
score where here we've chosen this n
just so that the values of this score
are always be um bounded between zero
and one and the idea being that the
greater this score is the more
significant the circular feature that's
detected by p 0 is and one nice thing
about defining it this way is that this
ring score is scale invariant so if you
have your collection of points and you
you know sort of you apply um a scale
change of scale so that everything gets
expanded like this the significance of
your fixed feature is not going to
change. You could also choose instead of
looking at death minus birth, you could
take DI divided by BI. That's another
looking at the what's called persistent
ratio is another interesting thing to
look at. But here we'll consider just
these differences
here. So using these ring scores can
tell us how significant the circular
feature that we've detected
is. So how are we going to determine its
statistical significance? So let's go
back to the case that we're really
interested in which has to do with
expression data for uh for different
genes. So suppose we've decided we're
going to focus on m genes and we have
some point cloud of expression data in
this m dimensional space for which we've
computed uh this persistent chromology.
We've detected a circular feature. We've
computed its ring score. You say okay
the ring score seems big but is it
really statistically
significant? And so what you can do is a
permutation test to come up with an
empirical p value to tell you how
significant this feature actually is. So
what we did was to we have this huge set
of 20,000 genes. We can take 2 to the 10
possible sets of m genes and do the same
analysis on these randomly chosen sets
of genes which then gives you a null
distribution of ring scores. Because it
could be that if you just make a random
choice of genes, you're also going to be
finding these circular structures. But
how sign, you know, so this will give
you a way of deciding when I've made
this specific choice of genes using my
hallmark gene set and whatever, am I
really getting something
significant? So then you can calculate
once you have your null distribution, an
empirical p value for your original ring
score and decide, okay, is this
significant or not?
So that's what we do in order to detect
the circular structure and be able to
say something about how significant it
is. So there we're looking in this space
where for each cell corres to each cell
we have a point in this space the
coordinates of which correspond to
genes.
Now what we want to think about is okay
once we've detected this structure what
actually is the process what cascade of
genes is leading to this circular
cyclical
process. So remember that when we have
one of these statistically significant
circular features that it's going to be
encoded by one of these one code chains
one of these fun fun functions from the
edges of the complex to the real
numbers. So what we want to do now is to
be able to assign phases to each of the
individual cells. Once we've made a
choice of what's called a harmonic
circular coordinate and that's going to
explain to you how we once we've made a
choice of this encoding alpha, we're
going to make a good choice so in some
sense a canonical good choice of a
circular
coordinate. And then once we've done
that, we're going to be able to now look
at the gene expression and figure out
which gene is weeding leading which gene
in the process and what the phase
differences between them and the
amplitude and so on. And for that we're
going to need more geometry. But to do
either one of these stages we need to
introduce some
geometry. So what is the story of
harmonic representatives? So just to
mention that the original work on such
things went back to work of Dilva Pike
and Park and Perea. So what we've what
I'm describing here is a way of sort of
integrating and amplifying a bit the
work that they did. So recall that we
had at some particular threshold in this
process in our case it was 0.9 we had
this statistically significant circular
feature that appears. So we're there
right and so R is this critical
threshold at which this structure
appears. All right. So now what I'm
going to do to introduce geometry is to
introduce inner products because once we
have inner products I can talk about
angles. I can talk about distances. I
can talk about norms and things like
that. So what I can do is then choose
inner products on the spaces of
functions from the set of nodes to the
real numbers and on the set of edges to
the real numbers. So these are these one
code chains we already talked about and
these other ones are called zero code
chains. And there's a way of cleverly
choosing this inner product that
corrects for the fact that this cloud of
points has non-uniform density because
if your density of the of the cloud is
very unequal, then if you're a little
bit uh naive about how you choose your
inner product, you're not going to
you're it's not really taking into
account the geometry the natural
geometry of your space of points. So
there's a there's a um a way to do this
that takes this point cloud density into
account.
And then now you can define inner
products on these real vector spaces.
And once you have these inner products
we're in the world of
geometry. So once you have inner
products then there's a way of computing
a discrete lelassian on these vector
spaces. And when you have a discrete
lelassian then you can start taking
harmonics which are which are kernels of
the lelassian. So you can find a
unique representative in here a unique
one coycle. So map from the edges of
this uh collection of points and edges
to the real numbers that really is going
to encode your circular structure and
that you can extend in a certain way to
a map to the circle and there and um the
way to think about this is it really has
some map to the circle that is the
smoothest gradient with respect to it to
the inner products you've chosen. So I'm
not going to go into details about how
you do this, but just to say it is
possible to choose a circular coordinate
like
this. And then what you want to do once
you have that you can determine the
phases of the nodes of this complex VR
which correspond to your cells and show
you where in the circular process each
one of these cells actually was when the
single cell uh assay was
done. All right. So how does this work?
So we're now we're back in this here's
our critical threshold 0.9 where we had
this circular structure that appeared
and so now we've chosen we have our
circular coordinate this map theta h so
it's corresponding to our choice of
harmonic representative gives us a map
from here to here and this idea of
determining the phase of the cells is
using this map here so that we can now
use this to assign phases to the points
via this coordinate so if I have a blue
coordinate here I look at which points
were over that green there and so on. So
it's a way of assigning phases to the
points in the point cloud. Quite
straightforward once you have this theta
H. But we can do more. That's just, you
know, still in the world of what's going
on with the cells. We want to say what's
going on with the genes. How can we
figure out which gene is leading which
gene to figure out the gene
cascades. But before I do that, just
would mention what going on. the
difference between theta h and alpha h.
So theta h was giving us a way of
assigning a circular coordinate to the
different points. So here we're in the
space where each one of these is a cell
in the space where the coordinates are
actually genes. And then if you think
about what alpha h is doing, alpha h
assigns a real number to every edge in
this vr, right? And when you're
assigning a real number to an edge, you
can think of that like a vector field.
it's assigning a weight to uh a path in
some sense. So we have on the one hand a
coordinate on the other hand you're also
picking up this one-dimensional
structure and that's what's interesting.
You've got both the zero and the
onedimensional structure
here.
Okay, but on to figuring out which gene
needs which gene. So there's something
called lead lag analysis which was uh
for which we're basing this on the work
of Bishna Cafodal. Maybe they were the
first ones to do it. So the idea is
suppose that we have here in this toy
example we have two functions the blue
function and the orange function. The
blue function is sort of lagging behind
the orange one which is leading it. So
they're it's the same function but
they're just shifted from each other.
And if you plot uh for every x the if
you plot the pairs of coordinates sorry
as you go around it it translates into a
curve like this in the plane. So you can
go back and forth between these two
representations of the same information.
And so you're getting a closed curve
from these two curves that are following
each other. So you can think about this
as giving you some this pair of curves
here is giving you some function from
the circle S1 into in this case
R2. And under nice conditions which is
usually what's going to happen in the in
with real data you can actually extend
it over the entire disc. So you think of
the disk the boundary of which is a
circle. Then usually there's a way of
extending this over the entire
disc. Now what you how can you use this
interpretation in order to figure out
you know from this curve here for
example which of these curves was
leading the other that the orange one
was leading the blue one. How can we
detect
that? So here is our situation. we have
some map from a circle into Rn n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n equals 2
in this case extended over the disk. So
now we're going to look at this sort of
angular momentum vector field in the
plane determined by x i and
xj. And we think about our curve as
being embedded with respect to this
vector field. And if you think of the
integral around the boundary of the disk
which according to Stokes theorem is
just all you can also express in terms
of the integral over the whole disc then
it turns out that this signed
area of the the region in the plane that
is bounded by this curve actually
measures the extent to which gamma I is
leading gamma j. So I'm not going to go
into the mathematical explanation but
just to say that this computation is
helpful for finding out basically if
it's positive then I is leading J. If
it's negative J is leading I. Okay. So
you can use this basic idea. So this is
just about you know closed curves in the
plane. But now let's think about how we
can apply this
biologically. So now let's think about
again a periodic curve. So it's a a map
from S1 into Rn. And suppose that each
coordinate of this uh function so gamma
j is the j coordinate can be written as
a product of some aj times there's a
fixed periodic function from s1 into the
real
numbers that is just if I take some
complex value s zed on the circle and I
want to calculate gamma j of zed I have
some amplitude that's changing and I
have some phase shift that's coming from
bg but otherwise the the function is the
same the it's just the amplitude and the
phase shift that are varying. So that's
what what you would call a chain of
offsets in this case and often when
people think about a simple model or so
a naive model of gene cascades you can
think about it as being this kind of
chain of
offsets. Now usually a function like kai
will have some sort of forier expansion
that has many terms. If it has just one
term, it's just a real part of some of
this of a first forier mode. Then it
turns out that this um if you take if
you calculate this lead lag that we had
before, it's actually proportional to
the sign of the difference between the
phase
shifts. And so this whole if we take the
whole matrix of these lead lag, what
it's encoding is precisely these phase
offsets of the coordinates. So that's
the interest of calculating this this
matrix. It's going to give you what the
how these phase shifts are working with
respect to each
other.
Okay. So now we want to apply this in
the case of our V at our critical
threshold R 0.9 in our case. So now we
suppose we have our harmonic
representative our unique harmonic
representative of this circular
structure. So it's one of these uh one
code
chains and what we can do is we're going
to choose if you're thinking about this
this complex given by these points and
edges it can be really complex but one
thing we know as mathematicians is that
for a large enough n you can find a way
of taking this thing and embedding it
really embedding it not in the computer
science sense but the real sense that
we're it's only it's injective we can
embi Okay, embed this a finally in Rn
for large enough of
N. And then we're going to define a
function for every pair of numbers I and
J less than equal to N from the edges of
our VR, right, to the real numbers
that's defined as follows. It's it's a
basically an integral. So it's going to
send an edge of this complex VR to the
integral of this particular uh one form
we were looking at before this angular
velocity type one form that you see
again up here along the path in Rn
determined by the embedding of the edge.
So if I have an
edge in the in here and I look at this
embedding, it's going to embed it as
some path in Rn and I can integrate this
angular momentum form along that path
and I get a real number. So I have this
way of associating to every edge a real
number and that's exactly a one
co-chain, right? So it's given me a one
code chain in this way and I'm
using process. So I haven't yet used
alpha H. All I've used is this embedding
so far. How does alpha H come into the
story? All right. So I have my alpha H.
I have my FI embedding. And now I can
define a sort of a generalized lead lag
matrix as follows. I'm going to say the
J coordinate is given by taking the
inner product of alpha H and this one
co-chain because remember I defined an
inner product on the one co-chain. So on
this vector space of maps from the edges
into the real numbers and so here I have
a one code chain which is alpha h here I
have this one code chain that I just
defined by taking the integral along
these paths and so I it makes sense to
calculate this inner product and I get a
real number and this real number is
again telling me something about who is
leading whom. So if I what it's if I
think about what this is computing here
this is computing for every inj it's
computing the area of the parallelogram
that's determined by the so if I have an
edge from a vertex to a vertex and it's
mapped by this aphine embedding into Rn
each endpoint of the edge is mapped to a
to a vector in Rn if I look at the
parallelogram that's determined by those
two vectors what this computes is the
area of that parallelogram and So this
here is computing some sort of uh linear
combination of these uh signed areas of
parallelograms weighted by alpha h which
t taking the density into account as
well. So it's some sort of very
sophisticated version of what we saw
with the two dimensional
thing. Now this matrix here is sku
symmetric which means that we have
lovely ways of analyzing it finding its
complex values. the igen vectors and so
on and you can look for the largest igen
value at or the ones that have largest
real value. you can find the sort of
principal igon vectors and if you look
at the plane determined by the principal
igen vectors of this matrix that's going
to give you uh a nice plane and looking
at projections onto that plane can
actually give you a way of inferring the
ordering and the amplitude of the
different genes. So that's a whole
there's a bit more math to do in that
case but the basic idea is that we have
this really lovely sku symmetric matrix
which we can analyze by standard methods
from linear algebra and come up with
um appropriate vectors onto which we can
project and determine interesting
information about our
genes. Okay, so here's the basic idea.
We're looking at these lead lag uh
profiles for different pairs of genes.
It gives us our lead lag matrix like
this and from that we can determine the
principal lead lag plane like this onto
which we can project and then determine
from that what the components of the
different genes are along this path and
it tells us how we can order them as we
go around our cyclic process.
Okay, so that's the that's the basic
idea. So that's the math. Now it seems
like uh we've made a lot of assumptions
along the way assuming that we can use
this sort of lead lag analysis. And in
particular when I was saying we look we
can pick up the the the phase
differences and so on. I was making this
assumption that the dominant fora mode
by far was the first. Real life is of
course much more complex. Does this
actually work when you apply it to real
data? That's what we'll see next. So, a
bit of
validation. Okay.
So, first we're going to look at some
synthetic data, right? That's what one
always does
first. So, what kind of synthetic data
are we going to use? Well, we're going
to look at a linear OD model of genes
transcription and translation.
And in particular, so I'll just click
through here, we have a couple pair of
ODs where we're looking at the vectors
of mRNA and protein levels for different
genes. We have an interaction matrix
that's describing the effect of the
protein of the linear effect of the
protein on an RNA production etc. So the
typical sort of OD model that one would
have for thinking about gene
transcription. And then what we do is we
make a choice of this interaction matrix
that's going to force the existence of
cyclic structure. Okay. So we know it's
got to be there and we say can we detect
it? Can we detect it properly? Are we
going to get the right ordering of the
genes and so
on. Also in order to make it as a little
more realistic we're going to use the
negative binomial sampling that was
proposed last year in nature methods. So
it looks more like really noisy single
cell data. Okay. So it's not just going
to actually lie beautifully on a circle.
Okay. All right. So we do this. We did
it for a couple different examples. We
look at one example of synthetic data
where this was really the true the
underlying interaction matrix between
the different genes in terms of the
strength of their interactions. And then
this was the lead lag matrix that we
deduced from the methods that I was just
describing to you. So it matches quite
nicely. Okay. And then what about you
know having the circular enrichment of
the gene set that we're talking about.
So by choosing PCA components
appropriately we ended up with very nice
ring scores that were detecting actual
circular structures like this. Okay. In
the case where we're looking here at PC1
PC2. All right. And now if we do the
simplicity analysis with respect to the
genes now. So this is looking at here
they're plotting the lead lag matrix PCA
with its real value and its imaginary
value and we see a nice circular
structure coming up which then we can
translate into the individual genes and
see how they're plotted their what their
particular phases are and their
particular
amplitudes doing this kind of analysis
that I was talking about
before. That's just what it looks like.
And say, okay, does it work? Are we
picking up what we would expect to from
the synthetic data? And so here we're
plotting the gene index, which is really
the order of gene activation according
to the synthetic model against the phase
as detected by our method. And we see it
matches quite nicely correlation
coefficient
986. And then we say, okay, well, what
about the relation between the the
strength of the ground interactions and
the lead lag that we detected? Not too
bad. 642 the correlation coefficient. So
pretty happy with how well we could
extract the the ground truth using this
method. Another example with another
interaction matrix, the corresponding
lead lag matrix that we deduced by our
method from this. And also here we see
here the correlation between the ground
truth of the interaction and the lead
lag was actually excellent in this
case. And they could do again this
cylicity analysis. Again we're looking
at the the genes now where we're looking
at the lead lag matrix with its real PCA
and imaginary PCA here and seeing again
the distribution of amplitudes and
phases of the different genes. And it
corresponds very well
to synthetic model. Again here we're
looking or plotting the gene index which
is saying the order in which the genes
are actually activated in this synthetic
data corres and then the corresponding
phase which is computed from the gene
expression data and we say again it
aligns very very nicely with a
coefficient of
0.998. And then we look at here we also
had a qu there is a time element when
you're looking at the these ODEs we
actually have ground truth time and
compare the ground truth time against
the estimated circular coordinate and
since it's being plotted like this you
really see the circle here coming around
and coming around like this so that the
circular structure maps very well with
the time component of this linear OD
model.
Okay, so that was nice validation with
synthetic data. The other validation we
did was with actual cell cycle data
which is something that's extremely well
understood. And so the data that we took
was from from cycling human dermal
fiberblasts from a paper by
Capalupo. And the data set that we used
was known markers of certain families of
genes which are activated in the in the
cell cycle.
And so when we look at this, so here
we're again we're looking at the the
gene the cichlicity of the genes. So
here saying something about the the
counts of the different cells as you go
around. And what you see here the the
color scheme here is telling you about
the activation of the genes. And you see
that in this upper part of the cycle you
have the S genes that are being
activated. In the lower part you see the
G2M. So this is for the biologist
straightforward that this is the way it
should be and it is indeed exactly what
shows up when we apply this uh lead lag
analysis to the um to the actual data
from Capalupo's
paper and again you can plot the where
exactly the phase and the amplitude of
these different genes are the S and the
G2M here and the lead matrix which
corresponds very well to what you see in
real life with S activating G2M and so
on. So it when we do this comparison
with actual cell cycle data, you see
that it it it you see what you would
expect to see. So we didn't learn
anything from this except that we seem
to be picking things up
properly. And another thing that can be
interesting to look at is here there are
five different sample genes that we've
considered and the color scheme again is
saying where are things being activated.
Here we have the phase moving in this
direction and you for those who know uh
what these different genes mean and when
you would expect to see them activated
you can sort of see their activation
moving around this cycle
appropriately. Okay. So the and this so
the the reason I'm showing this is
because it's just to to illustrate the
fact that this method enables you to say
okay for a particular gene when is it
actually being
uh when is it actually being activated
where do I see what is it its phase and
so
on
okay
so where things really get interesting
is not when you're just doing validation
and making sure the model actually is
you know working appropriately but it's
when it can tell you something new. And
that's what I'd like to tell you now is
some new things. In fact, some of it is
so new that um I modified my slides
after a conversation with Kelly this
morning. So, there's some stuff that he
finished up over the weekend. So,
experiments, right? So, what I'm going
to think about is a case where we're
silencing the androgen receptors using
viruses. And the first thing we wanted
to do was to say, okay, well, at least
in the control case, because we're going
to do silencing on the one hand, then
we're going to have a control case on
the other. I'd like to see that at least
in the control case that the the cell
cycle data looks like that of capalupo
because the the we're looking at
different batches from different labs,
different pre-processing, different
everything, but there's both a cell
cycle. Do we see the same kind of
results? That's the first thing. And the
second thing is okay, what is the
impact of androgen receptor silencing on
gene expression? This is the sort of
question you like you want to go and you
perturb something you say what breaks
what doesn't break and to what extent
and can we actually measure this and see
this using these kinds of
methods so the data we had was single
cell RNA data seek again from human
dermal fibroblasts and we're using two
different lentiviruses they were to uh
express AR silencing and also a
control and then we're looking at two
different hallmark gene sets or maybe
even three. Uh one was from Velocycle
and the other was uh something called
SASP that has to do with
scinessence. Okay. So what did we
discover in this case? First of all, we
looked at a comparison between just the
cell cycle and here we were looking at
uh actually both the control and the uh
AR silence genes cells. And what you see
is that when you compute the phases of
the genes and their amplitudes, they
correspond beautifully between the two
different data sets. So one from the
Capalupa paper I was talking about
before and then this new set done in the
lab of of Talo Doto. So a very nice
correspondence there shows that this
sort of topological or the geometric
computation we've been doing actually is
something that's stable across data sets
pre-processing and so
on.
Okay. Right. So essentially identical
phases and
amplitudes despite the different
experimental
protocols. Okay. Now what about the
existence of cyclic structures? So in
the case here we're looking at this SASP
gene set. We do the persistence diagram.
We see a point that is far from the
diagonal. How significant is it? So it
corresponds to uh do this permutation
test. So its ring score is somewhere out
here which is very very far from the
rest of the distribution. So this would
be your null distribution. And you have
a very nice p value. Say okay looks like
I have uh a significant
feature. And then you can say okay now I
look at the gene clicity analysis. So
here I would have the two different
conditions the orange being the control
condition the blue being the silenced
condition. And what you see is that you
get you know roughly a circular
structure. It isn't as pretty as in the
synthetic data of course but you do see
basically a secular circular structure.
And this is uh showing you for a couple
of specific genes when they are actually
activated.
And what but one thing that is
interesting so so far we haven't seen
much of a difference between the genes
the the AR silence case and the control
case is that here there's a way of
measuring what's called the AR silencing
score. So this is a looking at the
expression of the 200 most um highly
expressed genes in the case of AR
silencing and you see that there's a
point in this cell cycle. So this is
looking at sort of a three-dimensional
version of what we were look had on the
previous slide where we have the the
lead lag PCA real and imaginary here and
then we're looking at this AR silencing
score and you see there's a very
specific point in the cell cycle where
all of a sudden these genes are really
expressed and so one thought is are we
moving into some sort of scinessence at
this point that you're sort of moving
out of the cell cycle when you reach
this point is that what we're seeing as
a phenomenon here so that's one
hypothesis about what how to interpret
this image that you have this moving
away from the the cell cycle here. And
we'll see that this is confirmed in a
certain
sense. So what we'd like to see is how
stressed the cells are when they're in
this AR silenced mode. So what we're
looking at here are the looking at the
entire data set, both controls and the
uh androgen silenced androgen receptor
silenced ones. And we're looking at the
most highly variable genes and then
projecting onto PC0
PC1. And what we see is that here we
have again orange is the control and
blue is the AR silence that there are
certain gene that are much much more
highly expressed in the blue than in the
red. And we see examples here that we
have these four genes, three genes,
sorry, that are particularly highly
expressed these coming from this light
color here in the cells that are AR
silenced. So there's something very
special going on with these genes in
these androgen silenced uh cases.
So if we look at that and say okay let's
look at what's really going on with
those genes and we take the we look at
the some measure of the stress is being
how highly expressed these particular
genes are in these AR silence genes and
we have the following picture. So what
we what this is showing us here on the
one hand we're looking at the cell cycle
coordinates. So the cell cycle is moving
along here from left to right. And on
the on the y- axis here, I'm looking at
the the uh extent of this stress that's
coming from the AR
silencing. And so we have the different
phases that are measured here.
Everything that's in blue is the G1,
orange is this G2M, and green is this
S. And so there, that's just showing me
where I am in the phase. But if we look
now again at this division between the
orange being the AR silenced ones and
the blue being the control, we see that
for the orange ones, there's a kind of a
threshold. When the AR silencing stress
goes too high, they just don't enter the
cell cycle.
There are some that can enter the cell
cycle that are more resilient where they
have a stress level that's lower, but
those that are above this threshold some
somehow get
stuck. And so what we have is that the
cells that are expressing high levels of
this sort of androgen receptor stress
don't enter the cell cycle, but those
that are lower seem to be able to. So
there's some sort of degree of
resilience to what's going It's a sort
of a a phenotype that we're seeing
expressed here in terms of how resilient
they are to this andigen receptor
stress. And then you can see that if you
think about the ones that are the sort
of AR resilient, the ones that do manage
to enter the cell cycle, then they
actually have a behave identically
essentially to the non-signed cells in
the cell cycle because you have
practically perfect correspondence
between the gene phases and the gene
amplitudes in these two cases. So there
seem to be these really two different
phenotypes for these her human dermal
fibroblasts. There are those that when
faced with this androgen silencing,
they're just blocked. They're stressed
too much. And there are others that
manage to get over it and continue in
the cell
cycle. One observation is that the ones
that uh do seem to get blocked seem to
be ones that are maybe becoming more
similar to epithelial cells. And we'll
see why this may be relevant in just a
moment.
So specifically now we're going to think
about another case in which we have
androgen receptors uh silencing well
androgen silencing because we're going
to think about a case where we actually
going to castrate some poor
mice and uh so all of a sudden there's
no more androgen and see what happens.
This is very different from using
lentiviruses to silence androgen
receptors, but we're going to the the
results the same. So, we're looking at
is data from a study of prosthetic
epithelial cell regeneration from uh
cart house in 2020 and we looked at 50
different hallmark gene sets. So, the
process is this. you castrate the mice
and then the the prostate involves and
by 28 days there's reduced I think 90%
or something like that. Then you add t
testes back and it regenerates and at
the end of 28 days is practically back
to normal and then then what the what
the researchers did was to take samples
at different times throughout this cycle
to see what was happening with the
cells. So you really have this time
element which is very explicit
there. And so when you compare that to
gene sets having to do with androgen
response or even having to do with
cholesterol homoasis or even others, you
do get significant circular
structure and you even get you know
quite nice p values even for myiogenesis
which has to do with muscle
rehabilitation. So we get significant
circular structure with respect to
multiple hallmark gene
sets. And so you get the same kind of
cyclic structure showing up in both for
both the andigen receptor and the
cholesterol homeostasis gene sets. And
you can see the here the time points. So
the different colors here correspond to
different days in this process all the
way from intact to the last day of
castration which is the purple and then
back to full halfway through the
regeneration. So we have these nice
circular
structures. We can measure again the
gene phase and amplitude. This gene for
example is one that's highly known to be
related to prostate for
example. And then you see a similar kind
of thresholding effect coming in. So if
you look at this plot where we're
plotting cell cycle versus tissue
regeneration process in ter as two
processes that can be ongoing in the
cell. You see that in the case of the
intact ones, some of them are here and
some of them are here. And you go along
and you when you get to the 28th day of
castration, just before they get more
testosterone, again, let's see right
there. You see that they're all
concentrated here. They get blocked.
They can't enter the cell cycle. We're
seeing the same kind of phenomenon here
with uh inability to enter the cell
cycle. And there are very very few that
actually do enter the cell cycle. So
there seems to be something about
epithelial cells that makes it more
difficult for them to uh or maybe it has
something else to do with the
experimental protocol I don't know but
in any case in this case they don't seem
to be able to enter the cell cycle when
there don't have androgen.
So conclusions from this first of all
using topology and geometry we can
detect significant these these
significant circular structures which
then enables us to determine phases of
our individual cells and then we can
infer these processes underlying the
circular
structures. Some advantages well the
first one is not going to be kind of is
will be kind of controversial here. We
actually don't use any machine learning
techniques, but maybe this the kind of
output we're producing could be useful
as input to different machine learning
techniques. We've demonstrated that it's
applicable over a wide range of
experimental settings, different kinds
of samples, different kinds of pro uh
pre-processing, multiple gene sets and
so on. And we're getting robust across
gene sets across so on zero and
onedimensional information. One
dimensional information being
information about processes. The zero
dimensional information being more about
expression of individual cells or and so
on. Limitations because there are always
limitations. there are hyperparameter
choices that have to be made when we do
the pre-processing for
example which genes to study and the
impact of outliers. So this is something
that's still a serious problem can be a
serious problem when one is applying
tools from topological data analysis
although there are ways around this as
well. Interesting future directions we'd
like to
consider. RNA velocity of course is
something that people study a lot in the
context of single cell data. We have
preliminary data showing if you look at
the spliced versus unsplaced for RNA
then you you do see the sort of
directionality you would expect from RNA
velocity. I'd like to integrate the two
together. I think that could be very
powerful.
One thing that's interest would be
interesting to study is really get more
deeply into concurrent biological
processes because one thing we see we've
already seen for example when looking at
um comparing the
uh androgen receptor cycle together with
a cholesterol homeostasis cycle. You see
these sort of things being they're wound
together in some sort of interesting
complex way. And also how does this uh
how do you
uh integrate together these sort of
cyclic processes with more linear
processes that are happening at the same
time and more experimental data
definitely want to go there. So with
that I thank you very much for your
attention and be very happy to answer
any of your
[Applause]
questions. you very very much for a
wonderful talk. Okay, questions. So
maybe could you just go to the
microphone and I will come here.
Thanks.
Thank you so much. That was a great
talk. Um I had two questions about the
lead lag analysis. The first is does it
assume that the genes have very similar
distributions? What if like the leading
gene is expressed very differently than
the lagging gene I guess? And then the
second question is could you use it in a
naive way where you don't previously
define a gene set and you just kind of
ask over the whole data set which genes
might be leading
others. So those are both really good
questions. I think that yes implicitly
for the time being we're assuming the
distributions are very similar. Clearly
I mean this is a so far it's I would say
fairly naive and it'd be really nice to
to make it uh a more careful analysis. I
think it'd be a very good idea. That's a
really good question.
And um as far as I know, we haven't
thought about what happens if you don't
have any prior knowledge of what genes
are there. But I think it could
be could be interesting to to see
whether whether there's a way of going
about it in sort of um I mean this would
appeal actually to a topologist not to
have to choose coordinates, right? To be
able to pick out the sort of structures
without having predetermined the
coordinates. That's a really interesting
idea. Thanks.
Hey. Um, yeah, thanks for the great
talk. Thank you. Uh, so yeah, persistent
homology is like a great technique for
detecting circular structure. Uh, but
when I've when the few times I've looked
at like single cell RNA seek data for
like developmental trajectories,
then rather than having a circular
structure like you would have for like
cell cycle or like menstrual cycle like
you mentioned in the beginning, you end
up with like a kind of like branching
structure. So from a topological
perspective, that's a point, right? But
it seems like there's kind of similar
methods that should be helpful for like
still kind of like uncovering that
branching structure. So I'm wondering if
you have any thoughts on that. No,
that's a really good question and I
agree that uh and then this is one thing
that uh that Kelly is giving a lot of
thought to like what can you do to
integrate more linear structures with
cyclic structures and I think that one
thing I mean clearly the what I was
thinking about the lead lag analysis
that doesn't require us actually to have
an underlying circular structure. So I
think one should be able to take that
part of the story because you no longer
no longer worried about you know
detecting uh circular structure and then
be able to say something about in within
a developmental process which gene is
leading which other gene. I think that
should be possible to extend to that
class. Cool. Thank you. You're welcome.
This is maybe a slightly different
version of the first question but
hopefully it's different enough. uh I
have you know in a previous life done
some work on like nonlinear coupled
oscillators and things like this and so
this last story here where you're
looking at the cell cycle and then also
this regeneration cycle it seemed like
so uh at the outset of each one you
subset down to genes that you think were
important um but if you were to let's
say take the union of this these gene
sets and presumably you would would do
you believe that you would find you know
a a a second order loop for example. And
my question really is um when you have
what you have here is a highly nonlinear
relationship between the cell cycle and
the regeneration cycle or one is
actually gating the other. Yeah. Um and
you have genes that are probably going
to be in common between the two of them.
And I'm wondering if you have any
thoughts on how you think the um the
phase estimation would go if you had
these if you had sort of two linked
cycles that have a nonlinear
relationship rather than the linear
relationship which you had when you were
doing your validation which is easy
because they you it's linear and it's
all sort of sorts itself out.
Absolutely. Absolutely. So I think that
I think there's potential to work these
things out. I think the math is not
going to be
easy but I think that it's worth doing.
I think that uh I mean even you know
moving beyond okay thinking about all
right the the first fury your face is
dominant and being able to ignore ignore
the rest I think that's a little bit too
naive and and being able to say you know
slowly slowly build in more of these
complexities now I and this is something
that that Kelly and I definitely agree
on that the really important thing
what's going to be really interesting
and this is a long-term project is to
think about inter interwoven phasing
interwoven processes and uh
understanding really how one impacts the
other in terms of uh phase estimations
and so on. It's not going to be trivial.
It's going to be really interesting but
it's not going to be trivial but it's a
because it's a really good
question and I don't know the answer
yet.
Thanks as well for a great talk. Um, so
you had some really nice visualizations
and so I have them in my mind. And so my
question is if you're I guess you're in
5D, I can't do that, but let's say 3D.
Um, if I had 3D data that's going along
like a corkcrew on a tube, uh, what
would your method say about that? And
then if that instead kind of collapsed
kind of like a like into a cone and they
went to a point, what would your what
would your methods would would they find
cycles sometimes? What would we see? So
I think that if it would actually you
know go down to a point probably we
wouldn't get a significant cyclic
structure. Um but because it really you
know you it's an interesting question.
Um yeah because I yeah because the
topology would would sort of start
seeing this as a point but I think that
if it's a corkcrew that doesn't actually
converge to a point I think then you
would definitely pick up a cyclic
structure right because you're looking
for this S1 parameterization so as long
as you have that and I guess is that
like an average across the depth of the
hole and so whatever Yeah I think that
would that's that's a good question I'd
have to think I'd have to think more
about that but I would I would think so.
Yeah. Can I ask another question? Sure.
Okay. So, you you simulated uh in the
your first example, you had a simulated
like uh OD and then you tried to recover
some structure about it. Um have you
thought about a lot of times I I
wouldn't be surprised if that OD's
parameters are pretty hard to recover
from the data you generate. There there
are ways to do it, but I wouldn't be
surprised if it's hard. Yeah. Um, I'm
curious a if you've tried that, but also
b after you do this analysis, do you
think it tells you what kinds of
generating dynamical systems or what
kinds of properties those things have?
In other words, like if we're trying to
do system ID, we'd love to have a
generating model that looks like
physics. Um, could these kinds of
approaches tell us which models we
should be designing and things like that
or properties of them?
So um to to the second question I think
that there's potential there for sure I
think that could be really helpful
provide an interesting perspective maybe
not everything but it could provide some
interesting information and then
recovering all the parameters I don't
know because I mean at least it seems we
can recover as I said the amplitudes and
the phase shifts uh recover everything
I'm not sure but uh at least that part
of the story
what is known about how PCA interacts
with persistent coology because at the
beginning you're going down to I mean
okay one is gene set analysis and then
but then you're doing PCA so how robust
is this? So that's a that's an excellent
question. I don't know the answer. Um so
I think that uh for the time being in
terms of robustness we've uh you know
seeing actually the sort of same cyclic
structure showing up in different data
sets seems to indicate that okay what
we're doing is not
unreasonable. Now as a mathematician I
would love to have a proof that it
actually is not unreasonable. I don't
know maybe somebody like uh like Jose
Pereah might know the the extent to
which this is stable under doing these
sort of PCA projections. I don't
um but uh real life experience seems to
show that it's not a bad
idea. I've learned something about being
an engineer since I started doing this.
Okay, other
questions. Oh, great. So, thank you so
much again for
[Applause]