um I want to wrap up a tiny bit of um
problem set seven but before we do I'm
going want us to jump ahead to the
second part where I say algorithmic
composition for a Markoff data set if
you could get your um uh what do you
call it your Jupiter notebooks going and
now uh we're getting to the point in the
semester where I'm just going to say you
can import everything from music 21 but
I will give you a few restrictions from
time to time so I don't really care what
that you're doing and um in the past
I've tried to have everyone download a
pre-prepared um set and it's always had
problems so we're just going to uh do
something that takes about three or four
minutes of your processor time um and
get that started now so this will
probably take a second or two you're
learning a new T term ter Corpus search
jig I can't remember if it's um if it's
important if this is capital or not but
uh that's I put on and this will go
through the music so music 21 comes with
about I can't remember what the number
is something 14,000 pieces um when you
do it just so you can do it and this
will get everything that calls itself
jig I don't know if there's any word
that begins with jig that um that is not
a jig but you know uh this might be
garbage in garbage out I'm getting 327
depending on what version you're on you
might be slightly higher slightly lower
won't influence that too much great so
um give me a quick actually the the
easiest thing I can tell is yeah up or a
snap of a finger when you when you've
got it and then I can kind of hear okay
okay good all of our computers are
slightly different speeds but I think
you can also start typing the next uh
Expressions while you're doing it so
jigs is something called a metadata
bundle that means it's a collection of
everything whose metadata whose titles
author something match a particular
search term uh you can look through you
can find things by Key by um by starting
uh meter and things like that but often
searching by title or composer it's one
of the first things and um what you can
do is if we look at this so as a very
short introduction to this uh jigs is a
whole 327 things we can look at the
first one with jigs zero and we can get
that it comes from some particular piece
song 47 in uh collection of Irish Tunes
called ards airs book one um so it's not
a piece in order to get that we can say
uh I'm going to go J1 I'm going to
equals jigs one because jigs zero had uh
some funny things on it and J jigs one.
parse calling it as a method and that
will actually load it cuz otherwise
loading 327 pieces would take a little
too long and then I can do show
hopefully a Spanish jig everyone get a
Spanish jig on
theirs okay good so what we're going to
do is we're GNA just get every jig that
is in G major so I I'm going to call it
because I I have my um uh verbose
variable names I'm GNA call it jigs in G
with underscores you might just call it
JG whatever you want um and I'll just
say
for we'll say J
meta in jigs so I remember this is thing
I'll say J sorry I'll go slower I'll
make this bigger right slower and bigger
always
important I have a whole big screen if
I'm not using it
okay that a little B better so I'll I'll
parse each one the
metadata so we'll say J is that one
parsed and now uh I'll do just kidding
JK for jigs key equals
J analyze the
key and here just for now so we can all
get caught up I'm going to print them
all
okay just letting
everybody okay and then I'm going to be
grabbing in a second every piece that is
in um that is in G
major why because looks like there's a
lot of jigs in G major so seems like a
good thing to grab
do we
feel let's we'll just keep snapping when
when you're when you're caught
up okay okay good good we we'll
eventually synchronize on a rhythm uh
for the things okay good now I'll say is
uh tonic name I'll just be verbose again
I keep jumping back and forth is that
keys do tonic which returns a pitch
object and a pitch object has
aame and what we'll do is we'll get all
the ones in G major or in G minor but no
actually maybe we should maybe we should
do uh no we'll just do all them if tonic
name equals g I don't think there's a
lot in G minor um jigs in g.
append
J and and that's where we're going to
put this aside for a bit but um you can
do the snap when you're done because
this will take a little long a while to
do and then I'll move on to the next
thing but so don't don't snap when it's
done snap when you're done uh done
programming this so that we have it for
later good
good okay now by the way mine's running
a lot faster than yours not because
mit's bought me a fancy computer but
because when you parse something once in
music 21 it stores it as a cash
somewhere um on your hard drive and so
it goes faster the second time so um if
it if you're feeling like ah I need to
upgrade my computer because it mine was
so much slower than his no it's just um
I may have you know like like they do on
the cooking shows I may have already
baked this once this morning just to
make sure it works okay good put that
aside for a little bit um I want to open
up um actually well I don't need to put
that aside too much um your problem Set
uh seven where' that go here it
is
um sorry about that
y'all a little bit more organized
great problem set seven ah here we go
seven and eight so I want to just talk
through um some of the things that
you've just been working on a couple
people um have requested and been
granted extra time for the last couple
questions so I'm not going to go through
them and uh besides we all have
different answers on the open-ended ones
right um actually actually yeah we no
we'll do this um so the major scales one
how hard do we find this particular one
easy hard little bit what was the um
what do you think a test case that I'm
going to run that uh on that um that
you're you can already tell me if yeah
you're going to do something
pathological like flat flat uh E flat
flat what's that well major yeah I'm
going to probably start with e sharp
major um or or even um yeah so certain
things like that to make sure or even a
normal thing like FSH major what am I
going to be looking for what's the
leading tone in FSH
major e sharp F natural Eble sharp uh
who goes for e
sharp F natural
Eble sharp yeah I'm going to be looking
for e sharp because a major scale um one
of the things about it is it uses every
one of the lines and
spaces once and only once regard using
some sort of sharp or
flat great
um now uh let's talk a little bit about
the second question any any questions
that you had on the roots this is um
depending on how much you chose to do
this by hand which um when we didn't
combine the two problem sets I'd like to
use this one as something do by hand
um you know it gets quite a bit harder
what's what's some of the techniques
that anybody remembers using on this
yeah convert everything to between zero
and 11 so ah convert everything to zero
and
11 for yeah no for now great and then so
so we have sort of a the pitch class
space um maybe I should so I have a
side yeah there we
go oops uh so you know zero one is this
what you're thinking of y two great uh
so that can be one part of it and then
what do you what do we do how are we
going to use this somebody else yeah go
ahead idea but also added a Cass set so
like there repeated notes so if there's
repeated notes yeah so we're going to
use the set operation
good to remove things that are in there
multiple times um what's the the yeah so
for root for the root of the chord
doesn't matter what's what octave
something's
in no so root is a kind of equivalence
class that implies octave equivalence
right great um so we're going to be
using a set we're going to be discarding
octaves no octaves um great what are
other things that you did in
this just want to spr it around yes oh
similar but I use the dionic note
numbers instead so use dionic note
numbers
instead note numbers so that you have
something like and uh I can't believe
there's a part a brain cell in my head
that uh remembers this so you had
something like 31 32 33
34 um great the number C4 as 29 is
pretty arbitrary I just like there's a
if you go to the media lab they have a
Booz and door for Imperial Grand one
that has the extra keys down here and
the lowest note on that one I assigned
to one and um just went up from there so
C4 ends up being 29 good and so we can
use that for certain parts who used
dionic note numbers or something like
that in their example in your answer to
two yep three four who used something
like pitch
classes answer good who used both
anybody my implementation ends up using
uh both of them so I'm going to say both
of these can be a right way to
work good um now what are some other
techniques that we did on
rotness yeah check for fths check for
fifths good
check
for
fifths what's the best which one of
these do you think works better for
checking for
fifths you want to take a
guess I we don't want to say either them
just cuz they're both like number based
so you could like have S like augmented
thing so like return the same difference
yeah so it has a lot to do with whether
we we care about spelling equivalents or
not right so we can always have um you
know a doubly augmented fourth sounds
the same as a perfect fifth but it
repulses me because it is a dissonance
right actually I'm not repulsed by
dissonance but uh it is and what do we
have the problem if we're only looking
at dionic note numbers give me a fifth
that's um that might actually supposed
to well change does it change the root
which fifth you
find no not really good so we check for
fifths anybody check for any other
intervals yeah I did the dumb thing in
here for 2/3 check for two 2/3 in a row
2/3 so if you have
one3 and you have
2/3 then you might have something yeah
you're right that was a very very dumb
thing to say that it was a dumb thing
because I think it's a great way of
doing it so we have if you can have 2/3
then presumably the bottom one is a root
uh where's the problem
come yeah a major child
minor okay great so minor third versus
major
third I want you to think in your head
and then tell your neighbor yes or no on
the counter three on whether does the
does a major third or minor third does
this affect the
rout one two 3 no no okay so we might so
we're not going to do that for right now
but I'm going to put this in the save
for later pile because uh Roots only one
of the things we're going to want to do
uh safe for later but no so not going to
do uh what's an issue that you might
still have but but that's going to be
important with
this so you've gotten rid of
octaves so let's say we're going to
write everything in the same octave
number for second can I blank this for a
second and um
yep
okay is that supposed to yep okay
okay you still have it over there if you
need it
um so if we're not if we're saying
everything is in octave 4 and I'm going
to rewrite that
f a c the F major Triad
f
a c right is that going to
work third
third yeah um I mean like yeah if we use
the um like pitch uh class then this
upper c will be um yeah zero which so
you won't be able to find it just so it
will be yeah where will it be if we
let's say we put everything Optive four
it'll look like it's below it it'll
below
it so what is this now
still a major still a major TR what what
would we call this by the
way first inversion second inversion
second inversion
64 numbering instead of I've I've just
switched between two different systems
that are kind of equivalences of each
other I switched from the calling this 3
three system which we use sometimes to
the calling this 53 system which we use
more often where one system where you
measure everything from the note below
and one thing where you measure
everything from the
base boy isn't this like terrible in
music that we do this um do you remember
the first time that uh that somebody
said to you something like you know oh I
was in meth major and I was on scale
degree 2 on a 57 chord and you actually
meent heard in your head I was on scale
degree 2 in a Roman numeral 5
superscript 7 thing uh somebody figure
out what part of our brain is doing this
kind of translation on the Fly that the
exact same numbers are being translated
in different ways our memory so this is
not one that we talk about very much
this particular translation but but we
do it quite a bit and I just did it
maybe too fast so yeah 64 or the other
way you can do it is say it's a third
stacked on top of a fourth right 3 + 4
in music
equals six yep yeah um okay so this is
also something we have to worry about
that was a parenthesis within a
parenthesis how do we get around this
problem yeah um I basically added 12 to
the lowest I sorted then added 12 to the
lowest not twice and check
so okay so you you sort and then if this
doesn't match 3 three then what do you
do you um I I bump the lowest note up an
octave you bump the lowest note up the
octave
great will that always be enough no so
what you have to decid do next so let's
let's sometimes you'll will have uh yeah
Adam go ahead I took the initial cord
and I duplicated it the whole cord above
so I guarantee that I will see a pattern
that will be either major
Min okay so you take whatever notes you
see now I'm going to put it in first
inversion except there are chords
besides C major Michael um so we'll put
it in first
inversion
ACF call that 63 chord and if you just
keep duplicating things up
is that right yep you will eventually at
some point have this three ah five3
stack right the stack of thirds there
will be a 53 embedded in
there yeah do that great hair or just
fixing go super um these are all
techniques that work really well here
what are the techniques that will work
if you have sevenths
or if you might might be given something
that is not a Triad at
all how would you do this with sevenths
begin with did anybody do that as their
extension you did yeah the way I did it
is I worked off of like what I guess
like first I had a function that kind of
like reduced the um the input to see
whether or not it could like kind of
work as a tri or as a cord okay so first
you I'm just repeating for the bicr
first you had a function that reduced as
a Triad or seventh to see if it worked
with the previous thing uhuh then and
then I kind of there's a like I guess I
combine both functions and so first I
iterate through a list of
potential um like interval distances and
then just for
each um potential candidate I had like a
rout and then iterate through each
potential candidate and see check
whether or not like the interval
distances were the same after adjusting
it was like bigger so you you checked
each one for each candidate as if the
root and then you checked to see if the
interval distances matched something
great super it was a second hand for
doing it how yeah really similar yeah so
increasingly similar great super this by
the way it's not one of the great
unsolved problems in algorithms but I do
not know if it has been proven what the
most uh algorithmically efficient way of
finding a root in um in anything
especially when we have uh chords like
here's one of our favorite in C
major what we want to call that
chord no close
but dominant seventh
chord should be four pitches which one's
missing d d which is the what of the
chord
fifth of the chord yeah the fifth of the
chord missing most common note in the
chord to leave out unless you're chopan
and then he likes to leave out that one
leave out the third
uh usually you can't leave out the base
otherwise you don't have a five although
uh there's a music theorist Hugo reman
who would disagree with you on that and
of course you can't leave out the
seventh otherwise you don't have that
but yeah so how to deal with this and
how to uh do these things is still
something that uh we're working on and I
was giving a presentation a few uh
months ago on how things were calculated
and in the middle of the presentation I
go oh my gosh that's not algorithmically
efficient and so somewhere in the music
21 thing I quickly stetched to do
remember how to make this faster and
I've forgotten how to make it faster so
so maybe we'll go back into that great
um then the last topic sorry let's put
that back back
and so Roman
numerals what are some of the
differences between the Roman numerals
and um and uh just finding the root yeah
go ahead I took theic that we given and
made a scale it and once I had the scale
I um found the of the cord and then saw
what position it was in in the scale
great so you created a Scale based on
the what was given the tonic the tonic
yeah I I only gave the tonic I didn't
give the key right because we're still
we're that created a major scale based
on the tonic and you saw which position
it was in that's that's really a great
great way of doing it what if it uh it I
didn't give it in this but what if I it
wasn't in the scale how would you do
that
anyone know of things like flat three or
flat 7even yeah just match the step just
match the step and then figure out the
subtraction of the difference so great
so we can find a position in the scale
if if you were wondering why um question
one was on major
scales that's exactly one of the
approaches I thought you could do
anybody else um have a different
methodology for this yeah if it wasn't
in the scale I just return never say
this invalid yep and it's invalid in
this assignment right was it not yep um
good um any other things to take all
your information now was Jake right who
who brought in major third minor 3r yeah
yep now I think it's time to get that in
what do you how do you convert
that what what does this information
tell us about the Roman numeral
yeah upper lower case uppercase lower
case good or there's one other thing
to put on what's the what's the Roman
numeral that often takes a special
symbol diminish seven yeah so the
seventh scale degree quite often the
five with the with the o seven with an O
after it the diminished seven
good um yeah and then inversions those
become kind of the problem
there so I want to give um like a twom
minute Peak on um the code that you've
now unlocked uh sorry there is a way to
make this
bigger nope there we
go
um and just to give a little bit of peek
at uh music
21s where we
go sorry tiny bit too big tell me yeah
okay that should be right
size sorry a lot of docks over time uh
things Roman numeral for from chord so
this is um something so given a chord
object and a key object um and then
possibly a preference for do we prefer
secondary dominance can you have in
major can you have a major chord on two
or is that the dominant of the dominant
of five um and try to give an
appropriate um name so why I don't know
why my first one was is so complicated I
guess the back then I was just like hey
I can do this uh let's see if we can
come up sign so if you have a chord E C
G B flat and then a few extra octave
things just to uh throw throw off in F
major that should be a five six5 who
remembers their uh inversions of seventh
chords so root position five seven then
first inversion five 65 second
inversion 543 and third
inversion 542 some people also teach the
tradition two and some people uh so 42
is the most commonly used one I've seen
some people have the less the even more
Compact 2 and some people the more
verbose 642 um
any Baseball fans I always think of um
double plays as oh I mean second
inversion that was a because they always
never mind um okay so you can have
certain certain things and then the one
of the big issues is that people call um
Roman Nu Roman numeral six and seven in
minor according to different naming
Traditions so some people say that um
that the the harmonic minor scale always
dictates what the um letter name is and
some people say that um that the uh that
if you say it's diminished like
diminished seven you already know it's
been raised and you say it's major you
know it's been lowered and you don't
need a sharp or a flat in front of it so
there's a whole bunch of different uh
conventions and unfortunately that's
something we haven't standardized uh for
anyone who's had two different music
theory teachers you might have already
encountered that okay so let's get down
to the code
um to show some of the things that I
found and maybe you'll come up with
better one uh who has taken a 302 or a
class that has encountered augmented
sixth chords yeah so you know these
these country codes Italian French Swiss
some people call it some people English
German don't need to worry about that
for this class um since we didn't have
it but um one of the other things that
uh comes up a lot is that you need to be
able to change
certain um certain things that might
come up so that's a 57 chord is
753 or 7531 if you want to call it and
but we only call it seven uh 65 seventh
chord first inversion is um is 653 but
we call it 65 so you just need a bunch
of of substitution things and some and
these aren't all of them because we grab
them from a lot of places to do make
sure ninth works that's all is a nice um
thing to do so we find is the first
thing you want to know is uh what's the
root of the chord and finding the root
as I said is already an interesting
algorithm and then figure out how many
semmit tones is there between that root
and whatever is the third and find out
if it's on the basis of major or minor
because that's going to determine
uppercase or lowercase right uh we'll
skip anything uh that says if there
isn't key um put that in then created
this conceptual device called a figure
tupple which um is the notion of
something like if you had a
chord with I don't
know you might sorry that is not a
French vocal cff
um you know you might
have call that
flat five flat
3 in some
ways that this one of these figures call
this a figure tupple which tells
you trip Hazard uh how what's the thing
over the base um It's just sometimes
easier to keep track of how many
semitones is it altered and what do we
call it so you might think that negative
one always means flat but there's some
cases where that's implied by other
parts of the
thing then correct the flat six to six
in minor depending on people's
spelling then we end up trying to figure
out all these things on how we can
figure how we can transpose the tonic so
that we can um deal with those things
that are outside the scale so like what
we said um if you have a root that is
not part of the scale then we just
really quickly construct a whole other
scale down a semitone or up a semitone
and so we can do all the other
calculations and then just throw Flats
on everything
afterwards um probably guess what this
does capitalize if it's major cap lower
case it's ner um and then a lot of these
things are slow so a lot of if we've
already seen this before get it from the
cache um
and then something to turn uh you know
one to I two to I I 3 to you know
whatever convert a number from 1 to
3,999 to a Roman numeral um I don't know
why I stopped at 3
3,999 um and it's because I'm a
historian and the numbers above 3,999
were never standardized no matter what
your teachers tell you um then we try to
figure out uh
what kind of figure it's going to be to
try to get how what kind of inversion
it's going to be so what's the string
for that and that's where a lot of these
uh what is it 6 4 3 become 64 and so on
um then there's then we try to think
about okay so we take what's the prefix
is it flat 2 whatever add to that the
Roman letter is it 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 and
then the inversion and then everything
after that is every special case that
we've encountered over time that uh that
turns out to um be an inconsistency in
the standard of Roman
numerals this is not a history class but
there's a really fascinating thing about
Roman numerals analysis and that is it
is a mashing together of two different
incompatible um analysis types that's
over time got put together into one but
that um so that things like the
uppercase and lowercase duplicating the
function of putting a flat three on
something and so what happens if you're
in C major and then you see lowercase 5
flat three
so let's say you're in C major and you
see lowercase 5 flat 3 what do you think
that should
be G as the base as a root yep flat B
flat and D what happens if I leave off
the flat
three same same so is this a cautionary
you can add it or you can put it out um
but then there are other cases what if
I'm in C major and I put 17
versus One Flat
7 or but the same thing with 57 doesn't
need the
flat five flat 7 same thing so there are
all these inconsistencies in the world
of Roman numeral analysis and it really
begins to get exposed when you start
doing things that uh we're going to be
looking into right now so we're going to
get to the algorithmic composition in
just a bit but I'd like you do for a
second is oops which which one's
here we'll go back into our favorite bck
piece because Corpus sorry Switching
gears up laptops open again
um we did this once already bwv
66.6 and we'll um remember cify
corded and we'll say cord boach today
cordach equals bach.
chordify and um I remember this one as
basically an F minor so we'll say uh FM
equals key. key FP lowercase
f and what we'll do on this is just for
so actually snap up when you've got
this yeah and also by the way if I'm
typoing this one I don't have a template
for so if I typo uh definitely correct
me on this so for chord in ch I often
say I don't write the word chord because
I don't want to lose access to my chord
module uh chord boach chord. chord for
each
chord we'll say is RN equals Roman do
that Roman numeral
from
chord CH and we're in the key of F minor
said you could just write the string FM
there but it'll be a lot
slower and then we'll just say
CH so actually give a second on that so
you're going to iterate for the recursed
that's square brackets mean all the
chords in chord boach get the chord out
get analyze the Roman numeral from chord
uh if I were a really really mean uh
Prof I would say your next assignment is
to reimplement that but uh the the you
can see the gray hairs here that's
exactly from that uh from implementing
that one um that and quartery are the
two reasons uh I'm getting old and um
now what we're going to do is we'll say
the chords lyric we did this once right
chords lyric equals RN's figure
I think we did this but we did rather
fast so I want to make sure
that oops that's not going to do
anything right because
I because I put it onto the thing I want
uh cordach doow my
apologies and you're going to realize
there's one thing I didn't do that's
going to make it look really funny I
forgot to put all of the chords in
in closed position but at least it works
pretty
well so we I'm going to scroll to the
end so about
here if you didn't get it all don't
worry um
uh some some of y'all have are are to be
thanked in the class especially John and
Adam for when I forget to put uh a
notebook up U that remind me and now all
the previous notebooks up so if you miss
anything uh they'll they'll be going up
later but you can see that there's some
places where you see chords that look
like cords that you've seen in your life
four 5 6
1 And Then There Are Places yeah five
that looks pretty good sorry that auto
saave thing knocks it
down and then chords
763 that's um rather unusual
um flat six augmented in sixth FL
position you all you all remember how to
resolve that chord
right no no I've never heard of that
chord in my life so this is um a pretty
dumb way of working with things in fact
I'm just going to go straight from uh
this to the to the last uh part here
then if you get to the top you see a lot
of figures that look pretty normal no
nothing after the three you see six
nothing six whatever these look a lot
better seven those those are numbers you
used to seeing the Arabic numerals used
to seeing but the Romans are way off why
are the these Romans so
weird because we're wearing Togos and no
no why are the Roman numerals so
weird remember this
piece goe it start in a starts in a yeah
if we go back into no we don't we don't
have to we remember uh how it goes bit
right it starts in a
major so one of the things you can real
start thinking about on your computer
system is if you see a lot of three Flat
6 Flat 6 three or flat 7 three three
flat 7 and you're dealing with a
classical piece of music what have you
probably gotten
wrong the key the key specifically
you've put it in blank instead of blank
you've put it
in what kind of relative minor instead
of the relative major good what if you
accidentally analyze the piece in major
instead of minor what would you be
seeing a lot of instead for one to
five um yeah you'll see six minor you'll
see two minor and three major six minor
two yeah six six twos and threes so that
might tell you something about hey
you're in a different um position great
so strange Roman strange Roman numerals
probably means failure of key strange
figures what what do these strange
figures probably
mean yeah Adam isn't a very compatible
cord isn't a very compatible chord or
it's a chord that has embedded possibly
what in
it non- chord tones good let's let's um
everybody's favorites non- chord tones
we'll go Hannah favorite non- chord
tone doesn't have to be your favorite
just name one I'm not going to lie I
don't remember what don't remember
anything great great so you so that's
great because you'll be listening up
because we're going to be doing some of
these
dimin F diminish fifth ah so diminish
fifth is a chord tone when you say it
that way but it's not um it's it's or uh
it's or non-harm non-harmonic tone is
probably maybe the term that you've
heard in other things when you say it
that way it might be part of a chord but
it might has to have function in order
to do it so function like John
anticipation an anticipation yeah where
you um where you you get to the the cord
maybe you get to the tonic a little bit
too early good anticipation is a really
good one anyone else have a favorite
one yep
suspension suspension yeah where you
hold the cord a little the tone too long
I mean it's great don't you know
obviously it's wonderful but too long
for the harmonic analysis so let's let's
say when computationally if if your job
is to get rid of non- cord tones what
are you going to do how do you get rid
of uh anticipation
rest of the cord following yeah you just
have the rest of the chord following
great how do you get rid of a
suspension I cut it shorter you cut it
shorter great great um so what's what's
another non- chord tone nobody's done
the one that you the first one that most
of us learn these are more yeah step
wise stepwise yeah between two things
what what do we call
that passing tone yes the passing tone
so great well how do you usually get rid
of a passing
tone just cut it out and make the
previous note longer right how do you
identify a passing
tone it just looks like it doesn't it
it's so easy on our neural processors of
our eyes it just sounds like it what
kinds of
things what criteria do we need to know
that sign's a passing time
those the worst stems
ever like the cff doesn't matter does it
um no it's still passing what which
one's the passing tone who votes for C
who votes for D who votes for E okay
good lots of lots of D's especially on
the side of the room that I've
privileged by making it much easier to
see right okay sorry about that I'm not
going to stay here very long so just
squint for a little bit and feel free to
shout out what um what I'm doing so free
close captioning great so what what
kinds of What kinds of things would you
be putting if statements on if you were
you all like I'll just throw it in
neural net and it'll learn but no um
what if you had to program it what what
would you be looking
for yeah seconds seconds so we have to
have a second and then a second do the
seconds have to
be
ascending no do they can they be in
opposite
directions no why not because then you
nebor then you have a neighbor tone yep
so 2 2 two second second equals passing
tone -2 -2 equals passing tone 2 -2
equals neighbor tone and -2 2 is
neighbor tone I know some of you are
already trying to pass your leak code
things and thinking okay what's the bit
wide operation that's going to make it
so I don't have to put all four of those
uh no it's okay there only four so you
can you can look find find these uh in
here so yeah you might be doing that
then anything else that you think is
important for saying that something is a
passing
tone let's have this
format yeah making sure the notes
surrounding it are CES making sure the
notes surrounding it are chord tones
yeah so these things have to fit into
into this and this is uh this is why I
was saying that you know uh diminish
fifth might be a a might not be a non-
chord Tone If the surrounding chord is
happens to be in Minish Triad and you
might say well then all of these might
be chord tones because maybe the
surrounding chord really is
4763 but probably not what do you what
do we so so now there there's two ways
to look at this we can do this on the
individual voice level and so that's
what we're going or individual part
level if you're looking at a crow that's
what you're going to do before
certifying the other thing you can do
what do you think is happening here you
can't even really see
um what's happening but you can kind of
see that we have 46 something weird
happening and then
four so we're going something's
happening here where we're going from
the first inversion of a chord to the
root position of the
cord and these there might be a lot of
passing Motion in there so you might be
able to identify these non- chord tones
at the chord level or you might be
working on the uh individual voice
level which one do you think works
better individual voice level chord
level individual
voice
chord yeah uh and the answer we don't
really know uh I try to do both because
some some things are easier to get from
one than the other so um great we've
gone through and um we've done
question uh outline one and most of
Outline Three on here I jumped around
because I realized that a different
ordering was going to be better um so
we're going to sort of gone through
three A and B and then I'll leave CD uh
C and D for a little bit
later um what I want to do since we have
our jigs loaded up I want to do a little
bit of two um yeah scratch well we'll
say take two if we're doing it no we're
not doing that level of editing but one
one last little thing problem set N9
you're going to be getting in a little
bit and what you're going to be doing in
problem set nine is this kind of chord
tone identification and removal so
you're going to be given various you're
going to be given various four-part
corals and what I want to see is instead
of um things like this that look really
hilarious something pretty clear out and
a nice sort of reduction of that um one
of the things you might start thinking
about is that Roman numerals are a type
of equivalence class on a set of pitches
that's not only about uh well it helps
to say that this is the same cord the
same cordal function in different Keys
it's also an equivalence class
on on a sort of the cloud of notes
including non non- chord tones that we
can that we can say these two things are
the same Roman numeral even though one
of them has filled in all the passing
tones or neighbor tones um suspensions
what do we get them all Escape tones
this pretty hard one there there a bunch
of other um ones uh but yeah so these
are uh things that you're going to be
doing so I'll be giving it to you in
just a little bit so you want to be able
to take something um and make it quite a
bit nicer your you're going to have help
on this um couple things of help it's
you're going to have uh at least a week
I'm thinking next Friday uh there's the
danger between uh I don't want to give I
don't want to give too little time but I
also don't want to go so late that
you're can't have your full attention on
the final projects so what's your thing
what I'd like you to do is you're going
to be doing problem set nine with your
partner that you're working on the uh
final project with and one other team so
groups of four the the team of four I
think you're a natural group of four so
why don't you put them there what i' but
what I'd like you to do is there are
different steps along the process here
I'll just I'll pop up P at nine right
now so you can see it while it's here
even though I'm doing some last second
uh tweaks depending on what we get
through today
um great so
P set 9 you're going to be doing
reduction and key analysis of tonal
music and I want you to say note this
you need not get every chord right it
need not work on every cral I'm asking
for a decent amount of work toward a
solution not a complete solution in
itself great okay so you're not going to
be doing that
um so what you probably like to do is um
well what you're you're going to do is
going I'm going to call vocabulary
reduce on a score and you're going to
give me either a score or a part
depending on how you try to choose to
represent it that is the reduced one um
you have four people on your
team you probably do not want to
implement you definitely do not want to
implement your entire solution inside V
this vocabulary reduce programming in a
Jupiter notebook
take this divide it up and um share it
among your favorite collaboration uh
collaborative coding tools um I'm
starting you the with a crow that's
easier than the one we've been working
on in class
66.6 and here are the four I'm going to
test you on for 90% of your points so
I'm going to tell you that um oops so
this is why I'm still editing you have
key analysis unlocked because we lost uh
sort of four classes this year so you'll
be allowed to analyze the key using
analysis things we're going to cify um
say this ad part ID is group is
something that lets you figure out for
each pitch in your cified score what
part it originally came from which can
be very useful for figuring out what to
delete and
um yeah we'll just show the first um put
it put it in actually I'll show show
different steps that might happen um
here so what I've done is I've gone
through one chord that if you um load
these things sorry one Corral
oops okay uh sorry I forgot I have to
restart and run
all yep here we go so you're here's the
original Corral that I'm asking you to
work on and then um unlocking sign
called implode which you might find
useful just for seeing a crow onto
stance staves it might not be too useful
for you um analytically and then what
I've done is given
you the first part of the answer how an
answer how I think the this might work
with all the non- chord tones
labeled and then second one um here is
after um after they've been after
they've been removed so you have them
all AED now you have all them removed
and then the last step you might be
trying to figure out that actually
there's some key changes in here so you
move from a major to D major to a major
and so
on why have I given you these uh
intermediate steps if this is what
you're trying to get to it's because you
have a larger team and so what I would
like is that somebody can be working on
part four while somebody else is working
on part three while somebody else is
working on part two and part one so then
uh what I'll say the last little thing
is just to show um a little preview of
some of the things that we might be
doing later and um I know it's not on
the right screen I can make that bigger
this is something I've been working on
on an
automatic um well let's let it run first
on uh AI based
automatically um trying to do labeling
of Roman numerals based on um sets of
pitches and training data what I've done
is uh right now I'm only having it work
with a few Roman
numerals and always take a guess when
you're trying to figure out what things
are these how many entries are there one
in each of these arrays 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
9 10 11 12 so these are the pitch
classes above the um above the tonic of
thing so that one has I can't even reach
up there so that one has the most
entries in you know call that c c sh d e
flat o e that's quite a bit F fshp
almost nothing G quite a bit and so this
is how many times you see that chord
tone in everything that in our labeled
training data was was labeled one and so
on for for five you see a lot of five
scale degree five scale degree 7 and
scale degree 2 kind of what you
expect and put everything into um a
neural net that I'm still trying to make
this a little bit better a little bit
better run it hopefully it's running um
you can see run it through one time it's
starting to get 62% accurate keep going
up at 62 62 62 quite a long time jumps
up 67 68 hopefully it's going pretty
well eventually gets 87 88 90 and so on
so it is possible to do this kind of
things with today's um computational
resources kind of ending it around are
we going to be able to get to 99
today how big is it so that's what I'm
gonna get to in just a second so so this
oh of course my computer can barely
handle this while projecting I think I
did 400 um well while while it tries to
scroll down to the bottom the danger is
this data set took me years to get and
it took years to put in this is the
complete piano sonatas of
Mozart complete piano sonatas of Mozart
all labeled and when I divided it up
into half training half test I still
didn't have enough information for it to
be able to get on so I'm dividing it
into 90% training 10% test and that
seems to be about what's there so the
other thing was when I decided I oh this
sounded like a fun project for over the
holiday break so I thought you know I'd
be able to present this on the first day
of class or something I went in and the
entire Roman numeral set could not be
trusted because compared to the encoding
of the things because people slightly
disagreed on where measure 14 was or
where measure 113 was or this Edition
had this this part of the minuette uh
the repeats were written out and they
weren't so I was going through and when
I was spot checking the Roman numerals
just look totally wrong to me or it
would say um Roman numeral placed after
end of peace and so again it was about
um I don't know it was about like like
three hours a night for about three
weeks of just okay well let's realign
this one let's realign now it was a
little bit less than that but some about
two weeks maybe um so this ends up being
one of the dangers and why I'm pushing
even though I think we're starting to
get how many EPO did I do this time I
must have changed it but we're we're
getting pretty close um and it takes a
very long time before the computers
being able to get things up um so these
are some of the reasons why I'm going to
teach you some of these techniques but
then I'm going to encourage you not to
use them on your final projects even
though they're they are kind of the
coolest new thing um going great any
questions I'm sorry I'm not getting oh
here we go finally we get to the done um
and my computer's still so slow here's
the mistakes that it was making oh this
time it only got there um last time it
got to all but all but one correct um
yep but 177 times it saw one it
predicted it one one time it saw it and
predicted five um you can kind of
imagine that four and two have some
confusion with the computer and five and
seven um also had some confusion six six
and four have some confusion so um then
the nice thing was actually going back
the last time I did this and um looking
at every place that there was um a
confusion and saying ooh about half the
time I agreed with the with the neur net
and not with the professional encoder