[Music]
hello everyone I think we can uh start
to get started now I'm Stephen Johnson
I'm on the host for today and I'm happy
to introduce Dr jeppe
Romano uh who's our speaker today he's a
research scientist uh a longtime
collaborator of mine at the MIT
Institute for Soldier
nanotechnologies uh he works on
materials inverse design with a focus on
energy and Computing he's currently the
pi of a project uh funded by through the
MIT IBM Watson AI lab on thermal
management and microprocessors and he's
also a world leader in the computational
modeling and design of nanoscale thermal
transport for which he maintains the
open source software open BTE uh and he
also maintains other open source
software such as uh dpv for solar energy
in 2019 he was distinguished uh visiting
scientist at the University of Colorado
Boulder uh in 2018 he was a visiting
scientist at the NASA jet propulsion lab
uh he first arrived at MIT way back in
2010 as a postto in Material Science and
Engineering after receiving a PhD in
electrical engineering uh from the
University of Rome T vagata and he
became a research scientist at MIT in uh
2014 so I'm going to hand it over to you
uh JPI I'm looking forward to your talk
thank you Stephen for this warm
introduction and and thanks actually sh
also for organizing this uh this uh
seminar also for the very nice music
selection oh sorry I forgot to say one
thing uh the uh if you have questions
they'll have be a 15minute Q&A session
at the end of the the talk so please
please hold your questions until then
but you can type them into the chat or
into the
Q&A or or ask them verbally uh by
raising your hand at the end so sorry
about
that thank you all right so today I'm
GNA cover I'm gonna um span upon our
recent efforts on researching
differentiable physical sers uh there
lies at the intersection between physic
sers automatic differentiation and
flexible software design uh there are
several applications that can benefit
from in design um particular those that
are close to my research interest are
pertains to pertain to theral energy
harvesting for example we can Harvest
our body's here through the soal
materials or we can even manage heat in
batteries in electrical vehicle or heat
Management in microprocessors or even
designing different layers in AC now
what do this uh applications I said uh
do this uh
physical well uh or what do they need
right uh so the starting point is uh
given by the plora of popular uh
software for uh for machine learn you're
only aware there are several their like
Bor or the whole scientific ml ecosystem
in Julia and Ja more recently and they
all they all have one thing they are
based on automatic differentiation which
is the the Cornerstone I would say the
king ingredients uh for B propagation uh
which is also call it also
reversible so now I'm going to give a
little bit of an introduction to
a so let's say we want to define a
function FX that takes an input X and it
just the sign of it so same X okay
automatic differentiation not only
comput this uh this function but also
the gradient of this function and in
particular if you're working on this say
a reverse mode automatic differentiation
the software also compute the derivative
of c x okay and multiplies by in this
case scaler which comes from the F that
maybe we are composing different
functions so we have to use the soal
chain rules in particular uh uh strictly
speaking what we are working here with
is called Vector products but I don't
want to go to technical here um so but
the key the key Point here is that the F
ofx can be really any anything
differentiable right so what if we have
a linear system that we are inverting so
let's say we have a function that invert
a matrix that depends on some parameters
and multiplies by this Vector B so this
is why right now is the solution of a
linear system and why do we care about
it it's because most linear systems are
they dig the represent of a partial
differential equation and PDS
are I would say uh govern the majority
of of the physics of okay so if you are
able to I would say hijack this machine
learning software for Inver sign then we
can rely on automatic differentiation to
let's say propagate sensitivity from
let's say a user defin uh a user def
cause function all the way to the of
they going to go through that very quick
all right so in this case uh we have as
a scen the case above uh the system also
the gradient along ra of why and this is
done without using this is the key the
key
Point all right so uh let's make make a
particular case so let's say we have a
material that is described by aous
density raw okay so let's say we have a
picture here okay so raw equal to one is
equal that corresponds to a solid phase
and equal to zero is a void case
and then we have a solware broadly to
find that in this case a of sare
actually and then we compute the
effective term of conductivity so this
is what this is called forward model so
we have the material and then we compute
a property of
that but eventually ultimately we are
interested in going the other way around
let say we want a material that with a
prescribed effective th here could be
also linear
elasticity and so yeah um so what how we
do that well uh so let's say we um um we
have a so we begin with theti density
raw and we Sol the linear system and
then we Define a cost function that
depends on those parameters raw of theal
density raw and the the solution of our
leing system now to do inverse design
what we need ultimately is the gradient
as I said along RW of G it turns out
that if you apply a reverse mode
automatic differentiation to a linear
system and so basically we are doing an
analytical derivative uh it turns out
that what we have to do is to just solve
an additional linear Sol and then we get
the sensitivity of the cost function
with respect to each pixel of our tises
density and I think this is a pretty
remarkable result imagine that the
thetive would be for example to comp the
this gradient with Planet differences
which of course scale scales very
badly and so this is not new uh the the
the method behind called Joint method
has been applied for decades mechanics
and also more recently in Optics from
group Stanford the group of Professor
Johnson here at but the key Innovation
brought by this machine learning
software uh uh the machine learning
packages that now we can uh compose uh
user Define uh cause functions with uh
you know arbitrary differentiable cost
functions with uh with our physics sare
so we can iterate research we can
research much quicker without doing the
derivative by hands all the time and
also there are also problems that are
domain dependent for example we're GNA
see through this
talk talk about Nill transer where
inverted sign not only need the adjoint
me but also a mat
interpolation that correlates the the
links the physics of your problems with
with the with the St all right so this
just a little example just a quick
example of microscopic in transport so
say we want to Des an autop material
that meta material this Cas perodic in
all directions that differently along
all those three directions so here we
have for example the desire ter
conductivity here we Define this uh this
this cost function so you eventually
what you want to do is to G find draw
right the Min
G okay all right so and so this is the
evolution of the trajectory this is just
microscopy just an idea see here we have
the three values so here we have the
term of probity for those three values
the diagonal so the diagonal
Z if you want and we see the three
numbers converting
Des eventually the material you're here
on the left side has the desire effect
in all right so how do we use it uh how
do we use this framework for the
application about in this case th
Harvest so let's let me give you a
little introduction about thric so
thermetrics is it's a f not as known as
photo but um
the a are converting he directly into
electricity by using solid state
material so no flexible part no noise
and so on and uh materials have been uh
used very heavily in space craft for
example the Voyager space grab was byasa
two decades ago the outer space has been
Power by a generator where theour is
given
by that
case um but also reaching some materials
for converting our bod the issue that
this this technolog is not as wi spread
asv1 is that efficienc is very low
because in atic material we want a low
and high
electrical and unfortunately at a high C
which is a the temperature responds to
the water responds to navigation
different temperature and all those
parameters are interrelated one emerging
part is given by Nan structuring that
enables to destroy heat transport more
effectively than he does with electronic
transort so if we have a a
characteristic size of a nanomaterial
let say about 100 nanometers heat heat
carriers in this case given by phom are
destroyed much more than electrical
electrical
carers whose me path for example is much
smaller than the
characteristics sides so power El high
it's about
just the average distance between two
consecutive conditions so by properly
engineering a material we can suppress
he byly by not suppressing trans as so
this the called zp that eventually goes
into the expression of the
system uh is is is the one that we need
to um boost and and
maximize um so this uh so as you can
imagine shape here is very important the
shape really detes the stand of boundary
scattering the stand of scattering B at
the boundaries of our our materials and
in fact the key Point here is that at
the Nanos scales he transport does not
obey food is food is not any um so there
is an incre there is a a dominant uh
there is I would say um a significant
contribution given by
thatat clearly by this law so we have to
use another model talk about very very
soon so here you can see that by just
changing the arrangement of of pores in
se you have a wide range of effect in
ter this is new to microscopic f for
sure because we have different different
uh geometries and different material and
let's say different fori here but also
uh this is due to the different strength
of of of scattering components and at
the boundaries all right so here in this
design is to go the other way around is
to find the perfect shape or an idea
shape or one of the optimal shapes that
can minimize the Thal conductivity while
keeping the electrical conductivity
above a certain
pressure and just yesterday a very nice
paper came out in science showing
corroborating the fact that indeed food
is lo and anos is violated here is the
Cor responding to this law for
electrical currents here the researcher
from eth measure uh vortices electrical
vertices at the nanoscale in graphy um
of course vertices is an hamic is not
covered by F law however it is covered
by a more fundamental law that is called
that is given by the bation so it turns
out that if you work with the B transp
equation and you comp the moments of it
you can end up with some terms that
resemble
the all right so if you buy a license
from conso you're going to get this
equation which is PR SL but over the
past I would say a decade I've been uh
involved in developing uh models and and
software for
the way more complex I'm not going go
the details but one thing I want to say
that the input parameters here are given
by first for calculations for example
computed by
here so for the remaining of this talk
I'm going to I'm going to solve this
equation here but very simpli for for
this we fure this equation in the more
complex uh form that eventually can also
include
the but for the propos a very simplified
version this all right so here we have
some not clearly clear s hamic signature
of Transport so we have FL here that
possible flux in fields and here finally
we are able
toes in the structure that is similar to
those computed by uh measure from the
that I just shown so it means that the
model is doing the job inting non K
signature all right U and this is the
code of open BT that uh the Implements
of these models and also be used for
predicting material properties but also
for regarding experiments
going so let's see how can Inver sign
help us here so in this case the
optimization problem so here on on the
left side we have the Baseline okay and
to with an
Associated uh electrical conductivity
here called f chance just diffusive and
here we have 0.31 this normalized values
and the goal here is to minimize the
thermal conductivity computed by the BP
while keeping this thres above the one
of the Bas so essentially the question
is we have a material so the problem
that we trying to solve here is we have
a material with the given electrical
conductivity and th conductivity how
long can you go with the termal
conductivity while keeping the
electrical conductivity above a c fure
this is uh this can be nicely FR in a
constraint ofation problem where both
the F diffusive and the bers are
differenti in a way that I just shown so
we can
use all right so this is the evolution
uh
the evolution the
optimization um and then after say 100
iterations we end up with a structure
that is made by Islands connected by
Bridges and now in a in a hand side is
okay this makes sense because if you
have a bridge the f f transport the F
transport is not is not as affected as
the B so the ratio between the two vales
goes goes out okay so this probably
something that intuition might have come
up with but I mean I haven't before
doing this this problem you know it's
it's very easy to say after we say oh
okay that makes sense right but but
thankfully than this large scale inter
design problem we can uh outour some of
the ination say computer all right so
and and we fabricate this m ning Focus I
this are our collaboration uh with
Professor can professor
Johnson here and and
also from now
profess so essentially here uh we have a
two N 200 nanom Big silicon membrane
bombarded by ions and uh and uh using
the the feed from M here the the um the
purose distance is about
100 and so now the next step will be
just to evaluate or to measure
the experiment and the the prediction it
turns out that we are close to the so
there is a a qualitative agreement
between experiments and Theory here as
you can see a part
two is there and the reason we suspected
the reason this this little discrepancy
I mean this discrepancy is due uh to
some numerical issues uh some numerical
this even is due to the numerical
distrib in the reci space that we are
trying out
to okay but but at least here we have
very nice so this the trend is is
respected and and and so we're very
excited about this and that's what we
are moving forward now to the next
challenge the next challenge is the
minimum length scale con straint so as
we noticed yes we got four I I I didn't
say that actually we have a fourfold
increase in ZT here however it expands
at a smaller at at a smaller P size so
feature L however it would be desirable
to actually have some degree of control
of that fion left and it turns out that
Um this can be nicely framed in a
constraint optimization problem where
the constraints the inquality
constraints depend of functions called
indicator function that measure your
characteristic
L and and this has been applied in
mechanics again in Optics and now we are
doing it in in N
scale um so uh so the next challenge was
to uh design in a material with a given
uh manufacturable constraints in that
case we uh were able uh to get 60
nanometers by the way this is this work
has is
really has been so the the measurements
the the Fabrications be driven by by y
from from right that is managing reion
and we have a post iteration and it was
very nice you know was very nice
interuption you would say okay you can
get a manufacturable constraint down to
6 nanometers that we get this we would
put this number in our Sol and we come
up with a with a a new structure um so
16 nanometers are the thickness now the
membrane is 50 and
here can maximize directly this ratio
you know the El conductivity over there
thermal condu and we obtain stres like
this and this is indeed 69 so the
manufactur strain is being fully
respected and now we are measuring and
here we obtain even larger um even
larger thermal conductivity boost in in
Z so we're very excited about this and
and measurements are ongoing right now
much we can have a better match in this
case all right so um yes so let's talk
about uh the second uh application case
so I would say the the the the the
titles are not the slides are associated
this uh titles are not uniformly uh
spaced so don't worry so Chip is going
to be four
slides and that's it all right so how
can we use um lingers design and terat
for to make our micros so uh our chips
get less C okay so there is a new
paradigm emerging recently based on
chiplet instead of having a a monol chip
we can uh just
integrate chiplets that are chips that
but there are task optimized so we have
a chiplet for Io a chiplet for for for
memory and so on and for Compu right so
and then those can come from different
uh manufactur
manufacturers and so they have to agree
to S of standard standard in terms of of
communication and this has great uh
benefits in terms of modularity of
course cost efficiency and so on and
another benefit is that we can move them
around now in order to minimize the max
temperature so what we want is that when
the chip is operating the maximum uh
operational speed so they get very H we
want to move them around of course we
move them around only once when we do
that when when when we make the chip uh
and and and in order to minimize the max
how do we do this Wells out that we can
use what I just uh
describe so let's PR the problem so
let's say uh the fundry um in this case
we C with IBM so let's say the IBM
found tell that they have a set of
chiplets that are connected through this
agency M Matrix AJ so say chip in this
case chiplet Zero is connected to chip
one and each shiplet adds as their own
as its own sites LX and L Y and very
importantly each uh chiplet is assigned
a a power
uh a power generator okay by je C so the
problem here is to to minimize the
maximum temperature unfortunately
maximum temperature is not
differentiable but there are many tricks
one of them is is using the P so
essentially if you take this let's say
the the temperature vector and you
elevate each element to a very high
number and then you do the square root
of that high number I would say Okay um
or one over Alpha be more more more
precise you get the max approximately
the Max and this is different this is a
concept that I borrow from another work
based on connectivity constraint and and
so all right so this is
differentiable another problem that we
wanted to uh there are other two
problems here how do how do we account
for heat dissipation to the substrate
while keep it simulation domain to uh
like after some simple algebra and and
consideration it turns out that we can
use an effective heat syn here is given
by L gamma T gamma isent that we can CH
and depends on the
substrate property in fact if I mean if
you move this on the other side has a
minus sign so it is an effect sync and
here okay so that part is taking into
account here on the right hand side we
have a smed version of the heat SCE so
we can just have step like heat SCE
given by chip let what we smoo them out
with 2 the function given by
H and um so now the problem is end to
end differential so we have the degree
of Freedom the position reach cheap this
right side is differentiable once we get
T and T with respect to P is uh is this
is even easier than PR sign because the
MX a Now does not even depend on on the
degree of Freedom we can just invert it
once and reduceing our reducing it
during our optimization all right let's
go to the by no another thing um we also
have to make sure that the cheaps do not
overlap we uh we use this uh inequality
constraint I'm not going to go into
details but also we have to Ure that the
uh the maximum wirelength doesn't exceed
that so those are two in constraints
that we take in in our optimization
problem so let's say uh this is a design
given by intuition where they hit the
maximum Peak is
k h from from from environmental
temperature if we don't use the wildel
constraint we have uh this design uh
where actually we got a a peak that is
40 degre uh smaller and if we had to
compromise a little bit because take we
want to take into account the max left
constraint we have this other scenario
where we have a little bit other harder
uh maximum harder environment
um for chip sorry but you know at least
here we are respecting the mass V so
it's kind of we have to play these
numbers and all right so um all right so
um all right so we have I'm not going to
go into details but we have some future
directions that I would like to talk
about so one uh uh that direction is
given by uh transformation Optics um so
essentially this is a very nice result
uh
where where where let's say you want
heat FL not going in certain directions
and you can change the metric of your
system it turns out that once you do
that your the functional form of your
equation for Optics and therat Remains
the Same so we can use the same solver
on a
different with the space dependent space
dependent uh in this case therac so we
are using we are now the issue is that
though to find the space dependent
thermal conductivity you had to compute
a lot of many ja and so on so we like to
do it with automatic differentiation so
so here um this is one type of one line
of research and second line of research
here is that to do topology
timization so we we don't use
transformation Optics but we do topology
ofation in order to have in this case we
have a thermac clock so we want to have
external temperature equal to the case
where the the obstacle were there this
is too much now I just wanted to throw
it out there um so this is where
automatic differentiation can have in
two
ways another another case uh another
project that that we are working on is
to extend ass sign from a pure space
mulated material a case where the
materials are mulated in space and time
for example we can modulate the local th
contivity time just by shining it and
there are many papers coming up now
where damun
ter and what do we care about well there
are some uh recent studies is shown that
you can really uh en the physics that
you want to to to give your metam
material for example instead of having a
space interface you can have a Time
interface okay so so it's a it's a Well
we have a material that abruptly change
time um so the question is natural uh so
the natural question here is how to
extend the you know invers design space
and time so here we have a simple case
let's say we have a a material where we
want to state state temper pressure
here part a certain number so let's say
we are keeping this material at just at
the beginning and we want to have a uh
the final temperature equal to uh a
given number and here we have the time
dependent n that we designed in to
shrink the the channel and to keep the
material at a given temperature okay
this is a Time depend problem and then
the last SL all right I think you're one
minut
um a software all right so all those
applications share the same software
infrastructures uh
infrastructure uh uh which turns out
very useful if you want to extend it for
to M problem so and then the software
now is called is that M inverse so
essentially takes an inut manufactural
constraint and and it and it
orchestrates different solers uh that uh
each of them influenced by depend
influenced by the parameter the raw in
this case which is the material density
and and uh so from this is and from the
user point of view what they have to do
is just to write arbitary differentiable
cost function uh that depends on the
output of those sers in this case for
example we want to miniz the norm or Dem
contivity with respect yes okay the norm
of the difference theity with the
desired this only thing that the user
has
to and uh in fact M inverse uh has been
uh now used for all these applications
uh that I I talked about and now we also
breaking uh data to to M to to benefit
all the routines that the ma is offering
um so um I I would like to uh conclude
by saying that essentially here we using
uh software like jacks or or scientific
ml uh from from Julia for example right
so that originally okay for example Jack
or or pych or or tensor that originally
been designed from neet for machine
learning and we are we are hijacking
that okay to use it for for for physics
if you notice there was no NE Network
here right just using the auto automatic
differentiation and and and but you know
as our sers are are differentiable we
can compose them with networks to
supplement with the lack of knowledge
let's say we don't have part of uh uh we
know everything about the system except
for few things and then we can
supplement those few things with a
surate so uh based on your so this class
of sers then can be composed and can
bearm existing sugar all right thank you
very
much thank you jepe so I I think we have
a few minutes 10 minutes now for
questions if people have uh questions I
don't see any in the in the chat uh yet
or the Q&A you can type them or you can
also click the raise hand button uh if
you want to ask a question uh
verbally so well people are thinking let
me ask a question so you know the ad
Frameworks a lot of them they were
designed a lot of them are designed
right now primarily for machine learning
applications of people using for the
things and for so for for doing them for
scientific Computing are there places
where they fall down where you have to
you know supplement them with manually
written uh chain rules uh I mean what's
what's the main weakness of those things
when you apply them to to to these these
kind of very non-neural Network like
competions yeah yeah this is very
question yes uh you had to supplement
with with custom in this case cting
product certain for example in this case
in in one case uh for example the the
the whole join meth the whole thing that
has to be hardcoded in as we speak uh in
some cases you can rely on the
infrastructure itself but uh for example
in my case as we speak I had to come out
with my for example if we have a a l
system that we want to Sol right um so
it might happen that the first guess
that we want in the back pass is
different from the first guess that we
want from the forward pass so we can can
just use uh the the the iterative
solware even if they use the AJ method
underneath you just can use it directly
because we have different for gases in
that case we have to we have to include
our own our own custom back produ
another point I wanted to say is that
sometimes we don't even have the the
problem is SE joint so we don't have to
compute The Joint but the system does
not recognize it so uh so we had to do
for example when I was when we actually
we were working on N for couple years
ago for for for um periodic materials uh
at some point I realized that they joint
with just some slight manipulation of
the over model and so I didn't have to
compute it again um but if we just use
plain machine learning uh automatic
differentiation framework the system
would not realize that that we just
waste so there are few things that
all right are there any other
questions you can raise your hand or or
type them in and I'll read them out
okay so then um I think I we'll close
the uh the webinar now uh so I want to
mention there is a um an an upcoming
talk on June 11th is the next talk by
Richard
swartwout uh who's co-founder of and CTO
of active surfaces and um he's going to
be
the um
so so he's going to give a Reflections
talk he was actually the first Nano
exploration speaker back on March 31st
20120 when he was a PhD candidate and
now he's going to give a Reflections
talk talking about his journey uh as the
first speaker in this seminar series as
a PhD candidate to now being a CTO of
active surfaces Incorporated and that
will be the last seminar uh of this
Academic Year at MIT so we're done now
so thank you everyone for coming thank
want I think you