so now let's discuss the link between
ulcerative colitis and cancer so
unfortunately ulcerative colitis
patients have an increased risk for
coloral cancer it can be up to twofold
higher so to remind you all cancer is a
disease where healthy cells transform
start to grow uncontrollably and spread
throughout the body so on the left here
we see normal tissue and on the right we
see the cancer cells where there's this
uncontrolled growth and cancer is
triggered by by genetic changes changes
to the DNA inside the nucleus of your
cells and in ulcerative colitis there's
as I said before chronic inflammation
which results in the epithelial cells
constantly being destroyed and
regenerated and during these Cycles
there's damage to the DNA and this can
trigger the cancer that occurs in the
colon so for patients with ulcerative
colitis it's important that they undergo
screenings for cancer so we know that
early detection of cancer leads to
better patient outcomes so here we're
looking at statistics from the UK for
three different types of cancer lung
breast and coloral and we're seeing that
when cancer is caught at the earlier
stage uh there's much better chance of
survival over 5 years underscoring why
we need to really try to capture cancer
early now when a pathologist is looking
at an ulcerative kidus tissue section
that's been stained with h& e they are
looking for signs of displasia and
displasia is an abnormal growth of cells
in your colon that may become cancer so
it's something that needs to be looked
at so on the left here is a colonoscopy
and the gastrologist and the
Pathologists have noted that there's a
region here of displasia and this is
still pretty hard to see just with you
know a camera so what happens is uh they
take a biopsy from this section and a
pathologist then stains it with h& and
examines the tissue more closely and in
this darker region of the colon tissue
you can start to see what a pathologist
would consider
dysplasia so dysplasia occurs across a
Continuum in the kind of cancer
landscape so here we have a cartoon of
cancer development where on the left we
have normal colon mucosa and then you
start to see that the mucosa starts to
change and the structures are really
changing and you go from low grade
dysplasia to high- grade dysplasia which
is more of a risk for cancer and then
finally you have carcinoma which in this
case would be real colar rectal cancer
so now let's look at what those tissue
histology images would look like from
the displasia so on the left we have an
h& image of low grade displasia and on
the right an h& image of high-grade
displasia and one thing a pathologist
would note for the low grade displasia
is you have these hyper chromatic nuclei
so this is a mouthful but what this
means is the nuclei are darker than
normal so remember the h& stain stains
the nuclei of the cells this purple blue
and now these are showing up even darker
and this is often a sign of accumulating
DNA in the nucleus which typically uh is
associated with cancerous cells in the
high-grade displasia the pathologist has
noted this loss of nuclear polarity so
when you look at the nuclei they're kind
of scattered a little bit all over the
place so normally the nuclei of the cell
is in a specific region of the cell and
during cancer you start to lose this
regulation of where the nucleus is in
the cell so that's the loss of nuclear
polarity that a pathologist would note
in this tissue section so you know what
have we learned so far well you've seen
a lot of tissue pathology images and you
probably can see that they're incredibly
powerful I mean you haven't seen enough
to probably become a board certified
pathologist but you hopefully kind of
realize that you know these images are
really helpful for diagnosing ulcerative
colitis figuring out what treatment to
use and also detecting cancer early
which is super important the other thing
I want to point out about these tissue
pathology images these h& images is that
they are very cheap to collect this is
routine care and millions of these
images exist in hospitals so this is a
in a sense a really amazing data set for
machine learning because it's images and
you have many many of them and often
they are
annotated so at the same time the tissue
pathology images don't tell us
everything uh they don't don't tell us
how ulcerative colitis arises it just
tells us there is ulcerative colitis so
it doesn't tell us anything about the
disease mechanism it doesn't tell us you
know how a cancer could arise and you
know there's a lot of interest in
understanding disease mechanism because
once we understand how a disease arises
we have Pathways that we can start to
Target with drugs that we could develop
and these are really active areas of
clinical research so if you go to
clinical trials.gov you'll see that
there's 3 active studies right now for
ulcerative colitis and about 2,000
active studies for colar rectal
cancer so there's a lot of opportunity
in this challenge to work with these
tissue pathology images but ask what
more can we learn from them than what a
pathologist already learned and then
also using these images could we get
even better at detecting cancer earlier
and impacting uh patients with ultra of
citis so at this point I've given you an
introduction to the biology of
autoimmune disease in particular ulcer
of colitis and we've learned how uh
Pathologists can diagnose this disease
these diseases and also how ulcerative
colitis increases your risk of cancer
and why that means we need better ways
to detect cancer earlier