So with MITHIC, we have four
different funds to support
research of different types.
And what research means
means different things
for different faculty.
So for our next
presentation is actually
a partial screening of a film.
So this is a film by Vivek
Bald from comparative media
studies and writing.
And he's going to come
give a little introduction
to the movie.
And then, we'll watch
about 15 minutes.
So, Vivek, are you here?
Yes, you are.
Here you go.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
I feel honored to be here to
present some of this work.
Before I start, of
course, I'd like
to express my sincere gratitude
to Provost Chandrakasan, Dean
Rayo, Associate Dean
Makan for their vision
and leadership in bringing
the MITHIC initiative to life,
To Jen Dalton and Elena Nosiglia
for organizing today's event,
and to President Kornbluth for
her commitment to humanities,
arts, and social
sciences at a moment
in which critical thinking,
creativity, and social analysis
are both more endangered
and more needed than ever.
As some of you know, I am
a historian and documentary
filmmaker.
And my work combines
scholarship and media production
to illuminate the past
and present stories
of people of
Indian, Bangladeshi,
and Pakistani descent
in the US and Britain.
I focus particularly
on the lives
that South Asians have
built with and alongside
other immigrant communities
and communities of color.
For the past several years, I've
been documenting a previously
unknown history of
South Asian Muslim men,
men from colonized
British India,
who came to New York in
the 1920s, '30s, and '40s.
This was at the height of what
is known as the Asian Exclusion
Era, a period stretching
for more than 80 years, when
the United States passed a
series of race-based immigration
laws that barred the entry of
the vast majority of people
from Asia.
These men, undocumented
and unwelcomed
by the larger US nation,
found refuge and respite
in Black and Puerto
Rican communities
on the Lower East
Side and in Harlem.
They found jobs, married, and
started families with women
from their adopted
neighborhoods and crafted
new multiracial lives.
Together, these South Asian
Muslim immigrants, their Black
and Puerto Rican partners,
their children and grandchildren
have been an unacknowledged
part of the fabric of New York
City for over 100
years and forging
a kind of long
prehistory, now I can
say, to the first South
Asian Muslim immigrant mayor
of New York.
As someone who worked in
documentary film for more
than a decade before
pursuing a PhD,
I'm still driven by
the goal of making
my scholarship
accessible and meaningful
to broader publics
outside the Academy
and especially to the
communities whose histories I
document.
I'm just going to put that over.
It is for this reason
that I continue
to work across multiple
media forums norms,
producing written scholarship,
film, and digital oral histories
for the web.
It is also for this reason that
I treat each of my documentaries
not as an endpoint, as a
finished product to be marketed,
but rather as a starting
point, an opportunity
to bring people together in
the collective act of viewing
to cultivate discussion and
dialogue about shared histories
and experiences and
to forge understanding
and new connections across
our supposed differences.
This public-facing
work is a key aspect
of my work as a
scholar, entwined
with my more traditional
writing and research.
So I was understandably
excited to hear
about the initial round
of MITHIC funding,
not just as a new
stream of funding
within the institute,
but as an initiative that
values and supports
bridge-building internally
across disciplines as well as
externally between the academy
and the public.
As part of the first cohort of
recipients of the Humanities
Cultivation Fund, I partnered
with South Asian and other
community-based organizations
locally in the Boston area,
as well as internationally
in the United Kingdom,
on a series of public
screenings and discussions
of my documentary In
Search of Bengali Harlem,
focusing on three of
the film's key themes--
xenophobia and
anti-immigrant violence;
Black South Asian
intimacies, solidarities,
and community-making; and
intergenerational trauma
and healing within
immigrant families.
In London and Birmingham--
and I'll show you a few
of the slides here
from those events--
in London and Birmingham,
I collaborated
with four organizations.
Rich Mix, a community
arts organization
grounded in the
historically Bangladeshi
immigrant neighborhood of
Tower Hamlets in East London.
Brown girl in the
Ring, which showcases
spoken-word literature,
music, and dance
by British South Asian women.
Soul City Arts, an arts
organization and performance
space in the heart of Britain's
second largest Bangladeshi
neighborhood in Birmingham.
And the BlindianProject, an
online community of more than
30,000 black and South Asian
families in the US and UK.
These are just a few
slides from these events,
which I've just returned from.
The Boston-based event was
at Bartos Theater in October
and was a collaboration
with the Cambridge-
and Boston-based South Asian
arts organization Subcontinental
Drift, who some of you might be
familiar with from the Diwali
celebration that
they do at the MFA.
Along with MIT student groups,
the Asian-American initiative,
South Asian Association
of Students,
and the Bangladeshi Student
Organization, both at MIT
and the BSA of Wellesley
as well, and featured
its discussants, two
of my former students,
the president of MIT BSA, and
a Bangladeshi American student
from Cambridge's high school,
CRLS, where my own daughter just
started.
So this was a really
rich discussion.
Also, we brought up my
editor, Beyza Boyacioglu,
who is an alum of the
CMS master's program
and has become a very
sought-after editor in New York
City.
So In Search of Bengali
Harlem itself, the film,
is 84 minutes
long, so I can only
show two short segments
totaling about 10 minutes.
But I hope it will give you
a sense of the film as a film
but also as a catalyst for
the kind of collective work
that I've described.
All right, let's roll.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- --part of some larger history
that hadn't been recorded yet.
I started the process
looking at the indexes.
- These look like ATRAX.
- Yeah.
- [CHUCKLES]
- Grooms index, all
boroughs, 1928 to 1932.
- Right.
- So I started looking
through these for those names.
Ali, [INAUDIBLE],
[INAUDIBLE], Mia,
surnames that were common
among Bengali Muslims.
So over in these cabinets are
microfilms of the actual--
- Marriage certificates?
- Marriage certificates.
- OK.
- Yes.
- 29364, Muhammad Abdul is
married to Sadie Simmons.
- Yeah.
- Wow, 1923.
Can you imagine what
their wedding was like?
Most of them says India.
Right, because, back then,
It wasn't Bangladesh.
It was India.
- When they came here,
first they were Indian,
then they were
Pakistani, then they
were Bangladeshi because of
the independence movements
that were unfolding--
- So in a lifetime, my
father had three identities.
- All right, so here we go.
- 1925, wow.
Yankees won the World
series that year,
Babe Ruth and Lou Gehrig.
- Your whole
reference to history
is the history of the New York--
- My only way of remembering
history is the Yankees.
Who are these people?
What ever happened to them?
But I feel their one degree of
separation away from my dad.
- So let's take a look
at the one from 1939.
- So you roll it around first.
This is August 8.
- OK, we're looking for May 27.
1046.
This, can you read that?
- Ali Habib, Maria
V. Echavarria.
- That's your father.
And this is Victoria.
So he went by Habib Ali.
- Ali, right.
- Right?
Color or race, it
says Indian white.
- What's Indian white?
- Sometimes they're referred
to as white, sometimes colored,
sometimes black.
Occupation.
- Cook, age 28.
- Age 28.
- Wow.
- So this was a pattern that
there were a lot more men
than just your father and
his small circle of friends.
They were almost all marrying
either African-American
or Puerto Rican women.
They were almost all working in
these service-type jobs, which
were all also occupations that
other men of color in that era
would have been doing.
And we know that they were
settling in the Lower East Side
and in Harlem.
- I didn't realize
there was that many.
- So then the next thing
that I started looking at
was ship's passenger records.
I didn't find any
passengers with these names,
but I found lots and lots
and lots of ship workers.
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
Ali, Mia, [INAUDIBLE], Udin, the
same names, one after the next,
after the next being
listed as firemen.
And those were the
people who shoveled coal
into the furnaces,
the stokers who
also kept the fire at a
particular temperature, cooks
and stewards.
So, then, it started
to make sense.
So they were actually men
who had come as ship workers
and jumped ship.
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
As colonial subjects
on these British ships,
they were like
indentured laborers.
There are these
stories of men who
are described as having gone
crazy in the heat of the boiler
room and jumping overboard
in the middle of the sea.
In this book by Rozina
Visram, she recounts a story
that she found in the
archives in Britain,
a group of South Asian
Muslim ship workers
who were punished for
something on board their ship.
The ship's captain hung
them up on meat hooks
and shoved pig entrails
into their mouths.
All the crew jumped
ship at the next port.
Whenever I would see Chacha
Victor talk to my dad,
these two men were like,
oh, let me tell you.
No, let me tell you.
I can't see both of them
cooped up in the village.
It's the one trait that
they all have in common.
Like, let's go for a walk.
Let's go outside.
- Yeah.
- Auntie Helen and Chacha
Victor were friends of my dad's.
They were the couple
that I imagined
my dad and Victoria were.
How did Victor get to Harlem?
And how did he and Helen meet?
- He was a tender on
the British ships.
He had to shovel coal
to run the engines.
The ship landed in
Baltimore, and his friend
told him to come with
him, that they were
going to go see some people.
But as the night wore on,
he says, well, I'm staying.
You have no choice.
You have to go with me.
And they took a bus and
landed up in New York.
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
Now there was a lady,
she was a Black lady.
He stayed in her rooming house,
and there were other Indians
there.
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
My mother used to take
the train with my sisters.
My future husband, he
would wait for my mother,
and he would give her his seat.
And then, my mother
invited him to the house.
I said, I guess he's
interested in my sister.
She said, you can have him.
I said, I don't want him.
- [LAUGHING]
- You had a boyfriend already?
- No, I had no boyfriend.
I worked as a nurse, and I
didn't want to be a housewife.
He came back just
before Christmas.
He proposed to me, and
I was flabbergasted.
And I said, oh my goodness.
We decided we would get married.
And I said to my
mother, you don't
have to worry about the gown.
We're not going to be married
in the Catholic Church.
No pork.
That's what I told my mother.
That's when I was introduced
into the Indian community.
- Well, it was great seeing you.
- Good to see you.
Good to see you.
Welcome, welcome.
- Come on in.
- [INAUDIBLE] and Ruth Ali ran
a restaurant together in Harlem,
not long after my dad and
Victoria opened the Bengali
Garden in Times Square.
I had heard about how Malcolm
X's circle used to eat there.
This place became like a
fixture in the neighborhood.
- How are you?
How are you?
- I'm good.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
- --take your shoes off?
- No.
[CHATTER]
- Come on and have a seat.
There's just no great
order of any kind.
- You know, it's funny, because
when we started this project,
I never had any
pictures of my dad.
I only knew him as an old man.
- I remember that
picture so well.
She was crying, and he was
taking care of a customer.
And he'd just picked her up,
and then she stopped crying.
- I think I was
about three months--
- Yeah, something.
- --three months
old, four months old.
- And I was sitting in
the window like this.
And he was passing with
a priest, and he was--
I said, wow.
I'm going to get
that guy right there.
that guy one day.
Just like that.
So I watched where he was going.
It was this Indian restaurant
between 134th and 135th Street.
He gave me the phone number
on the back of a matchbox.
- Did you notice he had a
strong accent, or was he--
- Yeah, I didn't care.
I was going for the good one.
[LAUGHTER]
I didn't care where he was from.
[LAUGHS]
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
He was a foreigner and
knowing in my heart
that my family would
not accept him.
I wasn't in South Carolina,
and I wasn't being watched.
I felt a freedom.
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
He opened the
restaurant in 1958.
And shortly after
that, he got married.
He lived to get
up and go to work.
He loved it.
That was him in the kitchen.
There was a counter in
the front, very American.
There was four of us--
my brother, my mother.
We worked-- chop
up, peel carrots.
I'd stand on the soda crate
and watch him butcher the lamb,
or the beef, or the
chicken and cut it up.
And I had chicken curry just
about every day of my life,
as far as I can recall.
She would cook on Friday nights.
We'd have our Southern
food on Friday nights
up in the apartment.
- But he liked it.
He liked it.
- We had our birthday
parties there.
Miles Davis used to come in.
I used to serve
him all the time.
I remember Cicely
Tyson sitting there.
- Morgan Freeman came.
- Mark Breland, a boxer;
Kareem Abdul-Jabbar.
[INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC]
My father passed away in 1982.
She ran it for another
15 years without him.
This little black woman
from Pawleys Island,
South Carolina, you know what?
That's why she went after him.
Because she had to carry
on the legacy of running
this Indian restaurant
17 years after he died.
- Wow, he's no joke.
- [LAUGHS]
[END PLAYBACK]
[APPLAUSE]
Vivek?
Oh, well, I was going to
say we should applaud Vivek,
but I can't find him.
Oh, there he is.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks so much.
And as you can imagine, as a
multiracial child of a South
Asian immigrant, this
resonates strongly for me.