Hello everyone and welcome to the
startup lightning talks. This is the
more fast-paced part of the conference
today. I'm Marianstein, program manager
with MIT startup exchange and I'm glad
that you're here with us in person and
also thank you to those joining via the
liveream. Shortly you will hear from 10
exciting startups. They're among those
that have more recently joined Startup
Exchange and they're working on nimble
solutions that are benefiting a variety
of industries including manufacturing,
energy, defense, mobility, finance,
agriculture, and retail just to name a
few. They will share a little bit about
their applications and use cases. And
they're looking of course for more
partners and customers. So I hope that
after their presentations you talk with
them a little more and explore what's
possible today.
So first though I will share a little
overview of our program.
MIT startup exchange was created to
support MIT connected startups as they
grow, expand and help solve some of the
world's greatest challenges. And we do
this by fostering partnerships and
collaborations between the startups and
industry primarily members of the
industrial design program or ILP
represented by so many of you here today
and also the MIT innovation ecosystem
and beyond.
The startups in the program have a very
strong connection to the institute. They
may be based on licensed technology or
may be founded by MIT faculty, staff or
alumni. and they could also be vetted by
some of our MIT peers including the
engine start nano or cel startup connect
plus
we have around 800 startups in the
program as skayatri mentioned earlier
today and they usually join at pilot
stage or beyond and they may represent
any sector and any geography and here
you can see some of the trending
technologies of the MIT startups and
I've noted in bold those represented by
the startups joining today of course we
start with AI and ML big data and
analytics, robotics, IoT and sensing,
sustainability and many others.
So when it comes to value,
we have a very customized approach and
we do this in a variety of ways. Um
everything that we do is for the
exposure of the startups and um creating
opportunities for connections to
industry. For example, we launch call
for startups. We call these
opportunities and they're based on
corporates's priorities and internal
challenges. And as a startup, you can
apply on the website and if selected,
you can work with an ILP member to help
them solve a problem that they may be
facing in the industry. We also host
one-on-one meetings, virtual demo days,
other webinars, and conferences like
today where there are startup lightning
talks and an exhibit. And we also host
workshops and trainings sometimes in
conjunction with other MIT peers. So I
hope everyone is taking advantage of
these benefits and let us know any
questions throughout the day.
And so here you can see some of the
success cases that um have developed
between the startups in our program and
ILP members. This is just a very small
sample and they can take the shape of a
proof of concept proof of concept um a
large scale pilot becoming a customer um
joint R&D and all the way even to an
acquisition for example. So my hope is
that some of the conversations that
start here today will lead to more of
these success cases.
And before passing it on to the
startups,
um I wanted to highlight a few of our
upcoming events. On December 10th, I
will be hosting the next virtual and
quarterly demo day. It's eight startups,
lightning talks, Q&A, breakout rooms,
short and sweet. So please register and
join us. And we have two dates for March
and June for 2026 as well. On December
11th, we have the webinar quantum at a
turning point. In January, we'll be in
Asia for the Korea and Japan
conferences. And we'll be back here at
the Marriott on April 14th for the next
AI conference. And in between, there's
more events coming. So, please check out
the back of the program today and also
the startup exchange and ILP websites
for more information.