Okay, good morning. So speaking of skill
sets, uh in my previous life I was an
electrical engineer. Uh but then as I
typically joke I switched to a dark
side. So I got my PhD in economics and
uh you will hear in many of my remarks
well my inner economist. Right? So here
in the United States economics is a
dismal science. So it means that we
economists are always unhappy and so it
means that we always try to find okay
what is really about that. So that's why
I admire presentations like Charles has
done recently and well we have many of
these wonderful researchers at MIT who
are so enthusiastic that well we are
going to solve all the problems and kind
of here are the all the solutions. So my
job is to find where's the catch. So
sometimes we assume for example well a
catalyst in one of the paper on
directory capture wonderful fantastic
paper which will say well we will be
able to do that at a reasonable cost and
well kind of we were trying to
understand and find out that well they
assume a catalyst which hasn't been
invented yet and so well things like
that may slow you down. So as a result
what we are trying to do we are trying
to understand globally where we are
going and what are the current pathways
what we should expect as a company you
want to have the optimism you want to
think well what are the latest and
greatest but also you need to understand
well what are the realistic things and
when we might come to the market. So
well let's start with a big big picture
and we always like to try to make sure
that we are speaking in the same
language that we are making sure that uh
we know where we are going where the
world is going. So I start with this
diagram which should be familiar to many
of you. This is a diagram from the
latest IPCC report intergovernmental
intergovernmental panel on climate
change. And this is the diagram which
shows where the world is currently going
well according to their projections uh
at that point and where we need to be.
And you can see that well those
trajectories are very very different.
And even more than that if you're going
to take a look where we were in last
year last published numbers uh in terms
of the total greenhouse gases we
actually about outside of their
confidence interval. So 5 to 95%. So we
are still moving in the wrong direction
in terms of the greenhouse gases at the
global level and well uh there is a
recent UN uh emissions gap report and
you see some quotes from there where
they try to understand in the Paris
agreement process there is something
which is called NDC
and so national determined contributions
where countries are making pledges we're
making promises what they are going to
do and you have to be careful with
interpreting those pled pledges but at
least that gives you the incentives what
countries are trying to do and for
example there is a pledge from the
United States which is still on the
website which says that in 2035 United
States is going to reduce emissions by
60% well more precisely 61 to 66 is that
going to happen well your guess is as
good as my guess but most likely we are
not going to be there not in 2030 not in
2035 so again whenever you are looking
at those NDCs you also need to provide
some expert judgments where we are going
and we are not going fast enough. So
coming back to going fast enough and I
just show you the graph which is in the
emission units but if we're talking
about sustainable pathways emissions
just a part of the game we need to
understand what else matters and so well
what the world is doing about that word
sustainability which is a very fantastic
world everybody word everybody likes
that word uh because everybody has a
different meaning to that word so you
can interpret that in many many way you
can do it like UN with sustainable
development goals uh which has 17 of
them you are seeing all of them the
problem with that it's too many and how
to quantify so a lot of issues with
trying to cover everything so typically
when we talk about sustainability we try
to boil it down to something little bit
more manageable which you can
communicate so again emission reduction
is very important so we know that we
need to make sure that We are avoiding
these future extreme events which uh
changes uh which climate change is going
to bring to us. But there are other
aspects which are equally important
sometimes even more important and you
see the listed there while obviously
affordability
and you need to have affordable
solutions. So not just technologically
possible solution but also well is it
going to make economic sense and also
right now in the world of change
geopolitics or kind of where we are
going in terms of the geopolitics we
also need to understand more and more
about the security of supply and
security of supply not just energy but
food water and many other aspects
and also you need to make sure that you
are not just talking about the big
picture. Oh well, what is the energy at
the level of the country or at the level
of European Union or the level of
Africa? Because after all, you are doing
that to make sure that you are making
resilient your local community. And it
means that you have the integration
problem or integration issue to resolve
where you are not only provide energy in
a resilient fashion and you are not only
making sure that your energy
infrastructure is resilient to different
type of extreme events but also how that
relates to transportation system to
buildings to food to water and so there
are many aspects where do need to have a
system which looks at the resilience at
local level, how much you can do at the
local level but also how it is connected
to the outside forces. So for example,
we just had a conversation with the
visitors from Iceland and they said well
well we are doing a lot of good things.
They're blessed with a lot of good
resources but we are still uh subject to
the prices for wind equipments or solar
equipments or other things. And so it
means you also need to understand what
are the trajectories for all these other
things which you will use as an input to
resolve your uh energy uh resiliency.
[clears throat]
So there is another aspect on the
physical side. I'm not going to go too
much about the physical risks. So we are
doing a lot of studies on the physical
risk. Again the slides are going to be
available. There is a reference uh down
below where you can take a look and try
to understand what's our thinking. So
this is one of the projects which we are
doing for department of energy, US
department of energy where we are trying
to understand well how vulnerable is the
energy infrastructure in particular
cases. And so this particular study we
are applying to a port of South
Louisiana where we are trying to
understand how the major port which is a
connection of all a lot of agricultural
trade other things how that is going to
be affected by both the gradual changes
like sea level rise temperature change
but also the extreme events and how all
that connected to other energy
infrastructure.
Okay. So switching gears back to the
story in terms of the emission
trajectories. So uh what I put here uh
are the latest projections from
international energy agency. So they
released their world energy outlook I
think last week or two weeks ago. Uh so
a couple things to note. Uh well one
thing to note that IAA uh returned back
their uh current policy scenario. Uh and
you can see the trajectories in current
policy scenario versus stated policy
scenario. and also uh they dropped
something which used to be called
announce pledges scenario. So those are
the long-term pledges for Paris
agreement. Those are not NDC. So NDCs
are still in their stated policies. But
if China for example is saying oh we are
going to be carbon neutral by60 or India
saying something like that that's in
announced pledges scenario and right now
kind of they're saying we are not sure
how to do about that. And so if you're
going to take a look at the latest world
energy outlook, you will see three
scenarios. Uh current policies, stated
policies, and net zero emissions. We at
our group at MIT doing our own outlooks.
And so you can see the trajectories of
the outlook which is going to be
released next week hopefully or uh after
the Thanksgiving. So it's almost ready
uh for the press and you will see uh how
we are thinking where the world is
going. So that's our current trend
scenario. We also try to understand okay
where this story with tariffs where we
try to impose Trump's tariffs. The
problem with that they constantly
changing. So it's not clear what number
to put and what is going to be the
reciprocal action and so on. So but the
point is take a look where we need to be
for net zero emission scenario where is
NZE and where are the realities. So
again, uh, when I'm in my festive mood,
typically I'm saying, well, that NZ
scenario, it's like Santa Claus
scenario. It's a wonderful world. It
would be nice if Santa Claus will come
and give us all these gifts, but I'm
getting older and older and I'm less and
less believing in Santa Claus. So it
means that we whenever we are making the
decisions we need to take a look where
the world is going how competitive we
are going to be where is our comparative
advantage under these conditions where
uh we are going to be uh trying to be uh
very competitive in the world and then
uh well uh people would throw picture
like that and so there are many many
versions of this type of a diagram uh
this one happens happens to be from IIA
geothermal and you see that it's a lot
of geothermal resource and you see that
almost invis invisible dashed line so
this is the current use of power
generation or current current power
capacity installed globally and kind of
immediately if you are an uninformed
person you will say oh what's the
problem why we are talking about fossil
fuels there are plenty of other stuff
which we can use so what why it's so
hard to do the shift to lowcarbon
resources
And well all these details this is where
uh all these grumpy economists come and
say well that's nice but it will cost
you much more money if you're what
trying to do this way and note that well
here uh I haven't mentioned uh nuclear
so these are the renewable resources and
so uh Charles uh has done a very good uh
application cases uh for nuclear and
indeed nuclear is very attractive if you
are going to take a look at the life
cycle emissions. Take a look at the
nuclear. It's very very attractive. But
also take a look at the cost, right? So
it's one of the most expensive options.
And well, these costs which are stated
there also quite optimistic. So if
you're going to take a look at that
diagram, you see that well according to
that document from IAA, uh well that's
about $4,000 per kW electric. Uh well
the last uh two units and Charles can
correct me if I'm wrong which we built
in this country uh the waggle. So the
original price tag was $6,000 per kW.
The realized price is $16,000
per kW. So kind of whenever you're
talking about nuclear well that's not
really a cheap option uh at least in
this country. And if you're talking
about small modular reactors, you see
kind of in this diagram uh the current
question which we are getting many many
many times. Oh but SMRs are cheaper,
right? So let's build SMRs. Well, you
can do a very simple division kind of
the how much electricity you are going
to get from there for the cost and you
will get the very simple answer which
you cannot beat that well the big plant
are actually going to be much uh less
expensive. So again uh if you're going
to take a look at the uh for example uh
IAA projections for levelized cost which
they use in their projection you see the
costs which are listed there. So, and
for SMR, $8,500.
If you are going to take and follow the
news where the first commercial SMR is
currently being built in Canada,
Darlington, Gnova, and if you're going
to take a look the announced cost of the
first reactor, so they're thinking of
building four of them, you will end up
at the number $12,000 per KW. So, again,
they are not going to be cheap. So, it's
a good option. Well, it's a lot of
demand. It's a lot of demand from data
centers and hyperscalers and I provide
you some of the numbers for the current
capacity here in the US and well
estimated capacity is going to be
doubled by 2030 well almost 200 gawatt
so that's a sizable amount which is
needed just for data centers kind of but
there are many many other requirements
for uh the electricity [snorts] and I'm
not going to talk about too much about
nuclear batteries again if you have
questions well Charles colleagues know
much more about that concept fascinated
concept cept I'll have the picture at
the end of that and I'll I'll I'll make
some statements uh but also uh kind of
coming back to sustainability coming
back to realism so for example last week
I got this question so we work a lot of
the financial company asset management
company and one of the big investors
sent me a clip from the some Indian
newspaper which states oh look Chinese
are developing ship which will run on
thorium and that ship uh doesn't need
refueling and so that is going to put uh
the Chinese shipping uh at the
comparative advantage and so well kind
of that's kind of the worry for India
because well that also can be used in
nuclear submarines and so on and I've
started digging kind of to the story of
to thorium and kind of indeed uh it was
a successful uh announcement uh out of
China uh that they were converted to
uranium 233 Uh but well once you start
digging into the details looking at the
economics you start realizing that well
even the statement from that entity
which has done that successful test they
said oh the first demonstration plan is
expected to be like in 2035 and that the
first demonstration plan will have a
capacity of about 100 megawatt thermal.
So kind of which is 30 megawatt
electric.
You need all these kind of take kind of
all these grandio statements uh at the
granite of salt and try to understand
where's the reality how much difference
that indeed is going to make where
things are going to be uh going on uh
because well uh as you will hear uh
during the next presentation uh well by
that time we will be done the fusion so
Dennis will tell you uh all about that
fusion uh is going to be commercial by
uh I'm going to make some of the
comments. But again, be careful with my
comments. I already warned you. It's
like in the mirror, right? The objects
may appear closer than you think. So my
statements may appear more sarcastic
than the their reality are, but you
always need to kind of have a very good
dose of realism.
Okay. So how we do in addition to
telling nice stories and so this is kind
of the story how we put the numbers
behind our statements. uh we have the
model which is called the EPA model. So
if you're interested working with us, we
will be more than happy. We are working
with many many energy companies uh
financial companies, asset management,
other other companies where we try to
make this type of a projection. So I
showed you the outlook. Well, this is
the tool which we used in order to
produce the outlook and it captures a
lot of things and we use that for many
applications
and we are connecting that not only kind
of to the economic side but also to the
physical side where we see well what are
the impacts on the water use what are
the impacts on land use what the impacts
on air pollution what's the impact on
temperature sea level and vice versa how
that impacts the economics back so there
are many dimensions which we can try and
understand well both in terms of the
physical resilience but also in terms of
the transition risk which you may face
if you are trying to develop a strategy
for your particular country or your
particular company and so mostly what we
do we are doing this uh assessment of
future technologies so most of the work
which we do is we're trying to
understand okay what's the story with
direct air capture so is again picking
up on Iceland is that experience in
Iceland is representative or maybe they
have such a good uh uh geothermal
resource which makes this a unique cost
experiment uh which you cannot really
put uh into other locations. So if
you're going to put that into other
locations like Canada, well you needed a
lot of weathering and other things which
in Iceland well they don't really need
to do. So a lot of things like that
where we try to understand what's
realistic, what's not. How to
decarbonize hardtopate sector. So uh
Charles mentioned uh steel making well
we are doing trying to understand a lot
of pathways which are related to that.
So hydrogen sustainable aviation fuels
many things. So I wouldn't be able to
cover uh uh all of these topics but you
have my email there. You're going to
have slides if you are interested like
Charles we can send you tons of
references more than you will be able to
read but kind of that's the the work
which we are doing which we are
producing. So moving on uh data centers
that's the hot topic that's kind of the
question which we are getting right and
left what's the energy use and so kind
of this is our assessment again which we
are going to provide in our upcoming
outlook where you see well it's not true
it's quite sizable amount if you're
going to take a look at that number 3700
terowatt hours well that's the amount of
electricity generation currently in
Europe so basically you are going to
power data centers in the same amount
which you cover covering Europe not
European Union the whole Europe and so
kind of another point which is important
on this well where we currently see the
data centers is US and China and
immediately you're thinking about a lot
of geopolitics oh what about Europe what
about India what about other places and
again there are many many reasons why
that is happening but even more uh
important story how that is going to
affect the economy, how that is going to
affect the labor force. Are you going to
replace people or is it going to be
substitute? How productive you are going
to be? Where the productivity will be
increasing? Is it going to be in
services sectors in other sectors? So
there are still many questions which we
are still trying to answer. But well, no
matter how you look at that, the
requirement for energy from data centers
are going to be huge.
And it means that well if you want to
attract these hyperscalers offer them
stable and cheap prices and they will
come. They will be more than happy to
get to there. I'm not going to go too
much about uh these diagrams again
that's going to be publicly available in
a week or two. These are from our
outlook. One point which I want to make
take a look at the middle picture. It's
just India and China. And take a look at
that bar which is kind of the lowest bar
that's coal. And so the story when you
are trying to say you want to
decarbonize the world you want to have
net zero for the whole world you need to
solve that and that's a difficult
difficult task to do what to do about
coal just in two countries and so well
if they are not going to make progress
the overall progress is going to be much
much harder to achieve and this is our
story for accelerated actions where you
see that well that call is going down
much more renewables but all that will
come at a cost and so you're going to
reshape certain things you're going to
reshape other things. Another point is
the story for natural gas which is also
somewhat different in the rest of the
world between these two scenarios and we
have all these projections for our all
regions. So here I just put that for
three regions but kind of we are going
to release the data for uh all our
modeling regions but uh on the other
side the story for wind and solar for
renewables is bright regardless of the
scenario. So it means that most of that
is not driven by incentives a lot of
that is driven by economics but another
point even in the very aggressive
scenario it's not just wind and solar we
need other options for many many reasons
uh for global power generation
and then uh the important part whenever
you are talking about the
degarbonization
it's not just what governments can do
it's not just what companies can do.
It's also how you and I are going to
behave, how consumers are going to react
to these incentives. And this is very
important. What is our willingness to
pay? It's nice to talk about some
company which needs to decarbonize,
which needs to move to clean hydrogen or
something like that. And another point,
how much shall we willing to pay for
that? And here is the story. So kind of
very very nice story. uh you know the
name Mark Carney. He used to be the head
of Bank of Canada. When he was at the
Bank of Canada, he created something
which is called well carbon tax in
Canada. So he was behind kind of doing
that at the federal level. Then he moved
to Bank of England. In Bank of England
he created something which is called
NGFS network for greening financial
system. He was he made very powerful
speech why central banks needs to pay
attention to that. So he was behind that
and then he became the prime minister of
Canada on his first day on job which
happens to be April 1st. So those of you
who know the meaning of fool's day kind
of see the irony. What did he do on his
first day of job? He killed the carbon
tax in Canada. And so why? because we
are not doing very well in terms of
communicating
why we are doing that, how much
expensive these things are going to get
and where's the political support. He
didn't think that it's a bad idea
because he was behind all these
instruments but he has to deal with
political reality. So again the lesson
you need to know about the technologies
but you also need to understand how
people are going to react to all these
policies. Where is that fine line? And
the fine line in Canada, he killed the
consumerf facing carbon tax. He didn't
kill the industry carbon tax. And the
idea is well the consumers probably will
not realize that they are still paying.
It's just in very indirect way. So kind
of again the story is whenever you're
talking about how you want to
incentivize actions, you need to do
something like that. Why is that?
Because distributional impacts matter.
And so this is another uh area of the
research where we are trying to
understand how different income groups,
how different demographics, how
different regions are going to be
affected and that is the information for
support of actions, how you are going to
provide the incentives those who are the
most vulnerable.
And the answer to all of the
decarbonization may be different again
depending on what kind of industry
you're talking about uh and what kind of
fuel. So the I like this particular
diagram from the US government. Uh and
you can see that well US government can
be very useful for particular things at
least well to produce this very
informative diagram where kind of what
they try to do they try to put icons
well where do we see the answer which
kind of the fuel might be a good idea.
You also can see that well this is from
2023 and if you're going to take a look
at longhaul heavy duty trucks you see
that they were still quite optimistic
about hydrogen. I think if we we will do
it right now probably we will put one
more icon to battery and one less into
hydrogen but can again the story is
you're not going to have a solution
which fits all the needs. you really
need to understand where is the market
where you can apply and where you go and
especially kind of these R&D priorities.
Another interesting story about that
report which is listed there. So we have
done a study for sustainable aviation
fuels. It was done by uh kind of uh at
the request of Airbus and Latam
airlines. So the several countries in
Latin America. So Brazil currently has a
mandate for sustainable aviation fuels.
is it just transferred into law and kind
of there are some uh additional
information about that and so we have
done a study so I've spent a lot of time
in all of these capitals talking to a
lot of uh policy makers where we were
trying to educate what's the story
behind sustainabation fuels I did the
presentation when we released
preliminary results in the middle of
2024 and we showed the costs we showed
the feed stocks we showed the impact on
aviation and I got the reaction at the
meeting so had presented at at IATA at
IARE kind of major CEOs of airlines and
in middle of 2024 the reaction was no
probably you're too pessimistic no the
reality is much brighter so so yeah it
we will learn kind of cost will go down
I did exactly the same presentation in
the middle of this year more or less to
exactly the same group and same numbers
I didn't change any number I showed
exactly the same thing and I got a
reaction. No, no, no, no. Sustainable
fuels is much much harder. No, you you
are too optimistic. So know the reality
because they start learning. They start
seeing how much that is cost and what
are the impacts. And you can see that
the perception is also changing for what
is doable, what is not doable in
particular industries. So couple of
concluding slides. I see that claus
already looking at me nervously kind of
that we need to finish. uh so it's many
applications where we need to understand
and that's why you don't really uh
looking at particular technology in
particular sector but you're trying to
understand what are the competitions
where are the synergies uh where are the
things uh where you can also use the
same learning and apply that into
different regions or different sectors.
So kind of many things uh and many
answers and many opportunities and again
to kind be a little bit more optimistic
and this is hopefully a nice segue to
Denny's presentation. So I'm not sure if
he's going to show this spark diagram.
Uh this is the plant which uh he and his
team is building uh very close by a
spark facility. uh and uh why uh I feel
like I can put this picture because we
have done a study where we uh did the uh
economic analysis uh what is the value
of fusion in the decarbonized system and
so we issued the report there is a
mighty report uh on the fusion uh but
also that report uh was liked by
international atomic energy agency they
said oh we want to have that chapter and
put it into our outlook so if you're
going to take a look at IA world fusion
outlook you will see that well they're
using our projections in terms of the
what would be the value of the fusion in
trying to decarbonize the society. The
picture uh on your right is that nuclear
battery. So again uh fascinating topic
uh kind of try to talk to our uh nuclear
uh department specialists uh again they
will talk to you probably endlessly for
many many hours. How good is this? And
then this last picture is another uh
good thing which we are trying to uh
also understand what's the economics of
that. So what I'm trying to kind of
represent there is natural gas
pyrolysis. So whenever you are producing
hydrogen through pyrolysis you have a
lot of solid carbon as a product. So you
don't really need capture CO2 in a
gaseous form but you have the solid
carbon. And so the story is can we find
a use for that solid carbon because if
you're really talking about hydrogen
production at scale you have too much
and you don't really know what to do
about that. And then this is these are
another uh things which we are trying to
understand is well how we change the
property that you can convert that into
construction material.
Well, then you're replacing the
traditional cement and reducing all the
emissions and which are associated with
processing and kind of producing of
cement. In addition to that, well, that
can serve as a battery. So, think of the
wall where you can charge your phone or
think of the parking lot where you can
charge your EV. So again a lot of things
which are none of projections currently
but which can be a gamecher and again uh
you need to understand well what are the
niches with whom you competing where you
are going and if we are going to get at
least one of these somewhere close to
the reality where we will be able to use
that in the near future. So then
hopefully we will be living in the world
like this. So where we have this
wonderful world where I'm pretty sure
one way or another we will have to get
to that world but I'm not sure where and
when because definitely not by 2050 but
the things otherwise will go much much
worse that the public the customers us
will require much more action and sooner
or later well all these aspects of
sustainability will have to come to the
same place where we are talk about
emission reductions where we talk about
making sure that we have secure systems
and making sure that we can afford that.
And so if we can merge all these goals
together, well that's where we are
trying to quantify what it would take,
what is the cost, what are the actions,
what are the incentives and you are here
well creating all these pathways. So if
you have wonderful technologies which
you want to test and try to see how that
is going to fit the picture, well please
contact us and we will be more than
happy to address them. Here I'll stop.
Thank you.
>> [applause]
>> WELL, THANK YOU VERY MUCH, SERGE. Is
there Sergey? Is there any questions to
this? Because this is quite an
incredible picture.
Ah, Charles, you don't need a mic. No
question. Last year, China
hours,
US four, Europe 2.4.
DNS at an incredible rate of China's
virtually all energy technologies in
terms of deployment. Does anything the
west do except technologies have any
impact
on carbon dioxide emissions because
there's a 900 lb gorilla over there and
everybody else is down here. I know
that's a very politely incorrect
question but every time I go check I
remind you of this.
Well, so you are exactly right and so
that diagram shows that if we're really
serious about the global action, if we
are not successful with making sure that
China and India are moving much faster
than what they are currently doing, uh
that's why those trajectories are still
sticking. And so yeah, Europe can
decarbonize to zero, but if the rest of
not just China and India, well think of
Africa while they're still lacking
access to energy in many places and it's
still a question what kind of energy
they are going to get. Southeast Asia.
So most of the natural gas actually
projected to be used in Southeast Asia.
So because well these are the mark these
the market. So coming back uh where the
optimism you mentioned that China is
leading in all the technologies they're
also leading in clean technologies right
so again we can question what is the
real incentives but they are pushing all
these alternative technologies where
they're saying to the rest of the world
well you were fantastic in producing
your Mercedes and Audi's look but our
BYD is much better car and so this is
much more sustainable and they are
beating They're competing they out
competing many places where we see that
is happening and name oh you mentioned
nuclear right so you mentioned kind of
uh carbon capture you mentioned uh wind
solar well traditional things so a lot
of things which are going to be driven
by China uh China is actually very easy
country to project at the same time it's
very difficult country to project why
it's easy read their fiveyear plan you
know what they are going to do why it's
difficult because after five years you
don't know what they're going to do and
so kind of we kind of know where they're
going we know their story we know the
reasons uh but I fully agree uh the
story where US where Europe might
influence things in a big way is again
coming back to data centers how AI is
going to play in this thing is the hype
who knows at this point there are many
questions about that but if that is
going to change things in if what is
going to change things in the big way is
where we are going to go with artificial
intelligence and how we are going to
apply that for the economic purposes.
>> Super. Any other questions?
And I have a very loaded question. So I
mean when I look at your slides there
seems to be an urgency really to act.
Why are nobody is moving in that and has
the urgency to move forward?
>> Well, very simple answer because
whatever alternative
typically it cost more money.
>> Mhm.
>> And so we all do not like pay more.
That's again that's why unless uh Dennis
is going to be very very successful in
very cheap fusion and sorry for picking
up on Dennis many many times but well
the kind of it's a enormous weight on
your shoulders to provide cheap
electricity to the world and so this
type of the breakthrough where you are
going to provide similar service or even
better service at a cheaper price that's
where we can see where we are going to
move much much quickly. Okay.
>> And otherwise well we are talking to
like governments in Africa, Latin
America and others they say yeah we care
about the emission reduction we care
about climate change we want to do
something but there are 15 other
priorities which are on our agenda. So
we need to make sure that's why it's
sustainable. It's not only about
climate. You need to provide a
sustainable answer to uh this d the kind
of
>> re really really uh important topic and
uh it doesn't help that the current
attitude from the current administration
is changing the dynamics quite
dramatically.
>> Yeah. So you mentioned the last slide
that we have conductive self eating
cement. Yeah.
>> When do you think we might be able to
solution available to scale up?
>> Well, I'm not going to name a company
name. So, currently we have a project
where uh they produced that carbon
block. Uh it's tested here at MIT. Uh we
are trying to understand the properties.
We are trying to understand how useful
again this is still at a very very small
scale. And the same story what Charles
is saying well kind of realistically if
you have something something in a lab
and when you have the full scale uh
industry it's at least 10 15 years at
least. So that's when we might see
something like that.
>> Super. Thank you very much Serge. Uh,
okay. Thank you. [applause]