Good afternoon, everyone.
On the afternoon of
Friday, July 30, 2021,
I stood outside
the emergency room
entrance of UT Southwestern
medical Center in Dallas, Texas.
I'd been there for a few hours--
not an unexpected amount of
time to spend at the ER--
while my sister and I waited
with our mother for a visit
from her surgeon.
A year earlier, she'd had a
bilateral mastectomy, performed
at the height of the COVID-19
pandemic and nearly 19 years
after her first breast
cancer diagnosis.
Our visit to the ER in
2021 was about eight weeks
after a second
eight-hour surgery
that was the direct result of
the prior year's mastectomy--
this time, for a quick check to
examine a troublesome incision.
Mom's surgeon released
her with instructions
to come back the following
Monday for a surgical cleanse,
and I set off to
retrieve the car.
As I stood waiting for
the car to arrive--
$5 valet parking for patients
is a nice side benefit
in a state with so much land
available for parking garages--
the valet attendant
started chatting with me.
After a few innocuous
comments, he suddenly asked,
did you take the COVID vaccine?
I replied, yes, absolutely, and
so did all of my family members.
And so began a
fascinating conversation
that included tales of
government conspiracies
and plots to track
citizens based
on devices included in the
vaccine, and even a connection
to monkeypox.
I decided not to tell him
that if he was worried
about being tracked
by the government,
he should put down
his cell phone.
[LAUGHTER]
At one point, the
attendant posed a question
that he undoubtedly thought
would carry weight with me.
Answer me this, he asked--
how did they manage to
develop a vaccine so fast?
My response--
because practically
the entire biomedical
world, from academic labs
to multinational
pharmaceutical companies,
started working on it.
Imagine the global problems
we could solve if only
we worked together to do it.
My name is Kristala
Jones-Prather.
I'm the Arthur D. Little
professor and department
head of chemical
engineering here at MIT,
and I am also a class of
1994 undergraduate alumna.
In my time as a student
and a faculty member,
I have come to see that
MIT is an institution that
is collaborative by design,
with our infinite corridor
representing endless
possibilities,
and our connected buildings
and hallways serving
as a physical reminder of
the lack of true boundaries
between our disciplines.
After all, the beneficiaries of
our scientific and technological
advancements,
including my mother,
who participated
in a clinical trial
after her initial cancer
diagnosis in 2001,
that, I learned 15 years later,
established the standard of care
for adjuvant hormonal therapy.
These patients are not concerned
with the fields of study
or the affiliations
of the inventors.
And so as we launched the
MIT Hills Collaborative,
we do so with the intention of
tackling big problems by asking,
what if?
And working together across
boundaries and barriers
and even institutions
to find the answers
and deliver solutions.
What if detection of
diseases like breast cancer
could be made easier, less
invasive, more accessible,
and more comprehensive?
Could this lead to earlier
detection, better health
outcomes, and greater
patient survival?
What if we really work to
understand the unique dimensions
of women's health, with women
being disproportionately
affected by autoimmune and
chronic inflammatory diseases?
Could we see new
human tissue models
giving way to novel
physiological insights
and new paths for
effective treatments?
What if we tackled ovarian
cancer in a fundamentally
new way, fusing knowledge
gained from basic immunological
sciences with novel
engineering approaches
to delivering immunotherapies?
Could we leverage
the partnerships
of academics and clinicians
to change the outlook
on this disease.
What if we thought
about education
in a radically different way
by working not just in research
labs but also in the communities
where epidemics take hold?
Could we incorporate
the social scientists
to foster a deeper understanding
of the challenges associated
with the adoption
of new medicines,
and develop new approaches
to more deeply understand
the many dimensions of health?
In this session,
you'll hear from four
of my amazing
colleagues, each of whom
is using interdisciplinary
approaches and collaborative
partnerships to ask and
answer these questions.
As you listen to
them, I hope you're
inspired to think about the
possibilities, the promise,
and the hope that
their work represents
to reflect on the patients,
perhaps some well-known to you,
and others who may remain
nameless, that would benefit
from the achievements yet to
come, and to consider if and how
you can contribute
to these missions.
Oh, and yes, my
mother is continuing
to live her best life, having
spent Thanksgiving week
traveling in Australia,
thanks, in no small part,
to a continuous community
of scientists, physicians,
and engineers who never
stop asking, what if?
[APPLAUSE]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Nobody knows your
body like you do.
Imagine spotting
dangerous diseases way
before symptoms arrive.
Protecting yourself by
detecting yourself is the goal.
- So this variable, non-invasive
ultrasound patch is specifically
for early breast
cancer detection.
- Professor Dagdeviren has
been working with her students
for six years on a
wearable breast monitor.
Because it uses ultrasound
waves instead of radiation
to create an image, the
monitor can be used regularly.
This invention
inspired her students
to create smaller, even
less-invasive silicone
patches that can scan
for other cancers.
- Wearable technologies will
grow rapidly in the near future.
But in the far
future, they will be
one of the most powerful
tools that we will
be seeing in our daily life.
[AUDIO LOGO]
[PLAYBACK ENDS]
So we create that far future
right here at the MIT Media Lab
by blending media,
arts, and sciences.
Specifically for my group, we
are focusing on women's health.
And we create technologies
for female technologies,
which I often called femtech.
And let me tell you why by
giving three dramatic facts.
80% of autoimmune
diseases are in women,
and we still don't
understand why.
Heart disease remains
the number one cause
of death in both genders,
yet women wait more in ER
to be treated.
Women were excluded from
clinical trials until 1993.
Hormones were
given as an excuse,
and which means there
is a massive data
gap in hormone health.
And since mice don't
menstruate, how can we catch up?
To catch it up, in my
group at the MIT Media Lab,
we create devices which
are organ-specific.
These devices can be thinner
than your hair fiber,
and implantable like a needle,
can go in the deep brain,
and do neurological
explorations and stimulus.
And at the same
time, these devices
can be directly worn on
your largest organ skin
to do hormonal drug delivery
all the way from face
to the abdominal skin
throughout the IVF process.
Or these devices
can be attachable
to your personal garments, like
your daily bra or underwear,
and they can detect your
breast cancer at an early stage
and/or monitor
your bladder volume
to better understand your
kidney health and wellness.
Let me give you an
example more in depth.
It's a wearable ultrasound
breast patch for early breast
cancer detection.
It's a technology that
was invented here at MIT,
and this device is non-invasive
and can be directly placed
in the internal
wall of your bra.
By using safe non-radiative
ultrasound technology,
this device can detect any
anomalies within subseconds,
literally by sitting
on your seats
and listening to
this presentation.
And this data is sent
to your medical doctors.
And your medical
doctors can tell
if you are supposed to come for
more sophisticated treatments
or screening at the hospital.
This is specifically
important for the women who
have barriers to this kind of
technologies in the rural areas,
and also for women
who are on high risk
and needs to do
periodic screening
to increase their
survival rate to up to 98%
And this is also important
because high-risk women often
are often diagnosed
between two mammographies
and decrease their
survival rate up to 22%
So with our technology,
what we are trying to do--
not only doing the science, also
creating stories behind that.
I'm not only doing
science at MIT.
It's a calling for me, and
it has a personal story.
I lost my aunt at the
age of 49.5 years old.
In this picture, she is Fatima.
She's very happy,
very beautiful,
and holds tons of
hopes for the future.
Whereas in this picture,
she is only 49.5 sick,
tired, and in pain.
The entire process was miserable
not only for her, for all of us
around her.
Despite the fact that she
had regular breast screening,
she was diagnosed
with breast cancer
and could survive
only six months
after this picture was taken.
So like my aunt,
many women suffer
from this devastating disease.
And the breast cancer
is the number one cancer
type among women.
And even the number is
higher than the combination
of other leading cancer types.
And more dramatically,
every eight women, one
will be diagnosed with breast
cancer during their lifespan.
And the current standard
screening tool is mammography.
It's painful, and
it's radioactive.
So you can't do it periodically.
You can't screen
your breast tissue.
And by the time you have
your second mammography,
by assuming the first one is
clear, 40% of high-risk women
develop incurable
cancer in between,
with the survival rate of 22%.
Imagine a world in which
your daily bra will
allow you to check your
breast tissue regularly
to increase your
survival rate up to 98%
That world is right here at MIT.
This is our product,
our technology.
It's a daily bra that you wear
with a wearable ultrasound
technology inside,
which can capture
the data within subseconds
with no skill operator needed.
And this data is sent to the
cloud and collect the data.
And by using AI and
machine learning,
your radiologist and doctor can
have an AI-supported report.
This is important because
current ultrasonography
technologies are handheld.
You need an operator.
You have to go to a doctor.
And oftentimes, as you can see
in the picture, they are bulky.
They have to press--
doctors needs to press against
your very personal part
of yourself.
And you need to use a
message [INAUDIBLE].
You need to clean up
afterwards, time consuming.
It cannot offer frequent
visiting, and it's expensive.
Whereas in our
technology, one scan
will cost less than
a cup of coffee.
And how it works?
We use-- anyhow, it doesn't go.
But anyway, we use inflexible
cables which can come all
together and print on a
biocompatible substrates,
which can go into your bra and
scan the tissue up to 260-degree
angle with 12-centimeter
information.
Why it matters?
Because our technology can
provide a resolution up
to 0.02 centimeters, which
is an order of magnitude
smaller than the
stage one tumor sizes.
With frequent screening, we
can enable early breast cancer
detection.
It matters because just in
US, we have 44,000 women lost
their life because
of this disease.
And the breast screening
is $30 billion,
and it increasing 30%
every single year.
With our technology, we can
increase the survival rate up
to 100% by decreasing the
medical costs by half.
So this was a dream
on a piece of paper
that I drew on the bedside
of my aunt just to relax her.
And even while she was in pain,
she was giving me feedback.
Now it's real and I can touch
people's bodies, skins, breasts
and their lives altogether
with my amazing students
at MIT Media Lab.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Good afternoon.
It's great to be here.
I'm Linda Griffith from
biological engineering,
and I direct the Center
for Gynepathology Research
here at MIT.
What I want to tell
you about today
is a new movement that
we're starting at MIT.
It's called the Move
Over, Mice movement.
And what inspired it is
the incredible challenges
we have creating
effective therapies
for diseases that
preferentially afflict women.
Now, they'll help
everybody, but they
are motivated by helping women.
Now, why do we want
to move over the mice?
Well, think back before
COVID, we had colds.
We had the flu, and then we
had that very special disease,
the man flu.
And you know what
I'm talking about.
Husband and wife get a cold.
The husband's in bed
dying while the wife's
taking the kids to soccer.
OK, everybody knows that story.
And if you look at the x and Y
chromosome, it's not surprising.
So many things missing from the
Y, including some immune genes.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, now so it's
biologically true
that men will get
sick-- this is proven.
They'll get more acutely sick.
But women stay sick
longer, and they
develop more chronic
autoimmune and
chronic inflammatory diseases.
They're the result of
multiple gene environment
interactions in humans--
very, very difficult to
study in mice-- and that
have provocative
links to the way
we reproduce and menstruation.
And so we can't really hope
to make a lot of progress
if we continue to study animals.
We really need to
study the patients
and replace our animals
with living patient avatars
and studies on patients.
Now, I'm going to tell one story
to illustrate the Move Over,
Mice principles.
About 15 years ago,
we started working
in a chronic systemic
inflammatory disease called
endometriosis.
And probably most people
have heard of this,
but it's when you
find bits of tissue
similar to the uterine
lining, the endometrium
growing, other places
like the abdominal wall,
invading into the bowel.
It can invade through the
diaphragm and get to the lungs
and so on and so on.
It's incredibly
debilitating, causes
pain, infertility,
vomiting, systemic sickness.
And we don't know what causes
it, but we do about 10% of women
after the age of 12 or so
will have this disease,
and it's very hard to diagnose.
Now, I wouldn't be here
talking to you today
if we had good
treatments for it.
Some patients respond
to birth control pills
or menopause drugs,
but a lot of them
have repeated,
repeated surgeries.
Now, I got involved in this when
a local surgeon, Keith Isaacson,
who's a fantastic
surgeon and clinician,
called me one day and said, I
operated on a 23-year-old woman.
It was her 10th surgery
for endometriosis.
And she got operated
on in that OR
there on the right
at Newton-Wellesley,
where we now collect patient
samples because I got together
a group of people, and we
started to study endometriosis.
OK, so what do we do?
Well, I'm not a-- we're not
the kind of engineers who
make devices or surgical tools.
We're biological engineers.
We study how systems work.
So we reasoned
that we could maybe
start to classify patients by
studying their immune networks
in the peritoneal fluid.
So we studied
about 100 patients,
did some targeted
proteomics, and we
were able to identify in
about a third of the patients
a particular inflammatory
network associated
with an intracellular enzyme and
immune cells called Jun kinase.
And so Jun kinase--
this is very exciting--
maybe if we inhibit it,
we could have a new
non-hormonal drug target.
And so it turns out, we go and
find out that there was a--
find these two papers--
that there was a drug
company, Merck Serono,
that had been
developing Jun kinase
inhibitors for other diseases.
And one of their amazing
scientists, Steve Palmer,
convinced them to do preclinical
models of endometriosis,
and that their
drug worked there.
Unfortunately, it
didn't work when
they licensed it out and there
went into clinical trials.
It didn't have the right potency
or patient heterogeneity,
whatever.
But the Steve Palmer
there turns out
to stay involved in the field.
So I got invited to give a
keynote talk at the American
Society for Reproductive
Medicine meeting in Hawaii
in 2014.
There was a hurricane, over
a foot of rain that weekend.
And who did I run
into but Steve Palmer?
So we sat inside, and we
talked about the future
of endometriosis drugs.
And he said, I'm leaving Merck.
I'm going into academia.
I'm going to develop new drugs.
But what we need to
get into the clinic
is we need human
efficacy models.
We need the patient on a chip.
We need a lesion connected
to blood vessels,
circulating immune
cells and all of that.
So you go do that.
Well, then, OK.
So the first thing we had to
do-- we had plenty of access
to patient biopsies.
And other people in the
field had figured out,
how do you make organoids
from these patient biopsies.
You can see the glands from
the endometrium on the left.
But what they were doing is
using some terrible reagents
to make 3D cultures of these.
They had something derived from
a mouse tumor to make the 3D
environment.
It degraded.
It was really not
great for the biology.
So we used our polymer science
and biological engineering
skills to design a
completely synthetic hydrogel
to support all the different
cell types in a lesion.
So you see here the
beautiful epithelial organoid
blue with green in the middle.
And the red cells are the
supporting fibroblasts
growing in this gel.
And labs around the
world have used this,
and it's now being
commercialized.
But of course, the lesion
has to be in contact
with blood vessels.
And we were fortunate that
our colleague Roger Kamm
had invented a way
to grow a vascular
bed in between two microfluidic
channels, as shown here.
And our student in the
movies not playing--
but if it were playing--
why is it not playing?
Our student Ellen
Khan had shown how
to flow immune cells
through that vascular bed
from one side to the other.
But what we had to do was
adapt this to accommodate
endometriosis lesions.
And so what we did is designed
a new chip, bigger with pumps.
And we put the vascular cells
and the lesions together.
And what you see, over a
six-day time lapse here,
you can see the lesions.
They're in the
green boxes growing.
And you can see
the blood vessels
forming from the vascular cells
to build a network of blood
vessels around them.
And there's immune
cells in there also.
OK.
So now we're ready to go.
We did our part.
What did Steve Palmer do?
He went to Baylor Drug
Discovery Institute,
developed a whole new set
of Jun kinase inhibitors
with NIH funding.
And then he licensed them to
a company called Celmatix.
He left Baylor.
He's now at Celmatix.
And here we are a few weeks ago,
starting the launch of a project
so that we will do
preclinical efficacy
testing with the Celmatix team,
Steve Palmer, and the CEO Piraye
Beim, and the MIT team.
Of course, Laura Bahlmann
actually does all the work.
She's a postdoc in the lab.
But this EndoChip,
there's still a lot
of things evolving about
how regulatory agencies view
this kind of efficacy data.
So there's great
conversation going on.
But no matter what, you have
to prove your drugs are safe.
And so we come into this project
with decades of experience
working with drug
companies on building
these kind of patient avatars
for drug safety, particularly
liver.
So I invented something
called the liver chip.
It's widely used.
Novo Nordisk has built a lab
close to MIT to interact with
our team on how to use this
3D liver model of human liver
for cardiometabolic disease.
We've done interacting organ
systems as shown on the right.
And smaller versions of them
are commercially available.
So we know we have
to get these out
into the wild in collaboration
with lots and lots of users.
And we have to also
build many other organ
systems similar to what
we have for the chip
and connect them together.
So our vision and it's
under construction
is a living patient avatar
core facility at MIT.
And Kelly Pate, the
head of the division
of comparative medicine,
is very on board with this
because she would like to
move some of MIT's mice over.
In order to do this, we had to
develop a whole new platform
technology.
What I showed you on
the previous slide
is about 10 years old.
So together with Dave Trumper
in partnership with Novo Nordisk
and a lot of other
partners, we're
developing all of these
for pain, for liver,
for chronic infection like
Lyme disease, gut microbiome.
And these are real
things that we
want to have on campus for
people to be able to use.
So I'll close there
and invite you
to come to the poster session.
If you want to hear more
about this and other diseases
we study, I encourage you
to join the MIT Move Over,
Mice movement and
be happy to talk
to you about it later today.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Good afternoon, everyone.
So I am a chemical engineer
who works in biology,
and I'm going to be talking
about how we can use extremely
small lasers to address cancer.
In our work, we
actually use alternation
of positive and negative
charge to build up
extremely thin nanoscale films.
And in this work, we've been
studying how we could take
an existing small
drug nanoparticle,
like a liposome or a
polymeric particle--
maybe it has a net
negative charge--
and positive and
negatively charged layers.
In this way, we can actually
incorporate a chemotherapy drug
in the core and wrap around
this nanoparticle other agents.
For example, after
positively charged layer,
we can put something
negatively charged,
like siRNA that can silence a
gene that enables the cancer
cells to survive that
chemotherapy drug, thus creating
a way to address
chemo resistance.
And one of the most important
parts of these layers
is that final layer,
negatively charged,
that enables us to have
a nanoparticle that
doesn't engage with other cells
but might be designed to engage
specifically with cancer cells.
So these are squishy materials.
I'm a polymer
materials scientist,
and we enjoy making
these systems.
But the idea is that we
can actually coat them
in a way that allows us
to direct therapeutics,
specifically to cancer
cells in chemotherapy.
And I like to compare
this to a Wonka Gobstopper
for anyone who remembers
what those things are--
[LAUGHTER]
--that have layers of
candy that dissolve
at different times, which
gives us a chance to regulate
how the drug is introduced.
However, when we became
really interested
in addressing ovarian
cancer, we found
that this approach
was not necessarily
the best approach using siRNA.
Ovarian cancer has been a very
difficult cancer to address.
It affects a large
number of women,
and it is detected late stage
because of the very subtle
symptoms that it provides us.
For that reason, although
a large number of patients
are able to recover after the
first chemotherapy treatment,
about 80% to 85% of them
will suffer a recurrence,
and that recurrence will
be a highly resistant form
of the tensor.
For that reason,
it would be really
interesting to have
an immunotherapy that
would allow this
cancer to be attacked
by the human immune
system when it comes back.
Unfortunately, there's
been little progress
in doing this
because there are not
a large number of immune cells
that reside in ovarian cancers.
So when we began
looking at this problem,
we started thinking about
making a nanoparticle that
would be extremely sticky
to ovarian cancer cells
but not to other cells.
And we did this by looking
at a library in which we
started with the liposome
and wrapped positive charge,
and then a range of
different negatively
charged stealth layers,
polysaccharides, polypeptides,
and a range of other
biomacromolecules, that
might be able to help
us with targeting,
as well as with getting
through the ovarian
space, this
intraperitoneal space.
And in doing so, we found
that there were a few that
were very interesting to us.
And those few actually
showed a very high affinity
for ovarian cancer,
whether it appeared
in the primary tumor-- here
we see a tumor lit up--
and the infrared
particle showing up
and a very nice
overlay, but also
in metastases within that
intraperitoneal or abdominal
space like this gut system.
Now, we found that
there were two that
were really interesting to us--
one of them, hyaluronic acid
actually binds to cancer cells
and gets taken up
into the interior
and releases things like
siRNA in chemotherapy drugs.
That's really interesting.
But we found
another one of them,
poly glutamic acid, a
very simple polymer,
that causes the
nanoparticle to stick
on the outside of the
ovarian cancer cell--
not great for delivering siRNA,
which has to-- on the inside.
However, it does allow
us to present something
to neighboring cells.
And we began to think about how
we might be able to use this.
I began to talk to my
downstairs neighbor
at the Koch Institute, Darrell
Irvin, who knows everything
about immunology and cancer.
And he was able to
inform about how
we might be able to use this
to deliver a cytokine, known
as interleukin 12.
IL-12 actually can
induce large amounts
of infiltration of immune
cells, in particular T
cells and NK cells that are
responsible for killing cancer.
So we decided to then
take our liposome,
attach that IL-12 the liposome
directly, wrap it in plus charge
and then minus charge.
And that minus charge will take
us to the ovarian cancer cell.
Deliver this into the
intraperitoneal cavity
and let this get presented
to neighboring cells, which
will eventually lead to the
generation of interferons
and the infiltration of T cells.
And we did indeed find
that we had enriched
T cell infiltration
in these layer
by layer nanoparticle systems.
In fact, when we looked in
mouse ovarian cancer model,
we found that there were
something like 10,000 or more
infiltrated T cells
compared to untreated mice.
And what was really
exciting is that we
found we could combine
this IL-12 treatment
with checkpoint inhibitors.
Now, it's worth mentioning
that the reason IL-12 isn't
used in the clinic today is
because it is extremely toxic.
It can also excite the immune
system in the bloodstream.
In our work, attaching
it to a nanoparticle that
is very specific to
the cancer allows
us to rescue that toxicity and
avoid any kind of side effect.
Checkpoint inhibitors
are typically
not effective in
ovarian cancer at all.
So what we did was we combined
IL-12 with checkpoint inhibitor.
And in this case, we changed
the immune microenvironment.
So now there are
immune cells that
can be impacted by the
checkpoint inhibitor.
And what we found remarkably,
was in this red line as you see
here, 100% of the
treated mice survived,
compared to all of
the other treatments--
checkpoint inhibitor,
which does barely nothing--
and any of the other IL-12
combinations that we looked at.
So we're very excited
about this work
and looking at how we can
take this on to clinic.
Now, I mentioned
that little story
about getting inside the cell.
With other collaborators,
Joan Brugge,
who is at Harvard Medical, and
Ursula Matulonis at Dana-Farber,
we've been looking at how we can
encapsulate inhibitor molecules,
again, so toxic that,
although they are together
very effective against
ovarian cancer,
they're also very effective
at harming the liver.
And in this case,
we encapsulated
these in a polymeric
nanoparticle
and used our hyaluronic
acid targeting system
to get this directly inside
ovarian cancer cells.
And again, we saw a
great deal of improvement
in ovarian cancer treatment.
So this theme of collaboration
is really important to us.
I usually show a slide of
all of the students involved,
and we have some incredible
students and postdocs involved
in this work, but I
wanted to point out
collaborators who have
impacted us in our journey
to address ovarian cancer.
I mentioned Darryl Ervin,
my wonderful neighbor,
who has informed us about
every aspect of the design
of these systems, and we have
worked together to develop it,
but we also have had this
wonderful collaboration
with Harvard Medical
School in Dana-Farber.
We're involved in breakthrough
cancer, which brings us together
with one of our
younger colleagues
at the Koch Institute,
Stephanie Springer, also
an expert in immunology
and tumor biology,
and Sohrab Shah at Memorial
Sloan Kettering, who is looking
at patient cells that are being
treated and determining changes
in the genetic
signatures of those cells
before and after chemotherapy.
If we can understand what the
outside markers of those cells
are, we can find
nanoparticles that can then
be targeted directly to
minimal residual disease
and treat them and excite
the immune response in them
using the studies that
Stephanie is doing.
And finally, we have a
wonderful collaboration
with my MIT colleagues
and colleagues
at Johns Hopkins with Angela
Belcher, Sangeeta Bhatia, Kripa
Varanasi, and Rebecca
Stone at Johns Hopkins.
And in this case, we're
reaching much earlier.
Intervention is really critical.
Ovarian cancer tends to be
detected at very late stages.
Angie has developed
nanoparticles
that are able to allow us
to see inside deep tissue.
And we are using our
sticky nanoparticles
to address being able to
detect those tumors and even
early tumors that appear
on the fallopian tube.
So with that, thank you.
And I'm really excited
about collaboration.
And I think that
this new initiative
is going to allow even
more of these opportunities
to take place.
[APPLAUSE]
Hello, my name's Bruce Walker.
I'm a physician scientist.
I've spent my career taking care
of patients and studying HIV.
And it's my great pleasure
to tell you about a course
that I teach to
MIT undergraduates.
Each January in
the intersession,
we select 20 students
from all majors
and take them to experience
an ongoing epidemic
to understand the many
dimensions of an epidemic.
We go to South Africa.
You can see from this
slide the staggering,
staggering prevalence of HIV
infection there in the areas
that we work.
40% of men and 62% of
women in the ages 25 to 44
are infected and will
need lifelong therapy.
It's in that context
that the students
get to see what it's
fueling, that epidemic.
We land first in
Johannesburg, where
we begin the didactic
portion of the course.
We incorporate a number
of African students
with the MIT
students, and we begin
to teach them where
HIV came from,
how it causes disease,
how the body fights back,
and how therapies are
developed, and why
four and a half decades
after discovery of HIV,
there's still no vaccine,
but we don't stop there.
We also teach them about how
policy and advocacy influence
the course of an epidemic.
Here, they're learning
from Edwin Cameron, who
was the chief justice of the
South African Supreme Court,
who presided over the trial
that led to the forced--
to force the South
African government
to provide treatment
to its citizens.
He's also a gay man, and
he tells the students
about the problems of
stigma and discrimination
that he himself
encountered and that
are so widespread
in that population.
We then go to Durban,
where we had participated
in collaborative research for 25
years with African scientists.
We helped catalyze the
construction of two research
institutes there by funneling
money from the United States
to support that construction.
The students get a chance
to see African scientists
and talk to them about the
opportunities and challenges
of doing research
there, but they also
get a chance to see ongoing
projects that are underway.
One of those projects is
called FRESH, probably
the most exciting project I've
ever worked on as a scientist.
Stands for Females Rising
Through Education, Support,
and Health.
And it has two goals.
One is it's an HIV prevention
program and poverty reduction
program geared at young,
high-risk women 18 to 23 years
old who are living in poverty
and because of that, are
at high risk for HIV infection.
But it's also a study
of acute HIV infection.
And essentially, we see
the women twice a week
for nine months, teach them
empowerment, life skills,
job readiness training.
And each time they come in,
we do a finger stick blood
draw to identify anybody, who
despite our efforts to prevent
infection, has become infected.
The students get a chance
to talk to these women
and understand what
it is that's fueling
the 10% per year
incidence rate of new HIV
infection in that population.
They also get a chance to see
part of the empowerment program,
which is teaching these
women, most of whom
have never graduated
from high school,
teaching them how
to use a computer.
Most of them have never
touched a computer before.
And we conduct the
study at a shopping mall
to avoid stigma that
would be associated
with coming to a clinic
or to a or to a hospital.
And the course really
completely changes
the lives of these young women.
They come in with no real
sense of hope about the future.
And they leave having
found their voices
and feeling like they really
can make a difference.
Of the 3,000 or more women that
have gone through this course,
80% of them we've been
able to get employed.
And the unemployment
rate is so high
that these women
would really never
have had an opportunity
to become employed,
which moves them out
of poverty and reduces
their risk of HIV infection.
We also take the students
to local hospitals
to understand
delivery of care in
a resource-constrained setting.
Here, talking to
a young man who's
infected not just with
HIV, but also with TB,
and the challenges in
a resource constrained
setting of delivering care with
a highly contagious disease
like tuberculosis.
We go deeper into the rural
areas of KwaZulu-Natal
to teach them about delivery
of health care there.
This is a pharmacy.
And out on the table, you
see traditional medicines.
80% of South Africans will go
to see a traditional healer
before they go to
see Western medicine.
We've been collaborating
with traditional healers
for the past seven years.
And through a process
of building mutual trust
and respect, we've been able
to implement with them an HIV
counseling and testing program
so that when they see patients,
they now not just rely on
their traditional medicines,
but they test them
for HIV and refer them
to us if they need therapy.
So the students see
those traditional healers
and hear from them how they
were called to that profession.
We also introduced them
to infected mothers
and their infected
babies so that they
can understand how those
mothers became infected,
what the factors were
that led to that,
and understand how
difficult it is to raise
a child who's HIV infected.
We also go deep into the
rural areas of KwaZulu-Natal.
Here are some of the students
with a mobile clinic.
This is a catchment area where
the Africa Health Research
Institute has been collecting
data on the whole population
of about 160,000 patients once
a year on every person in that
region.
And the students go
and make house calls
with the RE investigators
and then come back
to the Research
Institute and use
that data to answer questions
that they have generated
through the research that--
or through the visits
that they've made.
At that point, we're so
far north in KwaZulu-Natal,
that there are no local
hotels to stay in.
So we take advantage of that
and take them to a game park
where there is a hotel.
And there they do problem sets
in traditional MIT fashion,
comparing and contrasting
different epidemics, cetera.
And they then present those data
to one another as a wrap up.
In between the problem
sets, they go on game drives
to see another dimension
of the African landscape.
And finally, when we
get back to Durban
to the airport to
head back home,
I think it's fair to say
that their lives have really
been changed by the experience.
They realize that epidemics
are multifactorial.
They're not just the realm of
medical doctors and scientists.
But really, every
discipline has something
to offer to help
come to a solution.
They also learn that
it's really important
to learn from the
patients themselves
and to understand
what the barriers are
to care that prevent
some of the things
that we develop from ever
being actually utilized.
And what I learned year after
year from teaching this course
is that MIT students are
incredibly motivated, incredibly
bright, and
incredibly passionate
about making a
difference in the world.
And I think we as educators
have to show them those worlds
and facilitate their
involvement in that.
I'd like to finish
just by acknowledging
MISTI and IMES and the Reagan
Institute for their support,
as well as
philanthropic support.
We set up this
course specifically
so that it would not
cost any of the students
any funds of their
own because we didn't
want economic considerations,
to prevent anybody
from taking the course.
And so I thank
you for listening.
[APPLAUSE]