all right welcome everyone we're going
to go ahead and get started with
tonight's uh session for our diverse
views at MIT Sloan my name is Terell
Williams and I serve as the associate
director for diversity equity and
inclusion I am excited about tonight's
uh uh panel and this discussion that
we're gonna have with this Dynamic group
of slony uh Morgan will you be able to
kick us off happy to um so much to say
I'm so happy to be here um I so I think
the short story is I'm originally from
Texas I will always them Texas but I've
lived many places so those of you who
are coming um um from not the East Coast
I'm happy to share that perspective as
well uh right before Sloan I was in the
greater New York area um so that's kind
of where um I ended up moving from when
I got to Massachusetts uh I uh was a
part of the stone fellows class of 2023
um I graduated last year and I'm happy
to talk a little bit about what that
Journey for me was like um as one of I
guess well the only executive um program
representation here but um my Pivot had
a lot to do with focusing on operations
infrastructure on the real estate side
wanting to switch Industries into the
automotive sector and focus on that
infrastructure side um and then kind of
shift out of the mode that I had been in
kind of starting up operations teams to
scaling up operations so that was um
kind of my focus while I was on campus
um am I missing anything Terrell is is
there anything cover happy to get into
the questions then thank thank you thank
you ka would you kick us off next of
course hi everyone I'm Ka Thomas I
graduated from the leader from Global
operations program last year and I so I
got my MBA and my Master's in civil and
environmental engineering before Sloan I
was a software engineer um lived out in
the Bay Area I'm originally from New
York though so all the East Coasters are
presenting and after Sloan I when I
graduated I worked as a consultant um
for a year and now I'm a Senior
Solutions engineer at a startup um based
in Raleigh North
Carolina thank you and then namni can
you wrap us
up happy to so hey everyone good evening
uh my name is Nami I am originally from
Lagos Nigeria um most recently before
Sloan I lived in Houston Texas so I'm
like um Morgan I've lived all over the
place um so I was an engineer by I have
a background in engineering ultimately
decided I wanted to do a career switch
and so um attended the SLO program I was
a um NBA class of 2022 and now I am an
equity research associate um at partam
investment so I did a total career
change I'm in finance now so happy to
get into the
questions thank you thank you so I'll
actually be in room moderator for the
time being but I will be able to uh
pivot as we do well here at Sloan so the
first question I have for our panelist
tonight is could you just kind of give
us a you know a a glimpse into your
thought process of why you chose Sloan
as your particular uh degree option for
the lgo program SLO fellows and our MBA
programs respectively do you want us to
make up the order do you care about the
order yeah you can go ahead you can kick
us off Morgan okay happy to so um very
very very long journey um about four
years after undergrad um you know I'd
been in the workforce I was thinking
kind of what did I want to do next and
um it was clear to me because I was
already working in kind of the gr space
of starting up an operations team in
healthcare um that I wanted to have the
training um of that comes with the
business degree and as soon as I knew
that uh I knew that I wanted to go to
saloan or not go to business school at
all um I was very focused on Sloan I
mean in a kind of weird way um I visited
probably over four times I applied to
the diversity uh weekend and ended up
staying uh with a with a host um I knew
nearly everybody in the admissions
office um and it kind of was me checking
in every year and they were like are you
gonna apply and I'm like oh I don't
think I'm ready yet I don't think I'm
ready yet and um you know fast forward
about four and a half rolls later um I
think covid happened and I kind of sat
with this you know this was M this is a
dream um am I still serious about this
dream um you know I I and I I decided
yes right that MIT was the place for me
and so I just wanted to see if they felt
the same way and so I applied um and and
then ended up matriculating um just
after I I'll say the core covid season
so um starting in the fall of of
2022 um is when I entered um I guess
I'll just say two things on the on the
why slan um
I I felt very strongly about the way
that Sloan trains
its students and probably equally as
strong about like the type of student
that is at MIT at large right and so um
I think if you haven't heard it already
it
is very much true that this is a place
of kind of Silent doers and I felt like
that was in line with who I am um I love
tackling kind of the messy problems uh
with very talented people and have um
just so much excitement when when I'm
with those kinds of people and so I
think to find people that are kind of in
their own Lanes just achieving really
phenomenal things and wanting to
collaborate with them and feeling like
it could not only be true in my cohort
um across Sloan but also across MIT um
felt
like how could I how could I not take
advantage of this opportunity right so
as soon as I was admitted um I knew it
was a go um I think the other thing that
came became apparent for for me over
time is obviously when I was first
considering this path um four years out
of undergrad looks very different from
14 years later right so um I think it
ended up working out perfectly for me I
think I knew much more about where I
wanted to go uh professionally I was
much more assure of myself and I think
business school then was more of like a
gut check that you know because I had
never had the formal
training was I where where did I line up
right like is this kind of a self
assessment to come and back to school
and and see like you know where do I
need to kind of fine-tune things what
are my strengths where do I lean in um
and and so the slow fellow MBA ended up
being perfect for that right because
it's kind of the NBA but it's
fast-tracked it's with um it's it's like
without like the internship summer right
you're basically taking a very similar
um set of courses and um the
conversation for me was at the perfect
level right so like people who you know
may be coming from a non-finance
backgrounds got to take Finance with
people that are CFOs right or PE as as
myself an operator like like I got to
help people that are highly technical
right in thinking about how do you do
ops management and so um loved that the
conversation was at that level and I
also am very partial to The Faculty um
that we had uh leading us guiding us and
and happy to talk more about that
because that was actually um my greatest
networking tool was The Faculty
so thank you for sharing Morgan so Kai I
want to pass it over to you because I
know LG was a very Niche program given
the fact that it's a doal degree with
our School of Engineering so could you
give our audience a glimpse into your
thought process of you know why you felt
that LGL was a great fit for you
definitely so as a software engineer I
think I was a little bit intimidated by
MBA programs to be honest I because I
didn't have that business background and
so when I was looking into programs I
only really looked at dual degree
programs program that combined
engineering and business because I felt
like that was more of a comfort zone for
me because I had that technical
background I think when I looked at
different programs the reason why the
lgo program stood out to me so much was
because MIT was the first institution to
have a program like this to have a
business Master's and Engineering master
program combined and because of that it
has the kind of most uh you know large
Alumni network of these type of folks
and so for me I think that was one of
the most important thing that wherever I
went had a robust Alumni network and
Alumni network that was not only robust
but that was actively kind of engaged
and wanted to still like talk to
students help students give back and I
saw that in the in the ljo program that
there was a lot of willingness to um
still be engaged uh with the program and
still be engaged with students and help
and and that to me I think was a
differentiator and why I was interested
in in joining
LGL thank you K and and Nam could you
wrap us up as it pertains to your
experience you know within the pre-mba
phase and you know what stuck out to you
about SM of course um so first off I
mentioned that I have an engineering
background and what engineer
does um but um all jokes aside though
what the main thing for that stuck out
to me was um I mentioned I am Nigerian
and so mits work in Africa and also um
just the alums uh the Alumni network and
the reach of uh MIT was what really
pulled me in and then um once I started
to get to know the school door and get
to know like people who went there and
uh familiarized myself with the program
uh the one thing that also stuck out to
me was um the teamwork so MIT focuses
heavily on teamwork so you will hardly
ever do anything by yourself you're most
likely going to be in a team working on
different projects different uh problems
very very tough creative problems and so
I think Morgan mentioned this earlier
just meeting very low Eco people who are
incredibly smart and just coming
together to work on things together that
was a huge um uh draw for me so the
culture of MIT the reach of MIT uh the
work they do in Africa was what really
uh pulled and also the Alumni network as
well so as I got to talking as I got to
start meeting and talking to different
people who went to MIT I got to know of
the phrase that was um a SL never lets
another SL fail and MIT folks take this
very seriously so I'd reach out to
people who were in you know different
levels of um leadership positions in
different organizations that I was
interested in uh while I was recruiting
and they went to MIT as as soon as they
saw the uh mit.edu I usually would get a
response um because once again it's like
hey you know this person went to slow
how can I help what can I do so just all
those factors were very instrumental in
drawing me in and ultimately uh making
me um choose to attend
MIT thank you all for sharing I know one
common thing that we've heard within
these particular responses is the
community at loan and how big that's um
that how big that is here at our
particular institution um so could you
kind of dive into uh the community at
Stone and you know talk about the things
that you were involved in as a student
and how you you know have uh inclusivity
as it pertains to the black business
Student Association or the Africa
Business Club and anybody can take that
one okay so I could start off uh so I so
I was a member of both
organizations um and so
essentially both organizations to me are
kind of intertwined in the sense that um
you know we have the Africa Business
Club but a lot of the members are also
part of the uh of bbsa and so um we had
you know just different meetings but Mo
most importantly I think what I got out
of it was really the community so
meeting people from you know um uh
different backgrounds like technical
backgrounds but then you share the same
you know um life experiences and things
like that and then you guys all come
together as a community and like really
helping each other it could be anything
it could be in recruiting it could be um
assignments what classes to take um from
the people another resource that I found
where from the second years when I was
the first year um what classes did you
guys take you know what what do old
exams look like you know can you help me
with this you know how how did you know
um um like pass questions I'm I'm
struggling in this class I need some
help can you tutor me can you help me
and they were usually very very helpful
like instrument telling me like you know
passing classes well and I I mentioned I
was a career switcher so leaning heavily
on people who had um Finance experience
to talk about like the experiences in
recruiting um what do I need to know
things like that so those were very very
instrumental and helpful in me
ultimately achieving my goals and then
once I became a second year I was also
able to try to help out with the first
years as well so really the culture of
giving back is also um something that is
very strong in the MIT community in the
MIT black black or diverse
Community yeah to just to follow up um
to what n was saying I was um on the
exec Board of the
bbsa um and so I think being a part of
that that Community especially from a
leadership position I think it was
really special to be with the other exec
board members and to try to figure out
like how we could create events and
opportunities and things for the
community um and just figuring out like
what the community needs how we can
especially I think like you were saying
that first year second year relationship
is really important and so like okay how
can we you know once you become second
year it happens so fast but you're like
okay how can I get back and support the
first year what resources that can we
you know put together to make sure that
they're well supported and so I really I
thought it was a really special
experience for me and I think um being a
part even as an lgo I never felt like I
you know I wasn't a part of the the MBA
Community I was you know just a member
as as anyone else even though you know I
had my engineering experience as well so
it was it was a great uh experience
being a part of the executive board and
be able to have that leadership and be
able to kind of pass the torch of
building Community for for the students
that were coming
in yeah and I'll Echo that you know I
think because I didn't have two years
right um I was I think Hy hper focused
on the um number of people that I wanted
to meet right and so one of the ways
that that was kind of extended outside
of my particular program was to join
right so I was I was also in the black
business Student Association um I was a
member of swim um and then I was also
very focused right on this pivot so um
basically every Mobility Club you can
imagine I was on the leadership um team
for um the space Club um and and the
automotive club and
um yeah I think I think those are all
the groups
yeah thank you off for Sharon there's a
a wide range of options for students to
be involved in while they're on campus
so there's over 80 plus clubs at Sloan
there are some affinity and identity
groups that we mentioned before with our
Africa Business Club our SLO women in
management or bbsa but also there's some
IND specific clubs as well so if you
have a specific area of interest there
are there is a club here for you and if
we don't have it you can go to Our Salon
Center to be able to create a club here
as well so there's a lot of uh community
in within our particular program to
ensure that students have support as
they're navigating the social aspects of
school um versus the academic so that's
a great pivot for our next uh question
that I have so more so focusing on the
curriculum So within these three
different programs the curriculum looks
uh extremely different so can you all
talk about you know the curriculum at
loan and how it was built for you and
talk about the flexibility that it
offered as it pertains to the the the
MBA program and SL fellows I know K the
lgo program wasn't as flexible because
given that you have to have two degrees
but can you just kind of talk about ways
that you've the classes that you've
taken and how you were able to kind of
explore why you
ATL okay so I could us off again um so
for me uh the curriculum was the the MIT
curriculum was something that you know I
found attractive because essentially
it's you have your first semester you
have your four classes that you take
your first semester and after that the
world is your oyster so you build your
own experience and so for me um coming
from an engineering background um a lot
of the um the classes I took were all
like brand new to me like taking like
econ Finance but I was hyperfocused on I
knew I wanted to um do a career switch
into finance and so a lot of the classes
I took were Finance um Rel related
classes and what I really liked about
the MIT
curriculum dmit curriculum and classes
um was compared to like um other schools
um other business schools a lot of the
MIT folks were people who were like me
like where were all career switchers so
a lot of the classes like these are
Finance professors who are like world
renowned um Finance professors but they
more than happy to break it down for you
where there's no question literally no
question is a dumb question and and even
if you feel like it's a dumb question
and you ask it once again the people at
MIT are so low ego hump like no one is
is judging you no one is like oh my God
that was such a you know stupid question
or anything like that so that was very I
was able to get very comfortable in
classes where I was so um I built my own
um my my build my own experience was
focused mainly on taking um heavy
Finance classes however MIT is also a
huge huge huge um entrepreneurship Hub
and the entrepreneurial spirit is very
very uh big at MIT so there are lots of
class classes and labs and things that
you can take as well um to be able to
like you know grow in that area so I
took some as well also um where where um
for one of the classes that I took um
you have a real life like real world
problem so um one of the the classes I
took was um we had a project where we
had to work with uh ab and Bev which is
one of the biggest like uh beverage
manufacturers in the world and we had a
real project where they had a real
business problem in um the for their um
South America operations and so we
worked on it during the semester and
then during our break we actually got to
travel to Mexico City and spend three
weeks in Mexico City where we were
working on real life like problems
meeting with um their senior leadership
in in South America learning what their
issues were like um and coming up with
solutions for the for the issues that
they were having so these are like real
world challenges or real world problems
that we got to um work on and solve um
uh through through classes at MIT so
that that to me was um something that
was very attractive when I was going
through the application process as
well thank you for sharing I know
experience your learning is really big
here at Sloan especially the the action
learning Labs that we have but also the
the the opportunity to kind of get in
the the weeds and be able to actually
experience it um in real time um so
Morgan or KY did you all want to share
about the curriculum that you all
experienced um sure um so I think uh a l
many similarities but some differences
right so um when you know it says that
the program is a year it is literally SE
65 days I mean people were coming and
right it's just as International so
people were coming you know just before
Memorial Day weekend that's the last
weekend in May for those of you not
familiar um probably still finishing
their jobs through June 15th right so it
was very very tight and um
another I think unique part of the
program is that um it is it is skewing
differently now but it has historically
been the case that for many of the
executive programs um the students are
sponsored which means that while we do
have a lot of flexibility the people
that are really going back to their
employers probably not in the same roles
but at least going back to their
employers um there's an expectation that
they have a certain type of training
right um I was not in that camp so I had
a lot of freedom um and what that meant
then was our core our so summer we're
basically by ourselves although we
started to notice that there were lgs's
in the hall um and so it's very quiet um
and then you kind of Hit the rest of the
campus uh return in the fall right so
that's uh a major core we're going
through um kind of two terms in the span
right because we have basically if if
you think of it as a quarter system we
split our summer in half so it is very
intense that for summer is our core we
have eight classes that we're taking and
then um come fall and spring there are
really only two requirements where we're
all together and otherwise you have your
your pick um I uh you know because I was
kind of pivoting right so unique in that
I was not sponsored and unique in that I
was trying to Pivot in 365 days um it
kind of made life a nightmare um but it
was worth it right so um you know
usually you would do that right by not
just taking the classes but starting to
have some of the experiential learning
maybe even an internship to kind of get
get some experience on your resume to
prepare you for those conversations with
employers um I didn't have that luxury
of time but um Sloan offers kind of the
ability to do independent studies and so
it was Visa that that I negotiated an
internship or Consulting it was really
um with Mercedes which again came
through faculty and allowed me to get
some like real experience to say like
okay these are this is how I'm thinking
about these problems I'm starting to
understand the industry I have the
experience now and so I was I was in a
better position right when it came um
time for recruiting to talk about that
and so that was that was critical right
for me to have that independent study um
many of the kind of transportation and
Mobility related courses were outside of
Sloan um so I loved that I had enough
time and flexibility to venture into
some of the other departments and um and
then I and then I again I was there for
a year I was very committed to meeting
as many people as possible and getting
as much um you know of a of a spectrum
of of training as possible POS so I also
took classes at Harvard um and and that
come that kind of rounded out kind of
what I couldn't find at Sloan or or
elsewhere at MIT I was able to take at
Harvard and so happy to talk about that
from you um it's an interesting one in
the winter uh but it it was worth it
yeah and I can uh share a bit I think
the slone fellows um and lgo program has
some s similarities in terms of that
schedule so we start in summer as well
and so we we had eight courses over that
summer and so we kind of had like two
course semesters one course semester
during the summer where we're doing
engineering and um some some business
courses but it's more like a engineering
kind of core during that summer um and
then during the fall of course we have
the core with the rest of the mbas which
is focused on those main business
experiences I think to with the lgo
program there is still flexibility
although like you have to take your
engineering courses simultaneously with
your MBA courses so it it is a mix but
you still have the freedom to decide
like what your elective are and so I was
able to actually do the sustainability
certificate um during my time and so I
did the sustainability business lab
which is the action learning lab which
is a great experience got to work with
um a company there on a sustainability
project and so you still in the lgo
program get the freedom same freedom and
flexibility to take any electives that
you're truly really interested
in thank you all for sharing and
something that we get um in the
admissions office From perspective
students is the fact that there are
certificate programs affiliated with the
MBA and the LG program as well as some
fellows uh have you all had did you all
have any experience with the certificate
programs while you were here and if so
could you all share which program you
participated
in yeah I can uh start there so the
sustainability certificate is um what I
chose to pursue and that's through the
MIT uh slow sustainability initiative
and uh that was a great experience for
me I think sustainability is something
I've always been really interested in
and um one of the reasons why I also
decided to go to grad school was to kind
of learn more about that space and so
through the sustainability initiative
they really kind of just give you a
really well-rounded training of
understanding sustainability from a
business perspective from a societal
perspective um and also just how you can
solve real problems um in the space
through the business lens and you do
this through coursework um you are
required to do action learning learning
lab as well so you get that actual
practical experience of doing a
sustainability project with um with a
company but then you also get the
community aspect so the other folks who
are doing the sustainability certificate
you build community with them as well
and that for me was a big part of it
because you learn from each other
everyone's coming from different angles
there are folks who are interested in
energy there are folks who are
interested in food there's folks who are
interested in cpg and like across this
just across every kind of sustainability
angle you can think of and so it's just
a great melding of Mind of folks who are
passionate about something and so I
think that's what's cool about their
certificate programs and you're you have
a a group of people who are interested
or passionate about a topic but they're
all coming from it at different angles
um so I really appreciate
that so I will actually add something so
while I I personally did not get a
certificate what I do know about MIT is
MIT is one of the only programs that
like I think has the um the
sustainability certificate and the MIT
sustainability certificate is one of the
only certificates that is actually uh
recognized like industrywide like no
matter what industry you're going into
if you mentioned um you have a
sustainability certificate a lot of
different um organizations have their
own sustainability like uh tracks so
like say I don't know if you worked at
GE for example they have like some
sustainability training that they you
can do um at GE however if you get an
MIT one it's usually industry um it's
recognized industry F just wanted to add
that awesome so we we've talked about
the curriculum we've talked about your
your paths to MIT Sloan so now we're
going to talk about ways that you can
leverage the alumni community so could
you all share what your experience has
been like as an Alum but also while you
in the program what ways did you
leverage the alumni community maybe as
it pertains to internships or maybe as
it pertains to just you know just
brainstorm sessions the ways that you
were able to have postgraduation uh
success so just kind of talk about the
ways that you Leverage The Alumni
network yeah I can start um wow okay so
I mean from the
moment uh so our orientation is in April
before we start um from that moment we
are meant to be recruiting and
developing a career plan right so um
it's really from that moment we already
meet kind of the outgoing cohort um and
whoever stays in the area because many
people end up staying right in Cambridge
or or the Greater Boston area um so
already I felt like I was walking
into like a network that was much larger
than my class um and that didn't stop
right so you know as I spent more time
and um you know spent time with the
career advisor spent time with people on
campus um was like always connected with
you know classes further and further out
um so that was a constant I mean I I
think there probably other than the
holidays there wasn't a week where I
wasn't talking to some Alum to
understand how why what right did you do
to like turn this experience into
something that worked for you um so I
think that was just that was just a very
much a part of the the the ethos right I
think it's and and I think that's
important actually I think you know
while it was MIT or nothing for me um
because I also understand that like
business works because of the network I
was worried about the size of MIT um
that being said the the size is an
active size right so it's almost more
meaningful because I think the way that
people show up the you know what what is
the SLO there's a actual slogan that's I
think
um you about no well for us though like
no fellow Left Behind is what it's is
what our slan is and and that is that
that's it's it rings true through and
through um and so you know from a just
feeling like people had my back in terms
of like how I should spend my time at
Sloan how I should start thinking about
what I'm going to do after Sloan um it
was it was probable right so I was not
walking only into a an immediate
Community right of 115 people I was
already walking out into the world with
like MIT at my side um and a very very
real example of this is um so when I
took this current role um I ended up
moving to a new place um I am now in
Michigan and I knew no one um you know I
so I was like okay I know my colleague I
mean there's obviously there's a big
Ford presence um many of the Fords also
went to Sloan uh right so there were
lots of connections there already but um
it was the the PE how I ended up finding
a home how I ended up finding like all
of my like Health Care needs and social
needs and um just like even where to you
know where's my local post office uh was
because I was literally hosted by a a
Sloan fellow who who did not know me um
off of a connection right so immediately
just opened his home to me um allowed me
to spend weekends there as I was like
commuting back and forth between New
York and Michigan trying to make this
move real um I I knew nothing of this
person before um an email um interaction
and like just I mean felt safe felt like
we had known each other forever um but I
and and and now you know the the the
kind of passing it down is like I am
meant to recruit more people to Detroit
so um you know I think it really it is
not you know just words it really is
action um it's really the mind and hand
thing that it might um brings to life
and and I can tell you it's it's it's
it's real in so many
ways yeah I can try in in terms of the
alumni I think um for me I pursued
Consulting um after graduating Sloan and
definitely relied on Alum there as well
so like hearing what their experience
was doing practice case interviews um
and really you know folks are are will
to to take their time um out of their
busy busy schedules to to do a case
interview um and so that I I really
appreciate it and I think oftentimes
folks are just willing to take time for
a conversation and I think a lot of us
are talking about career switching and
so like that was a career switch for me
and so people are always willing to just
chat with you about kind of what their
what their career currently is and give
you perspective of like you know how you
could potentially break in and so I just
think that uh a um are very approachable
um for Sloan and I I can't speak to
obviously any other programs but I I
really appreciated that and and I felt
that I never really felt like I couldn't
just reach out to someone and say like
hey like I'm you know I'm at Sloan as
well and see that you graduated even if
they graduated 10 years ago or something
you know folks are are willing to to
connect with
you uh rounding off uh Echo everything
Morgan and K have said um for me I
really leverag the Alum Network during
my recruiting um Journey so it was
really like finding like I would find
the company that I was interested in and
I'd find an alarm in the company and I
just reach out just be like hey you know
I'm trying to make this switch from
engineering into this I noticed you're
at this company can you spend 15 minutes
of your time and usually response like
once again once you they see the at
mit.edu it's like what can I do for you
like how can I help so it's like you
know I'm trying to do this I'm trying
okay well I mean my company's not
hireing right now but I know someone
else who is and then you just kind of
you just start to to Branch out and your
network just continues to grow and grow
from there so I can't um speak highly
enough of the MIT uh Alumni network and
just their willingness to help and so
once you then become an Alum you're also
willing to because you know what the
expectation is now and you know what the
people who went before you have done and
so now there's that expectation on you
as well so for me personally once I once
again see at mit.edu always happy to
help my phone line is always open
willing to always take 15 minutes of my
time to help out another
SL awesome this great and I know with uh
paying it forward nature here at Sloan
um could you all kind of share some
additional information as it pertains to
like generating more representation of
the black and African-American Community
Ed loan and how it extends not just
within the NBA program but out to all of
our programs so just talk about ways
that we're you know advocating for more
representation within our program could
you highlight any mentorship programs
that we have in um in an in an active
State here at
SLO so I could I could start since I
left off last time um so uh so while I
was while I was um at MIT and even now
to a certain extent
um what as a member of both uh bbsa and
um and uh ABC both organizations had uh
buddy programs and Buddy systems so what
that means is um for folks who are
applying to um to the programs they
could reach out to the leadership of the
of the of both um uh uh of both clubs
and say Hey you know I'm very interested
in learning about this you know can I be
connected to someone who's like you know
a current student um who is willing to
like listen to my story um help me with
like interviews help me with my um
application things like that and so that
was very helpful for me coming in like
because when I was coming in um I didn't
know about this uh but once I got in I
iMed it like okay hey this is something
we have to do because we need to
increase our representation so usually
like there would be different rounds
obviously like you have you know round
one round two round three and so every
round um or in each round you know take
a few uh prospective uh candidates and
just kind of you know talk them through
my experience listen to their story help
them refine their story things like that
and I wasn't the only one doing it like
there were multiple like I think all of
the um all of and it wasn't just even
the the black community all the
communities of color you know um the
latinx community um the South Asian
Community everybody had something
similar and so um once again but it just
goes back to the um Spirit of SL of
giving back so that was a thing like so
just mentorship of like prospective um
candidates and as a second year also
giving back to the first years as well
making sure you know everyone is good no
one is struggling in classes what do you
need things like
that we going to K El you wanted to add
to
that I I think that the Buddy program
definitely was probably the first thing
that came to mind there um I think that
there's also oftentimes informal members
uh mentorship that happens um a lot so
it doesn't always have to be do formal
programs um but for the LGL program
specifically there is a mentor program
where you get matched um with and Alum
and they did really try to emphasize for
the uh women and diverse like students
who are part of the lgo program trying
to match with lgo alum in that same area
and so and there is that as
well awesome awesome so uh I see we're
about at 7:45 eastern time so I want to
give us an opportunity to be able to
Pivot to you know some questions from
our audience that came in in the Q&A so
we do have a few that came in um one
that I want to highlight is specifically
about the uh the black experience and
the Boston area so all could you all
kind of share like what your experience
was like on and off campus as somebody
um that may have migrated to the Boston
area whether it's for for graduate
school or somebody that was just for
that was there maybe for undergrad can
you all talk about the experience for a
black person within the Greater Boston
area and ways that you found community
at Sloan but also outside of
Sloan I I can speak to that um so G
given that I'm from New York I think New
York and and right have their rival and
so I didn't know much about Boston and I
had heard similar things in terms of it
being potentially unwelcoming but um for
fortunately that that was not my
experience I think Boston is much more
diverse than people um give give credit
um to it and so I think exploring the
different communities kind of outside of
Cambridge going to Roxberry Dorchester
you know having some Haitian food food
and um just getting outside of the kind
of Cambridge bubble is really important
and I think you'd be surprised at at how
diverse it actually is um much more than
I think people people give it credit
for oh sorry Morgan CUO not much more to
add I mean I think honestly it's what
you make it right I I just you know if
you if you haven't moved a lot it will
always be a shock I think if you if
you've moved a lot I think you know the
Pains of like what does it take to like
find your Necessities what does it take
to find a broader Community I you know I
think to the point of the bubble like it
works for and against you I think you
don't have to experience great Boston if
you don't want to um in some ways you
are protected as a student um but if you
are interested in it I think there's a
lot to learn and it has a lot to offer
right it is one of the major US cities
um you know I I kept like my gym
membership that I had at home so like
then I had like a whole gym crew that I
was meeting in Somerville it's a place
of like this is probably not even right
anymore but when I was in underg like
had at least 27
universities just near city center right
and so you know in terms of just like
the the population of people that are
you know are probably around your age
um certainly intellectual in nature um
um and and probably also transient so
like are trying to figure out like how
do I navigate this like you're not alone
in that right so both within MIT and I
think at large there's just a a broader
um student and professional population
um of color and not right that's
accessible to you um uh if you if you
love sports I mean it's again if it's as
a major city it has things that will
bring people together like sports like
music right like like the Arts um um I
definitely recommend going to the museum
they have like an after dark thing you
know once a month which is like akin to
like the New York like culture that I
loved so like I sought those things um I
was also partial to New York so like you
know the food is the food but it's it's
survivable you're there for a period of
time uh rounding us off so um for me I
spent most of my time in Cambridge
because I mean school was in Cambridge
and there's a lot of stuff to do in
Cambridge um but post uh uh business
school I've stayed in the Boston area
and like I think K mentioned this
earlier like everyone has like you know
prior to moving here I'd always heard of
Boston not being as welcoming as you
know as it can be um first of like
Cambridge is the total like opposite of
what I was expecting like just once I
got there just the number that the
diversity in Cambridge ising you meet
people from every background you can
think of and I think Morgan also
mentioned this where um there are so
many schools in the Boston area where um
even expanding out of Cambridge you're
still meeting a lot of like younger um
like-minded individuals who are here you
know to get an education or early in
their career and so it's easy to network
and really build a network uh from that
so I I will say that about the Boston
there great and as somebody that
migrated here from this
uh coming here from Florida about 2 and
a half years ago um it was a coaching
shop for me but being able to come here
with a significant other was a huge help
for me I know everybody doesn't have
that luxury but also being uh a part of
you know uh a fraternity um that also
was a big help being able to kind of
Leverage that a particular community so
there's a lot of ways that students can
get connected if they have things that
they're affiliated with also one thing
about Boston I think that's you know
relatively unknown is the fact that the
the there is a very a very large Melting
Pot here as it pertains to different you
know cultures so when I was
transitioning here I didn't know that we
had such a large Haitian population or a
large K Verdian population being able to
find those particular communities within
Boston like K mentioned in terms of you
know Roxberry and Dorchester being able
to have these different Pockets where
you can kind of find a sense of home or
a sense of comfort also Boston has a
very rich black history uh here as well
so being able to you know to tap into
you know where Martin Luther King went
the school or being able to you know
have the black her is within the area
but there's a lot of black history here
that I don't think people really know
about and the the the country was you
know technically built on the backs of
black people so we have a strong DNA
within the city of Boston so I want to
be able to have students tap into that
versus looking at it from you know a
hesitation perspective or maybe from a
deficit perspective so there's a lot
that Boston has to offer and we also
mentioned ways that we have integrated
um uh culture within the the program so
one thing that we do um within the Sloan
program is have course 15 dinners where
students are actually going out in the
community and having dinners not just
with Sloan students but students from
all across MIT so able to kind of build
those networks so the the the best way
to kind of have those conversations is
over a good meal of food and our our
Student Life office does a great job of
being able to kind of find um hidden
gyms within the Boston area that people
find uh really comforting and being able
to have that Community Support so um I
want people to you know feel empowered
to you know consider SL as an option and
don't you know at Boston as almost a
negative aspect being able to say okay
what is Boston doing to be able to
attract me within the program and I
think having those small pockets of
communities will be helpful and I think
we need to do a better job of amplifying
those voices within the Greater Boston
area so I you know no we're getting
close to time but I want to be able to
transition to our um next process so I
want to give a action item for our
panelists something to think about as we
go through these next slides so if you
all were to give a a piece of advice to
prospective students as they going
through this process uh just you know
you just kind of think about that for
now but I'll come back to you all to
answer that particular question sound
good awesome so I want to um highlight
the uh upcoming application deadlines
that we have for our variety of programs
um our applications are now live and you
can see those corresponding dates here
um as a token of our appreciation
tonight we will provide all attendees
with an application fee waiver so if
you're interested in one of these three
programs that were mentioned tonight we
will apply that particular email that
you use for this particular session and
apply that for your particular
application if you don't see it um when
you're applying let us know we'll be
able to add that for you so you don't
have to worry about that application fee
if you are interested in learning about
more diverse views at MIT Sloan we have
a host of other events that'll uh be uh
throughout this semester throughout this
month um we'll also have our uh visit
days that are kicking off later this
month as well we will have our diversity
visit day uh next month so if you all
are interested and coming to the
Cambridge area being able to experience
what it's like to be in a slone class
interact with our black business Student
Association our Hispanic Business Club
and our Africa Business Club we
definitely encourage you to make the
trip if you can that that visit day is a
great uh sense of confirmation for a lot
of people that you know see Salone as
option but sitting on the class does uh
uh hit different in a way being able to
kind of say okay I can see myself here
as somebody that may be from a technical
background or from a non-traditional
background we want to be able to have
that opportunity for students to be able
to have that sense of uh comfort and
then the last thing I want to talk about
is ways that you can learn more about
diversity and inclusion here at Mi sloom
and our black business student Community
you can visit their websites here and we
will uh be forwarding uh the information
from tonight's session about the the the
uh the leadership so feel free to reach
out to them I know we mentioned tonight
the Buddy program so that's a great
resource for students that are going
through the perspective application
Phase to be able to reach out to our
first year and second year students to
talk about ways that they can make a
more competitive application as they're
going through the particular process so
I want to come back to our panelist to
wrap up for tonight's session so just
you know just share a piece of advice
that you would give to a prospective
black applicant as they're going through
this particular
process I can start I think the number
one thing that's important in the
application process is to really bring
your whole self um to your application
and I really mean that I think that
that's something that
slown missions really uh takes into
consideration and they put a lot of work
into building a really unique and
diverse class and the experience of
going to Sloan like I've met people from
just so many different walks of life
that I never experienced before even
being from New York where you know I've
met so many people from different places
it wasn't until Sloan where I think I
just learn so much just because of how
much effort they put into really
building a unique um in diverse class
and the only way they can do that if is
if they know like the true personality
and experience of the people applying
and so I would say really bring your
whole self especially that video
component bring your whole true self you
know your personality to that and and
don't be afraid to to bring yourself in
that
application okay I could jump in um my
advice is apply because I know a lot of
different people who they you know it's
it's MIT you know you're very
intimidated by the name you're
intimidated and then you look at like
you know all the different scores you
look at you know the GPA requirements
you look at all these things and it's
very easy to get in your own head and
Rule yourself out before anybody has a
chance to rule you out so the if you
don't apply or if you decide to rule
yourself out you're never even going to
give the admissions uh panel a chance to
even review your application um and so
my piece of advice is put your best foot
forward um lean in strongly lean in
heavily on like the the different um
budy programs and the and these type of
um events where you get to hear from
different people lean into those
experiences so that way you can get to
know like um have some connection with
uh the institution and when you're
applying you're able to put your best
foood
forward so I think my advice is is
probably a a a combination of the two
but I think it's to know what you want
to get out of the program um and maybe
that's true of any business school but I
think I think the I think having that
Focus means that you will be very clear
about
then what at Sloan is available to help
you achieve that um and what experience
you bear that tells that story right and
I think once you package that that
becomes just your compass right through
the admissions process and even through
the program I mean even if you're here
for the the the longest program I mean
really being at Sloan is like being a
kid in a candy store you time time could
fly by and you could not do anything
right and so I think it's just so
important that you get out of this
experience not only that you get in
right but that you get out of this
experience what you are so um strongly
seeking right now and that can only be
true the clearer you are and I'm not
saying you need to know your next title
or your next role or your next company
but I am saying you need to be very
clear about what it is you want out of
this right what it is for yourself or
what it is for your community what it is
for your career what it right like what
if it's a skill set based thing whatever
it is let that be your right your guide
tell your story around that figure out
what at Sloan complements that and what
you you can do to again contribute to
that community and and Achieve that at
the same time