And um our next speaker is Eric Bosworth
from Eversource Energy and he has
collaborated with Eversource in the
Framingham site acquiring temperature
data down the bore holes.
>> Awesome.
>> What's your time?
>> Hi, I'm good. I I am the uh privileged
individual that gets to run anchor here
before lunch. So, thanks for bearing
with me. Um, for those of you that I
don't know, my name is Eric Bosworth. I
work in the clean technologies
department at Eversource. And for better
or worse, I have had the privilege of
overseeing the Framingham project from
before site selection. So, I joined on
to the team to kind of oversee it as we
were figuring out where and how we were
going to do this. and all the way
through today uh when we are up in
operation with customers using the
system. So folks have talked about the
project a lot over the last day and a
half here. I I don't need to go over
Framingham necessarily. What I'm hoping
to do is bring the perspective of we've
had a lot of insight into what's the big
picture? What's the policy direction we
need to go into? How do we design a
system like this? How do we operate a
system like this? I'm going to bring you
the perspective of what happens when you
get out there and start tearing up
pavement and actually putting it in
because uh nothing really prepares you
for that until you're into it. And
there's certainly some some lessons
learned and scars along the way that you
pick up.
Here's a basic breakdown of kind of the
three main work streams that go into
actually building a shared thermal
network in a community. You've got the
ground exchanger. Brock was just talking
about drilling. Uh we've talked about
thermal conductivity testing and kind of
how the ground exchanger works. It's
pretty straightforward, but that's your
energy source. You're putting holes into
the ground. You're pulling heat out in
the winter. You're putting heat in in
the summer. That's what's fueling your
network. But the other pieces are just
important. You have the distribution
loop, the pipes in the street, the
service lines that you're pulling into
the homes. How do you move the energy
through the neighborhood? And then
finally, the building conversions. Um
certainly not third in importance here.
What are you doing to the building
envelope and how are you interfacing
with that thermal network? How are you
keeping your customers warm in the
winter, cool in the summer? And what
equipment is involved there? So, sort of
stepping through each of those, I I like
to start with main installation pipes in
the street because as a utility, this is
our bread and butter. Um, we put in
hundreds and hundreds of miles of this
HDPE pipe every year. We know this. We
know how to open the street. We know how
to fuse pipe. We know how to get it into
the ground. We know how to test it. Um
to the points that Mark brought up, you
know, making sure that the fusions are
good and the pressure testing is
appropriate and documented. Uh this part
of the project was, I will say, the
smoothest part from a timeline, a cost,
an execution standpoint. Our crews know
how to do this. We actually took crews
that had been putting gas pipe in the
year before, did a little bit of
retraining on them, showed them how to
stencil geothermal on the side of the
pipe, and they were off to the races.
They got out there and they installed
all of this mile of pipe plus all 38
services in about 2 to 3 months. It was
great. It was exactly as we planned it.
Um, similarly, the service lines, just
like a water service or a gas service or
anything else that you would pull to a
home, we dug a trench. There's two lines
in this case instead of one. So, we have
a send and a receive line, but for the
most part, it's all the same materials.
It's HDPE pipe that we're fusing. We're
pulling it into the home. We're putting
it into a pair of shut off valves on the
inside of the basement. And it feels
just like utility work. Even from the
outside, if you watched a crew doing
this trenching, um, repaving in the
street, you'd have no idea that they
were putting geothermal in. It just
looks like everyday utility work. So,
these two work streams. Great.
Fantastic. We understand them. We do
them all the time. They were easy.
Borefield drilling, not necessarily a
utility's forte. I think this is one of
the first times that a at least a gas
utility in the nation has drilled bore
holes. Um, and there were some lessons
learned. You know, Brock talked a lot
about this, so I'm not going to harp too
much on drilling specifically, but
there's questions about site layout and
what formation are you drilling in? How
quickly can you drill? How do you manage
your water and your cutings? We were
learning. We brought in experts. They
did a great job. They designed great
ground exchangers. They executed well.
Uh, but for us as the utility, you know,
it was more a learning opportunity than
anything. We certainly weren't out there
directing the drillers on how to run
their operation. We were letting the
experts do what they do best. And then
in the future, you know, we look at
Framingham, we potentially have an
expansion coming up here in the next
year or two, and we've learned some
lessons from the first time around that
we will apply the next time we go out to
drill a bore field. And hopefully we can
do it quicker, we can do it more
cost-effectively the second time around.
Um just to talk a little bit to the
pictures here there. There's a lot going
on, but um we did take advantage of some
of those nice deviated drilling
techniques on our project that you can
see here on the left and then on the
right that's what the manifold looks
like when you come out of a bore hole.
So once you've got all those holes in
the ground, you got to tie them together
with pipes. So you pull all of the
inlets and outlets together into a
single vault. You have a nice long
header for each of them. And that way
you can control the individual borehole
runs. You can turn them on and off with
valves if you want to. You can pressure
test them. You can make sure that the
system is on and running appropriately
uh before you cover it back up because
again, Mark mentioned this multiple
times, but you really, really want to
make sure that there are no issues or
leaks before you back fill these
systems.
The pump house, kind of similar to the
distribution loop, but this is the only
above ground structure on our system. We
chose to do it as a pre-fabricated
building. So, we came in and we laid a
foundation. We had as much of the
mechanical work and piping and
electrical done as we possibly could
beforehand and then dropped the building
down on top of the foundation
afterwards.
And really, all it does is it's got the
central pumps, it's got our control
system, and it's got a little bit of
backup in the sense that we have a
central boiler in there just in case we
need to add some heat to the system. It
was designed to not need it, but you
know, as a utility, the very first time
out, we want to make absolutely sure
that there are no problems with the
operation of the system. That comes back
to customer perception and could affect
adoption long term. So, you know, for
our project, it also now serves as a
very nice area where when we come out
and have tours, we can kind of talk
through some of the equipment involved
and how the system works. Uh, it's
really paid dividends to end up going
above ground in this case. We won't
necessarily always do that. You know,
looking to future iterations, we may
vault pumps. We may bury things if we
don't have the space to do it. Uh but at
least in Framingham, the pump house was
a critical part of the loop. Finally,
getting into building conversions. This
this has by far been and was the most
challenging part of getting a system
online and running. Having the loop in
the street, having it on and running, we
kind of knew what we were getting into.
It wasn't necessarily all skill sets
that we were familiar with, but we sort
of knew what to expect. Um, building
conversions are every single one. You
have no idea what you're getting into
when you get into that building. We
found mold, we found asbestous, we found
knob and tube wiring. You name it, we
found it in one of these homes or
buildings. And that may be somewhat
unique to the building stock here in the
Northeast. Uh, but it's a reality of
large retrofit projects. you're going to
have to tackle these types of problems.
So, from an execution standpoint, we
really tried to individualize it for all
of our customers, get into their home,
explain exactly what we needed to do,
how we were going to do it. We ran
ducting. We did about 15 to 20 main
panel upgrades in this neighborhood. So,
it wasn't just how do I put a heat pump
in. That's generally pretty
straightforward. You get the unit in,
you may need some ducting. You may need
to adjust the existing ducting in the
room, but the rest of the building is
important, too. Are we air sealing? Are
we weatherizing? Are we upgrading
electrical systems? So, the whole
picture ends up playing into what the
building conversions look like. And we
demonstrated virtually every type of
conversion as well on this project that
you can have. The good news is there's
equipment out there to tackle almost all
of it. Most of the residential homes
were using forced air systems. So we
came in, we put a heat pump in, we
distributed it with ducting and air
systems. The commercial buildings, we
had rooftop units that we could actually
just lift their old unit off and drop
their new unit on top of the roof and
reuse all of the existing distribution
system in the building. And then we had
some more niche applications, um, things
like console units that look almost like
one of those hotel air conditioners that
sit under the window. We put those into
a number of the uh the subsidized
housing apartments on this loop as well.
And just to emphasize that it's not
necessarily will it work, it's how do I
make it work with every single one of
these.
Finally, overall project management. I
talked a little bit about this on
building conversions, but um you know,
making sure that we were having a very
detailed and customer focused approach
through the entire project was important
too. As a utility, generally we stay in
the streets. We're putting pipes. We're
pulling them. There's a demarcation
point and everything downstream is is
usually the customer's responsibility.
Not in the case of this project. The
scope of our pilot approved by the
department was including all of the
building side equipment and work. So, we
had to manage that part of the project
as well. We were meeting with the
customers in the field. We were
explaining things. We were having them
look at exactly what was going in, where
it was going in. We were getting
feedback on things like, "I'd like the
ducting over here versus over there. Can
you box it in with drywall? Can you
paint it after the fact?" All of these
little details that make project
management very challenging, but it's
extremely important because at the end
of the day, I want these customers to
have a good experience. I want them to
like their new systems and I want them
to tell all of their neighbors about how
great it was as well because that's how
we grow the system and get adoption to
continue.
Sort of summing up the construction side
of things, you know, timeline and
parallel work streams. If I were to go
do this project again, there are a lot
of levers I could pull here for having
simultaneous jobs go on so that my
overall timeline could be shrunk. I
think in the second iteration, I could
probably trim about 25 to 30% of our
schedule off if I was going into it
knowing what I know now. Um, there are
always the traditional utility
challenges. You know, we ran into buried
infrastructure that wasn't on any map,
wasn't on any diagram, and you're
digging along and all of a sudden you
see a wooden conduit in the street. So,
you got to navigate around it. You have
to make some on the-job decisions, some
on the-ly, you know, changes to your
system. Those were manageable. There
were some geothermal specific
challenges. You know, the drilling went
well, but there was a learning curve
there. The geology, what type of
drilling we were using. We tried air
hammer, we did mud rotary. We kind of
traded off to decide what was exactly
the best way to drill in this specific
neighborhood. And then on the HVAC side
of things, you know, to this day, I'm
still helping customers dial their
systems in. So it's not necessarily as
soon as everything is installed, you
walk away and it runs perfectly. There
is definitely a period of adjustment and
improvement and optimization that you
can make. Um site access and scheduling.
This was actually something that ended
up affecting us quite a lot in terms of
overall project schedule, but the
reality is you're installing these in a
community. It's people's yards. It's
people's homes. It's school property.
And so when you're first planning the
project, you're not necessarily thinking
about, ooh, maybe they're not going to
let me drill or have access to the
school property in the fall as
everything is ramping up and students
are all coming back. Individual
customers, they go on vacation. They
have their own lives. They have their
work schedules. So, you have to really
work around all of the individual pieces
to get everything to come together.
Otherwise, you find yourself sitting and
waiting and saying, "Well, I, you know,
I guess I can't get access to the site
today. let's wait a week until I can and
that has impacts on the overall job. Um,
finally, I mentioned these, but unknown
building conditions. I'm going to
mention it again because it was uh it
was such a challenge on the project.
Really taking good stock of what
buildings are in your planned community
or planned area, understanding what some
of the common things that you may
encounter are, and having a plan for it
ahead of time. Um, asbestous remediation
delayed some of our building conversions
a good 3 to four months in this case.
Um, we got into specifically the the
lowincome housing apartment buildings.
We realized there may be some asbestous
in the joining compound and the walls
that they had used to construct those.
And it was about a four-month process to
test every single unit, document it with
the state, come up with a remediation
plan, have that plan approved, and then
have qualified contractors come in, set
up all of their air containment, and do
that remediation so that we could
actually install the heat pumps. So,
it's those types of things that when
you're in the initial planning stage, if
you know there's a chance that these
buildings may have asbestous in them, go
ahead and test it during design. come up
with your remediation plan. That way
when you're into project execution,
you've got it all baked into the
schedule and it's not going to delay
that particular part of the project.
Moving on a little bit to commissions
and operations because as I said once
the system is in the ground physically
that does not necessarily mean it's up
and running. Um a lot of lessons learned
and challenges here as well. These
screenshots here below are from our
real-time SCA system. uh you know there
was a great discussion earlier around
optimization and control and feedback on
how you run and operate one of these
thermal energy networks. That's what we
did. We had a SCADA system set up so
that real time any time of the day I can
see what my pump speeds are. I can see
my temperatures. I can see my pressures.
I can see customer behavior based on the
historic temperature trends. So getting
that system up and running was almost
step one before I could even add a
single customer. I wanted to be able to
see the system remotely in a in a
web-based SCADA. In addition to that,
borefield flushing, pressure testing,
getting air out of the system. These are
all steps that we had to take as we
turned it on, as we started the pumps
up, and as we added customer loads to
make sure that there wasn't any
disruption in service because the last
thing that I wanted was to add a
customer and then shut them down
immediately right there after and say,
"Oo, something's wrong with the system.
Hang on. let me address that and we'll
come back in a few days and turn you
back on. So, a lot of work went into
making sure that the system was on,
stable, free of air, running properly
before we could add customer loads.
And then on the building commissioning
side, once the loop is on and running,
now you got to turn the buildings on as
well. So, that followed a very similar
process, but it was about getting the
equipment in, making sure the electrical
work was done, the plumbing work was
done. You then have to pressure test
everything on the building side as well
because the last thing you want is a
leak in one of these pipes carrying
water and some glycol in this case
that's going to flood a basement, flood
a room. Again, the perspective there
from the customer, it's not going to be
a very good one if you have to come in
and say, "Sorry, I just flooded your
basement. I'm going to pump it out, but
let me try again." So, a lot of testing,
getting the equipment on and running,
and then opening those valves and
actually tying it into the main loop and
making sure that it's getting energy um
from the system.
One of the the challenges that I faced
is because we were reusing traditional
gas contractors, they had a perception
around how you should handle valves on
this system. In their mind, open valves
are good. You want every valve on the
system open because in a gas system
that's what you do. You open everything
up. You've got flow. You're great. I had
to go through that entire system and
check every single bypass valve that I
had because 75% of them were left open.
What that means is when I turn a
customer's system on, they're not
exchanging fluid with the loop. They're
exchanging fluid with themselves and
their systems very quickly cool down.
They shut off. They throw an error. So,
it's those types of things and
troubleshooting through the
commissioning that, you know, the next
time around, I'm going to be totally
sure every bypass on a system is closed
before I turn a customer on.
So, lessons learned, you know,
procedures and compliance. I I cannot
stress enough how important it is to
know what you're doing before you do it.
Have a documented procedure. Make sure
you check it with your engineering team,
your external engineers, experts in the
industry that have done this before.
have them look at it. They're going to
have some great feedback. Valve
positioning, don't need to harp on it
again, but it's very important. Uh loop
flushing and purging, you know, the
biggest issue that I have seen on our
system at least is air. There's a
there's a procedure, there's a flushing
procedure, but there's always a little
bit of entrained air in these systems.
And so getting it out is extremely
important because it can shut down
customer systems. You got to come out,
it's a trouble call, you purge the air,
you start them back up. Um, so
definitely a step you don't want to
shortcut or miss. Troubleshooting
systems, you know, fortunately as we've
gone into operation here, the problems
have decreased dramatically. We're
having less, you know, issues, errors,
reasons that we need to go out and
address things, but you always need to
be ready to do that, especially at
first. And then finally, I I threw
temporary space conditioning in here
because on the theme of scheduling and
having work done simultaneously,
you know, the way our project played
out, you didn't necessarily have every
single building ready to just be turned
on straight away. There was a process
for building conversions. So, we
actually had to have a plan in the
schools, for example, when we were
pulling those rooftop units on and
putting the new ones back, how are we
keeping that space conditioned? Do we
have temporary air conditioners? Do we
have temporary heaters? So, all playing
into the whole project management and
logistics of a system like this and how
you actually build it and turn it on.
Um, you know, going forward, I I I have
a laundry list of things that I'm going
to be able to address the next time
around and head off. So, with that,
hopefully I stayed on time and we've got
a little bit of time here for Q&A.
>> Thank you.