Thank you all for joining us today and
for your interest in the MIN program. As
Diane mentioned, my name's Laura Engo
and I lead the career um services and
career advising for the Master of
Finance students. Diane, it's it's
amazing to say to hear you say you've
been here for 11 years. For me, it's
been over nine now, and the time does
fly. Um I work in the career development
office, which we call the CDO. So,
you'll see the CDO mission here on the
slide, which I'm going to read in just a
moment. But I'm excited to be here with
you today and to talk about the career
development support you receive as an
MIN student as well as I will touch on
the career outcomes of our graduates. So
I wanted to start with reading the co
mission because I recognize that you may
have different experiences with prior
career development offices or career
services and wanted to share our
philosophy and how we work with
students. So, um, I'm going to read
this. The co delivers a values and
outcomesdriven career development
experience that empowers mins to pursue
their unique journeys and develop
lifelong skills to thrive and an expens
exponentially changing world. Through
advising, employer and alumni engagement
and customized resources, we help MIFN
develop the mindsets and networks that
provide learning and propel the careers
forward.
So in other words, you know, we really
aim to act as your partner and are there
for you throughout your career journey
to help you not only access resources
but also develop the skills that you'll
need for career success, not just in
your summer internship during the
program or your first job coming out of
the program, but are really going to
help you throughout your career. So with
that, I'm going to talk about how do we
partner with you in the CDO on the next
slide. Thank you. So, how do we do that?
Um, one way that we do that is we
provide advising for our students. So,
as an MINI student, you'll be assigned a
dedicated career advisor who will be a
resource for you throughout your entire
career journey as an MIN student. And
they'll really work with you to help
customize a um recruiting strategy for
your own unique goals as well as based
on what your prior background is. And if
you're in the career exploration phase,
they will help you navigate learning
about the industry so that you can
discover what it is that you want to
pursue. We provide career education
throughout your time in the program. It
actually starts four months prior to
when the program starts. So when you get
your letter of admissions to the
program, we're also providing you with
career education and support and
accesses access access to resources.
This is all to help you learn about how
to recruit and how to um prepare for
interviews and be really successful in
your job search. We build career
community to help connect you with the
incredible network that is MIT, MIT
Sloan and Minn. And so we do that
through our programs. Our career classes
are integrated with alumni, industry
professionals and recruiters as well as
we have networking events throughout the
year that give you opportunities to
connect with people in market directly.
Um there's an incredible program called
the Sloan Industry Adviserss Program and
these are um MIN excuse me MIT Sloan
alumni including MIN who are in various
roles that are really active mentors and
want to serve as adviserss to students
in a really safe way where there's no
judgment. So you can talk to them about
just general questions of what is it
like in the work that they do or you
could do something like a mock interview
with them. And then we also launched
this year quant mentor program
specifically for mfins. Those are
second-year MIN students who have
successfully completed a quant
internship who are an active mentor and
resource for the new MIN students who
are interested in quant opportunities.
So there are a lot of ways that we are
helping to build career community in the
CDO. Um we're also um proactively
sharing market insight. So, we're
constantly talking to employers and we
share what we're learning about
recruiting and hiring trends back with
students. Um, we want you to have the
information that we have about what's
happening in the market. And with that,
we're organizing company events as well.
So, this is facilitating opportunities
for connections with you as I mentioned
with alumni, but we do this also
directly with employers. So there are
many company events um on campus that
are available to to help you learn about
different roles organizations and to
also make connections that will help you
stand out in the application and
interview process. And as for the types
of employers that we engage, it's across
all industries. Um so but specifically
for M fins you know you can think about
that within finance we're talking to buy
side sell side you know hedge funds uh
the bulge bracket banks we're talking to
fintech um those in sustainability
private equity VC um management
consulting economic consulting um
anything you you really name it tech is
also a growing space we're seeing more
and Finn's interested in so we have
relationships with companies across Ross
all those industries. So this is a broad
overview of our services and how we
partner with students in the MIN
program. And on the next slide I'm going
to start to walk through what your
specific journey would look like as an
MIN with career support.
So as I mentioned the support starts
with your letter of admissions to the
MIN program which would be in March four
months prior to the start of the program
in July. And we want to provide you with
this support really for a couple of
reasons. One is because we recognize
that there are some um companies and
specifically functions such as
investment banking that recruit really
early and so we want you to have the
information and access to resources that
you need to be successful in that early
recruiting market. Another reason we
provide this support for you is because
the summer is very busy and the more
work that you can do in advance to get
career ready that often set students up
for a stronger start in the the program.
So we have what is called career
foundations which is a self-paced online
career course that is designed to really
prepare you for the career journey at
Sloan. It starts with, you know, career
exploration resources as well as
preparation tools if you're ready for
that next step to get all of your
recruiting materials ready. Um, and it's
all broken out as well by industry and
function. So, the guidance will vary
based on what your career interests are.
And we include a checklist as well for
you, so you can make sure that you feel
like you're staying on track even before
you come to campus.
um in the months prior to the program
starting that career advising
relationship will begin. So we have
monthly opportunities for you to drop in
and connect with the career advising
team and ask whatever questions are on
your mind that you're curious about. And
we also launch our um initial individual
advising appointments and offer resume
feedback from a career adviser all
before the program begins. You will also
have access to recruiting resources. And
this is really incredible because it
gives you the opportunity to not only
learn about recruiting timelines for
industry and employers specifically, but
it gives you the access to apply for job
postings that open up early and you're
able to make sure you don't miss out on
those opportunities.
And another thing that we do that has
been really I think well received and
appreciated by MIN students is career
path webinars with alumni. So we do
these for three different um functional
areas. Quant research and quant trading
is paired together um investment banking
and consulting. And this is led with the
CDO where we have a panel of MIN alumni
who are talking about each industry
there that they are working in to give
you general information about those
career fields, how they have progressed,
what their recruiting experience is
like, any tips and advice that they have
for you. You get it firsthand from
former M fins that were in your seat not
long ago about how to break into that
space and we give you the opportunity to
ask them questions directly and all of
that happens even before July. So
there's an incredible amount of
resources that are available to you as
soon as you become admitted. We really
welcome you into our MIN um world and
access to support. Um but it doesn't
stop then. On the next slide, I'll talk
about what happens during summer term.
So, when the program starts in July, um
that's when you'll go through our MIN
Career Core. And Career Core is a um
consists of four in-person classes led
by the CDO that brings in alumni,
industry professionals, and recruiters
to help you discover industry
opportunities and prepare for
recruiting. It's a highly interactive
learning experience that will have you
out of your seats in every class and
interacting with each other and as well
as the professionals. And so it's it's
just a lot of fun. There's a lot of
positive energy around it when sometimes
career and recruiting can feel um
sometimes overwhelming for students or
perhaps daunting or stressful. It's a
really fun engaging experience that we
create during the summer. You'll learn
how to market yourself. you'll have the
opportunity to network and you'll
complete career core um with this solid
foundation and career tool toolkit that
will really help you be market ready. Um
coupled with career core throughout
summer you will have the access you'll
have access to career advising support.
So this includes one-on-one career
advising that I mentioned as well as
resumeé reviews, cover letter reviews.
You can have access to mock interviews
and strength coaching. So career support
is really intense um during summer term
as you're going through career core, but
it doesn't stop there. Um on the next
slide, I'll speak to how the support
continues throughout the program.
So you will continue to have access to
resources and workshops throughout the
um your time as an M Finn. And this is
we we have these career workshops really
to support your ongoing development of
career skills and to help you navigate
recruiting. So an example of that is we
have a workshop prior to your summer
internship on how to make the most of
your summer internship where we bring in
um alumni again to talk about what they
learn from their experience about how to
prepare for the summer internship and
actions that you can do to position
yourself for a return offer. Um, so
we'll have thematic workshops like that
throughout the year or full-time
recruiting strategies session when
you're in the full-time market um, based
on whatever the need is. So those career
workshops are going to continue
throughout your time in the program as
well as the individual career advising
that I mentioned that is always
available to you as an MIN. And then as
um, various times throughout the
program, we do small group career
sessions and these are often done on a
career skill level. So the focus might
be resumeumés for example or we do it by
function so that you're having a shared
career interest in these small group
sessions.
Um and while I'm speaking on behalf of
the co I'd really be remiss if I didn't
mention that career is really everywhere
at MIT Sloan. So the co is just one
piece of that. We think that Sloan does
a really wonderful job of integating
integrating career throughout your
experience. So you'll learn and um
develop um skills even through your
academics, clubs, conferences,
competitions, career fairs in the
broader MIT community. So there's a lot
on this page here and I won't go through
it all but I just wanted to highlight
that how u many opportunities there are
for you to explore and experiment and to
find out what your next path is going to
be. On the club level, there's over 50,
you know, career and regional clubs. And
those that are most popular for Mfins
are the quantitative financial markets
club, the investment banking club,
private equity VC, investment
management, fintech, um,
entrepreneurship. I think those are the
ones that come to mind as being most
popular for Mins that really help them
on the career side. And then there are
some really fun social clubs that they
enjoy as well. Conferences and
competitions are a great opportunity for
you to practice what you're learning and
maybe do a stock pitch or um have the
chance to connect with industry
professionals outside of the classroom
or outside of the CDO. Those can be
really rewarding for students. And
again, just the broader MIT community.
as an MIN you're you're joining a
network of over a thousand MIN alumni
over 24,000 Sloan alumni and you know
over 130,000 MIT alumni and it's a
really proud uh network that has a
culture of giving back and supporting
one another and so it's great
opportunity for you to build connections
with within that network.
This is a lot of information and so what
we have done is created a website called
your CDO. You can go to it now. It's
cdo.mmit.edu.
And this is what the co's effort has
been to create one place where we could
centralize a lot of the career
happenings around
MIT Sloan, you know. Um, and so you're
welcome to look at this. Now, some of
the resources you would need to be a
student in order to access, but there is
a lot of information that you will be
able to see today. And so, I encourage
you if you're interested to please check
it out. You would be able to find the
employment reports for the MIN program
where you can learn about what prior MIN
graduates have accepted for their first
job coming out of the program. And on
your CDO, we have career resources based
on your program. So there's a specific
MIF page as well as industry pages with
resources based on whatever your
industry area of interest is. There's a
lot to explore on this page and on this
website. And so I encourage you to check
it out now if you're interested and know
that it's really the tip of the iceberg
as to what you can see right now. now
and then when you're a student you have
access to full visibility on your CDO.
Great. So next I wanted to turn to um
the career outcomes. You know I just
spent a lot of time talking about the
career support available to you as a
student and now I want to turn to how
that support translates into outcomes
and what our MFIN students are um
choosing to do following graduation.
So this right here gives us a highle
snapshot of some of the job titles and
employers that have hired Mfins in in
recent years. You we are a master of
finance program. The majority of our
students are going to work in the
finance industry. And I will go on a a
following slide about specifically where
an industry and what functions and you
can see also the different job titles
that our students are accepting for
their positions. Majority of students
are entering at that analyst level role
into the market. But there are those who
are also going at that senior analyst or
associate level position depending on
what their prior background was before
they came to the MIN program. All of
these companies that I see on the slide
here, these represent companies who hire
our students year after year. we have
great relationships with them and um
you'll have the opportunity certainly to
connect with them and learn about um
roles where you could make make an
impact at their organizations. So um
worldrenowned names I think come to MIT
and you have great opportunities to
connect with them.
So um I mentioned the employment reports
um when I spoke about the your co
website and each year we do publish what
our employment outcomes and this gives a
snapshot of the class of 2024. It
includes both the February 2024
graduates as well as the May 24
graduates and 98% of those um graduates
accepted uh post-graduate offers within
six months of graduation. 100% of the
Feb students did a summer internship.
You can see the average salary and
median signing bonus are very
competitive market rates in terms of
what our students are earning from
compensation.
And uh 54% of our graduates from the FEB
class ended up joining their summer
internship um when they when they
graduated for in a full-time position.
Now, that number doesn't reflect the
number that received full-time offers.
It just reflects the number that chose
to accept them. And so, they went and
back to their internship company. And
41% of our class of 24 graduates
accepted roles in quantitative roles.
So, think about quant research or quant
trading. That's included in that. I
would say 25% accepted in investment
banking. And so really twothirds of our
students are interested in more
quantitative roles or the investment
bank and corporate finance paths. And
I'll get into the functions on a another
slide, but if you're interested, I
really do encourage you to look at the
employment reports. And this data does
reflect 100% of our outcomes for our
graduates. So we're really proud of that
that we're capturing every single
student's outcome in term and sharing
that data with you.
These are um more companies. It's just a
snapshot of some of the hiring companies
that have come to campus and hired our
our graduates recently. Um almost all of
these companies have hired at least two
students in this past year of 2024 and
also for each of the past three years.
So as I mentioned, these are really
strong um partners. You'll see bulge
bracket banks like Bank of America,
Barlays, JP Morgan, Goldman Sachs,
Morgan Stanley as well as um you know
hedge funds, Balias, Citadel, uh Two
Sigma, QRT. Um so there's a lot of great
opportunities for you to connect with
employers. And in the employment report
on the last page, we show a full list of
all the companies that hired our
graduates this year. Here
you can see the types of functions that
they're going into and industry. So as I
mentioned on the right side of the slide
here you'll see the industry. I'll start
there with majority of students are
going into the finance industry but you
can see there's also an interest in
consulting. Um last year 7.7% of our
graduates accepted opportunities at
consulting firms. Usually those are uh
Mackenzie Bane and and and BCG, but they
can also be some boutique consulting
firms or um economic consulting or
financial services consulting like
analysis group or NRA as well. And we
we're seeing a little bit of a growing
interest in the tech industry too. So
you'll see that there with the 6% but
largely you know over 80% of the
graduates accepted opportunities within
the financial services space. And then
as for the functions, I mentioned that
there's a really strong interest in
quantitative roles as well as corporate
finance roles. So you can see that at
the top there um private equity and
venture capital is a space that many of
our students are interested in um and
tend to get there as a later path but
from that initial path following MIN
they tend to find their way there
through another avenue such as banking
or consulting before landing in PE.
there are some ENIN graduates who go
directly into uh PE or VC coming out of
the program
as well as other roles that they're
interested in. I will say what's not
shown here on this slide is that there
are um students each year who do choose
to continue education and pursue a PhD
or who decide to start a business and go
more the entrepreneurial route. that's
not um shown on this slide, but each
year there's a handful of students who
pursue those opportunities and we can
support you in that as well if those are
your goals.
And so where in the world are these
students um working? The MPIN program is
a global program and so you'll see
that's reflected in our career outcomes
as well. Um the class of 2024 over 90%
of students were international. Less
than 10% were US citizen or permanent
resident and still 50% of the class
chose to stay in uh the United States or
Canada. And I think that what is
important to know when you're looking at
these outcomes is that we do support UN
students who are interested in an
international job search. So, you know,
a quarter of our graduates um went to
work in Asia and about 20% went to
Europe. And we have strong ties with
employers as well as alumni networks in
those regions. And I think that there's
it's often a question from students
wondering if they can secure an
opportunity in the US. And I think the
answer there is that we have a lot of
students who choose to do that path and
are successful. And then there are also
students who recognize that MIN is a
global program and that's part of what
they love about it and they want to work
internationally and so their goal isn't
always to work in the US and you see
that reflected here in our outcomes.
And I think that that was it Rachel for
me. I think this might be um a slide
that you want to speak to Rachel or
Diane.
Yes. Amazing. Thank you so much, Laura.
Um, and we will get to questions in just
a moment. Um, but I see Diane popped on.
Did you want to speak?
>> Yes. Sorry. I was trying to furiously
answering. Great questions. Thank you so
much for submitting them. We're really
um, you know, glad to see them. I know
there's a lot here to digest. Um, and I
know there were quite a number of
questions maybe, um, first and foremost
just in terms of the class size and the,
um, profile. This is a great way um for
you to kind of get a sense. It's really
a snapshot if you will of the class. And
you know, I will say that, you know,
while there have been some, you know,
differences year-over-year, the the fact
of the matter is it still remains very
much um similar to what it has been.
It's an early career, you know,
pre-professional program. Most of our um
MVIN students are coming directly from
university and they do not necessarily
and you do not necessarily have to come
with a lot of coursework in finance for
example or even internships in finance
for that matter. Uh as one of our
finance faculty likes to say we are
looking for individuals who have great
problem solving and analytical skills.
We can teach you finance. So, um I think
that really speaks to what you see here
in terms of the class profile and and
should absolutely give you a good gauge
around what are the things that going
to, you know, help me to thrive in the
program because that's really what it's
all about. Um there's a lot of, you
know, deep dive into quantitative
finance obviously as part of the
curriculum. Yes, we are asking in the
application and I know I'm not going to
get too much into this for this session,
but uh there have been a number of
questions about it. You know the fact of
the matter is is we are looking at
everything in your application. Do not
overlook one component. You just you
should really be focused on everything
that we are asking as part of the
application that's required. Uh and go
ahead and take your time in submitting
it but submit it by the January 5th
deadline. There's absolutely no
advantage to submitting it early. We do
not have a rolling admissions uh process
at all. So I know there were quite a few
questions about that. Um I will also
just mention that you know again we look
at everything but what we're mostly
focused on is what are your you know the
strength of your um academic background
and we're looking at both your
undergraduate or bachelor's level as
well as your um any anyone who's had
advanced degrees of any kind. We're
going to be looking at um if you submit
test scores great they're not required
but certainly it's up to you if you feel
that that helps to support your
application. And then we're also going
to be looking at, you know, what's your
understanding of and passion for
pursuing a course that's a deep dive
into finance. What is it about the
financial world and the field that most
interests you or that you have knowledge
about? Um, and then last but probably
not least, because again, I'm skimming
over this for the purpose of this
session is you're you have to have
excellent English communication skills.
Um, and there are many ways for us to
determine that as part of the
application and admissions process. um
we do not require the IELTS or TOEFL.
However, again, if you feel that's
another great data point and you want to
submit them or submit a test score,
that's fine. Go ahead and do that. Uh
the point I'm trying to make is that
again, this is an early career
pre-professional program. We're looking
for individuals who are really looking
to learn more and want to pursue or
launch their careers in the field of
finance. And there are many ways and
many sides of finance as Laura's just
described that you could do that. So, I
I don't know if there's any other
questions that I missed, Rachel, or that
you think need to be addressed further.
>> I think maybe you both can can take a
stab at a few questions we've been
getting for our international students.
Thank you so much for being here and for
joining us. Um but in terms of you know
our of application um what is what is
the outlook in terms of international
students applying to MIN Diane and then
Laura um given the the visa situation um
you know kind of what is the what is the
thought process for our CDO office?
Yeah, I mean again to be perfectly
transparent. I mean this is all new to
all of us too. So we you know and Laura
can attest to this I'm sure you know
we're not seeing any immediate impact as
a result of this change. It's so recent
nobody really knows for sure. Um but be
rest assured that you know both our co
as well as our ISO as well as just you
know overall MIT is monitoring this very
closely. Um, we were so relieved really
that our students were able to get to
campus this year based on other things
that were challenges that were happening
on the visa front for many of our
international students. Um, but you
know, we we don't know. It's too early
to tell. And um, at this point, we have
a whole team that's part of Laura's
group that's employer relations. They
are working very closely with them as
well as the ISO. So, you know, it's MIT
after all. We have a lot of resources
that are dedicated to our students and
helping them. I don't know if there's
anything else you wanted to add, Laura.
>> No, I think that was really well said.
It's evolving and we are really being
proactive and trying to understand what
is going to happen. So, I think from the
CDO side, there's three main ways I
would say that we are supporting
students. Um, one is by proactive
outreach with employers to ask them how
the proclamation is impacting their
hiring or consideration of hiring or if
at all any effect to their policy. So,
that's something we are proactively
doing and sharing insights back that
we're gaining from employers directly to
students so that we can help educate and
prepare and inform students. But that's
happening now. And a lot of employers,
they don't know themselves yet all those
decisions. that that's one way that we
are supporting students in that area.
The other area is you know thinking
ahead that whether there may be a
increase of interest in working
internationally um and will we see a
decrease in students wanting to stay in
the US post um the program that's
something we don't know but in uh
preparation for that we're making sure
that our relationships with companies um
internationally and in key cities like
you know London and Hong Kong and Paris
are really strong and engaging in those
networks so that we can support
students. And then the third piece that
I would say that really is a you know
thread to your whole experience as an
MIN is that career advisor relationship.
So working with students on an
individual basis to understand what are
their goals not only function but
geographical goals and how can we
support them in navigating that
successfully. So, those are all things
that our team is doing really
proactively um as we monitor what's
happening in the world.
>> Great. Thank you. How are we doing on
questions, Rachel?
>> Yeah, that's super helpful. Um I I want
to just um point out something Laura
mentioned about the individualized
support here in the in the MIN program,
but this also applies, you know, at this
stage of the process. So, you're
thinking about MIN and you're not sure
about your profile. We've gotten a few
just personal questions about their
specific profile. So, we do want to
encourage you to reach out to us via
email if you have some questions about
your eligibility or what this would look
like for you. So, that applies to the
admissions process as well as career
supports and so many other things. So,
please reach out to us and we also have
a number of events coming up to really
break down the application. So, so be on
the lookout for more from for us. Um but
with that in mind for the individualized
support Laura um we have some students
asking some prospective students asking
questions about you know varied
interests. So so let's say a student is
thinking about um VC but also has some
interest in some other areas. What would
you say the career adviserss are able to
do for folks that are a little
open-minded when it comes to future
goals? Yeah, that's a great question.
And I think it's okay to be open-minded
um at the start of the program. I will
also say some students come into the
program knowing exactly what they want
to do and that's what they're focused on
and they're successful in that avenue.
And other students come into the program
thinking they know exactly what they
want to do and they discover something
else that they didn't even know was
possible and they change their mind. And
our program really supports you with
that. So, one thing that we're doing um
really early on is trying to provide you
with opportunities to explore and learn
about the market opportunities that are
available to you. And I think one of the
best ways to do that. It's not by
reading uh blogs online. It's not by
looking at company websites. It's by
talking to people in the seats doing the
jobs themselves and learning from their
experience. And that's why so much of
our career curriculum is integrated with
alumni and industry professionals. So
you have those opportunities to connect
and learn about what they're doing
across different roles. And so that's
really what we focus on in the beginning
of the program. And yes, we do
complement it with resources that you
can access online and in your own time
so that you can feel like you're doing
your own research and preparation. but
giving you the opportunity to connect
with the market is a fantastic way for
you to discover what do the jobs look
like and feel like. Um, and then I will
also say throughout the program you're
going to have opportunities to learn
throughout your academics. Um if you
choose to do proseminar or finab which
um you will have to choose one or the
other as it's an action learning
requirement as an MPIN student those are
opportunities for you to apply what
you're learning in the classroom to work
on real problems with employers and that
gives you another insight into the
industry and then also your summer
internship experience. That's a great
way for you to test if this is something
that you want to continue to pursue. And
while I mentioned that, you know, 54% of
students did accept um and rejoin their
summer internship employer, that's still
about half the class that did not. And
you know, so what they they maybe
realized that that wasn't the career
path for them or they realized that they
wanted to work for a different company,
for a different culture. And so whatever
your career journey looks like, we're
able to support you with it. And I think
that's why we value the career advising
model so much because we recognize it's
a diverse class. Your interests are
diverse and so your own experience and
how you navigate it will be unique and
we want to support you as an individual,
not just as an entire MIN class.
>> That's great. Thank you so much.
>> Yeah.
And I mean, you you basically answered
this question already, but maybe we can
be a little more explicit. When it comes
to someone that's really interested in
something more niche that may not be
represented on some of the slides that
we've shared today, um what would you
say your advice is or um how does how do
the adviserss handle this if it's
something that doesn't necessarily fit
into those buckets that they're
interested in?
>> Yeah. Um
well I think I would want to know what
the niche is right so um are we talking
about working specifically with
derivatives and exotics you know in a
quantitative trading capacity and that's
their focus or they only want to do
distress debt and credit and their focus
there specifically or sustainability and
climate or is it something else that
isn't a fit for the MIN program. So I
think at this stage I would encourage
you to you know not only look at the
employment reports but you know try to
find MIN alumni through LinkedIn
profiles and see if there are people
doing the work that you're interested
in. We have an incredible network not
just with MIN but I would also lean into
Sloan and MIT if you're in more of a
niche space to connect you with people
in those areas and also making sure that
the MIN program is appropriate for you.
I think the MIN program can help support
MIN students in reaching their goals
that are aligned but then there are some
programs that maybe MIN is not the fit
for you. So I would need to understand
what that specific niche is.
That's great. That's super helpful.
Thank you.
>> It seems like we're getting through most
of these questions. I do still see a few
um application
um questions. So, be on the lookout. We
will we'll be here to answer more of
those of those questions. Um and then
another thing that you've answered and
and you did just briefly explain. So, we
we got a few questions around, you know,
placement and do we place folks in
positions? And while the answer is that
we're not a placement agency, Laura gave
an overview of all the different ways
students are getting exposed to um to
employers through their coursework and
through their projects and things. But
can you give us any examples, Laura, of
a success story around um students
finding their their future employers
during their time at in the MIN program?
Yeah, I c I can give you one thing that
I'm really excited about that we just
had two weeks ago is our annual MIN
networking night. And so this happens
every year in September where I think we
had 30 employers and over 50
professionals from those employers come
to talk just to MIN students for you
know a couple hour evening event. And
this is a fantastic opportunity for
students to connect with a variety of
different companies, different
individuals there. Many of them are
professionals um that were not alum and
many of them are MIN alum as well. So
you can learn about how they navigated
the MIN experience. And while it is a
networking event and it is not intended
to be a career fair where you're talking
specifically about applying for a job
there, every year there's always
students who find their jobs through
these connections because they're able
to discover something that they weren't
aware of beforehand or they're able to,
you know, make an introduction introduce
themselves and help them stand apart in
the application process. So, I think
that's an event that it's just really
fun. There's a lot of buzz in the room
and high energy and then it really can
have a material impact in their students
recruiting experiences.