so here's an experiment this is a
checker board this is about perception
the brain sometimes plays tricks on us
and you see this object right here and
you see it cast a shadow so my question
to you is is the shade in square number
one the same as the shade in square
number two yes or no more people say no
okay so we have to train ourselves to do
this so this one is label number one
this is label number two I'm going to
Now cover
this and now you see that they both have
the same shape right so those of you who
said yes before probably have seen
this your brain is using the knowledge
that you had from before that's great
okay so let's look at this one more time
the shadow is telling the brain
something we have to develop the skills
and with our brains to sort out the
information and be very careful about it
so we have the proper interpretations
for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow