[Music]
from the MIT Energy Initiative. This is
What If It Works, a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate change.
I'm Cara Miller. And I'm Rob Stoner.
[Music]
Today we're talking with Yakabo Bonjouro
about a source of energy that's drawn a
lot of fashion and a lot of controversy.
Nuclear. If an individual were to use
only nuclear energy for his or her
energy needs throughout the lifetime,
you would produce an amount of spent
fuel or waste that would fit within a
coffee cup. Yakapo is the director of
the center for advanced nuclear energy
systems and a professor in the
department of nuclear science and
engineering at MIT. the United States
where we consume a lot of electricity. A
gigawatt reactor, a gigawatt plant
basically would be enough to power a
city the size of Boston,
750,000
people/housel. It's a big chunk of
power. He argues you can't get to a
robust clean energy portfolio without
nuclear. But that doesn't mean the road
ahead's going to be easy for those who
advocate for nuclear. At least not in
the US. What it has to do with is the
the way in which the process to select,
license, and eventually operate a final
repository. The way in which that
process has evolved in the United States
has been characteristically
dysfunctional, if I can put it that way.
Here's Yakapo in conversation with me
and Rob. I'll start off with a a little
bit of a funny question maybe, but do
people ever meet you, hear what you do,
and say, "Really? You go around the
world supporting more nuclear power?" Do
you ever get that kind of shocked
reaction? No, I actually I don't think I
get shock. I get uh curiosity and
interest. I think people find general
topic of energy and particular energy
intriguing. And so sometimes they ask
questions. Sometimes they say, "Wow,
sounds really challenging. Sounds really
difficult." And it sort of makes sense
with being a professor of MIT. You know,
people immediately give you credit and
then you need to sort of confirm that
you know what you're talking about.
That's the reaction. Now, that's not the
reaction you get in Italy or New Zealand
where I was last week. They're, you
know, strongly anti-uclear.
Well, I can't comment on New Zealand
because it's a situation that I don't
know. Well, um, growing up in Italy, of
course, I was exposed to a lot of, um,
you know, opposition to nuclear, but my
understanding is that the, uh, current,
uh, government, the current
administration in Italy actually has,
uh, made a significant overture, uh, for
nuclear and, um, we'll see where it
goes. I am generally skeptical about
things getting done in Italy uh just
because the country tends to be a little
bit dysfunctional and decisions are made
and when the political landscape changes
those decisions are reversed that's all
but you know at the moment even in Italy
which is usually hopeless u the wind
seems to have changed you want to edit
any of this out
no not at all no no I feel comfortable
badmouthing it's my own country so I can
say whatever I want
Um, what's the toughest country you can
remember ever sort of trying to make the
case to or where people were the most
resistant to what you had to say about
nuclear? Yeah, I think that's an easy
question. It has been for the past 15
years, maybe even longer than that, has
been Germany. Okay. Yeah. And why? Well,
they have a long history of nuclear
opposition which goes back to the Cold
War. In fact, I'm told right after World
War II sort of they conflated the
opposition to nuclear weapons with
opposition to nuclear energy. I see. And
that persisted certainly the general
population maybe in the political arena
a little bit less. There were ups and
downs. the um the administration of
Prime Minister um Schroeder in the '9s
actually passed a nuclear phase out
policy which then was put on pause by
Angela Merkel during her first term. But
then Fukushima happened and then the
country just decided they wanted to
phase out and they finally did it. Uh
last year they shut down their last
nuclear power plant and predictably
their emissions have gone up. They had
to restart some coal fire plants. It's
been a complete mess, but they no longer
have nuclear energy in Germany. So,
that's always been sort of a tough
audience. Uh, of course, they've got a
wonderful neighbor with nuclear in
France that supplies some of the
electricity to the European grid. Uh, a
lot of the electricity to the European
grid and I think the by far the lion
share of the of the carbon-f free
electricity. So, it's interesting to see
two countries that they're very
different, but in many ways they have
such strong ties. They've really gone
two different directions and it has been
that way for a long time. So let's just
step back because in the back of
everybody's mind is some sort of nuclear
accident in Chernobyl through my
Fukushima. What is the essence of the
case that you make to a politician or
regular person who's trying to think
like hm would we want nuclear around
here? Well the first thing I will say
that there are risks associated with all
technologies not just energy
technologies. Everything we do as human
beings entails a risk and we just have
to weigh what the benefits are and what
the risks are and then decide is it
acceptable or not. But having said that
the value proposition for nuclear in the
current context is in my opinion
three-fold. First obviously we're all
concerned about greenhouse gas emissions
and how we're going to address climate
change mitigation as well as adaptation.
And needless to say all lowcarbon energy
technologies can potentially play a
role. The specific role that nuclear can
play is not only being low carbon,
carbon free if you will during
operation, but it's also dispatchable,
stable, reliable. So it's not subject to
intermittency. And so dispatchable
meaning you can make it come on when you
want and you can make it go off when you
don't want it to some extent. Correct.
Yeah. You can control basically the
energy output of your system to some
extent. Right. Because these are not
systems that are designed to go up and
down in power very very rapidly. There
are both economic and technical reasons
for why you don't want to do that, but
pretty much you can you can get the
output that you want uh within within
reasonable limits. And are you
contrasting that with kind of like solar
and wind and wind which are great,
they're cheap as we know, they're also
low carbon, but you're subject to
intermittency. And so all the studies
that we've done at this point, many
other groups have done around the world
um show that the generation mix that
gets you to deeply decarbonized
scenarios at the lowest cost and highest
reliability is not 100% nuclear, is not
100% renewables, is actually a mix of
both with a little bit of storage. to
deal with what we just mentioned a
minute ago sort of the fast changes in
demand and and generation that a nuclear
reactor does not handle very well
thousand megawatt reactor by the way
there there's only one solar field on
the planet I think that's of a scale
that's comparable to the the capable of
generating a gawatt of electricity and I
suspect I don't know where that is but I
suspect that's probably the capacity is
not what you get on average it probably
well of course it's off at night
every single night. So just for scale, I
mean a gigawatt nuclear power plant is
going to provide enough electricity for
what 100,000 homes or something like
that. No, a lot more than that. So a
gigawatt, of course, it depends on which
country it is because we all consume
different, you know, uh electricity at
different rates. But United States where
we consume a lot of electricity, a
gigawatt uh reactor or a gigawatt plant
basically would be enough to power a
city the size of Boston, 750,000
uh people slash househous. homes, right?
So, so it's a big Yeah. So, it's a it's
a big chunk of power. If you were like,
you know, king of the world and you were
thinking about the energy mix of
countries and you were saying, "Here's
what I think is optimal." Now, clearly
you're a nuclear guy, but I don't know.
Would you say the ideal for the US would
be like 100% nuclear? What what would
you say? I would say first of all that
it's highly country dependent. Okay. So
there are countries that have natural
resources either in the form of hydro or
exceptionally good renewables or
plentiful domestic uranium and so it
there really is no one size fits all
right I mean if you look for example
East Asia uh countries with very very
strong industry but zero natural
resources and they tend to be very
densely populated and so you know lots
of energy needs but not a lot of options
and so what We talked about this Japan
being like this
classic. I was in Taiwan just last week,
right? They have no options. It's a very
very dense uh island. They have very
strong economy with energy hungry
industries and they have no natural
resources. So what are they left with?
Well, they import 98% of their energy at
the moment is imported. Wow. Okay. And
so it's natural gas, oil, coal, of
course. And uh and so what options do
they have? Well, you can carpet cover
the whole island with solar and wind.
You won't even get you to where you
need, but they're doing what they can
with renewables. Uh but at one point,
you got to sort of say, okay, well,
nuclear is pretty dense. And having
nuclear in a sense makes them more
energy independent than they are now
because they have to rely on LNG from
the United States, coal from other
neighbors, Australia. But of course, it
doesn't make them completely energy
independent. No, it doesn't because they
don't have any uranium. They have No,
they don't have any uranium. And they
actually and they have a domestic
nuclear industry in the sense that they
have a nuclear operator. They have a
utility that operates nuclear power
plants, but they don't build their own
nuclear plants. And they don't even make
their own fuel. So even nuclear is now
obviously doesn't give you 100% energy
security but the energy density of
uranium fuel is so high that if you buy
a significant amount you have a lot of
energy for a long period of time without
having to go back to the market and
getting a continuous supply of fuel. So
in that sense is is good. The other
factor that of course has to be weighted
and it's highly country dependent is
where you going to get your fuel. Right.
And this has become very evident as a
problem even in the United States with
the recent Russian embargo. With the
Russian embargo. Exactly. Because we
don't make our own fuel in particular.
You're talking about nuclear fuel.
Nuclear fuel fuel. So the uranium market
is very mature as a commodity market.
And so the way it has evolved is that
the countries that produce at the lowest
cost are the countries that produce the
most. Right? That's it's commodity,
right? At least for uranium. Now,
uranium is not what you put straight in
the core in the reactor. You got to
first enrich it and then you got to
fabricate a fuel assembly which is a
highly engineered system. So there are
several different steps, but let's just
stay with the raw material with uranium.
If you just look from a geological point
of view, the countries that have the
highest reserves are Australia, Canada,
the United States actually, Kazakhstan,
Namibia, a bunch of other countries.
okay of uranium. This is the okay they
naturally have it but that doesn't mean
that Australia can US are the ones that
are producing the most because the
countries that produce the most are the
ones that have the cheapest uranium
right so you may have a lot of uranium
but it doesn't matter if it takes a lot
of money to extract it okay so at the
moment if you look at the the pie chart
of who is making uranium Kazakhstan is
actually the the highest uh Australia is
big is big uh you have Russia you have
Namibia but Russia is not a dominant uh
producer of uranium, but it's big enough
that post February 2022 when a lot of
countries don't want to deal with Russia
anymore, if you push them out of that
market, that creates a problem. And
that's where the United States is at the
moment because we were relying
partially, not entirely, but partially
for I think the percentage is something
like 20% or so of our uranium uh on
Russia. And so, and it's not like you
snap your fingers and all of a sudden
you get that 20% replaced overnight. It
takes a certain amount of time. I don't
think it's it's certainly not an
insurmountable problem. It's just a
matter of making the investment and
developing a little bit more resilient
supply chain of uranium for our own
reactor. So, let's can we stay on this
topic of fuel for for a bit? Sure. We
come back to it. I if you want to.
Sorry, I'm all over the place. But we
were starting so we were going with with
Taiwan and so on and it and it's true.
So nuclear is no silver bullet in terms
of energy independent, right? I I didn't
want to dodge your question of what is
the ideal mix. Oh yeah. So yeah, because
that's fascinating, right? So indeed,
first of all, let me say it's not one
sizefits-all, right? So each country is
going to have its own. But I go back to
what I said earlier in the in in the
interview here, and that is let's just
stay on the on the power sector on the
electric markets.
All the studies that have been done
serious studies show that because of the
issue of intermittency on one end and
because of the issue of relatively high
cost of nuclear on the other end the
ideal mix is neither all intermittent
renewables nor all nuclear. So I would
not recommend 100% nuclear or close to
100%. I would absolutely not recommend
close to 100% renewables. is really the
combination of the two plus the storage
that helps you handle the very rapid
variability of of of renewables that
gives you basically the decarbonization
the desired decarbonization deep
decarbonization at the lowest cost and
most likely at the highest reliability.
So then we can you know not debate but
then we have to analyze country by
country is it in one case 30% nuclear
and 70% renewables or in another case
might be more nuclear and less
renewables that's going to be country
dependent I'm guessing you think in the
US we could have a lot more nuclear we
could certainly have a lot more nuclear
on the grid maybe we'll see uh certainly
I think in other sectors of the economy
jacking up nuclear would make a ton of
sense we already talk about uh for
example heat industry very very
difficult to use renewables for heat
from a technical point of view in a
sense that these are industries that
require heat all the time again you're
you're bumping against the issue of
intermittency but also because from a
thermodynamic point of view if you will
if you're generating electricity which
is what uh PV and uh and wind do then
downgrading it to heat is you know is
very very inefficient whereas if you
have a heat source to begin with it's
it's more efficient
So again, it's a wellbalanced mix that
usually wins wins the game. And we
haven't even talked about well, I just
alluded to reliability, but that's a big
deal. Not just reliability of the system
on a database, also resilience to
disruptions, right? Whether they are
natural disasters or uh man-made events,
you know, terrorism, etc. So, I think
it's uh it's not wise to put all your
eggs in in one basket.
Yakapo, you mentioned that you were in
Taiwan last week and and thinking about
this this great problem they have of of
trying to establish an a domestic energy
supply. And and when you get into those
conversations, I find you end up talking
about this idea of energy independence
as as a virtue and something we should
all be striving for, which I'm not so
convinced about. I mean, to me, it seems
like we should be thinking about energy
security.
How does that play out in in the nuclear
realm? When you talk about energy
independence, you know, are we are we
meaning here that like the US can just
provide its own energy and like
whatever? We can have fights with a lot
of people, but it's okay. We don't need
them. Yeah. The idea sort of originates
in the in the area of oil and gas. Like
we don't have to import oil and gas. We
got our own and it's forever and and
we're stockpiling it. Here we're talking
about, you know, the supply of reliable
energy for industry and the economy.
But it doesn't have to come from within
your own borders. It can come from
outside. It can come from friends. It
can can even come from not friends. You
mentioned Russia being a big supplier
provided there are enough friends out
there to fill the gap if they fall off
in their production. What are the
options in the emerging plants for
making us more energy secure in the
supply of of uranium for those plants
that that we should be thinking about?
Okay. Okay. So, first of all, I agree
with with the way you have set up the
question and the problem here. I think
the goal realistically should not be
energy independence. There are probably
a half a dozen countries that might
theoretically achieve energy
independence. US being blessed one of
one of them. A question I may ask is do
we really want to you know that's is the
what's the what's the big benefit? So, I
I agree with you. energy security and
and given that a lot of these energy
technologies
um have a global supply chain then the
question as you correctly posed it is do
I have enough friendly suppliers out
there so that given a uh potential
scenario I can get the energy that I
need at the cost that I want and so um
in that sense nuclear is not dissimilar
from fossil fuels uh because you do have
a fairly large number of uranium
producers. You have a fairly large
number of uranium enrichers. We'd like
to see a few more. Uh we'd like to see
the US actually rebuild that capability
because yeah, it's not so easy for any
one supplier to ramp up production. It
isn't it isn't it entails it entails
cost and time all feasible and the US
government is taking steps so that the
US is uh going to become again capable
of enriching uranium for its commercial
sector and then there is a uh very
wellestablished and capable supply chain
for fuel fabrication in Europe in Asia
and in the United States. So in that
sense, you know, I'm confident that the
US or any other countries that we would
help to build reactors for, they will
have the fuel that they need in the
longer term. Natural uranium is what is
mined. It's 99 plus% is uranium 238.
That's the isotope 238 of uranium, which
for the purpose of generating energy in
traditional reactor designs is not very
useful. and 7% is uranium 235 is the
asotop 235 of uranium and that's sort of
the juicy part of uranium that's what we
actually use to sustain the cherry
reaction within the core so at the
moment we use less than 1% of the
natural uranium in our current reactors
if we were able to use also the
remaining 99% of course the uranium
resources would immediately multiply
quite dramatically so in the current
design you cannot do that they're just
laws of physics it's prevented. But
there is a whole class of reactors that
are called fast breather reactors in
which the neutrons are not slowed down
intentionally and you have an excess of
neutrons and you allow for some of these
neutrons to be absorbed by uranium 238
and that uranium 38 turns into plutonium
239 which is also good fuel. And so you
in fact this seems incredible but you
can in these systems you can actually
make more fuel than you're consuming.
That's why they're called breathers. And
so you multiply the amount of fuel uh
quite dramatically. Uh we're not at a
point where this is needed. Uh it
certainly adds cost and complexity to
the fuel cycle. So at the moment for the
foreseeable future essentially all
countries around the world are going to
stay with the traditional fuel cycle
approach which means we continue to use
about 1% of the natural uranium we mind.
So, so you used the P word plutonium
there. Uh, um, which made the hair on
the back of my neck stand up quickly
because that's, you know, makes for a
very efficient bombs and and making more
plutonium than you're burning up sort of
sends you in the direction of the
breeder reactor of making file material
that could be used in weapons. Is that a
problem? And is is that preventing the
proliferation of breeder reactors? It's
always been a concern, right? The way it
works is that you make plutonium 239 in
the fuel that is in the core. But then
in order to do the breeding, you got to
or to to use that plutonium, you got to
reprocess the fuel. Okay? Once the fuel
comes out of the core, you essentially
separate that plutonium 239 from the
rest of the fuel. And depending on how
long it has been in the reactor, that
plutonium could be weapons grade, as you
said. And so that's always been the
concern that if you go down that path
and you separate plutonium then in
principle you have weapons grade
material and so then it becomes a
proliferation concern. The US decided in
the late '7s that we we're not going to
reprocess our fuel for that reasons to
show sort of you know to set the bright
example and say we you know we don't
want to go down that path because that
could open up the uh the possibility of
proliferation. But the French do the
French have been doing it for 40 years
and uh it's all done under the uh
inspections and monitoring of the IIA.
So I think it's reasonably well
controlled. But they don't use fast
breeders really in France. But they do
extract the plutonium, the little amount
of plutonium that comes out of their
traditional reactors, thermal reactors,
and they reuse it in the same reactors.
It's called Mox fuel, mix oxide fuel.
[Music]
How much push back do you get in
different countries when it comes to
where do we put this stuff? You know, I
mean, we've heard a lot of controversy
here like is this going to go in deep
deep inside of a mountain and that seems
tricky in trying to get people to build
more nuclear. So, it comes up in every
conversation, right? So, you have to
make a few points here. First, what do
we mean by waste is to spend fuel,
right? So, forget about barrels
uh oozing out um green glowing fluids,
radioactive fluids. So, the the waste
for nuclear reactor really looks like
the same fuel assemblies that go into
the reactor when when it's fresh fuel
that you can literally hold in your hand
and you know with with basically zero
radiation. But what has happened when it
has spent the time in the reactor is
that some of that uranium that uranium
35 that we were talking about as fision
and as a result of that fision process a
lot of radioactivity has been generated.
So it looks the same if I take a picture
it looks exactly the same it went in. So
it's a highly engineered solid very
robust piece of uh piece of um
technology but it's now highly
radioactive and it and and and it stays
radioactive for a long period of time.
So, so the first order of business is to
put those fuel assemblies into a span
fuel pool which is colllocated with the
reactor and it stays there for a couple
of years and then and that's just normal
water, right? And that's just water.
Just water, right? So, water happens to
be very good at shielding radiation. So,
you can literally take a tour of these
pen fuel pools and you have your highly
radioactive fuel assemblies just a few
meters underwater. You can look down.
They they have a nice glow blue the
cheranc light. So they look
characteristically radioactive but but
it's perfectly safe. And now
radioactivity naturally decays off. And
so after a couple of years the
radioactivity level is low enough that
you can pull these fuel assemblies out
of the span fuel pool and put them into
what we call dry casks which are
basically cylindrical canisters made of
steel and concrete. And the
radioactivity is sufficiently low that
basically the shielding provided by the
steel and the concrete is sufficient so
that if you were to spend an afternoon
turn noon outside is you know in contact
with this dry cask you would get a very
very small amount of radiation minimal
and the volumes and masses are very
small right for all these reactors. Why?
Because the energy density of uranium is
extraordinarily high. So you don't need
a lot of uranium to produce a lot of
energy to begin with. And because the
the waste is the spent fuel is the ur is
the the residual material that comes out
of the reactor. You don't have a lot of
it. So help us visualize how much there
is say from the US. Okay. So so you can
you can use a lot of different
analogies. Um, the one that I think is
going to stick the most, I think, with
the with a lay audience, if an
individual were to use only nuclear
energy for his or her energy needs
throughout the lifetime, that you would
produce an amount of spend fuel or waste
that would fit within a coffee cup.
That's it. That would be the amount for
a single person for a single person is a
coffee cup. Now, of course, if you start
producing that energy for millions or
billions, it adds up. But how much does
it add up? So in the United States, we
have had a nuclear reactors uh the
nuclear industry for close to maybe 60
years now. At the moment and for the
past 20 plus years has been generating
20% of our electricity. Incidentally,
that translates to roughly 50% of our
lowcarbon electricity. So it's a big
impact on our lowcarbon energy
infrastructure. And the accumulated
waste for 20% of the electricity in
United States from the past 40 or 50
years or whatever it is would basically
fit within a football field uh about 10
mters tall. That's it for the whole
country. That's the amount of high level
waste or spent fuel that we generated.
So again, not a lot of not a lot of
material. But even though as you say
it's not that big, maybe it's not that
dangerous. There still seem to be fights
over people being like, "Yeah, but I
don't want it near me." Oh. Oh,
absolutely. And I think what what it has
to do with is the the way in which the
process to select, license, and
eventually operate a final repository.
The way in which that process has
evolved in the United States has been
characteristically dysfunctional, if I
can put it that way.
And I would say the the story of Yaka
Mountain and the geological repository
for high level nuclear waste is one of
the brightest examples of how
dysfunctional our politics are. Now the
Finns have found a way, right? Yes. Yes.
So so I was going to get to that. Right.
So this is the US, right? And and and
there are other countries that have
followed an equally inefficient and
dysfunctional process, but there are
also countries that have gotten this
right. And and yeah, you mentioned
Finland is one. these high functioning
northern European countries. Yes. What
are they doing? So the N the Nordics are
doing well in that in that department.
Uh France also which of course uses so
much uh nuclear energy in their energy
mix is not that far behind. And so in
the three countries that I just
mentioned Finland I don't think I
mentioned Sweden but Sweden is the
second and then the third is France. the
process of site
identification, analysis, licensing,
etc. has been a lot healthier in the
United States. And so Finland is going
to be the first country to, you know,
cross the finish line. They have
excavated and it's now built a final
repository. It's happens to be
colloccated with an existing nuclear
power plant, which I think helps
dramatically also with acceptance and
comfort because these are communities
that have been living with a nuclear
power plant for decades. So they you
know they they their neighbor works at a
nuclear power plant but they they
themselves work at a nuclear power
plant. So they have developed a level of
comfort and confidence in the technology
and so it's expected to open uh and
start to accept uh that waste next year
or the year after. I think it's next
year actually. Are there any indications
that that will lead
to can I use the word renaissance of
nuclear power in those countries? I mean
Finland if I don't use the the word
renaissance because it was bad luck when
we started using it 15 16 years ago but
in Finland it never stopped in a sense
that it's a country that has been
growing its reliance on nuclear
constantly in spite of being the uh you
know the host of one of the least
successful new build projects the whole
kilow 3 which really took at least twice
as long as it was supposed to and cost a
lot of money. So Finland is another one
of those countries where they made the
decision early on that nuclear would be
part of their mix and they very
deliberately went through a rational
process of approval and uh you know
public acceptance and all of that and as
well uh coming up in parallel with the
solution for the waste etc etc and so
now I forgot what the percentage is but
it's over I think 30% of their
electricity comes from nuclear and they
have appetite for more and a lot of heat
they need too and they need heat for the
for the winter as for the industries.
You know, it's another uh it's a small
country in terms of population, but
they're pretty industryheavy and and
energy hungry in that sense. And so, so
nuclear will grow there. Sweden similar,
right? They went from u relying a lot on
nuclear to actually having at one point
a nuclear phase out policy and then a
couple of years ago, I think the the new
government came in and said, "No, no,
no, we're not going to phase it out. In
fact, we want to rebuild again." And in
parallel with all of this, they had this
process of identifying a site for their
final repository of the waste. And it
was uh wonderful because they actually
had multiple communities that competed
to be the host of this of this site. And
that that speaks volume about their
trust, I think, that people have in
their government and the uh the health
of the uh of the decision- making
process opposed to it's like an Amazon
second headquarters but functional.
Right. So you use that word or the
phrase public trust. I mean how do we
get it back in the US to enable that
sort of progress to I'm not sure that
I'm this is a question that it goes so
far beyond nuclear. You need like a
couple more degrees and well well but I
guess what I mean is that it's not just
nuclear. I mean everything our public
debate is
so broken at the moment on everything.
In in fact, I would almost say nuclear
is miraculously one of the few topics on
which at least the two parties seem to
agree that they both want more, right?
They disagree on everything. But when it
comes to tough decisions like where to
put a repository, etc. at the moment to
me seems pretty hopeless in the United
States. Uh and again, nuclear is not the
only example. I was intrigued looking at
the designs of these these northern
European repositories that unlike Yaka
where they made a huge effort to find a
mountain that enabled you to put the
waste underground, but a mountain whose
water table was so far below the
mountain that you were almost guaranteed
that over a very long period of time
water would never enter the the
repository. But but the the Fins put it
below the water table. Well, the geology
matters, right? So the geology in the in
Scandinavia is also very conducive to
this type of repositories because it's
granite has very low porocity, very low
mobility. But we we don't have a
shortage of great Yeah. sites. It
doesn't take a Yakamount. No, it doesn't
take a Yakamount. Yeah. But you know the
history of Yakamount, it was chosen not
because of its good geology. It was
chosen for political reasons. At that
time, you know, in the Senate, the state
of Nevada was not well was not
represented very seniorly, so to speak.
And so they, you know, they pulled the
shortest straw. I suppose it doesn't
help that Nevada is one of uh several
states that doesn't actually benefit
from nuclear energy because they don't
have nuclear reactors, right? So in a
sense, you can see why the initial
conditions were bad, right? So it would
make a lot of sense to find a site in
Illinois or Tennessee or North Carolina
because those are states that rely
heavily on nuclear. So they would also
see the point of taking care of the
waste. I think for many people when you
talk about
nuclear the sort of elephant in the room
is always Chernobyl, Fukushima through
my island. How do you talk to people or
to politicians who are trying to talk to
their own constituents about like we're
going to be able to build a nuclear
power plant but avoid these mistakes?
How do you how do you sort of deal with
people's knowledge and fear? Right.
Right. Right. Well, the the the first
point I usually make is that the
technology evolves, right? So, it's a
little bit like uh cars, right? They've
been around for the longest time, but if
you're buying a car now, you're not
buying a German Trabent from the 1970s.
You're probably buying a Mercedes latest
model and it has safety belts and it's
got a whole bunch of sensors and and and
uh and and safety uh safety features
that make it a lot more reliable and
safe than than the old models. The same
is good is true for nuclear. The
difference though is that a lot of our
reactors in operation now were built
back in the 70s and the 80s, but they've
been retrofitted. They've been upgraded.
I mean, this is an the fact that the
machine or the plant has been there for
several decades doesn't mean that it's
the same plant than when it was built.
And not to put a positive spins on
accidents and accidents were were
painful, certainly damaged the
reputation and and economically the
industry. A big deal. uh but each
accident objectively has been also a
learning experience and uh the um
reliability and safety of the plants
around the world not just in the
countries that experienced the accidents
have improved as a result of the
accident. Lots of lessons learned for
all three of them. You mentioned Three
Mile Island, uh, Chernobyl, Fukushima. I
would say the one that is maybe least
interesting, but at the same time most
spectacular is Chernobyl. And I say
least interesting because it happened
for a technology and for a cultural
context that are so in many ways
irrelevant to to our own that it's hard
to draw a lot of lessons other than very
high level about you know the arrogance
of human beings thinking that they can
do whatever they want and not paying any
price for it. But the two accidents are
have been a lot more interesting and
consequential for the industry on a on a
world scale were three mile island which
was a serious accident because the uh
you know they had partial meltdown of
the core and that particular reactor
never operated again but at the same
time also show that the uh safety
structures that are built into these
reactors are very robust because that
was a serious accident but there was
essentially no release or activity. the
containment structure function perfectly
well and then Fukushima which is a lot
more recent again technology 2011 right
2011 in that case also good lessons
learned about the importance of what we
call external events things like you
know earthquake and tsunami beyond
design basis this is all jargon but what
that means is that you thought that you
know the maximum credible accident that
you can have at this site would be x but
in fact mother nature gave you x plus
20% how do you cope with that, right?
Because you can overengineer and
overbuild, etc., etc., but at one point
you got to draw a line otherwise you
never going to use these machines
because they become too expensive,
right? So then you have to be more
clever. You have to have a way to assess
what is the probability that these
things happen. But also if they do
happen, you have to have more robust
mitigation measures in place. Okay. So
all of this has been has been good
learning experience and particularly
after Fukushima I would say because it's
so recent and the industry on a global
scale is so well integrated uh uh the
lessons learned have percolated
really across the whole fleet worldwide.
So like Fukushima made every nuclear
plant get better. Absolutely. Okay.
Absolutely. So indications are as far as
I know that you know young people are
more positive about nuclear energy than
older people like say us me who
experienced Fukushima and tmi and
Chernobyl. Is that is that something
you're seeing and does it make you feel
optimistic about the future of nuclear
power here? Yeah, we we see it I think
it's again very much country dependent.
There are some interesting interesting
studies here that look at the
demographics within different countries.
they look even at political orientation,
gender, everything matters and in
different ways etc. But if you look at
sort of averages uh in the US the at the
moment it's uh the support for nuclear
let me call it generic support for
nuclear is an all-time high. I mean
you're looking at mid 70%. Which is
really really stellar. Now I you know
and I I you think okay well I'm here and
let's open a bottle of champagne right
that's great people love nuclear uh I
tend to be not skeptical but I tend not
to over um estimate that uh because
there is a difference in my opinion
between generic support and specific
support and I'm going to elaborate on
that generic support is at a time of
crisis particular when uh energy prices
are high or there is a perception that
energy secure the energy supply may not
be as secure. Um, all energy
technologies sound good, you know, like,
um, hey, energy cost a lot of money and
I don't know if I have enough. Can
nuclear provide it? Why not? You know,
like so it's good. Um, and that's great
and and the same is true for renewables
skyrocket. you know, 90% plus we lost
solar and wind. But there is a
difference between that kind of support
and then hey in your town in your county
next door we're going to put a new
corrector or or a wind farm. I was going
to say same with windmills, right? I
think people are generically for it but
against it in their town. I mean look at
all the issues we're having here in New
England, right? It' be lovely to bring
in some hydro power from Quebec but you
got to, you know, put those transmission
lines through New Hampshire and Vermont.
They don't want it. So, so then nimism
comes in right not in my backyard and
that's an issue and is that a huge
problem you think in the US and so for
for nuclear green field possibly
although not a lot of people are
proposing green field for brownfield
which means adding nuclear reactors to
sites that already have nuclear power
plants has not been an issue at all and
green field I guess would just mean like
putting it in a field somewhere like no
it simply means a site that has no
history of of nuclear energy a new
place. A new place. If you if you try to
put it at existing nuclear power plant
sites is is uh we have not seen any any
real opposition. In fact, typically the
locals will love it. They want more
because again I think you develop a
comfort and confidence in the technology
by simply living in those areas. And
it's not just that it's also the
economic benefit which are very
substantial. You know they they pay the
the plant pays a lot of local taxes. It
pays for a lot of well-paid jobs, right?
It creates a lot of well-paid jobs. So,
there are a few plants that were shut
down. You say at the beginning, the
fleet is shrinking. In the US, for a
while, it was slowly shrinking. You
know, maybe a dozen reactors that maybe
less than a dozen that were shut down.
Some for economic reasons, others
because of botched component
replacement, etc. But they were they
shut down and and we saw two clear
effects every time. One, environmentally
emissions always went up in that state,
right? You shut down a nuclear power
plant, there is this naive expectation,
oh, we're going to replace with solar.
Well, yes, in principle, you could
replace with solar and wind. In
practice, you're replacing with a little
bit of solar and wind and a lot of
natural gas. And so, the emissions go
up. Uh but number two importantly the
counties and towns where these reactors
or these power power plant were uh were
operating they went through very very
rough times uh economically speaking
because again these are big sort of
engines economic engines for the local
economy. So we've got tremendous
operating record. We've got new designs
coming online, different scales of
reactors that can fit into applications,
reactors that might not require these
external infrastructures, make them
easier to install. I'm even beginning to
feel optimistic about nuclear. I mean,
when when you look out 10, 20 years, are
are you seeing a lot of nuclear power
globally and in the United States in
particular? So at the moment in terms of
general support and policies at the
government level in
media, NOS's, environmental
organizations that is probably an
all-time high. I never seen so much
support for nuclear. So that's all good,
right? Is that automatically going to
translate into a uh you know impetuous
growth of nuclear in the US or on a
global scale? Not necessarily. And the
reason for that is twofold. We talked a
lot about economics and a lot about
cost. Unless the industry, particularly
in the US and Western Europe, can bring
down the cost of new construction, I
don't see this technology being adopted
widely. And number two, unless they
diversify a little bit their mindset,
it's not just about the power grid. The
grid is fundamentally a commodity
market. There's not a lot of money to be
made there. If they on the other end
they go more decisively for um markets
in which nuclear energy is valued more
because of its attributes because it
generate because it produces as we said
over and over again not just electricity
but heat and electricity so you got
co-generation because it's carbon free
because of reliable etc. Unless you can
monetize a little bit more of those
features, I also don't see it growing
much. So, um, so we'll see. And a lot of
this is in the hands, frankly, of the
industry. They got to sort of pull their
act together. Very good, as we said, in
Asia, nuclear industry, very good there.
In the US, very, very good at running
the plants, right? The industry here
runs the existing plants exceptionally
well. The capacity factors are through
the roof, very efficient, very safe,
very reliably. But building new ones,
the record doesn't show that they're
very good. So, and they got to become
good because growth means you got to
build new plants. So, at the moment,
we're in sort of that potential
inflection point. It could go up, it
could go down, it could stay the same.
Very hard to tell. I'm also optimistic
cuz I'm by nature optimistic, but there
are still big big uncertainties there.
Yakapo Bonjouro is a professor in the
department of nuclear engineering at
MIT. Thanks for being here. Yeah,
thanks. Thanks, Yakobo. Interesting
conversation.
[Music]
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen. And remember to
subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify, or
wherever you get your
podcasts. You can find an archive of
every episode, all of our show notes,
and a lot more at
energy.mmit.edu/mpodcasts. And you can
learn more about the work of the energy
initiative and the energy transition at
energy.mmit.edu. Our original podcast
artwork is by Zitler Design. Special
thanks to all the people at Mighty and
MIT who make this show possible. I'm
Cara Miller and I'm Rob Zer. Thanks for
listening.
[Music]