So today's class uh is uh introductory
class. We'll talk uh about the class
itself uh and uh about the program of
the class. uh uh then uh uh Jake will
talk a little bit about the uh uh
financial uh financial terms uh and uh
uh and ideas and I'll talk uh about bond
mass a little bit. So the the class is
because it is
uh organized
to introduce you uh to uh to the uh
applications of of mass in real world.
Uh the class is split between a
mathematical part which will be taught
by by Peter and uh application part uh
which will be taught by many people uh
who come from industry.
uh maybe start with a little bit of
introduction of myself uh and how it is
all comes together. So uh I I was at MIT
a long time ago. I got my PhD uh from
mass department in uh 92. Uh my adviser
was Gil Strang.
uh and uh my uh topic of my uh PhD was
has nothing had nothing to do with with
finance.
It was actually applications where it
was about wavelets uh and applications
were in signal processing. So after that
I was a mass professor for for a few
years uh and did mass research. Uh but
at some point I decided to to switch to
uh to the industry and um somehow I did
uh like mathematical finance. So since
then I've been at quant working in uh in
mathematical finance. I've worked in in
many many places for a long time. I was
with Morgan Stanley and right now I I
run uh fixed income quants at RBC.
Uh so uh
the uh
and and uh my history is definitely
I I very much uh appreciate having
experience both with academia and and
and with industry and that's what uh
what I would like to uh to show and uh
to show you through through the class.
So now a little bit more about the
class.
Uh so as I said there will be math part
and uh there will be finance part. The
the uh lectures will be intertwined not
necessarily one after another but uh but
more or less uh
in equal proportion.
uh the um
in terms of prerequisites uh I do think
that you all have uh necessary
mathematical prerequisites which is uh
linear algebra some statistics uh and
some uh probably some uh calculus and
mathematical analysis uh we don't
require any prior knowledge uh of
finance uh even though uh if you have
been doing uh some uh some work or
internships before that that certainly
helps.
Here is uh the schedule uh which we
intend to to keep and please keep in
mind that things may change and may
shift uh uh particularly with uh with
invited speakers. Uh Peter will talk uh
about the mathematical uh part uh here
but I I'll just introduce uh the uh a
few classes. So in a week's time uh Jeff
Shen from uh from Black Rockck will talk
about uh equity investing in particular
quantitative equity investing. Uh then
uh Stefan Andre from Two Sigma will talk
about principal component analysis uh
and finance which should go well
together with uh with what Peter will be
talking about at the time. Uh then uh
Andrew Constensson from Mizuho
uh will will talk uh about uh linear
rates products, swaps, bonds and curve
construction. Um then James Shepard from
Quantel Technologies which is now part
of uh London Stock Exchange will talk
about optimization uh and compress
compressing derivative portfolios.
Uh then uh very interesting uh lecture
uh by Takman Mansour uh and and uh uh
Luna Lopez from Kchi. Uh they'll talk
about their company and how they
started. They all they both are MIT
alums uh and actually uh alums from the
class from a few years ago. Uh then um
uh Ross Garham from Millennium uh will
talk uh
about investments uh in systematic
investments. Uh Andrew Law from MIT will
talk actually about applying uh some
techniques from computational finance
into uh biio medicine and biomedical
portfolio. and uh oh I I missed uh both
Jake and myself uh there but Jake will
talk about about portfolio optimization
I'll and I'll talk about uh black shaws
and and the last invited lecture will be
by John Hull uh who is u legendary in
derivative space but he will actually
talk uh uh about machine uh machine
learning his newest interest
With that, let me pass it on to Peter.
>> Okay. Thank you, M.
Let's see. Let me just page back up to
the schedule of lectures. Um, although
before that, let me give a brief
self-introduction. I have a PhD degree
in statistics and this was a
mathematical statistics program at UC
Berkeley and I was getting rather uh
distracted with mathematical uh
arguments and analysis and took a class
at the business school at Berkeley the
high school and that renewed my uh
passion basically for studying finance
and quantitative finance. Um I taught in
the statistics department at Harvard and
then joined the Sloan school where I
pursued research on financial
statistical modeling and finance. Uh
that led to interesting consulting
projects where one client uh hired well
wanted to hire me to work on a trading
program in international equities and we
ended up agreeing on becoming partners
rather than deciding how much I should
get paid for that. And so I worked uh
with hedge funds uh for a number of
years. um ultimately had the great
pleasure of uh working for ICOs, a hedge
fund in Cyprus, which is in the eastern
Mediterranean.
Um following that uh I came back to
academics actually to help with this
course uh now what 11 years ago or 12
years ago and had the great pleasure to
work with Vasili and Jake on this class.
And what I think is really important to
highlight is how the mathematics
lectures are teaching you mathematics
that's really quite practical and
useful. So um I like I I love
mathematics but I love I guess financial
uh applications even more. And so we'll
be stressing those tools that are useful
uh in financial modeling. Um I do think
it's important to emphasize the stature
of many of these guest lectures. Uh and
you're really going to be hearing from
uh people who are the top in the field
like John Hall. Many of you probably are
familiar with his work uh and Andrew
Lowe. Um and uh actually I had the
pleasure of teaching uh Tar and Lana uh
in statistics classes, one of which was
this. And uh what they've done is
created a new futures exchange
which is rather impressive. Um, when you
look at the history of the Commodity
Futures Trading Commission, there are
maybe, I don't know, 50 or so futures
exchanges that have come and gone. Uh,
maybe the most important is the Chicago
Merkantile Exchange. But here were two
students who uh basically create an
exchange where you bet on discrete
events, whether things will or will not
occur. And uh anyway, it's a it's a
great uh to have them join the class.
Well, um let's see with the different
statistics or math lectures, you can see
the range of topics. Um and these are
all uh lectures that introduce you to
these topics without much background. So
I think it provides an excellent
introduction to to the different topics.
Um, we will also be using uh the
language R in our studio for
illustrations. And I think most students
here probably are Python experts. I am
not a Python expert, so I use R. But let
me uh just tab over to
a slide showing this.
Let's see with using R. One of the
reasons for using R is that it gives you
immediate access to state-of-the-art
statistical methods that get developed
and but in addition to that it
facilitates the downloading and
collection of financial data from the
internet or from other sources that you
might have access to. uh but one can see
issues like nonlinear volatility models,
regime modeling, those are uh packages
that uh are quite useful and powerful.
Um in terms of sources of financial
data, everyone I'm sure looks at uh the
financial markets a bit and any data
that's available on Yahoo is importable
into R. Also the Federal Reserve
economic data base has all well around
80,000 different time series of
different rates. So um let's see we
distributed in the canvas site this R
notebook FM intro1
which basically uses um the R studio
cloud to uh collect data and display it.
And so this year um we have an
alternative to asking students to
install our desktop on their machines
but just to sign up to this uh R studio
cloud and you can basically with a
simple login create simple files which
we give you and display different uh
time series. So this um
this FM intro one uh R program
basically will dis collect and display
data and
you don't need to know anything except
to maybe update the dates for starting
and ending data collection.
And so one can look at the S&P 500
index, the VIX index. Uh perhaps one of
the more important indexes in uh equity
markets is the VIX index, sort of a fear
gauge. And uh it turns out that the sort
of fear gauge tends to spike when the
market drops. And so there are
interesting uh relationships between
these that actually get formalized with
option pricing theory. And let's see
just for interest there's here's the
time series for Bitcoin.
Um the beginning of this time series is
about when our class began.
And if you were fortunate to be uh at
MIT at that time, uh an alum of MIT gave
all the incoming students, I think, $100
in Bitcoin.
And uh
many years later, some of them still had
their Bitcoin keys and could cash in.
Some uh were very regretful that they
somehow lost their their Bitcoin keys.
But it's really an interesting market.
Um I I was a complete skeptic back here.
Uh and I guess I'm still a complete
skeptic, but uh that being said, you
know, there's obviously great potential
there. Um here's the time series graph
of Nvidia. Um, curiously, in last year's
notes, we displayed Nvidia
and since then
it's risen rather dramatically. Um, a
really interesting topic for
analysis is the uh creation of bubbles
in financial markets and can you detect
a bubble and when it might uh might
burst very challenging. Um let's say one
last uh point to uh illustrate was the
crude oil futures contract. Um it's one
of the more popular futures contracts
traded. Um and what's rather striking is
that in 2020
the price of this contract went negative
significantly. And this was an event
that the brokers, important brokers,
didn't program in that possibility into
their systems. And so uh when the system
sort of became updated on this day when
the price was significantly negative um
those who held say thousands of
contracts of the contract actually uh
owed money to the exchange for their
negative position. Um anyway, the
financial markets offer these cases
where surprising seemingly impossible
events can occur such as negative
interest rates. When I was studying
finance u the thought of negative
interest rates was uh was just
considered um an impossibility. So um
with that um let's see I just want to
highlight this uh
our uh our studio uh
cloud um allows you just to log in with
just a username and password and it's
free and then you can create our
programs
and it should display
the R studio
running from the cloud. And so here is a
directory in this cloud project which
has an RMD for our markdown file which
is displayed in the top left and that
simple program runs creates that HTML
file. So analyses are very easy to
illustrate with our studio and we I hope
to uh share with you various R programs
that you can use to replicate studies we
do in our lectures. All right. Um, let's
see. Finally, uh, let's see. We
distributed assignment zero today, which
is asking everyone to fill out a simple
survey of where you come from, what your
interests are, and to submit perhaps a
resume or CV if you have that accessible
so we can get to know all of you.