I'd like to start since today it's it's
March
8th
2024 I don't know if it is politically
correct so maybe MIT uh open course
whereare will cut this part but uh I
like to dedicate
this um to one special woman for me who
is my mother who would have been 100
today so that's kind of
a u dedication personal dedication any
anyway okay so we
are talking about uh exelis and today
we'll hopefully finish this uh this
part uh remember last time
we um talked about what
the the exergy associ associated with
the bulk flow uh in
state which uh is this um linear
combination of enthalpy and
entropy and which represents the
maximum work you can extract from that
Bulow uh state in this situation but it
also represents the minimum work to
produce from environmental condition uh
that same bulk Flow
State
so that means that if you combine those
two ideas and you consider a a
flow that you want to change from a bulk
Flow State one to another state two
depending
on uh what how these states are uh how
they
compare you may um be able to do that
while extracting some work or you may be
uh needing to spend some work to do that
change of
state and the work
involved always in a machine
I mean you you can picture it in terms
of a Machinery that uh always has to
interact with the environment so as to
uh perform the entropy exchanges that
are
needed so that uh the changes here are
not accomplished by entropy production
by reversibility which would
be loss of
efficiency uh but uh the entropy changes
are provided through the Machinery by
the
environment uh so the maximum work you
can extract or the minimum work you need
to
spend uh is equal to the difference in
the uh exergies between the uh input and
the output or the output and the
input and as you see
here I've rearranged this uh
expression collecting um the m dot Delta
H
outside and so this uh see this
represents uh the energy
change of of your bulk flow um and uh so
you could you could even call it
heat it's not really a heat interaction
because the bulk flow typically changes
in temperature along the pipe or uh
whatever um pieces of equipment it flows
through uh so it it as it changes in
temperature if it experiences heat
interactions there are going to be many
different heat interactions at different
temperatures but you could also
represent this as an overall uh or say
an equivalent heat interaction that
would transfer the same amount of
energy and so you get this quote
heat multiplied by something that looks
like a carau
coefficient if you
interpret Delta H over Delta S as an
equivalent heat
temperature uh then this becomes a Kel
coefficient I'm mentioning that because
often people like to um Trace back to
the to find caral coefficient
in all situations and right so this is
the correct Carno coefficient in this
situation so for
example this would be a heat pump set up
and then you want so you uh you can
define a first flow efficiency which is
the ratio of the heating of your uh flow
um to the the work you spent that's the
cop you can also call call it first flow
efficiency but it can be greater than
one and you can define a second LW
efficiency as the
ratio of the exergy associated with the
useful effect which is in this case is
heating up this
flow so this this is x 2 minus
X1 on the numerator divided by the
exergy of the resource that youve used
in this case uh the
work and um again you can
represent this changing enthalpy uh as a
as a heat you can call it heat and then
that heat gets multiplied uh by a a
Carno coefficient that transforms it to
the associated exergy as we have
seen now it turns out that this
temperature so it's the
equivalent temperature uh of a heat
source that would provide the same
amount of energy and the Chang in
enthalpy and the same amount of entropy
to the to the flow and the ratio of that
energy over entropy provided to the flow
is dimensions of temperature and we'll
see in a moment that it corresponds in
several um
cases to the logarithmic mean
temperature between the two um the inlet
and
Outlet uh before I go to
that let me take up a very simple
example but which is any any way
interesting it's uh the exergy of a
waterfall of a hydraul hydraulic
jump as you know um wherever there is
such an opportunity people have invested
and uh uh it's very hard to find a a
hydraulic jump that has not been uh
transformed in a renewable energy uh
Source this waterfall is the highest in
Europe among uh it's not the highest
waterfall but it's the highest
artificial one it was made up by the
Romans uh not for energy reasons that I
think they only needed to avoid some
floods related to
Lake that was above
there but as soon as it was possible uh
probably at the end of
U I think the 19th
century um they they started exploiting
it now uh it is um used almost every
hour of the day except when the groups
of tourists are there then they uh stop
they let the water fall
so just to to show
it because it is an
attraction okay so how do we you anal
analyze something like
that in in in an example like that the
bulk flow state is characterized not
only by the thermal aspect so is not
only a change in the
enthalpy uh but you also have to take
remember that the bulk Flow State also
has a the kinetic energy and the
potential energy in this case what's
important is the potential energy which
of course changes from this elevation to
the elevation at the bottom where then
the water goes
away you can neglect instead uh the
kinetic
energy so the energy balance reads like
this presumably this is when you um
don't just let it go as a waterfall but
you pass it through a a proper turbine
hydraulic turbine to uh to use to
transform
the uh this energy into work mechanical
work also if you recall
our formulas for the um
ideal um fluid ideal um Inc compressible
fluid the change in uh the enthalpy is
equal to the specific heat times the
change in temperature there would be
also an additional term which is a spe
plus the specific volume times the
change in pressure but here um the water
up and down is that same atmospheric
pressure so that doesn't uh
contribute so this is what we are left
with so the change in elevation or the
change in potential energy can be
transformed in either in work if you're
using it or it in in an increase in
temperature so if you uh do not exploit
uh
the
um this thing and this energy and you
just let it run as a waterfall there is
no work so this and that become equal
and if you put them equal you find that
the there is an increase in
temperature of the
water
which per unit
of uh jump or change in
elevation is given by G the
gravitational constant divided by C the
specific heat of water which is 4.2 KJ
per kilogram
K and that if you change if you
represent it in the the fancy units like
degrees Celsius over per meter it says
that if you have a
waterfall uh higher than this one 430 M
the the temperature increase uh below
will be 1°
c not
much uh then you can compute of course
the entropy produced by irreversibility
because that's the entropy
balance and uh and again you remember
what uh for the in compressible fluid
model uh the entropy goes as c times the
logarithm of the
temperatures so you can rewrite this
this way and since the temperature
increase is small just one degree is
small with respect to say the absolute
temperature we
which is like
300K so one over 300 is small with
respect to one so you can approximate
the logarithm of one plus X as
X all right and so here is
the the approximation and you find you
can compute how much entrop is produced
by irreversibility if this uh work is
zero if this formula is also valid also
if you get some work but not the entire
maximum
the maximum you get of course when uh
there is no entropy produced by IR
reversibility so so if in as far as this
is a good formula for the entropy
production it is set to zero when the
work is equal to the potential energy
change and that
is you can it's like per unit uh so per
per unit mass of uh water that falls and
per unit of
height it's equal to
G and G can be written as of course 9.8
M seconds squared but it can also be
written in these other fancy units is 42
megga per
ton over 4.3
kilomet now 4.3 kilomet is about the
height of the tallest mountain in Europe
mon
Blanc so this means that if you take a
ton of
water and uh have it pull it down by
from the top of bom blank to ca
level you get 42 Mega and 42 megga is is
an interesting number because it is the
heating power of 1 kilogram of
oil okay so that gives you the order of
magnitude of this kind
of things so you need one
ton uh and the entire height of Monon
Blanc to match what you can do with one
kilogram of oil that shows you the
density of
uh available power that is in
hydrocarbons
okay you can do the
same in uh
cooling so uh I won't
go much over the details of this uh
slide you find the same ratio here
and U
again you when you do when you analyze
problems like
this for
example you could have a situation in
which you your Machinery not
only processes a flow of material but
maybe it also uses uh heat from some
Source given temperature and then uses
work or produces work
so this uh would require that you make
an energy balance like this so you have
two working I mean two heat interactions
one with the heat Source at temperature
T Q and the other uh with the uh heat
Source uh the environment which is
always there to match to balance the
entropy and then you have your entropy
balance and then as you have seen we've
seen it several times now if you combine
these two balances by taking the entropy
balance multiplied by the environmental
temperature and subtracting it from the
energy balance you get the so-called
xergy balance where you have the various
um Heats multiplied by their
own Carno
coefficient fact the caral coefficient
of the environmental temperature is zero
here so there's no involved with the um
um with with this uh heat
interaction this is the Caro coefficient
that we just talked about associated
with bulk flow changes and this is the
exergy loss or destroyed due to the
entropy production by
irreversibility now when you compute the
change
in uh exergy for a bulk
flow and you compute it for particular
substances then you have to substitute
the constitutive relations for that for
those substances those relations that
relate uh the enthalpy and the entropy
to the temperature and the pressure for
example if we are using a liquid so this
SL slide is for a
liquid uh as I said the
enthalpy change is equal to C specific
it times the temperature change times
the specific volume you can also write
that as one over the density times the
uh pressure
change and the entropy is c times the
log of the ratio of two
temperatures now if you okay so you can
substitute collect
U yeah collect
the the heat part so that you may you
put in evidence this carol coefficient
looking like uh term and then there is a
term here which is connected with the
pressure
drops pressure drop uh as the flow goes
there now if you can neglect this
pressure
drop at least neglect these with respect
to the thermal as part of this changing
exergy then you you get that the your
changing ex exg is equal to the the heat
times the kernal coefficient and this
temperature equivalent TQ is given by
this logarithmic mean temperature of the
inlet Outlet
temperatures I do the same for ideal
gas so for the ideal
gas things change a bit because now the
enthalpy is a function only of
temperature and the Chang in enthalpy is
the specific he at constant pressure
times the changeing
temperature and it's now the entropy
that uh depends on pressure and
temperature so it's CP log of the ratio
of the T minus r log of the ratios of
the p ratio of the
pressures so you get uh you can put it
in exactly the C same formal relation
except that here you have a c CP instead
of c and here you have the log of the
rati the
pressures this is again related to the
pressure
drop
um
namely the work you need to spend in
order to overcome the friction forces
over along the the pipe in order to make
the flow uh um
overcome those but if you can neglect
those then we get again this formula and
again TQ is the log mean
temperature and there is a third case in
which you have a similar situation which
is whenever you are changing phase your
flow is maybe boiling or
condensing
um then the change in alpy is equal to
the change in the
quality of the so the The Vapor fraction
that we defined last time it's a so the
changing quality times the enthalpy
vaporization for H2 minus H1
or the change in quality times the
entropy of vaporization for the change
in entropy so you can also do the same
thing put out outside uh the the energy
change of your flow call it
q and what's left as a form of a Caro
ratio where the TQ is the ratio between
the enthalpy and the entropy of
vaporization which is exactly the
temperature at which uh the boiling and
or condensation
occurs
so for example let's compute
this
number uh for the case of heating water
which is useful for for example
industrial uh applications you often
need uh steam or hot water to for many
processes or Residential
Heating to heat up your homes
all right so if so what we what I want
to compute is the this
carau
coefficient which you see is therefore
the ratio between the
exergy over the heat that is
provided so it's it's the exergy content
of your heated water after you heat it
that's the exoy and the exoy remember is
the
minimum work required to do that uh
job so this ratio exergy change over
heat represents the
minimum work per unit
energy of your
heating and uh so that is
useful so it's it's the best you can
do so if you compute it for these uh
temperatures from say heating water from
60 Dees to 120 which corresponds to an
industrial
application
and assume an environment at
300K at 27° C
here's the number you you compute that
number you get
17.2% If instead you you're you're
needing water from 20 to 60 degrees
Celsius in the same environment that
would be
4%
okay so this is interesting because for
example let me ask you
with this number can you tell me what is
the second LW
efficiency of doing for example this
heating uh this heating with an electric
boiler an electric boiler uses
electricity electricity is pure
exergy all right so how do you define
the second law efficiency it's AA
2 is equal to the
exergy of your
uh uh
result useful
effects times the
xergy
consumed all
right so in this case you're using work
the the xergy consumed is equal to the
work that you're using in your electric
boiler and the
exergy up
there is Q * 1 -
ta/ TQ where TQ is the logarithmic mean
temperature so it's precisely what we
have computed
here now in an electric
boiler your work is completely
transformed into heat by Jewel
effect so even if if your boiler were
100% efficient very well
insulated you get that Q is equal to
W
okay so we are left that the second low
efficiency is
equal in this case to
4% so 4% and this is the kind of
efficiency that signals how much room
for improvement is there so there is 96%
room for improvement
nevertheless we do use electric boilers
but
where you use them where uh you don't
need to this to heat water all the all
the time for example in the south of
Italy uh where I have a small house with
olive trees and I go there just for the
summer I have electric boilers
because I use them maybe one month per
year so the cost uh the investment
cost uh doesn't uh uh wouldn't pay if I
buy a more efficient equipment like
would be a heat
pump or even a gas which is sort of
intermediate because the more efficient
is the equipment the high higher the
more complicated is the Machinery so the
higher the cost and so the
uh if I use it for only few months a
year I uh it doesn't pay to invest that
much so but still you have to keep that
in mind that this is the idea and
maybe I could have uh uh invested in uh
solar thermal
heating okay which would even save me
the cost of
electricity at the expense of uh
investment cost for the
equipment but also that as a problem in
in some uh countries and especially in
the countryside where uh these equipment
is left outside with nobody watching uh
it's it is easily stolen so uh that's
another uh issue uh
security all
right so we talked we we let me say a
little more about uh fuels because we
will u in the second part of the course
we will uh uh do
um systems with chemical reactions and
uh so we will return to this in in much
more detail but for the moment let me
just say that if I were to heat up
something uh or water with with a gas
boiler I would need to put here the
exergy of the fuel that I have consumed
so how do you compute exergy for a fuel
right the the the idea is the following
you take your fuel
at environmental conditions and in uh
the and you mix
it or keep it separate uh with
um the sufficient just sufficient air so
the stochiometric amount of air that is
needed to oxidize that
fuel and then you have
a piece of
equipment which um you try to make as
close to reversible as
possible and while this equipment
produces the combustion or the oxidation
of your fuels and therefore produces
products of
combustion it produces also
work it needs as usual an interaction
with the environment so as to exchange
the entropy that is needed
to perform uh to to balance the entropy
without the need of
irreversibility and uh so this result is
the exergy of your fuel the maximum work
you can
extract while your products of
combustion notice
are down in mutual equilibrium with the
environment so are again at
environmental
conditions so typical
we will see that
um the exergy of the fuel will be given
by this expression we will define an
enthalpy of of the
combustion reaction and an entropy of
combustion so this will be this
combination is the Gibs free energy
of the combustion at standard conditions
of pressure and temperature that's the
meaning of the not up there the
superscript and with a minus in front
that will
be uh um the most the most important
contribution to the exergy of the fuel
there will be some term related to
mixing that we will see later uh
regarding the heat of the heating Val
value the heating value if I go back to
this previous slide now
suppose I don't have
any uh work extraction here and all I
have is a an interaction with the en
environment and uh and so I burn my fuel
and then exit the products so cool down
the products at uh of combustion at an
environmental temperature in order to
cool uh that doing that cool cooling
down I need to extract heat that heat is
the heating value of the
fuel again we'll return to
those the message
here for practical uh applications in
which you need to to compute exergy of a
fuel
the the rule of f is that U turns out
that for all hydrocarbons we'll see the
the detail the
list the ratio of this part of the
contribution to that part is
small plus or minus
2.5% so if you accept that kind of
approximation and typically in exg
computations you can you can afford that
kind of precision uh you can simply see
can neglect this part and so see that
the xgy and the
heating value are approximately equal so
you can say that the exergy of the fuel
is approximately equal to the heating
Val to to the yeah to
the yes to the heating value of the fuel
which is all in turn approximately equal
to the lower uh heating value
as you know there is a distinction
between lower heating value and higher
heating value which has to do with the
fact that in the products of combustion
there is
water and if you do the cooling of that
water uh of that um stream of produ
combustion down to environmental
conditions some of the
water will condense
and U and that uh and so the condensing
of the water releases the enthalpy of
vaporization and that is additional uh
energy that you can in principle
extract so the the difference so they
you call lower heating value when
you uh we you you pretend that water
doesn't doesn't condense even even if
you're going down to 25
Celsius and the higher heating value is
the opposite case you pretend that it
all condenses even though uh in part of
the water remains is a form of vapor
mixed with the products of combustion so
these are two extremes and for example
methane has a lower heating value of 50
megga per
kilogram and a higher heating value of
55 so it's it's not an an important
effect it's like 10% the contribution
the difference so the contribution of
condensation
okay in this table I
listed some heating values of some
typical fuels
um
yes there are still technical units
around in Europe it's like kilo Cals per
kilogram here you get still
BTUs per
pound
um International System of Units is more
like Jews this is Mega per kilogram
and you see that more or less when you
present uh in terms of these units per
kilogram the fuels have different
definitely heating
values but they are within a limited
range they're all around 40 42 is crude
oil I mean a typical value because crude
oil is varies a lot from place to place
but the
uh the the the canonical standard is 42
megga that number that we've uh
corresponds as we've seen in this
waterfall example to lifting one ton of
water up to the top of mon Blanc from
sea
level the same energy is what is needed
to heat up one ton of water by 10
degrees Celsius
or to evaporate not one ton but 18
kilograms of water at atmospheric
pressure so that's also oxidizing 1
kilogram of
oil so that's the heating value of 1
kilogram if you compare it to the power
density in some other uh
uh natural I mean resource for
a for primary energy fish of uranium
isotope to
233 a half milligram of that will give
you that same amount so you see how
different U uh concentrations of
energies we we
have okay
now for reasons that we will see later
but also just for fun you can plot on a
uh this
graph uh the history of efficiencies
second low
efficiencies
of technologies that man
mankind has developed uh over the years
uh to
convert uh fuel exergy into
work starting from the early
um the beginning of the Industrial
Revolution in in in England where you
would use a
vapor uh to extract uh to pump water out
of the coal
mines and then you see recognize here
some names see this were efficiency of
the order of this number is um okay I'm
sorry the efficiency are on this side of
the graph it's like
1% today you go
up we are of the order of
60 65 almost
65% the best available
technology is of is is reaching this
much um the the the
diagram is made a straight line by
plotting not the in
linear you see this scale is not linear
in the second low efficiency it's linear
in the efficiency over the one minus the
efficiency so the the efficiency divided
by the room for improvement this ratio
is called the logistic
scale uh you could plot the same diagram
on a linear scale for for and you you
would get a typical s shaped curve
typical of any
learning
process and in fact fact you see and you
can even write the the differential
equation for this uh to obtain this
formula from which it is interesting to
that you extract the time constant the
characteristic time of this
learning and this time constant is 60
years
right uh I think it you can prove that U
it's related to
this slope here the maximum height so in
other words it took us 300 years to go
from 1% to
65% and we are not done
yet H because you you know this is the
second low efficiency the upper limit is
one so that means that we
will
continue so at the end of this
Century if we if our learning process
goes
on uh we will be at
85% and still it will go at least this
is what history uh tells
us but since the remarkable cor
correlation is very remarkable here it's
very likely that we we do uh since this
is typical of any human there are uh um
there is an entire section of the
literature about the studies of the
history of technologies that represent
many uh other Technologies uh of on
these logistic graphs and they all show
similar Behavior you could also plot
here
um the number of words of that a child
learns uh during his um
from when it doesn't speak to when it
starts speaking and it follows the same
curve
okay and here also for fun I just
uh put the arrows on the
timeline where the various names that
are associated with thermodynamics see
ranking balsman and so on
um are placed with respect to this
graph somewhere I
think somewhere
here or is it there yeah no probably
here um that name
moer um who gave the name of uh to the
to the graph the to the to the enthalpy
versus entropy graph that I discussed
the other
day uh he's here and he
um he's also important because his
student was nelt nelt is another name
you might have heard from he transfer so
he was a student of moer and actually I
think it's we pronounce it moer think
that it is French but he was German so I
don't know how the German pronounced M
but I'll let you figure it
out in any case if you like I also put
this slide because I wanted to advertise
uh if you click here you go to the
proceedings of a conference that we held
uh U 2008 uh in memory of Professor
Kenan and uh uh so we Ed at this volume
and there are contributions about the
this the state of thermodynamics at that
time which is not very different from
the current one with big names including
uh Sten Chu Max Tark
and many others that U are considered
big uh big names in in the field of
thermodynamics and
energy all all right
so why am I talking about that all right
well
because we've seen the history tells us
that we are going to to to go to 85%
efficient by the end of the century now
how can we do that because currently we
the point of this slide is that uh we
cannot do it with current
technology at least not with the current
technology that uses the fuel to burn uh
to to in a flame in a combustion process
the reason is because this is the the
philosophy of of our uh traditional
power plants flame based is that you
burn the
fuel and with the hot products of
combustion you hit some working fluid
and you put it somewhere and you make it
work in a thermal uh
cycle the thermal
cycle for example in a combined gas uh
turbine and U gas turbine and steam
thermal
cycle has an efficiency of about 85% so
it means that your irreversibility in
your power plant waste only 15% of the
exit that that thermal part of your
power plant receives from the hot
product of
combustion and then you have the
flame the flame per se by itself without
losing one uh BTU of energy um wastes
because because it's an IR reversible
process wastes 25% of the
exergy so if you multiply the two
efficiencies here 75 * 85 you get about
64 and that's the
explanation of why so 64 it means that
we are wasting uh
36% of the
exy and where is where is that wasted
okay 25 here and another 15 or or more
or less here
so how so you see in order to get to
85% we must we must get rid of the uh
ways that we have in combustion we must
use the fuel not by burning it but in
some other
way as we
go uh um and as we will treat combustion
in a few
weeks we will end up drawing this
diagram in which you have the enthalpy
versus entropy looks like an energy
versus entropy diagram you have the fuel
air mixture here and the product of
combustion there and it turns out that
when
you burn your fuel in the
flame what you do is to move from this
to that and you produce entropy by
reversibility
whereas before burning it your fuel had
an exergy which is represented by this
much and
uh you have now here it has an exy that
is represented by this much so you've
wasted this much
because of this
irreversibility so that
is the Flames are the bottleneck of
efficiency in uh fuel U usage to power
conversion and this is why people
realized that of course and uh they've
worked they are working
on
developing
alternatives to uh this way of
burning instead of the
flame for example with the fuel
cells you oxidize your your
fuel while you are also extracting
electrical
energy because you see in order to avoid
the irreversibilities in uh you need to
be
quick um for example in an internal
combustion engine when you engine when
you light the
spark uh at the top that Center and the
the the fueler mixture starts to burn
there is a flame which propagates so you
you can view it in slow motion it takes
a while
to uh and Trin the entire combustion
chamber but in reality that happens in
milliseconds
so you have to be quicker than
that if you want to do it at that
level or you have to develop
alternatives
to um to
Flame for example you can determine a
different path to of oxid the fuel with
intermediate steps so that you can
control the intermediate steps uh and uh
in and use them more avoid the
reversibilities or you can use the fuel
cell which does it with
electrochemistry and then you can
integrate your uh fuel cell in a thermal
cycle that uses the thermal the thermal
energy that is released so the the
entropy that needs to be taken away from
the fuel cell is going to be used by a
bottoming uh thermal cycle and just
doing
that uh on paper you can you you I least
here some efficiencies that can already
be
reached which go beyond uh the limit of
flames
okay and this takes me
to this last topic of the first
part which is also going to be the topic
of the uh homework that I will put out
today regarding
that I'm going to put a deadline uh uh
uh which is just before uh the the
spring break
but just I did that because I want you
to be free for the spring break but if
you need to take more time feel free to
do it uh but I don't want to spoil your
your your your spring break but if you
even if you want an extra 10 days do
take them I don't really care it's your
choice so there is an official deadline
but it's not it can be
broken all
right so allocation why do we need why
is uh this problem uh
interesting okay the question what's the
question that it
answers what fraction of the
fuel consumed in a
co-generation
facility should be allocated to the heat
produced you now in a cogeneration
facility we use the
fuel and it produces not only
electricity but it also produces
heat which can be used for industrial or
for
residential uh
uses okay
uh that heat that is produced this way
goes into the
homes and it is important to know how
much primary energy was used to produce
it why is it
important because of real estate uh and
efficiency
regulations now almost all countries and
I listed hear the names of
uh these regulations in various
countries see it it goes from
Europe uh uh almost anywhere including
of course the US Energy performance
certificate of building or energy score
home energy
score it
essentially tells you of your house what
the level of efficiency and that level
of efficiency determines the value of
your house if I go by by a house I care
about how much it consumes because
that's the bills I will receive to heat
it up uh and so if it is a an efficient
house it's it's more uh has more value
than in inefficiency
okay so this problem in fact
uh it's very since in order to compute
this energy score you need to
know uh among the various parameters
it's not only how good are the windows
and uh the walls and so on but uh the
roof but it's also how efficient is the
equipment that you're are using in order
to produce the heating
and if
you live in a city like braa or if you
live at MIT now I I know that also here
we have the same problem that you have a
a a co-generation facility which is not
in your house but it's somewhere else in
town and then through pipes they send
heat to
you in order to do that calculation of
the home energy score you need to know
how much energy was consumed was is
behind that heat that you are
using which
substitutes your local uh um boiler or
gas boiler
that you you have in standard so so in
my condominium I still have a the gas
boiler so the the question is easily
answered I look up how much heat I has
been produced over one year how much gas
I I I paid and that's that tells me how
much energy is behind my uh BTU of heat
produced but if it is co-produced
cogenerated in a um heat and power
uh
facility combined hit and power CHP
facility then uh the question is not
that
simple so here's the
scheme here's the the facility which
produces work and heat and uses
fuel now
normally that
work would be produced in a separate
production facility that uses just some
fuel uh and produces only work and that
heat would be produced like in my gas
burner by a separate
production uh equipment that uses some
fuel and produces that
heat so the question is how do we
compare this separate
production uh scenario with a
cogeneration uh facility and how
uh you see the the the reason is that we
know before we start I mean without any
uh
additional discussion we we can
compute how much fuel we saved with
respect to the separate production that
is called primary Energy
savings it is defined as
the the ratio of the difference between
what I would consume in a separate
production what I actually consume
in my co generation facility
divided uh with by the what I consumed
with the reference production so that's
this is the
ratio and we know that in um typical
cogeneration facilities allow you to
save between 20 and
40% so we're talking about large amounts
that's why it is
uh it is pursued and done
so we know how much uh that's the
overall
savings but the problem is
that in order to uh do that calculation
for the home um energy
[Music]
um uh parameter uh is you need to you
need another
number you need essentially the cop for
the for the
heat it's how much uh the efficiency it
says see you need you need this to know
this
denominator how much of the fuel which
has been used in the cogeneration
facility has to be assigned to the
production of heat
and there is some arbitrariness into how
we Define this it there's no yeah some
people claim there is a thermodynamic
we'll see that exergy some the exergy
people will will claim that that's uh
the method that you should use but in
our discussion we we show that that's
not
appropriate not
yet so we need
to uh Define allocation factors so
suppose we have these allocation factors
Alpha they add up to one so essentially
it's the percentage of fuel that we
think uh is been used
for uh say Alpha W for the work
production line and for the heat
production line so you think of your Co
generation facility as an equivalent
separate production facility in which or
or has having two internal
lines if in fact if your combined
production was simply that you have two
separate lines then you would easily
find what the alpha is you just uh use
whatever goes on one line and whatever
fuel goes on the other line
but uh the
combined heat and power uh is best when
you don't have separate you but it
is using the various levels of uh of of
temperature at which your working fluids
are to do what is appropriate to to
reduce the irreversibilities and so you
have a lot of equipment here in which
which which play the game and uh and uh
uh of
both uh
they are both on the side of the work
production and of the heat
production but in any case suppose we
have these alphas
and okay then for example we could
Define the separate efficiency so the
partial efficiencies partial efficiency
of work production would be the work
divided by the amount of fuel only the
part that I have associated with the
production and and the cop for heat is
the heat divided
by the complt to add so that's the
that's the energ the the fuel
energy uh associated with the heat
production and of course you can also
compute partial primary Energy
savings by
comparing what the amount of fuel that
was that is
um that the amount of fuel that
is used in separate production you
subtract what you actually uh consume in
your cogeneration facility so that's the
numerator and compare it to the separate
production so that gives you the savings
of the cogenerate on con Co generation
with respect to partial to the
production of of of electricity
and the same for
heat okay and if you have that number
Alpha q that number Alpha Q is what is
needed for the home
index efficiency
index so in the beginning of cenation
people reasoned
uh and
defined uh these allocation factors in
this way
they we call this uh method the
incremental electricity centered
allocation it basically says all right I
in my cogeneration facility I produced
this much
work if I produced it in the
reference separate production facility
I would have with this reference
efficiency I would have consumed this
much fuel W over the reference
efficiency okay so that in my
cogeneration plant I produce more than
that I I'm sorry I consume more than
that fuel I consume
F so if I subtract what I would have
consumed in the for the production of
the of that work it means that the extra
fuel
I'm consuming
is attributed to the heat that
I'm
producing and
therefore you would put a denominator
here you would assign to that
heat this extra fuel with respect to the
separate production of the electricity
that You' have
done but this of course course is
unfair
because it assigns all the primary
Energy
savings to the
Heat and zero to the
work if it is true that microgeneration
facility saves 40% of the
fuel uh the benefit it means that there
is a benefit of cogeneration and that
benefit is it really all due to the
production of heat or is it should be be
distributed between the two
products so uh
another more balanced way of
reasoning which to cover later is
um to
Define maybe some uh local or state
Authority Energy Authority
defines or states in some standards uh
reference values for the
efficiencies of
uh separate production of heat of heat
and work okay so they Define some
reference
values and then they
say all right
use as a location
factors the
weighted uh
fraction of what you would have consumed
by
producing the same W and same Q in
separate
facilities so this defines because this
W over ATF is the fuel you would have
consumed if you produced this amount of
electricity in separate production and Q
over Coop reference
is uh the fuel that you would have
consumed if you have produced that
amount of Q the same as your
cogeneration facility in a separate
production
okay the the good thing about these
allocation
factors is that it distributes equally
the primary Energy
savings to the Heat and the water work
so so that the primary average the
the the partial primary Energy savings
for work is equal to the partial energy
saving for heat and it's equal to the
overall partial Energy
savings the question
is what reference values should the the
the authority
select okay one method is to Simply uh
do it arbitrarily or maybe do it by some
logic you publish it and it stays there
for some years then maybe you update
that uh those reference
values The Other
Extreme is you
select uh the
exergy
reasoning so you say well let's use as
reference values the best you could
do namely the reversible
processes
yes earlier didn't
reques efficieny
of proding
yes uh yes at the beginning uh certainly
it was an easy way of reasoning it
didn't require an authority to Define
and also you didn't have the
motivation the motivation came and this
is how we came with this uh question and
this is how U uh I'll give you the
reference to a paper with with your
advisor Professor gonan we worked
together on this
problem because uh the utility which
produces District Heating in braia came
uh to us and asked okay we have a
problem now because we are giving these
numbers but with these numbers uh uh
every apartment uh goes into the top
class we are signing so low uh um
consumption of of fuel to the heat that
we are providing them that they are so
happy they they are in class A Plus even
with the windows open no so it doesn't
make sense that's why they came and so I
said we need something more and so they
also after these discussions they also
went to the European community and
change the and have them change the uh
regulations
yeah um so the exergy the exergy uh idea
is let's take as reference the best we
could
do and the best we could do is the
reversible uh the reversible case
so so what is the the best we could
do in terms of
uh
efficiency for work
production so if I
have uh to produce this much work
and I'm using a
fuel with an
xergy that is this much
X well if there are no irreversibilities
in my Machinery so it's irreversible the
exergy gets all transformed there is no
loss of exergy so the exergy of the fuel
goes all into exergy of the product so
it's one to one so w Max
or let say
rev is equal to the exergy of the fuel
but the exergy of the fuel we said is
approximately equal to the heating value
let's call it qf to
simplify so that means that this
Machinery uh reversible Machinery that
would do that has a first low efficiency
which is what we call AA
W ref
which is the
work
produced uh first law so it's uh divided
by the the heat the heating value of the
fuel the energy that has been consumed
but this is also approximately equal to
uh to the exy of the fuel and as you see
here this is approxim
one
whereas the same story if I use my
fuel and I want to produce
heat uh at the temperature
TQ the
exergy of that heat is this and if I
have no
reversibility all that goes into
this so the
AA um let's call it
cop would be the would be the the
Q divided by the
energy of the fuel because cop is a
first law idea so uh the energy of of
the
fuel and the energy of the fuel is um is
qf but
qf again is
approximately
x f
so this is
Q divided by the the ex the exit gets
all transformed in that so here in the
denominator I put q1 minus t over
TQ okay so the cop is one of the over
the caral
coefficient calculated at the
temperature of our uh production heat
production
so you certainly can do that so I'll
give you a numerical example for this in
a
moment so here is uh here's the
paper with Professor Gan and another
colleague of mine in bracia Pao
yora with which we sort of addressed the
issue
and acknowledge that there is
no correct way to do it you have to
uh uh it's hand waving and it's um it's
arbitrary in some
sense
but
uh the idea that we introduced was this
uh
okay suppose even suppose this this this
Lo local
Authority uh has to decide what uh
efficiencies to reference efficiency to
to to set uh what what Criterion should
they
use well they would
look at their local area and by local
area it could be a small District it
could be a town uh it could be State
could be a nation it could be uh
uh Europe no it could it could do this
at various levels because there are
standards local standards and so
on in in the homework I'll give you
reference to a an European Standard
which was
2007 uh which had the the the issue
so I frankly I didn't follow up but I'm
sure that they've improved a lot with
recent
standards so that means that the problem
is of Interest also at the European
level which is
congregation the community of several
Nations okay so you you do
take take the data that come from
various facilities in your local area
every facility is always um um obliged
to uh communicate to to some energy
Authority their consumptions and their
Productions yearly at least
yearly and and so take those
data and look at your um
overall
system as a cogeneration system because
after all it produces work and
heat and therefore
and you know how much fuel has been uh
used for each of
them so
uh if
I okay so if I have a
assigned a value for the allocation
factors like Alpha W and Alpha Q so if
I'm the authority I decided these
numbers with these
numbers those who have combined heat and
power facilities have used them in order
to to compute their own um partial
efficiencies so they will tell me how
much fuel they have used or his behind
this work and how much is behind the
heat so I compute the overall uh
efficiency for the heat production and
for the work production for the local
facility I mean for the local
area but then I can also apply my
same uh rules or or allocation
coefficients allocation fractions to the
local
area
viewed overall as an overall com
combined heaten power
facility
and if I have
given the correct values of
alpha I should get the same
number whether I look at it locally with
small
[Music]
facilities or the overall facility or
overall local area system okay so that
was
uh uh that was the method that we
have provided and here's an
example with some
numbers so suppose we have a local area
and suppose that we have a separate
production
facilities that have a
52% efficiency for energy for
electricity
and 90% so 0.9
cop for the production of heat like
industrial
boilers and here is a the combined heat
and power plant is a is a combined
cycle this is also a back back um
pressure steam turbine data but I'm I'm
going to discuss only this one and these
are two parameters that characterize a
combined cycle so it's the ratio of the
work to the heat that is
produced and
the first LW
efficiency so 778
so suppose
that the reference volumes are taken
uh as the values of the uh separate
Productions in my local area 52 and
90 here are the numbers that so look at
just the first line here are the numbers
that come out with the three methods
that we discussed so far so the
electricity centered
gives H keeps uh essentially the same
efficiency for the electricity as
separate production because and it gives
all the advantage to the heat so it
would make it appear that you are
producing heat with a cop of
354 that created that problem that uh I
told you of um and um
unfair
and
unacceptable to much advantage to to the
heat in a sense if you kept that
everybody would want the district
heating so it will be a fight uh to have
the your houses to be District
heated if you do the exergy which is the
Other Extreme
method okay the electricity
efficiency goes
down and the cop is still very
high if you use this the separate
production method with these
references this gets more
reasonable what's reasonable is that um
there is an increment in the separate
production I mean in the partial
efficiency for work and
also the same
increment uh for heat so if you if going
from 52 to
63 uh is say an increment of um maybe
what
20% uh well also going from 90
to 10 109 109 is 20% so you have uh
evenly distributed youve treated equally
work and heat so you gave to both work
and heat the same um weight or the same
advantage of U the co
generation but the problem what the
problem yeah a problem is that when you
now
compute for your local
area uh
the uh local average of the
efficiencies you don't
find the same
values for in this example here suppose
you have uh so you have to Define uh how
important is cogeneration is in your
local
area and so you you have to Define an
electric index which is 50% in this
case that means that heat
is like
twice the
work and also that your cogeneration
facilities cover 40% of the heat
production in the local area okay with
these numbers you you can compute the
local
averages and uh these local average are
62 for work and
96.8 for
heat for work it's not too far but for
heat it's far because 109 is very far
from
so what we proposed is simply to say all
right let's use the local areas numbers
and use them as reference
so if I use them as
reference I get uh of course numbers
change and the local numbers get
closer but not yet I have to keep doing
so if I iterate at a certain stage I get
oops I get
to a place in which um
yeah in principle I should get that
these these two numbers become
equal and
also so there's no more Improvement and
so the the local area so the
the yeah the local areas and I'm not
sure um these numbers are really correct
because this 90.8 is is
92 uh so there may be something wrong in
this uh numbers because the idea was I
believe but I may be wrong now so you
check it check check on me because uh
that this should become almost equal in
the long
run all right so that's that's the uh
that's the
idea
uh but story is not finished because now
this same
uh issue of allocation comes up also
when you have a
hybrid
uh facilities hybrid power
plants for
example you know that
um we could use solar
energy
for
uh for heating water
and one way of course so you have solar
energy and suppose you have one of
those parabolic mirrors that uh Focus
the solar energy onto a
pipe and in this pipe you run
um water or you r run a mixture of
molten Souls so that you can go higher
temperatures or you got you run dimal
oil so that it doesn't boil so you R run
a fluid that takes up that that
heat depending on what fluid you use you
can reach different
temperatures for example
with air and
water uh
you can you can go uh
maybe if you pressurize it you can go
120 degrees
C maybe higher but you have to go higher
pressures with dimal oils you can go up
to
300 350 because then the at higher
temperatures the oil disg gregates and
so you reach some technological limits
there molten Souls you can can reach
maybe 500
550 so people have built uh power plants
with this idea of concentrating solar
energy
these mirrors follow the Sun so that you
use it
efficiently there are other um
architectures of similar ideas like you
have lots of uh mirrors on on your field
and there is a
tower and your pipe is there so the
sunlight with the mirrors hits this uh
hits up this
um this pipe that is up there and there
way that way you concentrate and you get
high
temperatures and then the rest one once
you have these high temperatures you can
use your standard thermal cycle and
convert thermal energy into mechanical
and then electrical
work so no problem about that uh this
belongs to the realm of renewable
facilities that uh obtain important
incentives from States governments and
uh
um and so
uh those are very important because they
allow you to pay for the uh equipment
and some some of
these uh helps are in for example here I
gave examples of tax
credits uh cash grants loan programs all
sorts of different uh things and this is
just only uh something in the United
States all every country has his own way
of doing this
it's
similar to what you do for photovoltaic
uh
um so the photovolatic is is a direct
conversion of solar energy into
electricity this is a less less direct
it goes through heat uh and then you
have a power plant and in the end you
also produce
electricity
okay so what is the uh uh what is the
problem the problem is that
sometimes when you do these um power
plants it is also uh useful to hybridize
it in other words uh use this heat
yes in your facility but you use also
some
fuel use that heat but use also some
fuel
because that allows you to use the the
facility more hours per year for example
or maybe it allows you to increment the
temperatures and improve on the overall
efficiency or and so uh it's either that
you start from a solar facility and
hybridized using fuel or sometimes which
also happen
very often uh you start from a
traditional facility fuel based and you
hybridize it by putting a solar field on
the side to for example provide the low
temperature heating that the fuel does
in a less efficient way or do some other
kind of integration okay so in all these
hybrid uh uh
problems uh the
important aspect is that the important
question is all right I I produced work
electricity the question is how much of
that electricity that I produce can be
said to be renewable and how much is not
because the renewable fraction gets the
incentives the other not doesn't so even
here we have a problem which is entirely
dual to the one that we have discussed
and that's that's why I'm going to go
fast on
this but uh I will ask you uh in your U
homework which by the way this is a a
heavier homework so is more is also more
work at
uh it's so it will have two parts two
videos one with a with a problem on
cogeneration and the other is uh put
words in these slides about uh uh this
part of the hybrid
facilities
so uh in any case the The Duality stands
on the fact that in the previous problem
we had the alphas on the left hand side
here we have the betas on the uh right
hand side which which so beta R is the
renewable fraction of electricity so
beta R is the key is the number that
will give you access to these economic
incentives uh also here you can uh talk
about primary energy uh savings and also
talk
about um partial efficiencies where you
put up
there um you see f is the fuel is the
it's the hydrocarbon that you're using
and R is the solar energy
okay so um you again you you sort of
think once you have this betas you can
think that your um hybrid facility has
two lines one is the one that produces
electricity starting from the fuel and
the other that
starts produces other electricity
starting from
solar and you want to do this
splitting so
uh you can Define the primary Energy
savings with respect to separate
production so separate production would
be I only have one solar facility and
one fossil fuel facility
separate apparently they it is better if
you combine them you get higher
efficiencies um I don't have experience
so I don't have the numbers of uh if it
is of the same order maybe 40% is is is
too much but uh uh for sure there is a
some improvement in some uh in in the
overall efficiency also
here uh again at the beginning and
perhaps even still now because I don't
know if this problem is evolved uh
enough
um there is
a there is one way uh that we call
incremental fossil Center where you give
priority to uh to the renewable and so
you said all right I use that fuel with
that fuel I usually produce this much
electricity fine so the extra
electricity is attributed to the
solar but that's
unfair because it gives a it doesn't
distribute evenly the the primary Energy
savings so again you can use a a
separate production
um method like uh like we did for the
other case and again you could use
exy here only one point I need to uh um
to to explain is
that I use uh what's the
exergy of solar energy that's a chapter
in
itself uh but if you You could argue
that there are some papers I can give
you references to those papers
um we also contributed some
um a good number is this of course there
there are formulas that get you to this
one
and meaning that you know energy coming
from the Sun comes from a very high
temperature Source the order of uh
this many k
Kelvin that so the photons that come
from the Sun carry not only energy but
also
entropy but then uh there is a problem
that you it gets to the
atmosphere and you get to the surface of
the Earth you get some direct lights and
some rays and some indirect
through def fraction
and
yeah so so from the sky uh the sky has a
certain temperature so there are lots of
of reasoning that go behind the number
like this and so again this is a chapter
in itself but in any case the the
problem here is is
that
H with the exergy
method yeah uh you're using the
reversible uh you're using the
reversible heat engine as a as a
reference and that is uh not feasible
actually I see that the time is over so
maybe we'll return just with few words
at the beginning of next lecture about
this because I there's still something I
want to say that I didn't and it is
important also so hold on don't do the
homework yet okay all right so I'll see
you next time see you Tuesday