Our next speaker is Adam Chapala who is
a professor of electrical engineering
and computer science here at MIT also a
member of Seesale and Adam is going to
discuss AI powered integrated
development environments or idees. Thank
you. Let's hear for Adam.
So, so I also need to start my
presentation like Daniel's with a
confession which is kind of a related
one. Especially a few years ago, I would
often describe myself as the last person
standing in the ECS department who
wasn't working on on AI. Uh so given
that how do I find myself speaking to
you today? Well, let me tell you a
little bit about my background. So, I
started my career uh in in the software
industry as a high school intern working
at a company that did contract
development of e-commerce websites and
learned all about the practicalities of
creating enterprise software and got
into even creating developer tools to
support this kind of stuff. And then as
I learned about what kind of methods
would be most effective for supporting
quality in software, I gravitated in in
my uh university career towards this
specialty of formal methods where we
actually do mathematical proofs showing
that pieces of software or hardware are
correct, secure, etc. And I came to be
one of the few people in the world who's
thinking about both of these topics at
once. The process of building enterprise
software and deep mathematical
guarantees about correctness. This is
very much at odds with at least the uh
the caricaturured idea of of AI and
machine learning as not giving you very
strong
guarantees. So uh now I want to step
back and muse about this phenomenon of
AI coding.
So uh I just want to stop and think
about why LLM assisted programming is
being so successful in industry these
days and then step back and ask the
question what new abstractions could we
develop that would make this sort of
thing even more effective and then how
should programming change based on those
abstractions. So uh from the the title
and abstract of my presentation, you
might have expected I was going to give
an overview of the most popular tools
today and give you suggestions of which
which already popular systems you should
adopt. I'm just going to briefly name
check the kind of tools you're probably
used to thinking about and then I'm
going to spend most of my time on on an
alternative perspective. So there are
all these co-pilot style coding
assistants out there that you use to
sort of solve targeted challenges within
a codebase where you point somewhere and
give some text and say make it better in
this way. And then there are tools like
a a popular one at the moment is lovable
that will take a sort of a requirements
document for a software app and go off
and write it for you pretty
autonomously. Why do these these kind of
tools in both categories work well? And
there's been some echoes of this already
in the previous presentations, but
basically my take is they work because
of on average low novelty in in the
world of software engineering. Most
programs that are being written are
actually highly similar to programs that
have already been written and are maybe
even in the training sets of the the
machine learning models. So as a result,
AI assisted coding can work more like a
smart search engine than like a
reasoning engine. It's finding all the
little bits and pieces out there that
are very similar to what you're looking
for and doing some some light reasoning
to put them together for you
effectively. Now, the software
engineering world has lots of experience
with what can go wrong when you develop
software with copying and pasting. It
was already the case a lot of developers
uh before LLMs became big would do many
searches in websites like Stack Overflow
with questions and they'd copy and paste
snippets of code out of there and some
research has shown that this was a
pretty risky thing for them to do. So
let's take the example of security
critical code maybe setting up
encryption or something that this paper
came out in 2019
uh showing not only is can you not
necessarily trust the answers you get to
security questions on Stack Overflow but
actually the popular answers are worse
than the unpopular answers. Uh you get
more view counts for the insecure
answers to questions and there are
significantly higher scores on average
for the insecure answers. So this was
bad enough when it was a feedback system
just involving people. But now imagine
LLMs are choosing these insecure answers
preferentially. Putting them in new code
that's posted on the web and becomes
part of the training data for future
generations could be a downward spiral
very
easily. Uh so let's step back and think
about why we're trying to use machine
learning for for coding. U I think of
machine learning as a good tool for
learning a blackbox model of a complex
system because we can't think of any
better ideas. this system is is is
beyond our intuitions. We we can't get a
more structured understanding of it. In
some sense, when we're trying to
understand biology or the visual world,
we don't have any better options. Uh
these unfortunately were not built for
our ease of understanding. They kind of
uh developed through natural laws and we
evolved in some way that that doesn't
predispose us to have a really simple
way to understand why our own bodies
work in a in a particular way. But
software code, I would argue, is
different. This is not a natural system
that we just need to handle. We build
the ecosystem of software development
tools. It's our responsibility as
software engineers to build these tools
for legibility so that we don't need to
rely at least not rely completely on
blackbox function learning to do a good
job building software. So if we
reconsider that responsibility, what
might we do differently? I'm going to
argue for two approaches. One we just
heard uh 30 minutes about from Daniel
Jackson. I'll I'll say uh just a few
minutes myself about it. The importance
of modularity in doing a good job
combining the strengths of AI based and
other software development techniques.
And then I'll I'll talk about formal
verification as a an effective antidote
for some of the worst things that can
happen with the the kind of flows we're
used to with with AI in software
engineering.
So today we can send a paragraph to chat
GPT saying here's this the web app I
want go off and build it for me and
chatgpt does its best it generates uh
pages of code and sometimes they're not
even all you're looking for and for
instance I asked this question it showed
me only the backend code for the app I
asked about and I said okay great now
could you please write the front-end
code as well and then five seconds later
it gave me some obscure error message I
don't know what's going on there uh So,
but it's a it's a good starting point at
one level, but every line of code here
is pretty dense and low level, and it's
just no fun to read output like this,
even for such a simple application, to
check that you got the functionality you
were looking
for. Why is it so verbose? I I happen to
show a prompt that we can sort of
decompose at the English level into a
bunch of standard ideas which are very
similar to the concepts that Daniel was
talking about. I brought together the
idea of a CSV import, fuzzy matching of
data, and a connection to the the
Salesforce system. And uh it's at some
level, this is all the description we
need to completely describe what we're
looking for. And because each of these
little bubbles and boxes is such a
standard thing in the world of of
enterprise software development, there
should just be a library that has all
these in it or multiple libraries. And
we should be referencing libraries and
not copying and pasting their code or
copy and pasting code out of particular
apps. that just seems
barbaric. So, uh I de developed a new
programming language uh starting about
20 years ago called webweb which is able
to support the right level of component
reuse for that level of programming. And
so it's a domain specific language for
full stack databasebacked web
applications. And the key idea is you
can write modules that have first class
status in this language that encapsulate
in the same way that maybe a Java class
for a hash table encapsulates an array
that no one can touch directly. In our
web modules can encapsulate all the
pieces you need for a full stack web
application. Front end, backend, and
database aspects can be private fields
of a module that can only be accessed
through the the public methods of that
module. And then it's relatively
lightweight to plum these together in
new ways.
So I'm going to have a presentation in
the the startup part of of today uh a
bit later talking about a company called
Nectrie that we've spun out based on
those ideas. But the the brief version
is we're able to take the diagram I
showed you before and embody it in the
code shown on the left where I've orange
underlined five invocations of library
components and that's almost all that's
going on here. Uh we also built an LLM
based front end that can take natural
language requirements and help the user
craft this code and doesn't the user
doesn't even necessarily see the code
version. We render this as English. So
it looks like a requirements document in
the end and we then use the technology
I'm going to talk about next to get very
reliable implementation of this
description in a productionready secure
high performance application.
One more point I I want to make about
modularity. Uh, of course, when you go
to sit down and write some code, what
you want is for the world to help you.
You want to bring in code from other
places and start putting it to use for
your application. I think it's also a
good thing for the community, say the
the world of open source developers to
try to use AI to identify opportunities
for new modules where say some system is
is constantly surveilling all the code
out there and finding there sure is a
lot of similarity across this this code
and this code and this code. I'm going
to suggest a whole new library or I'm
going to suggest a new function or a new
class in an existing library and I'm
even going to write some great
documentation for it. I think that I'
I'd love to see more use of AI in this
way as well.
Okay, so now let me talk about formal
verification and how it I think really
pays off for solving some of the the
problems that plague AI based software
engineering. Um, one thing we can do is
we can use an arbitrary potentially
unreliable coding assistant to write
some code and it would be lovely to have
some kind of tool that we can call a
program verifier that looks at the
output and actually confirms that it's
doing what we wanted it to do.
Unfortunately, this guy called Turring
told us we can't expect a fully
automatic checker that's able to confirm
that any program is correct. Uh, but
there are a lot of of heristic things
that work pretty well in practice.
Another trick we can use, we can
actually ask the coding assistant to not
just generate the code, but accompany it
with a mathematical proof that shows
that it does what we want it to do. And
then our program verifier just becomes a
proof checker. Doesn't need to develop
the creative arguments for correctness
on its own. it only needs to check the
argument that the the tool produced for
it. So many of you have probably seen
the the or heard about the Google alpha
proof system which is using machine
learning to generate uh fully rigorous
mathematical proofs that are checked by
a pre-existing software package called
lean. Uh so people building foundation
models really love to find new kinds of
benchmarks that they can compete with
each other on. And at some point someone
realized mathematical proofs were a good
one. So this has become a hot topic. But
I promise we were working on this kind
of stuff decades before the machine
learning people found it to use it for
for competitions. And uh not only is
there a lot of work on machine check
mathematical proofs about math, but
there's also a lot of work in showing
the correctness of software. And that's
been the the main subject that I've been
working on in in academia for a while.
So let me tell you about a place where
we applied that kind of technology and
were able to kind of combine some of the
nice benefits of AI and these these
classical techniques. In 2014 there was
an important security vulnerability in a
widely used library called OpenSSL.
Vulnerability was called heartbleleed
and it it allowed uh attackers to
interfere with the the proper use of
encrypted connections over the internet.
It was a big deal and it inspired the
Linux Foundation to start running a
series of workshops to bring together
academics who are experts in programming
technology and formal assurance with the
people in charge of the most important
open-source artifacts. And one of the
things I learned participating in those
workshops is that it's very hard to get
arithmetic right in cryptographic
software when you're working with really
big numbers that the hardware doesn't
support natively. You have to write
pretty complicated code if you want to
get good enough performance. and people
do accidentally put in bugs that lead to
significant
problems. So,
uh, in particular, there's a a
moderately large set of different
cryptographic algorithms that matter for
internet standards, and they're
typically parameterized over large prime
numbers that are used as the modulus of
arithmetic. And then there's a small but
non-trivized set of different hardware
architectures where depending on which
one you're targeting, you write your
code differently to get the best
performance. And I was shocked to learn
coming into this area that the
state-of-the-art was when you pick a new
element of the three-way cross product,
pick one circle inside each each cloud
and you picked a new choice that no one
had done before, you have to find
someone from a small population of
experts to rewrite all the arithmetic
code from scratch in C or assembly
because this was seen as the only way to
get good enough performance without
giving up security.
So we wanted to automate that process
and we built a tool called fiat
cryptography that starts from a library
of generic algorithms or you could call
them algorithm templates in this domain
that are written and proved in another
one of these theorem proving tools. It's
kind of a cousin of lean. It's called
coaul coq and that's what the rooster
icon stands for. And then we also built
a automatic code specializer that given
the parameters like the big prime number
that'll be the modulus that you want to
instantiate the algorithm with it. It uh
it shrinks down the code and keeps just
the parts of it that are relevant to the
parameter you chose and produces
something like the C code that the
experts were writing by hand. And we
also formally proved the correctness of
this specializer. So you you can get a a
extremely trustworthy pathway from more
or less Blackboard level math down to
pretty fast CC
code. And the the value proposition here
was so compelling that this tool was
widely adopted by all the major web
browsers to generate parts of their
their there software bases that are
running every time the browser shows you
a little lock icon to tell you you have
a secure connection to a server. So over
95% of secure web connections by
browsers are running this code that was
created with a a method that actually
has strong mathematical assurance of
correctness while still producing pretty
reasonable
code. Unfortunately in version one of
this project where in the first paper we
published we had this uh this
performance table for one of the most
popular algorithms that we're applying
the tool to. And we can see like for all
the other algorithms we we we used as
examples, we produced the fastest known
CC code, which is a good start, but
handwritten assembly language by experts
was still doing better by about a factor
of two. And that was embarrassing. This
was still good enough to get wide
adoption, but we we wanted to do
better. Okay, so here I'm going to bring
up a quick quote bringing uh our
attention to this standard idea. When we
ask the question, what is AI? It's
basically the stuff that we don't know
how to do systematically yet. It's the
the the domain of of heruristics. And we
were able to be systematic about the
process of producing the CC code that
goes with one of the algorithms in this
family. But we couldn't figure out a
systematic way to apply all the assembly
level tricks that the experts were
applying. So uh why don't we try to use
something more on the AI side of the
spectrum to address that second part.
So we adopted a hybrid method where we
have the the the code generation
pipeline from before still as
mathematically solid as it was. Uh but
then starting in the the middle of this
picture, we have the CC code and we
apply a random search procedure that
keeps uh generating small variations of
assembly programs, switching one
instruction for another, reordering
instructions, that kind of thing. You
can let it run all night exploring
different assembly programs,
benchmarking each one and keeping the
fastest ones. And then in the end of
this process to maintain the
mathematical guarantees, we apply an
equivalence checker that can actually
take in a C program and assembly program
and confirm that they compute the same
mathematical function. And this
equivalence checker we formally proved
to be correct. So that means that this
whole pipeline which does bring in some
heristic elements uh is totally
trustworthy and you get an endto-end
mathematical theorem connecting the
blackboard level math with the fast
assembly program that comes out in the
end. Now this project just used genetic
algorithms random program search uh but
in fact any kind of smart heristic
program transformer could be useful
here. We can imagine some follow-up work
that used LLM to suggest promising
variations of assembly programs or some
other machine learning based approach. U
nice thing about this domain which is
only straight line code, no loops or or
anything like that is that you can build
a pretty robust equivalence checker
that's ready for all sorts of huristic
program transformation
approaches. And uh this extension of our
tool is used in production at at Google.
Uh this is a quick screenshot of a a
pull request where they improved the
performance of one of the central
algorithms of security in Chrome by
about 50% on x86
processors. So now we are actually back
up to having world champion
implementations of some routines like we
found the fastest implementation of the
Bitcoin uh elliptic curve on on most
recent Intel processors using these
these
tools with still a theorem a
mathematical theorem of correctness.
Okay, so that was a domain where having
heruristics write code for you aligns
well with using a relatively simple
checker that you got the right answer
out. In other domains, we need help to
be able to check the correctness of
code. I mentioned the idea of get the
machine learning tool to generate a
mathematical proof that you're the
program it wrote for you is correct. So
we can imagine some scenario like I
showed you before. We asked Chat GBT to
write this app. It gives not just the
code but also a mathematical proof which
we feed into a proof-checking
algorithm.
Um I think that kind of approach can
work well but it'll work especially well
when we don't just keep programming the
same way as it has always been but we
actually co-design programming and
verification to make it easier to check
the correctness of of programs. In
particular, as a a call back to Daniel's
presentation and the first part of mine,
I think it'll be easiest to check
programs, the more we can make them be
expressed as compositions of nice highle
pieces that have been curated carefully
as a as a library. And then we can take
advantage of libraries of mathematical
facts that are known about these pieces
to very efficiently show the correctness
of the the overall program that we've
built from them.
Let me give you one example in a a
project that I've been involved with.
It's a a programming language called
ATL, a tensor language. It's for coding
computations over tensors of the kind
you would use to implement machine
learning. And you actually write your
program as shown at the top right here
as basically a mathematical expression
uh describing how to compute some
tensors. And then we developed a
compiler that turns those programs into
nested loop C programs that work with
with arrays.
And the compiler itself is formally
proved as correct. So you know that the
C program computes the same answers as
the mathematical expression. But the
when you have your nice uh beautiful
mathematical expression, the C code that
comes out probably isn't nearly the
right optimized C code that you'd like
to have eventually. But we did develop a
an approach to allowing uh the
mathematical expression to be
manipulated in various ways that
influence which CC code you get. So that
if you choose the right manipulations,
you can actually get your nice optimized
C program. And then you just have to
convince yourself that the less obvious
looking math expression is correct. Our
tool handles the rest of the process of
producing the C code. But how do you
come up with the right math expression?
How do you know it's correct? The
approach that we use is this idea called
user scheduling that was first uh
introduced in tools like a programming
language called haly that my
collaborator on this project Jonathan
Reagan Kelly developed. We start with
the naive version of your math
expression and then on the left we're
accumulating a series of directives and
everyone we run modifies that program.
Every directive is itself proved
correct. So we know it preserves the
meaning of the math expression. And when
we line up enough of those, we've
transformed into a new math expression.
And we can compose together the proofs
of all the steps that we used to get
there to get a theorem linking this
expression back to the original one,
proving that they're equal. And then we
can combine that with our our compiler,
which is also proved to get an endto-end
path from the original simple math
expression to the optimized C program.
So now imagine using that kind of
approach where it's not a human writing
a sequence of directives, but we
actually get the AI involved in choosing
the right way to optimize your your math
expression. We stock a library with
proved rewrite rules that explain how to
rearrange math expressions. Humans can
do the work of demonstrating the
correctness of each of these rules. And
then we can let AI do what it does best.
heristically explore the space of
possible sequences of rules that will
will will change the math expression and
at every step we pause and recompile
benchmark the program and we're we're
trying to keep the the best one at each
point we get some of the the the
benefits of both the classical and AI
approaches here this is still a correct
by construction approach we don't have
to worry about bugs anymore uh but also
we can take advantage of whatever sort
of uh leaps of insight a machine
learning system can provide to us in
choosing the right way to take advantage
of a library of pieces that are provided
by the
programmer. So, uh summing up here are
my thoughts on the way we should aim in
redeveloping future IDs to take maximal
advantage of both classical IDs and uh
machine learning and AI techniques. We
want developers not to just think about
the task at hand, but work on stalking a
library of good idea components. Maybe
even spend some time explaining why
they're good. Something like uh writing
specifications or helping a system that
checks
correctness. Tell the ID what are all
the components that it should be taking
into account. And then set it loose to
heristically search for programs that
can be built from the blessed
components. And if we set this up right,
there can also be a formal verification
element that is able to check that the
generated artifact meets the
requirements with no trust in the AI
process that created that code in the
first place. We're kind of reconfirming
everything uh from scratch. And then
finally, I think there's a lot of room
for interesting feedback mechanisms
where idees can uh consume many code
bases and make suggestions for new
components that might be worth creating,
putting out there with with good
documentation, etc., and then just feed
this this virtuous cycle where humans do
what what they're good at and the uh the
AIs do what they're good
at. Thank you.
So when it comes to component in AI
generated code if the components have a
flaw then your verification will treat
that flaw as a correct thing and then
we'll try to verify that way right and
we may be just trusting the verification
result is that something you guys think
is a concern or need to be worked upon
because if I'm writing a component I may
be thinking it's the correct Yeah, you
know thing that or a correct prompt I
already passed on to AI and now AI
generated code verification is thinking
the prompt is also correct right and
it's using that as a baseline to just
verify the code maybe you're asking
about the question of how do we know
what correctness means for a particular
uh software engineering project if the
correctness is expressed in English and
we use AI to translate that into a more
rigorous form then that AI translation
is the weakest link Is that the concern
you're you're bringing up? Yes. Or maybe
I'm missing some requirements in my
component and prompt itself that I
wasn't aware of. Right. Yeah. It it in
formal methods in general knowing you
have the right specification is one of
the the classic challenges that at some
level is not completely solvable
automatically. Um but the the way we can
get around it is just try to come up
with nice concise readable languages of
requirements.
And
uh that means that humans can audit the
description of what they've
accomplished. Maybe several of them can
just like we do code review today.
Instead of of code reviewing the whole
sprawling codebase, you reduce the scope
to auditing the description of the
requirements for your your particular
program and then checking that the the
big code base matches those requirements
can be automated. And I think that's a
big improvement. There's still room for
streamlining the process of capturing
requirements formally.
Anyone
else? Okay, let's hear it for Adam.
Thank you.