So today is the last day of our unit
about random walks on groups and um the
main the goal of the day is to digest
think about the banan gamber theorem
about mixing on SL2FP
um so we stated it at the end of last
time first I'll Remember, remind
everybody what it says.
Okay. So it's about mixing on SL2FP.
So it says if mu is a probability
measure
SL2F
actually maybe we it doesn't matter that
much but maybe we said it in ter in
terms of subsets.
Okay. So the question is when when does
the random walk coming from a u mix? So
um
um so then the conclusion will be
the singular value of this walk is less
than 1 minus c of epsilon meaning that
it does mix.
Okay. Um
so and um to see that this happens we
need to know that a doesn't lie in any
subgroup. And so we have a hypothesis
that's related to that. It says that for
any
borell subgroup B
um A intersect
GB. So any G in our group
and this guy is bounded by K of epsilon
P the minus epsilon* A. So only a small
fraction of A lies in any co-et of a
burell group.
Okay. Um, and we'll put in parenthesis
that a is symmetric. We don't really
need it, but it also doesn't matter that
much. And, uh, it will make things a
little cleaner.
>> Yeah.
>> Question about the difference between
hey, is a sub or a subset versus a
measure. Is it possible to kind of pass
between the two cases by just waiting by
different subgroup sets?
>> Yeah, that's right. So the question was
what's the difference between taking a
subset or taking a measure? I think
there's not that much difference. I
think if you can use this as a black box
and prove things about measures, I think
we also could just use measures through
the whole proof and it would work fine.
Okay. So this proof breaks into the
proof of this theorem breaks into two
important pieces which are both
interesting and which are both connected
in different ways to themes of our
class.
[Applause]
Okay,
so the first part says that if if you
just have any pretty much any set and
you do this random walk, the only way it
can fail to mix if is if it gets stuck
in something which is sort of
approximately a subgroup.
So, so it can fail to mix if it's
literally contained in a subgroup. And a
little bit more generally, it can it can
only fail to mix if there's a set which
is a lot like a subgroup which contains
a lot of the mass of the measure. Okay,
so let's try to write this down.
Um,
so this is probably true for any group.
I'm going to write it for SL2FP for now
and then as we talk about it more let's
keep our eyes open of what we actually
used
symmetric
um
and
sigma one ta it's bigger than 1 minus
here I'll put
1 - epsilon Um then
there exists uh some kind of approximate
subgroup called H
um
yeah hold let me adjust a little bit.
Let me also say that a is pretty big
and is not not too tiny. Um then there
exists some H.
Um so that mu tensored to some power of
H is pretty big
and this H is sort of like a subgroup in
the following sense.
So h if you multiply it by itself many
times for example five you could do more
um this is less than p to the o of delta
* h and h also is not too big.
Okay so if you had another group you
would have to adjust these things but I
think that that that's sort of minor I
think that's all you would have to
change.
Okay. So if you have a set which is a
decent sized fraction of our group and
let's say it's symmetric
um then either that random walks mixes
or there is some subset which is sort of
like a group and
when you take K steps of your random
walk you have a high probability of
being in this set.
Um and this set is sort of like a group
in in this sense.
Okay.
All right. And so there's delta and
epsilon. Maybe at the beginning I should
say this and delta depends on epsilon.
That's possible.
All right. Any questions or comments
about theorem one? It's theorem one is
is gamber essentially.
>> Yeah.
>> Where does the two
>> Yeah. So um
um
what's significant here is just that
this is is less significantly smaller
than the whole group. Um and if we
yeah
>> like power group less than one or like
little of the group
>> um right right yeah okay so so this
comes last time from this um uh
so actually it's also important that
this is bigger than two so we had this
um important property of SL2FP
that it's um uh that it it's um ah yeah
so this actually this wouldn't work for
any group. So we have this important
property for SL2FP from last time that
every non-trivial representation has a
large dimension and that had the
property that if you got if this thing
had a small L2 norm so it was like kind
of decently well mixed then we would get
a spectral gap and then if you kept
going it would become really really well
mixed and that's crucially being used
here. Um, and so here you could put
anything bigger than two. Um, and the
the point is that it can only go wrong
by getting stuck in something of size
really smaller than P squed because we
know once it spread over something of
size bigger than P^ squ then it's going
to keep going and spread all the way.
Yeah. Thanks.
Yeah.
Okay. Well, this theorem raises a
question. um who are all the subsets H
that are like this it becomes a much
nicer theorem when we can write them all
down and um or at least say something
meaningful about them. Okay, so theorem
two says something about that.
So this theorem is due to healthcott
and it builds on
rushski.
Okay. So it says if h is a subset of
sl2fp
um
and it has these two properties.
So all of this stuff is smaller than p
to the delta h.
Um and h is at least p to the epsilon.
You can kind of read that off from here.
It's not going to get stuck in something
smaller than a um and at most p to the
2.5.
Then the conclusion is that h is
concentrated in a burell subgroup or
burell coet. So then there exists
a burell subgroup
B with an element G in our group. Um so
that H intersect B is bigger than some
small constant times H.
So our approximate subgroups basically
have to sit in a burell subgroup. This
isn't a complete classification because
some of the subsets of B are approximate
subgroups and many of them aren't. Um
but it's a meaningful piece of
information.
Okay, cool. So um you you put these two
theorems together, you can prove that
theorem pretty quickly.
>> Yeah.
>> Um if this C does it depend on anything
or is it universe?
>> Does it depend on anything? Let's put
this here. Um
let's see. I have all these epsilons and
deltas.
don't think it depends on anything. So I
guess here there should be
this
we can do this. So this is getting
stronger as epsilon's getting smaller.
Epsilon's telling us that our thing is
not too small. Um and uh and then I
think that this is just a constant.
Um I guess that does suggest that we
could have said something stronger up
there.
Yeah,
this is definitely H, not B.
>> I think it's right.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, this is a question about kind of the
choice of G. If point H is a symmetric
subset, would that kind of imply that
the sort of optimal G is always going to
just be the identity because you think
of H as kind of being centered in some
way around the identity. So shifting a
subgroup by by kind of non identity
element wouldn't change the
intersection.
>> Yeah. So the question is if maybe if H
were itself symmetric which in fact I
think will happen in this setup um then
maybe you don't need this G and maybe
it's actually only actual subgroups. Um
I think that may be so let me just
describe that I'm not sure we need G.
Um,
correct. Yeah. So, so a good example to
think about is if you just take a co-et
of a burell subgroup and in the aelion
world a co-et of a subgroup will be very
small when you add it to itself.
But in the nonabelian world it's not so
clear.
So I'll make a remark
if H is a co-et of a group then um how
big is just H * H? Well it's G * B * G *
B.
And because it's not commutative I can't
bring this across.
So it's not obvious that this is small.
So I I think this is in fact large.
So based on that, I think it's likely
that we don't need this. Um but it made
the proof it makes the proof a little
shorter.
Okay, cool. Okay, so I have a couple of
big picture comments about this. Um one
comment is um let's compare to the
perhaps simpler setting of an aelion
group. So we maybe have the group of the
integers or the group of the integers
modulo P. Suppose we had a subset in
there that had this property
and this property. So when you add it to
itself many times it expands but only by
a little bit by a small power of the
size of the set. Then what can we say
about the structure of such things?
That's a big open problem in additive
combinatorics.
Um that's the sort of friend and rouia
problem. If you have something even
smaller here like log p or or so um then
there would be a classification that
would have to look like a generalized
arithmetic progression. But in this
range there's there's not a whole lot
there's nothing like a structure theorem
that currently exists in this range. So
in a certain sense it's this is stronger
information in the non-commutive world
than we have in the commutive world. Of
course you might point out that this is
not a complete structure theorem either.
Um but this is a really strong piece of
information about our group and I think
in some ways it's stronger than any what
we know in the community world.
Yeah. Um another comment so I'm not
sure. So so Rashki and Hut both worked
on this. Rashowski came from logic and I
think that he was interested in the idea
from the point of view of logic of like
an approximate subgroup. You know like a
a basic thing we have axioms for is that
you know axims for a group and what
happens if you uh relax those axioms a
little bit. What can you say? So
interesting question from the point of
view of logic.
Okay cool. Uh all right. So the goal for
the class is to discuss each of these
things in moderate depth probably
without giving complete proofs. Um
uh and and they're they have quite
different ideas but in both cases the
ideas are related to stuff in in our
class.
Okay. So first let's talk about theorem
one.
Um
so on the board
okay so we start with the measure mu
which is mu aa and we notice that mu l2
is one over the size of a. So that's
like is at most p to the minus epsilon
because it was it was built into our
assumptions here that a is is at least p
the epsilon. Okay. Now let's start
convolving mu with itself and we want to
see if we convolve it with itself enough
times um is what will happen to the L2
norm. So let's say mu2
so that's let's call this mu1. Mu2 is
mu1 convolved with mu1 and in general mu
k + 1 is mu k convolved with mu k. So
we're convolving with this thing with
itself many times and we're going to see
what happens to the L2 norm. Okay. So
recall
um that if at some point mu k l2^2 were
to be smaller than 1 over p the 2.1
then we would get um that sigma 1 of t
mu k was bounded by well bounded by
okay and then we would get that sigma 1
of t mu
So mu k is mu convolved with itself 2
the k times. So that would be um p the
minus1 / 10 * 2 the k. So if k is not
too big we would get a spectral bank. So
that's our plan.
Okay. So we keep doing these
convolutions and we watch what happens
to the L2 norm. And at every step maybe
the L2 norm goes down significantly. In
that case we're happy. or maybe it
doesn't go down. In that case, we're
stuck. And the stuck situation, we'll
try to analyze it carefully and see that
the stuck situation only arises because
of this situ this structure, this setup.
So, let me write that out.
So, let's say G stands for our goal,
which is that mu k
L2 is less than 1 over P 2.1. If we get
there, we're happy. P will stand for
progress.
We're not necessarily there, but mu k +
one l2^ 2 is bounded by p the minus
delta
mu k l2.
Okay.
And then s stands for stuck which means
we are not at our goal and we are not
making progress.
not goal and not progress.
Okay,
cool.
Okay, so as long as we don't get stuck,
we will reach our goal in about one over
delta steps.
So
if s never happens
we reach the goal
and less than one over delta steps and
no matter what delta is delta is just a
large constant and that still that is
enough to to to give the conclusion. So
then if you if you do a little
calculation using this you'll you'll get
a spectrum.
Okay. So suppose we do get stuck. Let's
think about what that means.
Okay. So, there was a comment at the
beginning of the class that perhaps
there's not a big difference between a
set and a measure because if you have a
set, you can turn it into a measure. If
you have a measure, you can look at the
points that where the measure is pretty
big and you get a set. Um, and that's
actually what we're going to do.
So um let's say that a lambda of mu k is
the set of group elements for our group
sl2fp
where mu k of g is approximately lambda.
Okay so we can decompose our group into
pieces where muk has various sizes and
one of these sizes must have a decent
fraction of the measure. So we choose
lambda so that muk k of a lambda
is around one.
So we've we've cut our whole group into
maybe logarithmically many pieces. They
their total measure is one. So one of
them has to be pretty big. All right.
And now let's say a k is defined to be
this set.
Right. So what we've learned is that mu
k is roughly uniform on ak and ak has a
good fraction of the total measure of
mu.
Okay, great.
Um
okay so more or less you could imagine
that mu k is just the uniform measure on
ak. Um all right so now what would we
learn algebraically about ak from the
fact that we are stuck?
um that actually has a nice
interpretation in terms of a previous
character in our course which was the
idea of energy. So let's recall what
what energy means and put it in a
non-commutative context and we'll see
that it sort of exactly fits here.
Okay. So let's say
that so if we have two subsets
A and B in our group the energy of AB
is the number of
uh A1 A2 B1 B2 these guys are in A and
these guys are in B.
So that a1 * b1 is the same as a2 * b2
energy a. Now we this is the same
definition that we saw before in the
context of a commutive group. A group is
now not commutive which means that it
matters what order I wrote those things
in. And so it matters what order I wrote
those things in. So eab is not actually
the same as eba.
Okay. But it's otherwise it's a very
similar looking definition. Um and um
um okay and and we can relate this to
what to what to to this setup. We can
notice that EAB
is I take the characteristic function of
A and I convolve it with the
characteristic function of B. When I do
that, if I evaluate this at G, it will
tell me how many ways are there to write
G as little A times little B.
Now I'm going to square it because I
want to how many ways and that many
choices for this and that many choices
for that and sum over B. So this is
this.
Okay. So notice um I took something I
convolved it by something else and I
took its L2 norm that's the character
that's involved in being stuck.
So something we can say
um okay actually so before before we do
that let me make a little normalization
um so remark
E A A is in between A cubed and A squ
right. So the A squared comes from I
could take these to be equal and I could
take those to be equal and a cubed upper
bound comes from once I've chosen these
three there's at most one choice for the
last one. Okay. So the these ones are
have a lot of additive structure and the
typical example is an actual subgroup
and these have very little additive
structure.
Okay. Um so now let's relate to being
stuck.
So if we are in the stuck case for ak
for mu k
and we could see um
this
um
okay so mu k is essentially 1 over a k
this characteristic function of a k and
if we want to be rigorous I guess we say
something like this.
And um if we say mu k convolved with mu
k is smaller than is larger than p the
minus delta
mu k.
This is equivalent to saying that the
energy a k with a k is smaller than some
p to the delta
time a k cubed
claim. If we unwind this we'll get this.
So we unwind this we'll see an energy
the energy of AK and this you know this
is almost the minimum possible value of
the L2 norm and so it's almost the um
sorry it's almost the
this goes the other way. So the the um
there let me say that again. So this is
encoding this energy. It's a lower bound
for it and the lower bound is almost um
the biggest it could be. So this energy
is almost the biggest it could be. Yes.
>> That be ak
lower bound for energy.
>> Uh right. No. So no it's ak cubed and
this is a minus sign. So this is
possible. Yeah.
>> Okay. So this just got copied there. And
um uh all right. So okay. So if you look
at this L2 norm, these are probability
measures. So this L2 norm is at most
that L2 norm.
So when you look at this inequality,
this L2 norm is really pinched.
It's at least a small fraction. It's at
least a large fraction of mu2 and it's
at most mu2.
So it's just about as big as it could
be. So this energy is just about as big
as it could be.
Okay, cool.
All right. So if we get stuck there must
be a subset of very high energy
and that is
step towards being an approximate
subgroup but it's not as strong as the
conclusion of theorem one.
Um okay so at this point the story
connects to some characters that we
talked about when we were doing
projection theory over finite fields. um
it relates to the balag summary gow
theorem and the punicarusa inequality.
So first of all let me just recall what
they said um in the commutive case and
then this is a non-commutive case. So
then we'll have to talk about you know
what's actually true in the
non-commutive case.
Okay.
So you recall that if we have a
contained in z a commutative group
um then we have two important theorems
gaus
says that if a has a lot of energy
then it has a large subset
And the large subset is actually has a
small subset.
So this set has additive structure in
one sense but it has a large subset
which has additive structure in a
stronger sense.
And then once we have this there's
another important theorem the plunicus
theorem that says if a prime plus a
prime smaller than l * a prime so l will
be this
um then you can also look at the sum of
three of them or four of them or
whatever. So I'll write I'll just write
this guy is bounded by L to the 50th.
You could put other things. You get the
idea.
Okay. So this is a sort this sequence of
theorems is important because it gives a
sort of amplification of structure.
So this has this assumption is that A
has some additive structure in some
fairly weak sense and that implies that
a big subset has additive structure in a
stronger sense and then therefore it has
additive structure in even stronger
sense.
Okay. So if we were allowed to just
apply these two theorems then from this
moment we would get the conclusion of
theorem one. Conclusion of theorem one
would be that there's some set H which
could be could have been AK which obeys
this.
Okay. So
um so we we can't we can't do that
because this is for a commutive group.
So we need to talk about what happens in
a non-commutive group. Um but I thought
it was we'll talk about that. But I also
thought it was a nice moment to recall
these theorems and uh reappreciate that
they're important and useful and do
something kind of neat.
Um in our halfway through the course
check-in email when I asked people uh
you know what what things that we did do
you feel like they really sunk in and
you understood them and what things you
feel like it was sort of maybe hard to
remember what actually was happening. um
these this theorem in particular was
cited as something where it was hard
people did not feel like they remembered
very well what actually happened
so okay so we get to talk about it again
cool
um yeah oh I guess another thing you
might you might wonder is okay this is
logically is stronger than this but does
it really matter later when we look at
theorem two we'll have a good example
theorem two like really requires this as
an input so we'll see an interesting
example of why you might want this.
Okay.
So, um
let's talk about the balac summarity
garish theorem.
Um
so I will tell you okay yeah I guess
first I should tell you what is true in
the non-commutive world which really
looks pretty similar to this. Um, and
then we'll actually remember the proof a
little bit um to to see if we can get
the proof to sink in a little bit
deeper.
Okay.
So, I'm going to erase this and what I
want us to remember is just that to
finish theorem one, what we need is a
good version of balag sum dows and
plunker rouia in the non-commutive fold.
All right. Um so theorem
non-commutative
balance over gallons. So it says if A is
a subset of a group G
um and the energy
a A is at least K inverse A cubed.
Um then there exists a subset a prime
and a so that it's pretty big
and um there are a few different things
we could write but
actually let me call this a tilda
a tilda time a tilda inverse is not too
Okay. So it looks very little different.
Um, but let's take this opportunity to
remember how the proof worked and see if
we can get it to sink in a little bit
more deeply.
All right, so proof sketch.
All right.
So, remember that the energy AA
is the sum over all of our group
elements
of R A of G squared where R A of G is
the number of pairs A1 A2
squared. So that A1 A2 is G.
That's the energy. Okay. So for the
energy to be large, there must be a lot
of group elements G where this is pretty
large. We'll call those popular
products.
So um
P the set of popular products this is
the set of G where R A of G is greater
than K to the minus something.
times the size of a which so the size of
a is the biggest it could be and so
they're almost as big as it could be. So
they're quite popular.
Okay.
Uh all right. So it's an exercise to see
that if the energy is really big most of
the energy actually comes from popular
products.
So
energy aa is pretty much is yeah is more
than half comes from so half of the
energy of a is less than the sum over g
and the popular products of ra a g.
Okay. And so this is this is having
popular products that's almost
equivalent to having a line of energy.
Those are basically the same thing. Um,
all right. So then we'll do a little
thought experiment. Suppose that every
product was popular.
Every product in the product set of A
had the same number of representations.
Well, that number of representations
would have to be pretty large because
there's a lot of energy. And that would
tell us that A times A was small.
Okay. Um, so then we would be done. and
a tilda could just be a but that's not
true because it's it's not true that the
every every element can be written as a
product in the same number of ways.
Um so what we want to do we're hoping to
find a subset a tilda
so that all the products in a tilda a
tilda time a tilda they all can be
written uh as a product in lots of ways
or something in that space.
Okay. So now let's make the popular
product to graph.
So the vertices are G cross G. Here's a
copy of G. Here's a copy of G.
And um we put an edge
from A to B.
edge from a to b if um a * b is a
popular product.
Okay. And
um
right actually this is not a g by g
graph. This is an a by a graph taking
elements of our set and looking at their
products. Okay. So not every pair is a
popular product. They might not all be
popular. Uh but there are by hypothesis
because of there's a lot of energy.
There's a lot of popular products. So
the number of edges is at least
there are lots of edges in this graph.
Okay.
Um
so a tilda is going to be some subset o
over here. And the good feature of a
tilda
is that for every a1 and a2 both in a
tilda there are many edges there are
many paths. So let me let me draw it. Um
okay so let's say this is a1 and this is
a2. And then we're going to think of
paths of length four that go
from A1 to A2.
So there are many
are
more than something
paths of length four that go from A1 to
A2 in our graph.
Okay. Um and how many? Well,
the from a typical point there are about
maybe one over k times a uh edges out.
And so
uh so we have you know a choices a
choices a choices and then we have to go
to a2.
Okay. So there was a graph theory lema
that we can choose a substantial set a
tilda here that has all of these edges
and that was the hardest part of the
proof but it's exactly the same as
before. It had nothing to do with
anything being commutative. So I I just
uh that part I won't repeat.
So there was a lema
that we can choose
a tilda so that this is true. Um and a
tilda is pretty big.
Okay.
Um
cool.
So, let's name everybody in the middle
here.
Um,
name these. Let me actually rename
these.
Um,
I'll call these a
a and a prime. And then we go over here
to a1 to a2 to a3.
So we know a a1 is popular. We know a2 *
a1 is popular. We know a2 * a3 is
popular and so on.
Okay.
And what this allows us to do is to
write a over a prime in many different
ways.
Okay. So
a over. Okay. I have to be careful
because I'm in a non-commutive group. I
think I want to write a let's call this
a tilda
a * a tilda inverse.
So that's a * a1.
And now I'll put a2 * a1 inverse.
And now I'll put a2 * a3. And then I'll
put a
tilda * a3 inverse.
So if we do this out.
So this guy here is a1 inverse a2
inverse. You can see cancellation
cancellation.
And this guy here is a3 inverse a tilda
inverse. Cancel that. So that's this
equality. So not difficult.
Um but we've written it in terms of four
guys that are popular.
So this um a2 * a1 is not just a2 * a1.
It's a popular product. It can be
written in many different ways.
So
a tilda a * a tilda inverse can be
written as um
z1 z2 inverse or maybe p1
p2 inverse
p3 p4 inverse where pi are popular.
Um and so
um
right okay and it and this can be done
in many different ways
and and the number of choices
for the pi is at least uh a cubed.
Okay. So the conclusion is that the size
of a tilda time a tilda inverse is
bounded by I'm going to choose four
popular guys. So that's p to the 4th and
then I I've overcounted because each
person has now been represented a cubed
different ways and ignoring some factors
of k.
And so that's
a
Okay.
Okay. So, I remember the first time I
taught it, I struggled a little bit with
the intuition of this. Um the first
thing you might hope to do is to choose
a tilda so that every product in a tilda
can be is popular. they all can be
written in many ways just as a product
of two things in a and then there are
clearly not so many of those but I think
it's not possible to do that it's not
possible to choose a tilda where every
one of these products is popular in that
sense
but by take by by by being a little bit
more flexible we've chosen a tilda so
that every quotient can be written in
many ways um not just as a quotient of
two things in a but many ways in this in
this uh slightly more flexible
framework.
Okay. Any questions or comments?
>> Yeah.
>> So, why can't you get the same result
for a * a if you just choose paths of
length three?
>> Yeah, I think you could get the same
result for a * a if you choose paths of
length three or a * b. Yeah. So, okay.
Um, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry, I maybe was
not transparent about um so the the
thing with positive length three still
still works. Um I think that might
produce two different subsets. Um
actually maybe in the commutive case I
actually should have had two different
subsets.
Um
at least initially um it works fine and
the and the reason that I have a tilda*
a tilda inverse the motivation for that
is going to come in a moment and
actually I'm going to try to argue that
this is better than a * a
And uh just a clarifying thing the way
you stated it before the popular
products here is the subset of a * a
with a small projection
right it was stated in terms of uh a
subset having a um large projection then
that leads to you can choose a subset of
a such that the um subset is small.
>> Yeah that's right. That's right. So in
the projection theory version the this
would be the small projection and
there'd be some big piece of a cross a
that that projects here. Yeah.
Okay cool. Um so this is the
non-commutative analog of bacity gow. It
really looks a lot like bacity gus and
this inverse is because we want it. We
probably could we could also have had a
tilda time b tilda if we want.
Okay. Um the situation with Pluna Caruza
is actually a little bit more
complicated.
So non-commutative
All right. So let's ask a question.
Suppose we have a is a subset of a group
and a * a is small.
Does it imply that a * a * a is small?
So this would be that natural analog of
plumus inequality. And the answer to
this is no.
Okay, here's the example.
So let's say H contained in G is a
subgroup and A is H union one other
element which is not in the subgroup.
Now what happens when I take A * A? A *
A is H * H. That's good.
plus or union h * g union g * h union g
* g.
Okay, there's nothing special about
these, but because g is only one
element, all of this stuff is small.
So we can see that a * a is smaller than
1 2 3 smaller than 4 a probably 3 a.
Okay. But now what happens when I take a
* a * a?
Okay. Now I have three factors. And so
that concludes h * g * h.
And in the non-commutative world, I
cannot slide this over. And this is not
so good. There's no reason for this to
be small. And so the size of h * g * h
is could be
could well be the size of h squ.
Okay, so that didn't work very well.
Um
what to do about it?
There is a theorem that if a * a * a is
small then a * a * a * a is small. Yeah.
>> Does the time example that you show have
an example in s of p?
>> Yeah it does. Um so h could be any any
subgroup say a burell subgroup and g is
not in there. Yeah this will happen.
So this this could happen in SL2F.
Okay.
Um so there is a theorem that if you
assume that a product of three copies of
A is small then the product of four
copies of A is also small. Um but that
theorem is not immediately useful to us
because we don't have any input that a
product of three things is small.
Um okay there's another fix to this.
Let's just suppose think about this
example and how we might fix it. Um
so this example has a lot of algebraic
structure and this is the algebraically
structured part and this is garbage.
um and
we need it would be helpful to separate
a into the structured part and the
garbage.
So how might we do that?
So let's let's look at
um so this is the continuing in the
example.
Let's look at a * a inverse
You could do a time. Anyway, this works
a little bit better for a time a so what
do we have? We have h * h
actually. Yeah. So, so we will
eventually look at a * a inverse. But um
let's think about how we how we might
separate this. So,
so this set has different pieces
and we can
if we want to separate the algebraic
part from the garbage.
So, we'd like to find this part and
distinguish it from that part, right?
How are they different from each other?
Well, let's think about how many
representations there are for each
product in this product set. Any product
in here has many, many representations.
And the products here have only one
representation.
So this guy here is the set of popular
products.
And actually that if once we identified
it, the popular product set then is an
actual subgroup. It has a lot of
algebraic structure.
Okay. So now let that motivate the
following proposition which is an analog
of plate.
It says if um a * a inverse is less than
or equal to k a
so a inverse that means take each
element of a and take its inverse.
Um then
okay and then if Q is the set of popular
quotients
so it's the set of g so that um r a a
inverse of g is bigger than k to the
something a
then
you can raise q to any power you like q
let's say we do L times.
So Q has a lot of algebraic structure
and their proof has a similar idea of
writing things in many different ways.
Okay. So proof um
Okay.
Oh, actually I think it's a little bit
tricky. I think it should be that.
Okay. So the proof is let's look at a *
Q * Q
say I'll illustrate the proof in L= 4.
Let's illustrate with L equ= 3. That'll
give you the idea. Times A inverse.
So somebody in here can be written as
little a and now this is a popular
quotient. So this is little a2 inverse
little a3
and there are many choices
and then actually let's illustrate with
l equals 2
and then we have
uh here we'll have little a4 inverse
little a5
We have many choices here. How many
choices? We have about a choices
have about a
choices
and then at the end I'll do this
A6 inverse A7 about eight traces
and then A8 inverse.
All right. So, so to say more better
what I'm saying, suppose that I have an
element of this set, then I can write
the element this way. And so I can say
that X belongs to um
a A inverse.
So x can be written
as um all right okay so x can be written
in in many different ways
and for each way of writing it we'll
notice that this guy lives in a a
inverse that guy lives in a aa ina
inverse and so on
so can be written in around a cubed ways
as b1 b2 b3 b4 where the b i are in a a
inverse.
Okay. So
the size of this set
this is bounded by the size of a a
inverse to the fourth.
So I get to choose these B's and now
I've overounted because each for each X
there are around a cub different choices
of how I could write it
/ Aub and that is smaller than
Um, okay. There's one thing I hid at the
beginning. Um, let me do it properly and
then pause and see what people think. So
we were given a * a inverse
is small and that implies that the
energy of a a inverse is large.
This is stronger than this.
And now I'd like to switch these. And
this is is actually the same as this.
So even though I don't know a inverse
time a is small, I do know that a
inverse a has a lot of energy. And the
reason I can switch them is if I have a1
a2 inverse equals a3 a4 inverse, that's
a quadruple that's being counted in this
energy. Uh let's just rearrange things a
little bit. I divide by a3 a3 inverse a1
a2 inverse equals a4 inverse. Then I
will multiply on the right by a2.
So that's a quadruple that's being
counted here. Yeah.
>> Didn't you know that big inverse a has
to be small because it's just the
inverse of any element in a inverse or a
a
>> Oh. Um
yeah, maybe that's true. Yeah, maybe I
made this too complicated. So these are
equal but you you claim that actually a
inverse time a is a a * a inverse. So
over here I have a1 a2 inverse. If I
invert it if I invert that I get
uh what's the inverse of this? Should
invert this one. I don't think this
quite works.
>> So I didn't manage to switch the order
when I did that. But I can switch the
order when I look at the quadruple.
Okay, good try.
Okay, so so this is large.
So therefore there are lots of popular
quotients.
So Q is large which is what we used
here.
Okay. So both both of these proofs have
a following highle idea. Um there's a
lot of energy around. So it frequently
happens that you can write a product or
a quotient in many different ways. And
if you could arrange a set where every
product could be written in many ways
then you estimate you could get a clean
estimate for the size of the product
set. And um by uh playing around with
the sort of products that that you
consider and by some experience and
craft and skill we we can get that to
happen.
Okay. So this is the analog of Plunka's
inequality and the reason that it was
sort of desirable to put a tilda a tilda
inverse in bali gowers is that that
thing is designed to fit into to this
thing.
Okay. So this Q is the approximate
subgroup that we were that we were
looking for which is the you know the
conclusion of of of theorem one.
Okay, so this finishes the discussion of
theorem one as a pretty detailed proof
sketch. Um, and it is a fair somewhat
different setup that shows the
significance of the idea of like balm
garrison and plarusa and this
cominatorial methods.
Okay. So now in the 15 minutes that's
left, I'd like to I'm going to try to
say a little bit about the proof of
theorem 2. Uh and the proof of theorem 2
it also connects um with um with themes
of the of the class and especially with
how some estimates are different in the
case of a prime field or the case of a
non-prime field.
Okay.
So let's have so let's do discussion of
theorem too.
All right, I'd like to put us in the
following framework. We're going to look
at SL2 of KAR where K bar is an
algebraically closed field. Could
imagine it's the the algebraic closure
of FP.
All right. And we're going to look at
subgroups
of SL2 and K bar.
Um, okay. So here let's remember the
some easy ones
have a subgroup like this where a and a
inverse are in this field. Um we have
the burell subgroup.
So that's a a inverse t and we have the
unitary subgroup.
So those are some subgroups.
We can take uh conjugates of them
actually. Let me come back to that.
Okay. Yeah. So then we can do two
general things. We can look at sub
fields.
So I can take SL2K
where K contained in K bar is a sub
field.
Or you could take this any of these with
a sub field. Those are subgroups. And
you could take conjugates.
conjugate any any subgroup you get
another subgroup.
Okay, so that is a bunch of subgroups
that we can identify without too much
trouble that sit inside of SL2 of K bar.
Um, okay. And there is a theorem that
says that this is not exactly but
reasonably close to the to the full
list.
Um,
okay.
So Dixon in 1901 gave a full
classification
of these subgroups
and it's a little bit messy. It includes
a variety of finite subgroups in certain
cases and so on. Um and his theorem
implies that if H is an actual subgroup
um then
either um H is contained in a conjugate
of SL2K
where K is a sub field
uh or most of H is contained in a
conjugative.
Okay. And if we know from the beginning
that we're talking about a subgroup of
SL2 of FP, a proper subgroup of SL2 FP,
it eliminates the first case. So we must
be in the second case.
All right.
Um,
but Dixon's methods are are some of them
at least are not very robust. If you
replace the hypothesis of being an
actual subgroup by something like H* H
is pretty small. Um, so here's a here's
a common example of a technique that we
use to classify subgroups that does not
do very well if we replace it by
approximate subgroups. example is
there's a uh the order of the subgroup
divides the order of the group. That's
really useful in 18701.
You want to classify the subgroups of
some group with eight elements. Um but
it is something like that is not going
to survive an approximate subgroup in
any useful way.
Okay. Um so the the proof of theorem two
is based on a rather different strategy
for for this classification that's due
to Larsson and pink. Um okay so um so
let me say part A which is the Larson
and pink strategy.
All right. So we're going to think about
how a subgroup inter intersects this
these uh
these subgroups.
Uh so if you take SL2K and you intersect
it with one of these,
it will either be empty or it would just
be identity or something like that or it
will be a subgroup that's like t0 of K.
Um okay. So we're going to study
H intersected with T.
T of K bar
H intersected with B of K bar.
H intersected with U of K bar.
And we'll see the following behavior.
The h intersected with t of k bar
is roughly h to the 1/3 or big o of 1.
So if I take sl2 fp and I intersect it
with this I'll get t0 of fp there'll be
about p of those which is about the cube
root of the size of sl2fp.
if I take some crazy Taurus in algebraic
closure that it may not intersect this
except at the identity. Um so so these
these are the two things that could
happen and then similarly with these
Right? So they first proved that if you
take an arbitrary group and you consider
how it intersects these kind of
fundamental algebraic subgroups that it
behaves a lot like it were SL2 of a sub
field
and then building from this they were
able to see that actually it it would
have to be SL2 of a sub field. So that's
their approach to the rough
classification.
Um yeah so this so this was a a cool
paper um in pure group they they weren't
interested in approximate subgroups they
they were interested in pure group
theory problem classifying subgroups of
SLD of K or other other like le groups
over finite fields. Um
and the complete classification is
clearly hard because any finite group
embeds in a permutation group which
embeds in SLD of FP. So all finite
groups occur as subgroups of SLD of FP
for sum D and sum P. Um and so it's so
so it's it's not really plausible to
give a complete classification or anyway
it would be at least as hard as
classifying finite groups to give a
complete classification but they were
able to classify um I think it's like
subgroups of SLD of FP which have at
least some size like P to the epsilon or
epsilon* d or something like this the
ones that are decently large um and uh
and that was in you know around 2000s
really is a hard thing Um, okay. But it
also turns out that their method uh
interacts well with just assuming that h
* h * h * h is small.
So here this whole argument works if we
just assume
that h * h * h * h *
okay I may or may not have like two
minutes to try to describe what they
yeah how this part works significance of
the algebraic closure like why if if we
only care about subgroups of a sub2 to
FP. What is the what what information
are you gaining from intersecting with
that?
>> Yeah. So the question is why bring into
play the algebraic closure
>> also what is the algebraic closure of
FP?
>> And what is the algebraic closure of FP?
Yeah. Um
I am um
right. Okay. you you do you do need this
for the following reason that should
that should be familiar to us even as
analysts. Um so suppose you have a
matrix in SL2R
and you would like to diagonalize it.
You'd like to look at its IGEN values or
whatever. Well, you can't necessarily do
that in SL2R
um um because the IGEN values could be
complex. So in order to diagonalize it,
you might want to move to SL2C. And
diagonalizing matrices is is useful
because um you know you can
you can classify matrices by their
Jordan canonical form. And this is a
convenient way to organize things. And
that's the same thing that's going on
here.
>> But like the intersections look the same
though, right? Like the intersection of
if H is just a subgroup of SL2 K, then
the intersection of T K bar is the same
as the intersection of TK.
>> Yeah, that's correct. That's correct.
But um okay, so the comment the comment
was that if if uh okay so what did this
so um if h is in sl2 k then h
intersected with t kn of k bar is the
same thing as h intersected with t kn of
k.
Yeah. Okay. I think the problem with is
that I I forgot to say something about
what's written on the board here. This t
is not t.
Um the conjugates are really important.
So t of k bar is a conjugate of t kn of
k bar.
>> Yeah. Are the kind of elements that are
being diagonalized like just elements of
SL2 or kind of bigger linear operators
on SL2?
>> Uh think if it's just SL2, you only need
the degree two extensions.
>> Yeah, that so the comment is that if we
just want to diagonalize matrices in SL2
FP, we probably only need a degree 2
extension of FP, which which we might
feel more comfortable with. Uh I think
that's probably right. I think we could
probably work with the degree two
extension.
Okay.
Um
All right. So the output
of the Larsson pink argument
is um after conjugating.
Okay. So yeah. So first so first of all
we can arrange that um our h intersected
with some unitary guy
is pretty big.
And after conjugating we can arrange
that this is you not k.
So
so
h contains
some guys like this where t is in sub
subset that I'll call e and e is pretty
big.
Um
okay and moreover this part is still
should not expand too much when we take
products. Um so here let's call let's
call this thing sort of a unitary piece
of h
uh * uh also this isn't completely
obvious but it's not that difficult. It
shouldn't be that much bigger than uh H.
And that tells us that E plus E
shouldn't be that much bigger than E.
Okay.
Also, we should have this this U is in
some B and H intersect
B of K bar.
Uh well, so we've we've already
conjugated so that U is U not. So this
is going to be b and this should be
around um h to the 2/3.
Okay. So uh and inside of there we'll
have a t and h intersect that should be
like h to the 1/3.
So h intersect t k bar. Um that's going
to be some guys that look like this.
and these A's live in some set that I'll
call F.
Okay. So then if you think about how
these matrices act on these matrices,
um we should get
so T0.
So let's call this guy uh T the T part
of H and U
here.
Wow. Okay. and um and and and and this
thing here is the B part of H.
Okay, so the B part of H times the B
part of H should be not that much bigger
than the B part of H.
And if you unwind what that means, you
multiply these you'll have things like a
a inverse a T where a is an F, T is an
E. So the conclusion is that E* F is
also not that much bigger than E or F.
So in other words once you have like a
unipotent piece where you have have
these guys then this multiplication
operation just gives you addition of the
numbers in here. So you have a like a
simpler thing. And then once you have a
bunch of upper triangular guys um then
um
uh
um then this multiplication just gives
you this matrix multiplication induces
this regular multiplication and we have
small products.
Okay.
So this is consistent with the pro
possibility that E and F could both be
just some sub field K or some
approximate sub fields. But the sum
product theorem says that FP has no
approximate subfields. And so the
subproduct theorem rules out the
possibility that this could happen.
So the conclusion is the
sum product theorem
that this can't happen.
Yeah.
[Applause]
Yeah. So, so what's on the board? Let me
I I should add one thing. So, we're
going to assume
that H is not contained in a BL guy.
Right? So this this whole thing would
that that wouldn't be true for the
burell subgroup. Um it's only true once
we assume that our subgroup is not not
contained in burell. And then we get
this and that tells us that it has to
look uh
uh like the intersection sizes have to
match SL2 of a sub field.
And then if you look more carefully at
what the matrices that appear in the
intersections, you see that the entries
there have to be kind of like a sub
field. And then it becomes a question of
whether there are approximate subfields.
Okay, let me say it one more time and
then we will break for the week. So the
theorem says that if you have a subgroup
which is not pretty much contained in a
burell subgroup then it must be SL2 of a
sub field.
Okay. Uh so we take and and it's going
to be true for honest subgroups but it's
also true for approximate subgroups. So
imagine we have an approximate subgroup.
We're going to gradually prove that it
has more and more properties of SL2 of a
finite field.
So the first property we will consider
is uh how it intersects various
algebraic subgroups of SL2 of KAR and
the sizes of those intersections behave
in a way that matches what you would
expect from SL2 of a sub field.
There's this there's a substantial thing
to say about this proof that we we won't
have time to do in this class. Um okay
but once you know that um these
subgroups are useful because the
matrices in here are simpler than
general 2x2 matrices. So the unitary
subgroup has matrices that look like
this. And when we multiply them you just
add the upper right hand corner. And so
now if you just look at these upper
right hand corners you see that adding
those numbers it doesn't change very
much. That's a property of a sub field.
So it's behaving like a sub field. and
the upper diagonal matrices um you are
the multiplication rule is only a little
bit more complicated. It's a it's a
pretty simple mix of multiplication and
addition. So you could see you know that
that that these diagonal entries they
should be almost closed under
multiplication and they interact with
each other and and so you would get
something like this. Anyway, all those
things being consistent algebraically
with being a sub field.
>> Okay. Yeah. How did we use 2.5?
>> Uh, where did we use 2.5?
Yeah, that's a good question. Actually,
I don't see where we used that here.
um
ah yeah we used that um here so so at
the end we have to say E and F cannot be
approximately a sub field so and that
requires that they're significantly
smaller than FP so if you take FP and
you remove like two or three elements it
is almost closed under addition and
multiplication so that would be this
could happen then if you were allowed to
take a really large subset of FP a
really large subset of sub 2 FP.
Okay, cool. I apologize for going over.
Thanks for your patience. Uh, have a
good weekend and I will see you next
week.