We got to see above again. We back on
track.
We
burn again.
Do what you please.
>> [music]
>> some
[music]
look at me now.
Hey
you want to do
the sky
[music]
again. We got to see above again
burn again
[music]
up.
>> [cheering]
[music]
>> Give it up for MVP Z K-pop crowd.
I was a ghost. I was
so [music]
grown. I didn't know how to. I was a
queen that I meant to [music] be.
Sorry, but I could run my whole
child cuz got to
now I'm getting
I'm done.
Now I'm sorry.
We dreaming
so far.
[music] We're going
up without
you know we're going to be going [music]
[music]
>> [music]
[screaming]
[cheering]
>> brought to you by
>> Let's have a round of applause for MVP.
Thank you.
>> If you'd like to take a bow, take a bow.
Perfect. It's amazing. Thank you so much
MVP.