um yeah it's been a tremendous honor and
pleasure to be associated with the MTL
for the past 40 years and as Rona
mentioned and this is my 40th
anniversary of becoming a faculty member
at MTL so I always joke that the MTL was
established in honor of my arrival at
MIT
MIT with a joke
aside um I'm I'm truly honored to host a
really distinguish it uh panelist on
today's topic on MTL impact in the next
years
um there was going to be five panel
members but there were uh two panelists
who had to cancel at the last minute
last night um Jen Lloyd from
ADI um faing sick with a bad case of flu
and her doctor would not let her
fly uh and uh dar Hill IBM uh had to uh
go to UK on an emergency business trip
uh so um Marcy black of advanced silicon
group graciously agreed to be the fourth
panelist on an alra short
notice
uh so uh let me uh welcome uh the
panelist one by one
um first I'll do it in an alphabetical
order so uh Marcy
[Applause]
black yes have any seat so Marcy black
is a CEO and co-founder of advanced
silicon group and Dr Black brings to the
company expertise in building strong
teams managing development projects
patents IP strategy encouraging a
healthy company culture cost modeling
and running a startup in addition Dr
Black has a strong technical background
in areas of electronic materials Optics
semiconductors solar cell photo voltes
batteries re reable renewable energy
nanotechnology device design opto
electronics and so forth uh prior to
founding ASG advaned silicon group Mercy
was the president and co-founder of band
Gap engineering which focused on
lowering the cost of solar electricity
through black silicon or silicon
nanowire solar cells uh before joining
ban Gap Marcy was a technical staff
member at Lo Los alus National
Laboratory and worked on a variety of
nanotechnology and Optical systems Marcy
has a PhD from MIT in electrical
engineering ing in mil dressle houses
research group prior to her PhD work
Mari was a device engineer at Motorola
where she worked on combining
nonvolatile memory and logic circuits
onto the same chip in 2009 she was
awarded an R&D 100 award for her
contributions to work at
lamus Mari also was honored as one of
the 10 uh women to watch in 2010 by
Massachusetts Hightech um welcome to the
panel by the way uh the panelists were
chosen among MIT alumni uh who have very
strong connection to MTL so next
panelist is Susan
find uh please uh come over to the
podium Susan serves as natk senior vice
president of ecosystem development ment
prior to natc she served as an exe
executive and Technical fellow at Analog
Devices where she led technology
strategy and Innovation specializing in
advanced process and device development
she has spent the majority of her career
developing new technology and ensuring
its successful transfer to high volume
manufacturing Susan received her BS in
chemical engineering from MIT she has
served on many industry and academic
Advisory Board including most recently
as Vice chair of the Department of
Commerce industrial advisory committee
formed through the chips act she also
served on mit. Nano and MTL industrial
Advisory board for many many years in
her role within ncast Susan focuses on
defining nstc membership strategy and
structure PRI prioritizing
uh program offerings engaging the
broader ecosystem advocating for the
semiconductor ecosystem's interest and
collaborate with government
entries thank you for joining the
panel next I would like to introduce uh
Professor Thomas Lee I would like to
welcome you to the
podium uh Tom Lee received uh SB as Sam
and SCD all three degrees in electrical
engineering all from MIT he was also
awarded on honor honor his uh kza
doctorate from the University of watero
in 2012 in recognition of his
contribution to wireless technology he
joined Analog Devices in 1990 where he
was primarily engaged in the design of
highspeed clock recovery devices in
1992 he joined rambas incorporation in
Mountain View where he developed
high-speed analog circuitry for seos
drams he has also contributed to
contributed to the development of phase
lock Loops in the strong arm Alpha and
AMD k6 K7 and K8
microprocessors since
1994 he has been a professor of
electrical engineering at Stanford
University where his research Focus has
been on gigar speed Wireline and
wireless integrated circuits he founded
or co-founded a number of companies
including Matrix semiconductor zero gy
list and AAS networks he also served as
MTO director at DARPA from April 2011 to
uh October 2012 so he can bring not only
academic and Industry viewpoints but
also the government Viewpoint as
well uh next panelist is Professor
Kenneth
o please come to the
stage kenno received his SB SM and PhD
degrees in electrical engineering and
computer science all from MIT he is the
director of the SRC Texas analog center
of excellence and TI distinguished
University chair professor of analog
circuits and systems at the University
of Texas at Dallas his research group is
developing circuits and components
required to implement systems operating
at frequencies up to 40 terets using
silicon IC
Technologies Ken was the president of
the it it solid state circuit Society in
2020 and
2021 Ken received the the 2014
semiconductor research Association
University Research award and he is an i
fellow so let's again welcome all the
panelists
so um I believe MTL has been at least
fairly successful uh in its mission in
the past uh 40
years and uh we would like
to as the panelist um their thoughts on
the next 40 years uh of the M of MTL
what we should do and what we should not
do for example but uh we would like to
to put this in perspective so put it uh
to put it in the right context let's
just review mtl's impact uh during the
past 40 years or so uh Tomas pesus gave
a really nice presentation on history of
um MTL uh MTL and this is sort of a very
brief summary of what um Tomas uh talked
about in the
morning uh again uh the panelist we went
through them
um let's
see so uh first of all MTL has been an
interdepartmental laboratory for
Semiconductor fabrication so it offer
the uh tools and the facilities for
Semiconductor fabrication for every
member of MIT Community as well as um uh
outside uh
MIT and this part of the mtl's mission
has been transferred to MIT Nano in 2018
about 6 years ago but not only MTL
provided the tools and facilities for
Semiconductor fabrication it also
provided tools and services for uh
design for example device circuit and
system design they maintain all the cat
tools and
licenses and uh for design of IC PC
boards and photonics and
mems uh one of the very important
mission of MTL was being an inter uh
departmental research laboratory and as
such uh it's been an intellectual home
for more than 60 core faculty members so
as of now we have U almost 70 core
faculty members at MTL as thas
mentioned and MTL has been known for
very strong collaboration with industry
through its Microsystems industrial
group or M and many of its um uh
research C centers such as CICS uh Med
RC and MIT CG and other
centers and although this is more like a
consequence rather than the initial goal
uh MTL motivated a lot of startups uh
because MTL uh researchers came up with
uh so many exciting ideas it motivated
the startups and as Tomas thas mentioned
in the morning uh
there there are more than 50 spin-offs
of the MTL research as a startup
companies um research has been a very
very strong uh point of mtl's past
history and here's a very partial list
of the uh pioneering research that
originated from
MIT uh I want to mention that this is
really a very very uh partial list and
uh please don't be offended if you don't
see your own research in this list
because the true uh list is very very
long uh with hundreds of ENT uh entries
if not thousands of entries so I had to
make it uh fit in one page so again
please don't be offended if you don't
see your own research
yes uh so these have a widely ranging
industry and scientific Community um
impacts like the twist Electronics uh
from uh Pablo rioo uh R and quantum dot
strain silicon super deep retrograde
Channel doping from Dimitri Anton
antonetti's lab also from antonier Lab a
virtual Source velocity F model that's
been widely adopted by industry and an
chantra cousin's Dynamic voltage and
frequency scaling is used pretty much
everywhere these days uh Charlie sadin
group's high order Delta Sigma ads
became industry standard and Son Han's
activation orware weight quantization
has been uh really adopted very very uh
widely in uh machine learning industry
and uh bbnz and Jo emmer Iris high
energy efficient reconfigurable
accelerator has been adopted widely and
there are again hundreds and thousands
of U others like this um so MTL has had
a very very strong history of impact on
the research field so now the question
is what should be the impact of mtl's
next 40 years 40 years is a very long
time so it is it's going to be very
difficult to predict but uh I hope uh
the panelist will have some thoughts
first of all again it's a very long time
and I would look like
this according to photoshop but I think
Photoshop is actually very
underestimating the effect of Aging so I
would be more than happy if I look like
this at the age well over
100 okay with that um I would uh invite
I would like to invite the panelist to
kind of provide us with their view what
MTL should look like what MTL should do
uh in the in the next U 40 years and uh
we have Susan's slide on this machine so
naturally I would like to invite Susan
that's good
engineering to uh give her point do you
want me to stand there or just uh yes
you can stand here on the the podium and
you got a clicker there oh thanks thank
you for having me and happy iversary to
the MTL and to Harry
congratulations
great I think I was here for 32o I hope
I'm here for 50 um so this slide I think
what's what you're seeing semiconductors
transformed the world I think all of us
know this right like we all know this
and now the rest of the world is
learning this since the pandemic as it
was talked about this morning the
awareness of semiconductors and
everything they impact almost every
aspect of our economy they're changing
um and contributing to our health our
Safety and Security our quality of life
it's it's just amazing and and it's
amazing to think that in 1947 while it
wasn't invented here um the transistor
that then be went to a four planer
transistor circuit in the
1950s that now today uh Nvidia has
announced the black weld chip that has
208 billion transistors on it that's
just like amazing and I know that we're
all being driven and propelled by
Moore's law but it's and and a lot of
people think it's just about the you
know the feature size and that next node
but we all know that's the contributions
and the work that you've all done and
others because it's at the materials
level it's it's strained materials it's
it's low K and high K dialectric it's
new devices and architectures finfets C
fets it's it's new packaging Packaging
is like really hot right like who would
have thought um it's it's circuit design
it's the architecture it's it's the
whole system solution and I it's like
amazing where we've come I think we
should all be proud of that but there's
a long way to go and there's a lot of
challenges I mean there's the the
climate's changing um the world the
geopolitics our safety our security our
health the healthcare I made a lot of
emphasis on that today and yesterday I
think that there's so much we could do
there so with great challenges come
great potential and I think that's the
way we should look at it is there so
much that we could be doing from the
health care perspective to um prevention
early detection diagnosis treatment so
that we can all live healthier and
longer lives um from Automotive
perspective from a safety perspective
there with autonomous driving um
electrification of vehicles there's so
much more that can be done
we you know longer range on our vehicles
from the energy I mean we need to
diversify our sources of energy we need
to strengthen our grid we need to um
Renewables we need to shift to that
there's there's a lot that we could be
doing there and increasing the
efficiency um security communication so
there is a lot we could be doing and as
I noted before I think that we have to
be doing it in a holistic fashion and I
know that many of you you've seen this
before it's the full stack right from
the materials to the application Level
and everything in between and what I'd
like to see is it looks more like this
is that we need to be co-developing
co-designing
co-optimizing and it was talk today
there was a lot of talk on combinatorial
and heterogeneous integration and system
Solutions but it you really need to be
optimizing at the whole stack you need
to be thinking about what materials
you're going to be using in in those new
devices and
and how you're going to be you know I
think Ry was saying just don't just want
to buy a bag of chips you know they you
want to go to chiplets but then you
still need to be thinking about the
interfaces and and all the challenges of
combining them and co-designing so
there's a lot of challenges out there
and I know that these I I think Ray said
it too he said a lot of good things
today right he always does but when he
said that you're like a kid in a candy
store and there's so many things out
there to be working on so in the next 40
years there are a lot of things and I
know that where I'm working right now
with ncast I worked at Analog Devices
for 36 years so I want to talk about
that a little bit too because Jen
couldn't make it but um I've only been
six months at ncast but ncast was formed
as part of the chips act and so if you
look at for those of you that may not be
familiar with it there was 52 billion
that was approved for the chips act 39
billion of it is for manufacturing to
onshore to have that security of Supply
to bring back those the Leading Edge
nodes to the United States and and
Legacy
nodes along with that we had 11 billion
was allocated for
R&D and I think it's really smart of the
government I remember Marty Schmidt who
was a MTL director he's now president of
RPI he gave a talk at Congress and
talked about the inextricable link
between manufacturing and R&D and we
can't just onshore manufacturing and
expect that that's going to be it we
need to be investing in the Next
Generation
technology in order to have sustained
leadership for the future and that's
what this 11 billion is for and there's
and that's through the docc there was
two billion that's also through the drd
dod and that is the microelectronics
common funding that many of you are
probably familiar with we even part of
so the the doc 11 billion and the reason
I'm talking about this is I think that
what we're trying to do here is a lot of
what the MTL has tried to do and and and
the example that they've set is so the
11 billion was split between the nstc
which is the national semiconductor
technology Center and I'll talk about
that more a National Advanced packaging
program manufacturing USA which is
focused on digital Twins and that was
announced just earlier this week that
SRC is won that and is going to be
leading that and then the chips
Metrology
program I'm under the
nstc and nstc is a
Consortium public private Consortium we
want everybody participating in it we
want Academia we want government we want
industry industry large and small and
across that entire stack these solutions
that the challenges that we have and the
solutions that we need are going to
require interdisciplinary and it's going
to require everybody working together so
that's what and and ncast where I am is
a um a nonprofit purpose-built entity to
operate the nstc so we'll be standing up
um facilities um supporting research um
initiatives in various ways we'll have
an innovation or investment fund we um
want to help reduce that time and cost
to prototyping so really a lot of what
we're setting up is to help startups and
small businesses to lower the barrier to
entry um again all the these kinds of
things are things that the MTL and Nano
have been trying to do as well to
provide more access and Facilities to to
to have new businesses that we can't
even imagine so it's hard to predict 40
years but we're there's going to be a
lot of things that we can't even imagine
today that we're going to have and then
then the biggest thing that runs across
all of this funding is
Workforce I mean if we continue the way
we are and I think that was brought up
today too that um computer science is
more attractive to many than Hardware is
but I think that it's all related and
when they don't see the promise of jobs
in the united they you know they go
where the jobs are and I think that this
is going to bring a lot of jobs back and
it's predicted that we continue at the
trajectory that we're on we will be
short 60,000 jobs by 2030 so we need to
change this and so a big part of this is
the Workforce Development initiatives
and
um I could I can go on about a lot of
things but I think my five minutes was
up a long time ago but I'm going to take
Jen's five minutes because I want to
also talk about Analog Devices and how
we have participated as Ry said this
morning we were founding members of of
the um MTL we're founding members of
Nano we find it's really important to be
working with um collaboratively like
this to you know make sure that they're
working on I mean I think there is that
feedback of we we get exposed to new
ideas but then the students get exposed
to what are the what's important out
there so um we've participated in the
Gan Consortium we participated in um
metrc and that's a really great one that
char
L and still leads um which is bringing
together again Academia industry and the
medical um field so we've participated
in a lot of those but I would say the
biggest benefit to ADI is not
necessarily the technology that we were
exposed to or that we learned but the
talent and I mean that was the hardest
thing for me to leave at ADI was there
many of them are in the audience too is
the talent we have amazing people that
that came from here CHR Jim are here
merik was here this morning I mean just
so many graduates and I know Ken I mean
just like everyone on the state and and
they may not stay at Analog although we
hope that they do they go all over the
over the world and you have
representation and that is truly two the
top two that's truly the the the
greatest thing that we get from our
participation in the MTL is the talent
so um we could talk more about the next
40 years but I think there's a lot out
there that we can be contributing and I
just just appreciate being able to share
this with you today thank
you yes I forgot to mention that Susan
agreed to uh represent uh Jen ly's
Viewpoint a little bit because she
couldn't make it um the next uh panelist
I would like to invite is um Keno again
because there is a file in this computer
when I asked Keno to be on the panel he
treated it like G gigantic homework
assignment and as was his habit when he
was a student here he worked until the
last minute so he kept uh sending us the
updated version until this
morning this is the most upto-date
version of assignment thank you thank
you Harry I know it's really good to be
back uh at MIT uh it's and um really uh
you know of course I was um a student
when it was actually fairly early and so
I can go back and um if you uh look at
the uh the key Focus area for MTL uh in
the early years was actually mixed
signal Technologies and
circuits and now if you look at today uh
almost all new integrate circuits are
either mixed signal or analog and um you
know the founders
of the MTL really had great vision for
what the future is going to be and um of
course one of the people who contribute
to the uh this Vision uh was Stanis bus
uh from TI at that time and um actually
in
2018 he shared us a presentation uh
which entitled industry in transition uh
with me and um so in there he was
actually outlining what the uh next 30
years of the semiconductor industry
would be and um so that was a great
resource for me uh as I prepare this uh
presentation uh so this slide uh was
actually something similar to what
Thomas showed this morning uh it's just
a different version and um so what this
slide shows is the uh energy uh that's
consumed uh in Jewels per year uh for
computation and communication
and uh what you see is that uh by year
2035 almost uh thir 50% of electricity
uh will be uh consumed by the
computation and communication if it goes
the way it's going right now and um of
course this is for the world and um so
if you look at uh you know what's
happening in developed countries this is
going to be actually significantly worse
and um so if you look at also this
plot if you look at the total electrical
energy generation it increases by about
3% a year and um this is something
that's been going on many decades this
is not something recent but it's just
been going on like this uh for many
decades and so what this means is that
we are going to pay a lot more for
electricity if this happens and of
course that will ultimately limit the
growth of um ICT
and um so our challenge is we have
to increase the uh the rate of Energy
Efficiency Improvement of course you
know
microelectronics improves Energy
Efficiency the scaling uh improves but
we have to increase the rate of um
Improvement so these are the things some
of the thoughts that I have that uh that
we should be doing and I think we are
already doing it right uh of course the
first is improve the Energy Efficiency
of computation itself there are uh I
think this morning and uh this afternoon
I saw many ideas about how that can be
done and um you know I think one of the
things that I've uh recently learned is
that just going from CPUs to gpus is
actually helping it's actually improving
the uh Energy Efficiency so that's
really good news and of course you know
we have amazing technologies that uh in
our uh portfolio and um going forward we
have to use the best of um the things
that we have so that we can uh improve
the Energy Efficiency faster and of
course that leads to heterogeneous
integration and of course that happens
right and then so if you think about
heterogeneous integration there all the
things but so many things that needs to
be done right um of course you know we
are all just odd by uh euv at this point
but we in 40 years we really do have to
think about what's going to be beyond
the 13.5 nanometer lithography and um so
last 40 years I our ability to image
things have um gone down by well
increased by factor of 100 right so you
know it's getting harder so you know if
you say it's factor of 10 in next 40
years we're going to be down in the
nanometer range and um so at that point
we're really not talking about nanometer
devices it's really atomic scale devices
that we're going to be dealing with and
um as suan mentioned you know we have to
do close disciplinary optimization of um
all levels and
um we have to account while doing that
we have to account for for
the and accounting or exploit the
variabilities uh that we have with all
uh our Technologies and also have to
worry about the mechanical thermal
electromagnetic and electronic effects
all these things have to happen at the
same time and so if you think about the
complexity that we'll have to deal with
it's
just mindboggling it's not just the
design but you also have to verify the
design you have to test the design and
you have to ensure the security of this
how about the reliability of this you
know you have 280 billion but now you're
going to have 50 of those in
the heterogeneous Integrated Systems how
are you going to assure the
reliability and um how about the power
delivery I think ultimately we're going
to be going toward 3D integration how
are I going to deliver power to this 3D
Integrated Systems and um of course I
think ultimately uh the rate of
generation of electric power electrical
power has to increase and so I think the
grid has to be upgraded and also uh
expanded and I
think obviously also the efficiency has
to be improved and I think that really
points toward the high voltage
semiconductors and I think that's going
to be a very important uh opportunities
for
everybody and
um because of these complexities that we
are dealing with ultimately the
heterogeneous integration will have a
limit on the complexity and the scale
and so beyond that we have to be
thinking about how I going to connect
these heterogeneous Integrated Systems
together to do something even bigger and
um of course the last thing is um
3D integration you know it's something
that we've been talking about for ages
uh and I think even when I was
undergraduate student people are talking
about 3D integration but we don't have
it yet and um what we really need is
energy efficient on chip and uh in
package Cooling and this can change the
whole picture and gee in 40 years you
know I'm not going to do it but you
should be able to do it
right so when I you know if you look at
what Dennis uh has actually put together
uh he talks about a fork uh for the
semiconductor industry and um so what he
was talking about is the fact that there
will be only few companies that will be
able to keep scaling which is true right
so we have about three companies that's
doing and um so the question is what do
other guys do and um so what he was
proposing is stop scaling uh of course
at uh 28 to 22 nanometer range in the in
the noes and um sorry can you wrap yeah
yeah yeah I'm done yeah and um so sorry
Harry so uh what he was talking about is
um rep
up
uh so stop scaling and then add more
functions into the integrate circuits so
talking about the heterogeneous
integration uh in order to uh solve
really the big problems uh for the
society and um you know we really do
have amazing set of Technologies and uh
we can do a lot more and if you actually
look at you know the past 40 years all
the things that I have not seen really
thought of when I was a graduate
students it has happened using just
existing Technologies I mean like the RF
RFC Moss uh it's one uh seos imagers and
I think you may always to argue that the
gpus was one of the things that actually
happened uh you know without really you
know the technology was not intended for
that and so I think there is a really
important thread of research along this
line and of course uh the other one is
you know what else can we
integrate uh with our Technologies so
that we can once again solve big
problems and um so you know things like
RF passive silicon fonics you know these
are the examples of what happened but
you know the things that will happen is
not on this uh chart but it's really
about the kind of way that you can think
about and what to work on and um I'll
finish by just saying that 40 years from
now somebody uh in this panel in this
future panel will mention this uh
something that came out along this
thread of um thought which is uh low
cost wafer scale and display panel scale
electronically s reflectors uh for uh
order of magnitude uh better efficiency
and of course this is something that
Professor uh Ronan h is working on at
this point but I think we need to make
it low cost and really make it scalable
and thank you for this
opportunity sorry
Harry all right I think I'll go with
Marcy last because she had zero time to
think little more time
I so I will go with Tom uh so we we're
going to have to change the um laptop
all right hopefully this won't crash the
system
so all right okay I'll just put it over
here
great so Tom mentioned this morning that
he prepared 45 minutes worth of material
so I hope he can condense it by a pack
it's only 200 slides how long can that
take it's uh it's always a dangerous
thing to give a professor microphone oh
yeah they never want to let it go
all right well I'm going to try to uh
slice up this a little bit differently
perhaps than um is normally done I
always inflict history upon my students
if you ask them they'll say with an
exasperated tone yes that's indeed true
but the reason for doing this is not out
of a nostalgic feeling for the past the
good old days allegedly uh it's really
because even if history doesn't
literally rhyme uh lit literally repeat
itself it certainly seems to rhyme a lot
so when you try to do the impossible
thing of predicting the future the best
we can really do is take a look at the
rhymes of the past and see what happens
if you consider that to be a motif that
will repeat in the future so first of
all mvin Kelly Marvin Kelly you in the
Old Country uh is someone who should be
on our T-shirts because we owe him our
jobs uh this is a case where one
Visionary person not only noticed
something about the track that history
was falling and didn't like it and did
something to change it he actually
successfully changed it uh so Marvin
Kelly was the head of bell labs when
Bell Labs was just forming and he
noticed that the number of technicians
for the AT&T folks was growing at an
exponential rate and he noticed in fact
that if he extrapolated the curve a
little bit more that by the year 2000
basically every adult in America would
have to be an AT&T technician and so he
thought that was unlikely and so he had
identified a scaling barrier to AT&T's
total dominance of everything so uh he
looked about for possible solutions and
the problem of course was
electromechanical relays and vacuum
tubes had limited lifetimes and uh there
was one slender existence proof of a
solid state device its operational uh
properties were not understood no one
knew Quantum really well enough to
explain these things but a copper oxide
rectifier was in use uh at Bell Labs or
actually in the T&T system and So based
on that tiny tiny uh existence proof of
a non-moving part thing that does some
useful signal processing he bet the
entire future of not only AT&T but us on
the solid state so he assigns a guy
named Bill Shockley the task of heading
up a group that's going to deliver what
would later be called the transistor so
that's a to me that's a remarkable thing
my crystal ball is permanently broken
it's cloudy uh I have successfully
predicted uh the last 12 well 12 the
last two uh downturns so uh and that's
apparently typical but Marvin Kelly just
nailed it so it's pretty a remarkable
thing now was that a one-off well it
turns out that we can identify yet
another character with similar Visionary
Powers uh in the story of semiconductors
Bob Noy who is uh according to history
the co-inventor of the IC but he is the
inventor of the IC as it's currently
instantiated noise was making
transistors at Fairchild and he saw the
absurdity of building multiple
transistors on a wafer dicing up the
Wafers packaging up the individual dice
shipping them to customers who then
soldered them back together again it
felt an awful lot like a government
works project where you hire one group
to dig a ditch and another one group to
fill it up and you say yay uh and so he
thought of the interconnect problem as
being an important part of making
integrated circuits valuable he saw that
as a scaling limiter to be unlimited and
luckily he had in his employee Jean who
gave him the planer process which also
turned out to have solved the
interconnect problem for him so that's
why we have the 208 Giga transistor ic's
today it's because noise sort of
uniquely and before anyone else
recognized this would be a scaling
limiter saw that unlocking the power of
IC would require overcoming that barrier
and then overcoming it really remarkable
so here we have two examples in the
history of our business where it was
sort of one Visionary just looking out
into the future looking at scaling
problems and preemptively getting rid of
them so trying to channel the spirit of
both Marvin Kelly and noise what kind of
scaling challenges do we face today well
luckily we've already had two speakers
present curves that sort of speak to
that uh Professor Palos gave a curve and
good old Keno uh did the same thing if
you take a look at the scaling trends of
just CPUs as an example of what's going
on broadly certainly the transistor
count is growing so that seems to be a
sign that everything's well with with
Moore's law but if you read Moore's
paper very carefully he actually
mentions explicitly that the value of
doing this shrinkage only is sustained
by a diminution in the cost of the
transistor and that's no longer
happening the cost per transistor is
kind of flattened out since the finfet
days and that sort of saturation is
showing up in the single thread
performance of CPUs CPUs uh kind of
flattening there and we're trying to
compensate by giving it more and more
cores but if you notice this is parallel
to that curve so we're throwing more
core more transistors at cores but we're
not allowed to light up all the course
because the part would incandesce and
desolder itself from the PC board so we
have a problem here that's caused by
sort of the dinard scaling uh no longer
holding and at the same time that we're
delivering sort of less per
generation uh to the users of these
devices they're just demanding more of
the devices uh this is a a typical uh
plot showing the evolution of model
parameter number for deep Learning
Systems uh on the left it's hard to see
but the Top Line there is a trillion
parameters and that was passed by uh
what is this switch C at Google uh if
you try to fit a curve through this
thing this is a a logarithmic plot and
the best fit curve is an exponential all
right so if you're you my students
they've seen curves all the time it's
just too abstract for them so I say
imagine this is your bank account
balance they oh that would be good okay
now you got it so the growth rate here
is insane it's in this case it's 177,000
X every 3 years for the last segment of
that
plot and while our transistors are still
kind of transis the same as they have
for several Generations so this is a
problem so that's conspiring to produce
this curve which has been shown a couple
times but I'll add a couple fiducials to
the curve uh just to make sure that
we're calibrated on what the meaning of
these curves is the green curve is data
center power growth and it's nicely
following a factor of 10 slope every
decade the red curve is the uh amount of
electrical energy generated on the
planet and the gold curve is the total
amount of energy generated on the planet
so we're right here along this line here
and the major divisions here are two
orders of magnitude and energy so we're
in the sort
of approximately 10% of global
electrical energy being consumed by data
centers and it's on an upward slope so
if 10% doesn't make you frightened
the fact that that 10% is today and is
growing a factor of 10 per decade that
should concern you look at the first
derivative and not just the the base
value so and again just to calibrate us
uh to the reality that this cannot
continue much longer the total energy
received by uh the Earth received from
the Sun by the Earth is on the order of
10 to the 24th Jewels uh per year and
this is you know 10 to the 20th right
there so in mid-century if that curve
were to continue without bending over we
would need to consume all of the energy
incident upon the earth from the sun
that's including all the sunlight
hitting the oceans the poles everything
else yes I know the big Hook is coming
out very soon so so this is going to
bend over and the question is what's
going to make it bend over is because
you know humans wake up one day and say
we've got all the the the goodness we
need and compute when's that that ever
happen no uh or is it you know statutory
limitations on the consumption of energy
for compute like no Netflix on Saturday
is for you or or only wealthy people or
wealthy Nations or companies will be
allowed to compute so we don't want that
to happen so what's the existence proof
that gives us hope that there is a way
out of this yes we'll do all the things
that have mentioned we'll do process
things we'll do magic we'll do 3D we'll
do better heat pipes we'll do all sorts
of algorithmic tweaking and all those
things but the the effectiveness of
those tricks I argue will be very
limited because those are sort of linear
bandages trying to staunch a an
exponential blood flow so I think we're
going to have to look elsewhere we're
going to have to look out of the box now
but there is an existence proof biology
has given us the brain for example which
is remarkable it's 20 watts okay uh
politicians maybe a little less but
overall about 20 watts and it consists
of millisecond speed neurons these are
dog slow
things uh and yet it's um it's able to
do many many things Google's very proud
of imet where they showed it a 100
billion pictures of cats and now can
tell what a cat is that's not very
impressive compared to my niece who at
age three knew cat you know and we did
not train her with a 100 billion
pictures of cat she just new cat furry
purs likes it you know has sharp claws
got it it didn't need to see a bazillion
example so there's something about
biological brains that can do certain
tasks very very efficiently using
horrible resources it's meat-based
technology for God's sake when I want to
build something I don't reach for you
know steak to build my circuits and yet
somehow nature figured out a way to make
that work so I use that as uh a data
point that should also shame the
engineers into working harder and
smarter and also to give us hope that
there in fact is a solution out of this
box thank you
uh last but not the least uh Marcy black
I hope uh you can summarize your uh
thoughts in it's literally true couple
of
minutes hi happy 40th birthday everyone
um so tamas has a little bit of an
accent right and so when he said um
mtl's fabulous I thought he said mtl's
family because we have we have such a
good culture here and a good group group
of people I I hope the next 40 years we
continue that community of growth um so
I wanted to comment a little bit because
I figured people would comment on the
research side more I wanted to comment a
little on the other hat that MTL plays
and the other role which is education
and I'll mention a little bit of
research at the end um so education is
going to change a lot uh not in 40 years
but in 10 years I'd say um with the
expansion of AI like that just how is
just exploding and with open education
and so what that means is that it will
free up it will change education and it
will free up teachers and professors to
teach in in a lot deeper way in a lot
better way and I I think that a lot of
the ways that education is going to
change are going to make use of some of
the areas that MTL and M is particularly
strong at so for example um we have
amazing professors here as as everyone
knows um I did all three degrees here
and I remember in particular uh several
professors continued to Mentor me a
couple in this room actually um and so I
I think the importance of mentorship and
one-on-one teaching and office hours
like how many times that did you guys go
to office hours and be completely
clueless when you read the book and then
the professor figured out what you
didn't understand and was able to
explain it to you so I think that type
of teaching is going to become more and
more important with the explosion of
AI I also think um another area that MIT
is very strong with is is our Labs we
have this beautiful uh Fab that was just
built and did this just okay um and um
so that's gonna allow teaching to be
more Hands-On which I think is very
important um because you can read about
it in the book but unless you actually
do semiconductor processing you don't
really understand how to do it um and
also continuing to get students involved
in R&D um all the way undergrad through
grad I think is going to become more and
more important um I also think MIT is
particularly good at not just teaching
material but teaching students how to
think and I think I think that's going
to become more and more important
because frankly I have no idea where
technolog is going to go in 40 years um
but if someone is taught how to think
they'll be able to learn how to do that
and be able to to contribute to society
um so I don't know if that means that
education might change like maybe we'll
hand students papers and ask them to
critique it or maybe we will um give
them a new innovation and ask them to
brainstorm ideas of different
applications for it but um I think
teaching kids or our students how to
teach is going to be continually
important and I think MIT is very strong
at that um another area that MIT is
particularly strong at is our students
and our diversity in in in who we have
here um both internationally but also in
expertise um like there was a couple
slides that showed how we're number one
in so many different technical Fields
like that's just amazing that one
University can be number one in so many
different areas um so in addition to
engineering and Technology we also have
SL in the business school and so having
all these expertise together in one
place is really going to help
cross-pollinate ideas and allow us to
innovate better and I I think I've
noticed in my career that a lot of the
best ideas come from cross-pollinations
across different areas in in stem but
even outside stem um and um my career
has been focused on entrepreneurship so
having exposure to the business school
and the entrepreneurs Club really helped
me in in my career
um so on the R&D side
um my advice to students is always to
focus on the problem and I feel like I I
think it's interesting how we all pick
some of the same problems so the things
that I see as some of the bigger
problems in the near future are energy
health care and defense um and I just
wanted to and and all of these really
need Microsystems and semiconductor
development like all of them like
they're they're a large part of those
problems are going to be solved by the
people in this community and in similar
communities um but I wanted to spend
just a minute on biosensing and the
healthcare because that's what my
company event silicon work group works
on um so we're developing a silicon ship
that can measure proteins uh in a very
very rapidly and very low cost and I
think um biosensing in general is really
going to revolutionize how we see
Healthcare and well
I I think it's absolutely ridiculous how
little we know about our own bodies um
but in the very near future I think
we're going to have access to daily
measurements of how our body is doing
and and tell us everything from oh
you're starting to get sick to you drank
too much last night or uh you need to
hydrate or you need electrolytes like
there there's so much information that
we're literally just throwing down the
toilet every day so I I see um
biosensing and silicon ships is being
able to really impact our our healthc
care and and well and wellness um so
with that I I to summarize I I think a
lot of the areas um that are going to be
needed in both R&D and education I think
MTL and MIT um in addition to MTL are
very strong at and so I I look forward
to seeing what the community does in the
next 40 years
all right let's uh give another uh round
of of Applause to the
panelist so I did prepare a few
questions uh but I think uh since we
don't have a whole lot of time left uh I
would like to invite questions from the
audience um I think uh probably the best
way at this point is for you to raise
your hands and then yell
[Laughter]
I would like the the uh live questions
first
yeah I've been thinking today speakers
Tom summarized it well few ago about how
um it's becoming ridiculous the amount
of energy that we're using for computing
and communication and we've also
mentioned today how a lot of our
industry um came from the inventure of
the transistor
of new
revolutionary um history break invention
that we can come up with to totally
change this you mentioned the brain is
being an example is there any way we can
replicate that without actually needing
stakes and stuff to our company um I
don't know yet but I've spent the last 5
years uh trying to translate the
Neuroscience literature into terms that
are understandable to me that's been a
long slog but I I found a a person who's
bilingual she actually has a PHD in uh
in circuits and changed her career from
Imaging the brain to actually studying
the brain itself and fixing broken
brains so she's been my Ally my
dictionary who's been helping
me she steered me to the right
literature and then translated the weird
verbiage that they use into oh Vehicles
IR they're talking about M's law now I
got it um
the stuff I've been able to abstract
from that is that the brain is not
something that I can reduce to
transistors in the kinds of circuits
that we use um it's as far as I can tell
it's really an analog machine that has
within it um spatial reasoning engines
which makes sense from an evolutionary
point of view you need to be able to map
out just your space around you and then
the uh evolution of higher level
thinking just exapted that existing
Hardware to do metaphorical places and
so information processing is really just
metaphorically moving from one room to
another or combining different spaces
together and so when you start to think
about that as the model of computation
then you end up with very different
structures and so we've been pursuing
them we're we're taping out our first
test chip this January maybe um to test
out pieces of that to see if the Energy
savings doing certain tasks are what
we're hoping for but it's it's all very
spective I expect to be wrong many more
times than we get it right but we we
feel like we're on to something because
we've been able to sort of take some
insights from evolutionary biology make
them together with other stuff
interestingly enough from two different
domains here at MIT from gome Chomsky
who showed that we have an inborn
Universal grammar engine and um max
tegmark who I think wrote the most
important AI papers that no AI
researchers have read uh he showed that
you can do symbolic uh regression much
more efficiently using um his methods
which don't just do machine learning the
normal way uh he found out that if you
just give it the biases that humans have
we believe in the beauty of nature
that's just a a poetic way of saying
that nature obey certain symmetry laws
if you use those symmetry laws as
pre-filters to prune your neural net he
was able to use the original data from
350 years of physics when people just
looked out the night sky and figured
things out using that original data he
was able to reproduce 100 equations of
physics fundamental equations in physics
and from the original data and often
times using fewer than 10 data points
it's really quite remarkable so he took
an NP hard problem added this very very
simple pre-filter and it went from
impossible to genius uh it's really
quite amazing I think there's a lot of
that that we've got inbuilt and
sometimes those biases are unhelpful but
uh but a lot of the efficiencies that we
attribute to Mom magical biology bits is
just really um preconfiguring the brain
to prefer things that obey certain
asymmetry principles so we're taking
advantage of those in go to uh the
question uh from Pigeon Hall uh what is
the best way to transfer the skills and
knowledge from retiring Workforce to
younger generation do we have enough
younger people showing interest in
semiconductor Hardware who wants to uh
take that question I I can just add that
I have a lot of trouble hiring uh
semiconductor experts um in particular
those with uh that
have um what's the right word approval
to work in the US so it's it's a big
challenge it' be interesting to hear
from the folks in Academia and what what
is the trend is it is it changing with
the promise of manufacturing coming on
Shore and the investment that the US is
making yeah it is anecdotal but the
classes that deal with circuits and and
semiconductors uh the enrollment uh
enrollments have gone up it could be
temporary uh but at least the the the
the derivative is
[Laughter]
positive yeah I was shocked we we've
seen a doubling in the enrollment and
Hardware classes uh in the LA over the
last three years and I don't know if
it's a one-time blip but it's it's held
for three years running uh it's actually
straining our resources because we we
had been shrinking the amount of space
available for lab classes to respond to
the previous signal where the slope was
negative and just as we were doing this
all of a sudden you now now we're
cramped so students are contending for
res course that's a good problem to have
relative to the previous one but still a
problem but hopefully it continues to
sustain at this higher level I mean we
we see the same thing at the
undergraduate level uh for us at The
Graduate level it's different because of
the uh you know we rely heavily on
International students and it has been
actually difficult for a lot of
international uh students to come to the
United States in the past few years uh
but in the undergraduate level we see a
great deal of excitement among students
I think that there's the the it
semiconductors a lot it's the awareness
that we talked about that you know
semiconductors are going to transform
our future and I think that and the
promise of jobs in the United States so
I think that I do think it's not going
to be a blip I think that there's a
shift and more folks are going to and I
think that some of the Workforce
Development initiatives that we we're
going to have for the chips program are
going to help that because we have to
reach back to you know stem education
and see it all the way through and track
these and I going around the country
there are so many different programs
that I see for Workforce Development and
I think we just need to share the
learning amplify the ones that work I I
think there's a lot for you know
training young people and um retraining
older people so I think it's I see a
positive trajectory here uh let's um
invite a question from the live audience
or even the comos
audience take them all this may be a
silly question but between humanoids and
AR glasses what do you think will hit 1%
adoption in the US first what is the
question what the two AR glasses and and
humanoids I didn't humanoids humanoids
we have about 10 companies that have
developed humanoids um prototypes
that's a hard question because part of
that is not technology it's it's uh
human behavior so
you it's hard to say because we we have
a large robotics lab that we just funded
and we had a big uh inaugural ceremony
in fact and you know I sort of pinged
people as they were walking away from it
they all thought it was really neat and
then when I asked the second question so
would you want these in your home answer
was almost universally no way and I said
why not well I have kids I'm worried
that these things will go berserk you
know didn't just e Terminator you know
they they think it was a documentary and
so I I think that's the the sort of bias
that may be overcome but I have no idea
how long that takes I mean something you
know the right
movie perhaps change U people's thinking
overnight but I have no idea I've been
horrible at predicting social trends you
know we cannot predict anything anyway I
can't I absolutely can't I've proven it
over and over
again all right the uh timer is showing
a red blinking light that means that we
went over time Susan is nervously
looking at her watch CU she has a pright
to catch so um let's uh thank the
panelists for their wonderful view
points and presentations