Look, I
think it's just because everyone is
graduating after
graduating which is good. So I can go to
all of them but also bad basically every
also graduating.
Yeah.
So, he's going to have Is there any
special event
for graduates? I guess not. Senior week.
You're doing great. If I can have your
attention, please.
So, first I just wanted to say thank you
to all of you for coming to this event
for fusion energy week. As most of you
know, this is somewhat the beginning of
my career here at MIT and certainly my
first fusion energy week. I was very
nervous about planning this. So, I'm
very grateful to see such an
enthusiastic audience both here and
those of us on Zoom. So, thank you to
all of you for coming and making this
event wonderful. And thank you to Alex
and Maria who agreed to give us an
amazing presentation and who got us that
pizza or worked for us to get the plot
for the pizza. You're welcome for the
pizza. Um, all right. Uh, let's go ahead
and get started. So, those uh who are
offsite, I hope you could get pizza for
yourselves at home or wherever you're
at. Uh today, Maria and I are going to
put on a a boxing match of sorts. Uh you
know, the race to fusion energy, magnets
versus lasers. Um right, and you know,
kicking off fusion energy week. Um we
had a similar type of presentation about
a year ago now at the MIT Energy
Conference. And so, uh, we've kind of
reprised our roles, revamped the slides
a bit. Um, and, uh, we hope you enjoy.
Also, I just want to say we recognize a
lot of familiar faces here in the
audience. So, for those folks who know
things about magnetic fusion energy,
like my part is probably be pretty
boring for you. Uh, and then for those a
lot of my part you'll have heard before.
Yeah. Yeah. This is a really sort of
intro to fusion and hopefully a lot of
folks um online will also get a lot out
of this. Uh, and then maybe we'll hold
questions until the very end, but we
should have plenty of time to do Q&A and
stuff. So, this will be the third time
we battle this out, Alex, I think. Oh,
third time. Okay, nice. Yeah. All right.
And you've won every time. All
right. Um, okay. So, for those of you
who don't know me, maybe some people
offline. I'm Maria Gota Johnson. Um,
this kind of my introduction slide. So I
do nuclear diagnostics for inertia
infusion and high energy density science
which is where I will be talking about
the laser part throughout this talk. Um
I got my PhD from UPS university in
Sweden in 2010 in applied nuclear
physics and back then I was actually
working on magnetic confinement fusion.
So this is the instrument that I built
in grad school the time of flight
optimized for rate or to neutron
spectrometer. Look at DD neutrons and
it's illustrated with the inside of the
jet to mech right there. uh but now and
then I uh did my postto here at MIT uh
from 2010 to 2013 working on this
magnetic recall neutron spectrometer at
the national facility which looks like
that this is that's the actual detector
um and I've been working that's been
part of my role ever since I really
analyzed a lot of MR
data this is a picture from our lab
across the street in NW21 where we do
all the diagnostic development as a
group for the national ignition facility
in the Bmore in California. I'll show
you some pictures from there and for the
Omega laser in Rochester in upstate New
York and also for the Z machine and also
starting to do it for some private
fusion companies now. So diagnostic
development is our focus and this lab in
NW1 is where we enjoy showing this
picture.
Fighter number one, fighter number two.
Uh my name is Alex Tingley. I'm a
research scientist here. Uh also a group
leader in energetic particles in
magnetic fusion plasmas. I did my PhD
here um now started 10 over 10 years ago
and I worked on the Alcatore CEO tokmac
and so for those people who don't know
what a tokamac is we I will talk about
that but you can see this picture on the
left the inside of alcator cmod and sort
of a picture of me working inside the
tokamac and and then me standing outside
the tokamac on the bottom. Um then I
went to Jet uh into the UK for my
posttock for a few years and so here's a
picture of me standing on top of Jet and
you can then see inside of Jet. Uh and
then I came back to MIT um where as I
said I'm a research scientist. I
primarily work on the spark tokamac and
again we'll talk about each of these. Um
and uh here you can see inside the
tokamac hall for spark and in the sort
of magenta box on the other side of
those those holes were inside this room
here which is the neutron lab and I I
mainly work on neutron diagnostics and
fast ions and and electrons and fusion
plasmas. Um but why do we do the work
that we do? Um well I mean first fusion
would be a pretty amazing human
achievement but there is sort of a a
more um you know valuable role that
fusion can play in the world today. So
uh when Marie and I were making this
presentation um now a few years ago uh
we got this data um on um the climate
change and the and the world warming.
And so here you can see the very sad
graph of uh 50 years of the temperature
getting hotter and hotter. Um, and then,
um, here's a global map of of the
temperatures across the world being, uh,
in white is average, and then all the
red is is above average with the the
darkest red being the record warmest.
So, back in 2023, you can see a lot of
red and a lot of dark red splotches. So,
that that is not good. Um, and I've just
updated this for 2025. Uh, you know,
things do look a little better. There's
there's a little more white, but there's
still a lot of red. Um, and so we are
looking for a clean energy source that
is not carbon producing to help combat
climate
change. Um, and so here's Bill Gates who
maybe said it best. We need an energy
miracle. Uh, what could that be? Uh,
this is the the cover of uh, time where
fusion is unlimited energy for everyone
forever. Sounds pretty cool, right? So,
and then actually the little tagline
there, it might actually work this time.
So, you know,
That's also nice.
So, uh let's get into what is fusion. Um
so, what we're doing in fusion is we're
taking uh the atomic nuclei. So, in all
your atoms, you have in the center a
positively charged nucleus and we're
taking that nucleus, so two light
elements like these two light hydrogen
nuclei here, and we're forcing them
together. And if you bring them close
enough together with enough energy, they
will actually stick together. they'll
fuse into a new element and release a
lot of energy. So you can see that now
these two types of hydrogen come
together helium nucleus flies out and
then also a neutron comes out and we
want to basically harness that energy in
fusion. Uh where does that energy come
from? Uh well if you actually weigh the
the different components here. So the
two types of hydrogen which are on the
left the dutyium and tridium if you
weigh those before they react they are a
little bit heavier than the products the
neutron and the helium nucleus. So that
really tiny mass difference actually
gets changed into energy by Einstein's
famous equation E= MC^2. And the speed
of light is huge. So the C^2 is huge and
that's how you get a lot of energy out
of this. So the basic idea for what we
want to do for fusion on Earth is number
one, heat our fuel enough to turn it
into a plasma and have our fusion
reactions start occurring. Number two,
for this particular type of fusion,
those helium particles that are created,
we want them to stick around and
continue to heat the plasma as well to
keep our plasma hot, to keep the fusion
reactions going. And then number three,
the neutron that flies out, we want to
capture that energy and basically use it
to heat up water, turn water into steam
that goes through a steam cycle and
generates electricity. So in a way, it's
very similar to how electricity is
currently generated around the world. Uh
the parameter that we like to define is
Q and that's the energy out divided by
energy in. And so we want that to be
much greater than what we want to be
producing a lot more fusion power than
we're using for heating power. And so
throughout this talk we'll we'll touch
on the Q values uh for some of the
magnetic fusion and then also for um the
uh laser
fusion. So there are three main
approaches to confining a fusion plasma.
Um and and these are the most studied.
There are a lot of companies we'll
actually highlight companies at the end
of this talk and so a lot of different
strategies but these are kind of the
three main ones. Um there's
gravitational confinement, magnetic
confinement and inertial confinement. Uh
gravitational confinement has been
around for a long
time. Uh yeah. So you know basically
that's how stars work, right? Uh so all
stars are fusion reactors. Uh and so you
need something that is the size of the
sun in order to have your fusion
reactions occur in. Then we uh have
magnetic confinement which is what I'm
going to talk about. Uh and inertial
confinement is sort of the laser side
and that's what Maria's going to talk
about.
uh the different types of scales that
are required for each of these um are
pretty dramatic. So uh in the sun the
density that's that's n there um is
really really high in the core of the
sun and the temperature is also very hot
10 million degrees approximately. Um now
you need your particles to basically
kind of stay around in the same place
for long enough to get fusion reactions
to occur. And the time scales that we're
looking at for the sun are on on the
order of 10,000 years. But when you know
the sun is billions of years old, you
have a lot of time for these fusion
reactions to be occurring. For magnetic
confinement on the other hand, uh we are
much lower density. So about 12 orders
of magnitude lower. Um our temperatures
are about 10 times hotter than the
center of the sun, which is a huge
challenge for fusion here on Earth. And
our time scales are much more normal to
what humans are used to. So around a
second. Uh inertial confinement. Uh
we'll have Maria explain more later. The
densities are actually similar to the
sun. So they're basically creating
little tiny stars or at least that's how
I describe it. I don't know if you would
describe it that way. Temperatures are
similar around 100 million degrees. And
time scales are really, really, really
short. And so I think Maria will talk
more about that
later. So I am going to focus now on
magnetic fusion. And this is the jet
tokamac if it was made out of glass. Uh
which is kind of a cool picture to
see. So what is a tokamac? Basically, we
are trying to trap our fusion plasma in
a magnetic donut shaped bottle. So, we
see our pink plasma donut on the left
and the black line there is our magnetic
field line. And our charged particles,
those uh nuclei that want to fuse, they
want to follow those magnetic field
lines. And in here, they're actually
making little tiny spirals around the
field lines. And those field lines are
wrapping around on themselves. So, these
particles basically will just move
around in a circle forever. and they
keep colliding with each other over and
over and over until sometimes they'll
fuse together. Um, on this video on the
right, I want to demonstrate how a
magnet can sort of influence a plasma
and and make the plasma follow those
field lines. It's a very different
configuration. Um, that is a rare earth
magnet that's on the left. It's a dipole
magnet. So, the field is kind of coming
out of the top and going around to the
bottom there. And then the U plasma is
just like an basically an arc of plasma
between two electrodes. So we'll watch
this video. As our plasma moves over the
magnet, it goes from being basically
linear to sort of encompassing the
entire magnet, right? The plasma is
moving through the magnetic field and it
tries to move from the top of the magnet
down to the bottom of the magnet. So
that's sort of another type of of
magnetic confinement. It's not the same
geometry, but I think it's a nice
demonstration. Also, don't try that at
home unless you have high voltage
training and all those supplies.
So, here at MIT, we have a lot of
experience with magnetic confinement
fusion over many decades. Uh, but I just
want to highlight uh one sort of uh
exciting result that we had back in 2016
while I was a graduate student here. So,
this is again the Alcatore Seamont
tokamac. We're showing a picture of the
inside again in the upper right hand
corner. Now this device um was
relatively small about 2 meters in
diameter. So you know six feet or so on
the inside. Uh the magnetic field
strength this is really what's important
to help confine our plasma. We could
vary that from 2 to 8 Tesla. And your
MRI machine is around 1 to two Tesla. So
this is significantly stronger than what
most humans would ever experience. Now
the Q value this power out over in was
very very small in CMOD. Um, and that's
just because we didn't we weren't using
the right type of fuel in the first
place. And so it wasn't really one of
the main goals of the machine. However,
we were able to achieve a new record
which was the highest stored plasma
pressure. Basically, the magnetic
pressure fighting against the the heat
and the pressure inside our plasma. And
so on the left you can see this is the
day. A lot of people in the room
probably recognize people in the photo.
I put a little arrow to where I was
standing on that day. It was all very
exciting. And here is a video of that
discharge. So, we're looking inside. You
can see the inner wall kind of matching
the the photo above there. The plasma is
very bright. It lasts for only about a
second, but that's when we achieved the
highest plasma pressure record. Um,
maybe I can play that again for folks.
I'll just say that this is not what it
really looks like. This is a false color
video. And the brightest parts of the
plasma are actually the coldest parts of
the plasma where it's emitting visible
radiation which the camera can see. Um,
if we had a an X-ray camera, video
camera, then we would be able to see
sort of the the shape of the plasma, the
real doughnut
shaped. So, I was very lucky to have
been here for that record and the and
the end of CMOD's lifetime. Um, then I
moved over to the jet tokamac which at
the time was the largest operating
tokamac in the world. Um, and I was very
fortunate to also be there for their own
record for highest uh, fusion energy
achieved. So on the right we're seeing
again inside the jet tokamac. It's quite
a bit bigger than CMOD. So uh, from the
center out to the edge it's about 4
meters. So it's kind of four times
bigger than the CMO tokamac but the
magnetic field is smaller around three
Tesla. So, uh, this machine, uh, one of
its sort of general goals was to try to,
you know, get close to this Q of one.
Um, but it didn't quite get there. It
got to around Q of point4, which is not
bad, but we're not actually, you know,
breaking that break even barrier. Um,
still they achieved a nice record of 69
mega in terms of uh a a total energy um,
fusion energy emitted by the plasma. And
for reference of 4 mega is 1 kg of TNT.
So, it's about 10 kilos of TNT of
energy, which is pretty impressive. So,
let's go ahead and watch this video
here. We're going to see the left half
of the tokamac now, sort of mirroring
what's on the right. You can see the
visible emission down in the bottom of
the machine. And as the plasma goes,
here's the high power phase where we see
a lot of light. And you can see sort of
the entire machine lighting up. Again,
this is a visible um emission, so we're
not seeing the the X-ray emission from
the center of the plasma.
Um around that same time uh MIT was
exploring these high temperature
superconducting magnets. So high
temperature superconductors shown up in
the the top right corner there. Um these
are very thin tapes and when you get
them cold enough they can basically
carry current forever. So the team here
at MIT uh in collaboration with a
private company Fusion Systems built
this magnet which you can see in the
picture. It's quite a large magnet, you
know, about there are some people for
reference there. Um, and they wound this
out of the high temperature
superconducting tape and they achieved a
magnetic fields on the coil that was
greater than 20 Tesla. So remember, we
went from, you know, jet was three
Tesla, CMOD could go up to eight Tesla
and now we're getting up to 20 Tesla,
you know, over 10 times or even 20 times
the MRI magnetic field strength that
most people experience. And now this uh
achievement here basically unlocked the
funding to pursue building the spark
tokamac which is mostly what I work on
now. Um and this is there's this private
company fusion systems that spun out of
MIT. So here's kind of the current state
status of that device. Um there's a big
site up in Devons, Massachusetts. You
can see an aerial view here of the site.
In the in the background is the magnet
factory where they're building more of
the magnets like you saw on the previous
slide. And then in the foreground, this
is where the tokamac will live. So this
uh magenta arrows pointing to the
tokamac hall and inside you can see
inside in this upper right hand plot um
is where the tok will sit. Now a sort of
poster of what the tok will look like is
up on the far wall there, but it will
sit in the in the center of the floor.
And in the uh bottom right hand corner
is sort of a CAD rendering of what the
device will look like with a person per
for reference. So the magnetic field in
the center of the plasma is around 12
Tesla. So 50% higher than CMOD was able
to achieve. The diameter is about five
meters. So it's somewhere in between the
size that we built here at MIT and then
the size of the jet tok in the UK. And
the goal is to achieve Q greater than
one to demonstrate for the first time in
magnetic confinement fusion that we can
get more power out from fusion than we
put in to heat the plasma. Now, that
picture in the top right is a little out
of date. Here is a more recent picture
where they've actually in just installed
the Kryostat base, uh, which is where
the tokamac will sit. And they're busy
building the magnets for this tok. And
the vacuum vessel is also about to
arrive and we'll hopefully see our first
plasma sometime in
2026. Lastly, I just want to touch on uh
some challenges for for Tokamax. There
are way more than I could put on a
slide. Could be a whole other talk. Um
but I would say the trajectory for
tokamax is looking very good. Uh but we
have some things we need to address. One
is there are inherent plasma
instabilities in tokamax that can lead
to disruptions of your plasma and also
lead to relativistic electrons. This is
something I studied for my PhD. So
here's a video uh and you're going to
see the kind of a normal looking plasma
but runaway electrons are going to hit
that that metal thing on the right and
you'll see a shower of molten metal at
the end of the video. Okay, hopefully
you saw that. I'll play it one more
time. Um, this is something we
definitely want to avoid in future
tokamax because it can melt uh the the
metal that we have and you can see a
picture um of melting in jet um that
occurred. Also, there are a lot of
materials challenges related to melting
also you know getting power out of the
machine. We don't exactly know how
that's going to work yet. The sort of
plan that was developed at MIT also
being carried forward by CFS is to use
this molten salt fly which is shown here
in the the molten form on the right and
when it's its solid uh form on the left
there. Uh so there's a project going on
here Libra which is going to test how
this uh molten salt is able to breed
some of the fuel needed for fusion. Um
and um this is the plan for the future
uh fusion devices that CFS is going to
to build as well. So I hope I gave I've
given you a pretty good overview of
magnetic fusion. Now I'm going to turn
it over to Maria. Let's talk about laser
[Applause]
fusion. Um okay
so laser fusion uh works a little bit
differently than magnetic and fine
fusion. Although we obviously have the
same goal. Uh Alex showed the fusion
reaction at the
start alpha and that's still what we're
using in laser fusion as well. Uh but
the way that we do it in inertia
confinement fusion, we rely on the
inertia of the fuel to keep it together
long enough to burn. Uh so this is a
very simple illustration of how it
works. We'll get back to some examples
of how this is actually done. Uh but
basically you have a laser or X-rays
irradiating the surface of a a spherical
castle eating the surface
and when you do that when you irdiate
the surface with either the laser
directly or with X-rays as we'll get
back to uh you get ablation of the
surface material so you have a bunch of
material that starts moving off that
surface and then just from momentum and
energy conservation the rest of the
materials can start moving inwards the
kinetic energy of the shell that's
moving inwards and that kinetic energy
um is transformed into heat. So you get
a um heating of the fuel and you get
compression. So you get much higher
density and higher temperature brings us
down here. And once we get hot enough
and dense enough, that's when we get the
fusion reactions going. And the idea is
that the alpha particle is going to stay
in this fuel. So once you start getting
enough alpha particles generated in the
fusion reactions, you're going to get a
burn wave going. you can burn a
significant amount of this assembled
fuel. Um, and same as Alex said, the
neutron will escape for energy
production. The idea is to use the
neutron um to boil water essentially in
a reactor. Now, we're using the neutron
as a diagnostic indicator so we can
figure out what's going on in these
explosions. Uh, we talked about bank
time uh in in our circusion or ICF and
that's the time of peak nuclear
production. So to give you a sense of
the time scale basically this whole um
the laser poles the ablation the
compression and the convergence all
happens over about 10 nanocond for a
full scale implosion and then the actual
burn duration is order 50 picosconds. So
it's it's really a very very fast
experiment that we're talking about. Um
and just to give you a sense of the
scale uh the level of compression that
you have to do for these the capsule
starts out at about two millimeters in
diameter. So this is the scale model but
basically the equivalent is if you took
a basketball and squeeze it down to the
size of a green pee which also gives you
a sense of the challenge involved.
Imagine if you take a balloon and try to
squeeze it on all
sides. That level of squeezing without
the balloon bursting out through your
fingers. So it it's not an easy
one. Um there are three primary
approaches to doing this and two of them
use laser. So it's a little bit of a
misnomer to call this laser fusion but
we often do anyway because it's simpler
for people to understand than
inertifying fusion. But we have direct
drive which is where the laser beams
directly hit the DT fil capsule. And
then again just to give you a sense of
the scale, it's a 2 millimeter diameter
capsule like that. Um we also have
indirect in here. This is what I alluded
to on the previous slide. We have a
cylindrical cavity which we call a
whole. Um it's a German word that
basically means cylindrical cavity. Um
and the laces are incident on the walls
of that whole and converted to X-rays.
And it's actually the X-rays that drive
the capsule. And I have a example of a
whole here. So, I'm going to pass this
around and let you guys look at it. Uh,
this is an actual NIFA, but it's from
many years ago. So, it's not the same
scale that's used these days. But if you
turn this on its side, you can also see
that little fuel pellet in the center of
the So, look at it like this first. See
the cylindrical can and then turn it on
the side to actually see the fuel
capsule. Okay. So, that's the indirect
drive. We have the cylinder that we use
for that. And then finally we have
magnetic drive which is done at the Z
machine. Uh so here we drive a current
plasma uh to get the confinement and
I'll explain it in a little bit more
detail on a later slide. Um so all
current ICF facilities are research
facilities not aimed at generating
energy. We'll come back at that to that
a little bit later as well. And that in
the US we do have one flagship facility
that's pursuing each of these three
approaches.
So let me talk you through those. We
have the Omega laser facility at the
University of Rochester in upstate New
York. And this facility is optimized to
use a direct drive
approach. This is a a picture of the
full facility or obviously not a picture
schematic. Uh and what's actually taking
up most of the space here is the laser
bay. So this whole part is the laser
bay. uh and we have 60 laser beams at
omega which ultimately reach the target
chamber over here which is ball-shaped.
Uh this is the picture of the target
chamber. You can almost not even see the
ball because of all these white boxes.
These white boxes are where the lasers
enter into the target chamber. So again
there are 60 of them and they're
distributed uniformly around the chamber
optimized for direct drive. We really
want to hit all sides of that capsule
uniformly for the
lasers. This target chamber is three
meters in diameter just to give you a
sense of scale. And actually when you
look inside the chamber is not empty. Uh
you have a lot of diagnostics entering
into the chamber during the experiment
to actually be able to figure out what's
going on in these really uh short time
scale these really hot plasmas. So
again, Omega has 60 laser beams and it's
capable of delivering 30 kg total to the
target, which when we look at the N at
the next slide, you'll see that 30 kg is
a really small amount of energy. So this
is really a subscale facility. Um, but
experiments at Omega have been really
successful over the last few years. Um
and what we can look at the way we can
look at that is okay we only have 30
kilogjles of energy available but if the
laser energy was scaled up to two megles
which is what the NF can deliver then
will direct implosions ignite and this
is actually from a recent nature physics
paper um demonstration of a
hydronamically equivalent burning plasma
in direct drive fusion. So we can show
the extrapolated fusion yield with melee
from these omega implosions if you scale
it from the 30 kilogjles in to the two
mega in you reach the burning plasma
regime but you're not quite in the
ignition machine yet. So these are
bigger results from Omega but they're
not quite on the level of indirect drive
even if they were at a full scale
facility. And with that let's uh take a
look at the Z machine. So magnetic drive
ICF is being pursued at the Z pulse
power facility at Sandia National Labs
in New Mexico. And the idea here is that
in magnetic drive ICF an actual current
creates a JRO speed B force that's used
to implode a gas field pre-magnetized
target. So we call this mag um
magnetized liner in fusion. You start
with the pre-magnetization and also a
little bit of of preheating using a
laser. Uh and then you drive the um
current through to get the J press B
force and the compression. Uh and this
is done in the machine like this. So the
target is about a centimeter tall
cylinder which sits right here and the
current is coming through here. Um and
this a discharge can look like this. Um
this is actually a fail discharge. It
doesn't normally look like this but it
makes for a pretty picture. Um the goal
of this imaging is to demonstrate 100 kJ
DT equivalent fusion yield. Uh this
imaging runs with pure dutarium as the
fuel but they've started experimenting
with adding some some trace tridium. Uh
it's 33 m in diameter uh 26 mega current
and 22 mega stored energy. Uh, and I'm
not I'm not going to talk more about
this today, but just to mention our
group here at MIT is working on we have
one diagnostic installed on the Z
machine, which is a compact recoil
spectrometer to look at the neutrons
from the DD reactions and we're working
on developing a magnetic recoil
spectrometer for the Z machine as
well. Okay. And then uh the big one
indirect drive lace diffusion
experiments are being done at the
national ignition facility which I keep
referring to as N in Livermore in
California. And here you can easily see
the comparison to Omega. Uh this is
actually the scale comparison. So very
similar footprint of the facil or sorry
very similar layout of the facilities
but the foot is very different. This is
the direct scale comparison.
Um, at the N facility again we have the
laser bay taking up most of the space
and people typically talk about that
it's the size of three football fields
which for me as a suite doesn't mean a
whole lot but
um and then we have the target chamber
over here which is now 10 mters in
diameter so significantly bigger and if
you look at this you can kind of see
that all the lasers coming in from the
top and bottom instead uniformly from
all sides. uh that's seen easier in this
picture which is the side view of the
target chamber. This blue ball is the
target chamber and obviously the reason
for this is that N is optimized for
indirect drive. So you have that that
cylinder you're trying to get the laser
beams into the bottom. Um this is what
it can look like. It's obviously just a
artist's impression. uh but you have the
cylindrical ho round laser beams are
incidentated in rings and converted to
x-rays and then you can drive the
capsules and we already passed around
the picture of the actual model of so n
delivers about 2 megaj of laser energy
to a centimeter
scaled and it's got 192 laser beams
compared omega
60 okay I have let's see I don't think
we can do sound here right it's it's
just imagine this
very eerie very um interesting sound.
Let me see if we can put it. This is a N
beamline movie just to give you an idea
of how it actually
works. Okay. And it um first he calls
out shot director ready for shot and
then they um they show the seed
poles. Okay. It's a little jumping
today. So yeah, imagine this really um
adventure movie kind of music.
Okay, we have a seed pulse which is
really small originally. It's
pre-amplified. Um here comes the seed
pulse
there master oscillator and then it's
going to get split and amplified in two
stages. A pre-amplification stage and
then a main amplification stage after
it's split into all the 192 beams where
it bounces back and forth four times
until it gets to its final energy.
There are parts
bouncing and then eventually we're
actually need to follow these laser
beams into the target chamber
bouncing. It's um yeah, it's more fun
with the music, but it's also very
irritating.
Okay, so now we're moving with the laser
beams in from the laser bay into the
target bay. This is the wall towards the
target bay.
Yes. So now you can see the
target and again it's 192 beams. They're
all coming in on their individual beam
lines. Uh
and you can see frequency from 1053
nmters to 351. And that's pretty color
change. And this 351 nmter wavelength
laser beams all hit a
horiz. And you can see in the walls of
the hormone and we'll soon get the X-ray
conversion. There we go. Here are the
X-rays and the abilation of the surface
material. Rest of material starts moving
inwards and we get okay. So that's how
an experiment did
work. I think you can look it up on
YouTube if you want with the music too
like
Uh just a couple of uh fun pictures from
the N. So this one is from the
inauguration. Uh and this one is from uh
one of the Star Trek movies. So this is
actually a gamma reaction history
diagnostic uh which somehow turned into
the warp core in the movie. uh my
colleague Hans Herman at Los Alamos was
nationalist the brain behind this
diagnostic and he took his kids to the
movies to see this movie was very proud
to be able to point out his
um okay so you may have all heard or
most of you may have heard that on
December 5th 2022 fusion ignition energy
gain were demonstrated in the laboratory
for the first time uh and this really
was a moment 60 plus years in the
meeting so what happened on this shot
with 3.15 megajoules per output and 3.05
megajles laser input. So that's a target
gain of 1.5 and there's a whole gallery
of videos about this result uh if you go
to the uh
lasers.lm.gov web page uh and give you a
little bit of background to that. So
getting to ignition and energy took more
than a decade of meticulous research at
the NIF and there were many many
challenges along the way. This is uh
kind of illustrating progress in target
gain. So from the first experiments in
uh 2011 with DT and working up towards
this result in December 2022 uh we went
from a target gain of 10 to the minus 3
if you 10 to the minus 4 uh and worked
our way through many many different
permutations until we finally achieved
um target gain on December 4th 2022. So
some of the changes just to give you an
idea I'm not going to go through this in
detail. We started with a plastic
ablator and tried to do really long
laser poles to drive it um to really uh
drive it like really high compression
and it turns out you have a lot of
instabilities you have to worry about
when you do that. So basically all these
implosions were killed by mix. So the
first thing that happened was we figured
out how to mitigate some of that high Z
mix links with a shorter laser pulse
which led to this jump in target gain to
10 to the
minus2. Uh and then um started looking
at using different surface material of
the capsule from these plastic abladers.
We went to high density carbon which is
just another word for diamond basically
switching to mostly diamond the bladers
starting in 2016. uh and then figured
out ways to increase the coupling
efficiency of the lasers using larger
capsules, changing this uh shape of the
or the dimensions of the capsule
relative to the whole arm, changing how
long you let the laser poles drive the
capsule uh versus just letting it coast
at the end. Uh as well as learning how
to do cleaner targets. Um and just to
this I'm going to play a little video
unfortunately in um Google slides. It's
hiding this text, but this is from a 3D
hydra simulation. Uh, and we got
temperature on the left hand side and
density on the right hand side. Uh, and
below is just saying who did it is a
simulation by Dan Clark at Lawrence
Livermore. Uh,
and this is just so this is the capsule
only simulation and this is one that
probably is somewhere in this range. Uh
where you could see I'm gonna play it a
couple times, but you could see already
at the start print uh both at the top
and bottom and the little divot coming
in from the right. So if you see that
again um those are actually engineering
features on the target. So the way you
hold that capsule inside the whole
really thin membrane which we call a
tent. It doesn't just levitate. It has
to be held in place somehow. And that's
what's uh giving rise to these really
bad ruptures at the top and bottom. So
learning how to mitigate that by shaping
the laser pools better using thinner
tents was one big thing. The other thing
is where the fuel gets inserted into the
capsule. That's the fill tube right
here. That became a really bad problem
too in terms of engineering. That would
rupture uh the compression and not allow
us to do uniformly. So we actually went
from I think originally we were working
with something like 20 micron fill tubes
and the igniting implosion is now a two
micron fill tube. So that's thinner than
a human hair that's used to inject the
fuel into the capsule which is kind of
crazy. So we don't think the implosions
look like this anymore but these were
definitely some of the issues that we
had to work through uh to get to where
we're at
today. Thank you. Okay. So, but once
things started taking off, rapid
progress was made. So, the first thing
that happened was in the winter of 2021
where we started having burning plasmas.
Uh, and this was published in nature in
January 2022. There's a picture of the
cover right there. Uh, and what that
means is really that the alpha particle
started doing its job. So, uh, this is
the article from nature, burning plasma
achieved in inertial fusion. And um I'm
quoting Livermore's Alex Sster here.
Alex was also previously of MIT. He uh
he got his PhD from the plasma science
fusion center and he was the a respons
responsible individual for some of these
shots in this campaign. And what he said
was experiments over decades have
produced fusion reactions using large
amounts of external heating to get the
plasma hot. But now for the first time
we have a system where the fusion itself
is providing most of the heating. So
really in this paper it explicitly says
a burning plasma state signifies a
transformational change to the energy
and power balance in the DT plasma
opening up the potential for rapidly
increasing performance and rapidly
increas increasing performance is what
we got. The next thing that happened was
in August 2021
um this is what we as ICF scientists
call ignition. So we got 1.3 megajoules
out for 1.9 megajoules in. It's not
target gain. But this is the first time
we really saw that thermonuclear
instability taken off where it got much
hotter. The burn duration got much
shorter and we started seeing that the
burning plasma was actually bigger
meaning that it's burning on its way out
as it's exploding. So this is what we
call ignition. Uh but it didn't meet the
I think it was the national academy of
sciences that had said ignition is when
uh the output exceeds the laser energy
in. So for a long time we're not allowed
to call this ignition but for us this
was really still really the the biggest
news. Uh and there were around 470 news
reports in August 2021 alone. And uh
Alex Silstster again shared the um
spreadsheet with me so I can show you
exactly. Okay. So after this pretty soon
is where we had this target gain larger
than one shot. Uh and this is one of
those moments on a personal note. This
is one of those moments in time you
really know what you were doing. So this
is is me um during a Swedish Christmas
concert in between rounds of MRS
analysis. Um so MRS I mean I did I think
briefly mentioned it on my bio but this
is that's the detector that we have
installed at the N that measures the
neutron spectra. Um so this is me and
Chris with that spectrometer.
And I think I should shouldn't take too
much time there, but just to give you an
idea, the neutrons uh are produced at
the target chamber center. A fraction of
them will scatter in a um duterrated
plastic conversion foil and forward
scattered recoil dutans will go on to
take a different trajectory through this
magnet depending on their energy. They
end up in a different physical location
on the array. So based on where you find
duturans on these plastic detectors
which are processed after the shot in
the dedicated etchin scan lab, you can
figure out how many nutrients were born
here, how hot the plasma was, and how
tightly it was compressed. So it's
pretty neat. So anyway, I was analyzing
that data. I was um camping with scouts
that weekend. I got the first scans in
the morning, found an office at the camp
where I could do the analysis and went
and did the Christmas concert and got
the next round of of scans and was able
to confirm the results. So yes, we got
target gain and that was a lot of fun.
Since then, uh we've managed to repeat
it seven more times. Uh so there are now
eight of these target gain larger than
one shots on the timeline and the most
recent one was in April, April 6th where
we got 8.6 modules. So you will see that
in absolute numbers this is less than
what Alex was getting at the jet. Uh but
this is a target gain of
4.1. Um okay so to put this in
perspective it is a research facility.
So we're really not anywhere close to
putting energy on the grid. There's a
lot of losses in the system. Uh and we
worked our way through first we showed
scientific break break even in 2014. we
were able to show more energy output and
it was coupled to the fuel. Uh burning
plasma was more energy out than was
coupled to the capsule. Uh then
ignition, we actually had more energy
out uh uh than the X-rays were
delivering. And then target gain is when
we had more energy out than the laser
delivered to the target. And that's
where we're at right now. So, but in
order for the laser to be able to
deliver this much energy to the capsule,
the capacitors are using 400 m. So it's
definitely not facility gain yet and
that's what people in private companies
are starting to work towards now. N is
never going to reach facility gain. N is
aiming for ever higher performance with
the near-term goal of 10 megajoules
which we said 8.6. So it's really not
too far away right now and they also
have an enhanced yield capability which
is pushing up towards 30 or 60
megajoules. It's never going to get to
400 megles. So what's needed there
architecture changes many different
things.
uh and the other thing uh is we need to
repeat this often. So there are many
steps remaining to make inertial fusion
a reality and this is kind this is from
a a report that I think is about to come
out from measurement innovations basic
research needs workshop just to give you
a sense we have shot rate hertz on the
x- axis and the performance in terms of
gain on the y- axis and it's just
illustrating so n at at the time I made
this plot just over a year ago was at a
gain of slight two uh and omega is at
you know, well less than one gain uh but
can repeat more often at 12 shots per
day there. Um then we also have a large
number of smaller lasers around the US
that are actually already capable of
operating at rep rate but don't have any
gain at all. They're not intended to do
implosions. So what where we need to get
in order to have an inertial fusion
energy plant is up here where we have a
gain of about 100 and a rep rate of
about 10 hertz. So there's quite a bit
of research remaining to do. Uh one
thing though the N is built on 90s
architecture. So we think that we could
already now get to uh um 10% laser
efficiency compared to that 400 megles
to two megales. That's that's really
bad. That's not what we think we could
do these days. Uh and there's been an
explosion number of private companies
working on this. We'll get back to it
right at the end. Uh okay. Yeah, I don't
think we really need to talk to this.
The plant design will look similar to
any other power plant. This is just for
the the laser driver and the ICF type
chamber, but the rest of this part can
be the same for vision as well.
So, Alex, you want to come back up for
this
last win? We'll see. I I What's What's
the next slide? That'll probably tell
us. No, I mean, we
uh do you want to talk? Yeah, sure. So
you know you know it's clear that both
hocamax and magnetic confinement fusion
and and sort of lasers in terms of
inertial com confinement fusion are are
leading the path you know the leading
candidates to to produce net fusion
energy and electricity. I mean we've
seen net fusion energy already with
lasers. Uh this is a pretty common plot
which most people have seen before
plotting um various metrics but really
what you want to know is you want to be
in the upper right hand corner and I've
highlighted here some of the experiments
that Marie and I have worked on um which
are already up there and hopefully as
Spark comes online we'll we'll continue
to push there and as these new companies
build more facilities we'll get up into
that right hand corner. Just to briefly
say that um you saw how the sort of
pathway for inertial confinement in
terms of um their idea for a fusion
power plant and Commonwealth Fusion
Systems which spun out of MIT has taken
on sort of the path that was developed
here uh to go this compact high field
route. Uh so after spark creating
something that is is bigger um but
similar size to the jet took Mac hoping
to to create a power that's on the order
of hundreds of megawatts of electricity
and do you want to see oh yeah okay so
the recent results um and both magnetic
and inertia confinement fusion have
generated a lot of excitement and also a
jump in private fusion companies this
slide specifically is about the ICF
schemes so uh There was inertial fusion
energy basic research needs workshop
that happened shortly after the ignition
result and there's also been um a new
initiative which we call if star
inertial fusion energy science and
technology accelerated research with
three different hubs that form a kind of
national consortium to push these
efforts. uh MIT is part of the star fire
hub which is led by uh Lawrence
Livermore and then yeah this is uh I
think our our final slide right? Yeah,
this is just to say that you know uh
there are a lot of private companies
now. Uh I went to the fusion industry
association which um has all of these
members. So I just copied everything
from their web page here. There probably
more fusion companies that might not
even be on here. Uh I put in these uh
sort of magenta boxes uh companies that
either MIT is working with or people
from MIT have gone on to be founders or
work closely in the uh early startup
phases. So, it's really exciting to see
um these companies spin out and and of
course continue to work with MIT as well
and and hopefully at least one of them
will succeed. So, okay, the race of
fusion energy, who will win? Well, we
all win, right? Uh doesn't matter so
much who who wins at the end of the day
except you know their shareholders when
they I but uh but you know this will be
a huge uh success for humanity. Uh with
that, we're happy to take some
questions. Thank you for attending. Um
and uh
[Applause]
yeah, if I can, I think it would be best
to take some questions maybe from folks
who are sort of new to Fusion. Um all
the other PSFC folks, you know, we can
obviously talk to most times. Uh so, uh
anybody have a burning question?
Yeah, first um which instabilities in
magnetic confinement are currently kind
of subjects of focus? I know about the
uh catarash uh record last year about 22
minutes. What feels like a long time,
right? What time do we need to get to
and what challenges do we have to get to
that point? Yeah, that's a good
question. So I think yeah you're
referring to these uh really long
plasmas like existing for for many
minutes and and it's true that in the
future we'll want to get to creating
plasma pulses in magnetic confinement
fusion that are on the order of say 20
minutes or so. There there is some push
to do fully steady state but in magnetic
confinement fusion you have to drive
well for tokamax you have to drive
current in your plasma and so to
continuously drive current in the plasma
um well there are different techniques
for doing that. If you can pulse your
plasma so keep it on for 20 minutes and
let it come back down which is what they
were doing um in in France and also in
in China um you know that might be a
little more viable. Um but there are
methods to do continuous current drive.
It's some of that's being explored.
People here at MIT work out in the D3D
tokamac in San Diego and so um and it
was also installed on CMOD. So um so
there are a few ways to do this
and not not super super long times but
right uh 20 minutes still is a long time
and then there are a lot of
instabilities. Most of them arise
because of the current that we actually
have to put in to a tokamac. So, there
are other types of magnetic fusion
devices called stellarators. We didn't
even touch here. You don't you're not
supplying current to them. Um, and
you're creating these really twisted
magnetic field coils to create the
magnetic geometry that you need to
confine all your plasma. Um, and that is
a way to have sort
of steady state plasma that could kind
of exist for as long as your other, you
know, you know, heating or cooling
parameters would need. Um, I hope that
sort of answered your question. Yeah.
Yeah. No, it answers it well. I might
ask some more detailed questions later.
Sure. Yeah, maybe we see. Are there any
other questions and we can come to you?
There is one. So, you're talking about
20 minutes for that for like an Aquator
type of reactor. But yours, I can't even
visualize in my head how that would go
from this tiny little itty bitty thing
into some sort of a mass production
where you would actually producing
energy. There have to be like billions
of those things firing off all the time.
Right. That's exactly right. Kind of
hurts. It's
I mean and there are experiments on yeah
make well making simpler targets uh
working on how to inject them. Uh so
yeah those efforts have started
guess that would be it's more like a
almost like a car engine of like lots of
explosions. So so some yeah so some of
the other things actually uh get easier.
you need less tridium than you would for
a magnetic confinement facility. It's
easier to protect the target chamber.
But we definitely have to solve those
problems. So yeah, so one of the things
that people are working on is um wedded
foam targets where you can basically you
have a foam matrix 3D printed foam
matrix that you can just soak in
liquidity instead of the ice layers that
are used in current targets. So that
would be a much cheaper path and and we
do have one of our grad students is
working on looking at asymmetries in
wooded forms for example.
Question online we could get to or I
guess there are two but the first one um
how can high performance computing and
simulations help in ICF and MCF. I mean
it's incredibly incredibly helpful and I
think as you are going toward um you
know projecting to fusion power plants
in the next five 10 years uh they need a
lot of simulations to back them up
because your investors are wanting to
invest a lot of money into these types
of things. Um but you know on the other
side of that like experiments are really
at the end of the day are going to show
you if it works or not. So um here at
MIT there's a huge push on on both on
both sides and people running in some of
the biggest super supercomputers in the
world. Anything you want? Yeah, I mean
the the N is an excellent example of
like kind of like that back and forth
between experiments and simulations. I
showed the the chart of how the gain has
uh improved over more than a decade. uh
at the outset the simulation people
thought that we were immediately going
to ignite actually dudded the fuel
adding hydrogen into it because if you
had pure DT it would just ignite and we
get too many neutrons that we couldn't
count uh but of course it turns out that
there are more experimental problems
than you think about uh so uh throughout
the years the experiments have come back
to simulations but then you can run a
lot more simulations you can run
experiments so the simulations have also
guided what the next experiment ments
would be and there's a continuous back
and forth. Maybe last thing I'd just say
that um machine learning is a is a huge
thing that people are pursuing as well
to try to make models more efficient or
I mean some things are often hard to
explain as well and so learning can take
in a lot of
data discover some
physics other questions there's there's
another online and we can take two but
any in the room
here I'll take this other one online
real quick uh what recommend
commendations do you have for
undergraduates in engineering physics to
get into fusion? What would you
recommend pursuing a masters or
prioritize finding experience after
graduation? Yeah, these are great
questions. I could take an initial stab
at it. Um there are a lot of uh programs
for internships and things I would
suggest undergraduates look into.
There's a program called u suli suli
which allows you to work at a national
lab in the US and and um kind of get
into fusion and that's a lot of students
here graduate students and myself came
through that path um there also you know
MIT has open courses you can start to
learn from fusion online and now I would
say in the past it you kind of you had
to sort of go into grad school to get
into fusion but that's no longer true
with all these private companies I still
think, you know, grad school's good. Uh
I mean, but but maybe um masters
infusion or um or or even having um some
experience at a private company can help
some people do a few years of work and
then come back. So, uh look around at
the different companies. They also have
internship programs as well. Um and as
to the national labs like Lauren Silver,
summer internships. Yeah, I don't have
much to add. I think you're actually
perfect.
Any other questions? Yeah. Um on
inertial confinement, what's the primary
limitation on um on rate of fire? So So
I mean at the N the primary limit is the
architecture of the laser. So like the
you need to have the like the glass
amplifiers cooled down. Um but in in the
future I mean it depends on the laser
architecture.
So the laser architecture itself rather
than um injecting the pellet or I mean
we have to figure out how to inject the
pellet too but yeah but that doesn't
limit the the rate at this point.
Any final questions?
I'm sure Maria and I can stick around
for a few minutes, but maybe we should
call this meeting to a close. So thank
you all for coming. Enjoy some extra
pizza.
[Applause]