good morning everyone uh I'm calling in
from the West Coast this week so still
morning for me even though on the East
Coast we're getting in the afternoon uh
I'm Sam wso Director of Business
Development at Alam energy we are new
battery cell chemistry uh battery cell
manufacturer uh really with the key
differentiating factors of being
non-flammable uh but yet still high
performance and cost competitive with
incumbent lithium ion
technology just real quick I want to
show you some of our leadership so we're
by mes chatter he's a Serial
entrepreneur has built and exited
companies in the Telecom industry Krypto
Varanasi is our MIT connection from the
uh Department of mechanical engineering
and then we also have representatives
from RPI Harvard uh and Industry
Executives like Mark little from
GE so in the energy storage uh Market
the situations is that you know demand
is increasing across all sectors um and
the fact of the matter is energy storage
is never going to become a primary uh
Renewables are never going to become a
primary source of power until we have
energy storage paired along them so when
the sun's not shining when the wind's
not blowing you have to have a bank of
energy that you can draw on uh so that
we're not turning to fossil fuels um
lithium ion is the incumbent technology
it's it's great uh it has high energy
density but the drawback is that it
really doesn't have a suitable safety
profile for all segments um and what we
also see in the market is that there's
demand for more uh longer durations
across uh different
markets I'm sure you've also seen in the
media lots of different uh lithium ion
fires I like I said I'm in La this week
I'm looking out the window at a wildfire
across the way and just down the the
coast there is another lithium ion fire
in San Diego which is still burning and
you know we also have fires with with um
fossil fuels every day which we we deal
with and I'm not saying I'm not waving
the red flag stop everything lithium ion
is is a challenge but the fact of the
matter is that we have to be really
careful about where we're citing energy
storage systems uh in urban or Suburban
centers because you can have really you
you can have problems uh even uh
recently the fire department in New York
has spent over a million dollars
launching a public education campaign
about the dangers of lithium ion
technology
so that's where we come in uh we are a
new chemistry that doesn't exist on the
market today uh and importantly we are
cost competitive with lithium ion even
with recent uh price drops um from
overseas within the subset of
non-lithium energy storage Technologies
we have the highest performance across
round trip efficiency and uh energy
density and the the really key factor is
here is that we're inherently
non-flammable and what I mean by that is
that our materials cannot burn some
other aspects we don't release any toxic
gases uh and that our materials are
readily available from us free trade
Partners our first product will be Elum
green uh this is targeted towards a
stationary grid storage Market uh it'll
have an energy density of 3.4 megawatt
hour in a standard 40 foot container yes
that is less than lithium ion uh but
it's higher than all other lithium ion
Alternatives that'll be available q1 of
2026 of course we're always looking
ahead to Future markets too for marine
and
just a few other things to highlight
about that first product Alum green so
uh I said safe stable chemistry we're
not using lithium we're not using Cobalt
we're not using nickel all of our
materials are readily available um and
again the key the key factor being we're
nonflammable and
non-toxic our battery form factor looks
like a lithium ion cell is built like a
lithium ion cell so as we scale we can
use all that existing lithium ion
infrastructure just without the
considerations for dry rooms fire locks
uh worrying about uh dangerous solvents
everything that we do is processed in in
water um and then looking at the the
battery energy storage system itself uh
cost competitive high performance there
are some specs the 1.7 megawatt hour
there is in a 20 foot container format
uh footprint with 92% DC roundt trip
efficiency you can also configure the
system for short duration medium
duration long duration uh so as you see
demand for intraday and Inay storage uh
are our batteries are capable of
that over the past few years we're we've
been focused on uh prototyping and and
scaling up our sampling so we have a
line a sampling line coming on coming on
end of this year and then in 2025 we'll
be scaling our commercial
production the ask for you all today is
we're we're seeking Partners so we're
working towards our first system pilots
in the field both grid scale as well as
residential so we need uh where the
battery cell manufact but we need
partners for integration for project
developers uh oems then we also need
off-takers so whether it's utility data
center uh heavy industry that want to
Pilot a novel battery chemistry and
Technology uh please reach out my email
there is there at the bottom um reach
out today we have a couple colleagues at
energy storage conference this week in
La so uh maybe there's opportunity to
set up a meeting today thank you very
much thank you
Sam um um as questions come in let me
ask you you mentioned pilot field tests
what kind of size are we talking about
so if we're talking utility scale that
would probably be a one container to
start but with plans to to scale out to
multi megawatt hour but also for the
residential scale think like a a Tesla
power wall size unit so um 10 kilowatt
hours something to power a
home okay again a reminder to POS your
questions to the Q&A chat uh tab at the
bottom of your screen um Tom also um
could you tell us more about the use
cases for utilities data centers data
centers is also a key word coming up um
and heavy industry for example yeah so
everyone needs energy um and if you're
uh if you're paying high prices during
the day and Peak loads it would be great
to have a bank of energy there that you
can draw on when prices are high so that
you're not pay that expensive expensive
cost or you're not causing the grid to
turn on fossil fuel um utilities like
peer plants which are high power but um
High
emissions and can you talk a little more
about what the chemistry is um sure so
it's still proprietary but what I can
say is that our electrodes are mixed
metal oxides and then our electrolyte is
uh is water-based so water with salt
compare that to lithium ion where you
have um A flammable
liquid okay thanks Sam more questions
coming in so we'll put them in the chat