Al I want to welcome everybody my name
is Terrell Williams and I serve as the
associate director for diversity equity
and inclusion and the office of
admissions I'm really excited about
tonight's opportunity to host this panel
um with our Dy Dynamic group of sonies
who will introduce themselves shortly
and I want to be able to give us some
time to uh introduce our moderator for
the evening um Sebastian Sebastian will
share a brief introduction about himself
and introduce our panelist for the
evening Sebastian the floor is yours uh
hi everyone uh my name is
Sebastian um I'm really excited for this
panel and to share with you guys a
little more about Sloan um I'm
co-president of the currently the
Hispanic Business Club prior to Sloan I
was mostly working in education working
for a private Equity Fund and I spent
this past summer at uh the corporate
strategy intern at an education company
so a company that does um education
curriculum um providing so really
excited about having everyone here and
I'm happy to kind of start intros um if
that's cool with everyone else so um
Jessica if you can get us started
awesome um Jessica alone I did my MBA in
2021 also I I guess I did The Bu degre
programs so
graduated my with my in 2021 and then
spent an additional year in
2022 um so I did mine separate versus
together happy to talk about that
there's a question on that um um
originally from Idaho um daughter of
Farm Workers my parents are from caloa
Mexico and um I worked in finance before
coming to MIT and Goldman Saxon City
group and then wanted to trib it into
Venture so decided to get my NBA um at
MIT technology and and finance skill set
and entation skill set and then um after
MIT I decided to
to be a leadership coach and uh kind of
carve my own path depending on like what
I wanted to do so became a leadership
coach uh did a fellowship at Harvard on
leadership and I'm currently the CEO and
founder of um launch Etc which is a
company that's creating a digital
platform that allows Brands and
companies to sell in the United States
better using artificial intelligence and
data to drive sales and product Market
channels um and I also do side House of
Consulting I I support people and
connect people and um finding Capital uh
I know it's it's it's a lot but I think
that uh I I I like to be a jack of all
trades and and see how I can and be
helpful in in many ways happy to answer
any questions and excited for y all to
be here um favier you can go next yeah
thank you SAS
and happy to be here hi everyone my name
is Javier a SL fellow uh from the NBA
program I graduated in 2022 it's two
years ago it seems like it was
yesterday uh I chose the the um longf
NBA program because I think it's the
best mid career program that there is in
in the world I can discuss that further
and later um before MIT I just had to my
previous experience was in capital
markets and then I mov and created the
largest public private Equity Fund in
Colombia for managing State own
Enterprises there the portfolio of State
Enterprises um I did my my NBA in 2020
2021 to 2022 and then I pivot into
Consulting I became the director for the
energy practice of FDI Consulting is a
large consulting firm uh here in the US
and worldwide uh I became the director
of the energy practice for Latin America
so pretty much during the past two years
I've been uh working with uh companies
across Latin America providing business
strategy and restructuring Services
pretty much and now probably I'm I'm
transitioning to to a new role but so
far I'm I'm at FDI and happy to discuss
U later later with all of you thank you
Sebastian hi everyone uh my name is
Nardo I'm originally from Brazil uh I
was a MERS in finance uh graduated in
2022 prior to slow I worked at uh fenny
may I was a credit valuation and uh
Financial modeling and data analy data
analytics specialist um so I worked with
Mortage back security pricing npl and
RPL sales that kind of thing
um joined Sloan because of how
passionate I was about Finance I think
Sloan's the birth place in mod Finance
um can talk a lot in depth later about
that but um it really was the experience
that I was hoping for and after leaving
loan I decided to join McKenzie at the
strategy and corporate finance practice
so I work
primarily with um Corporate Finance
Endeavors and the financial institutions
group mostly with banks around
recapitalization high level strategy
Transformations um I focus specifically
on commercial Banking and the small
business banking so try to do a little
bit of those two but happy to chat more
about my work later on hi everyone my
name is EST Stella um I graduated from
the master of business analytics program
last year uh as you saw on the slide
previously of early career I had two
years of work experience as a data
analyst at Dix sporting goods and I
wanted to Pivot into a more technical
role in data science um and now I'm
currently a data scientist at the
Library of Congress um and I chose the
mban program because I liked how they
put an emphasis on real world
applications and not just technical
skills and putting it into practice in
businesses so um yeah happy to talk more
about my experience uh questions
arise hey good evening everyone uh my
name is Scott Hungerford uh I graduated
from the leaders glob operations program
in
2023 uh before I went to MIT uh I
actually was an engineering associate
for the city of Los Angeles for about
six years uh developing large capital
projects uh large water projects and
power projects uh so I actually really
enjoyed that work and I probably would
still be there uh if I didn't go to MIT
and it at MIT is such an amazing
experience I love my my time there I
love all the the friends I made and the
times and experiences I had um after MIT
I joined Verizon and their energy
sustainability team essentially
decarbonizing our operation so reducing
our electricity uh bills so saving costs
on the operation side and also reducing
the emissions associated with the energy
that powers our data centers our
technical buildings and our admin
buildings um so I looked at different
opportunities during MIT and always came
back to energy uh and sustainability so
I wanted to do that right after school
and Verizon gave me that opportunity
happy to talk about the lgo program life
after Sloan and uh my decision to go to
SL during the panel thanks thanks
everyone it's it's really cool to be in
this room it's not it's not super um
common that you have so many people from
different backgrounds like this so
appreciate y'all all being here um I
guess like the first question for y'all
is to really understand kind of in your
experience from being at slow and how
did you guys feel that MIT fostered an
inclusive environment for Hispanic
students like what were the ways that
latinx students at Sloan like came
together and that you felt that and I'm
happy to kind of hear this from everyone
especially knowing the fact that we're
all kind of in different programs happy
to get get it kicked off uh my
experience was around a lot of the the
groups that they created in campus it
there's really a wide range of groups
that you can participate in but both the
Hispanic group and the Brazilian Club as
well um are extremely active and people
get together constantly people help each
other out and even though we are all
different groups I think every single
one of us has probably been in similar
if not the same classes uh at some point
in time at least a few of them so it's
also helped with study groups and so on
um so yeah that's my experience mostly
through the groups and the relationships
we start building there yeah know I I uh
Echo everything you said I think uh the
events a lot of the underrepresented
minority groups hosted I thought was a
really great way to just meet folks kind
of from similar backgrounds and actually
a lot of different backgrounds as well
um and just get together and and kind of
just get to know each other and
understand where perspectives come from
and just you know just get a create a
sense of community at Sloan um so I
really appreciated that and I always try
to attend all the events that Hispanic
Business Club black Student Association
all the other urm communities uh were
hosting and I always had an amazing time
there I'll jump in I always try to keep
it real and to be real there isn't a lot
of L there and there's less now with
this new lot that um was reversed as you
seen the the Articles and everything so
I think that is something that we could
do better um I came in a at a time where
it was just like Co and I have I came
and then Co happen so definitely I think
that um something that I did was just
like you need to push to make things
better and I took it upon myself to
really organize a lot of events and
everything because I want to that
community and wherever I go I go and
create that community so the Hispanic
Business Club uh for example I was a
president of that I also was very
involved with the black Student
Association and the ab ABC which is
African student uh Business Club um
which led me to start my own nonprofit
which is latinx MBA so I'm the founder
of latinx NBA which I founded with
another a couple of other students
across different Business Schools but it
was again to create Community among
among mbas because there's so few of us
and at least in the United States we are
now up to like $3.6 trillion Which is
higher than the GDP of France yet we're
not being represented in a lot of these
programs not only M everyone is
struggling with this but also it's just
like we're not represented in the
brogans we're also not represented in
Corporate America we're not represented
as we get 3% eventure back funding 3% of
our business make it to $1 million so
you have to go and create this space
sometimes and go build it and I think
MIT gives you the right tools and
infrastructure and the resources to go
do that and I push you guys to do more
of that versus expecting that there will
be something that will be there created
there will be but also take some
ownership and um be able to show a
little bit more
activism yeah building on what uh
Jessica has just mentioned I mean
sometimes you I think you have your
tools available and then you need to
actually like know how to use them it's
not that it's already given it's not
that okay you have some clubs you have
some like organization already
established but it's not like the way
where you can actually get like all the
all the support that sometimes you you
need and mainly as as a as a Latin or
spanic student I'm just going to tell
you a story about my my my partner I
just met her at MIT when we were
studying same program and uh she's from
Spain but we organize as Latinos just to
have someone who represented us uh at
the Senate you know there is a senate of
students and there are pretty much like
four or five people who are representing
uh so we try like you know try to be
more organized we had the the
possibility of have someone who were
like there at the same like speaking
from on our behalf uh so we just made it
happen we just like organize it and take
advantage or took advantage of all these
tools that we we had available just to
have like a more direct discussion with
uh the the faculty and and and and the
management and at that time also we were
we were studying during covid so those
times were were harsh I'm not going to
go into it but um you know it gives you
a sense of you you have you have someone
there and can can can make that your
voice is is heard when when it's
necessary
um thanks everyone it's it's it's it's
helpful it's helpful to kind of hear
what you guys really took advantage of
um while you're here and as now
president of the fanic club and from
from Jessica's lineage um it's been it's
been really cool to like also kind of
take this on um to try to really build
this community at slone but agree with
Jessica that often times it it justes
fall on you to kind of think about that
and kind of a little bit of of what that
looks like I guess like what advice
would y'all give um for prospective
students like both like some I bet a
bunch of people here are applying to
school or have like submitted their
applications or kind of all different
places but when people who are kind of
on the outside looking in like what
advice would you give them as they're
applying to
school just apply let them tell you no
oftentimes we we say oh I'm not gonna
you know my test goore my essay like
make excuses like just do it and like
that's really what stopping you and when
I got to MIT I was just like it it
wasn't I mean the challenging part is
getting to MIT and like applying to
these programs and getting in and then
it's just like okay everything is kind
of downhill from there um but I would
say this apply let them tell you know
even if you're scared even if you don't
think you'll get in like let them tell
you you really never know I I Echo what
Jessica said I had a already accepted
and paid for my my like my reservation
fee at another school like my backup
school because I did not think I was
going to get in so the the feeling of
getting that phone call was incredible
and I think I Echo like Jessica's
feeling nothing happens if you don't
apply if you don't try so just go for
it especially my women we need more and
y'all need need
I think uh just coming from like I guess
an LGL perspective uh I know some people
get intimidated by like the the MIT
Engineering portion of it and uh I'd say
kind of echo everyone else said you know
you don't know until you you try and
apply um MIT is is such an amazing
campus and I think another
recommendation I would have is when
you're looking at Business Schools like
also look at the the campus and the
school attached to the business school
like when you go to slow you go to MIT
and MIT is just like another level of
experience and academics and there's so
many great things going on outside of
Sloan that you can experience just
because you you are an MIT student when
you come to Sloan um so that's just kind
of one my recommendation when you're
looking at Business Schools look at the
business school yes but also look at the
campus the community everything else
that the campus and and the school as a
as a whole can provide to
you going off of that same sentiment um
I did a very technical program
and I would advise don't let the idea of
it's too hard stop you uh cuz the people
who get in and succeed thought it was
hard so um and I know from the mbam
program and MIT more generally we have
each other's backs and we'll help each
other get through the material um so MIT
is hard but that doesn't mean that you
can't do
it yeah you already got the the no so
just go and look for the
yes um yeah I definitely Echo a lot of
the the sentiment that people said I
feel like um from my perspective it was
often um you kind of like play the game
like oh this person got into this school
and had this Gat and had this and that
and like it's all kind of a crapshoot
like a lot of it kind of goes down to
like who you are as a person and it's
just really important to like know that
I keep the back of your head when you're
kind of applying there is there is no
magic formula or game that you can
gamify throughout the entire process
um uh I guess like one question for
everyone I've seen a couple of the Q&A
also asked this question is like um how
have y'all seen what has been your
experience on how the LX community at
Sloan has able to like engage or empower
the local LX community in the Boston
area um what have y'all's experien has
been been that way maybe not in the
Boston area just but at Large
mine is going to be very targeted um and
much like Jessica I'll say honestly I I
don't know um about like Ventures from P
from clubs or panels that necessarily
were trying to do that but I will share
my experience which was um at Sloan we
got to do a class called Pro seminar in
corporate finance in which it's
sponsored by um by companies and and one
of the companies it was McKenzie and a
lot of the reason I decided to go there
was because of this I met one of the
partners in the Boston office who was um
you know former MBA she's his um from
Spain her brother was in in um the NBA I
believe as well and her kids lived in
the area and through her and like her
network they invested heavily into the
development of B bilingual speaking
schools in the Boston area um so I think
it's something that derived from MIT
it's something that or derived from from
the network and from the school I think
it's something that is really important
for uh the local community but I'll say
it was in my experience at least much
like Jessica said it's more about the
individual um Endeavors and like
activism that people had over
necessarily something that I saw from a
club
I've been very involved in I don't know
all the community since I was in high
school um I think that I mean I started
a national nonprofit with nmba we also
started a scholarship at MIT Sloan that
helps people while they are applying to
school so using IV advisors which is
also latinx NBA scholarship uh in a way
but used his IV advisers as like the
consultant but also Within
the the club like um advisers and
mentors to help you through the
application process and it really came
from the fact that it's expensive to
apply to these schools from application
fees test prep and overall you know
although people say don't get a
consultant everyone else is getting
consultant so then it's just like ah you
feel like you need one too and I'm not
saying you need one but it's just
helpful and don't wouldn't you want to
to make sure your application was at the
best places possible so we started a
scholarship for that both at Hispanic
Business Club and also at latinx
MBA and um also within the Boston
Community I would help small businesses
in Lawrence which is largely Dominican
uh Community there uh I helped like a
business owner try to think about a
private Equity um a real estate fund and
how to raise that and this is through a
program that I cross-registered to HBS
which was like uh scaling minority
businesses and then from there um was uh
I actually got like 30 under 30 Boston I
was involved in uh just going to to
speak to like high schools uh around the
area and motivating them to you know go
to school uh so I think that there's a
lot of things that you can do it just
depends on your bandwidth like you also
don't have can't forget that you're
there for school you're there to try to
like um you know get a degree try to
take as as much as possible and it also
it often can be taxing for um students
of color or students that are are trying
to like support these communities so I
would say like do as much as you can and
that is
also yours like that you enjoy like for
me it gives me joy and it pushes me to
work harder and it pushes me uh to just
be in the path that I am but I know that
not not it doesn't do that for everyone
thank thanks y'all for for sharing um
and I I mean I think that like outside
of that there's a lot of
like you like a lot of it you kind of
have to find it yourself and kind of
like do the things that um you have
energy for right um it's really
important as we like kind of look into
like what can you get involved in how
can you look at this um kind of Shifting
track and also kind of incorporating
some of the questions from the audience
to kind of what just y'all's MBA Sloan
experience was like um outside of of
being kind of in the Hispanic um
ecosystem that MIT has created did um
would love to hear um from y'all um how
would you guys describe that like MIT
has like really influenced change kind
of your direction um kind of who you
what you thought you were going to do
before and after slow and like while you
were at school like how was MIT really
like instrumental in doing that love to
hear that experience from
people okay I think first of all and the
the the first advice that I that I gave
to people when they add me okay what
what should I do when when I need when I
when I'm preparing to go to to to to
this loan like you need to have a plan
it doesn't matter if you need to change
the plan thousand times but just like be
focused because you're going to lose
yourself if you if you don't really know
what you want to get from from your
experience as L because I mean actually
you can do whatever whatever you want to
do you can be more involved in
Innovation you can be more involved in
AI which is more popular now or Finance
or Tech or um I mean you name it so the
thing like just be be open just to um
adjust the plan that you have but have
have at least one and just focus in two
things and if you need to change one of
those things that you you want to do
it's fine but don't don't try you know
like to do uh anything and try to be
Expos as as that many things that uh you
can I think you can do it but at some
point you are going to miss something so
just I mean like building on on on on on
my experience I think that I would like
to I like to I meanly recommend you just
have a plan let's just focus on what you
want to get from from your experience at
this loan be open to adjust the plan but
always be have something uh present that
is what I what I what I want to get from
from from from from this don't don't let
that just classes and clubs and events
just happen just be be mindful that your
time there is is limited and for some
reason the the the the clocks start like
taking a little bit faster when you uh
studying and doing your your program
there know I actually I really like what
Javier just mentioned um I think coming
on the plan is is critical like have an
understanding of what your time at Sloan
can offer you and what how how could it
advance in your career and professional
life and personal life um but also be
ready to Pivot extremely hard on certain
things because I know folks who knew
exactly what they were going to do after
Sloan and they did not do that they
found something that excited them even
more because they talked to another slon
or they met a a industry professional
during a coffee chat or something and
they pivoted 180 degrees and they went
somewhere else um but also understanding
what Javier just mentioned like your SL
your time at slown two years maybe less
if you do a different program um it's a
very important part of your professional
development is to understand like what
you want to do um how you or who who
where you want to work like what
industry you want to be in and the best
way to kind of solve that and answer
those questions is just to meet folks uh
take as much time as you can to engage
with different communi ities talk to
professionals alumni and different
Industries and just make the most out of
the MIT student name that you have
because the moment you reach out to
someone and say hey I'm an MIT student
I'm a Sloan student there's a high
likelihood you're going to get a
response take advantage of that and
learn as much as you can those two years
and figure out what you want to do after
but be ready to to make a hard pivot
because you're going to learn so much at
at MIT and Sloan that you're going to be
interested in a lot of different things
um I just I mean even today I don't know
you do whatever you want to do with your
time there like even right now there you
know people are like oh you should look
for a full-time job like that's at least
for me one of the worst advice you can
give an entrepreneur so it's just like
you know it's just you go get you know
the degree I think another thing is like
the name does carry uh some brand so
it's just like people I'm like I'm in
Tijuana looking for clients here like
manufacturing clients I don't know
anything about it but I'll figure it out
because have contacts like Scott who did
the lgo program I'll reach out to you
and be like hey who do I connect how do
I know how to figure this out it's about
figuring it out and like you figured
everything else in your life out you can
also figure this out I was very much
focused well in school in the transition
between uh just like institutional um
banking to like now more of a venture
capital route so I had exposure to that
I realized that and I I was always
hustling because um I come from a Lo
family I couldn't really um afford a lot
of these trips that my classmates did so
like I was always I always had a
full-time job not full-time but like a
side household like part-time job and um
so you know that exposed me to the world
Adventure which uh I realized I didn't
necessarily want to go into um and I
wanted to build my company instead
because as I was helping people raise
money I saw that a lot of people um that
I was raising money from didn't make it
up in corporate and this is my own view
right Jessica you it's like and I wanted
to be in in the other camps and other
campus entrepreneurship and I was like
you know what I'm G regret not doing
this now so let me go see what could
happen and um if it works out great if
not like at least I didn't live with
regret so it's just you know I would
have loved to be very focused and like
had the startup that I had now and have
worked on it when I was uh in school but
I didn't what I knew was like I wanted
to be in VC I was able to make the
transition now I'm I'm more on the
entrepreneurship side uh and leveraging
still some of those resources and like
some of the network and everything to
just make it happen amazing um I know we
talked kind of a bit about um like the
things around so recruiting career
Pathways Etc like love to kind of like
focus it a little more like in the
classroom like we love to hear from from
Young all kind of what was y'all's
favorite class at slim like your most
impactful class the one that you're kind
of like taking with you were thinking
about um little to he what y'all
think I think uh sorry Jessica you want
to go
ahead yeah you can go all right I think
for me and this is going to be a bailout
but I have three for different reasons
So Pro seminar uh for me was a lot of
the reason that I ended up in Consulting
and where I am where I am um it was my
first taste at you know the work that I
do now and like why I decided a career
that I did decide on so I'd say that for
for that reason um my second favorite
class was p and
VC and because it was given by anet
skolar she like for a variety of reasons
for my prior career she's really the
main reason why I came to Sloan um she
was someone I looked up to someone that
I read articles like academic articles
uh from and all of that um so I was
really excited to get into her class and
something I pursue it actively and I
think the third one was Advanced uh
Corporate Finance as you guys can tell
like I'm really into it um and that one
was just some one that surprised me and
how you know the depth that we went I
thought these were things that I would
have seen before
um and in a way it is like if you go to
business school the general concepts are
always the same but the level of depth
and Nuance that this class went was a
lot deeper than I thought it would be um
so it was one that I really really
enjoyed and I built great relationship
with the professors as well uh you know
or friends up to this day I help with
courses and that kind of thing because I
just love going back to Sloan as much as
I can so those three um mine was um
corporate boards and just like the
amount of exposure to to people um and
the the people that come and speak about
kind of like their path to boards but
also like I think it was also sea site
so like and to the Sea suite and that's
something that's very interesting to me
and um I loved kind of apprach that I
wish it was a person but I we were on
Zoom uh but I think that that's an
amazing thought that everyone should
take advantage of the one that I have
nightmares about is DMD um I think it's
really helpful and everything that data
management decision but you know I don't
think it was my favorite class and I
don't know but I'm glad I took it but I
don't know I would say my favorite class
was Hands-On deep learning um it was in
Sloan and it took some of the Cutting
Edge Technologies like Ai and large
language models and the professor um
Professor ramach Krishnan was the one I
took it with uh took the material and
explained expained it in a way that was
accessible to not only mban students but
to mba's students and people all over
Sloan um and it was a very enjoyable
class I think a lot of people would also
agree who took it um would say that it
was a really great
class uh I I really liked uh the class
called Energy Ventures uh it's
essentially like developing a startup in
the energy sustainability world and you
work work with the team and uh there's a
handful of students that already come in
the class with with ideas because
they're like phds or Advanced degree
students at MIT and Harvard um and so
they come up with a really cool idea and
and then you join their team to help
with their business development um help
with their Market attack Pro like uh
program and like just understand how to
develop a business plan and Pitch to to
venture capitalist and I thought that
was super cool because I came from
utility and that world was just
different than what I ever came from so
I thought that was interesting and I
like intro to operations um just because
it's it kind of showed you how companies
work like operations is the heart of
like how a company operates and I
thought that was really interesting to
kind of get involved in different
Industries like
manufacturing um you know other industry
that I didn't come I didn't have a
background in and just understand how
they actually do the day-to-day
activities um and I thought was really
cool and I think Sean Williams was was
an amazing Professor uh for inops
well for me mean my favorite class was
economics for strategic decisions with
Bob Pik Robert Pik I think this guy
needs to be awarded with a Nobel priz at
some point in the next years think is
that is one of the best strategy courses
in in
in in his loan and um that that was the
I think the main reason was because when
I was doing my undergrad like 20 years
ago most of the microeconomics books
were written by Bob pinik so you know it
was the dream that when you go to MIT
you actually you are meeting those guys
to I mean at some point you thought that
they were just like living just in a
dream and just just realize that they're
like I mean normal people but super
super smart so Bob p is one of the I
mean one of the best professors uh that
I had opportunity to to to to meet when
I was at his loan and also that class
was at Harbor you know that you can you
have the opportunity to take some cses
at harbard I was very focused on
strategy so I I Tred to like take as
much most strategy courses in at the m
harb and harbard as I could I took this
one called
um executing a strategy I think like is
also one of the I mean more more most
relevant strategy courses focus on how
you execute the the the strategy of a
company and how you actually like to it
in real life I think you have the
opportunity to study with dunan or with
I mean many many strategy professors
about the theory uh but there are some
other courses that help you to
understand how you put it in
practice amazing thank thanks you I I
mean I think the the cool part right is
that you can take like classes at MIT
classes at Harvard classes at um uh in
the engineering department like it's
just like so many places that you can
take and take advantage of kind of like
what's out there so I like definitely
recommend kind of Y checking out um and
also just like class where you work with
real companies
um um we're coming up time soon but kind
of one last question for the group I
think that like a lot of the people kind
of on the call here are both from the US
and outside the US right like people who
kind of aren't um necessarily born and
raised here um what was it like kind of
both creating a network um an experience
outside of the US within latinx
communities or outside of latinx
communities um and maybe potentially
working even with um countries outside
of the
US I'm in Mexico right now so that's
something that's like really much I've
been working on both sides I think at
MIT um I could have done a better job in
engaging better with the international
Latinos um
um but I think
that
um yeah I could have yeah I I don't know
Co was like weird um but I think that
you know it's it's about the network in
terms of are you reallying to reach out
and everything I'm part of like
Theo MIT network uh and it's just like
reaching out to people and trying to tap
into these different communities um I at
the end of the day is like what are you
working on like what is it that really
like interested in doing so um it's also
like building your own network and be
being able to like you know figure out
what that ecosystem to people going to
look like I think for me uh it's been a
great experience not not just in the US
in the US my network you know got was
Pro it's definitely the largest but um
at least my program there was a lot of
um both European and Asian students so
that did go back to their home countries
afterwards so it was very interesting to
see a lot of my friends go back and
develop these really interesting
business careers um in other countries I
know um that there was also a lot of MIT
alumni in Brazil um so when I go back
occasionally in s Paulo there is a
community there so it's really great to
like to connect and meet a lot of these
alumni um so i' say the school has been
great and fostering you know people that
go to Sloan I feel like usually are very
proud of it and do want to connect with
other sles and have the community built
out so I think that's definitely
something I've felt
throughout amazing thank you all and
like I mean speaking for myself like I
did a a class um with the action
learning office uh where I was work
helping um company in Jakarta Indonesia
um with their AI strategy and was like
able to connect with alumni while I was
in Jakarta for a week and like talk to a
bunch of people who are in the market
and it was kind of really easy to kind
of make that connection because like I
was very surprised that the slan kind of
um brand really kind of transcends these
these markets um but again really really
appreciate all y'all's responses and and
taking the time was super cool to like
hear every else's perspective and super
cool to to meet yall