the MIT energy initiative presents new
class explores paths to reducing
Transportation emissions written by
Katherine M
O'Neal transportation is responsible for
nearly a quarter of all energy related
carbon dioxide CO2 emissions worldwide
making decarbonizing the sector critical
to reducing carbon emissions and
addressing climate
change last fall MIT unveiled a new core
11.44 decarbonizing Urban Mobility to
introduce students to the factors
involved in addressing this complex
challenge we want people to be grounded
in reality so they can make good
decisions about what it takes to get to
zero carbon emissions says Andrew
salsberg a lecturer in mit's Department
of urban studies and planning the former
head of Transportation policy at Uber
salsberg taught the class together with
Jin waza the Edward and Joy Lind
associate professor of city and
Transportation Planning and director of
the MIT Mobility initiative this course
the first of its kind at MIT Works to
place transportation in the context of
broader decarbonization efforts while
also situating the decarbonization
challenge in the specific landscape of
Transportation Planning Z says
transportation is now the leading source
of carbon pollution in the United States
this is a unique moment that calls for a
course specifically and narrowly focused
on decarbonization in urban Mobility
Urban Mobility is an important Focus
because cities are the epicenter of the
technology Revolution taking place in
Mobility with new options such as ride
sharing autonomous vehicles and
passenger drones nevertheless
Transportation has proved stubbornly
difficult to decarbonize making this
sector ripe for further studies Z says
Transportation presents a special
challenge because it involves just about
everyone salsburg says we're talking
about hundreds of millions of Vehicles
almost all burning fossil fuels so there
are a great many decision makers who are
choosing how they want to get around he
says you have to win a lot of hearts and
Minds so that makes it hard the
complexity of the topic came as a
surprise to paja biy 24 a computer
science and engineering major who took
the inaugural class in Fall 2021 I
thought if everyone just adopted
electric vehicles and took public
transportation we'd be good she says
instead biology learned that many
factors contribute to the problem
including how far people need to travel
the fuel efficiency of vehicles and the
amount of carbon emitted to power
vehicles even electric cars which can
draw power from either renewable or
fossil fueled sources there are also
Myriad possible solutions including not
only the adoption of more energy
efficient modes of transportation but
also policy approaches such as
establishing low emission zones or
imposing carbon taxes when you talk
about decarbonizing Transportation two
main themes are to approach with
technology electric cars clean energy
Etc or through the policy side we try to
emphasize to students that just one or
the other was not going to be a
sufficient approach given the scale of
the problem says Nicholas caros a PhD
student in civil and environmental
engineering who served as a teaching
assistant for the class hopefully this
expanded their thinking decarbonizing
transportation is a Hot Topic so there's
a lot of information out there but it's
hard to understand what you should
prioritize says Mara kedi Sanchez a PhD
student in the media lab who took the
class which was open to both
undergraduate and graduate students they
don't give you the answers of course but
it's a very good class in the sense that
you start to understand that these are
the tools that we have these are the
potential impacts and these are the
challenges quantitative
approach to help students assess
decarbonizing options The Faculty began
by introducing a mathematical construct
known as the Kaya identity which uses
factors such as population gross
domestic product and energy consumption
data to quantify how much human sources
contribute to carbon emissions it's MIT
so it helps to be quantitative when we
can salsberg says carus explains that
Transportation emissions are also broken
down into contributing factors with each
providing a lever for control the
components of a commute by car for
example would include how energy
efficient the vehicle is but also the
distance traveled so while technology
can make the vehicle more energy
efficient working from home could reduce
emissions even further which was a key
takeaway for kti one of the biggest
lessons from the class is the importance
of reducing the vehicle miles traveled
she says similarly while public
transportation can often be a better
choice in terms of emissions that's not
invariably the case if you're the only
person on the bus taking it might be a
worse decision than driving by yourself
Cara says to illustrate such trade-offs
in one assignment the instructors gave
students a simple spreadsheet tool and
asked them to design their own Pathways
to reducing Boston's carbon emissions it
was a sobering exercise salsburg says
because even in a city like Boston with
fairly robust public transportation
options it's hard to find alternatives
to driving for long distances students
were also assigned to debate
decarbonization solutions they could
choose either to reduce vehicle miles
traveled or to Electrify everything but
after choosing their topics salsburg had
the students argue the opposing point of
that was a very good experience K says I
was going to argue for reducing vehicle
miles traveled then I switched to
electrification and learn that there are
also very valid Arguments for that
option learning from
experts over the course of the semester
students heard from more than a dozen
guest speakers on topics ranging from
city planning to the power generation
needs of electric vehicles we've never
decarbonized Transportation so you can't
look back to get those lessons we're
trying to learn from people who are
doing it as we speak ssbg says Reed ying
a professor of city and Metropolitan
planning at the University of Utah
explained that City design directly
impacts Transportation emissions since
people in dense cities such as New York
or Boston don't have to travel as far
for everyday activities as do residents
of sprawling cities such as Houston
Nathaniel whoredom a managing consultant
at the nonprofit Center for
transportation and the environment
illuminated the challenge es of
switching to battery powered electric
buses they don't work very well in the
cold the batteries don't perform as well
and you have to heat the bus caros says
bologi says she most enjoyed the talk by
Greg Rogers from nuro a robotics company
that makes autonomous zero emission
delivery vehicles it was interesting to
hear his perspective on how that kind of
Transportation will impact climate
change she
says a variety of
solutions for the final assignment
salsberg and Z asked students to lay out
a strategy for reducing emissions in a
city of their choice proposed Solutions
varied from electrifying New York City's
taxi Fleet to revamping the parking
requirements for new buildings in San
Diego bology for example focused on the
advantages of electrifying Boston's bus
fleet ketti who is working on autonomous
bicycles for her PhD research examined
the impact on emissions of enabling
shared bicycles to relocate themselves
to spots where they are most needed
currently trucks are often used for this
job we gave them no constraints ssbg
says the range of projects from parking
standards to bike lane design felt like
a real endorsement of the whole idea of
the course which is that there's a wide
range of solutions that we should be
talking about together for kti the
assignment underscored her main takeaway
from the class you have to do a lot of
everything to meet the climate Target
salsberg and zal note that
11.49 111449 decarbonizing Urban
Mobility will be held again in Fall 2022
down the line the class will also be
publicly available to online audiences
via mitx thanks to a project supported
by the MIT energy initiative and
underwritten in part by a grant from the
UN habitat program