thank you hi everybody good
morning so I'm Natalie ke I'm a slow
fellow 17 my co-founder uh she's s
fellow 16 I'm a systems engineer and
Technology architect she's the
intellectual property attorney so she's
keeping our assets very safe and with a
lot of value so uh we work together to
build this um we are we are a old women
team from all the rules um this is um
something because we were building
something on AI we want to be
responsible but we also want to be uh
very conscious around what we're
building and really be inclusive by
Design okay so problem right now with
all the things related to hiring is very
biased because a lot of people with good
intentions of course we put the best and
sometimes a lot of more the best of
things we have on our resumés profiles
on job marketplaces on lending
everywhere so that doesn't help very
very good tools that are on the market
that are doing resume screening that are
doing Talent matching because of data is
bias is what we put what we reported so
what we're doing right now is okay
there's data in accuracy here so we need
to solve that so we came to one idea
after founding that there's standards uh
right now that are being pushed globally
around credentials those are verifiable
credentials that's a standard that um
registers work experience Education
Health and more and this is managed by
digital wallets so all of you at some
point and I think right now you may have
one of those credentials already but you
don't know I I'll explain that later if
you stop by so you can take advantage of
that so what we're doing is that data is
real because it gets verifications from
several parties you can know that data
and then we are collecting that data so
you heard in some of the expositions
before that AI is cool but the is the
data sometimes if it's biased or it's
really not super good so what we're
doing is providing those credentials a
source of retraining those
tools or providing our own tools we have
our own chat Bots and so to really
improve the hiring process so the key
here is not to have better tools or
better algorithms or better models is to
have a better data at the end so what
we're doing right now is we have
credential verification this is very
mechanical we keep doing and we keep
collecting data we have ai matching and
then we have two things here one we
provide our own tools to companies that
want to hire better faster we improve
that processing
90% uh and efforts and time or we
provide other platforms that are on need
of this better data like job
marketplaces HR platforms and others
that can consume our data to do better
with their tools we also have um
connection with digital wallets globally
that i r now um deploying globally as
well so you can manage those credentials
that we can acquire that data from there
too okay so trusted data this is number
one we also have blockchain of course we
use it and leverage to to keep that data
safe if we also have Global reach what
is the key from our customers uh during
the pandemic and after the pandemic they
realized that that was better uh there
was a lot of talent globally that they
weren't able to reach also universities
they realized that there was a lot of
global opportunities but they need to
help uh their students or alumni to get
to those opportunities this of course
helps to move the talent pool around the
world so we have a company that can get
our tools or Empower their own tools to
get better job matches and we can also
get talent that use our chat Bo to say
okay I got I need to put my resume
better or what are the opportunities
worldwide that I can get based on my
real profile so that's the type of
things we're doing with users and
companies today well also as well
helping other platforms to get that data
to do better matches okay ask what we're
doing with companies right now we're
running Pilots some of them are paying
customers as well to get this to 90%
better it's not a lot of effort we need
some data but we'll get in there second
academic a lot of universities are
asking us and we're working with them to
have this credentials that get their
talent sposed globally so they can get
better opportunities of course I
educational institutions are welcome to
come and this is the plot twist we are
working with other startups not only
from MIT to get better data to these
platforms to the platforms that are
running right now so we are not the only
ones collecting this data we are not the
only ones trying to get better AI um
there's a lot of other companies doing
this so please join us to to do that
thank you so much for having us