Okay. So, so today we want to talk a
little bit more about sequences and how
sequence connect to
um to um uh a function being continuous.
And then the second thing we will talk
about is metric spaces.
So let me just remind you first
uh that if you take a subset here say of
r and you have a function on a into r
then uh f is set to be continuous.
Uh if for all x0
in a
uh uh um the function is continuous
is continuous
at x0 and and it is the function is
continuous.
is continuous
uh at x0.
If um for all
if for all
epsilon greater than zero there exist
delta greater than zero such that
if the
two points so x0 and this other point X
they deviate at most by delta
then their images deviate at most by
epsilon
and in general right this delta here
depends not only on x0 but also on on
epsilon. So delta would in general be
expected to depend on both of these
things.
Okay, so this is what so we talked about
this a number of times and we will also
generalize this later in the lecture. So
this is what it means to be continuous
that it needs to be continuous at all
points and this is what it means need
what it means to be continuous at a
point.
Now, two things we talked about before
is the extreme value theorem
and the intermediate value.
And I want to think about these two
theorems in terms of sequences.
And so this is and and and that's often
a really useful way of thinking about
it.
So the extreme value theorem is that we
have a function. So the extreme value
theorem
abbreviated like this. Um that's the
theorem that say that if you take a
function on some interval from a to b a
and b are both included
into r and this function is continuous
then the claim is that then there exist
then they exist.
So one way I formulated it is that then
there exist
x m capital m this is something in that
interval. So there exist some point that
we call x capital m and and x little m
also in the interval.
And the first one has a property that
for all
x in x in the interval
you have that f ofx
is less or equal to the value
at xm. So you have this and you also
have that f ofx at this here is bigger
equal to the value at this other point.
Right? So this means in particular that
the maximum and the minimum is achieved.
It also means that the function is
actually bounded on that interval. So
that's a extreme value theorem
and we talked about that before but I
want to think about it in terms of
sequences. So and the other thing I want
to think about in terms of sequences is
the inter the uh intermediate value
theorem.
So the intermediate values theorem say
that um that all values let me just
formulate it loosely
all values
between
so sorry uh f here is as above. So f is
again
so you have again a function
[Applause]
from there into r like this into r and
this is is continuous.
So you have this continuous function
and then the intermediate value theorem.
So a loosely formulated is say that all
values
between
f of a
and f of b
are achieved.
So this means that if you take a
function so you have a function it's
it's this here is the value at the end
point this here is here you have the
value in the beginning then it's say
that everything in between these two
these here is the image of something
right that's what the inter uh the
intermediate I'm
Okay. And I want to prove these two
using uh sequences.
And so in order to do that and we need
the following lema which is which is
often
so again this here is like the
definition of being continuous right but
often you uh often when you're proving
that something is continuous you would
instead use this lema here.
So if it's really an if and only if
statement but I will just uh prove the
if statement. So if f is continuous.
So the it's only the if statement I need
in this case here. But in other cases
you it would it's useful to have the if
and only if statement. So if f is
continuous
uh and
xn so it's continuous
um
it's continuous let me just say where
the function is defined so in this case
it's just defined on some subset of r.
If this is continuous
and xn is a sequence in a and xn
converge to x and x is also in a
then then the claim is that then
this sequence here
converge
to to this
And sometimes remember that
if this here is the case then we write
this here as x is the limit of xn as n
go to infinity.
This statement here can be written as
that f ofx is the limit as n goes to
infinity
of um of of this thing here.
And so if you combine these two things,
if you fill in x is equal to that, then
this here can also be written as that f
of the limit
of x n as n goes to infinity.
This is this right filling in this and
then equal to the limit. So in a way
if you want to think about it
like it's something about that if it's
continuous you can exchange the order of
taking limits right okay so but but you
yeah but that's like a more formal way
in a way but I I always just think about
like this
okay so we want to prove this lema and
so then we want to use this lema to
prove these two theorems
[Applause]
Okay. So now
let's prove this lema.
So uh so I want to show that that this
so I want to show so we want to show
that f of xn converts to f ofx.
So I'm first going to use that f. So use
first
that uh f is continuous
at this point x. So this is some point
in a. So this means that given epsilon
therefore given
given epsilon greater than zero there
exist
delta greater than zero
such that
if
x minus
uh so any other element y
if this thing here is less than delta
then their images
deviate at most epsilon right this is
just using the definition that x here x
here is now thought about as being some
fixed point right a fixed point and then
y is like any other point right okay so
we have that
but then we second we use
second use
that the sequence xn converts to x. So
this means that now thinking about this
delta here that this epsilon is spitting
out. So this means that uh for this
delta for delta there exist
capital n. So that such that if
little n is bigger than the capital n
then actually x n
minus x
is smaller than delta
right
but you see that so now combining this
so combining this
uh
So maybe I'll go over here. So combining
this
uh combining this then we get that if n
here is bigger than capital n then x n
minus x is smaller than delta.
But this means that now if if they are
smaller than delta then the first part
say that their images so this means that
f of xn minus f ofx
is smaller than epsilon right and that's
exactly what we wanted to prove to show
that this that if you are sufficiently
far out then these two things are very
close together right so that was quite
easy right
Now I want to use this but this is like
you know like you use this sort of thing
to you know for continuity this is like
a standard thing to use it's kind of
used implicitly and again there's this
one has a converse and the converse is
also very useful.
So now let's come back to the extreme
value theorem and the intermediate value
theorem.
So now let's try to prove. So using the
lema.
So, so, so using the lema
the lema
uh we'll prove
we'll show
the extreme value theorem
uh and the intermediate value theorem.
Okay.
And so now first to prove the extreme
value theorem. So prove
of the extreme value.
I'm first going to prove that the image
so first show
that the image of this interval here
is bounded.
Okay. So this is what I first want to
show and so I suppose not. So suppose
not
this means that um that um if I for each
n
for each n which is a integer
let's say that it's not bounded from
above right to show that it's not
bounded from below is similar. So I'm
just going to prove that is is bounded
from above
but but the proof
that it is uh bounded from below is is
similar with obvious modifications.
So suppose it's not bounded from below
above then for each integer there exist
there must exist
x
in this interval
so that such that
f ofx
is bigger equal to n right because
otherwise n would have been an upper
bound right and so I can So I just pick
such a n. So pick
such n x
and and let's call it xn. Right? So for
each n you now have xn and it has a
property that f of xn is bigger equal to
n.
Okay.
Now you have that that this gives you a
sequence. So you have that xn here is a
sequence. It's a sequence
in sorry it's not in this interval here.
But this means that it's so it's a
bounded sequence. It's a bounded
sequence.
So that by the vias
theorem
theorem.
So by the bolano vasium
um it has
a convergent subsequent
X and K right so you have that X and K
so this is this sequence subsequence
and it converts to some X right but this
means that but now this means that there
are by the lema over there you have that
this sequence this sequence then because
the function was continuous converts to
this right but on the other hand this
here x n k is a subsequence
of xn but this means that this number
here remember that a subsequence just
means that this here I mean it means in
particular that this here would be
further out than n. So, so you have that
f of x n k is supposed to be bigger
equal to n k but this is supposed to be
bigger than n
right? So, so these guys here, this here
goes to these here goes to, you know,
these here are are unbounded, right? But
this on the other hand, we're saying
that this sequence converts to this
sequence. So any convergence sequence is
bounded. So that's a contradiction,
right?
Okay. So that's that's so this is like
proving first using the lema we have now
that the image here is bounded from
above
the almost exact same proof with obvious
modification give that is bounded from
below. So now you have that the image of
this is actually bounded from both above
and below.
And and now
so now
um so now this means that if you're
looking at the image here
you uh this here is a bounded subset. So
this is is a bounded substance
and so you can look at the soup
of this set.
You can look at the soup of the set.
And I'm going to take the soup. I'm
going to call this capital M.
And now for each
for each
little n the n is an integer.
Then I can look at m minus 1 / n. Right?
So this is obviously strictly smaller
than capital m. So it's not an upper
bound. Right? So this means that for
little n this here is not an upper bound
for this set. So this means that there
must exist a x. So so that you have this
for some
x in this interval here.
Right? Because this here is not an upper
bound. This means that there must be
something larger than that. Right?
And now so you just pick for each little
n you just pick such a x and we call
this xn. So we have that so xn is in the
interval
and we have that m -1 / little n is
strictly less than f of xn.
Remember that this thing here is of
course obviously less than the soup over
all images. So you even have that.
Okay. Now, but now you see that now you
have a sequence here.
So now you have a sequence
and so you have a sequence XN
and so by the bulani. So by the bosani
by the person
why
um this sequence here
has a convergent subsequence.
Right? This is because this is a
sequence. The xn lie in this bounded
interval. So it's a bounded sequence,
right? So it has a convergent
subsequence and this convergence
subsequence I call xn
k like that. So this is converging to
some something
and that something I'm going to call xm.
Right? Okay. and I then will prove that
this has the property that I wanted.
Okay.
So I have that and so I have because f
was continuous then I have that the
images
converge to the image of this
right this is by continuity
of f right and the and by the continuity
of f and the little lema we proved
before mine
so So you have that but now we have you
see that this here tells us this here
right we have this inequality here but
this is just saying that as as n go to
infinity
this sequence here converge to m right
so we also have that this sequence here
converts to m this is just because it's
squeezed
It's squeezed here in this interval and
this here is going this lower bound is
going to the upper bound. Right?
But but so if you have that this here is
converging then any subsequence would
also converge to the same thing. Right?
So this imply that for the sub this here
that is a subsequence of these but this
is then converging to the same thing.
So now you see that we have that this is
converging to that but it's also
converging to this by uniqueness of
limits we have by uniqueness of limits.
Then we have that f of x m is equal to
this right and and capital m again was
the soup. So this means that the soup is
actually achieved. You found a point
where the soup was achieved right. Okay.
So that proves the extreme value
theorem. It proves by one of the two
parts of the extreme value theorem. It
proved that the soup was achieved and
the proof that the inf is achieved is is
is almost identical with some obvious
changes.
Now for the intermediate value theorem,
so let's try to prove that. So how do we
prove the intermediate value theorem?
and so
so proof of intermediate values
and I'm going to prove but it's not
really I mean it is it's uh the general
case follow uh easily from this so I'm
going to make an assumption
I'm going to assume that the value at A
is strictly less than zero and the value
of B is strictly bigger than zero.
And then I want to show that zero is
achieved as the image of something.
Right?
You can say that sounds like a special
case. It is a special case. But once you
can prove this, it's easy to uh get this
the general case. You can either get it
directly from this by modifying the
function by or you can once you see how
the proof of this go then it's easy to
to prove it to set up the you know what
are the different possible cases right
and then prove the them using the same
sort of argument as we do here.
Okay. So, so this is what I'm going to
show want to show
that there exist
x between a and b
such that f ofx
is equal to uh zero. So this is what we
want to show.
Now
and again of of course the function f is
obviously continuous.
So now
okay so now let me define
a inter set. It's actually an interval.
So I define E here
to be the sets of uh of X
between
uh let's call this here. So I want to
show that exists some
um X let's call it X0 just to have
something to refer to just it's I call
it X0 because the value is going to be
zero.
So I define a set a a x e sorry e and
this is the x in the interval but I'm
now requiring that that f of y
is lesser equal to zero for all
y
for all y which is between A and X.
Okay.
Now E here is not empty.
E is not empty. E here is not the empty
set. Why?
Because actually a here this is since
A here is in E. Why? Because if you take
a then the value is actually strictly
less than zero right
and and and everything that lies in here
but lies to the left of a well that's
only a right so this is kind of trivial
statement so this is not zero
so now you can take the soup of this
right so maybe I should make one more
remark
that of course not only is it not the
triv the empty set but E here is bounded
so the soup
of E is less or equal to B right because
E all of the elements in E are in this
set so they're trivally bounded by B
right
so I now can look at the soup so the
soup soup here is is a nice number
and I can look at the soup
and I claim so the claim here is
that uh that so claim that if set
or maybe maybe let me just first say set
x0 equal to that soup
V and then the claim is
that f of x0
is actually zero. Okay.
And so
now you see that
If you take
um
right. So now take uh look at the soup.
So like so so for each
for each n
say integer
if you're looking at x0
minus
1 / n right this is not the soup of e so
this means that there exist an element
uh that is there exist an element For
for each n there exist an element which
are called xn
and this xn here and it's larger than
this and the xn is in in e
right
but you see that that's for it to be an
E then in fact this element has to be
the value has to be less or equal to
zero. So f of xn
has to be lesser equal to zero
right because since it's an e right so
since it's in e then we have that right
but now of course the xns
the xns they converge this it's bigger
than this but they're less than right
the soup of all such guys. Right? So
this means that the xn so the xn
converge to x0
and so this means that f of xn
converge to f of x0
right now
this means that this here is so and
these here are all non negative numbers.
This means that this number here must be
non- negative,
right?
If it's actually zero, then that's what
we wanted, right? So, so we're done.
If f ofx0
is actually zero. So we will assume so
assume
that f of x0
is then strictly less than zero.
Right?
But if the value here is strictly less
than zero.
If the value is strictly if this is the
case then there exist then if you take
so if you take so here you have here you
have um here you have zero
here you have f of x0.
You can then take a little interval
around it.
And now so now take so take
uh take epsilon
bigger than zero.
So that uh such that
if um
uh by such that um this thing here such
that f of x0
plus epsilon this is still negative
right
so now I'm looking at
so I'm going to look at so here I have f
of x0 zero this is actually negative
and I'm taking a interval around it so
this is like a interval here we have f
of x0 plus epsilon and here we have f of
x0
minus epsilon right so I'm looking at
this little interval here around f of x0
and here I have here I have x0
but now I I know that there is because
the function is continuous. I know that
there exist an interval. So there exists
some delta. There exist delta
delta bigger than zero. So that if I'm
in this little interval, this is the
interval from x0 minus delta x0 plus
delta.
If I'm looking at this little integ
right so I have in other words I have
that if x minus x0 is less than delta
then uh f of x
minus f of x0
is less than epsilon. But everything
that is in this interim here is still
strictly negative. So this means that in
fact I have that f ofx
uh is actually in particular this
implied that such a f ofx is actually
negative right
and so now you see that that so now I
want to get a contradiction
because I know so I have now so now I
have this picture Here
I have my I have my X0 here. The X0 was
supposed to be the the soup of the set
A,
right?
And then I know that so I know that
actually
on a little interval around this Xure
everything is T the if I take anything
in a little interval around this x0 then
the values of f under is are actually
negative right
but you see that this x0 was was limits
of points where
everything to the left was was
non-positive
but so it means that everything to the
left was nonpositive
but then even a little bit further was
still non positive, right?
But then it wasn't like the soup, right?
Because you could actually any here
would be larger and it still would have
the property that everything to the left
was was uh under f was non negative.
Okay,
so that's like the proof of the extreme
value theorem and intermediate value
theorem using this using sequences and
using that little lema from before.
Okay. So now the next thing I want to
talk about is another really important
concept and that's a generalization to
some extent it's a generalization of
things we know from the real numbers.
Um
and so this is this concept of a metric
space
and so let me just give you a definition
and then I'll give you a bunch of
examples.
So a metric space it's a set X. So this
is the set
and then it's a map
for each pair of points.
So let me explain what this what I mean
by this. So whenever you have x in in x
and and another element in this space
then
when you have any such pair then d x
comma y this is should be this gives you
a real number. Okay
and so this here is what you usually
call the distance
between
X and Y.
Okay, that's the distance between X and
Y. Now, what property should this have?
It's just it's not just any any map from
the space the space cross itself into R.
It has three properties. The first is
that the distance
between parent points
I mean and then there are generalization
of this but but anyway so I'll talk
about it that's generalization like if
you're working with like general
relativity then you would actually not
quite work with this definition you work
with some generalization of this but so
what property should this distance have
it should have three properties
The first is that for any x and y
the distance between any two points
should always give you a non- negative
number. Right? So this here should be
non- negative. And
if the distance between two points is
zero then
those two points should be the same.
So in fact the distance here is equal to
zero if and only if x is equal to y.
Okay.
So that's the first property.
And the second property is
so just that distances are non- negative
if you will. The second property is that
if you looking at what is the distance
from X to Y, the distance from X to Y
should be the same as the distance from
Y to X. So this is
so this is this and this is sometimes
referred to that is symmetric.
It doesn't matter whether you first you
begin at X and go to Y or you begin at Y
and go to X.
And then the third thing which is kind
of like the non-trivial part of it and
the thing that makes it really useful
which is called the triangle inequality
that if you have three points X Y and Z
in this space and you're looking at the
distance from X to C.
So if you imagine that you take you have
three points X Y and then you have
another point C sorry no it's not so X
you have three point X Y and Z but you
think about that you're looking at the
distance from X to C.
Well instead of going kind of directly
from X to C. If you went over y then
this distance here should be longer than
if you went directly. So this thing here
should be less or equal to the distance
from x to y plus the distance from y to
c. And this here is like the non-trivial
part of it.
And this is called the triangular.
Now what are some examples of this? And
then let's look at a bunch of examples.
The first example is
the first example is just
is just where x is r
and so you have two points in x in r and
now the distance between them is simply
x minus one
right this is obviously non- negative if
It's zero that means that x is equal to
y. It's obviously also symmetric. And
the triangle inequality is this
inequality that we're using all the
time. Right?
Another example
uh is uh if you're looking at where x
here is r squ say and then you're
looking at you're thinking about x and y
you may think about it as vector or
whatever you want to think about it. So
this means that X here has coordinates
X1 and X2
and Y has coordinates
Y1 and Y2.
And now the distance between these two
points
is just the square root
of x1 - y1
squared plus x2 -
uh y2
squared. That's the distance. And this
here is often referred to as a uking
distance.
Right. So this is this distance that you
know this is like the distance is given
by pagas here. Right. And so that is so
it's clear the first two property but
those are always clear and the triangle
inequality that's the one that sometimes
is tricky to prove.
Okay. So that's another example of a
distance.
I want to give you a few more examples.
Uh and so another example is like where
you do this in R3 and so you have
instead of points having two coordinates
they now have three coordinates and you
do the same sort of thing but now there
would be a third term in under the
square root sign which be the square of
the difference between the third
coordinates. Right?
Okay. Uh then
then let me give you a few more
examples.
Uh there's a one that is to some extent
simpler than this one here
and it's sometimes useful but it's not
as
useful as the
as the
ukian distances.
And again these sort of things are
generalized there are you know example
of something much more general like this
here is what's called a helper space
example of a helper space the next is
some something which is example of
something called a bar space but so the
next example I will look at is what is
sometimes called the box distance
and so if space in this case is is R2.
I mean you could do it in R3 also if you
wanted and you take two points here X
and Y
in R2 and so so X this here underline X
has coordinates X1 and X2 and now the
distance between these two points
would be uh would be you didn't do this
fancy thing with square root but you did
the more trivial thing where you're just
adding right so you're taking two points
here in R2 this is maybe x1 comma x2
this is y1
y1 comma y2 the ukian distance is simply
this distance here the box distance is
where you take this distance here and
you add in this distance here so this is
this here plus uh x2 2 minus Y2.
That's a box distance. And obviously
this is a non- negative. It gives you
for any pair. It's non- negative. It's
obviously symmetric. It doesn't matter
the ordering of these two, right? It's
just switching the order, but you're
taking absolute value sign anyway. So it
doesn't matter. And it's also clear that
it's zero if and only if these two
points. It means that the coordinates
are are the same, right?
So and and then in this case the
triangle inequality is not very hard to
establish, right? I mean proving the
trigon even just for the ukleian are
non-trivial thing.
Okay. Now so that's another example and
I want to give you a few more examples.
Here's a sort of interesting
um example.
that if you take suppose you take a
interval
let's just make the interval from 0 to
one so suppose you're looking at the
interval from 0 to one and now looking
at so this here this is now your space x
and so this means by that I mean that
that x
x consist of so x there consists of.
So an an element in X is an element in X
an element
in X is a continuous
function
on the interval from 0 to one.
So this means that if you take two
elements
So if you take one continuous function
on the interval from 0 to one and
another continuous function what should
be the distance between two continuous
functions
right
well the distance here so this here is
defined to be the maximum
of so if you're looking at the if you're
looking at f minus g if f is continuous.
G is continuous. This here is
continuous.
Right? So this means that and now this
is a continuous function defined on this
interval.
So the extreme value theorem say that
the maximum
in so this here is continuous and in
fact even this here is continuous. So
the maximum of this here is achieved.
So this is the maximum
where x is in 0 to one. So this is
achieved right and this is clearly again
symmetric because of the absolute value
sign is clearly symmetric
uh in terms of f and g. It's also clear
that it's non- negative and it's also
clear that it's zero if and only if the
two functions are the same. And in this
case it's quite easy to prove that uh
that this is a um a metric.
Okay. So maybe I'll just leave that.
Okay. Now I want to give you a couple of
more examples and then then I'll stop
with examples and talk about I want to
give you a couple of more examples. And
the the two next examples
are one is um
one I mean so and the reason why I want
to give you two other examples is that
it's the I mean just so you know a lot
of things about distances already and
this give you excellent intuition to
proving many things
but you should just keep in mind that a
metric space could be very wild. Okay,
so I give you an example of some strange
and directly wild metric spaces. So the
first one is kind of a strange and then
I'll give you another example which is
which is wild. to the strange one to a
strange example.
And so this is like if you're looking at
the integers. So the space is now the
integers.
And so you want to look at what is the
distance between two integers. Right?
Now of course your sort of intuition
would say that if one dis one integer is
really large and the other one is not
very large you would think that the
distance was large right but it doesn't
have to be large so I defined this
distance to be 1 / n minus one / m
this here gives you so the absolute
value of the difference of one over each
of Um this here gives you a distance
and and in particular um you see that if
both
N and M are really large then they are
in this metric they're very close
together right it looks like that the
distance is very small
now instead of actually proving that
this thing here is so you could try to
prove so I mean The as usual to prove
that this is a metric the first and
second property the property that is
non- negative that's obvious. It's also
obvious that is zero if and only if n
and m are the same. It's also obvious
that it's symmetric right the triangle
equality might be not quite as obvious.
It's not very hard in this case, but it
actually is a triviality
because you could think about this one
here as a map.
Suppose you take a map from the integers
into the real numbers
and the map is just that you take a the
image of a integer. It's just one over
it.
If you think about the usual distance
over here, right? And so the usual
distance by that I mean that the
distance between X and Y is just this,
right? If you think about this but now
thinking about that sinks here that's
that's and so you think about the usual
distance but you're now restricted to
everything not just all real numbers but
just things that are one over integers
right on that space it gives you a
a metric okay and but then you can just
think about that this gives you another
way of labeling things. And so it's kind
of a triviality that it is a metric
space. But it but distances looks a
little counterintuitive because right if
you have two very large numbers then
actually the distance between them is
small even though those two large number
could be very far apart. Okay. So the
other thing the the last example I want
to give you that's a kind of example of
a wild metric
and so this is
[Applause]
this is one
vitamin and so essentially all of these
occur naturally
um
and so this example is what's called the
French well metric
right? Which is maybe not a super
flattering name uh but probably
accurate. So the thing is that if you
travel in France, if you travel, so if
you imagine that this sort of as France
here, here you have Paris
and if you want to go to
the French Riviera, which is maybe down
here. So, two cities on the French
Riviera that are incredibly close
together is K
uh and Nice. This is Can and here you
have Nice. They're very very close
together.
But if you were going to go with the
French railroad, then you would have to
go to Paris first.
I mean, so this here would take you
maybe 20 minutes uh by train if there
was a train, but you have to go to Paris
first. And that's really far, right? I
mean, the good thing is that the French
have this TGB, which is this incredible
fast train, but it still would take him
many hours.
Okay. And so that's the idea of the
French railway metric that the space
here is
is R2.
And if you take two points X and Y in
R2.
Now if then what is the distance between
this this pair?
So the distance between the pair is
uh the distance here is
distance between x and y
is um if
um
if x and y
lie on the same. So imagine that this
here is Paris
and so just think about Paris as being
the origin.
So if X and Y lie on the same line, so
lying on the same line just means that X
here is equal to some constant, right?
If this has Y,
then
X is like a constant times Y. Or you
could have I mean if one of them was
zero then you could have that y is equal
to constant times x. So this just means
that these x and y lie on the same line.
Okay. So if they lie on the same line.
So if x here is equal to
c * y or y is equal to c * x for some uh
real number.
If that's the case then it's just the
the distance between them. It's just
like this usual distance here right
between them.
But if they don't lie on the same line,
they may lie on two lines that are very
very close together.
Then the distance here would be the sum
of these two
otherwise.
Okay. So that's a French word mic
if I didn't have some sort of strange
properties
some somewhat counterintuitive
properties.
Um the next thing I want to talk about
is um is convergence in a metric space.
So a lot of the things we have done
generalizes to uh general metric spaces.
So first let's talk about what is a
sequence in a metric space.
So now you have a metric space here. So
this is a metric space
and a sequence xn is a sequence. So if
you have a maybe I should say like
before that if you take a map from the
integers into X.
This is is a sequence
and as before the image
of a integer you would usually denote it
like this. Right? So this is the same
definition that we use for the wheel.
So this is a sequence a subsequence
a subsequence of a given sequence. Well,
then then you have another map another
map G from the integers into the
integers and it's supposed to be
strictly increasing.
And then you're looking at f of g of n.
And you think about this, you will
typically write it like this. f of g of
k say and you would typically write this
as n k right this is a subsequences
right
right so it's just exactly like the way
we define it for for the real numbers
okay
now
that a sequence is converging in a
metric space that makes also sense
So suppose that you have suppose that
you now have a general metric space
and xn is a sequence
in x then we say that we say that
that xn converts to x. So,
so x here is another element in x. If
for all
uh epsilon greater than zero, there
exist
there exist a capital n. So that if
little n is bigger equal to capital n
uh then the distance
between xn and x is smaller than
epsilon. This is what it means to
converge.
Now similarly
the concept of big accusence
this also extends to metric spaces. So
accus
the following.
So it's a sequence. So, so a cruise
sequence let's call it xn
it's the following that for all
for all epsilon greater than zero there
exist
capital n such that
if uh little m and little n are bigger
than this capital n then the distance
between them
is smaller than epsilon. This is what it
means to be a sequence. Okay.
Now we have a theorem that is like the
same theorem. The proof is like the same
proof but we'll just go over it.
So we have a theorem let's say that if
you have a this theorem is the following
that so again x comma d is a metric
space
and if
XN
is a convergent sequence
in X
then
XN is a cushy sequence is also
accus C sequence.
Okay. Now, how do we prove this? So, the
proof really is kind of the same as we
did before. So, prove
so we have that xn converge. Let's say
that the limit is x.
So this means that given
given epsilon greater than zero there
exist
capital n such that
if little n is bigger equal to capital n
then the distance here
and I'm using now in a definition of
convergence I'm using not epsilon But
epsilon / two, right? So I have that,
right? But this means that if you take
therefore
if little M and little M if they're both
bigger than capital N and you're now
looking at the distance from X M to XN.
Well, by the triangle inequality, this
thing here, it's it's worse or it's
certainly not better if you go over this
other point.
But you see this one here and this one
each of them is smaller than epsilon
over two.
So this thing here is so the difference
here is bounded by epsilon as it should
be. So this proved that if you take a
convergence sequence then it is a cushy
sequence. Remember that cushi
convergence theorem was saying that in
Rh if you have a cushi sequence
then it was also convergent right but
that actually fails this is not true and
it's like some important property of a
metric space if it has the cush
convergence property so let me give you
a very simple example
so suppose
that your metric space. So the space
here,
let's just take the interval
from 0 to one. And what is the distance
between two elements? So x and y
are in this interval from 0 to one.
What is the distance? I just take the
usual distance,
right?
But now if I'm looking at this sequence
here xn which is 1 / n right this thing
here is a cushy sequence.
It is a cushy sequence. Right.
Right. Because when n and n are really
large then both of them is close to this
end point right but they don't converge
because they in the larger space are
they converge to zero but zero is not
part of the space so they don't converge
to anything in this space right so this
is an example so this is an example so
so it's a sequence but
XN does not converge
in x
zero.
This is because zero is not part of this
interval,
right? And zero would have to be the
limit. Yeah. Is that the only
>> No, no, this but this is this does
provide an important example of counter
examples because then it becomes like a
question can you make the space cushy
complete okay and sometimes you can
sometimes you can't so but it's that's a
good question and and but it is I mean
it seems utterly trivial example but
it's not I mean it is kind of I mean it
does show you this sort of important
part that you uh that is useful. It's
often useful to have the kushik
convergence property and so can you
enlarge the space to to get that
property.
Um okay
uh let's
talk about uh what it means for a
function to be continuous also.
So uh and now so now I want to
now I want to think about so I have a
so I want to think about continuity
for general metric spaces
and one can do this even more generally
but let me settle on something sort of
in between something more general and
and what we already have.
So I have a metric space here
and I'm thinking about that I have a map
from this space into R
and then I I want to and so what does it
mean for this function here to be
continuous? So f is continuous
at some point x0
in this space.
If
for all
epsilon greater than zero they exist.
They're also greater than zero. So that
if the distance between X and this X0
is smaller than delta
then their images
is epsilon close together. Okay. So you
see this is kind of like you know this
is like a kind of obvious generalization
of how we defined continuity at a point
for when x was part of r. And so of
course the function is so this is a
continuous in a point and so f is set to
be continuous
if it is continuous
uh at all points.
Okay. So this is what it means for a
function to be continuous.
Um okay. Now
uh let's just let me just give you an
example of something like this.
So remember before we looked at the
continuous functions. So we looked at
where the space was the continuous
function on the interval from 0 to one
and we said that the distance between
two continuous functions defined on the
interval this thing here is um is the
max
of the differences here
like that.
And that was that's quite easy to see,
but it's a good exercise to do. It's
quite easy to see that this is a metric.
Now I can so I have so this is a metric
space. So now I can think about so now
here's an example of a function. This is
a function that
is like evaluating. So, so now you see
this getting a little bit abstract
because now I'm thinking about a
function
on so I now looking at the function
so from x into r
but in this case x here is a space of
continuous function on the interval.
Okay. So what should be my So my
function
is now supposed to be defined on a
continuous function, right? And I just
take it to be equal to the value of this
continuous function at the initial end
point initial point in the interval.
Okay.
And I claim that this function here so
so the claim is
that this capital f is continuous.
So, so again it's it's it's it's like
continuous in this sense that you have
this general metric space and this here
is
sort of just so that it lines up with
with u
with the example.
So we have this general metric space and
we have now a map from this general
metric space into R. This is definitely
a map from this general metric space
into R. Right?
And I claim that this is continuous in
this sense here. Okay. And uh and that's
also quite easy to prove. And let me
just give you uh so let me just make one
observation.
that if I'm looking at this thing here,
so this is the image or under this map
in one continuous function and then I
subtract the image in another continuous
function and now I'm looking at this
difference here.
But this thing here is nothing but f of
zero and this is nothing but g of zero.
Right? But you see that this is
obviously less or equal to the maximum
of all x in this interval
of f ofx minus g of x.
Right? Like that. But that is the
distance
between these two elements of this
general metric space. Right? And so you
see that you see that this here is an
example with that if you so for given
epsilon I'm going to pick delta equal to
that epsilon because if these guys here
are now epsilon close by this inequality
their images is also epsilon close right
so so this map is clearly continuous
okay so I'll stop here so there's a
little lema in the note that we didn't
go through and that lema is just the
lema that I had over here that if I had
a a continuous function and I have a
sequence that converge to a limit then I
could exchange the order of limits and
the same proof works in a general metric
space. Okay.
>> Okay. Great.
>> Yep.
>> What kind of properties do you need to
kind of like
space like
some kind of like closure under
>> Yeah. Yeah. Right. That's right. I mean,
so addition, right, is something about a
field, right? And so in for these
spaces, I mean, you know, most of the
things I looked at here, I mean, some of
it does. I mean, like the continuous
function has some structure. The space
of continuous function has some
structure. It's not exactly a field, but
it has some of those properties, some of
these algebra. It's like a a important
example of something called a sea star
of algebra. So it's have this algebraic
structure.
Um but but it's not the algebraic
structure you need in order to be
completeness, right? It's not that.
Yeah. And and it's like but it and and
yeah um I think it's sort of taken us a
little bit far field but it's the same.
You see this sort of property also in uh
in you see it so the these are prop you
know like metric space is extremely
useful you see it all over the place I
mean like one of many places where you
see it is also in general reactivity and
in general reactivativity the space you
looking at are typically not complete
okay so so that you know there's
something about that is you know that
you reach something in finite time you
reach it you you're going this is like
the same thing that you reach like the
end of things
anyway but yeah but it's not the
algebraic property that is is used for