And so without further
ado, our um first uh finalist, Martin
Stoodka, who's a master's student
from our tech and policy
program. Take it away, Martin.
And the clicker
Is this it?
Yeah. Tonight, I'd like to try to
convince you all of three
things. I'm going to talk about a system
I call fossil tokens and hopefully I
will convince you that it is effective
at mitigating climate change. Hopefully
I will convince you that it is
technically feasible and finally that it
is within reach of what we can do from
where we are
today. Let's get
started. 75% of climate change is caused
by fossil fuels. What this means is we
must restructure our energy systems away
from fossil fuels.
The good news is we have the
technologies to do this at least most of
the way. We have electric vehicles,
renewable energy, energy storage, etc.
The challenge is a lot of these
technologies are expensive and we lack
the incentives to roll these out at
scale. Governments have tried different
things, tax credits, carbon tax,
restricting fossil fuel extraction. But
each of these have their own drawbacks
and challenges. So here's an idea. What
if everybody knew the amount of fossil
fuels used in making every products they
might purchase? What if you could go to
the to the grocery store and come back
home and open up an app and it would
tell you exactly for each item you
purchased how much fossil fuels were
used to produce it? In this case, the
apples used 2 g kilograms of CO2 to make
that product. What if this app was
actually your banking app and you could
see it for all of your purchases over
the last
month? Now, if you think Martin,
nobody's going to care, I don't blame
you. In fact, we've seen similar efforts
with all these labels and the entire
point of these labels in theory is to
empower consumers to make better
purchasing decisions. But the truth is,
eco labels are marketing tools and they
overwhelm us and we don't really trust
them often. And for good reason. A lot
of these eco labels are created by
industry groups and have lower
performance
standards. The truth is consumers want
to be able to fight climate change. One
in two Americans say they're willing to
contribute up to 1% of their income to
fight climate change. And if this
statistic seems surprising, well,
consider that the same paper in nature
climate change found that the vast
majority of respondents underestimated
the actual proportion of people willing
to fight for climate change in their
country. So let's think again. If data
on fossil fuel usage is widely
available, then perhaps apps like these
could be helpful. Perhaps the apps would
help consumers feel good when they have
less emissions. And perhaps the apps
could help them figure out which of
their purchases are actually the most
polluting. This is what I call decision
tools. Now, there's another nice thing
with having this data available and
that's that we could have labels like
these in grocery stores. Now, these
aren't like eco labels. They are not
created by the producers of that
product. They are created by the grocery
store that compares all the different
apples. And truth be told, when I go
shopping for apples, I don't really care
which ones I get. I just like, yeah,
they're all the same to me. So, I think
that these types of labels in some cases
would make a big difference. So, we
could say we will also get some trust
trusted
advertising. So, why does any of this
matter? Well, now that we have this, we
can organize consumer buying power. We
can get consumers to be shifting their
purchases towards products that are more
sustainable. This in turn creates
competition among industry to lower
emissions. And now we have a way for
consumers to incentivize companies to
reduce their emissions. And suddenly
companies will be starting to use better
technologies and we will be able to
restructure our energy systems away from
fossil fuels. So hopefully I've made a
decent case of why such a system might
be effective. So now let's look at how
this might actually work.
This is what I call a fossil
token. But unlike a currency, the more
you have, the worse it is fossil is
equal to 1 kg of CO2. The way it works
is governments would issue fossil tokens
to fossil fuel producers. So the more
fossil fuels you produce, the more
tokens you get.
Next, businesses that receive tokens
have to pass on their tokens to the
people they're selling their products
to. And this goes throughout the supply
chain. We often have very lengthy supply
chains, but eventually we sell products
to actual people. And those people start
accumulating the tokens in their bank
account. Let's have an example. This is
Jill. She works at Steamy Beans
Cafe. And the cafe uses electricity as
well as coffee
beans. So both of those require some
amount of fossil fuels to produce. And
so when Jill receives electricity, she
receives some tokens with that. And when
Jill receives the coffee beans, she also
receives some tokens. Then she's going
to produce some coffee cups. And those
tokens get allocated among those coffee
cups. And let me just pause here because
this is an important step. Um what
happens if those coffee cups are not the
same? I mean, if they're same, every
coffee cup has the same number of
tokens. But what if one is bigger than
the other? This is what we call
allocation. Maybe one coffee cup will
get more tokens than the other. That's
okay. The main rules to remember here is
that we want allocation to be faithful
to the concept that one token is equal
to one kilogram of CO2 and that it's
simple enough to implement. So maybe we
will have exceptions for smaller
businesses. And finally, the coffee cups
and the coffee goes to the end users and
they receive the tokens in their bank
accounts. Now, how do these tokens
actually move through the system? Well,
I propose that the tokens are actually
managed by the banks. So, each of these
companies has a bank account and a bank
and Steamy Beans Cafe is going to pay
for the coffee. But when Steamy Beans
Cafe sends the tokens over, in exchange
sends the money over, sorry, in exchange
tokens are sent and then the coffee
beans are also sent.
So to recap, tokens are handled by the
banks and transferred upon
payment. And that's that. And finally,
for the last part, I'd like to read a
segment of my essay that hopefully will
try to give a story as to how this is
not so far out of reach of where we are
today.
Global greenhouse gas emissions declined
for a second consecutive year announced
an international committee of climate
scientists this morning. Such an event
hasn't occured since the 1991 collapse
of the Soviet Union. This time, however,
improvements of in quality of life
haven't slowed. How did we get here? In
my retelling, our story starts in the
city of Calgary, Alberta in
2025. Jamal and Paul Pavlov were
brothers and gym bros. Yes, you know
what I mean. Gym bros, those dead pan
bulky men in skimpy outfits who emit
tiny grunts when they lift their heavy
but not that heavy
weights. If you ever start a
conversation with one, you'll find
they're surprisingly friendly and
pleasant to chat with once you get past
the unsolicited financial advice.
Connoisseurs of the gymro type also know
of their obsession for nutrition. Fueled
by gooey green protein shakes, they
measure, track, and allocate their
intakes of fats, carbohydrates, and
proteins at every meal. But back in
2025, doing so was a tedious task. Apps
like My Fitness Pal would help them scan
the barcodes on their grocery items to
automatically sum up the nutritional
content of their grocery runs. Still,
scanning every grocery item with your
phone's camera was like going through
selfch checkckout twice, but worse.
Jamal and Paul had the brilliant idea to
launch a credit card for Jim Bro's flex
card. Its particularity was that it
recorded not only the usual transaction
data but also data on which items were
purchased. This way users could
automatically obtain the groceries
nutritional content without scanning any
barcodes. The startup was a success.
Tabloids printed headlines like
astonishing new credit card to become
ripped in 50 days.
While it's hard to verify the card's
effect on muscular gains, Flex Card was
truly astonishing. Unlike Costco,
Walmart, Target, and Amazon, who had
previously launched branded credit
cards, Jamal and Paul had no leverage to
negotiate a deal with the banks.
Instead, they had to get their cards
issued via Stripe, a financial service
provider that kept a significant cut of
the transaction fee revenues. Moreover,
the payment terminals that the cards
interfaced with didn't have access to
the purchase data they needed to
collect. Only the cash register software
knew the details of what was being
purchased. Undaunted, the brothers
offered to share their profits with
Safeway, a popular supermarket chain,
under the condition that it tweak its
cash register software to make the
purchase data available to consumers
through their credit cards. Their
solution around the payments terminal's
restricted capabilities was particularly
innovative. The cash register software
would post an encrypted copy of the
purchase data online and send the
requisite decryption key to Flex Card
via an unused field in the payment
terminals transaction protocol. The
gambit worked once Safeway upgraded
their software. Other supermarkets
followed suit, afraid of losing out on
Calgary's lucrative Jim Bro
clientele. Flex Card quickly proved too
popular for its own good. Many
restaurants and fast food chains happen
to be using the same cash register
software as the supermarkets and
therefore easily upgraded their system
to support Flex Card. Weight loss apps,
grocery list apps, medical apps, travel
apps, and budgeting apps all requested
integration of Flex Card data into their
platform, which the brothers gladly
agreed to for a substantive fee. All
sorts of shoppers began switching to
Flex Card, and the banks issuing regular
credit cards became frightened.
Groceries amount to 20% of credit card
spending and profits. Suddenly, every
major Canadian bank upgraded its credit
and debit cards to Transact Plus, a
nearly identical replica of the
transaction protocol Flex Card had
pioneered, only renamed to avoid
trademark litigation. Before long, Flex
Card had been superseded by Transact
Plus. The banks had won. Unforese
unforeseeably to all involved, Jamal and
Paul had triggered a historic chain of
events. Through Flex Card, they had
created and popularized a system that
enabled banks and financial service
providers to track alongside standard
monetary data whatever non-monetary data
sellers were willing or required to
provide. This development caught the
attention of Elizabeth Nash, director of
the policy evaluation department of
environment and climate change Canada.
She directed her team to write what we
know now know as the fossil token
proposal. While you'll have to keep
reading this essay to know the details,
suffice to say, the proposal was adopted
for political reasons, and today's news
speaks to its
effect. Thank
you. Are you
done? Thank you so much, Martin. Now,
questions. Hands up. Hands up. Hands up.
So I'm wondering if you could talk about
the So one very notable contrast between
the fitness flex card case and the
climate change case is that the climate
change case raises a collective action
problem that isn't present in the
fitness case. So uh it might be that
people are willing to say I'd spend I'd
be willing to spend 1% I think the data
was of of my income on an effective
climate solution. But they might be
thinking uh an effective climate
solution would be one in which there's
collective action. It's not if I'm just
unilaterally doing that, it won't be
effective. So they're imagining a
situation in which people in general
sacrifice 1%. But there's nothing about
the design of your climate token system
that does anything to address uh
problems of free writing or really
collective action issues at all. Can you
can you say something on the on from the
point of view of efficacy of how you
think the collective action problem
would be addressed by this? Yeah, for
sure. A great question. Um, so I think
in many ways the goal of this is to give
consumers the option of being able to
actually pave towards fighting climate
change. And I think given the statistics
we saw of one in two Americans want to
do that, um, if it was easy to do, I
think they probably would be do willing
to do it. Now, not in all cases, of
course. I mean, I think in some
situations like there to make a
sustainable product will just be a lot
more expensive and so maybe consumers
won't be willing to pay. But I think
there are a lot of cases where if you're
buying apples or clothing, maybe there
are comparable products in terms of
sustainability that or in terms of
price, but one is a lot more sustainable
and we just don't know about it. So I
think in many cases the collective
action isn't as much of an issue in
those cases where the sustainability
where the price is comparable and I also
think we have a lot of cases where
people making individual decisions
without necessarily being coordinated
end up creating collective action. I
mean if we look at vegetarianism if 20
years ago it was a lot less of a thing
than today but each of that like
everyone who decided to become
vegetarian did that as an individual and
today we see a lot of restaurants
offering different menus right
sorry oh sorry thank you so much I
wonder if you could speak to the sort of
personal infrastructure decisions that
are going to be a bit more um that are
going to matter a bit more in the in the
broader scheme such as solar cell
installation on our roofs or or our heat
pumps or our electric vehicles and
particularly these higher expense
options that require maybe also kind of
uh pulled infrastructure to try to
invest in. Yeah, for sure. I mean, I
think when we look at for example, a lot
of the data centers today are spending a
decent amount of money to get clean
energy for their data centers and that's
partly because they want to be able to
say that um they they're running on
clean power. And so I think when
consumers actually care um or or are
enabled to care then companies react to
that and we see companies spending uh
money on all kinds of initiatives that
are for attracting consumers especially
in big industries that are consumerf
facing like fashion. So I I think those
high capex expenditures especially when
they're amotized over so many products
um are are feasible but of course this
is not like a catch-all solution. And I
think there will be cases where um we
need different solutions as well. Great.
Um thank you so much. Um what are the
consequences of accumulating a lot of
tokens and so uh let's say I I just
stash it all up in my bank account. What
happens to me next? Yeah. So in the
version I envision of this, this is not
like some kind of way to blame consumers
for accumulating tokens. I think there
should be no consequences to
accumulating tokens. Um, I think the
real benefit of this is not in making
people feel guilty, but rather in terms
of giving them the choice when they're
shopping. Um, but I mean, you could
envision different systems that do that
differently. But the way I would propose
this is your token information is as
private as your financial information to
kind of prevent any of those concerns.
Great.
Hi. So, I take it that clean energy
sources are more expensive than the
fossil fuels. That's part of the
problem. Yes. I'm worried I'm wondering
what you think about, you know,
technological ways of avoiding your
technological solution. So, companies
might try to find alternative ways to
pay for their energy. They don't go by
way of banks and then the banks aren't
sending them any fossil tokens since
they're using cash or they're using
Bitcoin or something like that. and then
they can sell their cheaper products and
they don't have the number of tokens
that appear on the product doesn't equal
or represent the accurate account of how
much fossil fuels being used. Yeah,
that's a great question and I think in
my essay I talk a bit about fraud and
dishonest mechanisms. Um so a few of
them is you could for example try to
sell or like transfer all your tokens to
someone who really doesn't care about
climate change and then give everyone
else lower tokens. Um, the idea of this
token allocation rule is to prevent
that. Um, but still there there probably
are mechanisms to do it. I mean, I think
we have a tax system. There are
definitely loopholes in the tax system.
It's not necessarily a reason not to
have taxes. Um, you're always going to
find loopholes, but I think with good
government regulation, there are ways to
to prevent the worst offenders.
Is there a risk that suddenly even
though you know some large fraction of
people might really care about this and
want to not accumulate lots of tokens
that you'll get some counterculture of
people who take pride in accumulating
lots of tokens and that those might
actually then be an opportunity to
arbitrage because now the companies can
launder all their tokens to those people
who want more tokens.
Um, yeah, absolutely. I mean, I think
there are memes online of people being
like, "Oh, I ate twice the amount of
meat today to like make up for all the
vegetarians."
Um, I mean, in terms of kind of
offloading your tokens to specific
consumers, I think if you follow like
typical carbon accounting rules, the
idea is basically that uh the tokens
represent CO2. So, you can't just
allocate all your tokens based on how
consumers want. And in the essay, I go a
bit more in depth into like specific
rules that could achieve that to some
extent. Um, so I think it would be
challenging to just arbitrage between
consumers. But yeah, great. I I think
it's hard to imagine tracking something
and not having it um the monitoring be
used at some point, right? And so uh
much like a credit score, right? If you
track something, then some entity that
has access to that will use it. it's
going to be used and so have you thought
through you know in this sort of credit
score like situation
um you know it it does have uh
downstream effects even when we think
about things like food stamps or SNAP
benefits right where um there are you
know some rules about what you're
allowed to buy using those and some
people maybe blame people who are using
food stamps and saying well they
shouldn't be buying soda or they
shouldn't be buying candy whatever it is
right you could imagine Analogously,
once you're tracking something, if
there's some sort of monitoring, people
would say, "Well, you're poor, you don't
get to have fresh food because that
costs a lot of carbon. What are you
contributing?" Because we're tracking
it. What systems do you imagine putting
in place to stop the tracking of
something from becoming the policing
probably for people who don't have as
much power? Yeah, for sure. Um I mean I
think as I briefly mentioned earlier a
big part would be ensuring that there
are data privacy laws so that this
information cannot be like reshared. I
mean, a a a simple way could also be um
having the data be deleted, like instead
of having it accumulate in your bank
account, you could just every month like
clear the the database, right?
Um at the end of the day, I mean, you
could always imagine a government
turning somewhat evil and deciding to
collect this in the back end and that
kind of stuff, but I think the neat part
about having the banks handle the tokens
rather than the government itself is
that it's somewhat decentralized. I
mean, you could switch banks and the
different bank would have a different
software system. Um so yeah I I think
there are ways to mitigate this but I
absolutely think like that is a concern
that should be looked at. Great. Thank
you. Uh thank you for sharing. Uh this
is a topic that I'm personally very
interested in and uh during my
conversation with other people about
this. I've received two I think
difficult questions that I want to hear
your thoughts on it. So you can pick one
to to answer. Um so the first one is u
as we all know this is not this is a
fascinating idea but it's definitely lot
not like happening. It's not like the
new idea that just started this year.
We've seen it in policy. It's called
personal carbon allowance. At individual
level, you know, we all have a carbon
wallet. If we emit more than that, we
have to buy quota from other
individuals. From business, there is
that especially in transportation
sector. Uh if you choose sustainable uh
travel mode, you gain credits and that
credits can be used to redeem something.
So the question that I receive is that
this is a fascinating idea but then what
do you think is the bottleneck that make
it not happen today like why is it not
here and then the second question you
can choose one to answer is that uh in
terms of carbon emission we have a
production side and then the consumption
side we're talking about consumption
side right now but we all know that
there are looking at a sheer amount the
amount on the production side that we
can reduce is much larger than we can do
on the consumption side. So why should
we focus on consumer instead of
producer? Thank you. Yeah, I mean can I
answer both or
um I'll start with the second um so
production ver the consumption side
versus production. I think it's really
challenging to directly limit
production. I mean some countries have
done it to some extent. Um but it and
and it is to to be clear it is effective
to some extent because when you limit
production you increase costs and then
some people move away but at the end of
the day it is not going to be fully
effective. You also need to be able to
limit um consumption because if you just
limit production people are also going
to just move elsewhere and get um their
fossil fuels from another country for
example. So I think limiting consumption
is equally important and yeah um for
your first question as to remind me
the the topic.
Oh, right. Right. So, um I think the big
part about this is that in the way I've
presented it is that it's a government
that's implementing it. And when you
have a startup that comes up and says,
"Hey, we're going to do personal carbon
accounting." Um it just becomes one of
those other eco labels. Some people will
join, some people won't, people will
trust it, people will trust it less. I
think to really make change and this
comes back to the collective action
problem like maybe the organizing
mechanism to do collective action is
having a government supported by its uh
constituents actually go forwards with
this proposal and and bring people
along. So yeah that would be my main
thing. Well there were I think a
thousand questions and we got through
sort of seven of them but uh thank you
so much. Thank you so much.