So the question was, should I, Sarah
Hansen, use chat GPT right now to plan
my retirement? Not yet. Okay, please
explain.
>> Large language models are not yet ready
to be able to do delegated financial
decision-m for us. Turns out that saving
for retirement is one set of activities,
but then spending while in retirement,
that's a whole different set of
activities. But the more challenging
issue is how do we communicate that to
people who don't have any finance
background and and moreover can't afford
to hire the financial adviserss that
some of the higher net worth individuals
have access to. So we're working on an
AI solution uh an AI financial adviser
that can satisfy the most important
criterion of financial advice that
regulators impose which is something
called fiduciary duty.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu. edu.