[Music]
from the MIT energy initiative this is
what if it works a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate change
I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob
Stoner on today's show a glimpse into
the future the future of nuclear energy
of course nuclear power plants have been
with us for a long time and they produce
a lot of energy but traditional nuclear
energy comes from fision and for some
scientists an enormous source of
excitement is Fusion a type of nuclear
energy that could change our lives how
well think about it this way there are
only two inexhaustible sources of
effectively inexhaustible sources of
energy on Earth it's the heat content of
the earth which is what we call
geothermal okay and it's Fusion it's
fusing together the the things which are
in water the heavy forms of hydrogen
that's Dennis white a professor in the
department of nuclear science and
engineering at MIT and he's the former
director of the MIT plasma science and
fusion Center he says unlocking either
the heat content of the Earth or
unlocking Fusion would be totally
gamechanging and not just
scientifically access to energy is the
most Geo important geopolitical aspect
of of leadership right now in the world
and in fact it's also the greatest
source of conflict as we also see around
on those things and both of those have
interesting aspects to them that namely
that's the science truth of them and
then the reality of them as practical
energy sources is that they're both
technology driven where we we the United
States have an obvious Advantage about
being able to do that because we
won more or less all of the major
technical races of the last 50 years we
could win these ones as well too and I
think that would be really important not
just to the United States but to the
world but why should the government and
companies and institutions spend money
on Fusion if the fusion still in
development especially since solar
panels and windmills are out there in
the world working so the first answer is
math we are using exactly the same
percentage of our energy sources in the
world come from carbon based fuels as
they did 10 years ago as they did 50
years ago and so that's the math of it
so people are confused by this people
see wind farms they see solar farms and
they go well we must be getting greener
at sources of energy right worldwide we
are not why not white says the answer is
kind of stunning I have a chart which
basically shows the Energy Mix has
barely moved my plug was like to 1970 so
like 50 years ago that's good cuz you
know we can kind of realize this within
our lifetimes it's like it hasn't moved
oh but the world worldwide energy
production has almost
tripled so if you were to poll most
people like yourself you just go are we
emitting less or more carbon now into
the atmosphere than we were 50 years ago
every oh we think of our big gas guzzler
cars you know the ones that our dads
drove the big kers you know D D D and
all the smoke coming out oh we're way
less it's triple what it was 50 years
ago not only are there more people on
the planet than there were 50 years ago
but more of those people are living
energy hungry lives in general I think
we are not say we are not deluding
ourselves but we're feeling better about
ourselves by deploying things like wind
and solar which are actually are making
some difference but it's barely keeping
up with the increase in energy demand
worldwide so when we say things like
well don't build more coal power plants
country blank or something you know
we've got some hutzpah I have to say is
in terms of the West to me it's moral
issue it's like how can we tell you not
to deploy energy when we got rich and
wealthy by by using these energy sources
ourselves it's like now we're saying oh
no no you're doomed to Poverty because
we're not going to let you actually use
energy so I'm a scientist people don't
think of me as a as like a philosopher
around these I feel energy is the moral
issue of our time and it's because
energy is linked to human well-being
because it's linked to economic
well-being and by denying people access
to clean energy it's a moral issue so if
about 80% of our basic energy comes from
burning fossil fuels white says you need
an energy source that is usable on
demand that's scalable and creating such
a source is not a problem that's easy to
solve so right now if you even if I just
came along with a magic solution that
can provide carbon free electricity at
arbitrary levels we still can't use it
actually because our electrical grid not
tolerate the ability to actually
transmit that much more power and what
do I mean by use it you just like we
just replaced all liquid fuel
transportation with electric vehicles
now the grid literally cannot operate
because you don't have the transmission
capabilities and there's a subset of
people who make arguments that we have
all of the Technologies now to
decarbonize in my opinion that is false
we we actually do not have the
Technologies and what and what I make it
clear here is that Fusion is one of
those things which is driven by
technology which we should try to do
because it has the features of what I
just said right that it is carbon free
it's intense and it's on demand you
can't change that part of of Renewables
which I'm not against Renewables it's
just that they're they're part of the
solution it's extremely unlikely from a
science point of view that they're going
to be the total solution so let me just
qualify a little bit what you said for
our listeners cuz they'll be saying gee
we do have wind and solar and batteries
and we do have the Technologies we need
but I think what you're saying is that
the scale that we would need to deploy
those at is Impractical it's impractical
particularly not only to decarbonize our
electricity sources but all the other
things and which is only approximately
20 or 25% of our energy use comes from
making electricity we need things that
solve air travel and longrange
transportation and Industrial uses of
heat and all these other things and and
the further you go away from electricity
also this the science of of Renewables
of wind and solar get worse not better
and there's that's the reason they
haven't been deployed in those areas is
this other funny thing that goes on too
with with the transformation of our
Energy System you know with the
expansion of electricity using solar and
wind they inherently distributed forms
of generation they're all over the place
and and that necessitates a a
simultaneous change in the structure of
the grid it goes from being a
centralized source that that's radiating
outward through the wires to one that's
more of a mesh right and and that's an
expensive thing to do and it's also a
complicated thing for grid operators to
make a system like that work optimally
one of the nice things about nuclear
whether we're talking about fision or
Fusion is that like coal plants and gas
plants these are these are large
centralized plants we can literally drop
them into the grid as the grid now is
configured okay so you're saying I get
it solar and wind sort of they're good
but they're not going to do it all is
there anything else you know Fusion
again it's still in the future is there
anything else that exists right now we
could go with I mean we could go with
regular nuclear energy there are nuclear
power plants out there and they're
producing energy like right this second
and they're powering things so like why
think about something
that's maybe could work out and maybe
won't work out right so I am fully
supportive of
certainly that we should keep using our
present nuclear Fleet as well too and I
think we should expand it because it is
a solution that is right in front of us
this will get back to my discussions
about Fusion actually this shouldn't be
Dennis White's opinion about what energy
we should have we should do it's by the
way it's it's the other reason the 82%
doesn't move it's economics right if
Fusion Energy was less expensive andal
nuclear absolutely standard fision
nuclear power plants and they met the
market demands better then they would
they would be used more as well too so
all of that's good and that's exactly
what we should do so Fusion is
interesting because it uses literally
the opposite physics in many ways of
what fision does but it has features in
it which are as you pointed out Rob are
are similar right is that you get really
large amounts of power you have fairly
good access to fuel it's just
interesting there's sort of more social
and safety implications for fion but
those we figured out how to how to do
those but this also gets back to the
to my first graph and so forth what you
have to realize we are not solving the
problem for us for the United States in
many ways we've got it easy we have
really quite clean air we've got good
emissions controlled we have a really
robust mix of different energy uses got
Hydro nuclear gas really cheap uh gas
all those things what we're actually
solving for is how do you decarbonize a
growing economy like India's we need to
provide something to them so they're not
going to build more coal plants because
they're going to keep lifting their
people out of poverty by using energy
like let's let's not use coal to do that
but they're going to keep using coal to
do that and and by the way over the last
10 years or maybe even less India's gone
from having something like 60%
electrification to very close to 100%
electrification And it's because of coal
it's because of coal and they very
aggressively expanding that Fleet and
people are living better so I have a
question for you R when India thinks
about this question of the energy mix
and let's say thinks about traditional
nuclear is it all a monetary Dennis
you're talking about the kind of
economic push back is there also a
social pushback yeah there is I mean
India you know unlike us again lacks
this sort of enormous amount of land
that we have and they have a very high
population density and it's it's hard to
site nuclear power plants in the United
States it's really hard to site nuclear
power plants in crowded countries so
that's a challenge for them but I think
I think their their attraction to coal
and the same is true in China to a large
degree is that it's just so inexpensive
and when you're in a poor country and
the difference between having
electricity and not having electricity
is
money that's a powerful driving
force yeah and then there are
geopolitical consequences to to the use
of fision right because it is the the
the same technologies that you use to
make fision work have connections to
proliferation right because they're
they're linked by the by the science of
it now again we have good safeguards in
place and we do those things but it is a
complexity right uh around Vision that
that's certainly true now the Chinese
are advancing quite rapidly in building
up a nuclear Fleet it's not as big as
ours yet but it will be in a few years
the rate they're going and that's
different from the Indian
situation and it's not because China's
less crowded but they've got a lot more
power within the central government to
make these exciting decisions there's
some indication that that Chinese people
are not happy about that although they
are happy to have electricity and is
that also a question of money that the
the government's just like willing to
spend What It Takes yes and and you know
the Chinese are very very good at
manufacturing things and carrying out
large projects you know impressively so
and they're able to build these plants
much more inexpensively than we are here
and to some degree they're driven toward
that because they lack our abundance of
Natural Resources they don't have the
hydro capacity that we have they have
some they don't have the natural gas
capacity that we have and so that's
driving them down a different path and
the same sort of decisions play out in
different ways all around the world the
Japanese of course have even fewer
natural resources and are forced to make
decisions that would be impossible for
us to make here so far so so I think you
know conventional if you like nuclear
power has a role in the near term as
these countries convert and build up
their electricity supplies I think
what's exciting about Fusion is that it
enables us to open up yet another
direction that that is more socially
acceptable I think in this country and
that's because of the nature of the fuel
and the fact that Fusion plants aren't
going to produce the same large
quantities of nuclear waste that our
fision plants produce and that's been a
problem for social acceptance here yeah
guess who is racing towards Fusion
Energy
China uh exactly for the same reasons
that Rob just pointed out because if
it's sustainability it's a technology in
the end like a Fusion Energy industry
will have an enormous supply chain
that's pushing around these integrated
Technologies of pushing those forward
China wants to be a leader in that not
just for its own energy use in fact I I
would believe if I was them also for the
geopolitical influence that'll bring as
well too do you have a sense of what
that race between the US and China looks
like with Fusion are they head or they
are ahead is it like cled enough in
secrecy that you don't really know how
far ahead so maybe I will actually I'll
I'll
uh no no it's it's it's a good question
but but it has like most of these they
don't have simple answers is that if you
if you look at the government program of
China right now and its National intent
this is this is ahead of the United
States's National program we do not have
a national policy that says we are going
to develop Fusion energy we we should
right right and in that sense of what
what they're doing they're doing it in a
very centralized way that China can
bring to these kinds of uh this these
kinds of problems they just recently
announced in fact effectively an
industrial Consortium that they're going
to put the whole thing they're going to
put their shoulder behind that wheel and
push it it's not just well we're going
to give more money to research labs to
look at Fusion we're going to employ
basically all of these tools that we've
built up in our IND industrial toolkit
of steel manufacturing of their existing
nuclear industry concrete manufacturing
the whole thing and their stated goals
we're going to beat the West to Fusion
Energy so now but but you say are we are
we behind or ahead the one thing we're
where we are ahead is an
innovation this casts itself into a lot
of the other kinds of um challenges we
have around these two very different
systems about how you get to the goal
line and the the Chinese will have a
very centralized program and put
everything behind it and they they've
got their act together about figured it
out and they're very good technologists
and engineers and all those things but
you know the US I'll make it a little
bit broader like the UK and probably
Western Europe as well too our system
favors like inventiveness and Innovation
you know and so oh that's good and we've
got companies that are trying to
innovate their way to better products
you know it's interesting about which
one will win I'm not sure so this
reminds me of of your creation story so
to speak I mean talk about the
government not leaning into something
you when you were the head of the
nuclear Department here the government
withdrew funding yes and and applied it
instead to a Consortium called eer
that's operating in in South France to
build a reactor there but basically
withdrew their support for Fusion
research in the United States in the
University system at any rate so the
government was like yeah we're funding
fusion and uh research at MIT
yeah now we're done what happened
um
yes it's complicated again as usual so
part of it was it was an evaluation
about where Fusion was and this is
approximately 10 years ago that this
decision came down and so it's
interesting everybody kind of knew where
Fusion was going right we should U make
it clear like Fusion at this point was a
science Endeavor it was this was not
about Fusion Energy at all Okay and like
a lot of other Sciences like in the big
physical sciences like accelerators and
so forth the general Trend was are we're
going to go we're going to get bigger
and bigger to be able to and mean bigger
projects bigger checks that you have to
write and so forth we're going to get
bigger in this uh it leans towards
International collaboration and you know
if you sort of take CERN as a good
example you know in in Europe or these
other or International Space Station you
know these are good examples and and
this is where everyone saw Fusion was
going right and so what I mean was that
the next stages of science exploration
we're going to be in bigger projects not
smaller projects hence they all saw that
it's always 50 years in theut right and
and and and that made sense too here's
this project is going to take you know
whatever at that point it was going to
take still 10 years to construct it we
knew this the big thing where they
accelerate that's the big thing that
accelerates around even physically so
that takes all that accumulates all the
the countries in Europe and all that and
so this was just infusion looked like it
was just sitting in that usual trend of
this so you know smallscale University
experiments looked less and less
relevant right now I can make some
arguments about the fact that we weren't
irrelevant but for interesting
reasons is that it so there's some some
great irony in this like we were never
really to I mean in the end the the
political reality was there needed to be
budget freed up to be able to pay for
these extremely much larger experiments
and we not going to go small right so
this wasn't about effectiveness it
wasn't about uh like you know the the
science wasn't any good anymore and so
forth this just like that's the trend
and we're going to go there so I have to
say there's some great irony in this and
it's like what what is this is because
what has happened a a lot because of not
just because of what we did but a lot
because of what we did at MIT in the in
the start of Comm Fusion systems is that
we changed the narrative that it wasn't
just about science anymore is the idea
that we should actually think about
making this an energy source right
and in order to make it an energy source
you looked at um you looked at these
enormous International projects and you
did a quick calculation how much would
they cost per watt like what's the
dollars per watt this is how you
basically make keep score for energy
sources um and it showed it wasn't even
close I mean it's it it was like a
factor of a more or less like aund away
from other kinds of energy sources oh it
was like a 100 times expensive more
expensive for the same am yeah
collaborative in France yeah not even on
a commercial trajectory not not on a
commercial trajectory so it is so and
this is it is what it is it's a science
experiment about accessing that next
level of science so there's some great
irony in this as I always said is that
it turned out what we were doing at MIT
for science reasons and to keep it at a
scale that actually made sense for a
university we were using a particular
path which exploited access to very high
magnetic fields cuz it was a specialty
of what we did at MIT in in sort of the
history of MIT and the reason we did
that was to keep it intentionally very
small but High
performing and and in the end it's just
like oh the realization that there could
be a possibility of Translating that
into an argument for economic Fusion was
really what launched like the thing that
changed the trajectory for mit's Fusion
program and for I would argue about
setting us on a really valid path
towards Fusion as a power source so in
many ways they have different purposes
there's also an irony in it is that in a
weird way maybe that cancelling made us
think about what we were and it made me
think personally of what we were I was
in Fusion to do science I never really
thought of it as an energy source I that
the next Generations will maybe do that
and then what was dropped into our lap
was really an opportunity to translate
our science expertise into the idea of
actually making an energy source so wait
how did the withdrawing of funding and
the US government being like this is
kind of it sounds like this is kind of
small potatoes we need to we need to put
our bets on like sort of do the big bets
here how did that lead MIT to really a
place where like this stuff is being
commercialized I mean it's it's strange
that the money got taken away and then
things started to accelerate people
might look at it oh this was just a
different way because I know there's
some critics of this they go you just
convince some rich people to basically
give you money like through the private
sector to keep doing your sort of
science experiment um no no what it was
was actually it was an internal
transformation for a large part of us
inside the team at the plasma science
infusion center that realized we should
actually try to make an energy source I
remember the day when we said because we
had we worked on this plan which is
basically take our idea High Fields
confinement device these high magnetic
field confinement devices we came up
with a valid technical plan
but really our biggest commitment in
change was thinking of ourselves as
energy developers rather than scient
just scientists now obviously there's
science and technology that is behind
that that Evolution was the biggest
single change in my professional career
and the good part of it was to say oh
and we've got the team to be able to
execute this which was what we had at
the Plazma science infusion center and
then eventually spinning out in fact
commonw Fusion systems about doing that
but we were way too isol ated and
insulated in fact from the energy
development World in fact part of one of
the great um things that we did was walk
over to the energy initiative and
actually start learning about you know I
never talked to anybody in the energy
sector it's like oh no we're just we're
just physicists really playing with with
our toys it's like so walking over to a
place like the energy initiative MIT
also woke us up it's like holy cow it's
like this is actually what it's going to
look like what you're you just said Rob
right schedules timelines resource and
when you come with that and and put
yourself in that position then it's very
interesting it it still forces by the
way amazing science it's just that
you're working towards a different
[Music]
goal now Commonwealth Fusion systems
which you've talked about which spun out
of MIT which would you say it's the
leader in Fusion right now in the
private sector
so I know it's raised money from rich
people as you mention before so if
you're talking to a rich person who's
not a physicist and you're like this is
why you should give us money are you
like are you on their Board of advisors
or are you affiliated with the company I
have no it's for other reasons I can
explain but I have no official
affiliation with Ashley common but let's
say either you or they were like you
should give us money rich person to fund
this it's really very important how
would you to an ordinary person explain
what it is they funding and why they
should do it what is Fusion right so
well well so so Fusion is the fusing
together of of of hydrogen to produce
energy so this is the same process that
powers Stars our own Sun as well too it
happens in the middle of of the sun and
the most um well-known condition for
this has to get very hot it has to be
above on Earth it has to be above about
50 million degrees cels no by hot you
mean the the the hydrogen atoms have a
lot of has to get hot right so in the
middle of our sun it's about 20 million
de C and this gets hot enough that
basically it allows the hydrogen to push
against each other close enough that the
fusion can occur and again on Earth
about the minimum temperatur is about 50
million degrees C and and then there's a
requirement that you basic have to have
enough fuel around in order to create
enough Fusion reactions that then keeps
itself hot right and so once it gets to
that point it becomes like a star that
and basically it starts keeping itself
hot through its own Fusion reactions and
so it as we say it's a even though it
uses somewhat different reactions it's
basically the same thing as what's
happening in the middle of a of of a
star and they're being these these atoms
are being confined because the star is a
star it's a massive object can't get
away from each other exactly so Fusion
only works in one place naturally in the
universe it's in the center of stars and
the reason for this is because of their
enormous size so the containment of this
like it's 20 million degrees in the
center it's only 5,000 Dees it's like
way way it's a thousand times colder on
the on the surface of the Sun how does
that Center stay hot well because it
can't go anywhere because it's contained
it's confined by the gravity of the sun
itself and gravity as as you know Rob
gravity is the weakest of the
fundamental forces of nature by a lot
hard to reproduce yes and and and it
takes that's actually why you know so
Jupiter is interesting is actually has
almost the same composition as the sun
but it's not a star because it's not
quite big enough so there no really
except for some exotic examples there's
not really small functioning Stars
around so you cannot translate that
directly to Earth you need a much
stronger force and what you use is the
electromagnetic forces which are much
much stronger in fact than than gravity
so this goes to your question about like
what happens is that turns out that the
force that you're applying for the
containment is that you trade off you
can keep something hot by making it
larger like a like a star or in fact
this is what eater and other things like
this make themselves really really big
and that will keep it hotter longer or
you can apply a more effective force and
that force is a magnetic force and that
and that goes that comes from the making
this magnetic field that is produced by
electromagnets and so there's always a
trade-off between large which allows you
to keep it hot versus more Force the
analogy we use is that it's kind of like
a keeping your home warm is that you do
it in two one one of the ways is to just
like make it really really big like make
the walls like super super thick or you
improve the quality of the insulator got
it right and so making the magnetic
field stronger makes the insulator way
better and what it allows you to do is
it makes the object smaller but still
get the same containment that was the
science of it but it turns out the
economic impacts of this are staggering
because Fusion is a very interesting
energy source what you pay for is the
thing that you build the fuel is free
and it lasts forever
what you're paying for is the
containment system okay right so in this
particular one um which isn't the only
way to get to Fusion but it's that's the
one Commonwealth uses and the most
prevalent one right now you end up
building large electromagnets which make
a a containment cage which hold the hot
fuel so it actually costs very little
money and very little energy to get it
hot what's hard is the
containment they want to fly apart from
one
another keep to keep it hot continually
okay so then you have this very hot
thing y but the problem isn't solved yet
because like I want to power that
factory down the road and I want to
power my house so yeah so Fusion sounds
very exotic in a way you know it's
happening like this the process the
power of the star but in the end the the
what happens is that the fusion where
where is Fusion Energy when the fusion
occurs the energy is released it's
literally in the velocity or the kinetic
energy of the particles that are come
out they're the same particles as before
they're just rearranged by equals MC squ
they just have an enormous amount of
energy so what you do is you stick
something in front of those particles
and get back the energy and how you get
back the energy is you force them but
they basically bounce around like
billiard balls almost is the right
inside of the material and what you do
is you put some engineered object and we
call this a blanket because it kind of
surrounds or the fusion device that then
gets hot because those particles are
forced to give their energy into into
regular matter and it gets hot that's it
like so Fusion makes heat okay so the
engineered thing that we make is heat
this is why it's so lovely Fusion is
because heat is this is basically almost
all our energy sources is what we do is
we make heat with them right and and
then we do something with the heat like
make electricity or we make fuels or we
do or what whatever the thing is that
you want to do that's actually what
Fusion makes in the end so this the
almost your your vision of this is you
build an object it costs you something
to build this object right this complex
object then after that the fuel is you
can just burn arbitrary amounts of fuel
in the thing because it's almost for
free and then what's coming out of it is
heat that's why I get excited about
ideas that of like how would we use
Fusion not just to to make electricity
but to actually get after that 82%
business so the rich person that you're
pitching is too says uh-huh uh-huh um
when when will this be powering um like
what's your timeline here for powering
homes and factories so okay it's
interesting so it depends about who the
you know the person might be often those
people by the way are are in the
positions they are because they're
technologists okay yeah so to that
person I would describe what we're doing
I actually wouldn't get into the details
imediately of the physics and so forth I
would just you know I would I look at
this laptop right yeah um or or an
iPhone yeah and I would go you realize
like the they know this right the
Decades of science Innovations like when
when shocky invented the transistor
could he have imagined an iPhone right
but you realize that these are
fundamental pivot Points in the
understanding of the science and
technology and then you're working on
these things and all that information
Theory all these things and then at some
point you realize holy cow I can
actually put this together into
product and so all of those I guess most
of those very rich people are there
because they saw an aspect of an idea of
of commercializing something that just
looked like science fiction at the time
right and I was go that's what's
happening in INF Fusion it's like yeah
there are details about what the
technology will look like and so forth
the most important thing is that we've
built now or we've got the entities
called companies which are trying to
build a product
and that doesn't sound like much of a
breakthrough does it but it is because
until you have that you actually have
zero chance of actually making an energy
product because who can deliver it right
so I that's what I say to them is like
so come into this Eyes Wide Open
understand that some of the approaches
are not going to work right but what the
goal is it's not just fun sence it's
actually to make an economically viable
energy product and when you do that like
what you have is a possibility to
displace A10 trillion a year economy
which is basically the worldwide energy
right sector that's that's the argument
that you make and they all get that it's
just like what did Amazon disrupt right
retail right because of the invention of
the internet right which they didn't do
but they were the they pounced on that
opportunity I could just go on and on
about like we're surrounded here at MIT
by biotech biotech was built on Decades
of underlying scientific research and
all of a sudden wow we can edit the
human we can edit genes we can do these
things which actually allow us to do
things that looked impossible like even
20 years ago and you don't just mean
biotech like in Labs you mean like Merc
and fiser no like the companies came out
look at what and also to the people that
go oh this this is all going to be slow
you can't go fast like again look around
where we are right holy cow again we got
we got a vaccine like that fast right
against a global pandemic when we're
trying to solve really important
problems we can go fast and we go we go
fast by innovating by having the right
structures around us again imagine that
we were at a place and all we had and
this isn't against government LA because
curiosity based research absolutely
critical to these kinds of things but
imagine that came along and there were
no biotech companies how long do you
think it would have been I think we'd
still be waiting actually probably for a
vaccine far fewer of us or far yeah and
and they and it's because that's what
they're built to do right yeah so that
that's basically the the argument not
not just actually to the billionaires
but to us as a society right isn't this
what we should be doing so there are
these kinds of hard problems there's no
there's no blueprint for how you combine
those developments in science and and
our understanding into a working Fusion
reactor in fact there are a number of
startups around the world I last time I
looked there was something like 40 plus
trying it in different ways tell us a
little bit about the structure of that
sort of P Global right it's uh like I
almost can't believe I'm recording this
and saying there are 40 private sector
Fusion developers right this is so so so
part of it actually comes
from uh you how would how would it be
possible that there's 40 ways to do it
well this comes back as usual comes back
to some underlying science differences
in in Fusion the science of fusion
allows you to access high power and high
gain in just an staggering number of
ways and that's actually what these
approaches are in some sense exploiting
but also challenging because it's like
which one of those gets you to the goal
line which is economic product and so
then the answer about when you get there
actually becomes about how clever you
become how well you deploy the resources
and basically having a distributed
aspects of of many shots on goal in fact
to be able to do that we we call this
competition we call this the market
right and that's actually going to be
the answer by by the way not to pick on
it right but we already have Fusion
we've actually made Fusion happen in the
laboratory for a long time we've
actually you know the the experiment
here at MIT in something like only like
this big across was five times hotter
than the center of the sun right we have
experiments where we're making hundreds
of trillions of fusion reactions per
second the containment is absolutely
good we've actually made Fusion so let
me just the important point there is
it's not a burning plasma so to speak
it's not a burning plasma and and and
and and in fact now though by the fact
that we saw one at the national ignition
facility right we actually saw that as
well too so Fusion is not Science
Fiction it's not about that like we
already made Fusion what I'm talking
about what we when will we have Fusion
Energy Systems
commercialization but are are are is
this like give me a sense are we talking
like 10 years four year you know like
what's the scale you know people should
be thinking about can do it at right so
then that goes the specifics of each of
those kinds of approaches right so I can
speak to the one you know so what we did
was we we looked at and we we looked at
the scenario and said okay what would it
and we had the benefit by the way of the
particular particular approach with the
magnets like we' already built three of
them at MIT there had been sort of like
50 to 100 built around the world based
on the size and the complexity of them
we know how long they take to build
right and we said okay if we can
actually make this one we think it'll
take blank years to make this
fundamental technology development which
is the super conducting magnet then it
should take blank years to actually
build the Prototype and then blank years
to build the thing that goes on the
because we'd built them before so we
have that advantage and we added those
up in a very serious way and we said and
this was 2018 we said we're 15 years
it's like cuz it looks like that's how
long it takes and right now we're almost
exactly still on that timeline so that's
a decade from now so that's a decade
from now but I will just CAU every so
we're still on that pathway and there's
still challenges which are around on it
but at least we're making a try at it
right and imagine now you have a this
isn't just for your own country this can
scale to actually power the world
forever and you have control not just of
that particular design but all of the
things it takes to build it it's like so
just imagine a future where I I want to
see one where we develop in a political
system that actually that that favors
personal freedom and choices around
these things because in the end you know
it's going to be about people's
well-being that's why we want economic
clean energy sources I'm not sure if
we're going to win but I think we will
if we actually get our act together that
that namely you know and governments are
reflections of the societies that we
have it's like it almost goes back to my
beginning comments like we don't really
know first of all how hard this is going
to be about the energy transition like
rob you and I work in this every day I
still don't it's still hard to imagine
the SC of this and how hard it is but
it's like isn't this the thing worthy of
trying right tell me what there's where
there's a higher priority what if it
works and then what if it works holy cow
right and I think we should imagine a
world where it works um in all all
different kinds of ways yeah so so in
that world there are going to be
literally tens of thousands of fusion
reactors if if we continue down this
path what makes me worry is that that
that's really a deployment story that's
not an invention story and figuring out
how to do it elegantly which is what
we're doing right now in our current
gener you know in our current phase of
of
commercialization this deployment is
something that the Chinese have done
particularly well they've you know we
invented solar panels they own the
industry we invented lithium ion
batteries they own the industry we get
the first electric cars they're got to
own that too so how do you think about
that deployment and winning that race
not getting forced out of it what are we
going to have do to build a global
fusion industry in which we still
play so we've got to figure out all
kinds of things right it's a race in in
some sense between two different kinds
of development systems and the advantage
I would argue that we have is is that it
primarily gets driven by markets right
and then what happens is that companies
come in and make products that actually
that that respond to the markets so what
is the market it's about decarbonizing
vast amounts of our energy sources as
well too so I think what it looks like
is I I am pretty sure it doesn't not
look like a monolithic single design of
a fusion device and and the reason for
this is because energy itself as as you
know is a very complex Market about how
we what we actually use energy for and
fusion has this adaptability and
flexibility that comes from its
underlying science of those things I
described before that says there's all
different kinds of ways to make make a
product that respond in the energy
market so I think what success looks
like is actually multiple Energy
Products you know you have to get past
the goalpost of the science requirements
around it obvious on that but if you get
to that place then I I believe like the
Invisible Hand kind of wins right it's
it's going to be that aspect of spurring
on competition among different concepts
and about what how you respond in the
energy Market is that when you're coming
up with a new product go after a market
that almost not NE doesn't exist that
has no other choices right around on
that and I think we have a real chance
of doing that through these 40 companies
you know that are around not all of them
are going to work but if you come up
with a handful of different kinds of
different kinds of Concepts that can
actually respond to the energy Market
that's what success is going to look
like and I and I think that's why we can
still you know win that race in fact if
you you ask this question if I was in
front of really wealthy person i' say
please work with me so that I understand
like how did we get all these other
amazing Technologies because not
repeating the mistakes of history but
also learning from the the from the
successes of these other sectors is to
me a way that we can actually accelerate
Fusion across the board and that's
really what I where I personally feel U
really um committed to uh learning about
those aspects of it but also then
working along with my Fusion colleagues
to see about what we can actually
deliver in the next decade cuz if we can
deliver a few of them like a few pilot
plans in the next decade we're we're
changing I think our trajectory on clean
energy few pilot plants meaning
different Technologies just just getting
this stuff out
there Dennis white is Professor in the
department of nuclear science and
engineering former director of the MIT
plasma science and fusion Center Dennis
thank you so much this has been a great
conversation thank you yeah it's
exciting to watch thanks Dennis
what if it works is a production of the
MIT energy initiative if you like the
show please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen and remember to
subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
podcast and you can learn more about the
work of the energy initiative and the
energy transition at energy. mit.edu
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob Stoner thanks for listening