my name is Hussein ranima I'm a
professor at the human dynamics group at
MIT media lab my interest has always
been in the intersection of AI and
disciplines like design and Humanities
and my key Focus area at the lab is on a
concept called perspective aware
Computing essentially a type of AI that
allows us to see the world through other
people's lenses so instead of relying on
large language models we can basically
have our own personal models train it
ourselves and lended as expertise and
knowhow to others contributing to the
formation of a decentralized collective
intelligence if you look at the
literature of AI in the past 50 or 60
years they were very much based on
learning we looked at a lot of data we
looked at patterns of data and then we
had these Winters and summers in the
evolution of AI and the techniques that
we used if you go back to about 20 30
years ago we had dual based systems uh
we had expert systems as we called them
and they were very much based on rules
think about Excel sheets but at a at a
different level uh as we are thinking
about symbolic systems and hybrid
systems so these systems can all come
and work together rather than be relying
on one our interest is forming a new
type of AI and really find an
intersection between what we used to
call semantic Computing symbolic Ai and
Subs symbolic AI which are techniques
like neural networks and really bring
them all together to work in Tandem and
the context will basically decide what
components of this AI ecology we need to
bring together to bring the best
decision and action based on the context
of the request from the user so our
unique technique is to really combine
symbolic AI to really represent the
world and represent our behaviors and
our human traits and then in a hybrid
model combine it with neural networks
for learning process formation of what
we call AI graphs or graph-based Ai and
then use that to populate data
accordingly to really understand users
and entities on a much more broader and
contextual fashion uh so it has been a
unique but relatively a complex area of
AI in the past few years but what is
different different now is that with the
Advent of large language models the
great compute power that we have now
using gpus and tpus and cloud computing
and the relative
uh cheap storage of data and the ample
of data that we have if you think about
that physics and as have as how you're
bringing them together we can now
demonstrate the impact of these symbolic
AI systems at scale our system bu
believes in these AI ecologies where
different types of techniques and models
and de decentralized data schemes they
all come together to essentially forming
what we call an AI solar system or an AI
ecology now if you compare that with the
large language models uh they are great
and we use them we don't necessarily
compare our technique versus large
language models we just create these
full here and hybrid system so our
models can actually benefit from large
language models so if you think about
using an llm because there there is a
hypothesis out there that well if you
have a lot of parameters and a lot of
data training these models and you have
these amazing compute power it's just a
matter of time that llms will completely
displace agents and symbolic agents we
don't necessarily look at it that way
because the challenge with llms is that
you need
verifiability you need audit you need
Providence of course you can benefit
from an nlm but will you be able to say
where is that data coming from that is
giving me that answer can you actually
verify that answer you can try it and
you can ask a similar question in
different context windows and you may
get very different answers now large
language models are amazing if we can
use comp components of those in form of
vectors and bring them to our tiny
models which are more symbolic and
really bring the best of the two
techniques together to build verifiable
and reason ready models so if you need
to audit these models if you want to
verify these models especially when it
comes to personal data then I think you
will achieve the best of the best of the
Two Worlds when you're building these
next Generation AI systems