(logo whooshes)
(text crackles)
- Hello, everyone, and
welcome to another episode
of CSAIL Office Hours
where we dive into the brilliant
minds of the innovators
who are driving the future
of computing at CSAIL.
My name is Daniela Rus and
I'm the director of CSAIL.
Today we have a very special
guest, professor Tom Leighton.
Tom is distinguished MIT
professor, beloved member of CSAIL,
and co-founder and CEO
of Akamai Technologies,
the world's leading content
delivery network provider.
Tom's research on network algorithms
has laid the foundations of his company
and made a huge difference in how
you receive your information today,
so, let's dive into Tom's
research journey at CSAIL.
Tom, it's so great to have you here.
Your work and your impact
is so inspirational
and it's legendary for us at CSAIL,
and it goes back to the 1990s
when you were a professor
and you had some brilliant ideas
that ended up having huge impact.
Can you walk us through what
it was like in the 1990s
at CSAIL when you were
such a big innovator
in the field of networked algorithms?
- Really an exciting time at, then,
the Lab for Computer Science.
CCL didn't exist yet.
In fact, I remember
actually first coming to MIT
as a grad student, that
goes back to the late 70s,
and then, the work being
done in cryptography
was gonna change the world.
My first advisor, Len Adelman,
and Adi Shamir was visiting,
and Ron Rivest ran the theory group.
Then of course, you get to
the 80s, Goldwasser-Micali.
It's amazing what was happening
in the Lab for Computer Science.
It was really the who's who
of theoretical computer scientists,
people working on algorithms.
- A walk among touring award winners.
- Yeah, now you go fast
forward, big prize winners,
and of course, it changed
everything on the field.
And then you go to the 90s,
and my group was working on algorithms
for large-scale networks theory, right?
Improving theorems, and
how would you route packets
and store information so that
you could do it really efficiently.
All mathematics, and Mike Dertouzos really
was very instrumental.
Sure, we had really great
people with great collaboration,
a fabulous environment,
and recruited Tim Berners-Lee
to be head of the Web Consortium
and his office was down the hall,
so his group and my group,
the algorithms folks,
got together and talking,
and that ultimately led
to a lot of the stuff
that led to Akamai,
but just a fabulous, innovative,
cross-disciplinary environment
in the Lab of Computer Science.
- People often ask me, what
is the secret sauce at CSAIL
and at MIT, so what was
it like about those times?
Computer science was
still a very young field.
The visionaries and the
innovators were all at MIT,
were known for the wild and crazy ideas
and were known for cooking them up
in the middle of the night.
What was it like?
- I remember we would, before
the conference deadlines,
we'd be up all night, maybe
(giggles) two nights in a row,
getting the papers in just in
time, and yeah, a lot of wild
and crazy ideas, a lot of
excitement, great collaboration,
engaging with students, faculty, postdocs,
and, you don't think about it at the time,
but a lot of those wild ideas
were gonna change the world,
and then you see it, now
you fast forward to today
and it's like, oh my goodness.
The things that happened here back then
that just at the time were
just a lot of fun, you know?
Doing cool research.
- Tell us a little bit about
the research you were doing
at that time, especially
about some of the insights
and technical ideas that
ultimately led to this huge impact
of computation on communication networks.
- It was all theoretical,
and that meant we weren't constrained
by any practical realities.
The ideas we were thinking
about the conventional wisdom
would be where you could never do
anything like that in practice.
You think about routing
packets in the internet,
well you, you just used
BGP like everyone else,
but in our case, well
you could do it faster,
at least mathematically,
in proven theorem,
if you sent the packet over
here and then to there,
and even though it looks
like that's longer,
turned out to be a lot
better for congestion
and make the whole thing work better.
You think back then and with websites,
they were in one place, and
maybe you had a mirror site,
and that's just the way it was done.
Of course, pretty quickly, it
was realized that's a problem,
and Tim Berners-Lee, he knew
that was gonna be a problem
way back in the mid 90s
and that's when he
approached our group saying,
"there's gotta be a better way here
because you get popular content
and there'll be a lot of
traffic to the website,
it's gonna crash", and it did,
and back then, dub dub dub
stood for world wide wave,
in the early days.
I remember even things like DNS,
back then, the protocol standard was
you gave one resolution for a name.
Now, it could be a few IP addresses.
It was limited by the size of
the packet to a small number.
In our case, we weren't
constrained by those realities,
so we said, "hey, when
you do the lookup for DNS,
you should refer it to a local server
and not have it be everybody
goes to the same place",
which broke protocol,
and people told us, "you can't do that."
Well, we were theoreticians,
so yeah, we can do it
because (laughs) it's math
and we've proven theorem,
and it works better,
and then in practice we implemented it
and yeah, it works a lot better.
- What do you see as the role of analysis
and understanding a
solution that you deploy
in the physical world?
Today, we deploy a lot of
solutions we do not understand,
which is quite different from taking
this more rigorous approach
and saying, we're gonna
solve this problem,
we're gonna understand its
scope and its limitations,
and then we're going to do
something with a solution.
- It makes a big difference
when you can prove theorems
and do a rigorous treatment
of how this algorithm,
this system is going to perform
under certain conditions,
and that made a big difference for us
when we actually implemented it,
which is a whole different
exercise (laughs)
to take theoretical algorithms
and code it up into a system,
but when you did do that,
you would have confidence
that it was really gonna work
in a variety of environments.
It would really be fault
tolerant, it would really be fast,
and that makes a world of difference,
'cause often, if you don't have that
and you build a system, you find out, ah,
there's all these things that blow it up,
or you try to make it twice as big
and it doesn't work anymore.
We didn't have that problem
because the theory really worked.
- When you solve a problem theoretically,
you make a set of assumptions
and then the solution is
subject to those assumptions.
Then when you take the solution
and you move it into the physical world,
you have to ask which of
those assumptions hold.
Did you find that all
your assumptions were okay
for the physical world or
did you have to innovate?
- Oh, there's a lot of innovation
and of course, when theory meets practice,
(laughs) that's not an easy thing.
- Yeah, there's always a big
step from theory to practice.
- Yeah, and of course, we
were all theoreticians,
didn't really know how
to code all that well.
We were fortunate that we hired
and worked with a lot of
people who were very good.
Way back in the day, Bonnie and I
coached the MIT programming team.
- Oh, that's awesome!
- Yeah, and so we (laughs)
actually had a good talent pool,
and they came to work in
the early days at Akamai,
but part of the theory that we developed
was to make it be fully distributed
and really fault tolerant on the basis
that a lot of things could break
and we had the theory say, okay,
the system will still stay up and work,
and that is critical,
'cause there weren't
single points of failure
because sure enough, a
lot of things did break,
but the system would still work.
- It's really extraordinary
because you were imagining a system
of scales much bigger than
what was possible at the time
with an application scope much bigger,
and I think the reason
everything came together so well
is because you had a kind of
an interdisciplinary approach, right?
You had the theory, you
had the system side,
and then you had the
World Wide Web Consortium
who presented the important challenge.
This is one of the secret ingredients
that I think remains very important
for how CSAIL advances computing.
There's this multidisciplinary
approach to computing
with people who are
passionate about different
sub areas of computing.
How important was that for your group?
How easy was it to set
these collaborations up?
- It was great.
That's the way CSAIL was, and it is.
I think the collaborations
are very powerful
and it made all the difference.
Without that, we wouldn't exist,
and a lot of advances wouldn't take place,
but the interdisciplinary research,
all the way from theory to real practice,
makes a huge difference.
- It's really extraordinary to think about
this kind of end-to-end comprehensively.
So, another thing that
MIT and CSAIL cares about
is real-world impact.
Is taking our results, our theories,
and algorithms, and ideas,
developed with a long time horizon
and making them relevant,
so how did you know that your algorithms
would be so relevant?
How did the story of Akamai start?
- We were naive, and being theoreticians,
just thought it should work in practice.
In terms of becoming a company,
that wasn't our goal, initially anyway,
but we entered the 50K contest,
mostly to learn about how do
you write a business plan,
and literally (laughs) got
books out of the library,
"Business Plans for Dummies", you know?
And we learned a lot in the 50K.
We met venture capitalists.
None of us knew what a
venture capitalist was, even.
It's hard to believe
now, but that's the case.
We met with industry experts
and got a lot of advice.
Now, at the end of the
50K, we actually had offers
to start a company, but we decided not to.
- Did you win the 50K?
- No (giggles), we didn't.
It's sort of urban legend
is we did, but we didn't.
We made the final six, which
we were pretty excited about.
They only announced
first, second, and third.
We weren't announced.
I'm pretty sure we were last
among (giggles) the finalists,
just 'cause we had no business experience,
oh, and really saw much better
business plan presentations.
- But you had the tech
and you had the vision
and you had the impetus to
change the industry, right?
I mean, it was extraordinary.
- Yeah, we had good algorithms.
No code. We thought-
- Oh, no code?
- No code. No.
- When did you start implementing it?
- Our idea was to get other
people to use the technology,
so, during the 50K, we
went and talked to the ISPs
of the day, AOL, UUNET, (giggles)
HarvardNet here, locally,
and we wanted to get them
to use our algorithms,
which meant they would have to code it up
and make it all work,
and they talked to us
'cause we came from MIT
and it sounded interesting,
but then after they
heard what we were doing,
they said, "Ah, everybody
knows distributed computing
doesn't work in practice.
It's an ivory tower concept.
Thank you for coming, but please go back
to your ivory tower." (laughs)
So we totally struck out,
and then we actually decided
not to form a company
because we weren't sure
that we could actually
get the technology from theory
and algorithms to work in practice.
Danny, co-founder, he wanted
to be a theory professor.
Would've been a great one.
I liked (giggles) being a
professor here. It's really fun.
But we kept on thinking about it,
and then started talking to the big names
in content delivery.
The websites that had a lot
of people coming to them,
and they said, "Look, if you build this,
we would buy it because we
need our websites to be faster.
It makes a big difference
to our business."
And so then, it got down to the point
where the only way we were
gonna get the technology out
in the real world is to do it ourselves,
and that meant forming a
company, writing (laughs) code,
and building the infrastructure.
- So, how did you decide
then to form the company?
- Well, we decided that
this is a very rare chance
for us to have a difference in practice.
I mean, theoreticians,
they do very cool stuff,
but most of what we do isn't
really useful in practice
and takes a long time if it is.
Now, the cryptographers
has done amazing things.
You look at public-key
cryptography and the work there,
but most of theory doesn't cross over,
and this was a rare opportunity,
and we did believe it would work,
so we decided, okay, we're
gonna bite the bullet
and step away from MIT,
which is (giggles) sort of our nest,
and we hired the former students,
the programming team members,
and went to the incubator space next door
and started the company.
Got funding from angels
at first and then the VCs,
and then we were on our way,
and sure enough, the theory did work
once we got it coded into algorithms.
- You had proofs, right?
- We did, yeah,
(Daniela laughs)
and then we took off pretty
quickly at that point.
- [Daniela] And so, how
did you build the company
into the giants that it is today?
- It was great during the.com boom
because money was sort of
falling off trees for investment.
It didn't matter that the
company was profitable or not,
but then you had the .com blow up
and that was very, very difficult,
because now you had to become profitable.
We almost went broke.
Worst of all by far, of course,
Danny is killed on nine 11,
and that was just devastating for us.
Our customers are going broke
because most of them were
.com-crazy companies,
so really, it's the people
we had in the company then,
that made the difference.
The technology really did work
and it was a matter of
getting real companies
to buy our services,
and we were fortunate that
we were able to do that
in a way that we started
making money just in time.
Then we grew.
- So the cloud services
came online around 2007.
Was that important for your company?
- Yeah, it's interesting.
We were actually working
on edge computing,
distributed computing, way before AWS.
We were doing that in 2001, 2002,
but then, of course, the .com blow up,
we had to make massive cuts,
so we put that off to the side,
and AWS, it's amazing the
business they've built.
Now you have GCP and Azure as well.
Those guys are among our
largest customers today.
We do a lot of delivery for
them and we do their security,
and now we're actually getting
back into core compute,
so we have major data
centers like AWS would have,
and we're actually now in
the process of deploying VMs
and containers into edge regions.
So we have today, over 4,000
Edge locations in 750 cities,
and the goal this year
is to be able to have 100
of those cities where you can
run your VMs and containers.
- Does the machine learning
revolution have an impact on you
and on on your customers,
on how you do things?
- We've been using ML and AI forever
in our security solutions.
Anomaly detection, is
it a bot, is it a human?
If it's a human with
the right credentials,
is it a thief that stole the credentials?
All those kinds of
things, AI is pivotal for.
Now, you got some pretty
cool (laughs) advances
with GenAI and LLMs, and
a lot of use cases there.
I would say today, it's
giving a quick leg up
to the attackers,
because you can use that to generate code,
and you can train it about malware
and you can train how to
get around the defenses,
and so anybody now can make great
or really dangerous malware,
and that's not good,
and so we're already seeing penetrations
into the big enterprises rapidly increase.
- What should we do about it?
Because we have to stop the super villain.
- You need, more than
ever, defense in depth,
you need more than ever early detection
so you can detect the malwares in,
and we do now have the
market-leading solution to do that.
It's microsegmentation.
You gotta have an agent or a firewall
on every single app you have,
every single device,
and it's gotta govern
what that app can talk to,
it's gotta filter that communications,
'cause the malware is
in your internal network
and you've really (laughs)
gotta know where it is
and you gotta stop it from spreading.
Ransomware's not so bad if
it just gets into a server,
it's when it spreads
everywhere you got a problem.
Same with data exfiltration malware,
it gets into your HVAC system,
that's often where it'll go to call home,
not bad yet.
It's bad when it goes
and grabs all your data
and sends it out to
the command in control,
so I think microsegmentation
and the notion of very
localized internal firewalls
is very important.
- What do you see as the company outlook
for the next three to five years?
- We started in content delivery.
It's not our biggest business now.
Security is our biggest business. Yeah.
And I think, you go three to
five years, maybe compute,
cloud computing, 'cause that's
such an enormous market,
becomes the leading business for us,
but really is all those
things put together
in what is the world's
most distributed cloud.
The hyperscalers are
much bigger obviously,
but they're centralized.
They started in a data
center and then another,
and they have a small number today,
and Akamai started fully distributed
and we're in 4,000 locations
and now we're adding the
cloud computing aspect.
- Tom, you somehow managed
to be the superhero CEO,
a beloved teacher at MIT,
and also a researcher.
How do you manage to do it all?
- Well, I don't really do
research really anymore.
Every once in a while it's fun
to talk to somebody who is,
and the teaching I do every other fall
for the six 1,200 or 120,
they're gonna change the number,
and I do that instead of serving
on other corporate boards.
Most CEOs, you serve on a
couple other company boards
and it's about the same amount of time,
but I think much more interesting
and fun to teach six 1,200.
It's a chance also to talk to
the computer science students
about mathematics in a way
that I think is important for them,
and interesting, actually.
- What are some of the
pieces of advice you have
for the students who
aspire to be as impactful
and successful as you have been?
- I remember advice I
got when I was their age,
it was actually a Nobel Prize
winner talking to young kids
interested in science,
and he said that always
you wanna keep your eyes
and ears open and your brain turned on,
'cause you never know when
there's gonna be an opportunity
or a challenge presented,
that, if you're listening to it
and you see it, and you're thinking,
maybe you can make a contribution
and solve it, or help,
and I thought that was pretty good advice.
I think keeping an open mind,
just because something seems impossible
doesn't mean that it is,
and you know this, like
sometimes research problems
become homework problems, right?
Because once it's solved,
if you tell the student they
gotta do it for homework,
they figure it's solvable,
and then they do it,
and I think that's true in research
or tackling hard problems.
I remember somebody, a
knowledgeable guy in the field,
once saying that the only
reason Akamai was successful
is because we were too naive to know
what we were doing was impossible
and that couldn't be done,
and yeah, we were naive
and it just, well this made
sense to us theoreticians,
and you don't worry
about being in the box,
as a theoretician, and yeah,
it turns out it's possible.
- You gotta have guts.
- You do have to have,
yeah (giggles), tenacity,
that's for sure.
You gotta stick with it.
You wanna listen to the naysayers
and process what they say,
but if you think what
you're gonna do still works,
you gotta keep at it.
- What about the education side?
What should the students focus on?
What do you see as the role of theory,
versus systems, versus other
subfields of computer science?
- I do think they're all important.
Of course, I grew up in
theory, always partial to that,
and the rigor I think,
is really important.
I gained a lot of
appreciation for systems,
(laughs) through Akamai.
There's a big difference, I learned,
between writing an algorithm on paper
and proving a theorem,
and developing code that's
gonna work in the real world.
Very, very different endeavors,
and I gained a lot of respect
for what the systems folks do
and the engineers do.
- Tom, thank you so much
for all your contributions
to us at MIT, to computing, to the world.
You are really such an inspiration
and I'm gonna try really hard
to have more interdisciplinary
collaborations within CSAIL
to look for the next nugget
that could be as successful as Akamai.
- Awesome. Well, CSAIL is great.
Really appreciate your leadership here,
'cause it is a gem here.
Just really, really valuable,
I think for humanity broadly.
- Well, it's the people
who make it wonderful,
and you are one of our
superheroes, so thank you, Tom.
- Thank you.