All right, I think we are ready for this
first session. My name is Dontis. I'm
from Mos University and I'm also a part
of the NF NF um center and uh I'm
chairing this session and I have been
really looking forward to uh to hearing
uh these three speakers and the session
is on scaling variant interpretation and
the first speaker is Ruth Lo and Ruth is
um professor at the Novonics Foundation
Center for Metabolic uh re research at
the University of Copenhagen and the No
Foundation Center for Genomic Mechanisms
of Disease at Broad Institute. So,
welcome Ruth.
>> Uh good morning. Thank you so much for
having me and thank you for the
introduction Dita. My talk is on the
genetics of obesity and more
specifically and how we actually
shouldn't curate uh our phenotype in
this case obesity to to get to the next
level of uh of uh variant to function
translation.
So very briefly, my disclosures have no
effect on anything I tell you. So no no
secrets here. Obesity is a traditional
common disease just like type 2
diabetes, cardiovascular disease. The
environment has an important impact over
the past 30 40 years. Uh the prevalence
of obesity has doubled, tripled. Uh and
that's definitely driven by a changing
environment. We eat more, we move less.
Um but it's in particular people who are
genetically susceptible who will respond
to this environment and who will gain me
more more than people who are not so
much uh uh uh susceptible. So the
heritability has been estimated to be 40
to 70%. Which is considered and again
very similar to other complex diseases.
Maybe different from other complex
diseases is that obesity is a very
visible public disease but I'm not going
to talk about that today. But it's also
a very early onset disease unlike type
two diabetes and cardiovascular disease.
So that's when we think about um
prevention. That's something we need to
take into account. Furthermore, it's
also a disease that involves a lot of
organs uh or tissues, not just the
brain, not just the fat cell, but when
it comes to like connecting obesity with
coorbidities, many other tissues and
organs are involved.
Um when it comes to gene discovery, it's
been actually um a very successful um uh
pathway. I would say is that we started
in 2007 with the discovery of FTO with
only a sample size of 5,000 individuals
and then over time we've identified more
and more variance mostly because we
increased the sample size more and more
and many of these efforts have been uh
like uh driven by the giant consortium
like headed by Joel Joel Hershorn
and uh by now we have more than 1,700
variants that have been identified
mostly associated with body mass index
or first identified for body mass index.
A few have been identified for other
adepositi related phenotypes.
And what we've learned in the context of
the biology is that uh the brain is a
central is a central organ probably
affecting um uh like our um hunger,
satiety, reward systems uh in the brain.
The hypocampus lyic systems like are are
driving this whole process. You see
here, this is a a nice figure from from
2015, but it is still the case. Not much
has changed uh since then. Um but the
variant to function translation has been
very slow.
FDO was the first discovered uh
phenotype almost 20 years or 18 years
now. You see very nice signal. This is
again from an older paper where the p
value is 10 theus 60. Now we're at like
10 to the minus 200 and initially we
thought that FDO was the causal gene and
there was quite a few papers in cell in
nature nature genetics that showed very
credible results for FDO as a causal
gene within uh within the context of
obesity but soon after uh the discovery
others researchers started to venture
out like some thought it was RPG group
1L uh that was the causal gene because
it's in quotes the the basil body of the
primary Celia which we know from the
Barney Beetle syndrome may be cause of
obesity but like others including
Molina's team thought it was more IRX3
or even further down IRX 5 that was the
causal gene. So there was a little bit
of um discussion in the field but then
over time things got clearer and maybe
uh this story got concluded with the
paper in science by uh uh the Marcela
nogo and Molina's team where they in
indeed concluded that the signal here in
FDO within neurons and preadiposites
seem to reach to IRX3 and IRX5 and that
may be sort of the causal genes within
this locus and this is just an example
to tell is like it took them quite a
few. It's like took them about 14 years
to come to that conclusion and
there's,700 variants actually that are
waiting to be translated. Maybe there's
like a dozen of variants that have been
translated from variant to function
within the context of obesity but that's
about it. Within my team, we've tried to
approach the variant to function in a
more uh like bionirmatic ways like a
statistical way because I don't do
actually lab work. Uh so Diane um used I
think about eight approaches that were
were at the time that she was doing
these analyses to to do the gene
prioritization and then uh she counted
how much the same gene was prioritized
by the by the different approaches. Uh
so here summarized in this upset plot
for example here you see that here are
the different approaches that she
considered for the gene prioritization
and you see that uh 86 genes were were
prioritized by four approaches and could
be any combination um 34 genes by five
and uh six gene by uh six. So that's not
all approaches but uh these are these
six genes and I won't go into the detail
but some of them are indeed like
confirmed uh or not necessarily
confirmed but also supported by animal
studies that they may play a role in in
obesity context and not always uh they
do not always point to the brain but
often also like a deep side biology and
then another project that is in process
and this also is like a collaboration
with Molina's team like is Virginia.
She's doing using a more multi-omics
approach where we go from snip to BMI uh
through uh maybe gene expression and
proteomics data. So what she did is she
combined uh all the uh publicly
available EQL data uh across multiple
tissues. Sometimes she did a meta meta
analysis. She did the same for the
proteomics data and used that in her
analysis to um basically uh align all
the variants that we have and I should
have emphasized these are the the 500
variants that have been reported in the
Yangoidal paper which is the latest
giant paper. uh she prioritized 413
genes in 189 lowi. Again an upset plot
but the main message here is that again
the brain remains the most uh the tissue
in which the most genes are being
prioritized or seem to be playing a role
but other tissues are now also popping
up.
She then overlated so here are her
results uh based on the
collocicalization with EQL and PQL QTL
data. She overlaid that with the data
from from Diane right here and then
overlay that also with the results from
CS2G and you see there's 37 genes that
are prioritized by all three methods and
now she focuses on these 37 uh here are
some of them to to really summarize the
data in a paper that will be coming out
soon. So this is a plot that we use
where we have a variant the genes that
are prioritized in which tissue. So it's
just a lot of data to really summarize
into uh one uh nice uh story but that's
coming up because what's next is
actually is like the giant consortium
has been working so I haven't updated
this plot uh since 2021 and that's not
because I've been lazy but it's mostly
because there haven't been that many new
discovery uh studies. The giant
consortium has been working on a meta
analysis. uh giant itself combined the
data of 2.1 million individuals and then
collaborate with 23 y. So now we have a
meta analysis 5.6 million people and
this is um so now we have uh really
9,000 LOSA actually that we have
identified and the Manhattan plot looks
like this.
It's funny. Um
so the the the the significance
threshold is right here and you ask like
uh sometimes this it's like uh too much
data not not necessarily helpful. So
what can we do with this kind of data?
We we thought like let's start with the
easy things instead of varant to
function let's just do make a new
genetic score and we published that like
uh in the in the summer it's a rule of
let this effort. So now we made a
polygenic score um uh that that works
actually really well like better than
than the previously reported genetic
scores. You see here the results in the
European ancestry like let's focus on
the blue dot here like the explained
variance is now 17.5%
and we see actually it does pretty well
in other um ancestries
in central south Asian east Asian middle
eastern at mixed American but not still
not uh in in populations of African
ancestry. So that's definitely needs
more work and maybe starting point of of
predominantly European data is is not
the way to go. uh the prediction of
obesity has gotten better. So here are
the results in biomeds bio bank million
veterans program UK bio bank for obesity
class one which is BMI over 30 then
class 2 over 35 and class 3 is over 40
and um focus on these results here then
you see that the the area under the
receiver operating curve is is getting
pretty good so it's like 7 for just your
regular obesity and you have to keep in
mind like that obesity is still 50% %
heritable, 50% or 50% genetic, 50%
environment. So we'll we'll never be
perfect in predicting uh regular or
common obesity. So 72 is is pretty good.
And as we go to more extreme obesity, we
get better. And maybe that is because
more extreme obesity is maybe even more
genetic than just your common forms of
obesity. And we see this already at a
very young age. You see, it's like from
this is data from the Alps study from
zero to 25 years. And we have three
curves with the the people who are in
the lower desile of the uh the polygenic
score in red, the people in the top
desile in blue and then the average in
yellow. And you see already at age five
that genetic predisposition is coming
through. Um and it puts you on the track
throughout life uh to be heavier or
leaner than than the average depending
on where you are. Another thing we're
doing right now is is led by Victor
who's also here um is just building on
on the uh the the idea that genetics can
support uh drug development. We using
the giant data to to look in how how
many of the lossi indeed provide support
for uh gene uh for drug discovery. So
this is very preliminary preliminary
data. Um so out of the 9,000 LOSI we
prioritize 7,000 genes and 700 of these
genes actually are already the target of
either approved drugs or drugs that are
close to get on to the market but not
for weight loss. Um so the question is
here that how many of these drugs that
are approved or in in in the in the
process of of approval could be used to
for repurposing in the context of uh
weight loss. And then among the uh new
targets that are not currently um or
among the the new genes that are
currently not target for uh uh current
drugs, how many could be new targets?
And there we use the data from the uh
illuminating drugable genome initiative.
And here we see that again about 800
genes are predicted to be druggable with
high confidence. So maybe among those
there's maybe new anti-obesity targets.
Uh of those 700 so most of them are
anti- antibbody druggable and 100 of
those are small molecule drugable. Again
very preliminary data. uh but this these
are projects basically to avoid the real
task which is the variant to function
right so because uh remember I told this
maybe a dozen of variants associated
with body mass index that have been
translated into function but now we have
9,000 uh it's a little overwhelming it's
been taken a long time for us to really
write up the story into a a concise and
meaningful paper
um and maybe the real problem is is is
is
not just um the amount of data but is
also the phenotype. Some people have
tried to um shortcut the the variant to
function by uh focusing on rare
variants. Uh here you see a few
initiatives. Uh the giant consortium
here used the exone chip quite a while
ago. It was a cheap way to get to the
rare variants. We had 700,000
individuals find actually three variants
that are truly rare uh below the 1%
level including the two variants in the
JIP receptor. These are coding variants.
um a paper by Regeneron that combined
data of 600,000 people identified 16
genes mostly focusing their paper on
GPR75.
We don't know yet whether that's a real
drug target but they are definitely
working on that and then there's a
recent paper by the Cambridge group
combining data of 400,000 individuals
and their paper mostly focused on
bassoon. This is just to say that this
seems an an efficient way to to go from
varant to function within the obesity
field. Um but you still need a lot of
data uh for a few targets. Um so maybe
the problem is not so much uh with with
the amount of data. It seems that we
have a lot of data but maybe it's the
problem is really with the phenotype
body mass index. Everyone agrees that
it's actually not a very good uh
phenotype.
um because it's pretty crude and it's
far from the real biology. So in my
group we've really been focusing on
curating the phenotypes uh focusing on
more refined adiposity traits. Um, one
study is is focused on um, body
composition really and and tomorrow
Victor will uh, talk about this this I
think it's like an exciting study where
we look at variance associated with
muscle mass and fat mass in the same
direction or in the opposite direction.
He'll tell you more about that. I'll
tell you a little more about the
uncoupling of obesity from its
coorbidities and that that's coming
next. But we're also focusing on using
PETCT scan data from medical records of
Copenhagen Hospital um to to quantify
brown adapost tissue activity but also
other uh other depositive phenotypes and
that's uh very much in in development as
well. So we use AI to do the
quantification
and um we also focusing on fat
distribution. So obesity is is it's not
only about too much um adiposity but
also where exactly you will store it and
uh we also increasingly focusing on
biomarkers particularly with the
proteomics uh becoming increasingly
available. This this promises to be an
exciting field as well. So today I want
to focus on on this story and actually
just got published last week in nature
medicine and is led by Natalie Shami
who's here as well today and uh by JJ
Wang. So what we did is we did not do a
case control analysis of healthy obese
individuals versus unhealthy obese
individuals because there's a lot of
discussion about that but we we looked
at uh these phenotypes body mass index
body fat percentage and waist hip ratio
on one hand and uh these cardabolic risk
factors on the other hand. So lipids
blood pressure and glucose and insulin
and what we did is uh so this story
actually builds on a previous story
where where we use summary statistics.
So here we use individual level data of
mostly of the UK bio bank. So what we
did is we take a distribution of body
mass indexes. It's it's right skewed but
we made a standard normal a normal dist
a normal distribution with a mean of
zero standard deviation of one. And we
did the same for all the traits um and
also for the card metabolic trait. So
each phenotype is now on the same
distribution and um we made a new
phenotype by subtracting one from the
other. Say my body mass index is plus
three on the BMI side but minus3 on the
LDL side. So the if you subtract one
from the other depending on which one
you extract. Now I'm all of a sudden
plus six. So that becomes a whole new
distribution and now we did the G was on
that new distribution. So if I'm plus
six, it means that I'm a healthy obese.
I'm a person with healthy obesity
because I have a high BMI and low LDL.
If you're minus 6, you're the opposite.
You have may have a low poly index, but
you have a high LDL. And we did that for
BMI and LDL, but we did that for all
these possible combinations. So we did
uh created 24 new phenotypes. We did a G
G was across these 24 um new phenotypes.
We made sure that the signals we
observed are collocicalized and we ended
up with 205 new lossi in 206 with 206
independent association signals.
So just to confirm uh we then made uh a
score of these 206 uh lossi or 266 loi.
So we have the uncoupling score because
we really look at how adiposity is
uncoupled from these cardabolic risk
factors and we compare it with your
typical um unhealthy obesity score you
could say it. So red is is the healthy
score. Uh blue is the unhealthy score.
And you indeed see like if you do the
association within the UK bio bank
there's no effect on height but you
quickly see that um the um the
difference is particularly visible in
the VAT SAT ratio where if you have an
unhealthy score there's not so much an
effect and I should here's the null line
but if you have a healthy score you
actually have a favorable fat
distribution and you see the same for um
waist to hip ratio uh where the
unhealthy score is a source with a
higher waist ratio where the healthy
score does not have too much an effect
on fat distribution. Um it's more
visible if you look at the uh risk
factors where here is the null line and
you see that the healthy score lies
mostly on the inside uh on the negative
side. So the protective side of this uh
radar plot meaning weaning is associated
with lower blood pressure, lower glucose
levels um lower HBO and C triglycerate
and of course higher HCL as expected
whereas the unhealthy score is also as
expected uh lies on the the outside. So
this is just for confirming that what we
find is indeed healthy obesity versus
unhealthy obesity.
uh we do a FI was we did a FI was within
UK bio bank and indeed we see like a
nice confirmation that both scores are
associated with increased obesity but
the unhealthy score is indeed associated
with higher risk of um type 2 diabetes
hypertension and the uh healthy score is
has a protective effect of interest is
of course that the or the association
with other diseases um not the non-card
metabolic diseases that seem to be
associated with um weightbearing
diseases such as cellulitis um uh
varicose veins and so much. So it's of
course a bit tricky to call it healthy
and unhealthy because in the end uh the
risks of the people with a high healthy
obesity score uh they're still
associated with these these diseases in
the same way as unhealthy score. uh we
also confirm these results in uh
children uh focus on the cardioidabolic
risk factors. If children with a healthy
score and they're at around the age of
11 and 12, they already at that age you
see that they have a protective profile
compared to children with a high score
on the unhealthy score. If you look at
the card metabolic uh of if you look at
tissue enrichment analyses with the
healthy uh variance the it's
particularly the peripheral tissues that
show up adipos tissue abdominal fat and
so on but also cartilage adrenal stomach
uh whereas the unhealthy score uh in in
similar to the BMI score is associated
with um uh the central nervous systems
because of clearly different biology
that is being observed. We also look at
the proteins. We know from the UK bio
bank data that high body mass index is
associated with high protein levels
probably because this the bigger you are
the higher the levels. That makes sense.
And that's shown in this data from from
Sunidal. So when we looked at at the
scores and their association with um the
the the UK bio bank proteins um the
unhealthy score which has some more
power is associated with more proteins.
The unhealthy score is also associated
with 337 proteins. 28 are associated in
in uh are overlapping.
Um of the overlapping proteins 85% are
in the same direction. And this is what
you see here. This is somewhat like
there's three dimensions to this plot.
Um on the right hand side means higher
adiposity, higher cardabolic disease.
for the red dots. Uh but for the yellow
dots, it means like a higher adiposity,
lower cardium metabolic risk. And on the
left hand side, lower adiposity, lower
cardium metabolic risk. For the for the
red dots again and for uh the yellow
dots, lower adiposity, higher cardio
metabolic risk. Um so these 176 proteins
are they're actually consistent your the
traditional adiposity proteins, leptin,
fatty acid binding proteins. uh you see
them pop up uh in both uh at both plots
on the same time and the same like with
with some others on on this side. So
these recall these proteins are
adipositely driven. What about the 15%
others? There's about 32 proteins that
are actually going in the opposite
direction. So they will show up here in
the red dots but here on the on the
yellow dots and on this side on the red
dots and here on the yellow dots. So for
example um growth hormone receptor LDL
receptor APO um F uh FGF-21
um like too much data to really go into
the detail right now. Um but for us it
it suggests that they're they're not
driven by adiposity as such because then
they would lie on the same side but now
they lie on the other side and what
could explain here is that they're
driven by uh the health status the card
metabolic health status and then there's
another and then go a little faster.
There's 129 proteins that only show up
for the uncoupling even though this
uncoupling score has less power than the
uh unhealthy score. uh we see adipoq as
expected to show up uh lipoprotein
lipase myostatin so there's a lot of
interesting proteins that are showing up
to be associated with uh either score
telling us more about the biology
going a little faster um I showed you
like that we have one uh set of 206 uh
prote um genes that are associated or
variants that are associated with this
unh this healthy profile but actually
they also cluster within uh multiple um
subclusters. For example, here these are
the it's a heat plot. These are the 266
variants associate body fat percentage
and body mass index and by definition
because that's how we discovered them
with a protective profile with any of
these cardabolic risk factors. But you
see they clusters this cluster three is
a source with lower body fat uh lower
blood pressure. Cluster five with lower
glycemic traits. Cluster six uh with a
healthier lipid profile. Cluster one is
pretty complicated because it has a
healthy profile for triglycerides but
unhealthy for glycemic traits. And then
four, seven, and eight, they're actually
more globally associated with a
healthier profile. So combining u oh
yeah and then we did a variant to
function prioritization binatically
overlay with GTEx data and then in
collaboration with Molina also using
CS2G
and uh combining all that data and
knowing the the clusters in which these
variants fall and sort of having that
more refined phenotype for each of these
variants we were able to prioritize some
of these genes um better than we we
could without that information. So here
I'm just going through it highlighting
some of these genes. If any of these
genes are familiar like please let me
know because we're now working on like
the v the real variant of function. So
even though this study was published the
study is not complete and we're working
with Molina's team uh and one posted in
my group Molina um um uh uh Elonor
Manita is is here uh doing this real
variant of function in the lab with with
Molina's team.
Um this is just to say and maybe to
conclude that it's like uh gene
discovery is maybe complete but we
really need to work more on curating the
phenotype to get the phenotypes closer
to the biology to to facilitate and make
it make it much easier to do the variant
to function translation. So it's
important to just not forget about the
phenotype.
So uh just to point out that the biology
that we implicated with uh the the the
genes that we have identified are the
ones that we've identified before. Uh
but actually now with the with the more
data we we've we strengthened these
observations and we actually identified
a few new pathways that seem important
in the variant to function translation.
Just to say like identifying uh variance
is not hard but genetics may help
elucidate the the heterogeneity within
obesity or any complex trait. Uh we see
multiple loi that couple uncouple
adiposity from its coorbidities. uh
multiple mechanisms seem to be
underlying and by combining this like
better description of the phenotype with
uh the the variant to function
translation I think we may like expedite
uh the actual uh variant to biology uh
observations
very grateful to my team at CBMR at the
icon institute as well uh working with
Molina has been a a blessing like really
has pushed me to the next level of the
variant to function translation and
going beyond the bionformmatics uh and
of course also the oops the giant
consortium
um with Joel uh Herson leading it and of
course uh the funding for this work.
I'll finish here.
Thank you Ruth for a very very
interesting presentation. So are there
any questions from the audience?
So, so a couple questions R. So, one, if
if you were to filter genes um by just
the number of genes that definitively
have multiple variants uh that can can
be linked to um the phenotypes of
interest. Does that help um narrow the
list? So, I'll ask three quick
questions. That that's question number
one.
>> Question number two is I never saw GLP1
come up on any of your gene lists. So if
you were to do a retrospective on GLP1,
where would it have fallen out kind of
in in this list? And then the the final
question is on on FGF-21,
it looks like it goes in one direction
and then the other direction. So
increases risk of atyposity and and then
decreases risk of cardioabolic disease
or or cardiovascular disease. So if you
were to you perturb that, would you
expect uh differential effects across
those two phenotypes? Right. Actually, I
did uh the first question about
filtering genes. What was exactly what
you mean?
>> Multiple alals at a locus to help
whittle those down for
>> That's a good question. Actually, we
haven't looked into that. Um but indeed,
we are working on the variant of
function in the lab with Molina. Um
don't know what the process the stage is
at the moment but uh
[Laughter]
>> uh yeah.
Yeah, waiting for the data. Um, for
GLP-1 receptor varants, um, it's very
interesting with the 9 million uh, with
the 5 million meta analysis. It's it's
it's starting to show up. It's a very
nice peak on GLP-1 receptors. uh but
this is the first time we see it uh in a
meta analysis show up in adults is very
intriguing but uh a small well small
28,000 um individuals meta analyses in
children but but um in children before
the age of three GLP-1 receptor variants
are showing up there and that's actually
a phenotype BMI before the age of three
is not correlated with your adult
phenotype so it's very intriguing we
don't quite know what's happening so but
then we need 5 million people to find it
in adults. Um, and then your third
question I already forgot.
>> Yeah, it's true. It's like, and I didn't
mention it here, but these are plasma
proteins and um, these are still very
correlated phenotypes or correlated
observations. We haven't looked really
at the causality. Is FGF-21 up uh, as a
causal uh, or as a consequence or as a
compensatory? like there's a few other
of these proteins like LPL um and
myostatin that are in the direction that
we didn't really hypothesize would be
but that maybe have to do with with the
fact that it's plasma proteins.
So our next speaker will be Jason
Flanick. He's assistant professor at
pediatric ped pediatrics at Howard
Medical School and the division of
genetics and genomics at Boston
Children's Hospital and associate member
of the broad institute at mid and
Harvard.
>> All right. Um thank you um for the
invitation to speak here today and um
thank you all for um listening to me. Um
I'm going to talk today about a method
and resource um for trying to understand
mechanisms underlying um G-W was results
and also we'll see rare diseases too.
Um, and I've called this a gene to
variant approach. Um, because it comes
at the V2F problem from a little bit of
a different perspective. And that
perspective comes from our group's work
on genetics knowledge portals. If you
have not um, if you're not familiar with
our group, we build a lot of um, you
know, we work with a lot of communities
to make their G-W was data and
downstream work available um, through
public knowledge portals. If you haven't
checked out the association to function
knowledge portal, um, I'd encourage you
to do so. has a lot of interesting
results I think that's relevant to a lot
of the things we'll talk about today. Um
and this was a direct actual consequence
of one of the earliest um V2F
initiatives here at the Broad. It was
initially called the variant to function
portal and now it's funded by NHGRI to
be the association to function knowledge
portal. Um but our work in this area
kind of goes back even further to the
accelerating medicines partnership for
um initially type two diabetes and
subsequently common metabolic diseases.
Um and this was a consortium about I
think maybe seven or eight pharma
partners now over its course uh with a
bunch of academics and industry um and
nonprofits as well. And the goal was to
make human genetic data more broadly
accessible to catalyze drug discovery
primarily through um prioritizing
targets that had genetic support. And
one of the first projects that we did
actually as part of um AMT2D was kind of
a mini manual ad hoc V2F. This is way
before it was called V2F, but we took
all the type 2 diabetes genetics data
that existed at the time. We kind of
cross- referenced it with all these
other experimental data. It was very
kind of messy, but you know, after about
six or seven months, we produced this
report um with a list of potential
targets that we thought were, you know,
had very strong genetic support from the
genetic data as well as auxiliary
genomic data for type two diabetes. And
what I think was notable to me about
this activity was not that literally
every single one of these genes was
completely rejected by every pharma
partner that we worked with, but that
the reasons that they rejected them was
not because the genetics data wasn't
strong or they didn't believe that these
had genetic support, but that there were
a bunch of reasons that, you know, were
specific to each partner that just ruled
them out for like, you know, maybe it
wasn't competitive in the market, maybe
they didn't have an assay, it wasn't
area of interest. So there were all
these like very specific considerations
that each partner had that kind of they
could have told me in advance like we're
not going to be interested in that gene
if you prioritize that. So what that's
kind of how I thought about this over
the years is that we typically think of
the variant to function approach. I
think Ruth just illustrated this. We
have like 7,000 um LOSI. How do we come
up with technologies to map each one to
you know what it's implicating
functionally? um that's very difficult
to do and also a lot of these um LOSI
are not going to be of interest to a
vast majority of people who are going to
use them downstream and instead I think
of the problem more on the lines of can
we answer the question that if a user or
somebody you know not just pharma
partners but somebody who would be an
experimental biologist has a question
about the potential role of a mechanism
or gene in disease what can we tell them
about what human genetics says about it
and if you think about this is this is
you know while it's flipping the
question on its head, it's still using
the same data. But you can imagine many
cases where even if you don't haven't
definitively mapped every single variant
that informs on the function and you
maybe even there isn't a genomide
significant hit for a gene involved in
this mechanism, you might still have
information and you might have already
even solved the problem. So kind of what
I'm going to talk about today is how to
answer a question like this because I
think a mechanism we probably all mean
different things when we describe a
mechanism. Um but you know in my
experience most people have like a very
narrow range of interests. You know they
have like an assay that they work in.
They have investments that they've
already done. They want like novelty but
not too much novelty. So a very
complicated question like this. The
question is can we provide a resource
that enables people to kind of um you
know address this. So I'm going to walk
through a couple steps of how we do this
um and argue that I think with large
language models and really the amount of
G-W was data that we have across
thousands of traits now it's actually
becoming possible to provide useful
answers to this sort of question. All
right. So starting from the ground up um
I'm going to model a mechanism. Right.
So this is I'm not I'm going to be
intentionally very abstract and fuzzy.
So I'm going to define a mechanism just
to be a fuzzy set of genes. So I'm
ignoring anything involving like pathway
information, regulatory relationships.
It's just here's a bag of genes with
some weights. So all the context for
that mechanism, you know, like let's say
insulin signaling is the mechanism. You
might say the specific genes involved
might vary by tissue, it might vary by
context, disease state. those are going
to be encoded by completely different
gene sets. So what this means is we
might have like potentially an infinite
number of mechanisms that are actually
existing in the human body, right? And
moreover, we don't observe any of these,
right? We don't know actually this
precise genes that are involved in any
process that's really happening in the
human body. What we do have are a bunch
of experiments that we can do which will
produce a readout of genes and that
readout's going to be influenced by
whatever mechanisms that experiment is
targeting. So imagine you have like a
differential expression experiment in
the pancreas. People with type 1
diabetes versus healthy controls. You
might hypothesize that genes involved in
autoimmunity or insulin secretion or
beta cell growth might somehow
contribute to the readout of genes you
get from that differential expression
experiment. Okay? And while we can
observe like the true mechanisms, it's
trivial, not trivial, but extremely easy
to generate tons and tons and tons and
tons of these readouts, right? In fact,
there's like millions of them scattered
across all these different um bio
repositories. I work with a colleague
Avi Mayion um actually at Mount Si with
Ruth um who has built a ton of resources
for doing this. And while these are
biased and noisy and incomplete, you
would assume that like the label of a
gene set, you know, hopefully has
something to do with the mechanism it's
interrogating, right? So this um the
genes involved in you know annotated as
having abnormal gliposy glucose uptake
when you delete them in mice hopefully
inform on some mechanism that's relevant
to that. So you can think of this giant
matrix of like every gene by like every
readout you have. Everything's noisy.
It's incomplete. It's biased. It's
almost kind of like if you think about
it like a G-W was tag snip, right? So
like the tag snip is often not the
actual causal snip. Here you might tag a
mechanism with the gene set, but may not
necessarily be the causal one, but this
is still our input um information. So
what we're trying to do in the context
of V2F is when G-W was the readout. So
GB was going to um read out like you
know between cases and controls however
you define them a set of variants that
implicitly observe a readout of genes.
Okay. And we're trying to unpack which
mechanisms are kind of contributing to
that readout. Okay. Um and our goal is
to kind of go back from the G-W was
results to infer the underlying
mechanisms. So here's a statistical
model as to how you could model this. So
I'm going to I'll build this up from the
ground up going forward. So on the
bottom level we have a variable for
every gene set in that library. So it
could be a million of these. Okay. And
they have latent weights, the degree to
which they contribute to the trait. So
there's one model per trait. Okay? So we
don't know what these weights are. We do
know the gene sets and we know which
genes are in them. And so we have those
feed forward and they add on the log
odds scale to produce a probability of
disease relevance for every gene. So we
have 20,000 additional variables for
genes. And those probabilities are also
latent. We don't observe them. Okay. Um
we can put like and I'm kind of glossing
over the details, but you put
regularizing priors to make to kind of
handle like the super large scale of
like these number of gene sets. So what
you do observe are the variant
associations nearby each gene. Okay. And
so you need basically this is the key,
right? You need a model of how the genes
whether or not they're disease relevant
influence the associations you observe
nearby. Okay. So obviously this is a
very hard problem to some extent variant
to gene is like the whole thing we're
trying to do here. But I would argue
that while going from a specific variant
to confidently implicating a gene is
very hard it's comparatively easier to
given knowledge of a gene being disease
relevant to look at all the variants
nearby and model how their associations
change. And so we have a postoc in the
lab Alex Yamos who's working on this.
Actually a lot of the work that's been
done by people here at the broad AI
Price Ben Neil in particular over the
last decade have really worked out how
variant effects change in response to
like annotations that you know are
relevant to disease and you can kind of
incorporate genes into this model and
like again you know lay out equations
that are really just directly informed
by the work that a lot of people here
have done. Um I could spend like a whole
talk on this. I'm not um going to do
that today because I want to more focus
on kind of the mechanism inference here
and also this method is still a little
slow to you know use as part of what I'm
talking about here. So all the results
I'm going to show today instead are a
much simpler model of how variance um
effects change as a result of being near
a disease relevant gene. Um this is like
a very very simple is a variant nearby
the gene how far is it? It's called
human genetic evidence scores um that we
have a perspective on a couple years
ago. Uh again, I'm not going to go into
the details of this. Um I'm instead
going to go into like kind of how you
infer and what you get when you try to
back down and calculate the genes and
the mechanisms that underly um a G-W
was. So again, not going through the
details, you observe the G-W was variant
associations. You can then you want to
infer the latent gene probabilities and
mechanism/get
weights. Okay, you do that via technique
called Gibb sampling. I'm not going to
show the equations for that. and you
output a completely joint posterior
distribution over all 20,000 genes in
every gene setting and by nature of the
and again these priors you put on the
gene sets it's actually a very sparse
you kind of select out specific gene
sets in a way that's much more
interpretable so what that looks like
I'm showing results for like a heart
failure G-W was um you basically drop in
the G-W was it runs in about 20 minutes
um and um you get out on the the left
table is showing kind of those gene
level variables so that leftmost column
column is those probabilities of disease
relevance and those are actually broken
down on the log odds scale into effects
coming down from the um from the
variance. Okay, so that's what's called
G-W was log odds. That's how much
evidence there is from the G-W was for
that gene and then bottom up how much
are coming from the gene sets as part of
the model. Right? Everything's being
learned from the G-W was though. There's
no like you know like prespecification
of the gene sets. on the right is it's
showing the top gene sets that are
selected and these are remember they're
jointly fit. Okay, so they're all like
jointly modeled as to how they
contribute to gene probabilities which
is a distinct thing from fitting them
one by one which is done in most
traditional enrichment analyses and I'll
I'll return to that in a second. You can
kind of see like you know I don't know
how many of you know about heart
failure. I don't know much about it but
you know at least the gene sets and the
genes a priori if you look these up they
all they all kind of make sense. Um, now
one thing I also want to note is that I
kind of couched this in the language of
inferring mechanisms from a G-W was
where you have the snip data but if you
have direct estimates of gene
probabilities which you often get for a
rare disease for example you can run the
exact same model it's just here that
rather than you directly encoding the
gene probabilities you can get that from
like ofet or the genC and then you can
run the exact same model in any rare
disease right so this is like you know
kind of a rare form of you know heart
failure um you know cardiammyopathy and
you know obviously you can see from that
known log odds that's what we're hard
coding these genes to have a 95%
probability from the data but you still
infer the underlying gene sets and
allows you actually and I'm not going to
touch on this but kind of embed these
rare and common traits in this like kind
of gene set space which has a lot of
interesting implications so the method
for doing this is called pigeon um and
the name for this is prior is inferred
from gene annotations and that's because
the way um we usually I usually talk
about this in its initial motivation was
not to infer mechanisms but to just
infer um gene probabilities and you can
actually show that if you typically
think of genetic support as the
probability of genes involved in disease
given its associations nearby. If you
augment that to also consider its
annotations and then you fit that
jointly, you can kind of decompose like
the estimate into a prior that comes
from the annotations that you learn from
the data and then direct evidence
typically a base factor for those who
know basian statistics coming from the
direct data.
There's another interpretation if you're
familiar with the pops method. um you
can actually show that if you kind of um
do a couple of modifications to kind of
approximate or use shuristics to um kind
of truncate this model you can show that
you get the pops method. So this is kind
of a just a generalization of pops to be
probabilistic and directly fold in you
know both direct evidence and also uh
associations alongside the annotations
um which allows you to kind of you know
have a justification of what POPS is
doing when it's prioritizing genes at a
locust. But the interpretation I like
the most actually is thinking about a
new concept of genetic support which I
call indirect genetic support. So we
typically think of support for a gene
coming on the left just from the
variance nearby the gene. But on the
right you can kind of see that support
also comes from mechanisms that the gene
is involved in that you infer are
relevant to the trait and that's from
other genes across the genome that kind
of implicate the mechanism. So your
support for a gene actually comes from
the associations for every gene in the
genome with like the mechanisms that
they share kind of providing that link
as to how that information flows. So the
way I you know I think you can think
about genes that are relevant to a trait
is actually on an axis of you know two
dimensions right. So on the y- axis is
how much G-W was association
evidence there is for a tra gene and on
the right the x- axis is kind of how
much information there is from um the
you know just from the annotations. I'll
have more to say about this momentarily.
Um I'm not going to go through too much
of validation for this. We've done some
extensive validation. I'm just going to
um reference one which is this concept
of relative success. Um Eric Minnlel and
others um here at the Broad wrote this
paper a year ago and the headline
finding was basically if you have a gene
and it's near a published G-W was
association or a published rare disease
gene it's like 2.6 times more likely to
succeed as a drug target. Um and if you
kind of do we we worked with Eric to do
the exact same calculations and what you
see is for both direct and indirect
support as it increases this on
continuous scale you have it for every
gene in the genome as you go from no
support up to a very large number you
get a significant increase in relative
success. Um these appear additive so for
whatever threshold you have for direct
support adding indirect increases it
vice versa. Um, this is shown from just
like all of the annotations, but we've
also done this with like a time limited
where you only look at approval after
the date of which the annotations were
developed. Um, and putting it all
together, you have an uptick that you
know relative to like the 2.6fold
six-fold increase from like is it nearby
a published GW was hit. You get a shift
up when you look at like the comparable
like full probabilities and also of
course a much larger number of targets
that have support because you know you
have a lot of targets that aren't near
G-W was hits but have suggestive hits
and also all annotations that we're
inferring.
So we're still working on publishing
this method but we've applied it to
7,000 traits. You don't actually even
need full summary statistics to apply
this. You can run it just on a list of
known curated snips from the G-W was
catalog. Um you are welcome to browse
this um at um it's not publicly linked
from any of our portals, but if you just
put slash pigeon at the end of it, you
can type in any phenotype or gene um and
get a sense for how it's working. And if
you have any thoughts of this, please
I'd love to hear from you as we're kind
of working through how it might be of
interest. Um just to kind of walk you
through like some of the basic things
you can do. You can type in any trait.
you get this plot I was showing I think
I switched to coronary artery disease
rather than heart failure but you know
there's a lot of information in these
relationships right so if you expand any
dot on the plot you you can see like you
know the locus zoom plot that's in this
case contributing to this direct support
log odds of 4.26 26 which is like an 80%
probability and also all the gene sets
that learned that were learned from the
G-W was to actually support this right
so this is like a gene scarb one that's
kind of like in the upper right hand
corner of this plot so these are like
very these are all going to be your
completely well-known genes but you can
you know depending on where you go in
this plot depending on your interest of
novelty versus like associations you
know like things in this middle are
slightly more novel like just picking
out one like an example tspo you'll see
kind of where there's not a genomicide
significant variant nearby it. There's
one that's like near genomide
significant, but when you combine it
with all these annotations for
cholesterol metabolism, it bumps it up
to have like a probability that might be
higher than a gene that might be an
aector, you know, or you know, that gene
that's not clearly an aector in like a
known locus. Um, one thing I I can't
talk about, but I think interesting
perspective is that if you flip this
around and look at genes, you actually
get these incredibly dense fingerprints,
right? So you can almost just trivially
tell from you know across all these
traits for this gene that it's involved
in like heart um muscle function. So it,
you know, caused you to think about is
the real thing I take a G-W was and
define the phenotype and then I get the
function of the gene or do I just like
take the gene and look across every
trait and infer the function and like
actually an LMM is really good at
guessing just based on the phenotypes
what the function of the gene is and
that's before even getting that you have
these two axes right so like the traits
that have both direct and indirect
support or where you have a very clear
coherent biology but you know there are
genes that like you know I saw this on
George's slide where there's like super
well-known annotations but no
associations and kind of the inverse. So
you have these complicated patterns of
almost like these embeddings of these
genes I think tell you a lot about
function. Um but I want to return kind
of the remaining five minutes on back to
this question of mechanisms for for a
gloss. So if you kind of look at the
gene sets that are at the top of the
model, this is for again coronary artery
disease. You can kind of tell by their
labels that they're picking out
different mechanisms, right? So like the
cholesterol metabolism gene set looks
like it's probably a different thing
than the disorganized mioardium. So that
that one's a wiki pathway for
cholesterol metabolism. The second is a
mouse phenotype. Um this is very
different from traditional enrichment,
right? Because remember we're fitting
this jointly. So if you just sort by the
marginal effects, you get like nothing
but lipid traits, which is why, you
know, it's kind of similar to BMI where
we just see all the the brain stuff at
the top. That's because those are
marginal enrichments in a lot of cases.
Um, and when you fit it jointly, you
start to decompose into these orthogonal
different mechanisms. Um, and like you
know, if you expand these and see the
genes like you, you know, they are
completely different genes. So, you're
kind of segmenting these genes for the
for the G-W was. But the issue is that
gene sets as I mentioned are not
mechanisms, right? They're tags. You can
think of noisy incomplete bias tags for
true mechanisms. And so, here's where
though if you model it like this, right?
So imagine you have a matrix this I'm
calling the gene matrix that's the true
mechanism matrix as I defined it those
are latent you don't observe them and
then you model the gene set matrix as
readouts of those latent mechanisms okay
so we don't observe those but we observe
this gene bygene set matrix and if you
model this that you can show if like
these are plusone like distributions for
the entries a little messy there's
probably a better way to do it you can
use non- negative matrix factorization
to decompose the gene by gene set matrix
and get the underlying latent
inferences. Okay. And it's it's easier
to understand when you see the data. So
for example, um you run the heart
failure um results and you get like a
factor like this that loads on these
different gene sets. Now with an LMM
just based on the gene set labels, you
ask it what do you think this is doing
and can give you a little piffy thing.
Okay. So again, you're kind of
condensing, you know, all of these tag
gene sets on the right for going back to
heart failure into higher order
mechanisms. Okay? And you can tell by
kind of like the heart failure
hypertrophy is probably picking up a
different mechanism than liver lipid
abnormalities and etc. um to give you an
example of what they look like for each
latent mechanism. You have the list of
genes and those have loadings and then
you have you know so this is kind of
that original definition of a mechanism
I define and then you have the loadings
across all the gene sets. So those are
your annotations. It's what allows you
to interpret what the mechanism is
doing. Um that's for heart failure
hypertrophy. This is for liver lipid.
You can tell obviously you know very
different gene sets and different genes.
Again, they're all labeled just based on
the gene sets, but if you take the genes
in them and then you cross reference
them with like their fwases, you get
what you would expect in most cases. So
on the top, all those genes independent
data, right? Like in associate with a
bunch of lipid traits um from other G-W
was and on the bottom the heart
development abnormality genes associate
more with heart structure traits, right?
So ideally you'd probably build a joint
model that incorporates these patterns
of traits like Ruth was showing. Um, but
like you know, this is kind of
illustrating that the even with the bias
and the noisiness of annotations,
they're able to pick out stuff that you
can expect to see from the trade
patterns. Um, it's I really like
browsing these. I encourage you to type
in your favorite trait. There's some
really intuitive examples like you know
for waist tip ratio. It's a common
marker of um, you know, body fat
distribution. um you get mechanisms for
like the metabolic syndrome which
actually separates for like insulin um
hypoglycemia versus um dysipidemia but
also mechanisms like skeletal
development which of course would also
be relevant to waste ratio.
All right. So, in the final two minutes,
I want to return to this question.
Right? So, this is a really complicated
question that is not directly obvious
how you can just map it to what I just
showed you. But, LMMs are capable of
parsing this and actually doing a very
good job of inferring what the user
wants with whatever they want to type
in. But, I'm sure most of us are
actually using LMSM for this purpose,
but we're all aware they're only
searching public data sets. They're
searching, you know, text, qualitative
assertions. um maybe even not even
searching stuff and kind of informing um
using its only its training to answer.
The way you typically get around that is
through a process called retrieve
augmented generation where the LMM will
like be will fetch data from like a
vector database or a knowledge graph and
you encode your data in that and then
you pass that into the prompt and then
it can kind of like add additional data
to its prompt. But this is like a very
difficult like thing to scale. um you
need to kind of like manually take a G-W
was and like extract all these
assertions. So here now though you can
think of this as like what I just showed
you is this very highdimensional tensor
right where you have like phenotypes by
genes by mechanisms and there's like a
number for every single entry in the
matrix that's all completely uniformly
inferred right using human genetics to
calibrate everything ultimately and it's
it's still very complex. So like this is
just like a segment of that like you
know here the squares are like the
mechanisms and like the diamonds are are
like traits and the circles are genes.
So it's really hard for us to interpret.
But for an AI agent where you make this
available now the successor to rag is
called MCP um and you give it access to
other tools like internet search as well
as its own training. It's actually able
to parse these queries and actually
retrieve the information we've kind of
embedded and extracted from GWAS. And I
have to stop here and not really give
more details on like kind of the next
step for this but just kind of conclude
with an illustration that if you don't
even build a real agent but you just
give it a custom GPT on chat GPT you can
see at the top I just pasted in that
query and you can see it kind of like um
infers what you want and knows what
filters to apply to like these combined
indirect and indirect support based on
prompt engineering. it can then
contextualize that with like novelty,
drugability, the competitive landscape,
all of those things it knows pretty well
and actually arrive at like, you know, a
nice filter like helping you navigate
this data, you know, and again, it's
because, you know, maybe can't search
G-W was snips directly, but it can
search these higher order relationships.
So I guess um no I don't know if Molina
you're going to ask me but if a sentence
I would say um to summarize for V2F is
that well I think the problem of like
every single association can we map at
the function is hard I think the problem
of for a given function do I have
insights from G-W was that help me make
better decisions in the real world I
think there's an enormous amount of
structure already there and I'm actually
continuously amazed every time I run
these methods how much G-W was detects
at that statistical level. Um, if you're
interested in learning more, please
contact me. We're working on these
agents and hopefully on our knowledge
portals. You'll see them soon. Um, and
you can also contact me um our lab web
page or also our broader knowledge
portal team. And thank you. I'll take
questions.
Thank you very much for an interesting
talk and I would definitely personally
be very interested in looking into your
portal. So um any questions from the
audience?
>> Hi Jason. Uh I was curious uh the
linkages which are in linkage dis
equilibria when you put your indirect
support if a linkage is acting in one
direction in one case and in another
direction in another case how does that
show up on your gene scores?
>> Are you talking about snip linkages or
you talking about like the
>> snip linkages? So that would all be
encoded in that you know I kind of
glossed over it but that mapping of
given a gene knowledge of whether it's
disease relevant what snips are
regulating that gene and you would do
that disease by disease and like you
would use like the snip to gene act all
the work that everyone's being done here
all that has to be encoded in that model
and that can get quite sophisticated
which is why I didn't talk about it
today but the answer is you'd fit that
separately right now for each trait but
ultimately you would want to fit a joint
model of like every disease at the same
time whereas like knowledge of a causal
variant for one gene would inform that
it's causal for another related disease,
but that's computationally intensive.
So, we're kind of doing that post talk
right now.
>> Questions?
>> Yeah,
>> we discuss a lot. So if there's anyone
else anyone else can go um great work I
love it Jason as you know um I wonder
about the definition and validation of
mechanism itself which as you say and
acknowledge is massively noisy
particularly when you draw from gene
sets as a prior or proxy for mechanisms
itself and particularly when we're
talking about complex diseases
>> right
>> um so What are you thinking about the
next steps of improving the definition
of mechanism itself? And related to this
maybe a separate second question is the
looking at feas jointly modeling
phenomide association studies for a
particular target and drawing conclusion
from that is postulated across the
community currently and I think it's
very helpful to come to prioritization
of cell types tissues maybe cell states
>> I would argue though that the space of
physiological traits cataloged in bio
banks is limited to go down to cellular
mechanisms that are disease driving.
>> Right. So, okay. Um
I think you're correct that. So,
I define an experimental readout of a
mechanism and then I use the current
gene sets as like kind of the state of
what we are. But there's no reason like
your readout has to be a biased curated
thing, right? Your crisper screens and
li all those are actual features. So, I
think you could envision this almost as
like a fine mapping. Again this analogy
of like the current mechanisms are
tagged snips right the initial hatmap 2
was very biased so now can you like fill
that out with like more fine mapping of
those mechanisms for example um I think
second like yes I I right now we are not
really thinking it right now about how
to model more details of what's going on
within a mechanism beyond the group of
genes the hope here would be that this
would kind of get you at just the area
like a set of genes and then that would
narrow your search space and you're
ultimately going to have to do more
experiments. The feed loss approach the
third thing what I find really
fascinating is you can take like a
mandelian disease gene just run it based
on the genomwide association studies map
through this method give an LMM like the
just the pattern of associations and it
can guess the mandelian disease like
much more significantly above chance. So
what it tells me is that when you look
across enough traits, you can get at
like very very very specific phenotypes
and you
>> and you may not need to necessarily like
be as worried about a finding people
with that phenotype in a bio bank if
that makes sense.
>> It it makes complete sense and I
completely believe that it's um powerful
to predict the phenotype. What I wonder
about is the mechanism the mechanism
driven by you know at the cellular level
is this you know
>> so I can Yeah. Yeah. So like I just ran
a quick test yesterday like for plin one
right which is this rare disease gene.
It's involved in atapost expan right so
you give it just the feas plot you say
lmm what function do you think this is
and it guesses atapost expansion even
though there's no g-wets for it. So the
so the question is like is that a useful
definition of mechanism? I don't know
there's a there's a resolution at which
you're going to run out but I think the
answer is can you at least narrow it
enough and then like find math quote
unquote within that space to fill it out
more. It's kind of how I'm thinking
about it. But yeah, there's no
substitute for doing experiments,
obviously. Yeah. All right.
>> Yeah.