[applause]
Um so I'm originally in Boston this week
mostly to talk about power systems at
different events. Uh today is sort of a
you know side tour from power systems
where I talk about methods. Uh so don't
expect that but there will be some power
system applications in the end. Good. Uh
quick acknowledgements. Uh this work has
really been driven by my postto Feyron
Chao uh with different collaborators uh
from I guess three countries uh which
you can recognize by the flags uh China,
Italy and Sweden. So that's the team
that's been behind that.
Okay, I'd like to kick things off with
some perspectives on datadriven control
and I know this is a topic that
everybody has an opinion on. So please
take this as my personal opinion and
reading of the literature.
Um, first we should acknowledge there's
been a rich and vast history. I think we
can trace it back at least to Carl
Astramm and Hogland in the 70s when they
developed autotuned P controls of which
now tens of thousands maybe even
hundreds of thousands out in the field
tuning P responses on the fly. Uh, the
development of literatur has been
fragmented between different fields. Um,
system education for instance. But what
I want to highlight now are the two ones
namely uh reinforcement learning which
is of the newer kits in the block and
more classic adaptive control.
Uh there have been of course various
people that tried to build bridges.
Here's a very famous article by Barto
Sutton you know that invented Q-learning
that already recognized back in the day
that reinforcement learning is a
particular variation of adaptive control
and I guess also here from it uh there
are statements about you know bridging
the gap between the two. Okay. But these
have been sort of developing in parallel
in the last decade. Uh there has been a
common route to many of these approaches
which is uh dynamic programming. Okay.
The you can trace back approach in both
uh fields coming from dynamic
programming. Um there have been uh
attempts you know to bridge ideas from
you know approximate and neurodynamic
programming also developed here at MIT
over to adaptive control under the name
of adaptive dynamic programming. That
was around 2008 2010 uh mostly spared by
Frank Lewis. Um but that literature
somewhat never took off and faded away.
This crossing between adaptive control
dynamic programming or reinforcement
learning. I will later on comment why
not. [sighs]
I think the main reasons why this bridge
has never been crossed is mostly
cultural gaps. At least that's my
reading of the literature from both
fields. They just are going after
different goals. So when I give a
seminar in an adaptive control workshop,
they really care about stabilization. In
fact, most people work in depth of
control come out of nonlinear control
and they phrase every problem as let's
minimize an error coordinate. Let's
drive it to zero. So it's really a
stabilization problem. Whereas people in
reinforcement learning think about
problems in the spirit of online
optimization. You know everything is an
online optimization problem. And these
two of course clash with these two
perspectives.
Another one is how do you deal with
uncertainty? Of course control people
say oh you have to be robust. They solve
a minmax problem. Whereas in dynamic
sorry in a reinforcement learning they
would embrace this optimist in the face
of uncertainty. So you solve a minmmin
problem. Um also a bit difference in
culture. Do you embrace pen and paper or
do you embrace compute? And what are you
after? Are you after theory certificates
or are you after you know impressive
demos? You know that's so just some
cultural gaps why these two don't really
find together. So I'll make another
attempt to see if we can bridge the gap
and hope we can a little bit cross
fertilize ideas from both cultures. But
I think it's mostly cultural reasons why
these despite many attempts over
multiple decades have not found together
these two communities.
Okay. Um so the title of talk is about
datadriven pipelines. So let me review I
think four different classifications of
how you can set about pipeline for these
adaptive control problems. Uh one
distinction is the one of direct versus
indirect which is very classical and
old. Essentially the picture is the
following. You are the control designer.
You're the brain. You interface yourself
with a black box and you ask what should
you do? Should you build a model out of
the blackbox from the data a mechanistic
model do SIS ID plus insert
quantification and do model based design
that's the indirect approach or should
you just search for a control policy
compared with that you've seen which uh
nowadays people use mostly data
informativity and behavioral methods to
do that. So those are two different
views uh to arrive at the goal. two
other ways to classify the pipelines is
more like how do you run the algorithms
are the algorithms offline or are they
online and what I realized depending who
you talk to everybody has a different
understanding of what means online so
one is sort of episodic offline
algorithms that is you collect your data
in batches you decide on your control
policy you put it on a system you roll
out trajectories you get new data and
you repeat multiple times possibly
whereas what people typically understand
adaptive control is if the algorithm
itself is a feedback loop that is
recursive. That is you measure what you
get from the system. You adapt your
policy, you act and you repeat. So the
algorithm itself is feedback loop that
is non episodic and that's what I mean
by online. So recursive and with closed
loop real-time data.
Um there have been many well doumented
trade-offs on all of these aspects. You
know you can read papers and books back
to the 80s where people argue what is
better direct or indirect and uh you
know they're well understood by now. So
question, what are you after? Are you
after a robust stability or are you
after optimality? Uh do you care about a
modular pipeline that you can easily
debug or do you care about an end to-end
approach? I mean all of these have
merits depending on the problem that you
look at and they have different
complexity estimates from what you care
about like sample complexity, how much
compute use, how tractable it is and
people have been arguing about these
points over multiple decades.
I think the gold standard if you could
achieve it, I mean the set gold standard
means probably you cannot achieve it is
if you had a pipeline that was adaptive
that could adapt in real time that is
you know optimal ideally at the same
time robust cheap you know simple
computations and ideally direct reason
being people recognize that the
uncertainty propagation from data to the
model to the policy is too hard or you
have to do it very conservatively. So if
you can go directly after the policy
maybe that's what you should do.
Okay.
So, we've been studying this uh from
many perspectives or many years and you
know thrown all sorts of fancy tools at
this problem and demos and whatsoever.
But today I don't want to talk about
something fancy. So there will be no
deep learning or impressive robot demos.
I just want to discuss a very basic
problem and maybe the only problem where
we clearly understand what's going on
which is probably the most classic
problem in both fields. You know it's
sort of the benchmark from all of these
communities which is the LQR problem.
Okay, that is you have a linear system
in discrete time x + ax plus b u driven
by disturbance w you close the loop with
a linear policy u is kx the performance
output you care about this set is so
that when you squar it so set squared
would be the familiar xrpose qx plus
urposed ru and if you cannot say
anything about this problem then all
other problems are essentially hopeless
but for this problems you can more or
less understand the pros and cons of the
different approaches
so here's one way to post the lgr
problem. You want to minimize the
expected value of the long-term average
cost of xt + qx uransposed ru
expectation of a disturbance subject to
the linear dynamics and subject to the
linear policy. That's one out of many
ways how you can write down this problem
and people from all these communities of
course attack this problem. So almost
all these variations of direct indirect
offline episodic adaptive have more or
less been explored over the multiple
decades.
Um I was actually not interested in the
problem. I was s of working out a
tutorial paper for a tutorial for my
class. But then I realized even this
problem has some open gaps and it's
actually quite interesting. So he had
two gaps that identified that despite
multiple decades people have not looked
at them. I don't think they don't didn't
look at them because the problems are
too hard. It's just they didn't care
about them. For in turns out there has
never been any sort of direct adaptive
control attempt on the LQR problem.
Surprisingly, right? uh when I talked to
the people in depth of control the
old-timers they would tell me well first
of all we'd never cared about optimality
and the ones that tried to solve it they
didn't find the error coordinates to
stabilize so it's essentially a little
bit of a cultural mismatch
also when you look into the literature
of adaptive dynamic programming that
tried to bring these ideas from
approximate dynamic program to adaptive
control
none of these many many papers have been
written ever talked about the closed
loop you know it's all about algorithmic
conversions some policy iteration will
convert the value iteration will convert
to algorithmic conversion ions, but it's
not clear what happens in closed loop.
That's a question they've been
sidestepping. And I talked to some of
the people that have been writing these
papers in the late 2000s. And again,
they said, well, there was sort of a
mismatch again in the community. The
control community didn't care about all
these, you know, fancy approximation of
neural networks, and that's why they
published elsewhere. And these other
people didn't care about stability, and
that's why they didn't look at it. You
know, just some anecdotes that I heard
from people that were working on these
problems back in the time. But of course
curious uh if you had other anecdotes
why people have not looked into these
problems.
So today I want to revisit these
problems as a really old problems
classical problems but bringing some new
perspective. Um one of the new
perspectives to bring in uh it's
actually an old perspective that has
been rediscovered about 5 years ago is
behavioral system theory. So behavioral
system theory is uh you know invented by
Yan Williams a Dutch uh mathematical
system theorist who said let's not look
at dynamic systems as what if input
output maps state space transfer
functions whatsoever he said a system is
just a set of trajectories and we work
with a pure set theoretic definition for
instance a linear system would be in the
space of all time series it would span a
subspace it's time variant the subspace
some shift invariance properties he said
let's only work with this definition a
linear system is a subspace in the space
trajectories and how you characterize
subspace with models or with data is up
to you. Uh we will leverage a particular
par parameterization that has recently
gotten some attention among others by
plenary talk by probably knowers which
is sample coariance. So you build
empirical coariance matrices to
parameterize the subspace of
trajectories and that's sort of the
model in quotation marks that you work
with.
Um, and the other thing we bring in
which you know is seemingly obvious to I
guess the new generation like you get
new data points what you do where you go
down the gradient which I guess what
most people would do nowadays. It turns
out this idea was maybe outrageous in
the adaptive control community because
they did not consider that necessarily.
So we look into policy gradient methods
one of the working forces of
reinforcement learning. So you get a new
data point, you update your policy by
going down the gradient of this LQR type
cost function which has some challenges
non-convexity and so on, but these have
by now been mostly handled. And so we
bring these two different tools together
and see if we can from that build an
online adaptive control pipeline.
Okay, so here are the contents for the
remainder of the talk the menu. Um so
I'll talk about these learning
pipelines. Uh first only talk about
algorithmic properties, algorithmic
convergence. you know when would a
gradient descent on certain coordinates
with some normalization or so converge
and then I'll also talk about the closed
loop properties will this actually work
in closed loop or not actually the
answer is not necessarily you have to
adapt it a little bit and I brought some
case studies um from uh robotics uh
flight and power systems let's see if we
can cover them good
so let's go into the problem setup is
that it's very simple it's literally
what you could teach in a bachelor
control course but that makes it I guess
quite appealing because turns out not to
be not trivial.
Um, here's again the LQR problem. Linear
control policy around a linear system.
Uh, that's how it I wrote before. So,
you minimize over a policy K the
expected long-term average query cost.
This is not how you solve the problem. I
mean, you could try to solve it this
way, but people norally reformulate this
problem differently so it's easier to
solve. uh one reformulation that gained
a lot of traction uh I think I forgot
when probably in the 90s is when people
discovered you know we can attack this
problem through ricottian LMI equations
so we formulate this normally in terms
of what is called the controllability
grammarium so we write this in terms of
x * xrpost if you want so that's a state
coariance matrix and parameters problem
in terms of that state coariance matrix
let's call this one sigma
and then the cost function of xrpose kx
X would be the trace of Q sigma uh the
trace of K R sigma K and then as a
constraint you just have your leap of
equation which is sort of the steady
state coariance equation which you can
solve for sigma as you know there's a
unique positive definite solution to
that equation so then that's much more a
nice way to write this you can easily
convexify it put it into your
semi-definite solver and get a solution
so you can solve this with STPs you can
use contraction free equation or first
order methods policy violation
improvement. There's many approaches
people have developed over the years how
to solve that obviously and we all teach
this in our courses. So I don't tell you
anything new. [snorts]
So let me take a look at a sort of data
parameterization of that problem. Um
which again is very obvious but people
have only really rediscovered this about
maybe 5 years ago. So let's assume we
have a data from our system. Um let's
assume we have a a matrix x0 that
contains the entire time series of x
from x0 x1 until xt minus one. That's
our state uh data. Let's say we also
have a successor data. So that's just
everything shifted by plus one. So x1 is
time series from x1 to xt. We have the
input time series. In ideal world, you'd
also have the disturbance time series
w0. And all these matrices have to
satisfy the model equations because they
come from that model. Now of course
makes the problem interesting is you
don't know the W time series right you
don't know the disturbance [laughter]
and you need to assume to solve that
problem actually necessary condition for
serving LQR is an identifiability
condition so you have persistive
exitation that is your data matrix of
state and input pairs has full rank
which is sort of also the condition
under which you could solve at least
square problem
okay so it's just a reformulation
um and now let me tell you the let me
say vanilla approach to solving this
it's what is called the indirect
approach approach indirect certain
equalence approach. So use your data and
first solve a le square problem in an
inner loop. So it's formulated as a b
level optimization problems. So in loop
is figure out a and b by solving the le
square problem. So minimizing the
residual of your data equation. You take
this estimate and with the estimate you
go into the model based design. You
don't robustify things. You just take
this certain equivalent formulation.
Quite plain just abstract now as a b
level optimization prep.
Now you can do this of course um you can
write down all sorts of theorems about
that but I don't want to go there. I I
find this entire approach to datadriven
control a little bit lame just like I
would say 99% of all others for the
simple reasoning it's not very sporty
you do this all offline right I mean the
real problem is could you solve this
actually online you know can you not
separate offline learning online control
but do it in one shot okay why because
you would like to improve of course on
your policy online and adapt rapidly to
any sort of disturbance or timbering
nature of the equations so the question
is can you solve this in adaptive
fashion
And you know another fun fact I
discovered about adaptive control is you
talk to any sort of so-called expert on
adaptive control and ask them what is
adaptive control and you'll get you know
for everyone you get a different
definition and then it turns out
actually there's no definition everybody
agrees on respect if there is no
definition whatsoever.
The only definition I found really that
has been written down is one by so was
not an adapt of control person. He was
actually in the opposite camp and when I
talked to again people from before my
generation they said they were really
fighting each other. The adaptive
control people did not like sames at
all. Uh but he wrote down a very nice
definition in one of his last papers
before I think he passed away half a
year later and he defined adaptive
control by two monotonisticity
principles. One is you have to interact
with system and information increases
and the other one is of course also
control performance should increase. So
you want to improve upon the best
offline control that you construct with
our pre information.
I gave a similar talk in the IFAC
adaptive control workshop and they
essentially kicked me out of the room
when I showed the same picture. They did
not like him at all. They would say no
it means adaptive control is about
stabilization in face of uncertain
parameters. Um it has nothing to do with
that. So I guess you know there are
camps in there. I don't have an opinion
on that. I just want to say many people
would not say this is a proper
definition but let's let's run with that
because that's very much in the spirit
of reinforcement learning
and our desired solution would be we
want to have an adaptive solution so
that should work in real time with
closed loop data non episodic non batch
and ideally have a recursive
implementation and then we'll see if we
go indirect or direct and what the
merits are
and our idea how to find this adaptive
solution is very very very naive is we
just go down the gradient and see if
that works.
So here would be the block diagram. So
we close the loop with a linear control
policy and what we do is simultaneously
we do a gradient descent in policy
space. That is at any point in time I
collect my data and then I do a gradient
step going down the cost function of the
LQR problem which I would think nowadays
from a more modern perspective is the
most naive thing you could do. And you
wonder why why did people not do this
long time ago and I think the reason was
just again cultural graphs they didn't
care about
uh so it seems obvious uh what is not so
obvious is you know will this work so on
the algorithmic side will this converge
how do you compute the gradient actually
how do you compute it efficiently go do
you go direct indirect and in closed
loop do you have stability do you get
robustness or not uh let me just tell
you why it's not obvious to get
stability even if any point in time your
policy is stabilizing
At any point in time, the closed loop
system is different. Right? So you have
a sequence of stable matrices, but it
has zero implication about the entire
sequence being stable. So it's not
obvious that this would actually work in
closed loop.
So let let's just try it out before I
give you a little bit of the background.
So here's an example where we put it on
a little toy system with some
collaborators. So we have an autonomous
bike that we want to stabilize, drive
along. Uh it turns out if you just do LK
on that bike, it won't work. The bike is
a nonlayer system. it would just fall
down non face plenty of issues. Um so
what we did here is so we put around a
small feedback linearization controller
for a small bicycle model like it's just
a 2D model. We cancel out the main
linearity that wouldn't work by itself
but then we strapped around a linear
system uh this sort of adaptive LQR
where we go down the gradient policy
space and see if that work. So the outer
loop is this adaptive LQR.
So let's see if that
video is running. Yeah. So what maybe
should look at at is the sort of on the
side you see here the control gains and
they're nicely converging after some
iteration and we could actually now
stabilize the bicycle drives somehow. So
this naive idea of just online let's go
down the gradient apparently works and
for this example you could stabilize the
system. It turns out if you make the
control a little more aggressive it will
not work. It will break apart. So we
have to understand a little bit why and
when it works.
Okay
so let's go into different learning
pipelines. So here are the ones we have
explored and you know that's a big tree
of you know different directions you
could take. Do you go model based or do
you go model free and then you go down
the gradient. Do you modify the gradient
with some fish information or some
Newton metric or robustified? There's a
lot of variations you could take in the
problem. Um let me just do the most
simple thing first and we talked then
about maybe different paths. The most
simple one is the indirect path that is
use data to online identify your model
and then with the identified model you
go down the gradient and if you
understand that the others are also more
simple to grasp.
Okay.
So a problem that has a received a lot
of attention ever since 2019 when uh
Marian Facel sort of wrote a quite
similar paper on that is is the LQR
optimization landscape.
So let me introduce the main ingredients
here. So we have a LQR problem. We can
actually uniquely resolve the constraint
equation. It's a leap of equation. You
know the solution of the leapnov
equation is a + b k to the power k squar
and sum of all time. It's the gramian,
right? So we know the explicit solution.
So we can just think about this problem
as a function of k.
So here's what this looks like for a
simple example like a two-dimensional
system problem. You see this cost
function actually looks quite nice. uh
convex level sets seems like yeah
gradient descent should work in general.
It turns out this is a nice example. I
can also construct a two dimensional
examples where actually it's not convex
and it's not obvious what would happen.
So uh JFK is usually not convex but it
is differentiable and you can actually
write down the explicit gradient. It's a
formula above me is it to compute it you
would have to solve two leap of
equations. the closed loop
controllability grammarian and the
closed loop obserability grammarian the
fact that it's differentiable and we can
compute the gradient and this what the
gradient looks like was actually known
since the late '7s actually a paper from
MIT I think correctly who was it Mike
Ethes who was here right so early in the
70s people worked out the gradient
formulas and figured out it's
differentiable so it's nothing new per
se but one thing that surprisingly took
you know four or five decades is for
somebody to prove that this would
converge
And again I don't think because the
proof is very hard it's probably because
nobody cared about it because we had LMI
STP solvers so who created about first
order methods to solve that problem. So
that was in about 2019 I think when
Marian FEL Marisp and post of them
worked out that this gradient descent
would actually converge. So they worked
out this LQR cost function it's not
convex but it's cursive that it has
compact level sets you know it would
blow up when you become have
unstabilizing gains. It's smooth meaning
the derivative is actually lips
continuous. You can actually formally
show the hashness bounded and this has a
property was called gradient dominance
that is you could upper bound the cost
function J of K by the optimizer plus a
constant times the gradient squared and
these three ingredients together would
tell you if you initialize yourself at a
stabilized policy you converge. So that
took from the 1970s until today until
somebody showed that. But again I think
it's just because nobody cared about it.
So the formal result is following. So we
think about this J ofK the LQR cost and
then you know there's a few people that
worked on that. There's a nice survey
paper from Lena Tamil and others that
shows yes if you do gradient descent on
the LQR cost if initially stabilizing
policy then gradient descent will
actually converge with a linear rate to
the optimum.
Okay so we know gradient descent would
work and that's sort of one way how we
could now possibly build an adaptive
pipeline.
uh namely you know you collect your data
you collect your matrices of the x0 time
series the x1 time series everything
shifted by plus one the input time
series you update your model so you do
for instance a recursively square or a
meanly square step and then you compute
the two uh gramians and then you just do
the gra and you repeat okay so this is
one thing you could do and that actually
um well at least the algorithm would
converge but it's not clear if the
closed loop converges
So that's sort of the vanilla idea how
to approach it. Uh it turns out maybe
that's not the best way to do. So people
develop different results. One is what
is became known as the huer algorithm.
Essentially it's going down the gradient
in the hessen metric. Okay. So you don't
go down just gradient. You premultiply
it by the inverse hash or an
approximation thereof.
So you would premultiply the gradient by
some matrix m of k that approximates the
hash matrix. And if you go down in the
hash direction, you get a much quicker
path to conversions because you're not
always, you know, just like grades
orthogonal to the level sets. Whereas if
you go down the hash direction, you take
a straight path at least for objective.
Um so again people worked out many
variations of that and proofs. Uh but it
turns out this um Hu algorithm which is
iterative policy validation and policy
improvement would actually be the same
as an approximate uh uh descent in the
Newton direction.
Another premultiplier you could take is
an inverse fish information matrix. Um
you know that picture I it is not
necessary going down the gradient
inverse fish information matrix but nice
to illustrate what's going on. If you
just follow the gradient may take a very
long path to the objective. Maybe you
should also bias the gradient in the
direction where you have the largest
variance
and that's why you multiply it with
something like the inverse fish matrix
to explore essentially go where variance
is large. It turns out the LQR problem
you don't actually have to compute any
fish information. You can just post
multiply the gradient by the inverse
coariance. Okay, but inverse solution
sigma of your leopath equation and
that's very easy to evaluate. Turns out
actually if you want to that's gradient
you just comput one leop equation. So
it's very efficient and simple.
So there's maybe better ways than just
pure gradient descent.
But this is all indirect.
And so the question that we've been
asking is can you also do this direct?
Can you compute the gradient without
first identifying model and if so what
are the benefits of possibly doing okay
[snorts] and that's where we use this
behavioral system theory and coariance
parameterization.
So let let me first tell you why I mean
why do you want to go indirect? It turns
out for for two reasons indirect is of
preferred first is uncertainty
propagation. So you want to avoid
propagating uncertainty from your data
to your model to your control policy.
Can you sidestep that and go directly
for the policy? The other one often
brought up in SIS modification is to
avoid the bias error. So now this is in
state feedback but input output setting.
The hardest part about SIS ID is
actually what is called model order
selection is you choose a model class
and then you get a bias error because
inevitably you always choose the wrong
class. And if you do a direct approach,
you don't encounter that bias error. You
might get better policies.
So what people who classic do if I look
at my colleagues in reinforcement
learning um let's say let's estimate the
gradient with zero order methods
something as simple as let's use a
finite difference approximation pro left
probe it right take the difference
divided by two and there you go or you
know in higher dimensions you would
evaluate j of k plus a random direction
u sampled uniformly in you know with
some radius r uh compare two different
points and then go in the direction you
use. So this would be a directional
gradient and in expectation this will
recover actually a true gradient
and you that's sort of just a zero
optimization.
This works well in expectation. The
problem is following you have need to
take many samples because you don't
cannot take an expectation. You have to
average. But every time you want to
evaluate J of K. You know what is J of
K? It's the infinite horizon cost
function where you just need a long
enough trajectory to somewhat decently
evaluate that. Okay, so here's some of
the sample complexity estimates. Say we
have a fourth order system, just fourth
order. We want to get within 1% of
optimality. It turns if you want to get
there, you need in total like a 100
trajectories each of length 140,000. So
somewhere 10 to the 7 trajectories to
get to, you know, 1% optimality for a
fourth order system.
which somewhat kills this idea for me.
Why would you ever do you know blackbox
gradient descent? Okay. Um so you can do
it if you have a simulator and a lot of
time but it's not at all suited for any
sort of you know adaptive control
problem where you have to in real time
interact with the system. You cannot do
10^ the 7 times probing before you take
a step. That wouldn't fly. It's episodic
and more or less it's useless. Right? So
this idea of doing model free gradient
descent you cannot implement that.
Um so that's where you call this sample
coariance parameterization to rescue to
see can we actually compute the gradient
with only a single interaction with the
system. Can we also get the gradient
estimate
so
here's what I do again let me pull out
this equation that parameterizes the
problem. So I leave you know uncertainty
aside from now so there's no w I'll
bring it back in later. Let me just
explain to you the detistic case. So we
have our three data matrices X0 and X1
state and successor state and the input
time series. We know they're related by
this red box here.
Let me formulate the sort of the
empirical sample coariances. So let me
multiply data matrix time data matrix
transpose divided by the length of the
time series. This would be the state
input coariance. I'll call this one
lambda.
Let me also form the coariance with the
successor state. I call this one x1.
Okay. Now we just have two coariances
for um both the the state input and with
the successor state.
Um since the coariance matrix due to
posist exitation example is positive
definite I can use the coarian matrix to
perform a clever coordinate
transformation to go from policy space
to another space. In particular since
this matrix here is positive definite I
can rewrite a vector that contain or
matrix that contains k the unknown
policy and identity. uh formulate this
into another variable V. I just use this
coordinate transformation. Okay, yeah,
you can do this, but why why would you
do this? Why would you care?
So, here's like one line of a little bit
of linear algebra that maybe shows you
why you care about this.
What you're interested in if you want to
solve any sort of linear optimal control
problem, explicit feedback policies, you
want to know a plus bk because a plus bk
is the one thing that enters all of your
LMIS or recut equations. If you know how
to parameterize a plus bk, you're in
shape. So can we parameterize a plus bk
just by data?
So the way we do this, we write a plus
bk as b a ki. [snorts]
Now we pull out this green matrix. Okay,
b ki is our coariance matrix time v. So
that's going to new coordinates time v.
Now notice that here b * a time the
input and state time z. Oh, that's the
red box up here. That's the right hand
side of the red box.
So I use the red box and say oh this is
x1 my successor state time series times
my state input time series which again I
recognize as my successor coariance
and now I've written it in terms of the
successor coariance which all like cheap
linear algebra tricks and you wonder why
why the hell would you do this? The
takeaway is I can now take any sort of
modelbased control design formulation
and replace the A plus BK in my LMIS by
the expression above me. So I can take
any of my favorite formulations and
replace a plus bk by this successor
coariance time v and you know the green
equation here. I can do this for conman
filtering when I have a plus lc for h
infinity design lqr whatever you can
replace all of the lmis if you want by
that in in principle at least you still
have to solve them
um so there have been many people you
know exploring this coariance
printerization over many years and most
classic in stocastic realization theory
but also now more and more people look
into this um it seems like a clever
parameterization for these problems
so the idea for this coance I take my
formulation of the problem we have the a
plus bk and I replace a plus pk by this
successor coariance and my
reparameterization
and this is what it looks like okay so
now I have a problem that is formulated
only in terms of data matrices okay
there's no more a and b there's also no
more k I mean I could elim explicitly
eliminate k from these equations not
hard and now I optimize um over k the
coariant sigma as well as this new
variable v turns that this does not
change the problem class. I can still
easily convexify this with some
parameter changes and I can still go
down the gradient. I still have the
gradient dominance and then all of this
holds. It's just another
parameterization of the problem.
So it's really the same problem as
before now just written in V
coordinates. It's not anymore in policy
coordinates.
And sigma and K can be explicitly
eliminated. They just go down the
gradient in V. It turns out compared to
the previous foration, there's one thing
you had you have now that you didn't
have before, which is an equality
constraint. Meaning you have to project
a gradient on the equality constraint,
but that's just multiplying everything
by a matrix. You just product an
arranged space of that equality
constraint.
So now you just do gradient descent in
that new space V in the new variables
and the only thing you have to do extra
is project on that linear reparization.
So there's this pi a projection matrix
which just takes care of this
constraint.
You don't have to remember all the
details, all the formulas, just
takeaways. So you can parameterize
problem in terms of sample coariances
and do gradient descent on that sample
coarian space
and you know I can easily evaluate that
right I just have my sample coariance
from my data and I could now evaluate
you know solve this sort of leap
equation in that new space compute the
gradient actuate repeat and now taking
the same fourth order system as before I
can actually now solve this in the
deterministic case so no noise to global
optimality with six samples
not 10^ the 7 six right which is I guess
a big changer right so you go from 10^ 7
times sampling system to six times much
much cheaper none of this adaptive it's
not online I just take the data once
offline but that's enough to compute the
gradient descent which makes suddenly
this gradient descent in a direct way
very attractive right you don't have to
probe the system of zero mess to get a
gradient view you just use the different
parameterization and directly get a
gradient out of it which makes it useful
Good.
Are there any questions so far?
Yes.
Please.
>> Um, initially you uh explain displayed
several things in a van diagram direct
and direct
>> and also uh yeah sorry I don't quite
remember but it was in the slides.
>> I was wondering if some of them might be
might be gradients. Um
>> for example from my understanding direct
would be a human figuring out an
algorithm
>> to implement.
>> Y
>> while the indirect is the more the
machine having to to adapt itself to
reality.
>> Mhm.
>> And for for example that could be a
gradient of human in the loop. So it
might not be yes or wrong but there's
different scenarios where one is more
fitting
>> as well as soft and hard logic.
>> Mhm. uh and also the time context
windows like offline and online that's a
yes or a no
>> but perhaps you could look at it as
sometimes we need longer context
sometime we need shorter context
>> so I was just I was just wondering to
hear to hear your opinion about you know
these as readings
>> sure so the the goal I'm after would be
now maybe to answer the last question
first would be I would like to update my
policy every time I do it and there's
many paths I can do it through models or
through coariance matrices possible.
>> Yeah. And but you could argue is that
the best thing? Should you update all
the time
>> or should you have some sort of
information criterion such as when
variance is high then you update your
policy? Um I don't have the answer. It
turns empirically it's not best to
always update every time but to wait
until you collected enough information.
>> Yeah, it seems
>> in some sort of event triggered fashion.
>> That's a problem of like how adaptive do
you need to be? And if you could get AI
to decide when to be more adaptive, more
with more entropy and more chaotic, we
kind of give up. we say okay it's pretty
chaotic this problem we want to be very
adaptive or if the AI can identify this
as a direct solution that it can do some
transformation to the near space get an
accurate prediction and we can ensure
stability
>> so there's kind of this meta problem of
what of how adaptive do we need to be
>> yes uh I I fully agree I do not have an
answer for that but we also recognize
this you know you can adapt every time
but is this the best thing to do it
turns out in adaptive control people
worked out these solutions of adapting
continuously more historically because
adaptive control came out of nonlinear
control but also people have worked it
out sort of an event triggered fashion
like you adapt only if state exceeds a
bound or only if you know variance
exceed a bound or these type of things
I've not seen any statement about what's
the optimal adaptation rate uh but
that's definitely a very important
question to ask
>> yes yes how often should you adapt uh
but I've not I mean I've seen many
results but nobody said this is the rate
at which you should adapt it
>> interesting
>> yeah
um Maybe here first from left to right
>> do we need any assumption on the on the
X and U data so for the youance
information do we need to assume that
like those extend what is coming from
the exact K or
>> yes so uh normally if you do adaptive
control the the big question is
posessive exitation uh which means
plainly is this matrix invertible is it
positive definite here I take a big side
step in terms I assume it I I could of
course try to satisfy it by always
injecting noise in the problem
persistently exciting and I have always
full rank and I can always invert it. uh
how do you solve if you do not want to
inject noise which again in
reinforcement learning people do not
inject noise they would say let's
explore let's go in the direction of
maximum variance um here just make an
assumption it is invertible his full
rank but how you assure that separate
yeah
>> as long as you have the full rank the
the um the the co then you can always
apply these two
>> yes correct but full rank is a necessary
condition for almost everything you want
to do yeah Ali
>> this reminds reminds me a bit and maybe
I I got the timing of the results wrong
but can you comment on how this relates
to the work of Deep Perses and Tessy?
>> Yes, absolutely. Um it actually is fully
derived from them. So I I skipped that
but it would have been here in the
bottom of the slide.
>> Okay.
>> So the Persus and Ty they work with just
the data matrices. They did not take the
coariance. The problem with working with
data matrices they grow over time. They
become longer and longer and longer. So
it's not like the right data format that
you want to use whereas the coariance
matrix always stays square and you can
do cheap rank one updates and so on. But
in principle it's the very same tricks
just applied
>> you still get a convex optimization.
>> Yes policy
>> correct? Yes. But it's very much just
taking their formulation and writing it
in this coarian space.
Yes.
Is there a case star the unique minimum
of your
first function or not?
>> Yes, in this case there would be a con
unique minimum
>> for the LQR problem. It turns out when
you go to other problem formulation like
LQG or H infinity this unique minimum
would not exist anymore
>> and you say this works only.
>> Yes, people showed a necessary condition
for solving the LQR problem is
persistive exitation
>> and in that case you don't the whole
thing. What was the question?
>> In that case, you have a stability proof
of the the whole algorithm. So,
>> yes, it will come later. So, this is now
a statement only about this algorithm
converges. But I did not talk about what
happens in closed loop.
>> Yeah.
>> When you were talking about results and
you mentioned the abundance of the hash
uh I think globally I I I think it
completely forced in this condition
because if you have a climate
needs to expose to it, right? I
understand it doesn't matter because
within the level sets sure is bounded
and then
correct because I also have an adaptive
scenario that boundary moves and it
might approach and put within a place
where you have a fix and spread
gradient. Yes, you're unstable.
>> Yes. Um fully agree two comments.
Formally speaking, everything depends on
the initial condition. like the bound on
the derivative depends on the initial
condition and this is all just for LTI
which is the cheap solution where you
would have an LTV problem you know
further complications come in like this
boundary is moving and
>> you think this could be something as
simple as a various steps size reading
set or that if I did my step size the
hashing point but I'm point
>> it turns out that's what you have to do
at least in the LTI case you have to
adapt your step size to yeah the the
curvature of the cost function and if
it's time varying if you have some up
priority uniform bounds on how curved it
is you could do this yeah
>> yes
>> yeah
to the what kind of adaptivity we need
>> so in some sense if we are convinced
that the offline version of the
algorithm in our case uh first identify
system and then do MQR control stuff is
optimal given a certain data set
>> the optimal or the ideal Perfect
algorithm would be I run this offline
version every time I get new data right
>> but it's in feasible because some
practical reason says computition are
too expensive to do that time and it's
not feasible so I have to
>> find an approximation of this version
with adaptive more adaptive version that
I can actually run at each
>> sure time so do I have a comparison
between
>> this method the method they are
presenting and the ideal case where for
10 but I can solve the offline version.
>> So three comments I have some plots on
the later but maybe three comments. One
is solving an least square problem and
solving the LQR problem at any point in
time is actually rate optimal in terms
of regret. I guess Maximovich proved
that. So it is optimal however in
practice it doesn't work. The reason
being if your data is noisy the
minimizer of some noisy cost function
you know goes around. So every time you
get a different minimizer, whereas the
gradient direction doesn't care much
about the noise. It's much less
sensitive. So with noisy data, you just
go downhill. But if I jump directly to
the minimizer, it jumps around, right?
And then you get like quite zigzaggy
curves. So it longs to show the
greatness more robust direction. Just
like in other control problems, say you
want to go down a leapna function, you
don't jump to the minimum. You just say
go down minus gpose gradient v or
something like that, right? because that
descent direction is a robust one. It's
insensitive to uncertainty or noise or
whatsoever. So while you know
theoretically it's optimal to solve the
problem at any point in time in practice
it doesn't work quite well.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. I I will comment on that later. But
if you had no noise in the problem, all
of these equations would break apart
because this unknown additive noise
would destroy all these nice subspace
relation. The way we will deal with
that, we sort of robustify ourselves to
noise up a posteriority.
>> Yes.
>> Going back to assumptions and sort of
initial results we showed on policing
gradient you there was a requirement for
an initial stabilizing control that
required that the dirt rate data was
small. So I guess the first question is
how small is is small for the learning
rate
>> and the second question is do those
assumptions apply also the sample.
>> Sure. Um yes you need an initial
stabilizing policy. Uh actually most of
these algorithms would need an initial
stabilizing policy. I think there's a
few like uh value function iteration. We
could start anywhere but most of them
don't need that. Um how big is the steps
allowed to be? It's just the standard
rule from the gradient centers. You
don't want to jump on the other minimum.
So it depends on the hashen matrix on
the lipous constant of the gradient. So
that's yeah
okay so we can also do gradient descent
in these new coariance coordinates and
we get away essentially without doing it
knowing the model for that just some
statements on that. Um
so fact one you can do this polic
descent in the coariance coordinates and
if you translate the algorithm back into
modelbased coordinates just for um let
me say intuition it turns that you get
again some sort of pre-scaled gradient
where the gradient would now be
pre-scaled by some data matrices as well
as a projection of parameterization
constraint but you know that's more for
intuition essentially it's a scaled
version of gradient descent if you do it
in this coariance coordinates
second fact which I is in theory is well
known but it would take quite some time
to prove it is if you do the now the
natural gradient descent this is
coordinate invariant that if you do
natural gradient descent so you do
gradient descent premultiplied by sort
of inverse variance then you get the
same natural gradient descent as in the
modelbased coordinates
um so it's invariant with that long
story short why are these two effects
interesting because you just recycle all
the proofs from the modelbased case and
apply them one to one here so it's a big
shortcut for proving
translate that for transformation into
English.
>> Um,
>> what does it do?
>> What does it do? Um, so it turns out if
you if yeah, if I would just take my
gradient descent in,
you know, in these coordinates
and I translate this just, you know,
with this green box into the K
coordinates, this is what it looks like.
meaning you don't just go down the
gradient but the gradient is
premultiplied by some scaling matrix
depends on data. If instead I would do
here what is called natural gradient
descent that is a premultiply the
gradient by the inverse coariance I get
the same gradient descent as in k
coordinates things don't change so you
don't get this pre-scaling
and again we use this mostly as a crux
that we don't have to write the proofs
again so we can use the old proofs and
apply them here
and you get all the desired properties
of course
now I want to go back to your question
here you said what do you do with noise
right uh so when you have noise in the
these nice coariance coordinates look
different. So if you were to you know
repeat all these tricks here that I
showed you that is how do I go from you
know the a plus bk into a new
formulation that just depends on
coariance coordinates and now there will
be a noise here like plus w that you
don't know but it turns out your a plus
bk is not the successor coariance time v
it will be something different
it will be so when you have your noise
it will be the successor coariance minus
some matrix depends on noise time v
where this matrix sort of your your
Third effect it's the coariance between
noise state input which you don't know
right so you don't know now the the
problem you should really be solving is
the one that is in red here right but
you don't know the disturbance right so
that's a little bit idealized
um one thing we learned from the
datadriven control literature over the
last six seven years is that you know
when you solve the idealized problem and
then you want to apply to the noisy
problem a very simple trick that works
quite well is just do the regularization
So don't solve the original problem but
cleverly regularize it. So what
regularization should we pick here?
Um so what you can do you can work out
the leap of equation that gives you the
stability equation
in case you were to know the noise. So
the leap of equation that would include
the red term you could work it out what
it looks like but of course you know you
don't know the noise. You compare this
to the original leapnov equation that
you're actually solving and you see the
two leapniff equations are differing by
a term that is depending on your
coariances you know on the new policy
variable v on the state coariance sigma
as well as the empirical coariance
lambda
and you know one way now to you know
when you solve the idealize the
amplification but you also make sure the
noisy one is true is just say let's
minimize the difference so it's a very
naive idea in that regard so let's just
regularize the LQR problem and as a
regularization term we throw on top of
it the difference between the noisy and
the idealized leap equation making sure
that if you solve one of them you also
solve the other that you also have
stability in presence of noise
and you know these are again some tricks
that people have already explored in
like some datadriven control context uh
you know in deep sea or by uh cloud
pairs and others that you know this is a
good regularization term you can also
write in model based setting then this
is what it looks like uh maybe That's
interesting. What is maybe the main
takeaway is the optimization class does
not change. You're still within the same
optimization class. You just add like
one more term to your objective
function, but it does not destroy any
sort of uh of the gradient dominance
properties and everything still goes
through. Instead of minimizing LTR cost,
you could minimize this regularized
cost.
Let me show you what the effect of that.
So I put in front of the regularization
term this lambda. And here's the plot
that happen shows when you change l what
happens. So if lambda is zero and you
don't regularize I think this like for
fourth order system 1,000 realizations
it turns out only 90% of the solutions
you get will actually be stable because
your data was corrupted by noise and
about 10% of the cases if you solve the
problem by noise corrupted data you get
an unstable solution whereas you
regularize it with this extra term
suddenly go up to 100% of solutions
being stabilizing and you don't need
much like 10 to the minus 2. Uh so that
was expected. What we didn't expect was
a nice takeway is that also your
relative performance gap would improve.
That is if you start regularizing you
get typically better solutions
which was I guess unexpected but we take
it
turns out also improves the algorithmic
convergence maybe not so surprising you
had an extra strongly convex term to
your cost function. The iterates are
more nicely behaved. Maybe that's
expected. Okay. So if you compare the
curves one are with and one without
regularization some are much smoother.
Um now should you always regularize?
Should you always make sure you solve
that problem? Um it turns out um yeah
you need to decrease the constant front
to regularizer but maybe that's not so.
So last main topic and Julia what are we
doing? Okay what happens in closed loop?
Okay so it's not obvious that this would
actually work in closed loop going down
the gradient any of these gradients.
Reason being every time you get a
stabilizing policy but every time you
have a different policy meaning every
time you have different closed loop
matrix if I switch system and you know
the famous joint spectral radio radius
problem the product of a whole bunch of
stable matrices is not stable
that's a problem that in reinforcement
learning they call sequential stability
um what's the takeaway so here's the
result you get in closed loop let me
skip that so one thing I have to
introduce is that there's a signal to
noise ratio introduced in the noisy case
your signal part is the lower single
value of the coariance matrix and your
noise part is the upper bound of the
coariance on the noise
so here's the result you get what
happens to closed loop when you analyze
stability uh let me unpack it there's a
few assumption one is you need initially
stabilizing policy
the other one is you need a sufficiently
large signal to noise ratio and you need
a sufficiently small step size which
maybe is not surprising from the depth
control because it's well known when you
adapt too fast bad things happen. So you
need to choose fish small step size so
that it works and in this case you get
actually nice convergence that is both
your state will have an exponential
convergence plus a bias due to noise as
well as your policy has an exponential
convergence plus a bias due to noise.
Okay, things work also in closed loop.
Um in the tool we leverage there's what
is called sequential stability which
boils down to asking you know along your
sequence of matrices they shouldn't
change too much from one step to the
other and that's why you need a small
enough step size and we've also been
applying this type of analys
reinforcement learning algorithms again
if you don't impose a bound on the rate
of change when you do it in closed loop
they go unstable so it turns out that's
a necessary condition
so let me skip those comments on
on the result maybe look some closed
loop properties which go back to one of
your questions. So here's what is a
benchmark example by Sarah Dean and Nick
Mutney and I compare different
algorithms. If you just solve the
oneshot problem that any point in time
you solve LQR and le squares and applied
yeah might work but you get horrible
transient lots of you know oscillations
because the optimiz is very sensitive to
noise whereas any of the gradient
descent methods would actually nicely
converge.
Um likewise when you look at different
data sets so quality data versus noisy
data the gradient descent would always
nicely converge. It turns out the
oneshotrop method give you quite high
variance and also what is called the the
gaus Newton so the hu algorithm the it
policy evaluation improvement would
actually also give you a lot of
oscillations the reason being it doesn't
have a step size you cannot make it
small enough at least not the vanilla
algorithm and that's why you get a lot
of oscillations so you cannot make the
step size small which I guess shows you
have to adapt sufficiently slow
last to conclude maybe I show you one
implementation we work on we looked into
a ones, but here's the one I care most
about. Power systems. So, what you see
is a very complicated block diagram of a
wind turbine connected to the power
grid, the power electronics, the
turbine, the grid. It turns out we can
leave that all aside because the person
that has to implement the controls of
the wind turbine does not have a model
of the power system, a dynamic model,
and does not have a model from the
vendor of the wind turbine. So in
practice you tune these out what are
called power loops of the power
converters essentially as a PI with you
know tune it until it works because
model based design is model based design
just existing papers you cannot do it in
reality because you just don't have the
models the data is siloed between
different companies they will not share
it
so let's apply the gradient descent here
a challenge is of course this model you
don't have the state but you can easily
construct a state realization uh non
minimal resolation that is you just take
your inputs and outputs and the time
shifts and from that you build your
state specialization. I guess it's what
you learn in class as controllable
canotic form just a time shifts.
You apply the gradient descent here.
[snorts]
So you see some oscillations from your
wind turbine to the grid. You collect
data. So you probe the system a little
with you know additive noise to get the
persistive exitation and you see uh this
would nicely converge. Whereas if you do
any not with no control you get
persistence oscillations.
What happens when you have a fault? So
everything is stable, everything is
nice. You change a parameter in the
system. In this case, the DC control
power set point would change if you know
what that is. Nothing happens.
Everything is stable. I mean you are at
steady state. Everything is nice. But
then you get a fault and the control you
have was tuned for the wrong model. But
when you start adapting this would
actually nicely converge compared to the
control is non adapted. So I guess you
see the benefits for depth control.
which brings to the end. So summary,
[snorts]
I I I talked about this gap. I think
mostly a cultural gap between
reinforcement learning and adaptive
control and I you know launch maybe
another N plus1 attempt to bridge it
which many people have done before. Uh
it was a very naive idea just go down
the policy gradient in real time see if
that works and you saw you can get the
closed loop stability if you choose a
small enough step size which is
important
uh for future work. um I guess from all
the obvious ones like improve the
assumptions is uh I'd like to go beyond
noise injection like persistive extation
by putting in noise I think is a very
naive idea can you do better can you do
something more clever than putting in
noise and there's also the question uh
asked by you namely we know what's the
best batch size when should you adapt
should you adapt every point in time or
is there some sort of information
criterion tells you when you should
adapt or not
uh and I don't have answers to these but
we're looking at those thank you Thank
you very much. [applause]