hello everyone my name is Derek Miller
I'm the vice president of platform
research here at deepure and I'm excited
to talk a little bit about some of the
things we've been working on so deepure
was founded at the MIT media lab six
years ago and since then we've raised
over $70 million we have over 30
employees we've started an automated
chemistry lab that can handle multi-step
synthesis and we have three drug
Discovery programs one which will be
starting clinical trial in
2025 and that is our brd4 bd2 program we
have multiple exciting indications that
we're looking into um we also have stat
6 which uh is entering late stage
Discovery we have a a couple exciting
scaffolds there we have an undisclosed
Target which we'll be announcing very
soon when we approach our pipeline we
have two things that we look at one
we're looking for an un unmet need in
the clinical setting that has validated
biology and two we're looking for
targets that have particular medal
chemistry challenges that we think our
next Generation AI platform is built to
solve so with that in mind immune
targets became an obvious uh uh option
for us to Target one because they tend
to have protein protein interactions um
these typically require larger and 3D
molecules a lot of these proteins also
have highly charged surfaces with
hydrophobic surrounding areas making it
incredibly difficult to build a
drug-like small molecule for or they
have very precise Target selectivity
issues so precise that even at times it
can be the difference between a
non-toxic uh uh outcome or or or toxic
outcome and these these types of
problems and going after these targets
are very difficult and most AI
methodologies struggle here for two
different reasons one if there's no data
at all um we've we've heard about data
sets and models uh um consistently it's
very difficult to go after these targets
with no data there's no binding mode to
understand there's no starting chemical
matter if we're going after an alisic
site there's no you know peptide or
anything that we can use as a basis
second if there is data sometimes that
can be worse because you get stuck in
local Minima trying to design around a
compound or a peptide and fulfill its
interactions that may be impossible to
build a drug for with that in mind
deepure has developed a technology to
address both of those issues and at the
heart of it we believe that if AI in is
going to be in drug Discovery and make
an impact it should make an impact on
the most challenging
targets with that in mind we have our
pipeline laid out here and it's composed
of about three different different items
um we have our pocket expander our
pocket expander looks at exploring novel
interactions and opportunities and how
we can interact with the protein we have
mulen which is our generative AI
algorithm um it designs compounds to
completely fulfill the interactions from
pocket expander we also in the mulen
process co-optimize for adme properties
ensuring that we're not going to hit a
liability down the road that's
immediately obvious and then we have our
inspired chemistry lab which is a
completely automated chemistry lab that
can handle multi-step
synthesis so the Innovation starts with
our pocket expander our pocket expander
looks for novel interactions and this
goes beyond just hydrogen bonds we're
looking for uh through quantum mechanics
through molecular Dynamics unique
interaction opportunities with a protein
that could deliver the phenotype that
we're trying to address and this will
create multiple hypotheses in how you
could interact with the protein um most
of the times it can be in in the realm
of 8 to 10 and we take those hypotheses
and we use our molecular generation
which is our reinforcement learning
algorithm that will try to build a
compound to fulfill all the novel
interactions and these compounds are
most important importantly not only
synthesizable with a very high
probability it's also cost effective
because one of the things we wanted to
do with our model is ensure that it
produces a synthetic path so it tells
you exactly how it thinks it should
design the
compound in finally once we've designed
the compound that specifically meets the
interaction needs we can send it to our
automated chemistry lab which we call
inspired chemistry which has a very high
throughput has 28 different reaction
types which which allows us to explore a
large diversity of of uh molecules and
can handle up to 10 steps very recently
we had a a completely an automated
setting we showed that we could
synthesize Pax loid um and that we have
a publication on that or or um output on
that and finally on the partnership
opportunities we're looking for two
different areas one's on our inspired
chemistry on the platform side when
we're developing new targets we use
inspired chemistry almost as a customer
and so we're actually taking customers
specifically for inspired chemistry and
working with a few to build custom
synthesis for them second we're looking
uh you know at collaboration not only on
some of the new challenging targets that
I was defining earlier but some of the
existing programs um as
well so I want to highlight our team we
have a diverse set of backgrounds from
machine learning to computer science to
biology to Medicinal Chemistry and
automated chemistry um we also have a
great group of leaders ship as well um
um and yeah thank you again my name's
Derek and if you want to interact
afterwards I'd be happy to