the MIT energy initiative presents
responsive design meets responsibility
for the planet's future senior syus
Horowitz tackles engineering projects
with a focus on challenges related to
clean energy climate Justice and
sustainable development written by
Deborah halber MIT senior syus Horowitz
kneeled at the edge of a marsh tinkering
with a blue and black robot about the
size and shape of a shoe box and studded
with lights and many propell
the robot was a remotely operated
vehicle ROV an underwater drone slated
to collect water samples from beneath a
sheet of Arctic ice but its pump wasn't
working and its intake line was clogged
with sand and seaweed of course
something must always go wrong Horowitz
a mechanical engineering major with
minors and energy studies and
environment and sustainability later
blogged about the Falmouth massachus its
field test by making some adjustments
Horowitz was able to get the Drone
functioning on site through 2020
collaboration between mit's Department
of mechanical engineering and the woods
hle oceanographic Institute huie Horwitz
have been assembling and retrofitting
the high performance ROV to measure the
greenhouse gas emitted by thawing
permafrost the Arctic permafrost holds
an estimated
1,700 billion metric tons of methane and
carbon dioxide roughly 50 times the
amount of carbon tied to fossil fuel
emissions in 2019 according to climate
research from NASA's jet propulsion
Laboratory
huie scientists wanted to understand the
role the Arctic plays as a greenhouse
gas Source or sink horowitz's ROV would
be deployed from a small boat and
subfreezing temperatures to measure
carbon dioxide and methane in the water
meanwhile a flying drone would sample
the air an MIT student sustainability
Coalition leader and one of the first
members of the MIT Environmental
Solutions initiatives rapid response
group Horowitz is focused on challenges
related to clean energy climate Justice
and sustainable development in addition
to the ROV Horowitz has tackled
engineering projects through daab where
Community Partners from around the world
work with M students on practical
approaches to alleviating Global poverty
Horowitz worked on fashioning waste bins
out of heat fused recycled plastic for
underserved communities in Liberia their
fais project also initiated through daab
is designing and building userfriendly
space and fuele efficient firewood cook
stoves to improve the lives of women in
Santa Catarina palopo and in northern
Guatemala through the Tata MIT grid Edge
solar research program they help develop
flexible lightweight solar panels to
mount on the roofs of Street vendors e
Rick Shaws in Bahar India the thread
that runs through hitz's projects is
user- centered design that creates a
more Equitable Society in the transition
to sustainable energy we want our
technology to adapt to the society that
we live in they said something I've
learned from the dlab projects and also
from the ROV project is that when you're
an engineer you need to understand the
societal and political implications of
your work because all of that should get
factored into the design Horowitz
describes their personal mission as
creating Systems and Technology that
serve the well-being and longevity of
communities and the ecosystems We Exist
within I want to relate mechanical
engineering to sustainability and
environmental justice they said
Engineers need to think about how
technology fits into the greater
societal context of people in the
environment we want our technology to
adapt to the society we live in and for
people to be able based on their needs
to interface with the
technology imagination and
inspiration in dicks Hills New York a
Long Island suburb horowitz's dad is in
baking and their mom is a speech
therapist the family hike together but
horo doesn't tie their love for the
natural world to any one experience I
like to play in the dirt they said I've
always had a connection to Nature it was
a kind of childlike Wonder seeing
footage of the massive 2010 oil SP in
the Gulf of Mexico caused by an
explosion on the deep water Horizon oil
rig which occurred when Horowitz was
around 10 was a jarring introduction to
how human activity can impact the health
of the planet their first interest was
art painting and drawing portraits album
covers and more recently digital images
such as a figure watering a house plant
at a window while lightning flashes
outside a neon pink jellyfish in a deep
blue sea and for an MIT wide Co
quarantine project two figures washing
the sunset over a Greenline subway
platform art dovetailed into a
fascination with architecture then
shifted to engineering in high school
Horowitz and a friend were co- captains
of an all girls robotics team it was
just really wonderful having this
community and being able to build stuff
they said Horowitz and another friend on
the team learned they were accepted to
MIT on Pi Day
2018 art architecture engineering it's
all kind of the same horo said I like
the creative aspect of design being able
to create things out of
imagination sustaining political
awareness at MIT horo connected with a
like-minded community of makers they
also launched themselves into taking
action against environmental Injustice
in 2022 through the student
sustainability Coalition SSC they
encouraged MIT students to get involved
in advocating for the Cambridge Green
New Deal legislation aimed at reducing
emissions from new large commercial
buildings such as those owned by MIT and
creating a green jobs training program
in February 2022 horis took part in a
sit in in building 3 as part of MIT
divest a student-led initiative urging
the MIT Administration to divest his
endowment of fossil fuel companies I
want to see MIT students more locally
involved in politics around
sustainability not just the technology
side Horwitz said I think there's a lot
of power from students coming together
they could be really
influential user oriented design the
Arctic underwater ROV had to be
waterproof and with stand water
temperatures as low as 5° f it was
Tethered to a computer by a 150 M long
cable that had to spool and unspool
without tangling the pump and tubing
that collected water samples had to work
without kinking it was cool throughout
the project to think okay what kind of
needs will these scientists have when
they're out in these really harsh
conditions in the Arctic how can I make
a machine that will make their field
work easier I really like being able to
design things directly with the users
working within their design constraints
they said inevitably snafus occurred but
in photos and videos taken the day of
the F of field tests Horowitz is smiling
here's a fun unexpected or maybe quite
expected occurrence they reported later
the plastic mount for the shaft collar
used in the motor's power transmission
ripped itself apart undaunted horor with
Jerry rigged a replacement out of sheet
metal horites replaced broken wires in
the winch like device that spooled the
cable they added a filter at the intake
to prevent sand and plants from clogging
the pump with a few more tweaks the ROV
was ready to descend into frigid Waters
in summer 20122 it was successfully
deployed on a field run in the Canadian
High Arctic a few months later Horowitz
was slated to attend oceans 2022 Hampton
Roads their first professional
conference to present a poster on their
contribution ution to the hoie
permafrost research ultimately Horowitz
hopes to pursue a career in renewable
energy sustainable design or sustainable
agriculture or perhaps Graduate Studies
in data science or econometrics to
quantify environmental justice issues
such as the disproportionate exposure to
pollution among certain populations and
the effect of systematic changes
designed to tackle these issues after
graduating in February 2023 Horowitz
will spend 6 months with MIT
international science and techn
techology initiatives MTI which Fosters
Partnerships with industry leaders and
host organizations around the world horo
is thinking of working with Renewable
Energy company in Denmark one of the
countries they toured during a summer
2019 field trip led by the MIT energy
initiative's Director of Education anre
danelson they were particularly struck
by samso the world's first carbon
neutral Island run entirely on renewable
energy it inspired me to see what's out
there when I was a sophomore horo it
said they're ready to see where
inspiration takes them next