Today I'm very excited to introduce
Mahel Chudich who's going to talk about
um AI in medicine from code to clinic.
Uh Dr. Chudich is a T32 postdoctoral
research fellow in precision in genomic
medicine at the center for precision
psychiatry at Mass General Hospital and
Harvard Medical School. He is jointly
mentored by Drs. Jordan Smaller and
Elvis Price and he earned his PhD at the
University of Oxford where he studied
computer vision applications of visual
neuroscience.
His current research integrates AI and
biomedical sciences with a particular
emphasis on psychiatry, genetic and
neuroscience. Um, and with that I
welcome our speaker. Thank you.
>> Well, thank you for having me. Uh this
presentation is going to be a little bit
different than the other primers because
there's going to be a lot less genetics
and a lot more AI. Um but to begin, I
think when we talk about artificial
intelligence, there's not really a clear
definition of what AI is, and I'm
definitely not an expert uh to be able
to define it. So I think for the scope
of this presentation and and the way
that we use artificial intelligence in
the mainstream I think really
corresponds to maybe some key
technological innovations.
Um and we can look at the Google trends
for artificial intelligence and there's
certain spikes that maybe will key us in
on uh what these innovations are. The
most obvious one is the release of chat
GPT in November 2022.
Um once that was released, it felt like
everybody was using the term artificial
intelligence. And the technology that I
think is central in artificial
intelligence as we know it today is deep
learning. So the structure of this
primer um we'll talk a little bit about
deep learning, what it is. Um I won't go
too heavy in the mathematics but will
give you a good introduction as to what
deep learning is. Then we'll talk about
convolutional neural networks,
generative AI and self-supervised
learning. So most of the data that we'll
be talking about in this primer is on
medical images. Uh why? because
artificial intelligence
um really I felt became what it is
through its ability to tackle a lot of
image data sets which easily translated
into medical image data sets and then
through then there were different
applications that came about that we'll
talk about in a little bit but images
were really the foundation for where
artificial intelligence built off of and
also there's some like it's very easy to
understand through just the images
themselves as to what these AI systems
are doing rather than maybe just seeing
some metric performance and and seeing
how that's optimized.
So to begin um we let's start with deep
learning. What is it? Well, in some ways
it's just a really complicated way to
fit a line. You have an input which are
just some numbers and you have an
output. Uh and and those uh inputs can
be maybe pixels in an image. It could be
the voltage of an audio waveform. It
could be a board game state. Um you also
have an output which are just other
numbers. And those other numbers can be
a boolean to determine whether
something's true or false. It could be
text. It could be a future board game
state. And then there's this mapping
function that we're trying to learn. And
that mapping function could be a dog
classifier. It could be a speechtoext
algorithm or it could maybe be a chess
AI.
And what essentially
deep learning is trying to do like any
learning optimization algorithm
um it essentially has some initial
parameters. is tries to see how
accurately it can predict um the thing
that it wants it to predict and then it
slowly changes the parameters of the
model to get closer and closer to the
outcome that we care about.
And uh this is very similar to linear
regression, something that I'm sure
we're all familiar with um with
genomewide association studies, but just
as a refresher for linear regression, we
can just view it as maybe a slope and a
bias. And then um we can try to optimize
that based on some cost function. So
that's a penalty to determine how poorly
your model is doing. In this case, it's
mean squared error. And then um in a
gradient descent algorithm where you uh
just slowly adjust these parameters,
there's a learning rate and a learning
um equation to to adjust the parameters
over time. And we can see on the image
in the the right how this line slowly
changes to best fit the data points. And
in a lot of ways, this is what deep
learning is doing. Maybe not over two
parameters, maybe over billions of
parameters, but this is a very similar
concept.
And in data science, I think we are all
familiar with this. Um, we can have
maybe models that are underfit to the
solution. So maybe the solution that we
want to know is quite complex but we
have uh less number of parameters that
we need to um solve the problem
accurately. Uh alternatively maybe we
introduce more parameters into the model
and uh we get a really really good fit
on the training data but we don't
necessarily learn the underlying
distribution because we're overfitting
to the training data and it doesn't
create a general uh solution. And then
ideally we would want a perfect balance
of these parameters to maximally fit
this data in a way that can generalize
quite well. But understanding what is
this balance of the number of parameters
that we need that's that's quite tricky.
So when we think about artificial
intelligence
um one way to think about it is how do
we make decisions? How do we know
whether a case or a patient has a
certain condition? How do we know um
whether a certain pixel in an image is
that of a a tumor? And one way we can
think about it, a very simple example is
just a classification problem where you
have some data points that belong to
class one, you have some data points
that belong to class two. And um the
first
uh solution to this and and kind of the
the start of artificial intelligence
came from this unit called the
perceptron which was a model of just how
neurons operate in the brain and action
potentials where it integrates
information and if the in uh information
integrated doesn't reach a certain
threshold then it won't fire but if it
surpasses that threshold it will fire.
Um, and that is kind of summarized by
you have some inputs, you multiply it by
some weights, you add everything
together, and then you have this
activation function, which in this case
is a step function.
Um, now maybe we can change it into
something a little bit more familiar. We
can replace that step function with the
sigmoid function. And we can see that
this equation then becomes a logistic
regression. And this is something we
should be familiar with.
Now
logistic regression can solve some
problems but obviously there are more
complex problems we would like uh a
classification solution to have um to be
able to solve. So linear reg um logistic
regression is really good at solving um
problems where the classes are linearly
separable. But if we see on the example
on the right the continuous exor problem
where the upper right and the lower
right uh quadrants are one class and
then the upper left and the lower right
quadrants are belong to another class.
Uh one line is not sufficient to
separate this data. So we need something
more complex. Now one solution might be
okay maybe we can add essentially
another perceptron to that layer and
have a perceptron that integrates the
previous two perceptrons and that can
give us a solution but it does better
but maybe it's not the solution that we
think of in our head.
So another possible thing that we can do
is we continue adding perceptrons. And
this is called a multi-layer perceptron
in MLP. And this is where we start to
get to the birth of deep learning
because we realize we can just make
things bigger. And if we make things
bigger, then we start getting to more
complex solutions. But of course, the
complexity of these problems can keep on
expanding. And if we see the problem all
the way to the right, maybe it's not
entirely clear what the solution is. Um
and to go about this what uh deep
learning tries to do is it not only
increases the width of the network by
adding more vertical units stack units
but also adds more depth. So more layers
of perceptrons
and when you keep on stacking these
perceptrons you enable more more complex
solutions to be learned. So deep
learning essentially is just
logistic regressions and multiple of
them in stacked in multiple different
ways. Over time we figured out ways uh
to optimize it more efficiently moving
away from just a sigmoid function to
some other activation units. But this is
the basis of deep learning. And kind of
the main rule of thumb was the more data
you have, the bigger models you can
train, the more complex solutions you
can learn and the better performance you
have overall. And one of the main
drivers for all this technological
innovation that we see is really
propelled by the idea that data keeps on
expanding in our society. We keep on
collecting more and more data so we can
train these bigger and bigger models. So
in the early days of AI, as you'll see,
a lot of what was being done to increase
performance was just to find ways to
continue stacking these networks.
And that brings us to uh convolutional
neural networks. Not always will it work
just to increase the size of these
networks. Sometimes it requires certain
architectural advancements
uh depending on the domain that you're
in. So convolutional neural networks
were what was developed for images and
started uh maybe its first applications
in medicine.
And what a convolutional neural network
does is it realizes that um an image has
translation and variance meaning that if
you take an image of a dog and you shift
that dog a little bit the classification
of that image doesn't change. Whereas if
you were to take that image and you were
to flat it into a vector, you're going
to lose all that spatial information of
that image. So what a convolutional
neural network does is instead of just
having a a one-dimensional vector where
it multiplies the weights of of the um
multiplies the pixels by weights what it
does is it takes the matrix it creates
it into a 2D matrix and it sec
throughout the entire image or it
convolves throughout the entire image
and it tries to find features at any
location throughout the image. So you
can imagine if it's trying to figure out
a dog face, it doesn't matter whether
that face of the dog is in the top left
of the image or the bottom right of the
image. It's translation invariant. So
that was a really key technological
innovation that allowed for image
processing to really become what uh it
to to have the success that it has had.
And also there were just massive amounts
of data that was widely available to
start developing these algorithms. So um
this was a really popular data set and
still is. It's called ImageNet. It's 1.2
million images. It has over 1,000 object
classifications. The images are RGB. So
um they're just natural scene images.
And it's easy to collect this data
because you can just kind of do a Google
search, type dog, and then maybe
download the top 10 dog images and that
could be your part of your training data
set.
And um what ended up happening to to
really excel on this data set uh there
were a lot of different perturbations to
architectures some of which included
expanding the architectural complexity.
So what you see in this figure on the x-
axis is the number of operations that
this architecture uses to compute its
final output on the y- ais is the
performance on imageet and you see this
trend where if the architecture is per
um performing more operations it
typically does better on this data set.
So in some ways maybe not exactly true
but like the more complex the
architecture the better it is but
obviously that's dependent on the
availability of large amounts of data
and that simply is just not the case in
medical imaging. There's different
problems that happen when we apply
machine learning and AI technology into
medicine. First of all medical images
can be a lot noisier than natural scene
images. medical images are
three-dimensional when we think of MRI
or CT scans and just the quantity of
data is significantly smaller than what
we can see for just regular applications
of AI um because we can't just download
you know a 100,000 MRI images.
So one technique that was really useful
is this idea of pre-training
architectures.
So um when you train a convolutional
neural network on natural scene images,
some of the these perceptrons or these
features that get encoded are really
useful features for image processing.
They can be edge detectors. They can be
color opponency. There are these
features that end up kind of compressing
these images into a way that's a lot
more trackable for later on layers to
determine whether something is a dog or
a cat. Um, but you can't learn these
features as well if you play around and
and train the architecture from scratch
on a smaller amount of data. So what
pre-training does is it says okay well
maybe we can take advantage of these uh
publicly available large data sets and
we can train an architecture on that and
then we kind of breeze the early and
middle parameters and we simply retrain
the final layers of that architecture on
the domain that we care about. So in
this way you're kind of getting the best
of both worlds. you're getting the
feature extractors uh using large
amounts of data um but you're also
fine-tuning you're adjusting this
architecture to your specific
application and this is when we start
seeing its utility in medicine so I
think one of the seminal papers in
medical AI was this paper in nature
looking at dermatological images and
trying to classify the different uh skin
conditions and its malignancy it had
129,000 clinical images of over 2,000
different diseases. Uh it used an
inception model which was something that
was shown on the previous graph. Um but
interestingly it was pre-trained on
imageet. Why? Because if the features
are useful for natural scene images just
like as humans we've evolved to be able
to adapt and and go through the world
and natural scenes. um it might be
useful to detect skin lesions and that
ends up being the case and when you do
that pre-training um what they were able
to show is that performance was on par
with all uh tested experts. So this was
when it was starting to challenge the
narrative that that maybe AI can do as
well as clinicians.
Now similarly um this was an
architecture used for radiology um to
pick up pneumonia and yeah I think maybe
in the mainstream people were saying
that AI was going to come for
radiologists. I think this was one of
the papers that started that trajectory
and essentially it's 10,000 X-ray
images. In this case, they have a custom
convolutional neural network. Um, but
again, it's pre-trained on imageet and
uh this architecture exceeds the average
performance of radiologists.
So, what's really interesting about this
architecture as well is not only does it
give a classification, but it kind of
helps localize where the important
regions of that image is. And the way
that it's able to do this is as
convolutional neural networks, as I
explained prior, it's cicading through
the entire image. In parts of the image,
the uh architecture, the convolutional
neural network isn't really doing much.
There's not a lot of activation of these
perceptrons, but in other parts of the
image, there is a lot of activity. And
the basic idea is if there's a lot of
activity in that part of the image, then
there's something that the architecture
is finding interesting. there's probably
something that maybe clinicians should
pay closer attention to. Um, so that's
one way of localizing regions of
interest in an image, but we can kind of
formalize it more explicitly through uh
image segmentation. So this is an
architecture called fully convolutional
neural networks. Instead of just
outputting one class for the entire
image, what it does is it outputs a
classification for every pixel in the
image. And what you can see here, it
kind of is able to segment the
differences between the dog and the cat
and the background. And uh unlike the
previous architectures where maybe
there's a hybrid between convolutional
uh layers and fully connected layers or
dense layers, this is fully
convolutional. So um the entire
architecture is just like essentially
going pixel by pixel and and classifying
or
patches of the image by patches of the
images and and classifying.
And you can imagine this is incredibly
useful in medicine. But there are
additional technological limitations for
its application in medicine. One being
that medical images are just a lot
bigger and that's problematic because
just there's memory constraints for a
GPU or a graphical processing unit. One
of the key hardwares that's needed in um
um medical AI or AI in general. And uh
this architecture came out it's called
the UNET. What it does quite well, and I
don't want to go into too much detail,
is it found a way to efficiently
represent really high-level
global features of that image um in a
very lowdimensional space. So very
memory efficient uh embedding. So you
can imagine it might be important in an
MRI image to know which part of the head
you're looking at. Um obviously that
spans multiple pixels and it's not
efficient to store that in multiple
pixels. Um but a unit tries to compress
that. And what we see on the right are
just some examples of more biomedical
applications of just segmentations of
different cells. Um obviously we can
take this a step further. we can uh
instead of just having 2D convolutions
and just looking at images, we can
instead look at 3D images and the way we
do that is replace 2D convolutions by 3D
convolutions.
And what we see on the right is a
conffocal image of a frog kidney and um
and and the right panel of that is the
3D reconstruction of that kidney.
And you can imagine that the
applications here in medicine are quite
quite big. Um there's constant iteration
of these architectures. This paper tries
to come up with just a general approach
to dealing with all these uh imaging
data sets. But you can kind of uh do
vascular segmentation, you can do tumor
segmentation. All of this is of interest
to clinicians.
And one application I I find really
interesting was the ability to do neural
circuit reconstruction. So if you're
studying parts of the brain, brain
tissue, uh you can get an EM block of
that brain tissue. Um and you can see
the edges of the neurons
uh but you can imagine just how much
data is there. So they were able to use
convolutional neural networks to
essentially follow the neuron throughout
its entirety and kind of reconstruct it
as a 3D object. And on the right you see
the reconstruction of the neuropill.
This was first done in the mouse retina,
but they also done it in the fly brain
and I think as well as the human brain.
Um, and now we're at generative AI.
um
and it's a little bit different than
um supervised learning and it's harder
to define in some ways. In supervised
learning, you essentially have some
input like an image and uh you have a
mapping function to some output that you
care about that can be a completely
different domain like you know whether
something's a dog or a cat, right? Um,
but what generative AI tries to do is
essentially create another type of data
point in the domain that you care about.
So in the way that I wrote it here, you
have some variable Z. So this can be
random noise or it can be you know a a
different type of data and you have a
mapping function that takes that laten
embedding Z and maps it into a new data
point X and this X prime uh it should be
thought as belonging to the distribution
of all other um like data points. This
will make sense in the next couple
slides. So let's say we want to create
fake images of handwritten digits. So
one of the key architectures which later
got expanded to images um is called a
generative adversarial network. And this
is when people started becoming really
creative with their cost functions and
and really allowed the explosions of
applications in AI. And what a
generative adversarial network tries to
do is it actually has two architectures
that are competing against each other.
You have one architecture that goes from
random noise to some fake generated
image. And then you have another
architecture that is a discriminator
that tries to determine whether the
image it's seeing is from the real
distribution or whether it's from the
generated distribution. And these two
architectures compete with one another.
So that the generated the generator
tries to come up with more and more
realistic images. And then the
discriminator needs to have uh in and um
needs to learn how to discriminate
between fake and real images. Um and
when they compete, they eventually
stabilize and you're left with this
generator that's able to just produce a
bunch of different fake images. So a
very simple application of this is in
uh handwritten digits but you can also
imagine that um yeah it can be for you
know natural scene images. It could be
for faces. Um we can also
uh kind of expand how we create these uh
generated images. we can essentially
condition what the generated images
based off of some other version of that
image. So in this conditional GAN um for
image translation image to image
translation we have a sketch of a boot
and it's tasked to kind of create an
image of that boot and the discriminator
again needs to determine whether the
sketch and the boot uh align with one
another but also is a realistic
representation of that translation.
Um
>> yes
>> going back two slides I just want to
understand the adversarial network. Um
so with the discriminator the
discriminator is working until
the two computers are only until the
generator is making things that the
discriminator is just saying are real.
Is that
>> Yeah. I mean, so you can imagine like if
the I mean they technically need to
always be competitive and there these
architectures are very unstable because
if the generator becomes really really
good at figuring out what is a fake
image then the discriminator just
doesn't have the ability to like learn
as much and then it kind of is an easier
test for the generator. So the generator
ends up not being able to produce maybe
the best images. So ideally uh they're
training together and then there's a
whole like literature on when to stop
these two trainings, but they can
diverge and that's really problematic.
So you can also get the discriminator
that ends up becoming so much better
than the generator to the point where
the generator is just unable to produce
any images because whatever it puts out
the discriminator is like no that's
clearly fake. So ideally they're like
learning together in a symbiotic
relationship of sorts and if one starts
doing much better than the other then it
becomes problematic.
Yeah. Yeah. Please ask questions if
anybody has questions.
So this is really cool. This is also an
application of generative AI. It's a
little bit of a different twist. This is
called style transfer. And this idea is
you have some image uh you know and you
have the content of that image but you
want to represent the content of that
image um in a different style like Van
Go star night and able the way that
they're able to do this is to minimize
the style loss constraint. There's a lot
of mathematical jargon in here. I won't
really explain it but this basic idea is
to take um kind of this texture of one
image and apply it to the content of
another.
And these ideas these concepts become
really useful in medicine when we talk
about harmonization. Uh so a huge issue
in medical image analysis as you can
imagine is uh the MRI images in one
hospital can produce slightly different
images than MR uh from an MRI at a
different hospital. And when you try to
do analysis uh you end up not
necessarily picking out the features
that you care about but rather just you
stratify based on population differences
between these two hospitals. So to be
able to harmonize the different sites is
really important when we start talking
about metaanalyses.
And there are more conventional or
statistical approaches to do this. But
we can also frame it as a deep learning
problem where uh the top row are these
images from some site and the bottom row
are images from another site that we
want the top row to look like. And the
middle row is just essentially the same
exact image uh from the top row but just
in the style of the bottom row. So it's
almost as if you're taking that patient
and you're reimaging them in the
hospital that uh you're going to do the
primary analysis in.
Um and this also becomes useful in
something called domain adaptation.
So let's say you essentially have two
different types of image of the same
concept. Let's say you have a PET scan
and you also have a CT scan and you want
to go from the CT scan to uh from the
PET scan to the CT scan. Then you can do
domain translation. It's the same thing.
Instead of uh figuring out the similar
textures between sites, you just find
the similar textures between the imaging
modality. And this allows you to
increase the amount of data potentially
um because maybe you don't need such
heavy and sophisticated equipment. Maybe
you can find cheaper ways to collect all
the data that you care about for maybe
tumor segmentation and then you can
translate those uh cheaper images into
the domain that you do end up caring
about.
And this isn't only for images. There
are other applications for domains
translation. This is going from RNA
expression to ATAC profiles. Um, but
they're very similar concepts and uh
it's just basically taking one
representation of the data and
transferring it to another
representation and it in some ways
allows you to imputee data that might be
missing which could be really useful.
And I think that um why this is really
important, why I brought this in this uh
primer is because a lot of research in
medical AI is really just a game with
different publicly available data sets
and kind of piecing them together to do
the task that you care about. Like
ideally, we would have just these
massive data sets for the task that we
care about, but that just doesn't exist.
we have maybe you know some data for the
task we care about and then we have lots
of data and something that's different
but tangentially related and what we can
do with domain transl uh translation is
we essentially can augment the data that
we have um by being really smart with uh
the way that we handle it. So you can
imagine that if we have an MRI image and
we care about tumor segmentation but we
don't have that many images but what we
do have are CT images and tumor
segmentations and CT to MRI images then
you can come up with a way uh to to um
pre-train your architecture without
having to collect more of the MRI and
tumor segmentation images.
And um I think this is an example that I
found really cool. This was presented in
the center for precision psychiatry a
while ago and when she gave the
presentation I was like this is kind of
the perfect example of um you know
playing around with the different data
sets and domains that are available and
in this paper what they were trying to
do is essentially going from nocturnal
breathing to be able to predict uh
Parkinson's disease looking at um just
kind of yeah breathing patterns during
night um and you can imagine there's
maybe not that much data to do that
analysis, but what there is is there's
relationships between nocturnal
breathing and EEG signals. And um you
can kind of play around with the
different um like paired data sets and
you can learn really rich
representations of these features which
allows uh for you to require like less
data to solve the task that you end up
caring about which in this case is
prediction of Parkinson's.
Okay. So now we're going to talk about
self-supervised learning and this is
when large language models um start
coming into play. But what self-superi
supervised learning tries to do is it
says okay well maybe there's a really
smart way we can just handle the data uh
to to make use of the data that we do
have. There's so much structure in this
data. So for images a really kind of
creative solution is okay maybe we take
an image we rotate that image and we ask
the architecture to determine its
rotation. And you can imagine that this
is actually quite a hard problem. Um
because to know that an image of a bird
sitting on a branch is upside down, you
have to understand what a bird is and
what the eyes are and what the branch
is. And in doing so, the you end up
learning these features that are quite
rich and you can use that as the
pre-trained features for your network
and then you can do the fine-tuning on
the subsequent task that you care about.
Um there's so many uh subsequent
applications to this. You can
essentially take patches of the image.
You can ask the architecture to figure
out what part of the image it's looking
at. You can um kind of show a grayscale
image and a color version of that image
and ask it to predict the other
representation of that image.
Um this becomes a little bit more clear
when we start talking about multimodal
learning especially in videos. So what
you can do um like with videos as you
can imagine um the sound corresponds to
what the image of that video is and you
can have a network that essentially
where you shift the audio. You randomly
shuffle the audio and you have the video
and you ask the network to determine
whether the audio is shuffled. And if
it's able to tell whether it's the real
corresponding audio or the shuffled
audio, it starts learning an
understanding of how a video should
sound like and in that way you start
getting rich features for video um
segmentation.
So what you we can see in the bottom
right is essentially uh the architecture
learning where the individual sounds of
guitar are just based off of the ability
to know whether the the audio of a
guitar was shuffled or not.
Um so in medical applications uh we can
have maybe a synographer that is um
looking at um a fetus and at the same
time speaking into a microphone and we
can do a very similar uh correspondence
test where we kind of shuffle the audio
and we ask the artificial neural network
to determine whether the audio is
corresponding or not corresponding. And
this ends up uh producing great features
for sub subsequent analysis. In this
case, it's just trying to show in uh
that um these architectures when you do
this pre-training can better figure out
the gaze of the the synographer. Um
yeah,
so another application of
self-supervised learning which I think
is a lot more ubiquitous is that of
phrase completion. So you can have a
sentence after running for miles she
finally reached the and you ask the
architecture to fill that in. Um, and
you can imagine that if there's a lot of
these sentences, you can kind of blind
the architecture to certain parts of
that sentence. And that allows for the
advent of large language models. Um, I
was always confused as to how you can
take text and put it into an artificial
neural network. Um, and OpenAI has a
really good demonstration of this, uh,
where you can see the words on the left
being tokenized and they correspond to
actual numbers. And once you have
numbers, you can, uh, train, um, uh,
yeah, it becomes differentiable. So you
can train architectures to map those
numbers into something more useful.
Um, and one of the key advances that
allowed for large language models are
these transformer systems. Uh, I don't
want to go into too much detail of what
a transformer is, but it's a way to
integrate sequential information and it
but it does so such that it allows to
focus on specific parts of the sequence
at different points in time. This
becomes really useful when we're looking
at maybe an entire paragraph and we want
to predict the word of the next sentence
but we need to know the context of uh
the first sentence in that paragraph.
But also transformers are used for any
sequence-based analysis. So, Alphafold
has been um uh gamechanging in terms of
protein folding and a way was able to do
that is through transformers.
And with the advent of large language
models, there's so many more
applications
uh to use it for clinical notes. So, one
really straightforward application is
patient recruitment. Um the idea is you
just take u a pre-trained model
something like from open AI and you
essentially go through all you know a
subset of patients and you try to see
which subset is eligible for the trial
that you care about. Um and in doing so
and and using LMS it allows for um
clinicians to it reduces clinician
effort by 42% which is quite high. Um we
also can train large language models not
only on English text. We can also just
train them on clinical notes to have a
better understanding of clinical
trajectory. These subset of large
language models are called uh clinical
language models or clams. Um, so a
really big clinical language model is
Gatorron from the University of Florida
is trained on 82 billion words from
clinical notes from over two million
patients. And in some medical
questionans answering tasks, uh,
clinicians were unable to determine
whether it was from experts or whether
it was from, uh, Gatorron. And then
finally, I I think maybe this is a very
exciting future direction
um is using these large language models
for outcome prediction. So for very rare
conditions where you have limited
amounts of data, it can be hard to
create data sets um that that have
enough samples to do the prediction that
you want. But there's some early
research showing that if you are able to
train just on the corpus of medical text
that there is that it has more
contextual understanding. So when you
try to apply it for these rare cases, it
actually does better at predicting that
outcome. Um and this is a potentially uh
you know useful
uh to expand artificial intelligence or
machine learning past just structured
data sets.
So overall, uh there's a lot of great
potential with AI and medicine, but
there are also a lot of limitations. I
didn't really have a lot of time to talk
about those limitations, but overall, uh
there's always going to be limited
amounts of data, especially in medicine.
Um there's a lot of different sites that
can uh are have those data points secure
and
um there's no public consortium of the
data available. So it's hard to run
really large models. So there's always
going to be innovation on how to adjust
these models for limited amounts of
data. But equally, I I think this is a
growing concern is just making sure that
the data stays private. Um when we kind
of have these large language models that
learn the corpus of text, um it's still
uh trying to understand like how private
that information is once it gets
absorbed into large language model. And
with all machine learning tasks,
mitigating bias and hallucinations are a
huge problem. If you train on a subset
of individuals maybe of a certain
ancestry and apply to different uh
ancestry, you will get performance
differences. But overall, thank you for
the presentation. If you have any
questions, let me know.
>> Thank you so much. Um
questions. I do have one online I can
start with. Um, what are some examples
of biological questions or problems that
are poor candidates for using OpenAI's
pre-trained models of fine tuning given
that these are trained on all of the
>> Yeah, I mean I I don't know whether I
know unfortunately I feel like that's
still an ongoing question because the
amount that it can do is probably more
is what's driving the research rather
than um what its limitations are
currently. So I think that's still an
unanswered question of figuring out what
exactly are its best use cases.
of them and they celebrate these great
research and so how I can understand
the a lot of the examples that you
presented where we're classifying things
or even like multimodal making decisions
but to accelerate scientific research
you know like how does one program that
or program architecture to that
>> yeah I mean I I I think that's like
that's the trillion dollar question.
Yeah, I
I think the angle that they're probably
going for is more of from this
generative AI point of view where um
essentially you're taking very defined
mappings from two different domains and
you're essentially doing something
that's greater than the sum of its parts
like taking the style of Van Go and
pasting it on an a photo of of houses.
So I think the idea is that if you are
just kind of training on all these
different data sets then maybe can kind
of pull ideas from different places and
create something more comprehensive.
Um but to my understanding like I
haven't seen applications where it was
able to
like be more creative than um an expert
in that field. Yeah. I think Terrence
Tao he's a very famous mathematician and
he has a blog post where he talks about
um open AI and chat GPT models in
mathematics and he basically said that
um they do quite well at solving the
problem when you frame it to them
already but I think as a scientist it's
the framing that's always the most
challenging bit so yeah
>> I have like 100 questions but is no one
in the room.
>> Um, okay. So, I think the style transfer
is really interesting, especially when
you have maybe batch effects across
institutions. I was wondering if those
if the results are robust to the data
set that you use as like an anchor
point.
>> Oh, like as in can you switch the anchor
point?
>> Make everything look like hospital A and
everything like hospital B and do the
same analysis. Are you going to get
similar results? Yeah, I mean I I think
like usually the reference point is the
one where you have more examples.
Um yeah, I'm not I'm not sure whether
you'll have that much variability. Um
yeah, I mean yeah I yeah I'm not exactly
sure.
>> Um and then how do these models do with
novel finding? So if you had some sort
of image for whatever phenotype and it's
it's a rare disease and it's never seen
it before, is it forced to go into one
of the bins that you're looking at or
are these models able to like flag it
say, hey, this looks something different
like someone
>> Yeah. So yeah, I think that's an
interesting question and in a lot of
cases like AI where it does really well
is when the input output is defined in
large quantities. Um I think for rare
cases I I think there's a lot of
experimentation of understanding what is
a normal distribution of maybe a healthy
MRI images and trying to understand
those anomalies because obviously you
won't have a lot of examples of what
these rare cases are but maybe have a
better understanding of what a healthy
distribution looks like. But I think
that's like a huge limitation especially
in medical imaging because sometimes in
these rare cases that you know in an MRI
image there's so many pixels but what
you care about is in such a small part
of that image. So there's just not a lot
of signal to train the entire AI system.
So this presentation was mostly focused
on where AI I felt has had the most
significance in medicine and I think it
really comes down to how well phenotyped
the data is. Yeah,
>> we have one more online. Is anyone
looking at creating scale open data sets
like Nomad of medical imaging data? It
sounds like one of the biggest issues in
the field is just getting access to the
data. Yeah, I mean I'm sure that there's
a lot of different um consortiums that
that are trying to do I I think the
issue is always with the identification.
Um but even then
if you were to
have a public place to and I think there
are um online tools and and websites
that try to consolidate all this
information um but there's always going
to be differences in the instruments
that are used between sites. um even
within the institution in 10 years time
we can have a completely different MRI
setup that will just change the types of
data. So you always have to be cognizant
of um the really the amount of data
that's available and you're always going
to have this game of constraints given
data limitations and even if you were to
consolidate all these different types of
data I think you'll never get to the
scale of more um like natural
data sets that are being solved in
regular computer science like uh natural
scene images or large language because
uh it's there's so the data is so
ubiquitous.
>> Great. All right, let's think our
speaker one more time.