[MUSIC PLAYING]
MEGAN MITCHELL: Good morning.
Good afternoon.
Good evening, whatever your
time zone, wherever you are.
Welcome.
As always, we'd love to know
where people are, who you are,
where you're joining us from.
To add a little--
I see some familiar faces,
some familiar names,
a few people who I know have
been on vacation and are back.
This is exciting.
But we'd love to hear from
you and share who you are
and where you're
joining us from.
But I suppose I should start
with myself in that case.
How's everyone doing?
I am Megan Mitchell.
I am currently the
acting director
for strategy and operations for
the Jameel World Education Lab.
And many of you are
familiar with J-WEL.
But, actually, this is an event
that we open to the public
and open more broadly
beyond just our members.
So let me just ground us there.
The Jameel World Education Lab
at MIT is a center designed--
our mission is education
designed for everyone to thrive.
And educators everywhere, as
I think everyone on this call
knows and feels, are
being asked to do
more, to reach more students,
to upgrade their learning,
to fuel the economy,
and serve the community
in new and unique ways.
And integrating technology
and considering technology,
I'm sure, is particularly
relevant to those
who chose to join this call.
So we work to meet
this imperative
by working with educational
innovators around the world.
And, together, we look
to disrupt the status
quo in education by creating
practical, actionable new ideas
that can transform
learning at scale.
We do this through
ambitious projects.
We couldn't do this without
our member organizations
and our staff and faculty.
Together, we explore new
ideas, share thinking,
what's the global context, local
context for the type of work
we're all doing.
And we do this through
workshops and campus visits
to MIT, sessions like
this one and really hope
to bridge the transition
from education
to the workforce in cultivating
innovations to better connect
learners to understand
what's happening particularly
in the technology space and
how that impacts all of us.
And so, today, you're joining
us for our first event
in our AI Innovation Series.
So welcome.
Welcome to all of you.
There are five events
in this series.
And some are public
forums like this one.
Others are designed as
interactive discussions,
just for our members so that
they can reflect on and react
to maybe the previous sessions
and share their own experiences
and what this means to them, as
they reflect on what was said
and react.
But also think about what
it means for them and share
with one another,
because this really isn't
meant to be a one-way dialogue.
This is meant to be a
space to learn together.
So for the members
on this call, I just
want to call out
that next week we'll
have a follow-on
to this discussion
where Hae Won Park, who's a
colleague and a researcher
in Cynthia Breazeal's
lab, will lead
a discussion with our members
around reflections and reactions
and really sharing.
And then for those of you who
aren't members, or members,
our August 22 event will
also be open to the public.
And that will be focused on
some entrepreneurial ventures
and people who are taking this
really interesting technology
and these innovations and
applying them in ways,
maybe in, we'll say, a more
commercial application.
So what's the building
blocks from the research?
And what's being done
at places like MIT
to the implementation
in the field?
And so, I think the potential
and the promise and even
the perils, whether they're real
or imagined of generative AI,
I think, have been--
I mean, I know they've been
a core theme of J-WEL's work
this year.
And I think even--
it touches on every conversation
we have, every opportunity.
And I think for a lot of people
in the world, this is new.
And this is something
that is just everywhere.
In fact, I was having dinner
with my nine-year-old nephew
last night.
And he said, Auntie
Meg, generative AI--
AI is everywhere.
It's exploded.
Yes and no.
It's been around.
We tried to talk about
that a little bit.
But when you're eating pizza
after a Little League Baseball
game and the topic
is AI, I think
it just shows how it's
crossed so many dimensions.
But I think it's been
real for all of us
on this call for a long time.
And so generative AI has
really been a core theme
of J-WEL's work this year.
And, in fact, in May,
about 30 representatives,
from across our
member institutions,
joined us in Cambridge for a
week of shared conversations,
collaborations, and workshops.
We brought in what we think were
very insightful presentations,
whether they were
from our members
or from folks within the
MIT community and even
some in-person demonstrations,
to really deepen
the understanding of what's
happening in the space, feel
collaboration, and the like.
And some of the key themes
that we felt that emerged--
and I think the pain
points we felt is--
governance in AI is
taking place in real time.
And for us, it was in higher ed.
I think we're feeling that
in every aspect of society,
whether that's university,
government, governance.
That's geopolitical.
That is what our political
leaders are doing.
And, really, baseline
literacy in AI
is needed for educators
across the spectrum.
And then, I think
some core tenets
that undergird all of this are
trust, governance, transparency,
and inclusion.
Those are building blocks that
organizations and institutions
need to think about and
consider and address
as they embark on these
types of integration
and thinking about
AI in their space.
And so, I think those are some
things that you'll hear from.
And we're excited for
today's conversation.
So, today, as I mentioned, this
is our grounding conversation
for our AI Innovators Series.
And so today you will hear from
MIT Dean for Digital Learning,
Professor Cynthia Breazeal.
And she'll give an
introduction to how
these types of
technologies work,
how students and teachers
might deploy these tools
and approaches,
and how schools can
take advantage of
new opportunities,
and manage the many
challenges we know we'll face.
But a challenge
is an opportunity
if you turn it
around when promoting
student-independent learning.
So before I turn it over
to Professor Breazeal--
she is a leader in this space
globally and a leader at MIT.
She is the director
of MIT RAISE, which
is Responsible AI for
Social Empowerment,
is what RAISE stands for, which
is across MIT research effort
on advancing and
democratizing AI
education, particularly through
K to 12 and adult education.
It's a collaboration
between MIT Open Learning--
Open Learning is where
J-WEL sits and lives within
the institution--
the Media Lab, and the
Schwarzman College of Computing.
RAISE offers annual K
to 12 outreach programs,
including a six-week summer
program called MIT Future
Makers.
They do the Day of AI,
which is a great opportunity
for thousands of teachers
across the world to bring AI
literacy into their classrooms.
And under her leadership,
she's launched these programs
to introduce students of
all backgrounds and teachers
to the foundational concepts of
AI and its role in their lives.
And so, there's where
you start to-- you
build in that inclusion that's
so important in all of the work
that we do and the
considerations that we do.
Dean Breazeal also heads the
Personal Robotics Research Group
at the MIT Media Lab.
And that's where she's a
professor of media, arts,
and sciences.
And her research focus includes
technical innovation in AI
and user-experience design and
understanding the psychology
of engagement to design
personified-AI technologies that
can promote human flourishing
and personal growth.
Professor Dean Breazeal is
also the faculty director head
that we work closely with at
the Jameel World Education Lab.
So, her work intersects
in so many places
and is so important to all that
we do at J-WEL but then also
the work that is
happening across MIT,
in this transformational space.
So now what I'd like
to do is-- actually,
before we turn it
over to Dean Breazeal,
I'm going to actually introduce
Bill Bonvillian, who is the--
he has the-- we'll call it
the "distinguished moniker"
to be the head of
our Thinking Series.
And I think if you spent
any time with his bio,
you'd understand why that's a
perfect Thinking Series for him
to be leading for us.
He's authored many books
and articles and chapters
on science, technology, and
science-technology policy
and workforce education.
And he's been teaching science
and policy at MIT since 2007.
So he's really been
integral in helping
us think about what this
series would look like
and has worked, really, over
time to help us and help MIT
support their relationships
with research and development
operations actions
at the government
and institutional level there.
And he's just a wonderful
collaborator and member
of our team and our community.
So what I'd like to
do is-- he's going
to share a little
bit of his thoughts
and the origins of
this series and then
turn it over to Dean Breazeal.
So, Bill, can I turn it to you?
WILLIAM B. BONVILLAIN:
Sure, thanks, Megan.
And I'll just be
very brief because I
want to get to Cynthia too.
AI offers, as I think we
know, a whole new suite
of opportunities.
So it's the second
big revolution
that's been coming along in
education in the last decade.
The first really was the
advent of online education
at real scale and the technical
mechanisms to do that.
This is the latest.
And it offers an
opportunity for--
and I'll just hit
some highlights--
a new personalization
of education,
where teachers can really
adapt education, really,
to the needs of
particular students.
Part of that is that
it opens an opportunity
for digital tutoring.
AI can help in grading, at
least on simple exams that
use answer keys, but over time,
potentially more than that.
It can offer
feedback to students
on what they're learning.
In other words, it can
alert them to things
that they're missing and
put them into feedback loops
to catch up.
And it can reduce time
on administrative tasks
for teachers and
for administrators.
Obviously, there's
drawbacks to AI.
Like all new technologies, it's
always a double-edged sword.
Some of the issues include
reduced human interaction
for students, overdependence
on technology,
and reduced interaction
with real, live teachers.
And there are,
obviously, data-privacy
and security issues.
And there's ethical issues.
Does this open big doors
to larger-scale cheating.
And how do we
manage that process?
So that's just a quick snapshot
on some of the background
issues.
But let's turn to Cynthia, who
is going to really educate us
on these kinds of issues.
Cynthia.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: Thank
you, Bill and Megan.
It's a pleasure to
be joining you here.
I'm going to be touching on
a lot of different topics,
as it relates to the
intersection of AI
and education.
My goal is to tell you a little
bit about the research that's
happening in academic
settings as AI
is advancing different roles
it can play in education.
I'm sure a lot of you are very
aware of the personalized AI
tutors.
I'm going to present our
particular take on that, which
is different than probably
what you've heard about Cognigo
and things like that.
Very different age
group, very different
focus on the kinds
of intelligence.
I am going to talk about
helping people learn about AI.
So learning with AI, you
could argue that's the "AI
personalized learning companion"
work, learning about AI,
so AI literacy.
And we at MIT now are actually
using a term, "AI fluency,"
which is a much deeper
engagement with this material
that empowers people to
create solutions with these
technologies.
And how do we empower a much
more diverse group of people
to do that?
And then at the
end of the talk, I
want to just share
a bunch of resources
that we at MIT and
RAISE have developed
on a broad set of topics
that you may find helpful
and interesting from curriculum
materials and policy documents
and so forth.
And, hopefully, that can
maybe inform the discussion
you have with Hae Won later on.
So, again, to talk
about learning with AI,
learning about AI, and
then some resources
that hopefully you'll
find useful to you--
a lot of the work that I
am going to be presenting
is going to be through
the lens of K-12.
But I can assure you
many of the technologies
and insights and lessons
apply to people of all ages
and learning stages.
So let me get started.
So I first, again, want to
talk about my research group
to orient you towards the
lens upon which we approach
this challenge or
this opportunity of,
how do you design interactive AI
systems that help people learn?
So as Megan mentioned, I
am the founder and director
in the MIT Media Lab of
the Personal Robots Group.
And as that title suggests,
we actually design and develop
physical robots.
And so what kind of robots?
Well, if you think
about science fiction,
like Star Wars and
R2-D2 and C-3PO,
that is actually the kind of
robot that we try to make,
so robots that can deeply
interact with people in a very
socially and "emotionally
intelligent human centered" way,
very much how we have dreamed
about them in the movies.
And our goal then is to--
obviously, we're not there yet.
So we are trying to
responsibly advance
the science, the computational
methods to endow machines,
in this case robots, with
these capabilities that
allow them to much deeply
understand and engage
and collaborate with us.
And it's really oriented
towards helping people
achieve our goals, right?
So how through that interaction,
can these social robots
help unlock human potential,
through education,
say, better health care, and
so forth, maximize our success?
How do we design to address what
humans need to be successful
so that we are actually more
effective with these tools
and technologies?
And a lot of this is about, how
do we promote human flourishing?
How do we help people become
who they aspire to be?
So that's the mission of
the Personal Robots Group.
And that's the lens upon,
which a lot of this work,
this first part of the talk,
I'm going to touch upon.
So we're in the age now of
this era of generative AI.
I can tell you as a roboticist,
we are extremely practical.
All of these cool new
tools and technologies--
obviously, before
generative AI, deep learning
was the latest hype cycle,
various hype cycles before that.
We basically just view these
as cool tools in a toolbox
that we actually
have to leverage
to design and create solutions.
Many of these techniques,
many of these methods
with human-centered
design to get a robot
to do anything interesting
or useful for people, right?
So we, basically, view each of
these new tools and technologies
as just another
thing we can leverage
to help us advance our mission
faster, more flexibly, more
robustly, et cetera.
So I will say, we have
been on this trajectory
certainly since I think
Siri came out on the iPhone,
where now a dominant mode of
which everyday people interact
with artificial intelligence
is as a personified entity.
Now, before that, a lot of that
was decision-support tools,
graphs, whatever,
more like a tool
that you would use
to make decisions.
The interfaces are
becoming more and more
social and interpersonal, right?
So there's a long
tradition, of course,
of AI for graphical
agents, virtual characters.
We mentioned Siri.
Then Alexa came along.
And now you had
far-field speech, right?
And the whole question
was, are people
actually going to talk to AI?
And it turned out
this idea of AI
that could be evoked
just with a wake word.
Suddenly, it allowed
people of all ages,
from young children
to older adults,
to access AI in a
much more easy way.
So that was another
big jump ahead.
And now, of course,
we're in this era
of generative AI with ChatGPT.
And now, ironically, we're back
to text on screen and typing.
But the language and the
multi-turn interaction
is now much more
advanced, flexible,
and robust with these
generative methods
than they had been
done previously.
And now we're
seeing even more so,
people are very willing to have
long, intimate conversations
with AI.
So just to say,
we as human beings
are so willing to engage AIs
in a social and emotional way.
And I have seen this from
my own work for decades.
But now with the proliferation
of this personified-AI
technologies, I think now
everybody appreciates--
this is a dominant mode upon
which everyday people interact
with AIs.
And there are
important implications
of that, important
implications of that.
So, first of all, when
you look at human behavior
and intelligence, it's just
important to acknowledge
that we have evolved.
We have very specialized
regions in our brain
to understand and interact
with the social world.
Now, what do I mean
by the social world?
We have the inanimate world,
where objects are governed
by the laws of physics.
And we have parts
of our brain that
are good at understanding
those entities.
And then there
are social others.
And social others'
behavior is governed
by having a mind, so mental
states, things like thoughts,
beliefs, intents, desires,
inferring them and understanding
them, having your own and being
able to infer and recognize
that in others, in order to
understand and coordinate
behavior, is like--
we are like the super species
of that on the planet.
If you look at everything around
us, everything we've built,
it's all because we can
communicate and collaborate
in these extremely sophisticated
ways with one another.
This is an incredible
competence that we have.
And I can tell you,
it is very difficult
to endow machines with
this kind of capability.
But a list of these
things are here.
So how do you have a theory of
other minds, again, inferring
these mental states?
How do you empathize with other?
How can you connect,
communicate, harmonize?
All of these things are
about social intelligence.
And so, again, an
opportunity and challenge
that my group has
looked at for decades
is, what does that mean when
you talk about a machine that
can collaborate with
us in a much more
human-centered, natural way?
So a lot of my work
has looked at, again,
advancing the social and
emotional intelligence
of AI systems.
And particularly around
emotional engagement,
how do you design to be a
more richly collaborative
ally, real, bidirectional
give and take?
And thinking about
long-term interaction, when
you look at Star Wars and
you think about robots,
it's not like it's a device
that you turn on and turn
off and walk away from it.
But robots-- they live with you.
They are part of your world.
They are beyond the screen.
And there are different
challenges and opportunities
in designing something
that is of our world,
in our world, shares our
world, and over long periods
of time where it
goes beyond just
session-to-session interaction,
to this idea of building
a relationship.
And you're starting
to see the beginnings
of people's willingness to
build a relationship with AIs.
And so then what are
the appropriate roles
between people and
increasingly-intelligent
machines?
So when we think about
the foundational building
blocks of these capabilities,
the field of social robotics,
increasingly--
I would say even fields like
natural language processing
is broadening out to think about
social intelligence questions.
But how do you recognize,
again, all the richness
and sophistication and subtlety
of human communication?
Again, we're talking
about ChatGPT, which
is largely text and language.
Still, they're just starting to
release multimodal capabilities.
But if you look at the more
human side of literature,
I mean, people will say human
communication is anywhere
from 60% to 80% non-verbal.
Non-verbal.
[LAUGHS] There is
a lot of richness
in how we communicate that goes
beyond the words that we speak.
And, in fact, if given a person
an option between believing
what person a person
says, via their words,
versus how they say it with
their prosody or their body,
they tend to believe
how you say it
as your true meaning
and your true intention.
So non-verbal
communication is huge.
It's still a largely uncracked
nut, I would say, in AI.
But this is where things are
starting to try to go more,
not just on "one
to one individual"
interaction but to a group.
We can collaborate with
groups of people as well.
So, again, lots of room
to grow in the perception
of human social
cues-- and that's
giving you a sense of where
the new challenges are.
You've heard a lot
about machine learning.
I'm sure you heard a lot about
supervised machine learning,
with these large data
sets that you label
and you feed in to recognize and
classify and predict categories
and classes and patterns.
There's reinforcement learning.
You're going to see
some examples of that
in my talk, where
a system actually
learns through its own
firsthand experience.
You're hearing about generative
AI, which is a combination.
It's an unsupervised
learning approach
that combines aspects of
reinforcement learning
and supervised big neural
networks and so forth.
It's a mash up.
But the point is, when you look
at social-emotional learning,
it's not a
one-directional stream.
It's often a collaboration
between the teacher
versus the learner.
And often we think
about the machine
as being the learner and the
human being, the instructor,
whether it's through data
or interaction or whatever.
But the reality is--
and human interaction
is very fluid.
We can learn and collaborate
from each other as peers,
et cetera, et cetera.
So when you think about
this interaction of teaching
and learning, especially for a
robot, which is now something
facing you and is having to
learn from your real time
interaction, how do you view
that as a collaboration?
So there's a lot
of interesting work
in social forms of
learning that is
informing that work and beyond.
So, again, how do you interact
with and teach with something
that is physically there,
learning from you in the moment
to do something
that's customized,
personalized, context relevant.
That's a different
learning problem
than just feeding
a bunch of data
and trying to learn
classifiers and so forth.
When we talked about a system
that can coordinate with you,
it's not only important
that the robot
be able to understand
your social cues.
But you have to understand and
infer its states of mind, right?
And so, how the robot expresses
both verbally and non-verbally
is actually quite important,
because as human beings,
we are trying to read
both signals all the time,
whether you meant to design
something for that or not.
So the point is, we are
inferring all kinds of things
from a robot's behavior.
So you really have to
think holistically about,
how is it expressing
itself to the person
so that they have appropriate
mental models of what
the robot is actually
cognitively processing, right?
So that expression
becomes really important.
And then, in the
big picture, now
what happens when you're in this
interaction is collaboration.
Well, now you're in the realm
of human-social psychology
and social perception.
And, again, people
can't turn this off.
They will ascribe these
things to the nature
of the interaction,
even with the machine.
So when you're in
collaboration, things
like building rapport, building
trust and trustworthiness,
a sense of liking--
all of these things
come into play
when you start talking
about real interaction,
even with an AI system.
So how do you design robots
that can do that over repeated
"encountered over long
term" interactions.
So, again, this
is just giving you
a sense of the broad field
of play and advancements
we're trying to make
in the big picture.
OK, so given all of that, again,
I teed up-- what our group is--
our vision of how can we design
these technologies to help
people to succeed,
grow, and flourish.
So a lot of our work is
inspired by Positive Psychology.
This is a diagram
from Martin Siegelman.
And it's just to say, when you
talk about human flourishing,
these are the kinds of
qualities you have to address.
And these are profoundly
social and emotional.
They're not just cognitive
decision-making processes, which
has dominated the
conversation around AI, right?
So it's about engagement,
relationships, well-being,
meaning, positive emotion,
a sense of achievement.
That is not the
words we typically
talk about when we
talk about AI systems
or typically talking about
efficiency and saving money
and making money.
These are the things
that we need to address
to promote human flourishing.
So, again, this just to say
this is a different lens
upon which we look
at our work and why
we build the systems we do.
So, again, in the
big picture then,
this humanized
engagement is not just
about having a really good
experience with the AI
technology, say, it's a robot.
But if you can achieve this
deeper human engagement,
you can actually enable
transformative change
in people's lives.
So what do I mean by
transformative change?
Well, if somebody
can actually learn
new skills or mindsets
or capabilities,
they are transformed.
They are able to do things
they couldn't before.
They now have access
to opportunities
they didn't have before.
That's an example for me
of transformative change
in health care.
If you're better able to manage
a chronic condition-- if you're
better able to be emotionally
resilient in times of stress,
you are transformed.
And you are going to
be able to do things
you were not going to be able to
do before you were transformed.
So these are the
things that we try
to look at in our
group as case studies
and as contexts to
try to demonstrate,
in advance, our work with actual
people in real-world situations.
So we do a lot of work
across different domains.
I'm going to focus on our
particular work on education.
And so, in this
section, I'm going
to talk about our
personalized-learning-companion
work.
A lot of that work
is actually focused
on early childhood
education, so young children,
kindergarten-type age,
often in school settings.
So why does this matter?
So in the United States, we
do not have a "universal early
childhood education" system.
We're trying to change that.
But, historically,
we have not had one.
And because of
that, there's a lot
of inequity in children's
readiness, even in kindergarten.
And there's a lot of data
and studies that have shown
if children cannot even start
kindergarten ready to learn,
it is very difficult
to catch up.
And there's a lot of
down-the-road consequences
of that.
It can be extremely expensive
to try to catch children up.
So just to say, in
the United States,
there is a big societal
need to improve equity
in the quality of
early-childhood education.
So it's a serious challenge.
It's a serious problem that we
face here in the United States.
But I'm sure worldwide,
post pandemic,
we're all seeing the impacts
of this on children's education
of all grades.
So just to say,
this question of how
we can create
technologies that help
to enhance, to help children
learn in ways that allow them
to be at grade-appropriate
level, right now
is of particular
importance because there's
a lot of kids that are not
where they would have been
if we didn't have the pandemic.
So, anyway, there's just a lot
of global societal need, which
I think is why, again,
this idea of AI tutors
has been around for decades.
It's been around a long time.
And with every new technology,
we try to advance them.
This is just the
context upon which
I think we are really
seeing the next wave of why
having these personalized
learning technologies
are important for
kids today, beyond all
of the other
traditional reasons.
So when we talk about
AI-supported learning now,
we're talking about
physically-embodied,
socially-embodied robots.
Now, what are the
advantages of that?
We just heard about Cognigo.
And Bill was talking
about this concern
of social isolation
between students
to other students,
students to teachers.
That is a real risk.
A lot of these systems are
really designed like Cognigo
for one-to-one, text-based
interaction between a student
and the screen.
Right?
What we're trying
to do is create
learning companion
technologies that
are integrated into the
human-social environment
of learning.
Learning is profoundly social.
That is one thing
we have definitely
learned from all of our great
educational technologies.
Learning is profoundly social.
It's important that people learn
in the context of other people
and human teachers.
So that is table stakes for
what we're trying to design.
So in this photo here,
you see a social robot
that because it's
physically embodied,
it can actually interact
with a group of people.
It can interact with
the main child learner.
It can turn and
talk to the teacher.
There's a little
girl friend looking--
imagine that fluid
interaction in
a physically-socially-situated
environment, like a classroom.
That is what we're trying to do.
The robot then is
designed to try
to help facilitate
this interaction,
to promote, obviously,
the children's learning.
A lot of our context is around
early language and literacy
skills because we know
that's critical for a lot
of future academic success.
It is designed not to be a tutor
but to be a practice partner.
That's what we call it
a learning companion.
It's like a really
fun playmate that
plays games,
educational-learning games
with kids that
reinforces and gives them
additional practice to what the
teacher is actually teaching.
So we're not trying to
compete with the teacher.
We're trying to supplement
what the teacher does.
And, again, why did we
choose early childhood
beyond the societal challenge?
It is a real litmus test
because young children
aren't going to learn by
typing text and so forth.
They interact through play and
"real time social emotional"
interaction.
If you can design a
technology that can actually
engage a young child
in an authentic way,
your algorithms are doing
something right, right?
So it is a really acid
test, I would say,
as if our algorithms
and our advancements
are actually doing
something meaningful
and advancing the
ball, so to speak.
We are modeling
peer-to-peer interactions.
So the robot interacts more
like a peer-like, maybe slightly
more advanced learner than,
again, a human teacher.
And we do a lot of
personalization under the hood.
So we use a lot of reinforcement
learning to do that.
I'm sure we've heard
about generative AI
and how you can customize pumps.
A lot of our work
is about the robot
through real-time
interaction through how
the child expresses what they
say, what they do in the game.
The robot is trying to learn
what we call "a policy of what
the most optimal
next action is,"
to help achieve the goals of
keeping that child engaged
and promoting that
child's learning.
So that's
reinforcement learning.
We do a lot of reinforcement
learning in this.
We don't just do
this in a vacuum.
We engage teachers and students
and stakeholders in co-design.
And this is really,
really important
because whatever we
design has to fit, again,
in the human environment.
If it's not solving a
problem that the teachers
or the students
are really wanting,
they're not going to use it.
And we've seen that story in
technology again and again.
So we do a lot of co-design.
We are innovating at this
intersection of psychology
and engagement, so
understanding real people,
what they do in this context.
And with a technology
like a social robot,
we do a lot of
human-experience design
to make sure that these
games of these interactions
are not only effective but
delightful and engaging,
emotionally, socially
engaging for children.
And that is what is
defining and informing
what are the computational
challenges we're
trying to design.
We don't just say we want to
design a new machine learning
algorithm.
We ask the question,
what do people need?
What does it have
to be able to do?
What advancements are required?
And that is how we frame
the technical challenges
of the algorithms.
We try to innovate.
When you think about
AI-enabled personalization,
in some sense, that becomes part
of the design cycle as well,
because whatever
we design is going
to be adapted based on
this real-time interaction
with learners.
And then, again, that
is a constant monitoring
and redesigning with the
stakeholders as well.
So this is just
to say, co-design.
With AI, in this context,
is part of the process
we have to go through.
There's really no
cutting corners here.
There's no just throwing in
data and get something out.
It is a constant process of
trying to keep yourself honest
and making sure
you're delivering
something of value
that is working
in the authentic context.
And we learn a lot
through this process.
And we're able to make really
compelling advances to AI
when we do this process.
So I'm going to show
a series of videos
just so that you can see a
little bit of this in action.
So, again, we're talking
about peer-to-peer learning.
So how do we model a robot?
How do we create these models
that a robot can actually
engage in this interaction?
So one of the first
steps that we did--
and this was a few years ago--
was we brought in a lot of kids.
And we recorded how they engage
in a story-sharing interaction,
because a lot of what
we have the robot
do with the child is a
dialogic-story-sharing
interaction.
So we record these things.
We then start to train new
models based on the capability.
And then we
basically put a robot
in the context of
one of these children
and compare what does that
behavior look like when now it's
a child interacting
with a robot,
versus a child interacting
with another child.
How close are we to
capturing that dynamic?
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- So the cat broke the window.
And then it ran to
school and peeked inside.
- And then they
saw a caterpillar.
- And then some classmates--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: So a lot of
affective computing-- again,
this is other
machine-learning models
to track states and sequences
of interaction patterns.
- And they wanted to go in--
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: And then we
put the model in the robot.
And we bring in-- and, again,
a whole other group of children
are now engaging
in this interaction
and looking at the
social cues of the robot,
looking at the child's
non-verbal and verbal behavior,
to try to have it engage as an
interested, supportive-learning
companion.
So that gives you a sense of
how we endow these social skills
into the robot.
This next video is
the bigger picture
of starting to try to learn
policies, adaptive policies,
to personalize
interactions with children.
So, again,
reinforcement learning,
a different kind of machine
learning to learn, again,
personalized policies.
- Hi, my name is Tega.
Nice to meet you.
What is your name?
- Aliana.
- Early literacy
skills form the basis
of a large part of
children's future learning.
But children entering
preschool and kindergarten
come from linguistically
diverse backgrounds, affected
by many factors, including
their family's cultural origin
and socioeconomic status.
Therefore, it's important to
create personalized solutions
for promoting early literacy.
- What was your
favorite story so far?
- My favorite story?
It was the bunny one.
- Using a social robot
as an embodied AI agent
provides several advantages.
Studies show that early literacy
development requires exposure
to a rich variety of spoken
language and vocabulary
during social
interaction with others.
Children engage
with social robots
in an emotive and
relational way.
And the affective cues
that social robots
can elicit from children
provide a better opportunity
to assess their
engagement states.
Our reinforcement learning
personalization policy
takes full advantage of
these engagement cues.
The robot's goal is to
learn an action policy that
maximizes the chance
for each child
to learn new linguistic
knowledge while also promoting
engagement.
During the robot's
storytelling, the robot
models the child's
listening behavior
based on several
features, including
whether the child responds
to the robot's question--
- What would you see if you
went to a rainforest someday?
- Lions.
- --the length of the response,
and also the child's facial
affect cues during
the robot's story.
The robot's action space is the
lexical and syntactic complexity
of a sentence in the storybook.
The reward function
is a weighted sum
of engagement and learning.
- The frog went out of his pond.
- The reward
function was designed
to reward new lexical and
syntactic learning but balancing
this with engagement so that
the algorithm doesn't always
select a story with the
highest linguistic complexity.
Over the course of
three months, we
studied 67 bilingual and
English-language-learning
students from 12 local
kindergarten classrooms.
Students were divided into
three balanced groups.
The personalized and
non-personalized groups
interacted with our
social robot, Tega,
in a fully autonomous
interaction,
in which the robot and child
took turns telling stories.
The robot either
personalized its story choice
or selected from a
fixed curriculum.
Children in the
baseline group only
participated in pre and post
tests without robot interaction.
We found that the
story-selection policy did
personalize to each
child over time,
shown by the root-mean-square
distance from the initial policy
and the rate of "matching
maximum reward state action"
pairs in the Q table
between two policies.
Children who interacted
with a personalized robot
learned and used significantly
more target words
compared to the non-personalized
and baseline groups.
We also found that children's
engagement cues are
significantly correlated
and that this trend
was driven by the
personalization condition.
- At the crest of the hill,
stood a bear blinking blearily
outside his cave.
- They went to the crest of the
hill and found a bear standing.
- And he saw a bear.
And he was so cared.
So--
- Children in the
personalized condition
attempted to answer the
robot's questions more often.
And this tendency
was also reflected
in their affective arousal cues.
Analyzing children's
electrodermal activity and body
pose revealed that children
in the personalized condition
showed significantly higher
attention and engagement
levels throughout the sessions.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
With a relatable-social-robot
companion,
we have demonstrated that
when we match young students
with a learning partner that
can grow and engage with them,
those students flourish.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
OK, so punch line
is, the personalized
robot seemed
to be even more engaging
and able to help
support children learning than
the non-personalized robot.
But I can tell you, even
both of those robots
gave children's gain over
baseline classroom instruction.
So even just having
the presence of a robot
to help practice and
reinforce these behaviors
was beneficial to children.
So this was a result that
was shown on the slide.
Some other things
that we've looked at
is, what about the
quality of relationship
that children experience
with the robot?
And how does that
affect their learning?
So we know that when children
have a better relationship
with their teacher, it is often
correlated with higher learning
outcomes.
We are starting to see that
also with these AI systems.
So we looked at
measures of measuring
interpersonal relationship
in human-human interactions.
We adapted that to a
human-robot context.
We are seeing the same trends.
So children who report having a
closer relationship to the robot
tends to be correlated
with higher learning gains.
And when we add in
personalization,
that correlation
is even stronger.
So we're starting to
see these interactions
between personalization,
relationship, and learning.
You saw the video of benefits
of the practice partner.
We have also been bringing these
technologies into home settings
to try to foster
parent-child-robot triadic
interactions to enrich the
dialogue between parents
and children.
So, again, bringing
that social interaction
beyond the classroom
to the home--
and so the punch line here is,
there's a lot of assumption
that a human-human relationship
is what we should be going for.
And this work is showing it's
not necessarily the case.
It really just depends.
So one of the things that's so
appealing and interesting about
the social robot we've
designed is, yes,
there are absolutely attributes
of a "human motivating
supportive" ally,
learning with a friend.
It's also a cool
high-tech tool that
can access all
kinds of information
and so forth from the
internet, et cetera, et cetera.
But there are these
qualities, as I'm
sure you saw in these videos, of
this non-judgmental, attentive--
almost companion animal.
And that creates a safe
context for learning,
whereas a child might
be embarrassed to make
a mistake in front of
a friend or a teacher.
They don't seem to feel that
way in front of a social robot.
So they're able to try new
things, take safe learning
risks, which, of course,
benefits their learning.
So, again, there's a different
relationship that's possible,
where they can have actual
different kinds of benefits that
enhance and supplement
the peer-to-peer learning
and the teacher-student
learning that we
have in our educational system.
So I've talked a lot about
reinforcement learning.
You're like, what
about generative AI?
So, yes, of course we're
bringing generative AI
into our systems as well.
You can see we do a lot
of dialogic storytelling.
The generative AI
models are allowing
us to be much more flexible
and expansive in the kinds
of conversations and
questions asked and answered
that the robot is capable
of engaging children in.
We were much more
limited and constrained
before generative AI.
So I'm just going
to show one more
video of this example of now
having a dialogue around one
of the stories in the
library of storybooks that's
in our educational intervention.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- What was the doll made out of?
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
There's a story here.
- I'm not sure.
I think I remember
something with beads.
Can you tell me the rest?
- You're right about the beads.
They are part of the
doll's decorations.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
So giving hints.
- But let's focus on what
the whole doll is made from.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: Being
able to adjust the story--
- It's a type of soft material
that comes from an animal.
Can you guess which one?
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: Again,
this is a generated hint.
This is pretty good.
- It said buckskin.
But what animal
does that come from?
- Buckskin comes from a deer,
which is a kind of animal that
lives in the forest.
The doll was made from
the soft skin of a deer.
Let's start with the first pig.
Can you tell me what he
built his house out of?
- I think it's
made out of cakes.
- That sounds delicious.
Unfortunately, I don't
think that's right.
The first pig built
his house out of straw.
- What would you use
to build your house?
- That's an
interesting question.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: We're seeing
a mixed [INAUDIBLE] interaction.
- I think I'd build my
house out of solar panels
so that I can power my
home with renewable energy.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: And he's
like, renewable energy.
- Wow, that's very smart.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
That's a great answer.
[LAUGHS]
SPEAKER 2: Thank you.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
So, again, just much
more flexible, responsive,
open-ended bidirectional
interactions that's
powered by generative AI.
So, obviously,
this is allowing us
to approach this using new
tools and technologies that we
didn't have access beforehand.
And just before I
leave this section,
just to acknowledge
that education underlies
a lot of real world
applications across a lot
of different disciplines--
so when you talk about health
literacy, financial literacy,
coaching and training, behavior
change for health, at the crux
of a lot of these interventions
is helping people develop
new skills, new mindsets,
and new knowledge
so that they can
affect positive
change for themselves,
make better decisions.
So, again, learning is
so foundational to a lot
of these other domains,
where these agents could
have potentially a lot of use.
All right, so I'm going to end
this section on learning with AI
in this
social-emotional-human context
and now talk about how do we
help people become more AI
literate or even AI fluent
so that we are empowered
to create solutions to address
challenges in our communities?
So there's been a lot
of fear and concern
about AI replacing
people in jobs,
changing the landscape
of the job market,
et cetera, et cetera.
That is absolutely going
to happen to some extent.
But Erik Brynjolfsson
at Stanford
makes this point
that way more value
is going to be
unlocked when AI is
designed to help people create
something fundamentally new.
So he is basically
speaking to this deeper,
creative collaboration
between people and AI.
And this is what we
really need to focus on
is the creative, collaborative
interaction of people
with these new
empowering technologies.
And so, basically,
the argument is
AI is not going to replace
people for those jobs.
It's people who
know how to harness
AIs-- are going to be the ones
who get those jobs over people
who don't know how to
use these technologies.
So there's a lot of reason when
we think about the workforce,
as it is today, and how
it's going to continue
and helping people develop the
skills and abilities so they can
be competitive and effective
and creative problem
solvers in the workforce.
So we created this initiative,
RAISE, a couple of years ago.
RAISE, again, stands for
Responsible AI for Social
Empowerment and Education.
And the mission is to advance
equity and learning education
and empowerment through
artificial intelligence,
by rethinking and innovating
how to holistically
and equitably prepare
diverse students from K-12
to workforce, in
these technologies,
so that we can be happy,
engaged, empowered, successful,
in an increasingly
AI-powered society.
So that is our
mission for RAISE.
And now I'm going to talk
about a number of the programs
that we've been
developing and innovating
to deliver on this mission.
So another way to say
that mission statement
might be, we're
trying to advance
an empowered and wise
human-with-AI world,
by with and for all.
We want everyone to participate
and be engaged in this mission.
So there are three
main buckets that we
try to address-- in all of
our curriculum materials,
professional develop
materials, you name it,
one is to demystify
how AI actually works.
There's a lot of confusion
and hype out there.
We want people to have a
practical working knowledge,
grade-appropriate knowledge
of how AI actually works
and how to design and
use it responsibly.
We want people to become
informed AI digital citizens
so that we have a voice in
how we want these technologies
integrated and used in society.
We've heard many stories of
potential bias and inequities
that has arisen because of AI.
People need to
understand this and have
a voice in how they're used.
And the third bucket is
self-efficacy and empowerment,
being creative
makers and problem
solvers with these
technologies and making
that much more inclusive and
much greater access to that
as well.
So a lot of our
philosophy here at MIT
goes all the way back
to Seymour Papert.
He is the founding father
of constructionist learning.
He himself studied with Piaget
[LAUGHS] on constructionism,
structuralism.
Anyway, so Piaget's
constructionism,
where, basically, it's this
idea that when you actually
make something, learn to make
something, create something,
share it with others, you are
engaging in a much deeper sense
of knowledge and
empowerment than just
absorbing in this
lecture-style information.
So the act of creating
something meaningful,
integrating what you
learn in order to do that,
is really what
we're going to need
to empower a future
of children who
are going to be creative problem
solvers, creator makers, who
can, again, make
the world a better
place with these technologies.
I think the thing
that's really exciting
now is before it was
like, yeah, they're
going to get to do
that after college.
But the reality is these
tools and technologies
have gotten to the
point that they
are so accessible
that kids can actually
start to do this right now.
So I love this notion
of kid power with AI
because kids have this sense
of their inner superhero.
And what if their
superpower was AI?
And what if they could
combine those things
and go out and affect positive
change in their communities
and even the world, based on
what they're learning and doing?
I think a lot of
young people today
are feeling a sense
of hopelessness
because they feel like
they can't do anything.
AI and all this stuff
is happening to them.
We want to flip that
dialogue so they understand,
"you can create positive
change right now with these
technologies."
And we're going to
help them to do that.
So we are invading
new curriculum,
new pedagogical methods.
We have this framing we
call computational action.
So not just learning
through making, but learning
by solving, learning through
this action of children
can actually create things
with these innovative tools,
taking things like MIT
App Inventor, which
allow kids to make working
mobile apps on iOS and Android.
We've been infusing App Inventor
with state-of-the-art AI tools,
generative-AI tools,
deep-learning tools,
so they can apply them to
make solutions that can affect
their community.
And how do they do
that responsibly?
How do they do that ethically?
How do they do that
with their community?
That is what we're trying to
help teach kids what to do,
how to do that?
I'm going to give a quick
example with App Inventor.
So I'm sure many of you
are aware of App Inventor.
But this is one of the key
flagship platforms at MIT.
It is open source.
A lot of everything we
do basically in RAISE
is open source.
People are free to
use these materials,
adopt them, et
cetera, et cetera.
Again, "allows anyone to create
mobile apps in Android or iOS,"
this easy, intuitive block
based coding interface.
So lowers the barrier
to entry of students
being able to code
things with these, again,
block-based coding environments.
There's over 18 million
users in over 195 countries
who use App Inventor.
Almost 50% are from
developing economies.
So, again, widespread
uses, widespread usage.
I'm going to highlight one
example of computational action
that's particularly inspiring.
So we collaborate with a
non-profit called Technovation.
Technovation is a STEM program
for girls, particularly
high-school-aged girls,
around computational thinking
and innovation.
So this is one of the teams that
participated in Technovation.
And they're girls
who are living in one
of the largest slums in India.
And they decided
that they wanted
to create an app that basically
helped to schedule time
at when they would go--
the community could
go to the watering community
area to gather water.
Now, who tends to go to
gather water for the family?
It tends to be girls
about this age.
It could take hours to do this.
There could be fights
that would break out
because of a lot of tension.
So they wanted to
create this app
to help it be faster,
easier, and a better
experience for everyone
who went to those community
watering areas.
So, again, something that
actually really empowered
their community with
middle-school-aged girls--
so, again, anyone, anyone
can create solutions
with these tools
and technologies.
We have been creating
a lot of curriculum,
professional
development programs
for educators and teachers, to
bring these tools, technologies,
insights, concepts, mindsets,
and skill sets to students.
So one of our flagship
programs is called Day of AI.
Day of AI is short-format
curriculum for any teacher
to teach for all
students because it's not
just for computer
science students anymore.
The AI Genie's
out of the bottle.
Day of AI is really
about the intersection
of AI, digital citizenship,
and empowerment.
So it is truly for all students.
We have curriculum literally
from kindergarten to 12th grade,
including 12th grade
computer-science curriculum.
Its short format.
We know teachers
are overwhelmed.
So instead of asking
them to commit
to a whole semester-long
curriculum, these are short,
four to six-hour curriculum that
we're finding a lot of teachers
are like, that I can try out.
It introduces AI
literacy the way
I talked about and
in the way that it's
multidisciplinary,
highly-student-relatable
context, hands-on learning
and making, creating.
Lots of critical
decision making,
critical thinking,
creative decision making,
et cetera, et
cetera, is important.
It's free and open
for the materials.
And we have a lot of
online free asynchronous
professional development.
This is an example of
a lot of the topics
that we've been creating
over time, expanding that.
This year we just released one
in data science and climate.
This year, we might
do one on space.
We're seeing a lot of launches
to the moon and so forth.
So we think about
and look at how
AI is shaping topics that are
really interesting in the moment
to students.
And how can we create
materials to do that?
Last year, it was
all about ChatGPT.
We created that curriculum.
Last year it was the most
downloaded curriculum
of all of them.
So we try to be super
agile and responsive.
I'm going to show you a video of
what kids do once they've been
exposed to these materials.
This was the AI and
data science curriculum.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- My name is Ileana Fournier.
- My name is Jessie Magenyi.
- My name is Victoria Leeth.
And my project is Tree Saver.
- And we were basically
getting information
about deforestation
in Massachusetts.
And we used that
information to make an app--
- --where people can click
it and ChatGPT will give them
information on how the can
help save trees and help
their community.
- We found that it
was really important
because it's such a
stable part to human life.
In the backyard of our
school, we're filled by trees.
Trees are everywhere.
And then not even 30
minutes out in Boston,
there's really no trees at all.
So that duality and that drastic
change was really interesting
and intrigued all of us.
- The future is kind of scary to
think about because with the way
the climate is changing
and all that's happening,
I feel like if there
is no change done fast,
I feel like the future
would not be a good one.
- The whole point
of our project is
to help people find ways
to help their community
and help the environment by
improving the amount of trees
that are cut down.
AI can make us a
more powerful person
because it can help us find
ways to connect with others
and help us connect and
gain more information
that we can get ourselves.
- It could still be mastered
because it's so new.
And I feel like getting
that in schools everywhere,
you could really find the
new greatest minds that
will be able to use AI, for
the better of the world.
- And, yes, we did--
I felt powerful like,
"I can do this."
And I feel like I
can make an app now
that can change the world.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: So
this is what we're after.
I can tell you this
Day of AI program,
we're already all
over the world.
Over 110 countries,
over 10,000 educators,
K-12 teachers are bringing
Day of AI to their classroom
and growing through our
international partnerships.
We have other partners
who are bringing it
to other regions of the world,
like South America, Latin
America.
So, again, this is very much
a community-oriented endeavor.
"So what do kids solve with AI?"
I mean, we see this
again and again.
They want to create
a more just society.
They want to help
our planet to thrive.
people to flourish.
I mean, the kids
are truly inspiring,
as you could see, in that video.
So just kind of wrap
up with some resources
that I can point you to, we have
a lot of different curriculum
on RAISE.
You can check it
out the Day of AI.
Dayofai.org has all
those curriculum
I mentioned, teacher
professional development
serials.
We have other programs
and Data Activism,
so Data Science for Social Good.
Future Makers is a
technical-skills-building
program.
All these programs
are available.
We know that AI has to support
teachers and supporting
students.
All of our curriculum
professional development
is also oriented
to help teachers
feel informed and comfortable
in teaching their kids about AI.
We have written
a position paper.
I'm going to leave this screen
up just for a little bit,
for those of you who want to
get the QR code on Generative
AI and K-12 Education.
It gives a lot of
opportunities, challenges, et
cetera, et cetera, that
might be of interest to you.
We know that
teachers need to also
be up to speed on how
they can use generative
AI in their practice.
This is a free online course we
developed with Grow with Google.
It's a two-hour "go
at your own pace,"
all about how you can use
generative AI in your teaching
practice.
As Bill mentioned, things
like customizing lessons,
creating rubrics, et
cetera, et cetera,
these are actual
activities that you
go through as part
of the course to be
a very practical hands-on
thing for how generative AI can
be used to empower teachers.
Teachers are an important AI
workforce for this country.
So you can check that out.
Teachers and educators need to
be part of the conversation.
We just released "AI
Policy Guidance."
Thank you, Bill, for
helping preview earlier
versions of this paper.
But it's available now.
So when you think
about AI policy--
this is for K-12.
But, again, I
think this is going
to be relevant for other
age groups as well.
But, hopefully, this will be
informative and interesting
for you also, so around
AI policy guidance.
All right, and you're all here
joining the call because you're
interested in this stuff.
It's still early days,
so you're the pioneers.
You should experiment and share.
And I know J-WEL helps
to facilitate that.
So looking forward to see what
you are innovating and sharing
as well.
And with that, thank you.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Cynthia,
thank you so much,
amazing information,
knowledge, I think, to absorb.
As you were speaking,
I was getting messages
from teachers locally
and globally about,
how do I get involved?
And I think you
really shared so many
incredible, actionable
resources, which
is what makes, I think, the
work you're doing so fantastic,
to take it from the
lab, to give educators
a way to implement this.
You talked a little
bit about this.
And as I asked this question, I
mentioned in the chat, "Please,
folks, can we put questions in
the chat so, in the time we have
left-- you are able to ask--
we can get a few questions
from you all in too?
But how are these folks in
emerging economies globally
finding these resources?
So often when we talk even
to some of our members,
they'll say we just
feel like we're behind
because our young children don't
have the same access to just
core technology that
kids have in the US
that they might have in Europe.
And I think you've
developed tools
that these young
people can access.
But how are people finding them?
How do you see folks
overcoming, in some
of these markets, the
connectivity issues or even
their mindset that they don't
have the type of resources
that they need?
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
Yeah, so I'll tell you,
I mean, at least from what
we're doing in RAISE--
so one of the
advantages of being MIT
is, we are a place that people
tend to just Google and find,
what is MIT doing in this space?
And they do tend to find
MIT RAISE or Day of AI
from that search.
With the Day of AI
program, in particular,
that's because I
feel it's like-- it
is for all students
and all teachers.
It's designed for that.
It is like the
entry-level point, where
it's like, if
you're just curious,
and you want to try to
see what it's about,
and you're not able to take
a semester-long curriculum--
because there's a lot of
curriculum that are being
developed out there right now.
But it's mostly for
computer-science teachers.
This is positioned
very differently.
This is really AI and
digital citizenship.
And we've designed it
with access in mind.
So we have materials that
span the whole gamut from,
yeah, if you want to be coding
apps through App Inventor
and things like that,
you can do that.
We have curriculum that doesn't
involve technology at all.
So, for instance, when the
White House, last year,
released their blueprint
for an AI Bill of Rights,
we created a whole curriculum in
AI and human rights and policy
that kids debate.
Doesn't require any
technology whatsoever.
So we have tried
to create materials
that no matter how
technologically comfortable
teachers are or
resourced they are,
there is something there that
they should be able to access
and bring to their students.
We are now working more
systematically and strategically
with organizations
around the world.
These are usually ministries
of education, increasingly,
or non-profits, where
they want to take--
and I call them reference--
[INAUDIBLE] reference materials
and then localize them
so that they're relevant
to their local region
and adapt them for that context.
And then they help recruit
and train teachers.
So, again, it's
becoming a very network,
community-oriented
approach, where we've done,
again, the reference design.
But then we are-- it's open.
It's Open Creative Commons.
It's the expectation
that people will
take them and adapt them
to be relevant and on point
for their students.
And so, we're starting to
see that happen as well.
So, for instance, we have
a particular foundation
that we've been
collaborating with in Chile.
If you to the Day
of AI website--
they have been bringing it to
many, many different countries
in Latin and South America.
So we often rely again on
our local collaborators
to help get that scale.
So there are
materials out there.
And I know we've done research
around the Day of AI materials.
There's a whole
evaluation study,
if you go to the Day of
AI website, with teachers
from like 40 countries.
We're being successful, I
think, in teachers' ability
to take these materials and
adapt them to their context
and feel that they're
having a good experience,
both for themselves as teachers
and for their students.
So I would definitely encourage
people to check those out.
We have recommended grade bands.
But I can tell you
this material--
I think it's also super
relevant for post-secondary.
If you're really talking
about, what the heck is AI?
And what's the responsible use?
And how do I think about the
ethical implications of--
that's what this curriculum is.
You can age up the dialogue
and the projects or down,
accordingly.
We just have
recommended grade bands.
But I think this
is so foundational.
It's actually, again,
just a good foundation
course for all kinds of people.
So I would definitely point
people there first and foremost.
And it is different, I think,
because most other curriculum
that I know of has largely
been designed, again,
for computer-science-oriented
instructors.
So, anyway, this is different.
This is really, "AI
is for everyone."
[LAUGHS]
MEGAN MITCHELL: [LAUGHS]
That's fantastic.
We have our first question in
the chat-- that I'm going to--
from Marta Aymerich.
And she is at the eHealth
Center at our Open
University of Catalonia,
so one of J-WEL members.
And there's the age old--
there's a lot of resistance
from many teachers
in introducing AI in education.
And I was even thinking
about these building blocks
that they're learning
by doing, not
by the lecture, which is also
such a traditional mode in so
many parts of the world.
How do you actively
try and get people
past that those mindset biases?
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: So we're in a
couple intriguingly-interesting
conversations with
ministries of education.
I think we're just at a time
now where the world acknowledges
it's just really important
to build a foundational AI
literacy, if not AI
fluency, in general.
So you're always going to
have your early movers,
your innovators.
And that's who's coming to
us right now, understandably.
I think we're starting to
move into this next phase,
where ministries of
education are like,
no, this is actually important.
And we need to figure out how
to get it in systematically
into the formal education system
in a way that makes sense,
given that teachers already have
to teach a lot of other stuff.
But to make room for that--
so part of this is we have
to incentivize teachers
through the mechanisms
that allow them to advocate
or convince whoever they
need to that they can do so,
whether that's professional
development credits that they
need to do anyway or
advocate to the principal
or to the administrators of the
school that this is important.
Or if in different parts
of the world-- again,
if ministries of education
also help to signal,
this is actually really
important and is important that
you teach it--
I think we're trying to create
the conditions upon which
teachers feel they are able
to actually set the time aside
to actually do this.
And we're trying to be very
mindful of the amount of time
we're asking of
teachers to do this.
So, again, that's why we're
starting with short format?
But we're trying to do both
the top down and bottom up.
And we're running
some experiments
in different parts of
the world right now
to see what that looks like.
But I'm just
sharing, in general,
there seems to be
acknowledgment at the top level.
This is important.
And growing grassroots
and quality materials
that people can look
at and go, oh, people,
are having a good experience,
I should try that--
and it's not a super heavy lift.
That's how we're trying
to help bring those two
ends of the spectrum together.
The other thing that I think
is just worth people knowing is
an exercise that we're
actively involved in
is-- because we have, again,
a wide range of curriculum,
we're actually starting
to think about packaged
subject-relevant curriculum.
So if you're a math teacher
or a science teacher
or an arts teacher or a
social studies teacher
or an English or
language arts teacher,
what might be a short form
AI literacy curriculum
that both matches to what
you have to teach anyway,
but then also helps you
learn about AI, right?
So we're in that
exercise right now
as another tactic to try to
help teachers bring AI education
into their classrooms.
So we're trying to
figure out how to make
all of these incentives align.
But I think the broader
ecosystem is also starting
to align around this as well.
MEGAN MITCHELL: I think, for
the teachers on this call
and the educators who
might feel like they're
those early adopters,
I imagine it's
encouraging to hear that the
ministries are seeing this.
There are people
that they might not
get to hear from and talk to.
But you are seeing
this, at least
at either end of the spectrum.
And it'll come together,
which is, I think,
important and exciting.
One last question, also from
a member, Melchor Snchez
who's with UNAM in Mexico--
and he's interested just in
your thoughts and comments
on the challenges of
excessively anthropomorphizing
the different personal
characteristics when
you use these GenAI tools.
and what you're seeing-- you're
able to combat people's concerns
or respond to and
ameliorate their concerns--
would be interesting
to understand.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: Yeah.
So, I mean, I would
say, this is very much
why we started to go
deep into AI literacy
was exactly this point.
So we are designing these
personified AI technologies,
have done it for
decades, to try to help
promote human flourishing.
But we have seen examples now--
social media is like the poster
child for where a lot
of harm is being done
through these technologies.
And then with ChatGPT--
again, it started with Siri
and then Alexa, now ChatGPT.
We have seen it for decades,
people's willingness
to engage socially and
emotionally with these AI
technologies.
Now, you're seeing it at scale.
And then sometimes, the
media will present you
again stories and dialogues
where it's like, whoa,
maybe not so healthy, right?
So this is why the AI
literacy piece is so critical.
And I think the big thing people
have to understand right now--
and I have other
slides around this.
The paradox, if I'll
call it a paradox,
is that the generative-AI
technologies present themselves
as being very capable,
in a human-like way,
through language.
But they're not human.
The way they think, the way
they generate the outputs,
is not human at all.
It's completely
different, right?
I mean, a lot of these--
the large language models
are language models.
They're trying to predict
and generate the next word.
So we just have
to all understand
that when it's
generating an output that
could be really intriguing
and on point and exciting
or completely off, the
algorithm does not understand
what it's generating.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Yes.
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL:
All the meaning
is ascribed to the human
being who is looking at it
and making sense of it
to say, wow, that was
really useful or creative.
Or what the heck?
It's like, oh,
completely wrong, right?
The AI do not understand
what they're generating.
They are generating,
and human beings
are ascribing the meaning, which
is why we have to be critical,
in the right sense, of is that
output valuable, useful to me,
or not?
Because, again, when used
responsibly, appropriately,
it can help accelerate.
And it can be, again, terrific.
But it can also be
incredibly misleading.
We see examples of like, "It
seems so reasonable in its
response."
And if you're an
expert-- and you're
like, but that is completely
made up [LAUGHS] right?
So you just have to be
a critical thinker when
you use these kinds of
tools and technologies.
So the responsible use
piece of the AI literacy
and understanding what these
algorithms are actually
doing so you understand how
much you can rely on them
and not to over rely on
them is really important.
So whether it's the personified
aspects or the information--
no matter what the aspect,
it's just important, I think,
that people understand
what these algorithms are
doing so that you understand,
this is how much I can rely
on them to do something, right?
I always have to think
critically about the output.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Great.
Well, on that note, I hope
everyone can join me in thanking
Cynthia very much for an
incredibly interesting
and informative "packed with
good resources and information"
session.
For those of you who are here,
Amy has already put in the chat,
members will be doing a
roundtable discussion next week
with Hae Won Park, who is a very
valuable member of Cynthia's
team and lab, to do
further discussions.
And there's another
event on August 22
coming up, for the broader
public on emerging AI
innovations.
We have video recorded this.
And so, we'll make that video
available to the folks who
are here and publicly.
And we will be sending a survey.
So we really would appreciate
folks' feedback and input
because this is a give and take.
And I think that came
through loud and clear
even from what
Cynthia was sharing.
We don't do any of
our work alone at MIT.
We understand that there are
local contexts and information
and knowledge we can be
getting at every stage.
So thank you, everyone,
for being here.
Looking forward to seeing
some of you next week
and others later in August.
Take care.
Bye, bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]