Hi everyone. I'm delighted to be here to
present the startup lightning talks.
Today we're showcasing some of the
newest startups that have recently uh
joined Startup Exchange. They're all
working in the AI space and they focus
on a wide range of industries from
manufacturing to transportation,
insurance, forestry and others.
Application wise, this is a pretty
diverse uh group too with applications
ranging from workflow automation
uh infrastructure safety, human behavior
um among others. With this broad
selection of startups, we want to give
you an idea of the technologies emerging
from MIT. We believe these technologies
and businesses have the power to solve
some of the challenges you're likely
facing and can contribute to the growth
of your
businesses. They are going to show us
some of the use cases they've been
working on with partners and customers.
And one thing they need more of is
customers like you. So I encourage you
to meet them throughout the day and
start discussing uh potential joint
opportunities. And this is that's what
we do at Startup Exchange. We bring
together MIT connected startups and
industry to help you foster some kind of
collaborations and partnerships. We do
that in a few different ways as you'll
find out in a moment. So uh the startups
we support all of them have a strong
connection with MIT. In some cases the
connection comes through the founding
team in other cases through the
technology. And we also support startups
that although don't have origin at MIT,
they are vetted and supported by some of
our peers which then makes them eligible
to us. In this case, by peers I mean
Cale Startup Connect plus engine um um
and I'm blanking on one
center
if start on Nano. Thank you very
much. Um then uh our network uh
currently has uh about close to a
thousand startups virtually working in
any sector and we're also location
agnostic. So uh in our portfolio we have
companies that are based here but as
well spread throughout the world. Now
everything we do at Startup Exchange is
to expose and connect startups and
industry in a highly created way and we
also provide learning opportunities to
both parties. This includes launching
calls for startups based on corporate's
own priorities and challenges,
facilitating one-on-one meetings between
both parties, hosting uh virtual demo
days, although these typically tend to
take place once a quarter, but this year
we have a special live edition that is
taking place tomorrow, and other formats
of events. The learning opportunities
can take different formats as well from
workshops, training sessions and these
we tend to coorganize with peers such as
the Martin Trust Center for MIT
entrepreneurship
um uh E14, Sandbox, VMS uh and
others. This slide features a small
sample of the success cases we had to
date. again all focused on
collaborations and partnerships that um
and the ones we see taking shape more
often are proofs of concept pilots uh
joint development and even acquisitions.
This is startup exchange in a nutshell.
If you'd like to learn more about it,
please do reach out during the
breaks. And now before passing the word
to the entrepreneurs, I'd like to invite
you to our upcoming events. Tomorrow
we're hosting two additional events
dedicated to AI. We are at capacity, but
you can still register to get your uh
link a link to the live stream. Then on
April 10, we're hosting a new leading
edge webinar this time around about
computationally assisted materials. And
then on May 8, we're back with a new
edition of the Health Science Forum.
And now it is my pleasure to kick off
the startup lightning talks. Each
entrepreneur is presenting for five
minutes and then at the end you can meet
them all uh at the startup exhibit that
is taking place uh in the room next
door.