morning
everybody Welcome to our Leading
Edge energy webinar series my name is CJ
gu a program director with the uh office
of cooperate relations at MIT as many of
you know uh our office has a industrial
leis program and a start exchange
platform uh through which we've been
helping hundreds of the world most
Innovation minded companies to access
mit's research Technologies startups and
an overall Boston
Cambridge Innovation Innovation
ecosystem now tackling the climate
change
challenges and promoting sustainable
development have very high priorities at
MIT and we know that
decarbonization is the in the core of
many or any corporations sust
sustainable development
initiatives especially so for companies
in the manufacturing
energy and uh other
sectors but decarbonization and
sustainable development are not just
setting goals and investing in R&D and
doing commercial
projects you also need to have a very
deep understanding on technology
options is
economics it's interplay between
Technology Solutions and policies and
ultimately the viability of your
Solutions or your options
in the real
world that's why we organize today's
webinar focus on
decarbonization and we've invited to
Leading researchers from
MIT Dr Amir
gansi and Dr Jennifer Morris to share
their deep insights with us in this very
important
domain as you know in MIT we
also not just doing research developing
technology we also developing generating
companies and
many people from MIT start their own
companies to move the research results
further into the real world to make a
positive impact so we also invite two
MIT connect connected
startups to demonstrate what they do in
these important directions after the
presentation of the uh of uh Dr GF and
uh more
Morris so you of course you obviously
you can
participate by submit your
questions using the Q&A tab at the
bottom of your screen and we'll try to
answer your questions as much as as much
as as we
can now with that uh please welcome our
first Speaker
today uh Dr Amir
janser Amir is the a principal research
scientist at mit's energy initiative and
he is also
the co-founder and CEO of company called
Sesame technology a great system
modeling platform for the Energy
System Amir take it over from here
please thank you CJ for the introduction
and thank you for the invitation to
speak uh with this group uh so like
today I will be speaking about the novel
systems analysis platform uh which is
Sesame uh that was the research that we
were conducting at MIT energy initiative
and as CJ mentioned now we also have a
startup commercializing these
Technologies so this uh software is uh
helping industrial companies to make
better decision in terms of their
decarbonization and today's topic will
be showing you what kind of Technology
we have developed and also applications
of these technology in Iron and Steel
and green hydrogen projects and also
combination of uh hydrogen and
steel so like I I I know everybody knows
but like just a brief motivation about
why we are focusing on Industrial
decarbonization when we look at
industrial and transportation sector
emissions they amount approximately 46%
of global ghg
emissions and like there is also a huge
cost involved with this around 15
trillion to decarbonize through
2050 and every company and every
government is really focusing on how we
can decarbonize these uh like Industries
and also how we can make it cost
effective uh and one of the key areas
that we see as a challenge is that uh
planning reporting and verification of
these is not trivial and currently
existing software or existing
capabilities really like industrial
knoow and that's the Gap we are trying
to
fill so I will briefly mention about
Sesame what we do like in the next three
slides and I will directly dive into the
uh case study that I want to share with
you so in terms of what we are doing at
Sesame uh so this is a software platform
that brings together all modeling needs
for for portfolio decarbonization into a
single platform by this what I mean is
you need first principle process level
detailed models you need to understand
cost and emissions and in this emission
side it is basically life cycle
emissions throughout the life cycle of
these products uh you need to optimize
all these systems for location
technology options so and so forth and
of course depending on where you are uh
there might be some policy levs that
might benefit or uh selection of these
Technologies and all of these are
integrated to a single platform very
usable platform so that it can uh make
your decision making process easier and
also uh drive you with optimal
results and in terms of the type of
analysis that is required for energy
transition and decarbonization the first
one is really big picture comparison and
in this I mean like you have Supply
chains for whatever you product you are
producing from from whatever resources
you want to start and you will you need
to represent these Supply chains quite
of a uh in quite of a uh detail so like
how you resource your uh energy
resources how you transport store
convert to other uh forms so and so
forth and the first step is really
configuring these Supply chains and this
is where we have a very very flexible
platform so like we created hundreds of
modules that represent different
technology options and you can easily
configure Supply chains and customize
these based on your needs the second
piece which is key here is the analysis
which is a combination of cost and
Emissions analysis and traditionally
cost and Emissions analysis are uh
conducted separately and this has a main
problem of not having the same bases so
making Apples to Apples comparison
difficult and
by having everything in a single uh
consistent platform we are solving this
problem and you can see scope one to
three emissions as well as cost of the
product and finally to make the decision
you need a comparison metric and in
terms of decarbonization cost of CO2
avoided is the Natural Choice because it
combines cost and Emissions into a
single metric and then you can compare
all these different supply chain options
technology options and see what is
the best solution for your particular
case and the second type of analysis
which is critical for making good
decisions is how you will be optimizing
your projects in the renewable energy
resources Paradigm most of the
decarbonization efforts uses renewable
energy in one way or other and most
often we are really relying on
intermittent resources such as solar and
wind and the integration of these
resources are very region dependent as
well as uh process dependent so for most
industrial applications you need steady
state feed stock whether it is hydrogen
or power and the processes are not
really designed to be operated at a
variable load so this of course creates
a challenge because either you need to
uh like overbuild these to produce more
when these resources are available and
store your product or integrate uh uh
energy storage options like batteries
and to be able to do that you really
need to have a very sophisticated
optimization capability uh that will be
giving you renewable uh sizing as well
as design choices for every location of
interest and that's the second area that
uh like we have integrated in our
platform and then you will see in
examples how these are used uh and how
these can actually give very interesting
insights now as I promised I'm Switching
gears towards a detailed example uh and
I will start with Iron and Steel uh so
Iron and Steel is particularly
interesting because uh first of all it
is a uh like a very emission intensive
uh process So currently around 7% of
global emissions are sourced from Iron
and Steel uh
manufacturing uh and secondly uh the we
expect a major growth in the production
of Iron and Steel because of uh more
urbanization having buildings relying on
steel so on so
forth uh and when we currently look into
the production it is mostly uh in China
followed by uh like many other countries
and today's discussions will be India
and Us in this context because both have
different characterist characteristics
that makes the kind of analysis quite
interesting so why Iron and Steel is a
hard to Abate sector uh it is mostly
relying on fossil resources currently
and there are two main uh sources of CO2
emissions that we see and here this is a
schematic of blast furnace uh and uh
like this figure is from uh like Sydney
Johnson's PhD
CIS uh so what you see here here is that
there are mainly two sources of CO2 one
is combustion of uh coal or other fuels
that you use to be able to uh produce
heat uh that will be helping the running
the reaction and the second one is uh
reduction of iron step so for the
reduction of iron uh when you reduce uh
iron uh so you also release some CO2
basically you really need to be able to
decarbonize these two sources to uh get
as low as CO2 as
possible how can we decarbonize so this
is the main question that we are asking
for all the sectors and Iron and Steel
is again a
interesting example because we have all
three options that is mostly discussed
in the industrial decarbonization uh
concept so one is fuel switching uh so
today mostly uh steel production relies
on coal and switching to lower carbon
fuels uh including natural gas uh even
though it's fossil fuel it has lower CO2
content uh low carbon hydrogen or
biomass bofes can reduce the emissions
and in this case it can be a combination
of continuing using existing technology
by Fuel switching or also adding new
technologies to further reduce the
emissions because as we've discussed in
the previous slide so it is not only
about the fuel source but the reduction
steps also uh create some
emissions the second option is uh
continue using fossil Resources with or
without fuel switching and uh introduce
carbon capture and storage in this case
uh like in addition to adding carbon
capture you also have choices whether it
will be a post combustion chemical uh
capture or it will be combustion if you
are uh like making your fuel uh zero
emission or low emission and it can be
physical absorption base such as uh or
absorption based such as mea so and so
forth it can also be cryogenic capture
and the third option which is usually
the most expensive option is uh retiring
your existing plants and then changing
Technologies so here there are different
Technologies so you can switch PL from
blast furnace to uh direct reduced iron
options but also there are new
technologies coming into the market such
as molten oxide electrolyzers or uh that
will be helping with the smelting
reduction and there are some commercial
Technologies corex and hisna which is
based on these
Concepts so now I will directly go into
the results to compare these options and
provide some uh insights about what can
be
done the first uh like the first before
the results I just want to also show you
why we are focusing in India India is
like of course like as a like growing
economy and uh like the production of
Iron and Steel and other Industrial
Products will be quite important in the
coming years and when we look at the
projections India steel sector uh is
expected to increase production by
million tons uh by 2030 so it is a very
short period of time to significantly
increase the uh total production
level and India is also coming with a
specific challenge because when we look
at the emission intensity of uh steel
Pro manufactured or produced in India
its average carbon intensity is around
2.3 ton of CO2 per ton of Steel and this
is uh significantly higher than the
global average which is 1.8 T CO2 per
ton steel uh and currently it is mostly
coal based both for blast furnaces as
well as the direct reduced uh reduction
of iron and it really opens up all the
cap uh all the options that we discussed
in the previous uh slide so like it can
be a combination of using carbon
captures fuel switching or Bol to make
these uh emission intensity lower
so as you can see in this slide there
are many different options uh and these
options are shown on the left hand side
including Blast Furnace uh direct
reduced iron as well as the new
technologies of uh smelting Technologies
like corex and
hna and currently ER India relies on the
red box Technologies coal based direct
reduced iron and blast furnace using
coal so the emission intensities as you
can see are uh around 2.4 to 2.7 ton CO2
uh per ton of uh steel now we can you
can see there is a big uh range of
results here uh so depending on the
exact technology that's used but you can
see like whatever uh the decision is you
are always reducing emissions so
actually this is a good uh First Step
because like any technology change fuel
switching will end up uh improving the
emission intensity of uh the techn the
steel
manufacturing and if we start with the
best option in terms of emissions it is
switching to Green hydrogen direct
reduce iron so in this case uh the
emission intensity can be reduced by 81
to
84% relative to traditional co-based
Pathways and this is of course a
significant emission reduction uh and
just to remind you in this slide we are
only focusing on emission so like the
best solution is of course the solution
that will give us uh the highest
emission reduction and with this it also
uh we need to remind ourselves that
there are multiple questions here one is
how much it will cost the second one is
can we really do that uh like what are
supply chain uh challenges we might be
overseeing so on and so forth and all of
these will be addressed in the upcoming
slides uh but let's keep our Hope High
and say okay so if we are able to switch
to Green hydrogen we can have a
significant emission reduction and that
can be one of the cleanest uh hydrogen
production options uh that's available
the second option is adding carbon
capture uh so in this case if we include
carbon capture uh so it can reduce
emissions by
70% and that's also significant emission
reduction and so you can see in this
graph as well as uh the uh like the
other CCS options so this is uh quite
interesting and quite doable uh so the
main challenge for that is of course how
are we retrofitting these plants and the
second question that comes is what
carbon capture technology we use and
with what fuel we are uh powering these
carbon capture uh plants and the third
option that we see here which is quite
interesting is the uh direct reduced
iron uh so if we use natural gas based
drri so you can immediately cut down
emissions by
uh
70% and if you add ccs to that it will
further reduce emissions and so here
basically we have kind of compared all
these options uh and as you can see
these are quite detailed in terms of the
fuel use uh like byproduct uh
composition and as well as the
electricity input so on so forth and by
doing this sort of analysis for a
particular region and particular
industry you can easily compare
different options that might be viable
or that might not be viable and as I
mentioned for this particular slide
emission intensity is the only metric
but there are many other questions to be
asked uh and some of these answers will
be actually different than uh based on
the metric of
interest and in the case of uh cost
which is the real pain Point uh
so what we see here is that whatever we
switch to uh we see a seven like 5 to
75% increase in the cost of Steel
products and of course this is a quite
steep uh increase uh and we know there
is a penalty for uh most of the
decarbonization uh Pathways and in this
case uh switching from coal to any other
options uh will increase the cost by 5
to
75% so here uh I think the first uh bar
that will be probably uh getting
everyone's attention is the green
hydrogen so in this graph on the left
hand side we have the cost of Steel
which is uh represented as dollar per
ton of
steel and on the right hand side we have
the emission intensity so basically
these are the results from the previous
result slide and green hydrogen had the
lowest emission as you can see from the
uh dot here uh but it also has the
highest cost so like it is
73% uh like it is uh it has a
73% cost increase relative to Coal based
direct reduced iron and this is as you
can relative to other options is a uh it
might be prohibitively expensive but in
this particular uh slide and I I on
purpose included this there are other
questions that we will be asking so
what's the cost of green hydrogen where
do you produce these how do you handle
intermittency so and so forth and all of
these will be answered in the upcoming
slides uh but for one snapshot results
this is one snapshot and representative
results this is the uh
where the cost stands relative to other
options and the second one is the use of
carbon capture and in this case we are
looking into
mea based carbon capture and in this
case they increase the uh cost by
48% relative to blast furnace and uh mea
based carbon capture uh presents the uh
more expensive CCS options here so as
you can see we have included other
Technologies like selexol and use of uh
uh other PSA options vpsa and then uh
relative to all of these other options
uh it has the highest cost uh and
another interesting result we've seen is
that one of the Technologies new
technologies which is the using selting
reduction technology might actually be
cheaper than the current uh Tech
technology which is blast fors so again
so this results should be all always
taken with a grant of salt because these
are new technologies and the commercial
deployment might might be different so
and so forth but there is at least a
possibility that there will be a
decarbonization solution which will also
reduce cost and these kind of solutions
are great because you are not only
reducing emissions but also you are uh
cost saving so actually that can uh
motivate companies governments to really
push towards these Technologies as soon
as
possible uh but of course we need to
also take into account that the emission
reduction is uh like quite High relative
to basis but in terms of the total
emission uh intensity of Steel so it it
is much higher than other options that
we see in the uh CCS pain or uh the
green hydrogen
cases and finally as we briefly
mentioned in the first couple of slides
the comparison metrix in these cases is
cost of CO2
avoided and in this case uh like
basically we have compared all these
options uh in terms of uh relative to
blast furnace option and as you can
see uh some of these options are quite
uh cheap so and in the higher case
smelting reduction case actually it is
is uh cheaper than the uh Benchmark
option uh but some Alternatives like uh
green hydrogen or use of CCS for uh
blast furnace in terms of cost of CO2
avoided can be higher and I think
there's one interesting results that you
will see here even though green hydrogen
case was the most expensive solution in
terms of uh the uh
cost of Steel manufactured in terms of
cost of CO2 avoided it is not the most
expensive option and this is uh because
the emission reduction you achieved by
switching to Green hydrogen is more than
80% uh and the combined impact of cost
and Emissions is reflected in this graph
and as you can see like adding carbon
capture to existing blast furnace is
actually a much more expensive option
than switching to any other options or
even using green
hydrogen and this is a quite important
metric to use to compare these options
because ultimately our goal is really to
reduce emissions as much as possible to
get to uh our climate
goals so now uh like we've discussed
quite a bit about hydrogen green
hydrogen Pathways and how it can be
potentially interesting for the uh
emission uction in the steel industry so
now of course we need to really focus on
how can we optimize green hydrogen
production and just a brief definition
of what is green hydrogen green hydrogen
is basically hydrogen produced from
Renewable Power ER combined with
electrolyzers so by definition we are
relying on renewable energy sources and
renewable energy sources are
intermittently available and these uh
Vari abilities exists both day today
hour to hour but also there is a major
difference between season to season and
all of these kind of uh variabilities
intermittencies needs to be taken into
account when we are designing systems uh
to produce whatever product we are
interested using these options and just
as a reference here I have included a
solar PV profile and a onshore wind
profile uh so you can see for a one day
rep representative day for solar we have
around 5 hours or so solar energy so we
really need to produce whatever we need
to produce during this period of time
and for onshore wind the profile is a
little bit different depending on where
you are depending on the season uh but
it might have wider hours of uh wind
availability and then then you might see
actually multiple days of no wind
blowing at all and there are many
strategies to combine these uh resources
so it doesn't need to be really relying
on one uh and for that particular uh
study we are taking a sophisticated
optimization approach and in this
approach we are uh optimizing the
deployment of renewable assets as well
as
electrolyzers their
sizing uh in a single uh optimization
model and by doing that we are trying to
use all these resources to together to
increase the capacity factor of
electrolyzers or in return to come up
with the minimal cost uh optimal uh
levelized cost of
hydrogen and so if everything was
similar to Fossil resources where you
can just turn on Renewables and then use
uh that energy for whatever purpose you
need uh we can just connect Renewables
to electrolyzers and we can produce
hydrogen that will be uh meeting a
constant demand uh for industrial
applications but because of the profiles
that we just discussed we need to
include some uh options here and there
are mainly two options one is including
batteries so when you or energ any type
of energy storage when you produce
electricity from Renewables uh store
some of that electricity to be used
later to uh continuously Supply hydrogen
or you you can overbuild both renewable
capacity as well as electrolyzer
capacity to produce more of the product
in this case hydrogen uh when the
Renewables are available and then store
hydrogen and then make sure that you
still have the constant Supply uh to
meet the demand from industrial
facilities so we have performed many of
these type of analysis and what we've
seen is currently battery technologies
are prohibitively expensive so so like
even if we include in the uh
optimization the model never picks
batteries uh with current and projected
near-term cost so that's why we can
eliminate that uh for the uh making
these a little bit simpler optimization
problem and then we can focus on the
including hydrogen storage uh to make
these uh system work and Supply uh
steady state hydrogen
so I will I will be giving uh examples
from two regions uh and like our
capabilities and also many analysis we
have done actually is much more granular
than that so we can really do zip code
level analysis for the entire Globe uh
and this particular case study has been
actually performed for a recent study by
uh National Petroleum Council uh like
looking at the future of hydrogen in the
us context and all these results are
available in the report and we are more
than happy to share that report it's in
the public
domain but for the uh demonstration
purposes uh so like I will be looking
into comparison between West Coast and
Gulf Coast and these are two US regions
and on the right hand side you can see
the current uh hydrogen demand in these
uh locations so G Coast is uh is the
basically Hub of most the refineries as
a as well as other chemical uh
production facilities not surprisingly
we see a major uh consumption of
hydrogen uh which is around 5.8 million
tons per year and in the west coast
there are some refiner operations and
some chemical plants and also West Coast
is uh the there's the highest number of
hydrogen fuel of electric vehicles in
the US and you will see so the total
demand today is around 1 million tons
per year so uh now we will be looking at
the cost of these two options and why uh
we see a major cost difference uh when
we optimize these two systems so just to
start with uh so the tot to today's cost
of hydrogen from uh natural gas based
production is around $ and if you add
one1 to $1 and half dollar and when you
add carbon capture uh to reduce
emissions by 90
95% the cost can go up to $2 or so so
here in this case when we optimize
everything as you can see the cost of
green hydrogen at the production side is
around
5.7 per kilogram of hydrogen in the Gulf
Coast and it's around $7.2 per kilogram
of hydrogen in the west coast and uh you
will see this is like capex this
includes both renewable assets as well
as
electrolyzers uh contributes quite a bit
in both cases and the second uh piece is
the power cost which is the solar and
wind cost in this case so basically this
is mostly driven by uh renewable assets
as well as the expensive electrolyzer uh
deployment for these locations to
produce green clean
hydrogen so key Tes from this analysis
so we the uh like levelized cost of
hydrogen uh being around $1 and half per
kg of hydrogen more expensive in the
west cost and for the key drivers for
that it is the tradeoff between
electrolyzer capacity factor and power
cost so this is clearly seen in the
relative contribution of electr capex
and power costs so if the capacity
factor of uh renewable assets
were same exactly the same with Gulf
Coast we will see that actually relative
to capex of electrolyzers we should see
a similar uh capex in the uh power
system but we don't see it and the
reason for that is that for these two
regions uh the renewable availability
renewable resource availability is quite
different in the west coast first of all
it is mostly relying on solar uh solar
availability is great but solar
resources are also very intermittently
available and this having only few hours
a day available mean you need to
significantly oversize these assets uh
whenever you are building uh renew like
solar based uh chemical production
facilities ER and another advantage of
Golf Coast we see here is that the huge
uh potential in Wind resources so wind
capacity factor is not only High here
but also solar availability is quite
competitive with West so in GF cost
basically there is a combination of
complementary solar and wind resources
that really makes this location very
favorable to produce green hydrogen or
any type of uh green power Renewable
Power based uh
products uh and what we see in these
cases so like for the especially solar
relevant uh energy production so we
increase the generation of solar uh
electricity uh during the day so that we
can use the electrolyzers at highest
capacity Factor as possible and produce
as much hydrogen as possible during
these period of time and the reason we
see this kind of increase in the power
cost is actually coming from this
because you you are significantly
oversizing your Renewables uh to be able
to get every uh like light of sun as
well as you convert that into green
hydrogen and like in this approach the
first approach that we've didn't we have
done we have used kind of an average
capacity Factor uh for these locations
uh to optimize the entire system but the
problem is a little bit more
sophisticated than that because uh as we
mentioned initially so all of these
resources are extremely region dependent
so even like the big uh map we had for
West Coast and Gulf Coast is covering so
many different
regions and we see when we look into
this data you see a difference uh from
One Mile Square to Other M Square so
another uh way of doing these sort of
anal is really taking into account the
capacity factors at a very high temporal
and geospacial
resolution and in this case for uh
demonstration purposes we will be
looking into GF coast and here uh I
plotted uh like different capacity
factors in terms of wind solar geologic
storage which is another key driver for
uh the cost of hydrogen because you need
to also store these uh hydrogen resource
hydrogen products to be able to use in
whenever the demand is and then uh like
now we can take a much more granular
approach and then take these entire uh
regions and make it into different
nodes and the second question is how do
we optimize the entire system and the
entire network so here uh we have we
know all the available resources as well
as we know all the demand not so where
this hydrogen will be supplied to
produce whatever the end product we are
interested in and by doing this so we uh
create a multinodal optimization problem
where uh the we give all this
information to the model and then the
model picks where to build uh renewable
projects as well as electrolyzers and
how it can be deployed and transmitted
and in this case what you see is by
doing this
optimization uh the realistic cost of
delivered hydrogen and again so this is
delivered hydrogen and in the previous
graphs we were focusing only on the
production can go up to $6.1 uh dollar
per kilogram of hydrogen and what we see
here is that the model picks one region
to really produce all the hydrogen and
then all the electricity and most of the
hydrogen and then uh with red arrows it
uh picks a building a hydrogen pipeline
to cost effectively deliver these
hydrogen to the Final locations and in
some locations uh send the electricity
via the blue lines uh to produce
hydrogen for smaller demands uh at the
location of demand so that actually you
can see there's a tradeoff here so if
the demand is very high it's better to
produce hydrogen in a central location
and invest in pipelines versus if the uh
demand is relatively low it might be
more cost effective to uh produce
electricity stand that electricity and
produce hydrogen near the demand
site so in terms of key finding so like
we what we haven't discussed is like
there's an important trade-off between
the storage capability so if the storage
is uh available geologic storage that
makes the cost of hydrogen quite cheap
in all of these example what we've seen
is with inflation uction act and 45 F
tax credit actually green hydrogen can
be competitive with the
uh uh natural gas based options uh it is
still slightly higher uh at a slightly
higher cost when you include tax credit
but it might be competitive and green
hydrogen requires transport so like it
either it will be transmission or
transport we really need to take this
into account when we are doing these
sorts of analysis and in the final two
slides I will combine the discussion of
green hydrogen in Iron and Steel so we
we took an approach in India to compare
different technology options but when we
take a regional uh analysis stand so we
can really look into the US Fleet and
now that we also have all the tools and
uh necessary to be able to optimize the
green hydrogen availability and pro
capability so now we are uh taking this
approach to overlap the need for uh
emission reduction in US steel Fleet and
how we can make sure that we can do it
cost effectively so here we we are again
like using this inflation reduction tax
credits ER to compare these uh options
especially on the green hydrogen side
and here I have included two scenarios
one is uh without credit without tax
credit and the second one is with
extended tax credit that will include
the
um uh green hydrogen uh that will be
used in the Iron and Steel sector so in
terms of annual greenhouse gas emissions
from all the plans that you've seen uh
if we have uh the extension of uh
inflation reduction at tax credit we see
a lower emissions total
emissions uh and this is not
insignificant so you can see close to uh
30% reduction in total emissions and in
terms of cost actually
it is it might be slightly lower in
terms of the delivered cost of Steel and
on the bottom row what we see is that
whether we have credit or no credit
actually we see a massive change in the
production mix so in the case of there's
no credit we rely on mostly e electric
Arc furnace and also uh natural gas
based direct reduce iron uh but if the
there is uh extended tax credit then we
see that all the natural gas based
direct reduced iron is actually
switching to Green hydrogen because it
is both cost effective and also it
significantly reduce emissions relative
to other options so with that I will
conclude with these key takeaways so
whatever we do we really need detailed
cost and Emissions analysis and this is
quite challenging because in addition to
doing this kind of analysis for every
project we need to also take into
account new uncertainties with emerging
Technologies and implementation of the
Technologies for different
assets uh so the main challenge what we
see here is that we need to integrate uh
many conventional not connected energy
sub sector so this includes power
hydrogen so on and so forth and this
requires adapting a systems analysis
approach and this is what I really try
to show you with these examples that it
is actually a very multi-layer approach
and you really need to have everything
otherwise you will be making suboptimal
decisions Regional analysis is very
important and f one final key Point
whatever we do the first response is it
depends and then we really need to do
these all these detailed analysis and we
will see there's no silver blot that
will solve all our problems uh for
different regions different technology
options I'll stop here and uh back to
you CJ I think we are opening up for the
Q&A yeah yeah thanks Emir as great
analysis and great presentation and we
do have some good questions as well uh
the first one is uh how do you think of
the idea of replacing natural gas with
biomethane in in the steel
decarbonization uh
Direction yeah actually that's one of
the uh interesting option so it can be
either biomethane or renewable natural
gas and it can reduce emissions so of
course as we mentioned in the earlier
slide so like if you start with a carbon
containing fuel you will always have
some emissions uh but if it is sourced
by biobased or renewable uh based
sources or renewable natural gas which
is basically the today's uh the
emissions coming from mostly uh Solid
Waste or uh like farms uh so that
provides the emission reduction and I
think another good option using direct
reduced iron is down the line you can
also change switch to Green hydrogen or
uh sources that doesn't contain uh CO2
so I think that's one of the interesting
options and we have that analysis as
well I haven't included here but it's
also published so like we can also share
the publication uh with the person
asking the question okay great uh the
second question uh uh do you do you know
any uh pilot projects of uh steel making
with ccs that shows some
promises so I know projects but I
haven't seen anything that is already
deployed so like I know there are a
number of projects that has been
considered uh but I don't have a data
point where it is uh currently uh ready
to be used and we are collecting
data okay uh third question uh uh can
you discuss the hydrogen losses uh in
storage and
transmission yeah so that's a great
question so in terms of hydrogen uh
losses uh so hydrogen is a very small
molecule and it is even harder uh to
keep it relative to natural gas and when
we think about natural gas pipelines we
know that there is a couple of percent
uh leakage uh from these pipelines and
we expect that actually hydrogen will
have a little bit higher leakages uh due
to the being even smaller molecule and
for storage as well so for geologic
storage uh we assume uh certain daily ER
like in our analysis some daily ER
like uh
discharge uh and eventually that might
be quite big if uh we are really
switching to a hydrogen based Energy
System and I think secondary question to
that is the potential Global like global
warming potential impact of hydrogen and
if we have hydrogen as a molecule and if
we see more leakages more emissions of
hydrogen whether this will cause uh like
other uh negative impacts in terms of
climate change
uh so the short answer is like this is
still uh like a uh area of active
research so like many people including
uh couple of professors at MIT studying
actually the potential impact of
hydrogen leakages and emissions and what
they have seen is that its impact really
increases in with the increasing amount
of meane emissions so actually it makes
hydrogen emissions make maintain more
potent in terms of global warming
potential uh so all of these are
concerns and in our modeling we take
into account these uh leakages and uh
potential emissions uh but the next
level about like the their potential
Global uh warming potential uh we
haven't included anything in these
analysis
Okay one minute but uh I'm going to
combine this two questions uh one is do
you have similar analysis for cement
production uh and uh uh what do you see
the prospect of director direct H
like uh electrolysis of sea
Waters so for the cement we have we have
similar analysis for cement uh so it
will be very unfair to tell one
uh answer but what we've seen is
currently in most regions carbon capture
is the most cost effective
decarbonization of option for cement and
use of hydrogen is like prohibitively
expensive so that will never be an
option for cement in my opinion but it
might still Depend and for sea salt sea
water Dellin sea water electrolyzers or
use of desalination and use of
electrolyzers uh that's that's a
feasible option so there are active uh
research and some companies focusing on
directly using seawater for
electrolyzers uh but even if you use
decarbonization like reverse osmosis or
so uh actually the energy penalty of
decarbonization desalination is so low
relative to hydrogen production it
doesn't really move the needle in terms
of economics so and there are many
regions that are uh not great for Fresh
Water Resources so for these regions use
of seaw is definitely a option and the
total cost will not make a huge
difference okay thanks air uh we still
have questions but I'm confined by
schedule I'll let you go Emir thanks
again