Christopher Capozzola: Greetings, and welcome to MIT.
Today, we send special greetings
to our MicroMasters learners
from around the world.
My name is
Christopher Capozzola.
I'm a faculty member here at
MIT and our Senior Associate
Dean for Open Learning.
And it is my pleasure
to host here today
in this celebration of the
completion of your MicroMasters
credentials.
Congratulations.
Today, we honor 1,276 learners.
641 of you have earned
MicroMasters credentials
in Supply Chain Management; 230
in Data, Economics, and Design
of Policy; 57 in Principles
of Manufacturing;
285 in Statistics and Data
Science; and 63 in Finance.
Here at MIT, we now have more
than 1.8 million learners from
almost every country in
the world who have enrolled
in our MicroMasters courses,
and a total of 9,696 people have
earned their
MicroMasters credential.
That now includes you.
Congratulations again to today's
MicroMasters credential holders,
1,276 of you.
We're thrilled to have you
join the credential-holding
community, and welcome.
Now if you're not yet aware, MIT
MicroMasters credential holders
can claim affiliate membership
of the MIT Alumni Association,
and you will also be avail--
you will also be eligible for
affiliate membership benefits.
So please look
for the invitation
from the MIT Alumni office
in your email, and join us.
So now we'll turn
to our celebration.
Today, you'll be hearing
from leaders and learners
from all five
MicroMasters programs.
And at the end, at the
conclusion of our ceremony,
we will be honoring all
1,276 of you by showing each
of your names on the screen.
All right, let's begin.
Our first speakers are Dr.
Chris Caplice and Dr. Eva
Ponce from MIT's Center for
Transportation and Logistics.
They lead our MicroMasters
in Supply Chain Management.
Chris, take it away.
Chris Caplice: All right.
Thank you, Chris.
I apologize for everyone.
I don't have my regalia
because I'm offsite today.
I'm just glad that
I'm able to be here.
Congratulations to everyone.
You're going to hear
that over and over again,
because we all know how
much dedication, time,
and effort went in for you
to earn your MicroMasters
credential.
It's truly a
remarkable achievement.
And many of you did this
at night, on the weekends,
or whenever you could
squeeze in the time,
so we really appreciate that.
And I want to especially
thank your families
for their sacrifice,
because you were doing this
instead of their family time.
So today, we're thrilled
to celebrate this milestone
with all of you, especially
the 641 new credential
holders for the Supply
Chain Management program.
You've joined a global community
of learners and leaders,
and we could not
be prouder of you.
And now it's my pleasure
to introduce someone
who really leads the entire
MicroMasters for Supply Chain
Management, Dr. Eva Ponce.
Eva Ponce: Thank you, Chris.
As you can see, I'm
wearing my regalia just
to celebrate today with
you this huge milestone.
Hi, everyone, and
congratulations.
Congratulations to all
credential holders.
My name is Eva Ponce, and I am
the Director of Online Education
at MIT, the Center for
Transportation and Logistics.
I have been teaching
for more than 25 years.
And during the
last nine years, I
have been leading this massive
global and online MicroMasters
program in Supply
Chain Management.
This allows me to connect
with this special group
of online learners.
You have shown dedication,
perseverance, grit,
and determination.
And I want to take a moment to
celebrate your big achievement,
because online
education requires
another level of dedication.
I know that.
I have observed you
during this last month.
This is truly another
level of dedication.
Let me share with
you the presentation
we have prepared just to
celebrate this huge milestone.
The first thing we
want to celebrate
is the huge community of
MicroMasters credential holders
in Supply Chain Management.
We have 5,735 credential holders
Today, we are celebrating 641--
641 new credential holders.
And you have shown a lot
of dedication and effort
just to be here.
Most of you have watched a bunch
of videos, more than 900 videos,
and spent a lot of
hours per course.
Each of the courses
require more than 100 hours
of effort, a total
of 720 hours just
to complete the entire
MicroMasters program.
So we want to congratulate
you, but also your families,
because their support
also helped you
to achieve this huge milestone.
And also, the credential is
equivalent to one full semester
of coursework at MIT, so that's
why you put a lot of effort
on that.
So again, new
credential holders,
641 credential holders in
Supply Chain Management
from 67 countries.
We have about 46% of
you that performed
above 80% on the
comprehensive and final exam.
This exam is tough, we know.
And you did a very good
job performing well
on that comprehensive proctored
exam at the end of the program.
We have also 24% of our new
credential holders are female.
I'm glad to see this
number raising up.
I would love to see more
females completing this program.
But yes, definitely
congratulations
to everyone about that.
As I mentioned, it's a global
community of credential holders.
We have new credential holders
from many different countries.
I would say that all
continents-- almost
all continents are
represented here.
As you can see, many
new credential holders
from United States, from
Australia, from China,
from Latin America, from Africa,
and of course, from Europe,
and eight new credential
holders from Spain.
I need to mention that.
You know it's in my
heart, the Spaniards.
So eight new credential
holders from Spain.
In terms of the industries
represented here,
most of our new
credential holders
are in Supply Chain
Management, but some of them
are working on operations,
logistics, finance, information
technology, and
also in academia.
We have also many different
companies represented.
Some of our new
credential holders
work in big companies
like Coca-Cola,
tech companies like
SAP or Ericsson,
manufacturing
companies like SLB.
Congrats.
I know we have new credential
holders from SLB today
joining us.
And some are from
consulting companies
like Accenture and Deloitte.
So congratulations to everyone.
In terms of the job titles,
again, a huge variety
of different job
titles represented
in these new credential holders
from logistics managers,
supply chain planners,
directors, and also CEOs.
So we have a huge variety of
different titles represented.
We also asked our new credential
holders in our last survey,
once they complete the
entire program, about
the impact of these
credential holders.
And some of you got a raise,
a bonus, or a promotion.
Congrats on that.
I cannot end this presentation
without acknowledging that
running a program like this
one, a massive program online,
an open enrollment program,
it takes a village.
So 64 MIT staff, teaching
assistants, and instructors
has been working with us
from the last nine years
just to make this
program possible.
If we take into consideration
our group of community teaching
assistants, those
learners that volunteer
to help us to manage the
forums and help our learners,
then we are talking about
400 people just to run--
almost 100 course run
during the last nine years.
But I especially need
to thank my team.
I need to say thank you to
the MicroMasters Supply Chain
Management team for their
dedication, their passion,
and commitment to make
this program possible.
I also want to extend a
thank you to Open Learning,
to Shira Fruchtman, to
Brittney Law, to David Chotin,
and to Dana Doyle, because
they are also supporting
and has been supporting
us since day number 1.
So thank you for that.
And finally, welcome.
Welcome to this MicroMaster
community of learners.
We are really proud of you.
We are very proud
of your achievement.
Very proud of your
dedication and effort.
Stay tuned, because sometimes
we have some events,
and these events are only for
our MicroMaster credential
holders.
You are now part of this elite
group of credential holders.
So we would love to
see you, welcome you
here on campus Sunday if you
have a chance to join us.
And with that, I want to end the
presentation saying once more,
congratulations on
behalf of my team.
This should be the
beginning, the beginning
of a new adventure.
You are lifelong
learners, so keep it up.
And keep in touch with us, and
celebrate your big achievement.
And now let me introduce two
of our new credential holders.
Our first representative
is Caroline Barbosa.
Caroline lives in Sao
Paulo, Brazil, and works
for the company iFood
as a data scientist.
Caroline has been an active
member of our MicroMaster
community through
dedicated involvement
as a community teaching
assistant in some
of our courses.
Caroline, the floor is yours.
Caroline Barbosa: Hi.
Thanks, Eva.
Hello, everybody.
I'm Caroline.
As Eva mentioned, I work as
a data scientist at a food
delivery based in Brazil, and
it's an honor to be here today
with you.
I joined this program of Supply
Chain Management, MicroMasters,
with the goal of expanding
my knowledge in the supply
chain and analytics, which I
use to work a lot back then.
And I thought I was just
signing up for some lectures,
but I ended up going
so much more than that.
Not only did I learn from
world-class instructors,
but I also had hands-on
projects that I
worked really hard during the
nights or the lunch times.
And I also had the chance
to connect with people
from all over the world who were
on the same journey as I was.
One of the highlights
of my experience
was serving as a CTA, which
was also humbling and deeply
rewarding for me,
because you have
to be really creative to help
others understand something
that you know and
explain different ways
so that they can gain the
same knowledge as I did,
and also I learned
along the way.
This program opened
up some doors for me.
I ended up changing jobs
during this program,
and that really helped me
a lot gain some confidence
on technical discussions and how
to deal with some of the bigger
problems on logistics, which
is the field that I work today.
To everyone graduating
today over the best terms
in some of the MicroMasters,
congratulations.
Your dedication brought
us all today here,
and I hope that with this
knowledge that we gain,
we can build some extraordinary
things in the future.
So thanks, everyone,
and thank you, Eva.
Eva Ponce: Thank you, Caroline.
Thanks for sharing your
journey and experience with us.
Very inspiring.
OK.
And now we are going to
hear from Tianxu Wang.
Tianxu lives in
Toronto in Canada,
and is currently working as
an SAP Associate Consultant
for Westernacher Consulting.
Tianxu has also been an
active member of the community
as a committee-- is a teaching
assistant for supply chain
analytics.
Tianxu, thanks for joining us.
The floor is yours.
Tianxu Wang: Thank you, Eva.
Actually, it's such a
pleasure, and honestly
a bit surreal to
be here reflecting
on this journey with all of you.
So if I had to choose
one word to describe
what the MicroMasters
program gave me,
it would be perspective.
Not just new tools or
frameworks, but a new way
of seeing supply chains.
So when many of us
started in this field,
we focused on execution like
tools, systems, dashboards,
how to get things done faster,
cheaper, and more efficiently.
But this program
challenged that.
It pushed us to ask
why we are doing this.
Who does it affect?
And what does the long-term
value really look like?
It helped me see supply
chain not as isolated steps,
but as living systems shaped
by trade-offs, people,
and decisions.
So once that shift
happened, you start
seeing the world differently,
even in unexpected places.
Like at Costco,
my wife and I were
in line for a
rotisserie chicken,
and I suddenly found
myself recalling
the example Chris used to
illustrate expected unit
[? short ?] from [INAUDIBLE].
So I started wondering,
how does Costco
plan for this crazy demand?
And how much safety
stock do they
need to avoid stockout
while keeping costs low?
So that's when I realized this
wasn't just about knowledge.
It had changed how I think.
And that shift didn't
just stay with me.
So after a few
modules learning, I
started a small supply chain
concept series at work, just
like the informal lunch session.
But soon, more people joined.
So a colleague who used
to focus only on tools
started asking deeper
questions like,
how can we show customers
the value our system brings
across the entire supply chain?
Or how do we design
solutions that
truly enable end-to-end
visibility, not just
the digital version
of their own silos?
So that's when I knew the
mindset shift was spreading.
And that, to me, is where the
real transformation began.
So thank you to Chris, Eva,
and all other professors,
the team behind this program,
and all of my fellow learners.
So let's keep asking
better questions
and building the
future together.
Back to you, Eva.
Eva Ponce: Thank you, Tianxu.
Thanks for sharing
your experience,
and thanks for thinking
on supply chain,
the back end of the
supply chain when you go
to Costco, many other stores.
Thank you for that.
OK.
With that,
congratulations again.
And back to you,
Chris Capozzola.
Christopher Capozzola: All right.
Thanks to everyone in the Supply
Chain Management MicroMasters
program.
And congratulations to our
newest MicroMasters credential
holders.
And a special thanks
to Caroline and Tianxu
for sharing their stories.
Next, it's my privilege to
introduce Dr. Sara Ellison
and Thanh Nguyen from the
MIT Economics Department
and J-PAL, the Jameel
Poverty Action Lab.
They are leaders of the
MicroMasters and Data,
Economics, and Design of Policy.
Over to you, Sara.
Sara Ellison: Thanks, Chris.
I'm really happy
to be here today.
Some of you may know that
long before I became director
of the DEDP program, even before
I collaborated on the MOOC that
is part of the program, I was
an industrial organization
economist who studied the
effect that the internet was
having on traditional markets.
And broadly speaking, I
found that the internet had
vast potential for
increasing social welfare,
and that's basically
economist speak
for making the world better.
But I also found that it also--
that it had potential for
decreasing social welfare.
We are all well
aware of examples
in our own personal lives of
how the internet has sometimes
not lived up to its
positive potential,
and has actually made
markets work less well,
or people worse off.
When I joined my colleagues
Abhijit Banerjee, Esther Duflo,
and Ben Olken to work on
DEDP, I experienced up
close a powerful example,
though, of the positive effects
that internet
technologies can deliver.
And all of you are the proof.
You went online, and you sought
out these challenging courses
covering important topics.
You have worked
hard, deciphering
complicated equations,
working on p sets
late into the night, re-watching
videos until something finally
clicks, creating
community online.
And in doing so, you
have equipped yourself
with a toolkit to in turn help
improve the world for others.
Even given my years
of research, I'd
be hard pressed to think of a
better use for the internet.
So here we are, online
today to celebrate
these extraordinary
accomplishments of you,
our learners, who have earned
their MicroMasters credentials.
You have diverse backgrounds,
varying interests.
You come from
dozens of countries
and range widely in age.
But you have more in common
than what differentiates you--
your remarkable ability, your
hard work and persistence,
and your passion for making
the world a better place.
We are proud of you, but we
are also inspired by you.
It is a fondest hope of the
founders of the DEDP program,
one that I share as
well, that you will all
be part of a worldwide movement
of evidence-based policymaking
to improve government policy
in people's lives everywhere.
So that is my charge to you.
Use the knowledge and tools
you've acquired through the DEDP
MicroMasters to enrich your
life and further your career,
for sure, but also use
them to make the world
a better place for others.
Finally, speaking on behalf of
Thanh Nguyen, Brynn Fieldhouse,
and all of our extraordinary
faculty and staff
of the DEDP MicroMasters,
let me close by offering you
our warmest congratulations
and best of luck
in your future endeavors.
I will now turn it over to
Davis Heniford, the Education
Manager of our program,
for a few remarks.
Thanks.
Davis Heniford: Thank you so much, Sara.
It's always tough
to speak after you.
You do such a great job.
Honestly-- hello, everyone.
First of all, just
congratulations.
Everyone here, as Sara
said, has worked so hard.
Your dedication and
perseverance is inspiring,
and it's really my
pleasure to be here today.
It's just wonderful to see all
of the amazing learners who
have come so far and introduce
two incredible learners
from our program in particular.
But before I get to
that, I have a few words
to say about the DEDP
MicroMasters program.
Our mission is simple.
Empower cohorts of diverse,
exceptional individuals--
oh, excuse me-- with
the technical skills
to tackle poverty using
evidence-based approaches.
And you truly embody
that, all of you.
Our success is your success.
So here's a little bit of
information about all of you.
We launched our program
in 2017, and today,
you are over 365,000 strong.
You come from all around the
world with representation
from almost every country.
I don't want to belabor
the point too much,
but this is truly a
wide-reaching cohort.
You can see a bit more
about our demographics here.
One thing I particularly
like to highlight
is the fact that there is an
almost even split between those
of you who work in government,
NGOs, nonprofit organizations,
and for-profit organizations,
which I think is really special.
And now to celebrate you.
I'm so happy to announce that
230 new program credentials were
awarded this year.
Congrats to all
of you once again.
And as a quick final
message, I really
do hope you consider applying
for our master's program.
Honestly, nothing
would make me happier
than seeing you in Cambridge.
Of course, there are plenty
of other opportunities
for credential holders as well,
including our many pathways.
And on that note, just
thanks again once more.
It's truly a privilege
to work with you,
and congratulations, truly.
And now I have two learners--
credential holders now
to introduce to you.
I'm going to start
with Abdoul Aziz.
Abdoul Aziz grew
up in Niger, where
he witnessed the adverse
effects of poverty firsthand.
At a young age, he developed a
passion for tackling inequality.
As a researcher and
economic analyst,
he studied topics such as
youth socioeconomic outcomes
and the effect of child
care on female labor force
participation.
He will be joining the DEDP
master's program next year,
and he hopes to use the skills
he learned from the program
to address poverty
in sub-Saharan Africa
and create a more
equitable world
through evidence-based research.
Abdoul Aziz, please
take it away.
Abdoul Aziz: Hello, everyone.
My name is Abdoul Aziz,
and I'm from Niger.
I recently completed
my undergraduate degree
in economics at Altinbas
University in Turkey,
and I'm honored to
have been admitted
to the master's in Data
Economics and Design of Policy
at MIT.
Earlier this year, I completed
the DEDP MicroMasters program.
When I first
discovered the program,
I saw something that felt both
exciting and out of reach.
I was still adjusting
to life in a new country
and studying in a new
language, all during COVID-19,
and I was unsure of
my academic abilities.
However, with a fresh
perspective, I took a chance,
and that decision changed
the course of my journey.
The program challenged
me to grow beyond what
I thought I was capable of.
It sharpened my thinking,
deepened my understanding
of data and policymaking,
and most importantly,
showed me that learning
is most powerful when it
serves people and communities.
To all my fellow credential
earners, congratulations.
You all took on a
demanding journey,
often while balancing
life's challenges.
You also come from different
countries and walks of life,
but you are united by
our shared commitment
to growth and learning.
As we move forward,
let's carry what
we have learned not just
as knowledge, but as a tool
to make a real difference
wherever we are.
Congratulations again
to each of you, and best
wishes as you continue
writing your own stories.
Thank you.
Now back to Davis.
Davis Heniford: Thank you so much, Abdoul Aziz.
That was wonderful and
certainly tough to follow.
But I have to say, I'm
equally happy to introduce
Tejaswi Menda.
She truly is a veteran
learner, but also
someone I really
wanted to highlight
as a dynamic leader whose career
spans public service, media
innovation, and social impact.
Tejaswi is not only a first
generation student, but also
the first woman engineer
from her village.
Her career has spanned broadly.
In addition to
engineering, she worked
for a long time at the
Indian Information Service
where her goal was to
bridge gaps in opportunity
through the power
of information,
completing research on
topics like the efficacy
of communication strategies,
community health workers.
I'm going to do a little bit
more bragging here on you,
Tejaswi, if you don't
mind, because I just
saw that recently were promoted
to Joint Director of DD
News in India, which,
if I'm not mistaken,
brings in over 600
million viewers.
Beyond her professional
achievements, which are many,
Tejaswi is a passionate advocate
for education and community
welfare, founding a small
NGO which supports orphanages
and underserved students.
So on that note,
Tejaswi, take it away.
Tejaswi Menda: Thank you, Davis, for
the kind introduction.
Hello, everyone.
Namaste.
I am Tejaswi.
As Davis mentioned, I'm
a civil servant working
with government of India.
Prior to this, I worked
as a software engineer
for a couple of years.
So in my current role,
I've had the privilege
of working on various
interesting and challenging
assignments.
And I used to feel as if, you
know, something is lacking.
I wanted my work to be more
impactful and effective,
but I quite didn't know
what I was looking for.
And that's when I came
across the DEDP MicroMasters,
and my first course was The
Challenges of Global Poverty.
It was my introduction
to development economics
and research, and I just
fell in love with the field.
The possibility that the
world's most important
and often what seemed like small
but important questions could
be answered with the help of
rigorous and objective research
has been truly empowering.
I began to look at my day-to-day
work, issues, and challenges
as many potential RCT
experiments in my head.
I designed those
many RCTs in my head,
and it helped me zero in on more
better, effective solutions.
And I'm quite sure the learnings
I got from the MicroMasters
would help me as I
continue to take up
more challenging
assignments as a policymaker
and an administrator.
I also got the opportunity to
join the residential masters
at the MIT campus
for the DEDP, but due
to some personal
reasons, I couldn't
accept the offer of admission.
Still, I continue this journey
to be truly life changing.
As Davis mentioned, for someone
who grew up in rural India
and is a first-generation
graduate,
the DEDP MicroMasters
truly expanded
the vision of what's possible.
So here, I thank MIT
and the DEDP team
for making this happen.
The possibility-- the ability
to learn from world's best
professors sitting in my
bedroom, it was incredible.
So thank you, MIT.
And to all the fellow
MicroMaster credential earners
today, congratulations.
You deserve to be celebrated.
As a working mom, I
know how difficult
it is to complete
such a rigorous course
from an institute like
MIT, there or virtually.
I remember squeezing in some
lectures during my commute
or revising for exams while
putting my kids to sleep.
So I know how hard
you all worked,
so cheers to that,
and all the best.
All the best to everyone
on your continued journey.
So here's to perseverance
and to continuous learning.
Thank you.
Thank you for this
opportunity, MIT.
Davis Heniford: Thank you so much, Tejaswi.
Honestly, doing all of
that also while being
a mother, truly inspiring.
Fantastic.
I'm very happy to
pass it along now.
Thank you all, DEDP
credential holders.
Christopher Capozzola: All right.
Thank you, and congratulations
to this latest cohort
of MicroMasters
credential holders
in Data Economics and
the Design of Policy.
And thanks to Davis Heniford
and Professor Ellison
and to Abdoul and Tejaswi.
It's now my privilege to
introduce Professor David
Hardt, who, along with Dr. Aditi
Joshi of the MIT Mechanical
Engineering Department,
are the leaders
of our MicroMasters in the
Principles of Manufacturing.
Professor Hardt.
David Hart: Thank you, Chris.
And it's a pleasure
to get to address
this class of the Principles
of Manufacturing MicroMasters.
So let me add my
congratulations to you again
for completion of this
very rigorous program.
I want to remind
you that this is
identical to the
campus program that we
have for a full semester.
And I can tell you as well
that the students on campus
always find that semester
very challenging.
They also find it very
rewarding in the end.
And we believe the principles
that you've learned
will not only enable you to
become a leader in your field
in this exciting and vital
area of manufacturing,
but also enable you to
teach your colleagues how
to do so as well.
So we hope you'll be a
leader and a teacher based
on this, because you're
getting the real basics of it.
We look forward to hearing
about your accomplishments
in the future, and hope some of
you will consider coming to MIT,
applying for our program
in Advanced Manufacturing
and Design, whose regalia
I am wearing today.
And with that, I'll turn
it over to Professor Joshi,
who will tell you more
about our program.
Aditi Joshi: Thank you, Dave.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Dr.
Aditi Joshi, and I'm
the Program Lead for the
Principles of Manufacturing.
So firstly, I'm sure
you know what's coming.
Congratulations to all
the credential holders
and their loved ones.
And a special shout-out to
our cohort of the Principles
of Manufacturing.
This is my fifth year
at the celebration.
And like every year,
I really look forward
to the incredible stories that
all the learners share here.
We really admire the hard work,
the dedication that all of you
put into completing
this program,
and all the sacrifices
that also go into this.
A lot of credential
holders of our program,
which is Principles
of Manufacturing,
are working
professionals, which means
you are studying in the evenings
after a workday or at nights,
on the weekends,
taking leaves just
to be able to complete
a proctored exam.
And a lot of you also take
the exams at very odd hours,
just so you can get some
quiet time in the house,
and also you don't get flagged
for the background noise that
is generally there otherwise.
So we understand that a lot
of preparation and planning
goes into completing
this program.
So after that, I'm sure today
is a very special day for all
of you and your families.
And we are very excited
to be a part of it
and celebrate your achievements.
So congratulations
again to all of you.
I'm quickly going to share some
demographics of our learners.
So the Principles of
Manufacturing program has over
300,000 total enrollments,
out of which 7,400 are unique
verified enrollments.
The program now has a total
of 353 credential holders
from over 50 countries
across the globe.
Our cohort of credential
holders is mostly
in the age group of 25
to 35, and a lot of you
are working professionals with a
bachelor's or a master's degree.
So some of you
continue your studies
while doing masters at MIT
or some other institutions.
And some of you take up
some new jobs, new roles,
and new responsibilities.
So we do want to give our
best wishes to all of you
for a very bright future
that's ahead of you.
I would also like to
take this opportunity
to thank the course
faculties who
have built these wonderful
courses, the MITx
team for their constant
support and assistance,
and our last-minute
panic emails, the old
and the current course
teams, which you might be
familiar with, and our wonderful
community TAs who voluntarily
help out their fellow learners
to complete and do well
in the courses.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you for all your efforts.
So today, we have two of our
credentialed representatives
who will be sharing their
experiences with us.
Let's first hear from Lee
Nguyen. Over to you,
Lee Nguyen.
Thank you, Professor Joshi.
Hello, everyone.
It's a great honor
to join you all today
to celebrate the completion of
MIT MicroMasters, especially
Principles of Manufacturing.
I have been working in
manufacturing and supply chain
for 17 years, leading digital
transformation projects where
automation, IoT, and AI are
becoming increasingly common.
But as I progressed
through this program,
I was reminded that before
applying advanced technology,
we must first master the
fundamental principles that
govern manufacturing systems.
For example, in the
Manufacturing Process Control
course with Professor
David Hardt,
I was inspired by how
statistical process control
helps critically evaluate
assumptions like how
to estimate mean and standard
deviation from limited or even
noisy data.
This approach not only
applies to manufacturing,
but also influence how I monitor
data-driven systems in my work.
For example, using
cumulative sums
to detect shift early in machine
learning model performance
and avoid feature drift.
In the Supply Chain for
Manufacturing course
with Professor Stephen Graves,
I gained a comprehensive view
of inventory management
from basic newsvendor models
to network-wide optimization
under uncertainty.
This helped me better understand
how inventory decisions impact
the entire supply chain
while meeting service levels.
In practice, I believe it's easy
to collect large amount of data
through MIT and simulation and
to apply ready-made models.
But what this
program taught me is
that the true success comes
from understanding how system
behaves, how
variation propagates,
how flow is maintained,
and how every decision
impacts the broader operation.
I'm deeply grateful to MIT,
the professor, the course team
for this enriching experience.
Congratulations to all of us.
I believe this knowledge will
serve us well for many years
to come.
Thank you so much.
Back to you, Professor Joshi.
Thank you, Lee Nguyen.
Thank you for sharing your
experiences with us.
Our next credential holder
is Akshaya. Over
to you, Akshaya.
Thank you, Aditi.
Hi, everyone.
I am Akshaya. I started
Principles of Manufacturing
Program right when I began my
first job as a manufacturing
engineer in India's first
private aircraft final assembly
line.
At the time, I was
curious to understand
how a product makes its journey
from paper to the production
line.
How do global
supply chains work?
How do systems come
together efficiently?
And what is
operational excellence?
This program answered those
questions and many I didn't even
know I had.
It wasn't always easy
balancing a full-time work
with coursework.
It meant late nights
and early mornings,
and sometimes doubts about
whether I could do it.
But like many of
you, I kept going.
And that brought me
here with a belief
that learning can open doors
that we don't even see yet.
In fact, I started this
journey in one country
and completed it from another.
That shift wasn't
just geographical.
It reflected how much I
had grown both personally
and professionally.
To the professors and support
staff, thank you very much.
To my fellow learners
from all around the world,
sharing this virtual
space with you
reminded me that
curiosity is universal
and growth doesn't stop
with a certificate.
It starts with it.
As we all move forward
into new roles,
new industries, or
even new countries,
congratulations to all of us.
Over to you, Chris.
Christopher Capozzola: All right.
Thank you to everyone
in our cohort
from the Principles of
Manufacturing MicroMasters
credential.
Thanks to Aditi and Dave Hardt,
to Lee Nguyen and Akshaya.
And it's now
my pleasure to introduce Dr.
Karene Chu from MIT's Institute
for Data, Systems, and Society.
Karene is a leader in
our MicroMasters program
in Statistics and Data Science.
Karene?
Karene Chu: Thank you, Chris.
Congratulations, everyone,
on achieving the MicroMasters
program credential in Statistics
and Data Science to all 285
of you.
Just as everyone
before me have said,
we acknowledge the tremendous
commitment, determination,
and focus that you
have demonstrated
in these significant
accomplishments,
regardless of where you are,
what environment you're under,
and what other
commitments you have.
So in this age of
AI, we always ask,
do we still need our
foundational data science
skills?
So I want to highlight
that what you have learned
is still completely, if not
more, useful in this age of AI.
First, when AI model
predicts outcome,
we know that they do so
based on probabilities
rather than certainties.
So understanding how to
interpret these probabilities
is crucial to making
informed decisions.
And with this
nuanced understanding
that you now
possess, you will be
careful in interpreting
AI outputs,
leading to reliable decisions
and appropriate confidence
in the results.
And as our MicroMasters faculty
director, Professor Devavrat
asked, why do we still teach
basic mathematics when we have
tools that can do it for us?
And the answer's clear, because
foundational skills are still
essential.
Children around
the world continue
to learn math in school because
these foundational concepts are
vital, even in a world dominated
by really advanced technology.
So while generative AI
automates specific tasks,
effectively using
these powerful tools
require the deep understanding
of where and how to apply it.
You are now armed with
these foundational skills
necessary for analyzing,
evaluating, implementing,
and performing research
on complex data science
models and methods.
We expect that you will use
these skills and knowledge
to make progress in
your field of interest
and for the good
of your society.
So now let me present some
stats and tell you-- recount
what you have done
in this MicroMasters.
Let me share my screen.
I bring with me the greetings
from all the faculty
in this program and our faculty
director, Devavrat Shah,
along with all of the
course team members.
We are all very proud
of your accomplishments.
The MicroMasters in
Statistics and Data Science
come out of IDSS, the Institute
for Data, Systems, and Society.
And our mission is to advance
complex societal challenges
by advancing education
and research that
is at the intersection
of statistics,
data science, information,
and decision systems.
And hence, the MicroMasters
is a very important part
of this mission.
We have other programs
in our institute,
including this PhD in Social
Engineering Systems, which
is a pathway for this
MicroMasters program.
The MicroMasters program,
as you already all know,
covers four pillars of
data science, everything
that our faculty think is
necessary for a practitioner
in this day and age.
And with your
credential right now, we
look forward to hearing
stories about advancement
in your career.
Of course, applying your skills
everywhere that you can see fit.
And also, if you pursue an
academic degree afterwards,
there are more than
30 universities that
are pathways for this program.
And also, as I mentioned,
the MIT IDSS PhD
program in Social and
Engineering Systems.
So congratulations on having
this credential, and hope
that this will help
you be a vital--
hold a vital role in society.
To recount, I think you all
know that you have completed
the full courses
that are equivalent
to graduate-level courses in
statistics and data science
at MIT on campus.
You have done more than 15--
10 to 15 hours of work per
week and 200 hours per course.
These include 80 full professor
lectures and working on more
than 1,000 challenging problems.
These include from really
maybe simple concept
checks all the way
to full machine
learning tasks and projects.
And at the end, you also
completed the proctored exam,
which includes eight
hours of exams.
So congratulations on
this huge accomplishment.
And now, here are
some statistics
of our credential holders.
Our program is
now six years old,
and you are part of our more
than 1,800 credential holders.
There's 195 countries
represented.
Our program has around
80% male and 17% female.
We would like more female
to join our program.
This is our age distribution.
It's a big range, mainly
between 25 to 54 here,
reflecting that you are working
professionals, generally.
A lot of you hold a bachelor's
degree and a master's degree,
and some of you also
hold a doctorate degree.
And we have also 6% of high
school students joining us.
And the industries, the top 10
industries are plotted here.
A lot of you are in the
information and technology
space.
Computer software, banking,
financial services,
telecommunication, management,
consulting, higher education,
et cetera.
This is our map of
credential holders.
In total right now in North
America, there's around 500.
South America, 400.
It's sort of roughly spread
out around the whole world.
And here is also a map of
all our pathway school,
which is also spread
around the globe.
I will not say more.
I will want to look forward
to hearing from you about how
you're going to
use your knowledge
and use this credential in
your career, in your research,
in your own projects.
And we'll hear from
one of the learners who
have done volunteer work as
well, using his data science
skills.
And last but not least, I
want to thank our IDSS team
and Open Learning staff,
Susana, Jeremy, Erica from IDSS,
and Dana, David, Shelly,
Lana, Peter, Liou, Tim.
I mean, all of these people
are vital to the well-being
and the smooth running
of our program,
so we really want to
thank you for making
our program a success.
And finally, our community TAs.
You are making everyone's
experience online much better
for us, course team,
and for other learners.
So we really thank you for
your dedication and time
to involve in the course,
talking to other people.
And I hope that these
communications and networks
that you've built
throughout the course
will continue
beyond the program.
So finally,
congratulations once more.
I would like to
introduce now Jeff
as our next speaker,
who I'm going
to introduce to you right away.
So Jefff is a statistician
with a strong background
in data analytics, statistical
modeling, data science,
and economic research.
Deeply passionate about
research, innovation,
and the application of data
science to public policy,
Jeff has also led
several volunteer initiatives
in technology and education.
He actively contributes to
programming and AI communities
and is committed
to leveraging data
to solve complex challenges,
particularly those affecting
emerging economies.
Take it away, Jeff.
Jeff: Hello, everyone.
It's truly an honor
to be here today,
celebrating this
incredible milestone
with so many brilliant
minds from around the world.
When I began the
MITx MicroMasters
in Statistics and Data Science,
I was driven by a deep desire
to use data not just for
numbers, but for impact.
Coming from Haiti,
I've seen firsthand
how communities often
face major challenges,
not because they lack
intelligence or willpower,
because they lack access to
resources, to opportunities,
and to the language
of technology.
This program
changed that for me.
It gave me not only the
technical foundation
in data science, statistics,
and machine learning,
but also the confidence
to apply it meaningfully.
I've used what I learned to
build dashboards for COVID-19
analysis, develop
financial analytics platform,
and design a text-to-speech
system in Haitian Creole,
making technology
more accessible
to underserved communities.
The MicroMasters
didn't just teach me
how to model data
or build algorithms.
It empowered me to turn complex,
unstructured information
into actionable insight
and social impact.
But the journey wasn't easy.
Like many of you, I
balanced this program
with work, projects, and life.
There were late nights,
setbacks, and doubts.
Yet, we kept showing up because
what we are building here
is bigger than us.
It's a community
of problem solvers,
changemakers, and people who
care deeply about using data
to drive progress.
So today, I'm not just
part of the certificate.
I'm part of the
persistence, the resilience,
and the purpose behind it.
And I'm incredibly
grateful to the MIT team
for creating a program
that truly opens doors,
regardless of where you live
or what your background is.
I also want to thank all our
professors and CTAs.
To my fellow graduates,
congratulations.
Let's keep using what we learned
to lift up others, transform
systems, and write stories
that truly inspire.
Thank you.
And now I'll hand it
back to you, Dr. Karene.
Karene Chu: Thank you, Jeff.
Next, we will have Moumita Ghosh.
She is raised in a tranquil coastal state of India.
She's a PhD student specializing
in predictive modeling,
reinforcement learning,
and optimization.
She pairs her love for
algorithms with a poetic soul,
crafting poems and haikus
when she's not coding.
So both Jeff and Moumita
completed the general track
of this MicroMasters program.
So, Moumita, all yours.
Moumita Ghosh: Thank you so much, Dr. Karene,
for such a warm welcome to me.
So hello, everyone.
I am Moumita Ghosh.
I'm a PhD student.
I'm currently pursuing
my PhD focusing
on reinforcement
learning, optimization,
and predictive modeling.
And recently, I have completed
MicroMasters in Statistics
and Data Science from MIT.
Though I have a
background in engineering
with both a bachelor's
and master's in the field,
but my growing inspiration in
the machine learning and data
science led me to
seek a new direction.
So what inspired that
transition was witnessing
the remarkable impact of
machine learning and data
science in various fields,
especially in health care.
So as I was looking for
a career transition,
I wanted my first step correct.
And also, I firmly believe
that to excel in any field,
it is very essential to have a
solid foundation in that field
first.
So this MicroMasters
program not only offered us
a rigorous and very
practical approach
to handle the problems
in data science,
but also significantly
advanced my research,
and it helped me
develop my portfolio
with some solid projects.
So all these experiences
have laid the groundwork
for my dream of entering into
the data science industry
as my full-time career.
And most importantly,
I had the privilege
of learning from the
best people in the world.
And for that, I
am and will always
be sincerely grateful to MIT.
And finally, I
would like to extend
my heartfelt congratulations
and best wishes
to all the learners at MIT.
So here is to our continued
growth and success.
Thank you.
Christopher Capozzola: All right.
Thank you to Moumita and
Jeff. And congratulations
to the latest cohort in
Statistics and Data Science
MicroMasters.
It's now my pleasure
to introduce
Dr. Egor Matveyev from MIT Sloan.
Egor is one of the leaders
of our MicroMasters
program in Finance.
Take it away.
Egor Matveyev: Thank you, Chris.
Let me start by congratulating
all MicroMasters credential
holders, and especially the
graduates of the Finance
MicroMasters.
Congratulations on this
remarkable achievement.
I'm Egor Matveyev, Executive
Director of the MicroMasters
program in Finance.
I have been part of
this journey since 2019,
and have had the privilege of
leading the program since 2020.
This year marks five years
since the launch of the program.
It has been an
incredible journey.
To share more about
what we have built,
I have prepared a few slides.
The idea behind the program
was bold, but simple--
to open MIT finance
to the world.
We set out to offer the same
level of academic excellence
that defines MIT Sloan, and to
make it accessible to everyone,
everywhere.
We're incredibly proud
of what we have built.
More than 130,000 learners
have engaged with the content
of our courses.
Dedicating nearly
500,000 hours to study,
this is the equivalent of 57
years of continuous collective
learning.
Earning the MicroMasters
credential in Finance
is no small feat.
To complete the
program, learners
must take the full set of
core courses from MIT Sloan's
top-ranked Master of
Finance curriculum,
along with one
advanced elective.
Together, these courses
include more than 90 hours
of instruction.
Each module demands 10
to 14 hours of work.
With more than 50
modules in total,
this commitment ends up to
the equivalent of three months
of full-time study.
And it is not just about
watching lectures and doing
homework.
To earn the credential,
learners must
pass the same rigorous exams we
give to our students on campus.
That level of academic challenge
means only a select few make it
to the finish line.
Today, we proudly recognize
273 exceptional individuals
who have mastered all the
content, passed all the exams,
and learned their place
as credential holders.
We're incredibly proud of them.
Our credential holders come from
62 countries around the world,
with the United States,
India, and the United Kingdom
accounting for about
1/3 of the total.
The map on this slide gives
you a sense of how broad
our geographic reach is.
This is truly a global
community of learners.
Our community of
credential holders
is as diverse in
professional background
as it is in geography.
They work at central banks,
such as Central Bank of Peru,
the Bank of Thailand, and
the National Bank of Georgia.
Others serve in market
regulatory agencies,
including the Securities and
Exchange Commission of Brazil
and Japan's Financial
Services Agency.
You will also find them at
hedge funds, proprietary trading
firms, and asset managers like
Fidelity, Millennium Management,
Two Sigma, as well
as global banks
and consulting firms such as
Credit Suisse, Goldman Sachs,
and BCG.
And this is just a glimpse
of many organizations
where our graduates
are making an impact.
Now before I wrap up,
I want to acknowledge
the many people who have
made this program possible.
Our faculty, staff, Open
Learning colleagues,
teaching assistants,
and the learners
who serve this community,
teaching assistants.
This has truly been
a collective effort,
and I am deeply grateful to
everyone who contributed.
Now I am pleased to
welcome our Finance learner
representatives, My-Ni Pham
and Mauricio Hernandez.
We will first hear from
My-Ni, followed by Mauricio.
My-Ni, the floor is yours.
My-Ni Pham: Thank you, Egor.
Good morning, everyone.
My name is My-Ni,
and it's very honor
to speak on behalf
of Finance cohort
at this MIT MicroMasters
celebration.
As a quantitative analyst,
I joined the MIT MicroMaster
in finance with the background
in technology and strong passion
to deepen my expertise.
This program not only
enriched my understanding
of financial theory,
but also the--
but also inspired me impact on
the [INAUDIBLE] finance journey.
I'm thrilled to share with you
all that I also passed the Level
1 of CFA program in
February, just a few months
after completing
the MIT MicroMaster.
One of the most valuable
outcome from this course
is that now I can apply the
knowledge of financial modeling
in derivative market
directly to my work
at Tuan Loc Commodities,
a commodities trading
company in Vietnam.
And first, I would like to say
thank you to the MIT professor.
They are truly
inspiring teachers.
They made many tough
concepts accessible and more
than just the
financial knowledge.
They inspired me to
become a lifelong learner.
And I also want to
express my gratitude
to my boss, Mr. Kevin.
He is the one who
introduced me this program.
He encouraged me, supported
me every step of the way.
A special thanks to my
amazing learning partner, Mr. Jung.
I cannot remember
how many cups of coffee or how
many late night study sessions
we spent to motivate each other
to keep moving forward
and complete this course.
And finally, we did it, and you
are truly a dear friend of mine.
And to the MIT team,
thank you for creating
such a wonderful program.
And finally, to all of
you, congratulations.
You did it, and hope you the
best on your career ahead.
Thank you.
Egor Matveyev: Thank you, and
congratulations, My-Ni.
Next, I'd like to invite
Mao Hernandez to share
his remarks.
Mao?
Mao Hernandez: Thank you, Professor Egor.
Hello, everyone.
So first of all, as one of the
speakers for the Finance cohort.
I just want to take
this opportunity
to say thank you to the
humans behind the scenes that
really made these online courses
successful, like many of us.
So thank you for
the TAs for engaging
with our endless questions.
Thank you for the
staff answering
some of our frenetic emails,
especially during the exams.
Of course, thank you to the
professors for the classes
and the content.
So on behalf of the
MicroMasters Finance cohort,
I just want to say thank you.
If we all came to
MITx MicroMasters
because of the brand name
and quality we would expect,
we actually stayed because of
the people that made it happen.
And as Professor Egor said, my
name is Mao Hernandez.
I was born and raised
in Sao Paulo in Brazil.
But actually, I've
been living in Tokyo
in Japan for the past 15 years.
After my master's
in pure mathematics,
I came to Japan to do my
PhD in computer science.
I finished my studies
10 years or so ago
and went to work in the
finance industry here in Japan.
The MicroMasters
in Finance really
was a really-- just a
really good excuse for me
to go back to study.
And I just want to share
one of the skills I think
I'm going to take for life
that I learned in the course,
and it's essentially--
I really feel like I learned
how to identify and evaluate
options.
What do I mean?
Real-life options, right?
I know that sounds
silly, but to be honest,
a common option that
I need to choose
in this stage in my
career is which company
I'm going to help next.
I use these skills
from the course
every time I've been negotiating
a contract with companies.
So the questions I learned
in the course actually
can apply in my life, right?
So what is the volatility
of this new company?
What is the beta of the company?
What should be the
expected rate of return
for this risk investment?
Emotional, time investment
that I need to do.
As we all learned in the
course, volatility has a price,
and I may or may not
be willing to pay.
So my fellow MicroMasters in
Finance certificate earners,
congratulations to you and your
family for this achievement.
If you ever make your way
to Japan, sake is on me.
But you better tell me amazing
stories from your achievements
that I know you're
going to bring with you.
Thank you.
Professor Egor, the
floor is yours back.
Egor Matveyev: Yes. Mao,
thank you so much.
And I'll turn it
back over to Chris.
Christopher Capozzola: All right.
So thanks.
Congratulations to the
latest cohort of MicroMasters
credential holders in Finance.
Thanks to My-Ni
and to Mao.
And we will all take you up on
your offer of sake in Tokyo,
I'm sure someday.
We look forward to that.
We're coming to the close of
our ceremony this morning,
this afternoon, this evening.
And I wanted to thank all of you
who are joining us and watching
remotely online, because I
realize that many of you who
are watching are staying
up late to watch,
getting up early to watch,
interfering with your day,
missing time with your family to
watch and support our credential
holders, learners.
And that's exactly what our
MicroMasters learners have done.
You are people who
are willing to stay
up late, to get up early, to
make many sacrifices to pursue
this credential and to achieve
it, which you have done.
Together, you have put
in the time that makes
online learning meaningful.
You have connected
with your instructors.
You have connected with your
fellow learners, so thank you.
Not only congratulations,
but thank you
for making this learning
experience real, not only
for yourself, but for others.
You are fundamentally,
in the end, a community.
And now as you have
built this community,
you depart in many
different directions,
as we've heard today,
all around the world.
And I hope you will continue to
stay in touch with each other,
with the entire MicroMasters
community, and with all of us
here on campus at MIT.
Many of our credential holders
have started already pursuing
master's degrees at MIT or
at one of our 220 Pathway
programs, which are found at 58
universities in 32 countries.
Now, if the Pathway program to
MIT or another partner school
is something you're interested
in learning more about,
please visit our
MicroMasters website
to explore the many options.
And with that, congratulations
again to everyone, from me
and for all of us here at MIT.
We will close today's ceremony
by honoring each of you
individually by sharing all of
the names of this year's 1,267
MicroMasters credential
recipients on the screen.
Congratulations again from
all of us here at MIT.
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]