okay good
afternoon can
start all right so we are um talking
about non equilibrium and U this
table
summarizes a bit of what we have
done with talked
about forces and
fluxes
forces can be thought of as the degree
of dise equilibrium of the various
aspects and the flues are the modes with
which uh
molecules uh transfer stuff
properties the extensive properties
in fact this a fact that it that
molecules transport
something gives rise to this language
of ftic no like thermoptic
electroforesis foric
means uh the atmology of the word is
transporting
something and we want to to today to uh
introduce a couple of
U examples of this uh
uh transport cross effects that emerge
from this
table from the fact that
um not only we find things on on the
diagonal so we have processes like heat
transfer follows for year law or Mass
transfer that follows fix law that we
will
derive and
electric
Electro Statics
that uh provides HS
law and also fluid mechanics the low
that
connects with viscosity the stress and
the rate of strain of fluids but there
are also of diagonal terms these are
called cross
effects and in
some uh
cases some of these cross effects are
forbidden by symmetry reasons in
particular if you have an isotropic
fluid or Continuum
um the kuri principle forbids
uh
the cross effects between phenomena of
different tensorial
character although there are may be
other situations like we said for
example interfaces between
phases where the
isotropy is broken by the
interface and it's substituted by
another kind of
isotropy that will allow some additional
coupling that would not be allowed in
the
bulk
okay all right
so let's uh recall also that we have
defined
this uh relations that
um um def that um yeah this modee of
interaction that is the extension of the
idea of a heat interaction which we call
the Heat and
diffusion which is fundamental in U in
that it brings in a relation like the
heat uh Q overt relation here it becomes
a relation between
heat uh and also additional terms like
this one
in the uh flux for the energy and also
for the
entropy the language that you find in
papers and books on this
subject uh sometimes
is is varied and so you have to be
careful uh
often you find people calling this
uh
heat and this is the measurable heat
flux uh I have tried to call heat flux
only this and that I'll try to call it
just the energy
flux in
addition in some of the situations in
which you have multiple phenomena
occurring like heat and mass transfer
simultaneously or heat and electrical
charge uh
transfer there are is also languages
like the the heat of
transfer in some particular situations
for
example uh if you have no gradient in
temperature which doesn't necessarily
mean that QP Prime is zero but in in
that situation the overall energy flux
is sometimes
called uh the heat of
Transport uh because it's it's the heat
that is transported in the absence of
the traditional uh cause of heat
transfer which is a gradient in
temperature nevertheless it's it's it's
a combination of these
terms so beware of the language and if
you ever have to write on this subject
be careful and be consistent
now when we defined uh the Heat and
diffusion interaction we did it
uh for a situation in the absence of
fluid
flow so these
are the diffusive
flaxes with respect to uh a non-moving
uh bulk uh and therefore uh in next
slide we'll have to do a little bit of
additional job to introduce also the
idea that U typically in fluids there is
flow and of course is a complication it
complicates some some of the equations
but it's h is the right moment to bring
it in and
also
um what
else it escaped uh I'll come back and uh
so um so let's dig into this
uh a little little crowded slide as
usual but uh it's full of things that we
have already seen so just to have a way
to remember uh for example you remember
that we U as part of the local equili
assumption and together with a simple
system
model and like what when we describe bul
flow we say that the energy of our
system including like a a fluid
parcel is described by the energy of a
stable prop typical of a stable
equilibrium state
with the amounts of entropy volume and
uh constituency that are in that fluid
element plus additional terms that are
either mechanical or electrical like the
kinetic energy the potential
gravitational energy the potential
electrostatic energy and if you have
also
um your fluid in
a static in a
centrifugal field you can add this
negative potential
energy and of course we remember that
the
mass is related to the
concentrations via the molecular weights
and the charge Q is related to the
concentrations via the
individual charges of uh Z of of your
molecules
so we have seen a few times that when
you
do uh compute the derivative of the
energy that enters in the conditions for
Mutual equilibrium which is not the
chemical potential but the total
potential that picks up a contribution
from just the uh stable equilibri state
property and that's the chemical
potential but then there are also
additional contributions to the chemical
potential which makes it for example if
you add this one it makes it
electrochemical potential the
gravitational the kinetic and the
centrifugal in a moment uh below we'll
see that we can write these these terms
are highlighted in in white uh as energy
minus internal
energy because in specific because in in
indeed that is what what what it turns
out to
be um in fact you
remember that in general without before
we make any assumptions about mixture
being ideal or non ideal uh in general
we Define the partial properties and
this is the partial internal energy
which is related to the total internal
energy by this
summation which you can also cast in
terms of concentrations
CI so if you substitute if you rewrite
this expression for the
energy in terms of you write here in
terms of
energy um specific energy per unit
volume times the volume
and here you substitute this for the
internal energy which is the first term
here so you see that the overall energy
is given by a summation weighted on the
concentrations of of all these
terms all these terms somewhere have the
concentration coming in either through
the mass or the
charge and so this term in parenthesis
can be
called the specific um uh energy total
energy and uh it can be uh
split like we let's see
here
uh
so uh let's
see yeah I get lost myself in my slides
yes
sad all right
um okay so yeah we write it in terms of
uh the the E without is a per unit
volume the E with the star is per unit
mass that is also some kind of source of
confusion somewhere in in in in the
literature and all right so this is one
first equation the second relation that
we need to bring in is the fact that the
flues the fluxes of
constituents are not all
independent because these remember they
they not they don't have the not on
superscript so these are the um
diffusive
fluxes those so it's the flux relative
to the center uh the body center of the
uh of the fluid element
and with respect to that uh the the mass
flux by definition of bicentric velocity
is equal to
zero uh and
therefore the the weighted sum of the
uh mol fluxes of the various
constituents weighted on the molecular
their molecular weight must be equal to
zero that makes them U not all
independent
so we can uh
recast the equations by writing picking
for example the last
one so the flux of the last
constituent this is the mass is equal to
the negative of the sum of the flues of
masses of the the remaining
constituents and we can
introduce this
idea into the expression that we need
for U the Heat and diffusion interaction
because there we have the sum and in
this sum we have all the fluxes
playing but we have to also make a
system with this other relation between
fluxes
so one
way is to
uh
Rewrite by uh
subtracting this equation
here we first do it with a mass so that
this is easier to to to subtract so here
when I see the
summation with it goes from one to R to
the top total amount of constituents now
I substitute it with the summation that
goes from 1 to R
minus1 and the last
one is written is is in the is comes in
inside the summation by virtue of this
Mass oops what happens Yeah by by virtue
of this Mass uh balance suppos speak
equation no that's not a bu balance it's
simply uh definition of bicentric
velocity okay so now once we have this
expression here it's the difference
between the total
potentials but the difference between
the total
potentials uh we've seen
um somewhere
above I got the mouse stuck moment but
uh uh somewhere above you find a
relation that U gives you you here this
relation
here and uh and that one up up up there
so this
difference can be
substituted with uh this
one where the Z's uh stand
out and they bring in the uh charge uh
the charge
flux
okay and
um Okay so we've substituted so now this
expression has the advantage that of
having all the fluxes that are
independent because you are excluding
the AR um go the summation only up to R
minus
one then we do the usual trick we
remember that the chemical potential can
be written as H minus
TS and this is for the partial
properties so a partial H minus partial
partial uh TS which is written
here and so you can split U terms in
these flaxes that are multiplied by the
temperature and terms that are
not
okay um we can also go back to um molar
quantities molar fluxes without the
stars and uh uh eventually we recognize
that this term that is multiplied by T
is what we Define the meas measurable
heat flux or that is the heat flux heat
flux of uh heat transfer
okay so the bottom line is highlighted
here that we finally have
written the fluxes of energy and entropy
which are needed to make the energy and
entropy balances of course to the flux
of heat transfer so the measurable heat
flux to the fluxes of
constituents but not all of them only up
to R minus one and to the uh diffusive
Flux Of of electrical
charge so this is uh basic to analyze
any of uh those cross effects that we
need to
do now
uh just a little uh detour to mention
that
um since we're talking about fluxes
and we are talking about
uh heat and diffusion interaction then a
legitimate question is well is there
some kind kind some interaction that is
not like uh the Heat and diffusion it's
not like
heat and one important example which
also gives me a chance
to mention uh
is radiation electr itic radiation
contains not only energy the
photons that come from the Sun for for
example uh they do not have only uh
energy they also have
entropy you can think of actually the
the if you remember probably from your
physics uh course is this idea of the
black body radiation in a cavity in a
vacuum cavity you have
photons uh bouncing around and
exchanging with the with the
walls uh now the the electromagnetic
field is is an interesting
um subject
because if those walls in your uh um
cavity were perfect mirrors so they
wouldn't absorb the photons but they
simply uh bounce them
away uh
um this the modes of the electromagnetic
field would not uh interact with each
other so in other words you would have
that um photons with a certain frequency
will remain uh remain uh we will not
exchange with photons with another
frequency it is only through the
interaction with matter that radiation
can move energy from one mode namely one
frequency to another fre
uh okay this is all um described by
Plank's uh theory of electromagnetic
radiation and these are the typic the
well-known Spectra of of the various
items one is energy curve a for energy
curve B is for
entropy p
uh the pressure is
C uh and then you get
also yeah we plotted here also
the the functions in terms of instead of
frequency of w
wavelength but what is important is
that so the equivalent if you have two
bodies two yes
two two bodies at different temperatur
ta and TB and there is vacuum in between
uh they exchange energy via the
electromagnetic radiation because there
are photons in each of the solid the
solid is not uh you can you you think it
is a it is full completely but it's full
of empty space and in that empty space
the photon go in and out okay so the
photon that emerge
from one body
uh go directly ballistically so to speak
in like a ray to enter or to hit the
other uh the other solid and vice
versa and if you take if the if the
solids are at stable equilibrium and the
electrom Magnetic radiation that leaves
these solids is in equilibrium with that
it has the features of that temperature
so this the photons that come out of
body a have the temperature
ta and and and then they they arrive to
uh to system
B and that is a non equilibrium
situation they they have to interact and
thermalize and so by interacting and
being absorbed and and re emitted by the
molecules of of body B There is a a
remesal of um of the energy it's like in
the collisions that we talked about that
um that is an
irreversible fact and
then that allows thermalization of these
photons so
the so Sigma time T to 4 Sigma is the
Stefan bolman constant it's written down
here sure remember
um so the this Sigma t to the four is
the is the amount of energy that goes
out is the body a and and this is the
one that goes out of body B so they
exchange so the net exchange is the
difference and and together with the uh
Sigma to the T to the 4th which is very
well known there is also a 43 Sigma T to
the3 for the entropy that goes with it
so these photons do not carry only
energy they also carry
entropy like the photons that come from
the
sun the sun has photons that on the
surface have temperature of the order of
what is it 50
k um and those Photon leaves the uh the
plasma that is on the surface of of of
the sunand that we've seen very well
during the eclipse the other day and uh
they all the way travel to here to the
Earth and they
carry the features of energy and entropy
proper of that
temperature the fact that it that they
have
entropy limits the amount ount of work
that you can do with that energy so it's
not entire you cannot extract
100% of energy because of that entropy
that's the remember that when we talked
about um I think in the allocation
chapter we talked about the exergy of
solar radiation being around 93 okay
that is where part of the story it comes
from this anop
content but of course you can also uh
not
only uh talk about the flux overall flux
of energy carried by these photons but
also you can uh talk about the flux of
energy carried by each mode of the
electromagnetic
field so it's do this per frequency and
you can do that energy wise but also
entropy wise so this is the
uh the flux that
is exchanged between body a and body B
at temperature
T via photons of that frequency uh new
or or if you want you can write it also
in terms of
wavelength okay so in this paper that we
wrote long ago and then we was
republished recently uh you find all
these formulas that are used if you are
in the solar energy
business so let's go back now to
um uh the formula for the entropy
production which will be the starting
point for our
applications and we do uh
uh also here we we want
to introduce the
um the fact that use the fact that is a
fluxes are not all independent and
rewrite this
expression in which that you I don't go
over it because we've we we've talked
about it so many times but but we not
now want to concentrate only on this
term which has to do with the diffusion
of
particles uh and we want to rewrite it
in a form that goes only up to R to the
minus one or essentially that it is
written in terms of uh independent
fluxes and one way of doing it is
through these uh
steps because
now uh we also have to remember that um
the gradient in the chemical
potentials which appear appears
here uh this is the gradient done at
keeping the temperature constant um is
uh they are not all independent either
because of the Gibs doen relation
remember the Gibs do relation is written
here it Sayes that it says that the the
weighted sum of those
those gradients of chemical potentials
weighted on the concentrations of the
element of the
constituents is related is gives the
gradient in the
pressure remember that the pressure we
managed to make it disappear somehow
from by working in terms of properties
per unit volume but here it's where it
uh
reappears via the gbsd relation
uh now I let you play with with with
with the math here it explains
how the fact that if you have a relation
like this you can rewrite it uh in this
other
form just playing with um summing and
subtracting zeros and
U the the good uh thing is that if you
that now the right hand side of this
expression has
differences between chemical
potentials and
therefore this summation which goes
still from one to R but effectively goes
to R2 to minus one because when J is
equal to I this difference is
zero
okay so this is the first step that we
make we substitute this into
here and next once we have this
expression like
this again I let you play with the mafia
it's an expression of this uh type in
which it happens that the coefficients
that multiply here are in variant upon
exchange of I and
J and that symm allows you to add and
subtract um or to rewrite this ter this
summation by exchanging those indexes
and
then subtracting the two and uh
essentially you can get these
identity which we apply
there so now we can we have a this nice
expression in which we have the
summation it's a double
summation but it it has a number of zero
elements because every time it's all
written in terms of difference between
fluxes and differences between chemical
potentials which also has the advantage
that um uh makes it reference frame
independent because those are are fluxes
with respect to the bicentric
velocity so they depend on a reference
frame which is the bicentric one the one
that follows the
lran local uh following your fluid
element but if you take the difference
between the two then the difference is
independent of that frame and that is
also an
advantage so
finally yes we bring back uh uh the
pressure here
and uh we but we have this summation
which is expressed in terms of these
differences that we now rename so j i j
is the flux of particles of species I
with respect to particles of species J
so for example if you have a um the
water vapor that comes out of your
shower and you so it's those water
molecules travel in the air and go and
get your mirrors wet okay so that's
that's diffusion of particles of water
vapor and uh and of course uh the the
room that is made uh empty by those
particles of water vapor that goes away
are filled by the air molecules so there
is a a crossing of flows okay so here
we're talking about so j i J is the is
the is the Flux Of partic of the water
vapor with respect to the motion of to
the mo to the motion of the uh of the
air
molecules so it's a relative
flux and also
these chemical potential differences
that are also written here we can think
of them as the conjugates or this
relative forces
okay all right so now if we
uh we take this expression here we
substitute what we get here so we get a
term with the with gradient in the
pressure and we also have the term with
the dissipation function for from food
mechanics let's forget about those so
let's suppose we take no flow
and no yeah no flow so we move with the
with the
uh perhaps we have a box with um
particles that are steady with respect
to the laboratory
frame and let's suppose we are at
uniform
pressure and also we have no chemical
reactions then we are left with these
three terms and these are the three
terms that will allow us to
uh Define the the thermo diffusion and
the
thermoelectric phenomena that we are
interested in in dealing with as
examples of these cross
effects so this will be our starting
point um
so let's uh so let's take let's start
with the thermoelectric
effects as the more or less simple
example uh of uh of the procedure that
we need in order to to understand
it we start from this expression that of
the entropy production that we just uh
uh reviewed
and in this
case there is only one uh uh particle
which is the
electrons in your conductor or
semiconductor or or the or the holes in
the uh in the
semiconductor okay so
charges but a single a single
constituent it it means that the there
is no uh
diffusive
flux uh with anything else
so the term the term that we had a
couple of slides ago so this one this
one does oops sorry this one doesn't
contribute uh because there is no
relative motion with with anything it's
there is only one type of
particle
okay and here I I have highlighted in
blue and
red uh the flux and the conjugated
entropic uh
Force you'll see in a moment
why I I suggest that when
you do this you always start from this
entropic point of view because that's
the only safe place in which you can U
uh in which you can apply on Saga
relations without making
too many
mistakes all right so the next
step remember this is the extrinsic
relation it doesn't contain any feature
yet of your
material now in order to uh bring in the
features of the material you have to
model the relation between the fluxes
and the forces
and if we assume a linear Force flux
relation because we assume that we are
near equilibrium and so
on this is uh the most General linear
relation between these fluxes and these
forces and it has a a matrix of
coefficients which is the onager Matrix
of coefficients actually in this um
slide these are
tensors because because if you remember
suppose we didn't have uh suppose we had
only um Fier law for La is a linear
relation between the Heat flux which is
a vector and the gradient in Temper in
inverse temperature which is also vector
and the most General relation is through
a tensor which is the conductivity
tensor K double double underline that we
have already discussed and which is
symmetric by uh yag principle
here we have added also uh relations
with other tensors so this would be
instead the relation between electrical
current is current density so it's the
flux of
charge yeah I'm calling it now uh I
double Prime I should have
probably more
consistently called it uh JQ so the
the diffusive flat of charge because
this is still diffusive but since our
solid is a solid is not moving uh there
is no convective part of the of the
charge and so it's it's they are the
same so just to make it more appealing
to the idea that we're talking about
electrical current something that you
measure in a wire
and okay and so this is ohms this is
Ohm's Law if you take only this last
term the relation between current and
the gradient in potential is the the
thing that you measure in voltage with
the
voltmeter in
volts T is to is one /
T and
L is the um
resistivity of your
material which you would measure
in uh oh per me I guess and um and it is
a tensor also so if your material is
isotropic that tensor reduces to just
the one number one one scalar but if it
is an isotropic exactly like we have
seen for for heat transfer you would
have different uh principal directions
of where the where the where the
electrical current likes to run easier
than in other directions
okay so this is the first step assume
linear flux
relations
next what we typically
do is to
rewrite uh so re rearrange these
equations by bringing in more familiar
variables and in this case the more
familiar variable is simply the
temperature instead of tow so this is
one / t
uh but we also want to rewrite it in a
different way so we want in the first
equation to substitute this term here
with the electric
current so what we do is take the second
equation and extract the gradient in Fe
from the second
equation that we will then substitute in
the first
one so this is what we doing so we take
this we solve of course these are
tensors so in order to solve you have to
multiply to the right from the left with
the inverse of
this tensor uh which which it exists
because the tensor is positive definite
because of
uh because of the principle of entropy
non
decrease uh so you do that you get the
graded in feed you substitute up there
and here's what you get as a result so
you get now a relation between the Heat
flux the gradient in
temperature and the electrical
current and of
course the substitution that you've made
since the the gradient in in in the
electric field I'm sorry in the electro
electric potential
um depends on the current but also on
the gradient in
temperature when you substitute it up
there it gives its own contribution to
the term that multiplies the factor the
preactor of the gradient in temperature
so and that's why you see this
difference so this is the
direct say for like kind of term and
this is the
indirect the due to
uh
the due to the the flow of of charges of
electrons okay so and then
finally
we instead of carrying all these names
with the L's we just give different
names so uh the term that multiplies in
this equation um
the gradient in
temperature we call it
Epsilon and that's called the
cack
coefficient this other term we call it
the
electrical resistivity of the
material
[Music]
um so the L was was the conductivity
electrical conductivity I I I spoke
before now this combination of Els here
with the minus the one / t^2 we call it
uh thermal
conductivity and this last one we call
it the Peltier
coefficient and here we repeat their
definitions just for
clarity next we're not done yet
because these four numbers these four
properties these are equilibrium
properties they are uh remember that
this is a linearization around
equilibrium so these are measured at
equilibrium and uh they are not all
independent because there is the unag
principle of reciprocity so l12 is equal
to
l21 more precisely since we're talking
about 10 s you to think
of this big this is a big system in
which you have three equ three equations
here for the components of the heat flux
and three equations here for the
components of the uh current
density uh so you have so it's a 6X
six which you can
U cast in this more compact way but this
6x6 Matrix has to be uh
symmetric by the unag
reciprocity and so this
symmetry
requires that each of uh the groups
these um blocks that we have defined of
these Matrix are symmetric themselves
and also that these off diagonal are um
uh one equal to the to to the
other so if you apply that
symmetry you may uh
notice let's
see yeah you may notice that there is a
relation between the Peltier tensor and
the CC
tensor you take the transpose of the
PTI the transpose of the product of
matrixes uh you know when you do the
transpose you have to also change the
[Music]
order the product of the
transposed and then you apply uh
onager symmetry so this the T goes
away and here
comes something that is contained in
CC except the temperature so essentially
you find that the transpose of PTI is
equal to the temper temperature times CC
and of course if the material is
isotropic these tensors simplify to
simple scalars multiplied by the
identity tensor which is Matrix with all
ones on the diagonal and zeros outside
and and so the Onaga reciprocity implies
that the ptia coefficient is equal to
temperature times the C
effect moreover you can
also re
in terms of the these new uh uh
properties of of these
materials
material uh you can rewrite the the
entropy
production and you would like to like it
to write it in a canonical form just to
make sure that uh uh it is that your
model uh does indeed respect the
principle of entropy on decrease so
these are
quadratic canonical form and these are
quadratic forms which as you see they
are and you can write it in this way
also in this other
one a single quadratic
form
okay so let's see an example of uh where
we use the CC
effect uh every day in the lab which is
the
thermocouple so you see we started from
the general linear
relations and we ended up with these
other
relations now uh yeah let me go back one
moment sorry um I want to show you this
um
already at this
stage if I change one /
T and write the equations in terms of
temperature and not the inverse
temperature look what happens that
um just that little step makes you lose
the
Symmetry because l12 is equal to l21
but this coefficient here is divided by
T this is divided by
t^2 so they are not equal to one another
so if
you uh by mistake started
from or say say well who cares I mean
temp temperature or inverse temperature
so you took the wrong U so it's not the
temperature the um the witness of non
equilibrium the the degree of this
equilibrium uh it's the it's the
gradient of the inverse temperature so
that is minus 1 / t^ 2 time T so that is
the so this is why I I say U you better
be careful and start always from the
entropic point of view and and and the
proper degrees of dise equilibrium
otherwise you may you may end up
thinking that there are symmetries where
they
there are
not and you get wrong relations of
course even more so uh
here and the Symmetry between the this
and
that is uh there is a temperature in
between because beler is a um C time
times the temperature
okay right so what uh what is this
example so the if we apply these
equations
to an electric current that runs in a
wire in which there is a temperature
gradient uh okay then you have this
expression here that relates the
temperature gradient the electric
current
and the voltage drop along the the the
wire uh now a wire is a one-dimensional
thing so you can uh describe
it
uh
by set of
coordinates which is
a um like this so a local set of
coordinates where one versor is tangent
to the axis of the of your wire and the
other two are
orthogonal and and then you have these
vectors so these vectors are uh let's
say the gradient in Fe as a
vector but the important
part if you want to compute the
difference in voltage between 0.1 and
02 uh you have to
integrate the component of the gradient
in fe uh projected on to DL onto the
direction of the wire and and integrate
so you do the integral of D Fe dotted
into
DL from one to two and that gives you
the difference in voltage what is it V2
minus
V1 okay now it turns
out um I don't know if you have seen
this but this is easy to do so the
gradient remember what it is is
um this operator here
and
DL is also a vector which has as
component
DX the
y d
z so now what we're doing here is taking
the scalar
product of this applied onto the scalar
Fe scalar
Fe so when you do the dot product of two
vectors you get the
multiplication of these two so the
multiplication is going to be the
derivative of Fe with respect to X time
DX from these two that these two
components plus the derivative of V with
respect to
y n
z okay and what is this well this is the
expression for the differential of
Fe okay so you can rewrite this term
here as D Fe and therefore the integral
is very easy it's just F2 minus
F1
okay which is what we do
here now we are doing
it the
thermocouple has um has to have two uh
different uh materials so two different
uh
conductors uh here we call it a and we
call it
B that
are joint uh with a with the with a good
conducting uh
uh
Junction
um here and
here and
um at the other end in this
place uh they are not touching so they
are just it's an open circuit so that
there is no current
circulating and you will
measure a voltage differences if there
is
any now in order to compute that voltage
difference you need to do that
integral uh three times from one to
two with metal
a from two to three with metal D and
from three to four again with metal a
and what are we
integrating well the the governing
equation is this one but since we are at
open circuit there is no current so
there is no uh the current is equal to
zero so the remaining stuff is this
simple relation between the gradient in
Fe and the gradient in
temperature so you do those three in
integrals you cannot assume you should
not assume that Epsilon the C
coefficient is constant and so it goes
out of the integral yeah you could but
that would that would be an
approximation unless you use the proper
average in that temperature range
because C coefficients are functions of
temperature
um so let's keep them inside the
integrals this
way and then of course since at the
Junctions the the there is electrical um
continuity uh
the voltage so the electrostatic
potential is always is
equal and so now you can add these three
uh
equations and what you are left with
with is
this that F4 so voltage at four minus
voltage at one is equal to this integral
from 3 to two
um yeah because you're combining this
and that which are the integral or
Epsilon a into a single integral from uh
from four to from three to four and then
from one to two why because
at uh at four and one they you are
assuming the same temperature this is
the laboratory temperature the place
where you put your thermometer so you
assume that T1 is equal to
T4 and therefore you get this difference
and sometimes you call this
difference or actually each the generic
integral of this difference between a
reference temperature and a generic
temperature is called the characteristic
fun function of the thermocouple of the
couple of of the
materials and here are some plots of
those types of
thermocouples that
means at the end of this calculation
what's the final
result that we may have a difference in
in voltage measured by our voltmeter if
there is a difference in temperature es
between two and three T2 and
T3 and of course in order to have this
voltage you need that
the uh characteristic function of that
thermocouple be
different at these two
temperatures
this function here
is um is the function that you uh do
when you calibrate in your lab when you
buy a thermocouple you should do
calibration uh or maybe you buy it
certified so that it comes with a
calibration and calibration is that
somebody has actually measured this for
your
thermocouple
because yeah you could do it
theoretically but uh small uh variations
in in the section cross-section of your
material or some impurity of along the
wires may may result in a different
different uh features and properties of
your wires so you always work with we
always need to do a calibration for your
thermocap now the nice uh thing is that
therefore you have uh here something hot
here something cold and you generate a
voltage so you so if I have a a hot
Reservoir and a cold Reservoir and I
want to produce
electricity
thermocouple can be made to function as
a generator no this is the
thermoelectric generator which is
exactly what I just
said the difference is that now it's a
generator so I don't want just to
measure the voltage difference but I
want to do something useful like uh run
an electrical
engine uh light up some light
or use that
electricity so I have attach a load an
electrical load to the two places where
before I was attaching the
voltmeter and electric Flow Electric
current will start flowing because that
voltage will
cause
flow of of electrons but then that what
uh what does it um what does it do if
there is a current that goes from four
to one there is also a current inside
the um wires that goes all the way
around so when I do the calculation for
the voltage I also need to uh take into
account
now uh the other part of the equation
the one that has to do with uh the
electrical current so I have to adap for
the voltage
drop oh
slow so the
voltage goes down the more current you
have uh the the lower the
voltage and
uh you could actually
go all the way to short if you short the
um thing you have uh the highest
current
but it's all dissipated in Jewel effect
in
heating okay so now I have a voltage the
actual voltage multiplied by the current
that goes through my device the one that
uses that electrical energy voltage
times current is the electrical work the
power volts amp Watts okay so that's the
electrical power
which is given uh
by this expression
here and as you see there is a a jewel
effect dissipation so the highest the
higher is
this uh the more I more inefficient is
my my
engine the problem is that if I want to
make this zero I have to make I zero so
I also get zero
work so there is a compromise and one
way is to compute the maximum
power and so the maximum power is just
take the derivative of this with respect
to I and set it equal to zero that gives
you this uh value for the electric
current and you substitute in there and
you get
the the maximum power
which goes you see as the
square of the difference between the CC
coefficients of the your two materials
these material
pairs notice that
also
um not only for the thermoelectric
generator in which there is electrical
current but also for the
thermocouple let me go back one moment
uh we focused a lot on in order to do
this calculation on the first equation
but also the second equation is in place
and and in addition this we should also
remember that this is a an irreversible
phenomenon it's it's driven by uh
entropy
generation and in
fact there is
a heat Q Prime that runs across runs
down from along the the wire because the
wire is an electric conductor but it's
also a thermal conductor it has a
thermal
conductivity and it has a p coefficient
so it it uh it moves uh
heat both for two reasons one is the
gradient in temperature along the wire
and the other is the electrical current
that uh
uh how do you say carries with it some
heat that's the P
effect which is this this
proportionality
here so that heat is
dissipated and uh
produces of course it produces the
effect you could also think of it in the
other way around it's that it's the the
heat that flows drags also the
electrical
charges to together with with the flow
of of of heat and and that that is why
electrical charges accumulate on one
side of the thermocouple and that's how
you make measure the the voltage
okay so it's the combination of the
two so this same equation gives rise to
the Peltier
effect the peler
effect uh you you can see it uh here it
emerges from this second equation more
directly uh and the typical setup is
that you have a junction between two
different materials in which you run an
electric current so you uh they have to
be
conductor or
semiconductors so you have to have
possibility to drive a current through
this Junction from Material a to
material B so that's the current
I and let's assume for a moment that you
can uh that you are
um uh keeping no gradient in temperature
so the temperature is uniform throughout
here so this term in the equ is not
there and you but but but you still have
the equation it says that the the heat
flux is proportional to the uh electric
current but the problem is that this
proportionality uh coefficient is
different from Material a and material
B so at the
junction whereas the electric current
must be continuous because we cannot
create a
charge so at the junction there is a
continuity so the the electric current
that comes from a is the same that goes
into
B but this also this equation also says
that the the heat
QA uh is given by this and here I have
another heat which is given by this and
it's different because the p of B is
different from P of
a so there is a jump
here in the heat
Flux Of course jump in a heat
flux wouldn't satisfy the energy balance
unless
uh the there is energy coming from
somewhere so essentially this jump calls
in for the balance of energy that is
needed to for it to to exist and
therefore it this Junction transforms
into either a cooler or a heater
depending on the
difference of the Peltier coefficients
and the direction of the current so if
you choose a Peltier pair in which say
pi b is greater than Pi
a
then and you run the electric current in
this way so that this is
positive then QB is greater than
QA so that means you need to provide
energy so that means this Junction
becomes a
cooler this is the Peltier cooling
effect this is what you obtain when you
buy ptsl something that you can buy on
on the internet now for a couple of
bucks and uh and
uh or you can make it simply if you have
a
thermocouple also a thermocouple is
a where you have a junction between two
different materials you have the
possibility of using this
effect the nice aspect of the P effect
and also a nice aspect I forgot to say
it about
the thermoelectric generator is that um
uh they convert electrical energy into
uh heat and vice
versa H without moving parts so these
are engines that do not have
Machinery so these are uh very important
features for some applications for
example for space applications this is
fundamental because uh once you have
sent something in space uh and it's very
hard to provide maintenance so moving
parts are a problem and so if you
have these kind of
devices they
are they're good plus also in space you
have the availability of very large
temperature differences because you
have the photons coming from the Sun
that we just said it's uh 56 uh 5760 k
and on the other side you have the the
dark space which is maybe what is it 2.7
or
4K so
that through of course you need
electromagnetic gradiation because those
they don't have a heat
exchanger the provider of those fluxes
are the photons that we just talked
about the problem with u the development
of devices based on uh on these
effects is the
materials because standard materials
have a very small very small values of
the PTI or CC
coefficients for example
here I took the ones for
copper copper has a cic coefficient of
1.5
microvolt microvolt per
Kelvin against a very high conductivity
K and so the Peltier coefficient which
would mean would would would would would
mean if in this case if I have 1
mm cross-section of my
wire and I run one ampere into it
uh and suppose I have on the other side
an ideal material that is
zero so the difference is all only that
of
copper I would be able to generate Point
half of a
mwatt half a mwatt per ampere ampere is
a lot of
current mwatt is is pretty
little uh
yeah you can also uh read uh this
equation
here in another uh situation suppose you
have a no current Noor no heat
flux so no heat flux zero here so that
says that if you run an electric current
through your wire with no heat flux you
have a buildup of
temperature this is uh we call it also
Thompson effect
uh but no no I think it's p okay but um
so how much how much temperature
gradient does it build up so again see
if I take my millimeter wide and I put
one ampere into
it it does it builds up 1K
1.2k over a meter of
wire so these are small effects but
people are developing
materials for this purpose so there is
an entire literature that you might me
familiar if you're working on on the
field of uh
uh uh scientists working on
developing uh nanomaterials or special
materials designed to maximize these PTI
and um CC
coefficients some of these materials are
also
semiconductors so this is
a typical
setup and uh you put many of these
devices in in in parallel so as to
produce sensible amount of
uh of power each one contributes a
little but if you put a lot together uh
overall you may obtain the effect that
you need
and the typical design of these devices
is uh is the same whether you're using
the uh
Electro Thermo Electric
generator or if you want your sort of
solid state
thermocouple or you want the
ptsl so it's the same device that
depending on how you use it
performs in in different in this
different
ways now regarding the thermoelectric
generator uh
traditionally people like
to characteriz the
materials with this uh parameter here
which is called Figure of Merit for the
um thermoelectric
material which is the uh Epsilon so CC
Square time temperature divided by
resistivity and thermal
conductivity you may we may see how this
parameter comes out in in in our own uh
language or at least the language that
we have developed in this uh course if
you um accept that you can U uh rewrite
the the work the power of the electric
therm electric generator that we have
developed in the previous
slides as an
integral of what happens locally so as
if everywhere in the in the in the wire
there is a a something that is
the local contribution to the overall
effect so you integrate that local
contribution over the entire distance
and you get the overall
effect in a sense this is a power
density electrical useful useful power
density of your device okay so if you
accept uh accept that and then in fact
that power density is the
product of the the electric
current and the gradient in in in the
electric in the Vol in the voltage so
that's voltage times current is power no
so this is the density
though so I take this one and then I'm
going to in order I want to Define an
efficiency second low efficiency which
is down
here so I want to take the
work obtained and divided by the maximum
work I could obtain for that same
temperature difference now locally the
temperature difference is just the
temperature gradient and if you go back
in the notes and maybe this uh image
reminds you where to go you you see
remember that when we when we did this
the elements of the heat transfer we we
said yeah we could substitute our
material with a a little engine and how
much work would it be able to
do if you go back you find that that
maximum
work uh or work rate is given by uh the
heat times the the gradient in 1 / T *
T so this is the
expression
therefore the second L
efficiency of your thermoelectric
generator locally at least local
contribution is given by the ratio
between this and
that which we can calculate because we
have the equations for for the gradient
in Fe for Q that's it's the same
equations that we started
with so do the
substitutions and compute the the
work now again here the work can take uh
um
can take a maximum Max maximum
values uh I think there is an error here
this must be a minus
sign
yeah yeah because there's a minus
here
yeah I don't see it right off hand but
this I think this should be a
minus because this is the jewel effect
that should detract from the work that
is
done so you maximize this by taking the
derivative with respect to to the
current density and set it to zero
substitute and you get the expression
for the
[Music]
maximum power
density and this is the maximum that you
should get
ah no okay I see they are different in
sence because the gradient the gradient
is negative because the work uh you get
work when when the current goes down uh
the negative you need a decreasing
temperature gradient yeah okay in fact
you get the maximum when I is minus
gradient of
it and
so we take this substituting the
expression for the
Q and obtain therefore the maximum
reversible
work so at maximum power the ratio of
this to
that you see they both depend on the
square of the gradient
so they uh disappear this cancels with
that
and you're left with just a ratio of
coefficients where this parameter of
Merit appears this
Z okay so this is not the standard way
of presenting uh this parameter of
Merit but at least it has some value of
being local the problem is that in
practical applications since the
materialss that you use are temperature
dependent and uh and it is important
that that they be temperature
dependent um
often in these kind of derivations of of
this parameter you assume constant C
coefficient or constant
thermoconductivity or constant which is
uh which is only for the purpose of the
derivation and not uh
in order to arrive to this
expression
okay again in the the list of
thermoelectric effects we can
also list this Thompson effect which is
though um I think still the same thing
only said in a different uh language
so we have seen that in the interplay
between electric current and temperature
gradient uh allows you to
transform uh electrical
energy into thermal energy and vice
versa so what we do here is to take uh
to write the balance equation for the
internal energy and you can do this for
a for a for also for a flow situation we
have written if you go back where couple
of lectures ago when we did the general
balance equations we have we had an
expression for the balance for
energy and uh today in one of the
previous uh slides we've done uh the
difference
between the energy and the internal
energy which is all those terms kinetic
potential and so
on so in order to obtain a balance
equation for the just internal energy
you have to subtract from the energy
balance
equation uh uh the balance equation for
the non-thermal aspects so for the
mechanical aspects like the kinetic the
potential and the
electrical and if you do that uh this is
what uh what using the slide that
mentioned you can obtain
this of course in the uh in the balance
for energy there appears
the energy flux that's the
overall uh diffusive energy flux which
we have broken into
a nonwork and a work part the nonwork
part part is the one that now if for a
solid in the absence therefore of other
moving particles other than the just the
electrons in the in the in the conductor
is just given by these two terms
otherwise you would have the summation
of the enthalpies partial
enthalpies and for the work part it's
given by the um stress tensor times the
velocity but if we are assuming that
there's no velocity here this is really
going
away so uh if you get to the
end
U the terms that
survive are this so uh on the left hand
side of the balance equation you have
the material derivative of the internal
energy of your uh fluid element so
that's the internal energy that part of
the energy as of the fu elements as you
follow its
motion that gets
changed by what
by
uh heat
diffusion this is for for thermal
diffusion
so you should think of this as
the uh the equivalent of of the forier
law forier equation of of cond
conduction so this is would be row CV
times the DT DT D temperature of DT this
is K Times app of the temperature if if
K is independent dep of position
therefore of
temperature then you have this term here
this term here is the jewel effect this
is like a source term it's would be in
in heat transfer you would put it as a q
triple prime so it's a a source ter of
of thermal
energy and it
actually it's uh electrical energy that
gets dissipated into thermal energy via
the jewel
effect if you had written uh the balance
equation for the mechanical and
electrical parts this same term would
appear there with a negative sign so it
would detract it would destroy uh
mechanical and electrical energy so it
would be negative sign in those
equations and appears here with positive
sign because because it goes from
electrical to uh to Thermal and it's one
way it has a definite sign that cannot
be negative it goes only in that way you
can only kill uh electrical energy with
the jewel
effect
like uh although we in a solid this
doesn't really make sense but I just put
it for for our discussion if you also
had flow
the the viscous dissipation also has the
same feature it appears with a negative
sign in the equation for the kinetic
energy kinetic plus potential energy
because it kills that kind of energy and
it appears with a positive sign in the
internal
energy so that transforms so this is
always
positive but then there is also this
term this term is is the jewel the the
Thompson
effect uh it's it's you see there is a
scalar product of the electric current
and the gradient in
temperature this can
be all signs could be positive and
negative and
uh and it allows you and it is it is
that term which allows the effects that
we explained in in transform in uh
thermal energy into um electrical energy
if it is
negative because with a minor sign uh
I'm sorry since it is a minor sign if it
is POS if it is positive it consumes
internal energy and where does that
energy go it becomes
electrical or vice versa you use uh
electrical energy in order if for this
becoming thermal energy
okay so this adds a a
term the Thompson
coefficient
is if you follow the various steps at a
certain stage uh we have uh since there
is the the Divergence of of the energy
flux it brings in the gradient of the
ptia coefficient and the gradient of the
pelti coefficient can can be written as
the partial as how it varies with
temperature partial of of pi over T
times the gradient in
temperature and this uh Thompson
coefficient sometimes it's called with T
I use this
Epsilon T looking Greek symbol just not
confusing we have so many T's here that
one more would be too many so uh this is
given by U the difference
between the how the P coefficient varies
with temperature and the CC coefficient
but since Peltier and CC are
connected uh the the Onaga relation p is
Epsilon times T you can also write this
coefficient as T times how the C varies
with
temperature and uh recently there have
there have been
people discussing the fact
that there may be it may be more um or
at least maybe um a good idea to try to
build uh
Thermo Electric
Generators not so much on the
basis of that parameter there but on the
basis
of materials that have a very high
temperature dependence of the CC
coefficient so as to
enhance this gamma and therefore enhance
the capability for a given gr gradient
temperature to produce uh the highest Uh
current okay let me just mention uh
before yeah we have a couple of
minutes I'm not going into the details
here just want to mention that uh the
range so the the inventory the the
catalog of uh effects that we have
covered with that Matrix that we started
on today with the K principle uh is not
at all
complete uh
because for example if you add uh one
item the the magnetic
field you you add
another uh spot in that
Matrix and actually another for for
spots uh and these are uh effects that
belong to the same
category one is called and they also
belong to the history no like one is
called the all
effect uh H is the magnetic
field uh and the other is called and the
converse or let's say the Onaga re
reciprocal effect is called ner n
effect
and they generate they they gener if you
have an electric field and you have an
electric current in One Direction the
magnetic field produces an electric
current also in the opp in the
orthogonal direction this is the whole
effect and N does the same thing instead
of having this driving force the
electric field you have this driving
force the gradient in temperature which
uh we know that uh drives an electric
current like we just seen the
thermoelectric effect but in the
presence of magnetic field it also
drives an orthogonal current like the
all
effect and very recently as you see this
is just a few years ago
people uh have been working on the
equivalent of these effects also on uh
spin uh
currents so they're not moving charges
but they are moving the spin that is uh
internal into like uh the atoms or the
nuclei of the uh atoms that you move
around so and you look just at the
current of
Spin and they have found similar
effects and this is I guess it's see
similar uh
idea done with spin currents instead of
charge
currents and so this was only to say
that this is a a topic
that is so Broad
and and so full of applications that
it's very difficult to to cover in a in
a sort of a
systematic uh
way but it's also to show that
um it can be it it must be uh
regularized and understood in a in a
systematic framework like we have done
uh uh starting with the entropic point
of view and uh uh developing the linear
Force flux relations and applying on sag
relations
and
often uh
this way of proceeding uh is is what
drives the the the search for new
effects you didn't think about it until
you said all I see ah
so so by induction there must be an
effect like that because there is a spot
in that Matrix of a phenomena that is
that is related via the onager
principle all right so yes I think we
are done for today and U next time we do
the
thermal diffusive effects and and then
we will be done so next uh lecture will
be the last one