I appreciate the opportunity to
introduce J wafs to the R&D conference
attendees this year jwf is the abdulatif
jam water and Food Systems Lab at MIT we
were established 10 years ago as an
institute-wide program to support
actionable research on human need for
water and
food JW's mission is to catalyze
research Innovation and technology for
ensuring safe and resilient supplies of
water and food while reducing
environmental impact to meet the local
and Global needs of a rapidly expanding
and evolving population on a changing
Planet no small order our goal is
research with impact and technology that
can
transfer in support of this Mission jws
has funded 128 discret grants to date
including 78 seed grants to help launch
new research directions 28
commercialization grants to help spend
Technologies out of
MIT six corporate sponsored research
projects and one million a half doll
Grand Challenge Grant as well as
numerous additional smaller grants and
student fellowships our funding has
supported research by faculty staff and
students across all of MIT spanning
numerous departments and
disciplines we Implement a variety of
funding programs and other activities to
support water and food research in
addition to our direct research funding
opportunities we facilitate Partnerships
with companies and other research
institutions around the world that drive
the development of new technologies and
solutions We Gather National and
international experts to guide research
and Innovation for example on topics
like low carbon
desalination and we
support the next generation of water and
Food Systems leaders through our
fellowships and support from mit's water
and food
clubs the water and food related
research areas that MIT has expertise in
are quite Broad and varied JW's research
addresses challenges spanning Food
Safety Supply
chains crop fertilization and
productivity in the face of climate
change and a host of water quality and
water supply issues in developing and
developed countries
alike research projects draw from MIT
expertise across multiple disciplines
from chemical engineering for
separations and sensors to machine
learning and computer vision to create
crop maps for policy makers to
microbiome and plant engineering for
food
production The Faculty we have supported
come from most of mit's departments I'd
like to give you a sampling of some of
our varied research
projects Professor Sarah Barry is
applying AI to improve the the very
resource intensive process of counting
migrating salmon which is essential to
fisheries
management using computer vision
technology her approach will be deployed
in rivers across the Pacific Northwest
in partnership with the Alaska
Department of Fish and Game and the
National Oceanic and Atmospheric
Administration Professor gang Chen has
discovered a new photo molecular effect
that offers promise for decreasing the
energy needs for
desalination his seed Grant is
furthering his research demonstrating a
photo molecular evaporation rate that
can exceed pure thermal evaporation by
about 10
times Professor Patrick Doyle is
currently spinning out a new technology
that can remove micropollutants from
processed water he initially developed
the technology with a jwa seed Grant and
is currently commercializing it with a
grant from our Solutions program the
technology makes use of hydrogel micr
particles and can be customized to
remove specific
micropollutants Professor Swagger in
chemical engineering had a JW Solutions
Grant to spin out technology developed
in his lab that makes testing for food
pathogens dramatically faster for the
food processing industry zyus systems
has been through two funding rounds and
is commercializing technology
integrating materials Optics and
biotechnology Professor Mary Garing is a
plant biologist who works on improving
the productivity of the world's Food
Systems her jawwa supported research is
addressing the need to generate more
genetic diversity and crops such as
pigeon pea a major source of protein and
calories in many parts of Africa her
genetic engineering techniques and
generating are generating variants that
can be screened for resistance to
salinity and Heat stress two major
challenges with climate
change and not all of our research
around is around technology development
professor John Fernandez and Scott Odell
in the Environmental Solutions
initiative are looking into the
relationship between the mining industry
and water use climate change and the
agricultural communities that depend on
the glacial environment in
Chile the project will produce findings
that can be used by communities
government and Industry to reduce the
negative impacts of Mining and climate
change in water stressed regions of
Chile and around the
world entrepreneurship is one of the
most impactful paths for MIT research to
address real world
problems technologies that have been
commercialized through jwa Solutions
program commercialization grants range
from Advanced desalination and other
separation Technologies to Affordable
solutions to detect and remove
contaminants from from drinking water in
developing countries here you see eight
startups and two open-source products
that jws has helped launch that are
working to advance solutions for water
food and
agriculture jws also works to Advanced
industry collaboration with MIT and
corporate sponsored research around
sustainable water and food systems
through our research Affiliates program
we support research Partnerships with
industry and the development of new
techn techologies companies support the
development of new IP and Technologies
to provide solutions to industry or
customer needs that may lead to new
product lines new businesses
efficiencies in manufacturing processes
or other improvements to
sustainability we encourage corporate
Affiliates to bring their biggest
challenges around water and food
challenges that are appropriate to Mi
level research we provide access and
guidance to navigate the MIT research
Community we match challenges to
research capabilities and expertise from
across MIT and we work with the sponsor
and the researchers to define the
proposed scope and budget and facilitate
communication and oversight of sponsored
research
projects so I hope with this quick tour
through our programs and activities I
have made you aware of the many ways
that MIT is working to address the
world's need for clean water and healthy
food
jws is always interested in talking to
companies that have related business or
Market challenges and we're eager to
explore opportunities to collaborate
please visit our website sign up for our
newsletter or reach out to me personally
if you'd like to learn more thank you
for your kind attention
[Applause]