I'm here today to answer your question
how do you make a unicorn so let's talk
about making a horse with a horn in the
middle of its head you may have heard
about the human genome this is basically
the set of instructions for making you
you humans aren't the only ones to have
genomes all living organisms have
genomes when we understand these genomes
we can edit the genome and then change
the characteristics of the organism so
maybe we could take a look at the
rhinoceros genome because rhinos have a
horn in the middle of their head one
once we figure out what part of the
rhinog gome codes for one horn in the
middle of the head and develops properly
at the right time we can take those
pieces from The rhinog genome insert
them into the horse genome implant that
cell into a mother horse and Let It
multiply divide and eventually become a
baby unicorn magic not included for more
MIT moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow