Okay, great. Uh, so thanks everyone for
coming to MIA seminar today. Uh, I guess
now after daylight saving so it should
feel a little bit more awake. Um but
yeah uh so today we're very lucky to
have uh Jingi Jessica Lee here uh and
postto pan uh recently moved to the Fred
Hutch Cancer Institute and today they're
going to be talking about some exciting
new statistical work they've been doing
and so Jessica is going to lead off on
permutation enhances the rigor in
genomics data analysis. Thanks so much
for coming. Thank you Tabber for the
invitation and it's it's our great
pleasure to give our talk of our
research at the MIA seminar and so my
talk will be the primer and then Pang
will give a specific talk on her
research. So my primer hopefully can
open the door for her talk and I'll
introduce some basics and our thinking
in particular in this research. So the
theme of the talk today is permutation
but later I will go broader to talk
about how we think using some thing we
call as a synthetic null data can help
with our data analysis. I think we hope
this to be broad enough to be relevant
to your research. So I'll begin by this
interesting figure which was actually
something we found on social media after
the Nobel Prize in physics was announced
last year and Pan actually helped me do
the translation because it was
originally in Chinese. But I found this
very interesting because the question is
what is physics and it can be
characterized in two dimensions. The
objects we study and the methods we use.
So you can see that for either dimension
we can go from being very fundamentalism
to very liberal. So it means that we can
be very restrictive on what we study the
objects where there's something very
general or the methods we use like laws
or we can be very liberal and the
neuronet network is actually on the
liberal side for both dimensions. We
don't use physical laws and the object
study is not something we see as
concrete in real life. So this kind of
characterization made me wonder how
about genomics. So for many reasons
genomics can be seen as a liberal
discipline as many of you may be aware
of from because of research you can
judge because it's very
interdisciplinary. You may be trained in
in a very wide range of disciplines and
it's very datadriven. So we start from
data and there can be all sorts of
hypothesis we can ask and there's a
rapid revolution of methods just using
the single cell RNA seek as one example
you can see this rapid evolution of
methods thousands of methods and as a
result you can have f flexible
analytical approaches how do you design
the pipeline for data analysis there can
be many options since my research is at
the intersection of statistics and
genomics so I was a statistics professor
at UCLA for 12 years. So if I think
about statistics is very different from
genomics because people there really
talks about rigor. How can we have a
better method in terms of how to say
people have set up a set of criteria to
evaluate how good a method is or what
these methods should guarantee. So if we
trace it back to the history right the
most popular one of the most well-known
methods is called two sample datas from
introductory courses. So this method was
developed for a very simple reason to
comp compare a new way of um beer
brewing to a traditional way. So
essentially it's for quality assessment.
You want to know whether this new way is
actually different or better than a
traditional way or if the difference we
see in the two ways of beer brewing is
something meaningful not just due to
some measurement randomness. So because
of this origin I think about how these
two things could be bridged in some
meaningful way because rigor was
considered as important statistics but
on the other hand in genomics we have so
many options to do our data analysis. So
one article I hope to introduce to our
general audience is this very
interesting review or perspective piece
about eight most important statistical
ideas in the past five decades and one
of the ideas is related to what I will
talk about today bootstrapping and
simulationbased inference. So
permutation can be considered as a
special case for this idea. So the idea
is to do some resampling of your data to
break some dependency that potentially
exist between your variables and after
permutation by disrupting such
dependency you can actually obtain a
negative data set where the dep
dependency is removed. So I think this
can serve as a baseline for data
analysis because then you can say
whether the discoveries you observe in
your data analysis is something
meaningful is something that you cannot
observe from permitted data and how to
permute the data. I'll give several
examples in my talk today and P will
talk about one specific example which I
will briefly mention and she will go
into detail. So it depends on the set of
variables you have whether it's a
supervised learning setting in which you
have those features as predictors and a
response you want to predict for or it's
unsupervised learning setting which you
don't have the response or outcome but
just the features. So for bulk RNA data
I will consider it in this supervised
learning case because here I can
consider the samples belonging to more
than one condition and here the features
for RNA seek are genes for the
unsupervised learning I'll use single
cell RNA seek as example here the
samples are cells and the features are
genes so the bulk example is more like a
teaser to open up my talk to show you
that if you use primitive you may see
something quite interesting. So this is
a paper we published um three years ago
now. So which in which we pointed out
that by popularity you would choose
certain method by following tutorials to
do the the differential expression or de
analysis. However, if your sample size
is large enough, you may actually see
that some of the assumptions you assume
in the methods may not hold well in your
data sets and there as a result you may
have more than what you expected in
terms of false discoveries. And the
interesting thing is that this was a
coincidence finding and it was a
collaboration with Dr. way's lab who is
a computational biology lab his postto
who did analysis and my former student
who was trained in statistics. So this
is the major surprising result which
motivated us to look f look further into
the issue. So this is the data set from
patients. So we have 51 patients
pre-imunotherapy
and 58 patients on imunotherapy and oak
RNA data of their blood samples and DSC2
and HR are two of the most popular or
widely used EIC methods. They have very
good software implementations and very
detailed tutorials you can follow. So
the first finding that surprised us or
that actually it's not a surprise
because many people reported the same
thing but it's just that they didn't
look into the issue as detail. So
basically the two methods may not give
you similar findings. So in this case
for this particular data set the two
popular methods give you different
numbers of D genes edge are twice as
many as DC2s. And the first question we
want to ask is which set of results
should we trust more? Right? And if you
look at the overlap, it's not like the
C2 results are a subset of HRS. So here
the sample sizes are big enough for us
to do permutation because if we think
about the origin of these two methods
when they were developed more than 10
years ago when RNA seat bulk was still
considered a new technology the sample
sizes are quite small were quite small
because they're they're expensive so
typically if you're you run a wab you
may only be willing to just generate
three barnas replicates per condition
then it's three versus three comparison
and how can you get enough statistical
power out of it? Then both methods have
to assume a gene every gene follows a
parametric distribution under each
condition. So specifically both assumes
that for count data like RNA seek every
genes counts follow a negative binomial
distribution under each condition. So
with this parametric assumption they can
have more power for finding the genes.
So with just three data points as in
their design, it's not possible to check
how reliable negative binomial
assumption holds because you just have
to assume it. But with such large sample
sizes, then we can check the
distribution. But before I show that
result, let's just first show the
surprising result that is by
permutation. simple permutation in which
we randomly assign those 109 samples
into two into two groups with the sizes
kept as 51 and 58. But now because of
random assignments, these two groups no
longer make any sense. We just run each
method again on the period data and we
can get a DEG number. And we can repeat
this for a thousand times. We can have
1,000 DEG numbers from permitted data.
That will give us a distribution. And
here the height of the bar is the
average number and the standard error
bar is just the standard error standard
deviation. And we can see that compared
to the permuted data from the original
data actually the methods found even
fewer genes this doesn't doesn't make
any sense because we would expect fewer
D genes from permuted data. So why is
this happening? Right? That's our first
question. Why are so many genes found as
DE from permitted data? and we check the
negative binomial assumption. As I said
earlier, the interesting thing is that
for this data set, negative binomial
does not seem to be a reasonable
distribution. The reason is twofold.
First of all, negative binomial can be
theoretically justified if your B cores
data are technical replicates, meaning
that they are biologically identical.
But because of sampling um uncertainty,
you don't have exactly the same number
in each sample. So you have some
differences and that can be described by
like passon distribution for sampling
and before passon you can have a gamma
distribution for the biological
heterogeneity. However, here we are not
having replicates. Here the 51 are
patients and 58 are patients. And we
know that there could be greater
heterogeneity than replicates. That's
one reason. And the second reason here
is because we have enough data points to
check how the distribution fits. And
this is the commonly used quantile
quantile or QQ plot which can allow you
to check whether a theoretical
distribution fits data well. And because
we see this points that do not lie on a
straight line, we can conclude that here
negative binomial distribution does not
seem to hold well. And this is for that
was for HR and this is for DCQ. So we
see the similar train. So you may wonder
what will be the consequence if I didn't
know this but I just did the analysis. I
use DCQ or HR to report my results.
Here's what you will get from your um
gene ontology enrichment analysis. So
you'll actually see these terms enriched
in the genes you find with D62 or HR and
many of those are actually related to
immune response or immune process
process. So you may actually conclude
that yes I can see the differences in
immune responses between the two groups
patients because they are pre pre or
after imunotherapy. So you may be very
happy with your results but if you
actually know that okay these genes can
also be frequently identified from
permuted data then you may step back and
double think about the results probably
it's just that immune genes are so
dynamic that they can be easily found
from the analysis anyway so that could
be one possibility but that just open
door for more questions or critiques so
I'll just say that this teaser even
though we found this by coincidence and
it was not a method the paper but
somehow it received a lot of attention
and discussion in the field because many
people would think of bulk RNC analysis
as a done task you have popular methods
that have been used by many people then
there's no issue about considering using
or how to change my analysis or use
different methods but we are just
arguing that the data characteristics do
matter so essentially which method to
choose depend on your sample size and
also depend on whether you can check the
assumption of the methods no matter how
popular they are on your data. So for
this data set if we use this very
standard will coxin rank some test
because this is okay for two sample
comparison if you don't want to adjust
for other sample characteristics like
coariantss you can use that and at least
on this data set even though the results
are disappointing because will coxin
does not give you any findings but it's
not self-conlicting so you also don't
see any discoveries from permit data so
you don't have this conflicting results
that bother us all right so That's the
teaser part to show that popular
permutation as a very simple task can
review a lot of things but we just need
to just add it to our data analysis
without too much trouble.
>> Um
>> yes
>> so just quick question. So looking back
at the initial plot, it seemed like
there were two things that were um there
that one was that the kind of confidence
interval on the permutation was very
large. But then the other was that in
all of the examples shown the
>> kind of actual red box is far below the
mean of so
>> is that in a statistically significant
manner that the the red box is far
below.
>> Okay. Yeah, actually it's actually okay
because this is just one standard
deviation. So it's actually within one
standard deviation. Yeah, I think the
reason is that in this case because you
can see the two sample, right? So
essentially because of these outliers,
you can see that if you move one outlier
to another group, then the results will
be very different. So that can explain
why the numbers can change so large.
Yeah. Yeah. Thank you for the question.
>> Thanks. Um could you hi could you
explain like so what does the
distribution of gene expression look
like in that human data like is it just
that there's a lot of like outliers or
is there a lot of technical
>> I think that that's a very important
question yeah so when you see those
outliers which are actually very large
counts so essentially looking at one
gene you will see larger counts than
what you can explain using a negative
binomial and then the question is and
these are from patients. How do you look
at those data? Do you think they are
error measurements or do you think they
are potentially something meaningful? I
think that's the question or maybe in
this case looking at just the mean may
not be so meaningful, right? Probably
you should go with like looking at the
variance or you should specifically
focus on outliers. I think these are
very important questions. But if we just
run the DE analysis blindly, we'll miss
those opportunities. Yeah, thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Um, did you check more data set because
this is maybe this is only true for this
data set.
>> Of course, if you look at our paper, we
have multiple data sets. It's just that
this one is the most striking one and we
just report and we actually also tried
this on TCGA data sets and GTEC data
sets because both are from human
populations. So they are patient data
not replicate data. So in short I think
the conclusion we want to draw people's
attention to is that population if you
have data from human patients you cannot
treat them as replicates. And while the
negative binomial assumption was
justified only for replicates.
>> So this is more likely because the
heterogeneity of the exact people.
>> Exactly. Yeah. And these people may even
have subops, right? But you didn't
divide them.
>> Yeah. Another question is that do you
have any idea idea about if we can use a
better distribution to model the count
data rather than only using the negative
binomial distribution? in this case. So
there are if you look at the literature
there are more than a hundred DE methods
many of them didn't become popular
because every method but as long as they
were published right so they have their
reason they have their underlying model
assumptions some of them as you
mentioned they would go with some
non-parametric modeling for a change
distribution but the question is if the
distribution is something not like
negative binomial or not something you
can easily describe by a parametric
model whether the mean parameter is
still your primary interest. I think
that's the question. Yeah. So I think we
need to think about what we are really
looking for because for negative
binomial people think okay the mean
parameter means the biological
expression or the true expression we are
hoping to infer that's why they go with
the differential expression right but as
I said earlier I think it really depends
on the the data and also I think during
the discussion online discussion some
people did show that if you remove those
outliers you can make negative binomial
fit Well, and then you can pursue
proceed with your normal analysis. But
here I think we need to think about the
data as patients, right? So every data
point should be valuable in some way
unless we made a mistake in the
measurement. So how do we consider the
outliers? Yeah, but that's a very good
point. Yeah, thank you. So that's why
when we use the will coxin rank some
test, essentially we drop the parametric
assumption. We're just comparing the two
sets of numbers in terms of ranks.
All right. So now I will move on to the
unsupervised learning case with single
cellic data. Samples are cells, features
are genes. And I will talk about two
examples and first one about
visualization. Second one about this
meta cell practice and pan will because
pan is the first author for the metasel
MC rigger standing for metasell rigger
and she will give detailed discussion on
this so I'll be brief on this but I'll
talk about how we use permutation to
help us tune the hyperparameters of t or
um for better visualization.
So single cell visualization is a
commonly used way to to show the data
right because we know biological papers
have figures and they want to look at
the data people want to look at the data
but for single cell data challenge is
that every cell is represented as a
highdimensional gene expression vector
like depending on how many genes you
measure if it's 1,000 then every cell is
1,00 dimensional how can you see that
highdimensional space we don't know so
two dimensional space is what our human
eyes are most comfortable with or the
papers are printed as 2D. So that's why
the very how to say hopeful thing is
that we can see the cells in a 2D plot
and use the plot to have some idea about
their relationships. For example, people
want to see clusters representing cell
types. They want to see trajectories
representing cells continuous changing
process. But TNE which was actually
introduced in 2008 at that time there
was no single cell data but it was
introduced as a general visualization
technology of highdimensional data. It
was designed to encourage and similar
data points to be clustered together so
you can see clearer clusters. But there
is a key hyperparameter called
perplexity. Perplexity essentially
defines the size of a neighborhood. If
it's very small then you will have
smaller but many many smaller clusters.
If it's big then you will have a big
cluster. So looking at this toy example
in which the original data is just
two-dimensional. So this is considered
the true visualization. If you run TS
from a small perplexity to a large
perplexity you can see very different
visualizations. Sometimes you will see
the two clusters, sometimes you don't.
And also if you want to use the
visualization to say anything about
whether two clusters are close to each
other or very different, then the
distance may not mean anything. And this
critique has been also reported by this
commentary article on nature methods
about using tarap to see the data. And
the last sentence here is that the
abstra is sometimes these these methods
take a second thought. So our method the
one we propose kind of like a
compromise. So we know that there are
voices against using them for
visualizing our data. However, we think
it's very hard to discourage or let
people say okay don't use anymore
because they have been in every paper
right. So if we want to use them anyway
is there a way to use them better? So to
answer this question, we actually
formulated the problem as a question as
okay, is a sales embedding dubious or
trustworthy? How can we define this? How
can we know if we can trust a cell's
relative location in the figure in the
2D figure? And our idea is to compare
the cells neighbors before we do the
embedding which means that in the input
data before t near um mapap and after
the embedding which means the v the 2D
figure we see and we title our method
called we call our method sed for
answering this question. And our
intuition is to look at the what we call
mid range neighbors of a cell of a. So
this one the purple one cell one is of
our interest our target and we look at
the mid-range neighbors and we define
that as half of our cells in our
definition but this is something we can
change however we think this is a
reasonable proportion so if the
neighborhood is so small we know both
tney and um can do very well in
preserving the neighbors because that's
in their algorithm for encouraging the
close neighbors to be preserved but we
are looking at a mid-range neighbor
neighbors since we are interested in
between cluster relationships. So not
just the local neighborhoods. So in this
case we need to look at a bigger range
and also how do we define pre-mbbedding
neighbors. So in in practice when people
do um single cell data visualization the
pre-mbbedding neighbors or the
pre-mbbedding space is not the original
highdimensional space but what people
did after PCA. So essentially PCA is
commonly performed as a pre-processing
step to reduce the dimensions from a
thousand or thousands to 20 to 50 PCs.
The hope is that PCA removes noise but
preserves the major important signals
but still 20 to 50 PCs are not enough
for visualization. That's why we are not
good for visualization. That's why we
are using the tney UMAP to project them
from the PC space to the 2D space. So in
this case in the PC space cell distances
are measured by ukidian distance and
that's how we define the pre-mbed
neighbors and this is exactly what was
used in the TER um algorithm the ukidian
distance in the input space. While in
the 2D space, we are also using the
Ukrainian distance we see in this figure
because that's how our human mind or
eyes interpret this figure. So we want
to compare these two sets of neighbors
each chosen from each space and we want
to compare their ordered distances. So
essentially what we are doing here is
that we are taking each set preserve
their order in their previous in their
original space. So this one mean that
the neighbors are ordered by ukidian
distances from the closest to the
farthest in this half range and uh in
this PC space and we have another order
set of neighbors in the 2D space and for
each set given the order we actually
record the u the 2D ukia distance of
each neighboring cell to the target
cell. So in this case the two vectors we
construct are taken from the same 2D
space because that's how we interpret
the figure right so that's what we're
looking at and then we compare the
consistency of these two sets of order
distances and we use the the Pearson
correlation as the measure for
consistency and define that as a
reliability score. The reason we choose
Pearson correlations because it actually
considers the actual distance values not
just the ranking because for example
here this one is very far away but these
are not so far away. So when we look at
the figure we're not just interpreting
the relative ranking but actually the
actual distance. So that's how we define
the reliability score. And this cell
cell one is considered by us to have a
good reliability score while cell two is
something we consider to be bad or
dubious. So in this case if you see the
figure the pre-mbedded neighbors looking
at them on the 2D space you can see that
they are very scattered right so they're
not concentrated or they don't look like
the neighbors to cell two. So this means
that TC or UMAP embedding changed the
half range neighbors a lot after we do
the projection. So in this case the
reliability score is considered low. So
that's the intuition and our intuition
turned into this score definition but we
still need some calibration or we need
some baseline and here the no hypothesis
using the statistical language or the
baseline in the scientific language is
that here what will happen if the sales
neighbors are not meaningful. How can we
create such a scenario in which the
mid-range neighbors are just random
right? How can we do that? And in this
case we think about permutation. So if
we think about permuting
each gene randomly across all cells we
do that independently for all genes.
What will happen? So you'll see that by
such a permutation you did preserve
every genes marginal distribution
dimensional distribution because there
are same values just differently
ordered. But what should disrupt is ging
correlations and also cell cell
relationships because in this case your
period cells do not correspond to the
original cells they are a new sample and
this new sample come from this new
distribution but since these period
cells if you think about them
mathematically they're actually
exchangeable with each other. So
therefore each period cells can be
considered neighbors to any other
permeated cells right? So there you
don't have any meaningful biological
relationships and with such data if we
apply our score calculation to each per
media cell we can get a score but this
score comes from the null case in which
that you don't have meaningful
neighborhood preservation and we can get
one null score from each permitted cell
and that will give us a distribution and
this distribution can let us calibrate
the scores we calculate from our real
data from our original cells whether
they're high enough they must be high
enough to be called trustworthy right
they should be much higher than most of
the null scores but regarding the
dubious definition how do we set a
threshold so here in our paper we set a
threshold to be very very conservative
in the sense that if you are worse than
the majority of the no scores then they
you are really really bad and then we
flag that score as dubious is that you
may actually change this. You may
actually say, "Okay, I don't want to be
too conservative and this threshold is
adjustable." But regardless here, this
distribution just give you a way to
calibrate the scores for your real cells
to see whether they are good enough. And
also I want to clarify that here the
permutation only needs to be done once
because once we do this permutation once
for the whole matrix we can get a score
for each permitted cell and that pulling
them together we can get a distribution.
So we don't have to worry about the
computational cost for many rounds of
permutation. So let me just show you how
we can what we find. So this is one
figure from a 2019 science paper about a
species called hydra in the ocean for
their single cell RNA data measured for
the first time in history. So you can
see that this is the original tney plot
using the default perplexity 40 in
Surret. And if we run our dubious
detector to detecting dubious
embeddings, you can see that to our
interest like very interestingly a lot
of the dubious embeddings are in those
small clusters here. And so we just
wonder whether because of this how to
say distortion by the 2D embedding we
see those three these small clusters but
they shouldn't be as so isolated or
stand alone as we see in the figure and
in fact that's the case because if you
go back to the labels you see that a lot
of the labels of the clusters on tney
were given a number and the number
meaning that they share with the same
cell type label with some other clusters
but because they look like separate
clusters they were given different
numbers but that may not be biological.
So one example you can see here is in
the original figure you will have the
three small clusters surrounding the big
orange cluster and the orange cluster
represents stem cells but the three
small clusters have the same label
neuron ectoorm cells and with our
optimized visualization. So how we do
that? We can actually change perplexity
calculate the number of dubious
embeddings and find the perplexity value
in which at which the dubious embeddings
are minimized. So at this perplexity
which is larger we can see that the
three small clusters are now unified
down here and they become far away from
the big cluster representing stem cells.
And this representation has better
agreement with what we see from the gene
expression data in the heat map. So I
think this is just one example to show
that the way visualization is plotted
matters right it will change our
perception of the relationship of cell
types if we look at the figure closely.
Another application I'll just show
result in our paper. There are many but
I'm just showing a very small set of
that is this consistency between TC and
um so since um was popular the belief is
that it better preserves the global
topology or relationship of cells
compared to tene and indeed as we found
in our result um has two hyperparameters
the minimum distance and the number of
neighbors. So with the two
hyperparameters together we can see that
the UMAP results are more stable than TS
results. So TS results can change more
dramatically as you change perplexity.
The UMAP turns to be more stable.
However, the the other thing we have to
note we note is that if we use our
approach to minimize number of dubious
embeddings by changing the
hyperparameters of either method then we
can see that with the optimizing um
visualization their consistency becomes
better better than if we go with the
original or default. So that's another
indirect evidence to show that the
optimization is meaningful. So with the
time constraint I would just say that
conclude this part for visualization and
for the meta cell part I'll just briefly
mention the problem and I'll give the
time to pan for her talk. So what is a
meta cell? It is a common practice used
in the single cell analysis field or
>> go on quick question about your previous
thing. So are are you actually making
the case to use PCA instead of PNE or
UMAP?
>> No not at all. So PSCA here is just
using as a pre-processing step for
reducing dimensions from say thousand to
20 to 50 but it's not used as a
visualization tool because it can if you
just look at PC1 or PC2 in most in most
cases you cannot see clusters.
>> Okay. So so you still recommend using TE
or UMass?
>> I I wouldn't make a point for that. I
would say is what we propose for SE the
method we call SED is only when you want
to use um or TS anyway and we think that
using that's better than not using it
that's our point but whether you should
completely remove TER um from single
cell papers I think that's a separate
point
>> okay
>> yeah thank you yeah
>> I thank you for the uh wonderful method
so I wonder uh in the case that if I
want to visualize
uh cell from different uh tissue for
example and different batch
>> would you suggest to do the permutation
within each cell or each uh batch or
would you consider doing them jointly as
a wholeation
>> that's a very good question but I think
also I I also I always want to ask your
goal what is your goal of doing this
visualization what do you want to see in
your data right
>> yes yes I honestly so yeah maybe I I I
just a data in a data driven approach.
So maybe yeah, I pre previously do not
have a very clear goal about what I
want.
>> You just learn to look at the data,
right? Yes. So in this case, I would say
if I were you, I would do both ways.
>> Yeah. Because I will say if you look at
all the batches together, then you can
see where they are right underne
the together plot or the joint plot was
distorted in some way. I think I'll just
try multiple ways to visualize the data
including PCA, right? So and and try to
do exploration. Yeah, that's what I
would suggest. But but on the other
hand, it's very important to know
whether you want to preserve the cell
types or you want to how do you
interpret the batch effects? Are they
technical effects you want to remove or
do they also contain possibly biological
effects you want to preserve? Right.
That's also a question. Yeah. Yeah.
Hi, this is really interesting. Um, I
wanted to clarify. It sounds like you're
trying to perceive if the visualization
preserves uklidian distances based on
gene expression. I wonder if you thought
about maybe considering manifold
distances or geodzic distances since a
lot of people in the community think
that that's what we're trying to
preserve in the visualization.
>> Yeah, thank you. So, actually this is
another thing. So, the ukidian distances
we are considering them in two spaces. I
want to clarify further. The first one
going back here is the ukidian distance
in the PC space. So that is not so
basically you are you're there's a
belief underlying that is once you
project your data from say log transform
or log normalized gene expression in the
original space gene expression space to
the PC space the PC space preserves the
biological signal removes the technical
noise that's your belief so in this case
ukidian distance in the PC space is
considered to be okay but when people
say manifold distance they are thinking
that there is an even lower dimension
than the PC dimension and they want to
use the manifold to describe that and
that is why when they use that idea or
assumption to get a visualization you
will get a different visualization from
T near map but since here we're just
looking at T near map and in that in
their 2D space people are still
interpreting or at least our eyes are
reading 2D ukidian distance because
we're thinking about clustering
structure right the round cluster ers
and that is a ukian distancebased idea.
So that's why in this case we're
considering ukitian distance in 2D
versus uklidian distance in the PC space
and manifold is not part of the
discussion. Yeah, that is the
clarification.
>> Yeah, just a follow-up question. So
>> I I just heard you mention like doing
PCH just for removing the noise
beforehand. But has your group just look
at the original data and kind of
>> either you clean the distance or coign
or like how does it compare with this
like?
>> So could you say your question again?
>> So has your group look into the just
distance between the I mean within the
original data before even PCA. Oh
actually that is another mathematical
fact is that if you have such a high
dimensional space like 1,00 dimensional
space ukense is no longer meaningful.
>> Yeah that's the reason why we didn't
look at uklidian this is within the
original space.
>> I see.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. Thanks.
>> Thank you. Yeah.
All right. Thank you so much. That's a
very good discussion. And then I'll just
be quick for the second part. I'll just
say because time will introduce that in
detail. I'll just say that meta cell is
a common practice in the field because
of sparity. So people say that okay
given if especially if you look at
single cell multiom data for example RNA
seek versus a taxi we it is known that
the data is very sparse right many of
the genes or enhancers were zero in the
in the data. So how do you make sure
that you can still do something
meaningful to find something your
analysis man is a heristic solution in
which people just try to group cells
into very small clusters right and
hopefully each cluster represents the
same biological entity as the original
cells. Then you look at those small
clusters you take the average of each
feature in the cluster and you call
those meta cell profiles and then you
analyze those data instead of the
original data. And here the goal is that
you can be faster because there are
fewer meta cells than original cells and
also meta cells are less sparse. But the
question we want to address here is what
is a reasonable definition for meta
cells because you can have them very
very small or you can have them bigger.
But of course there must be some
underlying how to say sweet spot or
tradeoff in the middle you want to find
because you can think about two extremes
aggregating all cells into one meta cell
and that is what people call pseudo
bulk. So you're not having single cell
resolution or the other extreme is that
you don't do meta cell at all you just
keep single cells. So where should we
stop? So I'll just say that the
motivation for we want to come up with
the statistical definition again. So our
definition actually is based on this two
layer model from the literature pan will
talk about in which we believe that the
biological variability can be described
by what we call an expression model and
given the biological expression there is
a measurement model that performs the
sampling which is usually captured by
passon sampling to give us the count. So
if we believe that the cells should be
merged into a meta cell then their
differences should be only due to the
measurement model and they should be
largely identical in terms of biolog
biological expression and because of
this two layer assumption we can define
a meta cell and giving it a statistical
concept and one notable thing about the
measurement model is because it's only a
sampling process and you already have
the biological counts of RNAs you're
just sampling using the during the
sequencing experiment then we can assume
that reasonable assume that gene gene
correlations are not induced by
measurement model but only comes from
expression model. So this can give us an
idea to construct a statistic in which
we can measure how dubious the meta cell
each meta cell is based on gene gene
correlation. So the idea is if the meta
cell only contains single cells that
differ based on the measurement model
then gene gene correlations within the
meta cell should be minimal. So that is
how we design a statistic and we call
that mcdivid. So pal will give more
specifics about this. I will just go
back to my thing to say how permutation
can be helpful for calibrating the
values of the statistics. So we can use
that node distribution to define a
threshold. So we can call a meta cell as
dubious or trustworthy. So coming back
to permutation in sad we did within gene
permutation and what we preserved our
marginal distributions of each gene but
we made genes uncorrelated and
furthermore if you look at the permuted
cells they do not correspond to the
original cells. The cell cell library
sizes in the original cells are gone.
But if we go back to the two layer model
which pan again she will detail here is
that the cell cell library sizes perform
is very important because depends on how
many counts you receive each cell and
that total count is divided into genes
and because the total is the same then
the gene genes will within the cell will
have some small correlations just due to
this multinnomial sampling right to have
some dependence among the genes but we
need to model that and we need to
capture that in the cell library size.
So how can we do that? So we know that
just doing the within gene permutation
yes we can make genes uncorrelated as we
believe that should happen within a
trustworthy meta cell but removing cell
library sizes will make this not a valid
no for our statistic. So to account for
that pan came up with this smart idea of
permuting within each cell. So in this
case we can actually preserve the cell
every row sum or the total of the cell
library size for each cell. So you can
see that here we preserve the cell
library sizes but we change the genes
since you're randomly permuting the
genes within the cell. We call those
permuted genes and they do not
correspond to the original genes. So
even though this can give us a no case
in which the cell library sizes are
preserved but because the genes are
different we still miss something. So
then we did a normalization. So the
normalization is by removing the
differences of genes. So we would have a
normalization factor for the original
data by doing within gene permutation.
So this creates a uncorrelated case in
which the genes are the same original
genes and we do the same thing for the
permuted matrix. So here we after we do
the permutation within a cell we further
do the permutation within each permuted
gene and we call this double
permutation. So this can give us a
normalization factor to account for the
fact that here the permuted genes are
not the original genes. So each set of
genes have their corresponding
normalization factor and together we get
a test statistic no case. So this some
this is an idea which we think is very
interesting and it turns out to work
pretty well. So without specifying the
detail of the statistic definition, I'll
just say that what we did procedure-
wise is to perform double permutations
for each meta cell. So we just need to
do this double permutation again for
once. We get a no value for each meta
cell. So you can see that as a result we
will have a statistic for each meta cell
and the corresponding no statistic value
for each meta cell. and pulling
together. We want to use the null values
to calibrate a threshold for our actual
statistical values. And what we are
doing here is that we observe the null
values have some relationship with the
meta cell size. And here the size means
the number of single cells contained in
each meta cell. And this can give us a
size specific threshold based on the
null values. And given the null values,
we can consider each original meta cells
statistic. Whether it's too high above
the threshold, we call that dudas or if
they're too low or they're low enough
below the threshold, we call them
trustworthy. So again, we try to use
permutation to derive a threshold. Well,
and again like did we only did
permutation once. So I will just say
that for the permutation part I will
talk about here. So basically bulk de as
a teaser right here it's a simple thing
you just permute the condition labels
and for single cell we consider within
gym permutation or double permutation
because for the former we just want to
make sure that the permedia cells are
like exchangeable a random sample
without any biological relationships
among the cells and for the double
permutation we did it because we want to
preserve the cell library sizes first.
So for this part I want to acknowledge
my collaborators both from the
computational biology side and from
statistics side. Lucy she's a
statistician and also of course pan for
MC rigger. But before I end my talk I
just want to briefly say that this idea
of generating some null data is beyond
permutation. Permutation can be
considered as a special case for this
concept we hope to promote. We call that
synthetic null data. It means that we
generate data from the null hypothesis
and we can use that as a calibration
device for our original data. So one
example I want to point to is that we
propose this method called cluster DE
which is still a preprint but we are
making it more and more comprehensive as
time goes is a postclustering
differential expression method. we
showed this it's working for both single
cell and spatial transcripttoics data
and furthermore we're are planning to
add more to it to other omics to show
it's more general. So the idea briefly
is that we propose to generate synthetic
node data that represents a homogeneous
cluster but in other aspects it we try
to mimic the real data the original
data. So the hope is that if you perform
clustering, you identify clusters as
potential subopuls and then you compare
the two clusters to find DE genes as
markers, we help to avoid this
overclustering bias. In other words,
even though your original data is just
one homogeneous cluster, you may still
divide it and then even to have two
clusters and your DE results can still
show many many marker genes. This is
something we observe in Surat applied to
single cell line data. You can see that.
So we try to remove those biases and
also to prioritize the true markers. If
the two cell clusters are indeed
distinct, we use this negative control.
And I'll just be brief by showing that
it's working by prioritizing like true
marker genes in like the CD16 in a
comparison of two monocy subtypes CD16
versus CD4 and pushing down housekeeping
genes down the rank list in DE because
housekeeping genes are typically highly
variable with large variances and they
can actually drive the clustering or be
involved in the clustering and as a
result be identified by the D step
between two clusters.
But by setting up a negative control as
in our synthetic no data concept, we can
push down the ranking of the
housekeeping genes but preserving the
high ranking top ranking of the true
marker genes. And this gene set
enrichment analysis showing that yes the
non markers are ranked highly in our D
list but housekeeping genes are ranked
much lowly compared to what Surak give
us. And the result the reason for that
is because we have this contrast. So we
can have a target D set of D scores and
a no set of D scores. We do the
comparison and only the things the genes
with a large contrast will be high in
contrast score and we show that the
marker genes are higher than the
housekeeping genes and also applied to
the clustering result. This approach can
help us merge sperious clusters that are
not so well separated. we can decide to
merge them. And this can also show us
that if we use the idea then if you run
stack clustering with different
resolutions like the high resolution
will give you smaller more clusters
while lower resolution give you fewer
coarser clusters. We can apply this idea
to each branch to decide whether they
should be merged before we call the
genes. And we can see that we can make
the two sets of clustering results more
consistent by finding the same cell
types from the PBMC data where people
know the best and applied to spatial
data. I'll be quick by saying it's the
similar postclustering D issue. You use
spatial cluster to find regions and you
want to find markers. So our idea is
that if you really believe a spatial
cluster is something meaningful or
distinct, you should have a very clear
boundary between the the adjacent
cluster. But we can design negative
control or synthetic null data by making
the boundary smoothened. Then you don't
have the sharp changes in G expression.
But otherwise you have the same overall
trend from high to low or low to high
but just no sharp boundary. And with
this negative control then you can see
that
this is what we can find. So for your
spatial clusters the marker genes we
find we we nominate will be much sharper
markers compared to what you find from
because we set up negative control. So
in short I'll just say that this is a
general approach to set up synthetic
control for removing cluster induced
bias and beyond these two single cell
spatial omics we actually showed that it
works for other things right for other
types of omics like including population
based bulk RNA seek and also microbomb
data. So these new results will be added
and finally I'll say that cluster D can
further be generalized into this
approach called nostrap. It's led by my
postto choo who actually generalized
this to the variable selection problem
in a highdimensional prediction model.
So this is a very very general question
which okay if you have many many
predictors or features which are the
ones that are most predictable of your
response. So and our hope is to also
achieve the fast discovery control. So
not just variable selection but some
guarantee. Before our work in the
statistical literature there are methods
called model X knockoff or multiple data
splitting for FDR control and there was
a nature B tech paper if you are
interested it's called stable it was
published actually last year and it uses
the model X knockoff with multiple runs
and aggregation so it's like a stable
version of knockoff and we can see that
the issue with existing approaches is
that they often have low power. So both
of all these approaches depend on random
seeds and we can see that across many
random seeds you will have zero
discoveries no features found and that
could be an issue but using nodes we can
have a much higher power because we
preserve the original data we didn't
change the data we just have a parallel
synthetic negative control and we can
have feature selected with good
prediction power and to our surprise and
pleasure there was an independent
benchmark
uh just posted a few weeks ago which
compared our notrap which is still
unpublished to this published stable
method. And in this independent
benchmark we can see that they found in
terms of performance like AUPRC
precision recall curve and the
classification F1 score for true
features versus no features we are the
best even compared with the common
approaches like neutral information and
random forests for variable selection we
are better and notably we are very fast.
So we are even faster than the neutral
information in terms of computational
time. So which give us a lot of
confidence. So I'll stop here by saying
that my overall goal the overall goal in
my goal in my research group is toward
principled inference and in particular I
think this is very very challenging for
unsupervised learning because you don't
have a very clear prediction goal and
there are many many issues I can touch
about including what is considered
reasonable inference conditional or
unconditional but this synthetic control
setup from the beginning is for
unconditional so we want to consider
what is the bias introduced by the whole
procedure including clustering and also
D test and nstrap is something we really
draw the inspiration from bootstrap. So
we're thinking about using reampled or
synthetic data but we are sampling from
a no hypothesis or no model instead of
just the original data. So our outlook
is that we think there could be more
potential applications. So that's why I
squeeze some time at the end of my talk
to to introduce it. So and this is the
slide for the second part. Yeah, thank
you very much for the primer
for listening to my prime I should say.
Yeah, but I understand for the second
part was very fast. So I didn't I didn't
have time to go go into details but but
the permutation is the primary part.
Yeah,
>> I think that there were a lot of
questions during but if anyone has any
questions after talk.
All right,
>> I think let's break for like five
minutes or so and then we'll be back for
the
>> Thank you. Yeah talk. Thanks.
>> Thank you.
>> Great. Okay. So, thanks everyone for
sticking around. So, now we're going to
have uh an give her talk on uh MC
Rigger, which I mistakenly read as MC
Rigger the first time I was reading
this. So, statistical method to enhance
the rigor of metaell partitioning and
single cell data analysis. So, thanks
everyone.
Um, so thank you for the introduction.
Um, so my name is Pan and I'm now a
post-docctoral researcher working with
professor Jessica Lee at the Fred
Hudinson Cancer Center. Um, but
previously I work at UCLA and this work
was mostly performed when I was at UCLA.
Um so uh in today's talk I want to
further elaborate on this work um called
MC rigger which is exactly an example of
how to use um how to use permutation to
serve as a negative control to make the
our analysis more rigorous and as
introduced by Jessica previously and
this work aims at enhancing the rigor of
meta cell partitioning um in single cell
data analysis and here we do call this
method MC rigger instead of macar rigger
here MC stands for meta cell
and um let's just start with a quick
recap of what is uh what is a meta cell
in case that some people still don't
don't get it. So um here this figure is
from a very nicely written review paper
published in molecular system biology
last year right. So um so this figure is
from a very nicely written review paper
about the meta cell method and um so on
this top left panel here um this is a t
typical for format of the single cell
RNA sequencing data um where we which is
normally just a matrix with um cells for
columns and genes for rows and we know
that in this kind of data matrix there
could be many zeros maybe like as high
as 90% and many of them are due to the
imperfection of single cell sequencing
technology because this kind of
technology is very high throughput and
we can have very low per per single per
single cell sensitivity which means that
for many genes these genes may be
expressed in the cell but their
expression can be just not captured. So
intuitively we do not want like all
these zeros in our downstream analysis
that would cause a huge problem or to
say we want to solve this this kind of
sparcity issue and the meta cell method
is is exactly a pre-processing step in
single cell data analysis developed
mainly to solve this kind of sparity
issue.
So um what a ma what matterell method
does is that um you first try to
identify similar single cells shown as
the colored dots here within one black
circle um and then we just aggregate all
these similar single cells um like by
averaging. So here each black circle or
you can also think of it as a small
cluster represent one meta cell. Then we
just need to define like an average
profile for each circle. Um and then we
can end up with this um team by meta
cell matrix and we will proceed um we'll
proceed from from from here with all
other downstream analysis tasks. And by
doing so um by doing so we can reduce
the sparity level to approximately like
50%.
But at the same time we are also paying
some prices. Um the uh the main price is
that now we have a much smaller number
of analysis units or observations. Um we
have meta cells instead of single cells.
So that means we have lower resolution.
Um but there were also some cases where
people think that having a smaller
number of analysis units is not always
the bad thing because that also means we
have like better scalability right. So
um so due to all these reasons
um this meta idea has been pretty
popular in single cell data analysis and
it have been it has been adopted in many
high impact studies as I will show in
short. Um but the question that
motivated our research is what is a
reasonable definition for a meta cell
like um because if you think of two
extremes like mentioned by Jessica um
the two extreme is like um for one
extreme we can just aggregate all the
single cells into one meta cell then you
we just totally lose the information and
or on the other extreme if we just leave
the single cells as they are then we are
not doing any aggregations. So we think
there must be some sweet spot in the
middle um that could balance these two
extremes and we cannot just do it arbit
arbitrarily. So we wish to answer this
question like how can we find this this
sweet spot
and then this slide lists the existing
use of metael idea. There are five
general methods um starting from and
these general method by general method I
mean that these methods have been
developed into software packages where
people can just directly use them. So
start uh so start from the very first
version the meta cell method which
proposed the meta idea and um the the
second version metael 2 by the same
research group group and we also have
supercell seells and also the most
recent metaq which was published uh just
this year
and besides these five general methods
we also have and we also found that this
meta cell idea has been used by many
in-house data analysis published in very
high impact journals like nature, they
have either come up with a more
straightforward way like just um maybe
10 years neighbors um to define meta
cells or they just use one of the five
general methods.
But looking at all these papers, we do
not really see a consensus on metael
definition. People can just do it in
their own way. So um so motivated by
this by this problem we um we present we
develop our own method MC rigger because
we wish to improve the rigor of meta
definition and generally we wish to
answer answer three questions. The first
question is how to define a meta cell
and uh the second is how to find the
dubious meta cells generated by existing
metael methods that do not follow the
appropriate definition and the third
question is how do we optimize metael
partitioning for a given data set. Um
and just in short, our method is
designed as um as a way to help with
existing method to make them more
rigorous and obtain better meta cell
partitional result but it is not like a
completely new method to build meta
cells from scratch. So it is like it is
more like an add-on concept to make
existing methods more rigorous.
Okay. So the first question like how to
define a meta cell. So um to answer this
question we go back to the very first
publication the meta the one for metael
method that proposed this meta concept.
Um so in that paper a meta cell was
defined as a homogeneous collection of
single cell profiles that could have
been resampled from the same original
cell. Well this is a biological uh
interpretation or definition and we want
to translate it into something
statistical to work to work with it. So
our translation is that um within is is
like is that given this concept if we
find if we see obser variations within a
meta cell then we believe these
variations within a meta cell should be
attributed exclusively to measurements
or technical error instead of true
biological differences. So given this
translation how like how do we actually
address the problem?
Well, I think now the question becomes
how do we define this measurement error
in single cell sequencing data because
we believe a meta cell should um single
cells within meta cells should be varied
only by these um measurement errors.
Well, we actually used this paper's
formulation to answer this question. Um
this paper is a very nicely written um
paper about single cell um statistical
modeling. Um the p the authors of this
paper separated the single cell model
into two layers an expression model
layer and a measurement model layer. And
these two layers stay together give us
the model that we can obtain our
observed count eventually. So more
specifically, an expression model
describes the features true gene
expression in the cell. Um and the
measurement model is literally like a
conditional distribution. That is like
given the genes um true expression, what
are the observed count we can get in our
data?
And we formulate this two-layer model
into statistical language. Here we
consider the N cells as an observations
and the P genes as P features. Um and
just to briefly mention that our method
can only can also deal with other other
data type like SD attack data. So in
that kind of data the features are the
other peaks or the chromatin
accessibility. So that is why we call we
call we generally call it features
instead of just genes.
Okay. So um the first layer is the
expression model. The expression model
is about the true gene expression in
cell I represented by lambda i here. And
this lambda i is a pdimensional
statistics. is a p-dimensional vector
where each dimension represents one
feature or one gene because we usually
look at these features these p features
jointly and um the expression of these
pe these p features are assumed to
follow this f distribution about the
biological state of the cell I which is
represented by x i. So um examples of
this biological state information could
come from things like cell types or
pseudo times in a lineage trajectory.
And I also want to point out that this
lambda here um it represent the relative
expression level um with its components
summing up to one. The um the reason why
we focus on this relative expression
instead of um the the absolute
expression is because we believe the
single cell sequencing technology can
only provide or like reliable relative
expression information but not the
absolute abundance. We believe we
believe those absolute abundance
information are kind of lost in the
sequencing procedure.
And then for the second layer is that
given this lambda I the measurement
model depicts um the variations or the
errors introduced in the sequencing
procedure. Like um given the true
expression lambda, how do we end up
getting the observed count y and um this
kind of procedure is usually assumed to
be somehow similar to the sampling pro
procedure. So that is why we usually
just use the person distribution. um to
uh to model this layer and on this right
hand side the CI is the expectation of
um of the cell library size which is Yi
plus um and it is also called the cell
the pre-ell sequencing depth some
sometimes
so based on this two-layer model our
statistical definition of the meta cell
is a group of single cells that share
the same lambda so the cells in the same
meta out must have the same lambda, but
they can have like different different
ys.
And then we can formulate this into a
statistical question. Um like can we
check if an existing meta cell satisfy
this definition? If yes, we can just
call this meta cell a trustworthy meta
cell and otherwise we call it a dubious
meta cell.
So before we dive into our own method uh
just some more motivation of why we want
to identify dubious meta cells and why
is it so important. So this is again a
figure from the meta cell method review
paper. Here these single cells are
colored by their cell state. So each and
uh in this bottom left panel each black
circle represent a meta cell. And uh so
pretty so pretty obvious is that this
middle meta cell is dubious because it
is a mixture of cells from two different
cell states.
And if we are interested in um in
studying the association between two
genes like gene A and gene B here for
example which is a very common and
important analysis task for single cell
data analysis. If we if we want to study
this kind of association, we can first
um look at their association at the
single cell level. And at the single
cell level, you can see that actually
these two genes, they do not have much
association at least like no positive
association for sure. But if we compute
their association or correlation at a
meta cell level with one dubious meta
cell then this dubious one will lie here
in the middle and we will u and we may
get a false positive association because
of this um this single dubious meta
cell. So this is an example of um how
bias can be introduced by the dubious
meta cell and that is exactly why we are
we care about those so much and we want
to um we want to avoid that. So to avoid
these biases being carried down to
downstream analysis, we propose our
method MC rigger
which generally gives a statistical
criterion to first identify the dubious
meta cells consisting of cells from
different cell states and also after
identifying the dubious meta cells, the
next step could be to nominate the top
performing um metael methods and also
optimize it hyperparameter. Um and here
we mainly focus on the granularity level
hypoparameter gamma which is uh which is
essentially like the average number of
single cells within one meta cell or you
can think of it as the a as the meta
cell sizes on average.
And we hope to choose this gamma in a
data specific way.
And uh so at the most basic level we use
a feature feature correlation metric as
a way to help us build this criterion.
And in the intu and intuition has
already been mentioned by Jessica I
think which is that since we can
consider the the measurement process as
somehow similar to the sampling process
we can think that um we can think of it
as like the sampling for each genes are
somehow independent. So for a
trustworthy meta cell
um it's correlation it feature feature
correlation matrix should be something
similar to the bottom left matrix
something similar to an identity matrix
and um on contrast for a dubious manel
its feature feature correlation matrix
can usually um demonstrate this kind of
clear block structure.
So um so in order to make use of this uh
intuition what we do specifically is
that first we need to build a per meta
cell statistics that can that can
describe how much likely is this metael
dubious um and and well this uh preetell
statistics is called metael divergence
or mcdiv. It is built based on the
future feature correlation as I just
mentioned and and also we will need to
build a null construct a null for this
statistics because we will we will need
this null um to evaluate the
significance of the statistics
and uh as Jessica previously mentioned
we use a permutationbased strategy to
construct the null um and an important
fact an important point that we need to
consider is that In this null
construction, we want to preserve the
cell library sizes. Um, and the reason
for this is that um this pone
distribution
or this measurement model is equivalent
to the joint multinnomial distribution
and um and this cell library sizes CI
uh and and Yi plus is involved in in
this multinnormal distribution. And we
know that this uh this sum total this
salary sizes can introduce a small
amount of future feature correlation
into into this data and we need to
account for that.
So that is why we um we need to design
this uh very unique double permutation
strategy to make sure that we
>> can I ask a question can I ask a
question?
>> Yeah. um on the previous slide. So like
how do you calculate the correlations
first of all because there's like mostly
zeros and then
>> yes
>> like which type of correlation metric do
you use and then um
>> I think can you just go to the previous
slide sorry and then what what prevents
like this sort of
>> um I guess criteria about the
correlation like seems like the simplest
way then to solve like to get you know
not these sort of off diagonal things
would just to be would be to have like
very small meta cells like two or three
because then you don't have these off
diagonal sort of double meta cells
showing up like what what what is the
counterbalance to like actually make
meta cells that have lots of cells in
them because it feels like just the
simplest way to get a trustworthy one
would be to have like very few cells in
the meta cell because then you're not
going to have these correlations between
cells that don't belong together. Uh yes
exactly that is a very good question and
uh to answer your first part of the
question we actually simply use the um
Pearson correlation to calculate this
future feature correlation and the
reason for that is because we have this
null construction and in the null we
also use this P pearson correlation. So
although there are many zeros there in
the null since we use the same kind of
correlation you can still control for
that and actually uh I have also tried
the the spearmman correlation which may
um handle the ties better and it turns
out that that correlation gives similar
results. So we eventually still use this
those this pearson correlation and um it
is a very good point that you mentioned
for those meta cells with very few
single cells like two to three for those
um uh I mean like for if the meta cell
is that small then we then they are
usually trustworthy. So that is why um I
think in our correlation it doesn't
really matter if that two that meta cell
with two or three cells can re you can
get a very uh can get a very reliable
correlation estimates because those mana
cells are already small and we believe
they are very trustworthy and usually I
think usually for a dubious manel they
usually the size of them usually starts
from at least like seven eight or 10
something like this and for those we can
get a pretty um good correlation
estimate.
>> The meta cells are all the same size or
is it like kind of somewhat cluster
specific? It's not um tuned for the
cluster that they end up falling in.
They're all the same size.
>> Uh right. So this granularity level
parameter is actually like the average
size of all the meta cells. And uh this
is only the average size. And actually
those meta the size of those meta cells
could vary. they can vary like maybe
from two to three to even 50 or 100 and
um and how the size distributes across
all the meta cells they kind that that
thing kind of depends on the meta method
the the general meta method that has
been previously designed.
So, and we are actually also working on
um like developing a new medicine method
that could incorporate our
considerations but that that work is
still ongoing.
>> Hello. Uh I have a question. Why do you
think a good meta cell should have like
non-correlated features with within this
mentor cell? I don't quite understand
this uh conclusion.
>> Um okay. So right that that is like the
key um the key claim in our in our paper
and uh the reason for that is because we
believe the single cells within a
trustworthy meta cell or with a within a
good meta cell should be at the same
biological state. So there the
variations in um in those in the
expression of those genes should be
exclusively due to the measurement
error. And by measurement error we
usually mean the sampling error. And uh
in the sequencing procedure we usually
just sample those transcripts from um
from the the like the whole library pool
of the transcripts and we think that
procedure happens independently for each
gene assembling procedure. So within for
measurement error the gene gene
correlation um should generation should
not exist.
>> Okay. The second the second question is
about single cell attackic
as we know the single cell attackic is
even sparer than the iron sake and many
um elements are even zero or one. In
this cases, how do you um are you still
using on the p the pearson correlation?
>> Uh yes, we still use the cure pearson
correlation.
>> Um okay.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Um
I have two questions. uh one is what is
the optimal size of the DR uh like this
gamma what do you think is optimal
because if you think it's somewhere
between three to five cells in one meta
cell then we would have a lot of these
meta cells because we generally have
data sets that are around that are in
around 100k cells. So do we deal with
like 20k
groups of meta cells? That's first
question. And second question is
uh second question is
um second question is similar to what he
has. How do you claim that genes need to
be non-correlated? Because we have a lot
of GRNs and we do know that some genes
do control some other genes. So how will
you account for those cases wherein the
genes are actually being controlled by
some other genes
if you think that the genes are
completely non-correlated in nature
>> right uh so for your second question I
think um the the thing you're talking
about in uh the genes regulation
relationship where one gene regulate
another gene so those correlations are
are they those are all I I think those
things are already measured in our first
layer of the model which is the which is
this expression model. So we believe all
those biologically meaningful
correlations or variations are are
already measured are already described
in this first layer of model. You see
here we um here lambda is a p-
dimensional vector. We um we model these
p features jointly. So we already
incorporated those correlations there.
Um and could you repeat your first
question? I'm sorry.
>> We have a lot of cells generally like
around 100k cells. So if the meta cell
size is around five then we would have a
lot of groups right. So do we deal with
like 20k groups or something like that
or what would be a general size estimate
that you would say for large scale
data sets having having say 100k cells
200k cells like how would you
say the size of the group should be
>> I see so I think for that question that
would um the answer would depends on
what's what what is the aim for you
using this meta cell idea. Um if your
data set is very large and your aim of
using metael is to increase the
scalability then I believe you can just
choose a a higher granularity level. But
if your um if your goal is mainly to
solve the sparity issue like to find a
balance between sparity or trade-off
between sparity and and the like the
signal distortion then I think you can
still use our method to choose the
optimal one
>> to ensure that we solve sparity and at
the same time we ensure there's not too
much signal distortion.
>> Okay. Thanks.
So the primary reason of not primary but
like one of the reason of sparity is
also the the the nature of gene
expression in single cell right. Uh
there is like lot of genes which are
like have zero and some of them have
some gene expression binomial. So like
zim zen type of uh distribution. So this
only take cares of the sparity in the
cellular uh region right in this in the
cell cell column. But what about the
gene column right?
>> The gene columns
>> like
>> uh
>> yeah here
so we still have the same number of
genes. So is it possible that uh is
possible to sort of reduce the dimension
in the the gene column because you are
sort of taking care of that experimental
uh effects of correlation between the
genes right or is it just a cell like
you just club the cells together.
>> Um yes we just do aggregation on the
cells dimension because here we we treat
cells as observations. So we believe
there are only IDs um in AC uh over the
cells dimension. So we can only do
averaging along this dimension. But I I
think um the concept you're mentioning
is something similar to the meta gene
definition maybe. So there are also
people who try to find like a gene
program or um for to like to reduce the
dimensionality of this genes so that
they can aggregate multiple genes into
one man. I think that's similar to that
concept, right?
>> I see. Okay. Thanks.
>> Um hi, thank you. Uh and uh I'm
wondering like have you test maybe your
method on like the clonal for example so
you know the ground truth that like a
couple of cells they're actually have
like the similar uh single cell
expression. So for example like within a
cell line or like a conal of the cells
then like and that your method can also
like um like well capture the matter
cell and like not maybe clustering them
into like dubious like subcluster things
like that. Yes, actually in our paper we
have an an anal an case which we analyze
the cell line data set and we prove that
um we were able to um better we were
able to identify trustworthy meta cells
that which cons which is made up of
single cells mostly from one cell
cycles. So we can um I'm trying to say
we we we are able to handle multiple
layers of heterogeneity. So in the cell
we have also tried to sell.
>> Thank you.
Um okay so I believe I stopped here. So
um so this double permutation strategy
is mainly designed for null construction
and our goal is to disturb the those
changing correlation or feature feature
correlation and at the same time
preserve this uh the cell library sizes.
So as Jessica has have uh discussed um
what we did is we first permute these
genes um independently within each cell
and but that would turn each columns to
be one perturbed permuted genes which
means that these two um these two matrix
they're not uh they're not so comparable
because they have different features. So
that is why we need to do another layer
of permutation which is this within gene
permutation on the right to serve as a
normalization factor or for for the left
ones and this top row will form a pair
and this bottom row would form a pair
from the top row we will get our
statistics MCDIV and from the bottom row
we will get our null statistics MCDIV
null.
So uh this figure is um is uh is about
uh more details of how we compute our
MCDIV and MCDIV null. So um we so we com
we actually compute a pair of MCDIV
MCDIV null for each manel and uh here we
just use two meta cells for
illustration. one uh trustworthy meta
cell and one dubious meta cell and this
rectangle
matrix represent the original data
matrix with um cells for rows and genes
for columns and this square matrix is
the gene correlation matrix from uh
calculated from this data matrix. So to
calculate MCDIVV we use this uh we
calculate the forbinius norm of the
differences between this uh correlation
matrix and the identity matrix and we
divide it by the forbinous norm obtained
um obtained from um from a data matrix
after within gene permutation to serve
as a normalization factor. And for this
MCDIV null, we do the same thing but
this time just at this time we do it on
the within cell permuted data matrix.
And after we compute these um MCDIV and
MCDIV null for each of these meta cells
from meta cell one to meta cell M um we
just pull all these MCDIV null values
together to obtain a distri a null
distribution and we will be able to
derive a threshold from this null
distribution so that we can say if um if
if a meta cell's MCDIV value goes above
this threshold then it is considered as
dubious.
But we also notice that this uh MCDIVV
nulls distribution is kind of dependent
on the meta cell size. That is why um
the threshold is determined as the um
95th
uh fontile depend conditioning on the
mass cell size and by overlaying this
threshold on this original uh statistics
MCDF values we can um we can identify
whether each meta cell is dubious or
trust.
So this is our method for the first go
or say the first functionality of MC
rigger to identify those dubious amount
of cells and we first did a simulation
using a modified version of a simulator
called SC design 3. This IC design 3 was
uh was also developed by our group
Ashley which was published on nature
biotechnology last year and we modify
this uh this simulator a bit based on
our two-layer model um to in order to
generate a synthetic data set uh where
each single cell had has a ground truth
meta cell label
and we first noticed that um our
synthetic data set actually mimic this
reference data set pretty well and this
somehow already shows that um our
two-layer model and meta cell definition
is somehow reasonable because um they
align well with the real data and then
on this synthetic data set we first
apply the generate the general metael
methods um to partition the cells into
meta cells and then we apply our MC
rigger to check whether each generated
meta cell is dubious or trustworthy.
So here we first um compare our MCDIV
value statistics values with this meta
cell purity which is the highest fra
fraction of cells in a meta cell that
originate from the same original of
originate from the same ground truth
meta cell. Um or to say this purity is
like um this purity kind of like
represents the trustworthy the ground
truth trustworthiness of a mana cell.
And we can see that the these two values
share pretty similar patterns and they
have a very high correlation of 0.948.
So this means our MCDIV is a very good
indicator for the trustworthiness of a
manel. And then using our MC rigger we
were able to classify the meta cells
into dubious and trustworthy with a very
high F score like 0.921.
And these gave us confidence that our
method can work pretty well.
And uh and that is the simulation. We
have also performed some real data
validation. Thank well this one is uh is
thanks to uh thanks to one of our group
our lab member Manx who is from a bi
biology background. He pointed us to
this data set with barcode multiplat.
Well, um what barcode multiply means is
that um in a single cell in a single
cell sequencing procedure, it is
possible that multiple barcodes like um
for example three barcodes here could be
encapsulated into the same droplet with
um with just one cell.
So um and we know that in the sequencing
procedure um when we later try when we
later want to obtain the data matrix we
actually consider one uh one barcode as
one observation. So if this kind of
technical issues happens then we may
consider these three barcodes
as representing three different cells
but uh in fact they just all originate
from the same same cell. So uh so this
is an issue but this is good for us in
the in the sense that um since these
three barcodes they carry the gene
expression profile from the same cell
they have the same true expression
level. So these three barcodes could
naturally be considered as be able to
form like a trustworthy manel. And this
gave us a natural chance for validating
our methods
and
and uh and it turns out that when we
apply our MC rigger um it was able to
flag all these nine uh nine meta cells
that formed that was formed by barco
multipl as trustworthy mana cells. So
this somehow justifies that our MC
rigger can reliably identify the
trustworthy man cells.
Uh and another interesting application
of our MC rigger is on this data set of
blood cell gene expression. Um
and these data are from both healthy and
co 19 patients. This data was originally
used to study the gene gene
co-expression differences between the
two co cohorts. Since the meta cell was
um was believed to be able to somehow
strengthen the co-expression signal here
we apply the supercell method one of the
general meta cell method to this data
and we compute the gene expression over
those meta cells. And something in this
analysis that we need to pay attention
to is uh this gene module marked by this
yellow box.
So uh this is defined as the adaptive
immune response module. Uh so we first
compare the gene expression um on
calculated on the single cell level on
the left to the gen to the gene coexp
expression computed at the meta cell
level on the right. By doing this
comparison we can see that this meta
cell indeed was able to strengthen the
signal in both the healthy and covid-19
groups. Um but the problem is that we do
not really see a difference between
these two groups in this module. So this
so we say not enriched here.
But if we apply our MC rigger method to
remove those dubious M cells we can
observe like uh then we obtain this
changing cor coexp expression in the
middle. Here we can see a clear
enrichment um in the co 19 group
compared to the healthy group which
implies that the genes tend to coexpress
more strongly in this module and this is
consistent with the fact that these
genes are adaptive immune response
genes. So we went back to our data to
see why this is the case and we found
that the reason was that um these
dubious meta cells in um in uh within
all the meta cells like these these pink
one represent the dubious meta cells
they falsely drove the correlations uh
or the coexpression of genes within this
healthy cohort to be very high. So these
are just fake signals and uh or we say
there are bias in the data and our MC
rigger was able to re to remove them and
eventually being able to identify this
enrichment in the stream module.
Uh so this is like another example but
due to the time limit I would just uh
jump to the second functionality of our
MC rigger. So far I've been talking
about the first functionality of MC
rigger which is to identify dubious mana
cells and we also mentioned that our MC
rigger's second goal is to
optimize is to first nominate the best
the top performing meta method and also
at the same time we want to optimize the
hyperparameter um the granularity level
for uh for each um medicine method.
So uh the main idea here is that um we
will calculate an evaluation score for
each meta cell partition that results
from a specific meta cell method under a
specific granularity level.
And then um the method and
hyperparameter setting that receives the
highest score we would be considered the
optimal setting. And now so now the
problem becomes how do we define this
evaluation score?
Um well um if you remember we uh when we
mentioned granularity level we said that
we mentioned that a a higher granularity
level would result in a bigger mana
cells. Um so which means we can better
resolve the sparsity issue but at the
same time the bigger manels usually
comes with more dubious mana cells. So
that is like more signal distortion and
on the opposite side um this the small
granularity level usually gives um still
gives more zeros. So it may leave the um
sparity issue unsolved but at the same
time small meta cells may come with less
dubious meta cells. So less signal
distortion. So, so that is saying like
choosing an optimal hyperparameter or
choosing an optimal meta partition is
more like considering a trade-off
between the s sparity issue and the
signal distortion.
So that is why we um proposed two
metrics one to assess the sparity issue
when to assess the sparity level which
is this zero rate um that is defined as
the proportion of zeros left in this
meta cell profile. And then we also
define another metric this dup rate
metric
which is um essentially the proportion
of single cells that constitute a
dubious that constitute dubious mana
cells. So we our eventual evaluation
score is uh is one minus the sum of
these two uh of these two matrix to
consider a trade-off between these two
matrix
and uh the medicine partition that
receives the highest score would be
considered the optimal one. And we have
um we have proved through simulation
that um our method is able to nominate
the best meta cell partition that aligns
the best with the ground truth. For
example, here this ground truth gamma um
50 was exactly selected as the optimal
gamma by our method.
Right? So and to show our MC rigorous
ability in optimizing the
hyperparameter, let us look at an
example of um of an of an important use
of of MC rigger, which is that we hope
MC rigger could help us distinguish
biological zeros from technical zeros.
Here biological zeros means that those
genes are indeed not expressed at all in
in the cells. So that these are true
zeros. And for technical zeros we mean
that these genes they are actually
expressed but just that due to the
technical imperfection th those
expressions are not captured and
eventually shown as zeros in the
observed data.
So, so the reason why we expect MC river
to distinguish them is that um uh if we
have like a good meta cell partition
where um where only cells of the same
biological states um are aggregated into
one meta cell then the technical zeros
will naturally go away because if you um
like if a gene is expressed in the cells
in the physical cells then just by
chance some of the cells of this state
would have nonzero observed count then
by averaging them these zero just
naturally go away.
But if it's like a biological zero then
uh then for sure no cells of this state
would have a nonzero would have a
non-zero count. So all of them should be
zero and averaging them would still give
you a zero. So that is why we believe a
ma a good meta cell partition should be
able to preserve the biological zeros
while u eliminating the technological
zeros and we hope the meta cells
optimized by our MC rigger would be able
to achieve this. So we applied our MC
rigger to this data set where the SCA
where the single cell RNA sequencing
data was paired with the single cell
molecule fish data. The SM fish data use
fluoresence hybridization to measure the
gene expression. So we usually believe
that these are more accurate.
Usually we believe they have less uh
have not so many technical zeros. So
here so here we use as the SM fish data
as a go standards quantify those zeros
whether they are biological or
technical. So in our line plots here,
this uh this red horizontal line
represent the proportion of zeros in
this sm fish data which is around around
20%.
So that means we believe the true
proportion of biological zeros um in
this data should be around 20%.
And then we just apply our um uh the
general medicine methods along with MC
radar. We tried these three methods meta
cell cells and supercell
and you can see that for each method as
the uh gamma value increases the zero
proportion decreases as expected.
So since we mentioned that a good metal
partition should be able to preserve
biological zeros while removing the
technical zeros. We believe that the the
optimal metazal partition should be able
to give a zero proportion quite similar
to this um to this go standard from the
SM fish data and that is exactly what MC
rigger told us here. This u triangle for
example this blue triangle represent the
optimal uh granularity level selected
for meta cell and this uh this uh purple
one is the optimal gamma selected for
super C cells and this is the one
selected for supercell. You can see that
the zero proportion corresponding to
these gamma values align pretty well
with the uh with our gold standard this
horizontal red line.
So so this uh kind of help us justify
that our chosen gamma is indeed the
optimal one.
Well, I will I will also skip this
example because of time limit.
And uh so so far we have been talking
about the two main functionalities of
single uh of our MC rigger to detect the
dubious meta cells and also to to
nominate the top performing methods and
hyperparameter.
And a and beyond these two
functionalities, a frequently asked
question for our MC rigger is that how
shall we deal with these dubious dubious
amount of cells because if we just
naively throw them all away, then there
is a big chance that we may lose some
important information. Especially when
we have some cells of the rare cell
type, there's a high pro possibility
that the the cells of these rare cell
types could be aggregated with cells of
other types to form a dubious manel.
Then if we just throw it away then there
will be no information about this varile
type left in the data at all.
So, so that is why we propose also an
extension of the MC rigger um to handle
these dubious meta cells. And the main
idea is that we try to dist we try to
like decompose the single the uh the
dubious meta cells again into into
single cells and then uh and then for
this subset of single cells we try to
find a new manel partitioning for them.
Um and this partition usually consists
of more trustworthy and smaller meta
cells. So this is like the two step. In
the first step we first identify dubious
meta cells in a more conservative way by
using the 85 a quantile instead of 95th
quantile and then we decompose those
dubious meta cells into single cells
again. And in step two, we apply our
selected meta cell partition method
again to the subset of single cells and
to identify new meta cells. And we also
use our MC rigger to identify the
optimal granularity level.
And actually these two steps can be
repeated for many times until we have
zero dubious amount of cells. So uh that
is a way to handle the dubious ones. And
here we apply our MC rigger two step on
this um bone marrow single cell data
which has which has two uh rare cell
types. One is plasma blood cells and the
other is HSC and we want to see whether
our MC rigger two step would be able to
resolve these two rare cell types.
So here in this bar plot each bar
represent one trustworthy mana cell and
the height of the bar represent the size
of a trustworthy manel. So you can see
that compared with the uh compared with
the original partitioning our MC rigger
2 step would be able to provide a much a
large a much larger number of
trustworthy meta cells to work with for
each of these rare cell types. So that
means we have better representation for
these red cell types and this kind of
improvement is even more obvious uh if
we look at the supercell and mana cell
methods. So sometimes originally we have
zero trustworthy meta cells but if we
apply our two-step extension we have a
lot more.
So uh this comes to the here comes the
conclusion of our method. So so far we
have uh been able to answer our three
questions. We have been able to give a
statistical definition of manazel based
on the two-layer model and we have
detected dubious mana cells using the
permanel mcdi statistics and we have uh
through through building
uh the null through double permutation
and we have also been able to optimize
our mass partitioning by balancing the
sparsity and dubious dubiousness
and our paper have been have recently
been published on this nature
communication journal.
So, and we also have um quite user
friendly um online R packages and
tutorials on GitHub and please feel free
to check them out through these two
links.
Right. Uh so, and with these I would
like to thank our great great our great
grand sponsors and also mo most
importantly thank professor Jessica and
our all of our lab members from the JS
lab for supporting our work. And and I
would also like to thank you all for
your attention.