[Music]
I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it works coming to you
from the MIT energy initiative and
looking at the energy solutions to
climate
[Music]
change and today we're joined by a
researcher and entrepreneur who's not
afraid to swim against the tide there's
a lot of Fantasy around climate change
and the sense that if we can just really
focus on developing Renewables that will
solve all of our problems desroy PL
argues yes absolutely develop Renewables
but that's not where the conversation
should end we need to have a plan that
kind of gets us to that renewable future
and does it in a way that minimizes
emissions from our current practices we
can't escape our current practices so I
come from the great state of Maine and
there's a phrase there you can't get
there from here when you ask someone
directions you can't get to that
renewable future from the state that
we're at right now without going through
a
transition a transition that as we'll
discuss may involve making carbon
dioxide today a conversation with desire
Plata associate professor of civil and
environmental engineering at MIT and the
co-director of the MIT climate and
sustainability
Consortium Des re welcome good to see
you I'm good to see you too nice to see
you Des so I'm just going to start with
kind of a big provocative statement that
you made not long ago this is a quote we
can sit here today and entertain the
fantasy that coal-based energy is going
away but I can tell you that is not the
reality so I heard you say that in a
talk and um I think a lot of people
would think like wait what aren't we
phasing out coal aren't we sort of
almost done with that what's what is the
reality what's the fantasy yeah for sure
I mean the reality is that coal is not
going away at the rate that people
imagine and really one of the big
drivers for that is the fact that China
and India are experiencing enormous
economic growth and that growth is
underpinned by the extraction of coal in
those Nations we have a perception here
in the United States that coal is going
away because of the natural gas boom
actually which displaced a lot of coal
use but even here in the US Cole is even
undergoing a boom actually since the
Russia Ukraine conflict um the prices of
coal have gone up the Reliance on coal
is is here um and and that's necessary
to to meet our energy needs so while
we'd like to be going in the other
direction we're actually not so then
when you look at that landscape people
assume Cole is sort of on its way out
but you're saying really not as far as
you can tell not the story The Numbers
tell right yeah that's not the story The
Numbers tell now um I'll say that lots
of listeners are going to go Google this
right now and you can find charts that
will forecast past The Disappearance of
coal through time and you and you can
look at coal for energy production
decreasing and it looks like it's
decreasing all over the world that's
just not the reality in a couple of very
large um Holdings and again China India
Indonesia all extracting coal at at
fairly High rates because it's necessary
for their economy it's also um talked
about as uh socially just right so why
should we tell other nations that they
cannot use their domestic energy why
should we tell them that they can't
experience economic growth and so
there's a bit of a social element tied
into it uh that it's not just about
access to to energy but access to
domestic energy and enabling their
populations to experience the same
Prosperity that we've benefited from in
the United States and in the European
Union so as somebody who wants to
mitigate climate change when you see
that that story with coal and you see
the numbers and you understand the
trajectory what does that say to you
about what you should be doing we all
should be doing we all should be doing I
mean what it says to me is that we're
going to have to be pursuing carbon
removal strategies carbon emissions
reduction strategies both for carbon
dioxide that's released during energy
generation at large Point sources like
power plants but also geologic sources
of of methane that are emitted anytime
you open up a coal mine so thinking
about those emissions terms in a very
serious way and trying to develop novel
strategies there I also just want to say
for a minute to give credit where it's
due that you know China and India have
installed enormous amounts of Renewable
Power as well and and they should be
celebrated for that so it's just that
the pace of growth in these very large
populations is enormous and requires the
utilization of that coal as well as the
renewable energy sources so while Global
growth in Renewables is faster than the
global growth in fossil our hunger for
that energy outpaces our ability to
install Renewables and and that's what
keeps us pinned to Coal or one of the
things China also has different problems
from countries in in the sense of a
having not very many other resources to
rely on they don't have natural gas but
they've also got this this very
industrialized economy and a
concentration of people in big cities in
terrible pollution problems I mean a lot
of the really bad pollution days we see
in the world are either in Northern
India or in China the Chinese have
transitioned rapidly toward electric
vehicles over the last couple of years
and they're still racing ahead yes and
you hear about like byd and these
vehicles that we don't have in America
because of tariffs but like that are
competing in many places with the Teslas
of the world so it does seem like
they're the leader in solar well they're
coal powered
cars but it sounds sounds like there's
all of the above like yeah there's coal
but yeah they are it doesn't negate the
fact that they are doing a lot with
solar they are doing a lot with electric
cars yes that's right yeah and so I just
want to acknowledge that it's not um
some ignorance of climate change that is
that is driving these decisions it's
really that that drive towards more
prosperity for all of their citizens and
domestic availability of coal resources
um and in in India in particular coal
really underpins many facets of the
economy so the coal that's moved on the
trains those are subsidizes the movement
of the people who move by train in order
to get to work and so it's all kind of
really embedded in in how the the base
of the economy is structured um Rob I
know you spent a lot of time in India I
I feel like people sometimes in the US
will think well can't people in
countries that are developing now skip
some technologies like skip the kind of
dirty technologies that we went through
and get right to the clean ones in in in
some measure yes but one of the
challenges with transitioning away from
coal is that you're transitioning from a
very very energy dense medium to if if
if Renewables in the form of solar and
wind one that isn't very energy dense
one that takes up a lot of real estate
both in India and in China I think
there's there's a certain amount of
growing public push back toward building
these very very large solar arrays and
windmills and places where people can
see them along with the transmission
lines that bring that power to Market so
they're making great strides in other
areas as well particularly the Chinese
uh with the development of nuclear
technologies and they just announced
very recently that they they've built
and operated the world's first so-called
Pebble bed reactor which lends itself to
um very efficient uh use of of uranium
and uh very high temperature nuclear
reactors they're building a lot of
advanced reactors as well far more than
we are so that they're trying these
other directions that
work for them with their large
populations and and lack of land and and
more contention for land than we have
but it's it's a really hard battle
they're not cheaper uh and and they take
a lot of capital so you talked about how
when I think when we mine for coal a
whole bunch of methane comes out of the
ground so explain that and uh people I
think you know heard of methan but like
how does it compare to carbon dioxide as
problematic in terms of uh global
warming great question I'll I'll give
you a long answer okay to it um I
there's a a wonderful scientist um here
at MIT whose name is Penny Chisum and
Penny wrote a great series of books
called the sunlight series and she's got
one of these books in particular that's
a children's book actually and it's
called buried sunlight and I think it's
important for people to recognize that
all of our fossil fuels are uh buried
sunlight energy right there was a a
microscopic plant at some some point in
history floating on the surface ocean
that died and was buried and subducted
under the Continental shelves there it
experienced High pressures and
temperatures and was essentially cooked
into things like oil and coal and
methane so that methane is actually a
what's called a thermogenic byproduct of
that cooking process where you get coal
rocks and oil the liquids and gas the
the lighter hydrocarbons and so it's
there in in the coal bed formation it's
there when you extract oil it's a
naturally occurring geologic thing and
when you open up a coal mine there is
going to be methane there now and it
just escapes into the air you like open
up the ground you know people think like
strip mining or something you just open
up the ground and it goes up into the
that's right or even if you dig a hole
into the Earth and some of these mines
can be miles below the Earth's surface
you can functionally think of them as as
networks of cities almost like connected
Subway systems that are that are deep
within the Earth they might be a minutes
ele long elevator ride to get to some of
these coal mines so so right away you're
hearing energy intensity you've got to
get fresh air down there for the miners
to breathe you've got to make sure that
that methane doesn't accumulate to
levels where it's going to be explosive
and present a a big safety risk to the
miners themselves and so in order to
mitigate that risk they pull air out of
the mine to create a negative pressure
that pulls fresh air in in from outside
and that is called ventilation air and
that ventilation air is Laden with
methane now those ventilation air shafts
are moving air at astronomically High
rates so it can be on the order of a
million cubic feet a minute that's
something like 10 tractor trailers going
past you in six seconds it's a it's an
enormous volume of air and again that is
that is done in order to make sure the
miners can breathe and to make sure
methane doesn't accumulate to explosive
levels it's a safety measure that
ventilation air methane is responsible
for a large amount of atmospheric
methane emissions and while not all
mines are ventilated some are surface
strip mines so I can't give you a good
breakdown of of which is coming from
that ventilation AA and which is coming
from the strip bines but we know it
accounts for somewhere around 50 million
metric tons of methane annually the
atmospheric growth term for methane is
around 20 million metric tons annually
and so if you could get just less than
half of glob coal mines to adopt a
technology that destroyed that methane
you would stop the accumulation of
methane in an instant you know with one
technology and then the atmosphere can
start to clean itself through natural
processes so you're saying we you get
back to the Natural rate of evolution of
methane at that point because you're
removing the anthropogenic source almost
at least for coal mining yes there are
many other anthropogenic sources of
methane methane is really short-lived in
the atmosphere it's halflife is on the
order of about 12 years and so what that
means is if you could at least stop
dumping so much methane into the
atmosphere you'd see a really fast
cleaning process occurring where that
methane is is being destroyed by natural
processes now tell us why we should care
about methane is I mean carbon dioxide
is what we hear about you hear about
carbon dioxide a lot yeah so in in
carbon dioxide equivalence which is kind
of the term that that you hear about
methane is about 120 times as a as a
warming as CO2 uh
instantaneously um wow yeah so when
don't we talk about methane more
well that's why you're here yeah that's
why I'm here so the reason uh that we
don't talk about methane more is really
because when we think about our Global
Climate models we're thinking over very
long time scales what's going to happen
to us 100 years from now okay and if you
think about um 100e time scales
methane's fate in the atmosphere is to
naturally turn into CO2 anyway and so
most of the methane that's emitted today
will become CO2 o over time um about 90%
of it it becomes CO2 over time um and
and relatively short time scales and so
because we're looking on that long time
Horizon we say well it's going to be CO2
anyway and so our conversation hasn't
really emphasized methane so when we
look on that 100-year time scale we say
that our our methane emissions might be
equivalent to about 16% of our total
greenhouse gas emissions when you look
on the 20year time scale our methane
emissions are equivalent in total
warming to CO2 So within the next 10
years methane will warm the atmosphere
as much as CO2 even though methane is
more than 200 times less
concentrated okay so but if methane is
going to become CO2 why is it so M I
mean why don't we just sit around and
wait for that to happen like what would
be your argument for like no no let's
get on this now and why is it so much
more warming than CO2 if it's just going
to become CO2 yeah really really
important question yeah so so I like say
Co CO2 is a low and slow warmer um so we
could drop CO2 emissions to zero today
which is would be great but the
atmosphere wouldn't feel it for 50 to
100 years because it's accumulating um
over time methane does its damage right
away it's a really potent warmer and
then it slowly turns in to CO2 in the
atmosphere if we could accelerate that
process that's going to happen anyway um
and get methane to become CO2 really
quickly it wouldn't get a chance to warm
up the atmosphere the way that it does
that would allow us to change the rate
of climate forcing that we're going to
experience in the next two decades um
that could potentially save us from
passing so-called climate tipping points
with people might have heard about so as
we warm the planet the rate of release
of natural sources of methane actually
increases um and so if we can pump the
brakes on climate change we could
potentially reduce the amount of natural
methane emissions that are going to
occur in the next several decades now
some estimates say that if we drop
anthropogenic emissions man-made
emissions by 50% by 2030 we could save a
half a degree warming by 2100 it's
actually the only gas that does that
again modulating CO2 today doesn't
change the rate of warming it changes
the absolute amount of warming that
we're going to experience methane's the
only thing the only greenhouse gas that
will change the rate of warming in our
lifetimes I think it's important to also
get your head around the fact that it's
not equivalent to the same amount of CO2
I mean it so you'd only have to remove
or reduce CO2 emissions direct CO2
emissions by a relatively small amount
to compensate for the additional CO2
that's entering the atmosphere from the
degradation of the of the methane yeah
you you got it so methane emissions are
measured in millions of metric tons CO2
emissions are measured in billions of
metric tons and so you can convert a lot
of methane into CO2 and it it doesn't
end up being a big input term it's it's
like a minuscule contribution to glob
CO2 emissions and again that's what was
going to happen to it anyway um it
methane was going to become CO2 all
we're doing is trying to accelerate that
process so that methane doesn't get a
chance to to warm the atmosphere but it
turning it into CO2 I think it's
underline helps to mitigate global
warming that's right yeah not what You'
think right not what You' think right
because you hear about CO2 being so bad
and just to to put some numbers on it
you could take half of the atmosphere's
methane and convert it to CO2 and the
CO2 concentration in the atmosphere
would go from around 423 parts per
million to
424 parts per million right it's a
little blip in the CO2 contribution but
it saves you 16% of climate forcing over
the next hundred years it's a huge big
deal so I think we should talk about how
you would do this but Rob I wonder I
mean you've seen so many people
developing so many Technologies around
climate change is desire unusual in talk
A talking about methane and B I'm
creating carbon
dioxide well she is but in a good way
Ian does she stand out this is a very
pragmatic perspective I mean there's no
question about it and and it's it's a
very healthy one and I have to say it's
not an unusual perspective at MIT but
this is this is looking coldly at the
numbers and saying we could do this and
have this very large impact relatively
quickly and we should do that but we
also have to get on the CO2 and I think
people appreciate that as well and I
don't think you're in any sense arguing
that we don't that's right and I think
people get really confused about that
they say why coal why CO2 and I'm uh I I
would love to see Renewables expanded as
quickly as possible I would love to see
us get away from fossil energy sources
when and where we can um and I and we
definitely need to get control of our
CO2 emissions that's absolutely
important but the reality is that we're
going to have these emissions and if if
I can do something to stop that
accumulation I'm not too proud to to
engage in that activity yeah so you're
not just telling an interesting story
though I mean you are a an environmental
engineer you're doing stuff you're
researching it but you're also getting
involved as an entrepreneur right tell
us about that yeah sure um so on the
methane front we've we're standing up a
company that's called MOX a so we're
trying to oxidize methane in the
atmosphere um or at very low
concentrations and uh we're just
founding this company and it's really
the product of um you know several years
of research uh that we've been doing at
MIT and we'd like to get this into the
hands of of coal miners um and others
who have low-level methane emissions uh
all over the globe as really as fast as
we can and this this 2030 Target is
aggressive and on purpose because we
really need to stand up these
Technologies in order to see that that
uh that warming benefit to the rate of
climate change so we could get the
Indians and Chinese to use this
technology far less expensively than to
pay them to switch away from coal for
example I mean that's again I'm we're
all going to get into trouble for this
we're all going to get into trouble for
this yeah no that's right I mean it
would be it would be really lovely if we
could get the technology adopted in in
China and India there are a lot of
hurdles to that I will say that you know
there's really great people working in
the governments on both sides who are
who are trying to to make this happen
and to make it happen in a way that's
economically incentivized um if not
politically mandated and um there are
lots of barriers um and and so we
continue to try to be part of that
conversation I'm very tired most of the
time I take every phone call I hope I
don't get a lot of phone calls because
of that but but yeah I mean if somebody
calls and says how can we think through
how to remove barriers here we we try to
engage um on all fronts and having a
commercial entity is part of being able
to do that successfully
[Music]
so explain the technology so let's say I
run a coal mine and I say okay this
sounds interesting and what is it that
I'm buying or getting and what does it
look like and how does it work so I
think there's kind of two categories of
coal miners I ones that live in
regulated environments that have really
good pricing on on carbon dioxide
emissions reductions and then ones that
do not live in regulated environments
and have kind of the wild west of carbon
dioxide emissions credits where are the
regulated places places like Australia
and in the European Union there are some
pretty good Financial incentives to be
adopting methane emissions reductions at
your coal mine and in those cases the
miners themselves May reach out and say
look I need this to be compliant there's
going to be a tax on the amount of
methane emissions that that that I um
emit to the atmosphere so I have a
quantifiable number uh that I can spend
on your technology to stop that emission
from happening so so it puts a it puts a
ceiling on what they're going to be
willing to spend for for a technology
for an abatement technology they're also
allowed to sell that abated methane um
into Glo Global carbon markets and so
it's kind of a win-win the technology
can pay for itself on the order of you
know 3 to five years in in those cases
um in Europe where they're paying very
really very high dollar amounts for um
carbon dioxide credits the technology
could pay for itself even faster and
that's remarkable in the United States
we don't have we don't have the benefit
of a really well- constrained uh market
for voluntary carbon dioxide market and
what that means is that there's no
reason a coal miner would want to buy
this technology um why would you right
it's G to you've got to disrupt your
infrastructure um it costs many millions
of dollars to install the thing these
are Big we're talking about modulating
the the warming rates of the atmosphere
it is big stuff and people need to
recognize that it is going to cost a lot
of money to build the thing to start
with this is a big filter that goes on
the end of the the fan unit that I
described earlier that's ventilating the
the mine um and then we warm that unit
up and it starts destroying methane and
that's great but there's a risk to the
the coal miner saying they want it
because now they've got this big piece
of infrastructure there so in those
unregulated spaces they're actually
third-party developers who will come and
say hey coal miner I'll cut you a deal
I'll pay for all this infrastructure and
I'm going to give you a few bucks um you
know on the sale of the of the carbon
and and I'll keep the rest to pay for
the unit and so they're we're having to
be creative about how we deploy these um
and and really rely on on minor saying
okay I'll take the risk it's one of
those things feel like also where
expensive is a relative term right like
it may cost millions of dollars to it
sounds like to install right but on the
other hand it costs billions or
trillions of dollars to clean up after
storms that like ruin everybody's house
and so you could argue it's kind of
cheap if you can mitigate some climate
change and therefore have to say you
know be able to save billions of dollars
through like FEMA you know and the
things you would have to do to help
people so I'm really glad you raised the
point about extreme weather events I
think the number of billion dollar
storms um has been steadily increasing
over the past 20 years I think it's up
over 20 annually now in the United
States so the American taxpayer is
already paying for for climate change
and I would love to see us pay for
mitigation efforts uh I don't want to
communicate false hope here we are
committed to a certain amount of climate
change because of historic CO2 emissions
and and really contemporary methane
emissions from the past 20 years or so
um that that amount of forcing will
happen but if we could spend just a
fraction of those monies on uh climate
mitigation efforts I think they would go
a really long way uh we have to
incentivize the adoption of these
emissions reduction Technologies and
right now we're really not doing that
very well so there's as you know a lot
of
money
companies Venture Capital firms wealthy
families out there trying thinking about
this issue caring about it is it hard
for you to make your case because either
a this isn't like something people you
know people know what a solar panel is
or and people know what an electric car
is and you're saying well this is this
other thing and you probably never heard
of it slash is it hard to be like here's
what I'd like some money for to save the
planet making carbon dioxide and people
are like ah okay well I mean do you ever
get that I I do get that a lot I think
people can get their head around the
carbon dioxide thing because if you look
at the numbers there's not it's not a
lot of carbon dioxide that's what it was
going to become anyway you know a
molecule of of methane released always
does more damage than a molecule of CO2
because it becomes a molecule of CO2 so
if I can make that process faster and
cut methane's ability to warm the
atmosphere people are really on board
with that what people don't like
investing in is coal anything right they
don't want to touch coal with a 20ft
pole but the reality it is that coal is
here natural gas is here it is not going
away and we actually need it to get us
to those renewable energy systems and
all of the infrastructure that we're
imagining for the future um and so if
we're in that catch 22 we had better
damn be sure that we are minimizing the
emissions associated with those fossil
energy sources and that's what I think
people really really struggle with we
want to be in that future but we can't
quite Lea frog to that future let yet
there's a transition and somebody's got
to support that transition in a real and
meaningful way or else it's going to get
a lot worse and we got to get on this
methane thing right
away so this is an appeal to all our
listeners to uh there's a linkow invest
in desise company so this is not easy to
raise Venture Capital funding for yeah
it's really not very easy and I and I
you know I give a lot of credit to to my
partners at moxir who've been working
very hard to to raise capital for this
and to um you know the earnest uh folks
who are willing to go into coal mines um
and say look this is how we can help
reduce the the carbon footprint of this
process today and that's a really
important part uh I think rob you
mentioned you know we at MIT have
classically tried to work with people to
make more sustainable Technologies and
work with the technologies that are here
today including the fossil energy
industry and so that's what we've really
been trying to do like help us
understand your problems help us come up
with Creative Solutions during this
transition period um to to the future we
we want to that all of us want to see
really what about the other part of the
fossil industry the the the Natural Gas
part of the fossil industry basically
the methane part of the natural the
fossil industry yeah that's right I mean
so I natural gas of course it's its
primary component is methane there are a
lot of uh what are called fugitive
emissions across the the entire natural
gas production system from from the time
that you you drop that well to the
processing and refining of that methan
to the distribution into our homes there
are leaks all along the way including
that your natural gas stove that you
might have in your home and so how do we
deal with that those actually you know
people know about flares or you can
light a match and uh convert methane to
CO2 that's pretty easy that only works a
downside yeah that's kind of the
downside right it can be a downside but
that uh that only works at really high
concentrations of methane and it most of
me the world's methane emissions at
least 80% and probably closer to 90% are
in this dilute and diffuse concentration
range and so the technology that we've
tried to develop is actually doing that
same combustion chemistry methane to CO2
but it's doing it catalytically inside
of of of this porous uh clay that we've
developed so we've talked about a couple
things that you open up the ground for
right um natural gas and Mining
coal another thing that you open up the
ground for is to get metals and we need
those increasingly for these cleaner
technologies that are part of a
transition MH but does Methane also come
out of the ground when you are like well
we need we need a bunch of metals yeah
yeah there are certain there are certain
Minds um in the world in certain
minerals that that do have enriched
methane not all of them but certainly
some of them and so it's a concern there
I think that you know you bring up a
really good point uh in order to meet
our our modest 2040 sustainable
development energy goals I think we need
um something like four times the metals
that we've ever extracted on on planet
Earth and in order to get those Metals
we dig really big holes in the ground
they can be 5,000 m across and 500 M
deep um and you can't get to the bottom
of those mines and back out with a
battery there's no battery in the world
that does that for you and that very
specific problem beholds you to to
diesel fuel um and to fossil-based
carbon sources at least right now you
know and so there's a lot of innovation
that needs to happen in mining so that
we can get those minerals to the surface
of the Earth enable that renewable
energy transition but do it in a way
that doesn't come with the the really
burdensome carbon footprint Associated
both with extraction as well as
processing and refining those
materials I wonder rob you know when I
hear what's involved in mining metals
that we use for let's say electric cars
I don't know I wonder if you feel like
that's like that's a blind spot that
people tend to have where they think
well I've bought an electric car and now
I'm good because like you you know I'm
sort of absolved what whatever my
neighbor with this gas guzzling SUV you
know is doing I I am doing none of that
but complicated really yeah well when
you get that battery in your electric
car somebody's mining nickel probably
from a soil deposit a laterite deposit
in probably Indonesia or some part of
Southeast Asia and the forest is falling
and tailings are running into the ocean
and I sent a student to look around and
engine Asia uh where we have a lot of
relationships and we're working hard
together just to see the scale of
environmental damage and and it's
horrendous and that's just from the
extraction of Earth and and and exposing
exposing the material they want to
digging but then they go into these
horrific Toil and Trouble kind of
processes that desire was talking about
and there are different Pathways that
that they can follow but but right this
is getting electric cars here has all
kinds of consequences it has
consequences for mining it has consequen
es for electricity generation we do a
lot more of it we use a lot more fossil
fuels in the course of using of doing
that so you
know clearly it's beneficial uh to move
in the direction of electrification and
we need to do it rapidly but we really
do have to pay attention to that Metals
production end I like some of the stuff
you've been talking about with recycling
of batteries as we get more and more
these batteries out there we have the
possibility of reusing that material you
got it yeah yeah so um I think this is
you know really great example and I
would just underscore what you said like
people you know listening you definitely
should be you know moving towards
electrification as kind of as fast as we
can um and we're we're taking care of
the the metals problem so I'll say you
know I I have another a prior startup
company that um spun out of my lab uses
um a technique called Electro extraction
so we don't use the really high
temperatures we don't use the acids and
bases um we use just a fundamentally
different process um enabled by
nanomaterial I'm largely developed you
know during my PhD and afterwards I was
here at MIT um and you I think my second
PhD students a CEO of a company called
enth cycle um and en cycle um just
started the first domestic production of
nickel and Cobalt from recovered uh
spent battery materials uh here in the
US so um I got a a great message from
her the other day that said you know we
just produced our first product and it's
working even better than we expected and
you know it just almost brings tears to
your eyes because it's so amazing and it
happens with 92% reduction in the
greenhouse gas emissions because you're
using stuff that's already out there
don't need to go back into the Earth
because we all have all bunch of stuff
in our is this is coming from like old
phones old computers old whatever
largely old batteries today because you
know those that first generation of
hybrid electric vehicles and um and and
full electric vehicles are starting to
come offline and and we can take those
spent batteries and reuse them there are
also lots of different um Metals you
know we we the the technology really is
is very highly adaptable to lots of
different uh you know Metals in the
periodic table so you say send us your
you know send us your large volume
E-Waste and and we'll come up with a way
to process it and it's really fun you
can go to um our development plant here
in Burlington Mass and look through you
know just piles of of old materials uh
data centers are another big one you
know so where you have concentrated
stocks of lots of metals that's great
cuz the economics starts to work um and
it's not just uh that we are are not
digging the hole so to speak um we're
also not relying on those acids and
bases and those high temperature
processes it's really um very different
and it can be driven with Renewable
Power so it's it starts to decouple us
um and our mining Supply from carbon
emissions like we were talking about
earlier you don't need the diesel truck
anymore because you can use what you
have already at the surface of the Earth
the economy is growing so we still got
to get more uh so I don't want to imply
that it solves all your problem problems
but it's a really important part of the
problem and the technology is adaptable
that it might even be able to go into
those tailing ponds and and other spaces
in mining yeah so we're not going to
recycle our way out of the problem in
the short term until we get so many cars
out there that we're sort of in
equilibrium we're bringing in as many
batteries and recycling them as we're
putting back into cars you got it so
it's decades
away but it's it's still helping now I
mean it's it's it means that some amount
of environmental destruction doesn't
take place because we're separating that
yeah that's right and and if you're a
you know a synthetic chemist or material
scientist and I gave you a pile of used
Goods to use you would look at me like I
was insane so you'd say I want the
99.9999% Purity and what we're you know
engaged in some research that's showing
that you actually can get away with a
little bit less you can use recovered
materials um we we can produce a very
high Purity product I should be very
clear about that but because of that you
can actually reuse it and there's very
little the product performed and
performance is absolutely key you know
we're pursuing uh not just envir more
environmentally sustainable Technologies
but ones that that work uh Best in Class
and so that's um I think an exciting
outcrop and really a very new area of
research that needs to be further
explored do you you know we've talked
about a lot of complexities to uh
climate change that people don't
necessarily think about do you worry
about our ability to address climate
change or transitioning energy sources
if we can't talk about those
complexities I I just wonder what you
see and how you feel about that oh yeah
I mean there's a lot of Fantasy around
climate change and the sense that if we
can just really focus on developing
Renewables that will solve all of our
problems we absolutely should be
developing Renewables and it will it is
where we need to be going um but it
doesn't solve our near-term problems and
ignoring the transition will make it
worse we need to pay attention to the
reality of the situation we need to have
a plan that kind of gets us to that
renewable future and does it in a way
that minimizes emissions from our
current practices we can't escape our
current practices so I come from the
great state of Main and there's a phrase
there you can't get there from here when
you ask someone directions you can't get
to that renewable future from the state
that we're at right now without going
through a transition there's risk
associated with that there are
strategies we can deploy and we should
be deploying them and failure to talk
about them is only going to handicap Us
in pursuit of those goals how does that
affect your level of optimism about
what's ahead yeah I mean uh I am ever
The Optimist and uh I guess to give a
specific example when I was starting
grad school in this place 21 years ago I
had to explain to people why they should
care about the environment and why it
was it should be embedded in in their
Innovation practices um I don't have to
do that anymore but definitely was not
the Instinct at MIT 21 years ago oh for
sure why would you do that you foolish
person and um and now people come to me
and say we would really like to pursue
this and how can we do it systematically
quickly um cost effectively and
potentially even at a cost benefit and I
think that that's the transition that
we're part of right now that I'm really
excited to see is that um you know
caring about the environment actually
shouldn't shouldn't be a filter or a
patch or an economic cost it should be
an an opport opportunity and if we um if
we can kind of adapt our practices and
value uh you know the environment and
and yes take a little bit of time but
leverage all the Innovation that's going
on I think that we can get there the
methane mitigation strategy you're
talking about you know say if we just
think about the mine example is is
looking at a concentrated Source but not
a Pure Source of methane it's mixed with
air and other gases that are coming out
of the mine and so the strategy of
breaking down those methane molecules
that are in that stream is a good one
because you can't really burn it yeah
but if you can burn it isn't the smarter
thing to do to to aggregate all a lot of
small leaks and burn them make
electricity and release it as CO2 into
the atmosphere do you think about a lot
of people love that idea and that goes
into the calculation where people say
you could actually make money by
stopping these diffuse uh leaks a lot of
these diffuse leaks happen in really
remote regions where there's no
infrastructure to do that concentrating
and by the time you built it the leak
would be gone right like these are
transient in time they're transient in
space they're in remote areas so that's
another kind of bit of of fantasy that I
think is is a little bit dangerous um we
need to have alternative strategies to
finding and and abating those leaks and
and destruction can be a very important
one we are um you know just taking these
methane molecules and breaking them
apart the cool thing about that is even
when they're at really low levels they
still release heat there's a lot of heat
right yeah there's a lot of heat there
and so um if we're at a at a coal mine
and the air is moving itself um there's
actually enough methane there so that we
just heat our reactor up once and then
it's self- sustaining it's carbon
abatement for free which doesn't happen
very often so the cost goes way down the
energy requirement goes way down that
means a better net greenhouse gas
reduction term because you're not
requiring lots of thermal energy to to
destroy that methane molecule so it's
exciting for for those reasons it's a
really different type of carbon
emissions reduction
Des is a professor of civil and
environmental engineering at MIT she's a
multifaceted entrepreneur thanks so much
for being here thanks for having
me what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy. mit.edu
[Music]
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob Stoner thanks for listening
[Music]