Thank you for having me. Thank you to uh
the MIT Startup Exchange for hosting
this event. Um my name is Jamie New and
I am the co-founder and CEO of Podium
Automation. We are reimagining the
design and manufacturing of industrial
control panels to create a more
resilient and modern industrial supply
chain. Our team brings decades of
experience from companies like Tesla,
Blue Origin, Walmart, and Bowie Farming
to ultimately reduce lead times of
critical equipment from months to days.
Um, I am a Sloan grad. We also have a
couple of other MIT alumni on the
founding team.
So, industrial control panels are a
critical component of every industrial
machine and electromechanical process.
Physically, it is a collection of
devices like PLC's, relays, and circuit
breakers inside an enclosure. Control
panels are extremely pervasive
throughout the built world from
infrastructure to largecale
manufacturing plants, wastewater
treatment, data centers, and everything
in between. Um, once you start noticing
them, you will see them everywhere.
Despite the central role control panels
have in automation, the current design
and build process is extremely manual.
There is a long tale of thousands of
panel shops in the US alone that are
largely crafting panels by hand
resulting in long lead times um of 2 to
6 months for a single panel.
We have done a lot of listening in this
space and we believe that the new
generation of manufacturing companies
and leaders demand better and will need
better lead times in order to to meet
the sort of timelines that they're
looking for.
So what we are doing at podium is we are
combining proprietary software and
automation to build factories that
reduce lead time and increase margin for
custom industrial control panels
across the speed, quality um and cost
spectrum. We believe that customers
should not need to choose to and um our
goal is to build a low friction
experience for engineers and operators
to procure a control panel within days.
So we are currently UL508A certified. Um
we're also uh in process of UL698A
certification which is hazardous
locations and our current lead times are
less than four weeks per panel.
So, how do we actually do this? We have
created a seamless process to reduce
lead times across the quote design,
build, test, and delivery spectrum.
We've created a intake form for
customers and a process that allows us
to provide build quotes in less than 24
hours. Our internal software acts as a
co-pilot to an electrical engineer to
get to a full digital twin of the panel
itself, which ultimately unlocks
automation in the fabrication process in
our state-of-the-art factory and
facility.
And since our founding uh less than a
year ago, we have delivered over 30
projects across a varied customer base.
Recently, um, the case study highlighted
here, we completed four unique panel
builds for a Berkshire Hathaway owned
industrial filtration water equipment
company. We delivered those panels in
less than four weeks for a project where
the entire installation um was delayed
by the control panel showing up.
So, we have some incredible traction so
far, a team of seven currently full-time
employees, and we are in the uh midst of
expanding to a $20 million annual
capacity facility in the next couple of
months. Um, so alongside that expansion,
what we're looking for is corporate
partners to scale with us. From a
customer perspective, we work with OEMs
and end users across industries who
build or buy control panels today. We're
also looking for partners on the
component manufacturing side. So if you
are a manufacturer of components that go
into a control panel, Allah, a Seammens,
Honeywell, Schneider Electric, um we'd
love to chat as well about partnering on
the component database that we're
putting together.
Thank you and happy to answer any
questions.