so let's consider this problem of
generating images from text commands I
can tell the model what content I want
to create by describing that content in
natural language for example if I type
in bird the model should output an image
of a bird but how does the model know
which bird to generate if the model
outputs an image of a robin that does
indeed match the label bird but it also
would have been fine to generate a
different kind of bird so the way
generative models handle this mgy is by
randomizing the output and they achieve
this by inserting random variables into
the model you can think of these random
variables like the roll of dice so in
our example one roll of the dice will
result in one kind of bird a robin
another roll will result in another kind
of bird maybe a blue bird and rolling
again we might get a parrot for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow