Um so I want to thank ILP for inviting
me to talk about Lincoln Laboratory um
in its 75 years of supporting national
security through industry engagement. Um
so we uh strive to create as it says
prototype and deliver and that really
involves engaging with industry in a
significant way. So this discussion is
is about that engagement and I
understand um you know there might be an
opportunity for questions but if you
have any questions as I move forward
please feel free to ask.
Okay. So a little bit of history about
Lincoln Lab. So Lincoln Lab was actually
begun or its inception uh came with the
concurrence of the second world war. Um
the allies uh needed a way uh to better
monitor aircraft and yubot um and they
were looking for radar technology to be
developed to help with this monitoring.
So um Tizzard in England had come to the
United States with a secret technology
uh called a cavity mag uh magnetron. And
this cavity magnetron um was basically
able to use high power ultra
highfrequency radar um in a way that
would allow antennas to be shrunk and
put on aircraft so that you could detect
a yubot surfacing or aircraft coming in
the air uh from uh foreign uh space,
right? And so the amazing thing is they
had this capability but their industrial
base was decimated by the war. So the
partnership between the allies allowed
the United States to bring together
academia and industry to help create a
solution that really helped turn the
tide on the war. The um NA NDRC, the
National Defense Research Committee
decided that to help uh create a
prototype uh for the cavity magnet
magnetron um they would create a
laboratory at MIT that would include
academicians, researchers, and members
of industry to help develop this
technology. And so that's how the MIT
RAD lab or radiation lab was born. The
RAD lab was called radiation lab. And I
never knew this until I came for this
talk because I was like, what does
radiation have to do with radar? But in
fact it was a misnomer and it was an
intentional misnomer to I guess help
think help uh kind of foster the idea
that the lab was uh working on nuclear
energy when really we were working on
detection. So the lab was established in
temporary housing at MIT uh in about in
the 40s. Um, it employed over 4,000
people. And as they were developing this
technology for national security, they
invited industry to help with the
manufacturing and the scaling of that
technology. So RCA, Westinghouse, all of
these large companies came to learn
about the technology, to learn how to
make it, and then to productize it. This
really helped turn the tide of the war.
By the end of World War II, 50% of all
radar monitoring was based on this MIT
design. So that's how we got started. Um
after the war was over, the lab was
dismantled. But with the rise of Soviet
nuclear power, the United States decided
that it needed additional assistance
with surveillance. And so they came to
the secretary of the air force came to
MIT and asked would MIT help support
national security again and MIT said yes
but the nature of our work public
education you saw very global amazing
place right uh may not be the best uh
environment to hold classified
discussions about national security. So
MIT built uh right next to Hanscom Air
Force Base in Lexington, Massachusetts,
which is why we're called Lincoln,
right? Because we're in Lexington. I
never understood that we border
Lexington and Lincoln, but anyway, um
I'm not from Massachusetts. Uh so it's
Lincoln Laboratory because of its
location in Lexington. and we are an
organization here um dedicated to
developing advanced technology solutions
to support national security. We've had
se almost 75 years of this activity and
most of this activity has been
successful because we've been able to
partner with industry. So you can see
some of the accomplish accomplishments
over time. I'm just going to point out
one of them, the 193 optical lithography
technology that was developed by Lincoln
um in the 90s. So in the 90s the idea
was in order to make a leap in micro
electronics we needed to move into
X-rays. So Lincoln decided that might
not be the way to go that in order to
get the smaller feature size we should
stick to deep UV and that's what we did
and Lincoln developed a much smaller
feature- sized approach to micro
electronics and the integrated circuit
chip and we did it in coll we led an
industry collaboration that included IBM
and Corning and all of the other analog
devices all of the traditional companies
that you would think would be involved
olved in this endeavor were part of this
collaboration. We worked hand in hand
and really created a kind of next
generation chip that is still being used
today in much of the IoT devices that
you use. So um our success is made
possible through our ability to engage
with industry.
So this is a kind of an overview of what
Lincoln looks like. Um, as I said,
Lincoln is right next to Hanscom Air
Force Base, which makes parking really
difficult if there's an Air Force event,
but um, not a problem for you. Uh, so
um, we are in Lexington, Massachusetts,
but we do have other locations across
the United States. Uh, one in Westford,
Massachusetts, another in the Marshall
Islands, as well as in uh, Nevada. The
um Milstone telescope in Westford,
Massachusetts was the first telescope to
see Sputnik go over the skies in 1957.
Sorry. Go. So, Lincoln, as I might have
mentioned or the slides might have
mentioned, is an FFRDC.
Lincoln is a federally funded research
and development center.
MIT has a contract with the Air Force to
run this FFRDC.
Um, what MIT does as a service to the
nation um is run this in a at a kind of
benefit to the public. We do this in the
public interest and we are very careful
to uh keep to a strict conflict of
interest policy with respect to our
industry engagement but that does not
prevent us uh from engaging with
industry. Um so what we don't do is we
don't compete with industry in any way.
We don't manufacture products. um we
support the development of new
technology when that technology doesn't
exist in the commercial sector. That's
very important to us um to think about
uh us not competing with industry.
Examining whether the commercial sector
has a technology solution already that
the federal government needs. If it
does, we will encourage the federal
government to adopt that existing
commercial technology solution.
So um
these are some of the facilities at
Lincoln. Uh we have a number of advanced
technology facilities that are available
to us companies to use on an as
available basis at cost.
um the we use what's called a test
agreement that would allow a company to
come in and say listen I need you to
process this particular thing or we need
to do this experiment and in that
fashion no intellectual property is
generated we're just following a
protocol and the service that we're
providing is to the US economy to help
us businesses get access to advanced
technologies that they may not otherwise
have um so Some examples of these
facilities include the Strive Center,
which is a biomechanical
um uh
infrastructure that reproduces any kind
of environment that you would be
interested in reproducing from um
climbing a mountain to what it would be
like to stand on a a ship to swimming.
Right? So that that's an environmental
uh reconstruction
um facility. Uh we have a supercomputing
center. We have a hanger that was given
to us by the Air Force where we can look
at autonomous um flights and drones and
and track their capabilities over time.
Uh we have a micro electronics fab that
we can use to help small businesses with
their needs. Um and we have an RF
facility.
So what does Lincoln really do? So what
we do is we look at uh America's
technology gaps, our needs and national
security and we help understand,
articulate and develop solutions for
that technology gap. um primarily by
understanding what the commercial sector
has to offer and if it doesn't have
anything to offer to work with the
commercial sector to bring that advanced
technology solution needed by the
federal government to the war fighter to
the defense uh industrial base and for
the benefit of the nation and so as an
FFRDC
um that is an R&D FFRDC we are capable
of rapidly prototyping a solution in a
matter of months to field and to
collaboratively develop with industry a
solution for the DoD bow uh base.
So
this is just an example of something
that we did um in Iraq and Afghanistan.
You can imagine when there was an
immediate need to understand kind of the
the the physical clearance of space and
so we needed uh the ability um to
monitor uh land uh at it you know at at
great distances. So um the
federal agency reached out and said hey
we need a root clearance system and we
need it now. And so what Lincoln did was
it worked with a couple of companies to
say, "Hey, what technologies do you
have? How can we accommodate the
technologies that you currently have so
that we can then support this fielded
need?" So we worked with these companies
collaboratively. We came up with a
solution and we tested that solution in
the field setting within nine months of
the ask. And after we developed the
fielded solution, the companies then
moved forward to create uh more units
for the federal government because we're
not allowed to manufacture products.
So um another thing that we uh do is
obviously we we look at um kind of
surveillance and one of the kind of
surveillance we look at is uh
atmospheric and so we uh with NASA uh
have developed technologies to look at
the atmosphere the water content the air
the turbulence and and uh monitor storm
development. So NASA had a storm
development satellite um it was called
ATMS advanced technology microwave
sounder that obviously used microwaves
for the detection. This satellite was
over 2,000 kilograms in weight. It was a
huge bus. And so in order to get the
kind of accuracy that you would need for
storm prediction, you need a you need a
lot of satellites and you need them to
make that rotation around the Earth with
great frequency. And so NASA said,
"Listen, how can we work together to
improve our surveillance capabilities of
weather?" NASA reached out to Lincoln.
And Lincoln took that tw 2,000 kilogram
satellite and shrunk it down to 5.4 kg,
something that you can really make lots
of to then have repeated flights over
the earth to understand global weather.
So when we did this, this is amazing,
right? But we're not actually going to
make uh hundreds of satellites for
anybody or anything that we don't
produce. Um and so we said how can we
tech transition this technology? So we
went to look out for a partner. The
partner that we found that had the most
immediate and compelling interest was a
weather data company was a data service
company and the data service company had
no engineering capability. But they said
listen our interest is in this space to
provide intelligent data uh for the
United States and for our customers to
make decisions for business support. And
so we thought that was a good
partnership. So we worked with a company
called tomorrow.io IO which is again a
data company um not an engineering
company and we said how can we partner
to make this technology something that
you can use not just for the benefit of
your consumer base but for the benefit
of the United States in its
understanding of global weather patterns
and so we partnered with tomorrow.io IO
um to create a right now a nine
satellite constellation that has between
a 60 and 30 minute revisit rate. Um that
company has um again was a data service
company. So the question is how do you
work with a data service company to
provide them engineering support. So we
entered into a creda uh commercial
research and development agreement and
we transferred that technology both in a
license agreement that allows them
intellectual property access right and
gives gives them the rights to use the
technology but for a data company that's
really not going to be enough. They need
to be able to understand how to
recapitulate that technology from an
engineering perspective. So, we worked
with them and handinhand with their
subcontractors
and their vendors. Um, we said, "Listen,
this is kind of what the supply list you
you would you should need. These are the
suppliers you should probably use. Let's
get into relationships with these
companies. Let's show them how to make
one and then we will be there when they
make the next one." Um, and so the
technology is transferred from our
making it to their making it all while
being uh carefully watched and helped
and supported by Lincoln's activities.
So this is how we imagine working with
industry. It's not enough for us to say,
"Hey, you need intellectual property
access. We're giving this to you. you go
off and whether you make it or you break
it or you succeed or you fail, it's not
our concern. That really doesn't help um
us as an institution supporting national
security
and looking for the commercial sector to
provide advanced technology solutions
for the nation if we allow those
companies to kind of not have that
technology transfer support. So what we
did was we entered into a a crater. We
entered into a license agreement. We
entered into a technology support
agreement. All of which allowed the
company to transfer that technology
successfully and then if they wanted to
work on V2.
Uh so another example um came when the
army uh was looking for a solution for
uncontrollable like deaths on the field
through hemorrhaging. So 90% of
hemorrhage related deaths on the field
can be prevented if you can catheterize
the wounded and you can and usually this
in a deep vein or deep artery. It's
really hard to do in a fielded
situation. Uh but if you can find that
deep vein or deep uh artery and you can
catheterize it, you can have a
therapeutic intervention that 90% of the
time will save the patient. So the army
was looking for surgical interventions
that would not require a clinical
setting. And so they came to Lincoln and
Lincoln used um ultra their ultrasound
technology and their AI technology to
create a solution set which is about as
big as you see there um that can
literally examine a person's leg,
determine where the vein or the artery
is, image it, and then find the exact
location to enter u the the catheter.
and it will tell you as the user of the
device that they found the vein or the
the artery and you literally push the
button to allow the catheter to engage.
It's an amazing technology that has
immediate benefits obviously on the
field but it also has immediate benefits
in you know domestic situations outside
of war.
So having you know created this
technology we were looking for a
solution set to get this productized and
uh we had a spin out of Lincoln and MGB
that was interested in developing this
technology show we're transitioning that
technology to the company again very
carefully through a technology support
agreement through SBIRS and STRs to
really help them recreate that
technology successfully.
So um this is you know we have seven
patents actually we have more than that
we have more than nine disclosures
so it's quite an IP portfolio uh but
again it's not about the licensing it
really is about ensuring that our
commercial partner can take that
investment of the American taxpayer and
make it real.
show another example of how um I want to
make sure I know it's it says 517 but I
guess that means five minutes left so
I'll make it quick. Um so another
amazing example of a technology
developed um at MIT and at Lincoln is
optical coherence tomography. Every time
you go to an optometrist and you put
your chin on the little holder and they
take a picture that's OCT. one person uh
one every second gets this assay, right?
Um so this was developed really by an
individual who was working on satellite
communication technology
and so he saw an application space in uh
doing optical um you know resolution and
uh moved ahead. Uh he and his MIT
partners started multiple companies.
They did spinouts. these were acquired
and this technology is available right
now uh for all of us. So really amazing.
Um we do a lot of spinouts. Uh we do
about two a year um and so we're very
accustomed to working with small
businesses and supporting their um
development of advanced technology
solutions for uh the DOW base. And so
these are the ways we work with
industry. Um we have just started a new
technology transfer office um whose goal
is to support getting that technology
into the hands of companies so that they
can manufacture and support the DOW
base. Um we do that through exclusive
licensing or non-exclusive licensing to
a company. Um but we we do want to make
sure that we support the government's
interests. So when we do the licensing
we will be thinking about what the
taxpayer and the US uh citizen is going
to best benefit from um as a result of
this licensing activity. Uh as I said we
do which are our novel R&D contract to
support collaborating with industry in
developing new technology. We do that
all the time. Um most of the time the
technology space will have a national
security implication but you can see
that if you're working in satellite
communications and you can develop OCT
the the space is pretty broad for
creating new advanced technologies with
industry that could have a huge impact.
Um, we also, and this is I think really
underutilized,
that anything that is supported by the
federal government is available for the
federal government to use
and thereby any company working for the
federal government under a federal
program for free. So, if you are
proposing a grant to the federal
government and you see that Lincoln has
the capability, there's no need to
recreate it. There's no need to license
it. there's no need to pay for it,
right? This is available to the
government and its contractors for free
under a government program. It's an
amazing kind of value ad uh for for the
government and the people who are
working with the government. And then I
spoke a little bit about our facilities
access and so we have advanced
technology facilities that are available
uh primarily to US companies um on an as
available basis but only to the extent
that that those facilities are not also
uh available through a commercial source
because we don't compete with industry.
And so just to um get through this and
get to the questions, these are some of
the ways we can work with industry and
these are some of ways we cannot. The
most important of which is if a company
is getting a federal uh pro is under a
federal program and they're getting
federal monies, we cannot be a
subcontractor to a federal program.
Okay. Um and so I would urge you to
learn more. We have laboratory
workshops. Each of our nine divisions
annually has a conference to tell
everyone what we are doing and how we
are doing it. Um we have industry days
where we bring industry to Lincoln so
that we can select an appropriate
transition partner. Um we're happy to do
tech technical exchange meetings and we
do this all the time with companies to
say hey what's going on in this
particular space. We have a catalog of
our capabilities published on our
website. Um we invite large companies or
companies who are interested to come to
Lincoln and give talks to tell us about
their capabilities and their interests
and obviously we we do publish and uh
attend conferences. So I'm just going to
go to the questions that disappeared.
Oh here they are. Um
so what are what is the best way for
companies to engage with Lincoln? Um
again it would be to understand that
there's a synergy of R&D interests and
then to reach out either to the person
that seems to be the technical contact
or reach out to me and um you know I
could potentially put you in touch with
uh the appropriate technical contact.
Has there been any impact, positive or
negative,
of government spending at Lincoln? And
have there been staffing cutbacks as a
result of federal funding cutbacks in
the last couple of years? Um, the
government and the administration as
they change from administration to
administration will have different
folky. And so Lincoln is uh it's
important to Lincoln to support the
administration that's currently in
office and their priorities will change.
And so our programs to support the new
administration uh our program directives
may change depending on what the uh
overlap is. Um what is the target time
frame for a project and how is each
project evaluated for the decision
makers to continue funding or
allocation? It's a really good question.
So Lincoln does shortterm, you know,
prototyping to meet an immediate need
like I I showed you for for um the
ground clearance uh robot and that was
nine months. Um and we do long-term R&D.
So the 193 nanometer lithography project
took 20 years, right? And so we do
everything in between from less than a
year uh to 20 years because you're
developing essentially brand new
technology spaces. So the target time
frame for a project is going to depend
on who the stakeholder is and what
they're looking for. And it's a really
important conversation for us to have as
we engage with industry to understand
what their timelines look like and how
we can support their timelines and their
objectives.
Uh does Lincoln Lab work with J5? um
uh you know uh we are primarily an FFRDC
and so our primary work is with um the
US government. So
um so I think that was it.
Oh, one more question. Um
oh great that's it. Thank you so much.