Episode
9. All there is to unlearn.
Old habits die hard. We have all
invested a lifetime learning with the
sole objective of trying to be right.
Often our jobs require that we be always
right and that we certify our expertise.
But in this new mindset, to even start
innovating, you may need to accept that
you are most likely wrong from the
start. It will take some unlearning.
Each video in this series introduces one
idea to help you wrestle with what you
may need to unlearn. The following ideas
extracted from the videos you have just
seen can help. One, I have hinted that
innovating is a process of exploration.
The difficulty with any kind of
exploration is keeping yourself honest
and open-minded. I find it useful to
remind myself that there's a few things
we humans are really bad at and some
that we are really good at. Here they
go. We're notoriously bad at having good
ideas in just one go.
We're bad at inventing something
entirely from scratch.
We are horrible at predicting the
future. And we're even worse at
remembering how bad we are at predicting
the future.
And then there is the things we are
actually good at. We are really good at
coming up with hunches.
We're really good at reusing stuff. We
excel at saying that something will not
work. And we truly enjoy storytelling.
Two, I invited you to let go of the idea
of fail fast and to replace it for a
pursuit of excellence. What I'm asking
you to do is to build companies and
projects that fail to fail.
Three.
I have offered you an alternative to all
the innovation entrepreneurship
frameworks that require you to settle on
the product and the user before you even
start. We spoke about prototyping
problems and advancing a portfolio of
solutions.
Four, we distinguish between focusing
and narrowing. You can focus on the
problem and keep a space of options
open. Your risk goes up if you narrow
your options.
Five. Our own garage story suggests that
there was a time in which we did not
believe that spending little by little
was how you founded big projects.
This may have important implications for
how you decide to fund projects going
forward. At the very least, it may help
calibrate the real risk behind the
stringing along projects with little
amounts of funding.
Six. There's many more ideas we only
touched on partially like how to create
value from the technology shelf,
repurposing technologies, other ways to
prototype problems, the difference
between precision and accuracy, the
curse of hindsight, and the true meaning
of scale up to name some. You can learn
more about many of those from the book
Innovating Ador's Manifesto or following
my work.
There is just this one idea I told you
about at the very start of this series
of videos that I would like to come back
to. We are sitting on a gold mine of
underutilized technologies. That's the
last video in this series.
[Music]