All right, welcome back to 61200. Hope
you all had a good spring break. Uh,
today and this week we continue our
segment on graph theory. Uh, going to do
more graphs. Today is undirected graphs
and next class will be directed graphs.
Uh but remember an undirected graph or
the full mouthful is simple undirected
graph is what we defined a couple
lectures ago. Uh we have a set of
vertices V. We have a set of edges E
vertices can be anything but the edges
have to be pairs of vertices and those
vertices have to be distinct. So the set
of edges is always a subset of this.
This would be the maximum possible set
of edges. you have the set two two item
set uv for all vertices u and v where u
does not equal v. Okay. So uh today I'm
just going to remove omit these
adjectives and just say graph but
whenever I say graph today I really mean
simple undirected graph. Okay and we're
going to walk around in graphs today. Uh
so let's define a notion of walk.
This is going to be similar to an
execution in uh state machines. Next
lecture will be even more like that. Uh
but for today uh a walk is a sequence of
vertices. I'm going to write that
sequence with arrows, but it's really
just a list.
It's a finite sequence, let's say, uh
where
each consecutive uh vi to vi + one is an
edge
in the graph.
So this was like a valid transition in
the uh state machine world.
Uh so this is like I = 01
up to K minus one
is when that needs to apply. Uh so if
you have let me draw a graph here.
It's one of the first graphs I ever drew
in my life. still remember it for
reasons we will talk about in a moment.
Uh here's a graph with five vertices, a
bunch of edges, uh and let me get a
color.
[Applause]
So for example,
this is a path
which is uh sorry is a walk which I
would write A to B
to uh D to E to B back to D up to C.
That's writing it with commas. You can
also write it with arrows. Same thing.
Okay, so that's an example of a walk.
And for some terminology, it would be
helpful. We're going to call this a walk
uh from
V 0 to VK. V 0 is just the first vertex
in the sequence. VK is the last
sequence. I'm defining what from and two
means. Uh and we'll define the length of
this path
to equal K. K is the number of edges in
this uh sequence not the number of
vertices. Right? Number of edges is one
fewer than the number of vertices. So in
this example we have one two three four
five six edges. So this is a length six
uh walk. Okay. In particular we allow
uh length to equal zero.
What does a length zero walk look like?
Well it's a vertex and that's it. You
just stay there. So like C by itself is
a zero length walk. E by itself is a
zero length walk.
Okay, not so exciting yet. Uh let's
define a related notion which is path.
This is a special kind of walk uh with
no
repeated
vertices or edges.
Okay. Uh so in particular not this path.
Uh this this is this walk is not a path
because it visits some vertices multiple
times. It visits B twice. You can see
that in a sequence. It also visits some
edges multiple times. B to D is
repeated. Uh so if I redraw this graph
uh an example of a path between the same
two vertices would be this one. This is
still starting at A and ending at C, but
now it's shorter and it doesn't repeat
any vertices.
Okay, in particular with walks, if you
don't repeat uh a vertex, you probably
also don't repeat an edge. But I think
it's helpful here to highlight we really
don't want to repeat vertices or edges.
This will get a little more subtle uh
when we talk about closed walks in a
little bit. Uh so why might we care
about walking in a graph? Lots of
practical motivations. Every time you, I
don't know, look up something in Google
Maps, you're finding a path from A to B.
uh maybe you want the shortest path or
the least uh energy path or uh so on. Um
so we care about paths a lot when we're
finding routes in transportation
networks. We care about them when we're
finding routes on the internet or any
computer network. Uh in both those cases
the vertices are places you can be and
the edges are the routes like the
streets you can take for example. Um, in
a social network, if the vertices are
people and the edges are friendships,
then you might care about like degrees
of separation between people, like a
famous uh experiment where they asked
people to send physical letters to
people they knew on a firstname basis.
This is like in the 60s, Mgrim uh and uh
they found that the distance between two
people is only about six. These days is
about five. We're getting more
connected, display more people. Uh
anyway, those are some motivations. Also
in things like uh the eight puzzle that
we talked about uh some time ago, you
can think of each of these
configurations as vertices in a graph
and the edges are transitions. And
because uh every time I I make a move, I
can also unmake that move. This is an
undirected graph, right? Everywhere I
can go, I can immediately go back. And
uh you might care about what does the
this graph look like? It's big. It's got
like a 100,000 vertices. So I can't draw
it here but you can kind of explore it
by by moving around. Can you get
everywhere? That's a good question and
that's the next topic. Connectivity is
one of the is what this lecture is
mostly about.
So let's talk about
connectivity.
So we'll call uh two vertices connected
if there's a walk between them.
Now, I'd like to say there's a walk
between them, which is sort of not
caring about which one you start at and
which you end at. Uh, but the way we
define walk is it's it's starts at one
place and it goes to the other. Of
course, if v 0 to vk is a walk, then
also vk backwards to v 0 is also a walk.
Like if I flip the sequence, if I
reverse it, uh it's still a walk because
edges are sets. They don't care about
which order you follow them in. So if
you can go from vi to vi plus one, you
can go from vi plus1 to vi in an
undirected graph.
Uh so this is equivalent to uh there
existing a walk
from v to u like it doesn't matter which
one you put on the left and which you
put on the right. These are the same
thing. Uh technically this is a theorem.
You have to prove it. And the proof is
just reverse the walk.
If I have a walk from U to V, I can
reverse it and I get a walk from V to U.
If I have a walk from V to U, I can
reverse it and get a walk from U to V.
So in either direction, uh these two
things are equivalent. And so we just
say there's a walk between U and V or we
say U and V are connected or V and U are
connected all the same thing.
Okay. Uh there are some other equivalent
properties to this. So I want to write
some more. Uh the other big one is there
exists a path
from VTU.
This is perhaps a good moment to
mention. So we're using words walk and
path here uh in one consistent way
throughout this class but there are
other classes such as the very next
class 6121 where uh this is called path
and this is called simple path. So just
a warning there's two sets of
terminologies for whether a walk is
allowed to walks can always repeat
vertices. Paths uh sometimes they can
sometimes they can't and in this class
they cannot. So we're going to use walk
to mean the general thing and path to
mean the specific thing where you don't
repeat any vertices or edges. Okay. So
uh I claim there's a walk from U to V if
and only if there's a path from U to V.
Let's prove this.
Um so remember how do we prove that two
things are equivalent? How do we prove
an if and only if? We do it in two
parts. We prove left to right and right
to left. So, I'm going to do right to
left first because this is the easy one.
Why is it I ask you uh if I have a path
from U to V, is there necessarily a walk
from U to V? Any suggestions?
Yeah.
A path is a walk. Path is a special kind
of walk. So, if I have a path, then
definitely I have a walk because that
path is the walk. So I would usually
write uh path
is a kind of walk.
So that's the easy direction.
The more impressive thing is that if
there's a uh a walk, then there's
actually not only is there a walk, but
there's a walk that doesn't repeat any
uh vertices or edges. This is trickier.
Um, and
I'm going to tell you how to find it
because it needs a a nifty idea.
But first, we write the template, which
is okay, we want to prove that if
there's a walk from U to V, then there's
a path. So, let's assume there's a walk
from U to V. And let's give it
uh I'm not going to give it a name yet.
Um, so there exists a walk. There might
be many walks. I want to try to choose
not necessarily a particular one but a
more restricted type of walk that's
possible because I know that these at
least exist. So I want to take a
shortest walk.
Shortest in terms of uh length. So
minimum possible length among all walks.
I want one of them that minimizes the
length of the walk. Okay, we know there
exists some walk. So there is some
solution here. Uh because you can't go
below a walk of length zero. There's
some shortest.
Okay, and this one I'm going to give a
name. Let's say it starts at U, which is
also called V 0. Then it goes to V1.
Then it goes to V2, and so on until it
reaches V K, which equals V. So it's a
walk from U to V.
using some number of edges in between.
Okay. But now I know it's shortest.
All right. Uh
so I claim
uh that this is a path from U to V. I
claim that there are no repeated
vertices or edges in the sequence. uh in
particular I claim that there are no
repeated vertices. So let's uh
prove the claim.
So uh maybe as a picture first. Um so
suppose that let's let's do it by
contradiction.
Let's suppose that uh the path
uh does repeat a vertex. So it starts at
u and it then it goes which is v 0 then
it goes to v1 and so on. Um maybe at
some point
uh after going for a while it comes back
to a vertex it's been to before before
proceeding to uh vk over here which is v
Okay, this is what a walk looks like
that repeats at least one vertex. I
claim this is a general picture, but you
can write it down in words. Um, then the
idea is, well, if if the walk did this,
I should draw this as a continuous path
in red.
If the walk did this where it repeats
this vertex twice, why not just do this?
That's a shorter path. And that
contradicts that we started with the
shortest path. If this path is strictly
shorter than this one, that's a
contradiction.
Write that down a little more carefully.
Um let's uh so for contradiction, let's
say that uh vi equals vj for some i less
than j.
So this would be both vi and vj are the
same vertex in this sequence. The vertex
gets repeated. That's a general
situation. I can assume I is less than J
just by reabeling I and J swapping I and
J if I need to. And now um the idea is
that v 0
up to vi which equals vj and then going
directly to vj + one vj + 2 and so on up
to vk
uh is a shorter shorter walk
from between the same two vertices still
from u to v and so that is a
contradiction.
And so that ends the proof of the claim.
And that ends the proof of this claim
that if there's a walk, uh, I can turn
it into a path. I take the shortest
shortest walk. And it turns out that
must be a path. Proof by contradiction.
Okay,
so a bunch of work there. But now, uh,
for connectivity sake, we can use walk
when it's convenient. We can use path
when it's convenient.
Okay, for connectivity, these two
notions are interchangeable. We can use
whatever is nicest. All right, let me
mention a couple other fun properties of
connectivity
over here.
Um, so this one walk from U to V versus
V to U is property we call symmetry.
And there are two other properties uh
that are nice to know. One is called
reflexivity
uh or or this is the reflexive property.
Every vertex is connected to itself.
Why? Uh because we allowed zero length
walks and paths starting at V and doing
nothing that is a valid walk. So that's
a walk from V to V. Um and another
useful fact
is transitivity.
Connectedness is transitive relation. Uh
if we have U and V are connected
and we have V and W are connected
then we know uh U and W are connected.
Why?
Uh this is a particularly nice uh proof
by picture. Please don't think that
proof by picture is a valid proof
method. But uh I'll tell you the words
in a second. Suppose we have U vertices
UV and W and there's some path from U to
V and there's some path from V to W.
Well then there's a path from U to W.
You just concatenate the paths
or concatenate the walks.
We could at this point we could we could
assume we had paths initially but when
we glue them together it won't be a path
anymore necessarily. It might be a walk.
There might be some repetitions here and
here. But for the easy proof uh just
take uh take two walks concatenate them.
Still a walk. Therefore you and W are
connected. Okay. Uh next week we'll talk
about these properties symmetry,
reflexivity and transitivity even more.
So this is kind of a foreshadowing of
that. uh but it lets us define uh some
cool concepts
uh about connectivity. So first we're
going to call a graph connected
if uh
u and v are connected
for all vertices u and v.
So we sometimes call this uh pair-wise
connected. Pairwise is a useful notion
when you have uh something that only
makes sense on pairs of elements but you
want it to apply to the whole structure.
In this case the whole graph not just
pairs of vertices. Uh then you just put
a for all over the two things and that
that would be pair wise connected. Uh
but it really doesn't matter how you um
connected is kind of a robust notion
because of things like transitivity.
Like in in an undirected graph, it's the
same to say that every pair of vertices
is connected as it is to say that
there's some vertex that every ver that
every other vertex is connected to
because of transitivity. We know if you
can get from A to B and from B to C,
then you can also get from A to C. Okay.
So this is sort of why connect
connectivity is the right notion.
Uh even more interesting is a notion
called connected components.
So
So uh maybe let me draw an example
before I define this carefully. So this
graph for example is connected uh from
every vertex you can get to any other
right let's draw a disconnected graph
uh I had over here somewhere
let's say h got this guy here and maybe
just a vertex and some edge
AB C D E F G. So this is one graph. It
has six vertices, four edges.
Okay? And it's obviously not connected.
There's no walk, for example, from here
to here or from here to there, B to F, C
to E, whatever. Uh, but it's still
possible to get from A to C, A to B, A
to D. So A can get to everyone in this
chunk. And that chunk we call a
connected component. So in this graph
there are three connected components.
These are the mutually reachable regions
of the graph. Okay.
So, uh to define that precisely, I'm
going to you introduce a new term uh
which is induced subgraph.
Okay. So what does induce subgraph mean?
Uh it's a it's a notion given one graph
it defines a a graph that lives inside
the original graph. It's a subset of the
vertices and edges. That's what subgraph
means. Uh and it's defined by a set of
vertices. So it's a subgraph induced by
a particular set of vertices. In this
case uh the vertex set is all the
vertices connected to v. This is nice
shorthand for saying uh give me all the
u where u and v are connected.
And as we said doesn't matter whether I
say u and v or v and u same thing.
Uh and the edge set is determined by
this word induced. When I say induced I
mean I just specify the vertices and
then I want all the edges that could
possibly make sense. So in other words,
I want to take um all of the edges uv
that were in my original edge set with
the property that both u and v are in my
new vertex set.
So for example uh in this graph if I
take the subgraph induced by a b c d
that means I take these four vertices
and none of the others and I take all
the edges that are among those four
vertices.
Uh so that would be three of them these
three edges a to b to c and b to d are
the three edges in my induced subgraph
abcd.
uh if I just take the subset f and g
these are all the vertices connected to
f say uh then my subgraph will just be
this picture with these two vertices and
one edge connecting them
so that's what induced subgraph means
and so in particular if I take the
induced subgraph for vertices connected
to particular vertex I get what I call a
connected component so this is one
connected component here this is another
one and this is another And those are
the three connected components of the
graph. And in general uh the connected
components
partition the graph.
Partition means in this case that every
vertex or edge
is in exactly one connecting component.
So everybody is represented exactly
once.
Okay, this is just a fact which we will
take as given. It in some sense follows
from the symmetry reflexivity and
transitivity of the connectivity
relation.
Cool. So that's connected components.
Again many motivations for connected
components. Uh you would hope that the
road network of North America uh the
continental let's say continental United
States is connected. probably isn't
because of some weird things uh
disconnected things going on with
Canada. Uh or you might wonder uh is the
state space of this eight puzzle
connected? Can you get from any
configuration to any other? Or we
already know the answer is no. We proved
you can't get from an even permutation
to an odd permutation. Uh so uh this
example happens to be even. You can see
the number of ver of inversions written
down here. It's always even. uh and uh
if I take any other uh permutation
that's even uh it turns out it's
possible to get there. We didn't prove
that. But we did prove is that if we
take a different configuration where the
number of inversions is odd, all of
these configurations cannot get to
they're in a different connected
component from this one. And so it turns
out the eight puzzle has exactly two
connected components. One for the even
permutations, one for the odds. Uh the
Rubik's cube for example, depending on
how you define it, has 12 connected
components. Uh there, you know, in
general, you might care about how many
different types of states there are for
a given puzzle.
All right,
so that's uh a brief tour of
connectivity. Uh the next concept is
uh maybe I'll start with
right now we're just walking aimlessly
from one vertex to another. Let's think
about closing a loop. What if I it's I
guess it's even more aimless. I started
a vertex and what if I want to come back
to the same vertex? This is what we call
a closed walk.
So if a walk happens to start and end at
the same vertex, if v 0 equals vk, then
we call it closed.
And so in particular, we could try to
apply the closed notion to a path. That
would be kind of nice. Uh
so and we're going to give that a name
which is cycle.
Cycle is roughly this is not going to be
quite correct.
Start with closed path.
Can someone tell me what would be wrong
with this definition? If I say okay I
want I want to close. So closed is an
adjective that means you start and end
at the same vertex. If I apply it to
path, that means a walk, let's say from
some vertex V to the same vertex V with
no repeated vertices or edges. Any
problems with that? Yeah.
Right. The one you start with is going
to be repeated because that's what we
wanted. We want the start and the end to
be the same. So there is no closed path.
Actually, there's kind of one closed
path, which is the path that just starts
at a vertex V and doesn't go anywhere.
That I also want to exclude. This is
this is not this is not what I want to
call a cycle. So, there are two things.
I want a closed path of length more than
zero. You're not allowed to just stay
where you are. Um, and I need to add
this exception
uh that
the first vertex equals the last vertex.
I don't want any other vertices to be
the same.
Okay, so this is now this is sort of a
correct definition except I'm not a big
fan of definitions with exceptions. So I
will write another equivalent and less
controversial definition which is let's
start with our notion of walk
and we want a closed one
and so that implies that the first
vertex equals the last vertex and we
want no other repeated vertices or
edges.
And whereas with walk it was or with
path it wasn't that big a deal that I
said no repeated edges because if you
repeat an edge you also repeat its end
points. So repeating an edge implies
repeating vertices but I put them both
in there just for emphasis. Here it
actually matters to say a path with no a
closed walk with no other repeated
vertices or edges. There's another thing
that I want to exclude which is suppose
I have an edge
and I get my red color
and I start at this vertex. I go to the
other one and come back. Okay, you might
say, "Oh, that looks like a length two
cycle." But it's not. I don't want to
call this a length two cycle and it's
not allowed by this definition because
it repeats an edge,
right? It doesn't repeat any vertices
other than the ones it's supposed to. It
start the sequence here is uh u v u like
an emoji. Uh
so uh there's no repeated vertices
except the first one equaling the last
one, but there is a repeated edge. And
so I don't allow this. So this is not a
cycle. So in fact in an undirected graph
a cycle has to have length at least
three. The definition says it has to be
at least one. But uh oh I probably need
of length greater than zero here again.
Okay cool. So uh
cycle is sort of the analog of path and
closed walk is the analog of walk.
Obviously it's the closed version where
you come back to where you started.
Cycle is the best analog we have to a
closed path. Uh and these are nice in a
certain sense which I want to talk
about.
So let's talk about
a notion which is
an oiler walk and then we'll get to the
notion of
uh closed walk.
All right.
So uh oiler walk is a particular kind of
nice walk that visits all of the edges
exactly once. That's the definition.
Let's think about uh graphs where you
can take a walk starting somewhere,
ending somewhere and visit every edge
exactly once. For example,
this graph
has such a walk. The first graph that I
drew. This is why I was fascinated with
it reading some Scientific American
article by uh Martin Gardner.
Uh, you can draw this graph without
picking up your pen. You pen down, you
draw, and then you pen up. And that got
all of the edges. Okay, I didn't draw
the vertices, but hopefully you can
imagine that. Maybe you should draw the
vertices first, and then you could draw
all the edges in one swoop. So, this is
kind of a nice notion. Um,
if you like drawing things with pen or
pencil or stylus, whatever. Um, it's
actually a very old notion. Um, it goes
back to Oiler. Unsurprisingly, this guy
Leonard Oiler, who you know from like
the number E, that's E for Oiler. Uh, in
1736, he drew this rather beautiful
diagram of some islands and bridges in
Kigburg, which then was in Germany, now
is in Russia. Uh, and it has a this this
place, the city is famous for very
beautiful bridges, as many cities are.
But this one has a lot of them and some
non-trivial interesting uh topology. And
so he he wondered the the question was
posed, can you visit all of the bridges
without any repeats? Seems natural,
right? And if you think about it, right,
this is the vertices are like islands.
The edges are bridges and you want to
visit all the edges exactly once. Okay,
so natural problem also if you're
sightseeing and just for fun because I
dug up this 1736 paper here are some
more beautiful figures from that paper
um thinking about all the different
cases. So he characterized and this is
like the first paper one of the very
first papers in graph theory. This
started the whole world of graph theory
that we're talking about is
characterizing when this is possible and
when it isn't. It turns out uh in this
original example it's not possible.
Today some of these bridges have
collapsed or been destroyed. So maybe
it's possible again. I don't know about
current day uh Kingsburg. But uh that's
what we're going to talk about now is
when do oiler walks exist?
Why was it possible for that house graph
but not possible for
uh
this graph
this is the complete graph on four
vertices and you can't draw this in a
single path. Why is my red chalk always
the farthest possible point?
So let's try. This will not be a proof
that you can't do it, but we will
shortly prove that you can't do it in
one stroke. So, I can go here, here,
here, uh, here, here. It's pretty good.
But I missed this edge.
This edge is uncovered.
And turns out it's not possible for that
graph. It was possible for this graph.
Even better would be uh
I guess in the case
in the tourism case let's go back to
Kingsburg for a second uh suppose your
hotel is in island A you start there you
kind of like to end at the same hotel
without having to repeat a bridge again
so that would be an order closed
And that we call an orther tour just
because that's more common terminology
for it. Uh so that's really you where
you start. So closed means that you
start and end at the same place. Orther
means you visit every edge exactly once
every edge of the graph. Okay. So that's
even nicer. Turns out that's not
possible in this graph.
If you look at it, I started at this
vertex here and I ended at this vertex
here.
And it's that was the best I could do. I
couldn't actually start and end at the
same vertex. If, for example, I added uh
another vertex and a couple more edges,
then it would be possible for me to
complete the tour like this. Okay. So
that the new graph I drew here with six
vertices instead of five. That one has
an oiler tour. The original one just had
an oiler walk. And this one has neither.
So how can we characterize which graphs
these are?
So we're not going to read or's paper.
It's in Latin. Bit hard for me to read.
Uh we'll
write our own proof. This will be the
main theorem of the day. Though we have
a fun topic afterwards as well. Uh so
first let's think about the tour case
that turns out to be cleaner. So graph
has an oiler tour
if and only if it's connected.
That's certainly necessary because we've
said it should visit every vertex. Um
you don't have to include this as part
of the definition but it makes the
characterization cleaner.
Uh and we also need that every vertex
has even degree
for an order two or for closed walk we
need every vertex to have even degree.
Let's check that in our examples. This
graph remember the degree of a vertex is
how many edges are incident to it. So
the degree of this vertex is
three. degree of this vertex is three.
This graph is symmetric. So all the
vertices have degree three. Three is an
odd number and not even right. Uh in
this graph, this is degree two. This is
degree four. This is degree four. So far
everything's even. Uh this one is degree
three. This one is degree three. In the
original graph, if I add this dotted
part, then I convert this into degree
four and degree four and degree two down
here. And so then all the vertices have
even degree. So it seems to be working.
But let's not do a proof by example. Uh
let's prove it in general.
Okay.
So uh again this is the top level
statement here is an if and only if. So
we need to prove each direction
separately. Let's start with the easy
direction which is left to right. So if
I have an oiler tour
uh let's give it a name. Consider
an oiler tour
uh v 0 to v1
to uh v k and vk equals v 0
right that's because it's a closed walk
all right now I want to look at
uh
let's basically count
uh edges is
incident
to vi or some vertex.
I think that's unnecessary sentence. Let
me rewind.
Uh let's look at
each visit.
uh vi -1
to vi
to vi + 1
uh
to a vertex vi. So uh in this path I'm
just looking at a a little piece of the
path of two consecutive edges from vi
minus1 to vi to vi + one. And I'd like
this to work even with wraparound uh
because this is a closed tour. We start
at V 0 and we end at V 0. So, you know,
we do some stuff
and then we end up back at V 0.
Uh, so I'd like to just consider three
consecutive vertices on this tour.
Sorry, the wrong directions this way.
Including possibly V0. So to do that I
want to treat this modulo
uh k + one I guess and this also modulo
or no modulo k actually
because k vk equals v 0. So if I work
modulo K with these indices and for
every vertex I look at the one previous
possibly wrapping around to VK minus one
or VI plus one possibly wrapping around
back to V 0 uh then this is a well-
definfined notion for every vertex on
this visit. Okay, when I look at this
that visit to vi
uh in partic that's visiting a vertex
and it also includes or visits uh two
edges
incident to vi
sort of what goes in must come out. So
if I'm looking at a vertex here, VI,
this is the previous one.
No, this is the previous one. VI minus
one to VI + one. Uh by visiting VI, I
visited one edge coming into VI and I
visited one edge coming out of VI. And
so that's two. And maybe this path
visits this vertex VI again as some
other vertex VJ. But every time it
visits a vertex, it visits two edges
incident to it.
Okay, so that means the total number of
edges visited is going to be even
because I just keep adding two and then
two more and two more. So total number
of edges
uh I guess visited
edges
incident to to any vertex
must be even.
And how many how many edges incident to
that vertex do I visit? Well, all of
them because an oiler walk has to visit
every edge exactly once by the end. So
this total number of visited edges
incident to a vertex, that's exactly the
degree of the vertex.
It's exactly the total number of
incident edges. So this shows that if
you have an oiler tour, all the degrees
must be even.
Okay, what goes in must come out. It
also has to be connected just because it
has to visit every vertex. And so by
visiting every vertex in particular that
is a walk between any pair of vertices
or you take pieces of that walk and you
can go from any vertex to any other.
Okay. So that's one direction. That's
the easy one. Let's do the hard one.
[Applause]
And although I won't be explicit about
it, this proof also in some sense gives
you a strategy for finding these tours.
They're not too hard to find.
Okay, next page.
So now we want to go from right to left.
So we get to assume
that the graph is connected
and that all the vertices have even
degree.
Say all degrees even.
and we want to show that the graph has
an oiler tour.
Okay, for this proof,
so there's one clever idea and then the
rest is just mechanical. Um
whereas before in this proof that I just
erased, in order to convert a walk into
a path, we took the shortest path,
shortest walk, and the shortest walk
ended up having to be a path. For oiler
tour, we kind of want to do the
opposite. I want the longest walk that
doesn't repeat any edges. The longest
walk that doesn't repeat any edges. That
turns out it will visit every edge
exactly once.
Uh so for that it's maybe useful to
define another term which is trail.
We're really not going to use this much
in the class so feel free to forget it
other than in the context of this proof
which is a walk with no repeated edges.
So in other words, it visits every edge
at most once. And then we're going to
take the longest trail. So subject to
every edge being visited at most once, I
want to visit as many edges as possible.
And that turns out it will be an oiler
walk.
Okay. So let's uh
take the longest trail in the graph
and I'll call it t
and it's going to say start at vertex v
0 go to v1 and go to vk.
Okay, I need to prove two things about
this trail, right? In order to be
an oiler tour, it has to be oiler. It
has to visit every edge exactly once and
it has to be closed.
Turns out it's helpful to prove closed
first. So first claim
is that
this trail t is closed.
All right.
So we start at V 0 we end at VK closed
means that V 0 equals VK.
So if we do let's do a proof by
contradiction.
Uh suppose
V 0 does not equal VK.
Okay. Okay. And I want to get a
contradiction which basically means that
somehow I want to show the trail was not
actually longest in that case.
So again we have some we we start at V 0
we do some wiggly path and we end at VK.
And supposing these are different.
I'd like to claim that I can make this
walk longer. In particular, I claim that
there's an edge out of VK that I haven't
visited yet, which means I could extend
the path by one.
Okay, that's my claim. And I'm going to
do that by counting the edges at VK. How
many have I used?
Very similar to this proof actually.
So VK, so this is another sequence from
V 0 to VK except now we have not equals
at the end. So let's think about all the
visits to VK by this. I should really be
pointing at this. So here's VK. We know
there's a visit at the end. Possibly
it's visited in between. Maybe some of
the VI equal VK. We know V 0 doesn't
equal VK, but some of the others might
be. Every time I visit one of those, it
looks exactly like this. In other words,
I visit two edges incident to VK.
So uh let's say for every uh vi that's
equal to vk uh we visit
two edges
incident
to vk.
So that's an even number in total.
Uh this is for i not equal to k.
But then there's this last visit at the
end and there we this one is special
because we stop there's no edge after VK
because this doesn't loop around. So
there's an edge before coming into VK
but none after.
So that means uh
I guess uh for I equal K for that visit
to VK we visit
one edge
incident to VK.
So in this trail how many edges incident
to VK did we visit? an odd number
because we had an even number for all
the earlier visits and then we had one
more at the end. So even plus one is
odd.
So that means uh t visits
an odd number of edges
incident to v.
But we assume that the degrees are even
and that means there's at least one more
edge, right? We assumed
here all degrees are even. So in
particular VK's degree is even and so
that means uh there exists an edge
incident to VK not uh visited by T.
But then we can extend
T.
uh it can it can go uh in from v 0
uh up to vk and then plus whatever one
more edge.
So if I call this edge here uh VK comm,
VK plus one because I haven't defined a
VK plus one yet. Then this will become a
strictly longer trail
because that edge wasn't visited before.
Uh but now it is. This is a longer
trail. Contradiction.
What did it contradict? I assumed here
that v 0 does not equal vk. So in fact
we learned that v 0 equals vk. In other
words, t is closed. So I've proved this
claim. I haven't yet proved the whole
thing I want. So at this point I've
proved
that my walk is closed
but I still need to prove that it's
oiler. Those are the two things I need
to show.
So let's do that next.
[Applause]
All right. So, second claim.
This will be the last one for this
proof.
So t visits every edge.
I'm going to give it a name uv
in the edge side of the graph. So uh
this is what I want because by
definition because I started with a
trail it has no repeated edges. So it
visits every edge at most once and this
is saying that it visits every edge at
least once
and therefore it it in fact visits every
edge exactly once and that's definition
of oiler. Okay, so that's what I need to
prove.
Again, proof by contradiction.
Not sure why, but today has lots of
contradictions in it.
Seems to be the easiest way. Uh suppose
not, this is the very concise way to say
suppose that it doesn't visit some edge
UV and E. I'll write it out. uh
doesn't
visit
some edge
uv E.
Okay, again I want to get a
contradiction to uh t being the longest
trail. So I'm going to somehow try to
make t longer.
So it doesn't visit uv but you know it
visits some stuff v 0 to vk. So, let's
try to connect them together.
So, we've got here's uh the edge UV
that's not covered. And then uh over
here we have V 0
some crazy path. Can we revisit vertices
and whatever? It's a walk. Sorry, I keep
saying path when I mean walk to VK. Oh,
actually at this point we know that VK
equals V 0. So, it it ends where it
started.
But somehow it doesn't use this edge. It
might use these vertices, it might not.
Uh, but what I'd like to do is connect
V to V 0, which is also VK.
Why can I do that?
How do I know? I claim there's a walk.
Yeah,
because we assume the graph is
connected.
Uh way up here, assume connected. That's
part of this characterization. So when
we're going from right to left, we get
to assume the graph is connected.
Therefore, all pairs of vertices have a
walk. So in particular, these two
vertices have a walk. Now, it's not part
of the trail. It's just another walk. So
this thing over here is T. And this
thing I'm going to call W.
Okay. So let's write down some words. Uh
G is connected.
Uh so there exists a walk
w
uh or sorry the notes I called it x I
guess x for connection
from v to v k.
Okay.
Um
I think I really want this to be a path.
don't mind.
We know for connectivity sake this is
the same thing. If there's a walk,
there's also a path. So now let's assume
furthermore this is a path
in particular because I want it to be a
trail. So I don't want it to repeat any
edges. Uh
and a path won't repeat vertices or
edges. So that's a little better. It's
even better.
All right. And I'm going to give this
path some words. So it starts at V which
we're going to call X0 and then it goes
to X1 and so on to
uh
XL I guess which is V K.
It ends it ends at VK which is also V0.
Okay. Now I claim I can make the path
longer.
Sorry. I can make the original trail t
longer as follows. I'm going to start at
U. I'm going to go to V. I'm going to
follow X.
And now I'm at the loop.
And then I want to loop around. H. That
doesn't quite work because plausibly
some of the vertices along X here.
Maybe there's some vertex here which is
actually on this path. Sorry, on the
trail T.
I want to give this vertex a name. So
the whole path is called x. This vertex
I want to call x sub i.
So let's uh
let x subi which is also some v subj
uh be the first
vertex
of x that's on
t.
Okay. Uh, you know, we start at some
vertex. It might it may be the very
first vertex v is actually on t. So then
x subi is actually x sub0.
But we know eventually we get on to t
because the last vertex on this path x,
this is the path x. We know the last
vertex is v k and that's on t.
Okay. So somewhere along the way, could
be the first vertex, could be the last
one, could be anywhere in between, we
intersect T,
and that's going to be my path. So I'm
going to start at U, go to V, follow X
until I reach T. And now T is a is a
loop, is a closed walk, and
I'm going to follow that walk as it was
before.
I wish I didn't draw this quite so long.
exactly what I had before. This is
exactly the same edge as I had before or
walk. So, we can stop here. I claim that
this red red walk that I drew is a
longer trail. Why is it longer? Because
it has this edge now, UV, which it
didn't before. And it has all the edges
we had before. Maybe it has some more
here, but it also might not. Maybe these
two vertices are the same. But we got at
least plus one here. and we visited all
the edges we had before and uh because
of the way we chose xi all of these
edges were not used before. So it's
still a trail.
Uh and so I guess what do I write? Uh u
to v uh which is also known as x0.
Uh then we go to x i. x i equals uh vj.
And then we go to VJ + one and so on
around T. I in the notes I wrote it
explicitly. You go from VJ up to V K and
then you loop around and you go from V 0
up to V J again. And that will be uh all
the edges we had before.
Uh, so it's longer
and it still be a trail because we
didn't uh all the edges that we added
were not in the original trail t and
because we assumed a path here, there
weren't any duplicate edges within x.
And so I think we're good. And that
proves uh a contradiction
because we assumed that t was a longest
trail. Therefore, t actually visits
every edge in the graph. It also visits
every vertex at least once just because
the graph is connected. If you visit all
the edges and your graph is connected,
then you definitely visit all the
vertices. Okay, so uh that proves this
theorem. Any questions? A lot of details
there. Uh it's one of our bigger proofs,
but it's pretty cool.
All right. Uh let me this was Oiler
tours. You might also wonder about oiler
walks.
So we've now shown in particular that
this graph with the extra vertex here is
indeed orarian. I mean I also drew it
but we now understand why
when I remove this vertex not all the
vertex degrees were even. Two of them
were odd. It turns out that's the right
answer.
So uh correlary remember means a theorem
you can prove from the previous theorem
or follows fairly easily. Uh so I claim
that a graph has
an open
oiler walk.
Open here just means not closed.
So we've already characterized the
situation of closed or their walks.
That's this theorem. That's the or tour.
Uh so what's left is to characterize
when there's an open order walk where
you start and end at different vertices.
So let's ignore let's suppose that we
don't have a closed order walk but we do
have an open one. I claim this is
possible if and only if the graph is
connected as before
and exactly two vertices
have odd degree.
Intuitively
those odd degree vertices are where you
start and where you end. If you look at
this example with this erased
um I started here which had degree
three. I walked around and I ended here
which also had degree three. So the the
odd degree is essentially to compensate
for starting and ending at those
vertices. And that turns out to be all
you can do. So if you have a graph with
all even degree vertices, then there's
an oiler tour. And if you have a graph
with two odd degree vertices, uh then
there's an oiler walk. If you have more
than two uh odd degree vertices, like
here there's neither. What if I have one
odd degree vertex?
Yeah,
that's impossible.
That's impossible. What are you talking
about? because the number of odd degree
vertices is even. I think you probably
showed that in recitation. Okay, so or
even lecture I don't forget follows from
the handshaking lema from lecture. Uh so
those are your options.
Cool. Uh let me sketch a proof of this
and then I want to um go to the last
topic which is trees.
So uh I want to the the easy direction
as before if you have an oiler walk
you're still connected and if you do the
counting right you can see the number of
degree two vertices should be odd
because
uh it's just like this proof but now
it's not symmetric. We can no longer do
these things modulo okay which was
really nice. every visit look the same
because now there's a f there's v 0ero
and vk are visited in a different way
from every other vertex and just like we
said before the last vertex uh the last
visit has only one edge coming into it
so that makes this one odd and the first
vertex has only one edge going out of it
so it makes that vertex odd so this is
sort of easy
proof is in the notes if you're
interested uh the interesting part is
the other direction
uh I mean this is
roughly as before.
Okay, let's suppose that we have exactly
two vertices of odd degree. I want to
claim there's an open oiler walk and I
want to do it without repeating this
giant proof. That's a lot of work to I
mean you could repeat it and be more
careful and you can prove the oiler walk
thing but in fact there's a way to
convert this problem into the oiler tour
problem. So I'm going to do it by
picture. Suppose you have a graph and
you have two vertices U and V which are
odd
degree.
Maybe they're also just odd in general,
but they're odd degree. Uh, and now I'm
going to modify the graph. I'm going to
construct a new graph G prime. So this
graph that I drew is G
here. And in G prime,
I'm going to add a new vertex X and two
edges from U to X and X to V.
Why did I do that?
Because now all the degrees are even,
right? In G, the degree of U was odd.
And in G prime, it's one larger. So now
it's even. Same for V. And X has degree
two. So now everything's even. So that
means uh G prime has an oiler tour
by the previous.
So that was I don't have to repeat the
proof. It just I can apply the theorem
as a whole. And now I want to convert
this tour
uh
into an order walk in G.
How do I do that? I just erase these two
edges. Okay, the oiler tour visits every
edge in G prime exactly once and it's a
loop. So in particular at some point it
crosses over let's say from U to X and
then it can't go back along the same
edge because you can't repeat edges. So
then it has to go, let's say it goes
from U to X to V or it might go from V
to X to U at some point in the
in the closed walk, right, in the tour.
Um, and when it does that, I want to uh
instead in instead of going uh from
somewhere to U to X to V, I'm going to
start at V and then I'm going to keep
going along the tour until I get back to
U.
And that will include everything in the
tour except for uh these two edges. And
so that actually will be an oiler walk
in G. So I maybe went a little fast
there, but hopefully that's fairly
intuitive. This is a very powerful idea
called reduction where you take your
problem that you want to solve and you
convert it into a problem that you
already know how to solve. So we already
we just solved oiler tours and now we
wanted to solve open oiler walks and we
could do it by adding augmenting the
graph a little bit applying the theorem
and then we need to make sure that what
the result from that theorem is actually
good enough for what we need. We can
convert our order tour into an order
walk. Uh but because tours are are
cyclic in nature you can sort of rotate
it to start at V, keep going and visit
everything and end at U. Cool. So that
also proves that you start and end at
the two odd degree vertices in G, which
is nice.
Questions.
All right,
let's go back to
back to trees.
So we talked about walks, paths, cycles,
connectivity, order things and last
topic is trees.
That's a very sad board.
[Applause]
Uh, I guess now for something completely
different. Now we know how to draw
graphs without raising our pen. Uh,
define something called a tree, which
you've probably heard the word tree many
times in the past. Not just nature
trees, but also computer science trees
are all over the place. Like your
directory tree, your I don't know, there
trees everywhere. If you've done any
data structures, you know about trees,
tree data structures.
So what is the mathematical notion of a
tree?
It's a graph. It's and again today uh
we're always simple undirected graphs
and trees always require that. Uh it's a
graph that is both connected and as
cyclic. As cyclic just means no cycles.
What's a cycle? It's been a while.
Remember, a cycle is a closed path of
positive length. So, it doesn't repeat
any vertices or edges except that the
very first vertex equals the last
vertex.
Okay?
So, if there are no cycles, there's no
way to do this, then we call it a tree.
And some examples of trees
Sure.
Just a path is a tree.
This is a special kind of tree we call a
star. One vertex connected to a bunch of
things. In general, it looks something
like this. Okay, this if you've seen
computer science trees, these can be a
little bit different. Uh, so the only
thing requiring here is that they're
connected. So this is a tree. This is a
tree, but together this is not a tree.
It's actually what we call a forest.
This would be a forest with three trees
in it. Uh or individually, these are
each a tree graph.
Okay. Um
let's prove some properties about trees
because they're so useful,
just nice to work with.
In particular, there's a very useful
notion about trees called leaves.
You can guess where this came from
from real trees. But uh the idea is a uh
it's very simple. Just a leaf is a
vertex of degree one. You can apply this
to any uh graph. Sometimes you have
vertices degree one, sometimes you
don't. But trees have leaves. Shocking
news. Uh so this is I'll call it the
leaf lema.
It's not quite true that all trees have
leaves. Uh you know they have to start
growing for a little while first. Uh
and in mathematics this is every tree of
um I guess width is better
at least two vertices
has at least two leaves.
So as long as your graph as long as your
tree is not this graph. Okay, maybe I'll
add it to my list of examples. These
were all trees. Also, single vertex is a
tree, but it doesn't have any edges and
has degree zero vertex. No degree one
vertices. Okay, so other than this
exceptional case, every other tree has
at least two leaves. Okay, where are the
leaves in these graphs? Uh, here's a
leaf. Here's a leaf. Here's a leaf.
Here's a leaf. This one just has two.
This one has a whole bunch of leaves.
Okay,
let's
uh
sketch a proof of this llama
which is a familiar technique. Take a
longest
something. In this case, the something
is path. Okay, remember a path is a walk
that doesn't repeat any vertices or
edges. So, I want to take a longest path
in one of these graphs. For example, uh
if I take this, this turns out to be a
longest path in this graph. It's length
four. I believe you cannot find a path
of length five. Here you can find walks
that are arbitrarily long, but paths you
can only find length four in this
particular graph. I claim that the first
vertex and the last vertex in that path
must be leaves.
So ends
must be leaves
and they must be distinct.
Okay, why are they distinct? Well, uh
this is a path and path can't repeat
vertices. So unless the path has length
zero, uh the start vertex and the end
vertex are different. Okay, it's not
length zero basically because we're not
in this case. In this case, there's no
edges. You can't follow anything. But as
long as there's at least one edge, then
you know there is a path of length at
least one. And so the start vertex and
and the end vertex will be different.
And furthermore, I claim they must be
leaves. Basically, if this wasn't if
this vertex didn't have degree one, so
there wasn't just this one way to exit,
there'd be another edge incident to that
vertex. And then you could have made a
longer path. So a contradiction.
Okay, I'm going to call it there. And
you can read the notes for more details.
And instead I'm going to tell you what
you can do with these leaves. Why are
they useful?
Every tree except the one vertex tree
has a leaf.
And if you've ever taken care of a
plant, you know sometimes it's useful to
prune the plant. Grows better. In our
case, pruning is a very useful
operation.
that lets us use induction.
We've seen some inductions for graphs
and trees are really nice to induct on
because they have leaves to trim.
So this is a theorem for any leaf L in a
tree T
minus L is a tree.
Okay. What what is T minus L? This is
the graph
induced by
uh all the vertices minus L.
So in other words, it's the graph you
get if you take the tree and you clip
off the leaf and its incident edge.
This is that's the negative version. The
positive version is you say I keep
everything except L
and I take all the edges among those
vertices that do not include L. that
will end up having uh let's call this t
prime. Uh the number of edges in t prime
is going to be one less than the number
of edges in t. And the number of
vertices is also going to be one less
because we removed one vertex and one
edge. So here's our tree. Uh here's a
here's a leaf. This whole picture is t
and this inner picture is t prime. Okay,
this is a leaf L.
So T prime or T minus L is this smaller
thing. Okay, useful thing in general. If
you remove a vertex from a graph, you
also remove all of its incident edges.
Okay, so this is a thing which is pretty
easy to prove. Uh if because what we're
saying is suppose that T is connected as
cyclic, the claim is that T prime is
also connected and a cyclic. And you can
just show um that that's true. It's not
very hard.
Again, see the notes.
And what this enables to do together,
the leaf lama and this tree pruning lema
let you do induction over trees in a
really nice way. So let's argue let's
see an example of that with something
called the size of the tree.
Any tree
with n vertices
has n minus one edges.
Always.
If you look at these examples,
the one vertex tree has zero edges. The
four vertex path has three edges. The
six vertex star has five edges. This
thing has one fewer edge than vertices.
I won't count.
So, there are three kinds of
mathematicians in the world. Those who
can count and those who can't.
All right. So, I'm the latter kind.
So, finally we get to an induction. We
haven't done induction all day. It's
terrible. Finally, we can do induction.
Um, so we're gonna remember whenever you
do an induction over graphs, you're
really just doing regular induction or
strong induction over numbers. And so in
this case, we're going to induct over
the number of vertices in the graph. So
our induction hypothesis is this that
for a number n, p of n
is this statement that any tree with n
vertices has exactly n minus one edges.
I should write exactly here.
Okay. And we're going to prove it by
induction. So we probably need a base
case.
What is the smallest possible thing that
n can be? Uh one. Remember we forbid
zero vert vertex graphs. You have to
have at least one vertex to be a graph.
So in n equals one that means there's
only one graph with n equals one and it
has zero edges. Great.
My my vertex looks a lot like my number
zero. Sorry. Um okay. So let's do the
induction step. Now we're going to use
all of these beautiful lemas that we
have about leaves.
So let's suppose that n is bigger than
one. In other words, n is at least two.
And therefore, the leaf lema applies. It
says if you have n at least two, you
have at least two leaves. I actually
only need one of them. Uh but let's say
by leaf lema
there exists a leaf and let's call it l.
Okay. Now I'm gonna apply this pruning
this tree pruning lema that says if I
now I have a leaf I can remove it clip
it take the a new graph T prime which is
everything in T except L.
Okay. So by tree pruning
T prime which is T minus L is a tree.
Not only is it a tree, it's a smaller
tree.
It has exactly n minus one vertices.
Okay. So I can apply induction
because when in our induction step we
get to assume that this property is true
for all smaller n that's strong
induction in particular it's true for n
minus one that's weak induction. Uh so
by the induction hypothesis
uh we know that t prime
uh has
uh one fewer edge than vertex and it has
n minus one vertices and so it has n
minus2 edges
and t prime was everything in t except
for one edge that measly edge connected
to l.
So uh t has
one more edge than t prime.
So it has uh n minus one edges and
that's what we needed to show.
Okay, this is very nice for inducting
over trees. Uh the idea is if you have a
tree, you're going to do induction, you
should take a leaf and prune it. Usually
that's what you want to do. Sometimes
it's useful to know there's two of them.
You could take any vertex and remove it,
but if I took a vertex in the middle of
my tree, it might disconnect into
multiple trees and then I have to do a
lot more work. By choosing a leaf, when
I remove it, I guarantee I'm still a
tree and so I can still apply induction.
It was very helpful. Uh that's uh lots
of fun things about trees. Um it turns
out the reverse is true. If you have any
connected graph with one fewer edge than
vertex, it must be a tree. Uh trees also
have unique paths between any two
vertices and any graph that has unique
paths between any two vertices is a
tree. Uh other fun things like they're
the
minimal connected graphs or maximal
asyclic graphs. Lots of fun properties
which you can find in the notes or the
textbook. That's it for trees. Next time
we'll do directed graphs.