Right.
So this here is just to make sure that
you at the right place. This is uh 18
100B
or uh 18
uh 0 uh 100 uh and two.
Um and my name is Toby. So Toby coding
and uh by so we will be uh recorded uh
and the video from the lecture will be
posted online
uh and I will also write uh lecture
notes. I hope you appreciate it because
it I wrote the first one. It actually
took me quite a long time. I don't
typically uh type the lecture notes but
I will do this for this class. Um and I
also wanted to just give you an idea of
the structure. First of all, this is one
of the most important math classes at
MIT.
Uh and I'll tell you in a minute why it
is important. And of course I think that
being one of the most important math
classes is one of the most important
classes period. uh but um right but so
just to give you an idea of what's uh
the what will be expected from the class
so there would be uh 10 weekly homework
uh and the first one
the first one uh will be due it won't be
due next week it will probably be due
the week after next week and the and in
part it just allow you to kind of get
settle in a bit. But also um I'm waiting
for somebody else to assign the TA and
the graders. So it will be I think it
will be at least one graduate TA and
there will be some undergraduate uh uh
TAs and then there will also probably be
some graders and uh and most of these
including myself will have office hours
also. So it'll be 10 weekly weekly
homework.
There will be a midterm. So one midterm
and one final.
And the midterm is on March 20th.
And the the final u is uh I don't know
when it is. it's uh I'm not the one that
is uh deciding the date and it would be
a while before we know what date that
will be.
And so and in terms of the grade uh the
homework will count for 50% of your
grades. Uh midterm will count for 20%
and the final for 30%.
And you can see all this information
about this uh in there's a syllabus and
a course information posted uh in on the
Canvas. So right so make sure to check
out the Canvas site
for the class and there's also the
information about the book and also the
lecture notes will be posted on the
Canvas site. The lecture notes I think
will probably be posted on the files. So
lecture notes
uh will be posted under files
and one other thing is that uh that I
have activated what's called pet
partners
Right. So you are encouraged to uh to
work with other people on the pets but
you have everybody have to hand in their
own pets. Okay. Uh and and pet partners
is a way of finding uh other people uh
to work with. I mean of course you can
do it another way but but this is a tool
that is used in in a lot of classes.
Okay, I think this sort of covered the
basic information
and so the class here is so um the the
the two key topics for this class is so
key topics
uh is uh one is to uh you will learn how
to write
uh a mathematical proof.
So what does it mean to to to write
something so that it's kind of ma
mathematically rigorous and the second
thing that you will learn is how to
prove themsel
of this
that suppose you have a function.
So suppose you have some interval. So a
and b are real numbers and you have a
function f
defined on this interval
and they take real values
and so here you have the interval here a
here's b and assume that the value at
let's say that the value at a is
negative and the value at the other end
point b is positive right so you have so
if You sort of were drawing the graph.
Here you have a maybe here you have b
and then the function initially is
negative and it end up being positive.
So this is f of a here you have f of b
and then this function here is
continuous.
So the function sort of looks maybe like
this.
Um so f is continuous. So the
intermediate value theorem say
so there.
So the intermediate value theorem
value theorem
it say the following that if you have a
continuous function on an interval then
it takes all values in between. Right?
So the intermediate var say in
particular that there exist
a c and the c here is between a and b.
So that the value of the function at c
is zero right because the function start
off negative and it end positive. So
there must be somewhere in between where
it hits zero. Right? That's the
intermediate value. Right?
But now the question is then how do we
make this into right? So and and it's
kind of obvious. It's sort of
intuitively obvious that if you take a
function, right? Continuous just means
continuous means um something like that.
If you were drawing the graph then and
you have this like piece of chalk here
then then as you're drawing the graph
the chalk is not allowed to leave the
paper, right? It can't have a function
like this here that sort of jumps. So go
like this and then you jumps like this.
That's not continuous. Right? This here
is not continuous.
Right? So continuous function is like
that you have to when you draw it it's
like in one motion the chalk doesn't
leave the the blackboard. Right? And so
it seems obvious that there should be
some point in between where the value
where you're crossing this axis here.
But how do we make this into a rigorous
proof? Right? And what is the property?
Right? So how do we make this into a
proof?
[Applause]
So how do we
make this
intuition
into a proof,
right? And this is not just sort of a
semantic question. It's not just a sort
of crazy question.
Maybe in this case it sort of seemed
clear but very quickly if if your
foundation is not totally rigorous then
you get into something where it seems to
be the case but it might not be the case
right and it's also very difficult to
then you know it's quickly that's where
you arrive and you also quickly arrive
to that you don't even know whether it
should be the case or not right and so
it's really important to kind of build
things up step for step where each step
is totally rigorous and you um right
because it it's it not only uh you know
for sure that things are right but it
also makes it much easier to predict
what should be true
and so in order to to understand
uh why there should be some uh c between
uh a and b where the value is zero.
it immediately it's the first thing the
first question that arises what are you
using what property do we need to make
this into a proof what property do we
need of the real numbers right so this
is like the first question that arise so
what property
uh are we using
of the real numbers,
right?
And so in fact, what is the real
numbers, right? So what are the real
numbers?
Um and and so the thing is that
in particular you what you know
what is square root of of two. So what
is square root of two?
Square root of two.
Right?
And is that a real number?
Is square root of two a real number.
Right? So those are some of the
questions that you immediately get to.
And so now but so the answer to what are
the properties that you're using of the
real numbers. So the answer to this
question here
is is the following. And
[Applause]
so the answer to this question is so
what are the property of the real
numbers that you're using?
So the answer to that is the following.
uh that we that the real number so r
is a complete
ordered
field
uh that contains
the rational numbers.
the rational numbers Q and denote the
rational numbers by Q and the real
numbers by capital R.
So that is the to in order to make this
proof this this proof of the the to to
make this the intermediate value theorem
this property that if you have a
interval from a to b you have a
continuous function on that interval and
it start off negative and it ends
positive that then there is some value
in between where zero is achieved in
order to make that rigorous
what you're using about the real numbers
is that is complete ordered field that
contains a rising number. So we need to
understand what this here means right
and I will I will in this lecture here I
will not explain complete I'll do that
at a later lecture but we will
understand the rest of of of of what is
in what what are these properties that
we're using. So just first some
notation.
So first some notation
the natural numbers.
So the natural numbers.
So the natural numbers here
and this here is
one two three four five etc. Right? So
these are the natural numbers
uh the integers.
So two uh set here these are the
integers
and the integers are simply the natural
numbers but then it also allow them to
be negative and it also includes zero.
So this is 0 plus or minus1
plus and minus 2 plus and minus three
etc.
These are the integers
the rational numbers are then so the
rational numbers Q.
So these are numbers of the form m / n
where m here is an integer
and n here sorry yeah m is a integer and
n here is a natural number
that's a rational number
and so now what are the properties right
so in order so we're building up to
trying to understand what property of
the real numbers is. But let's try to
somehow understand a little bit better
what are the property that we really
have about the rational numbers.
So for rational numbers we have right so
we write a rational number as a quotient
like that right but of course there are
many ways that you can write a quotion
right so so property of the rational
numbers
so We write it as a quotion like this.
But this is not uniquely defined. Right?
There are you know if you take a quotion
like this you you think that this here
is equal to another quotient
right? Again, sorry. Again, m1 and m2
are integers
and n1 and n2 are natural numbers.
Two quotients are the same, right? If
and only if
right that if you multiply this over
here and this over there, then those
numbers are the same. So m_sub_1 *
n_sub_2 is equal to m_sub_2 * n1. Right?
Those two rational numbers are the same
if and only if those two natural numbers
are the same or integers, sorry,
integers, right? Because m is could be
negative. Right? So
right. So this is so again a rational
number it has a representative like this
but it's really kind of always you could
think about it as always you can write
this quotion right and two quotients are
the same if and only if this is the
case.
So this is what it means to be a
rational number.
uh but then there are some some
operations right if you have two
rational numbers then you can add two
rational numbers together right so and
that's really important that you have
some operations on the rational numbers
so if you take
this here is
this here is one rational number and if
you Now take another rational number
m_sub_2 over m_sub_2.
Uh then how do you add two rational
numbers together? Right? Well, of course
you know that you put it on the common
denominator. So this here is m_sub_1 *
n_sub_2 plus
m_sub_2 * n1 / n1 * n2. Right? This here
gives you this here is a integer in the
denominator and this is a natural number
in the denominator. Right? And so that's
a representative of a of a rational
number. Right? So that's an operation.
Now
in order to to really know that this is
all right. So the idea here is that if
you take one rational number
like this and you take another rational
number like that
then you can add them and that gives you
another rational number. Right? That's
that's that's this operation that we
know so well and is addition. Right?
In order to for this really to make
sense, you should check that this that
this that this
rational number you get is independent
on the representation. Right? If you
have another representation for the same
rational number and another
representation for the same rational
number, then when you add them, you
should get another representation for
the same natural number. rational
number, right? Um, okay.
And we'll check uh one of these things
in just a minute, right? The other thing
is
that um
right so that was one operation, right?
When you have the the the rational
number, then addition is one operation.
Another operation is of course
multiplication.
So
so another operation is multiplication.
And so
[Applause]
and so if you take one rational number
like this
and you take another rational number
like that, then if you multiply them
together, right? So what does it mean to
multiply two rational numbers together?
Well, of course you know this very well.
It's just multiplying the denominator.
So that gives you a integer and then
multiplying the denominator that gives
you a natural number. So this here is a
rational number.
Okay?
And then there's another thing. So this
is addition.
This was addition. This is
multiplication.
But there's another important
property that you have for the rational
number and that is an ordering.
Again, we're trying to understand this
question up there. We just trying to
understand how do we make the
intermediate value uh theorem? How do we
make this rigorous? And so we need to
understand what property of the real
numbers we we we need. And so this is
explained in this and we were working
towards trying to understand the
different concepts in this. What is a
field? That's what we're trying to
understand.
And so so we have addition in the
rational numbers. We have addition. We
have multiplication. But we have another
operation on which is an ordering. So if
you take a
If you take a a rational number here,
then you can say that this rational
number is less than another rational
number, right? When is it less than
another rational number? This is
equivalent. You're saying remember that
the that these here are natural numbers.
So they're positive. So that this
rational number is less than that just
means that m_sub_1 * n_sub_2 is less
than m_sub_2 * n1 right
here I'm using right I'm just
multiplying over here over here right
and I'm using of course that these
numbers here are positive
okay so this is an ordering so in the
rational numbers there is actually
ordering. Okay, so that's really
important also. Right. So we have these
two operations and then we have an
ordering. Okay.
And so here is so
right. So here is so let me just check
right. So I said that when we talked
about addition right when we talked
about addition here then there was
something really you had to check that
this even made any sense right and if
for this to make any sense means that
that this rational number you get from
adding these two is independent on how
you write this rational number and how
you write that rational number and the
same for multiplication.
So let us check that.
So
so this here is checking
that
multiplication
is a well- definfined
operation
I
it is independent
it is uh independent
uh of the
the representative
So, so we are multiplying we take this
rational number sorry write a little bit
bigger this rational number. So this is
one rational number
and we multiply it uh by we multiply
this rational number uh by another
rational number let's call it p1 comma
uh q1
and then we take another representative
for the same rational number and let's
call this m2
m2 and for this rational number. We take
another representative
and we want to prove that this here is
the same, right? This number here is the
same as that number here. Right.
So, how do we do that?
Right. So we have that this here and
this here is the same this two different
representation of the same rational
number. So we have that m1 / n1
is equal to m_sub_2 / n2.
So this just meant that remember that
this just meant that when you multiply
over here like that then you get the
same integers. So this here N2 plus
N_sub_2 * N1 right that's what it meant
that these here were the same and
likewise you have the two rational
numbers here this is one this here is
equal to that P2 / Q2
this just meant that when you multiply
over P1 Q2 is equal to P2
uh Q1
Right?
So this just meant that these that these
two represent the same rational number.
These two represent the same natural a
rational number. And now what we need to
prove is that the product here is
independent of these of these
representation.
So the product here
is so we need to prove the product of
the first
uh right the product this product here
this product here this is just m1 * p1
divided by n1
* q1 and we want to show this is what we
want to
that this thing here is the same if we
took this other representation and
multiply by the other reputation of
this. Right? So this is M2
* P2
M2 * Q2 that's what we want to prove
that those two are same.
And so we need to prove that. So we need
to show
that M1
P1
times this denominator here N2
Q2. Right? We need to prove
need to show
that this thing here is equal to N2
P2 N1 Q1. That's what we need to prove,
right?
But now let's let's see. So we know that
if we take
um if we take m1 right if we take
m_sub_1
and together with n2
right m1 together with n2 this is the
same as so this here is the same as
m_sub_2
n1 right this is what this here saying
Right? And it also say that if you take
P1 together with Q2, then you may as
well write this thing here. Right? So
you may as well write P2
Q1.
Right? So this thing here is equal to
that. But now you see that here you have
M2, here you have N1, here you have P2,
here you have Q1. So those two are the
same. Right? So this proves that this
operation of multiplication is well
defined in the rational number right and
similarly for addition. The reason of
course why I chose multiplication is
that it's looks a little simpler on the
blackboard right it's a little more
messy if you did addition but that's
really you know it's just exactly the
same.
Okay. So
um
right so now um so now and then so this
is also supposed to illustrate you know
how detail a proof is right that so you
know when we have a concept like this we
want to make sure that it really makes
sense right and in this case makes sense
that it's well defined it's independent
on the representation
and so the proof here this here would be
the proof.
Um, okay. So now, so now, so, so the
takeaway here at the moment is we're
building towards this with understanding
a field. We want to understand the the
real numbers. But the takeaway at the
moment is
that on the rational numbers, there is a
way of adding two rational numbers and
multiplying two rational numbers. And
there's also an ordering. Okay.
And so this leads us to to um the
following definition.
And so this is the definition of a
field.
So a field
And I will use uh f here capital f for
for a field
uh um is the following.
So it's a set
with two operations
and the operations we are denoting
suggestively by. So the two operations
are denoted suggestively by plus
and
and and
and uh and and multip like a
multiplication like a dot right so and
but these are this is just abstract
right so we have a set and we have these
two operations
what property do these two operation
need to have they each of them have five
properties and then there's a so that
means that there are 10 properties and
then there's 11 property that chain
those two operations together. Okay. So
let's start with addition. So properties
of addition.
So the first property is that addition
make any sense. So if you take a element
in the field and you take another
element in the field
then addition gives you a third element.
So when you add these together this is
just a third element in the field.
So this is the first property that it
really is an operation that when you
take two elements of the field then you
get another element in the field. So
this is one. Uh the second is
um that if you add two elements together
so x and y are in the field if you add
two elements together then the ordering
that you're adding it is is is is
irrelevant. So this here is the same as
y + x.
Then uh then the next one is this is
sometimes called a billion or
commutative this property here. Then
there's a third property uh which is
that if you add two elements together
and then you add a third element
to the sum of these two then this here
is the same as that you can add the last
two first
and then add the first one to the sum of
the other two.
Okay.
and
[Applause]
um
right and so the fourth property is that
there is a what is sometimes referred to
as a neutral element. So there is uh
there exist
an element
uh that we denote by denoted by
by zero but it's just to to make it kind
of easier to understand that we denote
it by zero and it has a property having
the property that has a property
that if you take this zero element and
you add it to any other element
then it just gives you back that other
element. So it's kind of neutral for the
operation.
And then there's supposed to be a fifth
property and the fifth property is that
for any element
X there exist
another element
and again we s we write this
suggestively by minus X with a bracket
around like this.
So there is another element with a
property
that if you take X and you're adding
this other element
then you get zero.
Okay. So those are the five properties
that addition has to have right and then
multiplication have to have five
properties also and it's these are
similar to this with a little twist
uh and so so
for multiplication
you need to have the following
properties.
So again it's five properties. The first
one is is the similar property to the
property one up there. Namely that if
you take two elements X and Y in the
field
then
when you multiply them together that
should give you another element in the
field. Right? So that's the first. The
second one is similar to true up there
is that x * y should be the same as y *
x.
So again that's often referred to that
it is a billion of community.
The third property is
that it's similar to the third property
up there is that if you take X time Y
and then you multiply it by a third
element, then you could as well have
first multiplied the two last elements
and then multiply by the first element
like that.
And then the then the uh the fourth
property is similar to that property
four up there
is that there exist
an element
denoted by denoted suggestively
by one here
with a property that one times any
element x
just give you back that element x.
And then the fifth is similar except
there's a twist slight twist.
Uh
and so the fifth property is
that
but it's very similar to that fifth over
there. The fifth property is the
following.
The fifth property here is that they
exist that for any
for any
uh x in the field
except
zero. You have to disregard zero. For
any other element there exist
there exist an element
and again denoted by suggestively
denoted by
by one of x with a property
that x* * 1 /x is equal to 1. Okay. So
those are the five properties for um for
addition, five properties for
multiplication. And you see that they
are like you know the one for
multiplication is like a mirror of the
one for addition except the fifth one
has this that you have to to look away
from the zero elements. Right?
and and then there is a right and so
again this is this is just one is just
that it is an operation two is usually
called the billion property or commutive
property this is called the associative
property this is called it's often also
referred to that's a neutral element and
this here
um that exist this element in this case
minus X is sometimes called the inverse
uh and and likewise for for
multiplication and then there is again
an 11th property and that's a property
because you see that those at the moment
is basically no interaction between
these two operations. The only way that
you see some interaction but this is
very little is that the fifth property
over here refer to the neutral element
for addition right but they don't really
chain the two operations together and
that is the last property that is often
referred to as a distributive law. So
this is a action
chaining
uh addition
write like this addition
uh together
uh with multiplication.
And that is that
that if you take x and you multiply it
by y + c
is you take this sum here and then you
multiply by x. That is supposed to be
the same as where you first multiply x
with y and then you add when you
multiply x by c. So this is often called
the distributive law. Okay. And that's a
law again or action that is chaining
these two operations together.
Okay. So now let's try to see
um let's try to see. So, so let me just
establish just one little property of a
field.
And you see like that
when we talked about
when we talked about the the actions for
addition, right? I just said that there
had to exist one element that we call
the zero element and it had to have some
property. But maybe there are many
elements, right? And so this is the
first field theorem
for any field
any field I I just write it as capital
field but it's just to kind of but you
don't really have to uh for any field um
f
uh there exist
only one
one z sure z sure z sure z sure z sure z
sure z sure z sure z sure z sure zero
element
okay now let's try to prove this
and again you know I'm um I'm trying to
I mean I mean there's all kind of
important concept in this class but
there's also there's also um the thing I
mean another thing that is important to
learn and usually uh and you have to be
a little bit patient because it will
take you a little bit of time to learn
it. Um is how to write a mathematical
proof
and so this here just gives you just a
little bit of idea of it. So we need to
we want to prove that there exist only
one zero element. So we have so assume
so assume
that
01 and O2
are both
uh zero elements,
right? So, so this means that so this
means
that if you take 01 that is a zero
element just means that if you take 01
and you add anything to it right x could
be anything in the field then you get x
back right that is that 01 is a zero
element that O2 is a zero element just
mean the same thing that if you take
anything in x then you get x back
Now we want to prove that 01 is equal to
O2. So I just write 01 plus O2. But now
I'm just thinking about this O2 as my X.
So I'm adding 01
to this X. So I know that I'm just
getting this here back. Right? That is
because 01 is a zero element. But I
could do the same with O2 that I take
and the ordering I know already is is
irrelevant, right? Whether it's 01 plus
O2 plus 01, that's the same. So I can
take I can think about this 01 here as
my X. And so I'm adding the O2 to it,
right? But then I know that I'm getting
this here back, right? So this here must
also be equal to 01, right? And so you
see that 01 is equal to O2.
And of course in the you know in the
notes uh in the in the notes that are
post things are kind of written slightly
more rigorous. I mean you know it's I
mean there's a little bit more
there's a little bit more meat to it.
Here I write it a little bit shorter on
the board but so so look also at the
notes.
Okay. So now we so so now we know what a
field is right. So a field again it has
these two operations additions and
multiplication. Each of those operations
have five property and then there's 11
property that chain those two operations
together.
And so the examples of a fields is
so we already have an example.
So the rational numbers here is a field
right. It has these two operations and
with all the 11 properties
the natural numbers is not is not a
field
it's not a field
it fails even the most basic
I mean it fails many of the properties
it needs but it fails that even the zero
element is not in it right of course
it's not even a yeah it's I And it
so and the integers here
is also is not a field.
It's not a field
that is
slightly closer to being a field but
it's still not. And why is this not a
field? It's for multiplication. Right?
If you take two then by two if you think
about two then there should be right the
the neutral element for multiplication
that's a usual one right but if you take
say the element two then there should be
an element like the inverse there should
be an element with a property that if
you take two and you multiply with with
that element then you should get one
right that should be the inverse element
right? One over it. But this is like a
half, but you're missing a half in the
in the integers, right? So that's why
this is not a field.
Okay. So the next concept is so we're
again we're working our way towards
trying to understand what property of
the real numbers that we need in order
to make that the intermediate value
theorem. uh proof rigorous
and so
so so we have now we now know what a
field is next time I'll talk about
or the next few times I'll talk about uh
complete what that means but but um but
we also have this ordering so what does
it mean that a field is ordered So, so,
so let's start with an ordered set.
So, an ordered set. So, this is a set
is a set
denoted by a capital S. And it has a
property that whenever you have two
elements in the set
then it should either be and the
ordering by the way. So an order set
with an ordering
and I denote the ordering again
suggestively by this. I could have used
any other symbol but I'm just
suggestively using this symbol just to
kind of make it easier to remember the
property you know it's like this sort of
property that you know so well
so an order set
is a set with an ordering
and again denoted by this so that if you
take any two elements in the set then
one of the three properties should hold.
The following three property should hold
[Applause]
should.
One is that uh so either x should be
equal to y.
Two the other possibility is that x is
smaller than y or three y is smaller
than x.
So basically if you have an order set
whenever you take two element you should
be able to compare these two elements.
Of course, these two element could be
the same elements, right? But if they're
not the same elements, then one should
be smaller than the other, right?
So that's the idea.
Okay. And so now uh the next concept is
uh an ordered field. And so again,
now we need so so now we have
a field and we have an ordered set. So
an ordered field
is a field.
that
is also
uh an ordered set
and then the operations from the fields
and the ordering they should be they
should speak to each other right so
there should be an interaction between
these two operations
uh so it has to have with the following
properties
with the following properties
that if you take
if you take if uh so it's finding two
properties that if x is less than y so
and you adding a uh c to both so if
you're adding so this here implies that
for any
set in in the field
uh if you add the sets to both sides. So
x + set is less than y + z.
So you should have you should be able to
add something to both sides and it does
it's still less than
like that.
And the other thing is so this is this
here is how how do the ordering
interacts with addition and the other
thing is how do it act interact with
multiplication
and there the property is that if you
take a x that is positive
and y is positive
and y and y so you have both x and y
that are positive
Then the product of these two should
also be positive. Right? So then this
here
the product of the two should also be
positive. Right? And so this is how how
do the ordering interact with
multiplication. Right? This is how it
interacts with addition. This is how it
interacts with multiplication.
Okay?
And so now
now uh well the first thing you observe
is that again you already know an
example of this.
So um
so the rational number of Q here
is an order field.
Right? We've already seen that it is a
field has those 11 property. It has
addition multiplication has each of
those are fine property. It has the 11
that chain the two together.
And we also discussed the ordering. If
you take two rational numbers, what does
mean that one is less than the other?
Right? It has the property of an
ordering that you can compare any two
elements, any two rational numbers that
either they are the same or if you have
two, one is less than the other.
Um
um and it also has this the additive
property, right? and also the ordering
interact with addition in this way and
it interacts with multiplication in this
way. Okay. So the rational number is
indeed an ordered field. Okay.
Now let me just establish one last
property.
Uh and that is that um if I take
[Applause]
so let me try to prove a little theorem
here.
Um so so
here's the theorem
that so we have uh so f here is supposed
to be an ordered
uh field.
Uh and then we have that x here is less
than y.
uh and
and uh and and C here is is positive.
Fine. So I I assume I have this and now
I want to show that then I claim that
from these properties uh that order
field have I get automatically then uh X
* C is less than Y * C. So I claim I get
the this property here right that you
know from the these properties over
here. Okay. So let's try to prove that.
[Applause]
So what I want to do is I want to so so
we want to show
that x * set is less than y * z.
This is what we want to show.
Now to say this here, right? This here
is equivalent. This is equivalent
to showing
that right. So if you take this you
could because this here if you if you
take if you add minus y * set sorry if
you add sorry if you take this thing
here
and to both sides so you take x + time
set and then you plus
- x * set
then this here is the same as by this
here that to say that this is less than
that is equivalent to saying that this
thing here
right why is that equivalent but this is
this this law here that is chaining the
ordering together with addition right
and this here this element here is right
this is just the the inverse element of
this product here.
But now you see that these two things
together that just gives you zero,
right?
This thing here,
this thing here is this here is the same
as um as x. Okay. So, we need to maybe
we need to show this, but this here is
not hard to believe that this this here
is the same as uh y * set minus uh x *
set. So, this here is now you can factor
out. So, this is this law, the 11th law
that allow you to factor this one out.
So this is the same as y - x
* 7, right? This was this distributive
law. That was the 11th law.
But now you see that because y was
bigger than x, right? Since
y here
was bigger than x, this here was
equivalent to saying that this is
equivalent to saying that y is bigger
than x, right? If you subtract
um x on both sides, this is equivalent
to saying that y - x is bigger than
zero. Right? This is again using the
first action over here, right?
And so you see that now we have that. So
we want to prove we want to prove that
this thing here right we this here is
all equivalent to proving that this
thing here is bigger than zero right the
claim up there is equivalent to proving
that this thing here is bigger than
zero. Right? But the difference here
this difference here is positive. This
is assumed to be positive.
The second law that is chaining the
ordering together with multiplication
say that if you have something positive
and you multiply by something positive,
you're getting something positive,
right? And so, so in order to prove this
here, it was the same as proving that
this thing here is actually positive and
we have now just reduced it to this
second action.
Is is that clear?
Okay, that's really so we go just a
little bit easy here in the first
lecture. This is this is what I have for
the first lecture, but there's a bunch
of different concepts.
Uh and again,
um feel free of course to ask any
questions uh on the class. Um I
typically just linger around for a few
minutes afterwards if anybody have any
questions after the class and we will
also have office hours. I'm just waiting
for the assignment for of the TAs. So
that will be put all on online right and
um yeah okay let me know how it goes but
and one more thing is that this again
this I mentioned before but so my
experience is that it takes people a
little bit of time to get a hang of this
with writing proofs so don't be
discouraged you know you know a few
weeks or months into the class things
will really turn around and and it will
all make sense and and then it will be
more fun also.
Okay.