The following content is provided under
a Creative Common License. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> All right. So, uh this is our first lab
session for CMS 608. And uh for folks
who who wasn't here last Wednesday uh
this past Wednesday.
>> So one two
>> who wasn't
>> who was not here on Wednesday.
>> Yeah. And then you guys So you weren't
here. Um let's see. We have some blank
index cards underneath the uh the
plastic Tupperware.
>> So if you can just fill in your name,
your email address or favorite board
game or card game. Uh the email address
basically just gets added to the email
list. Um did anyone not get an email
from Jason this like yesterday?
>> Yeah, last night
>> you didn't get an email. I don't think
so.
>> Okay. So
>> uh the email basically said that there
was a swap
>> uh of um Friday the 17th
>> and the 20th. So we're basically
swapping the readings around. Uh and uh
that's that's that's really the only
thing, right? Oh, and I fixed the link
for Zimmerman's article.
>> Yeah. And unfortunately, Eric Zimmerman
didn't migrate his website terribly
well, so all his pictures are broken.
This is
>> a pity. But I actually have one of his
games, uh, Cifi 3000. Um, in fact,
this is like before CI5 3000. So, the
CIFI 2,999, which is going to be the
non-digital version, uh, which is the
whole point. Um, it is actually a
computer game. It's actually a pretty
decent flash multiplayer game. uh back
in the day when flash multiplayer games
were not that common. And uh if you
haven't played it before online, uh
after today, if you especially if you
had a chance to play with the the
cardboard the the card deck, uh try out
the online version, do a Google search
for 65 3000 and try it online.
Hopefully, you'll be able there are
still people playing it because you need
kind of like a minimum of five people to
be able to get a good good.
>> Oh, suck. It was such a pretty game.
Okay, never mind. You know, um it's uh
basically what you had were you got
avatar customization in the games. You
could create your character and you
could um you had this really cool retro
pixelated uh look back in the time uh
back in the day when retro pixelated
stuff was not that popular yet. Uh but
uh the gameplay was is pretty much
exactly the same as what a card game
has.
Okay. Um
the readings today basically uh covered
a lot of uh jargon uh that we're going
to be going through. We're going to be
using a lot of that for the rest of the
class. Uh for the most part, I'm not
going to go through every single one of
them because for the because you folks
can read and if you if we mention
something and you don't get it, you can
always check back there. So just
remember that that the that first
chapter in breath has is a pretty good
glossery of terminology that we're going
to keep using. Um, but uh, one of the
big things that they ask is what is a
game? And, uh, it's one of those,
does anyone actually want to offer their
pet definition of what a game is?
>> Go for it. A game is something that
involves uh, players in a set of defined
rules beforehand. rules that you have to
abide by whether they be you can't uh go
outside it limits you have to abide by
certain uh you have to do certain
questions certain orders something that
has structure that is meant for one
person to go from point A to point B
>> okay structure rules limits players
anything
>> it's fun.
>> It accomplishes some goal.
>> He always has some kind of goal.
>> Are you working towards something?
>> Anything else?
>> Always an abstract system. Often an
abstraction of some system.
>> An abstract system.
>> Um
so so these these are actually pretty
good uh uh pretty good benchmarks. Now
there there are again as Brenda
describes there isn't one that's just
the canonical answer for everything. It
really depends on which theorist you're
reading at any given time. Uh but
usually they will involve a significant
subset of all of these uh in the
definition. Um, and I kind of like to
keep things broad and vague because for
the most part, um,
by if you if you define yourselves too
strictly, it might be useful if you're
an academic and you need to write papers
about it. But if you're a designer and
you're just trying to create something
fun, uh, or the word I would prefer to
use is engaging because, you know, fun
means a lot of different things to a lot
of different people. Engaging, you know,
basically means that this is going to be
something that you're going to want to
do for a while. uh that that is
motivating. It might be terrifying you
out of your wits, you know, but some
people enjoy that uh you know or will
find that experience compelling, but
they may not call it fun. Um so so I I
call that engagement. Um the problem
with using fun and engaging as a metric
for defining what a game is is that that
means that a bad game is not a game. uh
a game that fails to achieve fun, that
fails to be engaging, you know, is not a
game. But I will I wouldn't go that far.
Uh largely because that means a lot of
stuff that I've created is not a game.
Um but but you know, it should give you
the the the the you know there is no
magic point where your game becomes
where the thing that you're building
becomes fun and then suddenly becomes a
game you know. Uh I can imagine someone
making that argument. is like it's not
the game until it's fun. But uh I much
rather sort of say fun engagement is
kind of more of a metric of how
well-designed your game is, not
necessarily
whether your game is a game. Um but you
know what but but but that is a goal of
a game designer to try to create a a a
engaging experience. Uh something that
people are going to want to do. Um there
are I know some game designers who think
that is not in fact their job. um their
job is to maximize revenue for instance
especially if you work in social games
uh that there's a lot of discussion now
in how business and game design is
basically just one thing now you know
the whole point of game design is how do
we get people to pay a little bit more
um Zinga is going to be on town by the
way on September 30th and giving a talk
uh so that has those two points
>> so Um, so I I will sort of coordinate
this out there as something that you
that you're working towards, but all
these other things, you know, um, a game
should have players. Uh, again, I don't
want to be too strict on that because
I've certainly seen games that play
themselves and um, anyone here involved
in battle code that that game pretty
much plays itself, right? I mean you set
it going and then someone one side wins
but no there's no human person at least
during the time when the game is
actually being played or you could argue
that a whole course of uh of battle code
for those people who don't know it's
this IP course I believe where uh core 6
students basically write bits of AI to
play a realtime strategy game against
some other team's AI and uh the basic
idea is that you know if you win a real
time strategy game your AI wins but
there's no human actually playing it at
a given time. But of course there are
humans writing the AI. So if if you
think of the entire class as a game uh
then there are players there are people
um there are I have certainly seen
people make a case that there are games
that are zero player and uh and I've
heard um for example there's a game out
there called Nomic which is largely a
game about coming up with rules and um
and there are there is a system which
are actually in the rules themselves
about how you change rules and you And
um of course those rules themselves can
be changed. Uh and and that changes the
way how you change rules. And by the
time you actually play the game,
someone's already won because somebody
in the game has no legal moves. Uh
that's that's the whole game. It's
basically making it impossible for
someone else for someone else except for
you to win. Um so does that game
actually have players? Well, yes it does
because you guys are arguing over who uh
all the rule changes, you know, and
through uh through the rules of the
game. But in a sense, it had no players
because the game never actually got
played. The the the rules are basically
stating, you know, this is an unplayable
game for everybody but except for one
person uh in the in in who's playing the
game. Um
goals. Goals are one of those things
that I used to be very very adamant
about like like a game had to have a
goal. You you have to know what you're
going towards and and if you don't have
that then it's a toy or something you
know it's a dollhouse. It's an
experiment. The Sims was the one that I
was like railing about when I was in an
undergraduate. Um you know that's not a
game. Um and of course my uh uh um I was
working with many colleagues and
eventually came across uh came over to
the site that it doesn't matter whether
I think it's a game or not. If it's in
the game shelf of Best Buy, it's a game.
So, you know, because people think it's
a game. And if enough people think it's
a game, then it might as well be a game,
you know, because otherwise what what uh
uh uh because that's what people think
it's going to be. So when when when you
come up with your game,
I would say that goals are one of those
things that helps steer player behavior.
So and it gives it's one of those tools
that you have as a designer to basically
say this is important, this is not.
Reaching the end of 100 meters is
important for a sprinter. Um that that
end is really not interesting for you
know somebody who's running 400 400
meters or 50 meter dash. Um but uh that
gives someone a direction for them to go
towards. But there are plenty of games
where you have to invent your own goals.
Can other than Sims, anyone can think of
any
where inventing your own goals is kind
of the fun
>> RPGs.
>> A lot of MMO RPGs have have that they
have goals. They have quests, but you
know that's not where a lot of the fun
is.
>> Second life.
>> Second Life. A lot of virtual worlds.
>> Game like Eve.
>> Uh Eve. Yeah. I mean Eve. if if you you
you kind of want to you like you have to
set your own goals, right? Because
whatever's in the game is only good
enough for like a single player to uh to
to tell whether a single player whether
they're doing well or not.
>> But the Eve is not about a single
player. Eve is about what thousands and
thousands of people playing
simultaneously.
>> Um
um actually have people heard of Eve?
>> Okay. Right. So yeah. Cool. Cool.
>> I stopped the development.
>> Oh, cool. In Iceland. Yeah.
>> Was it like really cheap when you went
over there? Could could you have bought
the entire studio?
>> No.
>> Unfortunately.
>> Yeah.
>> It was really cheap.
>> Yeah. Like months ago.
>> So they must have been making tons of
money because Yeah. They're making money
in US dollars and
>> euros.
Yeah. They probably hire most of Yeah.
support most of the economy.
>> Icelandic economy.
>> Yeah.
>> The capital is 20,000 people.
Yep.
>> Um
so um so I would say goals are very
important tools and as a result of that
you see them in a lot of the games and
you know uh for most of the games that
you guys are going to be building. Yeah.
Uh you're going to give a very clear
goal of this is what you want to do.
Earn a certain amount of money. Uh
prevent your opponent from doing
anything else. you know, uh, take over
all of the land, that sort of thing. Um,
let's see.
Well, I'll get to rules last. Um, but,
um, systems are, um, I might already
have mentioned this in the last class,
but, uh, games are systems in a way that
most MIT engineers would think of
systems. you know, they're a bunch of
interconnected little modules, all of
them with sort of predictable behavior,
and then you put them into a big
interconnected system, and it is no
longer really all that predictable
anymore. Um, at least that's the kind of
games that we're interested in this
class. There's also the game theory
games where like the whole point of it
is trying to predict what could possibly
happen. uh and uh those are those are
great thought experiments and there's
some really really interesting math
behind all all them and some interesting
rules of thumb that can come out but for
the most part we aren't going to go into
too much detail about that largely
because I'm not a mathematician or
economist so I don't really have a good
a good sense of game theory uh just be
aware that you know there is this whole
field of game theory in economics uh if
you're doing a game like an auction
system if you're doing a game where
people are doing uh either a lot of
simultaneous moves or um yeah or the
whole point of the game is trying to
predict what your what strategy your
your opponent is going to do. You might
actually want to read up a little bit of
game theory if nothing else just to give
you some vocabulary to talk about it
with your teammates uh and some tools to
be able to think through some of the
design problems that you've got. Um and
then we we we do have one session where
we I'll introduce some of them. Um and
finally we're getting to rules. Um you
know the the things that give that give
your game structure and you know the
limit the constraints of the things that
you can't do. You you can't move from
here to there without having your foot
tied to another player. You know that
that sort of constraint uh or a rule
being you know you can't say anything uh
during a a certain part of part of the
game. Um there are two uh there are two
bits of terminology introduced by Brendo
uh and and Ian Shriber in in their book
which is um core mechanic and core
dynamic. Um so before I'm going to go
into core mechanic and core dynamic and
then talk about mechanic and dynamic. Um
anyone want to throw out the definition
of mechanic?
It's sort of the uh the actions like a
player takes during a game like the
physical uh physical actions he takes.
>> Okay. The the actions that a player
decides to take
>> decides to take action.
>> Sorry if this is a little
>> um I saw Patrick and Oh, did those hands
just go there?
>> I thought I saw a few more hands.
>> Actions that are sort of designed by the
game designer.
>> Okay. So, intensive actions.
>> Um, design is definitely a good point.
Uh, a game mechanic is definitely
something that you're uh that you as a
game designer control. Uh there are you
know if if if a player decides to do
something in the game that you did not
explicitly think about and you did not
explicitly say all right this is what
players are going to be doing in the
game then it might not not actually be a
mechanic. It might be something that
you're discovering in your play play
testing that you will turn into a
mechanic but because it's not designed
uh it's kind of it becomes more like a
strategy actually like a immersion
strategy. Sorry, you were saying Jeremy.
>> Is it more like a dynamic?
>> Um, possibly. There are times where it
is. Yeah. And yeah, um, actually let's
throw out some definitions of dynamic.
Uh, what do people
uh, well, Jeremy,
>> behavior that emerges from mechanics.
>> Okay. So, so emerges emergent behavior.
What what else
uh use of mechanics that isn't uh
directly stated in the rules of the
game?
>> Okay, so so unstated.
>> I'm running out of space here.
>> I thought I saw a hand.
No. Okay. Uh All right. So, um yeah,
dynamics are basically interactions of
mechanics. you know, it's like you don't
have a uh uh you don't have anything
that may necessarily explicitly say, you
know, because of this one rule and
because of one this other rule and
because of the things that the players
can do in that, you know, a a good
strategy is to do something else. So,
let me see whether I can think of an
example. Right now, everything that's
coming to my head is Starcraft. Um,
>> has that been the case for the past few
weeks?
>> Unfortunately, yes. Uh, by the way, if
anybody is playing Starcraft, I need
testers. Uh, because
>> yes,
>> I I I need testers for a map that I'm
resigning. Um,
>> especially
I play
>> there's a good example in Puerto Rico.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Right. So, there's this role selection
mechanic where everybody picks the thing
which they want to happen during the
turn and they get a bonus for doing it.
Um and also everybody chooses to like
build particular crops.
>> Um and the dynamic that emerges from the
sequence of play which goes clockwise is
that it's best to
optimize your strategy so that you are
doing so that you are benefiting from
the role that the person to your right
is most likely to choose.
>> But you're making the goods that the
person to your left is most likely to
want to ship or sell. So the mechanic is
roll selection and turn order
>> and then the dynamic is the strategy
written purpose out of that
>> which which gives you some idea on what
to select as oo you know the the
mechanic is you can select the dynamic
is here are a couple of strategies that
you can use in sort of assessing what
would be best to select. Um, and if all
the players start to understand that,
then it almost becomes like a, you know,
like a second layer of rules almost. And
if anyone's played a game like Bridge,
for instance, there's actually a ton of
things that are assumed in the play
which are not actually in the rules of
bridge. Uh, when it comes to bidding,
like when you call out a bid, it's
highly dependent on what you actually
have in your cart uh in in in your card
hand. And that's not actually written in
the rules anywhere. Um but the
assumption is that there is optimal way
to do it and since there's optimal way
to do it everyone's expected to know
there's optimal ways. Um the example in
the book was chess moves like you know
every single move uh piece of chess uh
has a set of moves that it can perform
right pawns go one or two squares
depending whether the starting uh
bishops move diagonally but there are
also opening gambits.
There are opening habits that that that
that are uh that are also wellknown at
least among professional uh chess
players. And the idea being oh this
person is using this opening therefore
if I counter it with this response I
actually have uh you know a reasonable
chance of actually winning the the this
game and professional chess players know
this. Um the other thing that comes up
in chess which is not in the book is uh
there is um there is the concept of
threatened squares. If you if you move u
if there is a square where there is no
piece on a chess board. Everyone here
knows the rules of chess more or less.
Yeah. Um, so say you've got a bishop and
you know this is my very simple chess
board and you've got a bishop
um and and and it can move like that,
right? So every single square along
these lines uh is threatened. It's it's
something which a uh which which a uh
the bishop could move to unless of
course it's you know blocked by by a
pawn or something and these are no
longer threatened. what it honest um
uh if if you're a knight obviously is no
longer straight lines. It becomes, you
know, specific sort of like a weird
stochastic pattern of squares that
become threatened. Uh but uh but but but
but the idea of here's this square now
that nobody dares move into until
something's done about that bishop.
Either move something gets moved in its
way or you know some something takes out
that bishop or forces the bishop to move
by threatening. it instead in a way that
they cannot respond. So threats and
squares is not a rule in in in in uh in
chess but it greatly shapes your
decision m your decision making and
that's the difference between dynamic
and mechanic. Um there's a lot of strong
correspondence between uh mechanics and
weights. Um but uh and and I had a long
long uh little rant about exactly what
the difference is between mechanics and
rules and uh and what I basically I I
I'm not going to give the rant right now
but but it's like overlapping ven
diagram you know there's a very very
large area where it's exactly the same
thing. Um, my general rubric for you for
trying to figure out whether something
is a mechanic or not is whether this is
the thing that changes the state of the
game. If it's an action, if it's if it's
something that someone's going to be
doing to change the state of what the
game is, you know, in chess, that's
largely the move the movement of of a
piece. Um if it's um
uh if it's ultimate you know it could be
just physical movement you know you are
limited on when you can physically move
if you have that frisbee you're not
moving uh well you're feet are not
moving I believe that's a of
um so so uh the the reason why I use
that definition is because there are
occasionally times where I need to talk
about mechanics that players aren't
actually doing like the game requires
certain pieces to move in a certain way,
certain things to happen in the game.
You know, um in Settlers of Katan, for
instance, you have these die rolls. Uh
and um actually that's not a good
example, let me think. Um well, right at
the beginning of Setters of Katanda is
the way how you set up the board and
that establishes what a game state is
going to be. You know, it it changes the
game state by giving you a game state in
the first place. um that I I I consider
that a mechanic that that is something
that's going uh that that it's but
that's not one one rule. It's actually a
whole collection of rules and if you're
interested in finding out what those
rules are, the box is actually in that
closet over there. Um but it's like
something like five or six different
rules on this is how you set up your
board. It's going to set up your game
state and I consider that a mechanic. Um
how people do bidding and buying things
in setters of katan that's dynamic. you
know that's that you know there are no
real rules on how much something costs
that's up to the players to work out on
their own um so that's how I sort of
consider the difference between core
dynamic uh between dynamic and and and
mechanic um really really useful
concepts because really for the most
part as a designer you have an idea of
what kind of dynamics are interesting uh
and the more games that you play the and
you know the more inspiration that you
get from various sources. Uh your vocab
your range of different ideas of what
kind of dynamics might be interesting is
going to expand. Uh but all you have
control on are mechanics are the
specific rules that that you're giving
your your
note that game mechanics don't
necessarily need to be written uh or
described out. Um, this is one thing
that I think you and your teammates
should figure out when you're talking
about mechanics for a given project. Are
we just talking about the things that
we're writing down? Because there are
some assumptions that uh that are just
given. Um, we are playing a game in,
you know, we're playing some sort of
schoolyard game or something, you know,
uh, hitting people with large solid
solid objects is disallowed or something
like that, you know, not necessarily
something you need to write down unless
you're playing with certain people, but
you have uh, you know, but you can
assume that's a game a game mechanic
there. Um, things like how fast, you
know, people normally do things. There's
a game over there over over here called
Falling uh which is actually a real-time
card game. It it goes as fast as you can
possibly play it. And uh there is no
there is no limit on how fast you can
play these cards, but there is a real
physical limit on how fast you can
physically grab a card out of your hand
and put it down. Uh so actually it's not
even on your hand. You're just moving
cards on the table. So uh so make sure
you give that a try uh today.
Oh um finally uh we'll we'll we'll we'll
be getting to aesthetics uh I think next
class next week.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, so which is another
thing which uh a game designer uh in
fact which is what I would like game
designers to actually spend more time
thinking about which is what is the
feeling you want your player to have as
opposed to this might be fun you know
it's like oh this might be engaging it's
like specifically how is it fun how is
it engaging is it fun as in like yes
victory I have crushed all my opponents
or is it fun as in wow we had a really
good time together and we got to know
each other really well you know there
are games that are designed for both of
those Um and uh and what what is the
aesthetic you're going for? You going
for something poetic? Are you going for
something, you know, fiercely
competitive, uh tournament competitive,
or you going for, you know, just a nice
little social experiment? Um
core mechanics and core dynamics are uh
are a tool again for designers. uh the
idea of there there really isn't a huge
difference between what's a core
mechanic and what's just a mechanic uh
except inside a designer or a design
team's uh discussion. Um the idea of
having a core core mechanic as you
identify this is what our game's about
uh or a core dynamic mean this is what
our game uh our game's about. And a lot
of core core mechanics in first-person
shooters is pointing and shooting,
right? I'm going to point at something
and I'm going to launch a projectile
that way and that projectile is going to
move in a certain some physical
properties. You know, maybe it arcs,
maybe it goes straight. Um, and other
core uh I would say that the core
mechanic of Halo isn't actually that
core uh who has not played Halo or seen
someone play Halo. Okay. Um, so like the
I the core mechanic or I think my Budgie
calls it the core gameplay loop um uh of
uh of Halo is you shoot at something,
you take cover, you throw a grenade at
it, you wait for the grenade to go off,
and then you shoot it again until it
dies. Um, right. That's pretty much all
you're doing for the entirety of Halo 1.
Um sure Halo 2 Halo 3 gets complicated.
Yeah. You know um but but but they
identify that if you actually read the
postmortems and and if you read at the
talks that they've given they say those
I can't I can't remember it's 20 seconds
or 5 seconds of gameplay which they use
to describe that. I think it's five that
5second of game play is what they
focused on. And if they could get every
little thing in that sequence correct
they can repeat that same thing at
infinitum and you'll still be having
fun.
um Halo one everyone,
you know, they're they're kind of right.
But the idea being, you know, if you've
got a core mechanic, if you've got one
thing in your game that someone's going
to be doing over and over and over
again, all your players are going to be
doing over and over again, maybe it's
bidding because they're making some kind
of auction game. Um, in falling, it's
and in pit it's transferring cards to
other people. Um,
uh, I'm trying to think of the other
games that we've got here. Um in in Siss
fight, I would imagine is the the main
the main core mechanic would be uh
putting down the card uh and and
everyone revealing the card
simultaneously because you you you all
take simultaneous turns. You know, make
sure that's really really fun and Yazi
is rolling dice. You know, that's that
action, that thing that you're going to
be doing over and over again has to be
at least fairly engaging. Um because if
you c if you can't get that right then
what happens is that that same movement
that happens 30 50 times in your game
you know just gets m the badness just
gets multiplied by 30 or 50 uh and and
and you don't want that. So for core
mechanics you know I I would say the
thing that happens in your game the most
and uh and you want to make sure that
that part is is as engaging as possible.
It also gives you a rubric to say what's
not a core mechanic might be in fact
expendable. You might not actually need
it in your game. So if you've got a
problem, this game takes too long to
play, this game's too hard to learn, uh
this game's over too fast, it's too
random or something, take a look at all
the things that are, you know, of course
make sure that your core mechanic is not
the cause of the problem. But if the
your core mechanic doesn't seem to be
the cause of the problem, that seems to
be working. Something else in the game
is not working. Everything else is
expandable. And so you you you you can
look at everything else in your game,
all these other rules that you've got
and say, "How does that work with the
coral mechanic? How does that help? How
does that hurt the coral mechanic?" It
just helps your discussion as a team. Uh
or as a game or as an individual game
designer, it helps your thinking about
what could we throw out, what could we
keep.
Um similarly for core dynamic it's you
know it's like here's this particular
um uh particular interaction that we
really really want um in cisifi is
guessing what other people are going to
do um and uh I'm trying to think of
other examples and like territorial
uh space acquisition I guess go is about
taking over territory in space um you
know if that's your core dynamic if you
say that's kind of fun. Just making sure
that I'm in control of a space and
nobody else can do anything that they
want to do in a certain part of the
board. That's fun. Um that's what I'm
going for. That's my core dynamic.
That's what this game is all about. Then
you can look at every single mechanic,
even your core mechanics, and say, is it
all serving that goal? Now, there's a
whole bunch of uh tips right at the end
of chapter one of uh of uh challenges
for game designers about how to break
designer block. Um but I would say
actually those things are just things
that you should be doing all the time.
Um not not just when you have a problem,
but you should be experimenting things
like, you know, okay, you've got a
variable, you know, draw two cards every
turn or something. Multiply it by two,
see what it does to your game. Have it,
draw one card, see what it does to your
game. um you know throw a rule out you
know um it and and that sort of gets you
to the whole iterative design thing is
that you don't actually because games
are systems they're these complex little
collections of seemingly simple things
you don't actually know how these
changes are really going to affect your
game. You may have a hunch but until you
actually play it out you don't actually
know. So um so the whole point of
iterative of iterative the design in in
engineering as well as in game design is
that you know you you make the change.
There has to be a substantial change. Um
and then you actually put it to the test
and see what happens. Um this means of
course testing and testing takes a long
time and if you're going to be making a
game that takes a long time then your
testing gets even longer. So, uh, for
the first project that's going to be
coming out, the assignment, uh,
assignment one, you want to be aiming
for games that take really not very long
to play. Um, these games that we've got
today, I'm not sure about shake, but I
know everything else that we've got on
that table is pretty darn fast, which
means, you know, if you've got an hour
with four people, uh, who've never
played your game before, maybe you get
through two or three rounds, four rounds
of them, you know, each time maybe
tweaking a rule once, uh, uh, here and
there and seeing how that change that
that changed the game. If you've got a
game that takes an hour to play, and
believe me, a lot of the of the projects
that we've gotten from previous
semesters take at least an hour to play,
um, then you know you've got four people
for an hour and they're not going to
finish the a single play of the game
because by the time they finish learning
your your your game, half your time is
up.
Um, so that's the process that we would
like you all to be using in your teams,
in your assignments. this iterative
design pro process right from the
beginning uh I wish I had more space um
but uh we're going to start with
brainstorming uh there that's actually
going to be Friday the 17th where we'll
actually sort of uh for folks who
haven't necessarily formally learned uh
bra bra bra bra bra bra bra bra bra bra
brainstorming, we're just going to do a
quick refresher uh so that everyone s
sort of is on the same page. You learn
how to do brainstorming. Um, you come up
with a basic idea of your game and you
start to identify things that could be
your core dynamics. You know, you think
of what what sort of core mechanics
could address that. Knock something up
really really quickly with the crappiest
materials you can get your hands on and
start playing. Um, since nobody in your
team knows really what game you're
making at that point of time, you can
probably test it with your team. As soon
as you do that a few times, your team
becomes useless as play as testers
because you already know too much about
about the game and what and and what the
game could have been and you start
playing it in ways that a fresh person
who's never seen your game before
wouldn't even consider. Um, so you
actually want to keep looking for people
who've never played your game before. So
the next step would be to broaden it to
other teams in this class. Um, since
everyone's going to be broken up in more
or less teams of three or four, that's
pretty much, you know, I'm going to take
this game that we designed for a team of
three or four and give it to that team
of three or four and then you play their
game and, you know, give each other
feedback. And that lasts for about one
more session and after that, everyone in
the class has used this now. So, you
have to go and look for doormates,
friends, you know, um, people on the
street, you know, just go right ahead
and try to get as much feedback as you
can.
Um
there is some value in replaying um
especially later on once your rules are
pretty set uh in that people start
developing strategies those sort of
emergent uh uh behaviors and you start
understanding sort of higher level play
of your game and you do want to test
that um but don't let that prevent you
from also testing with fresh players uh
because in the end um you have to get
past that initial hurdle. Anytime
someone sees your game, they are going
to have to learn to learn your game from
scratch at least once. And if they don't
even get that far, they're never playing
it your game a second or a third time.
So don't optimize for the people who
played your game, you know, for for
weeks because the um because you really
want the people who've only played it
once uh to have a good time as well.
Um, that's not necessarily the case if
you're making, you know, uh, a huge
wellunded game with based on a franchise
that, you know, that's been around
forever. If you're doing Halo 3 or
Modern Warfare 3 or something like that,
you know, then sure, you can sort of
cater to the fans uh, who've already
developed these strategies and and
skills. But in in our case, we're
develop we're going after a new
audience. We're going after someone
who's never played anything like what
what you've played before.
Cool. Any
questions?
I've been soap boxing here for a while
Jason.
>> Um,
so I guess the other thing that I would
that I would add from my experience,
especially with iterative design, is a
big trick of it is learning to kind of
distance yourself emotionally from what
you're working on. Um, because half the
time you end up chucking things that you
really like. you think, "Oh, this would
be so great, but it's best to just
remove it." Um, it helps to think of it
as putting kind of putting it on the
shelf for later and saying, "Okay, I'll
deal with this later. I can try this in
another game." Um, and on a related
note, I don't know about you, but I
found that when games I'm designing have
a problem, it's almost always fixed by
removing something as opposed to adding
more stuff on. Um, unless you're going
for something, I think really complex
off the start, I always prefer to try
and take something out something out and
simplify it.
>> Yeah, especially in short projects like
these, it almost always works better.
Um,
and then and in terms of testing too,
one thing just kind of a a tip that I
find works is if you're designing a game
that has a lot of different um like
paths to victory, and this is a little
bit higher level, but you'll see what I
mean when we get there, where if you
want a game that has different viable
strategies, a really good testing method
is to have different people kind of play
like a perfect version of that strategy.
And you say, I'm going to do this
strategy or I'm always going to do X.
And it doesn't matter if I think it's
dumb, I'm just going to do it. Um
because that'll really help you find
rules that are broken or find something
that's overpowered. Um a good example
would be Settlers, right? Like if you
say, "I'm obviously this wouldn't work
because the game is a good game, but
like I'm always going to build roads."
You know what I mean? Like in practice
that would be stupid, but if you're when
you're designing a game, you do that
kind of strategy and you just limit
yourself to one action, you can really
find things that are broken really
quickly.
Um,
thanks. Yeah.
Much appreciated. Cookies, dude. We have
cookies.
Thanks, Google. Just the Google family.
Uh,
uh, let's see. So, um, so yeah, we I
think after this we're just going to
play games. Uh well um we do have a play
testing as a topic coming up later in
the semester where we'll actually sort
of talk about the discipline on how you
do testing. Uh uh honestly it's
you shouldn't wait for that class to
necessarily start practicing. Uh you
know if you it could be as simple as
just grabbing a game that you have never
seen before and just trying to get a
whole bunch of people to play it and
critiquing it at the same time. you
know, it's like why did I do that? Why
did you do that? Why did you do that
move? You know, and um there are sort of
practices to make sure that when it's
your game, you are not sort of telling
the players what they should be doing uh
while they are trying to play the game
because that affects their player uh in
the game in a way that biases it. Uh but
uh but we'll get to that later in the
semester. for now, you know, uh just
just be aware the more that you're
testing, the more that you're sort of
tweaking your rules in between tests and
then getting another chance to test and
test and test, the closer you are to
getting a game that's actually fun and
engaging to play. Um, and that's what
we're looking for. That's the process
that we expect you folks to to stick in.
Whe whether you ever get to fun and
engaging, who knows? We don't know
whether you're going to get there. So,
we're not grading you based on that.
Just remember that. We're not grading
you on how engaging your games are, but
how well you stick to the process. Yes,
absolutely.
Um, there was a question on the forums
about when do you stop, right?
Did you put it up? Um, I didn't get a
chance to look too closely at it. What?
Um, can can you repeat?
>> So, essentially, it's the question of so
there's this iterative design process
and when do you know when to sort of get
out of that process?
>> Due date.
>> The due date. Okay. All right. That's
always a good reason. Uh,
>> but I guess like if you didn't have a
due date, like how would you know when
to ship or let's say you have control
over the due date?
>> Um, I guess part of that is you should
always be iterate like you should always
be updating blah blah.
>> So I guess the question is when do you
know when you have something that you
can put out into like the world?
>> Um, so the cynical answer yeah is that
is that you wait for you know you have
to ship right or you're not getting any
cash. Um, the I personally think it will
be sooner soon. s sooner than you think.
It's like, you know, oh, my game's
almost ready, but I notice something
wrong with it. Especially when you're a
student. Um, right. Right now, I'm in
this I'm in this mode with my Starcraft
apps, which is this map is crap. I know
there's something wrong with it. I have
no idea what it is. Therefore, I'm going
to release it. Uh, because until I do
that, I have no idea what's wrong with
it. I need to get that that that
information. The nice thing about stuff
like, you know, uh, computer games is
that you can ship updates. Um, it's
annoying, but you can. But even board
games and card games now have re rule
revisions, rule clarifications that you
can release o um, uh, over the net. Uh,
for the most part, if you are going to
go professional, your publisher will
tell you and then the answer really is
due date, right? You know, it's like
it's going to the presses on this date.
And uh that's one maxim which is game
projects are never finished. They're
just abandoned. Um you know it's just
all you know I can't do anything else
about this because I'm out of time. Ship
it. Um but one thing that you can do to
prepare for that um let me see is there
an er
there there's a guy who runs a blog
called Lost Garden. His name is Dan
Cook. He works over in Microsoft and he
talks a lot about game design um
specifically about video game design,
but actually his stuff is actually
really really applicable and he has this
concept that you know game design or
iterative game design kind of goes in
this in this kind of cycle where uh this
is this width down here is the number of
features that you've got in your game.
Uh the trick though is that um what you
are really doing is you are taking
let me see if this is right.
So this is all the good stuff. This is
all the stuff that's not so good. Um,
and the whole idea of of of
sort of like using iterative design is
to allow yourself to the space to come
up with a whole bunch of ideas not
knowing whether they're good or bad, but
then also give you a gate to cut out all
the bad stuff. So at any so at frequent
periodic intervals you have a collection
of rules of cards of designs of whatever
consists your game that is pretty much
as good as you possibly could have made
it given the amount of time that you've
got and that could ship. Um so you know
so if if your ship date was here you
would have as good a game as you
possibly could doing it. if ship date
turned out to be there all of a sudden.
You know, you've still got you still had
the opportunity to quiddle out all of
the all the stuff that you knew was bad.
Um so iterative design is not about
let's just keep accreating more and more
and more and more features. It's more
about you know we're going to add some
features and then we're going to remove
the ones that don't work. Um and that's
really really important. Uh so that at
any given time you're prepared to sort
of release it. Um, and as for when you
actually decide that this is now ready
to go out, I would again I would I would
repeat sooner than than you think
because you need that feedback. U
sometimes uh you don't know how a market
is going to respond until you actually
do it. But you can do a soft launch. Uh
if you're doing uh commercial product,
you you can do things where we're going
to release it to a few select stores and
get that feedback before we go into
major print run uh or you know uh burn
burn 10,000 different copies of the same
board game. Uh we're going to do 200
copies and see how that does for us. It
gives you the opportunity to to make a
revision, but it's still an official
release because those 200 people think
that this is the final package product.
Um that's pretty much how a lot of
manufacturing industries actually work
anyway. So if you think about u any kind
of product design, a lot of them have a
sort of like trial period.
>> Soft drinks
>> soft drinks you get a lot um Japanese
electronics you know it's like you
release it in Tokyo and then you release
it in the rest of Japan. Uh and
sometimes it never makes it out out of
Japan. uh because you know that initial
test yeah it was it was a good product
but not enough people bought it because
of these problems. So instead of
releasing into the world we're going to
make version two and maybe that will be
one release too. That's that's that's
one example.
All right. So we have games
um but who has not played?
>> Okay. All right. We have more games than
we have.
No. Okay. So, um Jason, you're going to
do a youer uh table. So, um
>> like just a four player trick taking
game. Kind of vehicles.
>> Um looks like we have exactly four
people. One, two, three. One, two,
three. Oh, yeah. We have an average of
three people per table. That table is
four. Um, I think most of these games
are three to five players, although I'm
going to be absolutely
>> Yeah. This is like four to eight.
>> You guys play fully.
>> Yeah. So, so falling might want to be
larger table. You guys might actually
want to try the round table in the
corner.
>> Yeah. It says table.
>> Yeah. 48 people.
>> I really want to play.
>> All right. Let's do this play.
Please. Um,
>> so basically take a game um uh from the
table. Uh, I'll I'll bring some out and
I'll see that play uh play them. Once
you've had a chance to play a few times,
feel free to switch
>> and try to get as many games played as
possible during during the next couple
of hours and stuff.
>> Cool.