I always love to talk after lunch
because my
my research is about food and
agriculture and so typically I can
relate
and I can give you many examples of what
you have eaten and how they've been
processed and how nanotechnology
enables the food and agriculture
business. But today we're not here to
talk about me. Today we're here to talk
about climate resilience and how
nanotechnology can support a society
that is more resilient to climate
change. And we have three amazing
speakers like these are really really
good top class speakers. So I'm very
happy that they um that they join us and
they're going to talk about the
research. Before doing that though, I
would like to give a mention and um
further resonate the speech that uh
President Kro gave this morning about
the importance of innovating in climate
and particularly she started as
presidential initiative the climate
project which I uh I'm part of and
really the climate project is a brand
new initiative that uh she launched and
the idea is to convey all the faculty to
work together to have an impact uh on
climate and also energy. of course with
the idea that we're going to have a
tangible impact on the trajectory of
climate change in the next 10 years.
We cannot do it alone. And so the what
the climate project wants to do is
really to uh leverage all the different
entities that are already part of MIT
and to work with them so that the
faculty can work to uh innovate in
climate
and particularly we see the project as
an ecosystem for innovation in deep
tech. So we really want MIT to become
the hub that puts together industry
incubators, investors, foundations, the
startups that come out of our uh
university together with the government,
national lab and other university
partners to work together to innovate in
the realm of climate. As you may know,
innovating climate is extremely
difficult. Uh the economy is developing.
There are no real models that can be
used particularly for uh some
technologies. And so this ecosystem for
innovation would particularly be focused
on innovation at scale and it's very
interesting because we talk about this
at the nano uh summit and nano is 10 to
minus 9 as you know and for climate we
need to go 10 to the 9 and up right so
we need to cover 18 order of magnitudes
even 20 so that's really the beauty the
challenge and the opportunities that
we're having and we really really need
to work as
as whole to solve this problem.
Uh the vision is summarized in the
well-being of humanity and prosperity of
humanity and to do that we need to take
care of ecology, health, mobility, the
built environment, food, energy,
policies and trade and industry. And so
really putting this at the center of
innovation of campus and thinking about
these topics as interconnected topic to
have a positive impact on our climate.
Um the climate change is or sorry the
climate change the climate project is
organized uh in different key areas and
we have six faculty leadership and as
you can see I'm one of them and
particularly I'm leading an effort that
is called the wild cards which are
high-risk high payoff projects that um
if successful can have a big big impact
uh on changing the trajectory of climate
change but of course they're also high
risk. We as area of interest we have
decarbonizing the energy and the
industry empowering frontline community
which are going to be the one most
affected by climate change. We need to
redesign uh resilience at prosperous
cities. We need to enable new policy to
be able to translate and then we have a
a focus on science. So what's the
science that um interests the
atmosphere, the land and the oceans and
then of course the wild card that I just
discussed. Um the one of the one of the
help that we want to give to faculty
through the climate project is to assess
priorities, identify gaps in knowledge
and technologies and then put several
faculty together in DARPA style program
that can be launched and that can um
really make an impact on the
technologies. We also support cutting um
crosscutting research among different
missions. particularly we recently
launched a two projects one on sensure
and understand climate and one related
to heat stress and cooling and I just
want to thank you for your attention and
I hope you're going to enjoy the next uh
50 minutes or so and I please welcome to
the stage professor Michael Strano who's
going to give us his talk. Thank you
very much Michael.
[Applause]
Thank you very much for that
introduction. I have um it's my my
pleasure to speak to to speak to you on
this on this topic of nano and climate
resilience. I'm a professor in chemical
engineering. I've been here about 17
years and I lead a nanotech technology
laboratory. Um and I'm pleased to be
here. I I thought I would start start
off why why are climate problems why why
can they be solved by nanotechnology? So
na n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
nanom materials give us new ways to to
to control catalysis and re reactivity.
So uh many climate problems are really
chemistry pro problems and at the nanome
meter scale we can design new catalysts
that can do transformations that can do
things like re react green greenhouse
gases to to to useful pro properties and
then climate problems also intersect
with energy conservation and how how how
we use energy and nanom materials give
give us new ways to manipulate uh and
control the way energy flows like
through like through carbon nano tubes
and nanowires
and many climate pro problems involve
our need to separate and and sort and to
process uh molecules and we have new
ways uh using nanopores that we can
manipulate molecules for for that
purpose. So what I thought I would talk
to to you today about are three projects
from from my my laboratory where we're
applying nano technology solutions to
long-standing climate challenges. The
the first uh addresses uh how how do we
valorize or or or make useful um waste
methane and ura and you you probably the
the the pioneer um who will speak next
in this area area has been Desiree Plata
u who's pointed out methane is a very
potent green green h greenhouse gas also
chemistry-wise it's actually notoriously
difficult to react act and so um it's
it's responsible for for.5% of warming
and so we want to do something with
waste methane it's produced um from from
the decay of bio gas and uh there are
many many social sources of waste
methane at the same time we we we have
an industry where we purposely make ura
and we make it from uh ammonia from the
habbash pro process a very
energyintensive process uh but at the
same time actually in waste water. We
have enough ura to actually supply to to
supply the whole the the whole economy.
And so we see this as a a wasted
opportunity. We've been working on
chemical ways to to react methane in in
water with ura. A big breakthrough in in
this space we published just earlier
this year. We made what we call a
synthetic methanotrope. Like what nano
allows us to do is to basically do what
nature can do with bacteria but in the
form of two different nanop particles. A
ZSM5 is an aluminino silicate nano
particle and it'll take methane and
it'll react it to to methanol which now
you you can go and make useful pro
products with uh if you use this enzyme
called al alcohol oxidase which we also
mount on a nanoparticle. Well, this will
actually couple back and will feed the
ZSM5 an oxidizer. And this this kind of
chemical cycle is what you what you
would what you would find in a living
organism, but nanotechnology allows us
to actually uh replicate it in in test
tube and replicate it into a larger
reactor. And so th this this does what
bacteria can can do in water. It can
take methane and it can it can make a
useful intermediate. And what we've been
doing is using this chem chemistry to
capture the ura in wastewater. And this
is opening up a new synthetic pa pathway
where we we we can take waste methane
waste ura and then make a a variety of
renewable materials like adhesives uh
green insulation materials for
sustainable con construction and even
fertilizer. So if you're interested
please please um please learn learn
more. You can go to go to my website and
other re resources. We're very excited
about that. I wanted to uh move on to
the next topic. These are new materials
that we just invented in the in in the
lab and they can solve the problem of of
uh in infrastructure for the hydrogen
economy. So we hydrogen is is the fuel
the growth of hydrogen as a fuel. We
have to make the transition to to it.
It's a perfect fuel. It burns to water.
uh and it's it's going to be ve very
important for sectors that are difficult
to electrify and so the the uh there's
there's uh substantial growth in the
hydrogen economy that's predicted but
there is a drawback. Um maybe few people
in the room know that you can't just put
hydrogen gas into our our natural gas
infrastructure. It it would be nice
there there there's an insidious
engineering problem that that happens.
It's called hydrogen in brittlement.
Hydrogen is so small as a as a molecule,
it'll actually intercolate even the
strongest steels. And when it does so,
it turns the steel into into basically
fragile glass. And the way you know it
happened is there's there's an
explosion. So this problem really needs
to be solved in order to transition to
the hydrogen economy. And so we um a few
years ago we invented a completely new
class of material material mater
materials. It's a It's a 2D polymer.
This is called a polyaramid. It's one of
the strongest polymers ever measured. Uh
if you're familiar with Kevlar and a
bulletproof vest, it's a similar
chemistry, but actually we solve the
problem of polymerizing in two
dimensions. And what what we've made is
a very interesting material. It's a it's
a polymer. We would all agree, the the
chemist would agree. But once we
actually spin it into a film, it makes a
very tightly bound, hydrogen-bound film
that starts to look like graphine. It's
a spray-on or paint on strong, durable
graphine. And I think science has never
seen anything like it. It forms these
very tightly bound bound stacks. And
what we found is it's the first
impermeable painton polymer. Actually,
we measure no gas permeability through
it at all. This graph permeability is is
measured in this unit called called
barer. All conventional polymers are are
are up here. This polymer is not even
close. It's orders of magnitude lower.
It's actually at the detection limit.
You really can't detect any further. And
the only other types of materials that s
that that have this property are like
graphine. So basically we have a painton
perfect barrier material. And this graph
highlights how unusual this material is.
It's a polymer, but you paint you paint
it on, it becomes like a perfect crystal
graphine. And so, we're using this to
solve the problem of hydrogen imbr.
Please go to this uh QR code, you can
find out more. We're very excited to
talk to you more about about that. And
then just really quick in the last
minute or so that that I have, we're
also working on technologies that that
that can enable the fourth agricultural
re revolution. and we're we're using uh
pioneering plant nano nanotech
technology. The problem here we're
trying to solve is global food prices
are are rising. They're rising for a
variety of reasons, but but one is that
climates are changing and there's
examples of that all all over. Uh the
the the the palm oil that we get on our
shelves, a lot of it comes from
Malaysia. And if you look at the
rainfall, it's just consistently
falling. the climate is changing and at
some point where we grow things uh we'll
we'll have to find alternatives to how
we grow the foods that we take for
granted. In the meantime prices are
going to rise. So this is definitely a
climate pro problem and it's
contributing to uh global food
insecurity. What uh my colleagues and
and I made a uh an an entity called
called Dist. It's a it's MIT's uh
research enterprise in Singapore through
the smart pro pro program. It gives uh
it gives my myself and also our our
chair Benedetto Morelli
um a a vehicle to work on problems like
this in agriculture. Briefly, what we're
trying to do are make tools that could
close the loop and and be able to to
grow crops. If you think of the input
light, water, CO2 and fertilizer. If you
think of th those as inputs, you could
imagine nanotech technology enabled
tools which give you feedback from the
plant that allow you to do rapid
feedback control and make technology
where you could essentially grow
anything. And so go here to this uh QR
code and you can find find out more
about our p our pioneering work. Um I'm
interested in hearing from the other
speakers. So, I'm going to I'm I'm going
to end end there and and I'm happy to
pass it off to the to the next speaker.
Yeah.
I think we're going to take questions at
the end, right?
I'm Desiree Plat. I am a professor in
civil and environmental engineering. And
I don't have a single SEM today, so I'm
going to apologize to Vlad personally,
but but I we have them. I'll show them
after. Um, so I want to start by talking
about sustainable innovation and the
role that it has in the restorative
economy. The economic systems that we
have today are depleting to our
resources, inherently polluting, and all
of that is an externality that's not
accommodated in the business model. So,
I'm going to take you to that
macroscopic scale that Benedetto
mentioned and then drive back down to
the to the nano scale. Uh, one thing
that I I want to underscore here for
those of you who aren't aware, the
climate project at MIT has an
articulated mission to change the
trajectory of global climate outcomes
within a decade. And this is what that
trajectory looks like. It looked like
this um five years ago. It looks like
this today. Uh, our global anthropogenic
CO2 emissions are around 51 gigatons
annually. Whoops, excuse me. Um, and
implemented policies have some ability
to to tune those total emissions. But in
order to hit any kind of twoderee
warming targets, we have to
fundamentally change the way that we do
things. I have a list of technologies
that I think are musthaves in order to
to meet this goal or bridge this gap. It
includes things that are being worked on
in the climate project like better
adaptation and resilience, smarter
cities, nuclear energy for data centers
and manufacturing, electrification, um
including systems integrated in the
materials that we need for for
electrification. Um industrial heating
or transportable uh liquid fuels um
sustainable agriculture is is enormous
um and and must be addressed. Today I'm
going to focus on biological carbon
removals and the associated bioeconomy
that would need to come along with that
to finance the whole thing. Now in order
to hit that twoderee line, the IPCC
estimates that we need 10 gigatons of
CO2 removal by 2050. Now 10 gigatons is
bigger than the coal industry itself.
And that's a rock. So we're talking
about pulling a gas out of the sky, a
dilute uh substrate. That's hard. this
industry had a hundred years to scale or
more. We've got to do this in a couple
of decades. One of the only places on
Earth where we move that amount of
material is actually in the agricultural
sector. So the the wet the excuse me the
dry weight of the agricultural sector se
sector is around 18 gigatons and the
residues or waste associated with that
are on the order of four to seven
gigatons of dry waste. So, we like to
call the agricultural biosphere the
sleeping giant of carbon removals that
hasn't really necessarily gotten the
attention that it deserves. And if you
do this accounting, there's somewhere
approaching 7 gigatons of CO2
equivalents removable available on on
the face of the earth today. Now, about
1.2 of that could be readily used. It's
either directly incinerated back to the
atmosphere or it it's left on the field.
And and you have to leave some of that
carbon on the field. I want to be clear
and fair there uh to to keep the soil
healthy, but you can remove a fraction
of it. And we're estimating that that's
around 1 gigaton of CO2 equivalents.
Food waste amounts to around one gigaton
of of C per year um CO2 equivalent
removal. So if you don't have composting
in your town, get that quickly. Um I
want to walk through why the the
financing of this system becomes really
important. How many people have heard
about direct air capture, right? So
you're pushing air through fans,
removing that 420 parts per million CO2
as it as it comes through. Direct air
capture carbon credits sell for around
900 to $1,200 per ton CO2 equivalent.
Now if we want to hit that 10 billion
metric ton mark, we're going to be
spending half of US GDP to do it right.
It's completely intractable. Not to
mention the fact that um direct air
capture would top out around a gigaton
of removal if we made every air handler
we ever made 80 times over. All right.
So let's just do what we did 80 times
again and see how that helps us out.
It's it's not a a great move. Right? So
the global GDP is around 100 and $110
trillion. US uh GDP around $25 trillion.
If we start to look at biio-based
storage technologies, we think those can
happen around $100 to $150 a ton CO2
removal. The methane emissions reduction
credits are on the order of $25 a ton
CO2 removal. And that's and that's
pretty exciting. And just for reference,
the value of our emissions, so if you
take the total global economy and divide
it by that 51 gigatons of CO2 emissions,
you've only got about $2,000 to play
with per ton of CO2 that we emit. So
nanomaterials and specialty chemicals
occupy a unique place in the market. If
we look at the way a barrel of oil is
used today, the m the value that's
derived from specialty chemicals is on
the order of the value that's derived
from the fuel itself. So if 76% of the
volume of a barrel of oil is going um to
make to products that we actually just
directly burn that generates almost a
trillion dollars in equal proportion
financially is the 16% of specialty
chemicals. So there's a lot of revenue
moving around in the specialty chemicals
market. Now how could we possibly take
advantage of a similar system for a
carbohydrate economy that's built on
biioaterials as opposed to prochemical
hydrocarbons? um how would we understand
the complexity of what nature is doing
in a way that we can manipulate that
matter on the nano scale ourselves?
Would we be tolerant to the product
distribution that nature is? Not every
leaf is the same, of course, but it
works perfectly well. Um how do we
reconcile the need to pace innovation
at a level that allows us to incorporate
environmental objectives into the design
process along with traditional
performance and cost ones? So the
example I'm going to tell you about
today is uh derived from ocean plastic
waste. And what I love about ocean
plastic waste is that it's wonderfully
photogenic as a pollutant. This brought
a lot of attention not only to the
dissolved chemicals that we've been
floating in for since the 1970s and and
50s or sooner. Um but it also brought a
lot of attention to climate change. We
can't grab CO2 in front of us. We can't
take a picture of it and put it on
Instagram. But plastic pollution has
brought an immense amount of attention
to these global scale problems. Now you
what you might not know is that plastic
production in the next 10 to 12 years is
going to outpace the integrated
production since plastics were invented.
So if you think this problem is bad now,
it will double in your lifetime if we
don't change how we're doing things. So
we started to look at those
transformation processes that occur
between the nanoase plastics and the
small particles that are formed and the
dissolved molecules and we can actually
pair those transformations together much
like you would a social network. Who's
friends with who, who's turning into
what and we can zoom in with chemical
molecular specificity. So not only can
we know which molecule is um parent
molecule is becoming which child
molecule, but how that transformation is
occurring. And something that is
important to point out here is one
degradation is is not monotonic. It
doesn't just fall apart. It forms other
things. Um but two that this is an
incredibly data dense network. This is
high throughput experimentation in one
pot. So if we can trace these complex
networks, every one of those nodes is a
molecule. Every one of those edges has a
reaction rate associated with it. This
is how we generate big data. This is how
I get molecules to carry cell phones in
their pocket and tell me everything they
ever bought and where they've been that
day. Um, so I'm pretty excited about
that. We've applied this technology to
several different industrial common
industrial chemicals, um, polymers here,
polyamid 6, polycaperactone, which is in
your medical implants, and polyactic
acid, the greenware. Um I won't get into
the details of this but functionally we
can start to ask the question if we just
mathematically multiply n there the
number of units that we're adding
together and ask what's left over we can
start to identify related groups of
molecules so subsets of molecules that
are all interrelated and as we grow
those molecules their retention time
changes on this instrument in a very
logical way that actually tells us how
it will behave in an environmental
system. Will it stick to a particle?
will it go into your cell um and what
have you and and we can also know
something about the chemical structure
based on how it behaves in response to
changes in pH. Now we can take that and
extend it to systems in the natural
world including biomolelecules that are
present um in in the ocean. Uh it so we
could we in this particular example we
suspended a complex polymer enriched
bacteria that were able to colonize that
polymer and started to systematically
study which bacteria and what proteins
in their in their um genetic makeup were
able to perform which chemical
transformations. Now this is a different
experimental set but functionally what
we can now try to do is step through the
biological molecules which are all
linked through that intellectual
exercise that we do in the data. Those
are the red symbols and the biomolecules
the gray ones. So we know who's turning
into what. We know what came from an
industrial material or maybe that's your
desired product in this case and what
came from the biological exodates
themselves. Now, if we were going to
really start to understand how nature
was performing bio transformations in
these complex mixtures, we would have to
amass a lot more data than what I'm
showing you here. So, high throughput
experimentation is truly necessary.
Those complex molecular networks exist
in every one of the examples here um
that I'll tell you about. So, Professor
Brad Olsen's group in chemical
engineering has ma synthetically uh made
se over 700 different polymers. I think
this is the world's largest uh synthetic
heteropolymer library. We subject th
those to high throughput degradation
testing along with high throughput
material performance testing. Right?
Nobody likes a paper straw. We want
these materials to be good at their at
their primary job in addition to being
compatible with the environment. And
then we can use that chemical
transformations data on mass to
understand what gives rise to
biodegradation and how can we manipulate
it using the tools of biology. This is
just some smiles code or big smiles as
we call it in polymers. It's a line
entry system. So your computer can
understand what the molecular structure
is. Um and we can start to understand
how chemical structure imparts a
particular reactivity or desired
biological output. This is available um
to you in encrypt app which is just
publicly launched. So it's all that cool
materials performance data, the
biodegradation data along with
performance and cost metrics to really
start to change the way we design
materials and processes so that they are
implicitly more compatible and with the
way the earth system works. So I'll end
by saying that nature's uh works
symbiotically and restoratively. The
materials and energy fluxes are are
locally balanced. Our economic systems
haven't done that very well. Prosperous
nations tend to emit 20 tons uh of
carbon CO2 equivalents per person per
year whereas um transitioning nations
emit 10 times less. The only way you
move between these lines is either with
substantive investment in a decarbonized
grid or renewable energy or through
geopolitical restructuring events like
war. The goal here is to use sustainable
design to move us down these lines and
not enormous global conflict. And that's
really what's at stake here. This is an
all of MIT effort uh in order to
transition the global economy. Now,
that's improbable, but it's not
impossible. So, I'd like to end with a
little homage to to the improbability
walk behind MIT Nano. This was the
brainchild of Vlad um as uh as to honor
Millie Drestle House, the queen of of
nanocarbon. And Millie used to say that
her path from being the daughter of a
Polish immigrant to an institute
professor at MIT was was highly
improbable, but importantly not
impossible. The same is true for this
challenge.
[Applause]
Wait as it comes on.
Okay. Okay. Can you guys hear me? All
right. Thank you. Uh, thanks for having
me, Vladimir and Benedto. Um, so I'm
going to talk about Huh.
I'm going to talk about uh uh uh what we
are doing in my lab. uh we work on
advanced materials and interfaces and
interestingly they go across climate to
health and in fact a lot of the climate
problems impact health and I'll
highlight two things we are doing on
carbon capture and on uh uh and on in
agriculture today um uh so as you've
already heard um uh the uh the carbon
problem is a gig scale problem uh and
for us to be able to remove uh so many
giga tons of CO2 we have been we need to
be thinking about scale from the get-
go. And as was highlighted before, there
are many scales here. And um we need to
go to macro scales, but using really
nanocale uh effects because surface to
volume ratio plays a very very important
role. And if you look at the whole
carbon problem, it's really a capex opex
problem. And how do we kind of solve
this capex opex problem has been at the
heart of a lot of the things that uh
we've been working on. And then if you
go to renewables, you need storage
otherwise uh it's it's hard to uh
transition. And um uh while I'm not
going to cover this today, but we've
been working on non-lethium,
nonflammable batteries. It's been
commercialized with a company where I
co-founded called Alim Energy and um u
and we hope to put things out into
market in maybe 2027. uh but it's really
kind of closing these loops uh will help
us to do the energy transition. So let
me kind of jump into the CO2 capture and
conversion and thinking about this at
scale uh from the get-go. And uh we've
been looking at different sources of CO2
whether it's point source all the way to
uh dock and DAC. So these are oceans
where you have CO2 concentrations that
are 100 times more than in air. So it's
more concentrated so you can process
less volumes. um you know shockingly the
same concentration as you would see in
the exhaust of a gas turbine. So uh
ocean acidification effects are already
having a big impact right here you know
next to us in Maine. So I'll talk uh
talk a little bit about that and then
how do you capture and then valorize
that CO2 so that you can make something
that's economically feasible. So if you
look at our conventional sort of ways to
do capture and conversion, you're going
um the capture step uh is you know uh if
I draw here the there are no numbers
here but it's cost versus uh cost versus
energetics. The um the cost to capture
is the capture is driven mostly by
kinetics. So it's a capex problem and
then you need to extract and then you
need to do something with it and you now
start to add uh a lot of energetics. But
if you're able to actually go and
integrate a number of these components
for example instead of doing extraction
you do direct conversion then you can
have a lot of savings and those are the
kind of system level architectures that
we are also been implementing. So an
example I like to start off with is the
Petronova plant. If some of you have uh
known or seen these, this is a u it took
500 where where is this going? Yeah,
it's a $500 million capex uh plant uh
and it's about the size of this
credential tower uses amines to capture
CO2 and where the solubility of CO2 is
pretty high. But so one of the questions
I had was why do you need such large
towers and we started looking at uh some
of these uh things to to to optimize
this and actually this went out of
business when uh oil markets crashed
because the CO2 was used for enhanced
oil recovery here. Um so if you uh kind
of look at this these are all packed bed
kind of reactors and um uh the
absorption rate is controlled by film
thickness which is on the order of
hundreds of microns. So the thought was
okay how do I increase surface area? I
could go to finer and finer drops and
create finer and finer mists and you can
now significantly increase sort of that
surface to volume ratio and go to large
capture and significantly reduce the
capex and cost etc. The question is okay
you know why didn't anyone do this
because you missed get entrained and you
can go out if you look out there you
know you can see a bunch of that plumes
coming out of cooling towers there you
can see a plume right there so we have
solved this problem before where we um
where we have invented a technology
where we sort of inject these plumes
with electrical charge and we when you
switch on we can sort of capture that
and this has actually been
commercialized now uh with a uh where
I've taken this out through a company
called infinite cooling and we
demonstrated this at scale actually at
MIT uh power plant here. So um so if you
take something like that and we're
combining that with our carbon capture
mists we can significantly reduce capex
costs uh and then bring this down and uh
we've actually proven this out for
cooling towers and we can bring this to
bear to uh to to some of these
absorption towers. So this is actually a
a prototype that went from lab the one
that I just showed you which was a
coffee strainer to uh to the MIT cooling
tower all the way to now industrial
cooling towers and now being deployed at
EDF uh where uh we've now modularized
this uh to do uh industrial cooling
tower capture but then we are uh using
these technologies and putting them
together to really think about
absorption towers in a totally different
uh way and kind of scale uh make them
more efficient and reduce the capex
costs.
The other uh another interesting uh
challenge that came up was in in all of
these capture systems, you have some
sort of an absorber, right? Like the
hydroxide solutions that I showed you.
Uh and then you need to then release the
CO2 or do conversion of that CO2. And
these are both at odds with each other.
And that's because what happens is the
absorption here u and the conversion
leads to when you want to do absorption
you need hydroxide concent hydroxides to
be there and when you are doing
conversion you want everything to go
into a carbonate and what happens is you
end up somewhere in the in in between
and so the higher the carbonate loading
the worse the absorption is and then or
the higher the hydroxide when you come
into the conversion part you're
essentially protonating this so you
create water so who want to make sure
that you get complete conversion but
most of the times you're not you're you
know sort of in this 50/50 kind of
range. So one of the things we did was
how do you solve this constraint? You
know you're in the absorption you're in
this corner. Ideally you want to be here
when you're doing conversion but you end
up sort of being here or in that
extreme. So you want to kind of uh
create some black box here that's going
to decouple these two systems. And uh
what we did was so that you can then uh
have something that do does the
absorption and then something that does
a conversion. So the way we did this was
using um you know nanopiltration where
you can now separate the carbonate and
the hydroxide ions in a way that uh you
can now create a system that uh uh feeds
that basically uses uh the hydroxides
here for the capture and the conversion
is uh purely u on the carbonate uh
solutions
and uh you know this uh was extremely
effective. uh we've gotten a significant
boost in the uh cost reduction but also
operational stability and operational
window for both the capture and release
uh kind of steps. So my kind of goal is
putting all these together uh we have
had few other uh nice inventions here on
uh looking at um conversion and scaling
conversion using hierarchical uh gas
diffusion electrodes. And so I start
with my source uh do this sort of a
capture and then using uh some of the
electrochemical reduction steps that
where we've shown uh using these
hierarchical conductors to scale we can
actually then regenerate our sorbent and
bring it back and so this kind of
overall cycle uh could really uh
increase the both reduce both capex and
opex and increase the operational
stability of these kind of systems. So
I'll quickly step to another side of the
story which is um which is uh oceans
right so a lot of about 30% of our
emissions partition into the oceans
leading to increased ocean acidification
and um uh but the interesting thing is
the oceans are the biggest contacttor
there is and you have about um you know
100 times more CO2 in ocean uh captured
than uh in air and therefore uh the
capture step is kind of already done for
you. So what we have done here is using
a process where we electrochemically uh
do convert the bicarbonate into
molecular CO2 where it could be stripped
off and then regenerated here where we
deeprotonate and can release alkalized
water. Uh we've been able to get this
with the some of the lowest energetics
per ton of CO2 uh no membranes and we
could create these nice um uh nice
effective alkalized ocean streams.
>> Yeah.
I'm sorry.
>> What? What?
>> Yeah.
>> Sure.
Okay. So uh so what we are doing is we
are trying to extract that CO2 out of
these uh out of the oceans and these
could be deployed in um you know in
offshore systems or in um or uh you know
with shipping and others and one uh
interesting application for us here is
in aquaculture where uh ocean
acidification effects have really sort
of diminished the carbonate that's that
is needed to actually form for shellfish
to form shells and is a uh interesting
market where the specific value of the
CO2 removal is quite high and um in fact
there's been a loss of productivity in
uh Washington oyster uh kind of market
as well as in U of Maine where ocean
waters are artificially buffered today.
So uh we are using this as a as a uh
opportunity for us to show that you can
actually do this capture and act and
have impact on um uh on coastline
communities as well as local economies
and uh and create a local economic case
for this uh for this uh problem. So uh
the way this is done is we are
partnering with UF main and this is
aragonite super saturation as a function
of pH. So there is a window where we can
optimize these waters today actually
they actually buffer the ocean water
artificially to be able to grow these
shellfish. So uh we are we are scaling
up our technology and what we have done
here is already shown with U of Main
that we can actually apply our buffered
waters. So we are electrochemically
removing the CO2 and taking these
alkalized streams that we're creating
and is already uh uh we've been we
demonstrated that we can instead of
artificially buffering we could sort of
do it this way and this is some some
recent experiments with scallops and and
other things. Um and how much time I
have I have in the last few minutes I'll
talk about some of the work we're doing
in agriculture. uh in agriculture you
know there's a lot of uh agrochemicals
that are sprayed for crop protection and
um this is a big challenge because
farmers are sort of you know some of the
most entrepreneurial people I've met
they want to try everything to make
things work uh and one of the issues is
crop protection is so important uh
otherwise you know you have significant
yield losses and so on and uh um you
know this is uh uh amount of pesticides
that are that are sprayed per year um
you know over a billion drops are
sprayed in an acre but we don't know
where all these drops are going. Uh we
uh and so spraying is kind of blind and
we you know we spray and pray that
things happen and your crops are
protected. So as a result there's a lot
of overspraying and one of the issues is
actually a lot of uh leaves tend to be
mildly or mostly hydrophobic and you end
up with lot of drops actually coming off
and leading to uh significant
agricultural runoff. And here what you
see is um a result of that leading to uh
contamination drift um you know ending
up in air in our soils uh and also at
the same time this is a huge market
right so uh we've kind of tried to
understand why this is the case and uh
this is looking at dynamics of drops
impinging these kind of surfaces and how
can you get them to stick better so you
can significantly cut this uh down
because if inefficiency is happening
because drops are bouncing off of
surfaces though they add aduants or
surfactants to these things and the and
the important thing is it's in this
contact time. So the time it takes for
surfactants to diffuse to the interface
is way larger than the uh impact time
scales. So uh long story short is we
came up with many different techniques
and one of them here was uh using uh you
know very thin nanoscopic cloaks that uh
can be then deployed onto these droplets
that allow immediate uh arrest and
striction. And these are all essentially
plant derived oils and we have uh other
things that we can use and what we have
seen is a significant reduction in the
amount of pesticide use uh and um uh and
so on. So we went to the farms we tried
it tried this out to take this out and
we actually formed a company called Axen
to commercialize this. When we went to
the farms you know farmers have to deal
with so many things. This is a boom
sprayer. There is all kinds of uh you
know parameters spray height you know
droplet size uh etc etc that these
people have to keep track of as this is
happening. So the farmers had asked okay
this is all great we want to use it how
what do I know about my current
coverage? how much of coverage am I
getting because they all know coverage
is a king in terms of crop protection
and uh so no one has measured this no
one knows where these drops are going so
we actually came up with a an approach
where uh we have a uh we we devised a
tool uh which is I know can can someone
click that u can you click the top thing
so we devised a tool where you can do a
bolt-on retrofit and actually in line
when the farmer is spraying we can find
out where these drops are landing, how
many drops are there, and how much
coverage they're getting. So, if they're
getting too fast, you can see that their
coverage is obviously dropping, if
they're going too slow, and they can
actually change uh what they what
chemicals they're using. And we have a
kind of a heat map of where they're
doing sprays better and not. And the the
amazing thing here is to give you a
billion dollars back to farming in a
year, all you need to do is 6% savings
in these agrochemicals. And today we
have shown that this is deployed now in
a million acres and we have shown that
we can do 30 to 50% savings. So uh we
are hoping that this will fundamentally
change spraying and can really deliver
value to uh to the customer uh to the to
the farmer. Um that's that's all I have.
Thanks.
[Applause]
I would like now to invite the speakers
to come to the podium so that we can
have the panel discussion at the end. So
first of all, thank you very much to
Kria, Desire and Michael for their great
talks. I think they were extremely
uh instructive and we all learn a lot.
I' I've been told that every time you go
to a talk at MIT, you need to learn
something
and I feel like I learned so much.
So um you clearly showed us different
type of innovation when it comes to
having impact on climate at different
level right starting from the very basic
science and how to design new materials
to uh valorize waste up to having a
system level approach where you're
really thinking of how to uh modify
industries that are well entrenched in
our life and how we can design new
materials to be able to solve them and
how to retrofit environmental princ
principles in the design of our
innovation. And then of course with KIPA
we saw a technology among the others
technologies that start from the lab and
then they go out and have impact uh in
in the in the real life and in the
environment.
And so the first question uh that I have
to you that I would like to ask you is
when you when you at the end of the day
for us always starts with a student or a
postoc in a lab right and an idea that
has to be developed. So when you think
about solving a problem for climate, how
do you pick the technology? Like you
start from the solution that you find in
the lab and then you go from the problem
or you try to do vice versa or you
integrate both
>> me first. Uh
I think both approaches uh we're at an
institute of technology and so I think
you can do both both approaches. I think
um we're we're constantly looking in out
for for solutions and then I learned
from my colleagues uh more more depth
about these problems. You have to do a
lot of homework to really understand the
uh climate challenges problems the the
scale I learned I learned a lot actually
even just from listening to to my co to
my colleagues here. So I hope so I'm
gonna punt I'm gonna say both you do
both.
>> Any other input? Yeah, I I think that um
for me lately at least I you know I
started out in in my career as a as a
geochemist and oceanographer really
tracking molecules and worrying very
much about what the impact of that would
ultimately be. Um and so lately my
approach is definitely to kind of look
at global scale materials fluxes and say
what can somebody studying nanocale
processes really start to contribute in
this space and a way that it it ends up
impacting that that largecale operation
and then thinking about how you actually
get that from the lab out into the
economy. But um the students are are
definitely a primary area of focus. What
are they going to like? What is their
ambition? Uh what are their interests?
um because you always want to make sure
that's well aligned.
>> I'll just add to this that um I think
the the key point for me is you know
ultimately to have that impact uh what's
sort of the business case here and what
is the what is what how how do things
scale right and as a result sometimes
you may have a great idea which can work
in a small you know coupon sample that
may not scale because of various
constraints. So what are those
constraints? How do you then
debottleneck them? Is it a technology
issue or is it a supply chain issue or
what is it? And then once you know that
then you can create a really great uh
great project to to address those. So
it's the quest for you know how do
things get deployed and then what is the
science that one needs to do to to get
there.
>> Awesome. And then when it comes to take
a technology and try to transition out
of the lab, what is really required is
to have an ecosystem that help you um
and supports the PI in uh managing IP,
managing the conflict of interest,
managing innovation, managing the
policies, uh getting the funds. Um and
so I think that to some extent the the
MIT nano is a good community to start
thinking about um not only the
preparation, the synthesis and the
preparation, the characterization of the
materials, but also to build a community
within MIT that allows us to think
carefully and critically how to spin out
the technology. At the same time though,
the three of you from your talks have
interacted with either governments or
with with venture capitalist with the
startup environments and and so you may
have experienced challenging challenges
in taking a technology working with
governments and working with um uh with
with the ecosystem to try to take it out
of the lab and so what are your
experiences and how do you think it I
don't think there's a there's a major
recipe for success particularly in
climate tech but what do you think are
the challenges that you that you
experience and how you think a solution
can be find to some of the challenges
>> this is a tough question I know so I
want to give you some
>> it's the perfect question for the two of
you actually it's a tough tough question
>> I could start if it's you
maybe kipa has many more startups than I
do I only have been through this twice
advice. Um but I think there are a few
uh you know failures in the way that the
academic to startup path is um ironed.
MIT is by far uh in a way the best at it
and I've seen other models. We we try to
remove as many barriers as possible and
yet they still exist. And a few that I I
guess I would highlight would be um the
mismatch of of time scale and
expectation in tough tech particularly.
So climate technologies um are hard,
right? We're not talking about using
software to program an app um to sell
dating or love or food services online
like we know those will sell themselves.
We're talking about really thin margin
industries that the whole world relies
on that are the basis of our economy and
then we have to make the technology work
on top of that which is often very
difficult um as you know this 18 order
of magnitude scaling is is no small feat
uh literally and figuratively and so
that I think um traditional venture
capitalists catalytic investors um
financial strategist strategic investors
are are are typically not um really
aware of the time scale and that can
lead to perceived failures that actually
criticize the entire industry or the
entire idea. So I'll I'll use algo
bofuel maybe as an example. There are
many um so I think that the time scale
adjustment is really critically
important. Um nth cycle is a technology
that uh came out of the carbon
nanocience that I did here at MIT as a
as a graduate student. It's now um com
we opened the first domestic cobalt and
nickel supply facility this year in
Ohio. Um that was an incredibly proud
moment. It's still incredibly
challenging to to have the struggle of
working with mining companies versus
battery companies versus um different
types of of investors and and managing
all of those expectations and the
timelines um and and they're just not uh
harmonized and that's really what
creates the lag and it's a luxury we
don't have. I think the second thing
that's a real challenge is um managing
conflict of interest. I'm kind of
naively, you know, optimistic that we're
all in this for the right reasons and we
want to see our technologies have the
impact on the world. Um not everybody is
like that, right? So we have to have
conflict of interest rules. Of course,
some of them are structured in a way
that once you spin out a company, you're
no longer allowed to work on that
technology. That doesn't make a lot of
sense um to take somebody who spent a
decade or their entire life thinking
about a problem really deeply and say
and now you're no longer allowed to work
on that in this capacity. You know, we
bring a lot to the table as professors.
We're able to mobilize, you know, uh
scores of of individuals, sometimes many
more than that and often many more than
that. Um we shouldn't be eliminated from
doing that because we had an idea that
we wanted to see be not just the paper
but actually the product.
Oh great those are good points
just to add to what the said uh I think
in my journey I found um
so first step was uh knowing your
customer what is where are you going and
most of the times you may start with ah
that's my problem I'm solving and you
find yourself at a point where maybe
that's not what is needed and you have
to then pivot or adjust and or you you
uh for example on the topic that I just
showed you, we had a solution for
reducing agricultural sprays, but then
the farmer wanted to know how much is
actually on their leaves. So if we
didn't listen to that, we wouldn't be we
wouldn't be in a place where we are
today because knowing that and taking
that as an opportunity, we came up with
a tool that tells them now how
inefficient they are and then we can,
you know, come up with ways to then
deploy what we have what we what we have
invented. And the other thing that also
also uh becomes useful is um you know
when I did my first startup I had a
proof of product which was a ketchup
bottle and people said oh this is great
uh I can see how this could be used and
then we went to the next and then you
know we had to scale from there well it
worked there and we we showed how we
could do it but scaling to making
hundreds of bottles per minute I did not
even think of that. So it's huge
manufacturing challenges uh there. So
the next thing next company I did we
started thinking about scale from the
get-go right doing that along with the
science and then you can see we then you
deploy it we deployed it here and what
that does is as you keep doing that you
can reduce the risk for investors and
these are all very capital intensive uh
markets. So how can you um how can you
get there fast and how can you reduce
the overall capex and opex as you go
through this journey has been an
important learning and as you said the
capital availability is not you know
infinite right so everyone has their own
liquidity timelines and so on so you
need to have a return on investment so
how quickly could you start making money
on on the things is is very very
important you can't just say okay I'm
going to do this for another 10 years in
a startup because then the startup won't
exist or the markets would have changed
or rules would have changed. Uh and so
keeping all that in mind and quickly
getting to revenue is is key to making
this happen.
And a question that I have uh for
Michael and if somebody wants to submit
questions you can always use the QR code
over there in case but although we are
running out of time but you Michael have
worked on carbon nanot tubes for um um
since I I I follow your research
and I think the the trajectory that I
saw for for the use of carbon nanot
tubes which are have been extremely
powerful like as a as an example of
nanotechnology has been that many people
have seen the potential but then when it
came to adoption
There was some skepticis because there
were many um some concern about safety
for example and although the community
fought back and and they presented cases
I think when it comes to use them in
plant you develop a very clever way to
justify the use of carbon nanot tubes
through the the plant sentinel model. So
um do you think that the question that I
have is how do you come up with the idea
of the plan sending
>> to that? Um well maybe maybe it's a
reminder maybe it's it's a reminder that
uh the solutions to the problems we
heard about today may may come from
inventions that that don't exist yet
actually that we're still at an
institute of te of technology and we we
can we can still innovate and and pull
pull pull things out. I mean I think my
I I I learn a lot from my colleagues
with respect to innovation. These are
some of the uh the most c creative
people here we have at at MIT. I think I
would like to think we inspire each
other. And uh I'll make a a comment
about about the the previous big not to
bring it down a notch but I have uh my
lab we have more experience I think in
licensing tech technology. We don't
think about that that that as well. you
can do a startup or somebody can come
and license te technology and I I've
always found that also to be an awkward
process that there's you're in this
liinal space just because someone else
now has the right to your patent it
doesn't mean all of that engineering
knowhow just magically transfers we have
to rely on our students sometimes people
that that have already gone and and and
it is awkward and there's conf conflict
of interest and I found that that
process could be streamlined a bit a bit
better some sometimes a firm will uh
hire you and your students as
consultants for a little bit of time
while you go and set up shop in their in
their facility. I often think maybe like
my colleagues sometimes a startup would
have been better a better vehicle and so
if there are people out from Sloan or
people that think on the on the policy
side uh we definitely need attention to
to that problem. I'm sorry that was a
little more into the
>> No, but that I think that's part of what
we need to do as a body of faculty when
it comes to particularly when it comes
to climate technology. It will require
new rules of engagement to be able to
bring these technologies out. The usual
model that we see doesn't work for us.
And so as the innovation enterprise and
the research enterprise of MIT will
change in the coming years, I think that
our voice has to be more and more heard
from the whole ecosystem of innovation
when it comes to what it takes and what
are the challenges and the opportunities
to take this deep tech outside the lab.
Thank you very much. I think our time is
up.
[Applause]