we're realizing that the whole
generative AI boom is actually starting
to impact autonomous vehicles a lot of
the development that we can do could be
completely automated whether that is
generating synthetic environments to
test whether that is some AI system that
will make high level decisions
immediately in the future I think a good
chunk of this AI discussion will form
into what we call embodied AI putting
the AI into a system say on little
quadropad dog like robots or humanoid
robots frankly we might realize that
making high level decisions for say a
large number of space Vehicles might
become so much more effective that we'd
be very comfortable just sending out
millions of vehicles to the asteroid
belt whether that's for mining or
sustainability and so there's just so
many applications that we would pursue
that I think self-driving cars sometimes
take the Limelight for more MIT moments
from MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow