There's all these hidden things that are
around us that are the stuff that makes
up our world that make up the the the
food we eat. Uh the the pharmaceuticals
we make uh the the chemicals and
materials that are around us, the
materials we use to build our built
world, those are also extraordinarily
carbon inensive. They lead to huge
amount of emissions that arise from the
production of those materials. things
like steel. We, you know, we we make
enormous quantities of steel around the
world. We build literally skyscrapers
with steel. Every single atom in that
steel corresponds to a certain number of
molecules of CO2 that were emitted to
make that