hi open course whereare Learners we've
gotten to the part of the first lecture
where the technical difficulties made it
little too hard to follow what was
happening there so I'm going to uh
re-record what we all did as the opening
of the class to begin go ahead and go to
the URL on the screen right now this is
a project from Google called collab that
allows you to run Python scripts
including music 21 in your own browser
without installing anything on your
computer
so so go ahead and click this play
button you're going to see a warning
that uh Google didn't write this
notebook I did U it's I think it's
pretty safe what it does is it installs
the latest version of music 21 and Muse
score and some other software needed to
uh run some of the tools we're going to
be using without installing python on
your computer Google already has a copy
of Music 21 but this just uh brings you
to the latest
version and go ahead and pause and we'll
come back after it's all installed
welcome back I hope that the cells
aren't um running anymore so we can
start uh coming in if you've never used
a Jupiter notebook or another online
collaborative environment the important
thing that you're going to need is to be
clicking into these cells the gray ones
are where U type and the uh ones with a
white or black background are the ones
where uh output's coming out in order to
run a cell you just type shift and
return or shift and enter so what we're
going to do is I'm just going to um
click into this cell and hit shift enter
and this will make sure that music 21
actually works sometimes the first time
you show a score it um it doesn't work
as well and on some browsers this will
work um you can listen to a score
and we's see if this works or
not there we go and now we're ready to
actually begin uh we're not going to
generate with AI today we'll write our
own
scores so with you're with me we're
going to start uh anything where you're
doing a python session by importing the
code that's useful and for this one it's
uh the music21 toolkit so we're going to
import everything from it if you're
somebody who done a lot of python and
cares about things like polluting your
namespace you can do individual mod
modules but I'm always going to do it as
if we have all the parts of Music 21 at
your
fingertips so we're going to load a
Corral by Johan Johan Sebastian Bach
it's a shortest Corral called bwv 66.6
so first I'll create a variable call it
boach and we'll use the Corpus tool from
music 21 and it's parse function to load
in Bach bwv 6 6.6 I'll hit shift enter
and it's assigned to boach and we can
call the method show on it to see the
score of that Yep looks like a crow by
Bach and you can see that has soprano
Alto tenor base and we can get the alter
part by saying um bach. Parts square
brackets open Alto and we'll just show
that
yes looks like the Alto part now we'll
get the soprano part and assign it to a
variable sop for soprano and we'll just
do that instead this time we'll get it
by doing the part number and so it's the
first part and so in Python that means
it's part zero Parts zero and one of the
things that we do in music 21 is when
something is in a programmer
rule we follow um the conventions of
programming where everything starts with
zero and when we're in musician space
such as talking about measures we don't
subtract one from the measure number or
anything like that so if we wanted to
just see measures 3 through five
inclusive of the soprano part we could
do something like that
oops or we could type the word measure
properly and then we'll get that measure
just gets a single measure this one got
that great and um in fact we'll use the
measure thing now and we'll get in
measure five the zero first second note
the one with the forada on it and so
we'll call it C because it's a c
actually it's a C sharp but um well
we'll see why not and so we'll get notes
number
two if we called it C
then everything after this would be a
common so that doesn't work so we'll
just call it c um and now what we can do
is manipulate it change its style it's
color to
red and now when I show the soprano part
because uh they're all linked to each
other we should see yep there's a note
that's in
Red so that's how we can manipulate a
score and now let's see how we can do
some analytical functions on things so
let's do Baka analyze and we'll analyze
the key of the
piece and it says it returns a key
object that says it's in F minor and one
of the things I really want to emphasize
is always go back and do the smell test
is this true ises it look like baloney
and we can kind of see well begins in a
but it does have three Sharps and at the
end yep there is an FP in the base so
looks kind of like F major but yeah okay
here some F minor okay it kind of passes
the spell tests and we'll see why that's
so important in just a little bit but it
did seem like it was beginning in a so
we can just analyze a portion of that so
we'll do B measures zero because we want
the pickup measure and two and we'll
analyze the of just that
passage uh does seem to start in a
major let's do something that seems
pretty simple let's count the number of
notes in the piece so we can just do Len
bach. notes that just gets uh all the
notes the piece in another language
would be bl. notes. length and I don't
know
um I don't know how many notes are in
the piece but I'm pretty sure it's more
than zero and the Reas reason for this
is that music 21 and most ways of
conceiving music on the computer don't
think of the score as having notes the
score has Parts the parts have measures
and the measures have notes so what we
could do is get the length of Bach Parts
one measure two do notes and see okay
that passes the smell test so what we
can do instead is we can use something
called recurse so we'll get the bach.
recurse that's a function or a method
and we get the notes on that and what
recurse says is open up every box you
get to a part open it up look inside for
measures open it up and keep going until
you find
notes and 165 notes that seems to pass
the smell test to
me right now we've been working with
this as a series of of parts that are
not connected to each other but of
course there are chords in there also
but if we do um B Dot and here's another
way you can say recurse I want to
recurse and get everything that's a
chord there are no chords in this piece
so we have to create some chords using
the chordify method so we'll say core
for chords equals buck. chordify
and now if we
show the cified
method and we can see that some of these
notes are way too low to be read
properly and they have duplicated notes
and things and over the course of the
semester we'll find ways that we can
make this a lot more representable
including things like getting rid of
passing tones and other things that
disturb looking at the chords but for
now we can look at chord chord for the
chords the number of chords in that and
see that yep that looks like a
reasonable
number so I hope that gives you a taste
of some of what we're going to be doing
over the course of the semester of this
class now we've gone very fast through a
bunch of things but don't worry because
we're going to lock all those things up
cify is going to be locked up anal
analyze key is going to be locked up and
what mean that means that it won't be
available to be used in the rest of the
class until it's unlocked again the way
this class is going to work is all these
analytical tools all these ways of
conceiving a score will Begin by being
locked and then you'll do an assignment
either as a problem set or as uh in in
class assignment where we'll figure out
how does this work what what are the
ways of doing this and then once you've
designed your own algorithm for doing
these things you can either continue to
use your own algorithm or you will have
unlocked the music 21 version of the
algorithm and from then on you can use
that instead so we're going to just be
building up knowledge little by little
until we have
everything one of the things that as an
open courseware learner you won't have
access to
is the extremely valuable things that
happened outside of class yes coming to
office hours but mostly with students
helping each other giving each other
inspiration for projects they could do
and helping them through some of the
more difficult parts of the class so I
encourage you if you can find somebody
else online who's also taking the course
or somebody who has taken it in the past
and get to know them that will give you
a lot more of the experience that the
students had at MIT when they were
taking the class in
person I'm so glad that you've chosen to
take your time to learn about the
fascinating world of Music Theory and
music analysis with a computer and I
look forward to seeing you again from
time to time in this course