hi everyone uh I'm Kina M the director
of MIT startup exchange I'm delighted to
be here with you today to present the
startup lightning talks we've invited 11
startups for you to meet uh first
they'll present here on stage and then
you can meet them all at the startup
exhibit that is taking place in the room
next door but first I'd like to um take
a few minutes to tell you about our
program startup Exchange was created
within MIT corpet relations to support
MIT connected startups grow expand and
solve The World's great challenges and
we do that by fostering collaborations
and Partnerships with industry such as
ILP carpet members as many of you are
and the MIT Innovation
ecosystem startup exchange we focus on
startups that have a strong connection
with the Institute and this connection
might come through the founding team the
technology as well as through their
affiliation to some of our peers on
campus who vet and support the startups
like start. Nano or MIT uh C sales
startup connect plus just to name a
couple um today our programs has a
network of about 1,000 startups
virtually working in any sector and this
is possible because the startups we
support they can come out from any part
of MIT any of the five schools and one
college uh some graduate from mbas other
courses and a considerable number of
companies they graduate from the MIT
entrepreneurship resources and there are
over 80 across campus you'll find most
of them listed at orbit. mit.edu that
our colleagues from The Martin trust
Center uh
created um the other two data points I'd
like to make here is that besides sector
agnostic startup exchange is also
location agnostic I mean startups can be
literally located in any country to
benefit from the program and we
typically start working with them when
they have a technology or a product that
is ready to be tested or used in Real
Environment now everything we do at
startup exchange is to expose and
connect startups and carpets in a highly
creative way
and we also provide learning
opportunities for them um this includes
launching calls for startups throughout
the year based on corporate uh
challenges uh facilitating uh one-on-one
meetings and hosting different kinds of
um events and um the workshops we co
organize them with our
peers um and uh just I forgot to make a
point here here um so the goal of all
our activities is to on the one hand
help startups validate pivot expand and
help corporates learn about the
Technologies and products that are
coming into the market to help you speed
up your Innovation or transformational
processes and even uh expand your
portfolio products or create new
business
lines this slide features is a small
sample of the success cases we had to
date that typically range from proofs of
concept Pilots joint development and
even Acquisitions this is startup
Exchange in a nutshell if you'd like to
learn more about our program happy to
talk uh over the course of this day um
please reach out to my team and I and um
before passing the word to the
entrepreneurs I'd like to invite you to
our upcoming events uh next week we're
hosting the health science forum and in
October we have a webinar about Advanced
design manufacturing and on October 22nd
we'll be back here at the marad for our
annual sustainability
conference and now it is my pleasure to
kick off the startup
presentations um as I mentioned earlier
each one of them will do a five minute
pitch followed by the exhibit