another type of quantum computer is a
Quantum simulator a processor that
simulates the behavior of a physical
system a chemical reaction or a
biological process it's estimated that
somewhere between 1 and 2% of worldwide
energy production is used to produce
ammonia for agricultural fertilizer the
key step is a process called nitrogen
fixation which requires both high
pressure and high temperature in
contrast there exist bacteria which even
at room temperature can catalyze
atmospheric nitrogen into ammonia how do
the bacteria do it well we don't really
know precisely simulations with
classical computers only provide
approximate answers on the other hand a
Quantum simulation would provide the
reaction energies that are involved in
the nitrogen fixation this type of
quantum chemistry simulation has many
applications for example developing new
pharmaceutical drugs or tailoring a
material to have unique properties for
more MIT moments from MIT open learning
like subscribe or follow