Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
MPG primer and today I have the pleasure
of introducing Masa Kai. He is a
research fellow in Dr. Remnik Xavier's
laboratory at MGH and at the Broad here.
Um he previously completed his PhD in
biomedical informatics at Harvard
Medical School where he was co-vised by
doctors Mark Daly and Hillary Finine. As
a statistical geneticist, his research
focuses on identifying causal genetic
variants underlying complex diseases and
traits across diverse population. Add
additionally he leverages multiomics
approaches to functionally characterize
these causal variants and aims to
elucidate the molecular mechanisms
driving complex diseases. Um if you have
questions throughout, please come down.
The microphones are here on the side
again. Um and yeah, take it away Masa.
Thank you. All right. Thank you so much.
Um and thank you so much joining my uh
MPG primer this morning. Uh I'd like to
talk about uh fine mapping complex
traits in the bio
ranks. So for the first part of my talk
uh I would like to give a brief
introduction to f mapping. Before diving
into uh the details of the introduction,
uh I would like to um give a special
thanks to my colleague Ram uh who have
been working together with me for many
projects and she did great MPG primer
two years ago and geniusly shared a
couple of her background slides um for
my talk today.
So as many of you are familiar with uh
Jersus have been very very successful at
finding associations uh in the last 20
years. Uh this is the latest skier jus
from the PGC consortium. There are
around 300 LOSI that are general
significant. But if you really zoom into
each of these significant lossi
uh you may realize um pinpointing a
causal variant is really challenging.
This is primary because of their uh
because uh these genetic variants are
created each other
uh which is called linkage dise
equilibrium or aldi. Uh and this
correlation makes harder to identify
which one of these corated variants are
actually causally associated with a
disease.
So many of the f mapping methods uh aim
to nominate causal variants uh based on
the
scenario. Now you have a GS data which
is
observed and there should be a causal
snips which is
unobserved. What we observe is basically
the representation of these two causal
variants. Um and uh due to Audi and
noise uh we observe you know this kind
of locust
part and f mapping methods uh basically
uh disentangle these audi structure uh
into independent signals uh aiming to
identify each of these uh causal
variants.
So suppose this is a goal. Uh many f
methods uh outputs two
things. Uh first outputs is called
posterior inclusion probability or pip
uh which is a probability that a variant
is causal uh given the observed data.
uh second outputs is a kable sets which
mean to capture the uncertainty uh of
the identity of the coal variance due to
LD so you often uh see you know quable
set 95% corable set or 99% corable set
which basically means uh this you know
quible sets capture 95% of the PIP for
debinding dependent
signal and fapping methods basically
outputs these you know p um two outputs
and we heavily rely on um these outputs
to interpret which causal variance or
which signal uh is more likely to
cause. So based on uh these concepts uh
now I'd like to uh give a brief overview
of the f mapping methods.
uh I think there are two major axis uh
to categorize these fine mapping
methods. The first axis on the y-axis is
basically whether you model single coal
variant or multiple coal variants. Uh
and the second axis you can see on the
x-axis is basically um whether a method
is primary for a single cohort or
multiple cohorts. And for multiple
cohorts uh there's a distinction whether
uh your analysis is based on the meta
analysis or joint analysis or mega
analysis.
Um I don't dive into uh details into
each of the method uh but I would like
to cover uh some of the major methods
here uh and give you know a basic
concepts behind it. So the first uh and
the most straightforward one is this uh
method code or
ABF. ABF or approximate base factor uh
is basically a B method person you know
base factor for uh each variant. Um this
is pretty simple as you can see in the
equation here. Um this method basically
assumes a single causal variant in a
locus.
So
um in most cases uh these base factors
are roughly a monotonic transformation
of the Gcores that you observe in the
Gus and highest PIP uh are almost always
given to the uh most significant
variant. Uh this is you know very simple
uh method but still um
uh powerful or robust method that you
can rely on in many cases especially if
you don't have access to the LD matrix
or you know good external LD difference
panel ABS method is um the first method
you must try for your summary
statistics but of course because we
assume a single causal variant in a
locus. Uh this is a big uh limitation of
the AVF
method. So suppose uh in a um scenario
like you have uh three variants uh in
this particular great there's one uh two
variants called purple and letters are
causal variants. Uh gray variants in the
middle is just a non-causal typing
variants. But if these two causal
variants are weakly targeting the middle
non-cooaler variants and the two causal
variants are independent to each other
then ABF assigns the highest PIP to the
non-cooaler variant because the uh this
you know non-cooal variant is ted weekly
by two causal variants and having the
highest uh Gcore
similarly in a scenario where you have
two causal variants in the locus. Uh but
um neither of these two causal variants
are generally significant because uh
these two coar variants are correlated
to each other and have opposite uh two
causal effects or uh they have same
cause effects that
um correlation negative between the two
and in this case basically Audi cancels
out these coal effects. and ABF assigns
a low PIP to the non
associations and this might sounds like
a hypothetical alterations but we do
actually observe you know such examples
in the G data. So here this is in the
chromosome 5 in FGFR
for height uh we find mapped you know uh
in three bio banks BBJ and the UK bio
bank. If you focus on this uh ROS
244711 uh variant uh this variant is
actually fine mapped in every cohort but
not general wireless significant only in
the biomark Japan.
If you look closely uh into the
underlying causal structure, we
basically found out that there's another
uh miss uh miss variant of the FGFR4
uh which is also fine mapped in a
cohort and this miss variant has a
negative correlation to the uh this
RS244 the second causal variant only in
the bio bank Japan. So only in the bio
bank Japan the causal effects are
canceled out and the secondary uh causal
variant is not generally significant in
the
BBJ. So this clearly illustrates uh we
have to model multiple posants
uh for um for whatever you know five
mapping method you use uh for highly
powered
right so this is a natural
uh introduction to the um second cross
obser mapping method uh which I'd like
to cover today uh which is basically the
single cohote multicoser variance f
mapping method. There's a plenty of
multiple variance f mapping method for a
single cohote. Uh but if you
um ask us to characterize into you know
uh three
categories I think the first category is
uh basically conditional analysis. Uh
this method is sometimes called uh cojo
AVF. Uh basically cojo is a method that
you can do a conditional analysis on the
summary statistical level.
Um and ABF is a method that I described
earlier. So suppose uh you have uh you
observed um this uh kind of a rogus part
from your giver. You if you condition
the leader signal
uh using co then there then you might
observe the secondary signal independent
from the first variant. Co IBF simply
applies ABF method to the first summary
statistics. uh that conditioned on um
the second variant and a second summary
statistics that conditioned on the first
variant. So that by um by doing a
conditional analysis uh you can get
approximate um independent signals for
uh each of the method.
Um this is a kind of a powerful approach
but uh has a one uh big c big caveat. Uh
this method basically doesn't uh handle
the situation uh like the one left where
your uh non-causal variant is tucked
weakly by multiple causal variant. In
this case the lead variant is a
non-cooaler variant and if you condition
on the non-coosal variant uh then you
you basically lose uh independent signal
for both of the coal variants that are
retired.
Um so there's a more sophisticated
method uh which directly model causal
confilations
uh such as chabier kab f map
andg. So suppose uh you have um m
variance in the locus. Uh they're 2 to m
uh combinations of uh whether each of
the variants in the locus are kosa. Uh
you typically limit how many coal
variants uh or how many ones in this
gamma array um can uh exist together.
uh and you're going to compute uh this
probability uh based on some some
algorithm. Um most of their uh prior
methods
behun stocastic search which basically
enables bunk scale mapping. Um and the
pastries don't have to be
yep
in your
screen. Close this hiding some of the uh
Thank you.
Sure. It's fine. All right. Uh
uh where okay is a sub category uh of
the matcha variant uh fapping method is
some of the single effects model or
suji.
Uh basically in this model instead of
uh creating your you know single gammer
coal configuration
uh you divide uh your coal configuration
into L independent uh single effect coal
configurations.
uh and they basically uh developer uh
MPase iterative
uh they use their iterative basian step
wise selection uh or IB assess method to
comput distribution um of these single
effects and this substantially
um you know speed ups the computition
uh compared to the um previous
methods and basically these
computationally efficient methods such
as fine map and sushi uh booster uh
publishing a 2016 and 2020 uh has
finally enabled uh bio bank scale f
mapping like in the scales are 500,000
like a UK bio bank
and this opens a new mapping in my
opinion um just you know find map every
in uh in each bio
bank. So I'd like to switch my gear uh
and talk uh about the f mapping the
biomarks. There are a couple of
motivations why we want to find mapping
the biomanks instead of the a single you
know disease consortium or just a single
you know prospective cohort for one
trade.
First obvious reasons is now in the era
of the bio banks uh we have
substantially higher uh bigger number of
the you know samples and substantially
bigger number of the phenotypes that are
systematically corrected uh in each bio
bank. These are just examples but you
know you all familiar with the UK bio
bank uh finang or medium veteran program
bio bank Japan all of them have you know
more than uh uh hundreds of thousands of
the samples and hundreds of the
phenotypes that are systematically
corrected within each bark. Um and this
enable us a systematic comparison of the
fine mapping and the causal variance
across the diverse
operations. Actually uh in a global
effort called the global bio bank
metanas initi
uh we are able to uh collaborate with 23
barb banks around the globe totaling 2.2
million individuals. This is a data from
the 2022 and I believe now we have
around 30 bar banks uh more
than well I don't remember actual exact
numbers but you know uh these numbers
are growing uh and this made us are you
know this empires us uh to do a fire
mapping in at the
scale. Uh the second uh motivation is uh
we do expect more f mapping discovery by
starting more diverse cohorts. So in
human populations uh low frequency
varants are often tend to be a
population and ditched or
spasic and some of these variants are
even under section. So this is this one
where my favorite example uh alcohol
fresh and the AOD2
uh uh variant called
RS671. Um if you drink alcohol or
ethanol to be spacic um there are two
genes that are basically involved in uh
metaborization of uh alcohol.
Um
if you
have this RS671 variant basically that
inactivates AOD2 and these two are
basically a phenomenon called alcohol
fresh.
uh this particular variant is selected
in the east Asian populations
uh in the east regions uh
26% minor frequency in the rest of the
world less
than.1%. And moreover uh because
drinking behavior is heavily
um associated uh with your diet. uh this
RS671 associate with espherical cancer
and many other diseases um including you
know your uh good dietary pattern like
whether you want to whether you are more
likely to eat uh cheese or um drink a
milk or even a natto uh which is
fermented in soybeans
uh s motivation uh as we going to fact a
higher fapping resolution as you know uh
different ancestries have a different
audi length uh and
legions. So suppose you have two
populations that have a slightly
different uh audi length and
audiions by combining uh multiple
populations you're going to expect uh to
narrow down um basically audiion and
narrow down the causal variance. This
will highly uh uh improve the fing
resolution. So based on these
motivations uh
there uh multiple methods have been
proposed uh to conduct a multiple uh
cohort f mapping or multiple population
mapping. Um these uh methods are
basically divided into two groups
whether the meta analysis best or a
joint analysis based. So I'm going to
next explain uh what are the differences
of these two uh
approaches actually three
uh the first approach is the most
straightforward maybe uh it which is
very similar to the ga analysis
approach. Suppose you have a two
cohorts. Um you basically run GS in each
cohort metalises. You also uh computer
metanized audi matrix based on the uh LD
matrix from independent cohorts. Then
you quap this metanized gus and the
metaanized audi matrix. uh assuming you
know this summary statistics actually
came from a single cohort and they might
apply additional post QC
um to further uh remove a
spousal
signals. Uh second approach is uh kind
of similar to the meta analysis approach
but uh this is particularly we call a
post hawk meta approach. uh instead of
we are doing a meta analysis on the gus
we do a kind of a meta analysis on the
fine map to the f mapping
results so we basically done a fine
mapping in each individual cohort then
you're going to combine uh these f
mapping f mapping results either taking
you know uh minimum of the pip or
maximum of pip across the cohorts
And the um third um approach is a joint
modeling approach. So um baser past two
previous two approaches
are analyzed uh after an um analyze you
know each cohort separately. But in this
approach uh you model two cohorts
jointly. Um presumably on a single
server uh you basically you know get a
gira
um summary statistics and the audi
matrix from each cohort and you run a uh
you run joint file mapping on these uh
summary statistics and the
matrices. Um all of these methods works
to some extent. uh but there are also
challenges uh underlying on these
methods. Uh in particular
uh if you have multiple cohorts you
should always expect there's some
heterogenity across the cohorts. It
could be phenotyping like you know um UK
bio bank is a population based uh bio
bank Japan is a hospital based. So for
disease phenotype we observe a higher
hatability in BBJ but for biomarkers you
observe a higher hat in the UK bio bank
because you know biomarkers in the BBJ
to some extent is influenced by the you
know these hospital-based
recruitment. Uh it could also be a
genotyping and amputation. Each cohort
uh by nature uses a different genotyping
array and a different imputation
uh methods and these differences in
phenotyping genotyping imputation uh
inevit inevitably creates a heterogenity
across cohorts that you know poses a
substantial challenge in f mapping. uh
there's also issue of the lack of the in
sample audi or adequate external audi
difference to conductor f mapping um but
which is a basically a separate issue um
and separate issue
um and again um the heterogenity issue
is a dr issue this is one example from
the covid-19 host genetic censorship
where we basically observe serve in a
well-known tick 2 locus
uh non missense variant is not general
wise significant just purely because uh
some of the cohorts are not well
imputing
uh well imputing this missence variant.
So just because of the missingness uh
not because of the real biology we miss
this you know missense variant uh from
the statistical mapping um and this
poses a significant challenge in the
underlying matter not the method itself
uh for you know for conducting a a
multico
mapping to evaluate uh to what extent
these heterogenity influence
uh fine mapping across the cohorts. We
did extensive
simulations. For example, uh we
simulated uh different geotyping array
um um under different scenario and
observe you know uh to what extent uh
that
um different genotyping arrays uh
contributes to the host discovery rate.
uh we simulated the different imputation
panels that actually substantially
contributes to the host discovery rate
because of the differential missingness
patterns. We genuated the genetic
ancestry which to some extent
contributes to their FDR. Uh but more
importantly having African uh ancestry
uh contribute a lot to the improved
decal or improved power and this is
because African population tend to have
a shorter audi length compared to the
other
population. And finally a mixed scenario
where we observe in the worst case
scenario um there's a host discovery
rate observe up to the 30 to
40%. Um and this uh basically
demonstrates uh all the metalis mapping
is sign significantly miscalibrated in
the
generations. So to mitigate uh this
phenomenon uh we develop a method called
slurum. The idea is pretty
simple suppose you have
a g summary statistics like this. You
can say there's a one causal variant uh
that has five ting variants in a very
high linkage dis
equal. So we try to
um detect um locus that contains this
kind of a you know outrier variance
um and um identify uh low side that
contains you know such outri variants as
a suspicious low side for f mapping
based on um local
structure. Uh in the simulations we show
that um
um also not perfect
um host discovery rate uh in the
non-suspicious ROS side is 60% lower
compared to the suspicious ROS side and
in the real data using the GS catalog
here we use a nonmmerous uh coding
variant as a true coaler variants
because we don't know what is the true
causal variance we do see there
substantial enrichment
uh in the in the of the non synonymous
coding variance in a non-suspicious side
compared to the suspicious side.
Um both you know suggesting um several
methods make the issue of these you know
um um
heterogenity
mapping. So basically our studies shows
that you know naive uh single causal
variant or multiple causal variant
mapping methods are often miscalibrated
uh and post hawk tushi like a serum is
very important for a single causal
variant assumption
um we develop a method called serum and
there's a a recent paper uh that also
models a multiple cause varants if you
have are very good at matching out the
difference. Um, and this method is
called karma. Uh, and as you can
see here, uh, in the example
figure,
uh, where, um, basically, you know, you
have a two causal variants. Well, where
where you have um varants
uh many variants in the high
uh in the customer um they correctly
assign you know u low but uh nearly
equal pip to their multiple variants
whereas if you naively use a sushi with
the external reference panel then you're
going to get you know many like more
than uh or nearly equal to 10
um coal variance with BIP equal one. So
um this karma method works um well uh in
a situation when you have a good audio
difference panel like you know if you
are doing a uh the homogeneous uh
European meta analysis and this might
you know be additional
um support
um in addition to you know um uh our
proposal
message. Um you can also do a post hawk
meta approach. Um this is purely bas
assumption that uh if your single cohort
fing method is well calibrated
uh post hawk matter is often calibrated
but less powerful. So suppose you know
you have a UK bio bank Japan uh in each
bio bank you did a decent job of find
mapping you know these geo summary
statistics with sushi
uh instead of you know trying to do a
meta analysis or trying to do a joint
modeling across the cohorts that gives
you you know extra computational cost.
You can simply take a f mapping method
from each coord uh and combine results
by either taking the maximum for
um for most discovery or either taking a
minimum of a pip or you know very
consumptive
method. Um and in this way you can uh
hope you can basically preserve the
world calibration but less power or less
recall um without uh doing additional u
joint uh fine mapping or joint met
analysis across the
cohorts. All right.
Um then uh I would like to uh talk about
the uh final um category of the fine
mapping which is a joint analysis. Um I
don't particularly see a single causal
variant multiple cohort joint analysis
method. Uh I'm pretty sure there is but
I don't think um you know there's
nothing
um widely um or nothing outstanding um
but uh in the multiple causal variant
multiple cohort sing uh there's a pranky
m development uh going on
uh one of the first uh moser variant mut
A fat method is called painter which is
which was published in uh 2014 so 10
years ago more than 10 years ago. Uh
this methods is pretty you know um
innovative at the moment. Uh but
unfortunately not very computationally
scalable like you cannot you know model
multiple cause of varants um like more
than two or three based on the
complexity uh of uh depending on the
complexity uh in your
orus. Uh thanks to the develop
development of the suji
um there is a waves of the suji
extensions to our multiple
cohorts. Uh namely there are uh three
methods uh proposed so far. Uh first
things are Emmy Sushi Gwal Nature
Gentics uh Suji Ax uh by
Yang also Nature Gentics uh and there
finally Miuji
Mos which is currently in on the meta
archive.
uh these methods uh by
D shares the you know
same intention or same desire you want
to extend your sushi method into a
multiple operations but there's a you
know methodological differences uh among
the you know three methods
uh first of all uh among the three
methods uh only the me sushi
uh
can well only the MUI models
unsuspic variants. Sushi X and M sushi
for the sake of the computational
efficiency assumes their uh causal
variance are shared across the
populations if they exist I mean if they
are frequent um in a in a given
population
um based on the um literature'ses uh I
think this uh shared cause assumption is
very valu So you know uh flexibility in
the model um use your liberty for me
sushi uh to model as this particles
effect then uh for your effect size
modeling uh multi suji and mu sushi uh
models effect sizes are created across
ancestries uh to some parameter row um
and this is you know b's observations
are cross population uh gen correlation
Uh and finally uh on the uh post hawk uh
processing level uh there is the sushi
has a filter called py filter which
basically removes uh
quos that contains
um varants
uh with uh our scare they're um less
than a certain threshold. So that if the
qual set for a single effect if the
variants are not related to each other
in for for a given credible s then that
credible sat is deemed to be a non-pure
and removed from theis removed from the
out
uh multisji paper uh basically finds
that if you have this future uh maybe
your credible sets are pure uh
but um um uh decode is substantially
decreased. Uh and SUJIX basically uh
implemented uh disputed filter uh so
that in in their in the M suji papers
comparison they actually compared uh
suji x with future and the suji x
without you know future future. But
these are you know basically main
differences in terms of the um
theoretical um um
modeling and in terms of the performance
uh these are u performance comparison uh
based on the
shimmerations on the panel a uh we
basically compare uh calibration
uh so what you can see here is you know
for pap
9 a threshold basically three all the
methods all the sushi extension methods
have are very well calibrated
uh followed by pip me pip meta methods
which is basically taking the maximum
pip across the cohorts
um
and u um
naive meta analysis methods like HB
matter SCB matter is not calibrated
compared to the other methods. Uh in
terms of the recoil uh again uh three
methods have a very uh comparable recoil
uh mi suji uh is a top followed by suji
x and m sushi then pip matter
um and you know again naive methods
won't work well uh precision n car
basically gives you a same conclusion
and pan is important practically because
you you know if you run into a if you
run f mapping methods your computational
cost is a huge constraint.
Um and basically multisuji authors uh
shows that uh me sushi is a prohibitary
um slow uh and memory intensive compared
to the sushi x and the m
sushi. So based on these results um you
know
uh we can conclude that you know um
these sushi extensions to the multiple
cohort methods have a higher potential
um and higher potential for mapping uh a
cohort jointly
uh at a biod scale. But this comes uh
this always comes with a caution uh
which um I have to stress
uh these methods uh still suffer from
the
interceding especially missing us due to
the amputation
cori paper uh mitigates this issue by
using all of us the whole genome
sequencing data. So all the cohorts they
find mapped in their paper uh is a whole
general sequence uh and from a single
bio bank
um meaning you know we expect lesser
heterogenity across their populations.
But if you want to find map say UK bio
bank and uh MVP then you know these two
bio banks have completely different
phenotyping scheme generyping and
limitation technologies and you should
um really um put extra caution uh when
analyzing and interpreting these data uh
using their you know joint uh using the
these joint file mapping methods. May I
ask a question Masa? Sure. um in the
last 3 minutes or so before the Q the
official Q&A um is there a way that you
can sort of flag these regions where you
have this heterogeneity and missingness
so that you at least know not to look
under those rocks as much. Sure. So
that's basically the methods uh here
throw which frogs these outraear
variants in a single coer variant or
customer if you assume multiple coer
variants but these are the methods that
mean to you know frog these side and
then remove them and that can work with
the multiple um cohorts together.
Thanks.
All right.
[Music]
Um so
uh instead of summary uh I would like to
show this uh tentative best practice
flowchart uh which is beautifully
designed by uh LAN um
um suppose uh you have a low data
um and you want to basify map your GS
summary statistics. Uh if you follow
this scen uh for church uh you need to
what we believe as a best practice so
far for
mapping for first part. If you have our
individual remote data then you you know
first have to do uh Q and the GS uh in
the standard procedure very carefully.
But if your underlying um individual
data contains multiple
ancestries then uh we going to recommend
uh using uh m suji or sushi x for joint
f mapping or a pip matter uh for you
know single cohort f mapping then taking
a max pip across across operations.
If your uh cohort is
um negatively heterogeneous but still
within a similar ancestry ve
uh I didn't cover this topic uh in
today's talk but there is a method to
compute a coordinate adjusted matrix uh
which is important if you are cahot is
heterogeneous and then you can run a
standard f mapping exclusion f map and
if you are homogeneous computing
samp that's you know our recommendation
if you have our individual level data if
you have a summary level data knowing
sampleing then the meta analysis uh be
sorry f mapping becomes more uh
challenging and you need extra
caution your summary statistics is still
formal one code uh or if your meta
analysis
uh in your meta analysis all studies are
from the same underlying cohort like
auto bus or you know whatever as a
single uh technology or single cohort
then you can probably carefully choose
the external row difference that
represent your summary statistics
um then you can for multiple cause of
variant file mapping or if you don't
find a good reference You can either run
a serum or AVF
simply if you have a meta analysis uh
from a different ancestries. Uh only
thing you can do is aum um because karma
is not um currently handle that
particular
situation. So hopefully uh this uh best
practice flowchart will guide you to
some extent how you going to do a fine
mapping in your future studies.
Uh and with that uh I'd like to
acknowledge
um uh my uh PhD mentors Mark and Harry
uh Jacob Hun uh for their great support
during you know our f mapping work and
the rest of the colleagues for their
input for our project.