we are um talking about how consumers
make decisions last time we talked about
preferences and utility functions and we
let you have as much money as you want
today the bad news today we impose a
budget constraint and talk about how
consumers actually make decisions
realistically when they face a limit on
their resources and that's what we focus
on today so let's start by talking about
what budget constraints are budget
constraints and let's start by Bud talk
about budget constraint
construction we're going to go back to
our
example um of pizza and cookies and in
particular for the next I don't know 19
lectures we are going to make the
critical assumption that your budget
equals your income that is there is no
saving or borrowing you consume all your
income okay we'll come back and talk
about people make savings and borrowing
decisions later sadly this is not a
terrible approximation for Americans the
average American has less than
$1,000 in available savings to access so
actually measuring saying your
consumption equals your income is not a
terrible approximation to the way most
people in America have to live their
lives today okay so but it's very
important to remember it's not we're
saying people don't save and borrow they
do both we're just going to leave that
complication to later and assume that
every penny you have you're going to
spend on consumption goods and in this
case it's just two consumption Goods
slice of pizza and cookies so you're
going to write your budget constraint as
your
income okay equals the number of cookies
times the the price of cookies plus the
number of slices of pizza times the
price of a slice of
pizza okay that is your total spending
on cookies will be the number of cookies
you eat times the number the price per
cookie your total spending on pizza
slices will be the number of slices you
eat times your spending per slice and
that will add up to your income because
you got to spend your
income and that leads us to what we see
in figure 31 which is the budget
constraint something you become very
very familiar with over the next over
the coming weeks okay it's just a graph
of this
representation the xaxis represents how
many cookies you'd get if you spend all
your income on cookies which is your
income divided by the price of
cookies the Y AIS represents how much
you'd get if you spend all your income
on slices of pizza which your income
divided by the cost of a slice of
pizza and the slope critically is the
opposite of is the negative price ratio
critically the slope is the negative of
the price ratio minus PC over
PS
okay this is critical and we're going to
come back to why this is such a critical
concept the slope of the budget
constraint let's start with an example
imagine that your income is
$24 that the price of cookies is
$2 and the price of slice of pizza is
$4 okay imagine those are the parameters
you were given now you might ask where's
your income come from where's the price
of cookies come where the price slice
come from these two things we will tell
you where they come from we get to
Consumer Theory producer Theory we'll
talk you about how firms set these
prices but during in consumer Theory
we're taking them as const as given okay
so for the consumer theory part of the
course for this lecture and next lecture
okay we take these things as given we
get to producer Theory derive where they
come from
income comes from how hard you work and
what are the sources of income you have
we'll talk about that in a few lectures
for the next Le couple lectur we'll take
that as given so for today's purposes
you are given an income you're given
price prices and you have to decide how
you're going to optimize your bundle
given your preferences and given that
budget constraint and what's cool about
this course like I said it's a layered
course we'll come back and tell you
where all these things come from but we
go step by step to develop it right now
we take the step of those things as
given
okay now what this means is the slope
the slope of the budget constraint in
this example is minus
one2 so minus the price of cookies over
the price slice of pizza is - 12 that's
the slope of the budget
constraint and we're going to call this
the marginal rate of transformation
remember yes last time we had the
marginal rate of
substitution this is the marginal rate
of
transformation this is the rate at which
you can effectively transform cookies in
a slice of pizza this is not a course
about alchemy we're not going to teach
you how to transform cookies into pizza
but given the prices in your income
opportunity cost dictates that every
time you eat a cookie you effectively
reading one half fewer slice of pizza
why because cookies cost half as much
and you have to spend your income so you
spend it on cookies you're not spending
on pizza and vice versa every S Pizza
you have effectively that's too fewer
cookies so you're effectively
transforming pizza into cookies and vice
versa through the market through the
market by choosing one you're not
choosing the other that's why we're
called the Dismal science that's the
concept of opportunity cost nothing is
nothing is free every cookie you have
means less pizza every Pizza you have
means less cookies okay so that is uh
exactly the application of opportunity
cost
so this is sort of a difficult concept I
think so I like to think about this in
perhaps the best real world example of
how people can use budget constraints in
their lives which is Weight Watchers you
guys are all young and fit uh it is sort
of amazing we'll come back and talk talk
about obesity later it is sort of
amazing you look around this room there
is you guys are incredibly young and fit
you realize that onethird of Americans
your age are obese onethird 0% of this
class and onethird of Americans
something to just think about as we
think about what's the role of the
government in dealing with the problems
of society to realize that we've really
separated a lot between the halves and
the have knots on many things not just
money but also Health okay let me ask a
question how many of you guys drink
calorie or non- calori
soda okay that is stunning okay that is
stunning 20 years ago it would have been
100% okay it is really amazing we've
switched away from soda we you all
exercise switched away from Bad eating
habits it's just sort of amazing but
only in the most educated populations
this happen it's really quite striking
anyway um but so for many people
struggling with your weight is an issue
and Weight Watchers has a program that's
very effective it's one of the a few
scientifically shown methods to actually
lose weight what does Weight Watchers do
they recognize that dieting does not
work telling people eat this and eat
that does not work there is no evidence
that any diet ever works okay what
Weight Watchers instead is establish a
budget constraint they say look we're
not going to tell you what to eat we're
just going to tell you what each piece
of food costs effectively in terms of
weight gain and we do that by assigning
each piece of food a weight so they say
for instance a carrot has zero points a
Snickers
bar has uh six points and you just add
up the points of what you eat up to the
point total you want to hit they say
look you tell us you can go wait watch
us and set it up for free you don't none
of you have to but when you're older uh
you can go set it up for free and you
basically say um what what weight do you
want to hit and they say okay this is
how many points you can have per day
plus you get cheat you get some cheat
points and if you hit if you consume
those points per day within X weeks you
will hit your goal weight but you decide
how to do it so for example let's say
you go to McDonald's for lunch and let's
say your budget's 30 points which is a
pretty typical budget okay what that
would say is for 30 points you if you go
to lunch for McDonald's and you get a
classic number one that's a Big Mac 14
points fries 10 points and a coke which
is six points that's 30 points on lunch
you're done
nothing else for the day on the other
hand you could say well wait if I got a
10piece nugget that's 12 points apple
slices is one point and a die Coke is
zero points you've only used 13 points
now unless you have strange tastes
that's a way worse lunch I mean who
wouldn't rather Big Mac and fries and a
coke than apple apple slices and chicken
nuggets I mean come on but is less than
half as expensive in terms of weight
gain and you can make that decision some
days you might might say screw it I want
a big lunch I'll skip dinner some days
you might say I got a I got a nice
dinner coming out a have a lower calorie
lunch but you decide because the budget
constraint is laid out for you and
that's why it's the most effective way
to lose weight because it put empowers
the consumer not follow arbitrary rules
but to follow their hearts within the
constraint it's basically what we're
going to do in this class of examed
optimization it says make yourself as
well off as possible subject to a
constraint and that constraint is
expressed in terms of the points
assigned to food so that's a great Weir
World example of how people can use
budget
constraints okay questions about
that okay let's now talk about what
happens when we run when we shock the
budget constraint when we in when
various things change to move the budget
constraint around let's talk about how
that works okay for example imagine
prices
change okay imagine the price of pizza
slices goes from $4 up to $6 a
slice $4 up to6 a slice what does this
do to your budget ex well that's
Illustrated in figure
32 note the xais the x intercept does
not change why does The X inter not not
change because if all you're buying as
cookies nothing's changed the only thing
that's changes if you want to buy slice
of pizza now instead of let's say you
only wanted Pizza instead of being able
to afford six slices on your $24 income
you can only afford four slices the
budget constraint has pivoted
Inward and the new slope hope instead of
being minus 1/2 is now minus
1/3 okay the opportunity cost of cookies
has
fallen the opportunity cost of pizza has
risen and critically your entire
opportunity set has shrunk you are worse
off why you're worse off because the UN
the area underneath the budget
constraint represents the full set of
choic that are available to you and that
area has shrunken this is a critical
Insight okay remember I'm going to
overstate that term okay which is
basically that your income hasn't
changed you still got 24 bucks all
that's Chang is price yet you're worse
off you're worse off because your income
is just a representation of what you can
buy as the price goes up you can buy
less so your opportunity set which is
the area under the budget con is shrunk
from the much larg area including the
light dots to only the darkened area so
it's a shrinkage in your opportunity set
because you can buy fewer stuff now once
again that's irrelevant if all you like
is cookies but for everyone else they
are worse
off okay so that's one example of how
the budget constraint can
change another example how the budget
can
change is your um your income can change
okay let's imagine for example um your
income decreases to $20 let's say
instead we'll go back to the original
prices but say your income goes from 24
to 20
okay well what happens there is
Illustrated in figure
33 now here it's a parallel shift in in
the budget constraint why is that why is
the budget constraint shift parallel as
opposed to
pivoting yeah SL do change the slope
doesn't change and
why yeah your the relative cost of pizza
and cookies has not changed the
opportunity cost of giving up cookies
for pizza is the same it's just you can
have less of both so it's say parallel
shift in in the budget
constraint but once again a shrinkage in
your opportunity set you are worse off
but for a different reason you're worse
off now for a more obvious reason which
you have less
money okay so two different changes one
changes one pivots the slope one just is
an inward parallel shift both reduce
your opportunity cost okay in both cases
you are uh unambiguously worse
off you're worse off now you might say
well technically in the first case
you're not worse off you like only
cookies but remember taste can change
things can happen you might someday want
a slice of pizza so we say you're worse
off even if you're someone who choose
cookies your opportunities have shrunk
so you're still technically worse off
because you have fewer opportunities to
eat pizza
yeah so great question so the question
is like what what happens if there's
inflation Etc we'll cover all that once
again we're going to go in steps we'll
cover inflation and what it does but
obviously inflation would be like a
price change now what's interesting is
if it's uniform
inflation that would look like figure
33 right if all prices go up constantly
by a constant percentage that like
figure 3 three if it's differential
inflation if cookies and pizza have
differential inflation it look more like
figure
32 okay so what's going to happen is
going to depend on the nature of
inflation yeah
ah great question great segue to the
next point which is why wouldn't you
always be on the line and the answer is
you would be okay uh the opportunity set
is still a relevant concept because even
if you're on the line the opportunity
the line is lower but you're asking a
great point which is why would you ever
spend less than your income if you can't
spend more than your income and the
answer is you wouldn't okay so basically
now we come back to
combining what we learned last time with
what I just taught you and we come to
the fundamental um tool of consumer
Choice which is constrain
choice we said last time you want to
have as much as you can more is better
we said this time you can't consume more
than your budget constraint as this
points out as this question points out
that means you're going to choose a
point in your budget constraint in
particular you're going to choose the
highest possible indifference curve you
can reach given your budget constraint
in other words the you will optimize at
the point of
tangency between your budget constraint
your indifference curves and the
intuition is just what this gentleman
said higher indifference curves are
better you can only go as far as your
budget constraint therefore the best
possible choice is when the indifference
curve is tangent to the budget strength
that's the furthest out you can
get okay and we could see this
in figure
34 figure 34 is our first example of
making a strange Choice decision so what
we have here is the budget constraint I
laid out there and the utility function
we use last time utility is square root
of c x s of cookies time slices okay and
and the budget States the one up there
income of 24 price of cookies two price
of pizza
four that is Illustrated in figure 34
how's it Illustrated well you know to
draw the indifference curves we taught
you that last
time okay you know how to draw the
budget constraint I just taught you that
so just draw both and you find the one
with the tangency so the optimal choice
is going to be at Point
d That's the farthest possible
indifference curve that can be reached
given your
budget and this gives utility Point D
give utility of square otk of 18 now
once again that number is meaningless
but it's useful in an ordinal sense
which it lets us ask well could we do
better at another point so for example
take Point
e okay why what what would why what
would our utility be at Point e and why
can't we have it someone raise their
hand and tell me
yeah no point point e I'm sorry Square
32 right
yeah exactly so Point e square of 32
you're happier but it's not you can't
afford it okay what about um point a
this is on the budget constraint why
don't you choose that
point
yeah I'm
sorry yes so point a you can afford it
but it's a square root of 10 why would
you want
it okay the point is you can show
yourself and then similarly Point
C would be crazy because then as this
earlier question pointed out you're way
inside your opportunity set you're
wasting money so the bottom line is you
can show yourself graphically why the
tangency is is the best possible choice
you can
make okay now once again I want you to
understand this intuitively graphically
and now mathematically so let's do the
math of constraint Choice okay always
risk when I start writing math on the
board so if I make a mistake please
don't jump down my throat just kindly
put it point point it out to me okay um
all right so basically the key decision
consumers make and this is the one of
the harder intuitions in economics it's
never about how much you have it's about
the next thing you might want to get we
operate in marginal space we're always
about not how many cookies do I have but
do I want another one okay it's always
about the marginal ision we talked about
margin utility margin rate substitution
last time it's always about what is the
on the margin should I be moving in One
Direction or another okay and basically
if we said that the equili is the
tangency what's the slope of the
indifference curve the slope of the
indifference curve is the marginal rate
of
substitution we derived that last
time okay the marginal rate of
substitution which is minus mu C over
muu s
what's now what's the tan what's the if
that's tangent that means that it's
equal to the marginal rate of
transformation at that
tangency we Define the marginal rate of
transformation as minus PC over PS and
that leads us to the fundamental rule of
consumer utility maximization which is
set mu C over mu or Marg is equal to
price
ratios utility is
optimized when margin the ratio of
margin utility equals the ratio of
prices we didn't have to think about
like we don't go and think like well
let's take eight piece slice of pizza
let's take 10 slice of pizza no we say
at the point we're at how do we feel
about incrementally trading pizza for
cookies pizza for cookies that's the way
to think about decision don't think of
like do I want eight slices of pizza or
five cookies or whatever no don't think
that way think from where I'm at today
do I want to move in One Direction or
another and the answer is you always
want to move in One Direction or another
until you get this
equality okay and if not you're not um
you're not
optimizing now basically this kind of
the fund the fundamental rule we do when
we do this constrain choice in economics
is we're always going to in general be
setting marginal benefits equal to
Marginal costs that's how we make
decisions in economics for every
decision we set the marginal benefit
that is the incremental benefit of a
decision equal to the marginal cost the
incremental cost and that's expressed
here what's the marginal
benefit what is the marginal benefit of
the next uh what's the what's what's
this ratio this is saying how much is
the next cookie Worth to me to me Rel to
pizza slices and what's going to cost me
Rel to pizza slices the maral benefit is
how happy I am with the next cookie in
terms of how much pizza I have to give
up the the cost is how much I have to
spend for the next cookie Rel to what
the next Pizza it's going to cost now I
find this is this is a I find this a
hard formula intuitively I like to
rewrite it for my own intuition in this
way I like to transform it and write it
as um mu u c over PC equals m over PS
and I call this a bang for the buck
equation think of as you want to consume
pizza and cookies until the ratio of
your happiness from each good to the
price of that good is equal to all the
other Goods it's your bang for your buck
your bang is your margin utility your
buck is what it's going to cost you okay
different ways of thinking about it and
once again this is something I need to
spend some time on
okay so let's think for a second about
why this rule makes sense imagine you
are in a place like you're on a place
where the Marg utility of
cookies over the Marg utility of pizza
is greater than the price of cookies or
the price of
pizza can anyone tell me what point on
this graph would illustrate that of the
labeled points which point would
illustrate that disequilibrium and
why which point illustrates a higher
marginal set of marginal utilities than
prices it's a hard question can anyone
get that
one uh yeah go
ahead uh uh and why would it be
C okay so that's a great it's not right
but a very illustrative wrong answer
because that illustrates why you want to
do marginal thinking economics you're
saying well Point C screwed up because
we're not spend anything we have well
that's irrelevant it's about the
marginal decision it's about the next
cookie versus is the next slice of pizza
so it's not Point C okay it's in fact
not Point D or E because at all of those
points this ratio
holds at points c d and e this ratio
holds at all those
points you're going to get those being
equal it's either point A or B anyone
know 50% chance
yeah exactly because at Point a the
univers Cur is cutting the quad strain
from above so it's a steeper slope so
this number this absolute value is
larger than this absolute value it's
cutting it from above so it's a steeper
slope of the inference curve than the
slope of the budget
constraint okay so here's how to think
about reestablishing equilibrium okay
what that says is at let's say this very
precisely listen this very precisely at
Point a it's so important I'm going to
read my notes okay the rate at which you
give the rate at which you're willing to
give up slices for
cookies is greater than the rate at
which the Market's demanding you give up
slices for
cookies okay so that is the marginal
benefit to you of another cookie in
terms of slices is greater than the
price to you of another cookie in terms
of slices so in other words at Point a
so let's show this mathematically okay
at Point a okay at Point a
what's the margin utility of cookies
well we used the same math we use last
time our utility function is square root
of C * s so what's the Marge utility of
cookies the margin utility of
cookies
is the derivative of this with respect
to C so it's 0.5 * s overun of s *
C
okay Mar at Marge utility of pizza
slices 0.5 * C over Square < TK of s *
C okay that's our formulas at Point a
you have two slices of
pizza okay so this margin utility you
have two slices of pizza so this margin
utility is one over < TK of 10 and you
have five cookies this Marg utility is 2
and a half overun of
10 so the marginal utility so the margin
rate of substitution at this
point is minus
2.5 what does that mean that means you
would like you'd be willing to give up
two and a half slices of pizza to get
one
cookie you have so few cookies at Point
a that you're willing to give up two and
a half slices piece to get one cookie
let me just pause there it's from last
lecture people understand that
given your preferences
yeah the uh Square s * C I'm just it's
derivative of this it's just the
derivative formula the derivative of
square C * s is 0.5 s * well I wrote s
time c c * s doesn't matter it's but
it's just it's just it's the derivative
formula once again if you know this I
said I don't require h01 but you do need
to sort of know basic differentiation
stuff so I still don't know it it's
always good to review it okay other
questions okay so what this is saying is
your preferences are such that you would
be willing to give up two and a half
slices of pizza to get a cookie but
here's the question what does the market
tell you you have to give up how many
slices of pizza do you have to give up
to get a cookie in the
market how many how many house SLI pie
you have to get up to give a cookie
someone raise their hand tell me how
many slice of piece you have to go up to
get a
cookie guys are so afraid to get it
wrong you know this
someone raise their hand and tell me
yeah a half because cookies cost $2 and
Pieces cost $4 so you're saying I would
give up two and a half slices a piece to
get a cookie the Market's saying you
know what you only have to give up half
a slice of piece to get a cookie so what
are you going to
do what are you going to do buy more
cookies and less
Pizza the market is saying you can move
in direction that makes you happier you
can move in direction that that makes
you happier because right now you're
willing up a lot of pizza to get cookies
but you don't have to you only think up
half a slice of pizza to get cookies the
margin rate of substitution is greater
is greater than the marginal rate of
transformation which is minus a
half okay the marginate of substitution
is minus two and a half margin rate of
transformation is minus a half that's
why the slope of the indifference curve
is steeper than the slope of the budget
constraint therefore you're are willing
to make trades the market is happy to
let you make and so you should move and
you should continue to do that you'll
see by that logic you'll continue to do
that until you come to rest at Point uh
at Point
D okay now give my bad handwriting I'm
not going to go through the opposite
case I strongly urge you to go home
right away while still in your mind and
redo this for point B and show yourself
that you get the opposite conclusion at
point B you will find that you are happy
to give up a lot lot of cookies to get
pizza well the market says that's a
great deal you know you have to give up
two cookies to get pizza you're going to
be happy to give up lots more than two
cookies to get pizza so you move back to
the middle again so there is pressure
the disequilibrium between the margin
rate of
substitution and the margin rate of
transformation leads to pressure to move
to the point where they're equal there's
a natural equating equilibrating
mechanism which is the the the uh
difference between your preferences and
the Market's price will drive you to
equalize
those and that's it that's how we make
all decisions ever I've now explain the
entire process of human decision making
to you g newk psychology I'm just joking
but actually the truth is once again
this simple model we learned in a
lecture and a half remember last lecture
was short so really sort of a lecture
and a quarter okay can explain probably
90% of everything consumers do okay it's
incredibly powerful tool yeah
oh the margin substitution remember is
the negative of the ratio of margin
utilties definitionally margin rate of
substitution so it's the margin utility
of cookies which is one over s of 10 to
over the margin slices which is two and
a half over square of 10 and a negative
sign in front of it because it's definit
negative the marginal
you
uh what did I do wrong here
uh oh you know what I did wrong I did
this wrong the number remember we have
here we have how many slices of pizza do
we have at Point a we have five slices
of pizza so this is two and a half good
catch that's two and a half I did and
that's
one that's the mistake which is I put in
the wrong number of slice of pizza I
inserted here you should insert here the
number of slice good catch this is this
is five this is two so I inserted the
wrong numbers there so the ratio is
right I just got these wrong in the
margin chilly calculations that's a good
catch okay other questions and once
again please speak up on those things
okay because now look at all the people
you've helped you're a giver okay you're
welcome uh okay other questions about
that okay let's do an
example and for the example I want to
come to one of the most important social
programs we have in the United States
which is the snap program
supplemental nutrition and assistance
program traditionally when I was a kid
it was called food
stamps it's basically the program in the
US that gives M gives resources to
people they can use to buy food
essentially the way this program works
is if you're poor enough we give you a
debit
card and that debit card has a certain
amount of money on it that you can use
to buy food and the way it works is is
when you go to the grocery store there's
certain items that the debit card will
ring up for and certainly won't so if
you take a snap card and try to buy a
magazine it won't bring up for that you
can only use to buy
food okay it used to literally be you'd
get stamps and you'd have to sort of
embarrassingly hand them to the cashier
now it just looks like a regular debit
card the difference it can only be used
on certain items okay and basically
roughly speaking in the US we have
something called the poverty line we'll
come back and talk more about this the
poverty line is is what we assume is of
the minimum
standard uh above which you need to have
to live in America it's embarrassingly
low we say the poverty line for an
individual is about
$14,000 I don't know how I would live in
Boston on $4,000 but whatever but that's
the poverty line and basically if you're
below a little below the poverty line a
little bit above it you get like a
couple hundred bucks a month in food
stamps in in in on on your debit card
okay now what I want to do is ask the
following question why do we do this why
don't we just give people cash if we
want poor people to have money why don't
we just give them money and so we're
going to analyze the answer to that
question not through introspection but
through
economics so what we're going to do is
talk about how snap operates relative to
giving people cash so to do this let's
go to figure
3-5a let me walk you through this figure
this is sort of multiple things if if I
if I had a projector is be done in
animation there's multiple things going
on in this figure okay we have an
original budget constraint imagine
someone has
$5,000 imagine world where someone has
an income of $5,000 they're very
poor and all they could spend their
money on all they need all they could
spend their money on is either food or
shelter now once again you might say
well gee don't they need health or
whatever leave that alone we're in a too
good world you can ex you can make this
threedimensional in your free time okay
so basically think about a simple world
where people have $5,000 of income very
poor people and all they can spend on is
food or shelter and they spend all their
income of course so the original budget
constraint looks like the line that's
labeled original budget line what I'm
going to do is I'm going to assume that
the price of food equals the price of
shelter equals one this is a trick we
use in economics or in mathematics in
general it's called the numer
good we don't want prices to mess up the
math so just let's set the prices to one
it doesn't do any harm it's
generalizable and this way you could
think of dollars as quantities so the
amount you spend as the quantity you get
and since food and shelter are vague
Concepts anyway having to find what food
is it's a basket of food and shelters a
basket of living arrangements no harm
setting the price to one so basically
the ratio of the slope of The Bu train
is minus one we' set these prices to one
for some vague concept called food and
some vague concept called shelter we set
the prices to one we have a budget
constraint where the intercepts are at
$5,000 on each axis because that's all
the money you have and the slope is
minus one once again any question along
the way shout out raise your hand okay
now imagine the government decides and
this graph is not to scale I'll say that
right up right up front the government
decides they want to give every poor
person $500 they want to give every
person $500 okay every poor person $500
so for this person what that means is
they are now richer their opportunity
set has expanded their budget constraint
has shifted out in a parallel fashion
prices haven't changed they're just
richer so the budget crade has shifted
out from 55500 once again not to scale
but allows some space to illustrate
things easily so the new budget
constraint is at the point uh is the
same slope but the higher
intercepts now let's talk about two
different people and the choices they
make person
X likes shelter and doesn't care much
about food once again we can't judge
preferences preferences come from some
innate psychological basis okay it turns
out psychology does matter okay we can't
judge preferences but their preferen are
such that they don't need to eat a lot
but they really want shelter so
originally they spent of their $5,000
they spent almost nothing on food they
spend 4,800 on shelter and 200 on
food person why on the other hand
doesn't care much about shelter but
really needs to eat so they spent only a
hundred on shelter originally 4,900 on
food
now what happens when we give each of
them
$500 well I'm not going to go through
the math these are these are actual
choices and actual utility function I'm
not going to do the underlying math of
this but given these
preferences person X chooses to say look
I love shelter I'm taking four of my 500
bucks and spending on shelter so I'm
going to go from 4,800 bucks in shelter
and 100 and 200 on food to 5200 bucks on
shelter and 300 on food once again that
is it's mathematically consistent with a
set of preferences there's a set of
preferences that delivered that
outcome person y says look I love
shelter so I'm going to spend most of my
new money on
shelter so it just sort of reinforces
their preferences if you will they get
wider apart they both have they're both
better off but they they're more
different in their choices okay
questions about
that now is the hard part imagine the
government says you know what poor
people we're not giving you $500 in cash
we're going to give you a $500 debit
card that you can only spend on food not
on shelter how does this change the
budget strength here's the hard part
okay we start with the same original
budget straight in figure 3.5 B but now
it's different than giving them $500 in
cash and why is that that's because you
the for the first $500 in food there is
no opportunity cost in terms of
shelter if you spend you can get the
same amount of sh you can get the same
amount of of uh shelter if you spend
$100 on food or $200 on food or $500 on
food so the budet trade is now flat from
the Y AIS to the point
X2 it's flat and then it rejoins the
original budget
constraint why is it flat because think
about it the all those points on that
flat segment are now the feasible points
no matter if you want $5,000 in shelter
before if you wanted $5,000 in shelter
and you want to and you couldn't have
any food now you can have up to $500 in
food and still $5,000 in shelter the
budget constraint is now flat and then
rejoins the original budget constraint
at that point x
to okay we're going to practice in
section these kind of piecewise budget
constraints this is hard to do but you
get good at
it now let's ask what effect does that
have on people's choices well let's
start with person
y we've just said to person y we're
going to give you
$500 that you can only spend on food yet
it has the same effect as giving them
cash
why why for person why is there no
difference between the two panels even
though we've given them the debit card
they can only spent on
food why is there no
difference uh
yeah okay that that's that's uh that's
partly right but you've got the the
basic idea the important point is the
important point is the second part of
your sense they're already spending that
money on food anyway and money is money
so they can just say fine I'll take $500
out of spending on food I'll call it
snap and I'll replace it with $500 more
I can spend on something
else as long money is
fungible as long as you're spending one
$500 on food if I give $500 say it must
be for food you're like whatever I was
always spending $500 on food I'll just
relabel it
okay it doesn't affect my choices
yeah no no no no they'll just spend it
on in other words the point is think
about when we give them cash this is
confusing we give them cash they say
great you give me 500 cash I'm going to
take my consumption from 4,900 to 5100
of of food um I'm going to take my
consumption of food I'm sorry 41 to
50100 I'm take my consumption of shelter
from 100 to
400 now I say oh no you have to spend I
cast are like fine I don't care I still
can I'm still going to spend 5100 on
food and 400 on shelter I'm just going
to label
55100 snap but nothing else has changed
just a labeling thing
okay now think about person X they can't
pull off that trick
why why is person X person X now has to
make a different Choice instead of
choosing what they wanted which was X2
they now have to choose X2 Prime which
is where a different indifference curve
hits that Kink where I3
Prime hits that Kink why why do they
make have to make a different Choice
yeah they can't we're not letting
them so what has happened is by
constraining this money to be on a debit
card rather than
cash we have changed their choice from
what they wanted to do which is 5200 in
shelter and 300 in food to now 5,000 in
shelter and 500 in food we forced them
to have less shelter and more food and
what have we done to their well-being
are they better off or worse off tell me
why so raise their hand tell me why is
person X better off or worse off when we
can strain their choice
yeah exactly more is better they're in a
lower indifference curve they are worse
off by constraining their choice we've
made them worse off
definitionally by giving people
something other than cash we make them
worse
off but we do it
anyway and to see why let's think of a
simple change to this diagram which
represents the way policy makers think
about poor people cross out on the Y AIS
cross out the world shelter and put in
the word cocaine
basically policy makers think we can't
give these guys money because they'll
just spend it badly they won't spend it
on things we want them to spend it on we
want them to spend it on food we're
going to force them to spend it on food
to make sure they don't waste it that is
policy makers think look there's a third
option which is cocaine or alcohol or
whatever and we don't want them spending
money on that so we are going to force
them to make sure they have the
food so that is why we have these kinds
of what we call in-kind benefits indeed
as teach you later semester and as I
spend a whole section of my course 1441
talking about the US government
redistributes in Goods vastly more than
in cash the amount of money we give poor
people in Goods is something like 10
times the amount of money we give poor
people in cash between Medical Care
housing and food those programs add up
to about 10 times of how much money we
give people in cash maybe five to 10
times okay because of this exact problem
because we think that we know better
government policy makers think that we
don't want to give people cash reward
what they spend it on so this raises the
natural
question
of actually raises two
questions one is the positive
question of what effect does this have
that is how much more food do we get
people to eat by giving them debit cards
rather than cash you don't know the
answer from this graph because maybe
everyone's like why
maybe no one's affected by maybe
everyone so maybe the answer is zero
okay the answer is and we've done this
from experiments we basically convert
we've we'll talk a lot about in this
course about experiments run economics
and really a Pioneer in that field is
our Nobel prize winning couple of uh es
Duo and abijit
bannery uh they've sort of pioneered the
use of of wides skill experiments in
economics one such experiment was run to
actually randomly give some people cash
and some people uh food stamps and what
they found was it does I'm sorry snap
giving snap does increase consumption of
food that is there's enough X's out
there that on average for every dollar
you give in food stamps rather than cash
you get about in sorry snap sorry about
that for every dollar given snap rather
than cash you get about 15 cents more in
food consumption not a dollar there's
some people like why but basically up
all the X and y's by giving people snap
instead of cash you do change their
consumption
Behavior okay so the positive question
is is snap having his intended effect
the answer is
yes the normative question is should we
do
this should we force people to be take
their take their uh good in um take
their goods in food rather than cash and
here once again we come to the value of
experiments it's a hard question
ask but this is where experimental
economics once again is pired here and
by their third Nobel Prize winner
Michael Kramer who's now Chicago du Flo
benergy and Kramer set up something
called
japal the jam poverty action lab it's in
the department of Economics here at MIT
it is now the preeminent organization in
the
world for using experiments like real
scientists do to actually answer
economic questions to basically say as
an interesting economic question want to
answer answer let's answer by randomly
running an
experiment so for example JP palal has
now run dozens of experiments with the
experiment with giving people in
developing countries cash they mostly
focus on developing World okay giving
people developing countries cash versus
giving them
goods and the answer seems to be that
basically we should give people
cash they basically give people cash
very little of it getss spent on bad
things almost all of it gets spent on
education for children or food or
shelter but
moreover giving very poor people cash
allows them to make investments to
escape poverty so did is they took a
group of poor women in Uganda and gave
them $150 you might think wow big deal
$150 that is 50 to 100% of the annual
income in Uganda let's be clear okay
okay the
about half the world lives on less than
$2 a day okay so $150 big big money in
Uganda what they found was and they gave
some women that they randomly gave other
women did not give them the money what
they found is 18 months later the women
who gotten the cash had raised their
earning had doubled their earnings why
because they used that cash to set up
little shops to buy a cow to invest in
how they could make more money so not
only do they spend very little of it on
things you might consider bad they Ed it
in a productive way we even foresee to
invest in their own Futures and get
better off there's a recent experiment
in um gosh I don't remember was you
might have read of where they gave
homeless people in the US $7,500 a small
sample of homeless people like 60
homeless people and they found that once
again they spent most of it on getting
their lives back together not on
dangerous goods it's not to say that we
shouldn't worry about people consuming
dangerous goods we'll talk a lot about
this this semester it is to say that
when we want make a decision Economic
Policy we look to the evidence and the
evidence is a the positive evidence is a
giving snap cards rather than cash
changes people's behavior and B they
seem to be better off if we give them
cash okay and that's how we use the
tools of Economics to make informed
policy decisions okay let's stop there
we'll come back next time and talk about
how more putting this all together first
problem set is handed out Friday it is
due in two weeks because we have no
section next Friday at 5:00 p.m. in 2
weeks on September 30th