in the early 1980s Richard feeman
suggested that if we want to simulate a
Quantum system a task that's very hard
for a classical computer we should in
fact use a Quantum system to perform
that
simulation basically he was suggesting
we should build a quantum computer he
also noted that it's a very interesting
problem because it's not so easy and he
was right over the next decade or so
researchers thought about what kinds of
algorithms could potentially give a
Quantum Advantage for real world
problems of significance and also how
fragile Quantum States could ever be
used to implement such an algorithm the
answer started to come in the mid 1990s
with the discovery of shor's algorithm
developed by Peter Shore shor's
algorithm was not the first Quantum
algorithm to show Quantum Advantage but
it was the first that also addressed an
important practical problem namely the
factorization of large numbers for more
MIT moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow