uh welcome um on behalf of the MIT
Administration I'm going to uh start by
just sharing a few observations uh with
you about uh research in general
research at MIT and corporate
engagements uh with MIT and I'll start
with what I think is probably um obvious
to all of you and that's that we are at
a really unique and special time for uh
Innovation I've been in MIT for 33 years
and I can't remember a time where we've
had such a Confluence of things that are
all at that sort of hockey stick moment
um in the curve if you uh think about it
um a couple decades ago we learned how
to engineer um life and health but
because of the complexity of life and
health um we've only scratched the
surface of what's possible um in that
domain we're at the beginning of what
will be the most significant
transformation of how we power the
planet and economic prosperity in a
century you know way from fossil fuels
to other um sources with really exciting
things out there um fision Fusion
renewable
energy um and we've also designed the
algorithms and the hardware to make
inferences from complex data sets that
far outstrip the ability
of any individual human being to make
such inferences and we've put that in
the hands of
everyone and now of course we're taking
things like artificial intelligence and
using it with you know life and health
challenges where we have deep complexity
to really Advance things at a rate that
we haven't seen
before and then we have new things on
the horizon things that have benefited
from you know 50 60 years of development
and now um you know people think are on
the verge of yet another transition so
Quantum engineering is one of those
things and I see uh you know
presentations that people from that
field make where they you know put the
first quantum computers which we now
have next to the right flyer right that
they feel were at that kind of a moment
for uh advances in the field so a really
exciting time and then on our campus and
campus is elsewhere also a deep
realization that we can't develop Tech
devoid from all of the social and
ethical sort of consequences and
considerations that we must make um in
developing that kind of um technology
and those advances so it's a really neat
time I think on campus it's a neat time
in the overall field of advancing um
technology and MIT as gri said is really
an exceptional place place we have about
2.3 billion in sponsored research that's
including campus and Lincoln
Laboratories um and then MIT contributes
about another 7 or 800 million on top of
that in our own resources to support the
um research Enterprise so in some it's
over $3 billion dollar in work that's
being done by some of the most talented
people in the world we're a fantastic
magnet for talent we've got this great
tradition of Public Service very mission
driven mindset we like to work with
people both inside MIT and outside of
MIT um and have a really sort of
wonderful role to play I think in
advancing uh in many of these um key
fields that are at that sort of hockey
stick uh moment right
now and we've got this marvelous history
as an arrow and Astro guy I I'll start
with the one on the upper right A lot of
people say you know that oh we need a
moonshot for this or a moonshot for that
MIT is the only University that can
actually say that we did the
moonshot right we were the first
contractor it was a paragraph long that
came from con Congress right to um
campus um that's when you know contracts
could be a little bit shorter um we you
know basically developed the gu's
navigation control and computer systems
to navigate over 240,000 miles of open
space right something that still really
hard
today you look at the challenges in
getting back to the
Moon um but can't just talk about aasa
with you guys um first digital computer
the Whirlwind a Decades of uh Mna
research and other biological research
um along with other uh places which put
us in a position um several months into
uh the pandemic to develop vaccines that
saved thousands and millions of
lives and then we have the work on radar
that was done at Lincoln um and
continuing work o there over decade
after decade after decade that has
protected the nation and continued to
elevate Lincoln Labs as one of the key
National Assets for National Security
right so we got a lot of great things um
in our history and without a doubt we
have some challenges and some
opportunities that require that kind of
integrated um thinking across science
technology systems economics policy and
we have as Guri mentioned a new
president who's charged us with
continuing to do big things together and
you'll hear from our chief Innovation
and strategy officer ananur chander
cassen um who's the key architect in
building those um structures that enable
us to do big things together in these
domains um as shown here so an exciting
time for us um on campus
but what I want to highlight for you is
that uh doing big things together is not
just about doing big things together
with people on campus one of The
Marvelous things about mit's history is
that we like to work on real hard
nitty-gritty engineering problems with
the people who provide products and
services out there in the
marketplace you know I came from Caltech
I love Caltech as a school but sort of
engineering was sometimes used as an
epithet right the higher objective was
you know uh understanding you know
fundamental um uh science at MIT it's
always been part of our sort of DNA to
work on the hard nitty-gritty problems
we've always had a very strong Focus
today about 20% of our sponsored
research is uh industry funded and what
does that do um it enables us to have a
real appreciation for the problems
and how to solve those not just
hypothetically but in a
marketplace right where you have real
cost pressures real Market pressures on
you real complexity to deal with where
you can't always abstract away some of
the challenges that you wish you could
so it promotes this deeper understanding
of the problem it makes us be better at
solving problems it also of course
creates marvelous career opportunities
we have 12,000 students on campus and
not just the grad students are involved
in research but 91% of our undergrads
are involved in research so we have this
entire Enterprise that is focused on
advancing the State ofthe art and we
feel that partnering with um industry is
the way to do that it's really what
enables us to make uh great
progress and I've been here for 33 years
a little over 33 years I've had many
different roles at
MIT uh throughout that I've had very
strong Partnerships with industry and
with government in
policymaking and one of the things that
I've observed is that mit's strongest
Partnerships those that most benefit our
partner and most benefit MIT are those
where people think across just research
and across Human Resources but think
strategically um including both of those
domains
and most
universities and most companies you have
to go to the president to find the
person that has responsibility for both
HR and research and
development right so it's a challenge
both for universities and for corporates
to figure out how do I work in a
coordinated way across both of those
domains right don't just send the
technical people to the research and
development conference and the HR people
to the job fair and you work across both
of those things and there are many many
many opportunities that I'll highlight
for you outside of research at MIT to
get engaged in small ways that will be
very impactful in terms of amplifying
the sort of HR co- benefit that you get
out of um working with MIT on research
and development things and many people
in this room can talk with you about
those there's some listed here but we
had some companies that think so
strategically with us that when we've
hired a junior faculty
member they don't come and work for
MIT but I've called up the CTO of
companies before and said well we've
just hired someone can they come and
work for you for the first nine months
and then they're going to come back to
MIT right sounds like a a bad deal right
but what does it do it builds this
relationship with that company that then
persist persists through that person's
30-year career with them with their
students and also makes them very deeply
aware of the problems that Company's
trying to solve right so there's a a set
of ways to interact with us at a very
high level strategic way big things
small things that that really enable
that partnership between you know
objectives that you would have as a
company HR and Innovation and objectives
that we would have as a university which
are um Education and Research right and
how to bring those two things things
together so something I would have you
think about you're going to hear uh more
because it's the 40th anniversary of the
Micro Systems Technology lab about one
of our most
exceptional um Endeavors in bringing
together Education and Research
partnership between MIT and corporates
um so I don't want to say much more
about that because there's a celebration
of the 40th anniversary coming and
you're going to see many of the
different things they do to to jointly
bring value by by a very strong
strategic collaboration between MIT and
partner
companies so I'm going to end with that
and say that Excellence collaboration
and practical impact are part of our DNA
at MIT what that means is working with
all of
you right and figuring out ways that we
can do things that are jointly valuable
to you and to MIT and we look forward to
working with you to identify those
opportunities there are 50 different
ways uh to interact with you and I would
encourage you to explore uh multiple
ways of doing that you can try them for
a couple years if they don't work you
can move to other things uh but think
about it as a vital uh partnership or
collaboration uh between your
organization and our organization uh to
meet some joint goals okay so welcome
again and thank you for being here
I can take a few questions I've been
told thank
you a few questions from the uh audience
let's see oh I see them right here yeah
do you want me to take them one by one
yes please okay um what would be the
biggest hurdles for Academia to work
with industry from your
experience um I think the biggest
hurdles that I've seen
on really getting a joint Clarity that
means on both sides about what our goals
are and then driving the sort of
contract structures and the engagements
to enable those um often if we try to do
things without sitting down early and
understanding each other's goals and
being very clear about that and some of
the constraints that we have then it can
be a harder path to get to um the first
contract the other thing that I would
say is that we've sometimes
not done what you would ordinarily do in
any kind of an important relationship
like that which is strategically check
in you know once a year sit down and
evaluate it what worked what didn't work
what can we change what can we add what
can we remove right but to really uh
give it that care and feeding um and
when we do that um the the opportunities
and the relationships are fantastic so
so it's almost um kinds of things I
would put into the sort of management
101 category right getting clear on
goals um and then checking in and
monitoring progress on it it's not big
complicated things it's the smaller
things that I think really matter um in
terms of um
hurdles great next question would be
what is your biggest takea away from the
33 years of MIT experience oh so biggest
takeaway so A lot's changed in 33 years
and
and uh some things are the result of
careful planning other things are the
result of um happy
circumstance uh almost everything though
has some component of patience in it as
well so many of the things that you saw
in terms of the great opportunities
benefit from you know 50 60 70 years of
fundamental research uh that lead to
them and we often forget that when we're
in the hockey stick moment we forget the
long stick on the other end right CU
we're all focused on oh what's going to
happen next um so so I would say um
sometimes patience really matters uh in
things uh but then also what's happened
in the last 33 years that I've been here
is that Mi has always been a marvelous
tech school right we've always been
recognized that way um and we were set
within a world that had Tech and many
other things but now that world has
become essentially a tech World in a lot
of ways and so it's migrated sort of
towards MIT and those two things
together have really strengthened mit's
opportunities to be a magnet for talent
um the complete Recreation of the sort
of Cambridge and Brader Kendall air
Kendall Square area um so I think just
lots of changes brought about by both
being thoughtful and strategic but also
being patient you know if you were here
20 or 30 years ago Kendall Square would
not look like this um for people who
have uh a memory it just wouldn't be
that way at all and it's almost hard to
imagine um you know 33 3 years later um
what the place looks like and how strong
of a magnet for talent and great
Partnerships MIT
is is that it great thank you very much
thank you guys and welcome again
[Music]