so I'm really excited uh to be here
today and uh and with nor to talk about
um to talk about some of our work and uh
nor is going to talk about uh the the
more research part and I'm going to give
the the primer that gives the um the
relevant background so um the title for
this talk is counting is not easy
assessing and quantifying uncertainty
and abundance inferences from highr
sequencing data and the the title um was
inspired by one of my younger son's
favorite books which is waiting is not
easy um so credit to the artwork to Mo
Williams um so it's a great series of
books um so I want to start out with
acknowledgements um all of the work here
is done in collaboration with uh
students past and present uh as well as
external collaborators uh the work I'm
going to talk about today is
particularly related to work done by U
my former student hak and nor who you'll
hear talk later um and all of this is in
collaboration with Mike love parts of it
with Hector Kat Bravo and yui
wo okay so um we're going to talk about
RNA SE a lot um because that's going to
be the motivating assay type that we're
going to discuss so let me give sort of
my one slide overview uh simplified RNA
seek so um we have some gene on the
genome here the colored boxes denote
exons uh that gets transcribed into a
unspaced RNA molecule uh and then
alternative splicing occurs creating
different transcripts now in reality if
we're doing short read sequencing we
would reverse transcribe this in cdna
but let's uh gloss over that we're going
to sequence small bits of this RNA um
and that produces the uh the reads that
we're going to generate uh and then our
task is going to be to infer the
abundance of the original RNA molecules
from this set of
reads so um there are two parts to this
process the first one is mapping or
alignment um and sometimes a mapping
itself tells you exactly which original
molecule the read came from so for
example this read is easy to resolve
there's only one uh place in the set of
molecules where this read could have
Arisen from and that's at this xon xon
Junction this one's a little bit less
easy right there's two uh different
transcripts that alternatively place the
same pair of exons and so the read
itself is ambiguous uh and then this one
is even more ambiguous right it comes
from completely within an Exxon that's
contained in all three
transcripts uh so that's the first part
the second part of the process is once
we have all of that alignment
information we have to do some sort of
estimation process right because we have
to figure out what the abundances of the
transcripts is from the reads but the
reads themselves have an ambiguous
mapping or
align okay so uh the problem that we
have is how do you handle these reads
that align equally well to multiple
places the most common uh cause of this
is alternative splicing but it can also
happen even across genes when you have
genes of a paralus family for example um
so there are a couple things you could
do you could just throw away the
multimapping reads um but I'm going to
try to convince you that leads to
Incorrect and and biased quantification
um but also this happens even at the
gene level like I mentioned so even if
you're not interested in just transcript
level expression but Gene level
aggregate expression it's not a not a
good solution so um I want to start with
a non-biological example to try to uh
propose and um inform why we need to
solve this inference problem so here's a
thought experience imagine that uh I
have a circles on the caresan plane um
and they're one of two species either a
red circle or a blue circle and I can't
view them directly much like we can't
view the RNA directly unless you're
doing a lower throughput like
visualization assay um but I can sample
them and so my sampling procedures is
going to be I'm going to throw down a
dart on the plane and it's going to hit
and it's going to uh show a certain
color and the color it shows is the type
of circle in which it landed okay so I
throw down a dart it shows red it hit a
red circle I show down I throw down a
dart it shows blue it hit a blue circle
so uh through this sampling process this
random sampling process I can try and
answer different questions like what
type of circle is more prevalent blue or
red or what is the fraction of red
circles to Blue circles so without any
extra information if I just showed you
this uh this picture um and I asked the
question which type of circle is more
prevalent um there might be a natural
answer so a show of hands who would say
blue okay who would say
red okay so uh it's kind of a false
choice because there's something I
didn't tell you which is the area of the
circles now blue is the obvious correct
answer under the assumption the
parsimonious assumption that all circles
are equal area um but that was a hidden
assumption to make my point right uh
there's a direct analog here to rnac
which is that at least with short read
protocols the probability of sampling a
read is a function not only of the
abundance of that molecule but of the
length of the molecule if I have the
same number of copies of a short and
long molecule in short read sequencing
because of the fragmentation process I
will get more reads from the longer
molecule compared to the shorter one so
I need to know the length of a target
from what your read is drawn in order to
meaningfully inferus
abundance all right and so this is why I
need to resolve the read back to the
transcript of origin not just the gene
of origin so um let me give a couple
more motivations for this uh so this is
a plot in some simulated data from uh a
2016 paper uh by Charlotte sonis Mike
love and Mark Robinson uh where they did
simulations and then they compared
different counting approaches to
approaches that do transcript level
inference um and so this is different
genes that are in the parus family of
this Gene here uh on each case uh in the
plots the x- axis is the true abundance
of that Gene and the y- axis is the
estimated abundance of that Gene um and
what you can see is that uh the feature
counts approach which essentially counts
reads mapping to the genome uh
discarding ambiguous reads uh has some
some misestimation both the Spearman and
Pearson correlation are considerably
lower the inference approach does a
pretty good job not perfect but uh
resolves most of those uh abundances
correctly it turns out that this uh has
effects on Downstream processing as well
uh so these plots are showing again in
simulated data um the false Discovery
rate versus the true posit positive rate
in uh dge calling for these genes um and
this is particularly designed to be a
challenging example where between the
conditions of Interest there's
differential transcript usage so the
gene is overall expressed at a similar
level but the dominant transcripts are
changing um and so what you can see is
the variance of of the approaches that
solve via inference are up here whereas
the count approaches are down here um so
the problem overall is challenging we're
you know sort of maxing out at
reasonable false positive rates about a
50% true positive rate but clearly the
inference approaches are doing a lot
better okay um so this is a well-known
problem um and there's many times that
you really need information that is
subgene level um so uh one particular
example I really like is uh you know
this paper here which demonstrates that
during progression in Parkinson's
disease uh there's over overall similar
gene expression of key marker genes but
there's uh systematic changes in in the
dominant transcript usage right so
there's differential transcript usage so
uh understanding transcript or at least
subgene level abundances groups of
transcripts is critical to understanding
biological mechanisms and even if you
want to understand the transcript
abundance at the gene level you should
first quantify the transcripts and then
aggregate those estimates to the level
of the
gene so let me talk a little bit about
the underlying statistical model we
might use in order to perform this kind
of inference um so the Assumption we're
going to make is that we have some
population of molecules that we want to
sequence uh here there's only three
types red green and blue um they have
different lengths these lengths are
known to us a priority uh we could
assume for example we're working in a
well annotated model organism we know
the catalog of genes or we've assembled
them and we know what the gene models
are okay so here um there's fewer copies
of the blue transcript uh than the green
there's only six copies but it's long so
there's 600 total nucle Tides we could
sample from a blue transcript about 30%
of the total mixture at the nucleotide
level uh for the green there's about
1,00 nucleotides and for the red about
200 so uh we can think about the number
of nucleotides but it turns out that
because we're making relative
measurements uh the more we sequence the
more we'll see generally uh it's best to
think about these as as fractions right
so the mixture is about 30% blue 60%
green and 10% red at the nucleotide
level these are going to turn turn out
to be the quantities of interest that we
want to infer in our inference process
all right so let's look at what a a
sample experiment would be like in the
perfect case assuming no bias um in
sampling and everything works out like
we expect um what we're going to do is
pick a transcript uh proportional to the
total available nucle ties from that
transcript so proportional to the count
times the length and then pick a
position P uniformly at random on that
transcript now this is not exactly what
the sequencing experiment is doing
because it's usually fragmenting first
and then randomly sampling but the
probabilities will work out correctly
okay so uh if we sample we're going to
get uh a lot of green reads because that
is the most abundant thing we'll see
some blue eventually um and if we
sequence long enough we'll see the the
rare transcript like the red one here um
and then we get a mixture like this now
of course the problem is not this simple
because we don't get the reads
colorcoded by their transcript of origin
we just get the sequence right and as I
explained in my first uh two slides the
multimapping self is is part of what uh
induces the
challenge okay so um to motivate a
potential solution here I want to think
about the simplest case so imagine that
I have this read here this black read
and it aligns equally well to both the
green and the red
transcript um and assume that we also
know the overall nucleotide fractions so
these values here now of course we don't
right to know the nucleotide fractions
we have to solve the inference problem
but uh I want to argue that assigning a
read and estimating the nucleotide
abundances are really dual problems if
we know the answer to one we can easily
solve for the other and vice versa okay
so um imagine these are our nucleotide
fractions we observe one new read the
multimaps to both of these transcripts
uh the argument I want to make is that
we can make an informed estimate of the
probability of each of these events the
probability that the read actually came
from the green transcript versus that it
actually came from the red transcript um
and so by by looking at the model that
we have for how the reads are generated
we can estimate what those probabilities
are um and so the probability that the
read comes from the green transcript is
just proportional to the total
nucleotide fraction of the green
transcript over its length appropriately
normalized so that we observe the read
at all with probability one okay so this
works out to about a 75% chance that the
read comes from the green transcript and
here a 25% chance that it comes from Red
it works out regardless of how you do it
because of the normalization but because
there only two possibilities here we
could just say 1 minus
75 all right so these probabilities tell
us the probability that the read came
from each of these places um and in fact
um if I looked at the probabilistic
assignments of each read and summed them
up those would give me an estimate of
the nucleotide fractions of each
transcript right so this is why this
this problem is a dual problem so this
leads to a probabilistic generative
model um this is a variant of one of the
first models proposed for this problem
problem in the RSM paper by B and others
um and so the variables of interest uh
that that are going to be used here are
uh Ada are the nucleotide
abundances uh f is the set of observed
fra fragments uh T is a set of
transcript sequences this is assumed
known the set of things that could
generate reads and uh Z are these latent
variables so there's a matrix of of Z
variables um where every read has a a
single one designating the transcript
from which it actually arose and a zero
everywhere else but we don't observe
these they're latent and so uh the the
generative model says that the
probability the likelihood of generating
a particular set of fragments for a
particular Ada is equal to the product
over all of the fragments of the
probability of generating that fragment
given Ada okay so this is a likelihood
so we we are optimizing over the Ada uh
conditioned on the fragments in the
transcripts but um it's proportional
here to the probability of the data
given the parameters and so we're making
an assumption here which is Independence
assumption which is that we've generated
enough fragments such that the
probability of sampling one doesn't
affect the pool that we're sampling from
um and if we want to unfold this uh
product a little bit what we can say is
well that product of generating each
fragment is really asking what is the
product over all fragments of generating
every possible mapping for that fragment
so the uh the sum over all fragments
ments though here we can sort of ignore
or set to zero uh uh transcripts where
the fragment has no alignment right
assume that they're vanishingly small so
the sum over all transcripts were the
read aligns of the probability of first
selecting that transcript given our
estimated abundances and then the
probability of generating this
particular fragment conditioned on the
fact that it comes from this transcript
okay so the first term is the
probability of a transcript selecting it
and the second term is the probability
of observing this particular fragment
from the transcript in the simplest case
this is just one over the length of the
transcript because we're choosing
positions uniformly around them so there
are standard solutions to this problem
uh a statistical generative model gives
a nice principled way to solve this and
it turns out that we can at least
locally optimize this likelihood that is
find the Ada that maximize the
likelihood of The observed data using an
algorithm like the EM algorithm or the
variational beian EM algorithm or other
variational inference techniques okay
so this is a widely adopted solution to
these problems with different
formulations of the EM different things
being considered slightly different
changes to the model um some of the
original work uh in this field um goes
back to uh 2011 uh these papers here and
um then continues on into the current
day
actually so uh that's the model uh I'm
not going to go over pseudo code or
anything but I will give you the two
main steps of the EML algorithm uh it's
an iterative algorithm that goes back
and forth between an expectation step
and a maximization step so the
expectation step says uh what is the
expected value of each of my latent
variables right another way of thinking
about this is given my current estimate
of the transcript abundances here
denoted as Ada sup T where T is a Time
step in the algorithm what iteration I'm
in um I can ask for every lat what is
the probability that Z J equals 1 that
is the probability that read I comes
from transcript J um that's just equal
to this equation I showed in the other
slide right this is the generalized
version of it the abundance of this
transcript over its length uh normalized
so that the total sum is one okay so I
sum over all transcripts the total sum
of the expected values is going to be
one because I had to generate this once
I have determined the allocations or the
soft assignments for each read then I
can write down the maximum likelihood uh
parameter estimates conditioned on those
uh assignments as this uh the total
nucleotide fraction of a particular
transcript is just the sum over all
alignments for this read of the expected
value of that latent variable divided by
the total number of reads and so what
the EM algorithm does is it starts out
with a random guess for the adaa uh it
computes the expectations based on those
expectations it computes a new maximum
likelihood estimate based on that
likelihood estimate it updates the
expectations and it continues to do this
until convergence so this is a quite
effective method unfortunately uh it's
also somewhat slow so in terms of how
effective it is um this is a plots from
the original RSM paper and what they're
showing is in different simulated
experiments where we have the true
abundance on the x-axis and the
predicted abundance on the y- axis how
well do different methods do at
estimating uh transcript abundance and
so the first here uh the the top row is
in a mouse liver sample the bottom row
is in a maze uh sample so the the
leftmost column is showing if you just
used unique counting of reads and so
what you can see here is there's kind of
systematic underestimation because
you're throwing away those reads that
don't uniquely map to this this
transcript and so you're sort of
generally systematically underestimating
the abundances the rescue method uh in
the middle I'll come back to in one
second uh and then the best looking
method is this em procedure I just
discussed on the right so the rescue
method is something that that was
developed in some of the original work
for uh the RNA seek assay um and it was
a heuristic and it turns out that it's
really just uh equivalent to basically
running one round of the EM so you look
at the uniquely mapped reads you
estimate the abundances based on those
alone then you go back to all of the
reads that map to more than one place
and you allocate them proportionally
based on the estimates from the unique
mapping okay so it already resolves uh
you know a lot of the problems but it's
not as good as actually running the
algorithm to convergence as you would
expect okay so this is a great solution
why aren't we done what still remains uh
you know what what else is in this
primer so uh it it's this is a way to
find at least locally the maximum
likelihood estimates and parameters
however the problem is that every
iteration of the expectation
maximization algorithm scales in the
total number of alignments right even
when we're being sparse and not
considering every transcript to generate
every read we still have to Loop over
all of the transcripts to which this
read has an alignment and we have to
evaluate those expectations those those
expected values of the latent variables
and then uh we have to do that for as
many iterations as we need to converge
so uh in a typical rnas experiment we
might have 10 to the 7th to 10 to the
eth alignments and we might have
hundreds to thousands of iterations okay
so uh this whole thing is going to take
quite a while to
optimize luckily uh people have thought
about solving this problem as well
okay so uh a common way to reduce the uh
number of the complexity of the
likelihood function is to collapse
redundant reads there are many ways to
do this uh but they are um different
mostly in the details than the
fundamentals um and I'll give sort of
the most simple uh explanation of of how
this this process works um interestingly
this idea of collapsing redundant reads
into equivalence classes of reads goes
back almost to um the original work on
do solving that estimation problem so
from the GetGo people realized this was
a computationally challenging problem um
and thought about variable reduction
strategies that would allow us to solve
it more
quickly okay so what are these
equivalence classes and how are they
helpful so here's the key idea um
imagine I have an experiment where I
have a set of transcripts and a set of
fragments fragments is just the generic
term for a read could be a read or a
read pair and the arrows here show the
alignments of those fragments to the
transcripts so for example fragment one
maps to transcript B and also to
transcript e uh as does fragment three
andag fragment five whereas two and four
only map uniquely to transcript C and
this is not an atypical kind of pattern
because the alignment is not um
ambiguous randomly it's ambiguous mostly
driven by the sequence structure of the
transcript so when I have alternative
splicing those transcripts are going to
tend to have multimapping reads in the
areas where they share sequence and
transcripts that have unique SPL
Junctions are going to tend to have
uniquely mapping reads across those spce
Junctions so I I um tend to get very
structured patterns of read alignment so
despite the fact that I have five
fragments here I only have two types of
fragments right and so those types are
the type of fragment that aligns to B
and E and the type of fragment that
aligns to C so one way to classify this
experiment it does lose some information
um but it still turns out to be pretty
good for most cases is to represent my
experiment like this rather than
considering every alignment
independently I'm going to consider that
there are three alignments that uh map
to the group be and two alignments that
map uniquely to see I can optionally try
and keep a little extra information
about the Affinity of those fragments in
that group to each transcript or I can
just sort of assume that it's
uninformative and all I care about is uh
compatibility of
mapping okay so um this particular
notion of an equivalence class that is
completely induced by the mappings
itself uh goes back at least to the uh
work of turo at all in
2011 so what does this do for us what
does this give us so what we're really
doing if we optimize this new
representation of the data in the EM
algorithm is we had this original
likelihood um you know written in in
slightly simpler notation here which was
the product over all fragments that we
sequenced and then the sum over all
alignments of that fragment and we're
approximating that likelihood by this
thing which you know looks in notation
here maybe a little bit more complex but
it's actually much simpler it says we're
going to take the product overall
equivalence classes of fragments so all
types of fragment Ms and then we're
going to take the sum over all the
transcripts that label this equivalence
class so in our previous example one of
them was labeled B and uh go back B and
E and the other one was labeled C so
there's two types one labeled B and E we
sum over b and e one labeled with just C
we sum over C and this is the
probability of of selecting this
transcript given the parameters and then
this is the probability of generating a
fragment uh from this transcript given
that it comes from this equivalence CL
and then the idea here is because every
fragment in an equivalence class is
equivalent under our notion of the
generative model then the contribution
to the overall likelihood is just the
probability of that one fragment raised
to the number of fragments in that
equivalence class right because they're
all independent we're taking that that
multiplication by just exponentiating
this term so this turns out to be much
better um there are uh many fewer
equivalence classes then there are
transcripts yeah so quick question here
so would I so when so would these be the
same if I make the assumption that my
probability of FJ being generated from
TI is just the same independent of where
this was generated from within the
transcript I guess when should I assume
that these two are the same ah great
question um so uh if I go back here so
the the um typical Notions of
equivalence classes going back to the
original tarot at all work um well
actually I will mention Julia Salman's
work um so this is based primarily on
annotation so things coming from the
same Exon or not um the the uh turo all
work defines it in a data driven fashion
so the only thing that matters is the
specific set of transcripts to which
your read aligns that uniquely
determines the equivalence class so if
read align to the same set of
transcripts even if they're in different
positions they are equivalent for the
purposes of inference um we had a paper
in uh 17 where we looked at other
Notions of equivalence classes and it
turns out you can recover a little bit
of extra information because you're
throwing some stuff away so for example
here what we do is we look for every
transcript not just at the set of
transcripts that it maps to for every
fragment the set of transcripts that
they maps to but also the conditional
probability because there are other
things in the model that matter like the
implied fragment length they get thrown
away in the simpler Notions that get uh
captured in in other Notions right but
um for the purpose of this talk I'm just
going to assume compatibility is the
only thing we care about the reads map
to the same set of transcripts but um it
is right to think that there could be
differences even within an equivalence
class in terms of the actual
probabilities you care about in which
case you can refine that
notion thanks of
course okay so um this is great uh but
it still doesn't completely solve the
problems that we care about um because
even when I have this em solution this
this point solution it is exactly that
it's a point solution I have optimized
for the maximum likelihood set of
parameters for my model based on the
data uh I'm not guaranteed that I find a
local maximum so where I find my maximum
likelihood parameters could depend on
where I started the inference if I took
an a uniform guess as my initial step or
a random guess as my initial step um and
uh I'm not guaranteed uh to um to always
find a a global Optima okay and the
there could in fact be multiple Global
Optima different settings of the of the
transcript abundances that have the same
overall likelihood okay so uh there are
different kinds of variants in my my
whole process uh at least two of which
are important here so one is technical
variance uh which is if I had the same
biological sample and I sequenced it
again I would draw a different specific
set of transcripts and that transcript
fragments and that specific set of
fragments might lead to a different
maximum likelihood solution the other is
simply uncertainty and inference right
we are trying to optimize a likelihood
function in a a space of tens to
hundreds of thousands of parameters the
dimensionality is equal to the number of
transcripts and that's a hard inference
problem okay and so we have uncertainty
and inference as well we're never
guaranteed that we found a unique Global
Optimum uh if we start from different
places and so uh we'd like to assess
that uncertainty
so it turns out that people have studied
this problem for quite a while as well
is specifically in the context of RN
abundance estimation and there are
multiple different ways to try to assess
the uncertainty so one thing you could
do is get rid of this maximum likelihood
framework at all and think about doing
this in a fully beijan contents um so
one of the first tools to do this was uh
the bit seek work and there they
proposed a fully basan model for
transcript uh inference um and it's very
accurate it just turns out to be very
slow for uh large scale samples right um
in the original paper granted this is
quite a while ago so the computational
infastructure is different the slowest
samples took almost a week to do the uh
abundance
estimation you could uh do something
like um a posterior Gibb sampling where
you start from an informed location and
so actually uh the the RSM work uh did
this I think not the original paper but
the 2011 follow-up to the original paper
where the idea is you start from the
maximum likelihood estimate so now
you're in a good place in the parameter
space and you do some sort of sampling
around that um and you get a sense of
the variance of the posterior at least
close to the maximum likelihood estimate
this can be made to be quite fast right
you don't have to draw that many samples
to get a decent sense of the variance um
and then there's also um techniques like
bootstrap sample and this could be done
either at the level of the original
reads or could be done at the level of
the equivalence classes which is much
much faster and much more efficient um
and doesn't lose that much extra
information um and so the idea here like
a normal bootstrap procedure is you're
going to sample with replacement from
your data and then you're going to rerun
your whole inference procedure and so um
if I resample from the original reads I
just basically redo everything um I
could actually just resample from the
alignments I've already computed for
those reads but if I resample from the
equivalence class counts that's super
fast right I have a count Vector I
resample with replacement from that
count vector and I run my em algorithm
again all of these are going to give you
some sense of at least the variance of
the Poss poor the variance of of around
the point estimate uh some of them will
give you the full posterior
distribution okay so uh this uncertainty
matters so this uh the the next uh two
uh or three slides actually are uh all
images from uh Peter Glow's uh PhD
thesis he's one of the authors of bitse
and uh there's some really nice
visualizations here about how this
uncertainty is structured okay so for
example here we have three similar
isoforms of this Gene and what these
plots are showing is the density of the
posterior jointly between Pairs of
transcripts so here between the bottom
and top transcript what we see is
there's a strong anti-correlation the
more abundant this transcript is the
less abundant this transcript is uh and
then likewise between the the bottom and
middle transcripts there's a strong
anti-correlation there's not so much
between uh the the middle and um uh or I
think this is this is
B WM so that's this one and then this
one is o oh okay this one is the top so
between the middle and the top this line
is wrong there's not so much of a a
strong anti-correlation in the
posterior okay so this means that it's
not just variance in the estimate but
there's co-variance in the estimates
between different pairs of variables um
so this is important to understand the
variance of the estimate when you want
to do Downstream analysis so imagine we
wanted to do differential testing
between these these transcripts between
conditions um so if I look at the
posterior estimates of the abundance of
these transcripts what I can see is um
it's pretty clear that this red
transcript is more highly expressed than
the others um and the distributions are
not really overlapping that much but
between the green and the blue my
estimate is that the green transcript is
more abundant and the posterior supports
that but there's a fair degree of
Uncertain right it might be that these
are the same abundance or that the blue
uh transcript has higher abundance Etc
uh okay so finally um this kind of
happened systematically so what this uh
what this density plot is showing is the
um the total variance that I I measure
in the abundance estimate versus the
mean of the abundance and so if the only
uncertainty I had was shotgun sampling
uncertainty if this was a purely Pon
process then I would expect that the
variance scales exactly with the mean
it's the characteristic of the Pon
function but instead I see this this
extra dispersion this extra variance
right most things have a higher variance
than the me okay so it's a systematic
effect see how I'm doing one
time all right so um we can account for
this uncertainty in differential
expression testing uh and there's a a
lot of work that does this uh in
different various different ways um
we've worked on this this problem um in
collaboration with with Mike love and
folks in his group
um though I would say that the the sort
of most recent state-of-the-art approach
here is uh represented in the Ed R4
package uh where they tested different
methods for posterior uncertainty
estimation along with different
transcript expression estimates um and
found that uh the ed4 method along with
Gibb sampling to be the the most
accurate and efficient so I'm not going
to talk about the differential testing
today ough nor will talk about that a
little bit later um what I want to talk
about now is a new idea um and uh the
idea here is that we could imagine
trying to propagate this uncertainty
through the entire analysis from the
quantification to the differential
testing um in order to improve our
sensitivity and uh in order to maybe
improve our statistical power at a given
sensitivity and that definitely works
you get much better estimates of
transcript level differential expression
when you know the uncertainty in those
abundance estimates but sometimes you
just really can't decide there's not
enough information in the experiment so
in that case you could fall back to Gene
level estimates but maybe you're missing
the important biological signal of the
subgene level transcriptional activity
that's driving your biological process
so uh the idea uh that I'm going to talk
about is what if we could use the data
to generate inferentially
distinguishable groups that is groups of
transcripts where together the
uncertainty is low enough that we can
make confident predictions about their
abundance and therefore make confident
predictions about differential
expression so uh here's an example of
such a group so what I'm showing here is
the posterior density estimates um for
two different transcripts where the
density estimates are just the frequency
of of abundances over Gibb samples and
um this is the posterior density
estimate for the group okay so if I um
group these two transcripts together in
every iteration of my posterior sampling
and I look at the sum of their estimated
abundances it's very tightly centered
around uh this particular value around
1500 so the spread is very large for the
individual transcripts but the spread is
very narrow for this particular group
what this means is these probably have
highly anti-correlated posterior
distributions um or posterior samples
and uh when I group them together
there's very little uncertainty in their
abundance okay so how do we estimate
this uncertainty or how do we measure it
uh there there are different ways to do
it um but I'm going to propose this uh
this metric that we use originally in
the swish paper which we call the
inferential relative variance it's meant
to be sort of a scale-free measure of
the uh uncertainty in the estimate um
and this is just showing what this looks
like for transcript uh at the transcript
level and at the gene level where the uh
observation is just it's much wider the
transcript level and it's much narrower
at the gene level um and you can think
about this as just sort of a a scaled
version of the um the standard deviation
minus the mean over the mean there's uh
a couple of extra details about like
shifting and making sure you don't
divide by zero Etc but that's the idea
right we're measuring the spread of the
distribution over
its so um how should we address this
problem right what what is the primary
computational challenge here we we would
like
to find the abundances at the
finest grain level that is supported by
the data such that the inferential
groups we find are distinguishable from
each other and we'd like to do this in a
data driven way we want to let we want
to let the data speak for themselves and
tell us what the inferentially dist
distinguishable transcriptional groups
could
be so it turns out um that in 2013 only
two years after the uh the mm seek work
turo and others had a a very nice
solution to this problem as well
um so what they noticed in this paper
flexible analysis of RNA seek data using
mixed effect models is that often sets
of transcripts with poorly estimated
expression are anti-correlated because
reads can be mapped to the combined set
of transcripts with confidence but no
reads can be mapped to specific
transcripts within the set in these
circumstances it may be more informative
to treat the set of transcripts as a
unit of inference rather than the
individual transcripts and then they
propose algorithms to do this okay um so
when we read this paper uh it was very
inspiring um however there were some
places where we thought we might be able
to improve it okay so particularly the
problem is that as the size of the data
sets gets bigger uh both in terms of the
size of the annotated transcript set and
the number of reads we found that the
implementation becomes kind of
Impractical um and the reason for that
is that the first step of their
algorithm is to look at all of the
inferential samples so all the sort of
GIB samples for every transcript and
compute all the pawise anti-correlations
to group the things with the greatest
anti-correlations uh and then to
recompute those correlation estimates
right so there's this huge computation
um in every step that can be
parallelized but still grows quite slow
uh so we thought of a different way to
try to tackle this problem we're trying
to get at the same thing but doing it in
a different way uh and we're going to
make use of this equivalence class
notion and specifically a graph induced
by the equivalence classes uh that's
called the fragment ambiguity graph so
uh I'm going to sort of briefly describe
the approach uh behind a a method called
Terminus that was developed uh by my
former student HK and um no's work
naturally builds upon and extends this
in in several very useful ways so
um here's a another view of the example
that I was giving before okay so this is
actually showing over time or over
iterations of a Gibb sampler the
posterior estimates of uh abundance that
are assigned to each transcript so the
spread of these things right the the the
difference between the the lowest Valley
and uh the highest peak is the overall
sort of uncertainty we have in the
abundance of this transcript over all of
the Gib samples um and so it's big for
the orange and the blue transcripts but
if in each iteration we sum together
those two estimates we get this green
estimate and the spread of this is quite
small okay and in fact we can formalize
this notion um which is that if we take
random pairs of transcripts that are
uncorrelated and we sum together their
their Gib samples we expect that the sum
has not much smaller of a spread than
the individual components but if they
are well anti-correlated then that
spread should get much smaller okay and
so this is the intuition that we're
looking for we'd like to find groups of
transcripts such that when we sum them
together the uncertainty becomes much
smaller than it would be if they were
separate okay so we're going to employ
an iterative algorithm to do this this
follows the same idea as the turo at all
work uh which is that we're going to do
this greedily but the the real question
is how do we find good candidates
transcripts or transcript groups that
are good to collapse and what makes a
good cab so we're going to use this
notion of inferential relative variance
as kind of a score function to measure
how good it would be to take a pair of
transcripts or a pair of groups of
transcripts and merge them together in
terms of reducing the uncertainty in our
inference so specifically what we're
going to say is for uh any pair of
transcripts I andj where they could be
either transcripts in our original
annotation or groups that we've already
created earlier on in the algorithm
we're going to say the score is equal to
the inferential relative variance of the
um the vector of GIB samples from I and
J summed together minus the mean
inferential variance of them separately
right so what exactly is saying is um if
this value is very small the influential
relative variance um when I group them
together compared to the average of the
individuals then this is a good collapse
to make good things to group together if
they're similar then they're not a good
thing to group together and if they're
larger which shouldn't happen too often
um then they're definitely not good to
group together so what does this look
like this is just showing plotting this
score for for transcripts in the
original set um one way to view it is we
have it uh this is set up such that zero
is the variances are the same when I add
them together versus when I look at them
separately so things that are above this
line are pairs where collapse would be a
good thing right where I would reduce
the inferential uncertainty a lot so
especially these ones up here I would
get a big reduction in uncertainty by
grouping them together there are some
where I would actually do worse by
grouping them together um but you can't
see the density great on this plot um
but most points are sort of at zero or
slightly above the Yeah question so some
of this um uncertainty comes from like
you know sequence similarity yes so how
much of this um of these ones that you
can actually merge are like consistent
across many different data sets versus
specific to the yeah right so uh
excellent question um and something that
I think uh nor will tackle in a little
bit more detail but um it is largely
driven by the sequence um the main
reason we're not directly using the
sequence here but rather using the
grouping based on the sequence
similarity as viewed through
multimapping is that uh it does it in a
data dependent way so uh we we don't
have um like if things aren't expressed
they're never going to be group together
but also individual experiments uh
depending on the depth of coverage may
or may not be able to distinguish
between transcript so you could imagine
in some data set where it's low coverage
I don't get enough unique regions to be
able to separate a pair of very similar
transcripts but in a very high depth
experiment or in a sample where those
are highly expressed transcripts I might
have enough reads to cover those
distinctive regions right but yeah it's
it's driven by it's a function of both
the transcript structure as well as the
sequence
coverage thank you
thanks okay so um let me talk a little
bit about the computational idea here so
um finding all the and correlations is
kind of the prohibitive step so we want
to avoid that um but the intuition is
that not all pairs are important in fact
almost all pairs are probably not good
candidates for collapse pick two random
transcripts in the transcript Dome
probably not a good idea to merge them
together because they probably don't
have a lot of sequence similarity so the
key idea is we're going to use the
structure of the alignment ambiguity to
efficiently call the search
space all right so here's the idea uh we
talked about these equivalence classes
all right so we have this scenario where
reads multimap to transcripts this
induces some set of equivalence classes
um each equivalence class is a set of
transcripts and we can think about that
set as inducing edges pairwise between
all of the elements of that set so this
equivalence class induces a pairwise
edge between A and B this equivalence
class induces a pair wise Edge between B
and C uh a single equivalence class
could induce more than one Edge but here
there they're just pairs so we just get
edges so uh if we look at the full set
of edges induced by this graph uh by
this relation what we get is a graph
where the transcripts are the nodes and
there's edges between every pair of
nodes that co-occur in some equivalence
class and furthermore reads can co-occur
in many equivalence classes and so we
can assign weights to these edges so we
just get a weighted graph okay and what
we're going to do is we're going to view
the process of finding good candidates
and collapsing them is simply the
process of collapsing edges in this
graph we want to we want to merge pairs
of nodes that are good candidates this
will simplify the and then we're going
to iterate that process but the number
of edges is way smaller than the number
of transcripts choose to okay so here's
what this graph kind of looks like again
vertices are sets of transcripts the
edges uh exist between every pair VI VJ
such that vij co-occur in at least one
equivalence class so our motivation for
this interestingly enough uh is comes
from computer Graphics uh so there's a
similar problem in computer Graphics
where you have a fine resolution mesh
which you want to progressively simplify
while maintaining the core geometric
details um they do this with this notion
of a quadric aerometric and then Edge
collapse um we wanted to do the same
kind of thing in this graph right we
want to greedily collapse pairs of
transcripts such that uh we merge the
best things so we're going to take this
approach we're going to put all the
edges in a Min Heap uh and while we've
not exceeded our approximation budget
we're going to extract the edge with the
best collapse um we're going to contract
The Edge and then we're going to update
only those uh only those Edge weights
adjacent to our newly created node so
we're doing a small amount of work in
each iteration of the algorithm so
overall the algorithm looks like this uh
we're going to continue this process
until we exceed some threshold which I
won't have time to talk about threshold
selection today but we have a a
reasonably principled way to select when
to stop collapsing okay so let me just
quickly show some results from this this
approach um I'm going to focus in on
these two which are full transcriptome
simul data in in human and full
transcript a specific simulated data in
Mouse um okay so here is uh true Count
versus estimated count under mm collapse
salmon which is our transcript level
abundance estimator and Terminus which
is what I just described um and I'd like
to draw your attention to these off
diagonal places right Terminus reduces
the off diagonals uh again it's not
changing the underlying estimation
algorithm it's just using Salmon's
estimates but it's intelligently
grouping together things such that when
you group them together they move closer
to the Diagon okay so uh this is this is
effective uh both toward uh you know
places like this as well as along the
axes you get less extreme misestimates
but should shouldn't we kind of expect
this right I mean if I grouped
everything together it would exactly
fall in the day yes perfect yeah so if I
grouped everything together and I had
one group the only difference would be
the total estimate of aligned reads
versus the number of reads I sequenced
so you absolutely Ely expect this um the
the reasonable Baseline here is MM
collapse so these end up having a very
similar number of groups but we find
that the groups in Terminus tend to be
better but yeah that's that's a great
Point Baseline expectation is kind of
hard to determine in this case um and so
if we look at the correlation of the
estimates or the relative error we find
that um we improve the correlation of
the estimates it's actually pretty
similar to the transcript level but
there's a lot of transcripts so this
this change is non-trivial uh and then
the error goes
down um the same thing happens with AAL
specific transcript expression so here
what we did is we took um a known uh set
of alic variants and we induced a um an
alic uh transcriptome and simulated from
that um and then we can quantify what
the the error looks like and so we
notice that there are different types of
error distribution so for example mmek
tends to make the biggest errors um in
the case where the truth is zero but the
estimate is greater than one right so
that's the red bars here they're they're
calling a lot of nonzero things is uh a
lot of truly unexpressed things is
expressed um on on the flip side um
there tends to be some false negatives
under both salmon and uh Terminus but
fewer under Terminus and then for things
that are neither false positives nor
false negatives the estimation error is
the smallest under terminous right we
can sort of stratify that um and if we
look at how frequently we induce the
wrong dominant Al that is in Truth Al a
is greater than b um but we predict B to
be greater than a or actually the
opposite here the truth is B is greater
than a and we predict a is greater than
b the number of switches is small uh
less than half under the methods that
collapse and the method that doesn't now
you're not picking the right Al here
necessarily instead but uh the primary
mechanism to achieve this is we group
together alals where there's not enough
information to determine one or the
other and this happens in an intelligent
way so that we still do call the
dominant Al one is clear but when we
can't make that determination we don't
call any because we put them together in
the same group uh finally I'll just
mention the method is is fast uh and
memory efficient so uh Terminus you know
Works in a few gigabytes of memory at
least on samples of this size uh
compared to for large transcriptomes
hundreds of gigabytes of memory for mm
collaps uh and it's quite fast right
because we're avoiding all that
computation okay so uh in closing um I
just want to make a few observations to
sort of lead into what nor is going to
talk about um but some of them are
independent so when you're doing this
kind of inference you should always
account for inferential uncertainty this
is relatively common now in RNA seek
though I'd argue not as common as it
should be but it applies to other assays
wherever there's uh ambiguity as well so
uh quantification itself can be done on
a spectrum where transcripts are at one
end and genes or groups of genes are at
the other but one thing that might be a
nice way to view this is to let the data
themselves dictate what the group should
be rather than predetermining the level
of modification right rather than
choosing genes or transcripts allow the
data to tell us what is distinguishable
so I talked about a method to do that
which is uh Terminus and we've since
improved this method um and and made it
more accurate um we tend to find these
groups that are biologically meaningful
under known annotation so I haven't
shown the data for this for a lack of
time but despite the fact that the
algorithm is purely data driven we
recover um groups that preserve and
respect no annotations most of the time
and we can even apply these same ideas
to ambiguity that arises in other assay
types at different levels so for example
in tagged in single cell data we get the
similar kind of ambiguity at the gene
level uh we can apply the same kinds of
algorithms though we haven't actually
done that work yet uh but there's a
challenge a key challenge that was
brought up by one of the questioners uh
which is the groups are data driven and
can change between experiments so how
should we compare across the experiments
and how should we use these groups for
something like differential testing when
the groups M themselves can change uh
that's something that uh was subsequent
work to this uh that that nor is going
to tell us more
about okay so starting from where Rob
left so uh we uh we do have uncertainty
then we talking with RN abundance
estimates and the way we usually end up
estimating is like generating B either
we do a posterior sampling through Gib
sampling or mcmc or what we can do is uh
generate a bunch of bootstrap samples
and let's say for the purpose of this
these additional samples that are we are
generating for a given RM example to
either of these approaches let's call
them inferential replicates and the way
we are measuring uncertainty is using
this metric introduced in this paper
from Mike's group uh where they
introduced wish is called inferential
relative variance and again U it's a
sort of a scale fee metric and idea
being is like we are trying to we would
assume a poison variance where uh
variance skilles with the mean and any
additional variance that is observed uh
is sort of Duey uncertainty and we
comput it by subtracting mean from the
variance that is over these bootstap
samples and then divide by the mean and
the reason we care about it again is
like any Downstream analysis such as
differential testing is going to be at
the end of the day as good as the ab
estimates that we have
so higher the value for this metric the
higher the uncertainty that we going to
see so again if you look at the gene
level uh we don't need to worry that
much because in most for most genes we
have a very low uh value uh very there's
very low uncertainty and does we see
very low value for this particular
metric on the other hand for transcripts
this value can increase a lot and that's
why you you see that histogram spread
all over the place B uh while genes are
the most certain but and um thus we
should get very accurate analysis but
then we in many cases like we we are
then uh masking transcription level
Dynamics and which might be important
for uh certain applications other
transcripts not all but for many they
can be a lot of uncertainity so the then
the question is perhaps is um can we do
something in a Midway so in this talk
I'll be talking about two different
projects one is three Terminus which is
effectively the framework for handling
this uncertainty and then second is a
tool called mendi which is a sort of a
differential testing framework that is
built on based off on the top of the
street so uh starting witherus so uh we
already heard about uh Terminus and the
idea is to form sort of discreet groups
but what termin Tre Terminus is doing is
building on top of terminus but rather
than having a discrete group of
transcripts as an output we are rather
now outputting a set Forest of
transcript
trees so the input to is like a given RN
samples or a set of samples that are
Quantified using salmon uh we take make
use of the equivalence class information
and then output a set of uh of of uh set
of transcript trees and where the leaves
represent the uh individual transcripts
and the notes represent that aggregated
set of groups the key feature of this
tree is that that uncertainty decreases
as we go up the
tree um just to provide an examp example
so this is one particular Gene called uh
PK qr6 and this let sort of set of
transs that are present within it and
this is sort of the tree that is being
created uh for this vory
Terminus and if you just look at these
two particular transcripts and and look
at the corresponding uh arrangement of
exons within it you could see that these
two share a very similar set of exons
the only difference being is like one is
slightly shorter than the other in in
just a few bases so it is going to be
very hard to be
actually uh sort of be distinguished
between them when you're trying to
assign deeds and these sort of things
sort of get group first uh are very the
transcript that are very hard to
quantify so tend to get group first and
as denoted there in that particular
example so why do we just care about
these trees and not just uh looked at
the stopped at the uh transcript group
level the key thing is like when we at
the end we are getting discrete groups
as an output we are
the place that we sto grouping is
dependent on a threshold and that might
not be necessarily optimized for some
downam analysis further depending on the
use case and flexibility like if you
want to increase the resolution or
decrease it that would mean that we have
to rerun the entire grouping process
again so in this case uh the tree helps
and just to give you an example here is
a Terminus group and what we do is on a
similar data set we do a differential
testing between a set of uh between a
uh two group condition uh with each
group containing six samples and in this
particular thing we see that uh the the
uh in these two conditions there this
particular group is not
differential but when we look at the
three structure we uh it consists of
these three transcripts and it is
grouping these this terminous group
consists of this these three Set uh
transcripts but if we were not to over
agregate and we just were to look at
this particular group that just
consisted of two transcripts then there
was a clear differential signal so what
could happen there sometimes that uh you
having just a set of discrete proofs
with beforehand without considering the
downstream analysis we can over agregate
and in many cases we will also under
agregate in this particular example I
had an example for over agregation but
in MO most cases we see a lot of under
aggregation and where more aggregation
would have helped us in leveraging the
signal that was there in the data so the
tree structure sort from T Terminus sort
of can help in addressing these
issues so uh how the next question then
comes is perhaps that how do we go about
constructing such trees so again ideas
is built on top of uh ter Terminus which
Rob explained in the Prima
and idea is that we first construct a
graph on these transcripts and the edge
between these transcripts sort of denote
that they co-occurred in at least one
equivalence class and the reason again
for considering the equivalence classes
is because these are the places where
the transcripts are sh would be end up
would be sharing reads and which is sort
of one of the main causes of
uncertainty uh the weight for this Edge
is denoted um by again um
uh this uh value called s which is sort
of computing the difference in the
inferential relative variance between of
that particular group assuming that part
set of transcripts was to be collapsed
and the the mean across the individual
transcripts that constituted that group
and this sort of graph serves as a
starting point for for uh for towards
constructing this
Forest so um um here in in this toy
example I have a set of just let's say
four transcripts and the weights are
like denote like what how much reduction
and inferential relative variance we'll
observe if that particular pair of
transcript through collapse so it's a
this is a greedy approach and then uh
again we see that for the in this
particular graph these two particular
set of transcripts uh have the highest
reduction in fential relative Vari this
means that this is a good Edge to
collapse so as soon as we collapse this
Edge we end up sort of creating a tree
and now these two set of transcripts
that will collapse now they became the
children for my new node for that tree
that was constructed and now we uh since
this these two particular edges have
been collapsed uh what we end up doing
is uh we sort of re Computing the weight
with the uh neighboring transcripts
corresponding to this particular Edge so
that's why with uh we recompute the
weight for T4 and T1 T2 and T3 and T1 T2
and we um uh and then we continue this
procedure again and again end up picking
the picking up the edge with the lowest
weight and we keep doing this till the
time we can't collapse anymore or we
reach some sort of a stopping
criteria
now while I have been talking about
Forest here U but in this particular
example might seem that we just have
have a s a single tree but in many cases
what you might have is like this is just
I took a toy example but you could have
many disconnected components in the
original transer craft and so you would
be running this procedure IND
individually on each of these connected
components or sometimes you might end up
breaking that uh because of we might
have some stopping criteria and that
might need that we we just stop stop
there right there and then you'll get
two individual trees so the key key
thing to not is that with the this
procedure is run on a given individual
sample and we get sort of an output as a
forested piece now the next question um
which many had as well in the streamer
as well is like how do we do when we
have a set of RN examples because this
is just for a given given RN this is
this procedure right now that I've
demonstrated works on single RN example
but what we have in most RN analysis is
a set of
samples so uh we sort of provide two
different modes to constructores one is
called the mean mode and the second is
called the consensus mode each have its
own different
ways uh for the mean mode what we
provide is
um um we again go back to this graph
approach but now uh uh this time H
rather than for a given sample uh rather
than into a single sample now the S
denotes that it the these two transcript
set of occur in equivalence class in at
least one one RN example across a set of
samples and then what we do is we uh the
weight now denotes is the mean of that
collapse score across all the set of
samples and then we go by that same
procedure that we had for an individual
samples and this and we end up getting a
tree for the entire set of RM examples
the SE the second mode that we provide
is a consensus mode this idea sort of
borrows from
phenetics and idea is that the we want
to preserve that inferential uncertainty
structure that was uh preserved sort of
that is that represents that provides
some sort of summarized top political
structure across a set of samples so
what we do is we end up creating trees
for across each RN sample and then for
the set of samples uh what we do is we
apply uh a consensus algorithm and we
get sort of with a hope to get that
summarized structure that for that
uncertainty that is observed across
majority of samples uh um just a brief
notice that what we do is also apply
majority rule extended algorithm the
idea being there is let's say if there
are certain ages or certain structures
or clusters uh are going if um that are
present um between a certain set of
samples that are still not in majority
and if you can still add them to this
existing structure uh till the time they
don't end up breaking the threee
structure we try to add them so if there
is a pop if that structure is let's say
present in
a a rear population like a set of
samples that represent a condition um
which could be a real cell type or so
and if the a possibility to preserve
that this algorithm tries to take that
into account as
well so now once we have the three then
the question next question is like how
do we go about analyzing it so there are
different multiple options and what we
provide is like a dynamic programming
approach and you what we could do is
like given a objective function that we
can of objective metric that we care
about for each node we could run a DP
and sort
of optimize that over the entire set of
tree and get a cut from that tree and
then that cut perhaps can be used for
Downstream analysis
so we in this particular paper we we
looked at two different uh objective
functions which looked reasonable one
was like one could be that we want to
minimize the uncertainty but at the same
time we want the nodes to be situated at
a low height and that's why we minimize
that so and this this particular thing
can be computed for all node in the tree
so we have a DP that can optimize this
objective function from the differential
analysis perspective one could be that
we could compute the effect effect size
of the lock full changes and we want to
maximize that at the same time we want
to minimize the uncertainty so that's
the second objective function and we
sort of uh uh optimize for these two
metrics in that uh using the Tre termin
Tre uh on both simulated and
experimental data set and try to see
plot these metrics and then see and get
a cut and then see if he can use those
for Downstream
analysis so uh the U another key aspect
is since we have we get a forest again
to get uh we have another package which
sort of first unifies the individual
forest and then creates a unified tree
and then on that easily these objective
functions can can be
computed so so U now to talk about
results since the to the best of our
knowledge uh they existed no other
method that actually constructed
transcript Tre so what we uh for as a to
serve as a baseline we went back to the
idea of mm collapse from tarot which had
the initial grouping IDE of transcripts
and what they had they were grouping
transcripts based on anti-correlation so
what we did was like we sort of computed
the correlation or the negative of that
correlation between um all that all
pairs of transcripts and then converted
that to a distance metric and gave that
as an input to upgma which is sort of
does a high hierarchical clustering
based on a distance distance Matrix
across all set of features and then we
we sort of try to compare Tre terminous
tree with this tree just as give as a
baseline comparison and the first thing
that we look at is the
uncertainty and what we have on the
different axises the these are the three
terbus trees to the two modes consensus
and mean and this is the Baseline tree
and uh on the right we are plotting
rightmost is the we are plotting the
inferential the uncertainty metric for
the genes and this is for the transcript
uh we for the trees we are only looking
at nodes at four and as we could see
that while expected genes have the
lowest
uncertainty uh and transcripts have the
largest uh if you look at this file and
part both these consensus mean somewhere
between the transcript and the gene
genes and is sort of lower than the
anticorrelation
tree and just to show demonstrate that
I'm just not cherry picking on one
particular height we do it we do this is
the same plot but repeat it across
different heights and we tend sort of
tend to see a similar Behavior across
the across the different node situated
at different height in the
tree uh next thing uh so um uh since we
care about at the end for the groups to
have some sort of biological meaning we
also sort of tend to look the to uh try
to look at the total number of unique
genes these AR trees map to and as you
could consistently see that uh the total
number of unique genes that are mapped
by the nodes of Three termin Trees is
much lower compared to and the
anti-correlation tree and again no
annotation information has been provided
to as an input it's all just based on
the equivalence class information so
this nodes would have some can in many
ways be used for um uh have have a
consistent sort of biological
information and um uh we also then
though again I'll be talking about
differential testing Al together on its
own but just using some the cuts that I
had talked about and if I we try to
compare uh run uh do differential
testing on these uh using the Terminus
groups at the transcrip level at the
gene level and using the cuts and we see
that again um uh while genes have the
lowest FDR uh uh the the the particular
card that was optimized for the effect
size of the LFC that has the highest
DPR uh again it's these features are
since are different so it's not directly
one to one comparison between these
different features but a thing worth
noting is that what we next do a more of
a qualitative analysis uh
the cut that is obtained on this using
that was maximizing for the lock for
change uh that sort of ends up mapping
to more unique transcripts then that
would have been covered by Terminus so
on the other hand Terminus Maps the cut
that is covered by Terminus ends a maap
to relatively much few positive
transcripts that we actually so there's
definitely a PO like potential for being
able to recover more
signal so to summon summarize just uh
this part of the talk uh Tre Terminus is
sort of its one of its own sort of
methods that construct transcript trees
and provides the flexibility with the
end to the end user to analyze notes at
different resolutions uh it can be
leveraged to find signal with respect to
the transcripts which might be lost uh
by doing transcript level
analysis uh so far like we have
demonstrated this this its application
to its shorted sequence data but then
this is also equally applicable to Long
Reach uh the key being there again is
that they're still a read through
transcript mapping ambiguity for the
long read as well and it has a Rel it
has also low throughput so uncertainty
is bound to exist and then pre
terminuses also be will be applicable
for long days and another interesting
application would be of course to single
cells though again since if you look at
the 10x or the top based protocols the
uh since we are only able to effectively
sort of map uh map genes uh so there
rather than the transcript trees the key
would be the gene trees though again if
you have full length protocols like
smart seek or the ones with back bio
nanop for then of course then we can map
this to uh on transcript back though the
key thing then that they will be look at
would be looking at is is perhaps work
working on improving the scalability of
tre terminal because if we were to take
each cell as a sample then um and we
could have millions of cells that is
something we need to come up with more
intelligent strategies right now because
uh it uh the SP the inherent sparity
that is present within an e cell might
also be a hindrance to effectively
uh uh re run through that the UN IND
profile
uh so uh T Terminus is available quick
quick question yeah so I guess going
back it seems like you're generating
these trees kind of off of all of these
different samples and then you can show
that when you test you you identify
these like larger discrepancies between
samples are there any kind of double
dipping issues or is there some way of
mitigating anything yeah so yeah I'll be
talking about that in the late second
part of the talk so I'll wait until
thanks yeah
Co so because yeah the second part of
the talk I'll be talking differential
testing so go so uh so we
uh um PR terminat is available in Rust
and then we also have an R interface uh
so that since most of the downstream
tools are written in R so to effectively
read the input uh we have an r package
VR
so uh coming back now to this the second
part of the stock that sort of focuses
on differential testing because one of
the key uh Downstream analysis is that
is differential testing so we we we
focus on building a differential testing
tool that leverages the tree that we
have obtain from three
terminal so so again um uh um Rob
mentioned a bit about this uh there like
there bunch of differential testing
Methods at the level of transcripts that
leverage these additional inferential
replicates sluth switch recently EDR uh
for U uh just to name a few and a key
thing to note is like they they
demonstrate a high performance and this
is spe uh especially related to when the
transcripts are very high uncertainty so
if you look at this particular plot um
we could see that clearly that there's
U swish uh here which is which is the
method that is making use of inferential
replicates that has a much uh low false
positive uh low low much low FDR
compared to the other methods so using
these inferential replicates helps us in
uh uh preventing the aggregation of
false positives and um this is sort of
one of the guiding philosophies that m
Ed us to build further on top of
this so um the goal of the mendi is we
want to Output a set of differentially
expressed notes from the trees and these
notes can either consist of transcripts
or in a notes but this should be output
in a data driven Manner and at the same
time what we want to do is prevent over
aggregation and ideally an inner node
should be only output when there's exist
at least one underlying transcript whose
signal gets marked masked due to
uncertainty but at the same time uh we
want to make sure that whatever signal
there exists in data we are able to
capture
that so initially when we started with
the idea of tre Terminus was like we
thought since there's a lot of
literature that exists on uh tree based
differential testing methods we could
just use those and apply do on
determinist but when we started
exploring this project we sort of
realized like the existing methods don't
end up doing what we don't necessarily
do what we want them to do at least the
use case that is described above or are
perhaps not directly applicable to the
tree that is output by Tre Terminus so
to give a brief ey overview what exists
right now like a lot of them are focused
at improving the sensitivity at the leaf
level with the goal being that if an
inner node is selected uh then all the
underlying transcripts would also be
called differentially expressed then for
this we have no different again within
that we have different subcategories one
is trying to use the tree structure and
using correlation and then then to share
the information information among leaves
and then that's how they're propagating
the signal or you could and these
includes like struct TDR or Zazu and
then or there was three climb bar um
which has a different strategy but again
the goal is that all the underlying
transcripts are called differentially
expressed then there are a bunch of
methods which output nodes but then the
thing between with them is like if they
say if they find that uh in a node is
not differential then they stop testing
and then say that not none of the
underlying transcripts or the whatever
notes like between them are all
significant for this might not be uh
true U applic this is not applicable
when we for three ter Ministries or in
or at least when you have transcripts
groups together uh because let's say
what if you have a DTU and then the
signals get cancelled at an in a node
when uh definitely that there were
differential transcript that existed
below that particular node so for these
sort of cases we can't just directly
apply these sort of methods and then
none of these methods also take into
account inferential
uncertainty or infal relative variance
into the into account and they just work
on a given set of P values so mendi is
sort of designed to take these things
into account and what we do is propose a
top down solution and with a goal that
we get somewhere between the leaf and
the gene level so what we do
is first for each note we compute
certain metrics uh we compute we first
assign look at it inferential relative
variance which if this particular toy
example uh is denoted by these numbers
right next to this node and then we also
try to assign a
sign um to that particular node which uh
which says that whether that particular
node was up or down regulated between
the conditions of interest and a plus
minus means that we were uncertain about
that particular node what we do we
leverage are the information replicates
and then make uh if that particular sign
occurs in a certain proportion of this
inferential replicates then only we
assign that that we're confident about
the direction between this um the
conditions of interest for that
particular node and a plus minus means
that we not sure and then uh based on
these small informations that we have
from the node we start from the top of
the
and oh one thing I forgot to mention is
like we also sort of tend to label a
note sort of significant or
non-significant based on a particular P
value threshold and the the set of notes
that will be finally be output would be
a subset of these notes uh that have a
significant P
value so we start from the top from the
top of the tree and we keep iterating
down till the time we don't find a given
uh select a significant node or we reach
at the leaf level and once we reach a
significant node we check that it uh
follows three different criteria one
that at least one child note should be
non-significant because if all of them
are significant that means that there
already exist signal Downstream and we
are definitely over aggregating so we
want to go down the second criteria is
that all the under if uh under
underlying note should have the same
direction of sign change so for from the
biological interpretation it makes sense
that the direction is the same and
finally uh all the all the children node
should have a mean inferential relative
variance above a certain threshold
because uh if we are already confident
about our prediction then there's no
point of aggregation so keeping these
three criteria in mind if the uh if a
selected note follows all of these then
um um um if if a significant node
follows all of these then for for us
that node is called a selected node and
if you look at this particular example
uh even uh this particular node was had
a significant uh was significant but uh
since both the children had uh
significant P values so we go down and
output these two notes as a selected
note um when we uh uh
um uh when you go to Let's and9 again uh
the children had uh opposite signs so
that means we go down and then we select
N5 and uh similarly uh for N20 both N7
and N8 were nonsignificant so that means
we could take this into account and
again uh similarly for n21 again and and
11 we were not sure about the uh
particular sign changes so that means we
could aggregate
them so uh there are two sort of things
that we do is like when we are Computing
P values uh uh we tend to Cal compute
the P value separately for the inner
nodes and the leaf nodes the reason
being is that since there's less
uncertainty on the nature of the we
using we use Swit as a differential
testing method here and uh for computing
the P values of all these nodes uh in
the tree and the reason we we compute
this uh separately is because when we
computed them together we saw this sort
of shift in the P values uh which
ideally for um um um if there's no
differential signal they we should have
seen a sort of a uniform shift in P
distribution of the P values the reason
again here is because um high level
nodes have less uncertainty and as a
result that the value of the relative
relatively the value of the test
statistic get shifted so and and they
end up getting uh low low P values more
compared to the in notes so we compute
the P Valu separately for the uh Leaf
notes and the inner notes and uh uh to
have more of this sort of distribution
again this I'm talking about
showing this on a Sim similar data which
has no differential signal and this was
the test statistic that I was talking
about and could see that when they were
computed together and if you look at
distribution um this has a higher width
compared to the
Le so uh we were sort of uh since we are
not doing uh after any hypo hypothesis
correction later on on the set of filter
filtering criteria that we have so what
we did did was we generated bunch of
null simulations and um uh sort I think
here here A bunch of 10 n simulations
and then computed the total number of
false positives that we get in those
simulations and on the right on the
right we have if we were to just run it
on the transcripts you and on the left
is when we do it for M and we do it a
bunch of P value different P value
thresholds and what we see is again you
could see that the total number the
false positive rate at the different
thresholds of P values these are very
comparable between when
running when when we just run it on the
transcripts or when we run mendi on the
tree so this me this sort of gives us
some sort of an confidence that we are
not aggregating the false positives with
meni uh I'll skip for this one slide for
time constraints and U so then we
actually created a bunch of different
simulations this is one particular
simulation with actually differential
signal and again compare it with the
different methods and if you look at uh
particular
particularly uh this one which is mendi
blue one uh we are controlling the false
positives at the different thresholds uh
but in point
05 uh which is slightly aggregated but
still very close to the noral threshold
uh while at the same time having a very
high
sensitivity and genes again we compare
it with genes the terminous groups tree
climber is the other method uh and
threee climber is specifically designed
for it gives inner nodes as an output
but the key thing with threee climb bar
is that when an in a node is selected
then it assumes that all the underlying
transcripts are also
different and uh again we see an
exaggerated false positive these metrics
again because the feature features are
very different are not directly
comparable between the different methods
but still this does give us some sort of
an overall idea of how the method
performs and we then um run it um on
bunch of experimental data sets as well
and specifically we find many genes that
are called significant when testing at
the gene level but none of the
underlying trans if we were to do a
transcript level analysis now now their
transcripts would have been called
significant when doing differential
analysis on the other hand meny we find
a lot of notes that are given by Mii in
the form of these inner notes and this
is one such example in this Mii finds a
group with threee transcripts and on the
this is how the tree looks for that
particular Gene
uh that these notes belong to this note
belongs to and here in the bottom we
plot the uh the individual inferential
replicates across the samples this is
for the transcript that had the most
significant P value but still did not
meet that criteria and you can see that
the difference uh difference between in
the mendi group becomes much more
clearer for the note that is output via
mendi we find many such examples uh um
during the course of a experiment and
this is another such example and you
could clearly see the signal becomes
much more clearer when looked at that in
a
note so uh you summarize uh uh the uh us
think the tree from T Terminus we are
able to extract differential nodes in a
data driven manner uh again when we are
outputting an inner node we don't want
to comment anything about the
differential status for that underlying
transcript because we are whole point of
grouping is that we sort of are unsure
about at least one underlying
transcripts and that's why we want to
look at the groups and we are able to
preserve the signal that might have
existed at the transcript through the
inner notes and perhaps would have been
missed when doing a transcrip level
analysis so uh as you mentioned um So
currently uh we um there uh we are doing
double dipping and because we are using
that same data for creating the tree and
for differential testing and this is
something we plan to look uh work on and
uh in in the future one of the
approaches perhaps could be like so um
from Daniela vens group a paper came a
couple of years ago called count
splitting the idea there was that you
split the data into a training test test
and test set test set and accordingly uh
use one set for actually learning data
level properties and then the other set
for uh doing differential uh
differential testing or any other
Downstream analysis that you want to do
so that could be one area to explore the
key thing to note there would be is that
that leads to low power so we need to be
come up with appropriate um be mindful
of that and then come up with approaches
that sort of control that and the second
thing to be mindful is that at the end
we what we are
um the error FDR error control is
usually based on a given on the total
set on the total rejected set and not on
a filtered set by that I mean is like
once we do a differential testing we get
let's even on transcripts we get a bunch
of different transcripts as an output
but for analysis we end up looking in
most cases is at a set a a subset of
those transcripts that are above a given
effect size and even when you're looking
at that particular effect size though
more biologically meaningful we we lose
the error control so similarly while we
have r mendi on a bunch of different
data sets and we seem to control the
false positives based on the the way
filters have been designed um there's
still a possibility in some cases that
we might not be giving we we might we
might not be fully be able to control
the control so developing a more of a
the theoretical framework uh so that we
can control the r that is something we
plan to work in the
future and finally uh uh the pre-int is
out and we just put the pre uh uh an
updated prein just a couple of days ago
and the r package is available
here and I would like to acknowledge Rob
and uh Jason who who is a PG student in
a lab and then this both pre terminat
and meni have been done in collaboration
with Mike uh during this project the
student yui was involved and then
finally
hi who who actually started the Terminus
project and then had provided us some
really good ke insights during the
construction of PR ter thank you