so one of the Privileges that I've had
at MIT for the last 25 years is to be
the announcer at MIT commencement and
also to read the names of
graduates and it's really fun when you
get to the phds because when you
announce their school then you get to
say with all the rights and privileges
pertaining there to
I don't know what the rights and
privileges are I guess it's the right to
wear the magic robe and the privilege to
be called a doctor and now I'd like to
present a newly minted PhD from the MIT
media laboratory Dr Pat patar nutor was
awarded the PhD from the media
laboratory just in late 2024 he's
co-director of the MIT advancing human
AI interaction research program and his
research lies at the intersection of AI
and human computer interaction where he
develops and studies AI systems that
support human flourishing through
multimodal systems with explainable
feedback Dr Pat
welcome thank you so
much hello everyone hello good evening
hi um my name is Pat as uh Todd mention
I just finished my PhD so I'm not used
to people calling me doctor yet um and I
just you know flew from Cambridge uh to
uh Bangkok actually two days ago so
please excuse my jet lag as well so
today I would like to um talk to you
about my research on how can we um
better understand and develop AI to
support human flourishing especially
through studying of what I call cybor
psychology um the Art and Science of
human AI
interaction but first before I you know
begin um I'm actually from Thailand so
it's an honor to be here in Thailand uh
with uh MIT teams and um it's an awesome
thing to do um but one thing to think
about is that if you look at the word
Thailand closely you can see that there
is no Thailand without AI right you can
see that it's really important thank you
thank you but more important than that
if you look at that there is Edge before
Ai and I think this Ed for me I would
argue stand for human so in Thailand I
think you know as the name suggests
there's both the human aspect and the AI
and thinking about both of them together
I think is really really important as
especially in this country in this
context right so that's uh why my work
at MIT really focus on this question of
how can we understand and better design
AI system to support human flourishing
I'll talk more about uh that uh during
this presentation but you can see this
is my dissertation that I just finished
um actually last year at the end of last
year what it means to think about human
AI interaction is that instead of just
focusing on AI Alone um I think as a
speaker mentioned we need to shift the
Paradigm a little bit instead of
thinking of AI we can think about IIA or
intelligence augmentation where system
can support and enhance human you know
capability right but I think in my work
I want to push that further a little bit
um not just looking at narrow way that
AI can augment human intelligence but
way in which AI can support human
holistically um that's what I call AI
for human flourishing you know
intelligent system to support
multi-dimension of uh human growth and
development what I mean by this is that
we can start to really take Knowledge
from you know different
interdisciplinary subject like
psychology Behavioral Science and U many
subject and think about how AI can
augment any of that aspect and in my own
work I look at this sort of human AI
interaction across scale and across um
um context from in space like you know
this project where we work closely with
NASA um and that's actually me uh in
zero gravity floating was really cool um
all the way to you know things that are
happening on Earth in you know domain
like education Healthcare and and many
more but there are three things that I
want to talk to you today you know we're
looking at uh human AI interaction
research we can think about ways in
which we can invent new system we can
investigate existing system on you know
problems or challenges that are facing
us and also thinking about ways that we
can Inspire new use case New
Opportunities I think that tie very well
to the industry connection right so
invent investigate and Inspire the three
uh ways that we are investigating human
a interaction research right now first
let's look at invent you know at MIT we
invent things all the time in order to
think about AI for human flourishing we
are inventing sort of you know new type
of AI system that focus on three areas I
think most of the people today focus on
productivity right but I think you know
um my colleague actually once said to me
that if you measure the wrong thing
you're going to create the wrong things
right so we need to think about the
broader goal that AI can support human
how we can use it to support human
wisdom wonder and well-being these are
the three areas that my research focus
on what I mean and each of these
actually have many um research projects
that we have developed many papers as
you can see on screen um but for example
what do we what do I mean by AI for
enhancing human Wonder right here um we
are thinking a lot about language model
I think everyone probably familiar with
language model now which had GPT we
thinking about what happened when we are
shifting from language model into what
we call large human model model where we
can start to incorporate many dimension
of data Health Data behavioral data
financial data and many more and allow a
person to actually create an AI model or
AI digital twin of them um this is me
when I'm 60 years old and I can create a
profile of who I might actually become
when I'm that old you know um you know
in the 40 years in the future and and
it's kind of interesting because you
know this is um something that is really
exciting to us because we can now really
understand how a human P how a person
person um grow and and develop over time
right this is actually based on many uh
research that we have done at the media
lab um the first one we published in
2018 looking at how we can create
realistic AI characters um this is when
you know generative AI wasn't cool yet
um we were one of the first people to
actually explore this concept and how we
can kind of create pipeline that allow
us to take different data and create
this realistic human uh virtual human
but it doesn't stop there right just
making the appearance is one thing I
think what is the most most interesting
is when you can actually create a time
machine that allow a person to use their
own you know current data and project
what they might end up you know being
like uh when they're 60 years old we
published this study called future you
where we develop a colonization of AI
system that allow a person especially
you know teenagers to talk to their
older self um so we develop system that
can take um personal data like you know
their aspiration their profile their
behavior right now and then we create
what we call synthetic memory memories
that basically use that uh uh current
live event to create the memories that
the person might experience in the
future and then feed that to the
language model to actually generate
human conversation and um by doing this
a person can actually have a
conversation with an own version of the
future so kind of like having a time
machine to chat with your future self
and this is based on Research in
Psychology where we shown that well my
colleague have shown that you know when
you increase future self-continuity you
can actually make people make better
decision by thinking in long term you
know saving more money for the future
and also you know thinking about uh um
you know uh things that will have impact
in the future like you know climate
change and important things that are not
you know just have immediate gain right
and we have shown that when people use
these um future U AI system they become
less anxious and also become more
motivated to actually think about their
life in a you know more ambitious way
and we can also increase future
self-continuity as well compared to the
control groups so you know as I
mentioned when we invent something we
also study and also do randomized
control trial to understand the impact
of AI system that we develop and it's
really exciting because you know after
launching this project we have now over
190 PE countries um people from 190
countries worldwide are using this
platform and this is part of a larger
project to actually study how AI digital
twin interact with people in the real
world um right now we have about 60,000
user um and and participant that are
using this and helping us understand how
AI can help people think in long term
and you know it's really exciting
because this project was feature on the
main page of MIT um this was you know a
great a great honor um as well and it
has been you know talk about in many
places you know EU um the the
organization that create EU AI um uh act
or the the regulation of AI also feature
this project as something that is you
know a pro-social type of AI where you
use AI to support person uh uh
development and growth
right Beyond modeling oneself you can
also model other people as well you know
this guy was in the news a lot recently
um today especially right we also look
at what happened when you actually
create a digital twin of UT people like
people that you know have are famous or
people that other people might like or
admire them like you know Elon Musk for
example we did this study in 2022
actually uh two years um ago and we did
this during the pandemic where we
interested in what happened if we used
this digital twin or AI character to
help people learn better so motivate
them to learn and uh what we were
interested in was like if we create a
virtual character does it replicate the
effect of liking or admiring that person
and what we found is that even if people
know that these character are fake and
are not real people still feel more
motivated and learn much better when
they have a character based on someone
that they like or admire right at the
time we did uh use Elon mask as the
experiment subject I don't know if we do
it today we'll have the same result um I
think he quite changed a lot um in the
last couple years right but I think this
this um um result really show that um
these tools can be really personalized
and used to actually you know enhance
The Learning Experience make them more
personalized and engaging imagine you
can learn you know your favorite
subjects like you know calculus from
anyone in the world using this sort of
AI character right so that's what we
call AI for enhancing human Wonder make
people more inspired more engaged
engaging more exciting about their life
and themselves next we want to talk
about AI for enhancing human wisdom this
is also really really important you know
we have been looking at um AI not just
in the computer screen or um in mobile
platform but when the AI is actually
part of a person as a second brain right
this is a project where we embed AI into
a varable platform we call it varable
Reasoner is a system that that create to
not a person to pay more attention to
you know logical fallacy and you know to
make them think more critically when
they engaged with information right
right now I think it's very important
more important than ever we're going to
hear many more speech more information
more advertisement more of anything
right especially AI being used to create
contents we also need to use an AI to
help us filter and think more critically
about the content that we consume and
and and receive as well right and you
know platform are not going to do it for
us right you know you can see you may
have seen meta decide to remove um fact
checking or from that platform so it's
important that we help people develop
their own sort of you know critical
thinking by having tools that are always
with them and they can kind of wear like
you know their second brain essentially
so what does this system does is that um
we use uh a semantic marker in the
language um in the text that the the
system look at to figure out when there
is a logical fallacy or when the
statement you know uh like you know
advertisement political speech or
whatever is stay without evidence um
this is not factchecking um we are
looking at logical consistency and see
how the um the claim and the evidence
support each other and what we have
found is that when you use this system
to notch people you know to to pay more
attention to the statement that have
this logical fallacy we can make people
you know identify reasonable statement
better uh than if they are not having
the system and also they tend to agree
more with statement with uh evidence as
well so this is a tool that can be used
to notch people to pay the right
attention to pay the attention to the
right part of the sentence that they
that they encounter and to help them
sort of you know develop critical
thinking we hope that once these system
start to kind of give them this nudging
mechanism um people can start to
internalize that and then they can you
know leave without the the system so
helping people cultivate this process
themselves we also take that further and
thinking about how this system can also
ask questions well right we heard a lot
about AI giving the answer to the
student to the teacher to you know the
employee the employer all kind of thing
right but what happened with the AI
asked question you know we take the
project like variable Reasoner forward
and think about what happened if AI
asked interesting question and question
that make us think more critically so we
take the process um such as you know
Socratic method where you know Socrates
never answer um any question of of his
student right but he asked the question
back so here we compare what happened
when the AI asked the ask the person um
uh the question back um instead of
giving them the correct answer um and
what we have shown is that because when
AI ask the question by Framing the
statement or the information that they
you know people encounter into question
people can actually think for themselves
and that they can actually use logical
thinking that already inert in them but
maybe they're not using because you know
they are um sort of going with um the
Intuition or going with the sort of gut
instinct you using uh using this to kind
of make them um think more critically
and we have shown that when AI asks the
right question it actually perform help
people perform better than the AI giving
the answer itself right so this is
really really important because even
with the same model the way that you
interact with people can lead to
different outcomes and this is really
promising one of our colleagues at
Harvard say that this type of work is
really exciting because it opened up new
possibility for AI power decision
support rather than making making people
over rely on a answer we use them to
nudge people to think for themselves and
provide the right uh stimulus to for
them to to kind of think critically
about the
statement so this type of work you might
consider them as some kind of proactive
agent system that are always on with the
person always asking question always
sort of providing feedback without the
person needing them right and um we're
doing many more of this type of
proactive agent where not only that we
can use them to kind of make people
think critically we can also help people
think more divergently as as well this
is a study where we look at what
happened when AI present an opposite
argument or pres present opposite bias
as the person right A lot of people try
to get rid of AI bias by trying to you
know retrain them think about alignment
research and many more but as a FCI
researcher we think what happened if we
use the AI bias to our advantage and
instead when we know what kind of bias a
person have we can have the AI bias be
the opposite of that right if you uh
someone that really like um um I don't
know like uh capitalism we can create AI
That's more pro-social or if you like
hierarchy we can create AI that this
anti- hierarchy um to actually balance
that out and we did an experiment where
people brainstorming this different kind
of AI and with different kind of bias
and what we have shown is that people
can be n to be more in the center where
you have ai that are opposite of them as
them right so you can see that when you
have ai that have the opposite bias as a
person they tend to have more neutral
value in the brainstorming outcome but
at the same time um this tool can also
be used to nudge people to become more
extreme right so it's really depending
on the context of what you want to use
this sort of agent
for I think a lot of people today I
think uh think a lot about agents right
people that are in the field of
artificial intelligence today will you
know consider AI agent as sort of the
the next Frontier we're going beyond the
chat interface into system that can act
and automate many process by itself
right you know our friend Sam otman say
that agent is the you know the killer
application of AI but um this is
actually something very funny because
this is what we have been doing at the
media lab for the last 30 years my
adviser you know when you have a cool
advisor at MIT you can brag about it um
my advisor Professor pimas has been
working on AI agent in fact many of her
companies you know have sold on this
topic already and her last latest
company was you know wellue over 900
million um dollar she have been one of
the pioneer of AI agent and you know if
you look at her work you know at the
time it was called software agents
before AI became a thing right but her
idea was always the same that if we want
to think about how technology support
people we need to pay attention to the
experience not just what the AI can do
but what experience does the AI bring to
the person right this is from her uh uh
early work on the direct manipulation
versus um interface agent which is a you
know a really famous debate in uh human
computer interaction research so the
experience of interacting with agent
really
matter one project that I would like to
highlight here is what we have been
exploring when we think about agent that
collaborate with people so here we have
a project called talk to the hand right
it's like a fun phrase to say talk to
the hand but what we mean is that we can
make AI have a hand or have some kind of
pointer that the user and AI can sort of
you know uh interacting in the same
space
um you can see one of these you know the
blue one is the AI and the the uh red
one is the user and the human and AI can
actually inter interact and and and work
together you know as these two sort of
hand or these two finger interact you
can ask question to the AI and then the
AI will answer and also you know you
will see the AI will kind of have
expression as well and it can kind of
you know collaborate and do different
tasks together with a person right you
know like I'm say thank you and then the
AI is going to move around and and
interact a little bit
so we did this um experiment in the
context of what happened if the AI work
with the person to help them you know
plan for you know do the financial
planning you can see instead of having a
person go to the chatbot or go to um
some kind of interface where they type
question they can actually you know
interact all naturally uh with the with
the system right um oops my clickers is
not working I need an AI agent right now
to help me um
okay see even we have ai and advanced
technology it alwayss that the projector
will break or the computer would break
or whatever at one point it was at
actually at Google and the CTO was
trying to hook his laptop to the
projector and they had like five
engineer trying to figure that out and
he was going to talk about Advanced Ai
and I think you know we need that first
yeah as you see right um this is uh
really interesting the the the person is
actually you know doing the task and the
AI is actually moving around um and
pointing to the right things and then
helping answer question in the context
in the location um right so this is I
think a really exciting um area where
you don't just focus on what the agent
can do but the way in which the agent
interact with the person you know in a
way that it can answer and talk and do
all the kind of thing right and we think
that this is a new type of interface
that will open up new possibility when
we think about human agent interaction
when the agent had another hand you the
same area or in the SP in the same spal
location as a person and what we have
shown in this study is that it can
actually increase the sense of human
agent collaboration which I think is
really important if you feel that the AI
that you're working with doesn't make
you feel more Empower or doesn't make
you feel that you want to work more or
actually you know feel that you are
being empowered or or or being sort of
inspired to work then you know what's
the point right so paying attention to
the way in which we design AI interface
really
matter and I think you know as as Sam
Alman said right that the um this is I
think going to be a killer application
of AI but I think it would only be a
killer application if we figure out the
right interface for it um oops Yeah so I
think that's for the invent category
right we have look at you know different
dimension and there are many more Works
many more example um in this area that I
can talk more about it would you know be
a whole day um so that's the invent
category we also need to investigate as
AI are becoming integrated into you know
our life right there are many positive
application as I mentioned helping us
with wonder where well-being and wisdom
helping us develop these skills but
there are also negative consequences as
well that we need to understand so in my
work I try to study the science of human
AI interaction on the positive side and
also on the negative sides as well many
study have point out that if you use the
AI without considering this impact it
can lead to dis Skilling disconnection
thisinformation and dehumanization I
think the worst of all right so we need
to understand when AI is used
how does it lead to some of these
unintended consequence or some of these
negative consequences and this happened
you know with everyone right Tha prime
minister was scammed by AI recently um
so this type of thing can happen to
everyone is really important right AI
scam call um Tai PM um but I think this
is you know just the beginning right we
see many more of this crime and many
more of the problems I think there are
many of them uh and but I want to start
with this one first I how many people
know uh what is this AI anyone no one
okay it mean it's haven't hit Thailand
yet that's great this is a type of
virtual companion or AI that act as your
friend and can actually you know have a
romantic relationship with you can
pretend to be your boyfriend girlfriend
or you know different kind of friends
and um you know similar to the movie
like her this AI can flirt with a person
and actually um talk to them on
different topics help you you know think
about many things right um my colleague
and I we wrote an article to MIT tech
review um many months ago now on how we
need to prepare for Addictive
intelligence that when we study AI
system it can be designed to be
addictive in the same way that social
media can also you know be addictive AI
not are not bounded by the content
generated by human right create new
content personalized to the person and
after you know we published that article
a couple week later my friend and I we
got an email from C CNN reporter talking
about this serious case that an AI
convince a boy to commit suicide which
is really horrible and you know a really
sad thing it happened um in the early
2024 and it's you know um you know it
happened you know it start very
innocently the person the boy was
actually talking to this virtual
character that uh are supposed to be a
character from Game of Throne and then
the conversation get darker and darker
and you know the boy ask like you know U
what if I can go home right now which
mean he will kill himself to go leave in
the digital world with the AI the AI say
please do my sweet king and the boy
killed himself after that so my
colleague and I we serve as the expert
on this case we you know give an
interview and you can see the mother of
the the boy was also um um there as well
um but I think the big question that
people are asking especially right now
there's a lawsuit going on with this
case was can AI be blamed for this teen
suicide right and you know people have
different answers some people say yes
some people say no um it's a complicated
uh uh uh scenario it's a complicated
study right we have shown that AI when
personified as a person can have the
same impact as actually having a
conversation with or having a um re
learning from the real Elon Musk even
though people know that they're fake
right they still carry the impact um we
did this following followup study
looking at the impact of believing in AI
if you believe that AI has certain um uh
characteristics like the AI love you or
the AI is caring for you you tend to
actually um use more language that make
the AI have that exhibition have that
behavior and um I'm going to go very
quickly because my time is running out
but what we have shown is that when
people evaluate the AI is not what the
AI is but what they believe the AI is so
it's the mental model that have an
impact and when we look at the behavior
of the person in AI over time we see
this reinforcement learn learning where
people start to learn that oh if I talk
to AI this way the AI I behave this way
and then I can continue to kind of shape
the AI Behavior into what they want you
know you can start off having this
neutral conversation with AI but if you
start saying that you love certain
aspect of it it can create this feedback
loop and that feedback loop can be very
addictive and as you can see if you use
more negative language toward ai ai will
use more negative language toward you
and maybe make you hate more hat AI more
and vice versa right if you use more
positive language toward AI it also Echo
that and create this kind of feedback
back Loop so when we ask can AI blame
for this you know a teen suicide we need
to conduct a deep study um where we look
at real people using this kind of system
um this is an ongoing work but we have
we have seen that people are you know
younger and younger people are using Ai
and having relationship with AI rather
than with other people um and you know
people have using this for over months
and over you know some people use it for
years and um they use it you know for
many uh uh hours per day right but I
think the most interesting thing about
this study is that we found from the um
you know clustering of behavior pattern
of usage that some people that use AI
become more addictive but some that use
the same amount of AI um um don't become
addictive at all so there are many
social and psychological aspect
surrounding it that we start to uncover
and I think that will allow us to
predict who are vulnerable to this type
of AI manipulation or this type of
virtual companion right and that could
lead to targeted policy right so not
that everyone should receive the same
treatment maybe there need to be some
kind of targeted intervention if the AI
start to you know act this way or
convince someone to commit suicide right
it's really important and that's why
we're working closely with open AI on a
secret project which we Ann now next
month so you'll hear more on that but
we're looking at many phenomena
surrounding you know negative impact of
AI especially when AI are persuasive and
can you know use language that make us
you know fall for it like you know here
we look at what happen happened when AI
explain Us in the wrong way give false
explanation right human uh uh research
in in um explainable AI tend to be you
know that tend to be the Holy Grail if
the AI can Prov explanation it is
trustworthy but our work debunk that and
show that if the AI give false
explanation it can actually make people
worse than the AI not giving explanation
at all right so false explanation can
also be very dangerous especially if the
AI hallucinate that right we have shown
that this is actually worse than you
know the type of false flag that that
you might have seen when the AI just say
yes or no when you say yes or no with
false reason it tend to lead to more
negative outcome as you can see on this
graph the final project in this category
that I want to mention is something that
we also really uh start to you know be
interested about is how AI affect human
memories right memory is something that
is internal to us but AI could
potentially rewrite our memory or give
false memories to the person right you
know like movie Inception right where
you go into people dream and start to
mess around with what they believe or
what they have seen or what they what
happened to them in the past right we've
been working with Professor Elizabeth
lofas who is a leading psychologist in
false memory to study what happened when
AI is introduced you know in the context
of crime or in you know when they are
when you're talking to AI in general
actually um where the AI create or
depict your past memory but in a
different way or or differently right
like if you have certain experience in
the past the AI could generate image or
video that convince you that no no no
what you think happen did not happen or
no no no what you happen actually
happened in a different way right for
example you know like you may seen the
picture with the the ex- prime minister
right the original picture has no tank
in it there's no military tank but the
AI can actually put the tank in and make
it animated so look it more convincing
right and you're like oh actually I see
him with the tank the other day right so
that is the kind of false memory we
talking about um so it's like memory
editing you go back and change what
people imagine or or or or or remember
or another work that we look into like
you know you have like a unhappy wedding
right AI could create okay a happy
wedding and then make you remember that
experience differently right so we have
been investigating this phenomena of
what happened when we use this um to
create false memory in people and we
want to do this to you know so we can
prevent it not that we want to give more
false memory to people right we have
seen that um when AI generate image and
also video it can actually significantly
more um than you know false memory that
happen naturally that it can actually
increase the rate of false memory in
people and make they remember things
incorrectly we think that this is the
next you know generation of deep fake or
fake news right it's not going to mess
around with thing that you just see it
will mess around with thing that you
might have experience in the past right
and we're doing this um as I said we're
trying to come up with new um
preventative um measure and and and new
ways that we can prevent this from
happening but at the same time it can
also be used for positive thing like
people would have PTSD or people that
have you know traumatic memories AI can
also help reide that or or imagine that
in different way right so that's good
and bad um for for that type of research
so there are a lot of exciting things um
in this area and we need to focus on
both the positive side and the negative
side especially when AI interact with
people at the psychological level um and
dark pattern is you know something
really really dangerous last but not
least I want to end with something more
uplifting right inspiring we want to use
AI you know that we invent that we
investigate to inspire new possibility
New Hope right that's what I think what
we say um in Thailand we talk a lot
about soft power right and our cultural
heritage I was fortunate to actually
work with um a choreographer in Thailand
P grun who is a you know national uh
internationally uh uh renowned Thai
choreographer to think about how we can
use AI to understand traditional Thai uh
choreography or natas Tha or the way
that you know cone and and auto
performance was created and here what we
create is a system um that allow us to
come up with new choreography based on
how the AI learn from you know uh uh
traditional or cultural knowledge right
and I think this is really really
important you can see some weird
choreography but it's still based on on
um the knowledge in Thai uh traditional
dance right I think this is really
important because you know we want to
create nonwestern AI right the AI that
have knowledge that is not just Western
but new type of of knowledge system that
can be integrated into this virtual
character right and this actually had
led to a performance that was Premier in
Taiwan national uh theater um where we
actually have the dancer interact with
AI live on stage right both of them have
the same traditional knowledge of tha
choreography and they can interact with
one another one can go and say well I
want to change the choreography this way
or that way and the AI would help create
new choreography some that human may not
able to replicate or or dance with but I
think that uh limitation make us human
right it make us unique and we can
interact with AI and get more
inspiration in this way right this is
really exciting as I said we need to
create more diverse AI epistemology not
just Western knowledge but you know
Asian knowledge Thai knowledge need to
be embedded into AI so we can create you
know more you know diverse intelligence
right and we also make a version of this
that is accessible you can all go visit
it right now it's uh cyber subin is the
name of the project umm media. mit.edu
we make a website that teacher can
actually you know teach um tight
traditional dance with AI so that our
soft power can be taught in a fun way
you know I don't like to learn nasin
when I was a kid you know I I don't like
that subject at all but I think we can
teach you know our tradition in an
interactive way with technologies that
can be a way that we can push this
forward right and really make um Tha
culture or Thai soft power stand out
right so as you say it's like Ai and
Thai we had AI in it and using our own
cultural heritage as the as the
resources to create more interesting and
unique AI
system but as I said right there's no
Thailand without AI I want to end with
one more thing you know people say that
there's no I say that there's no uh uh
Thailand without AI but around the world
people say that there's no Thailand
without this guy this girl right mudang
very important mudang have capture the
world attention right everyone know
mudang anyone that doesn't know
mudang okay no one don't know mudang
right mudang is so famous very important
um I was actually at the um the standard
economic Forum um um earlier last year
and uh we were having a conversation
about the future of um you know the AI
road map for Thailand and there were
many many conversation about what
Thailand should do and I was joking that
well you know we have something that is
so special like mudang why don't we make
mudang AI right and at the time it was
like a very funny conversation it was a
joke um but I had more more conversation
with uh Dr napat Who is over there I
think okay he's in the back um who is
also you know on the panel with me right
we were together and um yeah uh here
yeah he were there he was moderating
that session and was like well you know
it's not just a joke right it's kind of
interesting what if we think about
mudang AI um what is but but what is
mudang AI right that's kind of a weird
question anyway um normally when we
think about you know the the research in
human AI interaction right today I talk
a lot about human plus AI but I think
the important part here is also we need
to introduce nature right it's not just
human and AI need to interact with one
another we as a human species also need
to care more with nature and pay more
attention to what happened in the
natural world right um otherwise we will
end up with something that is horrible
like climate change and you know
pollution and things like that and at
the same time right when you think about
AI self it can also represent animal
intelligence as well not just artificial
intelligence right so when we think
about this uh question of what is
moodang AI we can look at you know many
great projects like the work at MIT this
is a project where they use AI to
understand well you know wh actually
have language similar to human you can
actually translate that using you know
Advanced AI model or you know the work
by my colleagues at the media lab where
she used you know technology to connect
people and animal in the Su like this is
um a musical instrument that was
designed to help parot um connect with
people right so I think it's like
actually a Treeway um and I think it
could be really exciting to think about
human Ai and animal interaction and
today um I I think for the first time I
never say it to anyone else we are
announcing the moodang AI challenge can
I have a round of applause please yeah
for mudang yay thank you thank you um
this is you know uh I think a very
unique challenge um uh and I think it's
a collaboration between many
organization that you see you know with
you know Dr napat uh with the standard
with you know Bangkok with you know the
Su organization in Thailand to think
about how we can design new type of AI
that help us better with animal and the
and the natural world right so this is a
really exciting challenge it's a global
competition for AI human and animal
interaction and the goal is to promote
deeper connection with nature right and
we have three tracks you can submit an
AI to this challenge that help us decode
the animal like help us understand what
mudang is thinking help us promote
better connection with mudang that's
track number two and also help the
sueper that take care of mud do better
job right so these are the Tre track of
the moodang AI Challenge and you can
also work with moodang friends as well
like the the elephant or otter species
we open for that this is in the spirit
of moodang but you can use otter um um
animal as well right and we have worked
um you know with you know the the Sue
and and many partner to have the data
set of mudang be available um so that
people can actually use it and make some
interesting AI with that right and the
prize the many priz like you know you
could get some money but the most
important thing and this is very special
with the Sue they will arrange a special
unique session where the winner of this
mudang AI challenge will be able to come
and happy birthday mudang in person in
Thailand yeah thank you so they can be
anywhere and um this is international
challenge so we'll fly them to happy
birthday mudang and I don't know maybe
mudang will see the AI we'll see what
happen um but you know the submission is
May 1st uh 2025 and you can go to mang.
media. edu is a really exciting idea
right to really promote um human Ai and
animal interaction um again I think this
is a it's a fun idea but it's represent
a bigger vision of thinking about how AI
can promote deeper connection with
nature right and I think from that panel
discussion at the standard economic
Forum people asking what can Thailand do
for AI and I say well we need to use our
soft power to inspire Global AI we have
powerful moodang why don't we use this
to make Thailand the of conversation
about human animal and AI interaction
that would be very unique right so we
are launching this today um you are the
first people to see this I think they're
going to be news released uh this
afternoon on this project we are very
excited for this mudang AI challenge yay
yeah and um I want to thank my team um
Dr npat is over there and Pap Pap is
another amazing person who I collaborate
with on many projects you can see them
please say hi to them and you can ask
them mooding or whether they are mooding
themselves um yeah so that is Inspire
right we can use AI to inspire new
possibility um from culture to human
animal interaction and many more right
so these are the three type of research
that you know my uh work at MIT have
been focusing on invent new technologies
new platform new system new algorithm
investigate how human interact with AI
for positive and for negative as outcome
and finally inspire people to think more
about this important question of human
AI interaction right there's so much
more to be done so much more I feel like
I need more sleep now um but I cannot do
it alone right that's me I love wearing
dinosaur because it remind me of that
boy uh when I was younger and I love
dinosaur so much and it allowed me to
pursue science dinosaur was the reason
for me to to study at MIT and to do all
this uh uh fun thing um so you know they
cannot do it alone so that's why um
right now as I finish my PhD I'm helping
my advisor start a new research program
at the media lab um we call it aha
aha you know aha we want to create aha
moment but this aha actually stand for
advancing human AI interaction it's a
really exciting research program that
you know I have a privilege to serve as
a co-director along with professor pimas
of uh the media lab and we are doing
many exciting thing but the first thing
that um um we're going to announce
actually is a collaboration with open AI
on really important projects that I
think you know we you will see how it
connect to the work that that uh we're
doing I'm sharing today right but we
have also great network of collaborators
around the world that are working with
us to push this question forward how we
can advance human AI interaction because
AI is not just technical problem is you
know in involve all of us so the aha
moment um will launch oh uh the AHA uh
program will launch uh this April 2025
right so that's um what I'm focusing on
right now in conclusion there's no AI
there's no Thailand without AI but more
important we need to think about human
and AI working together right today um I
talk about invent investigate Inspire I
hope you be inspired to do your own
research and you own your own work on
human AI interaction as well right I
will end with this slide here we have a
great opportunity to work with this
advancing you know advanced technology
right we are making technology that are
more and more like us we are humanizing
the machine but at the same time as we
using this technology we also need to
pay attention to the UT side right when
people are being mechanized into human
right as technology become better and
better we are humanizing the machine why
are we not using the machine to humanize
ourself and don't you know and and and
prevent this kind of mechanized human
right this is a question I will pose to
all of you how we can use AI to make us
more human than ever and with that my
future my past and my future my past my
future and my current self yeah that's a
long thing to say my past my future and
my current self thank you everyone for
coming to this MIT Symposium thank you
so much thank you thank
you would you like to take one question
oh sure yeah one one question yeah
Thailand face a stem shortage do you
think using AI teachers combined with
fun engaging techniques could Inspire
interest in stem uh from for young uh
student yeah absolutely I think that's a
really important question and I think
you know um learning you know when I
when I get to MIT uh uh the director of
media upet that learning is something
that you do to yourself education is
something that someone else do to you
right I think we need to promote the
kind of learning where people feel more
motivated to learn and the AI is a great
tool for that right I mean if you want
to you know do something fun just go to
mudang AI Challenge and work on
something right and that could help
solve the stem uh challenge in Thailand
so thank you thank you Pat thank you so
much