Good morning. Good morning. Welcome.
Welcome to lecture 11 of 6120 61200. I
never know how to pronounce it. It's one
of them probably. Um we have finished
our number theory unit and we're now
starting a new unit on graphs. Graph
theory. Um this is a a new topic, a new
kind of mathematical abstraction that
we'll see oops that we'll see um really
interesting uses for across this class,
across algorithms, across other contexts
as well. Um before we dig into what
they're good at, let's talk about a bit
about what they are, how they're
defined. Uh so I've written an example
of a graph up here. Totally clear,
right? It's easy to read and comprehend.
Um but let me define it for you. So a
simple
graph
let's say a simple undirected graph
which are the only kind of graphs we'll
be talking about for the next couple
lectures
um is defined as a pair.
So G is the graph G is a pair V comma E
where V is a non
empty set
of what we call nodes
also known as vertices.
Um
and
E is a set
of two element subsets
of V. Not all of them but some of them
possibly none of them could be all of
them as well where um any amount that
you want. So a graph is just a set of um
a set V um where we call the objects
vertices or nodes. Um, sorry.
These are edges.
So, it's a set V of nodes and a set E of
pairs of nodes. And those pairs are
called edges. So, in its purest set
theoretic form, here is a graph. Here's
a set of vertices. Here's a set of some
of the two element subsets of V. Of
course, I don't really think about the
graph in this form.
Let me give you an alternative way to uh
express this graph up here.
One, two, three, four, five, six, 7. Uh
these are going to be my nodes. This is
A, this is B, C,
uh D, E, F, and G.
And anytime we have an edge, let's
connect them by drawing an arc between
them. So we have AB, AC, and BC. We have
these, these, these, this, this, and
this. This is a visual representation of
this graph, but it's conveying the same
information. This is a lot easier to
look at in my opinion, but they're both
conveying the same information. This is
the general idea of a graph. It's a set
of vertices which are the dots and edges
which are the segments connecting them.
Does that make sense?
Wonderful.
Um I want to mention that there there
are some subtle differences in the
definitions in other sources. Um
sometimes
uh sometimes uh when people are talking
about undirected graphs
um some people will allow what are
called parallel edges.
Oops.
which is when you have two different
edges connecting the same pair of
vertices.
Um or
uh self loops
which is when you have a single edge
connecting a vertex back to itself
and we are disallowing both of those.
So we will never be working with graphs
like this that have parallel edges or
that have self loops. Uh so that is what
what people usually mean by simple. Um
and it's why all of the undirected
graphs we work with are going to be
simple. Um likewise some sources
allow the vertex set to be empty. U I
stipulated up there that V should be a
non-MP set.
Um,
so we're just disagreeing on a single
graph that has zero vertices and then
necessarily zero edges because there's
nothing to connect. Um, the reason we
are not allowing that for our purposes
is that often it's going to be a counter
example to a lot of the theorems we want
to state. We would always have to say
for every non-mpy graph, for every graph
with a positive number of vertices,
something like that. And it just gets
cumbersome. Um, so we chose this
definition because it makes that more
convenient. Not really a big deal, not
really something we'll need to think
about much. It's just a part of the
definition to be vaguely aware of in the
back of your mind. Um,
we do allow
the set of edges to be empty.
For example, here is a graph
with five vertices and zero edges. Let's
call them vertices one, two, three,
four, and five. Five vertices, zero
edges. That's totally fine. That's a
valid graph. Uh so this has an empty set
for the set of edges, which is fine. All
right. Um so what are graphs good at? Um
graphs are great at representing um
two-way relationships between pairs of
objects. Uh let me give some some real
world examples like friendship. Um you
can imagine the graph of all the friends
in the world. Uh the the vertices here
let's see the friend
graph
the vertices are going to be the set of
people
each person is a vertex. The set of
edges is pairs of friends.
Now I'm making an assumption here that
friendship always goes both ways. If I'm
friends with you then you're friends
with me. No unrequited friendships here.
Um,
for example, Facebook friendships always
go both ways. You're either friends on
Facebook or you're not. Um, so the graph
of Facebook friends is a concrete
representation of this kind of thing
which is which can be interesting. Um,
whoops.
Uh, let's see. Another example is the
brain.
The brain is just a network of neurons.
The neurons are the vertices.
neurons and connections.
Some neurons connect to neighboring
neurons and it's those neurons and their
connections that somehow creates
cognition and memory and intelligence
and I wish we understood how but at
least it's a graph.
Um, also we have the internet.
Um most network connections on the
internet go both ways
network connections.
So the servers are the vertices and the
which servers can talk to which other
servers u are the edges. Uh and most
communications have to go both ways
because you have to like communicate
back and forth and make sure that each
of you trusts the other party before you
actually send any information over. So
you have to go both ways to to make that
connection first. Uh and then you can
send information in whatever direction
you want. Um a non-example
is hyperlinks on websites.
If site A has a link that takes you to
site B, there isn't necessarily a link
back. Um so this would not be an example
of an undirected graph. That would be a
directed relationship which we're going
to talk about later after break. Um but
that's not an example for today.
Similarly, Twitter followers is a
directed relationship. If I follow you,
you don't necessarily follow me. So that
would be a directed graph which will fit
into um into lectures after break, not
this one. Um all right.
And graphs uh I said earlier graphs are
a really useful abstraction. And I claim
that they're useful because uh they
strike a nice balance between simplicity
and complexity.
On one hand, graphs are simple to define
and describe. They're simple
conceptually. It's just a set of objects
and a set of pair-wise relationships.
um easy to define. So, as we just saw,
there are lots and lots of real
scenarios that can be modeled faithfully
as a graph. On the other hand, they're
complex in that there's a rich
mathematical theory of graphs.
There are lots of powerful tools and
definitions and theorems that we can
bring to bear anytime we're trying to
analyze a graph and therefore we can
apply all of that to all the real world
scenarios that we have been able to
model as a graph. So it's a really nice
balance between the two.
Um so let's dig into this rich
mathematical theory and see what what
tools and theorems we can develop.
So the next definition is vertex degree
um sorry the next definition is um
adjacency. Let's see.
Two vertices U and V are adjacent
adjacent
if and only if
um they're connected
by an edge.
i.e. UV is one of our edges.
So there vertices are adjacent if
they're connected by an edge. Um we'll
say that
uh let's see
an edge UV
has end points
U and V.
Just the the two end points of the edge.
And we'll say that
edge uv
is incident
to u and v.
So a vertex and an edge are incident if
that edge has that vertex as one of its
end points. Um these words sound a
little alike. Adjacent is used for two
vertices that have an edge between them.
Incident is used for an edge and a
vertex where the vertex is an endpoint
of the edge. Um but useful terminology.
Uh and that lets us define the next
thing
which is for a vertex V.
Uh the degree of V
is the number
of edges
uh incident
to V. So the degree of a vertex is the
number of edges it has. So what's the
degree of E? Just yell it out.
Three. Yeah. One, two, three. What's the
degree of C?
Four. Degree of f two. What's the degree
of this vertex two?
Zero. It doesn't have any edges.
Excellent. Degree is just the number of
incident vert uh incident edges.
Wonderful.
Uh you can understand some not
everything but some things about a graph
just from the degrees of its vertices.
Uh for example uh that graph way over
there on the left. The degrees of its
vertices are let's go through them all.
We've got 2 2 4 3 3 2 in that order. I
think I got that right. Sometimes this
is called the degree sequence.
That's less important than the degree
itself um than the concept of degree
itself. But we can we can play with this
concept a little bit. For example, does
there exist a graph
with degree sequence 2 2 1?
Sorry, that's supposed to be a question
mark. There we go. Does there exist a
graph with degree sequence 221? So,
three vertices, two have degree 2, one
has degree 1.
Think about that for a second and then
we'll try it together.
Okay, I see someone violently shaking
their head. I think they're cracking
their neck.
Uh, let's try it. Um, so 221 means we
need three vertices. One, two, three.
Um, first vertex has degree two. Well,
there's really only one way to do that.
It has to connect here and here. The
next vertex also has to have degree two.
Well, that means it also has to connect
there. Only way for it to get a second
edge. Then the third vertex is supposed
to have degree 1, which it doesn't. So
we're sad it didn't work. Um, you can
think of this, by the way, as a proof by
contradiction. Um, if there were a graph
that satisfied this, then it would have
to look like this. But this graph
doesn't work, so nothing works.
Sound good? Okay. But what if we asked a
more complicated uh version of the
question? Does there exist a graph with
degree sequence two two two
one?
This time there would need to be six
vertices and now there are lots of ways
that we could choose two edges for each
of those vertices. Um so there are lots
of cases that we would need to try out
in our proof by contradiction. Um so
maybe a different strategy would work
better. Does there exist a graph with
this degree sequence?
Yes.
always.
No, because the sum always has to be
even. Interesting. Why does the sum have
to be even?
All right. So, if an edge connects to
one vertex, then it also can connects to
another vertex. So, each edge is somehow
counted twice. Yeah, that's exactly the
right intuition for the following
theorem. In fact, that's the correct
proof for the following theorem. Um,
we've got the handshake
shake lema.
Let's see.
For graph G, which is vertices and
edges, we have the sum
of vertices in the set of vertices of
the degree of that vertex equals. So if
you take all the degrees and add them
all up, um your colleague here claimed
that what you're going to get is 2 times
the number of edges.
And we can see that for this example, if
we add this up, 4 8 14 16 18 and there
are nine edges, that checks out.
Um
and the reason this is true is also
exactly what your colleague said earlier
over here. We're adding the degree of
every vertex
um which means we're basically counting
every end point of all the edges and
every edge has two end points. So every
edge was counted twice in this count on
the left. So that's the handshake lema.
It's called handshake lema because if
you imagine a room full of people and
some pairs of them shake hands, then if
each person counts the number of
handshakes they had and you add that all
up, that equals two times the number of
handshakes because each handshake had
two hands involved. Um it's exactly the
same explanation and proof. It's just
with hands
uh instead of um pairs instead of half
edges.
Um all right. So does this help us with
that?
Can someone tell me why there doesn't
exist a graph with this degree sequence?
Yes.
Yeah, because the sum is odd. Um, this
would have to have what? 11 divided by
two edges,
which isn't great. Uh, I don't know how
to draw a half edge in these graphs. So
there is no such graph. Awesome. Here's
one more application of the handshake
lema. Uh let's see.
What is the maximum
number
of edges
in an nvertex
graph?
What is the maximum number of edges in
an nvertex graph?
Um well
each vertex
has degree at most n minus one because
at most it connects to all the other
vertices. There are no other vertices to
connect to. You can't connect to
yourself. You can't repeat any
connections. Uh once again that's what
we meant by simple graph and all our
graphs are simple. Um so every vertex
has degree at most n minus one.
So the sum of the degrees
uh is at most n * n minus one.
But the sum of the degrees is equal to 2
* the number of edges.
So the number of edges is at most n * n
minus one / 2.
Didn't have to do any fancy induction.
Didn't have to compute some sum. I
wonder if this equals a sum that we've
seen before.
Um,
but so we have an upper bound. The
number of edges is at most that. And
turns out this is achievable
achieved by the complete graph
kn which is the graph with n vertices
and all possible edges.
So this vertex connects to everyone.
This vertex connects to everyone. This
connects to everyone. Connects to
everyone. I think I got them all. So
this is a drawing of K6.
There are six vertices and everyone
connects to everyone. This graph indeed
has every vertex with degree N minus
one. So it has exactly this many edges.
Um the K for KN this is standard. You'll
see KN uh everywhere. I think it comes
from German. Uh it kind of sounds like
complete graph, right? Um, but we'll be
using this notation a lot.
All right,
let me ask another question. Um,
so most of us here are MIT students. I
know we have some crossregistered
students. Welcome. You're um I'm glad
you're here. Um, for the MIT students in
the room, do you have any friends at
Harvard?
Yeah. Awesome. Um, okay. So, I got at
least one hand. I got more than one
hand. But let me ask, how many Harvard
friends do you think the typical MIT
student has? Don't answer that. It's
rhetorical. Uh, what about the reverse
question? How many MIT friends does the
typical Harvard student have?
Which one's bigger?
Let's see. So on one hand we've got the
average number of
Harvard friends
for the typical MIT student
or the average number of MIT friends for
the typical Harvard student.
Which one's bigger? And how could we
know? How do we how can we decide this?
Maybe I could do a big survey. I could
sample a bunch of MIT students, sample a
bunch of Harvard students, um take the
average of whatever is reported and and
take that as ground truth. Um that is
how a lot of empirical statistics ends
up working. Um
can anyone suggest a better way? Yes.
All right. Uh, so let me let me rephrase
that. Um, so we know that every
friendship goes both ways. There's one
MIAT student and one Harvard student.
Again, we're assuming friendship is uh
is two-way, no unrequited friendships.
Um, can't the two schools just get
along?
Um, but because there are the same
number of friendships on both sides, um,
when we're taking the average, we're
dividing by the number of Harvard
students and dividing by the number of
MIT students. But Harvard has more
undergrads than MIT, so we've divided by
a bigger number. So, the MIT average
should be bigger. Woo, that was a lot.
Um, thank you for saying all that. Let's
unpack it a little more slowly. Um, but
you are absolutely correct in every step
of your reasoning. Um, so what I'm going
to do is let's draw a graph
where the vertices are going to equal um
the set of MIT undergrads and the set of
Harvard undergrads.
Um, and I want to emphasize that these
are two disjoint sets. No student is
enrolled in both schools. Um, we're not
counting cross registration. That's why
I mentioned that earlier. uh and
sometimes to emphasize that these two
sets are disjoint sometimes you put a
little dot inside the union sign. So our
set of vertices is the disjoint union of
MIT students and Harvard students. And
um our edge set is going to be the set
of let's see M comma H where M is an MIT
student, H is a Harvard student and M
and H are friends.
And we can draw an example of what this
might look like. So here's all of my
Harvard vertices on the left. Here's all
of my MIT students on the right. Um here
we have like I don't know Bill and Helen
and Natalie
and Neil and TS on the right. Maybe we
have uh Buzz and Kenji
and Lisa.
And these lists go on. Um, this is just
an example. I don't know if they're
actually students with these names. Um,
and some pairs of them are friends.
Maybe these are friends. And these and
these are friends. And Buzz is just
friends with most people. And TS only
likes Lisa among this graph. Some pairs
of them are friends. Here's our graph.
Again, there are more vertices, more
edges, but here's an example of our
graph. And this graph has a special
property called bipartite. This is a
bipartite graph.
Um let's see definition
um G is
bipartite
um when it's possible
to partition V as the disjoints disjoint
union of two sets. I'm going to call
them left and right. That's common
notation for for bipartite graphs. um
such that every edge
has one end point
in L and one end point in R.
So you have some vertices on the left,
some vertices on the right, and every
edge crosses between them. One end point
on the left, one end point on the right.
These graphs are called bipartite, and
the one we just drew certainly has that
property.
Sound good with me so far? Awesome.
And now um we have a bipartite version
of the handshake lema.
Let's see.
handshake lema
bipartite
which says that if you add up all the
degrees just on the left
the vertices in the left side degree of
v.
Well, every edge has one endpoint on the
left and one end point on the right. So
this is just equal to the number of
edges.
And likewise you can do the same thing
on the right.
So all the degrees on the left add to
the number of edges. All the degrees on
the right add to the number of edges.
But remember we are interested in the
averages. The average degree on the left
versus the average degree on the right.
All right.
So, we've got, let's say, average degree
on the MIT side
divided by the
average degree on the Harvard side.
Well, this is equal to the
total degree on the MIT side. So, just
adding up all the degrees um of the MIT
students
divided by
the number of MIT students.
And this denominator
is the total
degree on the Harvard side divided by uh
the number of Harvard students.
Right? That's what we mean by average.
Add them up, divide by the number. Add
them up, divide by the number. Okay? But
we just said that the total degree on
the Mside and the total degree on the H
side, both of those are equal to just
the number of edges.
So this is the number of edges divided
by the size of M.
divided by the number of edges divided
by the size of h.
The e cancel. This just becomes the size
of h divided by the size of m.
All right, we've now caught up to your
comment. Thank you so much. Um, and now
we can just ask how many students there
are in each school. Um, this is about,
let's see, I wrote something down. About
7,200 divided by 4600.
Those are close anyway. They might be a
bit out of date. Um, but this is about
1.6.
So, the average MIT student has about
1.6 times more Harvard students, Harvard
friends, uh, than the number of MIT
friends the average Harvard student has.
And that's not um any judgment about
behavior on the two sides of the
schools. It's just a fact about averages
uh after knowing a little bit of graph
theory.
Um but our number is bigger so we're
better.
Um, but
so already
we've just defined a couple things and
we've already been able to prove some
non-obvious theorems and facts. Um,
again, they still look like toy
examples, but there are real scientific
studies that have studied questions like
that and not known the graph theory and
then came up with conclusions that were
very obviously wrong to anyone who did
know the graph theory. Um for example uh
there's a very famous study um out of
Chicago from 1994
uh called the social organization of
sexuality sexual practices in the US. Uh
so it was a big sweeping um study about
sexual practices and behavior and health
across the country. Um they had
thousands of participants. They asked
lots and lots of questions and came up
with lots of statistics and measurements
and trends and published all their
results in a big 700page writeup, a very
famous study. Um, and out of all the
questions they asked, I'm going to
single out one of one of them uh for the
single purpose that their results are
obviously wrong because of exactly this
argument. So, one question they asked um
specifically to their male and female
participants um they asked the men um
how many female partners they've had.
They asked the women how many male
partners they've had. Um don't worry,
they had lots of other questions about
other kinds of relationships. Uh they
had lots of other questions for their
non-binary participants as well. Like I
said, I'm just singling out this one of
many questions. Um so, what's the
average number of female partners a man
has had? what's the average number of
male partners a woman has had. Um, and
according to their reports and surveys,
um, the men reported about 1.74 times as
many partners as the women. Um,
let's see. So the average
degree of the men
um was equal to about 1.74
times the average degree of the women.
Um, a different study, this time from
ABC News in 2004,
um, got a similar result, but instead of
1.74, so sorry, this was from Chicago,
um, ABC News
approximated this number to be about
3.3.
Um, yet another study from the National
Center of Health, National
Center of Health
this time from 2007 got this number to
be about 1.75
when of course we know the exact answer.
This ratio should be the number of women
divided by the number of men. Because of
the specific question they were asking
about this subset of relationships among
this subset of the population. They put
themselves in a bipartite scenario where
this theorem applies and the correct
answer is just the number of women
divided by the number of men.
The uh let's see the number of women
divided by the number of men which um
according to the 2010 census was about
157 million over 152 million
which is about 1.03. 03.
The correct answer is 1.03.
And it's not a question of behavior.
It's a question of just averages.
Uh there is nothing to learn from this
ratio except this is how many men and
women are in the country. Not a very
interesting example for a behavioral
study if you ask me. Um I'm not going to
speculate on why these numbers don't
match reality. Um,
I don't know. Think about it yourselves
if you want.
Uh, are there questions about this
example
or anything else we've talked about so
far?
All right, let's move on to another
topic in graph theory, another common
application.
[Applause]
So instead of measuring affinities or
friendships among pairs of objects,
let's measure conflicts between them.
So here's an example graph.
Let's say
let's define the vertex set of our graph
to be the set of all
MIT classes
with
a final exam
and E is going to be pairs of classes.
is
C1 C2
that have someone
enrolled
in both.
So you're the registar. Your goal is to
assign a time for the final exam for
every class.
And if some student is taking two
different classes and those classes are
scheduled for the same time slot or
overlapping time slots, then that
student can't be in the same place at uh
can't be in two different places at the
same time. So you have a conflict. So
this graph here is measuring all of the
conflicts among uh final exam times.
There's an edge precisely when the two
classes can't be scheduled for
overlapping times.
Does that make sense so far? Cool. So,
edges
are conflicts
in exam scheduling.
And let me draw an example.
Let's see.
So in this example, MIT only has five
courses.
Um six um 3700, 6,000,
6200,
6 3,000,
and 64,100.
So this is some fake approximation of
what this graph might look like. So,
this says that there's someone taking
our class and 62000.
Um, there's some people there's at least
one student taking both of these
classes. There's no one taking uh 6 3700
and 63000.
Um, so for example, these two are
allowed to be scheduled at the same
time.
Um, so this is listing all of our
conflicts.
And this brings us to the graph coloring
problem.
[Applause]
Uh, so we say that a
proper K coloring
a proper K coloring of a graph G
uh is defined to be
I'll write it down mathematically first
and then explain it in words. a function
f from the set of vertices to a set c of
colors
um
where there are at most k colors
and for all edges
uv
fu does not equal
fv.
So in other words, we have some set of
colors available and we want to assign a
color to every vertex.
Um, and we want to assign a color to
every vertex so that no two adjacent
vertices are ever assigned the same
color.
In this example, you can think of colors
as time slots for final exams.
If two vertices are given the same
color, that means that they'll be
administered at the same time. And this
condition that edges have to have two
different colors on their endpoints
means that anytime there's a scheduling
conflict, they will always be given
different colors, which means they'll be
given different time slots.
So this is what we mean by a proper K
coloring. It's an assignment of um of a
color to every vertex from a possible
choice of K different colors where the
two end points of every edge are
assigned different colors.
Uh, and as an example,
so let's let's try to color this graph.
Um, okay. I'm going to color
let's say I'm going to color this red
and this green and this blue and this
yellow and this purple. Is that a proper
coloring?
Yeah. Yeah. Every edge has two different
colors on its end points because all the
colors are distinct. This is a proper
five coloring.
Can be five colored.
All right. But that means we need five
different time slots for the final exams
and we'd like to be a little more
efficient. Uh can we color this with
just four colors?
Yes, I claim we can. Let's make that red
instead of purple.
Now, this class and this class are both
red,
but because there's no edge between
them, uh, that's fine. All of the edges
have two different colors on their end
points, and that's all we need. All
right, so this can be fourcolored.
Can we do better?
Can we get away with just three colors?
All right. Interesting. I'm seeing one
headshake and and one head nod. Um, so
yes, please.
How about making the yellow?
Make yellow red.
Okay, we'll make this blue or green.
Yeah. All right. So, we've got red,
green, blue, red, blue. So, we've got
two reds, but there's no edge between
them, so we're fine. And we've got two
blues, but there's no edge between them,
so we're fine. This is absolutely a
valid threec coloring.
can be three-colored.
Can this be 17 colored?
Is there a proper 17 coloring for this
graph? This is a bit of a weird edge
case, but yes. Um, this set C um says
that there have to be at most 17 colors
available.
We don't have to use all of those
colors.
Um so if we were if we had a 17 color
palette and we found this proper
coloring that would be a be considered a
valid 17 coloring. So this is a valid uh
this is a proper 17 coloring of the
graph but more directly it's a proper
three coloring because usually we're
trying to minimize the number of colors.
All right. And we can make that notion
concrete
definition. Uh the chromatic
number
of a graph G. The chromatic number is
denoted
kai of G. That's a lowercase Greek. Kai
is the smallest
number of colors
needed
for a proper
coloring of G.
All right.
So, the chromatic number asks, what's
the fewest colors you can get away with?
Um, in our scheduling problem, what's
the fewest number of time slots that we
need to cover all of the final exams?
Um, for this graph, what is its
chromatic number? Have we shown that
it's three?
First of all, is it five?
Is the chromatic number of this graph
five? Why not?
because we can we can get away with
fewer colors. That's right. It's not
five because we can do fewer. Uh it's
not four because we can do fewer. Is it
three?
I don't know yet. Can we get away with
fewer colors?
Well, let's see.
Um can it be two-colored? Is there a
proper coloring with just two colors for
this graph?
And in this case, there isn't because
this triangle right here shows us that
all three of these vertices need
different colors.
Uh you can think of this as a proof by
contradiction as well. Assume it's
possible to color with just two colors.
Well then, well, these three vertices
would have a conflict among them
somehow, which is a contradiction.
Um so
cannot
be two-colored
and these two statements together can be
colored with three colors cannot be
colored with two colors. This is what we
need to confirm that the chromatic
number is three. Three is the smallest
because three works and fewer doesn't
work.
uh and I want to emphasize that in
general
to show that the chromatic number of G
is some value K
um usually we need both an upper bound
and a lower bound.
We need an upper bound
which is that K of G is less equal K.
And how do we prove that?
usually by giving a K coloring. If you
know it's possible to color in K colors,
then the chromatic number has to be K or
smaller.
Give a K coloring.
But you also need a lower bound
that K of G has to be greater than K
minus one.
And how do you prove that?
You prove you have to prove that it
can't
be kus one colored
usually by contradiction.
So I just wanted to emphasize that the
definition of chromatic number as the
smallest thing that works there are two
parts to that. It works and nothing
smaller works. Make sense?
Cool.
All right.
So,
let me Yes.
So, graph coloring. We've seen one
application which is the registar
scheduling final exams. They actually do
something exactly like this. By the way,
this is why uh final exam schedules
don't come out till a couple weeks into
the semester because they need to see
who's enrolled in which pairs of classes
so we can try to schedule those um apart
from each other. They're trying to find
a coloring with few colors. Um in
practice, if they were looking for an
actual proper coloring with no conflicts
whatsoever,
probably wouldn't fit into exam week. So
instead they're looking to minimize the
number of conflicts which is a slightly
different problem but still an
interesting one.
But there are lots of scenarios where
you're trying to avoid conflicts
um just like the registar is trying to
avoid conflicts.
So other
coloring applications,
um, a really common one and one that's
appropriate for this computer science
class is register allocation.
When designing compilers,
um, you have multiple values that you're
trying to compute, different operations
you need to do with them. Yes,
matters,
that's a great question. Thank you for
asking. Um, do the elements of C matter
or just the size of C? C is the set of
colors available. Um, so if you change
the set C, then you're you're giving a
different coloring because your colors
mean different things. Um, but you're
not going to change how many colors are
needed. You're not going to change the
chromatic number if you change the set
of colors available. Um,
and you you said we could have put like
green green here instead of here.
Yeah. Like we could have made the reds
could in could instead be green and this
green could be red or this green could
be yellow.
Now we've got some greens, some blues,
and a yellow. Still three colors,
different coloring because we're
assigning different colors to them, but
um still the same number of colors. And
often for the applications we're about
to talk about, the number of colors is
all that matters because the colors just
mean these are the different classes
that you need to put them in. and then
you do something with each class.
Um so this application register
allocation when you're computing
multiple values um the your processor
has a small number like 16 or 32
registers which are really really fast
memory that it can um that it can do
operations on and in fact it has to
bring data into a register before it can
compute on them usually. Um, and
some values you're computing and you
need lots of different pieces to go into
that computation. Some values, well,
you're done with it. You don't need to
remember it anymore. So, let's evict
that and put something else in that
register. And ideally, you can figure
out a way to schedule all of your values
in the different registers so that
everything fits in the registers and
everything's fast instead of having to
spill them out into RAM. um you don't
need to understand compilers or exactly
what I'm saying here. The point is um
your variables, the values you're
computing have different lifetimes.
Times when they need to still exist and
other times when you're allowed to
forget them. Um and compiler writers
often draw exactly the conflict graph
between these lifetimes. This value has
to exist at the same time that this
value also has to exist. So they can't
be in the same register
um because then one would overwrite the
other. And if you can write down your
conflict graph and find a coloring with
a small number of colors um ideally
smaller than the number of registers
available then everything works in
registers and you're really fast.
Um another one is
radio tower frequencies.
Um, if each if each tower in a radio
network needs to broadcast with some
frequencies, well, if two towers use the
same frequency that can reach the same
places, then they're going to conflict.
You're going to get static in the noise.
You're getting noise from two different
places at once. Um, so any conflicting
towers need to use different
frequencies. And this is again a graph
coloring problem. Um, draw your your
conflict graph, color it with a small
number of colors. each color is a
different frequency. And since different
towers that are assigned the same color
don't have an edge in the conflict
graph, it means they don't conflict. And
so they're allowed to use the same
frequency just fine.
Um,
in general, where did I put this list?
Way over here. No, come back.
Um, let's see. Map coloring.
Uh a while ago, Eric told us about the
four color theorem that every planer map
uh every map that you draw uh on a sheet
of paper, you can color all the regions
in different colors so that two
neighboring regions never have the same
color. Uh and four colors is always
enough.
Excuse me. Um this is just saying that
certain kinds of graphs can always be
fourcolored. Not every graph but certain
kinds of graphs um the so-called planer
graphs can always be fourcolored.
Um
this is this is the language that that
proof is written in. It's it's a theorem
about graph theory. It uses graph
theory. Um
but it's an example we've already seen
which is nice in general. Anytime you're
trying to avoid
pairwise
conflicts,
graph coloring is a great tool to reach
for
because it's such a great tool to reach
for in many contexts. Wouldn't it be
great if there was a really fast, simple
algorithm that says, "Here's a graph.
Here's a target number of colors. Please
give me a coloring, a proper coloring
that uses this number of colors.
Um so an algorithm
to k color
any input graph
um or decide
it's not possible
if I'm the registar and I know I have
what is it five days of exams two
sessions each so I have 10 different
exam sessions I really want a 10
coloring of my graph
Um
and so I want to ask please give me a 10
coloring of this conflict graph and then
that's my schedule. Is there an
algorithm to do that? Um likewise
uh instead of asking give me 10 colors
um you can ask algorithm to compute
k of g. I don't know in advance how many
colors I'm expecting. Just give me the
best coloring. Give me a coloring that
uses the fewest number of colors. Is
there an algorithm to do that? That
would be really great in lots of
applications. Um, unfortunately, I'm
talking in hypotheticals here because
these algorithms very very likely don't
exist. Uh, these problems
are what we call NP
well this problem's nplete. This one's
possibly even harder. Um,
at least this problem is npmplete. Like
I said, this one might be even harder
than NP. Um, what does this mean? I
don't care so much. Uh, I don't really
want to dig into what NPMPlete means
right now or NP hard or any of those
things. What I will say is that there
are thousands upon thousands of
computational problems like graph
coloring
um like the traveling salesman problem
if you've heard of that one it's pretty
famous um like sudoku on n squ by n
squared boards instead of just 9 by9 um
there are thousands upon thousands of
these problems that computer scientists
have decided are all equally difficult
So if we were able to find an efficient
algorithm to solve any one of them like
to solve the k coloring problem then
that would immediately give us an
algorithm to solve all the other ones
efficiently as well. Uh and all the
problems that are easier than those. Um
a notable problem that we've already
talked about is factoring
large numbers.
This is known to be in NP. It's not
known whether it's NP complete. It's in
fact thought to be even easier than than
most of these. So it's thought that
factoring numbers is somehow easier than
K coloring your graph. Also, by the way,
even if we're just asking for three
colors, does this graph have a coloring
with just three colors? That's already
nplete. That's already too hard. and we
don't believe there's going to be an
efficient algorithm for it. Um, so if
you solve this easier problem, factoring
large numbers, if you find an efficient
algorithm for that, well, you'll be able
to break all the public RSA keys, uh,
read everyone's encrypted messages,
steal all the electronic money, um,
including the real currency from
electronic banks, um, run from all of
the world governments that are trying to
hire and/or silence you.
Um,
but if you solve the even harder problem
of threecoloring a graph, you get all
that plus a million-doll prize for
solving a famous millennium problem. So,
you've got choices.
Point is
graph coloring is a hard computational
problem and we strongly believe most
computer scientists strongly believe
that there is no efficient algorithm um
for graph coloring and so we're not it's
not realistic at least for very large
graphs. It's not realistic to ask for um
a coloring with a specific number of
colors or the the best possible
coloring,
which means that our applications are a
little bit sad because sometimes we
really want optimal colorings.
Thankfully, in practice, um optimal
colorings aren't really necessary.
Sometimes we can get away with good
enough.
Um, and so for all of these NP complete
or NP hard problems, the best you can
hope for is an algorithm that's good
enough. Um, usually the answer it gives
is a little worse, but it runs faster.
Uh, and let's let's see an algorithm for
that to give us some colorings of
graphs, even if they're not always
optimal colorings.
All right.
So we have a greedy
coloring
algorithm.
Um and here is the idea of the
algorithm. So first of all, um we're
going to
order the vertices
v1, v2
vn. So we're going to pick some ordering
of the vertices.
Uh we're going to order the colors.
Uh I'm going to use my favorite color
palette. One, two, three, and so on.
Those are my colors.
Um and then
for each vi in order
so we'll look at v1 then v2 then v3 and
so on and we'll assign each of them a
color one at a time.
Um,
assign vi the smallest
color
that doesn't introduce conflicts.
So when we get to vertex I, we're going
to ask, does color one work? Does color
two work? Does color three work? And
this the first time we get to a color
that is valid that it doesn't have a
neighbor of that same color, we're going
to assign it that color and then move on
to the next vertex.
It's greedy because you're um yeah, it's
called greedy because you're always
picking the smallest color you can at
any one time. It doesn't necessarily
mean that you're going to get an optimal
coloring. In fact, usually you won't. At
least, you know, for big graphs where
it's hard to find optimal colorings. Um,
let's run through this algorithm. Let's
see it happening just to get a more
concrete feel for what we mean. Um,
here we go. So, here's my graph. Nope.
Pause. Thank you. Six vertices. One,
two, three, four, five, seven edges.
Uh, and this is the vertex order we're
going to use. We could choose any vertex
order we want. Um, but we're going to
look at the vertices in this order and
always choose the smallest color that's
valid. So the first one, first color is
fine because there are no possible
conflicts. No one else has colors yet.
Uh second vertex, the first color is no
good because it already has a color.
Sorry, it already has a neighbor that's
been assigned that color. So instead of
the color triangle, we have to go up to
color square.
All right. Now, let's go to vertex
three. Our first color is valid this
time, so it gets color one.
Still with me? All right. Vertex four
can't use color one, but can use color
two.
Vertex five, let's take a look. Uh,
vertex 5 can't use the first color,
can't use the second color, but can use
the third color. So, it gets assigned
the third color. And finally, vertex 6
gets assigned the first color. And we
have our valid coloring, our proper
coloring. Does that algorithm make
sense? Awesome.
Um, one thing I want to mention is that
different vertex orderings
will often lead to
different colorings
and often lead to
colorings with a different
number
of colors.
So here with this ordering, we got a
coloring with three colors. We got a
proper three coloring. But if instead we
use this coloring, sorry, this ordering
where all I've done is change the order
of vertices 1, five, and six. This is a
different vertex order on the same
graph. So let's run the algorithm again
in this ordering and let's see what
coloring it gives us. So first color is
fine here. First color is fine here.
This one needs the second color because
it already has a neighbor with the first
color. Stop me if I'm going too quickly.
Um, the next one has neighbors with
colors one and two, so it needs the
third color.
Um, the fifth vertex has a neighbor with
color one, so it needs the second color.
Uh and then finally, vertex six has a
neighbor with color one and a neighbor
with color two and a neighbor with color
three. So it in fact needs a fourth
color.
So with this different vertex ordering
on the same graph, it gave us a four
coloring instead of a three-coloring.
All right. So some orderings are better
than others.
Yeah.
All right. Um, does this algorithm
actually work? Does it always give a
proper coloring?
So, yes, in this case it does. Um, and
an easy way to see that is that um, the
way the algorithm is designed, it never
introduces conflicts.
um always after we've assigned the next
vertex, we never have an edge that has
two end points of the same color because
that's kind of the point of the
algorithm. So we never introduce a
conflict on any edge. So when we get to
the end, we haven't introduced any
conflicts, so there aren't any
conflicts. That's kind of a a state
machine style proof of of that
algorithm. Yes.
Good question. If you try all the
orderings and then take the best one,
the best coloring you get, will that be
optimal? Um, so there there are sort of
two questions in there. Um, can you get
all colorings from this algorithm?
And the answer is no. You can't get all
colorings from this algorithm. For
example, colorings that never use color
one, you can't get from this algorithm
because you're always going to use color
one on the first vertex.
Um, but the other question, can you
always get some coloring that uses the
minimal number of colors? Even if you
can't get all different colorings, can
you at least get all different numbers
of colors? And that answer is yes. Um,
it takes a little bit of thought to
prove, but the answer is yes. So if you
do try all n factorial vertex orderings
uh and take the minimum minimal coloring
um you will in fact get the chromatic
number but n factorial is a runtime that
is not considered efficient for things
like np and and np hardness. Um so that
is absolutely an algorithm to compute
chromatic number uh just not an
efficient one.
Uh yeah great question. Um
let me let me prove one thing about this
greedy algorithm. Um as we said it's not
always going to give the the smallest
coloring depending on what order you
pick.
But we can prove something about the
quality of colorings we get.
And here is that theorem.
Okay. So
for all graphs G
for all vertex orderings,
excuse me. Um if
the max degree of our graph is less
equal d um by max degree here I mean
look at the degrees of all the vertices
and take the largest one. So the maximum
of the degrees of the vertices.
Um so if the max degree is at most d
said differently if all vertices in the
graph have degree at most d
then the greedy algorithm
returns a coloring a proper coloring
with at most D + one colors.
So if all the vertices of the graph have
degree at most D, then the greedy
algorithm will use at most D + one
colors.
Does the statement make sense?
So in this example, all the degrees are
three or less. So we're guaranteed to
produce a coloring that uses at most
four colors.
Uh, and I want to emphasize this depends
on the degrees of the vertices, not the
number of vertices. If if this graph had
thousands and thousands of vertices, but
all the degrees were three or less, we
would still get a coloring with at most
four colors.
All right, it's not necessarily optimal.
In this graph, it wasn't optimal. Um, we
found a three coloring, whereas this
only promises a four coloring.
Um, but at least it's some measure of
quality of the results we get out of
this greedy algorithm.
Does the claim make sense? Wonderful.
Let's prove it.
All right, we're going to prove this
by induction.
But induction on what?
Um, we might think, okay, well, there's
there's a D in the theorem statement.
So, what if we induct on D?
Well, that means at some point, um, we
know something about all graphs whose
degrees are at most eight, and we need
to prove something about all graphs
whose degrees are at most nine.
I don't really see how to get from one
to the next. That doesn't seem easy to
me, right?
Grasp with the degree nine. look with
max degree 9 look very different from
graphs with with max degree 8. If you
have a graph with max degree 9, there
might be many many many vertices with
degree 9. Um but to get anything useful
out of our inductive hypothesis, we
would need all degree all degrees to be
eight or less. Like there there's a
disconnect there. I don't know how to
make that proof work.
Um so let's see. Induction on what?
We just said induction on D maybe not
such a good idea.
Often when when proving a statement
about graphs by induction.
Um there are two common strategies to
try. You can try inducting on the number
of vertices or inducting on the number
of edges. I'll explain what that means
in just a second. Um but these are going
to be your best friends. If you're
trying to prove a thing about graphs by
induction, first try proving it by
induction on the number of vertices.
Then try proving it by induction on the
number of edges. If both of those don't
work, I don't know, cry.
That that's what I that's what I would
do. Um, but let's try this strategy.
Let's induct on the number of vertices
in our graph. And here's what that
means.
So we're going to let P of N
be the statement that
all graphs
with n vertices.
So all graphs with exactly n vertices
and
max degree at most d
um
result in at most d +1 colors
from the greedy algorithm.
So this is what we mean by we're
inducting on the number of vertices
because n the variable we're going to be
inducting on is measuring the number of
vertices of our graph.
So um if we think about induction as
proving things one step at a time. We're
going to first prove something about all
graphs with one vertex, then all graphs
with two vertices, then all graphs with
three vertices, then all graphs with
four vertices. This is fun. It's five,
six, seven. We're going to build up one
size at a time. Um, and that's how our
that's how our induction is going to go.
Um, all graphs with n vertices is the
key phrase here that makes this
inducting on the number of vertices. If
you wanted to induct on the number of
edges, you would say all graphs with n
edges or something like that.
All right, does this setup make sense?
So, we've defined PN here.
Our goal
we want
to prove
for all n greater equal one p of n is
true.
Yeah.
So for any number of vertices,
all graphs with that many vertices do
the thing.
So together all of these PNS starting at
P1 and going upward include all finite
graphs.
Does that make sense?
I failed to mention earlier, but most of
the graphs we're talking about in this
class are going to be finite. So if I
don't specify, go ahead and assume it's
finite.
Um, so this will cover all of the finite
graphs. So it'll cover all the graphs we
care about and we'll end up proving our
theorem. All right. So let's actually
prove our theorem. Um, base case
P of one.
Well, if there's only one vertex, we
know what the greedy coloring is going
to do.
Um, well, let's see. Max
degree is zero because there are no
edges if there's only one vertex.
Greedy coloring
uses one color.
One is 0 + 1 which is what was promised.
So P of 1 is fine. Let's do the
inductive step.
P of N. So here assume
P of N
want to show P of N plus one. And I
really want to emphasize one point right
here. Um, very often in this class,
students come away from uh the next
couple lectures with the belief that
induction on graphs is different. It
follows different rules. It's backwards.
We're going from n plus1 to n or
something like that. Um, and I I really
want to emphasize induction on graphs is
using regular induction in the way we're
used to that. We're not changing the
rules here. Um, what changes
is that what it means to prove P of N
implies P of N plus one is a little
different from what we're used to. We're
still proving that P of N implies P of N
plus one because that's what induction
tells us to do. But if we use our proof
outlining techniques from the first
couple lectures and really unpack what
it means to prove that this implies that
what it tells you to do is often a
little bit different from what your
intuition might tell you you're supposed
to do. So um it's doubly important when
inducting on graphs to lean heavily on
our proof outlining skills. to make sure
that we're setting up our proof
correctly to prove PN implies PN plus
one and not something that we just think
means PN implies PN plus1. Uh so let's
do that. Now we're assuming P of N. In
other words, we're assuming
all
uh let's see, nvertex
graphs
with
min degree at most D produce at most D+1
colors.
Right? That's that's P of N. We're
assuming P of N. And we want to show
we want to show that all n + one vertex
graphs
with min degree at most d produce at
most d plus1 colors.
All I've done is write out what pn and
pn plus1 mean in context. With me so
far?
All right. And here's where the the
confusing bit happens or at least the
non-intuitive bit. Um, our task is we
want to prove that all n plus1 vertex
graphs do some stuff. So the theorem
we're trying to prove is a for all. All
n plus1 vertex graphs do something.
But we know how to prove a forall. We
start with a generic thing in that set
and we prove the conclusion for that
thing.
So this for all immediately tells us
that the next line of our proof should
probably look something like this.
Suppose G
is an arbitrary
N +1
vertex to graph.
Yes.
writing out the meanings of PN. Did you
mean to say max degree?
Absolutely. I meant to say max degree
instead of min degree. That is a typo.
Thank you so much. I guess it's a rhto
because I'm not typing
for both. Yes. Thank you.
Thank you for catching that. All right.
Is everyone okay with the fact that this
for all all n plus1 vertex graphs tells
us that this next line should start with
suppose g is an n plus1 vertex graph
because this is the part that many
students get wrong. Um they will often
say suppose g is an arbitrary nvertex
graph and then they go on to try to
prove stuff about some n plus1 vertex
graphs but they haven't shown that
they're really getting all of them. It's
this for all that tells us we should
start like this and no other way.
All right. So what do we do next? Um so
vertices
v1
vn vn plus one. So we have whatever
vertex order we're using. Now the greedy
algorithm
will color V1 through VN
as if VN + one and its edges
didn't exist.
The algorithm never looks at edges that
connect to vertices that haven't been
colored yet.
So as far as the greedy algorithm is
concerned, coloring vertices v1 through
vn, so all but one of the vertices in
our graph is going to look just like
coloring an nvertex graph.
Yeah. So
this what's called a subgraph
um
on
v1 through vn if we take just the first
n vertices make a subgraph of just its
um just its vertices as our vertex set
and the edges between them as our edge
set
with all their edges.
This subgraph
also has max degree D.
Uh oh, sorry.
We're supposed to prove something about
all n plus1 vertex graphs with max
degree d. So assume g is some n plus1
vertex graph with max degree d.
Then when we look at the subgraph where
we're only taking some of the vertices
and some of the edges, well degree can't
go up when you do that.
So this subgraph also has max degree at
most d.
Okay
by p of n because we assumed p of n.
These n vertices
will use at most D+1 colors.
Right?
We have an nvertex graph that we're
talking about. We know it satisfies the
property. So we get the conclusion
because of our assumption. So it uses at
most D plus1 colors. So now all we need
to talk about is the last step of the
greedy algorithm.
Last step
for VN plus one.
Well, VN plus one has degree at most D.
So it has at most D colors that
conflict.
So um one of the first D+1 colors will
be sufficient.
Um uses
one
through D+1 uses one of these colors
because you can only have D conflicts
because this has degree at most D.
Therefore, the last color also uses one
of the first D+1 colors. So, the whole
coloring uses that many colors. And
we're done with the proof.
Did that make sense?
If it didn't, come up, talk to me
afterward. I'm happy to stay and answer
questions. Thank you so much. We'll see
you on Thursday.