Uh, and our next speaker is Mark Mezner
um from Endurance Energy and he's going
to talk about codes and standards for
geothermal heat pumps and uh networks.
>> Thank you. I got mine. I do have
Good morning and I want to thank Heat
and MIT for putting this meeting on. I
think it's absolutely vital that this
audience understands what is happening
now and where things are potentially
going. I'm going to talk to you about
the scintillating topic of codes and
standards. I'm sure you're on edge, but
they're they're good to to have. You
have to have standards. And just as a
note, a standard and a code actually,
but a standard in particular
lays out minimum standards. Okay? So
don't think this is the gold standard as
far as what you could do in a system.
Now that's up to a designer, engineer,
etc. These are the minimums that you
have to adhere to to be compliant to
this standard, which is the C448
standard, which is applicable in the
United States and Canada.
It actually worked. Excellent. Um, this
became a bational standard between
United States and Canada in 2016.
At that juncture, uh, it was a bit of a
milestone to get the two countries
actually to agree to things. So the the
background on that quickly was in 2014
is when the process started and we
gathered experts north and south of the
border approximately at that time 45 to
formulate the 2016 standard. Uh since
that time the standard has to go through
a a revision cycle. Unfortunately co
kind of hit and put a a pause on that.
So this should have been done in 2021 as
a new standard. It'll now be 2025. We
had to reaffirm this standard to allow
us to continue work on the new standard.
That new standard encompassed uh over 70
subject matter experts north and south
of the border as well as from Europe and
Asia.
Um there's a difference between a code
and a standard and I think it's
important that people understand that.
What they get mixed up. They think
they're all the same thing and they're
not. A standard is a voluntary set of
guidelines or prerequisites that you
adhere to. You can do it or not do it.
All right? You can say my system, my
geothermal system will be C448
compliant, which means you follow the
standard. You don't have to do that. In
Canada, I'll get to in a moment, you do.
In the United States, you don't. There's
a difference between the countries as we
all well know. Um however a standard can
become a code if the code body adopts
it. So as an example here in the US you
have uh code bodies like ICAMO
if they adopt this standard then it
becomes code basically becomes law. So
that's the genesis of how it works. And
again there's confusion out there but I
want to be clear that's kind of how this
works between a code and a standard.
quickly in Canada it's the C448 standard
and its various iterations before which
was C uh 445 C447 date back to 1992
and that's in the national building code
of Canada so in Canada we have one code
for the whole country and then that can
be modified province by province with
limitations you can only modify it so
far and that can be dropped down to the
city or municipal level as well so it's
bit of a different um approach between
Canada and United States. Uh if one of
the code bodies, like I say, like an
IATMO or IC adopts this code, then where
they have jurisdiction, it becomes quote
unquote the law of the land. And if
you're putting a geothermal system in
and either one of those bodies um adopt,
this is what you're going to quote
unquote have to do.
quickly. Um, we're not going to go
through all this because I got 10
minutes and h how much have I burned
through already? Too much. Okay. Uh,
what we did is is as a, uh, technical
committee, we gathered all of the
subject matter experts, um, that we
could, that we, you know, were
recommended to us, etc. Looked at the
2016 standard and said, "All right,
where are the gaps? Where are the
holes?" And there were. And the reason
why that happened is getting two
countries together to agree on something
is not easy as you can probably imagine.
So there was compromise accommodation
made in various areas and we lived with
that as an industry for that 5-year
period and then we identified wait a
second this has got to change. So there
was substantial changes done to the C448
standard. It will be published in May of
this year. So there's been some hiccups
along the road like I mentioned with
COVID etc. So it's a bit overdue is the
best way to say it.
Again, we uh worked with the EXPA
standards committee uh which by the way
I'm now the chair of so I don't think
it's a conflict of interest but I don't
know um to look at at their current
standard which was published in 2017
and technical committees went through
the standard of 2017 as well as the
bational standard of 2016 and say we
have to reconcile these two. What's
going to happen is once the 2025 edition
of C440 is published, the EXPA standard
gets sunset and there'll only be one
standard within the United States. Right
now there's kind of two, so it's a bit
awkward. The number of issues that we
went through that had to be relooked at
and uh expanded upon and more detail
given was what Garen was just talking
about was the formation thermal
conductivity testing. Thank you.
um as well as piping materials to have
absolute clarity on what you're putting
in the ground and more importantly what
you're not pardon me transfer fluids was
a a hot topic because when I'm talking
about heat transfer fluids that's the
fluid you're circulating through the
system and it could be just water it
depends on the design parameters a lot
of designers will put an antifreeze
agent into the system not so much to uh
combat freeze freezing from ambient, you
know, uh down 4 ft or whatever and you
had a really cold winter and you're
freezing the pipe. The real impetus is
to be able to run your heat pumps below
freezing. It's a bit of a combination,
but that's usually why people are doing
that. That's a whole design issue from a
designer. How cold do you want to run
your system? As Connor alluded to
earlier, um it depends, but usually your
parameters low are 30° Fahrenheit, high
about 90. Now, that's not written in
stone, but they're pretty good
goalposts.
Pardon me. The other one we looked at
very, very closely was hydrostatic
testing, and that's basically using a
fluid, water only, to pressurize and
test your system. If the system's
leaking because of a bad install, you
could be chasing it kind of quote
unquote forever. Where is the leak? So
you want to be doing a proper pressure
test prior to back filling because
imagine you have a bore field below a
40story building. You're not getting
back in there. So do it right the first
time. You have one chance.
I'm not going to go through this in too
much detail. The quick overview is there
is a general section which basically
encompasses a number of elements. One is
the all the the definitions that are in
the industry. So there's clarity. In a
lot of cases, you'll see the same item
referenced in two different ways
depending on a region. So we want to
clarify what those all are. So it's a
fairly exhaustive definition section
that um one should be looking at because
if you hear one term in Texas and it
could be something different in New
York. So we tried and did I think
successfully to capture all the
definitions and then use one throughout
the standard so there's no ambiguity.
That general section also included any
particular topic. So i.e. piping or heat
exchange fluid as examples that touched
on more of two source system
configurations.
They went into the general section so
there was no confusion. Then there was a
residential section focusing obviously
on single family homes, a commercial
section. There was a new section and
that's the district systems. Now a quick
segue, we're hearing gens, U10s, tens,
community loops, shared loops. There's a
whole bevy of terms out there.
We looked at it from a technical
committee side and went they're all
district systems. There are variations
to it. They are district systems and by
a definition you are servicing two or
more buildings with that system. So we
went into a lot of detail on a new
section for district energy system which
includes what you're all looking at is
ambient loop. It is one of the types of
district system. It's not the only one.
There's a number of them. Then after
that, we went into the various
configurations of source systems. What I
mean by that is the most prevalent one
out there is a vertically bore hole,
pardon me, vertically drilled bore hole.
So that's the vertical section and that
you'll find that in probably the
majority of commercial installs in urban
settings in particular. You'll see
horizontal systems, which was the next
one, where you have space. You have to
have a larger area land mass wise at the
surface to be able to put in a
horizontal system.
From there, we went into the the various
different types of source systems that
aren't that common, but are out there
depending on your geographic location
and your geology. So surface water
systems are basically looking at a lake,
a river, the ocean. So that's a source
system. We went through all of them that
are currently out there. Excuse me. Um,
groundwater systems are open systems.
You've probably heard the term pump and
dump. Maybe you have, maybe you haven't.
That's where you have a water well.
Basically, you're extracting water,
running it through a heat exchanger, and
then reinjecting that to the aquifer or
to surface depending on what the
jurisdiction allows. Um, standing column
well is is a um it's a bit of a niche
because you have to have competent
bedrock to be able to put them in. It's
it's very specialized here in the
Northeast. They're prevalent. Not so
much in the rest of the continent
reality. The new one that we put in that
was coming up is uh for um foundations
or energy piles. They're getting some
traction. We said we got to put this in
there, address it, and have a standard
around it.
There's informative annexes at the back
of the standard. These are not
mandatory. These are information. That's
why they're called informative annex. So
they give you um direction on things and
the new one was for wastewater energy
transfer. You've heard I think Nick was
talking about it. I think Connor maybe a
little bit. The Shark system is one.
There's different uh Hoover out of
Germany has them. There are pipe systems
and you're harvesting thermal energy
from your wastewater stream. So again,
we thought it was very important to put
that in. I am going to skip over this
because zero minutes. Oh well, that
means I'm done. Is that what you're
telling me? Uh, okay. Hang on. Let's get
get to Can I have two more minutes? I'll
talk real fast.
>> Okay. Thank you. Uh, back one. Uh,
piping. Okay. One of the big issues
there is what are you putting into the
ground? It's vitally important that
we're not putting garden hose down a
bore hole. So, in a standard, you tend
to be performanceoriented. Meet this
performance metric and you are
compliant. There are issues where it has
to be prescriptive. It it's kind of a
there's no way out of that one. We have
to be very careful in what we're putting
in to a bore hole. Bearing in mind we
are putting in infrastructure that's
going to last 50, 100 years, 150. We
don't even know. So what you're putting
in the ground has got to last. Sorry I'm
talking fast. Oh, that last thing. PVC
CPVC
no longer will be uh compliant with the
standard. A lot of testing, a lot of
research was done on PVC in particular.
And heat exchange fluids within PVC are
basically corrosive is the best way to
say it. They break down and you have
real problems. Again, infrastructure,
we're not doing that. I'll skip over
that. Heat exchange fluids. Um, a lot of
work went into this. What's available?
What can you do? There's tables in there
that give you properties of heat
transfer fluids. again for a designer to
choose what is the applicable heat
transfer fluid and may just be water.
That's quite possible. Pressure testing,
like I said, I'm not going to belabor
this one because I'm out of time. The
integrity of the ground loop system is
paramount. You have to be able to say
this is not leaking before you back
fill. Otherwise, you have huge problems.
That is a quick that's what an energy
pile looks like. It's a bit of a new um
approach to a source system. They're
gaining some traction. They are
applicable in some cases, not all cases.
The whole district energy systems um
many many people have been talking about
the various source inputs that you could
have to a district system. So we have
went fairly exhaustive on that and
deviated a bit from the format that is
currently within the rest of the
standard and that's under number four
pro project planning is you know as a
designer you're doing a district energy
system. These are some vital elements
you have to look at which are applicable
to gen, you know, generally to
geothermal systems, but really take a a
u a good look for a district system.
There's lots of moving parts and you
have to be um cognizant of what is out
there. Uh piping materials, again I said
very prescriptive on the piping
materials. This one here is for the
distribution materials inside or uh
above grade I should say of for district
systems. So there it's a little bit of a
deviation from what's in the ground
because there's more flexibility given
your different source systems and
temperatures.
Uh I think it was alluded to earlier
depending on how the system is being
designed. You may have insulated or
pre-insulated piping, hot pipe, cold
pipe. You got to be careful there. that
you're not having thermal interference
between the two. Insulation in a con
confined area is your best go. Uh energy
transfer stations. I believe Brian Erlab
touched upon that. That's one way of
isolating your system uh your ground
loop system from the building. And
that's the waste water. Again, the these
are uh informative annexes to say here's
what you could do. Uh you can do a pipe
as you can see on the left there. That's
another way of harvesting uh energy from
the wastewater stream. This is some of
the investigation we did. There's not a
lot of um information from a standards
point of view in North America. So, we
referenced a a German uh specification
to get some guidance. They've done a lot
of work. We're not going to reinvent the
wheel. This is the the timeline. Like I
say, the last bullet is what we're
looking at. Release at May 2025.
Uh that's just a quick overview of you
know sunsetting the standards from
EXGPA. Uh any standard is a bit of a
living document. There's a revision
cycle every 5 years. However, should
there be some monumental change within
the industry, there is the ability to do
a an update or NARTA. Uh looking at
things into the future, the A2L
refrigerants will be a big issue.
District energy systems will continue to
be on everyone's mind. And that's about
it. So, sorry, Stacey.