when you apply to the ba master of
business analytics program you know we
don't look at anything until the
deadline so this year the deadline is
January 3rd um and after the deadline
all applications are reviewed so we have
an admissions committee that's combined
um with faculty members the pro mbn uh
program office as well as admission
staff so there's about 20 people
involved in reviewing all of the
applications every application is
reviewed we use those initial reads to
determine who to invite to interview so
interviews are a required step in the
process um but only a subset of
applicants are invited to interview so
usually like around 20 to 25% of the
applicants are invited to interview and
then of the people who invited to
interview um we're admitting maybe
around 30% of those um again this year
interviews will be held on
Zoom um you know what are we looking for
at a high level you know we're looking
to admit people who are smart motivated
and have been able to demonstrate a
passion for analytics or data science in
some combination of things they've been
a part of so far so that might be from
you know work experiences it might be
from classes you've taken it might be
from you know internships or
extracurricular activities you've been a
part of um there's lots of different
ways for you to demonstrate this kind of
passion or excitement for analytics um
we are as I said said before looking for
evidence of a strong academic success um
so that is you know understanding um the
fundamentals of math so we like to see
classes like linear algebra
probabilities statistics multivariable
calculus um you'll see these are all
kind of highlighted in the application
when you look at um you know uh
preferred courses that we like to see or
relevant courses um we're also looking
for you know some evidence of your
ability
uh to succeed in computer programming so
some familiarity with python R SQL um
you know some some combination of things
it doesn't have to be that you've taken
an actual class for credit it could be
that you've done an online certificate
it can be that you are self-taught um
and you've been able to demonstrate this
through some of the skills and the work
that you've done um and then typically
we're seeing people as I said before
from a stem undergraduate discipline um
but of course there's exceptions to
everything um and then in terms of
having kind of a solid industry
knowledge what we mean here is you know
I'll I'll first say we get it most of
you are coming directly from undergrad
or applying with very few years of
experience full-time so we don't expect
for you to be an expert in the analytics
or data science Industry but we're
looking for you to show that you have
some you know um relevant exposure to
the industry and that can come from
research you've done it can come from a
hackathon you've been a part of a
conference that you help to plan it can
come from student organizations you've
been a part of or obviously it could
come from internship or work experiences
that you've been um involved in and then
um the application is also measuring
your ability to communicate effectively
and you know demonstrate that you can be
a good team player um so we're looking
for you know obviously um this program
is taught in English it is live and
inperson we are not a virtual program so
everyone who comes to the business
analytics program is expected to live
here in Cambridge for the year you
attend classes in person you know we're
looking for you to have um you know
strong collaboration skills much of the
work that you're going to be doing is in
a team setting um and we're also looking
for people who are strong enough
academically and have good interpersonal
skills so that they can become an active
member in the community at MIT and at
Sloan
so the way we measure all of this is
through this application process and so
the application itself consists of a
number of different um you know
components um and I'll kind of list
through them here um and then give some
tips along the way so here's a list of
everything in the application we have
you know um academic transcripts that's
all of the academic work you've done
whether it's been degree or non-degree
um seeking so we want to see anything
that you've done done that's relevant to
this program so all of your
undergraduate studies if you've studied
abroad if you have graduate degree work
if you've done um you know non-degree
work certificates anything like that all
of it we'd love to see it there's a
space in the application for everything
we ask for a resume I'll go into a bit
of detail about that in a minute but
it's a one-page resume and we have an
essay which is you know tell us a little
bit more about why you're interested in
the business analytics program and what
you're hoping to accomplish I'll kind of
expand on that as well we have a couple
videos um so the videos give us a chance
to understand how well you communicate
kind of on the spot as well as um you
know get a better sense of who you are
uh we asked for three letters of
recommendation and um we are happy to
accept a test if you've taken the GRE or
the GMAT um but it is not a required um
component of the application so it's
optional however um you know if you have
taken a test uh it's a great way for us
to uh better assess some of those skills
um and then as I mentioned before the
deadline is January 3rd um interviews
are also a required step in the process
and it takes us about a month or so to
read all of the applications and then
interview invitations go out towards the
end of January um and then interviews
happen throughout the month of February
and then decisions come out in early
March all right so we'll expand on a few
things here and give some tips so the
resume I understand if especially if
you're applying directly from undergrad
you know you might not have had a lot of
practice with creating a one-page resume
um but we are giving you these
parameters because when you graduate
from this program and you're looking for
employment this is how the resume will
be expected to look so a one-page resume
um that you know is listing everything
you've been a part of in Reverse
chronological order it should include
things like your educational experience
all of your work experience
internships any kind of research or
other relevant exposure you've had to
analytics um and then you should
highlight any additional Awards
extracurricular um activities you're
involved with leadership roles you've
had or any other additional information
you know that you think is relevant for
us to know um so the resume is a pretty
standard format um you know my tips
here um try to Showcase your
accomplishments and focus Less on the
job description and the reason for that
is you know in the application we ask a
bunch of demographic questions as well
and in those demographic questions there
are small text boxes you can use there
to provide us the job description that
you had an internship or the job
description you had at your full-time
employer and instead you can focus on
the resume and talk about like what are
the successes you've had or what is the
impact quantifiable outcomes that you've
been able to to be a part of um or help
to influence in the work that you've
done um so you have kind of two
different places you'll be talking about
your work experiences so try not to um
be too redundant in those spots um also
on your resume we want to make sure that
it's easy for us to read you know
sometimes I see resumés that you know
although they technically follow the
requirements of you know using Times New
Roman font in a size 10 they're so
densely packed that there's just two to
much information to analyze you know we
are um you're applying to a data
analytics program that is about
visualizing data and making things you
know easy for somebody to digest and
synthesize so we're looking for a resume
to be you know the highlight real um and
not something that um you know you're
trying to cram a 100 lines into one
piece of paper um and then we're looking
again for you know a combination of
things to be reflected here that should
also be um you know complimenting the
other aspects of your application but
you certainly would want to um highlight
any volunteer work that you do
extracurriculars you're a part of
leadership roles you've had or any
additional Awards or certificates you
might have accomplished um in addition
to your work
experiences all right um so the essay so
the essay um is pretty straightforward
and simple 500 words or less tell us why
you're interested in pursuing the master
of business Analytics degree at MIT slan
so it's really your chance to share with
us you know why you're passionate about
pursuing this why it makes sense for you
at this stage in your career or in your
path um you know a little bit about what
you're hoping to gain from the program
and then maybe tie it together with why
mat Sloan is a good match for you what
is it about this program that makes it
uniquely you know positioned to fit with
your goals so um you know what we're
trying to assess here is that you have a
realist IC understanding of what coming
to study with us for one year can get
you to um so you know trying to make a
change in your career or trying to you
know build skills in an area you don't
have exposure in or maybe you're coming
from you know a an undergraduate
experience where you didn't have as many
Global opportunities you know whatever
the case might be um you want to just
you know convey to us what is sort of
the value proposition for you in joining
us at MIT Sloan
we also have a short answer question we
ask everybody to tell us a little bit
more about the their background and kind
of where they come from you know you can
share lots of different things here but
you know ultimately we're trying to
understand what has been your path so
far you know what is it about that path
that has made it um you know unique for
you and how have you been able to
potentially overcome things or how have
you been able to create a more inclusive
environment for the people that you've
been a part of or the groups you've been
a part of so we've historically seen
people share stories about their family
their culture their Community all of the
above you know kind of if they've you
know moved from one place to the next or
if they've had to overcome certain um
barriers you know we're trying to better
understand really how the world you've
come from has helped you to become the
person you are
today in terms of recommendation letters
we get lots of questions about letter
um so we are asking for three letters of
recommendation and you know we want at
least one of those letters to speak to
your quantitative abilities ideally this
quantitative focused recommendation
letter would come from a faculty member
you've worked with or you took a class
with um that was you know something
that's relevant to analytics math or
data science um however we understand
that sometimes not everybody has that so
at least one letter to speak to your
quantitative abilities if you're a
current student you have um you know
we're looking for at least two letters
to come from an academic Source ideally
three so we really would prefer academic
faculty references um you know that are
talking about your skills that are
relevant to an analytics
program however you know it is really
your decision um if you choose three
academic letters or two academic letters
in one letter from somebody who is from
a professional source so you know if
you've had a really great internship or
you've had some type of a work
experience during those Summers or
during the course of a semester that you
think would be um important to highlight
we're going to let you decide you should
decide who to choose that third letter
from so know that if you're a current
student we are happy to have three
academic letters however if you feel
that you'd like to also highlight
relevant work experience that you've had
it's okay to have two academic letters
and one from a professional Source now
if you're currently working full-time we
definitely want a professional letter of
recommendation from you um so we would
want a letter from your current or most
recent employer as well as two academic
letters speaking to your you know um
quantitative or relevant cours workk
experiences um so a couple questions we
always get about letters of
recommendation number one the letters of
recommendation are all also due on
January 3rd so entire application is due
January 3rd not just your part um so we
would recommend that you talk to your
recommenders as soon as possible make
them aware of the deadline everything is
submitted online you send um a unique uh
link to your application with the form
to to your recommen recommenders make
sure they know what the deadlines are um
you know and we're asking pretty um you
know specific questions on those letters
of recommendation so you know talk to
your recommenders share with them what
your goals are why you're applying to
MIT Sloan um and you know ask those
recommenders to try to um you know speak
directly to the prompts that we give um
in that
form we have two videos in the
application and I recognize that these
can also create some anxiety for
applicants um however it's a nice tool
for us to get to know you better to
better understand how you communicate
and to learn a little bit more about
what's important to you outside of what
you've shared um in your essay and in
your resume so the first video um is
pretty straightforward you know we ask
you to upload a one minute video that is
really uh you introducing yourself to
your hypothetical future class
classmates um so what is it about you
that you want everyone to know you can
kind of think about this as you know if
you were about to walk into a room with
people um who you really wanted to
become friends with how would you
introduce yourself to them you'd likely
share a little bit about your personal
background maybe um what you are doing
right now but you'd probably share
something personal as well you know
something you like to do outside of work
or something that you're really um
passionate about so um so that's
typically what we're seeing you know
this video is not designed to be
something that you have to spend a lot
of time editing it's really you know one
take a selfie video very simple um and
you know the tips we have are really
just make sure you're aware of your
surroundings so if it's loud wherever
you're filming you know make sure you
have a microphone or that we can hear
you um and U make sure that we can see
you make sure you upload the video um
and that it's success y um uploads so
it's it's pretty simple you record it
and upload it to us the second video um
is a little bit more um is a little
different so the second video we control
and it's really a chance for us to you
know do two things to understand you
know how you um respond to a question in
real time and you know a good authentic
understanding of your communication
skill um so this is is uh a video prompt
so a question will appear on the screen
um and you'll have 10 seconds to read
that question and then the camera will
go on and you have one minute to respond
it's just one take um and these
questions are not questions that would
require any advanced preparation they're
really questions that are simple for you
to answer that should be you know
natural in terms of um you know your
understanding of how to respond to them
you know examples of this would be
question questions like you know tell me
about your favorite course that you've
taken from the past and why or you know
tell me about the best vacation you've
gone on and why they're really you know
very um open-ended really no wrong
answer type of questions but it's a way
for us to understand kind of how you
think on your feet um and really the
biggest tip for this is make sure that
when you are sitting down or standing to
do this um that you're well um aware of
your surroundings and that there isn't
any um extra distractions happening
behind
you uh in terms of academic records um
and relevant coursework I spoke about
this quickly before but we're looking to
really measure your academic aptitude
and how comfortable you are with really
the Quant quantitative challenging
nature of this program so we are
teaching classes that are you know
essentially at a PhD level they're
focused on um Advanced Techniques and
machine learning
optimization um you know and we're
really trying to understand how you've
been able to learn complex Concepts in
the past and succeed at that so we want
to see evidence of your comfort with
these challenging quantitative um topics
so we will thoroughly review all of your
transcripts that's why we also ask you
to include any other relevant um course
work or non-degree work that you've
completed that's you know important for
us to consider we recognize that over
the past you know five to seven years
the world has changed so much with
regard to generative Ai and computer
science and in order to keep up a lot of
people applying has uh um you know
completed non-degree options or they've
you know been self-taught in a lot of
things and that is great we love that we
we just want to see some evidence of
that in some capacity so if you've taken
a corsera class or if you've pursued you
know additional um professional
development type of work through an
internship or through um you know your
full-time work experiences to kind of
round out some of those skills just
include that in some capacity so that we
know that you've had exposure to these
things um and then a couple other
logistics if your undergraduate degree
um was not taught in English or your
transcripts are not in English we just
ask you to upload a translation in
English so um you know a certified
translation Works um you know any kind
of uh notorized translation I know many
um many universities provide a certified
English translation all of that works we
just want to try to make it as easy as
possible for our missions committee to
understand uh the details of um of your
academic
experiences as I said before test scores
are optional um however we are happy to
see test scores we accept all of the
above from GRE to G GMAT and GMAT Focus
that's the newer version we're happy to
see um evidence of tests that were
taking either in person or online all of
that is acceptable um and you know I'll
say we often get questions about TOEFL
or IELTS we really don't require that
and we don't even really look at it so
um you don't need to worry about that we
have this inperson or uh live I should
say um on Zoom interview with a member
of our admissions committee so we're
very much comfortable in assessing your
English language ability through that
interview process um and you know if you
have taken the test um you know it's
really up to you to include it or not
however it's a great way for us to
understand your ability as I said before
to uh Master something that's a little
bit foreign and challenging and complex
um and provide um us evidence that
you've been able to um successfully uh
learn some that's maybe not as familiar
as um you know things that you've been
accustomed to and to succeed at
that all right um a few important dates
to highlight and then we'll get to
questions um in a minute or two uh the
application deadline it's January 3rd as
I mentioned before all um application
components are due on January 3rd
recommendation letters essays videos
everything the interviews are going to
take place throughout the entire month
of February um and then final decision
will be released on March 3rd and if you
are accepted to the program you'll have
to respond to the deadline by April
15th um just a couple comments on the
interview uh so the interview um is
going to be about a 30 minute interview
on Zoom with a member of our admissions
committee um it will be a combination of
Behavioral type questions as well as
some technical questions um so we may be
asking questions about um computer
programming about you know different um
relevant courses that you've taken um in
addition to you know some questions
around your goals and why you're
interested in pursuing this program um
prior to the interview we have two
additional short answer questions we'd
like you to respond to um you have to
submit those no later than 24 hours
before the start of the interview just
so that if I'm interviewing you it gives
me a chance to read them and review them
all um before we meet um and you know in
the interview it's um it's really
designed to be convers
try not to um you know be too um you
know focused on notes that you have or
reading any answers we want it to
simulate a real conversation that we
might have with you if we were in the
room with one another um so again it's
30 minutes the best advice I have for
the interview is you know uh be prepared
in terms of feeling confident and how to
talk about your past experiences that
you've highlighted on the application
but also be prepared to to ask some
additional questions of us you know it's
also a chance for us to um you know help
to sell you on why MIT slan is a good
match for you and uh you know we' like
to see that you come prepared with uh
questions for us as
well just generally some additional tips
remember here we are looking for reasons
to admit you so um it is our job to you
know read through all of these
applications find different
characteristics find evidence of you
know the um the skills and the abilities
of students that we like to see
reflected here at MIT Sloan and to help
encourage and support you to get here um
applying early is great so what we mean
by that is try to get your pieces of the
application in as soon as possible um
you know and then making sure your
recommenders have the information they
need um we look at all we're we don't
look at any application data until the
day after the deadline um but we're
really looking to um um you know make
sure we have all the information we need
um to start the the review process on
January 4th obviously follow the
directions be yourself um and again
really just think of us as your advocate
here it is our job to admit you we work
in Admissions and we're really excited
to get to know you throughout the
process um and hopefully continue that
relationship once you become a
student all right so let's get to
questions
thanks Jen for the presentation I'll
kick it off with some of the questions
that we've had we've had a lot in the
chat um so thank you everyone for those
but we've definitely had a few about the
video question too some of them are
wondering if it's a technical question
or what they can expect for the types of
questions they'll see in video question
two yep so video question two is not a
technical question so it does not
require any advanced preparation as I
said before it's very much you know an
open-ended question that does doesn't
typically have any wrong answers it's
more about how you formulate a response
kind of in the moment um in your ease of
ability to kind of communicate on your
feet um so open-ended questions like you
know what's been your favorite job from
the past and why or what's been your
favorite class or can you talk about um
you know a recent accomplishment that
you've had you know very open-ended
questions what
great thank you so much we do seem to
have some folks here that are interested
in both business analytics and mfin so
the first question is is it possible for
students to apply to both programs and
is there any um information that should
or can be repeated between the two
applications yes so um it certainly is
possible to apply to both they both have
you know independent review processes so
the application deadline is the same um
but there's two independent committees
that um review applications so uh you
know my advice would be to tailor your
application to the program you're
applying to um that that's um you know
so it's your decision whether or not you
use the same video for instance for both
applications or the same essay we would
suggest that you try to be as specific
as possible in the content that you
share making sure that it relates to the
program you're applying to um but it
it's your call um in terms of the on
demand video you would have to do two
independent OnDemand um video twos um
and then in terms of the recommendation
letters that's your choice as
well that leads me well to some other
questions that we have on the letters of
recommendation um we have some questions
from those attending wondering what kind
of significance might be put on a letter
of recommendation for an Alum if that's
recommended um and then also some
questions if you want to talk a little
bit about the balance between academic
and professional recommendations again
okay so um we love to hear from members
of our community um about candidates who
are applying however um if I were an
applicant I would make sure that the
people who are writing my letters know
me really well and can speak with
specific examples to the prompts or the
questions that recommenders are being
asked so if I happen to know an alum who
does also know me really well then
perfect that's a great person to select
but if the Alum that you know is
somebody who's a couple degrees away
from the work that you were doing or not
somebody who can speak in specifics to
the type of person that you are it might
be better for that Alum just to send us
a quick note or an email and we'll get
it added to your file um I think that
recommendation letters are really much
about um you know giving us as much
tangible information about your recent
experiences so um so as I said before
it's not necessarily who writes the
letter it's what the letter says about
you yeah and then do you want to just
briefly talk about what we're looking
for in terms of the balance between
professional and academic
recommendations yeah so we're really um
this is a a very um academically focused
program and we're looking for evidence
of your quantitative abilities evidence
of your abilities to succeed s in a
successful way in um a challenging
academic environment and the faculty who
teach in the program really want to see
evidence of that from from your
recommenders which is why we have a
strong preference for faculty
recommendation letters you know so
people who you've taken um a course with
that's relevant to analytics or data
science or engineering um people who um
can speak to your ability to um succeed
you know in a in a a challenging
environment um so for for current
students you know we would like to see
uh three letters from an academic Source
but like I said before there's some
degree of flexibility there if you have
a really great internship or relevant
research experience or relevant
experience working in something um you
know that is not um going to give us
somebody who's a faculty reference so if
you've worked for a PhD student or if
you've worked for uh you know a
volunteer organization that you know is
really important to you you know there
you want to make sure that we hear from
the people who know you best so you have
some flexibility there um if you're a
working professional so if you've
already graduated school and you're
working full-time we definitely want one
letter from work um but we still would
like to see two letters from your
academic
past great that's super helpful we do
have student wondering about the
interview portion and the technical
aspects of that if you can explain a
little bit about what what things our
candidates should keep in mind with the
technical portion of the interview yeah
so um in the interview I I typically ask
you know two or three technical
questions and the questions um might be
you know something related to
multivariable calculus or linear algebra
statistics or probability I might also
ask a question related to um how you
might visualize an outcome of some type
of an analysis that you've done um so
different tools or techniques you might
prefer to use um you know to um to uh
clean Data before putting it into like a
machine learning model or how you've
been able to optimize a large data set
even if it's something that you've done
in somewhat less sophisticated tools
like Excel or something like that so um
there's a variety of questions that we
might ask and they're going to vary
dependent on um you know what you share
with us in your application we're really
trying to ask questions that help us to
balance out understanding all of the
different type of skills and abilities
that we're looking to see so if you talk
a lot about machine learning and
optimization techniques that you've had
in your application we're not likely to
ask a lot of questions about that again
in the interview but instead we might
ask questions about you know data
visualization or um probability or
statistics or something like that so if
if I do ask a question or two um that
that um requires you to calculate
something you can certainly use a piece
of paper and a pencil and we'll give you
the time that you need to kind of come
up with that calculation but you know
typically if it is a question that's
like a true mathematics problem I'm not
necessarily looking for a I'm looking to
understand how you would you know um put
together the steps to solve the problem
but you don't necessarily have to
compute the full problem or and come to
one um one value in the end um you know
you've all if you make it to the
interview stage this will be you know no
problem you'll all be great at the
technical
questions right thanks John yeah um we
have some other questions thinking about
applicants backgrounds um one of them an
applicant is wondering if we require any
Computing or programming knowledge to
apply to the program it's not required
but it is is preferred so um what I when
I say that um you know we do ask in the
application have you taken any computer
programming classes or are you familiar
with any programming languages um if if
you're not um it doesn't necessarily
mean that we wouldn't admit you but we
might require you to take a class or do
some type of prep work over the summer
prior to joining us so that your
learning curve Isn't So steep when you
start um our preferred um uh language
that we'd like to see some evidence of
is
python what
else I'm wondering if you can specify a
little bit for any International
students who are joining us today about
how they should submit their grades um
and and how we handle that based on
different International grading systems
yeah we are experts on analyzing
transcripts from different um different
countries from undergraduate degrees
I've been working in admissions here at
MIT for over 20 years we have a number
of colleagues um who have studied in
different countries and we have faculty
who are helping us and they've they've
come from lots of different culture
cultures and countries as well so um
we're really looking to you know make
sure we just have an English translation
of your transcript if it's not in
English already um and then we look very
closely at all of the relevant courses
that you've taken at the um the grade
point average that you show based on
whatever the grading system is if it's a
10-point scale a 20o scale you know if
it's um you know if the if a lower score
is that is more preferred so if you're
from Germany and you know a 1.0 is
better than a 3.0 we understand all of
the nuances of this so we're really
looking to you know dive deep into your
transcripts you do not need to modify
anything for us we just need to make
sure that it's um you know available in
English thinking a little further past
the application process if someone were
to be admitted to the program can you
talk a little bit about what the
fellowship process looks like yep so
everybody admitted to the program is
automatically considered for merit-based
Fellowship so that's fellowships that
are given based on um the strength of
your candidacy as well as you know the
diversity that you might represent In
terms of the academic exposure the
countries you're coming from um you know
the the path that you've been on so far
um so we look at um factors in terms of
Merit and diversity to award Fellowship
everyone is automatically considered um
there are also a couple of um you know
MIT graduate student wide fellowships
that mband students have historically
applied for that process would happen
after or you're admitted to the program
um but on the day you're admitted uh
which is uh I think going to be March
3rd this year um you would also find out
at that time if you've been awarded a
fellowship now let me just say that no
one is receiving a full tuition
Fellowship to come to this program the
fellowship funding we have um is
designed to give as many people a small
award as possible so typically those
awards are around
$20,000 um but there is a lot of value
to this program because in addition to
fellowships um you are also able to
receive a tuition offset for the
Capstone project that you participate in
in the final summer term and so you're
receiving a
$24,000 um uh offset of tuition um to
cover uh that that Capstone project so
$24,000 is automatically deducted from
your tuition um and then in addition you
get up to about a $5,000 stien for the
summer to cover your living expenses
also um over a third of students are
holding research assistant positions and
those research assistant positions are
paid in a combination of tuition and
stipended but in total they would be
around
$112,000 per semester so if you work as
a as a research assistant for the fall
and the spring semester and you have um
the Capstone project that's taking
$48,000 off the cost of attendance so um
there's a lot of value here there's a
lot of opportunities for you to offset
that tuition with the work that you do
um so you know typically students are
able to figure this out um and you know
we're happy to work with you to to
figure out any additional loan options
or any additional resources that we can
try to help identify for
you that's great thank you you're
answering so many of these questions I
have seen a few questions come in
between um students that are wondering
about the difference between the MBA
program and the business analytics
program if you wouldn't mind just
covering some main highlights of both
yeah so the business analytics program
is really designed for people who are a
little earlier in their career so who
have maybe between zero and five years
of experience with the majority of
students in mban coming directly from
undergrad I think this year it's over
70% of the students came directly from
undergrad but 30% of students had some
combination of full-time work experience
um and mban is really for students who
are looking to really focus and stay in
their Lane in terms of you know they
know what they want they're coming to
build quantitative skills in the field
of analytics and data science and that
is what their goal is after graduating
um where the MBA is a lot more flexible
you have two full years we're looking
for people who join that program to have
on average five years of experience
already um and there's an internship
component so it gives you a chance to
use the the academic experience to make
a change and to gain real world exposure
in things that you don't otherwise have
experience doing um so there is a path
or kind of the equivalent of like a
major um in the the MBA that focuses on
business analytics we call them
certificates um but you know you would
really want to make sure that you um
consider uh what the demographics look
like and what the class profile looks
like for the MBA verse the mband so if
you're an individual with five or more
years of experience we're happy to talk
to you but we we would um definitely
want to make sure we understand what
your goals are after um and that you
understand what the demographics look
like of either of the programs and the
type of students you'd be partnering
with that's great thank you so much Jen
and and I think we're getting through uh
these questions and we're right to time
and you've you've explained this but we
may have caused a little confusion but
for working professionals that are in
that 0 to five range can you clarify
once more about the letter of letters of
recommendation and who they should be
coming from yeah so if you're a working
professional you should have two
academic letters in one professional
letter so two letters still from
academics and one from your current or
most recent employer and any combination
of the three at least one of those
letters should speak to your technical
quantitative abilities