so today we are going to move on to a
new topic once again to remind you where
of of the path of how we got here in
within producer Theory we said that it's
harder than consumer Theory because you
don't only do the standard optimization
the consumer Theory but you need a third
condition you need a market structure
condition to pin down the equilibrium
for the last few lectures we relied on a
particular Market structure which was
perfect competition that allowed us to
show that a perfect competition price
equals marginal cost and that allowed us
to solve the system for how firms choose
their quantity and prices in perfect
competition but as we discussed that's
an incredibly extreme assumption and
pretty much unrealistic for almost any
Market there are some markets that more
competitive than others but there's
really no such thing as a perfectly
competitive market so what we're going
to do now is move on in the next few
lectures and talk about Alternative
Market structures and how they change
the conclusions we draw this is going to
be important for two reasons first of
all it's going to be important because
it's more
realistic second of all is going be
important because having established the
first fundamental theorem of welfare
economics which is the perfectly
competitive outcome is the best outcome
we're not going to talk you about why
that doesn't work in reality and why in
fact governments aren't just agents of
chaos but can actually do good things in
improving potential market failures so
by introducing these Alternative Market
structures will also juuce the concept
of a market failure which is markets not
working to deliver the efficient
outcome so we're going to start today by
talking about
Monopoly so we're going to go from one
extreme to another the one extreme we
started with was a perfectly competitive
market with a large number firms
competing to deliver identical products
we're going to move all the way to the
Other Extreme which is Monopoly which is
not the game but rather the name for a
market with one
firm that delivers all that delivers the
goods for the entire Market s from uh
many firms competing to one firm
dominating the market and the key thing
about Monopoly the key thing that's
going to change is that firms are going
to be price makers not just price acers
remember in perfect competition the
price was just sort of given to you from
God it came from some market equilibrium
you don't know where it came from you
just knows the price and you couldn't
affect it well that's kind of silly
firms can obviously choose the prices
they set so now we move to Monopoly
we'll actually let firms be price price
makers as well as price
takers okay now in fact once again
Monopoly is very extreme it's not
extreme perfect competition monopolies
do exist even if perfectly competitive
markets don't but but it's still a
relatively small share of reality after
a couple lectures of Monopoly we'll then
turn to the more realistic case in my
favorite word in economics
oligopoly which is the case of several
firms competing where this competition
but it's less than perfect competition
and we'll come back to that but for the
next two lectures we're going to move to
the Other Extreme which is Monopoly okay
and we're talk today about how
monopolists maximize profits how to
monopolis maximize
profits okay well to do that we're going
to turn to a
concept that we've already talked about
but it's been sort of meaningless so far
which is the concept of marginal
revenue the marginal revenue is the
revenue you earn on the next unit you
sell which in perfect competition wasn't
interesting it was just the
price but it's going to get more
interesting
today okay so we're going to talk about
what happen so let's go back
and think about a perfectly competitive
firm and think about what their marginal
revenues so in figure
111 you have a perfectly competitive
firm they The Firm M faces a perfectly
elastic demand curve a perfectly
competitive firm this doesn't mean the
market demand's elastic but each firm in
perfect competition faces a perfectly
elastic demand curve so if they sell
little Q units they make Revenue
a if they sell Q plus1 units they make
Revenue a plus b they add B well we know
what B is the width is one and the
height is the price so the marginal
revenue from selling the Q plus plus one
unit plus one
unit is the price okay it's just an
illustration what we learned before
Monopoly is going to be different and in
particular monopo is going to be
different because we're going to make a
critical
assumption for how monopolis behave we
are going to assume
that
monopolis that um we're assume that
monopolis uh cannot price
discriminate that is when a monopolis
sets a
price they set that price for All units
they sell so monopolis sets the price
they're price maker but it's not quite
free Price setting because we're not
going to let them set a different price
to me and you when they set price they
set the price for everyone so we're
going to assume no price discrimination
we'll come back to that but for now
we're going to say that when I'm we're
going to let the monopolis set his price
but critically it's one price for
everyone and you'll see in a minute why
this is
important okay so to understand that
let's go to figure
112 112 is for Monopoly Market all
that's changed
here is that now firm demand is market
demand
okay with perfect competition firm
demand was perfectly elastic because
there are many firms but now firm
demand's market demand and unless the
market itself features perfectly elastic
demand The Firm will now face a downward
sloping demand curve so now little Q is
Big Q you notice on the x- axis I moved
to Big Q which we used to refer to the
market well with Monopoly markets little
Q is Big Q there's one firm so the firm
is the market and that firm faces a
downward sloping demand curve so let's
say that firm initially wants to sell Q
q1 I'm sorry want sell Q if it wants to
sell
Q it has to respect demand so if it
wants to sell Q it's going to set the
price at
P1 a price of P1 allows them to sell Q
units remember they get set the price
now so price of P1 allows to sell Q
units now imagine they want to sell one
more
unit what happens well two things happen
okay and in particular if they want to
sell one more
unit okay they have to lower the
price why because demand is downward
sloping and there's just one price so if
the monopolis wants to move from selling
Q to selling q+ one it has to lower the
price from P1 to P2 there's no choice it
has to be on the demand
curve so when the anopolis wants to
sell two more two
units okay the marginal revenue they get
want sell one more unit they get the
amount
B which they sell one more unit at the
price P2 but they lose the amount
C they get the amount B but they lose
the amount C or in other words what do
they what does a monopolis get from
selling one more unit monopis say sells
one more unit the monopolis gets P2
minus P1
times um I'm sorry P2
minus P2 minus P1 minus P2 *
q1 okay the monopolist gets some money
from selling additional unit but loses
some money because it had to lower the
price on all its previous units you
might say that once again stop and think
for me for a second it doesn't make
sense why does it have to well it has to
because it can only set one
price so if it wants to set sell more
it's got to set a lower price which
means it's going to make less than all
its previous
units okay so basically when the
monopolis sets the price there's now a
tradeoff the tradeoff is if he wants to
sell more he has to lower the price but
in doing so the monopolis makes less
money on the previous units they
sold okay and that's because they set
the same price price for All consumers
this is the key intuition that drives
our analysis of
Monopoly okay I like to refer to
this as what I call the poisoning
effect I call it the poisoning effect
it's just the term I like to use because
the idea is if I want to sell one more
unit I have to poison all my previous
sales by lowering their
price because I can't sell another unit
without a lower price and if I lower
price I make less money on my previous
sales okay don't think it's a changing
your price day by day think of this I
have to set one price
yeah yes this is the marginal this is
the marginal
revenue yeah P P1 minus P2 * q1 it's in
parenthesis okay so basically the
marginal revenue is if I if I want to
sell one more unit I get P2 for that
unit that's what I get for that unit but
I give up what I was making on all the
old units the difference in the price
that I was making on all the old
units okay and that is basically the
definition of marginal revenue in the
monopolis case so in other words more
generally if you write Revenue as P * Q
then marginal revenue you can write if
you write P * Q the marginal revenue is
uh Dr DQ okay if you take margin with
respect to Q is
Dr
DQ well that equals P plus
d p DQ time
Q so when you want to sell one more unit
if I the marginal revenue there's a
positive term which I sell one more unit
but there's a negative term which is I
had to lower my price to sell that
unit so when I'm setting my price I have
to trade these things
off okay I have to trade these things
off which is basically that I have to
trade off the fact that I'm make I'm
going to sell more units but I'm going
to make um make less money to each unit
Why didn't the competitive firm face
this
tradeoff why why was this trade-off not
an issue for the competitive firm
mathematically what's different from the
competitive
firm yeah
dpq is zero for the competitive firm
because it's a price taker it can sell
as much as it wants at the market
price so for the competitive firm March
revenue is just
price but for the monopis that's not
true by to sell more it has to lower the
price okay so we can graph a monopolis
marginal revenue curve and we'll do that
in figure 113 so let's go through the
math here let's do an
example imagine we have an example where
demand is described by the equation Q =
24 minus P just a standard well- behaved
demand equation you know how to derive
that from utility okay imagine that's
the demand
equation well the first step to solve a
monopoly problem is let's rewrite this
as P equal 24 minus Q makes the math a
little
easier and now let's multiply both sides
by Q to make it a revenue equation so
Revenue which is p * Q = 24 Q - Q ^2
that's the revenue that the firm earns
it's p which comes from demand times the
amount of units sold differentiating
this marginal revenue is 24 minus 2
Q that's the marginal revenue curve for
that firm and you can see this in figure
113 here we graph the demain curve
that's the Blue Line the demand curve is
just a standard demand curve where you
can have 24 units per day at a price of
zero and you want zero units per day at
a price of
24 okay and then the the marginal
revenue curve is everywhere below the
demand curve it has the same
intersection on the y- axis but it's
everywhere below the demand curve is the
marginal revenue curve now um the fact
that the margin Ry curve starts at the
same Y intercept is not General it's
only because this is linear in a
nonlinear case the margin Ry curve can
start at a different Y intercept but the
fact that margin revenue is everywhere
below demand is
General margin revenue is always below
demand okay because of this poisoning
effect Marg revenue is always below uh
demand okay questions about that this is
not a simple intuition so questions
about how this works
okay well arm with that let's talk about
how monopolis maximize profits let's go
to figure 114 figure
114 I'm going to now add a cost function
let me say that
C equals I'm just going to assume C
equals 12 plus
q^2 I'm just making just once again you
know how to derive that if I gave you
production function input prices you
could derive that okay but I'm just
going to assume Cal 12+ q^2 so in that
case
what do we know we can draft we can
graph the marginal cost marginal cost is
just 2 Q right that's the marginal cost
line in figure 114 marginal cost is 2 Q
we can graph average total cost average
variable cost and average fixed cost
those are all things we learned to graph
before we can put those all in the
graph okay now we can solve for the
Monopoly profit maximizing decision
remember profit maximization always
happens regardless of Market
structure profit maximization happens
when marginal revenue equals marginal
cost right remember just to remind you
profits equals Revenue Minus cost so to
maximize this we say marginal revenue uh
minus marginal cost equals zero that's
how we maximize profits right so if
profits is revenue Minus cost and
profits are maximized or marginal rumiz
marginal cost equals zero so the profit
maximizing condition is marginal revenue
equals marginal
cost okay that's true with any Market
structure margin re that's always profit
maximizing well what's marginal marginal
revenue here is 24 minus 2
Q marginal cost is 2 Q oh I should have
made this a big Q well it doesn't matter
right because little Q is Big q but to
make life easier let's make that a big
Q so what this says is that
qar equal
six that the optimal Monopoly quantity
is
six and how did I do this once again not
too hard from the perspective of your
aome math skills I simply took the
demand curve created a revenue
equation differentiated that to get
marginal revenue have a cost equation
differentiate that to get marginal cost
set them equal and you get
qar that's all you got to do
okay now what is the
price I solve for Q but it's not obvious
here how you get back how do you get
price so what's what's what's what price
does the monopolis set
yeah why
18 exactly so you skip the usual thing
where someone gives the wrong answer
okay people often say well look Mar cost
equals marginal revenue the quantity six
and the price is
12 that's the typical answer you say
well look if marginal cost equals
marginal revenue it's six then you go
over to the y- axis and it's 12 and why
is that wrong that's wrong because the
monopolis still has to respect the
demand curve anopolis cannot charge a
price that people aren't willing to
pay okay at a price of 12 that on on the
demand curve people want way more at a
price of 12 to be on the demand could to
get to price we go back to the demand
equation Q = 20 P = 24 minus Q well I
just solved for qar so P
staral 24 minus
qar equals
18 and this is where people get screwed
up in the math here okay remember the
monopolis has to respect the demand
curve they're a price taker price maker
I'm sorry but a price maker within the
constraints the market gives them and
the constraint the market gives them is
the demain
curve so basic so the the the um profit
maximizing point is a price of 18 and
selling six units and you could see at
that point what are their profits well
the profits are price minus average cost
well at six units average cost is
eight so they are making 10 per
unit times six units is 60 and that's
their profits
now you might say
gee consumers are willing to buy a lot
more units think about think about the
seventh
unit say the seventh unit well this is
what's weird to me if you look at the
seventh unit demand is above
cost consumer's willingness to
pay at the seventh unit is seven I'm
sorry 17 right if you had a price if you
had a price of seven
uh I'm sorry if you want to sell seven
units consumer willing to pay
17 and what's the marginal cost at seven
units well it's
14 so this is weird marginal revenue I'm
sorry
price exceeds marginal cost so why don't
they produce that seventh unit because
of the poisoning
effect to produce that seventh unit
they'd have to lower the price to 17 to
sell it not to to produce it to sell it
lower price 17 they lower price 17 they
make less money on the first six
units indeed what are their profits if
they sell seven well if they sell seven
units what are their profits well they
sell seven units profits equal seven
units at a price of 17 minus costs what
are their costs if they're producing
seventh units well it's 12 + 7 squared
so it's 12 + 7 squared uh so that's uh
12 +
49 and if you do the math you get
profits are
58 they get lower profits selling seven
units this is crazy think about this we
have units where people are willing to
pay more than it costs to produce and
yet to sell them monopolis will actually
lower their
profits That's The Power of this
poisoning effect effect the reason lower
their profits because they they can make
more money by selling less at a higher
price
yeah what I said they can't do that I
just ruled that out we're going to come
back to that but that's the key is don't
the way I describe it is the way you
think of the decision- making don't
think of them saying I'm gon to set this
for this just think I want to sell X
units what do I have to charge so
they're sitting back saying how many
units should I produce well if I produce
six I can sell for 18 I make 60 if I
produce seven I sell for 17 I make 58
I'm going to produce six that's the way
they think about it okay so that is the
power here now what does this
mean this means that monopolists because
they can set price have something we
call Market
power monopolists have Market power what
do I mean by
that market power means that basically
monopolists can make money even in the
long run to see this let's think about
um the marginal revenue expression so
marginal
revenue okay marginal
revenue equals
p+ DP DQ * Q
now take that
equation and multip and take the uh
second term and multiply and divide by
price so I want to take the second term
I want to rewrite as P
plus
DP
DQ time Q over P * p i just multiply and
divide it by
price it's all I
did can anyone tell
me what this term looks
like
yeah the elasticity of demand but
inverted this is the inverse of price
elicity demand so I can rewrite marginal
revenue I can rewrite marginal
revenue as P * 1 + one over the
elasticity of
demand okay all I did no trick here I
just well there's a little math trick
rote margin Revenue multiply and divide
the second term by P kept the first
term then realize this is the inverse
the elasticity of demand so I can write
margin Revenue as P * 1 plus the inverse
the elasticity of
demand okay why is this
important because what this says is the
amount the ability of monopolis to make
money depends on how elastic is the
demand they
face okay so what would happen here if
the elasticity demand was negative
Infinity what would marginal revenue
be if the is negative Infinity what
marginal revenue
be come on you guys your MIT students
don't be shy raise your
hand yeah P what does that sound like
margin REM equals P we've heard that
before that's the perfectly competitive
case well perfectly competitive case
firms face perfectly elastic demand so
if demand in the market was perfectly
elastic monopolis would behave just like
perfectly competitive
firms okay on the other hand as the
elasticity Falls or Rises or Falls at
absolute value but rises from Nega 50
towards zero monopolists start to be
able to charge more than monopolis start
tab marginal revenue above the
price okay monopolis start tab marginal
revenue above the price okay so we can
rewrite this let's rewrite the condition
for profit maximization profit
maximization is that marginal revenue
which equals P * 1 + 1 over the Allis
demand equals marginal
cost okay that's our profit maximizing
condition okay so in other words we can
write that marginal cost over price
equals
1 + 1
Epsilon marginal cost over price equals
1 plus uh 1 plus 1 over Epsilon now
let's define something I'm going to call
the
markup the markup is how much more
monopolis can charge in perfectly
competitive firms I'm going to find the
markup as P minus MC over P that's what
we call the
markup that is how much more can
monopolis charge than competitive firms
it's the markup well the answer is equal
to if we do the math the answer is equal
to minus one over the elasticity of
demand if you do the math the markup is
minus one over thees demand in other
words the profits monopolis can make are
inversely proportional to the elasticity
of
demand why does that make
sense why does it makes sense that the
elastic demand as markets get more in
elastic monopolis make more money as
markets get more elastic monopolis make
less
money why does that make
sense
yeah yeah insulin the perfectly in
elastic
good exactly you have to buy it so given
that they can charge ever the hell they
want this is the answer to the question
you might have first thought or some
might think is well gee if a firm's a
monopoly why don't they just charge
whatever they want why do monopolists
have to with they're price makers
they're the only game in town why don't
they just charge whatever the hell they
want and the answer is because while
people can't substitute to other firms
they can substitute to other
Goods so if it's a good if you're
monopolizing a good with there's very
good substitutes and you try to charge a
very high price they'll just switch to
the The
Substitute so if the elastic demand is
very large a large negative number they
can't make much profit sure they're the
only firm but if they're the only firm
making spearmint gum and people are
pretty different between spearmint gum
and peppermint gum they can't charge
outrageously high prices because people
just switch to peppermint gum but if
they're the only firm making insulin
then they can charge an outrageously
high price because there's nowhere to
go so the money monopolis make monopolis
in a perfect competitive market firms
are disciplined by competition from
other firms in a monopoly Market firms
are disciplined only by the elasticity
of demand that's the only disciplining
effect on the
firm okay so let's do a simple example
two books you guys probably had to read
in high school Huckleberry thin and
Fahrenheit
451 if you go on Amazon right now you
can get Huckleberry fin for about four
bucks in paperback or zero on
Kindle uh fahren 451 is about n bucks
and about the same on
Kindle why they're both twoo old books
people have to basically read them about
the same they're all high school
required books the marginal cost of
production can't be that
different of producing Fahrenheit for
they're they're slightly different
lengths but not that different certainly
un Kindle the marginal cost of
Productions comparable so why why is
Fahrenheit 451 so much more expensive
than Huckleberry Finn
do anyone
know go ahead you have an idea any
thoughts okay well the reason is because
in the US oh yeah go
ahead exactly in the US we have
something called copyright laws which
say that for 75 years after the author's
death only the author or his estate or
her estate can approve production of the
book which gives them a monopoly Mark
Twain died more than 75 years ago Ray
Bradberry did not so as a result there's
no more Monopoly anybody with a printing
press or whatever it is to make an ebook
I don't know how you do that can make a
copy Huckleberry
Finn so it's perfectly
competitive okay and so profits get
driven to zero but fite 451 they still
have a monopoly right so they're making
profits now why is 451 everyone has to
read Fahrenheit 451 why don't they
charge a 100 bucks because then high
schools say you know what Fahrenheit 451
is fine but you know there's other ones
that are okay
too so there's some eless this demand
disciplining the market for Fahrenheit
451 but it's not as much as disciplin
the market for Huckleberry fin okay
questions about
that okay let's go on then and talk
about the welfare effects of Monopoly
because now we have the tools in this
class to move Beyond positive economics
talk about normative
economics and we have the tools to show
you that Monopoly causes our first
example what we call a market
failure let's look at figure
115 back to the example we used the
domain curve is 24 minus Q the marginal
cost is 2 Q same example we were just
using the monopolis sells six units at a
price of
18 okay the competitive
equilibrium would be eight units at a
price of
16 how do we know this well we just said
price equal the marginal cost marginal
cost equals 2 Q so that would be true at
qal 8 p equal 16 we all could see it
from the intersection the demand Supply
curves so the competitive case they sell
eight units at a price of 16 the
Monopoly case they sell six units at a
price of
18 what is the consumer surplus in the
competitive case what letters represent
the consumer surplus in the competitive
case at Point
EC don't raise their hand and tell
me come on guys help me out here yeah
loud
loud a plus b plus
C same person what's the producer
Surplus in competitive
case D plus e now now in the Monopoly
case what has happened to consumer
surplus it has fallen from a plus b plus
C to just a so consumer
surplus from the competitive case to
Monopoly case has gone from a plus b
plus C to just
a what about producer Surplus producer
Surplus in the competitive
case was just D plus e well now what is
it well they lose
e but they gain
B so what's happened is two things we
have
transferred area B from consumers to
producers remember that's sort of we
don't care from that in the total social
welfare framework we just care about the
sum producer consumer surplus we don't
care who has it so that transfer is not
important not consequential what's
consequential is we've created a dead
weight
loss of of
c+e we've created a dead weight loss of
c+e there's an inefficiency why because
there are trades that would make Society
better off that are not happening
remember if we went if we sold that
seventh
unit could the benefit of that unit to
Consumers exceeds the cost of producing
it therefore society's better off if
it's sold but it's not being sold
because this poisoning effect so
Monopoly has created a dead weight loss
and the first example the dead weight
loss and
Monopoly is the first example of what we
call in this class a
market
failure when I did welfare the last
couple lectures the only thing that
caused de loss was the government
screwing things up as long as you left
the market rip you got the perfectly
efficient outcome well here we're
letting the market rip and not getting
the perfectly efficient outcome now I'll
stop right there this does not imply
government can make things better we'll
talk about that next time all I'm saying
here is a simpler statement which is
unlike the perfectly competitive case if
you let the market rip you get an
inefficient
outcome that's a fundamental change
that's a fundamental challenge to
everything we've learned so far it
doesn't come from any magic or any
government intervention it's just the
way monopolis make
decisions okay so because monopolis
don't want to lower the price because
that's not profit maximizing we end up
not selling units that and that would
make Society better off so the private
incentives put another way the positive
and normative outcomes don't don't align
with the competitive market the positive
outcome was no profits that was also the
welfare maximizing outcome in a monopoly
case the private
outcome is different than the social
welfare maximizing outcome and that lead
leads to a market failure questions
about
that okay
now this raises the natural question
which was raised here and which has been
on your mind the whole time which is why
do monopolis have to charge just one
price what loss is that no firm charge
is just one price firms charge different
prices for different sorts of things you
know for different and we'll come to
some examples so what if we move to the
more realistic case where monopolist can
price
discriminate what if monopolis could
charge different prices for different
quantities well in fact what would
happen let's go to the extreme of
perfect price
discrimination Perfect Right
discrimination is a magag monopolist
could go to Every
individual figure out what their
willingness to pay was and charge them
that
amount that'd be perfectly price
discriminating monopolis they would
charge every person their own individual
price and that price will correspond to
their willingness to
pay what would that lead to that would
lead to figure
116 the first person person
one they are willing to pay that entire
um uh trapezoid that'll be to the left
of unit one they only pay a lot so you
charge them a lot all the way down to
the eighth person you charge them what
they're willing to pay which is 16
charge the eighth person 16 the seventh
person 17 the sixth person 18 and so on
why would you want to do
that well now what has happened to
consumer surplus someone raise their
hand and tell me yeah zero why is
consumer surplus
zero exactly consumer surplus is the
benefit you get from valuing something
above its price that's gone they're
charging you what you're willing to pay
so by definition there's no consumer
surplus so all the rest is producer
Surplus so the firm has converted the
entire Surplus to producer Surplus by
Perfect price
discrimination what else is notable in
this case with per price discrimination
firms will sell eight units so what else
is notable no dead weight
loss a perfectly priced discriminating
firm creates no dead weight loss why
because there's no poisoning effect the
poisoning effect comes from the fact
that if I want to sell more units I got
to lower my price well here I don't have
to lower my price to sell more units
given that I might as well sell as many
units as people are willing to pay for
that are above my cost so I might as
well do the welfare maximizing thing
which is sell 8
units this is the first inclination that
we have to car care about fairness in
economics because what this says what
the existing course would teach you so
far is I'm completely
indifferent between the perfectly
competitive case as illustrated by EC
above where consumers get a plus b plus
C I'm indifferent between that case and
the perfect price discrimination case
that is I'm indifferent between whether
consumer's
gift okay I'm completely indifferent all
I care about is the total right it's the
sum that can't make sense right it can't
make sense that I'm completely different
in a world where producers have
everything and where consumers have some
producers have some there's no way that
anyone would be truly indifferent in
those worlds and that's the first hint
that in economics we have to care about
fairness we have to not just care about
the total sum of social surplus but who
gets
what okay and we're going to come back
to that later for now we'll stick with
our definition we're just care about the
total but this is sort of the hint of
why we need to come back to
that okay so that is what would happen
with perfect price discrimination now in
fact okay um firms can't perfectly price
discriminate in fact firms can't go and
get your willingness to pay so in
reality what do firms do well they price
discriminate by trying to guess who is
more price
sensitive firms engage in price
discrimination and the way they do it is
they look for correlates of
Epsilon you you basically if you're a
monopolist you want to charge a higher
price to a low Epsilon guy and a low
remember guys gender neutral term and a
lower price to a high Epsilon guy so
basically if I knew everyone's Epsilon
I'd be done but I don't so what I do is
I look for signals that are correlated
with your
Epsilon so for
example airlines charge more if you buy
at the last minute
that if you buy four months in
advance why it's the same seat same
produ same marginal cost to flying on
the plane
yeah yeah if you buy the last you
clearly got to go okay you're a business
person's got a last minute meeting
you've gotta you've got to love one
who's sick who's got you got to go see
Etc if you buy four months in advance
you're clearly shopping you have lots of
options but if you're buying the last
minute you don't have a lot of options
now I can't charge you infinity because
as other airlines you could fly but
clearly you are less price sensitive if
you're buying at the last minute than if
you're buying four months in
advance that's one example okay why do
movie theaters charge less for Maes than
movies at night why do movie theaters
charge less when you go during the day
it's the same marginal cost again same
popcorn cost same projector costs why do
movie theaters charge less when you go
during the day
yeah well lower Demand by itself is not
necessarily the answer it's really about
elasticity of demand why are people less
price sensitive during the why are
people more price sensitive during the
day than at
night think about who goes to the movies
during the
day yeah mean people are like retirees
and things which have plenty of time in
their hands if you go to the movie at
night it's like you're done with work
you got to go at night you can't you
know maybe you decide between the 7
o'clock showing the 11:00 showing but
the bottom line is there's one time you
can go if you're going during the day
you've shown you have lots of time to go
see movies you can go at night you can
go during the day so anybody who goes to
movie during the day unless they work a
weird shift okay has basically shown
that they have more flexibility on when
they go to the
movie as a result you charge them a
lower
price this is everywhere you look all of
a sudden I've opened up to you a world
of understanding why price are
differentiated okay remember we
discussed this a long time ago we talked
about why the incremental large
drink at McDonald's the incremental cost
of a large drink is Tri is very small
compared to the cost of a small drink
because there's different elas demand
for the small drink and and the
incremental to the large drink so
everywhere you look when you go out in
the real world now look at prices you'll
see this firms pricing to try to Target
the lower prices to the most elastic
consumers
okay now perhaps the best example of
this was a example a few years ago with
Tesla Tesla sells electric cars you know
and the original model S could go for
250 miles on a battery charge what they
said is we are going to offer a cheaper
Model S that can only go about half as
far about 125 150 miles per per battery
charge so you can buy the more expensive
one because it's got this fancier
battery 250 miles you can go it cost
more money or the less expensive one
with a less expens less fancy battery it
only go 150
mil well um in September 2017 there was
a huge hurricane in Florida and people
had to evacuate and Tesla understood
that the limits on how far you could
drive Florida's a big state could get in
the way of people
evacuating so Tesla said you know what
all cars can now go 250 miles on their
battery people like what the what do you
mean we can go 250 miles in the battery
well turn out it's the same battery they
just had a piece of code that limited
how far you could go in the cheaper car
why would they do that why would they
literally have the same battery and
literally add money to add code to limit
how far you could go why' they do
that yeah
exactly there's two types of people
people who have a lot of money and are
willing to pay for a better car people
don't a lot of money not willing to pay
for a better car if they just simply
said we're going to sell Modelo 250
miles a bunch of lower income people
wouldn't have bought it if they said
we're going to let everyone go 250 miles
on a cheaper price then they wouldn't
have made as much money so they said a
high price for a premium product to grab
all the low elasticity consumers and a
lower price for a less premium product
to grab the high elasticity consumers
even though the products were the same
this actually uh Tesla is not Al loness
when IBM first created the the uh uh
digital
printer uh it uh said had a home version
which was much less efficient than the
office version and it turned out someone
took them apart and it was the same
printer there's added crap to the motor
on the home version to make it go
slower okay because they want to take
that same Advantage they want to be able
to charge a lot for the office one
because people are less price elastic in
the office okay turns out you could take
this too far Amazon tried to go further
with this Amazon actually tried to set
prices by IP
address so Amazon literally an exercise
where literally they would differentiate
the price you'd see online by your IP
address why would they do
that why would they be once again
regardless of your feelings about Jeff
Bezos why would they do that why would
they differentiate the price
yeah yeah but how would they know by
your IP
address what's
that P sales is one reason what else
yeah your ZIP code that's another
reason what else who's willing to pay a
lot yeah what's that yeah basically if
you're ordering from Goldman Sachs IP
address they're like you're rich we're
going to charge you a lot if you're
ordering from some you know homeless
shelter or some place people don't have
any money they'll charge you less so
basically they said we've got a great IP
address is a great signal of willingness
to pay will suck up all that consumer
surplus by varying the price by
willingness to pay they got busted and
couldn't do it
anymore uh they were told they couldn't
do that now it's not clear why not uh in
fact the reason why not you might say
well look why shouldn't they do that
they're increasing efficiency if they
don't do that we're losing C plus e by
doing that we're gaining efficiency
they're selling more units they wouldn't
have sold those low-income consumers
Tesla wouldn't have sold those cheaper
model X's or whatever they were so
what's wrong with that and the answer is
in a tral economics world nothing TR
economics world we should have let Tesla
do that we should have let IBM make the
crappy home printer we should have let
Amazon differentiate by IP address the
reason we didn't speaks the fact that
people don't think consumer producer
Surplus are really valed equally that we
care about both separately and that's
what we'll start talking about more in a
few lectures okay questions about that
all right uh we'll come back on
Wednesday do a second Monopoly lecture
you're responsible for the lectures this
week on the midterm Monday's lecture
will go on a new topic which is not in
the midterm but it's on the final so you
don't want to miss it plus it involves
allop which is fun