Hi, my name is Ally Bowman and I work
here in the admissions office at MIT
Sloan.
The MIT Sloan Min program was launched
in 2008 at the height of the financial
crisis. The program was designed to
empower the future leaders of the
finance field in a time that we really
needed strong leaders. If you enter the
MININ program, you will be able to learn
from faculty that are at the height of
the finance field. They are experienced
and knowledgeable and they are looking
to share that knowledge with you.
The EMP program is geared towards early
career professionals. We are looking for
candidates that are knowledgeable about
and passionate about a career in
finance. That being said, you don't have
to have a professional background in
finance in order to be eligible for the
program. Um again while passion and
knowledge about finance field is um
beneficial you don't have to have
professional work or internship
experience in order to be eligible for
the Emp
GMAT or GRE scores are optional.
However, we do strongly encourage
students to include their scores if they
have them. The more data that we can
know about you, the better. And so if
you do have those test scores, we
strongly encourage you to include that
on the application.