All
right. I want to welcome Stfan Andrev uh
as guest lecture today. He has been a
significant part of this course over the
past I think 11 years. Is that right,
Stefan?
A long a long period and
>> count that far
>> partly because his uh lectures are the
most popular in the course and we really
are glad to have him come back again.
His background um is very interesting.
He has a PhD in chemical physics from
Harvard and he has worked at the top
firms on Wall Street. Morgan Stanley
Cedell
and now to Sigma. So he's a really great
person to uh share his expertise with
us. So thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you. Thank you guys. Um
very nice to to meet you all. Big class
big class this year. That's exciting. Um
I like I I'll start with this before
everybody gets gets tired. But I wanted
to say that like I we're going to talk
about principal component analysis today
and the
some of the main things I want you to
take away from this are this is a
absolutely core data science tool in
finance. That's number one. Number two,
it's great to like this kind of stuff
you only learn by doing it. So doing
like actually doing some kind of project
that where you use this toolkit
is um is like essential for you to kind
of relearn it.
And um three if you ever want to get a
job in finance like I think having
having like some experience having like
done a project with this and having some
familiarity with what this is about
might help you during interviews quite a
bit. Um we're going to have lectures the
slides are minute we're going to have
some the slides are on the web on the
classroom website.
In addition to that there is um there is
a notebook and a Jupyter notebook and a
data set that I've used to prepare these
slides to at least the first the first
example we're going to talk about.
I've um like I think that that's like
that's a great reference if you ever
want to like like see how you actually
like how this stuff gets computed and if
you want to do a final or like a project
final project in the class. Um
it would be something like that notebook
but like a little more elaborate. So it
gives you like a little bit of a flavor
of what the starting point and uh what
you know what the project would be like.
Probably would be a little a little more
extensive than than what we're talking
about here, but but um like in the same
same spirit.
So yeah, that's so now that we got this
over with like we're g let's talk about
like what is PCA and where where does it
fit within the world of um machine
learning algorithms
and it's it's basically um it's it's a
un method for unsupervised learn
learning. So it's it basically a method
to cluster reduce dimensional
dimensionality to make sense of the
data.
It it's not it doesn't
it doesn't necessar it's not a
regression so it doesn't like there's no
causality implied when you use PCA but
it is it's uh yeah it's a way to
understand data better especially data
that has a lot of dimensions where
things are like many many of those
dimensions are highly correlated
here we have I've listed a bunch of
examples of where PCA can be applied
generally really
it's it's widely applied in large data
sets, multi-dimensional data, like a lot
of data. Um it's mostly like the actual
the actual calculations are mostly
linear algebra. So it's efficient and
fast and scalable. So and this is one of
the reasons people generally like to
to use it. I'm not going to go through
all of these, but like it's it's very
it's their applications are very widely
they widely across across science and
and in finance it's used like very
extensively as well.
Okay. So first thing I wanted to talk
about is like kind of go through a
visual example
of um these are some of these things
that I'm going to talk about are like my
mental toy models to understand that I
always refer to when I think about what
is happening when I'm using PCA.
In this example, uh do you guys see?
Well, okay, good. In this example, I've
prepared effectively
three data sets, but they're really like
one data set. Like it's one I've I've
just made this up, right? It's just one
it's like one dimensional data set. And
all I've done is I've taken this
onedimensional data set and
um I've made it two dimensional by just
adding an extra coordinate like the blue
line the extra coordinate y I made zero
and then I took this data set and I just
like rotated it like 45 degrees and 90
degrees. And in the in this two
dimensional world like it's it's two
each point has two coordinates. So it
looks like it's two dimensional, but I
know it's like it's onedimensional
because I I made it. And and the key
thing that that PCA would do is like is
PCA kind of would immediately tell you
when it looks at this data that it's
actually onedimensional.
If just by like you download the data,
you do the calculations, it's going to
be onedimensional. So how how would it
work? Um,
PCA basically you can think of PCA as
like a as a as a way to rotate the
coordinate system. And
we basically when when you apply PCA to
this it will tell you if you apply to
the blue blue data it will tell you that
the PC1 the first principal component
you guys have done uh Peter you guys
have done the math part already right of
PCA. Yeah. So the first principal
component is going to be the x
direction. When you do the the red line,
it's going to tell you that it's like
the the one one direction and and it's
going to just discover this this um
this dimensionality. And okay, the first
data set was like very very simple, but
there was no is purely onedimensional.
This one here is like kind of the same
thing, but I've added a little bit of
noise in in the other dimension.
And um now when I apply PCA to this,
it's going to tell me basically the same
thing. PC1 is going to be the same, but
PC2 is is going to have a little bit of
variance along PC2 along the
perpendicular direction. So in both of
these cases A and B, it will tell me
that PC1 and PC2 vectors are the same.
And it's what's going to be different is
the there's going to be zero variance in
case of B on the PC2 direction and a
little bit of variance in in in the
first in the in the example A
along the PC2 direction.
So it basically tells us the two thing
it tells us like the directions along
which the data is concentrated and the
variance or the how important that
direction is on a relative basis.
We can generally what's nice about this
like I've done this two-dimensional
plots but PCA like when you actually do
it it's just linear algebra and you can
do it on you can do it on any number of
dimensions you can do it on um yeah it
so when you have high dimensionality
this is a very robust and powerful tool
what's what's really nice about that and
the high dimensionality is like it's
it's not a minimization, it's not an
optimization, it's just a linear algebra
calculation and it's fast. So you can
you can process very large amounts of
data very quickly.
Like a very common
like when you use this in practice
like the answers that you get from like
the things you kind of learn from PCA
are going to be
it tells you like a relationship between
variables. Like in our first example, if
you look at this diagonal line, it's
going to tell you that like it's
basically like y equals x is kind of the
line, right? And then you can you can
think, well, I can discover the same
thing if I run a regression y regress y
on x and and then it's going to tell me
pretty much like the same if I if I look
at my diagonal line, it's going to tell
me the same thing.
And that that is true in the
one-dimensional example. But I wanted to
kind of give an illustration of what is
the difference between regression and
and PCA. And the difference is like the
PCA is is kind of um
it's remember it's it's unsupervised
learning. So there's no causality
implied. So X and Y are kind of on the
same footing.
Each dimension is on the same footing.
There's no special dimension that's
dependent and one that is independent.
So when you regress, this is like the
same data set and you can see here the
regression of Y versus X, the regression
of X versus Y and the PC1 line, they're
they're similar. They're not but they're
not the same. it it like it's actually
optimizing it's minimizing the distance
to the line but like in a in a
in a like this is this is like
minimizing the distance in the
perpendicular direction and the others
are minimizing distance in the
independent variable direction so when
you do a regression so it's not exactly
the same I think it's good to keep that
in mind because sometimes
if you really want to understand how
you know like given an observation X how
I should model I maybe PCA is not the
right approach maybe you should run a
regression
but like if you want to understand the
the correlation structure of X and Y of
two variables there there is no you
don't have necessarily one depends on
the other you don't know anything about
their relationship then then PCA is
probably a more appropriate tool
um yeah so I was just saying like if
there's there's some data that is in
some like if data is like in a
particular line PC1 which is the red
direction here would always discover
where that direction is and if you
actually map the the data into like PC
coordinates it's just going to look like
a straight line like that and a couple
of things that I like about this example
is like you can you can see how rotating
this data set doesn't doesn't change the
PC coordinate output so it look it's it
finds a direction appropriately The
second thing that's very important is
robustness. In the real world, like when
you do, it could be in science or in
finance,
you're not going to have perfect data.
Everything is very noisy. Noise is a
huge problem. And robustness to data
noise is very important. So this kind of
illustrates how robust things are. So if
if I if I take one point and I just move
it around
my um you can see that my the red the
red line which is the the direction of
my PC1 doesn't it's like it's quite
robust
it's quite robust to to to noise in to
one particular if everything else is
aligned like just moving around one data
is it doesn't really change things too
much um if I make them a little bit more
spread
It's it's a little less robust, but it's
still still pretty robust, right? And
the thing that I wanted to kind of say
like what happen people are just going
to very often you just take some data
and you just shove it into PCA and you
don't actually care too much before you
even know what the data is and you just
put it into PCA and PCA always gives you
something. But suppose the data doesn't
really have a dominant direction
then the PCA algorithm becomes not
robust. So you can see now look I'm
moving one data and look what happening
to the coordinate one data point is I
can just move that a little bit and like
it's just completely giving me the
output is like super sensitive to to any
noise in the data. So it's kind of
worthless.
So it's very important when we're
looking at the data
if we don't really know what this data
kind of looks like very sometimes it's
high dimensional you can't even really
visualize it you have to think how do I
understand whether there is actual
structure in the data that I'm trying to
discover this will help me discover
quantify the structure but it's also
good to understand qualitatively how
much the structure is um
one thing that is that PCA also like
part of the PCI analysis and the output.
Yes. Do you have any like tool for like
wiggling around the points to see how
how robust it is to see if the data is
actually alive or not?
Well, um it's
no but what it's not I don't have like
you can write tools to do that but like
I think what you want like one thing
that you can do that is very important
is to kind of when you do your PCI
analysis is to look at the en values
because people very often people like
look at the vectors and like oh these
are my directions and I'm going to
project things and I'm going to assume
everything is like factorized nicely
and like we don't really look as much at
the values but it's very important to
look at the values and the reason is
that in this example when there's no
dominant direction the values which
measure the variance along each
direction would be very similar. So when
you look at when you're look using a a
principal component like the first
principal component you want to make
sure that your the value of that
component you're using is is like quite
distinct from the rest of the values
in finance we'll see later like we're
dealing with a time series of PCA like
every day you construct the PCA model so
everything anything that's a number here
like a value is actually a time series
of value so the thing I look at a when
I'm doing analysis is I look at value
plots in log space and I want to see
that each distinct
component that I use ideally you want to
see it that it's like an order of
magnitude different than the next one in
in variance variance invariance
basically which if that's true like
that's great and that actually and that
doesn't always happen but at least you
want it to be like visually you want it
to be distinct You want it to be like
different. You don't want if you if you
have a time series of things, you don't
want like the first and the second one
to cross. And if that's happening, then
the first and second principal component
if they're if the values are small
changes are causing them to switch
places, this basically means there isn't
a lot of structure and the PC output is
noisy and it's actually going to
obiscate rather than clarify the thing
you're looking at. I've put here like a
little bit of math notation. You guys
have um done your math lecture on PCA.
So, we can be relatively quick here. But
I do want to go through it. The the main
thing is like you have um your we have
your data data matrix is generally like
there's
n observations in pd dimensions and we
think of that as a matrix and then uh if
this matrix is x then uh everyday's
observation are vectors of size p
and then you have a coarian matrix which
is xt * x
and um
um
the
and then like there is I I've here like
defined the the W K or the orthonormals
vectors representing the these are the
vectors W K and then I've written down
the math of how you do the projection of
data onto principal components
and um and how you compute the variance.
How do you get these vectors? Well,
there is
you could you could do you could take
your data compute coariance matrix feed
it into an veg value calculator which is
basically in in the in my work
our data is not really the number of
dimensions is not actually that high. So
that that's pretty that's okay. it does
kill
as um like that thing is
potentially maybe a little bit slow but
it's not actually that slow. There is
also a more efficient method called SVD
um single singular value composition
where you can just compute your
projections without calculating the
coariance matrix. I like to compute the
coarian matrix because we generally need
to compute the coarian matrix for other
things in any case. So if you have it
already then then it's then it's um you
might as well use it.
Some there's some I've listed here some
properties of this vector matrix that
are important that it's orthonormal
which means that it's the transpose of
the vector matrix is kind of also
inverse.
The coariance matrix is can be written
as the in this in this form where lambda
is the igen value matrix that's the svd
de composition that there's total
variance quantity you can think about
like which is the variance of x which is
just the trace of lambda so like the
product of ien values is the variance of
your data set
and there is something called percent
variance explained
which is just defined as how much
variance is is um along a particular PC
direction divided by the total variance.
So that adds up to 100%.
Like when you're and um but that's very
useful because remember how I was saying
you want to look at the values to
understand
how important each direction is.
Variance explained tells you that as a
kind of a number you want to look at.
You want to when you when you're trying
to model your data set with as few
dimensions as possible, you want to kind
of add more PC directions until you get
to a relatively high variance explain.
If you're able to explain
um if you have like a 10 dimensional
data set and you're able to explain
80% of it using three dimensions, that's
a pretty that's a pretty big win.
And I've also like written out this out
of sample variance explained or very
often what we do is we we calculate a
PCA we calibrated on historical data and
then we apply it to future data
that um we're trying to model like
trying to model what will happen in the
future and especially in finance we do
that. So when when the data you're cal
calibrating your your um PCA on is
different than than the other data then
this
you hope that the structure of the two
data sets are the same. So if if the
structure is the same you'll get the
same kind of variance explained
structure but to the extent that is not
true you you may not. So you may see
that um your dominance of certain PC1
factor becomes like it starts to explain
less variance as you as your um out of
sample data becomes more different from
the the data which you calibrate. So
this is a little bit of like the
modeling art of it where
you're going to be using some data to to
calibrate a model and then going to
you're going to use this to to um
predict the variance the correlation
structure of what hap what happens in
the future like future market moves or
future returns.
Okay. So um
a typical how do we like what do we
generally do when we apply PCA? We we're
going to take our data set we're going
to demean it and then maybe we're going
to normalize the variance to one. Like
when I say maybe and the reason this
maybe is like sometimes you want to do
that and sometimes you don't.
It's um
very often whether you want to do that
or not depends on
how exactly you're going to use your uh
PC factors and uh your your dimension
your dimensions. Generally I would say
that most of the time you you want to
normalize it in in a in a certain you
you want to normalize in a way that you
want the expected at least the expected
variance along different along your
dimensions to be unit to be similar.
Then you're going to compute your
coariance matrix and calculate the igen
values and then you're going to order
them by decreasing value.
Um and um and you're going to have like
a certain cut off where you say okay the
only the top I'm going to use only the
top X factors to model the the structure
of my data set.
>> Yeah.
>> So you say like maybe you would
normalize it. What would be like a
concrete example of like where it would
be better to not normalize it?
>> Um
well
here's an example.
So let let actually let yes I'll start
with this. So this is an example of like
it's a little bit of a toy example and
I'll talk about a real example. So in
this toy example there's the blue and
the red data set
and uh the red one looks that it's kind
of one-dimensional
and the blue looks like
it's just a blob. There's no direct
dimensionality. So when if I tell you
okay should we use PCA is there what is
PCA going to work on the blue data set
is going is it going to reduce
dimensionality and the answer will be no
no because it's there is no dominant
direction
and in the red one it definitely will it
will pick the right direction now what's
fun about these two examples is that
these two are the same data except I've
normal in the blue data set I've
normalized the variance along X and y
and in the red one I haven't.
So
if if I if these two dimensions were
you know like
I don't know temperature versus
um temperature in Seattle versus temp
in Atlanta or something. They're like
the kind of very distinct and generally
like different things where you're only
interested in correlation and the the
relative variance doesn't quite is not
very meaningful then you you would want
to normalize it because you're you're
that otherwise the units are not going
to be you want to have like somewhat
related units. So the units will be
standard deviations if you normalize it.
If you don't the units will be arbitrary
and they don't it wouldn't really make
sense.
On the other hand, if
um if this was like
if x- axis was your grades on quiz one
and y axis was your grades on quiz two,
these two are like the same units now.
And you you may not want to normalize.
You you want to actually like these
grades are these numbers are meaningful
relative to each other. So there's no
necessarily like you want to actually
model
the actual grades including the the
variance of quiz one and quiz two. So
there is no necessarily need to
normalize it.
>> That makes sense. Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's like that part is to be honest
that part is very much the art of
things. We've had a we have a lot of
discussion work. Are we normalizing it?
How are we normalizing it? What are we
using to normalize it? Like that's like
you'd be surp surprisingly this is
sometimes cutting edge research is to
actually understand how you normalize
it. It's that these are the things that
actually make a difference. The other
thing I mentioned is we need to demean
the data set. Why is that important?
Because remember the principle of
component analysis is a rotation. So it
it always rotates around zero zero. So
what zero is it matters a lot.
And this is two examples of the same
data set. These two blocks are the same
data set, but one is like not the mean
and the other is the means. So this one
here is centered at zero. And PCA
finds that there's a direction dominant
direction. It finds it. It works like
it's supposed to. This one here is not
centered at zero. Like for example,
let's say you do a bunch of stock
prices. Like you just put prices into
PCA.
Stock prices are not centered at zero.
They're always positive. So, it's going
to have some direction, but it's going
to be somewhere far away from zero. When
you run PCA on it, it's going to be like
it's going to try to rotate around zero,
but it's not it's like it can't find
anything because
it's not you're not like you can see why
like you can't rotate this thing. You
can't there's nothing to find if you
don't center it at zero.
You cannot rotate around it's rotating
always around the origin.
So
me mean that near zero or close to zero
or exactly zero is is very important
and surprising like it's surprising how
often comes up somebody just does PCA on
some
on some numbers that are just like large
positive numbers and like nothing comes
out and like ah this doesn't work but
you just have to normalize to zero. How
do we actually do it? Well um this is
just the examples of various places that
have implementations of this value
calculations. But I think when I started
doing this
um like 11 what I don't know how many
years ago this actually was more
relevant. Now it's like everybody uses
Python, everybody knows Jupyter
notebooks and like you guys um now now
it's like standard toolkit.
Okay. Now what's special about finance
when it comes to BCA?
It's mostly what is special about
finance. This is not exclusive by the
way, but like most of the time
we are going to be doing PCA on time
series
in in quantitative finance like in in
the quant world that I live in and I I
work in. I would say
it's our the general job is to discover
patterns in the that are that have
happened in the past and try to use that
information to model the future and to
somehow like it use that as part of your
toolkit to make predictions and to place
bets in the markets.
So every day, every every trading
session, every every observation is an
opportunity to bet and to make
predictions.
And you can understand like the thing
about time series is that the history
now and the history on the next
opportunity to bet is not that
different. Like it has one extra data
point maybe like later has an additional
data point, but everything else is the
same. So there is like there's a slow
changing time series of information and
what how we handle that there is a whole
time series
data science there class that one can
take but
in especially with regard to PCA
it's important to um to understand like
how what does what what
does impact does that time series aspect
of it have on PCA?
A couple of things I think are are
important. We
we generally are going to be interested
in in modeling the the changes of var of
things of variables like not the levels.
Part of that is that the thing I'm I was
just talking about which is demeaning.
And part of it is that when you make
bets in the market, you make money based
on how things change after your bet, not
the price, the absolute level of where
the price is at. So like returns are
what matters, not the price of
something, the absolute price.
Um then the next thing is like okay so
when we do when we model when we have
our data uh in finance like generally
the data is the historical returns or
histo history history of something
history of prices history of returns
history of anything of of whatever
you're modeling. It doesn't have to be
just prices could be could be any
anything that any any technical
indicator
and that means that every day there is a
there is a history that is similar but a
little different. So the history changes
your your information about what has
happened changes slowly
and that means that when you're looking
at your PCA you have to now define
how am I going to define my data matrix
which I'm using to calculate my vectors
and values and the one of the main
choices are how long of a history I want
to use and how much how do I weigh How
do I weight history? More recent history
versus further away history.
And this is these are some of the main
hyperparameters of principal component
analysis in finance.
How many things I'm I'm including in my
obser in my data data set.
How far back am I looking? How am I
waiting that those observations as I
pass through time?
And then the last thing is like the
robustness of the data.
Very often there is a trade-off between
including more data points
but each each marginal addition of data
like each marginal dimension of data
that I'm looking at could be less
robust. Like there's like and we'll talk
about in the examples later on, but
there's um we have to think carefully
about how
how robust the data we're putting in is
because if it's if it's too noisy, if
it's not representative of where our
bets are going to be, then it becomes
less relevant to our modeling down the
line. On the other hand, if we don't
include enough, we're also going to be
missing opportunities to to um
understand the structure, the
information. So again, that's part of
the art of of um of actually of the
practitioner is to actually kind of have
some feeling of have some intuition
about what I should include and what I
should not include. And we'll we'll talk
about an example here. The example first
example and the main example I want to
go through
is um applying principal component
analysis to the United States bond
market. Yes. I feel like you mentioned
that
PCA in this case time series
like historical historical but is there
you kind of play with the like
granularity of the time series as well
like the different um I guess window
sizes I would say of like how how
granular the date is going to be when
it's like
>> Yeah. Yeah. That that's another that's a
whole other dimension of how granular it
is. Absolutely right. It's not just
about how long of a history, but how
granular it is. Like
what like the examples I'm going to show
you right now
are based on daily observations.
But
why why did I decide to use daily
observations?
The short answer is like and we by the
way very often in in my work we use
daily observations. The reason is that
daily observations
are just a more available generally more
histories is high quality data history
is available for longer periods of time
for daily observations. Second
yes intraday observations are
they represent additional data.
However, the quality of
the quality of that data, meaning how
how much noise there is, can very often
in practice be much higher for interday
data than is for end of day data. That
might not always be true. There are
situations where that's not true, right?
But and there's there's entire fields in
finance that deal with high frequency
trading.
In those fields, end of day data is just
like they their whole trading buying,
holding and selling happens 10 times for
the entire day. So they start and end
the day with like no positions. And for
them daily is like not relevant. It's
too too slow. They need to understand
how the market moves on a very fast time
scale.
So that how how often like how you
sample time is a whole is a whole other
story. And basically how we sample time
is going to impact the units of
volatility because volatility is
measured in in units of square of time
basically. So it's it's very important
to like to know that and have to to to
understand to keep to keep that in mind
that whatever the frequency of sampling
is that's going to give you effectively
the unit of your volatility and then if
you want to annualize it like you need
to apply appropriate factors and
comparing volatilities of different
units is not going to be meaningful. So
that that's important.
Okay, going back to this example,
the um US bond market.
So why why am I like why is this an
interesting example? Like I work in
fixed income which is basically where we
trade
of
bonds and various derivatives of bonds
and those are the the biggest markets in
the world like the most there's huge
amounts of money being transferred.
They're not necessarily the most
volatile. Equities are much more
volatile, but they are extremely deep,
extremely liquid, and they also allow
like people who trade in them to take
large amounts of leverage. So even
though they're not by themselves that
volatile, if once you take leverage, you
can increase volatility by taking
leverage. So you can actually make um
you can construct portfolios that are
that are actually quite quite volatile
and deliver substantial um substantial
like market volatility and and returns.
So there's a lot of there's a lot of
huge industry of money managers, hedge
funds that trade fixed income and um the
US bond market is the kind of
prototypical example of fixed income.
It's the most liquid in the world by
far, the most well structured. So, it's
a great example to to play with.
Another reason I'm using it is because
there is pricing data from the Federal
Reserve that is freely available and
that's the data that we're going to use
right now to do our analysis.
this data is like it's it's actually
quite high quality data and um
yeah that like that's I think that um
if you want to do a project like this
will be a great great data set to play
with because it's real and um it's it's
goes on for a very long time and and you
can apply you can apply our PCA
techniques to it. So the first question
to ask is like is there remember like we
have our data set now what does it
consist of? Well, in the United States,
the US Treasury issues it just it issues
a bunch of T bills, short maturity bills
that they raise money. That's that's how
they raise money for the debt. But, uh,
the part we're going to concern with is
going to be the US Treasury notes and
bonds, which are kind of the longerdated
instruments that US Treasury issues.
They issue on a very regular basis.
Every month there is a schedule of
auctions that is very well known and
repetitive
and they always issue like a two-year
bond, a three-year bond, fiveyear bond,
seven-year bond, 10ear bond, and a
30-year bond. And there's actually now a
20-year bond that started about like
three, four years ago, but we're not
going to look at that right now because
it's it's fairly it's very new and it's
not not as liquid. So, we're just going
to focus on these.
And what are like the other thing about
these bonds is that they're
they're all debts of the US Treasury.
So, they're they're very in a sense
they're very similar. Like if you if you
if I give you money for six months and I
also give you a separate loan for like
three years,
I've I've given you two loans. The first
thing that these two things are they're
basically you still owe me money, right?
Yeah. one is longer in maturity than the
other, but like you're still wing money.
So, in terms of the way the price of
these of these securities evolves,
they're all kind of they all depend on
the interest rates, the short-term the
path of short-term interest rates of the
Federal Reserve and the expectations of
that path. So, that it's they're all
derivatives of that.
The implications of that is that the
returns or the um the changes of bond
yields are very highly correlated. So
here on the bottom right I've shown
the um
the the correlation matrix of changes
and you can see this is like these
numbers are very very high.
So this is a data set where
everything is very very highly
correlated
prime candidate for PCA. Whenever you
see a correlation matrix that has high
concentrations of high
high correlations prime candidate of
PCA. So what are these what are these
numbers I'm looking at on the on the
left chart I've shown the US yield
curve. So on any given day we can
observe the prices of two-year bonds,
three-year bonds, five year bond,
sevenyear bond, 10 year bond, 30-year
bond. What is the price of that? And I
don't know if uh if Peter have you have
you um guys done bond math yet?
>> A little. So so you we know the prices
where these things buy. So they're very
transparent prices and we can convert
prices to yields.
So basically a yield is like the implied
rate of return of the bonds effectively
given its price over the course of its
maturity. And then when we plot these
yields on on this plot here I've plotted
the yields the yield is on the y- axis
versus the maturity of the bond. And
I've sampled
five days from history.
And this is what's known as the yield
curve. that is a that is the most
important input of macroeconomics in the
world is the US the shape of the dollar
yield curve.
Um sometimes most of the time the yield
curve is upward sloping so people people
require a bigger return to lend money
for longer and the US treasury like
generally requires that. But sometimes
that is not true. Like sometimes you can
see this top blue line. Sometimes the
yields actually like is is starts out
downward sloping and then flattens out.
So these yields can have a variety of
shapes
and this is just the level of yields.
What we're betting on is the changes. So
we're betting on how this curve evolves
dayto day. And you can see from these
from these um yield curves that you can
imagine how if I just if I was to show
you a movie of the yield curve, it's
going to kind of flop around. It's going
to be like a little string. It's like
flop around, but it's going to be like
going up and down. It's going to slope
like this. It's going to have a whole
set of dynamics
and that that dynamics and that kind of
those dynamics is what we're trying to
kind of model with PCA here.
Um
bonus question is
do you guys know what is the shape of
the yield curve now? What does it look
like? What are what are the is are
short-term interest rates like higher
than long-term interest rates?
Have you has has anybody like
we had a a very prominent Federal
Reserve meeting recently
and uh they they do do you remember what
they did
the action the Fed took was the action
the Fed took was to cut interest rates
by 50 basis points. So what the Fed is
doing it's cutting the interest rate
that is the leftmost point on this yield
curve that that they're they're setting
that point. Everything else, the rest of
the curve is market expectations of what
that point would do in the future. So
they moved this point down by 50 basis
points. 50 basis points means half a
percent. So it went it went down by half
a percent.
Right now this blue curve, even though
it's from 2023, that's like that's
pretty recent, it's still the curve is
still downward sloping. It looks a
little bit more like like this right
now. So it's not it it was for a very
long time it was actually like really
inverted. It was going like downward
sloping like that. Now the back now the
back is like starting to flatten out but
it's still quite high in the front end
and downward sloping.
So that that unrelated to what we're
talking about but fun kind of a fun
fact. Okay. So now when we look at yield
changes
um
when we look at the we take our data we
compute your changes so the changes of
yields on dayto day
we we can we should demean that data set
but generally demeaning it doesn't
really help that much because the mean
is going to be very close to zero
because changes are sometimes the are
going to go up sometimes they're going
to go down you're not going to have over
the history of of 20 30 years that we're
talking about here, you're not going to
have a large large mean. Still, it's
always good practice to demean it.
Won't change much the result. But then
we take this
in this example, I didn't actually
normalize the variance. I think we just
just left it in there. So we did PCA on
coariance matrix. And the reason is that
the units the yield changes are they're
comparable units and there is
um looking at the PCA without without
normalizing the the variance is actually
like it's a very meaningful output like
it's it's we want to understand how
volatile is going to tell us something
about the relative volatilities of
points.
So when we do that and we look at the um
what what I what I'm plotting here on
the top are the the igen vectors. So the
the principal component factors the
shapes of the principal component
factors on variance days.
So this plot can be confusing right and
I want to make sure that we're all on
the same page what it is. This was
this is the shape. This is the yields.
Then we take these yields. We look at
the changes of yields. Then we put them
through PCA. And remember the output of
PCA is IGN vectors and values. IN
vectors means every every point like two
year, three year, 5 year, 10 year, 30
year everything has a number. Now a
loading
we call that the number the vector
coefficient. I call that loading. That's
a very a term that we use.
that loading is again there's a time
series of those and I'm plotting here a
select like five different dates in
history
of what that vector looks like what the
first principal component looks like
what the second principal component
looks like what the third principal
component looks like
these are f these are like snapshots
like five snapshots in time
and I'm plotting maturity versus loading
and there like there's actually three
dimensions here. There's maturity,
loading and time. So I can't like I can
show you a threedimensional plot but
that will just be like confusing. So I'm
I'm showing here cross-sections. So
these are these are various
cross-sections on time.
And you can see that
there is a clear and persistent pattern
in what the en vectors look like. The
first one PC1 is called the level.
That's basically means that
the that that is like it all the
loadings are positive. So it means when
the yield curves move generally they
move up and down together when in the
same direction. So if 10 year rate is
going up probably two-year rate is going
up as well. Five year rate is going up
as well. And hence the term rates are
going up. rates are going up is like
generally speaking everything is going
up or down and that's the most that is
the the move that that is explains most
of the variance of the yield curve
but on top of that now there's a second
move which is we call this PC2 and we
when we look at the shape of it we can
say oh it starts out negative and the
front end of the curve and it's positive
on the back end of the curve that's the
slope
so that's kind of a steepening of the
curve versus flattening the curve that
is the second PC factor.
So this first PC factor by the way
explains around like 90% of the variance
maybe like 85 or something and the
second PC factor explains like between
five and 10% of the variance
like very huge difference
and the third PC factor is like the
curvature. So how how curvy what is the
curvature of the of the like it's it's
positive on the front end positive on
the at the 30-year and negative at the
belly of the curve 10 year point
and that has the smallest amount of
variance. So what does that mean? If you
think mentally of the movie of what the
yield curve is doing it's mostly going
up and down mostly going up and down
like that but it's also like it's also
slope a little bit of slope. So it's
mostly up and down but like a little bit
of slope and a little bit of like
curvature like that.
So like that that's that's that's the
that's what this thing tells us is the
dynamics of the curve.
Um now
some of these things are like super the
structure of this thing actually tells
you a lot. You can see how the the PC1
level
it like
the the u the maturity at which it like
it starts out steep upward sloping and
then it levels out. The maturity at the
maturity in years at which it levels
out. I've plotted here what the maturity
is at which it it kind of levels out
where the short-term rate decoupled from
long-term rates. And if you plot that in
time in time series, you can kind of see
that um it was
very short like monetary policy was was
basically only governing the short end
of the curve up to two years up until
right after the postfinancial crisis.
And then the Fed became very very
powerful. Post financial crisis the Fed
said we're going to keep rates low for a
very long time and all of a sudden this
thing exploded. it became very very very
high. So like basically um the short end
rates were governing effectively the the
the um rates up to up to four or five
years and then up until co they started
to decrease up until co happened. Fed
came in and said we're going to bring
the bazooka so we're going to
everybody's like okay they're going to
keep rates low for a long time as well.
It exploded again and now it's back down
again. So that is like that's that's
already something that is kind of like a
regime indicator. You can see how the
market behavior is reflected in the
shape of these PC factors.
That tells you so much about what's
going on in the market when you look at
the these in the details of these
factors.
Something like
where is the bottom of PC3 where is the
belly you can see that sometimes is at
at 10 years sometimes it becomes close
to five sometimes close to 15. That's
also a regime indicator
PC loading stability. So here I'm taking
this this graph PC1 graph but instead of
plotting loading versus maturity I'm
plotting loading versus time and each
maturity point is line.
So that tells me the stability of my
loadings. you generally you want to look
at that because you want you want
factors that are stable
and PC1 loadings are are pretty stable
but these and the fact where the changes
in PC1 loadings they're very often like
they're quite meaningful like you can
2008 crisis two-year rate this blue line
is a two-year rate the short end the
short end becomes very volatile nobody
knows what the Fed is going to do
there's a lot of volatility and then
collapses post 2012 like the Fed is not
doing anything. So the to your point is
not moving.
Then it goes up. Maybe the Fed is going
to move. And then after CO it also
collapses
and now it's back up again. The Fed is
very active right now. This this ends in
like 2023 this data set. If I make it a
little bit longer, you see this line
actually went very high in the recent
history.
So all of that is um these things are
like they're they're
they all come from this data but they're
they tell you they they they tell you a
lot about the behavior the regime and
the uh dynamics of of interest rate
market.
This is the variance explained. I think
this is like this is a way remember how
I was telling you how we look at values
and we want to make sure that they're
well segregated. Well, this is a good
this is a way to look at it. If you look
at this chart and the first factor
explains so much variance, it's like
yeah, that that's that's a good factor.
That's a good factor to that like that's
a solid factor and you can um you know
that this thing is persistent. You're
very this thing is likely to continue is
likely to be stable and it's a good part
of your model for the future. If you
look at variance explained by factor,
this is a log plot.
You'll see that how the first and second
and third factor are separated in like
by order of magnitude. So they never
cross. So that means that these factors
are robust and
they they are like yeah they're they're
very useful modeling factors for
modeling. You want to see this kind of
picture. What you don't want to see is
like lines that are all entangled up
with each other. That's you don't want
to see that. You want to see something
like this in general when you're looking
at PCA.
Again this is these are values I'm
looking at variance explained
um
and this out of sample coariance is like
when I'm this is basically when I when I
calibrate my PCA remember my my in my if
I take a single data set however I
choose it and I do run my PCA the PC1
projections and the PC2 projections
are going to be uncorrelated with each
other by construction. But if I take the
same loadings now and I look at the
future returns,
there is nothing that says that
um if I project my future data, future
returns onto the same loadings, those
might not might actually become
correlated.
So here I'm computing like kind of
future returns
projected onto PC factors using that are
calibrated on like past past history and
and you see that it's not they're not
fully orthogonal. However, they're quite
orthogonal. So it means that like the
dynamics are mostly preserved.
They're the loading the PC factors are
mostly stable. This is not like this is
something you would expect you would
hope to see. You don't want to see you
don't want to see these numbers off
diagonal numbers to become like 30 50%
that will be like that means that your
PCI model is quite unstable but if it's
like if if your our sample correlation
is is pretty small that's that's a good
thing
and
now what do we do with this PCA
well one of the key things is like okay
I want to go back to this slide for one
reason suppose you say, well, I really I
want to bet on curve. I want to bet on
the second factor or I have a model that
on that I want to bet on like curve
stippling or relative value of 10ear
bonds versus fiveyear bonds or 30-year
bonds versus 10ear bonds.
I can use PCA to isolate effects that
are idiosyncratic to particular points
on the curve to particular factors. And
I can basically say well if I if I hedge
out the vast majority of the variance by
hedging out PC1
and I look at like the residual PC1
residuals which is PC2 and above. What
can I say about those uh about those
returns? How can I model those and how
do I and the key thing you can you can
construct these things. You can say,
"Oh, I want to model these things." But
the key is how do if once you once you
have a good model, how do you trade
them? So being able to construct P to
understand how PC loadings translate to
portfolios is very important because it
it tells you how I can use this
methodology to construct specific
portfolios that are uncorrelated to each
other and
um and give me like a new a new a new
kind of target to model.
If you if I didn't do that, I have I
still have like eight things I can trade
or six things. Two year, three year,
five year, 10 year, and 30-year bonds,
but they're so correlated where I'm
trading 10-year bond or 30-year bond.
Like, if I just trade 10-year bond
outright or 30-year bond outright, I'm
mostly getting the same return. So to be
able to increase the diversity of what
I'm of the target I'm capturing, I'm
using PCA to construct more portfolios
that are going to be uncorrelated and
present me with more opportunities to
model to make bets.
That's like that's a key use case for
PCA finance. Like we take these things
that are very highly correlated and now
I'm going to create out of these six
highly correlated portfolios, I'm going
to create three or four portfolios that
are not highly correlated.
What are like and these portfolios are
going to be my PCA are going to be
defined by my PCA factors.
So remember the factors
on any given day they give me a loading
on every tenor on every maturity.
Yeah. Did you have a question? Okay.
Yeah. They gave me a loading on every
maturity. So it tells me and I I can
think of this loading as telling me how
much to own of this particular
bond on on that maturity. So PC1 means
buy every bond in some in some equal
amount. That would be that's PC1. PC2
is like oh you should like sell some
two-year bonds, buy some 30-year bonds.
Like basically the portfolio is going to
be
the portfolio is going to be defined
like you're going to you're going to
basically buy bonds according to the
loading on every on every point on PC2.
Why is this portfolio interesting? Well,
it's interesting because PCA tells us
that if I construct this portfolio like
this, it would have no sensitivity to
PC1.
But PC1 is like 90% of my variance. So
that means that by if I construct the
PC2 portfolio, I have effectively hedged
out 90% of the variance of individual
bonds and I've constructed something
that's new, less volatile,
but uncorrelated to my original like
outright tenure bond.
Same thing with PC3. I can construct and
I can construct like these PC3
portfolios that are like and these by
the way these things actually trade in
the market. They're they're they're
called like curves PC2 things are like
they're curves like you you buy two year
you sell 10 year vice versa and then and
there's flies which are like 10 and 30s
where you sell 10 year and you buy two
year and 30 year. Yes. Is there any
application of the higher order PCs or
are they just they explain such little
variance that you don't really bother
with?
>> They are the most interesting thing
because
the PC1 stuff is easy to bet on like you
just bite your bond buy and sell. If you
can model that and predict it that's
awesome
but like first that's hard but also it's
only one thing you can predict whether
are you doing 10 year or 30 years you're
predicting only one thing. So you can
make a model for that.
Being able to construct these portfolios
PC2 and three, you're able to create out
of these
out of these like out of these bounds
that are highly correlated, you're able
to create something that is entirely
different from from the PC1
uncorrelated. So now you have something
else that you can model and you can and
because of the market is so the market
is is liquid. It needs to be very liquid
because remember this it doesn't explain
a lot of variance. So if you construct
this thing it's not going to move much.
But all that means is I just need to buy
more of it. If I buy enough of it even
though a single unit might not move much
when I buy enough of it is still going
to move enough. And that's the point of
leverage. So if I sell a bunch of
two-year bond, buy a bunch of 30-year
bond.
Now,
if I buy the same notional, buy and sell
the same notionals as as the PC1, it's
not going to, like you said, it's not
going to move very much. Maybe it's
going to move like only one/ird as much
as my PC1 portfolio. But if I scale it
up by by three by by a factor of three,
now my new portfolio PC2 has the same
daily standard deviation as my PC1
portfolio
and it's orthogonal. So you just need
basically so what did I need to do that?
I need to be able to buy three times as
much. So it needs the market needs to be
liquid. I need to have access to
leverage. You can do the same with PC3.
And yes, in in the in the big liquid
markets like US Treasury, there is
enough access for to leverage where you
can actually do that. You'll see a lot
of times in the press, it's a very hot
topic now. the CFTC is trying to
regulate like how much leverage exists
in the financial markets especially in
interest rates because because of this
because of the fact that PC1 is so
explained so much people use massive
amounts of leverage to gain access to to
basically enough volatility to make
these bets on on PC2 and three and um
that can create that means you own large
amount you own long and short massive
amounts of certain bonds that can be
dangerous if it's systemic in a certain
way and like this presents risk but it's
also but it's definitely it's doable
because there is so much debt there's so
much debt in the world that there is
enough out there where you can where you
can bet um you can gain this leverage
basically and it's it's very accessible
to professional investors
so yeah the actually the the far from
far from it being irrelevant like that
is actually where a lot of times the
money is made but like it is true that
as you go why can't we go to PC4 and
five the amount of leverage you need to
make this work is become so high it
becomes really expensive to trade
>> yes
that's like as you said before that this
is this allows you where allowing you to
kind of scale it up to get the
volatility that you need is only is
useful for like the fixed income because
it's more like liquid than like if buy
the same thing like equities for example
like since it's not as likely you
couldn't get like if you were to buy
that many of whatever um security cost
too much of a shift or stuff like that.
>> Well
it turns out that it's not that is not
it's it's not actually it's not really
true what you say and and the re the
reason is the following. Yeah, the
volumes in notional volumes of equity
market may be a little bit smaller.
They're still very large and the
variance explained of the first
principal component in equities is not
nearly as high as it is in rates. So you
don't need as much leverage to get like
the second principal components got a
lot of volatility a lot more relative to
the first than in in this example here
later in the slides which I think we
might not get to. There's also an
example with equity indices in Europe.
The same concept there. And by the way,
a lot of equity, there's a whole field
of hedge funds called equities that are
equity long short neutral. They are
basically betting on equities without
taking directional risk. So everybody is
trying those all these guys are hedging
out PC1. They're taking leverage. It
exists. It it's just a little more
expensive to trade, but it gives you
opportunities that you wouldn't be able
to access otherwise. Yeah.
>> Yes.
>> I was curious for like some big
statement products, especially ones that
are more liquid, they might trade like
one rarely and two around specific
events. So like the prices that you see
are necessarily indicative of how the
prices would have traded like a day or
two before that. in how do you think
about like how um to like I guess clean
data in a way or like understand that
there's a lot of idiosyncratic factors
that go on with fixing a product
especially ones that are more
>> yeah um it's a great question there's a
lot of art that goes a lot of like
domain knowledge that goes into that in
this example with bonds
um yeah there is certainly events
that where the market is very volatile
and
when we when we look at daily returns if
I look at like 10 years of daily returns
and I'm going to estimate like a
standard deviation
and I'm going to say well on average
the I could on average yields move by I
don't know five to six basis points per
day something but which is that's
roughly how much they
But and then I say like well if I'm
sitting there and tomorrow is like there
wasn't this example in in August that
there was a huge huge like
um you know there was a huge number that
comes out a huge print that was related
to um to inflation and
in on that day if you look at the the
price of the day before versus the price
after that announcement And the
volatility that people expected on this
on this day was probably twice as high.
So people expected the daily the
standard deviation of daily move that
was priced in was probably like 10 to 12
basis points per day.
Okay.
What does that does that mean that all
this is irrelevant? No, it's not. It
just means that when you're thinking
about the risk you're taking, you have
to understand that if you take a certain
amount of for the same notional same
number of bonds or the same number of
like the same investment that you hold,
if you hold it on that kind of a day,
you would just have a lot more risk. So
if you're when you're doing your risk
management, you have to account for
that. Do you want to do that? Do you
want to hold it? you may want to maybe
shrink your position or if you have a
view maybe you don't want to shrink your
position like but that you have to just
be aware of it the correlations are very
likely to continue to hold sometimes
things happen covid happens for example
covid hit these loadings the curve the
dynamics of the curve changed overnight
like the PC loadings
the that the way the curve started to
behave like the central bank came there
was an emergency cut and things changed
like super quickly
Being able to reflect that in your model
is very important because now if you're
trying to take a PC2 bet, but your PC
loadings are not indicative of how the
current dynamics are, you're going to be
ending up taking like massive massive
leverage, but you're not you're not
really PC1 hedge. So all this leverage
is going to produce huge amounts of
returns and noise in your P&L.
So that these are the practical
questions of when that you face when
you're actually doing this thing. How do
you and remember you need history to
train your model. So you're sitting
there COVID happened. There was a big
cut emergency cut in the central bank.
They cut like 1% in one day and you know
it's a new world but there is no data on
how the new world is going to behave
because it just happened two days ago.
You don't have 10 years of history to
calibrate your PCA model. So what are
you going to do? And there's a lot of
answers to that. You can look at implied
markets. There's a lot of answers to
that. But how you answer a question is
going to is like that's critical. That's
critical. Yeah.
>> Can I follow up to that? Do you think
like it's it's worth in some sense
almost like slicing up your data into
those pieces where you think um like
things will behave in similar fashions
and then like like I guess using or
something some other model to better
understand how they behave in those
specific like regimes and times.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That that's certainly a
thing that that is that is a thing that
you can do like regime specific. You can
group together data that are specific to
this regime like oh I'm going to look at
right now the Fed is cutting rates. I'm
going to model my curve behavior not by
looking at the last five years of
history but I'm going to look at like
join together historical periods where
rate Fed was cutting rates and just look
at that like it's an approach and it's a
sensible approach like for now when you
do that you you're introducing other yes
the Fed is cutting rates but there are
other things that were not the same so
there's no like perfect answer in that
because again you're you're still trying
to use the past to predict the future
And
there is no perfect answer but there
there are many valid answers.
Um
yeah I I kind of wanted to like this is
a description of how you construct these
PC portfolios and PC residuals.
We have like some of the pros and cons.
I already talked about some of these
and I kind of wanted to talk about
this part of um the output of this. So
here I've created like a little trading
strategy based on the the recent the
returns of um like basically a momentum
mean reversion strategy for PC1 and and
uh look to the performance. So it
doesn't really work great, but it that's
not the point. The point is that it's an
illustration of how this works. All the
code of how this was created and how you
can calculate these things is part of
that Jupyter notebook that is
accompanying the slides that you can
download and the data is there is in a
CSV file which you can pull from the fed
like an updated version of. So if you
are interested in like doing a project
there there's a lot of like a lot of
standard like strategies that you can
try for example to to write and and um
and and to test out like it's not there
not again the point is not to actually
go and trade it but like to actually
practice a little bit applying PCA to
real data and there's not there's no
substitute to actually doing it because
you you see that in every single step
there's choices to make there's little
details and these details matter and
being able to like to to to understand
the pros and cons of each of these
details. One lecture is like not enough
to go over everything. I I've kind of
wanted to give you a little taste of
what it's like to to deal with this
stuff, but it's a very powerful tool.
It's used all around the street for for
modeling of things like stocks and bonds
and um
it's a great thing to have in your
toolkit as somebody who is like looking
for a job in finance if you decide to do
that.
So I'm going to stop here down here like
this. There is another example which is
European stock market indices. Same
thing tells you about the correlation,
what the various principal components
are, what they mean and and tells you
about the strategy. So there's like
there's two examples in the slides. We
don't need to go through both of them. I
think I know that in five minutes you
kind of have to leave. So I I wanted to
give a little bit of time for questions
and and for discussion. I thank you so
much for being so active and
interactive rather. You guys have you
guys have asked more questions in this
class than than it's like definitely top
one of the top like question asking
classes in in my in my experience doing
this class. So I love that that that
shows that like the stuff is
interesting. So I'm very happy to hear
that. Um
so like yeah I I definitely wanted to
ask if you have any questions and in
particular if I if this is clear I
really want to make sure that this this
stuff is clear these top three plots
what they represent.
>> Yeah.
>> Is there any chance you could explain
the bottom left plot?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So the bottom left one
um basically
so if there's two PC1 shapes
this is date one and there is one that
is date two. I kind of said, well,
um,
what I'm looking for is basically
the
I'm looking for the the point maturity
point where the loadings cross a certain
threshold because at the end both of
these are going to be kind of relatively
flat towards the back end. So basically
10-year bonds and 30-year bonds when the
rates move up and down, they're going to
move like the same amount. But on the
very front end, that's not really true.
And why is that? Well, on the very front
end, it the rates are governed by the
central bank. So central bank is saying
we're going to set the rate here.
Expectations can vary for what happens
10 years down the line. But expectations
of what's going to happen over the next
couple of months are not going to vary
very much because that is basically the
Fed sets that the Fed tells you what
what is going to happen. So um the
loading of this PC1 like that that front
end point is like much less volatile in
general that can change like it could
also be that in the recent in the last
couple of months
that the actual shape of the PC1 factor
was probably like that and the reason is
that the front end was so uncertain
nobody knew are they going to cut are
they going to hike like we don't really
know what what's going to happen but
generally speaking the front end is
going to be less volatile than than the
back end because of the fact that the um
the the Federal Reserve like is like
they they control the front end part of
the curve.
So what I'm plotting is effectively
at what point does does the loadings
cross a threshold? Why? And if if the
Fed controls the curve, if if people
believe the Fed is going to have um if
if there's clarity on the Fed's policy
over a longer period of time, we're
going to have lower loadings on the
front of the curve for longer periods of
time. And if there is less clarity, that
period is going to shrink. Meaning,
yeah, they're always going to control
the front end, but like how quickly do
we decouple from that? And that's what
I'm plotting here. I'm I'm taking on
every day I'm I'm taking this point.
This is on day one it's going to be here
on day some other day it's going to be
here and I'm plotting a time series of
that of that point like at what time in
in maturity years like at which maturity
do we cross the threshold. Could you
explain the connection between the
curvature and the map situation?
>> The curvature and what
>> and the map.
>> Ah yeah right. Yeah. Um right. So the
PC3
shape remember was like there is like
it's this is zero
and it's like positive negative
positive. So the short end and the back
end are like basically like there's a
once you hedge out the curvature and and
the levels what remains is like the the
uh once you mention out the once you
hedge out the slope and levels what
remains is the curvature and the
question is like at that point
how does the curve move and I can give
it give you two examples in dollars you
can see that most of the time The bottom
of this graph is at like around 10 years
10 year maturity. So that means that
like once you hedge out slope and
curvature 10-year bonds are going to be
anti-correlated with two-year and
30-year bonds. So it's going to like
move around like that with where the
belly of the curve is 10ear point. Now
if I look at another country that is
like more like an emerging markets
country for example like Mexico
it's going to look like this.
where this is going to be around five
years.
What is the significance of this? Well,
it tells you like you can think of this
is like the curve has distinct like
parts that different things drive it.
the the very front end we said a central
bank. Then there's like a period after
that that is really mostly driven by
inflation expectations
and then the very long end is a lot of
it is about growth growth expectations
and um
this the the point where where this
bottom of the curvature is it really
tells you a lot about like where which
part where does the what part of the
curve is where does this crossover go
from like inflation expect inflation
being dominant to like growth being
dominant. Different players invest in
different parts of the curve. Certain
like um the back end of the curve
there's a lot of pensions, insurance
companies investing in the very long
end. They have long-term liabilities.
They invest here. Very front end is like
a lot of like two-year rates, a lot of
speculators, a lot of like like people
who need short-term financing. 10 year
in the US between five and 10 year is
where most most corporate bonds most
corporations they issue they raise that
in the five to 10 year maturity. So the
the different players participate in the
different parts of the curve and that
means the dynamics are they that means
the dynamics are are different. Once you
hedge out those two components, you
start to discover those like these
dynamics are small relatively speaking
on the scale of rates going up and down.
But once you remove that, you start to
discover these features. They're they're
kind of hidden under this this big noise
of like rates going up and down and you
start to kind of see these things start
to pop out.
This being longer term, it just it tells
you again something about developed
markets tend to have this belly be
further out because people have people
people look at like a longer term
horizon essentially for investing. This
the pension funds invest for longer they
buy longer term bonds
and like generally people invest in
longer term than than in say emerging
market countries.
So these are like when you look at when
you compare these factors across
countries,
you can actually make sense of some of
these p these things and you can
quantify those those feature those um
those things and they can become
features for modeling.
>> One more question perhaps.
>> Yeah,
>> for a lot of markets you're not going to
get prices easily for like US like is
there a way in which like by um like
trying to ask for like transacts you
like synthetically create data?
>> Yeah, getting getting um getting access
to good data is step one in every
quantitative finance project. I would
say that like
that may be true but it's I you can like
there's ways to get it. First of all, a
lot of there's bond futures which are
effectively futures on bonds. Those
trade on exchanges that data also tends
to be pretty high quality and readily
available. So there's ways to get it,
but like yeah, that's there for every
particular market you look at, there's
going to be certain data quality issues
you have to overcome.
US market is the easiest for that. Now,
it's part of, for example, that's why,
for example, if you're going to do your
project, you're not going to look at
like South African rates because it's
just like hard to get good data. But if
you're in a hedge fund, like maybe, oh,
it's worth getting the data and putting
some effort because maybe you have less
competition there. You can you can maybe
make some money or maybe you have some
ideas where you could model it, where
you can actually have some predictive
power in South African, right? So, you
make that investment of time. But it's
it's all part of that. Um the the less
the data the more the harder it is to
get the data usually means that there's
probably going to be more opportunities
for quantitative modeling because it's
hard for everybody. If it's easy then
everybody can do it. So you always have
to be on the edge of of the wave to to
find to make money.
>> Great. Thank you so much.
>> You're welcome.
[Applause]