good morning welcome back uh today is
lecture 12 We are continuing our graph
Theory unit this time talking about
matchings and stable matchings uh
matchings in general are a really useful
Concept in graph Theory they come up
frequently when you're trying to match
um pairs of OB objects you want everyone
to have one partner or possibly zero
Partners if they don't get a match then
they're sad that's fine um but matchings
are really useful concept so let's talk
about what they mean what they're good
at
um and a few ideas surrounding these so
first of all
definition a
matching in a graph
which remember has a set of vertices and
a set of edges which are pairs of
vertices um is a
subgraph
oops M and what subgraph means is we're
just taking a subset of the vertices and
a subset of the edges uh so long as
excuse me uh so long as all the edges
have their vertices in the
subset um let's see in which
uh every vertex
in sorry yeah every vertex in
V uh
has degree 1 in M degree less equal to 1
in
M uh and sorry this is vertex set of our
subset um said differently a different
definition which is just as good um a
matching
is a
subset of the edges of our
graph where no two selected
edges
edges share an end
point so we're just choosing some of the
edges of our graph making sure that we
never touch edges that have an endpoint
in common that uh for
example I can draw this bow tie looking
graph this this this this this here here
here and
here and then vertex A B
C D
E F G H so if this is our graph let me
give you an example of a matching so an
example of a matching is M the this is
going to be just the edges be and
DG uh this is an alternative uh notation
for edges by the way instead of writing
the set B comma e Clos curly brace uh I
can just write be next to each other and
it's clear we're talking about those two
vertices so we're dealing with the edge
be so that's this Edge and the edge DG
which is this
Edge is this a matching
I see I see some headshakes sorry some
head nods yeah this is a matching
because none of our selected edges have
end points in common if I had also
chosen Edge FD if I tried to put FD into
there as well then these two edges would
be in conflict and we would no longer
have a
matching does that make sense so said um
more similar to our first definition if
we look at just the subgraph that
includes our chosen
edges all of the vertices in that
subgraph need to have degree at most one
so this has degree one and one and one
and one and zeros for the others um if
we have edges sharing end points we'd
have higher degree which is not allowed
in a
matching um um like I said this has lots
of applications anytime we're trying to
pair things up uh for example online
dating services um you're trying to
recommend um say this user to that user
and you recommend them to each other and
they go on a date or something like that
um and maybe you want to try to match up
a bunch of them at once so you can have
lots of dates happening in parallel so
you want a matching that includes lots
of edges knowing that no one can go on
multiple dates at
once um sometimes you might have a bunch
of tasks in a in a an expensive um
computational project you have lots of
tasks you need to do and lots of servers
that can help you out in parallel but
each server can only do one job at a
time so you want to find a matching that
gets lots of servers working on
different tasks at the same time so you
want to find a matching that includes
lots of your servers and lots of your
tasks um and find a matching with lots
of edges so you get lots done in
parallel
um so in a lot of these examples we're
trying to maximize the number of edges
in our matching try to get lots and lots
of pairings all at once and there are a
couple different Notions of big a big
matching a matching with lots of edges
that we want to Define we want to define
a maximal matching and a maximum
matching and I'm sorry that those sound
very similar but let's talk about what
they mean uh so we'll say that m is a
maxim
mole
matching when it's not
possible to
find another
Edge e that's in our set but not yet in
our
matching such that M with that new
Edge is
matching so Maxim Mo means you can't add
new edges to the set of edges you
already have
so in this case with these two
edges um all of the other edges I might
try to add to these two have an end
point in common with one or the other so
I can't pick new edges to put into M
while keeping the ones I already have so
that makes M this matching is
maximal does that make sense this is
sort of a local notion where all you
have to do is look at the matching you
have and ask is there any single other
Edge that I can put in here as well and
if there isn't then it's
maximal and if it's not if there is
another Edge you can put in well go
ahead and put it in then search again if
there's yet another Edge you can put in
put it in keep going until there isn't
and then you have a maximal matching so
it's very easy to find a maximal
matching you just keep adding edges
until you
can't the difference is that that
maximal matching you find might not be
the biggest matching possible ever
and that's the other notion we
want a maximum
matching we'll say that m
is a maximum
matching when there does not
exist a bigger
matching a matching M
Prime with more edges
so this is a global measure of Maximum
we'll say of matching is maximum when
it's the biggest you can ever do I don't
care if you keep these particular edges
just is there any matching at all
anywhere that has more edges than
this so that's the difference between
maximal and maximum maximal is about
local search can you make a single
Improvement by adding a single thing
here maximum is a global property is it
the biggest possible ever and as you can
imagine um finding a maximum matching or
proving that a matching you have is
maximum is a lot harder than
maximal um this matching up here with DG
and be is that
maximum why not someone someone shaking
their head can you tell
me
yes all right ad d
um BG you
said and
C all
right is a
matching and is this a matching let's
take a
look we've got a D here b g here c e
here none of those circled edges um that
kind of look like coffee beans to me
none of those coffee beans share of an
end point so that is a matching and
since this has more edges than M up
there m is not
maximum right cool so matchings can be
maximal locally biggest even if they're
not maximum globally
biggest um is this matching maximum or
can we do even
better oh there was someone raising
their hands in the back but it's
brinmore
there was someone else raising their
hand but I think they were just
adjusting their
glasses all these fake outs plain jokes
on me okay so is this is this a maximum
matching or can we do better or what it
oh yes
all right so um let me uh let me say
that so everyone else can hear so if we
had a bigger matching we'd have to
include F or H is that what you said all
right um and if we try to include F then
it's going to share an end point with a
d uh which is not great um so yes that's
almost exactly the logic I'm looking for
um just a slight tweak to that uh when
we're asking if a matching is maximum
we're not really talking about adding to
this specific matching that's the
maximal side of things so instead of
comparing what we have or instead of
comparing to what we have to this
particular matching um I just want to be
able to prove that there is no bigger
matching at all uh so what would it mean
for there to be a bigger
matching a bigger matching
would
include well at least four
edges and therefore at least eight
vertices but we only have eight vertices
right 1 2 3 four five yep um so it would
include all the
vertices all right and any matching that
includes all the vertices in particular
includes a and
F and we we can't use a and F cuz they
would both have edges to D there's only
one way to use a there's only one way to
use F and they both use vertex D in the
middle and we can't do that can't use a
and F at the same
time and this is our
contradiction so if there's a bigger
matching bad stuff happens so there
doesn't exist a bigger matching that
doesn't mean this U these three coffee
beans are the only maximum match
matching um there are a couple more for
example we could replace ad with FD that
would be fine that would be a different
maximum matching uh so there can be
multiple maximum
matchings um that all necessarily have
to have the same
size um different maximal matchings
don't all have to have the same size as
we saw this two-edge matching is Maximo
and also this three-edge matching is
Maximo
does that distinction make sense
wonderful all
right let's see so next
definition a matching is
perfect if and only
if it
includes all vertices
so perfect matching gives everyone a
partner and therefore exactly one
partner does this graph have a perfect
matching no a perfect matching would
need to would need all eight vertices
and therefore four edges but we already
saw there are no matchings with four
edges in this graph so not all graphs
are going to have perfect matchings um
but often in your task allocation Pro uh
problems where you're trying to match
everyone to another resource um ideally
you'll end up with a perfect matching
where everyone gets a partner or every
task gets a
server uh and so perfect matchings are
um are very commonly the
goal now so far we've been talking about
matchings in general graphs um but
matchings are very common especially in
bipartite graphs so bipartite matchings
um so when we're trying to match tasks
to servers we have a bipartite graph all
the edges connect a task to a server
when it's possible for that task to be
done on that server and then we're
looking for a matching which tells you
which servers are doing which tasks um
so a lot of problems that involve
matchings are naturally
bipartite uh let's see and uh to
emphasize um remember from last time by
partite
graphs don't
need the same size on both
sides as we saw with the Harvard vers
MIT bipartite graph we had 7,000 on one
side and 4,000 on the other side still a
perfectly valid bipartite
graph however
um let's see let's
see perfect matching can't possibly
exist in a bipartite
graph when the two sides have different
sizes right there can never be a
bipartite uh sorry there can never be a
perfect matching between Harvard
undergrads and MIT undergrads because
there are more Harvard undergrads than
MIT undergrads every Edge includes one
of each so even if we max out all of the
MIT students and give them a Harvard
buddy there's still going to be 3,000
Harvard students that lose out so if
there's a perfect matching in your
bipartite graph you have to have the
same size doesn't mean there will always
be a perfect matching when the two sides
have the same size but it's at least
necessary all
right sometimes uh when you're trying to
make these matchings not only are you
trying to maximize the number of pairs
you get or possibly uh get a perfect
matching and get everyone a pair um but
often edges are
weighted uh so each Edge comes with a
number so we have a function W from the
set of
edges to real numbers
and each Edge comes with a number you
can imagine in the tasks versus servers
graph each Edge represents how long that
task would take on that
server and maybe certain tasks are going
to be faster in different servers maybe
because that server is more powerful or
maybe because it's closer to other
resources it might need and it can
access them more quickly um but often
when we have a weighted Edge like this
uh we want
a perfect
matching with minimum total
weight as an example of
that here's a nice bipartite
graph uh and maybe this Edge has weight
three this has weight one this has
weight five and this has weight
two and I can see two different perfect
matchings in this graph there's the one
that does
this and there's the
one that does
this I think that's all of
them and if we look at the weights well
this has weight three and two so this
has total weight
five uh and this has weight one and five
so this has total weight
six so you'd prefer this one to that one
cuz five is smaller than six the total
weight in this perfect matching is
better than the total weight in this
perfect
matching right so these are just very
common kinds of questions that you find
yourself asking when you're modeling
something in terms of matchings or
perfect matchings often there's more to
optimize than just finding a perfect
matching and I mention all of these
variations on these
problems um because unlike last time
where we saw that graph coloring is a
useful abstraction but hard to compute
exactly or hard to compute
optimally um all of the matching
problems I've mentioned we do have
efficient algorithms
for so we
have we can
find maximum
matchings in graphs
bipartite or otherwise uh yes
question
are oh um yeah where did these weights
come from um these are just arbitrary in
this example um I just picked them for
demonstration um in a real world
scenario the weights would represent
like how much work it takes um to do the
task corresponding to this pairing or
how expensive this is or how
desirable um so usually these weights
are going to come from whatever context
you're modeling and trying to optimize
for but yeah in this example I just
picked
them um but there is an algorithm to
find maximum matchings in graphs
bipartite or not doesn't matter um
excuse me uh we can
find uh and because we can find maximum
matchings we can find perfect matchings
if they exist if a perfect matching
exists it's certainly maximum because
you can't use more than that number of
edges
um we can find Min
weight perfect
matchings uh in bipartite
graphs we have algorithms to solve these
kinds of problems so if you ever find
yourself modeling a question with
matching trying to find a matching with
certain properties uh very often there
will be algorithms to solve it quickly
we're not going to cover those
algorithms in this class um you'll see
more of them in the follow-up classes
six um 121 and
122 um but just know that they're out
there and know that this is a useful
tool um both for modeling and for
computing are there questions about
these kinds of
things all right no
questions uh then let's move on to the
main topic for today which is stable
match
so this is a uh yeah so the topic is
stable
matchings we are going to be uh in this
problem we're going to be looking for
certain kinds of perfect matchings in
bipartite graphs so in this in the
specific scenario let's imagine we have
n
applicants and n evaluators
you can think of these like n interns
that are looking for managers and M and
N managers where we're going to match
them up one to one each intern gets one
manager and vice versa uh and we're
trying to find a way to match them
nicely uh you can think of these as the
applicants are um recently graduated
medical school students looking for
residencies um and I mentioned this
example specifically because the
algorithm were about about to talk about
is used in precisely that way um in
practice in the real world in the United
States at least um all residency
applicants submit their list of
preferences about which hospitals they
want to do their residencies at um and
they do interviews and hospitals submit
their preferences for which candidates
they
prefer uh and they send this all to a
national nonprofit
organization who does a big global
computation to find in some sense the
best perfect matching it can and then it
notifies everyone on the same day um all
residency applicants are told on Match
Day which was actually just a few weeks
ago it happens once a year uh they're
told where they're doing their residency
and it's a a big party and um many of
them are excited about going at their
top school many of them don't get their
top school and they're still happy
because they still get to be a
doctor um but they're going to use EX
actly the algorithm I'm about to
describe with some tweaks because the
real world is more complicated than the
simple math we're about to describe
um but um this is a real algorithm with
real consequences it was uh invented in
what
the Yeah in
1962 by Gail and
shapley uh that's that's two people um
I'm going to call it the Gail shapley
algorithm uh it was also improved um
many years later by El Roth uh together
they have found many real world
applications and
improvements um and it won them the 2012
Nobel prize in economics for uh for alth
and for shapley I don't know where Gail
was in all of this uh I don't think he
got the the prize as well anyway um
really important useful practical
algorithm that actually has some fairly
simple mathematical underpinnings enough
that we can describe it and analyze it
and prove things about it uh in the next
hour we have together
so um what is this algorithm what is it
for so as I said before we have n
applicants and N
evaluators um and each of them is going
to give a preference ordering for um for
all n of the opposite parties um in
order of their preference so all
applicants and
evaluators give a full
ranked
list of their
preferences so as a quick example
trying not to run too fast for the
cameraman back
there so here's an example where we're
we have five applicants and five
evaluators I haven't said which is which
because the relationship is pretty
symmetric at this
point um and so each person on the left
gives a full ranked preference order for
all of the people on the right so this
person a prefers H then J then F then G
then I
in this strict
ordering so each of these gives some
permutation of f through of f through J
each person over here gives some
permutation of a through
e uh with no restrictions on the kinds
of rankings that are allowed as long as
they give a full strict ranking of all
the
people not other
restrictions if all the applicants want
to choose the same evaluator as their
first choice they can they're not all
going to get it but they can all list it
for example if everyone really wants to
come to MGH uh for their uh for their
residency let's live in the fiction
where each Hospital only gets one
resident uh so we're trying to match One
hospital to one resident and vice versa
if everyone lists MGH as their first
choice that's fine they can only one's
going to get
it um so no other restrictions on which
per mutations they give uh and we
want a perfect
matching that leaves everyone
[Music]
happy happy
enough like I said we can't give
everyone their Top Choice especially if
all their top choices Collide um but we
want to make sure everyone's happy
enough and so let's look at an example
before we describe exactly what we mean
by happy
enough so let's
imagine back to our favorite
graph ab and CD so we have applicants AB
evaluators CD
and
a um prefers C over D so I'll list that
as a one and a two a prefers C and then
after C they prefer
D um B likewise prefers C over d c
prefers A over B and D also prefers A
over B if we write it out more similar
to the example over there this is saying
that a uh prefers C over D and B prefers
C over d
and also C uh let's see prefers A over B
and D prefers A over
B so we're already in a scenario where
not everyone can get their Top Choice
someone is going to have to take their
second
choice um and let's look at an example
what if we try to
match a
d and
BC so what's going to happen here so a
with D and B with
C so b gets C so B is Happy B got their
first
choice a with d d is Happy D got their
first choice right B and D have no
reason to want to switch but what about
a and C A and C are not paired
together but they each prefer each other
over their assigned
Partners so if you think of this as like
a a dating scenario
o um if we try to say that A and D are
paired and B and C are
paired uh then what's going to happen is
that a and C are going to run away with
each other because they each prefer to
be with each other than they're assigned
partner uh we can we call that a rogue
pair uh so we're going to
say um a
pair so an
applicant and an
evaluator form a
rogue
pair in a matching
M uh when E and A each
prefer each
other more than
their assigned partner
and by the way for the rest of lecture
when I mention matching I'm going to
mean a perfect
matching because we're trying to match
all the applicants to all the evaluators
and if I forget to say perfect I
apologize I mean
Perfect all right so a pair forms a
rogue pair in some matching if they
would each prefer each other than the
partners they're assigned in that
matching and what we're going to look
for so the of the scale shapley
algorithm we want a perfect
matching with no
Rogue
pairs so happy enough we want a matching
that makes everyone happy enough that
you're never going to get two people
running away with each other other
rather than staying with their own
partners for every pair that you match
up at least one of them prefers to be
with the partner they've been assigned
than anyone else who would prefer to be
with
them such a matching we call
stable so perfect matching with no Rogue
pairs is what we mean by a stable
matching
and that's going to be our goal does
there always exist a stable matching how
can we find out when there does exist
one can we come up with an algorithm
that will always find one if it
can in this example does there exist a
stable
matching well there are only two
matchings in this graph so let's check
the other one so we saw that AD and BC
is not stable what about AC with BD
okay so a with
C well A and C each got their Top Choice
there's no way they would ever go
Rogue
right and then if a and C can never go
then excuse me then no one can go Rogue
with them so B and D isn't going to
break up so because B and C aren't going
to run away together C is already happy
A and D aren't going to run away
together a is already
happy so this matching is
stable because none of the pairings are
rogue sorry because none none of the
possible pairs are a rogue
pair does this example make
sense cool so this particular example um
two people with two people each with
this preference
order has a stable matching will there
always be a stable matching
well if we if we relax our conditions a
little
[Applause]
bit and we decide
let's let's no longer require bipartite
let's just let everyone rank everyone
and then hope to find a stable
matching uh in that non-bipartite
graph and here's an example of that
so non-bipartite
example let me make sure I'm erasing
well
enough all right so let's imagine we
have four
people they're going to be a b c and
d and everyone's ranking everyone so
everyone has three other people to rank
uh and in this example a prefers
B then prefers
C then prefers
D B prefers C then prefers a then
prefers
d c let's see so a prefers b b prefers c
c prefers a then B then
D and I don't even care what these
preferences
are uh so let me write this out in the
other way so a prefers B then C then
D B prefers C then a then d c prefers
oops a then B then
D and D I don't care D can have any
preference order this example is already
not going to have a stable
matching
because this graph is in some sense
symmetric so of a B and C are all doing
the same thing they each prefer the next
in order among a b and c then the one
after that and then D is last B prefers
the next in order then the one after
that among a b and c then D is last C
prefers the next in cyclic order then
the next then D is
last so there are only uh three
different matchings that we can make D
has yeah D has to be matched with one of
these three people and then the other
two are paired together
but since these three people are
symmetric in this way all three of those
matchings basically behave the same way
so without loss of
generality um we can assume that the
matching looks
like let's say a goes with D and B goes
with
C the other two matchings are going to
are going to do something similar is
this matching stable
and the
answer uh if you look at it carefully if
you check all the pairs the
answer is that AC is
Rogue according to that matching AC is
Rogue um and let let's let's check that
what does it mean for AC to be Rogue
well it means a prefers C more than
their assigned partner so a is supposed
to prefer C more than their assigned
partner and C is supposed to prefer a
over their assigned partner which is B
so are these two things
true well does a prefer C over D well
yeah a prefers everyone to D so that's
true does c prefer A over B well yeah
that's the first thing we
said so A and C prefer each other more
than their assigned partners and are
therefore
Rogue so m is not
stable so this is an example where if
you have a bipartite graph uh and
preferences among
everyone then there won't always exist a
stable
matching which is why it's so amazing
that the Gil shapley algorithm which is
looking only at bipartite graphs it
turns out and we're going to prove it
always returns a stable matching in
particular there always exists a stable
matching
so let's talk about the Gail
shapley
algorithm uh this is again just for
bipartite graphs as as we set up over
there um we're going to prove it always
returns a stable
matching and therefore stable matchings
always exist in bipartite
graphs um frequently there will be many
many stable matchings for a given graph
and for a given set of preferences
um Gail shapley is only going to show us
one of them it's certainly going to find
a stable matching but not find all of
them all right so let me describe this
algorithm so the
algorithm on each
day we do the following two
steps first so step
one all applicants
approach their
favorite
evaluator who hasn't yet rejected
them so all the applicants walk up and
say hey I want to I want to go to your
uh your hospital for my residency and
maybe um Mass General gets seven
applicants um that morning at step two
oops not step one again step
two all
evaluators
reject all but their
favorite that approached them that day
so seven people all approach MGH MGH is
going to look at all seven and say out
of the seven of you I prefer Dr
Evil um and the other six you can you
can leave forever I never want to see
your face again kind of harsh but that's
how the algorithm Works um so you're
going to do step one and step two every
day and
stop when there are no
more
rejections if a day ends and no one was
rejected then that's the end of the
algorithm now what I haven't said is so
all applicants approach their favorite
evaluator who hasn't yet rejected them
if everyone has rejected them then
there's nothing for them to do they they
go home and
cry um if
possible so if they get through their
whole list and everyone has said no and
they have no one else they can approach
there's nothing else for them to do they
just drop out
all right let's
yes good question so if an evaluator has
two different favorites that are equally
preferable are they allowed to save both
of them uh so no because of the way we
set up the problem there are no ties
they give a full strict
ordering so among any two people they
know which one they prefer they have a
they have just a full list so you'll
never have ties for preferences out of
however many applicants you get that day
there will be one clear favorite and you
you temporarily hold on to them and
everyone else gets the boot
yes I'm
sorry a good question does this only
work for one to one ratios so yes still
um in this algorithm we're only talking
about n applicants and n evaluators and
each evaluator is going to end up with
one applicant and each applicant is
going to end up with one evaluator uh so
we have the same number on each side and
we're trying to find a perfect matching
that's those are the rules of the game
does that answer your question cool um
it can be useful to see this algorithm
running it can be yes awesome so here's
a a 4x4 example uh these preferences are
just you know whatever preferences they
have we have the evaluators on the top
so imagine those are the med schools on
the top and the doctors on the bottom
that are doing the
applications um so on day
one um each of the applicants is going
to approach the evaluator that they most
prefer because there have been no
rejections yet so they all just go to
their Top Choice um evaluator one says
okay well a you're my only applicant
today so I I guess I'll hold on to you
for now um uh Hospital 3 says oh no I
have three applicants among those I
prefer D so I'm going to reject B and C
so B and C are now Gone Forever Three
will never talk to to to B and C again
and they get sent back down to the
bottom and that's day one did that make
sense awesome now in day two um well A
and D still haven't been rejected by
their Top Choice so they're just going
to stay there for the next day um but B
and C who got rejected have to to go
find someone new so they're going to go
to the next one down their list and it
so happens that they're applying to the
same place again this time uh and now
they're in Conflict so Hospital 2 says I
prefer B so C get away from me and
that's the end of day two did that make
sense nice who can tell me what's going
to happen on day three at least the
first step of day
three yep up
there yeah C looks through their list
and says okay evaluator one is my next
favorite that hasn't rejected me so I'm
going to go over here to
one all right and now evaluator one says
oh there's a there's a contest between a
and C looks like I prefer C this time so
now a goes away so even though a had
been held on for a couple days someone
better came along so a gets gets kicked
out it's a it's a Cutthroat
game uh and let's keep going next day a
says okay well my next favorite is three
next down my list and I want to
emphasize it's now day four but we're
not looking at A's fourth
choice we're only looking at A's second
choice because a has only been rejected
once so far so we're always going to the
next choice for that person which might
be at a different place for each person
on that day so a goes to a hospital 3
Hospital 3 says nuh-uh and sends a away
again now a goes to hospital 2 hospit
hital 2 says oh yeah okay I like that
one so B can go away and now B has to go
fend for themselves somewhere else so B
goes to hospital one and says and gets
rejected B goes to hospital 4 and
finally there's nothing else to do no
one is rejected so the algorithm is done
did that make
sense
wonderful um let's make it make even
more sense by doing an algorithm
ourselves by hand so we've seen it run
once now let's run it ourselves
once excuse me so let's do this
algorithm so on day one uh so so let's
see uh let me make sure I'm matching my
notes yeah so I want these on the left
to be the evaluators
and these on the right to be the
applicants so every day F through J are
going to apply to their best remaining
choice and a through e you're going to
make
decisions so a b c d e what happens on
day
one F through J are each going to apply
to their Top Choice okay so F applies to
c g to a h to d i to a J to
a okay so F goes to
c g goes to a h goes to d i goes to a
and j goes to a so these are the the
applications on day one and then
evaluator a says between g i and
J between g i and
J I prefer
J so G G and I are
rejected G and I are rejected G and I
are
rejected sound
good I see some headshake was that a
question or is it just funny that we're
that we're being so
aggressive wonderful all right so that's
what happens on day one what about day
two um well JF and H weren't rejected so
they stay where they are so J a stays
here F stays here H stays here but G and
I have to go somewhere new so G is now
going over to
B uh and I is going over to
C all right and now C has a choice C can
choose between F and I C can choose
between F and I oh c is definitely
choosing i f is way down at the bottom
so
f is
sad and I believe that's the end of day
two stop me if I make mistake I very
well might make a mistake here um day
three well the only one that got
rejected was F so they're the only one
that needs to go somewhere new so we can
just copy over j g i h and f where is f
going F was rejected from C so they're
going to
B let's let's hope F has a better day
today than yesterday um so B is now
choosing between G and F and looks like
f wins this time so G is
rejected okay so G was rejected from B
and Tomorrow Needs to Go to
e so day four G is going down here to e
h i f and J We're Not rejected so they
stay put for the next day and
finally there's no cont test so there's
no
rejection and finally we have a matching
a with j b with f c with i d with h and
E with
G did that make
sense
question excellent question if we flip
the evaluators and the applicants do we
get the same matching um so as we said
earlier the relationship is kind of
symmetric right they're all giving
equivalent data we could have run this
in the opposite direction where F
through J are the evaluators and a
through e are the applicants and I have
claimed so far that we're going to end
up with a perfect matching um turns out
usually what you're going to get is a
different perfect
matching um and we're going to say very
precisely why that is uh a little later
on uh so really good question but yeah
just always keep that in the back of
your mind you could have run the
algorithm in the opposite direction and
you'll probably end up getting a
different stable matching
yes uh does the order of what matter
applicants the order of the applicants
um so the order of the applicants
doesn't matter the only thing that
matters for the algorithm is the
individual rankings for each person but
the fact that like g i and J approached
a in that order on day one didn't matter
all that matters that these three
approached and Jay is the best out of
these
three cool good
question all right um so we we got a
matching out of this example is it a
stable
matching if my theorem is to be believed
then or if Gail and shapley's Theorem is
to be believed then yes this should be a
stable matching and in this case if you
check all the possible Rogue pairs turns
out yes this is stable for this example
so that's at least one point in favor of
this algorithm producing correct results
question
interesting question if we wait if we
give a wait for um who gets which
preference So like um First Choice gets
one point second choice gets two points
and all the way down does this give an
Al does this algorithm give a matching
with lowest total weight uh that's a
really great question um
um at least if you're if you're counting
it on one side I'm pretty sure the
answer is yes if you're counting it on
the other side I'm pretty sure um it
gives a matching with the maximum total
weight uh which is probably not the side
that you want you want lower ranks um
but yeah really great question so there
are lots of ways you can see this as in
some sense some optimization problem we
want to maximize happiness which means
minimizing um how far along your ranking
list you have to to go before you find a
match uh cool so let's let's try to
prove why this algorithm does in fact
give us stable matchings and there are a
couple things to prove here let's see
where did I leave
off
okay so first question we so we've given
an
algorithm um in this class usually when
we're talking about algorithms we're
talking about State
machines and so we can think of this
algorithm as a state
machine machine where each
state is the set of rejections that have
happened so far
so to know where you are in the
algorithm and where you have to resume
to start the next day all you need to
know is which things have been crossed
off from which people's lists and then
you know what happens the next day
because each of the applicants just goes
to the next one in their
list right uh and transitions
correspond
to run one
day of the algorithm this is a way to
transl to transform one set of
rejections into probably a slightly
bigger set of rejections whatever
rejections happen on that day are now
also part of the new
state and now we can ask State machine
questions
like does the Gail shapley State machine
terminate
or might it run
forever who can tell
me yes it terminates
why it says so in the lecture notes o
appeal to
Authority I say it terminates and
therefore it terminates o um
unfortunately I can't use that
justification for myself CU if I wrote
the lecture notes then I am that
Authority so that that's not a valid
proof for me to use so I would ask that
you not use it either uh yes down
here awesome there are only a limited
number of rejections that can happen
exactly so every day that the algorithm
continues at least one rejection happens
but there are only N squared rejections
that can happen in total
right so there are at
most n s
rejections
possible we use at least
one for every
transition so we can follow at most n
squ
transitions uh before ter
minating yeah we terminate just because
we constantly use up a limited resource
and we have to finish at some point
before we eat up that resource or in the
worst case when we finish uh going
through all of that resource so worst
case everyone gets rejected from
everywhere and then we
stop Yes is n the number of applicants
yes n is the number of applicants and
the number of evaluators
they're the same
yes all right so it terminates yes
awesome next important
question when it
terminates does everyone have a
partner we were saying earlier that if
someone gets rejected from everyone they
go home crying so does anyone go home
crying we'd like that answer to be no
we'd like everyone to have a partner at
the end
all
right and the examples we've seen on the
board or sorry on the projector and on
the board over there um we did end with
an actual perfect matching um no one got
rejected from everywhere so is that true
in
general and to talk about this and also
to understand the algorithm a little
better in general um Let me give us some
uh invariance of this algorithm this
algorithm is a state machine so let's
use invariance and preserve properties
to talk about it
so um let's see
invariant each
applicant has been rejected
from a
prefix of their preference
list so on any particular day if you
look at one of these blue guys and ask
um who they've been rejected from It's
Always from the top of their list down
to some point and that's just because of
how the algorithm runs every day an
applicant goes to the Top Choice that
has hasn't rejected them yet and either
they stay with them for another day or
that evaluator rejects them and the
prefix gets one longer but either way
it's they're always rejected from a
prefix uh in
particular um let's
see each applicant
approaches worse
evaluators over
time since applicants always go down
their list from the
top um they're always approaching their
favorite evaluators every time they can
and if they're ever rejected they have
to go to someone worse and if they're
rejected they have to go to someone
worse again um so the the evaluators
that they're approaching only ever get
worse over time or stay constant if
they're not rejected that day but they
never get better so applicants prospects
only ever get
worse and the opposite happens for the
evaluators um I
claim uh that
evaluators
evaluators uh let's
see each
evaluator eval I can't spell evaluator
um let's see
picks from day to
day only get
better and if you think about this from
the perspective of an
evaluator um well if no one has ever
approached them then there's nothing for
them to do that day but if someone has
approached them and they have um they
have some number of people in front of
them they're always going to pick the
best from whoever's there when the next
day
happens they at least have that same
person again and possibly others and if
there's someone better then they'll
trade up and take someone better but
they never trade down the evaluators
always ever always only keep who they
had yesterday or trade up to someone
better for the next day so if valuator
prospects only get better and better
from day to day we can be a little more
precise about this
uh let's see so
invariant so for all
applicants and for all
evaluators um let's see if the evaluator
has
ever
rejected that
applicant then the evaluator has a
favorite
has has I'm going to call them a
candidate has a
candidate better than
a um so if Dr Jackal uh approaches briam
and women's uh and is rejected on day 12
then for all future days briam and
women's is going to have some candidate
that they finish the day with that's
better than Dr
Jackal uh and that's that's just a
precise way of saying this every day uh
they either keep who they had yesterday
or trade up to someone strictly
better so when they rejected Dr Jackal
that day they started or they they
finished that day with someone better
than Dr Jackal because that's why that's
the only reason you would reject Dr
Jackal um and then from then on they
either keep or trade up they only ever
get better does this invariant make
sense awesome so if evaluator has
rejected applicant then evaluator is
always going to have a candidate better
than that applicant from then on so now
let's answer this question does everyone
have a partner at the
end uh and let's see what happens if
they
don't so by way of contradiction let's
pick one particular applicant say Dr
Jackal uh so by way of
[Music]
contradiction assume Dr Jackal was
rejected by
everyone was rejected by all of the
evaluators all right and let's see what
goes wrong here well the end of the
algorithm at the end of the algorithm
since all of the evaluators red rejected
Dr
Jackal well what we wrote up here this
invariant says that all of the
evaluators have a candidate that's
better than Dr Jackal it was true when
they rejected Dr Jackal and it remains
true from then
on um all evaluators
have a
candidate better than Dr
J so we know we finish and when we
finish all of the evaluators end up
paired with someone better than Dr
J but there aren't enough people for
that they're in evaluators and N
applicants and if Dr Jackal isn't paired
with anyone
then there are only n minus one other
applicants that can possibly have
Partners uh so it can't be that all n of
the evaluators finish with a partner
better than Dr J because all n of the
the evaluators can't finish with anyone
or they can't all finish with anyone at
all
right
um but there're only n minus one other
candidate uh other
applicants so the N
evaluators can't all have
Partners
better than Dr J and there's our
contradiction so if we assume Dr J has
no partner at the end bad things happen
we find a contradiction so that doesn't
happen so Dr Jackal does end up with a
partner at the end and therefore
everyone
does so it returns a perfect
matching it returns a perfect matching
everyone gets some partner but is it
stable this is the part we really care
about is it
stable at the end
this is the part we really truly care
about and let's prove that it
is so to see why
um let's imagine what could possibly
result in a rogue
pair who can be
Rogue the algorithm returns some perfect
matching at the end what does it mean
for some pair of of of entities um to be
Rogue
well I claim there are three kinds of
applicant um in relation to one of the
particular evaluators so if we think of
tus as one of the evaluators tus Medical
Center um then some of the applicants
toughs rejected at some point in the
algorithm some of the applicants toughs
never spoke to and then one applicant
toughs
keeps until the end and ends up paired
with so let's consider each of those
three kinds of pairings and show that
toughs can't be Rogue with any of them
so let's
assume
Tufts rejected let's let's pick a
generic example tus rejected Dr
no uh let's say
TS um never spoke to
uh drct
who who's that I never spoke to them and
finally tus um is paired
with uh the good
doctor these are the three kinds of
people that can uh that can exist
relative to TS and let's show that none
of these can be
Rogue first of all toughs is paired with
the good doctor they're in our perfect
matching Rogue pairs are never in our
perfect matching they're pairs that are
preferred U mutually preferred to the
perfect matching so this is never
Rogue by definition of rogue if you're
in the matching you're not Rogue all
right so it's these other two cases that
we care
[Applause]
about so first let's look at Dr no
all right so tus
rejected Dr
No at some point in the
algorithm and because of this invariant
that we found we know that Tufts ends up
with someone better than Dr
no um is pair
with someone
better than Dr no because the moment uh
an evaluator rejects someone they know
they're always going to have someone
better from then on so tus and Dr No
can't possibly be Rogue because tus is
better with who they end up is U happier
with who they end up with than they
would be with Dr
no remember Rogue pair requires both
members of the pair to prefer each other
rather than their assigned partner so
since tus is happier with their assigned
partner than with Dr No TS and Dr No
cannot be
Rogue does that make
sense all right so we just use that
invariant to say that since tus rejected
Dr No their eventual partner is better
than Dr
No that's all that that is saying what
about the other side what about toughs
with Doctor Who Doctor Who Never spoke
with toughs during the algorithm all
right and since drct
who uh
never spoke with
toughs well remember what the applicants
are doing they're going down their list
from the top and since they stopped
before they got to Tufts wherever they
stopped they like better than they like
toughs so doctor
who
likes their
partner better than they like
toughs
right and
therefore toughs with Doctor Who Can't
Be Rogue not Rogue
because this time it's Doctor Who who's
happier with their assignment than they
would be with
TS so in this case tus would be happier
or tus is happier with their current
partner in this case Doctor Who is
happier with their current partner in
both of these cases tfts with this
person on the right cannot be Rogue so
toughs can't be Rogue with anyone so
there are no Rogue pairs
no rope pairs can exist the matching we
get at the end is in fact
stable did that make
sense
awesome okay let's return to this
question of how good is this matching is
this the one that makes everyone
maximally happy or minimally happy or
somewhere in the middle does anyone have
excuse me does anyone have an advantage
if you were participating in this
algorithm would you prefer to be an
applicant or an
evaluator well can kind of go both ways
we already said that applicants
prospects only get worse over time and
evaluators Prospects only get better
over time so maybe it's better to be an
evaluator on the other hand applicants
start at the top and they stay as close
to the top as they can until someone
grudgingly says okay I guess I'll keep
you um so maybe it's better to be an
applicant because you're always asking
the best um the best partner you you can
possibly have rather than the evaluators
who have to wait around for people to
come to
them so it's it's maybe not clear which
side is
preferable so let me give some let me
give a term so we can measure what we
mean by
preferable uh first of all let's say
um excuse me so if e is an evaluator and
a is an applicant uh let's say that E
and A are
feasible
Partners if and only if it's
possible to put E and A together
in a stable
matching not necessarily the stable
matching that the algorithm gives but if
there's any stable matching that pairs e
with a together then we'll say that they
are feasible
Partners all right and now we have the
following
theorems the Gail shapley
algorithm pairs every
applicant with
their most
preferred feasible
partner so each applicant doesn't get
their Top Choice we know they can't each
get their first choice because there
might be conflicts there um but each
applicant turns out gets the best
possible choice they could ever hope to
get among all possible stable
matchings so up here on the board we see
that um applicant a is paired with
evaluator 2 and not with one or
three and what this theorem says is that
a can never be paired with one and can
never be paired with three in any stable
matching there is no stable matching
that pairs a with one there is no stable
matching that pairs a with three a
paired with two is the highest
preference um partner that a has that is
feasible and Gail shap Gail shapley
gives him that
partner so every evaluator gets the best
partner they could possibly get in any
stable
matching I personally find this
surprising like often we when we have
some optimization problem but we have
lots of different metrics that we're
trying to optimize um like candidate a
wants to get their best possible partner
candidate B wants to get their best
possible partner and to me it it feels
intuitive that maybe these desires might
conflict with each other like maybe A
and B both have um evaluator 3 as their
optimal partner uh and there are just
two different stable matchings one that
pairs a with three one that pairs B with
three um so it's kind of weird to me
that each candidate can be given their
optimal partner their optimal feasible
partner
all at the same time and there's no
conflict among them so I find this a
little bit counterintuitive for that
reason beautiful fact but a little
counterintuitive
and Theorem Gail
shapley pairs every
evaluator with their this time least
preferred
feasible
partner so exactly the same idea but
this time the evaluators instead of
coming out as best as they possibly can
they come out as worst as they possibly
can because evaluator uh let's say
because evaluator one ended up with
partner
c um there is no stable matching that
pairs one with anyone worse than C
there's no stable matching that pairs
one with B there's no stable matching
that pairs one with
a um so it's best for all of the
applicants at the same time and
simultaneously worst uh for all of the
evaluators at the same time this single
matching that Gail shapley returns has
all of these properties in
it um which brings us back to the
question earlier if we were to run this
algorithm in reverse by swapping the
roles of the evaluators and the
applicants we're going to swap from
we're going to move from the matching
that is best for this set to to the one
that's best for the other set and the
one that's worst for the first set to
the one that's best for the other set
and that's why usually you're going to
get two different matchings out of it
because if there are multiple matchings
multiple stable matchings at all for
this set of preferences the worst and
the best are going to be different from
each other
do these ideas make sense we haven't
proven them yet but are the ideas do the
ideas make
sense all right uh let me give you just
a a brief hint at how we might go about
proving this we'll prove it more
precisely in recitation
tomorrow but the basic
idea pause for dramatic effect
the basic idea is going to be oh I'm
holding chalk I found
it um one more uh key invariant so
invariant for our Gail shapley
algorithm uh so if an
evaluator
ever rejects an applicant a
then
EA are not
feasible
Partners so if e rejects a at any time
during the Gil shapley
algorithm then there does not exist any
stable matching at all that puts e with
a
together uh turns out we can prove this
um as an invariant of our state machine
machine uh very briefly let's see if we
can do that um okay
so uh Al also this is true for all
evaluators and for all applicants if any
evaluator rejects any applicant at any
time then they're not feasible
Partners so the the heart of the proof
is let's
assume um that an evaluator
e uh rejects an applicant
a today
so we've newly rejected someone and so
now we're going to show that E and A
can't be feasible
Partners uh well in
favor of applicant B in favor sorry in
favor of a prime so if e rejects this
applicant in favor of that
applicant well then we know that e
prefers the new applicant over the old
applicant because that's the only reason
e would reject one for the
other uh and then the claim
here um or the the main
observation is that let's
see in any uh
hypothetical
stable matching not necessarily the one
that comes from Gil shapley but in any
possible stable matching you try to set
up
where a matches with E and then
necessarily a prime matches with someone
else um you can
prove that a sorry that e and a
prime are
rogue so because e rejected a prime in
favor of a on some day in the algorithm
um you can show that anytime you try to
pair a with e together in a stable
matching actually it's not stable cuz e
and a prime are are rogue they each
prefer each other uh you'll see the
details of that in recitation tomorrow
thank you so much