So I'm going to uh just show you about
what's going on at the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center, what's going on on
the ground uh and sort of where future
directions are for fusion, right? So we
start always with the description of
this because
why why do you do fusion energy? Well,
it's actually the universe already
voted. It is literally the reason life
exists in the in the universe. In fact,
the interesting atoms in your body were
made by fusion in stars and and life is
possible in the universe because of
fusion because that's what happens at
the center of stars and powers the
universe. So fusion basically takes
isotopes of hydrogen which are highly
available fuses them together to make
helium which is a very stable nucleus
and this releases massive amounts of
energy and in fact transforms it. In
fact that's what the sun is. It's
basically an enormous conversion engine
between hydrogen and helium. uh this has
to happen at extremely high
temperatures. So therefore all fusion
happens in the plasma state of matter
which is the fourth state of matter and
it only occurs in one place naturally in
the universe which is at the center of
stars because it's the only place where
the temperature requisite temperatures
to achieve the fusion reactivity exist
and the center of ownar is about 20
million degrees and it has enormous
pressure and it's basically the the way
it works is that it has that temperature
and isolation thermal isolation to stay
hot. uh because of the enormous forces
of gravity. That's why star but gravity
is extremely weak force. So basically in
the end if you want to translate this to
earth you need to figure out a way to
make star-like conditions but actually
happen in a container on earth which
means you have to replace gravity with
another fundamental force. Right? So why
do we pursue it as uh as as an energy
source on earth? So you get no polluting
emissions because the thing that it
makes is helium. Right? The fuel supply
is inexhaustible because it comes from
water and and and and the the light the
light abundant elements is basically
dutarium and lithium which come from
water and you get so much energy per
unit mass you basically cannot run out
of it. It's a it's it's also free
basically too. Um you also get 10
million times more energy than you can
get in a chemical reaction. So that's a
pretty big factor that's that has a that
that coincides with fision energy which
basically you get the same factor as
that. Unlike fision though because it
doesn't run on a uh it doesn't run on a
a chain reaction you actually is it it's
physically impossible to have a runaway
chain reaction. So you cannot directly
weaponize fusion. Meltdowns are
physically impossible because there's
not enough thermal energy in the system
to actually make that happen. So you
don't actually physics gives you safety
in fusion not engineering design. And
basically we've known this as as uh as
Klaus pointed out since we understood
how stars worked which wasn't that long
ago by the way give us a bit of a break
you know as a species right uh we're
actually coming up it's going to be in
about three or four years will be the
100th anniversary of when we understood
how stars work and what the fusion
process was. So, it's hasn't been that
long, right? I like to point out to my
students when my mother was born,
humanity didn't know how the universe
worked, right? Because we didn't know
about fusion. Okay? Um, and the key
other part of this is because of those
features, um, it's a it's a unique
energy source in the sense it's not
limited by the traditional kinds of
things that limit other kinds of energy
sources, which is access to some kind of
raw resource. So, in the cases of
petroleum, that's an obvious one. But
even in other things like in solar and
wind, it's access to places that have
wind and solar or hydroelectric things.
It's like that's not what fusion is.
Fusion is a purely technologydriven
uh energy source, not not not a resource
uh limited one, right? So it's it's like
the it's like the digitalization of
energy. That's what I like to say. And
if you in fact look at these this is
about why why you pursue this is that in
the end like these limitations around
like why is it hard, right? because well
chemical and fision reactions happen at
near room temperature. Fusion has to
happen on earth at about 100 million
degrees. Um but you cannot and because
this comes from the physics like the
things that come out of fision and
chemical reactions have significant
consequences. In the case of of
petroleum it has to do with CO2. In the
case of fusion it has to do with the
byproducts that come out of it and you
can't avoid those. In the in the case of
fusion in the end it is it is just
literally helium and another subatomic
particle that you actually recycle in
it. So those fundamentals are always
there. Just the question is like can you
actually achieve these conditions to
actually make this work right? So how do
you do this? So the way that you do this
is you as I as I stated you have to
replace uh the mechanism how it works in
the sun or in any star. And what this
requires is a containment force. But it
cannot be a physical containment force
because anything terrestrial that is in
contact with the fusion plasma fuel will
make it go cold and therefore the fusion
will stop. These are other reasons why
it's inherently safe because any the
moment it gets cold it instantly stops.
So in fact it's the the analogy I like
to do. So, a power plant that would be
running Cambridge um uh Massachusetts,
if I went like that on on the fusion
fuel, it would stop all fusion instantly
because it can't be at room temperature.
So, what does that actually mean? It
means the difficulty is that you have to
provide an a force which basically
exerts a pressure on this fuel to
isolate it away from anything
terrestrial. It can't even contact air,
right? So, how do you do this? Well, you
have to use the fundamental forces of
nature. And one of those is the
electromagnetic force, which is much
stronger than gravitational. And it
turns out one of the features of plasmas
is because it's very hot, all the
particles in it have a charge. And when
you immerse charged particles in a
magnetic field that it exerts a force.
So the the size of that force goes like
the strength of the magnetic field. And
in the end, what you do is you have a
there's a variety of these of these
configurations. The most common one is
this thing called a tokamac which is
basically just a configuration of
electromagnets which are those things
going around which make a magnetic field
which is immersed in the that is
immersed in the plasma. So the
interesting the plasma know there's a
magnetic field there because it exerts a
force on it but the magnets don't know
that there's a thermonuclear plasma
inside of it and neither does the plasma
know that there's magnets on the
outside. They just it's it's essentially
like a force at a distance. So that's
the nature of the isolation about how we
basically then hold the star in place.
Uh and because the the force is orders
of magnitude larger than gravity, this
allows you to now reduce it to a size
that you can actually place it in this
room rather than have to be the size of
a sun. Right? There's another way that
you can do this is that you can actually
use grav it's it's a different it's not
actually gravitational force. It's a
pressure force. And what you do is you
take lasers and you and you and you you
basically have a spherical target of
fuel. You ablate the uh outside of this
and by and by basically like an inverse
like an inside out rocket. What you do
is you so rapidly compress the fuel that
it gets hot in the center and basically
it ignites fusion. So you can actually
do this and actually MIT works on on
both of these uh both of these. I'll get
back to some right. So, you know, it's
important to remember is that while I'll
get to economics is like like this is
hard. This is this is really hard
science, right? And and it's this thing
that sits at uh the intersection always
of difficult science and and and and at
the edge of of technology, right? So,
this is just so for example, this is a
picture over here what's showing down on
the bottom right. Um so you this is this
is showing a simulation which is based
on decades of research around being able
to understand microurbulence that is
happening in in this plasma this fuel
that's uh immersed in this magnetic
field and it turns out because when you
heat it what happens is it drives
gradients. So these are the equivalents
of like solar flares that you see in the
sun this is happening in the inside of
the fusion device. So it turned out just
even measuring these things took a
decade of development because it was so
hard. These these are perturbations
which are at the order of only of a few
percent and things like the temperature
uh and and the and the and of the
background plasma. But it turned out
this was in fact what was limiting the
performance of of of it. Uh here's a
picture over here is my colleague Zach
Zack Hartwig over here one of the other
co-founders of Commonwealth Fusion
Systems. So we you'll I'll show you a
picture that this was a development of a
new magnet technology which has opened
up the possibility for commercial
fusion. But because the magnet itself
was in completely new territory, there
was literally nothing to test it with.
So we actually had to develop a
completely new technology just to
complete the test, let alone the actual
new technology. And there and and this
is not small science, right? This is one
of the largest experimental halls on the
MIT campus. You can see the size of
these kinds of things and and Zach uh I
hope he's being safe there uh standing
on top of it with cryogenic uh things
coming out of it. Yeah. So in the end
this is what fusion is it's it's it's
actually why you have fusion at a place
like MIT. It is the ultimate
multidisciplinary
uh endeavor. This is not just physics
but you have to know physics. It's
integrating pretty much every
engineering discipline and uh and many
and most of the scientific disciplines
as well too. That's why we have the
PSFC.
Um, so just to get back to some like why
are we excited about fusion and have we
made break and like I get interviewed a
lot like why are we excited about fusion
and there's basically three reasons and
I'll go through them. One of them is we
have made breakthroughs in the science
of this after decades of very difficult
research. we have we've gotten the place
in it and then probably the most
exciting scientific result is the is
this one is that in California a few
years ago as I said what they did was
they use these lasers by the way these
are these laser beams which are coming
in this is an extraordinary
accomplishment of technology each of
those each of the it has 192 lasers uh
each of those lasers was the biggest
laser built by humanity uh and then they
then they aim it at a thing which is the
size of about the the tip of my little
finger, right? And instantaneously the
power in those layers uh those lasers is
about triple the entire electric output
of the United States. Like wow, right? H
the reason you can do that is because it
happens for a billionth of a second,
right? It illuminates the inside of this
one of gold and other exotic materials,
creates an X-ray bath, and then that
X-ray bath illuminates this uh fusion
fuel target which is in the center. and
on fraction of a of a mil billionth of a
second so rapidly compresses it that you
get adiabatic heating in the center of
this and you reach the requisite
temperatures which are required to do
this so it took a decade of dedicated
research with MIT at the lead of a lot
of the this is very very difficult to
measure this because it's happening in a
billionth of a second so we actually had
a division um uh we have a division at
the fusion center training and in fact a
lot of the breakthroughs were done by
previous MIT students who were at the
Livermore National Laboratory where this
happened as well too. So we had a major
part in this. Um and after a decade of
of of under better understanding of
this, we finally got it to the point
where this actually exceeded the point
where the the total amount of energy
that was being released from the fusion
exceeded the amount of energy that was
being delivered by the lasers. So this
is still a far away from
commercialization, trust me. But this is
an enormous scientific accomplishment
because it showed us something really
important which is that namely it got
the fuel to the condition that it looked
like the sun. Right? You know this is
nothing plugged into the sun. It runs
itself. The how that works is because
fusion works by heating the fuel. So
when fusion reactions occur that
releases heat into the fuel and it's
that that heat that temperature that
then allows future fu fusion reactions
to occur. So instantaneously what
happened in a billionth of a second is
that this created so many fusion
reactions that the temperature of the
fuel spontaneously increased by a factor
of four
and that condition uh that self-heating
is a necessary and fundamental part of
every fusion concept that you will ever
have. So the fact that we know that this
works was an enormous check off of the
scientific risk list even even though
the technology itself has a this one has
a ways to go right to that one. But the
one that's the furthest along in terms
of commercialization is magnetic
confinement fusion. So as I said before
I described this before you create these
extremely large you have these strong
magnetic fields which are immersed in
it. So how do we know that this is close
to the commercialization? Because on the
MIT campus, we actually operated this
device called Alcatore Sea. It it ceased
operations about 8 years ago. But in
this thing which is about the size of a
coat closet and there it goes. So this
is immersed in magnetic fields which are
about a million times stronger than the
earth's magnetic field and in something
that I can actually wrap my my hands
around that had temperatures which ex
which are five times hotter than the
center of the sun. So was a about 100
million degrees and that was done about
30 times a day, right? And in fact in
that device we in fact exceeded another
key parameter which is that it exceeded
two atmospheres of pressure from the
plasma. So it turns out a power plant
has to operate at about four uh
atmospheres of pressure. Wow. Like this
is not mythology. This is real science
that was actually done. The pro the
challenge with this one though was that
while this science was was very
illuminating and in particular this this
what this came from was the deep
expertise at MIT about producing very
strong magnetic fields is that to
produce that magnetic field we had to
use about 250 megawatts of electricity.
Oops, that was bad. Right? So it was a
science demonstration. So what we had to
do was translate that into how would you
then commercialize that? Right. Oh,
sorry. Right. So, how you commercialize
that is sorry that's in the few slides.
So, this is in fact why we have the
PSFC. So, you're starting to get some
sense of the scale around this. Right.
So, I was as I said I was the director
Dun Lorero is now the director. This is
not your typical this is not a Bunson
burner and a postocck right to do fusion
you need scale right uh and I think this
is one of the other uh attributes of MIT
which I very much in fact I'm coming up
to my 20th anniversary of being lured to
MIT um it was this like the ability to
do research and integrated research at
scale and immerse it in the educational
experience is really quite unique to MIT
I'm not just and this happens not just
at the PSFC to places like Rlecale. So
what do we have? This is a 20 200 It's
like I it's almost like a small national
lab immersed at a university like
250,000 ft of lab space. Not just lab
space but things that can handle
ionizing radiation, large power. There's
if you take everybody in including
visiting scientists, it's almost 300
people there. 90 graduate students,
right? Obvious, right? And we take up a
city block which is over here. And very
important, you see over here that we
actually also encompass the magnet lab
as well too which is over here. And by
the way, there's the nuclear reactor
right beside us. So we have a lot of
more interactions actually going on
right now because of course we share
nuclear engineering as a discipline with
our colleagues over in fision, right? So
why are we all excited about this? Well,
it's mostly because remember I told you
there's basically three things that have
changed fusion in the last few years.
One of them was a major scientific
breakthrough which is that we see now it
will work if we get this if we get the
plasma to the right state. We we didn't
that wasn't confirmed before. And this
is the second one which is an
interesting one because it's both a
technological but it's also an
organizational innovation is that you'll
never get there if this always stays in
government labs because it will always
just be a science project which is
totally fine if you want to do science
projects. But if you want to save the
world, you got to build companies and
you have to make products as Sergey will
keep telling you uh and you have to
build economically efficient products
that actually that allow this to come to
market and you have to do that with
companies. So you know so what we did
was that we realized that there was a
technology innovation which I'll get to
actually run around on this um that what
it allowed was for a a great a vast
change not just infusion performance but
infusion economics
um and because of that realization we we
understood that in order to to deliver
on this we needed to be able to launch a
a private company and that was
Commonwealth Fusion Systems and what we
have built is basically a seven-year
partnership that has co-developed the
magnets and MIT has obviously the the
science uh and educational lead on this
and and Commonwealth Fusion Systems
which has now raised about $3 billion of
private money and its purpose is
commercialization because MIT can't hold
that purpose uh directly and in fact it
was not just a technical innovation I'm
vastly proud of the organizational
innovation that we did in this is that
we came up with a extremely transparent
licensing and working relationship that
particular particularly in the early
vulnerable stages of the technology. MIT
and and the company worked hand in hand
to actually develop this technology and
that and that collaboration continues to
go forward. So what is it doing? Well,
it's basically building this guy here.
It's called Spark. It's about 40 uh
minutes away in the western suburbs of
Boston. And then this little object you
can produce, and this is why you would
now get excited. Okay, so this will
produce around uh 200 million watts of
fusion power.
And unlike the example that I showed you
before, it's actually only a factor of
about two away from that device that I
showed you with a picture an but these
new but it has a new kind of magnet
around it that can produce a stronger
magnetic field and consumes zero
electricity because it's a
superconducting magnet.
So if you count up all of the power
going into it to get it hot compared to
the fusion power, it makes 10 times more
fusion power than the power it takes to
get the fuel hot.
And this fits in the corner of this
room.
So now the idea is and and by the way
compared to the previous technology it's
40 times smaller than this. And you
might have heard of this project called
it's called Ear which is in the south of
France. It's the world's largest
scientific project and that was one of
its problems. It was the world's largest
scientific project. Yeah you can see the
people standing beside it.
So what we developed uh with much toil
uh in fact this uh so what we developed
uh at the PSFC and then launched through
uh CFS was not just a technology but it
was a commercialization plan and it was
actually it was driven by if you're
going to make fusion uh attractive and
viable as an energy source you have to
get its cost to performance much much
better and you have to shorten the
development time. So that's what we did.
It was this really well-laidout plan and
in particular what this rested on were
were three uh things which were we had
the science of high field fusion and
then it was we had to build a
demonstration of this new kind of
superconducting magnet and this then
particularly this part we did in close
collaboration with commonalth fusion
systems. Oops. Um and then
Commonwealth's job was to start
commercializing around on those things.
Get out there raise money. In fact that
number is now 2.8 billion uh dollars as
well too. And then we collaborate on
this demonstration project called spark
which itself is protocommercial.
And then the idea is that that all
drives itself towards because this works
at the same specifications as this which
is arc which is the first commercial
fusion power plant. And I have to take
some pride in this is that this was in
fact uh this was invented in my fusion
design class. So the are this is another
hallmark of MIT is that and then the
students I had basically 12 MIT graduate
students saved fusion and maybe the
world actually around on this and those
students now run the company like that's
MIT. Yep. Um so uh and and no it doesn't
stand for Iron Man's uh fusion power
reactor in his chest because that would
be a trademark infringement. Um in fact
a very so we're basically we are seeing
this all the way through and of course
it's CFS's job to build this because it
is a commercial endeavor but of course
there's a lot of research to do around
on this and now recently uh in fact uh
just under a year ago the site and
commercial partners for building ARC are
set it's just outside of Richmond
Virginia uh at an ex uh at at a an
existing power station it's just south
of uh Virginia an interesting story of
that the reason that that site became
available able is because the local town
voted down um they they they basically
voted down uh the installation of a new
gas fired power plant there but they
open they they welcomed with open arms
the installation of a fusion power
plant.
Wow. Yeah. I've been on the site. It's
quite inspiring. Yeah. So what what
happened it was basically this. It was
this new I won't go through the details
of this but it was this new like almost
honestly like a miracle technology came
along. It was a new kind of
superconducting material called rare
earth barium copper oxide which what it
allowed was it had much higher tolerance
to very strong magnetic fields. So this
is what we built um in the span of about
3 years. Uh in fact another interesting
aspect of like this is an ILP conference
about an academic place working
alongside of a a commercial company
because that had took private investment
to do this. We said they said okay we'll
take this risk with you but you have to
deliver this in three years and we had a
nationalmy's report that said it would
take 15 years.
How are you going to do it? Well, that
was very interesting because what you
had to do is basically take a startup
attitude, right, of quickly build,
learn, fail this go at this really break
neck pace but still have incredible
science and technology innovations. So
there's something like 30 patents
involved in this as well too. And it
basically just was basically broke all
kinds of grounds and not just the
performance of the magnet but also the
scalability of the magnet. And the thing
that I'm the most proud of this in this
one and I got to write the physics paper
the physics validation which was an
incredible paper to read because it
broke new ground and and the physics of
superconducting magnets all amazing. The
thing I'm the most proud of is the fact
that there was CFS had a factory
building these magnets in less than a
year after the demonstration of this
magnet. And that was the other power
actually of coupling a place like the
PSFC and and and and um and a company
right along it. So what did it do? It
produces 20 Tesla magnificion times the
earth's magnetic field. And it was that
doubling of the magnetic field that
overnight basically changed the cost per
watt by about a factor of 40. And that
goes back to Sergey's comments. This is
why it was fusion was too expensive
before and now we've got a shot at it in
fact. Right. Right. Oh, it's also this
it's also uh uh the other amazing thing
about MIT is it alumni. This was this
was also started by a million-doll
donation by somebody who was an MIT a
fan of conservation and wanted to see
this actually have a chance. So this is
amazing. Now, um I would say that we had
no while while there were a few fusion
companies that existed before us, the
mere existence of MIT launching a fusion
company and raising $3 billion and
bringing like the who's who of investors
to the space uh really changed this. So,
not only uh did it did it launch
Commonwealth Fusion Systems, this
basically launched an international race
for commercializing fusion. uh and here
and you can see it's it's pretty heavy
USA based uh on this there's over $10
billion raised uh in this there's over
40 fusion companies I have an industry
association I love competition actually
in this space I'll also take with some
in fact I I I I took a as I said I took
a year sobbatical after stepping down as
the director uh and when I came back to
teach my design class I seen all those
fresh students out in the in the and I
realized I looked at this thing and it's
like oh my gosh five of those companies
were basically directly inspired that
the the CEOs or the ideas came out of
that design class. So it's not just
Commonwealth fusion systems were in fact
we're making these because so many of
them also use the new Rebco magnets as
well too. So very very exciting times uh
in that one.
So what's this is also spurred now is
basically this is because of the promise
of commercialization it has spurred a
geopolitical race in this space. So
here's the third thing that changed
right around on this which was in fact
it was two things at the same time which
was basically almost nobody talks about
fusion for uh decarbonization anymore.
That's actually not what it's about.
It's about energy security and it's
about supplying a delta in energy for
data centers which is a beautiful irony
because we're going to use AI like crazy
to actually make fusion work. Yes. Um,
and because of the geopolitical
importance of energy security and AI,
now national governments are stepping in
in a major way and understanding that if
you because if you can unlock this at
the right price point, it's the largest
geopolitical disruption of the century.
It's bigger than AI
because you can't do AI without energy.
again the biggest polit geopolitical
disruption of the century probably of
humanity actually because you will never
actually have to worry about energy
access ever again
just think about that right we are not
there but that's the prize that is out
there okay so what has this meant this
meant the UK has stepped in in a major
way in fact that slide is out of date
they've committed billions of pounds
actually to this already and they've
established a national program that puts
the US to shame actually on on this one
about commercializing fusion and China
has literally copied everything that
we've done. They actually admit they've
copied everything we've done. We we
published that paper, that magnet. They
actually in 14 months they replicated
that magnet. The entire supply chain
construction of that magnet and its
testing in 14 months.
So they're spending about about four or
five billion dollars actually into this.
And they're also putting us to shame
actually in this. In fact, it's a
national disgrace that the US government
in fact is sitting on his hands while
the major innovations actually in the
space have been spurred on by US indust
uh US industry and universities. It's
kind of amazing. Call your
congressperson please about this. If
you're an American company, if you live
if you're from from some other country,
good because you're you're you're
kicking you're kicking us on. Japan has
emerged actually already on this as well
too. And this is very interesting
because it's going to become
geopolitical because of the consequences
actually of this as well too. So like
the G7 now has a working uh group on
fusion energy. Wow.
So where's the where's the PSFC now?
Well, it's one of those fulcrum points
because we're not an industry. We're
still a research lab. But I would say we
turned around the purpose of the PSFC.
The PS the purpose of the PSC before was
multiddisciplinary research around this
this this science topic of fusion and
now our purpose is to support and uh
incubate basically a new energy industry
right and so what does that mean this
means you have to have extremely broad
sponsorship not just from this
traditional sponsors like the department
of energy and NSF and particularly
they're proving to be fickle sponsors
around this and need to get the RP is a
great one by the way because it
commercial focuses and
commercialization. Over here you can see
we have some of the companies that we
helped launch like CFS. We have deep
runs with type and these are a variety
of different kinds of configurations.
NTO which is another one that we came
out of the class and and I see Roberto
here in uh Ian and I was has been an
incredible sponsor of this both as a
member of mighty uh and all this and in
fact was one of the real thought leaders
in the energy space about supporting
this at a very early stage and in fact
is is is distributed widely around in
the fusion world. So this is amazing
actually for a place. But all I would
say is that you recognize to this
audience is that our purpose now has
changed and our and our ability to
couple into industries and think about
like emerging industries and think about
what that means is that that's really a
hallmark in fact of what of what the
PSFC is. Um so what do we need actually?
Well, as I said we're still quite a ways
like we have major technical challenges
because we actually go to this thing
which is again the design that came out.
How do we how do we in fact make all of
this work? Well, you have to have these
really strong and efficient
superconducting magnets that basically
check on that. And now we actually have
this at industrial capacity. Oh, and and
by the way, we see this now is that I it
took us uh in in the end the
construction of that of that test magnet
took about a year and now they're making
one of those every week in the factory
out in by Comusion Systems. A voila
industrialization and commercialization.
So that's kind of a check mark on that.
Uh we we are we are using machine
learning, quantum computing, AI out the
like like crazy because these are
complicated design and operational
objects, right? Uh you also have to make
sure that you convert the this fusion
energy into power and other things. So
we actually have this in the terms of a
this is this so-called blanket that
basically surrounds the fusion plasma.
And in the end, you also want to have
highly durable materials that can
actually withstand this kind of insane
environment. And that's actually our new
capability with uh at the with that. So
what are we accelerating progress on?
They said superconducting magnets. And
in fact, now we're working with a a a
company is in some sense a not not
necessarily competitor, but is it is a
different kind of topology for the
magnetic field. And so they have to
produce three-dimensional rather than
planer coils in this. And so we're
actually testing that with them right
now for the fusion company. Uh we're
designing new advanced concepts right
now in my class. We have a completely in
fact this was a uh this this this
actually came out of my uh design class
as well too uh for a different slightly
different mission actually of this and
can we continue to do that. We actually
have real u small versions of these
blankets which basically capture the
fusion energy. And we're also working on
things like uh for example additive
manufacturing which can really change
how you design uh and build some of
these complex objects that go inside of
the fusion power plant.
But we also have to remember is that
this is like like we have still a long
ways to go in this right. So while we've
invested like order of $10 billion, it's
also distributed around basically
something like 25 different concepts. So
getting each one concept to like a power
plant demonstration design is minimum
probably order of $5 billion. So guess
what financing
uh is a major uh and industrial capacity
are two major risks actually of fusion
right now. Again, it's one of the
reasons we act Andrew Low and I started
uh uh Ratherford Energy Ventures was to
actually open up new pathways for
different kinds of commercial uh um
commercialization uh and sorry um
financing mechanisms around on these
things. Um uh we we are still at a point
in we're still at an infant stage about
how we actually while we have a really
good bead about how to get the cost per
watt down. the levelized costs are
highly uncertain in fusion because the
integrated operational environment is
uncertain because we just haven't done
it before. So if I go to in fact if I
look I see Charles here if we go to our
fision colleagues when they when they
introduced the first commercial fision
reactors they only worked at about 40 or
50% capacity factor because the fuel
rods kept failing in them and they had
to stop and replace them and now they
work at like 90%. But that took like a
decade or more of experience. So how are
we going to improve that? We're actually
working on that at PSFC as well too.
Yeah.
So how are we doing this? So one of them
is this really exciting experiment
called Libra which I will not go through
the example of this. This basically is a
this this thing that surrounds the
fusion plasma which captures the fusion
energy and actually converts and yes
fusion is an alchemy tool. It actually
changes the elements of the things which
are around it. In fact, that's one of
the cool things in my class that I'm
working on right now. Not only do we we
use this to actually uh recircle the cat
the catalytic extra neutron that comes
into it. We can also use these to
produce things really interesting
isotopes like gold. So it turns out you
can you can actually produce gold at a
pretty significant scale actually in a
fusion device. So that's one of the
things my students are this week. In
fact, tomorrow morning I'm going to get
an update on that result as well too. So
this is a real experimental capability
and basically is a is on the frontier of
science. And by the way, this is an
interesting one because this is like a
totally set of different disciplines
than plasmas. There's no plasmas
involved in this. This is integrated
nuclear engineering, right? So it's like
well yeah that's why we have we do this
actually at the PSFC and in fact in
collaboration with our u with our
colleagues at the nuclear reactor lab.
But now it is getting to the real thing
that is that we're actually using real
fusion energy products and making real
fusion fuel actually out of this and
it's critical to fusion's ability to ex
uh to actually to expand um once we
start building the first ones. Another
key one is the fact that we have very
little um um information about how solid
materials will react to these very
energetic particles. um and they will
they have to react by the laws of
physics. So what we've done is in fact
this is another interesting another one
that came out of a student design effort
about 15 years ago uh and we designed
this and I think Charles actually you
might remember this right and we looked
at we said yeah but this cyclron
technology is not available and then in
the span of 10 years the cyclron which
is basically compact kind of accelerator
became available. So what this does is
it it it basically it tricks the
materials into thinking it's being
damaged by neutrons when it's actually
being damaged by protons. Um and this is
uh this is funded by a very generation
donation from Eric Schmidt uh and his
family. Uh and we're we're reutilizing
the space where we had the fusion
experiment and now we're going to be on
the frontier of in fact testing
materials for the first time in a
prototypic environment for for fusion.
And it is in fact a private public
partnership because it turns out we can
also use this for example to assay
fision materials as well too and this is
coming online uh in about 6 months.
Uh a final area which is a very
interesting one it's it's also the
reason that you do fusion like can I
guarantee that fusion will get there?
I'm always ask this when Dennis when is
it going to come because we've heard
about fusion for so long right? Well,
the fact is we already have the SC. You
have to be careful about what is like a
good professor. You have to ask the
right question. What do you mean? Is it
here? The science of fusion is here.
We've already done it. Like we create we
recreate the conditions of stars on
Earth. We already accomplished that.
We've already made net energy from
fusion. We just on the cusp of actually
scient protocommercial demonstration.
That's what spark will do which will
turn on in about a year and a half. If
you see something making 200 million
watts of power and have large net energy
gain, yeah, of course, it's ready to
take that step into commercialization.
But those are the wrong that's actually
not the question. The question is, can
you make affordable
fusion energy? So, I totally agree with
Sergey on that right on that one. And it
is hard. And it's hard because it's this
thing that sits at the intersection of
pretty much everything that you're doing
is right at the edge of what you're
allowed to do technologically, right? So
one of the good examples of that is like
how you heat the plasma and how you
construct objects which are close by to
the plasma. So in this case it turns out
another kind of like amazing thing which
also had its roots at MIT is additive
manufacturing. So we have these very
special microwaves that we basically
launch into the plasma and they need
these hollowed out kind of structures
with with traditional manufacturing.
They're a nightmare to make. We are now
making these at spec with additive
manufacturing. And in fact there's the
picture of it right here being installed
by my colleague Andrew. Fantastic. And
guess what? There's a synergy with this
because also an idea launched from the
PSFC was that one of my clever
colleagues Paul Wascov uh about 15 years
ago realized that this very specialized
radio frequency technology that was
being used for heating the thermonuclear
plasma that if you actually turned it
around instead of aiming it at the
plasma and aimed it at the earth you
could start drilling holes.
And what this meant was because it's a
totally different physical mechanism
than the mechanical drilling, this has
the theoretical possibility of being
able to drill holes kilometers into the
earth.
And what would for the reason of what
unlocking deep hard rock so so-called
hot hot hard hard rock geothermal
and this is not just theory. That's
actually holes that have been drilled in
rocks at the PSFC on this. So now
there's also an ongoing effort. I I
can't tell the details there. There's an
emerging effort about this. This is why
you do things like fusion. It's just
like that technology to develop that is
at the right at the cusp of everything
we know about superconducting magnets,
RF technology. Guess what? It might have
this other incredible use which is that
and there's ongoing efforts and that's
going to get a lot more serious. All I
can say is in the next few years and if
you're interested in that particular
space space, you know, please contact me
because there's a lot of very exciting
emerging efforts in that one, right?
Oh, and actually I guess they did have
the slide. Oh, yeah. This is the slide I
made. Yeah, there we go. um is that so
what this looks like is the idea of at
the PSFC have something which is
basically an engineering integrated tool
that starts answering these really this
questions about geothermal which is we
it's it's another one of these by the
way which we know it's physically
possible but is it economically possible
and we actually have to really uh do
some more work about uh properly
capturing what are the requirements of
this like what is the drilling rate what
is the depth that you can go to what
would be the durability of the holes and
basically put it to the economic litmus
test, not just the physics limus test.
Um so fusion is also interesting as I as
I said it's it's launched a geopolitical
race. um you know there are efforts
right now in the US government uh
attempting to stand up private public
partnerships um and a few of these but
this is also um
the biggest surprise in this if you
would have asked me 10 years ago that I
would be giving a talk that we've made
the superconducting magnet that we've
launched a multi-billion dollar company
that we've got tens of different
competitive ones and we have a bead on
commercial fusion energy and a with all
of that and the US government is doing
nothing different than it did 10 years
ago in supporting fusion is kind of
amazing, right? So, please call your
Congress people. This is ridiculous. Um,
we're being outspent by a factor of a
hundred by ch by by China in this area
about commercializing fusion around in
this. Yeah.
And I really do want to end with and of
course a hallmark of MIT is that the the
way that we make this work is through
our students, right? Is that um the
ideas like those companies are littered
with our with our graduates, right? And
now we have a whole new generation of
students not just working on plasma
physics but on this integrated
technology and they are inspiring
because they they they want this to get
all the way there which is all the way
to commercially viable fusion right and
u just say that our private research
partners are significant including ENI
commonwealth fusion systems one of our
own spinouts type one which actually
came out of University of Wisconsin but
is of our colleagues bridge 12
technologies which does these gyrons and
many many others as well too so it's a
very exciting time at the PSFC as you
say we've opened our doors to pretty
integrated research with industry with
the energy industry and with associated
technologies which are around it as well
too. So what's next? So please keep your
eye out for this. As I said I I I was I
was not I was hoping that it would be
been accept accepted yet but we've so I
took the last year and I sat down and I
took Sergey's advice and I realized I
didn't know anything about economics. So
I had one of the world's best e
economists teach me about e e e e e e e
e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e
e e e e e e e e e e e e e economics,
Andrew Low uh and but I know a lot about
fusion and I sat down and I wrote a
completely new framework for evaluating
fusion economics uh in this. So this is
going to be published fairly soon and u
maybe in a couple years I can give the
talk about that which which reveals some
very interesting things and by the way
Sergey you can get there.
You can get there.
I don't know if we can get there but you
can get there. Yeah, actually actually
right. Yep. Um, as I said, we're doing
the psychotron for these materials
testing. We have Libra for doing this uh
for doing the fusion fuel. Um, and I'll
end that with uh with machine learning
because as I said, I said three things
have changed, right? It was around to
that. It was scientific breakthroughs.
We've had true technology breakthroughs
and then this is the other one that's
changed it because the reasoning around
fusion and the sponsorship of something
like Fusion has completely changed under
our feet. Nobody. And in fact, I have
over the last two months I've been at
this is probably like my sixth kind of
talk or conference that is like this
that is out in the real world, not not
in the fusion world. And nobody's
talking about climate change. It's all
about the AI drive for energy that's
needed. And Fusion looks like it is
perfectly fit if you can meet the
economic requirements around it. It is a
perfect fit actually for this. And it's
also a perfect fit for that kind of
sponsor because I always thought
eventually at some point, you know, me
or one of my students would be in front
of a utility executive trying to
convince them to install a Fusion power
plant.
That's not going to be what it's like.
You're going to be in front of the CEO
of Google or Microsoft to convince them
that what they're going to do is run
their data center on a fusion one. The
reason I know that because it's already
happened.
Yes. And those companies have made
strategic decisions to that they
understand that this has to be one of
the arrows in their quivers. So instead
of a very cap so this is one of the
reasons I'm I'm optimistic surgey
because our sponsorship has totally
changed. This is not a small cap table
utility considering this very risky
technology. It's a technology company
that literally exists because and is one
of the biggest and they're all the
biggest companies in the world because
they live at the boundary of technology
and economic risks. They totally get
something like fusion and they have a
cap table which is 100 times bigger than
the utilities and that's going to be the
thing and that's the third thing because
it's interesting. It's the drive for
fusion and its timeline and its
performance and the kinds of resources
that we can put towards it are going to
totally change and are changing
underneath our feet. We just have to
keep delivering on the hard science and
technology which is focused on this end
goal of commercialization. So thank you
for your attention. So
well first of all thank you for for we
ran 50 minutes over but I think it was
absolutely needed because I think this
is such a disrupting technology that
will actually have impact in other
industries we don't even know yet. So I
mean there are any questions maybe take
one of quick questions before we go with
the network break and we can also still
ask the questions we around here doing
the network break if you're interested.
Oh, come on. There's got to be some
question. Sergey, you got a question.
>> What do you think the main the first
technical let's say difficulties you
will find
>> the first technical difficulty? Oh, it's
it's the magnet. The mag the magnet is
the the magnet is the hardest part of
it. Yeah. Yeah. So that's actually why
the focus of the company and so its
ability to not only produce the magnets
but also it it takes too long to explain
it but the ability to test the magnets
that's actually one of the things that
we innovated in significantly was which
you don't usually think of a university
innovating in the space of manufacturing
but we we understood that we actually
made technology choices that allowed for
extremely efficient quality control and
quality assurance all the way through
the manufacturing and assembly pro
process. test and that is proven to be
correct and that's actually why so uh so
now I so we still have we like MIT has
very little to do now with that because
it's at the commercial scale but seeing
that at commercial scale that you're
testing that like every week basically
approximately you're testing one of
those and knowing that that they meet
spec and that you're doing it in a
scalable way that's the one and and then
as usual in fusion uh you have
integrated assembly and it's mostly
about the magnets assembly so those are
the things which are in place But it's
it's it's it's progressing at at pace.
If you ever get a chance, it's it's hard
to get tours out there because they have
so many requests for tours. It is kind
of like breathtaking actually around
that about seeing it. Yeah. About
particular about how small it is, right?
Okay. Super. I mean, if I can leave you
with one last final note is on it. I
think uh you need to get involved in
fusion in fusion research on because it
will affect any industry going forward
on thinking really how we also going to
need the education, we need the talent,
we need the world actually to help us
move this forward.
>> So la last year we had the largest
application pool, applicant pool for
fusion in the history of the of the
40-year history of the PSFC and we had
the lowest number of admitted students
because we don't have the resources to
actually support them and we're underst
staffed actually. This is I I I that's
like I wake up every day and I think
about there there was 160 qualified uh
graduate students who are not working on
fusion right now.
Just think about that right as this is
not about MIT or anything. It's like as
a society like what the hell are we
doing? Like that's our most important
resource to unlock. We need to figure
out ways to have them working
meaningfully at at a pace which is 10
times what we're doing. So like this
institution MIT could do more around on
this. By the way, I I I' I'd encourage
everybody to go look at Fusion's
prominent place in the climate action
plan, by the way. Super. Thank you,
Dennis. I'll be happy for you.