(air whooshing)
(dramatic music)
- I'm Sara Beery.
I am a new assistant professor at MIT
and I'm also a PI at the Computer
Science and AI Laboratory.
And my new research
group is really focused
at this intersection between
AI, biodiversity, and ecology.
We're interested in
developing AI techniques
that help us better understand
how species are changing
at a global scale.
And we do this across
different data modalities.
Everything from images
to acoustics, to sonar,
to remote sensing data.
And we combine these different modalities
and try to interpret them,
so that we can understand
how species are changing
at a global scale.
So actually, I've always
loved the natural world.
I grew up camping with my
family in the Pacific Northwest,
but actually my first passion was dance.
I started training as a
ballerina very seriously.
I got my first job offer
with the Atlanta Ballet
when I was only 16,
and I moved from Seattle
to Atlanta by myself
to join a ballet company.
I lived in sort of like
a not super great area
that was kind of close to Georgia Tech.
They would put posters
on the telephone poles
for scientific talk that
always advertised free food,
so I would go.
I almost immediately found myself
hooked on the science,
and not specifically science writ large,
but it was eyeopening to me
in terms of how science and technology
can be used as a force for public good.
And that planted the seed.
So, I went on and I continued
to do professional ballet
for six years.
I loved it, but I always started,
I started to think about
how I might instead go back
after I finished, after
I retired from ballet,
and become a scientist.
And I ended up doing that.
I went back.
I retired from ballet
and I started a career in
electrical engineering.
So one of the projects I
actually started in my PhD
and have brought to my lab
here at MIT is a project
looking at improving the sustainability
of the salmon fisheries from Alaska
all the way down through
Canada to Northern California.
- This project is
working with stakeholders
in fishery management and conservation,
who are interested in monitoring
the number of salmon migrating every year.
And to do this, they
deploy sonar video cameras
at rivers around the world
and they have technicians deployed there
throughout the migration
season, counting how many salmon
are moving by the cameras every day.
We're working on developing
computer vision algorithms
to make the process more efficient
and more accurate for them.
So most of these sonar camera deployments
are out in the field with
limited connectivity and power.
A solution that we've been working on
for deploying these algorithms
uses edge computing.
It's basically a low power,
low cost Linux computer
that can be deployed out in
the field and powered by solar.
And we can deploy the
model on this device.
And we have a software
application that runs,
that allows technicians to
analyze all of their video.
The way that the algorithm works
is that each individual fish
has different colored box drawn around it.
It has a length estimation.
And then at the bottom,
we say how many fish
have gone left or right,
and they, based on the
orientation of the camera,
then change this to upstream
or downstream counts.
- So our interests are really,
from a research perspective,
how do you effectively use human time,
human decisions throughout this process,
so that you can maintain the
reliability of the system,
but also make it reasonably deployable.
The next project I wanna talk about
is a little more open-ended.
And here, what we're interested in
is as we start collecting
these large repositories of data
from different data modalities
like the fish sonar,
but actually specifically in this project,
data collected from passionate
volunteers around the world
who will take photos of plants and animals
that then become species
occurrence records.
And the way that they do that,
one mechanism they do that,
is through a platform called iNaturalist.
- We're using embedding
models, which are AI models
that are trained to find
the semantic relationships
between images and text.
So, we're able to pre-compute
these sort of semantically
meaningful embeddings
on all of our 5 million images.
So when you're trying to search through
and you give us a piece of text
describing what you're looking for,
we can, in less than
a second, look through
and compare with all the
millions of images we have
to give you exactly the closest
natural you're looking for.
We hope that our dataset
will provide the foundation
and the motivation for
researchers in the field
to actually work on building models
that are not just generally good,
but actually useful for scientists.
One great example is California condors.
This is a species that
almost went extinct in 1982.
There were only 22 individuals left.
But because of a successful
breeding program,
now there's a stable
population of hundreds.
And scientists still want to track them
to monitor the population
and understand where they
are and what they're doing.
So, all California
condors have tags on them
with a color and a few symbols
that identify who they are.
And so, scientists can't
be everywhere all at once.
So, it's been really difficult
to be able to successfully monitor them
and see where they're going.
But now with citizen
science and regular people
taking pictures of these
birds they find interesting
and uploading them with geotag locations,
we can automatically mine this information
with these vision language
models that understand
both text and images to
pinpoint all of their locations
and track them in a way
that we've never been able to do before.
- So we can try to design systems
that enable lots of scientists
to do diverse science efficiently
and hopefully opening up whole new avenues
for scientific discovery.
When I was in grad school,
I was passionately working
on developing these tools
for colleges in the field,
but I realized I hadn't
had that experience
of actually trying to collect data
and deploy monitoring
systems in the field myself.
So, I went out of my way
towards the end of my PhD
to actually start curating
some of that experience.
I really found it invaluable.
My first version of
this, I planned a survey
using static cameras in
Laikipia County and Kenya,
sort of north of Mount Kenya,
where we were trying to study
an endangered species of Grevy's zebra.
And I went out and I placed
all of those cameras myself,
hiking out sometimes miles into the forest
with a ranger with a gun,
because you're dealing
with very dangerous large
species out in the Savannah.
And really understanding
how much time and effort
goes into collecting
every single data point,
it really gives you a different mentality
about how to value that data.
But not only that,
there are things that you don't
even realize are challenges
if you're just sitting behind
your computer writing code
that actually really
reframe the priorities
I think I have in my research.
I found that experience
incredibly rewarding
but also incredibly informative,
and it's now something I
really seek to continue to do
in my lab here.
I want to require all of my
grad students to go to the field
to be working much more hands
on with specific projects.
Maybe not for every project,
but I think it's really valuable context.
And it does actually
mean that often our group
and my own research, we've
brought new challenges
to the machine learning
community, framed problems
in ways that potentially they
hadn't before seeing them.
And I think it's really that
application driven innovation
that really helps us move the needle on
in terms of what machine
learning needs to do.
One of the things I'm really
excited about moving forward
is actually starting to bridge the gaps
between these different data modalities
that are being collected globally.
Combining these
hyperspectral imaging systems
from space with drones,
capturing individual animals
moving through the environment,
with static networks of
bioacoustic sensors photos
collected by passionate human volunteers,
actually sharing information
across these modalities of data.
So that we can get a
much more nuanced picture
of the tree of life.
I think if I had any advice
for anyone who's excited to
get started in this field,
it would be to just talk to people.
And there is increasingly
these amazing communities resources
that are coming together.
I run a Slack channel
that has 2,500 global researchers on it,
just working on AI for conservation.
Getting onto these
platforms, meeting people,
asking questions, putting
yourself out there,
but learning about sort of all
of the different diverse ways
that people are sort of
tackling these problems.
I would love to see this continue to grow.