next next in the agenda is for me to
tell you a little bit more on where we
are at MTL after the very strong
foundation of the last 40 years what are
the key topical areas that our
researchers and our community are
working on and what are the next few
revolutions coming to electronics
through Microsystems and micro
technology and that's what we going to
be talking about for for the next half
an hour or so how MTL at 40 is uniquely
position to really tackle the challenges
of the
future so let's get started uh and let's
think a little bit about a semiconductor
technology and how it came about I I
think modern modern Electronics started
in 1947 with the invention of a
transistors and although it is a bit of
a stretch to argue that shle was an MTL
alarm but he he grew up in in the
community uh the amazing ecosystem that
MIT
forms but very shortly after the the
first transistor it was clear that there
was a problem transistor solate
devices they they they were something
that physicist understood but it was
very difficult for for engineers to
really take that to the next level and
that's where from my point of view the
the MTL Community kind of started to to
appear the identifi the need of taking
semiconductor devices from the domain of
physics into engineering and in 1960 the
MIT Community got together to put
together what what is called the
semiconductor Electronics education
committee that really set the
foundations
of semiconductor devices and
Microsystems as a an engineering
field ER that was in 1960 to to put
things in context I I went back to ER
Mo's original paper where he described
the exponential growth of the number of
devices in a chip and and so on and I I
tried to identify okay how many
transistors did we have back in in
1960 in in the microsystem and if you
look at at the plot on the bottom left
that that's a a log base
two and in 1960 there were probably two
transistors on on a chip so it was
fairly it was very
revolutionary that in 1960 the MIT
Community was already saying hey this
this is going to transform the world we
need to bring this from physics to to
engineering and let's develop the
curriculum to to make that a possible a
few years later
1968 the the first clean room facility
at MIT was open what is called the
integrated microelectronics laboratory
or microlab which was located in
building building 13 that was the the
very first seed for what would become a
MTL in the
future few years later
1978 the the the introduction to VSA
systems class H was put together this
was one of the very first multiproject
chip design courses in the world and it
happened here by the people who in a few
years who then officially start a
MTL the what is called today the MTL
seminar series was actually started in
in
1979 with the original title of the MIT
vsi seminar series which changed to MTL
seminar in
2007 and finally in 1980 MIT announced
plans to to establish what would later
become MTL and the original name was the
LSI fabrication
facility and then time went by and
finally we reach 1984
and that was a really busy year in in
the
US Ronald Reagan became
president we had the the Olympic Games
in in in
La Ghostbuster was a
blockbuster Apple released the
Macintosh Boston Celtics won the
MBA and back in Spain I was getting
ready to come to the
US everything happening everything
happening in 1984 I I was ready I was
ready but the the the the most important
thing that happened in 1984 was that
actually MTL as an entity the
Microsystems technology
Laboratories was
founded and it was founded by Professor
Demitri
Antonis who who many years later recall
that hey I I still remember vividly the
the afternoon that Professor Paul
Penfield walk into my his office in
Building
13 and told Professor
antoniadi you better sit down we MIT
have decided that we must build a state
of the art microelectronics lab and you
will be leading that that project and
that was the beginning of MTL what we
are celebrating
today and the rest is history
and it's all about the amazing community
that has been formed around that initial
that initial seed and I have L lots of
additional details here MTL move from
Building 13 to to building 39 back in
1986 the the PTC the process technology
committee that that that that has
overseen all the fabrication happening
at at MIT since then was start in
1990 Professor Rafael RI was appointed
MTL
director in in that around that
time ER more things MTL reporting moved
to the School of Engineering 1995 the
center for integrated circuits and
systems one one of the most important
building blocks o of MTL was founded by
Professor Harry Lee in
1998 year 2001
the MIT clean room got upgraded from 4
in to state-of-the-art 6 in Wafers back
back
then 2002 we decided that we had to open
up the
community for for industry to also use
our our facilities and and we created
what is called the Microsystems
affiliate program that allowed companies
from all over the US to actually use our
facilities and work work side by side
with MTL
researchers Coral the the the software
that manages the the Fab was introduced
2003 2
2014 MIT Nano was
created thanks to to the leadership of
President R thanks to the vision that he
had in collaboration with Professor
Vladimir bulovic and the MTL Community
the MIT
Community the decision was made to
upgrade our fabrication facility to what
I think is the world's best R&D cleaning
facility that was
2014 and in
2018 MIT Nano officially open and MTL be
became fabulous and I really hate that
that sentence I I don't know who came
out with the Moto MTL became fabulous I
hate that because it's not true I I
prefer I prefer to say that in in
2018 a my Nano opens and at that point
MTL was able to focus 100% of its energy
on how to change the the wall through
Microsystems I'm sure collaborating
closely with a MIT Nano to enable
stateoftheart fabrication at MIT but the
MTL Community was now free to have to
manage the clean room and we could focus
100% of our time on how to change the
the
wall and that brings us to the MTL of
today the natural home of Microsystems
research and education at at
MIT where we understand micros systems
in in very broad very broad terms from
materials to systems through Innovations
in microelectronics materials
nanotechnology electronic and photonic
devices sensors mems packaging
prototyping etc
etc ER the the this is the the the team
of people that are fortunate to to be
able to lead this amazing community
today Professor Ronan Han a w expert on
circuit design and Professor Bill GIS a
a leading expert well expert amazing
person and really a extraordinary
researcher on pushing the limits of
material Material Science and ai ai
Hardware they are joining me in the
leadership team with Dr Charles who our
Consortium manager
so when I was putting together this
presentation I I I thought okay how can
we summarize 40 years o of research in
into a few minutes how do I convince our
community of the tremendous impact that
that MTL is having in many different
levels and and and the question the
problem was how how to down select how
how to identify out of the thousands of
impactful papers that have come out how
to identify the the the the top ones
very quickly I I I decided that it was
impossible but I I I I can I I can give
you
a a glimpse o of the breath o of work
happening at at MTL
today we we are very proud of addressing
the full stack of innovation in in
Microsystems there is a lot of work
going on in materials Discovery using
machine learning and automatic
experimentation to really innovate in
new microelectronics
materials there is also lots of effort
in in in many many different groups to
discover the next big electronic device
the next big sensor device the next big
photonic device but then we take these
new materials and devices and we put
them into circuits for a wide variety of
applications all the way from 5G and 6G
networks and Communications to extremely
secure adcs and ID taxs going all the
way through a super conducting
Electronics flexible electronics that is
trying to change the form factor of
Microsystems a temperat Microsystems
that are pushing the limits of where
Microsystems can operate Etc and then we
take those chips made of a silicon as
well as other Advanced Materials and we
prototype a wide variety of systems in
lots of different applications the
energy
space
robotics
sustainability Health Care
Etc and we do that over and over again
and and I I was counting how many
different projects and Microsystems are
going on
at MTL today and it's more than 200
happening today right now in all these
topics and spending all all the way to
supply change and even policy policy
issues but how how do we
quantify um impact again I was
struggling with that question and I
thought okay maybe a way to quantify
impact is to to count how many best
papers Awards we we've had
and again that was very very difficult
but I I decid okay let's choose a a a a
few top journals for example the top
journals in in semiconductor devices are
electron device letters and the
transactions on electron devices so
let's count let's look at which are the
papers coming from the MTL community
that made it to the best paper of the
Year award in these top journals and and
I I I found
the these ones I I just have them here
to to highlight the breadth of our
community you'll find papers on Power
Electronics you'll find papers on white
banga RF amplifiers you'll find papers
on pushing the limits of simos
Technology through germanium
transistors increasing the performance
of silicon through the use of strain
silicon
germanium lowering the power consumption
in in transistors by dynamically
changing the threshold
voltage let's go to the top conferences
let's go to iedm and
vsi
issdc and and we again find more papers
on pushing the limits of compound
semiconductors pushing the limits of
two-dimensional materials and systems
pushing the limits of AI and and many
many more but I was completely wrong I
don't think this is the way to to
measure impact because although of
course we are very proud o o o o of
these and many other Awards
a when we try to to quantify the impact
that this has in the world is good but I
think is not the the the main point then
I thought okay we we have really nice
papers but we are more than papers we
are 70 different research groups really
pushing the limits o of Microsystems in
all different dimensions and they are
all the the best in the wall at what
they
do that's
impact and and sure we are very proud of
of our research groups and we think we
are making impact but I I I'm still
wrong this is not the right
metric the real way we are making impact
in the world today is through our
community is through our alarms it's
through everyone who has been touched by
the by the MTL e
ecosystem and it's an amazing banch I
mean it's just a truly remarkable
community and that's what we are TR
truly proud proud of and they are making
huge impact in all different dimensions
of of Microsystems and
technology so again when I think of of
what are the key enablers for for MTL
over the last four decades and what is
what is going to propel us into the
future it's the community upfront strong
Community uh and its values its full
commitment for for excellence in in all
different domains of of
knowledge we are a a a big lab and we
thrive on interdisciplinary research and
we organize ourselves into research
communities such as CICS the center for
integrated circuits and systems or metc
focusing on medical Electronics the MIT
AI Hardware program pushing the limits
of AI and the hardware to to lower the
power consumption of AI data centers and
many many more centers and initiatives
like this
we are also extremely fortunate to to
have an incredible partnership with MIT
Nano MTL was started to provide micro
and nanofabrication
services to
MIT we transfer that responsibility to
MIT Nano but we are still fully engaged
in in that facility and we are very
proud of MIT n
and it's one of our huge
assets and all that gives us a very
strong startup ecosystem and I was
sharing this with some of you yesterday
and 5 seconds after I I I finished my my
talk yesterday someone approached me and
said hey sure it is true that all these
startups have come out
of MIT MTL but it's only a very small
list so we we spend the night looking at
the full list and we found that there
are more than 50 startups that have come
out of MTL over the last four
decades and we are very proud of every
single one of them and how they are all
changing the world in their own
way and the the the final key enabler
that I want to highlight is our very
strong partnership with with industry at
all different levels I mean we work with
hundreds of Industry Partners every
single day to really push the limits of
of
Microsystems thank you thank you to all
all our industry
[Applause]
partners and out of all of
those I I do want to to highlight those
who are part of the Microsystems
technology Laboratories industrial group
or or M these are companies many of them
that have been with MTL for the last 40
years really supporting MTL at all
different
levels R&D of course but also building
the ecosystem
together helping us with workfor
development and really working with us
to develop a a talent both in the
companies and at
MTL so I really appreciate the members
of of the micro sistance industrial
group these 16 companies that have
really helped us to to reach a a a
amazing amazing level here at MTL thank
you thank you
and O of course the the the key leasons
at all these companies who have been
able to provide really really important
feedback over the decades to build
today's
MTL so in in the last nine minutes let
let me talk about the future and the
opportunities
ahead we we are in a truly amazing time
for microelectronics and we just need to
read the newspapers every day here we
have one The Wall Street Journal a few
months ago chips are the new oil and
America is spending billions to
safeguard its
Supply another one Taiwan launches its
own cheap Fab incentives to rival us
Japan and the European
Union another one soft Bank NEC Sony
Toyota plus team up to to build rapidos
Japan's bid for next chap
domination European union leaders strike
43 billion to Bo semiconductor
production in
Europe the key message here is that
microelectronics semiconductors devices
Microsystems engineers and scientists
that is all of you
MTL are really the rock stars of the
next 25 years we have an amazing
opportunity in front of us so next time
you you you you you look at yourself in
in in the mirror don't be surprised if
you see
this oh I'm I'm sorry I'm sorry my my
mistake that that's not you I'm
sorry because definitely you you are not
rock stars I'm
sorry you are actually the superheroes
of the 21st century that that that's
what the MTL Community is all about
because we need superheroes to to make
personalized Affordable Health Care in
the future and that will happen thanks
to the Microsystems that we are all
Building
Together We need superheroes to feed the
wall and we will be using Microsystems
to really increase the efficiency of
agriculture in a sustainable
way we need superheroes to fight climate
change and the Microsystems we are all
building here at MTL are critical
components of green
energy and of course microelectronics
and what we are building together it's
everywhere in the AI Revolution and this
is a huge opportunity at the same time a
big challenge ahead I mean the this plot
shows energy energy consumption by
Electronics by the Microsystems we are
all building in in Orange compared to
the world's energy production and the
key message is that by
2040 the Microsystems we are all
building are going to be using 100% of
all the energy being produced in the
worldall no more energy for food no more
energy for transportation only only
energy to power
Microsystems that's not
good we need to fix that and and that's
an important call for action for this
community and for all of you and I'm
sure we will'll do it we'll succeed
we'll change the world
again so as we think of M
MTL in the next in the next few decades
we we want to to continue being 100%
focused on on the three
pillars that that we have developed over
the last few decades research community
and Outreach and I do want to give you a
a a few examples o of things we are
doing in in each one of these three
pillars and there are many more but I I
I had to select a a
few on the research
side as I mentioned we we are in the
most exciting time for micro systems in
all its history and our
community is really taking advantage of
that to build the
future professor akmed bahai professor
Alex shalik and myself are working with
the entire Community to build what we
call the the MTL program on Health
Sciences and
semiconductors to really use
semiconductor Innovations to invent the
semiconductor innovations that are are
needed to
provide personalized affordable and more
successful Health Care in the future and
Professor ammed bahai we will tell us in
a few minutes a a lot more details about
this new program which is based on
bringing microelectronics everywhere
throughout the the Health Care System
bringing ous sensors everywhere to
really improve the outcomes and make it
more affordable and personal
what Professor bahai calls waves beads
and
molecules another example of new
programs that are coming out of the MTL
Community as we speak is the MTL program
on a augmented reality and virtual
reality display Technologies which is
led by Professor Yan Kim to invent the
future of VR and AR are in close
collaboration with machine learning
experts and of course we are heavily
involved on everything related to to the
chips to the chips and science act here
in the US we are applying to to many of
the programs and heavily involved in in
all the projects
there at the same time we continue to
remain 100% focused on the MTL community
and understanding that the M MTL
Community doesn't stop in Cambridge it
has a national and international
footprint and we are very very proud to
to to play a an important role a
foundational role in the Northeast micro
Electronics
Coalition that was started a year ago
here in the
Northeast and the final example of
initiative that I I want to highlight
for all of you here is in
Outreach the future of our
field completely relies on us bringing
the best people to work in this field
and and for
that freshman students first year
students are are absolutely critical but
when I asked them a a a a few years ago
a couple of years ago hey what is
preventing you from from joining
Microsystems and and Hardware they all
told me the same thing you know when we
first joined the university we were
super excited about hardware and
Microsystems but then we applied as
first year students we applied to summer
internships to all the Microsystems
companies out
there and we got rejected from every
single Microsystems company every single
hardware company said the same thing
it's great that you are in interested in
Hardware however you are not ready
please apply again when you are a junior
or a
senior at the same time the same
students had applied to a wide variety
of software companies and they got
amazing internships in software
companies and at that point they never
look
back that's a problem not only for
Microsystems but for all of us working
in Hardware that's a problem that our
community at MTL wanted to to fix and
that is why we we created this program
the Northeast microelectronics
internship program which is connecting
first year students with summer
internships in in in the in the hardware
and Microsystems a field the first year
we got 100 students second year 200
third year 300 students going into the
program this year we received more than
applications from students who are
telling us hey we want to be in Hardware
we want to work in Microsystems we want
to join this exciting
field but we cannot do it alone we need
the entire Community to help we need the
support of our industry partners and all
our friends here at MTL to make it
happen so that's everything I I had for
for for today's introductory a
presentation about MTL we are really
powering the next wave of
microelectronics innovation together but
if I want to
summarize MTL and everything we have
accomplished in the last four decades
with one word I would say community that
is really what makes us different that
is what really bring brings us all the
power to change the world the amazing
community that MTL represents with with
our students staff faculty and alumni
and Industry collaborators thank you
thank you all it's absolutely fantastic
to have you here today thank you
[Applause]