when you fuse this world of biology with
the world of electronics to read out
information from the body for health
monitoring or write information into the
body for Therapeutics the major
challenge in the field is bioelectronic
devices are highly invasive imagine a
new paradigm where we can have tiny Nano
electronic devices introduced into the
blast stream or body fluid and recognize
a Target disease region and self implant
these devices have the capability of
communicating wirelessly with external
transmitters so this could lead us to
early disease detection but they can
also modulate biological functions for
Therapeutics purposes our technology can
actually treat these brain cancers where
traditional therapies have failed for
more MIT moments from MIT open learning
like subscribe or follow