Great. So, I'm Scott, the CTO at Line
Lab. My background is in mechanical
engineering and operations. I co-founded
Line Lab with another MIT colleague
after related research collaboration
with Boeing. And so, currently there's a
big problem across industries of
struggling to engineer production and
supply chain to scale. Elon Musk talks
just about how hard the problem is and
at the same time we see huge capacity
being added in manufacturing. But the
inability to address the scaling design
problem is having major impact on
incumbents and startups and scaleups
alike. It's a significant problem not
just in terms of dollars but also in
missing capacity in the industrial base.
And what sits at the core of this
problem in most cases is this inability
to have accurate and informative
analysis to bridge the valley of death
into scaled profitable production after
a lot of initial investment. Excel can't
do this and traditional simulation tools
can't either. It's exactly here that
Line Lab finally delivers a real
solution.
Line Lab is new software that fixes the
way supply chains and production systems
are designed. Now, for the first time,
the problem can be solved from right to
left where we can input the design and
the manufacturing steps and the goals
for scale, rate, cost, etc. And Line Lab
will handle the thousands of trade-offs
to give us a prescriptive result about
how the system should be configured. At
its core is new technology for modeling
the complex interactions, variability,
and randomness in the production system
and supply chain. This is built on pure
mass and not AI. So there's no
hallucination or unpredictability. This
is right alongside the sophisticated
financial modeling which allows for all
of the decisions to be in business
relevant context. With transparency
characterizing the impact of every
input, teams are able to effectively
design course defined and focus efforts
on high-risisk decisions. When Line Lab
is run, it's automatically designing the
production system to meet the
requirements and constraints. It's
designing things like optimal capacity,
flow time, critical path, inventory, and
other resources. The minimal inputs
needed are the manufacturing process
steps, resource costs, and performance
requirements. But all these can be input
with uncertainty. Additional constraints
can be added like maximum floor space,
maximum capital, fixed existing
equipment, etc. So line lab can really
cover the range from updating existing
production to designing totally new
green field sites. We see a quick
example of processes, costs and rates
being updated and an entirely new
production system is designed that meets
those requirements
as outputs. We are getting things like
total cost the optimization of capacity
utilization and inventory. Line lab is
also producing the trade of how unit
cost actually changes with production
capacity. And finally, line lab is
characterizing and ranking the main cost
drivers across design, operations, and
finance to really give the insight on
which levers to pull. As an example,
a a major aerospace OEM, there you go.
Major aerospace UA OEM used line lab to
perform the trade-off analysis between
two production technologies with very
different TRL MRL. The model this in
line lab they were finally able to
quantify those maturity differences
using uncertainties on the inputs. Line
lab was then able to characterize the
resulting output uncertainties like in
unit cost for example. The team then
used the risk analysis shown here with
the size of the bubbles to determine
which factors were most significant for
selecting a technology. Using these data
they were able to quite clearly direct
their efforts and resources to only the
factors that mattered for de-risisking
the decision. As a result, capital costs
were reduced, unit costs improved, and
the design cycle substantially
accelerated.
So, we are looking for companies who
want to pilot Mine Lab. Generally,
Meline Lab is answering questions around
the costs and manufacturing strategy for
new products or new production. And it's
honestly never too early in the product
life cycle to start using line lab. Data
don't have to be complete or
sophisticated to have a big impact. It's
really about making better strategic
decisions in the system and flow where
those big levers are. We've worked with
customers in diverse verticals and we're
always open to more and exploring
exciting new potential applications. So,
if this sounds relevant to the problems
you're facing, feel free to reach out to
me and we'd love to consider the uh
conversation.