The farthest human beings have ever
traveled away from the earth was during
the Apollo flights to the moon from 1969
through 1972. [music]
I like to do an experiment with my
students to give them an idea of what
was really involved in leaving the
Earth. And you can see that this moon is
about the right size for this scale.
[music] The challenge is for them to
position themselves so that the Earth
and the Moon are the right distance
apart. And the results can sometimes be
amusing. The moon is about a quarter of
a million miles away, roughly 400,000
km. [music] And the circumference of the
Earth is about 25,000 miles or about
40,000 km. [music] So the distance to
the moon is about 10 times the
circumference of the Earth. [music] You
get the point. The moon is pretty far
away. Big hand for our demonstrators
here. [applause]
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.