Good morning everyone. Uh thank you for
making it uh early in the morning. I'll
um introduce our primary speaker Ben Fry
who is a PhD student uh with Nick Pelosi
who will give the seminar today in
Harvard biopysics department. So with
that I'm just going to hand over to
Nick. I hope you enjoy the primer.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Hopefully my voice
is being amplified and everyone can hear
me, especially people on Zoom. Um, yeah.
So, thank you for the invitation to give
the primer on, uh, sort of what we've
been working on in the Paley lab uh, for
the past couple years. uh I'm a fourth
year PhD student for context and our lab
generally works on problems that exist
in the protein structural domain uh for
context uh specifically at the interface
of like protein lians molecular
recognition
um so sort of questions that we're
interested in broadly are how can we
design proteins from scratch that can
bind specifically to any small molecule
liant uh how can we maybe redesign
existing proteins with novel functions
to modulate metabolites or ligans. Uh
and how can we maybe predict small
molecule binding sites across the human
proteome? And sort of that last question
is sort of the key to the content that
my PI Nick is going to present in the
core seminar later today. Um and sort of
on the right I'm showing some denovo
designed helical bundle proteins that
interact specifically with spa molecules
in a way that's sort of a new to nature
protein liant interface. Uh and that's
represents work that we've done in the
lab sort of prior.
So as you may know uh the protein
structure prediction and design fields
have undergone sort of a revolution in
the wake of the uh Nobel prize uh that
was awarded to David Baker and Deus
Habasus and John Jumper for protein
structure prediction with Alphaold 2. Uh
within the design field there have been
some deep learning methods that have
really revolutionized our methodology
and our toolbox. Uh specifically I'll
call attention to protein MPNN and this
RF diffusion model. Um uh there's also
been a lot of work uh on the language
modeling side with the ESM family of
models progen uh prot5 which you might
be familiar with if you've worked in the
protein uh sequence space at all sort of
categorizing these models there's two
different classes uh there's the 3D
structure based so alpha fold protein
mpn rf diffusion and the sequence based
and something to sort of call out is
just the many orders of magnitude
difference between the amount of
training data that you have for
sequence-based modeling versus structure
based modeling. Um so if you have a
problem that can be tackled uh with
sequence language model embed embeddings
uh it's probably fruitful to try using
the sequence-based modeling if you can.
Um but we've seen very good and
promising results from structure guided
modeling as well.
So sort of to review um
a general principle for all deep
learning models is that information is
stored in highdimensional vector
representations which I'm sure many of
you are familiar with. Uh sort of a
really nice canonical example of
studying this is the wordtovec model
that was published in 2013. Uh, and it's
this sort of classical natural language
processing example of if I embed words
in like what we would now consider to be
a relatively lowdimensional vector
embedding. Um, you can do sort of simple
vector arithmetic operations and then
look up from your library of words what
the closest resulting vector is. So like
uh an example that's brought up
frequently is this idea of like the king
vector minus the man vector plus the
woman vector equals queen or is the
closest in the embedding space to the
queen vector. And there's sort of all
different kinds of uh words that you can
replace uh king, man, woman, queen with
uh that have similar behaviors. And this
was also shown in 2013 with like a very
simple uh wordtovec model. But obviously
in 2017 we now have transformers. And
this has sort of revolutionaliz
revolutionized the way that we do a lot
of natural language processing modeling.
Uh and sort of recently with the advent
of like large language models. Uh you
can see we've gone from maybe 164
dimensional embeddings to 7,168
dimensional word embeddings which are
used by like the deepseek R1 model. Uh
so this embeddings being stored in
highdimensional vector representations
is a common thread that's been very
persistent throughout uh deep learning
methodology in the natural language
processing space. But it's also
something that's been uh key to the
function of protein structure and
protein sequence domain modeling as
well.
So representation learning as you might
be aware is a field that specifically
deals with building up representations
uh for downstream tasks. So sort of how
do you structure your vector space or
latent space in such a way that uh your
model understands
um for example protein protein
interactions protein lian interactions.
uh so I'm showing atomica which is a
Marinka Zitnik paper that was published
in the last year um which has been sort
of an exciting work uh trying to
generalize these at the atomic level uh
using threedimensional structure but
sort of something that is hypothesized
in the field is that alphafold 2 like
models these graph neural nets that are
trained on like the entire protein
structural database uh and protein
language models already use
highdimensional embeddings for the tasks
that they're trained to perform. So can
we train simple models like regressions,
decision trees, etc. uh that sort of
bootstrap off of these rich feature
embeddings that are already generated
for um these orthogonal modeling tasks.
Um so sort of to review the types of
embeddings that you can get out of these
different types of models, I'm going to
sort of briefly cover the alphafold 2
model. Um so as you probably know,
Alphaold 2 is a model for predicting
threedimensional protein structure from
an amino acid sequence. Uh the inputs
are sort of a protein sequence of
interest that you want to predict the
structure for uh and a multiple sequence
alignment of similar multiple of similar
protein sequences that are found
throughout the tree of life. Uh and
Alphold 2's task is to decode the
evolutionary co-variation in the
multiple sequence alignment uh and turn
that into a threedimensional structure.
So if you break down the architecture of
AlphaFold 2, you can sort of see how the
input sequence sort of flows through the
model resulting in a threedimensional
structure. Um, but there's two key
things that I want to call attention to.
Uh, there's basically two main blocks in
Alphold 2 that are responsible for the
transformations that are applied to this
input sequence that turn it into a
structure. The first of which is called
the EvoFormer, uh, which we'll cover in
a second, uh, and then the structure
module which actually generates the 3D
structure. But the Evoformer is tasked
with generating embeddings that we can
take out of the alpha 2 model and use
for downstream tasks. Uh there's two
main embeddings. One is the single
representation which is sort of the
embedding of every amino acid in the
query sequence that's passed into
alphafold 2. Uh so this is sort of n by
c where c is channels of the embedding
and n is just the number of amino acids
in the sequence. Uh, and then there's
also a pair representation which
explicitly encodes how every I residue
co-varies with every J residue and
there's a specific embedding for that
interaction between that pair. Um, so
why is this pair-wise covariation
information used in alphafold 2? Um so
something that's really interesting
that's fun to bring up is that prior to
like the deep learning revolution simple
protein structure prediction was
actually able to be performed solely
from pairwise uh co-variation using pots
models or direct couplings analysis. So
the way that this works is you would
take your query amino acid sequence,
generate a multiple sequence alignment
and then sort of look at columns in the
multiple sequence alignment that covary
with each other and then there was a
hypothesis that things that covary with
each other implies some sort of
structural constraint. So if you're
covariing which you can formulate with
this sort of pots model formulation
um this coupling term J should imply
some small uh distance in
threedimensional space and then sort of
energy based refinement could be applied
to an initial structural map uh which
allows you to generate a
threedimensional structure. Um but sort
of the key is that this methodology is
restricted only to pairwise evolutionary
co-ariation. So, Alphold 2's Evoformer
is explicitly a transformer-based model.
It can go beyond pair-wise information
uh and extract higher order
co-evolutionary signal from these MSAs.
Um and like I said uh the result of this
is that you get a pair representation
where every amino acid uh in your input
sequence uh has an explicit embedding
for how it attends to other amino acids
in that sequence uh which we can take
advantage of for training downstream
models.
Um, and something that's a fun caveat is
that the MSA information is actually
optional. Uh, and if you work in the
denovo protein design field, uh, we
almost never use multiple sequence
alignments to evaluate our denovo
designs because we can rely directly on
the sort of implicit energy function
that alphaold has learned to predict
threedimensional structure. I'm happy to
talk more about that if you're curious.
So if the evoiformer model is similar to
a language model encoder building up
these highdimensional representations uh
of the multiple sequence alignment
information query sequence the structure
model is this 3D rotation and variant
graph neural network that's tasked with
decoding those highdimensional
representations through a
threedimensional structure. Um how it
specifically works isn't super important
for this talk. Um but
yeah, it's basically tasked with just
decoding these representations to
threedimensional information.
So again looking at this overview, we
can take these single and pair
representations from AlphaFold 2 for
downstream applications and Nick is
going to talk more about how we do this
in a model called Alphault 2 bind. Um
but something to call out is that
Alphafold 2 only takes in an input amino
acid sequence. It literally doesn't know
anything about uh the presence or
absence of small molecules. Any
information that it might have about
where small molecule binding sites are
in a protein structure is purely from
like information that's contained in
that multiple sequence alignment and
stored in those embeddings. So uh sort
of an open question uh before this paper
was published is does alpha 2 understand
information about any uh implicit small
molecules in a protein sequence? Uh and
we'll talk more about this later.
Um so sort of calling back to my
previous slide uh there's significantly
more sequencing data than there is
protein structural data. So what about
models that take advantage of this? Uh
one such model is this ESM if where if
stands for inverse folding. So inverse
folding is the task of taking a
three-dimensional structure and
generating a protein sequence that's
compatible with folding to that
structure and ideally having whatever
function uh you could also condition it
with. Um for the ESM if model you can
extract sort of an N or L by 512
dimensional vector where L is just the
number of amino acids. uh and this model
was trained by leveraging the amount of
protein sequence information in these
large sequencing data sets uh using
alphaold 2 to generate sort of synthetic
crystal structures uh and then training
the ESM model for the inverse task of
generating amino acid sequences. Um so
this is sort of just another way to
extract embeddings solely from geometric
information by doing a convolution over
a 3D graph. Um which is sort of a
different type of information than you
might get from leveraging sequences
directly.
Um and then of course we have protein
language models which encode protein
sequences uh by pre-training with masked
language modeling objectives. So you
mask some amount of protein sequences in
these giant databases and have the model
try to recover the amino acids that were
masked. Uh the result of this is that
you get probabilities over the 20
natural amino acids for each masked
token. Uh and then sort of under the
hood ESM2 is just using like this BERT
style pre-training objective in order to
uh generate embeddings. It's an encoder
only model if you're familiar with the
terminology.
So along with the ESM2 model at its
release, uh the meta team that worked on
it also released uh ESM fold which uh in
the motivation of taking embeddings and
training them to do downstream tasks uh
literally takes the embeddings from ESM2
for your sequence uh and then recycles
the Alphold 2 structure module that I
introduced earlier uh in order to
perform 3D protein structure prediction
using the embeddings. And this allows
you to circumvent the task of generating
the multiple sequence alignments which
is generally pretty computationally
expensive and requires searching very
large databases.
Um so from this you can actually extract
uh pair and sequence representations uh
from ESM fold though that's very rarely
done because these are sort of
bootstrapped off of embeddings that are
generated by the ESM2 model uh in the
first place. So there's not really
additional information in these. Um
so the actual dimension that you can
extract from the ESM2 embedding sort of
depends on what size model uh you're
working with. They trained uh a bunch of
different models at different scales to
see sort of empirical scaling laws for
the protein domain. Um but the key is
that you can take embeddings again from
the ESM2 like models and use them for
downstream tasks like structure
prediction.
uh and yeah you have both single impair
representations in the same way that
alpha full 2 did.
They used the ESM fold model to predict
structures for 600 million uh amino acid
sequences across like metagenomic
sequencing databases which is pretty
cool. Uh and they show that their
structure prediction methodology is
comparable but maybe slightly worse than
alphafold 2 despite leveraging only
sequence domain information. Um so ESM
fold is this very heavyweight 3D
rotation equavariant graph neural
network that takes these ESM embeddings
and generates 3D structure. Um but other
work that's been performed in the field
using ESM embeddings uh has shown that
simple models such as linear regression
support vector machines uh decision
trees random forests etc uh can also be
used to leverage these highdimensional
embeddings from language models. So
here's a uh paper from Deborah Marx's
lab using ESM embeddings to predict
optimal enzyme pH.
Um so sort of a key point though is that
interesting proteins that we care about
are dynamic. Um particularly if you're
interested in lian binding function, uh
you might be interested in proteins that
possess so-called cryptic pockets. So
proteins that sort of have a uh
two-state equilibrium where in one state
a pocket is not available for small
molecule binding but in another it
fluctuates open and it suddenly becomes
uh available for small molecule binding.
Uh there's like a change in pocket
volume between the two states. Uh and if
you're leveraging a structure prediction
model like alpha 2, you're only getting
like a single snapshot of the protein
structure. So uh a hypothesis is that
maybe these protein structure models or
protein language models encode something
about protein dynamics or local
flexibility even if we don't have like
massive training data for like gigantic
long time scale molecular dynamics
trajectories. Uh we can get at
structural flexibility um or
confirmational heterogeneity through uh
interrogating these embeddings.
So, Dino 1 is a model that came out
recently in 2023. Uh, and actually my
friend and colleague Gina El Nesser is
giving a talk on this tonight at the
Boston Protein Design and Modeling Club.
So, if that sounds interesting to you,
like how you can use labels from nuclear
magnetic resonance spectroscopy
experiments uh to try to infer protein
structural flexibility. Um, check that
out. I think it's at 7 p.m., but Nick
can confirm that. Um, but something that
was cool is that they evaluated a bunch
of different representations that you
can use to try to predict these
confirmational flexibility labels, uh,
including the alpha full 2 pair
representation, ESM2 embeddings, ESM3
embeddings, and then ESM3 with
structural embeddings if you're familiar
with that model. Uh, and they took the
best performing uh, layer from the
transformer. So, you can actually
interrogate more than just the output
layer uh, embeddings.
um since different hierarchies of
information might be passed up through
as the model uh applies convolutions to
the input data. Um yeah,
so to answer my own question, uh you can
definitely train simple models on the
embeddings of these complicated deep
learning models. uh and sort of doing
this has the advantage of uh not
necessarily needing a massive training
data set uh in the way that you might
need to train something like ESM fold uh
you can use significantly fewer labels
uh which for the case of protein small
molecule interactions might be really
important um so this begs the question
what is this AF2 bind thing that I've
been sort of dancing around uh I'm not
going to go into too much detail because
we have a whole like keynote seminar
after this that Nick is going to present
on it but uh to sort of entice you to
stay for that. Um there are a bunch of
interesting questions that we can
potentially answer if we could predict
small molecule interactions and binding
sites across the proteome. Um one of
which is can we discover novel function
in unccharacterized natural proteins? Uh
can we identify novel sites with which
to target drug development um campaigns
to? Uh, and then sort of an interesting
philosophical question of like can we
actually learn what alpha 2 understands
about protein small molecule
interactions even though it's never
trained explicitly with this as an
objective. Um, and this is a table that
I grabbed directly from the AF2 bind
paper. Uh, and hopefully the models that
they're sort of using embeddings from
look familiar at this point. uh and you
can see how the uh ability of this model
to predict binding site changes
depending on what embeddings or
combinations thereof you're applying.
Um so AF2 bind under the hood is just a
logistic regression where it's doing a
binary classification task on the input
embeddings
um using the alpha alpha 2 pair
embeddings and generating uh a label
prediction one or zero for whether an
amino acid is interacting with a small
molecule.
Um and then to sort of contrast between
what existing methodologies for protein
pocket prediction might do. Um I
mentioned before that protein structure
prediction generates these snapshots.
X-ray crystalallography crym like the
traditional uh methodologies that we've
used to generate 3D structural
information only give you sort of static
snapshots of your protein. Um and
F-Pocket is sort of an established
method that uses uh 3D geometry
information uh specifically voronoid
tessillation in order to identify
cavities in the surface of a protein and
then sort of makes the leap that a
cavity inside of a protein is a
potential small molecule binding site.
Uh because this is completely dependent
on the 3D structure that you pass into
the model. Um if you have anything like
a cryptic pocket where you have a
collapsed form uh of your protein when a
small molecule is unbound like F-Pocket
as a methodology is not going to be able
to identify a small molecule binding
site. Uh so we hypothesize that because
alpha fold 2 binds takes these parametas
embeddings from the alpha 2 model even
though alphafold 2 doesn't generate
dynamics information directly it might
understand something about this
equilibrium that a natural protein might
have with its cryptic pocket uh and you
can see its actual predictions over a
cryptic pocket. it's still able to
identify some residues that might be
implicated in a binding interface uh
despite being applied specifically to
the uh structure where the binding site
is oluded.
Um so then just to sort of gratify
myself uh I haven't worked on alpha fold
2 bind personally but I have worked on
uh graph neural nets for protein
sequence design uh and pre-training uh
part of my network called laser mpnn uh
with an orthogonal task of predicting
predicting partial charges from quantum
mechanical calculations uh ended up
being sort of a useful task uh that
improved model performance for protein
sequence generation. uh we were able to
show that the laser ampana model that we
developed outperforms the
state-of-the-art allowed us to do
essentially zero shot design for small
molecule binding protein interactions uh
when you apply the same filtering and
ranking criteria uh and we were actually
able to optimize using just predicted
probabilities from our laser m&m model
our best design from 120 nanomear to a
one nanomer binder which was really
exciting. Um so that's all I have for
you today. I'm looking forward to the
seminar that Nick is going to give later
and I'm happy to take any questions you
may have.
>> Uh thank you for your presentation. Um
so for many of your tasks you were
prompting for example the different
layers of the transformers but this bit
this might be somehow very inefficient
because still you have a lot of faults
to try. Have you tried for example uh
Laura where you just fine- tune for a
few iterations and if that's improves
for example over you over like frozen
layers.
>> Yeah absolutely. So uh have we applied
Laura to the embeddings to maybe make
the training of these like downstream
simple models more efficient? Um I
haven't personally worked on these
problems myself. Um but something that I
have seen people do is do dimensionality
reduction techniques like PCA on the
embeddings to sort of reduce the
complexity before going into some
downstream thing. uh if you're training
something on like the deepseek model
embeddings where you have 7,000
dimensions like surely there's some
redundant information in those um so you
could absolutely try Laura uh in order
to compress that information uh PCA
might work as well.
>> Thanks for that uh presentation. I'm
wondering if you could just talk a
little more about laser mn. It sounded
intriguing but it was very uh uh brief
so I wasn't quite clear on the on the
method doing. I can talk about laser
ampn more uh but I think I might just
direct you to look up my name and the
BPDMC
acronym because I have a recorded talk
uh that's only about laser mn that goes
into all the details you might have. Uh
and if you do end up watching it feel
free to email me afterwards. I can
answer any additional questions.
Um thank you for the talk. So a quick
question about the dynamic nature of
cryptic pocket right. So you mentioned
multiple times that protein is not
static and then if pocket will give
always a static identification of
pocket. So um how static or stoastic the
nature of the if to bind output is
like is it possible that given one
confirmation do we get one prediction
and given multiple confirmation do we
get different predictions
>> so something that's interesting about
alphafold as a model is that you can
provide it templated information um
which is I think what they did to make
or force alpha fold to evaluate two
different structures uh and get
embeddings that change depending on
those structures. So, Alphafold
implicitly has some uncertainty when
it's generating a structural model. Uh
and if you just sample it a bunch of
times with a bunch of different seeds,
you can get like u some information
about how the alphafold confidence uh
about the structure uh is sort of like
uncertain. Uh so you get like a
confirmational ensemble. Um my guess is
to generate these they provided
templates from these PTB codes to
AlphaFold that caused it to change its
embeddings depending on uh what
confirmations were fed in.
>> I I was more referring to the AF2 bind.
>> So can we generate embedding pair from
different confirmation and give as an
input to generate different pockets
let's say?
>> Yes.
And for example, have you tried using
DNA language models on these type of
tasks?
>> And
>> no, but that could be an interesting
future direction.
>> And what's your intuition? Would it work
or
>> I know I'm at the bro, so I can't say
that I'm skeptical of DNA language
model. This is, but I think models that
were trained specifically for the
protein modeling structure domain might
be better for this task, but that's
purely based off of my biases.
It it might work in so far as the DNA
language models understand protein um
sequence and structure. So it might be
one step removed from just directly
using a protein language model or a
structure prediction model but it might
work. There might be something
>> maybe there's additional information in
uh what organism the sequence comes from
or the specific codons that are being
used. Uh so I know people have trained
inverse foldings like a protein MPN like
model specifically to generate codon
codon uh triplets instead of amino
acids. Uh, so I think that was a George
Church paper that came out. I don't know
if anyone's using it, but uh, definitely
there's additional information in the
DNA that might be lost when you convert
it to amino acids.
>> I know that the database is not working.
Um,
uh, TPU bio.xyz
human proteium that doesn't load up just
>> if if RTM is listening to this talk and
he's out there on Zoom, uh, your
database isn't working, Art.
>> Um, we'll get on that. Yeah. Um I will
say that the um and yeah, I mean a lot
of these questions you can just ask me I
guess after my my talk and hopefully
I'll answer some of them during my talk.
But um the AF2 bind uh paper, it's been
out in bioarchchive for a long time, but
it's actually recently accepted in a
journal. So um we we're going to um put
out a big list of all of the buying site
predictions basically as a CSV file. So
you can just pull them from a from a a
file repo. You don't have to rely on any
databases that are online and
interactive.
When I say like wild type structure, a
starting structure, if we could have the
cryptic pockets or how the
not the orthosic but alosic like alosic
and cryptic pockets open up in different
confirmation given one input or wild
type structure if we can have that
predictions and I think the
stockasticity of the embedding should
help with that that would be fun.
So, I guess I'm just we're just going
back and forth with the mic, but um so
I'll talk about that a little bit in my
in my talk. There's a lot um a lot more
that we did uh testing out AF2 bind
that's in the accepted version of the
paper that's not in the bioarchchive
paper. Um one of those was alisteric or
cryptic pocket analysis. Uh and I agree
that um it would be great to be able to
predict those and one um and it can do
that in some cases and I'll talk about
that which is interesting because
only 1% of the PTB has at least
annotated um alossteric binding sites.
Um so it's very underrepresented in
training. Um, but I I think that one of
the things that I'm really interested in
exploring in terms of future steps with
the AF2bind stuff is um an AF2 bind as
Ben um you know described quite well
during his primer uses these embeddings
from Alphal 2 uh which is tasked to
predict a single crystal structure given
the sequence in an MSA. Uh but could
other could other uh neural networks
that um maybe are trained on uh
predicting molecular dynamics snapshots
or trained on predicting ensembles would
embeddings from those neural networks
maybe they understand a little bit more
about where a pocket might open up and
those embeddings might be richer for
predicting cryptic sites and it's
something we haven't done yet but we
really want to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um I'm going to ask one more
question. Uh I'm I suspect that you are
going to get to it in your talk but
because we have time I'll just ask
anyway.
>> One um very critical contribution of
this type of model could be that if we
can use the pocket information to infer
small molecule design. I know that in
this paper you used amino acid just as a
proxy right as a probe.
>> But eventually we want to use those um
amino acid properties somehow if we so
first is if the pocket property can
infer which amino acid it is likely to
bind and then from that amino acid
property if we can infer small molecule
design.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I totally agree with that
and that's a a big motivation. It's one
of the tanalyzing things about the work
that I'll talk about is there is some
signal there uh for predicting what kind
of a small molecule might bind. I've
been um you know, if you really want to
uh you want an answer to this, you
should prod Ben because I've been um
trying to um uh sort of light Ben's fire
to train a new model uh that uses um uh
his graph neural network architecture
that he's trained for um for sequence
design uh that's conditioned on lians
and as well as protein structure and to
use that to not only predict pockets but
um predict predict which kinds of lians
might bind into certain pockets and then
um his his neural network it actually is
very very fast for inference. So you
should be able to cycle through many
different kinds of lians and home in on
what kind of lian might be compatible
with a pocket. So just just talk to Ben
later and say, "Ben, this is really
valuable for me. I'd love if you could
do this.
And do you think for example we need to
cycle across all the combinations or
have you tried for example reinforcement
learning and uh having like a reward
function and maybe also looking into the
literature with a language model
for example when you get your output and
then you in order to refine the output
let's say
>> so to to refine reinforcement learning
to refine the output of is this amino
acid possibly interacting with a a liant
or not.
>> Yeah. For example,
>> task. Um we haven't done reinforcement
learning on that. Um there's just not a
lot of data and you'll see in my talk
that there's not a lot of non-redundant
data, experimental data for this residue
is for sure interacting with a small
molecule lian in some instance of its
structure in a database. Um and so
there's and it's easy to make synthetic
data. I can dock small molecules to
proteins all day, but it doesn't really
change the labels of this residue might
be interacting with any kind of lian or
this residue might not be. Um, and so
reinforcement learning in that context
doesn't really
wouldn't in my mind wouldn't really help
too much because it's I can of course
tell the model it did a good job or a
bad job at predicting, but there's no
new training data really to um so I
think in reinforcement learning would
just be to equivalent to just doing
other
um epochs of training in this sense. And
um we sort of already and I think I'll
show this in my talk but we've or maybe
I won't but um for training the model we
actually it was easy to even though we
did a we went through great pains and
efforts to make a a a really good data
training set and a good split that
didn't have any data leakage um and a
number of examples of training were
still small um and we knew the test set
was completely different from anything
in training. for a lot of different
ways, a lot a lot of different angles.
Um, and we could still overfit this
logistic regression model quite easily.
Um, and so we had a validation set. Um,
and of course the classic way to to know
if you're overfitting is to look at the
loss of train versus validation set. uh
and so we we used L2 regularization on
the model weights for the logistic
regression model and figured out the
right weight for um the L2
regularization so that the train loss
and the validation loss were about the
same but if we kept training we could
keep training but then we knew we were
overfitting so I think reinforcement
learning in this context would just work
like by going into the overfitting uh
regime so
yeah You're welcome. All right. Thanks,
Ben. Appreciate the primer.
>> So, now it's my pleasure to introduce uh
Nick Pelosi. I'm saying it correctly.
>> Pity, whatever you want. There's no way
to no way to say it.
>> Okay. So, let me introduce Nick. Um Nick
is an assistant professor of biological
chemistry and molecular pharmacology in
Dana Farber Cancer Institute. Um Nick
has received uh his PhD from the
department of biochemistry at Duke
University in 2016 where he worked on
theory and time resolved spectroscopic
measurements of biological and
abiological electron transfer reactions.
Through this work he became interested
in denovo protein design and uh his uh
and did his post-doal studies in the
laboratory of um University of
California San Francisco where he
focused on developing new approaches for
accurate pro protein design. So today
Nick will present AF2 bind which is an
exciting method. I hope you all enjoy it
and with that I'll hand over to Nick.
>> Okay thanks Maya. Uh so thanks for the
invitation to talk about some of our
work that we've been doing in the lab.
Um and I want to thank Ben Fry for
giving an excellent primer. Uh Ben is a
a superstar in deep learning and machine
learning as it uh you know as it uh um
involves protein design. So be on the
lookout for Ben. Um, and so I guess what
I what I want to first do is is uh give
a shout out to people who have done the
work and uh and just describe the main
question that that the work is probing.
Um the big the big question is can
pre-trained neural networks are they
good at identifying small molecule
binding sites? That's the question. Um
we trained a model called AF2bind which
I'll talk about but um on the bottom
here is the mly crew uh of collaborators
uh that did all the work um to train the
model uh and iterate and so Sergey of
Chinikov a lot of people know um he's at
MIT and RTM
uh was in in Sergey's lab at the time
and now is in Debbie Marx's group um and
RTM uh is responsible for the online
interactive database which he has to
turn back online apparently. Um, and
then Anna and Jody are in my group and
Casper is actually in Bruno Koreah's
group and he was working on this a
little bit when when Bruno was at
Harvard for a sabatical a couple years
ago. Okay, so that's the Mley crew. I'll
thank them again later, but those are
the the faces behind the work. Um, so I
want to start with a little bit of
motivation, a little bit of high level
why do we want to do this at all? Um,
and I think Ben did a good job at that
already. But, but this idea that
proteins bind almost anything. Uh, here
I'm just showing a few proteins with
their lians in purple. Um, and and
binding is intimately tied to protein
function. In a lot of cases, if you know
a protein bind something, you might know
what its function is. Um, and it
basically underpins all of drug
discovery, small molecule binding. Um,
and so accurate prediction of binding
sites. um you know if you knew where a
small molecule pocket would be um you'd
know where to target in a
structure-based drug design program um
and you might actually uh it might
actually help to interpret disease
mutations but you know for that we would
need experts like Hillary to do um to do
that that analysis later um so there are
some a few ways that that uh the
prediction of binding pockets because
it's so important there are a lot of
existing methods that do this um and
that don't use neural networks to do it.
Uh and so here's one that might be the
most popular method for predicting
binding pockets. This is actually
adopted by the PDB. If you want to look
at binding pockets in the PDB, it uses
P2 rank. P2 rank takes a structure and
um there's no there's no neural network
here, but it takes the solvent
accessible surface of a protein
structure and it puts little probes
around the spheres in green here.
Um, and then there's a random forest
classifier that classifies each one of
these spheres according to if it's
druggable or not. You know, what amino
acids are around it? What's its what's
its burial with respect to the protein
surface? 40 or so features um and random
force classifier that that takes those
features as well as the density of those
probes and says this is a pocket or not.
Maybe even this is a druggable pocket.
So it works really pretty well uh given
a a structure. Um so one one question
would be why would we want neural
networks? Um and I'll hope to answer
that in a in a couple of slides. Um
another method is to use homology
modeling is just to say well this
protein is similar to this other protein
and I know this other protein binds
molecule X and this protein has a
similar pocket. So therefore it's a
pretty good guess that those residues
are binding residues and it's probably
binding a similar molecule. And when
AlphaFold 2 came out um a group actually
uh um use this approach of homology
modeling to transfer
lians found in proteins in the PDB in
the protein data bank to alphold
predicted structures of proteins that
aren't in the PDB but they're very
closely related. They had some criteria
of what is closely related. Um here's an
example of of a protein. I think this is
just myoglobin. Um and the alphafold
predicted structures on the first two
panels uh on the left. And then um they
could because there's so many structures
of myoglobin and PDB boundahem. They
could just superimpose one of those
structures onto the alpha predicted
structure and say, "Hey, this lian
that's in the crystal structure looks
like it should still fit into this
protein." And uh so we'll just transfer
that over. And it was one point I want
to make here is that alphafold 2 and Ben
made this point I think too. Alphold 2
wasn't trained at all on small molecule
lians. Of course alphaold 3 was and
other models like bolts and um and and
openfold are are were trained on on
small molecule lians as well. But
alphold 2 is not. All the lians were
stripped from the protein structures.
you just had protein there. But the task
for prediction was to predict the
structure of in this case the ligan
bound form with the side chain
confirmers that are in those
confirmations sometimes because the lian
is bound. And so under the hood,
alphafold should be able, I think, to
infer
small molecule binding confirmations
even without explicitly considering a
small molecule and and alphafill is an
example of this that that there's some
success there at transferring over um
small molecule binding sites. The
example here in the middle panel is that
these two histadines are in this
configuration so that they can
coordinate the metal and he alphafold
doesn't know about he explicitly in this
prediction. Okay, so that's that's
another way homology modeling. Um, and
then there's this question I sort of
brought up, which is can't neural
networks already find binding sites
well? Neural networks like um, alphafold
3, bolts 2,
um, other neural networks that handle
small molecules explicitly. Um, is this
problem already solved? um and and and
and what I want to point out. So here
I'm showing Rosetta all atom which was
the first neural network to um to get
published that could handle small
molecule lians at the same time as
protein structure and predicting it. Um
and I want to give you a little example
of of um some of the potential pitfalls
of always trusting these kinds of models
for for figuring out where a small
molecule might go and and how it might
bind. Um, these are great models, by the
way, and they're very useful, but it's I
think it's worth understanding where
they might go wrong so that you can
better use them uh for your own research
problems. So, here's an this is an
example straight out of their paper. And
this said, look, we trained our model
and we had a test set and we tested our
model on the test set and this is an
example of a protein from the test set
that's that's claimed to be completely
outside the training distribution of the
model for Zetapodal atom model. Um the
the technical claim is that the closest
protein sequence to the training set is
25% sequence identity. So that's you
know not not bad. Um the ligan was in
the training set. So this is I think a
flavven adinine um an FAD molecule um or
an FM f FMN molecule. And uh and so they
said oh look um this but our prediction
is spoton. So the so the the crystal
structure is in um white and the
prediction is in cyan and they look
indistinguishable. So the model did such
a good job even though this protein
wasn't in the training set.
Um but it's it's quite easy actually to
just search for other proteins to this
this protein that's outside the training
and look at proteins in the training set
um that that have that are less than 25%
identity but they still have identical
structures basically and identical
binding pockets. And so that cyan
protein that I'm or the the purple
protein that I'm showing you here is a
protein that is only 23% sequence
identity to that protein above. And yet
um I can overlay the structures which I
just did and they look very similar. And
the point here and even if you look at
the the pocket and and the um way the
ligan is bound is pretty much identical.
So so if you had a threshold of 25%
sequence identity means that there's no
data leakage. Think again. This was 23%
sequence identity. The point I want to
make here is that binding is so
important to protein function
that it is one of the parts of the
protein that is most conserved across
evolution. So the rest of the sequence
it can diverge and you can diverge and
still maintain those same structure but
oftent times the binding pocket doesn't
diverge. And so if you're considering
sequence identity of a whole protein as
your criterion for is a binding pocket
the same or not, you can run into issues
like this where you get data leakage and
you might think that your model is quote
unquote generalizing, but it's really
just memorizing.
Okay, so that that's one caveat. Of
course, these models are quite useful
still. Um, but if you want to make the
claim that the model is generalizing and
predicting denovo sites, um, it's hard
to, uh, um, to make that claim basically
without retraining the model. Here's the
point. I'm I'm going to, uh, uh, ask let
you ask your question in one second. Um,
but the point here is that it's hard to
know about these models like Alfold 3
and RFA and Boltz and how um, and how
well they generalize. So being able to
predict pockets and bind small molecules
and dock them accurately um if you can't
retrain them on a really rigorous data
split because a lot of those splits are
not extremely rigorous in term for this
task like it I'm just emphasizing that
this particular task you need to be very
rigorous I think about how you split um
and so this is the meme here is uh you
know training data test data they're the
same thing for a lot of these models um
for this particular task and there was
there was a question.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Uh exactly great great
illustration just so why has the field
not figured out how to deal with this? I
mean you have like
>> it's really well understood in
biochemistry and biohysics that there's
convergent evolution and yada yada and
and somehow
>> the machine learning people still make
these really naive train test splits and
it keeps it's every paper and it's all
these
>> oh yeah
>> really good journals and you know people
acknowledge the problem but there's no
like
>> why hasn't the field kind of put forward
a systematic framework about how to do
train testing?
>> Yeah. Yeah, it's a good question and um
some people are, you know, some people
have recognized this and are trying to
make very rigorous data splits for this
task. Um I won't call out anybody by
name explicitly, but there's a few
groups that I know of in industry as
well as academia that are really trying
to do this well and recognize the
problem. Um but why is it still
prevalent? I think it's because it's
easy to split in different ways that are
e like just by sequence identity. It's
very easy to do that. people have done
it before. It's been published. They got
their paper accepted. They did that. Um,
and so it's very I'll show you in the
next couple of slides um how much work
it actually does take to make a rigorous
data split. And oftentimes making the
data split is, as I tell Ben, sometimes
uh it's it's thankless work. um you're
the unsung hero of the work if you make
a really good data split for training
but no but you don't really get the
medal uh because you know if you haven't
train the model yourself so
>> disincentivized because when you make
the split well your model performance
just crashes right
>> exactly
>> and then people write papers after the
fact where they're like oh we went back
to these models did the split correctly
and now they have no performance
>> so there's also bad incentive ex That's
a really good point is that um oftent
times there's uh competition for if I
publish my model it has to do better
than the previous model and um the
previous model was tested on a split
that had data leakage and your if you're
very rigorous about how you train your
model and do your split then your model
will perform likely worse than the one
that was cheating in a sense and um so
that does lead to saying well I'm just
going to do it on this other split and
see if I do a little bit better but how
but it but that leads to the problem of
how why am I doing better? Is it because
I'm cheating better or because my model
is generalizing better and and and this
is really the a hard problem because um
it's expensive to retrain models
especially the protein structure
prediction models. Not every academic
lab has access to
uh thousand H200s
and half a million dollars to retrain
the models and then two months of time.
Right? So um so so how do you do that?
And so that's actually one of the
motivations for what we did with AF2
buying. Um yeah, another question.
>> Sorry, can I have a very pedestrian
question for the previous slide? Uh
>> where you show 23% sequence identity. So
23% sequent identity in this case does
it mean that there is like a match every
fourth amino acid or there is actually a
stretch of matches that correspond to
this binding site between two proteins.
>> Um usually what you'll see is that a lot
of the surface residues are very
different. Um and it's usually how
proteins evolve. If you look at two
proteins in the same family, um they
might have a very similar core packing
uh and and the least conserved residues
are all on the surface of the protein,
but the most conserved residues are the
ones that are involved directly in
binding liant usually. And so and so in
this case, it's not every four amino
acids are conserved. It would be that
the binding pocket in for these two
proteins look very similar. And as you
move out to the outside of the onion um
the the residues get more different
between the two. So that's how one can
it's not a uniform uh metric. So you can
fool yourself.
>> Another quick question here is that um
is the conservation across species or we
are talking also about conservation
across paralogs because in small
molecule
>> field we actually want not so conserved
pocket.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um you can get a lot of
conservation even across paralogues
different I mean species and paralogues
within a species. Um
yeah, I mean the thing that you
mentioned is is uh you know an important
one is that and that's one of the
problems with um trying to for drug
discovery to get a specific molecule
that'll bind to a specific target is
that the binding sites are so conserved
across different proteins paralogues of
you know the same species humans for
example um and that trying to design a
small molecule that binds to this pocket
and not that pocket is very challenging
because those those pockets are so the
residues in those pockets are so
conserved. Um and so but there it can be
one amino acid two amino acid difference
and that's what drug that's what you
know medicinal chemists and uh try to
take advantage of for specificity but
you could imagine that you know I mean a
lot of these neural networks if you
change one residue in the binding pocket
and then predict the same lian it'll
still put the lian there because it's
it's more of pattern matching than it is
about understanding really the physics
behind it. Um so if you classic thing
would be to do a bump hole you know um
do a bump hole uh um like you know since
we're at the broad you know Steuart
Shriber did bump holes all the time back
with uh um you know FKBP andrb and the
rapamy derivatives and to make these
these analoges very specific for a
protein you'd take a put a bump on the
ligant uh so so you have add a
functional group that would clash with
the binding pocket in the natural
protein
but then mutate the natural protein to
so that that residue that it would clash
with is now a smaller residue and now it
can fit. And so now your new lian can
fit into a a new pocket that's only one
amino acid different, but it allows for
specificity. If you did that for a
neural network and you took the bumped
lian and still predicted it with the
wild type pocket, it'll still put the
lian there, but it shouldn't bind. You
know, physically it should bind. So, um,
so that's that's one important thing to
note. Um, yeah. So, but the but the goal
of being able to find pockets that
aren't so conserved for drug discovery
is a good goal. And I'll get to that, I
think, a little bit, right? So, training
data, test data, um, you know, they're
the same picture. Good. So, how so how
did we go about doing this? Because our
motivation was to to actually train a
model that would be we would have
confidence deploying at scale to unknown
proteins and we want to be able to
predict denovo pockets. Denovo pockets
meaning ones that um you know alpha fill
wouldn't be able to predict by homology
simply for example. We want to be able
to know are there pockets in this
protein that um our model uh that we've
trained can pick up about features for
those pockets as opposed to just
cheating because that pocket was seen in
training. Okay. So we had to be very
rigorous about this. So Sergey and I
worked on this for several months I want
to say uh it was a we did many many
iterations of this training uh test data
set and refinement. I'll take you
through what we what we had to do. First
thing we did is we took every protein in
the PDB. There's about 200 200,000
proteins in the PDB, a little bit more
than that, crystal structures, cryom
structures, things like that. We focused
on crystal structures here. Um, but we
took proteins that in this case we we
whittleled it down to single chain
proteins
and uh proteins that were less than 500
amino acids. Uh, so single chain 500
amino acid or less. The average size was
about 300 amino acids. Protein had to be
greater than 40 amino acids. So, it
couldn't be a peptide. Um, it had to
bind one one small molecule liant in the
crystal structure. Um, and and that
small molecule couldn't be making
interactions with another protein in the
crystal structure or um another copy of
the same protein in the crystal via
crystal contact. We really wanted to
make sure that this small molecule was a
good binding site. Um, so we did that.
Uh, so that gives you from the
200,000ish, it gives you about 14,000
proteins. Uh we filtered by resolution
too. It was kind of modest resolution
like 3.5 angstrom resolution. So we
didn't we didn't get rid of many. Um and
then we clustered by here's that here's
that dirty word again sequence identity.
We clustered by sequence identity um
using M62 and that reduced the number of
um of protein structures to around
2,000. But we didn't stop there. A lot
of people would stop there and say we're
done. That's our that's our set. will
split the clusters um which are only 30%
similar. This is how something like
protein MPNM is trained. Uh split the
clusters and then that's our trained
test set. But for small molecule binding
prediction, we um needed to be a little
bit more rigorous. And so we did a few
things. We then took those and and uh
filtered them by similar families of of
sequences in PAM and interpro and then
we did structural similarity by TM align
and TM score. Uh so we wanted a we
wanted low structural similarity between
the the single chain proteins and then
then from there some of those single
chain proteins were multi-dommain
proteins and so we wanted to make sure
that um but many of them were single
domain uh we wanted to make sure that
there were no domains that were even the
same in our in our data set. Um and then
finally from that we uh just took the
pocket residues. You can identify
residues from the crystal structure
trivially by just saying these residues
are within five anstroms of a of a bound
liant and those are those are the pocket
residues and you can extract those
coordinates from the structure and then
instead of aligning the whole protein
you can align pockets to one another
using TM align as well and um and so we
wanted to make sure that the pockets
weren't similar and and you can see that
there would have been some pro if we
didn't do this there would have been
some proteins that passed all those
filters but yet still had similar
pockets. So, we lost some at the very
end. But look at look at the number that
we have at the end. We went from over
200,000 proteins in the PDB and filtered
by what we think are all necessary
criteria for eliminating data leakage
for this prediction task. And we ended
up with 200 proteins.
That's not a lot to train a deep neural
network, right? 200 data points. I don't
think anybody in this room would feel
comfortable trying to train a deep
neural network from scratch on 200 data
points. I hope not. Um and so okay, so
this could be an issue. And so um what
we did too, so we split that those 200
structures up into a training set and a
validation set and a test set. We
actually split them up into 11 different
groups so we could do 10-fold cross
validation where each group had about um
20 proteins in it. Um, and each group
was very different from the other group
by all those criteria that I just
mentioned. And then we enrich those a
little bit by saying, okay, within a
group, as long as it's different from
any other group, we can we can relax
some of those criteria from our 2,00
proteins. So just increase the numbers a
little bit. So now we have instead of
200, we have around 700 proteins. Okay?
But they're all but the these these 11
groups, which I'm not showing explicitly
here, these 11 groups are all very
different from one another.
um we always took one group as the test
set and then we would mix up the train
validation sets for cross validation for
training. Okay, so I I think I made the
point that um the amount of unique data
here, non-redundant data for this task
is just too small I think to train a a
neural network from scratch. Um and so
the question that that we we ask is can
we use embeddings from a pre-trained
model? And this is one of the reasons
why Ben took you through all these
models uh in the primer is all these
models, ESM2, protein sequence model,
alpha fold 2, ESM1
sequence prediction model, um even
protein MPN um these were all trained
and these were the ones available at the
time of this work anyway and um and
these were all trained not seeing ligans
at all but yet they were trained on much
more data uh on different tasks, right?
on the task of of sequence prediction or
structure prediction but on train on all
the PDB on all the proteins in um
sequence databases
uh and and even on you know self-dist
distilled proteins where you would
predict the structures of of real
proteins from sequence databases and
train on those um not train on lians at
all but yet could they develop a rich
enough embedding of what protein
structure is to be used for a downstream
prediction task like predicting is this
residue binding a lian you're not right.
That's the idea. So this you're not
trained on. So it's kind of
counterintuitive, but I want to take you
through why I think it might work and
why we thought this might work at the
time and why it does work. Uh I think
so. Um one of the reasons is that uh you
know the question is why why could these
embeddings be useful on models that
weren't trained on or don't haven't seen
leans before? uh and and the one of the
interesting uh things that I maybe I
want you to take away from this talk is
that protein small molecule interactions
um and I'm showing one on the left in
the bottom left here for example a green
glutamine interacting with a purple lian
small molecule drug these interactions
that proteins make with small molecules
look a heck of a lot like interactions
that proteins make with protein and in
scan it's just another that's just an
asparagene residue from another protein.
And these interaction geometries look
very similar. And so um you you could
think of drugs or small molecules or
metabolites as combinations of amino
acid features. You could think of that
and say that well if a model was trained
on predicting
interactions between residues even
within a chain
even within a chain of a protein as
opposed to even between different chains
of proteins that those interactions that
it's learned about could be transferable
interactions with small molecular drugs
or metabolites whatever molecules you
want. Um we actually took and we were
curious about this. If you take all the
lians in the PTB
about four 40,000 of them that we could
actually take the smile strings of and
RDKit would read them. So about 40,000
lians. Can we convert those to Morgan
fingerprints
uh for the small molecule lians just a
just a vector that's basically different
different functional groups of the ligan
a one or a zero and um and if we do the
same thing for the 20 amino acids
convert the 20 amino acids take a smile
string proteinated you know charge
uncharge for the 20 amino acids and
convert those to to um Morgan
fingerprints these vectors then you
could you could ask for any drug which
is represented as a vector
how many of its components
are represented in the 20 amino acid
vectors as a basis set for this drug,
the small molecule. And um and so this
histogram is uh the molecule counts by
just a fraction of the the molecule
covered by amino acids. So the average
is about 50%. Any molecule in the PTBE,
at least half of it on average can be
described by amino acids. And so I'm
showing you some of those examples down
below where the red circles are the bits
of it that were described by amino acids
via the Morgan fingerprint. So a lot of
these molecules can be described. So
it's serotonin, the drug down at the
bottom, a pixaban,
um, rap, what is the one in the the one
that's in the top second from the top on
the right? I guess I think that's LSD.
So but all these can be um can be
represented by amino acids. Okay. So
that's one motivation. So a lot of these
interaction you can go into any
individual crystal structure now and you
can mine for these kinds of interactions
with different fragments. Now so um so
here's an example. Um take any protein
from the PDB and you could say I want to
know how proteins interact with this
green functional group caroximate.
And there's a lot of caroxids in this
protein. They're amino acid side chains.
that's part of asparagene and glutamine.
So you can go into any single one of
them and you can say I want to know
what's interacting with this particular
asparagene in green and it looks like
there's three amino acids that interact
with it directly in white. And some of
those interactions within that single
chain protein are what I would call
local in sequence and some of them are
distant in sequence. And proteins are
like a polymer. They're just a polymer.
They have a persistence length where the
chain sort of forgets the direction that
it's going. And if you have two residues
interacting that are beyond the
persistence length of the polymer, it's
sort of like seeing um two different
molecules that are not part of the same
chain. Um so it's sort of like a protein
drug interaction and that would be the
one on the bottom. It's distant in
sequence. All right. So you could then
take those and say, okay, this is my
amino acid. It's interacting with a a a
the green caroximid at this position in
space. And you could do that for all the
proteins in the PDB and start to build
up massive data sets for how amino acids
interact with these kinds of fragments.
We made up a term for this called a
vandimer which is a um
it's related to the term is related to
amino acid rotimer a distinct side chain
configuration but a vandimer is a
configuration that a fragment might be
found and a fragment is coming from an
amino acid but that fragment
nevertheless could be used to describe
um uh we have a lot of these data sets
and and they could be used to describe
small molecules and their interactions
with uh proteins in the PDB. So here I'm
just showing a couple of examples of
crystal structures found to different
drugs. Um you have actually a pixaban
and then you have actually that's
adrenaline from a gpcr and and the
interactions with the small molecule can
be very well described by these
interactions just pulling out from
proteins how they interact with
functional groups from side chains of
amino acids. So that's kind of cool. Um
we just as an aside, this isn't really
the the point of this talk, but we took
that kind of a basis set and we designed
proteins from scratch in my group um
with Bill Drat too at UCSF um as a real
test for can we use these protein amino
acid interactions to design protein
small molecule interactions and this
worked. But this is a that's a different
talk, right? So, so that's what made us
believe that maybe these models that
were trained without lians but just to
predict maybe protein understanding of
protein protein interactions intrachain
interactions could be used to predict
small molecule binding sites. The last
thing that we thought was interesting uh
is that it's kind of well known that
when a small molecule binds a protein
that protein might get a little bit
smaller and it might finish folding. you
know, existing contacts might be more
enthalpically favorable after binding.
There's a really great review by Dudley
Williams from 20 years ago that I'm
citing here. And this is just showing if
you have a protein that's a big circle,
it gets a little small when it binds a
liant. And so can but so binding might
finish folding quote unquote the the
protein. And so if you had a a structure
prediction model like alphafold 2, could
you use the structure prediction model
somehow to finish folding the protein?
Could that signal be used and read out
to predict ligan binding sites? That was
another thing that we were wondering
about. And so here's one way you might
might go about doing that. Now I'm going
to get into like the guts of alpha AF2
bind and then the the the um and then
what we can do with it. So what we do is
we take and alphold 2 here is the single
chain alphaold model. So it's the first
one that came out. It's not alpha 2
multimer. It's the single chain. It's
only been trained on single chain
proteins. And um we use the target
sequence. So this is an example of a
four helix bundle. Um take the target
sequence of the protein and you take the
backbone coordinates. You could use the
side chain coordinates too of that
protein as a template to alpha fold
and um and then we use 20 bait amino
acids. beta amino acids then we can we
can in the single chain model of
alphafold you can represent different
chains um in a hacky way by saying by
giving the each each chain a large
residue offset and so each one of these
bait amino acids these are the 20
canonical amino acids we could just um
make a residue offset of 50 arbitrary
arbitrary number 50 residue offset and
alpha fold 2 sees it as sort of like a
separate chain it won't try to connect
them covealently
um and So, so we decided what if we ch
what if we use these beta amino acids as
surrogate lians that alphafold might be
able to finish folding with. There's no
multiple sequence alignment here because
we're using the template uh of the
protein. Um and alphafold if you give it
people don't know if you give alphafold
a template structure that has the same
sequence as the sequence you're
predicting with alphafold it'll
basically output the same structure as
the input.
So the STR and this so there was a
question before about can AF2 bind
handle multiple confirmations of
proteins and it can um if you give it
different templates uh because it'll
just output that same template structure
basically for identical sequences. Um
okay so this okay so this is the
question is could you just simply use it
and dock these lians and then use that
information. So this is what it looks
like if you do that, right? There's just
20 amino acids everywhere. Maybe some of
them go inside, some of them are
outside. This is also just a single pass
through the model. Um, we could maybe
try to make sense of this, but this is
kind this is a, you know, a little bit
messy. So we decided that maybe the best
signal to try to extract would be to go
into the guts of alpha 2. Not just look
at the output of alpha 2, but look go
into the guts of it and look at the
embeddings. and in particular look at
the pair representation and the single
representation Ben talked about. So
which alphafold converts the input
sequence into these embeddings in order
to predict structure.
Um and so in so instead of just docking
these molecules and then looking at the
output of alphafold we actually just run
alphafold 2 a single pass through the
model and we don't care about where
these beta amino acids actually go where
they're put by alphafold. What we care
about is how alphafold
um how alpha fold attends to each of
those bait residues with respect to any
residue in the template in the template
structure. And so the the alpha the pair
representation of alpha fold is a tensor
for any pair of molecu any pair of
residues that are that are folded. Um
you have an embedding
and that embedding is 128 numbers. And
so this tensor looks like this cube
where um in the in the um blue and in
the cyan it's actually not symmetric. So
the blue and the cyan um in a symmetric
mat matrix would be equal to one another
but in this case there's sort of
different numbers um and so for each of
the bait residues the 20 bait residues
we actually care how alphafold creates
an embedding for any of the residues in
the template structure and that those
are the features we're going to extract
from the from the pair representation
and train a model to predict if this is
a binding residue or not. I'll take you
through what that means. But this is um
this is basically the training objective
now is we take all these inputs on the
left for a particular protein. We don't
have to use a multiple sequence
alignment and we stick those into alpha
2 single pass through the model and then
we extract features from the pair
representation and linearly combine them
and train a logistic regression model in
order to predict which residues on that
protein are binding residues. We have
all those ground truth labels from that
data set that we painstakingly made. For
example, from a crystal structure of
this protein, we know it binds this
green lian. So, we know what the ground
truth labels are. They're in purple.
These are the these are the pocket
contact these are the ligan contacting
residues of the pocket. And um the goal
for um an AF2 bind like model is to
predict which those what those residues
are. All right. So, this is this is in
practice how it works. So what we do is
like I said we just take that pair
representation and we extract the um the
blue and the cyan parts of the pair
representation and we stack them. All
right so this is the best way I could
come up with an illustration of what it
is we're actually doing with AF2 bind
and and um and then I've highlighted a
single residue uh um in red as a slice
of the pair representation. I'm not sure
if you can see my you can't see my my
cursor but single residue in red um
residue let's call it residue n and so
we can extract that slice so if we're
interested in does residue n is there a
high probability of it binding a small
molecule liant or not then this is these
are the features we extract from the
pair representation for residue n we can
concatenate them and uh so we have about
so it's it's uh 20 by 128 um plus 128 so
it's around 5,28 features for just this
single uh the single residue because
it's it's the 20 different feature pair
features for the 20 different bait res.
Okay. And um and so then we we have
those those numbers which are just
numbers from AlphaFold's internal guts
and we train a weight matrix plus a
bias. That's the al that's the AF2 bind
model. a weight matrix is trained um and
a logistic regression model. Those the
weight matrix plus the bias converts
those 5,28 numbers into one number Z.
Z goes into a sigmoid and that's the
binding probability of the model. And we
know and it's just cross entropy loss,
right? So we uh or binary uh loss where
um where uh you get a one if it's the
correct prediction and it's a zero if
not and the weights are updated on the
model in order to predict the right
labels one or zero binding residue not
binding. Um so we call that probability
pbind probability of binding and um and
we train that in this cross validation
data set very rigorously. Um and this is
and it works on unseen folds. We
actually put these in our test set uh
because they're famous examples. The
muopioid receptor, it's a GPCR. Those
were not trained on nothing like GPCRs
were trained on. Chrommo domains bind
lots of lians. They weren't trained on
nothing like them. No similar pockets
were trained on. And AF2 binds using the
pair representation predicts those
pockets really really well. Um, but it
not only gives you just uh uh the
pocket, but what's what's what's you
know you could ask, well maybe uh P2
rank would do the same thing here
because there's a pocket is obvious.
What the subtlety here is that for every
residue in the pocket um AF2 bind gives
you a probability that that residue is
binding any small molecule liant. And
those probabilities are not the same for
every residue in the pocket. And so
there are some hotspot residues that
might be um more favorably interacting
with lians than other residues in this
pocket. And that we've actually this
isn't in the paper, but I I I was
playing around with this. And if you
just use the probabilities from AF2 bind
and a um a simple model that says rigid
body docking of a small molecule
um where it's a known small molecule. So
you kind of cheat and you take the right
configuration of the small molecule, but
it doesn't know where to go. All all
it's trying to do is maximize the
contacts of the small molecule with
residues that have high pbind. So so
maximize that score. You actually can
recover um in in in many examples you
can recover the true binding post which
is kind of cool because there's no
energy function other than just
maximizing speed but that's not in the
paper. Um no reviewer asked for that so
um we didn't put it in. Yeah. Couple
questions.
also learn about the uh the ligan itself
like do you have does
>> does it map at all to like the the
residues that it thinks in that
representation do they look do they have
similar functionality to the actual
opioid
>> yeah that that's a great question so can
we learn something about the actual
nature of the the um small molecule that
binds there and I'll skip I'll skip this
I'll go back to this slide in a second
but I'll go straight to your the answer
your question is that the model because
it's simple because it's just a simple
logistic regression model. we can go
immediately back to everything the 20
beta amino acids as the input and say so
um what we did here is this is the same
input that goes into the logistic
regression model these two um red boxes
of features but instead of converting
them all to one sum to one number Z that
goes into the sigmoid we can um do a do
a um a selective sum first and keep and
basically sum the uh the features so
that we collapse it from a 20 by 256 six
to a 20 by one. The 20 dimension being
each of the bait amino acids. So every
one of the canonical 20 amino acids and
we could say which of these 20 amino
acids actually is has an activation that
would be firing the sigmoid right to
predict binding or not binding. And so
the blue here is on the very right is uh
amino acids that would be firing high.
So being being correlated with a
prediction for this is a binding residue
and then the red are are
anti-correlated. Um and so what's kind
of cool is that you can do this for
every residue that's predicted in the
pocket, not just a single residue and
sort of build up these maps
of of um what of attributing bait
residues to the prediction of this is a
binding residue or not. And so you can
directly attribute. So the point of this
slide is that it it does correlate um
you know per as I would expect but it
was really great to see sort of maybe
unintuitive but um if you think of
pockets that bind apolar ligans like for
example the one in the bottom left here
this protein that binds this apolar
lipid
the bait residues that are responsible
for the prediction of that binding
pocket are I'm pointing out with a a a
black arrow are these hydrophobic amino
acids fenol alanine, tryptophan
and so those are the amino acids that
are that are leading to that prediction.
On the opposite on the right side of the
slide there's a a protein different
protein that binds to a very polar amino
acid. Um lot of different you can see a
lot of different oxygens and nitrogens
in that that that um it binds to a very
polar lian. Uh and and um the the beta
amino acids that actually lead to the
prediction there are polar beta amino
acids. So those are um in this case you
have glutamine asparagene um uh
aspartate and glutamate. So the blue
parts are the parts that are leading to
the predictions and there are different
the point is there are different beta
amino acids that do that depending on
the nature of the binding pocket kinds
of lians that are bind. One idea would
be to directly use these maps as input
features to predicting what kind of
lians. We haven't done that, but um one
could imagine doing that and taking
these as a a nice representation of the
pocket and saying, "Okay, I'm going to
figure out what drug or small molecule
might bind there." Future work. Um
that's one way to do it. Um and then
just the last point on this is we looked
at every those were just two anecdotal
examples but we looked at every protein
in our training set and test set all
across everything and um so many
thousands of of amino acids that are
predicted to be pockets and we knew the
nature of the lian uh because this is
ground truth. So we knew how many for
example the simplest thing is just to
count up how many carbons are in the
lian because that's sort of a a proxy
for a hydrophobicity of the ligan. And
so where what I'm plotting here here on
the y- axis um is fractions of um
non-carbon atoms. So the polar atoms I
guess and um and then the uh the x- axis
is the um the firing the fraction of
predicted bait residues um that that
correlate with um with these uh non the
amount of non-carbon polar atoms in the
ligan. And you can see that for on the
left, these are kind of hydrophobic
residues, fennel alanine and isolucine.
And they're um they're inversely
correlated as they start firing. You go
you go up the x- axis, the amount of
polar residues in the lians go goes down
and it's inversely correlated on the
right where you have a a glutamate and
histadine residues pretty polar. And
those um the the nature of the lians
become more polar when those amino acids
are starting to fire. Um let's see. I I
do want to go I want to go back to this
one slide first before I get into more
related results about that. Um but just
this is just to show that we looked at
one of the reasons why this was nice in
looking at um uh uh embeddings from
neural networks is we didn't have to
retrain the models. Number one, they
weren't trained on lians. So there's no
memorization in that sense. Um and we
could just extract the embeddings and
then we're just taking the embeddings
and training a logistic regression model
on those embeddings. So we can actually
just train the same logistic regression
model
um using the different embeddings from
the different neural networks on our
same data set. Right? So now we can sort
of compare apples to apples which
embeddings are are better for our data
set which has this rigorous split. Um so
we did the single representation alful
too. Um I usually don't show tables in
slides but um this is kind of a nice
table because it just shows you we did
um ESM2 protein sequence only ESM1
inverse folding structure only um alpha
fold 2 which is the AF2 the pair
representation which is AF2 bind um and
then these are the the combinations of
the models and the point here is that of
the single uh um uh embeddings from
different neural networks alphold 2 pair
representation does the best um if you
care about you know rock curves curves.
These are what the the rock curves look
like. Precision um recall curves and AF2
bind is up here and up here as well as
these linear combinations of the models.
And then ES ESM2 and ESM1 inverse
folding are these guys here. Um and so
we because of the interpretability, you
know, we can interpret which bait
residues belong to which we stuck with
AF2 the AF2 bind model. If you're
interested, all these other linear
combinations of models which we
retrained everything from scratch um for
a fair prediction. Um these are all
available to on GitHub if you want to
use these models. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So I have a question about the
input of your model. Uh you had these
two different pairs, the green one and
the blue one. I didn't get what's the
difference.
>> I had Sorry. Oh. Oh. Um what's the input
to this? What's the difference between
um between
>> the order the Yeah. So um they in in
theory they should be symmetric um but
they're not because it's just this is a
this is the um alphaold 2 attention
basically between bait residue one let's
say and amino acid n in the protein and
then this is the same attention bait
residue one and amino acid n up here. Um
so they but they're not actually
symmetric in the model.
>> And so and so instead of so you could
imagine just um taking one of them or
the other and training a model just on
one of them. Um and if they were the
exact same that's what you would get.
You would just get the same model. But
they're not exactly the same features.
They're very similar. And I'll show
actually if you do PCA on the input
features you don't need all 5,000
input features for the predictions. Um,
but the the motivation here is we were
just concatenating that because they're
actually different numbers although
they're they're pretty similar.
>> And for example, if you randomize the
concatenation,
is the performance going down? Did you
try?
>> If you randomize what?
>> The concatenation. So first, if you have
the green one, the blue one, or the blue
one, the green one?
>> Um, if you randomize them, so you don't
necessarily want to randomize them. um
because where the position is sort of
well actually once you have once you
have this already built up it doesn't m
the only thing that goes into the
logistic regression model is slices. So
we actually do randomize in the sense
that we we take this and we break it up
into all the slices and we can train in
parallel each one of these red slices.
Um but um but if you're talking about
putting this in front of this instead of
this behind it, I don't think that would
that would matter.
>> Yeah, because I was thinking maybe of a
deep set neuronet network.
>> You were thinking what? of a deep set
neuronet network where you have the only
the embedding. So you have you have half
the embedding size and then for for
example you one hoting code if if it's
the blue one or the green one.
>> Yeah. Um yeah I'm not sure. So but I I
yeah uh in this case in this case it
wouldn't matter. Um so I think just for
the sake of time we're going to keep
going um because I have a lot to to get
through I guess. So um I'm not going to
go through this is just to say yeah I
mean this point here in the scatter plot
is just to show you that the pair
representation
does better than ESM2 and ESM1 inverse
folding. I'll tell you a little bit
about this metric recall. What the
recall is is a threshold independent
metric where you take all the residues
in the protein predict binding
probability and just rank them based on
largest residues with the largest
binding probability to the lowest. And
then you if you know that this protein
has n residues that are binding
residues, let's say it was 20 20 of the
200 residues in the protein are binding
residues. Then you look at the top 20
that were ranked by AF2 bind or by any
of these models and you say are these
top 20 ranked by probability of binding,
are they the true binding residues? What
fraction of those are true binding
residues? That's that's what we're
calling um recovery here. Uh which is
this this term here. But if you wanted
more um more machine learning like uh
metrics, the rock curves are there and
the precision recall curves. Um okay, so
I went through this, I went through
this, I went through that. Uh the other
thing to just note is that um we did PCA
on we did principal component analysis
on these um these these pair features uh
on the dimension of the 20 bait. So we
could stack all these examples and then
do PCA and say what is what is cor are
the baits correlated with one another?
Do you need all 20 amino acids? Could
you could you get away with this
prediction by doing three baits instead
of 20 bait residues? Um, and what the
PCA shows is that um, at least for 95%
of the variants, you need about 17 out
of the 20 baits. So, you do need a lot
of these bait residues. Um, the only
bait res residue that really didn't seem
to matter uh, much was cyine. Like I
guess we could drop out cyine. Um, alpha
2 doesn't care about cyine at all. Um,
at least in this prediction task. Uh,
and um, and if you look at the principal
component vectors, um, you can see which
which amino which bait residues are
firing with one another. first principal
component, everything's firing together
except for cyine. Um, and then the other
two, which do explain a fair amount of
the variance, it's kind of bio sort of
biochemically related. It makes sense
that the the bait residues that are
correlated on the s second principal
component vector are these polar ones
and the ones that are anti-correlated
with that are apolar. That's kind of
cool. And then for the third principal
component, the positive residues of the
baits are anti-correlated with negative.
So this all makes sense. So, we also did
a Spearman rank correlation just to see
which which pairs fire together. It's
sort of redundant to the PCA. Um, but
just for sake of time, I'm just going to
sort of breeze through this and just say
that the um, as you would expect, the
hydrophobic baits sort of fire together.
Um, and the polar ones fire together and
the negative charged ones fire together
and the positively charged ones fire
together. That's all that really is
saying. Um, and then here's sort of
related to your question earlier. Do you
do you need all these features? If you
do PCA over the feature dimension and
you ask how many of these 5,128 features
are needed uh to explain all the
variance um you only need a little bit
over a thousand features um so you only
need a thousand components of of of the
PCA in order to explain about 90 95% of
the variance. I mean we use them all
because the logistic regression model is
so fast. We don't need to make it faster
by doing dimensionality reduction with
PCA. Um, but it does it goes to show
that probably those probably could have
just dropped out one of the pairs
because then that would have dropped out
a couple of thousand of features and you
don't need more than a thousand features
really. Um, but could be that you need
linear combinations of features. So
that's anyway. So um, so that was that.
Uh, what's really interesting for for
actually deploying AF2 bind and why it
might be different than a model like P2
rank is that we didn't need side chains.
If you delete side chain information
from the input template and have AF2ine
predict which residue. So it still knows
the sequence. It just doesn't know the
dihedral angles of the rotors in the
protein. So we just erase that. But it
knows the sequence and it knows the
backbone. And if you compare its its
performance so if you're on this side of
the line then the side chainless
template does better for AF2 bind for
the prediction of binding residues. If
you're on this side of the line, then um
input that has side chains does a little
bit better. And you see it's basically a
diagonal line. So um it's it's sort of a
wash whether you use side chains or not.
Some cases not using side chains is
better. And so that's kind of nice
because a lot of small molecule binding
uh sites in proteins um maybe they
change a rotimer or two on average when
they bind a lian. Sometimes they don't
change rotimer at all side chains at
all. Um but a lot of if you want to use
predicted structures you know and you
don't have a lian at all good luck
getting the right side chains for lian
binding right so if you have a model
that ignores side chains it still makes
good predictions this could be quite
advantageous so so that was really nice
so we um this is just a summary of what
it does uh these are the inputs and then
predictions for the outputs so we use no
side chain dihedrals as well and then we
deployed this at scale and I'm going to
get into a little bit of the results
none of this is I think really in the
bioarchchive paper. So we took the AF2
predicted human proteom structures which
is all single chain structures of
proteins um and uh and a lot but we took
those and we we ran AF2 bind on it. Um a
lot of human proteins are multi-chain a
lot of them are homoygr bind to other
things um and all this database is
single chain structures. So you could
you could imagine asking you know are
any of these structures relevant you
know to real proteins in in cells in
humans. Um and it turns out that a lot
of these single chain structures they
when you compare them to structures of
multi-chain proteins real structures the
predictive single chain structures look
like they look than when they're in the
multi-chain protein. And a lot of that
is because it's dealing with multiple
sequence alignments.
So there's a whole lot of subtleties of
why that might be what I don't have
really time to talk about right now. Um
but just take it take it for granted
right now that a lot of these single
chain structures actually resemble
multi-chain if there are multi-chain
proteins. Um and then in the human
proteome some of the some of the
proteins have low confidence from alpha.
We trim those off basically and we just
deal with the higher confidence bits of
the predictions. So that becomes the
input to AF2 bind. And uh then we just
we just say okay what are the binding
pockets that AF2 binds? What are the
binding sites um that AF2 bind finds. Um
and but first I want to say because
somebody was asking me this was asking
me this earlier is if you just stick any
really large protein into AF2 bind it
was only trained on proteins up to 500
amino acids. Um and the the pair
representation is there's a soft max
over that. the embeddings are normalized
and so the bigger the protein the lower
the magnitude of the embeddings
basically um but then this but AF2 bind
was trained for a certain magnitude of
the embeddings because the size of the
proteins was on average 300 amino acids
at most 500 amino acids but these
proteins can be thousands of amino acids
thousand or more and putting and if you
had a single threshold for the
probability of binding above which
you're saying this is a real binding
site below which you're saying this is
not a real binding site
And if if that threshold basically
depends on the size of the protein, it's
going to be harder to actually use this
and make real good predictions. And this
is an example. So if you take this
protein and you plug this into AF2
vanilla, we'll call it um the model as
we trained it, you see some weak blue
color here. And this is colored by the
probability of binding. So you can
almost say there's no binding sites, but
we know that there's binding sites in
here. Here are the binding sites
protein, right? And the question is how
can we recover this kind of thing
without you know how do we deal with
this dilution problem of pair embeddings
what's the so we thought about this a
lot and the the the best solution we
came up with actually is to split the
big proteins into domains and you can
use uh um you know already you know
computed domain labels from eod or you
could use a domain parser yourself. So
you split these into domains and then
you can do the um computations on on
different domains. So, so basically if
you have you know domains that are 300
residues or more is do the computation
on that and then any pair of contacting
domains
>> you can do the computation.
>> How would you decide the domain?
>> Sorry,
>> how would you decide which domain to
split?
>> How do you decide which domain? So um so
in this case because we did all human
proteins um the uh people who made um
ECOD which is the evolutionary
classification of domains actually have
already split all of the alphold 2
predicted structures into domains. So we
could just take a list and split them
that way. But if you if you didn't have
that list and you wanted your your
arbitrary protein to split it in
domains, you can use domain par. There's
a lot of domain parsers out there um
that are really fast and pretty accurate
um that are you know neural networks and
non-neural network based that you could
do. Um so this is the idea is that um we
we would then just do AF2 bind
predictions on these pairs and then we
would take the maximum probability for
any residue as the probability of
binding. We would zero out any um
residues that um when you look at them
in the full structure if they have no
solvent accessible surface area at all
and you remove the domain and now there
was a lot of solvent accessible surface
area it's unrealistic and AF2ine
predicts a binding site there well we
zero that out because in the in the full
in the full structure it would be
completely buried so if you take so
that's the one caveat maybe we could
miss some sites that way um but on in
practice I don't think we miss very
Um and so then we just take the maximum
binding probability across all for every
residue across these computations and
then we combine that into the one
structure. And so now you can see that
we do from that analysis we do recover
these true binding sites with high
binding probability. So this is what we
did to deploy AF2 bind across the whole
human proteome for structures that were
bigger than 500 amino acids. We would
split them up into into domains and then
do this. Um, okay. So, what does it
find? And what does it I think what does
it find? Well, what does it find more
importantly compared to what other
methods find already? Because you could
use P2 rank, you could use alpha fill to
look at the whole human proteome and
then you could use AF2 bind. And why
would we want to use AF2 bind? So,
ideally, you find something that the
other ones don't, right? And so, here's
a nice ven diagram of using those three
methods on the whole AF2 predicted human
proteome. Um and you can see that um
AF2bind has this are this is the number
of binding sites found in uh in in in
the human protein
sites that that P2 rank does not and
that alphaill does not and there's some
overlap between the two. Um so it's
finding very unique sites. The ones on
the right here I'm showing you are AF2
bindon sites that were not found by
alphaill. So the ones some some ones in
this blue region. They're not found by
alphaill, so by homology modeling, and
they're not found by P2 rank, which is
more of a classic classifier. Um, and
you could say, okay, are these binding
sites um relevant to drug discovery at
all? How druggable are they? Um, and so
you could take all the binding sites
that were predicted by, for example, P2
rank and AF2 bind, and you can classify
them in a another software, Schroinger's
sitemap software, which comes out with a
drugability score called Dcore. And um
and so drug ability
empirically it's been found if you have
a score above like 0.8 for drugability
maybe 082 or something um that for the
dcore in in Schroinger sitemap that it's
a pretty druggable pocket. Drugability
is basically how enclosed it is and how
hydrophobic it is. Um and so you can see
that on average the um the binding sites
from AF2 bind versus P2 rank are very
druggable above this threshold. And this
is um this is the morbid map database
here uh PT rank versus AF2 bind. So this
is actually about 4,000 5,000 proteins
in the human proteome that are known to
be involved in disease. And uh and so
you can see it's also finding sites in
that and it does find unique sites in
those proteins that P2 rank and alph
don't don't find which I'm not showing
here. So it's it's finding unique sites
which is really cool. If you look at the
protein families that are the most
druggable by AF2 bind these protein
families sort of make sense. You have um
I'm just I'm just pointing out a few
here. You've got um um these these uh
globin-l like proteins, these alenil
transfer proteins. GPCRs are up there.
I'm just not highlighting them with the
picture. Um tetraaspanins, a lot of
different proteins out there that you
would say, okay, yeah, I know these are
druggable. So, so it's making sense, but
then it finds proteins that you wouldn't
think about. Um which um I don't really
have time to highlight too much in this
talk. Uh the last thing I want to say
about the quality of the binding pockets
is um and I'm comparing them AF2 bind
and P2 rank. So AF2 bind is in blue and
P2 rank is in orange and these are all
the um features that that are output by
Schroinger sitemap. And I want to just
highlight the couple of features that
are different maybe strikingly different
uh between AF2bind versus P2 rank and
AF2bine has less on average a little bit
less enclosure of the pocket. So
shallower pockets, exposure of course
being higher and enclosure being a
little lower than sites in P2 rank. And
I want to point out a couple of, you
know, anecdotal examples of where that
might be advantageous that you have a
little bit shallower pockets that are
predicted by AF2 bind. Here's a few
examples is that these are missed by P2
rank there doesn't even predict
anything. There's P2 rank says there's
no site here. AF2 bind says yes, this is
a site. Here it is in purple. And this
is this is on the AF2 predicted
structures. But in these in this case,
there were actually crystal structures
of these proteins in the PDB. And so you
could look and say, well, okay, what
what lians are binding there? And in one
case, this is a part of tomeorase, I
think. And um and so it's binding to to
um to RNA. This is binding to DNA. This
is a transcription factor. Um, and then
this is a protein that binds to the um
oh uh the caps of of uh uh microtubules
actually. And so it's binding a peptide
up there in science. There's a few
residues of the peptide that are binding
into this pocket. And in this case,
there's RNA and DNA. You say, well, you
train this on small molecules. Why is it
predicting
peptide and RNA and DNA binding sites?
And my my answer to that, you know, my
philosophical answer to that is that
AF2bind is using AF2 embeddings
and then it's training a logistic
regression model to predict small
molecule binding pockets in so far as
those embeddings themselves from AF2
um uh in so far as they describe
small molecule or RNA or DNA or other
polymer binding then AF2 two bind is
going to predict that they're just the
same input AF2 bind. They're just going
to predict that that's small molecule
binding character if you will. And so
and so what what's really I think
tanalyzing about AF2 bind is you a
medicinal chemist might tell you that
these are not druggable sites. They bind
to DNA, they bind to RNA, they bind to
and we can't get a small molecule in
there and a lot of them aren't. But AF2
bind doesn't predict every DNA binding
site. It doesn't predict every RNA
binding site. It just is predicting
these ones. And and in my view, it's
because they they probably have some
small molecule binding character that it
might motivate somebody who's doing drug
discovery to say, I'm going to try to
find a small molecule that inhibits this
site. Um, and so it it did actually, if
you if you think about that for protein
protein interactions, for protein
protein interactions, these are also
considered somewhat undruggable because
they're very shallow interfaces. How do
you fit a small molecule there? These
are again sites that P2 rank wouldn't
say are um our binding pockets. And um
but nevertheless, here's here's some uh
proteins that are involved in protein
protein interfaces. I'm not showing the
protein partner here. Um but AF2bind in
purple predicts binding pockets for
these proteins. And there are crystal
structures. This is just using AF2
predicted structure, but there are
crystal structures of these proteins
where small molecule inhibitors have
been found that do inhibit the protein
protein interaction. So it's it's
actually finding that these are small
molecule bindable
uh protein protein binding interfaces.
It doesn't. So I have check mark check
mark and X here. It didn't work for this
one. This is a very shallow. This is 2
and this is a very shallow site. Um
there are actually instant this is a
microar inhibitor but there are some
nanomolar inhibitors there too. So it so
it missed that one. Okay it's not a
perfect thing but it's not it's not
really trained to do this. So the fact
that it does pick up two out of these
three I think is pretty tanalyzing and
one of the reasons why AF2 bind might be
giving a little bit more information
than a classic binding site predictor
model. Um I'm not sure how I think I
might be going way over time but um I
have a few more slides that just show
you a couple of tanalyzing features of
of AF2 binding and and one one slide is
this that if you look at big
confirmational changes between proteins.
So a lot of some proteins actually
undergo really big confirmational
changes when they bind a link. Is that
really important? I get this question
before. Is that really important? Could
AF2 mind pick that up? Um and in in
these cases it does. So I'm showing
three examples of proteins that calm
modulin multiples binding protein deny
kynise that have big confirmational
changes when they bind a small molecule
and in both cases the open and the
closed case um AF2bine is predicting the
binding pocket. It doesn't work for
everything. I mean these are open
binding pockets in both cases basically.
Um but if you have I'm g skip this for
now. If you have a binding pocket and
Ben showed this in his talk that's
completely cryptic and collapsed where
there's no pocket um AF2 bind does pred
I mean there's actually another small
molecule binding site here for
betalacttomies and it does predict that
but it doesn't predict this cryptic
pocket here which does open up when
there's a structure in the PDB where a
small molecule binds in between these
two helyses and so it predicts it it
predicts that pocket when you give it
the open structure when you give it the
the ligan bound structure it predicts
the pocket But if you didn't know that,
it wouldn't it wouldn't have told you
that because this is collapsed. So it
doesn't work in every case when the
structures are changing very much. But
it does work in in many cases. And I got
we got this question before about
alossteric sites. So here's the data
about alossteric sites again not in the
bioarchchive paper but will be in the um
the accepted paper that's coming out
soon. Uh is is we took there's about uh
50 to 60 proteins that are labeled as
alossteric site binders.
alossteric site. The PDB is dominated by
ligans that bind into so-cal orthosteric
sites, functional sites that are are
conserved and and shared between
proteins um of similar nature and
alossteric sites might be less conserved
and and those might be ones that people
want to drug um but those are only 1% of
the PDB has examples of alossteric sites
and 1% of the AF2 bind training set as
well. a small training set still 1% had
had alsteric sites and the question was
could AF2 bind actually predict these
alossteric sites um even though it was
barely trained on any of them I mean it
wasn't trained on any of them in that
we're testing out here um but it only
saw like one or two during training and
um and so here you can see that it
actually it can do that which is pretty
cool um that that AF2ine can do this uh
and so here it's showing that there's
some sites that are recover covered
versus some that are missed. It covers
about twothirds of the alisteric sites.
It doesn't really depend on the RMSD
uh between the crystal structure of the
alossteric site and the alphafold 2
predicted structure that we ran AF2 bind
on. We didn't run it on the on the
answer. We ran it on an AF2 prediction
and we asked can it predict the
alossteric site. Here's an example of
one of these where it's nowic inhibitor
is bound. Um and this is the AF2
predicted structure. But um but AF2 bind
predicts the alossteric site very purple
here. And if you overlay the the
structure with the AF2 bound prediction
or the AF2 um prediction of the
structure, you can see that there's a
big difference in the loops here. Um and
and in the AF2 predicted structure, the
loop would actually olude the ligan
binding. It would clash with it, but yet
it still predicts the lian binding site
is there. So that's good. So something
that P2 rank wouldn't predict. So P2
rank missed this, right? Um so that's
really great. We've talked about this
last slide. How could this synergize
with experiments?
So if we looked at chemopomics data from
Ben Crev's group and we said, okay, Ben
Cat and others have um done these
experiments where they have coalent
probes that go in in cells. They
permeate cells and then they bind to
cyines. If they bind to a a binding
pocket nearby then they can coalently
attach to a cysteine. Then you pop the
cells proteilize them and do mass spec
to read out which peptides get lied and
which don't. And so there's a bunch of
binding sites a bunch of cyines as that
are annotated that have been
experimentally quote ligan by
chemopomics experiments. Um and the
question is so those are basically
annotations of where binding pockets
might be right and and they may not be
obvious from AF2 predicted structures or
in crystal structures and so but
nevertheless we used AF2 predicted
structures with AF2 bind to see how many
of these in this case 200 lianted cyines
across the human proteome how much of
those are predicted by AF2bine is there
a pocket within 10 anstroms of that
cysteine that's predicted by AF2ine and
it turns out that AF2bine can predict
maybe a two
maybe about a
you know two-fifths of of the of the
liganted sites and then P2 rank could
predict another two- fifths um and
there's some overlap between them but
combined between P2 rank and AF2 bind
you can predict about half of the
liganted sites the other half why didn't
we predict them you know why would we
miss those why did all the methods miss
the other half and it could be for a
variety of reasons either the the site
itself is very cryptic and it's not
present in the AF2 predicted structure
or the site site might be a composite
site that involves other biomolelecules
that are not um represented in the
single chain prediction of the
structure. And that's something you
could address experimentally, right? You
could address the experiments by
overexpressing the protein and trying to
do this again. Um and so we're very
interested in trying to combine these
kinds of data sets with uh with with
CVAD and others uh to to create new
labels for especially for the cryptic um
binding site prediction. create new
labels for this site is likely going to
open up. It is a intrinsic cryptic site
or this site is a composite site with
this protein. We have new labels for
binding sites using using these models.
So then so these are the next steps.
This is the last slide is um is that
yeah we want to synergize with
chemopomics data to train the next
generation of models where the cryptic
sites um we want to um work with people
like Hillary to use these predictions to
um better predict pathogenic uh mutants
in human proteins. And then of course
the obvious thing might be to retrain
AF2 bind for something like AF3 bind
where you can actually use instead of a
basis set of 20 amino acids you could
use a basis set of a whole diverse
um a group of small molecule fragments
that might um might represent uh
nonnatural chemistry that amino acids
don't don't have like fluor like h
hallogens and um and and other kinds of
functional groups. Um so thank the
people did the work again summary is
that pre-trained neural networks can
actually accurately identify um small
molecule binding sites and proteins. um
we have to be really careful about how
we train and and test our our neural
nets. Um there are there's a GitHub to
use um AF2bind. Um there is a uh
interactive database that we need to
check to make sure it's still active um
on the right here for all the human
proteium results. And all of those
results will be coming out in a you know
basically a big CSV file soon with the
published paper if you're interested in
the human proteome prediction. I mean,
this is some people in my group. Um, Jod
and Anna did the work. And, uh, also
want to thank Ben for doing the primer
earlier. Thanks,