for the kind introduction it's a
pleasure to be here today and to talk to
you about building an aviation system
that can connect the world while at the
same time hopefully doing so with near
zero environmental
impacts so as I address this question
I'm trying to do this in three questions
today I will start by actually trying to
give you a sense of where the impact of
Aviation on the atmosphere spe
specifically on climate and air
pollution is actually coming from giving
you a baseline understanding then we use
that Baseline understanding to actually
strategically think about what are the
key technologies that we need to
actually get to this near zero
goal then you have a set of Peace meal
Technologies so we will talk about how
can we bring these Technologies together
into an aviation system that can
actually work connect the world with
near zero environmental impacts
so I don't have lots of time let's jump
right into it and let's start with the
first question so where do the impacts
of Aviation on the environment actually
come from let's start with climate if
you talk about climate impacts of
Aviation you probably have heard a ton
of different metrics on how you can
measure the climate impact of Aviation
you've probably had CO2 and global
warming potential and all this kind of
stuff I will use a metric that is
actually environmental cost cost to the
society because of these climate impacts
of Aviation how does that work well you
look at a unit of fuel burnt so a ton of
fuel you track that to the emissions
that come out of the jet engine you
track that to everything that happens in
the atmosphere until you actually get
concentration of greenhouse gases you
track that to warming and you track that
to socioeconomic impacts like for
example changes to agricultural yields
or for example Environmental disas
disasters similar to the social cost of
carbon so let me show you how that
assessment actually looks like so if you
look at a ton of fuel you actually have
some emissions that actually are cooling
so that's why you start with a negative
cost but then if you look at the cooling
component you see it's basically driven
by two effects one it's driven by CO2
that's no surprise to anybody in the
room because that is driven by you know
the fossil fuel use meaning we take
carbon from the geosphere and from crude
oil refine it combust it release the CO2
into the atmosphere increase atmospheric
CO2 concentration which contributes to
warming you all know that however the
effect of Aviation doesn't stop here it
also includes contrails condensation
Trails the white line shaped ice clouds
that you sometimes see forming behind an
aircraft what this actually is is it is
an icecloud it forms when the conditions
are sufficiently cool cool sufficiently
humid so that water which is in the
exhaust of the exhaust stream of the
aircraft so that first condenses and
then freezes so that you get an ice
Cloud many situations if you look up
into a sky you see something like on
this picture this is actually what we
call a non-persistent contrail that only
lasts seconds to minutes we don't
actually worry about those guys what we
worry about are these condensation
trails that actually last for long
periods of times possibly staying linear
potentially becoming diffused and even
indistinguishable from natural cus
clouds it's these clouds that have been
shown to be warming on
average however we do need to note this
impact is still subject to substantial
uncertainty so this effect may be a
little smaller a little larger however
the consensus is there's still
warming so this is the climate part of
the equation what's often forgotten is
Aviation also has an air pollution
contribution
where does this come from well we have
aircraft emission aircraft emissions
directly or indirectly lead to the
formation of air pollutants specifically
ozone and fine particulate matter and
that has Health impacts and you see this
impact isn't small it's actually on the
same order of magnitude again as CO2 and
it's mostly driven by nox
emissions so overall this externality I
I promised you a dollar metric is about
$860 per ton of fuel burnt a ton of fuel
costs about $730 right now so we are
talking a number which is very similar
to the cost of fuel but just to give you
a sense how large this climate and air
pollution externality for Aviation
really
is now this chart also leads you
directly into our second question so
what are the key technologies that we
now need to solve the problem well three
things right we need to worry about the
CO2 I talked about it this this is
really the low carbon energy transition
for the aviation sector because we need
to get away from fossil fuel use the
second thing we need to worry about is
contrails we need to avoid them
otherwise we can't get to near zero and
we need to worry about nox emissions
from aircraft engines and we need to get
rid of that as well so what we need to
do is talk through these three areas and
see what technologies we have to solve
the problem so let's do it let's start
with the low carbon energy transition as
I mentioned before here we really need
to get away from this Paradigm of fossil
fuel use first step we can take is use
drop in fuels we call them sustainable
Aviation fuels fuels you can use in
existing aircraft that look chemically
very similar
to Fossil Jed a however now you may say
well if this is chemically very similar
then it's a hydrocarbon which means if
you combust it you will release C2 into
the atmosphere the trick here is it's a
typical biof field trick you actually
try to sequester that carbon from the
atmosphere first as you make for example
your biomass feed stock and then
re-release it so you get this perfect
carbon cycle so this is how you can get
to zero obviously now you can get
worried about the scalability of the
biosphere to really produce all this
feed stock so you may want to do the
same thing with direct air capture as a
technology combine that carbon with
hydrogen and make a fuel out of that
yeah you can do this as
well however the base problem is that
jet fuel is basically a longchain
hydrocarbon it's a lot of carbon atoms
in a row so making that is a very energy
intensive process so are we better off
using this energy directly and put that
on board the aircraft in a non-rop in
fuel for example hydrogen or maybe even
the electric aircraft well if we want to
do this this obviously becomes an
aircraft level challenge and we know
that the electric aircraft doesn't
really solve that easy easily we also
know none of this actually has direct
CO2 emissions but we need to consider
the emissions in the supply chain to see
how close to zero we really get but
that's true for South as well and this
will come back in a
moment so that's the CO2 question we
know how we can attack that although
lots of work still to do second thing
that we need to do is we need to avoid
contrasts so what are we doing about
contrs well here lots of things are
being discussed you can change engines
and fuels to solve the problem however
one thing that people are really excited
about is flight path deviations changing
your flight path why you know that from
your own field experiment you looked up
into the air and not every flight makes
a
contrail so why is that because the
contol only forms if it's sufficiently
cold and sufficiently humid that's not
always the case so why don't we fly
around regions where contrails would
form
well that sounds like a good and very
intuitive approach and you can do that
horizontally you can fly around it but
the point is that these contal forming
regions are very flat they're very thin
a little pancake shaped so you can just
dive underneath or climb above them to
avoid the problem usually just a few
thousand feet now this is obviously
subject to a fuel burn trade-off because
you're not flying your optimal flight
anymore however the literature clearly
says that this fuel this benefit is very
small and likely outweighed by far by
the control
benefit now you might say why don't we
do this this sounds like a very cool
thing right so easy to do you have a
flight he has a cut through a flight
path Red Line you see it flies through a
contra forming region you take the green
line fly around it problem solved sounds
like something we could do today right
well not so fast because if you want to
be successful about this you have to be
right about two things
one actually have to be sure that the
flight would actually form a contrail if
you didn't reroute
it so that's Point number one which is
actually hard point number two that's
actually hard is you need to reroute the
flight into a region where it won't form
a contrail you need to know that as well
and you want to be as close to the to
your original flight path to minimize
your fuel band penalty it turns out this
is a really tough data Challenge and
we're doing a lot of research on this to
really figure out how we can dependably
do
this so lots of work still to be done
last problem aircraft nox
reductions this is something that we
rethought a little bit where we looked
at what can you actually what actually
do other sectors do to solve this
problem so look at Road Transportation
look at Power Generation in both cases
the way they solve the problem
is emissions control devices we don't do
that in aviation why not because
historically we couldn't because the
mass flow from a gastr is just too high
to put it through a catalytic converter
but with smaller gas turbines that we're
getting smaller course we start to be
able to do this but then still you don't
want to put a long bulky emissions
control device under the wing way too
much drag so how would you do this well
you would put the gas turbine in the
fuselage of the aircraft put the
emissions control behind it and have the
gas turbine actually produce power and
then use electric motors under the wing
to actually drive the aircraft turns out
if you do this furn penalty less than 1%
nox reduction about
95% so off the shelf you you may be able
to do this now we have three peace meal
Technologies can we put it together in a
coherent system in a system that has low
carbon energy that has our nox reduction
technology and that has control
avoidance well if you want to do this
you have to redesign your aircraft
around hydrogen around post combustion
emissions control and we can do this and
we did it for a 220 seat aircraft so
roughly like your Boeing
73710 or like your Airbus a321 3,000
nautical mile range we found a solution
big question is is this solution worth
it for
society so for that I'm going to go full
circle I'm going to go back to the very
beginning and you've basically seen this
chart it shows you the environmental
impacts of a conventional aircraft
climate and air quality this time not
per unit fuel bur but scaled to the
network that we're modeling
here and we put on top the fuel cost the
private cost of operating the system you
could also add other Airline operating
costs but we assume they don't really
change so we didn't add them here now
the big question is does this overall
environment societal cost of operating
the system go down if I go to our zero
impact aircraft here's the one that's
driven by sustainable aviation fuel you
see it does go down why because we get
the environmental cost to near zero fuel
is not entirely zero you have to do a
little bit of carbon removal but then
the fuel is much more expensive Factor
2.3 that's what we have here it's a very
expensive saf but it's worth it you do
get an overall cost reduction now the
question is is hydrogen better did the
same thing we modeled the hydrogen
aircraft you see it basic basically is
can do the same thing the cost reduction
is a little higher is because the energy
is a little cheaper which actually is a
trade-off because the aircraft needs a
little more energy but the fuel is more
expensive but still it's a little better
I wouldn't say this is conclusive at
this
point so what does this all lead to and
we imagine a zero impact air
transportation sector yeah I think this
is possible these were the three key
technologies that we just talked about
you didn't hear me talk about technical
efficiency your operational efficiency
why because it's not at the core of the
problem but it's very important you saw
the energy cost increase we need to be
as efficient as we can possibly be to
make this
work from here there's a lot left to do
that we're doing improving our
understanding of impacts and
Technologies that's what we do in the
lab for Aviation and the environment
here at MIT and we need to work with
Partners in the value chain to really
figure out how we can overcome the
hurdles to really get to the goal we're
working on that on the Zero impact
Aviation lines with that I'll leave it
there and um do I still have a time for
a question or
two okay we can take the first one do
contrast reflect any sunlight like was
recently recovered absolutely so the
point about contrails is not every
contrail is warming a contrail is like a
normal Cloud what it does is every
Contra does two things reflects incoming
sunlight which is a cooling impact and
it traps out going heat and for every
contrail whether it's warming or cooling
it's a balance of those two effects so
there are contrails that absolutely are
cooling there are also cont controls
that absolutely are warming every
nighttime contol is warming because it
doesn't have the reflection component so
what I told you is the average contrail
is warming however that can be cooling
contrails so that's very important to to
know okay perfect thank you very
much thank you leing fascinating thank
you so
much all right our next talk on the
carbonizing the industry I invite
Professor Jam tasan to speak about
sustainable steel Professor tasan is a
professor of Metallurgy in the
department Material Science and
Engineering at MIT professor
[Applause]
all right can everybody hear
me hi everybody um I'm my name is Jam
Tashan thank you for the invitation I'm
an associate professor in the department
of Material Science and Engineering here
at MIT and the work that I'm going to
talk about today is about steel making
and it's carried out mostly by postto in
my group who's also here with me Dr
honor Guan and other co-workers in our
group so the question on a Tuesday
afternoon at 4:30 might be do we really
need to talk about steel um and the
answer is yes uh so if you look at the
steel production uh in the short term um
you see a clear increase if you look at
projections uh about steel manufacturing
you also you know if you look at
projections going forward decades you
see an increase in steel uh steel
production that is projected now this is
for a reason we need steel and we will
keep on needing steel I don't know how
many talks you hear from MIT that talks
about new materials graphine and you
know spider silk and so forth we will
still need steel to do things now if you
look at the applications for which we
need steel some of these are very
demanding applications right so there's
a reason why we call this guy the Man of
Steel when you think about steel you
think about these demanding applications
right so so automotive industry you
think about bridges you know suspension
bridges and those cables that carry
those bridges and you nowadays you even
think about you know
spacecraft but also when we talk about
steel there are all those less demanding
applications any more or less any
restaurant that you would walk in in
Cambridge or in Boston if you could find
your way to the kitchen and take a look
at the um tabl Toops there you would see
that it's often stainless steel and
garbage cans and containers and all kind
of other things and this is not just a
standing Trend if you look at the
numbers again for instance the new
constructions over the over the years
looking at projections of new
constructions household appliances uh
you know air conditionings worldwide Etc
it's all increasing we will we use steel
and we will need steel so what's the
problem the problem is steel making is
demanding of course you hear about this
very very often but looking at numbers
is kind of shocking often so if you take
Hut roll steel for instance and if you
look at primary steel making so blast
furnaces and just take a look at these
numbers here this is really gigantic
both from an energy consumption
perspective and also from CO2 emissions
perspective now we often talk about
electric Arc furnaces and how it's much
better but because the numbers are so
large while it's much better in terms of
the energy penalty and in terms of CO2
emissions it's still gigantic now this
is sort of things that you often talk
about or or read about but there's also
additional challenges for instance
related with water consumption related
with steel uh processing so this is a
very demanding industry it's one of the
most demanding industries that we have
as humankind now if you want to think
about the solution for this we need to
look at the current processing
Technologies as most of you would know
we produce Steel in two different ways
you can start from an iron ore put it in
a blast furnace and go then through a
basic oxygen furnace continuous casting
rolling in some finishing treatments and
then you get this coil you make a car
out of it or you can start from a steel
scrap use an electric Arc furnace melt
it cast it and and similar steps now the
problem here from the pers from our
perspective is related with this initial
initial part now what you would notice
there is that we are dealing with liquid
metal and when we deal with liquid metal
then we need to increase the
temperatures we need very complicated
equipment we need very demanding
processes and that's the core reason why
this is so energy intensive and it's so
uh CO2 emitting now if there would be a
way to deal with steel in a solid state
life would be easier but it's of course
not so easy now this is what honor and I
have been working on for a while now for
it's been three four years where we are
trying to transform steel scrap to sheet
metal without melting it now you start
from a steel scrap you put it in an
envelope you know imagine pieces of
scrap you put it in an envelope and then
you roll it so that you can diffuse
bonded into a sheet and then you coil it
so that now now you have a coiled
steel now it looks very nice on a
PowerPoint uh you know schematic here
but obviously many of you would look at
this and already start thinking that it
may not be possible so easily for all
those kind of different
challenges and but if it were possible
just imagine the level of Energy savings
and CO2 emissions and you know capex
savings and so forth it it would be
pretty great now what owner has been
doing over the last few years is
literally trying tens of samples of
Steel sheet metal scrap industrial metal
scrap even corroded metal scrap using it
in our technology to make them into
coils and then to make them into sheets
rather and then mechanically test them
to demonstrate that this is actually
possible so this is actually possible we
can do it in our lab right now now when
you hear this kind of Technology there
are many reasons to be skeptical believe
believe me I I've been very skeptical
about this myself and I'm going to go
now one by one over each of these
concerns and hopefully show you that
there there's actually not so much of a
reason to be skeptical so let's start
with the first one now you think about
scrap and you think about bonding them
into a sheet that sounds like a terrible
idea because when you think about scrap
you think about the junkyard and all
these corroded irregularly shaped
components how are we even make them
into a into a sheet like you can't
really roll Bond these things and there
would be rust layers right oxide layers
well first of all keep in mind here what
we are talking about is high quality
manufacturing scrap so we are not
talking about junkyard scrap we are
talking about manufacturing scrap here
so form and damage factor is on our side
so what does that mean if you make a
simple plot here so in the y- AIS I have
shape change um and in the x-axis I have
the amount of damage or the locality of
damage so if you are thinking about an
end of life steel product ideally for
reuse or reapplication the opportunities
in this lower um left
quadrant if we have small amount of shap
change at the end of life and if we have
localized damage it's much more easy to
reuse it and Manufacturing scrap
actually falls into into this category
so there's an opportunity here now the
second point is that we've actually been
doing all these tests so we've been
doing test after test and what we see is
that you need to develop the right
processing regimes to be able to achieve
bonding so here for instance in the
xaxis you see processing temperature so
this is a hot rolling process in the y-
axis you see amount of reduction so how
much you reduce the thickness as you
roll versus how hot it is and basically
for all kind of different materials you
can see stainless steel mild Steel in in
that batch in those curves you get a
proc you get a line that determines the
regime of um bondability so basically as
you go from uh to the other side of the
red curve on stainless steel you would
always get bonding and for mild steel
basically more or less all you need to
do is go above 800° then you would
always get bonding based on our
experiments so there's really no reason
to be skeptical about not having bonding
so then you might say well I might Bond
these things but will they be usable
will you be able to do something with it
will it be formable so that I can make
something else from it uh you can
imagine for instance that there could be
gaps well basically what we've done is
all kind of mechanical testing uh that
shows that the formability of these
scrap bonded sheets are similar to
monolithic sheets of the same grade of
Steel so you can you can have the same
forming Behavior here here in fact I I
really like this image this is from one
of our graduate students who carried out
this measurement forming experiment the
sample is basically as the size of my
hand here palm of my hand and it shows
how formable these Steels can be you can
really deep draw these guys and the
reason for this is that the bonds that
we generate are pretty strong so now now
it's real science you are looking at
this is an insm experiment we actually
put a mechanical deformation device in a
scanning electron microscope so that we
can see these bonds here so now I so so
that you can easily see the bones I put
these lines over there so now we are
going to pull this in the horizontal
direction and you would expect that I
have this maybe imperfect Bond there so
it's going to collapse from that Bond
and fracture and what you actually see
as you pull this is that it seems like
it's going to indeed develop over that
Bond but afterwards it actually turns
right so the bond stays intact and the
crack appear somewhere else so by
bonding actually you can create um a
material response that's stronger than
the bulk response um of the
material now there are other examples of
this so this is for instance looking at
another cavity again in an electron
microscope we are Banning this to see if
this cavity will grow or rather if this
cavity will lead to cracking incidents
and it doesn't you see some growth but
you start from a five Micron crack and
now it becomes six microns it's nothing
basically from a stress
perspective all right so the next
question might be well you you might say
well you might be making the these uh
you know roll bonded sheets of scrap but
it might it still might not be feasible
there might be no real business case for
this well then you might the the very
here might be related with scrap
availability or scaling of the process
that I'm mentioning after all we are in
a lab here at the moment in terms of SC
scrap uh scrap availability basically
there is no concern I provide you some
data here and there is much many other
data available in the literature that
there is enough there's going to be
enough scrap and also there's going to
be enough manufacturing scrap to be able
to realize a technology of this sort and
in terms of uh whether this process can
be scaled up this is a recent patent
from owners work that shows that
basically you can do what we do in the
lab in a manual way in a in a scaled
continuous process a process that
essentially combines in our minds at
least it combines pipe M pipe making and
and rolling so this is what's going to
be happening next in our in our activity
now another reason to be skeptical might
be you know having a business case I
mean Metallurgy is a relatively old
field and there's a lot of inertia for
Change and even the typical example I
give is that even if I invent the next
best automotive steel and I go to
automotive industry and say this now I
have a new steel for you that's 50%
better than your current steel they say
it's great and then it takes 20 years
for them to use them in their cars
typically so it's a it's a slow industry
how do we deal with it well it turns out
that there's a very actually nice uh U
business model for this now the steel
industry normally works in a way where
you produce steel steel manufacturer
produce steel sends it to a fabricator
the fabricator makes a car a pipeline
whatever then gets some scrap sells it
to a scrap Trader scrap Trader sells it
to a steel maker now our technology is
so uh easy to miniaturize actually that
you can actually work only with the
fabricator so you can go to the
fabricator and say hey here's a
technology rolling technology that can
fit in a container if you want and
you'll get your own scrap and then
process it within your facility to give
back to you to to do the things that to
produce the things that you keep on
producing all the way so I'm not coming
to you to say I have a new material
that's going to be amazing I'm going to
give you your material back and you can
easily test it to see how how good it is
and remember here we are not talking
about airplane engines steel is
beautiful in that sense there are all
these less demanding applications that I
said that I mentioned at the
beginning and finally you might argue
that this kind of approach might not be
impactful um remember we start with some
you know sustainabil this is
sustainability conference after all so
when we put the numbers here so now I'm
showing the same graph i' same plot I've
shown at the beginning I've shown for
hot rolling but now you see it for Cold
Rolling for primary steel making and
secondary steel making and now I show
you the corresponding numbers if you use
solid state process in this scrap metal
consolidation process so you get a
tremendous benefit all in on all these
accounts energy um CO2 emissions water
use and and so forth so these were the
reasons to be skeptical at first I hope
I could convince you that um there are
really not many reasons to be skeptical
I mean if I put my scientist haton I can
still find many reasons to be skeptical
but you know we've been in a much better
place than we thought we would be at
this point so with that I would like to
conclude my talk and thank you very much
for your attention um and thanks also
for the researchers who contributed to
this work thank you
[Applause]
and happy to answer questions of
course um so should I be reading this um
what percentage of Steel now is used for
high strength applications or versus low
strength applications such as kitchen
equipment so there are many numbers that
can be thrown here uh but the one number
I remember in this context is that many
of the appliances cover if I'm not
mistaken around 10%
so use of Appliance Steels use for
appliances like dishwashers and
things and then of course um high
strength uh applications fall into many
different categories right so um whether
it's construction or Aerospace or others
um they cover different
percentages are there not many kinds of
Steel with various composition of other
elements is this a logistical challenge
very good question so the question is if
I have different compositions and if I'm
sort of combining things together is
this not a problem well remember the
business model there we are working with
one fabricator right the fabricator is
using their own steel the same type of
Steel for the application so for that
case the answer is no there's not going
to be big variation well there's going
to be variation within the scatter that
the steel provider originally provides
now what we see independent from that is
that even when there is variation even
when we intentionally create some
compositional variation many of the
formability elements uh formability
behavior is still is still okay unless
you go out of your way to you know add
really problematic elements like
copper thank you very
much Professor tson thank you so very
much and let's uh make a
Ste thank
you all right and uh
next talk design and computational
strategies for reusable building
components I invite Professor Caitlyn
Miller she's an assistant professor in
the Department of Civil and
environmental engineering building
Technology Program where she leads the
digital structured research group and
co-directs the structural Design Lab
Caitlin great thanks so much for having
me I'm wonderful to be with you at the
end of the day today I'm going to
continue the conversation on circularity
and materials um but focus on a
different application in a different
material stream um I want to start by
acknowledging the team that worked on
this project so um this is a project
that I'll present called pixel frame um
completed by an interdisciplinary team
at MIT between architecture Structural
Engineering mechanical design and
computation and it was a project um
funded through the MIT climate and
sustainability Consortium um together
with
wholesome um I'll start by talking about
the built environment which all of you
know well because we all occupy it every
day um buildings and infrastructure
together account for 42% of total
greenhouse gas emissions which is a
staggering number considering how
relatively little attention it often has
in sustainability conversations in
particular within this we often divide
between operational and embodied carbon
emissions and today I'm going to focus
on embodied the the carbon emissions
associated with extracting producing
transporting and assembling materials
into roads Bridges and buildings that
that occupy the entire world what's
really interesting about this within the
embodied emissions which is about 15% of
total greenhouse gas emissions about 8%
are from concrete and cement and another
7% are from steel um today in particular
I'm going to talk about cement and
concrete which is again um one of the
most ubiquitous materials on Earth and
only projected to grow as we saw from
steel similarly because of um rapid
urbanization and um the need for housing
around the world um in fact in in a few
years we're projected that um the amount
of concrete on Earth will surpass all of
the biomass on the planet um and what's
interesting about concrete is it's often
used in relatively short life cycles um
typical buildings only lasts for 20 30
years maximum up to 50 years maybe um
and the the end of life streams for them
are not very um there there aren't a lot
of good end of life life uses for them
they're typically either used either go
to landfill or they're used for back
there's a very tiny amount currently of
post um demolition concrete that is
recycled as aggregate but that's
considered down cycling because it's a
substantial degradation of the strength
in the original material in fact about
half of all of the concrete that we have
demand for globally on an annual basis
um by mass is demolished every year um
and often times the demolished concrete
um is functionally um still viable so
we're demolishing concrete not because
it's lost strength or it's no longer are
safe but because our demand for
buildings and infrastructure changes
over time in fact we anticipate that the
built environment will need to adapt and
change much more frequently in the
coming years um all this leads to a lot
of different possible solutions for
decarbonizing the Concrete Construction
sector we hear a lot about um so-called
production side um reduction strategies
so things like um changing the fuel
source to make cement using alternative
materials instead of cement um embedding
carbon or other materials that capture
car CO2 directly into concrete um and
these are all really exciting but a lot
of them are far away from large scale
application and require quite a lot of
investment and um large scale technology
changes to be deployed um I'm going to
instead Focus today on two um
alternative Pathways that are more on
the downstream demand side one is
efficiency based and the other is
looking at circularity through um
component
reuse efficiency has been along for a
around for a very long time um in most
Concrete Construction today we use far
more material than is structurally
mechanically necessary because um our
standards have evolved to prioritize
Simplicity in construction and a lot of
this is around sort of 20th Century
Technologies about what is easy to build
um if instead we look to how we could
remove material that is structurally
unnecessary we see substantial
reductions this is some from some of my
previous research showing that 50 60 70%
of the embodied carbon in Concrete
Construction in ubiquitous systems like
beams and slabs and Frames can be
removed just by removing unnecessary
structural
material we also have the potential to
reuse um structural material at various
scales all the way on the right we have
adaptive reuse that's the idea that a
whole building should be reused um for a
new purpose um and that's ideally the
most impactful but also the hardest to
implement at scale because many
buildings functionally need to change
over time all the way on um the left we
have down cycling so taking concrete
crushing it up and using it as aggregate
as I said that's a severe loss of value
and the value chain so while it's easy
to do it doesn't make a lot of sense
either from an economic or environmental
perspective I'm going to focus on in the
middle on on modular reuse and whole
element reuse and in particular I'm
going to tell you about a system that
we've developed that is a new pre-cast
concrete system made out of flexible
modules that can be taken apart and
reassembled into many um a wide variety
of um building structural systems um so
this is a system made out of individual
pre-cast concrete Parts called pixels
they're um they're geometrically
identical but have varying strengths
they are dry jointed and post tension
together with a recyclable steel system
that allows them to um create many
different spans with many different
capacities in many different
configurations um and are able to be
taken apart and reassembled many times
without
damage um this system is mostly a
functional system but as we've developed
it we've also thought about this as a
sort of Aesthetics and sort of marketing
exercise so part of this is about
changing the dynamic culturally about
how we see reuse in society so that
things that are treated as garbage like
concrete which is sent to the landfill
typically could instead really become a
valued asset that makes sense to take
care of keep track of and use and reuse
many
times the system is meant to balance
efficiency UPF front so it uses a very
smart cross-section that uses way less
concrete than a typical rectangular beam
and a post tensioning system that
allocates tension and compression in an
optimal configuration with modularity so
a typical shape optimized beam would be
really customized for every application
here we want to develop something that's
modular that can be used in many cases
and we wanted to develop a system that
had a lot of adaptability so there's a
small component size unlike a lot of
kind of kits of parts for buildings with
whole beams and columns here the small
unit size allows for many different
geometric configurations so you could
create houses schools commercial
buildings hospitals all with the same
kit of parts
um a lot of the Ingenuity of this comes
from the variation of strengths that we
allocate to different pixels so those of
you who are new to concrete and cement
the amount of cement in the concrete
determines both its carbon content and
its strength so higher strength concrete
is great because it allows you to use
less material but it also has a much
higher carbon intensity per unit um per
unit Mass so here we're creating this
pallet of pixel strength so that we only
use high carbon high strength elements
where they're structurally necessary but
they also fit together geometrically
because they have the same overall shape
and then they're all dry jointed
together into this um steel post tension
system um all the P pieces connect
together um with this non-structural
core that allows them to slide together
um and allows them to achieve many
different capacities this was a really
challenging problem to design this
system because most engineers and
Architects are designing oneoff products
over and over and over again each
building is different every structure
has different requirements here we
developed an ALG mic process to um
anticipate thousands and millions of
buildings in the future all of the
possible scenarios and loadings and uh
structural challenges they might undergo
and we designed our system in a data
Centric way to respond to that cluster
of possible buildings rather than a
single um instance um we nevertheless
also designed it to meet building code
today so we're making use of
Technologies and knowledge that is
already well established in the building
sector um this is a life cycle
assessment showing the pixel frame
system compared to um traditional
reinforced concrete so as you can see RC
stands for reinforced concrete the the
pixel frame system UPF front so this is
not considering circularity just A1
through A3 Cradle to gate emissions is
um dramatically reduced compared to
concrete the reinforced concrete and
that's because of the more intelligent
cross-section so just by having a
smarter shape and a better allocation of
strength where we're only using high
strength where it's necessary we can
achieve a lot up front and that not only
Compares well to concrete it compares
well to all other structural systems
that are on the market today so even
things like Mass Timber which g a lot of
attention for being very low carbon but
come at a cost premium the pixel frame
system is competitive in terms of carbon
with that um when we consider reuse or
second life um the savings are are more
significant so we can reduce the savings
by another 50% by reusing the pixel
elements all of the concrete parts are
designed to be reused many times and the
metal parts are designed to be recycled
we've also developed an algorithmic
process for designing buildings with the
pixel frame system so normally design is
a fairly um traditional process an
architect and engineer draws a design
does the calculations figures out what
material is needed and asks the
contractor to build it here we have an
inventory Centric um process in which we
have a set of material and we need to
figure out how we can use that to make
any kind of building we want to solve
that problem we've um leveraged an
algorithmic um assignment workflow that
has a digital twin of our inventory and
a and a design that the building owner
or architect is is interested in and
automatically figures out which pixels
in the inventory should go where um in
the design and here you see we're also
saying sometimes we might need to add a
new pixel to this design so those are
colored
pink um we're also thinking quite a lot
about how to manage this inventory this
is again very different from traditional
construction suddenly we need to keep
track of all of these assets in a
building there's a lot of thinking about
this in the circularity world um the
idea of material passports um promotes
creating a digital inventory or a
digital twin of all your pieces that are
linked physically to objects through
some kind of um RFID or other kind of
code this is just a quick example of a
material passport that we created for
the pixel frame system where one pixel
was cast about two years ago it then got
assembled into a large- scale beam that
was structurally tested for our research
it was then disassembled um so that we
could use it for something else that
same pixel became part of a new
demonstrator structure for an exhibition
where it was packaged and transported um
from MIT to Washington DC to be part of
an exhibit we kept track of that same
pixel on its way back where it was used
again for another structural test here
testing the sheer capacity of the system
where we finally um tested it on purpose
to failure and we retired the system
from the inventory we can repeat this
process at scale um here's a digital
representation of a larger inventory
that we've simulated where the same
pixels could for example become part of
a warehouse structure that has perhaps a
shorter life cycle
the same Parts could be taken apart and
reassembled into a cultural space like a
museum exhibition or Pavilion and then
again used even in an Adaptive reuse
setting here we imagined a large um
existing structural core where we've
designed an office frame around it to
make use of some existing
resources um with that I'll I'll end I
want to thank again the team and say
that the pixel frame system um started
as a research project but is now um um
in the fledgling stages of
commercialization so so these two former
students are co- founders of the pixel
frame company um which was recently
funded by the Massachusetts clean energy
center and they'd be very happy to talk
to you more if you're interested in
testing the system thank
[Applause]
you yep um is steel corrosion a risk due
to the joints do the joints need to be
sealed I mean we're we're imagining this
in indoor applications where steel is is
widely used already so we're not
proposing um a change to Steel we if
necessary we could either we could use
various um corrosion or fire protection
systems for the steel like intumescent
pain or other protect protective um uh
finishes but we're we're imagining using
steel as it already is very widely used
in post engined
applications yeah um this solution
definitely is a change to status quo
labor um our partners at holom are
actually really excited about the fact
that this is a much faster assembly
sequence so these individual Parts could
be assembled into beams and columns
offsite in a in a factory transported to
site and then assembled much much more
quickly than traditional reinforced
concrete ready mix construction cast in
place where um the setup time of the
concrete is a big um is a big sort of
pressure point in construction
sequencing here um these parts could be
because they're pre-cast and they're
already at full strength all the parts
could be assembled um much more quickly
with a lighter crew similar to how steel
and mass Timber is assembled today
thank
[Applause]
you all right and the last uh talk of
the day the last lightening
talk uh I invite uh San deep biswas a
young researcher to talk about
sustainable Transportation low carbon
Trucking s d perceived his Masters in
chemical engineering from MIT last year
he's currently a PhD candidate under the
supervision professor professor William
Grim
[Applause]
DP thank you so much for the invite and
the uh intro there so yeah I'm shy deep
I'm a graduate student uh working with
Professor William green and today I'll
be sharing a little bit about uh the
onboard dehydrogen ation based loc power
train that we are developing for
decarbonizing long hold Trucking the the
title can be a mouthful but I'll try to
sort of break it up into uh more
digestible pieces so the way of sort of
structured the talk is that we'll we'll
sort of start with why is Trucking sort
of a problem and what's the motivation
for this uh for this re research in the
first place I'll talk a little bit about
what the existing uh Solutions are and
why they don't really fit the tring
space we'll talk about potentially uh
promising fuel options for the trucking
space but then again sort of discuss
where this technological uh barrier is
that we're trying to solve I'll also be
talking a little bit about the
technoeconomic assessments and and what
sort of um you know like what what is
sort of the cost penalty for some of
these decarbonizing efforts and also
share with you guys uh what sort of
technical progress we have made and
where we are on that technology
Readiness scale uh kind of thinking
forward into commercializing this
technology as well so with that uh let's
kind of just look at the some of the U
numbers that that you know describe
Trucking today it's 7.1% of the annual
emissions so that's that's a pretty non-
negligible amount and I think something
that's more concerning is that when you
look at the look at the projected
Freight emissions It's actually an
upward Trend uh even by 2030 so instead
of going downstairs we're going to kind
of just keep we keep going up uh So
within the group we have kind of looked
very holistically at this problem so we
have kind of done technoeconomic studies
that look at um you know biofuels that
look at um battery electric options and
obviously conventional hydrogen options
that sort of include compressed and
liquified hydrogen I think one thing
that sort of keeps coming back is that
you you sort of see that there's this
massive cost penalty uh where it's like
more than two times uh expensive and
then even when you go all the way up to
2050 some of these options seem seem
quite pricey and trucking is sort of a
low margin business so you really do not
have that much um of a you know that of
that comfort that you can just um
increase the prices and everybody sort
of feels the the from the increase of
you know Trucking prices um so what we
sort of found from these technoeconomic
analyses was that hydrogen was a
promising option uh but what really
kills it is the fact that delivery of
hydrogen is super expensive so this is
where you can sort of look at different
options such as loc's that are liquid
organic hydrogen carriers so very
quickly to describe them they're these
organic molecules that can be reversibly
hydrogenated and dehydrogenated so you
can sort of um imagine that wherever
you're making hydrogen you perform the
hydrogenation Reaction store it in the
molecule now it's a room temperature
liquid which is easy to transport and
then as in when you use it you sort of
release it uh by heating it up in that
endo endothermic dehydrogenation process
uh the big big advantages of of loc's is
the fact that you know they're room
temperature liquid fuel so they
integrate well with our existing fuel
distribution infrastructure uh there's
very little additional safety concerns
very similar physiochemical properties
to existing liquid Fields like diesel uh
this is particularly important you know
considering these compared to like
ammonia for example which has the
toxicity issue the other thing is also
like it's commercially produced so when
you're kind of looking at applications
such as fuels uh you really kind of have
to think about can you get these
molecules at the scale that you need so
for Locs that's a yes um but if you look
at what existing Loc distrib ution
supply chain looks like and how people
imagine powering trucks with it you kind
of end up with this situation where you
have the dehydrogenation happening at
the gas station uh and then you take the
hydrogen that comes off of your off of
your um sort of hydrogen release unit
you compress it again to 700 bars put it
on trucks that have to like travel like
600 miles a day that's kind of Long Haul
Trucking and the issue is the
dehydrogenation requires you to burn
sort of 30% of the hydrogen that you
release just to keep it going it Al the
compression is super energy intensive
that's another 20 30% of the of the uh
you know energy intensity and then also
the fact that there is um there is sort
of this capital investment to convert
every existing gas station to be able to
deliver hydrogen that becomes more than
a million dollar investment and a pretty
difficult proposition in that regard so
effectively yeah from the OPC side the
supply chain is quite inefficient where
roughly 60% of the hydrogen is lost
before it actually makes it to the
engine or the fuel cell on the truck and
there is the capex limitation as well
also if you kind of look at it from the
emissions perspective given the fact
that we are so inefficient with the
hydrogen Supply if you're looking at
sort of the emissions of blue hydrogen
and the fact that you know when you're
running this compressor at a gas station
you're probably connected to the grid
which is also not clean you you realize
that this whole supply chain would have
minimal emission savings when you
compare it to diesel so how do we sort
of come in and fix this from a technical
perspective and for for us the idea is
to do this onboard dehydrogenation
scheme where the idea is now you load
your truck with this liquid instead of
like hydrogen gas so loading it with
liquid immediately takes carees of the
fact that the refueling station no
longer has to change how it currently
conducts business uh the other thing is
the Lo's do have sufficient volumetric
energy density so there's no range
anxiety or issues you can kind of have
the same as what diesel has uh the other
benefit we sort of get is the exhaust
heat now that comes from your internal
combustion engine or fuel cell you can
sort of think of using that to power
some of the dehydrogenation so you have
heat integration in that situation and
finally hydrogen can be generated at
sort of the necessary pressures for the
applications in ic engines or or fuel
cells so the compression cost has
completely been eliminated so all of
this together kind of really hits the
pain points of compression and and the
heat that needs to be provided this is
kind of a quick schematic of what we
envision the powertrain to be obviously
there's a lot more complexity
going on but the main idea sort of being
is you have your loc tank you heat it up
you send it to the reactor where the
dehydrogenation happens then you have
the separation train where you separate
out the hydrogen and the loc the the
lean loc goes back sort of to another
storage tank and your hydrogen sort of
keeps moving forward goes through your
engine and then you have sort of the
secondary burner which is sort of
important because 100% integration is
not possible you still need to burn a
little bit of hydrogen I'll talk to a
little bit about what what percentage of
that that we burn and what efficiencies
we're getting but effectively the idea
is by doing this on the truck you're
getting sort of the um savings from from
the heat integration and elimination of
compression also just to point out you
know for a schematic this is this has
been enlarge but in a real truck this is
really just 20 fet cubed worth of space
so you're really not taking out a lot of
payload or or or actually not really
affecting payload at all in in this in
this
situation um let's kind of quickly look
at the technoeconomic results that sort
of Feed in from the technical efficacy
as well so with the new proposed power
train what we sort of see is the the
Opex that uh that we sort of get from
Fuel and efficiencies the 40% delivery
efficiency can go all the way up to 80
87% so that's a that's a big massive
saving there uh additionally given that
loc's offer one to1 replacement to
diesel trucks this kind of comes from
like you're not really adding a lot of
weight with the L the main weight is the
fact that the fuel is not as
gravimetrically energy dense as diesel
so you put more fuel fuel on board you
kind of have to look at this hybrid
system so you have some batteries and
the reactor system but effectively all
of that barely adds any additional
weight it's about like 3,000 to 4,000 lb
for a truck that can weigh up to 80,000
other analysis shows that uh it's a
pretty minimal increase so when you kind
of put all of these numbers in the main
uh output is like when you're when
you're looking at you know a hydrogen
price of $2 a kilogram which is
something that is reasonable for blue
hydrogen today you sort of see that
you're getting sort of in that 18% more
expensive than the 2019 diesel Baseline
but given the sort of the volatility of
diesel prices that we have seen it's
very much within that range where you
can say it's compartible and you're also
getting sort of a 71% reduction in in
emissions so pretty big emission
reduction for what is a pretty minor or
almost no um cost penalty in that in
that regard and you know the other thing
is uh the prices of hydrogen are only
prod directed to sort of go down so if
this technology were to uh exist in a
commercial scale you can sort of think
that Trucking could be uh decarbonized
in a very competitive fashion the other
big thing to point out is the additional
Capital cost on a truck especially when
we running with hydrogen combustion
engine is only 30 to 40,000 extra and
this is quite important because you know
if you're looking at some of the battery
electric or the fuel cell based option
that people are looking at uh those
trucks are immensely expensive and that
cap capital really really uh messes up
the economics as well uh one thing to
definitely point out is we use a
platinum Catalyst for this reaction
which is kind of the primary reason for
that extra capex which is $10,000 um for
every truck but the big thing is there
are there's a lot of research going on
to sort of replace that with Earth
abundant metals and further bring that
price down uh so even sort of with the
with the economics sort of what we see
here one of the big things with um with
sort of the you know the system is like
the fuel delivery is still 30% that's
because you're still moving a lot of uh
loc it's like almost five times as much
um compared to the diesel and that
accounts for 30% of the cost but there
are different ways in which we are
looking at potentially reducing that
factor as well so this is all fun and
great but you know like where are we
with the with the system yeah um so I
I'll probably skip this a little bit
because of the time but I'll quickly
present sort of like the main um thing
as well here so where we are currently
sitting is we have a 10 kilowatt reactor
that we have already built uh for this
system in in the lab and we are
currently testing sort of this pilot
scale system which is about on10th the
size of the entire truck and currently
we are working to purchase modify and
engine uh to run it on with with
hydrogen that we will um sort of that we
will sort of integrate with the rest of
the system kind of looking at um you
know that's something that we're
expecting to demonstrate by May 2025 and
that would be the first time that a you
know like a fully integrated system has
been demonstrated and we really hoping
that that would be sufficient um you
know like technology demonstration for
oems to sort of also collaborate and
really really pick up the technology so
with that I'll just uh like to thank
everybody for being here and happy to
happy to take questions so I do see some
of those so I can maybe start with one
of the first ones rehydrogenation either
in the vehicle or the station without
needing yeah so this is something so the
same Catalyst can be used for for the
hydrogenation as well it just so happens
that you know if you are transporting it
as the loc you really do not want to
remove the hydrogen and and sort of put
it back so you want to keep keep it as
the loc from wherever your hydrogen
generation is uh so that's why the the
idea of like okay maybe I put compressed
hydrogen and then use that to sort of um
charge my loc it's possible but um that
particular um situation is actually less
cost competitive than what we propos
where you just sort of send the loc back
because the uh the current trucks you
know that would deliver the loc uh still
have to go back sort of empty so you can
sort of send the the spent Lo back with
that doesn't really add too much to the
to the cost there um is the loc system
scalable yes so we are just to kind of
understand um I'm not sure if are you
talking about the supply chain system or
or maybe the um you know like the the
powertrain system so maybe I'll take the
question as is it aable on the on the
truck itself like to the truck itself so
we we sort of definitely feel that we
can get it to the scale of 100 to 150
kilow which is the amount of power
that's needed for for a truck uh the
additional thing is you know something
that I skipped is we are currently in
talks with a lot of people oems in the
in the Marine space in the locomotive
space and those would be systems that
are significantly larger uh it's still a
little um it's still a little too far
away way to say definitely like what the
transients and things would look like
for the big big systems but um it is
something we we definitely feel as an is
an opportunity to to sort of explore and
more scientific work kind of has to be
done in that that space to figure out
how how large we can we can go on um on
you know like the ships or or the
locomotive there but there's definitely
opportunity there so I guess yeah with
that I think that's my time so I'm still
uh going to be sticking around so if
there's any more questions happy to
happy to uh take them as well thank you
thanks sh thank you so much