in today's fast evolving Market Talent
is your biggest competitive
Advantage the question is how are you
developing the next generation of
leaders who will drive your company's
future to answer this question I look
introspectively I start off with what
led me here today and my purpose of
being here today my name is Chu hang and
I am a proud first generation college
graduate raised by a single parent grew
up here in Boston Chinatown and I have
been through a proud public education
system here and I would not be here if
it were not for the shoulders of the
Giants who have led me here today my
parents my mentors my professors my
colleagues and my cousins family all to
say is it took a community for me to
build confidence and know that I am
important and that I have the ability to
create change and that I am part of
something bigger larger than myself and
that is what drew me into this this role
that I am in with breakthrough Tech AI
at the host site MIT schwarzman College
of computing and I am here because I
have been able to get here through
accessible resources and people who have
believed in me and so to answer this
question I wanted to be a part of the
solution be a part of the change in
developing the next generation of
leaders that will drive company's future
breakthrough Tech AI is a nationwide
organization that is partnering up with
here regionally where I will focus the
impact of the work that we're doing here
today on the MIT Campus schwarzman
College of computing breakthrough Tech
AI program is at the intersection of
Academia and Industry where we are
cultivating a tech ecosystem network of
individuals of Champions who see a big
future ahead of them and that is in
investing in a diverse talent group of
people on the rise and we are looking to
address the gender disparity in the tech
ecosystem and we have an emphasis on
underrepresented groups so as in part of
the tech ecosystem as everything is
advancing we need everyone involved we
need all the Champions we can find and
we need all the talent to not go to
waste and so because of some of the
gracious and generous funders and
sponsors we are able to offer this AI
program skills building program free of
cost for all participants of the
undergraduate college students and
participating companies who are
collaborating with us closely in seeing
the greater good and a very Innovative
future ahead of
us we welcome all companies of all sizes
of all
expertise you can be from a startup you
can be research-based you can be big
Tech Enterprise and you can come from
all types of sectors whether it be a
telecomunications biotech software
anything anything is we are all working
towards an advancement of technology and
there's every piece of of the ecosystem
in making a change so any company that's
out there we are eager and we are
excited to show you and collaborate with
you the diverse talent that we have
concentrated here on our
campus and we are now in our third
program iteration in launching this
novelty
program here are some of the data that I
wanted to proudly share with you
all we have scaled the participants of
undergraduate college students all
around Greater Boston area who are
representing 30 plus different colleges
and universities here in
Massachusetts and so our students know
that they are not alone on this journey
to break into Tech to see themselves to
know that they are not alone in shaping
their future throughout the hardships
throughout the challenges throughout the
balancing of Life commitments academic
commitments life in general it is always
helpful to know that there are others
that are in it with you throughout every
step of the way and so we have been very
very delighted to see the quick
expansion of our undergraduate students
here and 80% of our students
self-identify as women or non-binary and
they're all majoring in computer science
and stem we found them they are here and
we want them to stay and that is what
our current cohort looks like and it
will continue to grow and we will
continue to cultivate and nurture that
talent and as I mentioned we are at the
intersection of Academia and Industry we
would not be able to do this if it
weren't for our champions in the tech in
the in the tech industry and we are
proud to say that we have a 90% partner
return rate the companies that have been
there with us from the creation of
spearheading this this uh this work
remains with us and so it is really
exciting to see the kind of proposed
machine learning projects that different
companies propose and how fascinated
they are with the fresh perspective that
our emerging talents can come up with
and how they problem solve and apply
their critical thinking
skills and lastly one of the biggest
questions I get what what what's where
are they today what is the ultimate
impact of developing your talent where
are they and I am proud to say that 76%
of our students secure a full Tech role
after successful completion of our AI
program I'm going to give you a little
snap shot of the core elements of what
makes this impactful in our program all
the students that are accepted and are
eligible in our program they start off
the program with a 9 weeks summer course
machine learning foundations because our
students are coming from various
backgrounds we want to make sure that
they have secured the fundamentals
knowledge to be prepared so then they
can apply what they have learned so they
start off with a summer course course
being taught by MIT faculty and graduate
Tas after successful completion they
will earn a
certificate and then from there they
will get to move into the next phase of
the program where we where we match them
with a real world project proposed by
company partners and as mentioned we
have a whole variety a whole diverse
pallet of machine learning projects from
various um tech companies that have
shown what are some of the ways how
they're applying AI in their day-to-day
work and our students are very excited
to apply what they have learned from the
machine learning foundations course into
this real world project Additionally the
power of community and mentorship is
critical to building the community to
strengthening self-efficacy for talents
and so we also extend their network with
Champions with mentors who have been
right where they were when they were in
their undergraduate or in a different
kind of career pathway they have they
get to form authentic meaningful
relationships with our mentors and so
they get to have close um close contact
and Communications to learn directly
from those of how to prepare for a
coding interview of how how to prepare
for a behavioral interview so having
that undivided attention and support
from somebody that have created a a safe
space for them to learn and grow and
that it is okay to ask all the questions
that you may have that is a PE uh
another key of our program component and
this is essentially a one-year program
that occurs where students are traveling
from all across Massachusetts to be a
fellow in our program
and we have the research that backs up
the work that we are doing diverse teams
tend to generate more innovative
solutions it also helps with persistence
in stem think about retention think
about longevity think about maintaining
and keeping the talent who knows who
knows your organization who wants to
stay and grow in your organization so to
have visibility and representation is
clear is is critical towards retention
in in talent and lastly as you can tell
Hands-On training apply what they have
learned and put it into practice and
here are some key highlights that we
have heard from our partners in how they
have benefited from being a company
partner with us they were able to use
this partnership and demonstrate their
advancement towards their own diversity
and Tech objectives and as for the
employees it is a great way for the
employees to have an outlet to me mentor
and develop their managerial skills
their their soft skills to be able to
see the kind of uh impact that they have
on the Next Generation and essentially
it also helps with the greater good that
we are all shaping a future that
reflects the global world around us and
we cannot leave anyone
behind and so here are some of the ways
that we really wanted to encourage
people to join with us on how to engage
we ask for folks to think about all of
the people that are at your company who
who who is passionate about the work
that they do and want to pay it forward
we're looking for mentors we're Lo we're
also looking for subject matter experts
as well too because not only could they
be gifted and talented in their
technical expertise they can also share
and Coach all
about what their skill sets are in in
the subject matter expert and last and
so the ways to do so is in a fall
semester it happens really quickly
Within These 14 weeks but mentors and
students are extremely surprised by how
much growth they that can occur within
those 14 weeks by applying what they
have learned from the summertime of the
machine learning foundation's coursework
into fall and spring on their their real
world projects that could help enhance
their portfolio as they embark on their
journey in into Tech and lastly there
are many multiple multitude ways to
support the program and I am eager to
connect with everyone here in person and
virtually um to please connect because
you know we are all shaping the tech
ecosystem and every one of us there is a
space for us and I really hope that this
is a way um to invite you all a personal
invitation for you all to join us in
being a part of this Tech eal
system and I also wanted to share other
voices that have had experience a direct
impact through our program what other
way to hear from aside from me are the
folks who have been direct participants
who benefited from the program I share a
quote with you this is one of our
technical project advisors she proposed
a project on on an application to assist
blind people in describing the moments
and events and students were learning
sign language and many different ways to
think about all the different kind of
features that they can include in
developing this app and the project
advisor was
incredibly um impressed by the students
who are taking taking this as an
extracurricular bu uh skills building
program and being able to generate so
much um thoughts and and insights within
the time that they have together and so
I share this quote is because this is
not only a rewarding and fulfilling
experience for the talent but it's also
a way to really for those directly
involved in growing and cultivating the
talents they're also getting a
meaningful um impact throughout the
process as well and so I just wanted to
directly quote from this she said
serving as a challenge adviser was a
valuable experience for me and so this
is really a two-way street that it when
it helps it's not just only helping one
side of the group but it also helps both
sides of the
group and lastly I want to wrap up with
a closing quote of an alumni from our
very first cohort um I wanted to
highlight
her last statement in this quote being
the sense of accomplishment that
followed after completing the industry
project helped me find my footing as a
woman in Tech and these are the kind of
power compelling human elements that we
want to ensure that our program can
reach and continue to center
around and I share my contact with you
so I really hope to hear from you all to
connect with you to meet with you all
please join me in some of the impactful
work that we're doing here together
thank you so
much thank you very much to