Thank you, everyone, for
joining us for today's session.
If you have any questions
throughout today's presentation,
feel free to use
the Q&A feature.
My colleagues will be answering
some questions there virtually,
and then we'll also
answer some questions live
at the end of today's event.
As you just saw in
the video, hopefully,
you got a feel for the
culture and community
that is at the Sloan
School of Management.
Part of what we do in the
Sloan School of Management
is developing principled,
innovative leaders who
improve the world, and
generating ideas that
advance management practice.
This is our mission
statement and truly
at the heart of everything
that we do within the Sloan
School of Management.
As you think about the
first part of our mission,
developing principled,
innovative leaders
who improve the world.
This is done particularly
through our portfolio
of programs.
We have a variety of programs
offered for various points
in your students careers,
from early career
programs to mid-career programs
like our Sloan Fellows MBA
and our Executive MBA program.
Today, we're here to share more
about our Sloan Fellows MBA,
which we often refer to as the
SFMBA program here at Sloan.
Our Sloan Fellows MBA
program is a fully immersive
one-year experience.
At the end of the
12 months, students
get one of three
degrees either an MBA,
a master's in management, or
a masters in the management
of technology.
For those that pursue one
of the master's degrees,
they also complete a thesis
during their 12 months
on campus.
The degree is really focused
on the science of Management
and data driven
decisions, with principles
of innovation and
entrepreneurship and everything
that we do.
The Sloan Fellows MBA
program is a global community
with over 40 countries
represented every year,
and a lot of global perspectives
brought into the classroom.
As a Sloan Fellows MBA student,
you're also an MIT student.
And so you have access, not
just to Sloan resources,
but resources across the
broader MIT Institute.
And the Sloan
Fellows MBA program
is really designed to be
flexible and customizable so
that regardless of where you're
coming into the program from,
there are a lot of
opportunities and experiences
for you to engage and customize
that degree to exactly what you
need based on those
previous experiences,
but also where you want to
go after in your career.
So today's agenda, I'm going
to share a little bit more
about the curriculum of the
Sloan Fellows MBA program.
We'll talk about the community
aspects, career development
and support services,
and then go into Q&A
at the end of today's event.
Again, feel free to use the Q&A
feature to pose any questions
to my team, and then we'll
answer some questions
live at the end of the session.
So let's talk about the
curriculum of the Sloan Fellows
MBA program.
Starting in the first
semester, students
have a strong emphasis on
teamwork and collaboration.
You are put into a variety
of groups, a learning
team in a study group
in your first semester
to really have an
additional support
system within the broader
Sloan Fellows MBA program.
You will support each other
throughout the 12 months
in this network
that you're building
during your time will
be a network that you'll
have for the rest of
your careers as well.
One of the important components
of the Sloan Fellows MBA program
is a focus on leadership.
And so you start
establishing the foundations
even before arriving on campus
with a 360 degree leadership
assessment.
And then throughout
the program, you
have executive
coaching sessions.
As I previously
mentioned, students
pursuing one of the two master's
options will complete a thesis.
There's also the opportunity to
do a one semester independent
study for folks that are
interested in additional
research opportunities.
So previously, I
talked a little bit
about how the Sloan
Fellows MBA program is
both flexible and customizable.
So let's talk about what that
means for the Sloan Fellows
program.
You have a very
flexible path in that
each student designs their own
path throughout the program,
and has a lot of opportunities
to make different choices,
depending on their experiences.
So all incoming
students will start
preparing for the classroom
even before arriving on campus.
You'll start getting to know
the other incoming students.
You'll identify various
administrative items,
such as housing and the
student visa process
during the spring time.
All students complete a little
bit of academic prep work,
and then you'll also do
your 360 leadership survey.
All of those things
happen before you even
arrive on campus.
Once students arrive on campus,
they have an in-person June
orientation.
This is a four-day
period really focused
on getting you acquainted with
the various resources on campus,
getting you acquainted with
the executive degree program
team who supports our Sloan
Fellows, MBA students,
and our executive MBA students.
And really getting you
acquainted with other folks that
are in your class and starting
to form that community
within the Sloan
Fellows program.
After that June
orientation, then you
start your summer courses.
Summer courses are
only core classes.
You'll take seven out of
your nine core classes
during the summer term.
You will not take any
electives during the summer.
So the classes
that you're taking
are only with other Sloan
Fellows MBA students.
There's intensive teamwork.
Again, you'll be developing
learning groups and study
groups to support your
development throughout the 12
months.
You'll start focusing on
leadership development,
using things such as
your 360 leadership
assessment and
executive coaching
to get started on those
aspects and really building
that learning community
that will support you
through the 12 months.
This is the only semester
that all of your classes
are with other
Sloan Fellows MBA.
And so this is a really
important semester
to really build that
community within the cohort.
After the summer term,
you have about a week off
before your fall
semester courses begin.
Fall is a more lively
time on campus,
as many of our other
programs are starting,
or some of our
second year students
are returning to campus.
And so there are a
lot of folks on campus
and a lot of
opportunities to begin
engaging with folks in the
broader portfolio of programs,
such as our masters
of finance students
or masters of business analytics
students, two year MBA students.
You'll have plenty
of opportunities
to engage with them,
starting this semester.
During the fall semester,
you'll take one core class,
and the rest of your
classes will be electives.
Depending on the number
of units that you choose,
you might be taking
anywhere from four to seven
elective courses during
the fall semester.
During this time,
there will also
be frequent interactions
with senior executives
and entrepreneurs.
And you have the
opportunity to really choose
what teaching method may work
best for your learning style.
There are a variety of
opportunities with classes that
might be lecture or
case-based, they're
project-based learning courses.
Action learning
is a type of class
that I'll talk about in
a little more detail,
but you have the opportunity to
pick from hundreds of electives
to really start
crafting the degree.
After the fall semester,
you'll have a few weeks
off for your winter break.
And then here across MIT, we
have our independent activities
period.
During this period,
there are a lot
of opportunities
for Sloan Fellows
to engage in a variety of
different types of courses.
Some of those are a
negotiation seminar
that a lot of
Sloan Fellows take,
either six or nine electives.
That happens during IAP.
There's also the opportunity
to take in January executive
electives.
These are a unique
offering that are only
available to current Sloan
Fellows, MBA students,
current executive MBA
students, and alumni
of both of the programs.
They're about two-day courses,
intensive courses where
you focus on a specific
topic, and it's
really great for
the learnings that
happen in the class, but also
a really great opportunity
for further networking beyond
your cohort in the Sloan Fellows
MBA.
This past January, we
had about over 350 alumni
come back for the January
executive elective period.
During IAP, students
might who are pursuing
one of the master's
degrees will continue
working on their thesis.
And then there may
be opportunities
for international
experiences, whether formally
through action learning
labs or informally
through opportunities
with your classmates
or in the broader
Sloan community.
After IAP students
have a spring semester.
Again, you take one core class
during the spring semester,
and the rest of your
classes are electives.
Again, you're choosing
from hundreds of courses
to really design the degree
to what you need it to be.
And then students
graduate in May.
So a lot is packed
into 12 months.
A lot of opportunities
and experiences.
And then students go
off into the world.
Many students choose
to remain in the US,
and some might be
returning to their home
countries or the countries
that they were living in
prior to the program.
This is just a snapshot of
some of the popular electives
that Sloan Fellows
have taken in the past.
And you'll notice
some of the offerings
might be Sloan
Fellows MBA specific,
such as strategic
leadership communication.
A lot of the other offerings
are open to students
across the portfolio
of programs.
So again, a lot of
opportunities not just
to form community with
the Sloan Fellows MBA,
but also forming
community and connections
in the broader Sloan ecosystem.
So we've talked about
that flexible path
and how students have
various points of opportunity
to choose what classes
they're taking.
Let's talk about
some of the ways
that students might
customize the degree.
There are a variety of ways.
The first one is
through certificates.
So as a Sloan
Fellows MBA student,
you could pursue up to two
certificates during your time.
It does take a lot of time
management and proactive
planning to do that, but
it certainly is possible.
We have seven certificates in
business analytics, enterprise
management, entrepreneurship
and innovation, finance, health,
product management,
and sustainability.
These certificates require
45 units of electives
to be focused on
that specific topic.
And typically, a
certificate requires
two to three specific
courses and then two to three
elective offerings in
a broader category.
For folks that are looking to
make a change in their career
and move into one
of these spaces,
it can be a great signifier
to a future client,
a future co-founder,
or future employer.
Your dedication to that topic.
Oftentimes, we find
that Sloan Fellows MBAs
might use these
certificates as a path
that they're following or
choosing some electives from,
rather than pursuing
certificates,
because your interests might
lie across various topics.
Students can also customize the
degree through action learning.
And this is a
teaching method where
students are applying the
theories and frameworks
that they're learning
in the classroom
to a real-world
business challenge.
You work with a
real organization
solving a specific challenge.
Some of these
action learning labs
are focused on
specific industries,
some are focused on
specific functions,
some are focused on specific
geographic contexts,
and some are more
interdisciplinary.
I'll give you a snapshot of what
the current action learning labs
look like and when they run
during the academic year.
Some additional resources
for customization.
As the Sloan
Fellows MBA student,
you can cross cross-register
courses in the broader MIT
ecosystem and even at Harvard.
So there are additional
opportunities
for that customization.
Getting involved in various
research centers across MIT
can also broaden that horizon
and customize the degree
a little bit more.
This is a snapshot of the
current action learning labs.
You'll see a variety
of ones listed here.
One-- some of these
action learning labs
have travel components.
For instance, Global
Entrepreneurship lab
is a fall semester course that
happened that runs through IAP.
And so during IAP,
students typically
spend two to three weeks on
site with the host organization.
Since they're working with
companies in emerging markets,
students are literally
all over the world
during IAP for that class.
So a lot of opportunities
for that hands on learning
and for students
that are looking
to make some sort of
change in their career.
These are really
great opportunities
to explore in a safe
environment and try out
some new, innovative ideas and
propose solutions that hopefully
will be implemented in the work
that these organizations are
doing.
So we've talked a little
bit about the curriculum,
the flexible path, and
how students customize it.
Let's talk a little bit
about the community.
I think the Sloan Fellows MBA is
certainly not just what you're
doing in the classroom.
It's a lot of what you're doing
outside the classroom as well.
And there's a strong emphasis on
the community within the Sloan
Fellows MBA, but also the
broader Sloan community.
Our students come from
all over the world.
This changes year over year.
This is the current
classes makeup
where they came to us from.
So in terms of student life for
our Sloan Fellows, MBA students,
oftentimes, given
where students are
at in their careers and
their personal lives,
they may be joining
the program with folks
that are supporting
them, whether it's
children, Significant Others,
which we refer to as SOs.
A lot of students are entering
the program with that support
system, whether the
support system is
coming with them to
Cambridge or staying home,
students figure out
what is best for them.
For those that are
bringing SOs and families,
there is a very
intentional effort
to create community
for those folks.
And so there are
specific programming
for SOs and families.
And then a lot of
the programming
that's designed for our Fellows
is open to SOs and families.
An example of this when students
return after their short break
before the fall semester,
they have a welcome back
to campus event, typically
on a Sunday that's
open to families and students.
Oftentimes, it's a picnic.
Sometimes there may be
additional add-ons to that.
In previous years, they've
had the opportunity
to go to the Museum of
Science, which is right down
the road from Sloan.
And so that was open
to SOs and families
to really build that community.
There are some other events.
There's often an
event downtown that's
like a gala that is typically
just open to Fellows and SOs
no children at
that, but there are
a variety of different
co-curricular programmings
to ensure that community is
built not just with the Fellows,
but with those that are here
supporting them as well.
Outside of that,
our students get
involved in a variety of
different conferences,
competitions, hackathons
throughout the MIT ecosystem.
One of our current
Sloan Fellows is
leading the energy conference,
which is the largest student led
energy conference in the world.
And that is MIT focused.
Some of our students are
involved in Sloan specific
conferences or involved
in MIT $100K competition,
delta V accelerator, and other
opportunities within the Martin
Trust Center.
As we think about the
different experiences
that Sloan fellow
students are having they
engage in one of in three
different areas, the first one
being the MIT ecosystem.
As a Sloan Fellows MBA student,
you're also an MIT student,
so you're able to join
the hundreds of MIT clubs
and organizations.
You can get involved in
a variety of research
and innovation centers.
Some popular ones are CSAIL,
the Martin Trust Center
media, the MIT Media Lab.
As you think.
On a smaller scale,
within the Sloan School,
we have over 80 student led
clubs and organizations.
These clubs range from
focused on culture and arts,
to sports and recreation,
to specific industries
or functions.
So a variety of opportunities
and experiences to be
had in those.
And then within the Sloan
Fellows MBA program,
there's also a lot of
opportunity for leadership
and extracurriculars.
And so there are a lot of
co-curricular activities
that are designed to enhance
the cohort experience for Sloan
Fellows students.
Some of these committees
include a career committee,
which brings in folks that
have roles that are available
specifically for folks at a
similar point in their career.
As a Sloan Fellows
MBA students, there
are muddy talks which happen
throughout the whole academic
year, where every
Friday, two students
give a talk on their
experiences, their life,
whatever they want to
share with their cohort.
There is a women's committee.
There is a New York City
module committee and ADC module
committee.
Our Sloan Fellows are going
to New York City next week
during SIP week.
And this is an opportunity where
you're not taking your fall
semester courses, and
it's an opportunity
to engage more intentionally
in leadership and ethics.
As the focus of this
New York City module,
students opt into this, but most
students choose to opt into it.
And the committee for this
provides co-curricular offerings
outside of the
leadership and speaker
series that will happen
throughout that module.
The DC module is
similarly structured,
where students meet with
executives and various folks
in leadership roles.
And then there's also additional
co-curricular offerings.
Oftentimes, you're
networking with Sloan Fellows
and executive MBA alumni who
are in those areas as well.
So a lot of
opportunities to have
an impact on the experiences
that the cohort is
having as well.
So we've talked a little
bit about the curriculum.
We've talked about
the community aspects.
A lot of Sloan Fellows,
MBAs are joining the program
to make some change
in their career.
So let's talk about what
support resources are
available for students.
As I mentioned before, students
have executive coaching
throughout the entire
Sloan Fellows MBA program.
Students are able to work one on
one with these executive coach
to help identify your
strengths, your vision,
make sure you have
clarity in what you're
hoping to get out
of the program,
and move on to in
your career next.
And executive coaches really
use that 360 leadership
survey as a starting point
for those conversations.
You can choose to work
with one specific executive
coach or multiple
throughout your time.
As a Sloan student,
you also have access
to MIT Sloan industry advisors.
These are alumni experts
across more than 17 industries
that can really provide that
industry specific guidance
and advice.
Students are able
to make appointments
with industry advisors,
similarly as they
do to career coaches,
and they're there
to really provide that
additional guidance
but also help with
networking and connections.
One of the things with
the Sloan Fellows MBA
is that the career process is
very much student-initiated,
and it's very much a networked
job search and just in time
hiring.
So oftentimes, students will
start their very intentional
search in the spring
semester because that's when
the roles start opening up.
And so you do a lot of prep work
during the summer and the fall,
so that you're prepared for when
those roles do become available.
And a lot of it does
require networking.
And so industry advisors are
a really great opportunity
to expand your network
and specific spaces
so that you're prepared for
the networked job search.
And just overall, the
Career Development Office
is really there to work with you
in partnership of your career
goals, providing
you the resources
and directing you
to new resources
so that you can be successful
in that career search.
And career doesn't just stop
within the Career Development
Office.
There are really opportunities
everywhere throughout Sloan
and MIT for you to explore,
connect, experiment, and really
find that next career path.
And so oftentimes,
students are engaging
in conferences and clubs and
the broader MIT community,
and all of these
resources can really
help as you explore and figure
out what is next for you.
So we've talked a bit about
some of the different aspects
of the program.
Let's talk about
applying to the program.
Our first application deadline
is coming up in just less than
a week on Monday, October
20 at 3:00 PM Eastern time.
That is our first
round one deadline.
We strongly encourage
international applicants
to apply by the
round one deadline.
And as you're thinking
about your application,
there are a variety of
components that you'll have
to submit within
the application,
we require academic transcripts,
a 300-word or less cover letter,
test scores are optional
for the Sloan Fellows MBA.
You'll provide an
introductory video statement
introducing yourself to
your future classmates.
The caveat being your
future classmates
won't ever see that video.
It's just for us in the
admissions committee
to get to know you better.
You'll provide one professional
letter of recommendation
an organizational
chart, your resume.
You'll answer two
short answer questions.
The first one's about
your professional goals,
and the second one is about your
general management experience.
You'll answer the world
that shaped you question,
provide contact information
for two additional references,
and respond to video.
Question 2, which is
a randomly generated,
open ended question
that you'll have
about ten seconds to prepare
for in 60 seconds to record.
All of these materials
are due by the deadline.
So as you're thinking about who
to ask to be your recommender,
make sure that they know
the deadline that they
have to submit it by as well.
And we just want to
give a little caveat.
If you are submitting your
application around 3:00 PM
on the deadline day, and you
have a few components to upload
or your video to do, the
system can be slower close
to the deadline time.
So just have a little
patience with the system.
And we're happy to
work with you if there
are any technical difficulties
during that time as well.
Once applicants apply, we
review all applications
and then we invite a subset
of folks to interview with us.
All interviews are
conducted virtually.
And applicants respond to
one short answer question
prior to the interview.
Details of that question
and how to submit that
will be included in an
interview invitation email.
So this is a glimpse
of our current class.
We had 116 students
start in June this year.
Students entered the program.
The top three industries were
finance, technology, government,
education, and nonprofit.
In terms of where
students were coming from,
I previously had up
the globe, the world,
and where folks were coming
from with different percentages.
We have 42 countries
represented, 75% of our students
are international, and
25% of our students
are US or permanent residents.
Students entered the program
with 14 years of experience
on average, less than
a third of our class
had a previous advanced
degree, and you'll
see some additional
statistics listed here.
Hopefully, this gives
you a good glimpse
of what the current class
looks like, and also
allows you to envision yourself
in the Sloan Fellows MBA
program one day.
So we covered a lot,
and I'm sure there
have been a lot of questions
that have been answered
in the Q&A. I invite my
colleague Catherine to join me
for any additional questions
that we have in the Q&A
that we weren't able to get to.
Yes, thank you, Madi so
much for the presentation.
That definitely
covered quite a bit.
We do have a few
questions in there
that I would like to share.
One is what type of
resources does a Sloan fellow
have that's not just at the
School of Management at Sloan?
Are they able to engage with
other departments or conferences
outside of Sloan?
Yeah, absolutely.
As Sloan student, you're
also an MIT student.
And so we want students to
engage as much in the resources
at MIT as they do at Sloan.
And so we certainly
encourage it.
There are a variety
of students who
are involved in different
research initiatives
across the Institute.
There are a number
of students this year
who are Fellows within the--
I'm forgetting the name of it.
I apologize.
It used to be Legatum.
What's the new name?
Catherine, do you remember?
It's like the sharper.
Yeah.
They're focused on
entrepreneurship
in emerging markets.
So there are a few students who
are Fellows within that space.
In addition to being a part
of the Sloan Fellows MBA.
Like I mentioned, one of
our current Sloan Fellows
is one of the folks leading
the energy conference at MIT.
And so definitely a
lot of opportunities.
It does take a
little proactiveness
on the student's part to
engage with those, but plenty
of opportunities.
And oftentimes, if you talk
with any of our students,
they'll say there are far more
opportunities than you will
have the time to engage with.
And so thinking about
what's most important to you
and engaging with
but we encourage
as you have the bandwidth to do
all that you're interested in.
Great.
Thank you.
And for those who
are joining today
that have military
experience, what's
the best way for them to
share that in the application
and part?
Yeah, there are a
few different ways.
If you are currently involved
in your military service,
including that on your resume
in the employment section.
And that would also show up
in your organizational chart.
If you're not
currently serving, you
can still include it
in all of those spaces.
Definitely, including
it on your resume.
It may show up in some
of the other questions
that you answer as well.
So video question one, your
introductory video question,
you might talk a little bit
about your experiences there.
It could show up in
your cover letter
with examples from
your experiences.
And so we really encourage you
to use all the spaces to share
whatever details you would like
to about those experiences.
And we're excited
to hear about them.
Thank you.
A quick question.
On our slide deck, we
mostly mentioned the E-score
and shared that
median, but someone
was asking if we have any
range or median for GMAT?
Yeah, we don't
have one published
because test scores
are completely
optional for the
Sloan Fellows MBA.
We have a large number
of current students
who did not provide a test
score during their application
process, and so there's limited
numbers of test scores reported
for that.
Most often for
the Sloan Fellows,
MBA students are providing
an executive assessment score
if they're providing a score.
Again, completely optional.
But there's not enough data
to provide those data points.
Thank you.
Another question from someone.
If they're in between
the Sloan Fellows or MBA,
and they're trying to decide
between which program would
be best for them to
apply to, what advice
would you give them
specifically for maybe someone
who has maybe nine years of
work experience right now?
Yeah, we definitely get
this question a lot.
And I can provide a
little bit of guidance,
but it's also requires a
little bit of reflection
on the applicant's
side to figure out
what might be best for them.
Between our two year MBA
and our Sloan Fellows MBA,
one of the biggest
differences of the programs
is who they're designed for.
So our two year MBA
students oftentimes
are more individual
contributors looking
to make a pivot in their career.
And so the program's
really designed.
You have most students
complete an internship
between year one and
year two to support that,
that change in their career.
For our Sloan
Fellows MBA students,
oftentimes they are not
individual contributors.
One of the things we're looking
for within our Sloan Fellows MBA
applicants is general
management experience.
And so folks that are leading
functions, leading organizations
have responsibility
for strategy or budget.
Those are the folks
that the Sloan Fellows
MBA is designed for.
The core is based
on the foundation
that every student has
general management experience.
And so that's one of the key
differences in the experiences
that students are
entering the program with.
The experiences that
you have in the program.
For Sloan Fellows MBA students,
there is no internship.
And so if that's
something you're really
looking for in a program, you
might consider the two year MBA.
There are still plenty of
opportunities for students
to make a pivot in their career
through the Sloan Fellows MBA
program, and so those support
resources are still there.
So I think it
really depends what
experience you're hoping
for out of the program,
and also what you're
hoping for in your peers.
Sloan Fellows MBAs have about 14
years of experience on average.
Our two year MBAs
have about five years
of experience on average.
And so thinking about the folks
that you'll be sitting next to
in your core classes, the
backgrounds of those folks,
if that matters to you, really
figuring out which program
might be best for you.
You are welcome to apply to both
our two year MBA and our Sloan
Fellows MBA.
If you are still
unsure or think that
both programs could
be a good fit for you.
But I think really thinking
about those experiences
of yourself and the peers
can help you figure out
which might be the better fit.
Thank you.
And as a follow-up to
that, a couple of questions
around years of experience.
If you'll have a
little bit under 10,
if you apply by the time
you would matriculate
or you're not there, is the
requirement a hard requirement
or is there some flexibility?
Yeah, we do say, we are looking
for 10 years of experience.
I will say in the
current class, we
do have a couple students
who were right under 10
years of experience.
One of the things that's most
important in the experience
is having general
management experience.
So if you're at
nine and half years
with general
management experience,
certainly you could be eligible
for the Sloan Fellows program.
If you're at nine and
half years of experience
and don't have general
management experience,
we would direct you to
the two year MBA program.
Great.
Thank you for that.
Pivoting to an application
location question--
the video 1 and video 2.
We get a lot of
anxiety around those.
So folks are asking for
guidance for both of them
and sharing a little
more around them.
Yeah, these videos are--
I wouldn't say, make or
break for your application.
It's just one component of
the broader application.
We consider everything
as a whole package
and who you are
as a whole person.
Within the videos,
the first one,
it's really to get
to know you better.
Oftentimes students will
share more personal aspects
to themselves, maybe
their interests, what they
like to do outside of work.
And it's really a great
opportunity for us
to get to know you more
outside of what's already
on paper, in your resume
and your cover letter
and those more
professional aspects.
You're welcome to share
professional details
in the video statement,
but you can really
share whatever you would like
to share with the admissions
committee.
I really enjoy watching
them because it really
brings to life who
you are as a person
through that 60 second video.
The second video is the randomly
generated open-ended response.
And these videos are
really to just see
how you think on your feet, how
you communicate authentically.
There are no right or wrong
answers to those questions.
It can be nerve wracking
to have tens to prepare
and seconds to record, and you
just have the one chance at it.
But again, it's really
to just see how you think
and how you communicate
authentically.
It's a great way for us to
see how you might show up
in the Sloan classroom one day.
Most of the questions are
about your experiences.
So tell me about a time
when something happened
or what's your
proudest achievement.
There are some
additional questions
to see just how you think.
Like if you were a punctuation
mark, what one would you be.
And so again, no right
or wrong answers.
Just seeing how you
articulate your thoughts.
Prior to starting
the video question,
you will have the opportunity
to test out the software.
Well, you'll be required to
confirm that your video works,
that your audio works.
You'll be able to see where
the question will populate,
where it shows that
you're recording,
and how much time you have left.
So you'll get a feel for
the system before you start.
So just make sure you feel
comfortable with that system
before you click the checkbox
saying you're ready to go.
But again, try to
have fun with them.
They hopefully shouldn't
be too stressful.
You can approach them as you
would an interview question
or just a conversation.
We're really just looking
to get to know you better
through those two videos.
Thank you.
So another question around the
world that shaped you essay
question that we ask,
would you suggest or advise
that folks focus on earlier
years or more recent years
in their life experience?
Yeah, an applicant can
take it whichever direction
they would like.
I would say, oftentimes
we see applicants
talk about their
whole life experiences
and how it led them to
where they are today.
But you could also talk
about a more recent example.
It's really up to
you what you want
to share about your
background and how
the world that you're coming
from has shaped who you are.
So feel free to provide
newer examples or an earlier
one that has shaped
your life going forward.
Thank you.
Other than the length
of the program,
does the curriculum differ
between the MBA and SFMBA
programs?
Yeah, some of the core
classes, the titles
may be the same between the
MBA and the Sloan Fellows MBA.
The core classes
for Sloan Fellows
are designed with, again, the
basis that every student has
general management
experience, which
is a different level of
experience than our two year
MBAs.
And so while the
titles may be the same,
they are geared to those
specific student populations.
Once you finish
your core classes,
the rest of your
classes are electives.
Oftentimes electives are open
to students across Sloan.
And so you could be sitting
in class next to many two
year MBAs.
You could be sitting in class
next to masters of finance
or masters of business
analytics students.
There's a variety of folks
that you'll engage with,
but those core
classes are designed
for Sloan Fellows and then
the rest of the classes,
depending on which
ones you choose,
are designed for various
points in folks careers.
Great.
Thank you.
Just going through,
I know, we've
answered a lot of questions.
Some are asking is
the program full-time?
Is that set in stone or is
there flexibility with that?
Yeah, the program is
full-time, fully immersive
for the 12 months.
We do get questions like, can I
work while pursuing the degree.
The short answer is no.
You are spending
the large majority
of your time in classes, and
to get the full experience
of the program, engaging with
things outside of the classroom,
different extracurriculars,
and co-curriculars.
So a large majority
of your time is
spent focused either
on the curriculum
or the outside the classroom.
So there is not time
for a full-time job
within this program, and it's
really designed for students
to take, I would say, a
pause in their careers
to redefine their
leadership and prepare
for the next step
in their career.
And so it's really
designed for students
to not be working
during the program.
Thank you.
And I think probably the last
question, because we really
have answered a lot,
would be-- do you have
any advice for reapplicants?
Yeah, we get this
question a lot.
And I think as you approach the
application as a reapplicant,
you probably have a
lot of questions on.
Not much might have changed
in the last six months or year
since you applied.
How do you really stand
out in the applicant pool?
As a reapplicant, we want to see
whatever new information or data
you have to share.
And so updating your resume
using all of the spaces
to provide as much new
information as possible,
potentially asking
for a new recommender
to provide a new letter.
Or if you ask the same
recommender, still
having them provide a new
letter with new details.
As a reapplicant, we have
double the data on you.
We'll have your
reapplicant application
in addition your
initial application.
And so we'll be able to
see what those changes were
from your previous
application to now.
So really highlighting those
changes in your application
is really important.
You also have a
dedicated section
to provide a summary or
the highlights of what has
changed since you last applied.
So use all of those spaces to
provide as much new information
not as much new data
as possible for us
in the admissions committee.
And every year, we
have reapplicant who
are successful in admission.
And so my biggest
tip is just providing
as much new
information as you're
able to since we already have
your previous application
and all of that
information on file.
Thanks so much, Madi.
Well, I think we've covered
most of the questions.
This is a great presentation.
Awesome.
Thanks, Catherine.
And thank you, everyone,
for such great questions
and staying engaged with us for
today's information session.
If you do have
additional questions,
you're welcome to
email us or attend
one of our upcoming events.
With our application
deadline in less than a week,
we hope to see many of
your applications then,
but we look forward
to staying in touch
and we really thank you all for
joining us for today's session.
I hope everyone has a
good rest of your day.
Thanks, everyone.