All right. Well, let's continue with our
discussion of linear regression
modeling. And as we introduced last
time, there are ways one can formalize
fitting a model, which is to propose a
model, specify criteria for judging
different fits or estimators of model
parameters,
then find the best estimators, and then
check our assumptions underlying the
specification of the criterion. and
possibly uh if necessary modify the
model because the assumptions that we
made aren't satisfied. So we either want
to u add additional assumptions or
consider transformations of the model
perhaps.
Um so um with ordinary le squares
regression
um we have this criterion for specifying
regression parameters and we specify
these in terms of a y vector
and
this has values of a dependent variable
across cases in the data.
an X matrix
which will have n rows and p columns
and we'll have sort of general elements
x i j and then u our model will be that
y is equal to x the matrix times a beta
vector.
So we can have a beta vector
that has p components
and
an error vector
which
has n
terms corresponding to the n cases.
So
in specifying the regression model we
have that our n vector y is going to be
a linear combination of the columns of x
and there will be a an error vector uh
characterizing the discrepancy from
that. So um
so how should we specify this beta
vector if we have a least squares
criterion?
We can look at sum one to n of y i minus
y i
where
say y hat is equal to x beta hat
and this criterion uh
is basically a sum of squares criterion.
So it's like a sum of squared errors.
Now minimizing this can be done
just with simple calculus. We can plug
in for
uh the in the formula and
have this sum of squares criterion which
is simply
y - x beta transpose
y - x beta. So we have Q of beta is
basically
Y - X beta
squared. So it's the distance of our Y
our n vector
from the
prediction or fitted value. I guess
maybe I'll put the beta hat here to make
it uh explicit.
And we basically want our fitted values
to be as close as possible to the actual
values. Now, because this criterion is a
quadratic,
okay, it's a quadratic in the regression
coefficients. We can simply take
derivatives of Q and solve for those
derivatives equal to zero. So that's the
first order conditions and um let's see
how do we know whether the solution to
this
equation actually minimizes
the sum of squared errors criterion.
A first order condition is one where the
derivative of the function is equal to
zero. That could be at a minimum, but it
also could be at a maximum.
>> Yes.
>> You also want to check for the second
order
and make sure that it's positive.
>> Yes. Right. We want to take the second
order derivative. And
if it's positive then we have a I guess
it's a concave
or sorry a convex function and so the
first derivative will solve that. Now
this is the first derivative equation.
Um
if we were to
uh look at dq of beta
by d beta j
let's see is that beta j right um if we
were to look at the uh second order
derivative
by d beta
bet theta transpose then
analytically we'll basically get
this
term times minus x and so that will end
up being a positive term in terms of
products of columns of x and the full x
matrix
and uh so so with that we have this set
of equations um now if you read up on
regression theory, linear model theory.
Um, this equation
of the derivative of Q with respect to
beta equaling zero is equivalent to this
equation here,
which is just obtained by eliminating
the minus2 factor and solving for beta.
And this is called the normal equations.
Um
what is familiar to some people is that
in statistics theory the names of
important terms is often not very
sophisticated in terms of here we have
what we call the normal equations.
There's nothing really normal about it,
but it's a way of specifying a set of
equations that we need to solve. And if
the
xrpose x matrix
is invertible, then we have a solution
by multiplying both sides of this
equation by the inverse.
And in order for this process to work,
we need to have that X must have full
column rank.
And um
all right. So
so here if we plug in that le squares
estimate. So we have beta hat equal to
xrpose x inverse xrpose y
If we plug that into our
formula for the fitted values,
then
this becomes
this formula time y
and I'll put square brackets around
that.
um
and this is called
the hat matrix by uh some statisticians.
Now
this matrix H is actually a very special
matrix. Um it has special properties and
does anyone
sort of know what those special
properties might be?
Anybody
in the back? No. Kai,
>> uh,
>> from memory, it's a it's a projection on
this column space.
>> Yes, it is exactly. So, H is a
projection
matrix.
um and it's onto
sort of the column space of the X
matrix.
Now what are properties of
a projection matrix? If we multiply
the projection matrix by itself,
we actually get the projection matrix.
And what's um relevant is that if we
were to take sort of h yhat
um which is then equal to h * h y.
If this
first term is in the column space of X
as a projection, then projecting it onto
that same column space will have no
difference. So this is sort of logically
uh what it should be. And if we multiply
out the projection matrix times itself,
we get this um this property.
Okay. Well,
importantly in modeling is to look at
residuals
um which are sort of model errors. And
so if we have epsilon hat is equal to y
- yhat.
Okay, this is y -
or y * the identity matrix minus h
y
and
this um
this matrix here multiplying y to give
us our residuals.
It is also a projection matrix.
So this is a projection as well.
And if we multiply I - H * I - H and
expand it out, we get I
2 - 2 H + H 2
and that equ= I - H. So you know we can
mathematically verify that it's a
projection
and
a very important property of this
residual vector is that it is
orthogonal
um to the fitted value. So in the normal
equations we have this equation
must equal zero.
This term here is the residual vector.
And if we multiply that n vector by the
transpose of x and it's equal to zero
then we must have that um the error
vector epsilon hat is orthogonal to x.
Um, now
let's see. I'm not sure if it's on the
next slide
or not.
Um,
and something to keep in mind
that's really quite useful when we use
linear algebra with leaf squares is that
we have y
being in n-dimensional space.
Um
the uh we have an x matrix n by p um
which corresponds to sort of a column
space of x which is a subspace of r to
the n
and
um let's see if we have
yhat
and epsilon hat
these are orthogonal to each other. So
if we think in sort of n dimensions of
having a y vector
and
have
a
yhat n vector
um then
y minus y sorry y not yhat y minus yhat
So if we take the vector from here to
here
that's y minus y hat.
Um okay this is going to be orthogonal
to yhat. So we actually have
right angles here between the yhat
vector and the y vector. Sorry, we have
the yhat vector and the error vector.
And so
from this we have that
um
the squared length of y is equal to the
squared length of y hat plus the squared
length of the residual vector. And then
if we expand this
squared length out, we actually get zero
because of the orthogonality.
So with le squares, we basically have
a sort of Pythagorean theorem
that generalizes from two dimensions to
n dimensions.
And that generalization is quite
uh convenient and useful when we think
about
not the mathematical exercise of le
squares but we think about having
probability distributions on say the
errors. Um
so
so that leads us to trying to extend the
mathematical regression model to a
probability model. And so with this
we have constants
assumptions for the independent
variables and the X matrix constants for
the regression parameters.
But the error terms
uh those will be assumed to follow some
probability model.
What's useful to think about is well
what would be the simplest possible
probability model to to apply to a
regression? Well, we could assume that
the errors are IID
which means independent and identically
distributed.
And we could also for convenience assume
that they are normally uh distributed.
Um and so this is a normal linear
regression model. And when we write out
the model equation here,
um the model equation basically is
constants plus the error vector. and the
error vector
epsilon 1 to epsilon n being iid normal.
This in fact is consistent or is
equivalent to a multivariate normal
distribution of dimension n with a zero
vector for the mean and a covariance
matrix that's diagonal
with constant variance.
So this is going to be a convenient
model for us to work with. And what
we'll see is that different inferences
about how important different
independent variables are in a
regression model can be judged using
this model as sort of a baseline model
for that evaluation.
So
importantly
um the distribution of the residuals
leads us to a distribution
of
the dependent variable vector y.
And so in this slide we use the notation
of a mu vector for the conditional
expectation of the y vector
given x and beta.
And
we'll define this just to be a mu vector
that's an n vector.
And we'll define the co-variance matrix
of the y vector
for the conditional covariance.
Okay, this is going to be equal to the
product of y minus its mean
times the transpose of y minus its mean.
And so this is an n by one 1 by n
term. So this is an n byn
matrix
and we'll call this
capital sigma
as a coariance matrix. Now for the
special case of iid errors um this
coariance matrix will be diagonal with
constant sigma squared
and it will turn out that um this
conditional distribution of y given x
and beta
we'll have a multormal distribution with
a mean vector mu and a covariance matrix
sigma. So an n-dimensional
multivariant normal distribution.
Okay. Well,
what we're going to do is show
results of what distribution the Y
vector is as well as show
what the distribution is of the le
squares estimate is using moment
generating functions. So this um example
u of the application of moment
generating functions is really quite
neat because the arguments are
very simple and accessible. So if we
have a an nvariat
random vector y
and a constant vector t, then the moment
generating function of
the y vector is equal to the expected
value of the exponential of t transpose
y. So this moment generating function
has
uh is a function of the t vector and we
just plug into this formula. Now because
the y's in fact are independent of each
other then
we have this expected product of terms
is the product of the expectations.
So we're going to use that independence
property uh where expectations of
products are products of the
expectations.
And then for each of the y's
we can plug in the moment generating
function for each y
I and that's e to the ti mui plus a half
ti 2 sigma squ. We went through this
moment generating function you know in
our section on on probability theory.
Now
what's important from this example is if
we take this product of all the moment
generating functions and then try to
express it in terms of the T vector,
the mu vector and the sigma matrix.
we get this formula
and this formula is in fact the moment
generating function for a multivariant
normal with a given mean vector mu and a
given coariance matrix sigma.
So that result is sort of trivial, not
surprising.
What's less surprising is that we can
use moment generating functions to solve
for the distribution of the le squares
estimate.
So this first
formula here is the moment generating
function for beta hat.
And
in writing that out
m some sub beta hat I'm going to use a
different argument toao
which will be a p vector
and this is going to be the expected
value of e to the tow transpose beta
hat. So this is the definition of the
moment generating function.
And
if we
define
the matrix A to be the basically the
premultiple factor
of uh A that gives us beta hat.
Then our moment generating function for
beta hat can be written as
this expression just plugging in a y for
beta hat. But then we can express
to transpose a
equal to tanspose.
So this
moment generating function of the le
squares estimates beta hat is actually
the value of the moment generating
function of the multinnormal vector
evaluated at t equal to arpose
toao.
And so we can simply plug in this value
of uh t
and get
our result.
And so tanspose mu is ends up being to
transpose beta. and tRpose sigma t
is equal to this product.
And if we simplify it, we basically have
a sort of mean vector beta for the le
squares estimate and a covariance matrix
for the le squares estimate that's given
by
sigma^ 2 xrpose x inverse.
So this is our moment generating
function of beta hat and by the
uniqueness of moment generating
functions we can recognize this as a
multi-normal with the given mean vector
and the given coariance matrix.
So uh so we have multivariate normality
of the le squares estimates which is
very convenient and useful.
Now from this we end up getting marginal
distributions
that are normal for each of the le
squares estimates.
So we're just thinking in this slide of
the j component of beta hat. Well, it's
univariate normal with mean beta j and
variance given by sigma squar times the
j diagonal element of xrpose x inverse
and uh so so we get this nice
distribution result. Um
now there's more distribution theory
here to go through but um
let's see something just to think about
that's I think very powerful is um in
some examples
um
where we have this model
we may have control over what our
independent variable matrix is. And in a
scientific experiment, we might vary
different conditions of the experiment
yielding Y for different conditions of
X.
And
with these uh models, we might be
interested in
a particular sort of column of the X
matrix
and want to estimate
the beta J the regression parameter
relationship for that.
And so
if we had control over
the X matrix, we might try to make the J
diagonal
the smallest we can
so that the precision of that regression
parameter estimate is as small as
possible.
And so
suppose
I guess for simplicity that the X matrix
um
suppose that XRpose X is a diagonal
matrix
and here's CJ
the diagonal values of XRpose X
inverse
will simply
be
so if we do a minus one there we can do
a minus one here. Our uh diagonal
entries will be smallest
smaller the more large the J column is.
And so when you think of
um regression uh models and and uh uh
experiments, we basically would perhaps
want to have the spread in an
independent variable be as big as
possible in order to specify the line.
So
if we
if we think of uh a regression model of
y on x and we have um
if we have points
of x and y
um
basically the uh
if we look at the sample mean of the x's
and we consider consider
sort of concentrating our x values
as far away as possible. That presumably
will yield more accurate estimates of
the slope parameter in the relationship.
And so you can think of basically if we
observe points that are far away from
the mean
then those points will sort of pin down
the regression line the greatest and
this u issue arises in uh experimental
design.
Um and in experimental design, one can
think of how one can construct X
matrices that have these these
properties. And as you might expect,
the properties relate to
the igen values of xrpose x
and uh looking at
uh methods for maximizing those values.
All right. Well,
we have we can do some more distribution
theory which is to look at what the
distribution is of our error vector
y vector but we can also look at any uh
matrix A* Y
and look at the distribution of that
transformation.
It'll be a
linear combination of the Y's for each
component of Z. And
it will actually have an M dimensional
multinnormal distribution with mean
value given by A times the expected
value of Y and coariance matrix equal to
A times the coariance of Y a transpose.
And so this matrix A will give us the
distribution of beta hat as we just did.
But we can also use different
definitions of A and Z.
And
the normal distribution theory leads to
these sort of key properties of uh
normal linear model terms. We have
the beta hat le squar's estimate is
multinnormal.
We have that the error vector epsilon
hat is also multinnormal.
Um and but it's multormal in n
dimensions with
mean vector
zero.
So epsilon hat which is equal to i minus
h y
is distributed as a multinnormal
in n dimensions with a covariance matrix
given by sigma squ times the projection.
Now
what's
significant is that this co-variance
matrix here is not a full rank.
So um this is non-s singular
actually. Is that the right word? No,
it's singular
I guess. Um but it's singular. It's not
invertible.
And what does that mean?
Well, that means that
there are
linear combinations of the error vector
that have uh zero variance. There's a
linear dependence in the error vectors.
And so
if we consider xhat and xrpose this and
this is equal to the zero vector this is
the normal equations. Um
we basically have that fixed linear
combinations of these residuals
the residual vector are identically
equal to zero. So we don't have um n
sort of independent error terms.
And so um because of that uh when we
look at
for example estimating the error
variance sigma squared well if we take
the sum of the squared residuals that's
the trace of the coariance matrix
of the residual vector and that's equal
to the trace of this
projection uh matrix I n minus H. And so
the trace of a sum is the sum of the
traces.
And the trace of a matrix is product is
also the trace of the product with terms
reversed. So this gives us sigma^ 2 n
minus trace of h and we get n minus p
sigma squar for the expected value of
sigma squar. And in regression models
with normal linear models, we use this
relationship to estimate sigma squar
dividing both sides by n minus p, we get
an unbiased estimate
um of the error variance.
Now an additional property that's from
part C of this theorem is that the error
vector
epsilon hat and the regression parameter
beta hat those happen to be independent
of each other
and the independence
follows by looking at the joint
distribution
the moment joint moment generating
function of
a y
and showing that that is equal to the
moment generating function of beta hat
times the moment generating function of
epsilon hat. So the product of moment
generating functions sort of allows us
to determine the independence there.
And when we have independence of the
error vector and the regression
parameter vector, then we can compute
tstistics
for
regression parameters. And we end up as
stated in the notes there that TJ
equal to beta hat J minus the true beta
J divided by sigma hat
times C JJ J.
Um this distribution will have a T
distribution.
Now, when you studied statistics, if you
took a statistics course, you I'm sure
came across the t distribution.
And the t distribution is uh rather uh
remarkable. Um
this
this turns out to be equal in
distribution to a normal zero.
uh distribution
mean zero and some variance divided by
the square root of a ki squared
distribution
divided by its degrees of freedom
where these two things are independent
of each other.
And so um the t distribution
well who can comment on what properties
a t distribution has compared to a
normal.
The t distribution is symmetrical.
It's somewhat bell-shaped.
Well, if this numerator
is a normal and this denominator is
random,
it's random near one. Um, then we'll
have a heavier tail distribution.
with the t. And so
we need to uh be able to quantify sort
of how significantly different from uh
zero
the tstistic is. So if we have an H knot
that beta J is equal to zero then this
distribution
turns out to be um
basically have a t distribution
a t distribution
with uh n minus p degrees of freedom
and so we can uh
judge whether
our data provides evidence against this
null hypothesis or not. And we can test
other hypotheses
as well, not only that the beta j is
equal to zero. We'll be covering this in
a little more detail um with
uh one of the lecture notes that was
passed out for today. But um
the uh
let's see does anyone know the history
of the t distribution? how it was
discovered
>> through Guinness.
>> Yes. Uh there was a a statistician who
was working at Guinness with quality
control and uh he he would look at um
he would look at uh samples very small
samples of size four from a uh
so we'll just write here Guinness
um he
would look at samples say X1 X2 X2, X3,
X4
of a measurement. I'm not sure quite
what the qual quality measure was, but
you would calculate Xbar
and the standard deviation of X
um which is the square root of
uh the sum of Xi - Xar^ 2 over over um
over three. Well, actually I think he
did it. Well, I I'll write in three. And
um
what he discovered was that
uh if we look at Z
equal to sort of Xbar over SX
um
these outcomes of the sample means
which uh suitably rescaled should follow
a normal distribution because we're
looking at a zcore.
um this was not
uh distributed
as a normal 01.
there was much greater variability and
so um
the person who did this work they
wouldn't allow him to publish under his
uh real name and so he published a paper
under the pseudonym student and so we
call this the students t distribution
now but what was really quite remarkable
was to see that in small samples the
variability of these kinds of statistics
um
in theory should be close to normal but
in fact are systematically different. Um
and
with let's see with uh other questions
that come up in regression um one can
construct an F test
of whether all the regression parameters
beyond the first P are equal to zero or
not.
And one can look at the residual sum of
squares from fitting the full model
and then the residual sum of squares
from fitting a submodel using just the
first K. Sorry, the first K. I misspoke.
Um and then this F statistic
is a ratio
of normalized sort of sums of squares
and differences thereof. and and this F
test statistic comes up
as uh an analysis of variance statistic
where one can estimate variability
using the residual sum of squares from
the full model and one can then also
look at the residual sum of squares from
the submodel and if both models are true
meaning
beta k + 1 to p are equal to zero then
these formulas here are estimating the
same variance
and they're independent of each other
and so we get the f distribution as the
ratio of two uh kaiquare distributions
that have uh different degrees of
freedom.
All right. Well, let's take a look at
some real data. Um, the uh the the
example data set I want to introduce is
actually not a financial data set. This
is a medical study. But um this uh
this example
uh comes up in some work by Efron and
Hasty,
Brad Efine and uh Trevor Hasty and they
have some books. There's the elements of
statistical learning.
Actually this is uh hasty and then
there's um
with Ephrine there's u an advanced book
on sort of computational
uh uh statistics
um a book that I text that I use in 1865
um and uh in this data set
um one basically has a response variable
and independent variables. And what's
really key to know is
experience we have with one regression
problem extends to other regression
problems. Just sort of the names of
variables change and uh but the same
issues arise. And so with this data set
um we're trying to predict the uh LPSA
variable
um as it varies with other independent
variables
uh for subjects in a uh data set. This
data set happened to be a data set on uh
patients or subjects with prostate
cancer. And so with any
data set one can compute summary
statistics
which help us sort of detect whether
there are sort of issues with the data
or not. Um there's this pairs function
in R which is quite convenient for just
displaying all of the data. And if you
look at this pairs plot, every pair of
variables in the data set are
plotted
in a scatter plot with the other
variables. And so along the diagonal we
have the names of the variables and then
we have um different relationships of
those. Now if uh LPSA is the
uh dependent variable of interest, if we
look sort of across this row, um we're
looking at the scatter plot of different
independent variables with that. And it
looks like the LCA V is probably a very
strong relationship. Some of the
variables in fact are discrete
and we're able to see that as well.
Um and if we just fit a simple
regression,
we end up getting
output from the regression which
consists of an estimate.
We have a coefficient table
with
an estimate column,
a standard error column,
and then a t value.
And then finally
what's
called a p value column. This is the
probability that
we have a larger value of the tstistic
being observed.
And what's being tabled here is results
of hypothesis testing for each of the
regression coefficients equaling zero or
not in the true model. So we have
estimates of these different regression
parameters.
We can get standard errors of those. The
standard errors
correspond to sigma hat cj
actually it's I think it's the
it's the square root of sigma squar cj
um and then uh the t value is just the
signal estimate to noise ratio
which
scales u in magnitude how important
those factors are and we can calculate
the uh p value
let's see so if we have say a beta
uh hat j value
and it has this t distribution ution
which is centered at the true beta J and
um the spread is given by C hat CJ J
square root
um
we can
calculate
um
we can basically test whether beta J is
equal to zero
And so if we sort of set this equal to
zero, if we observe a value of beta hat
j,
um we can
calculate how likely is it that we get a
sort of beta hat j minus beta minus 0
over sigma hat cj.
This is our t statistic.
We can look at uh calculating this
probability
that the uh t statistic or of getting a
greater than
a large a larger value of that t
statistic.
And um with this
uh let's see if we sort of consider
Changing the scale here to just be beta
hat j / sigma hat cj square root. This
is our t statistic. Then we basically
have a
t distribution for the outcome of the le
squares estimate. and we're calculating
how likely is it we
would get as large or larger a t
statistic if uh the true
regression parameters were zero or not.
Now in looking at this these estimates,
one of the uh challenges in part is that
the scale of the parameter estimates
varies
depending on the units of the
independent variables. And so in some
problems we have very diverse
independent variables in the data set.
And the units
are a property of the data set, but
they're not really an important part of
the problem. Um, and so what we can do
is standardize the co-variants
by
normalizing them to have mean zero and
standard deviation one. So if we have
our X matrix equaling
let's see how do I want to do this. Um
so if we have P columns in our X matrix
um we can basically take X
one and transform it to
X1
- Xar1
* the vector of ones
and divide true by the standard
deviation
of X1.
And so this
we'll call this a random vector Z1 of
standardized values.
And
if we do this, we're basically shifting
the X's and rescaling the shifted
values. It turns out that our regression
model
on the zcores or standardized scores are
the same as the regression coefficients
in the original
units.
So
it's sort of obvious I guess but um if
we have uh
y
uh
is equal to
beta 1 x1
plus
beta 2 x2 up to beta pxp
plus an error vector.
And we consider Zj
is just simply equal to XJ
minus
Xar J * the vector of ones
and 1 over say SJ where SJ is equal to
the sample variance
of the X
J's.
Um
we basically
can sort of substitute in for each of
the x's the formula here. So xbar j is
equal to s j z j
plus xar j
uh
plus xar j.
So this times this is xar minus little
xar. So and this is times the vector of
ones.
So if we plug in to
our XJ values here, this then we end up
getting this
equation with um
the same uh regression parameters come
coming into play. All right. Um
well when we fit the scaled regression
uh independent variables uh model. Then
notice that the t values and the p
values for these two regressions are
identical.
So if we pick say the largest t value
SVI or that's not quite the largest LCA
of all but let's do SVI 2.949.
If we scroll back
to the original units, the t statistics
are identical across all the variables
and so are the p values. So in terms of
interpreting how important different
variables are, we get the same judge
judgments of what's important in terms
of t values and p values. But what's
particularly useful though when we use
the standardized covariants
is that the magnitude
of the
coefficients when we have the
standardized scale that corresponds to
the impact of a one standard deviation
move of the independent variable.
So if we have a an age value that's one
standard deviation above the mean, it
doesn't have much of an impact
on the dependent variable. If we have
the SVI a one standard deviation move
above a zcore of one then um it has a
larger impact on on the dependent
variable. So this
standard deviation units can be a very
convenient way to rescale our data.
All right. Um now in in in judging the
quality of regression models um we can
calculate fitted values and pair those
with the observed values and look at the
scatter plot of observed versus fitted
values. And this simple scatter plot
will have a correlation statistic.
And the square of that correlation
statistic is actually called the
multiple R squared or a coefficient of
determination.
If you're familiar with simple linear
regression where you calculate
correlation statistics,
um you can think of the squared
correlation as being useful. In multiple
regression, we generalize a single
correlation
um statistic with the multiple R 2
coefficient. And so it basically tells
us how um predictable
our dependent variable is given the
independent variables.
Um now uh in terms of evaluating
the assumptions of our regression model,
there are regression diagnostics that we
can apply to uh fitted models and there
are a number of different important
uh measures that we can uh apply and uh
in the stats package There's this
influence measures
uh general function which gives a table
of different statistics.
Um there's this r student for computing
studentized residuals. Um if we have
epsilon hat is distributed as
multivariant normal with mean zero and
covariance matrix i - h * sigma squar
um
our residuals
may have very different variances
because of this
i minus h factor in the co-variance and
so Studentized residuals
um basically will divide the residuals
by the square root of that variance and
an estimate of that. And that estimate
of the variance that's in the divisor
leads to non-normal
but t distributions for the epsilon
hats. So we'll see that play out in a
moment. Um and then there are other
statistics like how much does the
regression parameter change if we
include or exclude different data
points, different cases in the data. Um
so let's just see some of the results.
So here's the student residuals
for this regression model. And we h have
a histogram which is unimodal
symmetrical. Here is the uh what's
called a uh quantile plot of the
residuals that um where the
quantile plot will follow a straight
line if the data are consistent with the
normal distribution model. and uh
the t distribution for normalizing the
residuals by estimates of the variance.
Um what's uh what's rather
useful when you use these uh methods for
different regression problems is that
you'll see that um there's sampling
variability
due to just the data set we we're
working with. If you were to collect a
new data set under identical conditions,
you would get different results. These
red bands correspond to bands you might
expect to see with variation from one uh
example to another. Now um this uh here
is a plot called the influence plot in
the car package
and uh it plots hat values versus
studentized residuals. Um the hat values
are
the diagonals of the H matrix.
And um
what's important about the hat values is
that um
let's see if the hat values were equal
to one. So if
say h subi i equals 1
then
we would have y i is actually equal to y
i.
And so the i case it would be the sort
of
only case in the data set that allows
you to estimate that um
that value. So, so that case would have
very high influence. So, hat values
generally um are some well are close to
P over N um and uh
lower values correspond to lower
influence and studentized residuals um
are uh given by these magnitudes.
Um and I believe what is drawn in this
slide is yeah is the circle size is
proportional to cook's distance and so
um let's see with cook's distance
if we have beta hat equal to
uh xrpose x inverse xrpose y
Um
we can think of beta hat sub minus i
which is the le squares estimate if we
were to exclude the i case.
Um so this corresponds to excluding
the i case.
Then well we have that this beta hat is
distributed multinnormal
with a mean vector the true beta and
covariance matrix
given by this.
Um,
we can actually look at beta hat minus
or beta hat I minus beta hat
and then
consider the distance of this
or the magnitude of
the change in the beta and this cook's
distance um will actually correspond
closely to sort of a kai squared
distribution because of um the
relationship. Um so we're basically
looking at the distance of beta hat I
from the true beta um and normalizing
that by the coariance matrix.
Now um let's see and there there's
basically a whole slew of different
diagnostics that we can graph and I
think it's very useful to have graphical
methods to highlight what's perhaps
important. Um in looking at this uh
plotting from the car package or plot.lm
um we can see how the residuals compare
with the fitted values
and we don't like to see any systematic
pattern in that plot. We'd like that
just to be flat. How that will change
sometimes is that as the fitted values
increase the residuals might increase in
magnitude as well. So that would suggest
that the residuals
uh are dependent on the magnitude of the
fitted values. Okay. We can also look at
the normal QQ plot to see whether the
data consistent with normal or not. And
then one can look at the um the scale
uh of the uh the scale of measures of
the scale of the residual. So we can
take the square root of the standardized
residuals or the magnitude
and see whether those have variation
depending upon whether the fitted values
are small or large. Here it looks like
there may be a nonlinear relationship
there. When we discover relationships
then that u leads us to sort of refine
our model assumptions.
Um
let's see this
uh residual plots function
is uh actually a function that looks at
the sensitivity of our linear regression
model to potential nonlinearity
in the model dependence on on
independent factors. And so it actually
tries to fit curvature
terms in
to the residuals in the model. And if
there's residual pre if there's
curvature present in the residuals, then
we might have a nonlinear model and need
to expand with nonlinear terms.
Okay. Um
let's see. Well,
with this normal linear model,
um,
we can consider the assumptions
underlying that minus normality and
those are called the Gaus Markov
assumptions. So uh if we have our
regression model in our for our y vector
and x matrix um we set that up as the
conditional expectation is x beta and
the covariance matrix is equal to sigma^
2 times the identity
and with this gaus marov assumptions
there's a really important
theorem in uh linear models which is
that
the least squares estimates
of the regression parameters
give us the best estimates of any linear
combination of the true regression
parameters. So if we want to estimate a
parameter theta which is a linear
combination of the regression parameters
then if the gaus markoff assumptions are
satisfied then plugging in the le
squares estimates provides an unbiased
estimator
that is also
the unbiased estimator with the smallest
variability.
And these are called uh best linear
unbiased estimates. Um and what's
important well I mean as as it's framed
here it's quite general but think about
this if if we have the constants C1
through CP correspond to specific
values of the explanatory variables
corresponding to a different case. then
we can be estimating the sort of true
mean value for a given case of the X
variables.
If we have two X
values, X vectors for different cases
and we're interested in what's the
difference in it in val in mean values
for those two cases, then we can have
these C's represent the difference in
the X's. and we're estimating the
difference in y values, the difference
in mean values for different cases. So
it really is a very very general theorem
and
while it's a very wonderful theorem, it
depends on the Gaus Markov assumptions.
So what we can do is consider
generalizing the Gaus Markov assumptions
to
again have zero mean errors but have the
co-variance matrix of the errors be
given by sigma squared times a capital
sigma matrix.
And
this kind of covariant structure in
error terms
actually arises frequently in time
series modeling
where we're ordering our data by time
and maybe near
uh values of the error that are observed
at uh nearby times are more correlated
than those at far away times and the
covariant structure of those errors
might be systematically
represented by
a multiple of a known sigma matrix.
Well, if this is the case,
we can transform our original data
by
premultiplying by
the
inverse square root of sigma and do the
same for our x matrix.
And if we do that, we're basically
transforming our model to the starred
case where
the Y star and XAR as we've
represented here. The epsilon star will
have mean zero and the covariance matrix
of the epsilon stars will actually be
diagonal with constant variance. So in
this transformed case we have the same
regression parameters. we have
the epsilon stars with the uh
with the gaus marov assumptions being
satisfied. So by the Gaus Marov theorem
we just can write directly our le
squares estimate in terms of the x stars
and y stars. And when we write that out
it ends up giving us this formula for
the generalized
uh le squares estimate. And so if we
have variable errors where we know the
relative variation of those errors, we
can accommodate that and get best
estimates with this generalized le
squares uh formula. And importantly,
the
generalized le squares estimate
basically does sort of a weighted
regression
where we weight cases
proportional to the inverse of the
variance of the random variable. So if
this sigma matrix in fact were diagonal
with different variances, we would be
downweing those cases with high variance
and uh
performing the least squares
computations you know in a weighted way.
So that's the generalized le squares
estimate. All right. Well, we'll finish
there uh for today and uh
cover more regression next time.