So final session of the afternoon. Um
Fiona uh is my boss. She's the professor
and we are delighted to have her here
today. Uh she is also now known as
Professor Dame Fiona. Not only is she a
professor at MIT, but she was made a
dame of the realm uh for services to
science and technology and innovation
and keeping the world safe. Um she it
says on these slides that she's the vice
chair. She's actually just been elevated
to being the chair of the NATO
Innovation Fund. Um so round of applause
for that.
>> Thank you. NATO Innovation Fund is the
alliance's venture capital fund. So if
you think venture capital's tricky,
imagine doing it with multistakeholder,
multi- sovereign members. And Fiona is
the chair uh of that organization. Uh
her topic for this afternoon is
innovation in an era of geopolitics. So
Fiona, thank you very much for joining
us from what looks like your home. And
with that, without further ado,
Professor Fiona Murray,
take it away.
Brilliant. Thank you, Phil. Um, and it's
very nice to be able to connect to
everybody. I'm sorry not to be able to
be there in person. Um, I was in London,
gosh, last week and I have to be there
again next week and so I'm sorry I
couldn't actually sort of stay over, but
I'm really pleased that the technology
uh MIT can deliver some technology
around the world and and I can get to
join you and I think you're also in
incredibly good hands. Phil is a
longtime MIT colleague and co-author and
so if there are any difficult questions
we will definitely direct them to him.
Um as he kindly said I'm I'm an MIT
professor. Uh I've had the privilege of
being on the faculty at MIT for about 25
years. I'm in the management school
although originally I'm a scientist and
technologists by training. uh and so I
care very deeply about deep tech and how
we make sure that the investments that
we make in science and technology really
turn into the sorts of impacts that we
want uh in today's I think very complex
geopolitical world. Phil also mentioned
I've become chair of the NATO innovation
fund. This is a billion euro uh venture
capital fund uh where we have 24
contributing nations as our limited
partners and we're focused on making
early stage investments in companies
focused on defense security and
resilience across uh European nations.
We do direct investing and we also help
build invest funds uh particularly in
parts of Europe where capacity needs to
be built to really do additional
investment. And I hope that the reason
why I'm doing that sort of in a sense
becomes clear uh when I go through this
presentation. And so I really wanted to
talk about innovation in an era of
geopolitics uh because I think that has
become a very important theme and I hope
it helps us tie some of the threads
together that Steve Whitaker and his
colleagues have so sort of nicely
orchestrated for all of you. And next
slide.
So I don't think you need me to describe
that we are in an era of geopolitics. I
think we're in a quite increasingly
fragmented world. Uh there we definitely
have the rise and fall of great power
competition and I would argue that we're
definitely in a phase where that is
rising. Uh or I'm not sure we're at peak
great power competition but we
definitely have I think a very clear
sort of sense of a more complex
relationship between the United States
and China um in general terms uh in
military terms but also in technological
terms. We also know that the war in
Ukraine is incredibly important in sort
of shaping the world and particularly in
Europe I think shaping how we understand
um the importance of defense and
security and we see that Europe is I
think asking itself a lot of questions
about having really a new geopolitical
compass you know how do we think about
the relationship between our individual
nations um sort of collective
sovereignty as opposed to individual
sovereignty whether that's through the
scaffolding of organ of alliances like
the European Union or NATO, Orcus, we
have a number of these different sort of
collective sovereignty sort of
scaffolding on which we might think
about develop developing. Um, and this I
think is a very significant shift away
from a much more sort of globalized
period that we've lived through for the
for the pri prior you know multiple
decades. Next slide.
And I think more today, more than any
other period, um, innovation and
industrialization are in the spotlight
for policy makers and for decision
makers. And they're in the spotlight in
part because of geopolitics, but also
they're seen as an input into some of
the solutions. innovation and
industrialization as these twin engines
I think are absolutely essential to how
we're going to to continue to drive the
economic growth that matters but also to
produce some of the outcomes that matter
whether those be perhaps some of the
traditional social missions that we care
deeply about like healthare um climate
and so on but also increasingly I think
are seen as essential inputs into our
national security and that I think is
the new part of this conversation and
again why why is it that, you know,
we're seeing innovation and
industrialization and where does it show
up? It shows up in our understanding of
um how the war in Ukraine is being
fought and the role of innovation in
that war. It's certainly showing up
every time the US makes a move that's
focused around a particular company, a
particular industrial sector and I would
say especially in the US response to
some of the issues around rare earth
mineral needs. We're seeing both the use
of new tools and particularly private
sector capital related tools like equity
loans and offtake agreements but also
when it comes to just really paying
attention to sectors and parts of the
supply chain that we've never done
before. We see it in the debates I think
on in on the European side of the
Atlantic a real sort of question about
this issue of US sort of dependency on
US technology. I think we actually saw
it in a quite interesting way in the
response to the sort of announcements
between the US and the UK uh in the most
recent visit of President Trump uh to
Britain. On the one hand, I think a real
enthusiasm for um the willingness of
companies like Nvidia and others to
invest in the United Kingdom, but on the
other hand, a question about whether or
not we can or should have a little more
independence or sovereign to use that
word ability to deploy AI in particular
at various places in the stack and what
that how that might be manifest. What
would we need to do for that to happen
and should we does it does it matter?
And then of course it's not just about
the US and Europe or the US and China. I
think um middle powers if you like
Africa the Middle East and so on very
very important players particularly in
this geoeconomic world when we know an
enormous amount of capital in particular
uh in the Gulf States is extremely
relevant I think to these debates and
enormous markets and growing and
expanding markets in Africa.
Next slide. So why this turn towards
innovation and industrialization? I
think some of you possibly may have
heard from me or from Phil in the past
and we have spent a lot of time talking
about um innovation and the world I
think that we might have described until
quite recently was really focused on
innovation ecosystems in very specific
places sort of intertwined embedded in
an almost invisible globalized supply
chain. Now 2005 Thomas Freriedman wrote
a book called the world is flat. Phil is
another historian I think was quite
offended by that because he was writing
a a brief history of the 21st century
only five years in probably three years
in because it took him a while to
publish and he effectively said that
sort of innovation ideas connectivity
was global and at least with respect to
innovation I think we recognized that
that probably was a poor representation
of the reality on the ground and that
even at that time and certainly by today
it's clear that for innovation the world
isn't flat It's actually highly
distributed across the world but in very
very dense locations that we would refer
to as innovation ecosystems places in
the world where the key stakeholders the
entrepreneurs the risk capital providers
and the universities come together with
corporations and government that
multistakeholder model that I think
you've seen and particularly for the
early stages of innovation the early
part of the idea to impact journey it
was these places in the world where we
see huge concentration
of talent, of capital, of ideas, and
often of sophisticated early customers.
Silicon Valley is perhaps iconic. At
MIT, we like to think of Greater Boston
and Kendall Square as as sort of the
ultimate quite specialized innovation
ecosystem with deep deep expertise in
ideas in the life sciences, in robotics,
um, and increasingly in some of the
climate technologies, particularly
around batteries and so on.
And Phil and I recently wrote a book to
put those Oh, go back one. I wanted to
talk about our book. Don't move forward
yet. So, we've written recently written
a book accelerating innovation, which
really asks the question, how do large
organizations, whether it be global
corporations or governments, tap into
that early uh innovation activity, that
that private sector ingenuity happening
at universities, but then particularly
out in spinouts and startups. And we
would have I think argued that all of
this was embedded in these very global
supply chains. And I'm just have an
image here of the semiconductor supply
chains which just remind us of how
global the production of these ideas
really was uh when it when they were
taking place at scale. And the common
narrative would have been to an
entrepreneur, you know, be focused in an
ecosystem, find the right partners and
then scale up as quickly as efficiently
as you can. Use the global manufacturing
and production network. Don't worry
about where that is in the world. And
also don't worry about where your
capital comes from or your talent. It's
really focusing on that early stage of
innovation.
But as you'll see in the next slide,
uh what we are beginning to recognize is
that you know innovation in particular
is expanding beyond us and allies. So
these innovation ecosystems, the places
in the world who can innovate are
expanding and supply chains themselves
are becoming a source of power. And it's
really these two shifts that together I
think put innovation and
industrialization together on the stage
and are deeply influential and
influenced by geopolitics. So taking the
first piece of the puzzle uh I think
that this is the first time the US has
faced a real peer adversary um with
comparable expertise across a very wide
range of technological domains. You
might have argued that the US is perhaps
the the leading nation around technology
and innovation. um would have had
competition sometimes from friendly
allies um and potentially from
adversaries in very narrow areas of
technology and I think about say Russia
with nuclear technology but really I
think today is one of the first times
that we've really seen a peer adversary
with comparable expertise across an
incredibly wide range of domains. We I
could pick numerous examples but this
chart just looks at some of the
comparative patents for something like
battery storage, hydrogen, bio energy.
um and you really start to see sort of
the rise of of um knowledge production
and early innovation in China. I think
the story that we've told ourselves for
a long time is that that was just
imitation and I think all the evidence
is pointing to the fact that China is
indeed innovating very directly and
itself has learned from the US playbook
and learned from that ecosystem playbook
to really build very vibrant innovation
ecosystems. And so we have competition
at the level of the early stages of
innovation. But the second piece is the
industrialization piece that
increasingly the fact that supply chains
were not actually evenly globally
distributed. They were highly
concentrated and remain highly
concentrated in places like Shenzhen and
China that has been very efficient for
the global economy. Shenzhen is as
specialized if you like in in
manufacturing and supply chains as say
Boston is in biotech. Um but these
supply chains are increasingly being
used as a source of power projection.
And so we see technological independ uh
interdependency
as a sort of source of power. And so we
start to worry about whether or not the
lack of of uh western and allied
capability industrialization is as
important as the debate and discussion
around innovation. Next slide.
I think we can see this more um sharply
than anywhere probably in the case of
Ukraine and drones. So when we look at
Ukraine, we've often asked the question,
you know, what are the lessons uh from
Ukraine? And we often think about it in
terms of lessons in war fighting, right?
We think about how important it is to
have drones, to have mass, to have
autonomous systems, to be able to
operate in GPS denied environments and
so on. I would say let's ask some
economic and innovation lessons. And
what we see is I think one of the first
mo conflicts where a modern innovation
ecosystem is essential to the response
to conflict. And we actually see a whole
of society, whole of ecosystem response.
And we see an enormous amount of private
sector ingenuity of young people of risk
capital providers of universities all
leaning in to try to win the drone
startup war and to make sure that it's
really you know that that that
innovation and that ability to test and
evaluate incredibly quickly at the front
line that is providing Ukraine with some
of the advantage it so desperately
needs. And we also see Ukraine doing
that with a whole range of of other
startup and and scaleup companies uh
like Helsing coming from Germany, Tever
from Portugal, um Orion which is sort of
Swiss US and Anderil. Um and so this
very much is a sort of a startup
innovation ecosystem game and yet we've
also recognized that that's not quite
enough.
And so you'll see on the next slide that
um one of the challenges is a challenge
of accessing the drone supply chain. And
the challenge of accessing that supply
chain reminds us I think of the
essential role of industrialization.
And so Ukraine finds itself in a way
caught in the middle of USChina
hostilities as particular drone
components are are sort of being limited
in their availability to Ukraine where
American drone suppliers like Skyo for
example are having you know are
basically put on a Chinese sanction list
and being unable to access some of the
parts. And what you see on the right is
a chart based on some work I did with my
um colleague um Edlin Lavine where we
said well is it inevitable that um China
is the place where most of the core
components if you like if you the
anatomy of a drone if you look at the 12
components is it inevitable that they're
all produced in China. Well, it turns
out that it probably isn't. um the
origin of many of these deep
technologies whether it's uh the the
lithium polymer batteries some of the
brushless motors that are now on the
front page of the Wall Street Journal
the antenna and so on many of those were
developed in the US in Japan across
Europe uh in the UK but over time
because of this shift out of the
innovation phase into this sort of
industrialization phase where China was
specialized we've really seen this sort
of shift in the supply chain and we've
also seen been effectively a
vulnerability that's come from a lack of
manufacturing capacity and
industrialization. And so the real
debate now in Europe is to say, you
know, could we actually produce at
scale? Do we have the industrial
capacity? I think that debate is
becoming as loud and as as relevant not
only for sort of domestic job creation
but also frankly as having um you know
thinking of our industrial base as a
form of deterrent and I think that's
extremely important particularly for
deep tech where we actually have to
physically make something. So it's not
enough to actually be good at the
digital piece if we can't make the
physical assets where the an AI of
course wraps around them to make them
intelligent and effective. We absolutely
have to get the supply chains and the
manufacturing right. Uh less we think
this is just a drone problem. Let's have
a look at some emerging industries. I'll
do this very quickly. But take the
example of fusion energy. There's a
tremendous excitement around a company
like Commonwealth Fusion Systems which
is an MIT spinout that we're incredibly
proud of. Uh which you know is on track
having raised several billion dollars as
a company on track to deliver commercial
scale fusion systems. Uh they they are
switching on in the next uh little while
uh their their pilot uh phase uh spark
in Fort Devons and then they will be
building ARC which is the commercial
phase but I just had the opportunity to
meet their sort of um and spend time
with their head of manufacturing and
production and she was talking about the
fact that they're really trying to ramp
up manufacturing production supply
chains and that's actually one of the
huge challenges
and the question you might say is well
all right so what do you need what are
the supply chains of the future that
we're going to need if we want to not
only be winners in the core technology
of fusion energy systems, but actually
in the industrialization of them. And
when you start to pick it apart, you've
got to be good at things like thin film
processing, at cryoplants, that means
keeping everything cold, something that
the UK is actually very good at, at
large metal alloys, at power
electronics. and and Edlin myself um one
of our students Rory and and Dan Bruner
who was the chief science officer at
Commonwealth Fusion started to sort of
map out does China actually already have
such an advantage in some of these areas
that it's um it will be important for us
to have a really clear industrial
strategy to catch up and this will need
to be a whole of allied approach that
there's it's very unlikely for this to
be a US solution that some of the key
technologies and the key supply chains
are likely to run through for example
Finland where they have some very
specific ific expertise the UK and
elsewhere, Germany um and so on. And so
thinking about this, thinking not just
about the innovation but the
industrialization is going to be
essential.
Uh next slide. Um I could do this for a
whole series of priority technologies. I
won't suffice to say that it's not just
the old i.e. drones, the new i.e.
fusion, but also industries in
transition. Again, think of batteries. I
think we took for granted that um
China is the place that today has really
deep scale and economies of scale in
lithium-ion batteries. Again, you might
see you might ask the question, why is
that? The story is an interesting
combination actually of very early stage
IP being generated in the United States
um but actually then being scaled in
China through an interesting combination
of very explicit technology transfer,
very explicit licensing and also
probably some sprinkling of industrial
espionage and all kinds of other things.
Um as well as some very careful kind of
and thoughtful use of financial
instruments as companies weren't able to
access the capital they needed in the
US. that capital being provided in
China. But the really important thing is
the market. So China did some really
interesting things around growing their
EV market. So they absolutely created a
scaled market and that allowed their
companies um like CL and BYD to really
get those economies of scale. And so the
questions I think we have to ask as
companies and as countries is can we
catch up in that technology? Probably
not. Can we actually catch a march on
the next generation? Yes, but that will
I think require our startups, our
investors, our corporations to be have
some quite sophisticated views on
geopolitics and our governments to have
I think a fairly clear view about the
kind of tools of economic statecraftraft
that they might want to use.
Next slide. So as a result, right, I
think geopolitics is entering the
boardroom. It's very hard for us, I
think, as any of those of us who are,
you know, non-executives who sit on
boards, who advise startups and
investors as well as large companies to
um, you know, we would be remiss if we
didn't ask about geopolitical risk. But
more importantly, I think about
geopolitical dynamics. I think more than
just a risk assessment, we have to
really think about the dynamics. And we
see this whether it's a company like
ARM, you know, being sold to SoftBank,
um, you know, and then not being able to
IPO, etc., or the sale kind of being
blocked or Intel selling a stake. You
know, you you think about the changing
government reaction to these things and
we know that as companies we absolutely
have to pay attention as leaders. Next
slide.
The thing we have to respond to is what
I would call the set of economic
statecraftraft tools that governments
are increasingly putting into place. And
those statecraftraft tools might include
things that promote market. So offtake
agreements of the kind that we saw in
the US with MP materials um or the kind
of offtake that Google is doing with
Commonwealth Fusion advanced market
commitments um potentially reducing the
regulatory burden of deployment of
particular technologies more targeted
R&D support but also more sort of let's
say protectionoriented you could call
them protectionist more control of the
inputs and outputs of economic growth so
things like CPHAS in the US uh the
national security investment act in the
UK, the changing tariff landscape and
really things like export control
regulations that we used to think of as
this really specialized subject and I
think now is becoming more relevant. And
then the third piece of this is the
partnership the sort of state craft in
the context of partnerships. Is this all
going to be uh evolve around sort of
bilateral partnerships like the UK US
tech prosperity deal US Saudi on AI or
is it really going to be around
multi-country agreements or um you know
the US with DFC and others around
minerals for peace or multilateral
initiatives kind of grounded in things
like NATO? I I think we don't know yet
but absolutely as executives and I know
that's who many of you are. This is
really what we're starting to think
about is what should that geopolitical
kind of compass look like for you?
What's the toolkit? What's the calculus
that you need to have and really
understand?
Next slide. So, just to really kind of
conclude, we need a toolkit to sort of
for you to sort of evaluate your
geopolitical calculus and we need tools
and methods to bring these ideas to
life. And I think we're beginning to see
things like scenario planning,
potentially the use of more war games,
tools that are traditionally the the
realm of military policy makers. But
what how do we think about sort of
sudden geopolitical shocks on our supply
chains, on our industrial base co
started to bring that front and center,
but I think we need to do more of that.
What's our preparedness analysis? How do
we use simulation? And how do we have a
serious discussion in the boardroom um
about these topics?
Uh next slide.
So I think I just want to underscore
that I believe this is relevant for
large established corporations. You know
Apple can't ignore the trade the trade
war. Um its investors can't either. Its
exposure to China is quite significant.
And in fact if you look at the efforts
that they have made I think very
reasonably to shift production and
industrialization to India that's
extremely difficult. And we see the same
thing with TSMC moving to um moving to
the US. You know, these are very hard
things to do and we can't sort of shift
those in very short order, but we have
to have a calculus for understanding it.
Um likewise with small companies, you
know, whether it's the small companies
in the what used to be a rather obscure
part of the mining industry in rare
earth suddenly becoming front and
center. Are you a drone company? Are you
engaged in fusion or quantum? Um our
friends at Oxford Ionics I think were
delighted with the outcome of the
acquisition by INQ on the other hand you
know that's something that is going to
suddenly invoke uh the national security
investment act and so really
understanding these dynamics is I think
for the entire stakeholder uh
environment and all five of the
stakeholders that I think Phil will have
talked to you about absolutely got to
have this front and center.
Next slide. So I think lastly just
having a clear geopolitical calculus in
the boardroom I think matters today more
than ever. I spend a lot of my time kind
of working on this whether it's at the
level of the NATO innovation fund um
working with individual companies
thinking about this on campus at MIT it
affects universities as well on both
sides of the Atlantic. Um but this is I
think very much um the backdrop against
which many of our really key investment
decisions and resource allocation
choices are being made and it's it's a I
think a topic that's extremely important
and I'm really pleased I have a chance
to talk to you about it. So I think my
my last slide is going to be one that
just has a nice picture of MIT and I
just want to say thank you um and Phil
thank you for so wonderfully advancing
the slides. I'm really happy to answer
questions or um drop off or leave you to
answer all the questions. However you
would like to take our time together
forward.
>> Well, first of all, let's thank Fiona.
Fiona, can you hear me?
>> I can.
John, good. Well, we do have a few more
minutes before we do hand over. So,
because there may be tricky questions,
they're all yours. Um earlier we were
using a digital app called Pigeon Hole.
Um but I'm going to go old school. Uh we
have one with no votes from Mr.
Anonymous or Ms. anonymous. Uh, as your
diplomatic advisor, answer carefully.
Uh, what do you think of the UK
industrial strategy, Fiona?
>> The
>> the new one.
>> The new one. I was just going to say I
mean we Gosh, now my head is I can see
through the thing. My head is gigantic
on the screen. All right.
>> No, it's a just a trick of the light.
>> Thank you. I mean look I think the
government has you a s series of
governments one after another have
developed industrial strategies I I
think it's important that we have them
um know quite often people have said
look the US doesn't do industrial policy
we don't have an industrial strategy we
always have actually done industrial
policy um sometimes it just might be
quite lacair and at other times I think
it might be sort of all all-encompassing
and use this very wide set of tools of
economic statecraft um so I think think
it's important that the UK does that. I
um I think the thing that's difficult in
these strategies is both for a country
particularly the size of the UK uh I
don't think we need that slide but okay
perfect. Um, I think for a country
particularly the size of the UK, um, we
aren't going to be able to be good at
everything,
but we're not so small that we might
just pick one thing. And so I think we
sit in this rather uncomfortable middle
ground where the right number of things
for us as a country to excel at is
probably a handful of things. And that
requires prioritization and very um,
difficult choices. And I I see every
time governments struggling with where
they say a priority list and it'll have
17 things on it and and we all know
that's a shopping list and it's not
really a priority list because it's too
many things. And so I think that we need
to be a little bit more clear either
about the priority industries or frankly
the priority capabilities
and then really um try to make sure that
we continue to build the underlying
foundations. And so I would call those
the the talent piece of the puzzle, uh
the capital piece of the puzzle and and
the bit that I think is still difficult
in the UK is us as customer. The
government is a really important
customer particularly in areas like
defense and health and actually energy
and I do not believe that at the moment
we are using our buying power, our
customer power, our signaling power
particularly effectively. I think if we
were to do that better um it would be
much easier for us to really grow both
the startups, the scaleups and and
really support the large corporations
and their supply chains because we would
have more certainty about where markets
are going.
>> Excellent. Well, I think we're pretty
much at time. So, what I'm going to do
is walk across your your big in front of
your big head and put down the clicker.
Um the room has really enjoyed your uh
presentation this afternoon. I don't
know if you can feel that over the uh
communication system probably provided
by BT Fiber. Uh but the rumor has been
very positive about all this. So we're
going to give you a round of applause
and then turn to Steve. So thank you
Fiona.
>> My pleasure.