so I am one of those people that uh Andy
talked about who left her area of
education and expertise namely computer
science and AI because I felt that at um
the place where I was then the AI Lab at
MIT I couldn't quite combine my passion
with that field that I was working in
the field of engineering and Ai and that
passion was people
I was more interested in designing a
future and inventing technologies that
would benefit people that would make
people more intelligent for example
rather than inventing smarter robots and
possibly AI systems that would one day
replace us so that's why I joined the
media lab while initially starting at
the AI lab and that's also the work that
I'll talk about today so I've been
working in AI for a very long time and
um I believe that we are quickly moving
towards an era where AI is always with
us and is mediating our daily experience
whether it's at work whether it's at
home Etc how many of you have seen the
movie
her so about a quarter of the people the
other ones you know what to watch
tonight um I think think it's as
educational as the uh maybe some of the
talks at the conference today in terms
of telling you what future we are
heading towards basically the person uh
the main character in the movie has this
AI system uh it lives in its in his uh
shirt pocket actually it has the camera
always on it's basically a phone with a
camera always on and that and an AI
system that constantly talks to him
about everything going on everything
going on around him Etc uh it knows
about all of his data and personalizes
that whole experience is really Charming
on top of it voiced by Scarlet Johansson
and so on so a wearable AI system always
on aware of the user's context and
States through
sensors personalized aware of all the
users data and proac active anticipating
the needs of that user uh providing
informations helping with decision
making Etc that is the future of
computer human interaction that we are
very rapidly moving towards and of
course that future offers unprecedented
opportunities to benefit people in the
area of Health once our phones are even
more proactive more personalized have
have even more sensors to know what is
going on with our bodies Our mental
health Etc they can basically P um like
monitor uh all sorts of uh possible
issues diagnosis uh can be made early uh
these systems can intervene before
something becomes a problem Etc in the
area of learning there's huge
opportunities one day I believe our kids
will have a personal tool running on the
Next Generation phone that just helps
them learn about the world um all day
long and knows what their learning style
is how to get them excited and engaged
in learning about something and so on in
work of course the work area there's
huge opportunities for amplifying
creativity performance Discovery
decision making and more and the elderly
I think are also a group that really
could benefit from AI assistance because
maybe they almost needed most uh these
days and I'll talk about that a little
bit more later so wonderful
opportunities but also
unprecedented uh challenges for example
we are already seeing again I'll talk
about that more that people are over
relying on AI trusting it too much and
thereby making decisions that are are
not optimal uh so there's a lot of
misplaced uh trust in AI there's a lot
of loss of or there's a potential for
the loss of human agency the more we
rely on AI to help us make decisions and
solve problems the more we risk no
longer being in control of all of these
decisions we make especially when AI
gets better at things than we are um we
risk deskilling whenever you delegate a
task to AI or rely too much on AI to
help you with some decision you risk
losing that skill yourself because
you're no longer exercising it there's a
potential loss of understanding of how
the world Works how uh things should be
done Etc right now most science uh
scientific knowledge is the problem of
people uh basically coming up with all
of this knowledge and so we mostly
understand what um what things are uh in
all these different areas but
increasingly we are moving towards a
world where AI makes the discoveries and
discovers things that we no longer can
understand so it knows or it has
discovered something and we have to like
catch up over um uh and and maybe will
never catch catch up in trying to
understand what it discovered um
misinformation of course if you have an
AI with you all the time that is going
to help you interpret everything that
you come across you risk that um there
is a bias in that AI or that it's um um
a mischievous AI Etc so in our work we
show that there's uh very um big
potential for misinformation also
because of that misplaced trust in AI
manipulation AI is the biggest
persuasion uh technology ever
invented AI is fabulous at persuading us
of all sorts of things it's um and of
course that can be of a lot of uh
misinformation or it may try to sterious
to into certain biased directions and so
on loss of control privacy ER expion
unhealthy attachment to chatbots
increasingly an issue as well and
dehumanization if you no longer interact
with other people as much to that teach
you or that you work with or that um or
even for
socializing of course we risk losing
sort of a lot as a
society um because we no longer sort of
reinforce that human fabric um that uh
is so
important so AI is not just an
engineering challenge I hope that long
list made that clear to you AI is also
very much a human design challenge we
really have to think more carefully
about what this future with AI or this
present with AI because the future in AI
is next week basically what are these
going to do to us to people
people and that's actually what my work
uh at the media lab focuses on it's not
just my work people like Andy and others
uh other colleagues work in this area as
well we are actually starting a program
at the media lab to really reinforce um
this type of research uh the AHA
program um stands for advancing human AI
interaction with the eye upside down but
the goal really is to provide some aha
moments to research and development in
Ai and make people out there think a
little bit more carefully about how we
are designing Ai and whether we are
designing AI to benefit people so in
this aha program we do a number of
different activities we Inspire or we
aim to inspire with positive use cases
of AI that help people thrive um we
invent and we provide Insight uh we do
studies to show some of the possible
negative and positive impact of AI on
people's cognition and intelligence and
more so let me give you some examples
from my own work in uh sort of the
inspiration category and then in the
inside category so we do develop a lot
of novel use cases typically in areas
that Silicon Valley doesn't think all
that much about uh for example we have
been looking a lot at memory
augmentation all of us have to remember
more and more information but of course
as you age uh that also becomes more and
more difficult so we've been building
systems that uh assist you by basically
memorizing a everything you say or if
you have permission even conversations
with other people other data um from
your computer Etc and it's sort of acts
like your own personal chat GPT
basically um it can really uh predict
almost what you're going to say in a
certain moment and if you can think of
the words you just ask it and uh you
click a button and it gives you uh the
information you're looking for so super
quick video to show show this mamor is
an audio-based wearable memory assistant
powered by an AI agent it runs on
unobtrusive commercially available
Hardware hi nice to meet you I'm Robert
I'm an investment maner from Investments
oh and what do you do there so we invest
in B startups that help with rare
diseases oh wait what was his name again
Robert a biotic do you know where I can
look for investment oh yes I actually
just met this guy last week his name is
Dober and he works in fluid fluid
Investments and they specialize in rare
diseas biod startups working in
actually so we have a working prototype
of this system both on uh the hardware
you saw there but it can also work on a
Samsung Galaxy watch actually which it
turns out can record all your
conversations um so we have been working
on this um for a while trying to make
this system as uh nondisruptive as
possible actually if you think about the
smartphone today of course it can give
you a lot of that same information but
if you have to look up the name of a
person that you came across say at the
last last ILP conference it would take
you a long time um to actually go
through all your data Etc on your phone
you have to completely take away your
attention from say the person you're
talking with here at a conference to
look that information up so the input
required to use our phones today for
memory assistance is really very high
for a smartphone and also the output is
um uh effort required is very high um if
a system gives you an entire email or
the entire agenda from the last ILP
conference or something you still have
to like go find a little bit of
information that you forgot that you
were looking for so instead in our
Memorial system we try to make the
system context aware so it can predict
what words you need based on what you
previously said as well as the situation
you're in and we also aim for
conciseness in the output of the agent
so that uh it just gives you the word
that you need and you can be using this
system while you're talking to another
individual without it being uh so
disruptive now of course these memory
augmentation systems are uh potentially
very um uh useful for the elderly
population and in the spring last year
we've been organizing co-design
workshops with older adults um you see
some of them there together with all of
the students in my research group who
were helping facilitate this we had 40
people between the ages of of uh 74 and
94 that were really eager to learn about
generative Ai and to help us um design
and co-design possible use cases of
generative AI that could really help
them in their daily lives um we have a
paper um coming out in the the AI impact
volume that um our president corn Bluth
is uh editing uh on those workshops
one of the um systems that we have been
co-designing with these old older adults
is the meal system it's a little bit
similar to the previous one but it's
more focused on helping an older person
live in their home safely and
independently for longer so what it
consists of is just a camera that you
wear around your neck and a a speech
input output and that camera is constant
ly taking images uh uh pictures
basically of what it is that you're
doing with your hands so if I'm wearing
this it would know she picked up the
water bottle she opens the water bottle
she takes the Sip Etc it takes all these
images translates um uh basically these
images into descriptions using an AI um
Vision model and then puts that in a big
database of all the activities the
person does and that database can be
queried by the person themselves like
they can say where did I put my keys and
the system just has to look where was
were the keys last scene oh she put her
keys down next to the microwave in the
kitchen so we'll see a little demo hi
pal where is my
phone and she hears this spoken in her
ear so your phone was last seen in the
living area near near the gray upholster
chair white charger uh charger table
blah blah blah very
specific so we've been testing this in
people's homes uh 17 of them and um the
system doesn't just help you find
misplaced objects but it also prevents
repeated actions uh these are safety
measures if then rules that either the
older adult themselves or their
caregivers can enter for example you can
enter a rule saying she has to take her
meds before 9:00 a.m. and after 400 p.m.
if she tries to take her medications a
second time the system warns you and
says you took your medication at 8:06 or
it can tell her you haven't taken your
medication it's 9:00 a.m. um the system
also gives you other um safety reminders
uh if you turn the stove on you forget
to turn the stove off um motivated by a
real use case of one of our Cod
designers by the way who had the fire
department at her door after she left
her home with the stove on um uh so it
can U remind you of things like that it
can also reduce caregiver stress and um
uh for example tell the the kids of
these aging uh adults uh that their
mother has had three good meals and went
outside Etc or can even tell the doctor
this person is increasingly forgetting
where they put things not eating healthy
meals Etc so they can monitor but in a
safety preserving way um we've also been
focused a lot on
education a lot of our work is either
younger uh people education or older
adults aging population uh for example
um we know that unfortunately maybe kids
are no longer interested in reading
books um and um we thought well how can
we still let kids learn from say
historical figures like in the figure
there uh Leonardo da Vinci um without
necessarily having to go through um uh
his journals Etc so we trained an AI
system uh to basically um be able to
talk to people about um uh and represent
Leonardo hello I am an AI generated
living memory of Leonardo divin so the
whole system I mean that this is cute
the the VIS visual part of it but it's
actually using rag techniques in AI to
take the primary sources namely
Leonardo's journals to basically as well
as then secondary U sources biographies
about Leonardo to provide um trustworthy
um information and you can just talk to
Leonardo saying okay what did you what
are some things you're famous for and
tell me more about your experiments to
build flying machines and so on we're
actually um soon installing that at a
museum uh the last place where Leonardo
lived uh two hours away from France uh
from uh Paris um where a lot of school
kids visit Etc and they'll be able to
learn about Leonardo that way um another
um system focused on younger people
younger people often have a very hard
time imagining their future and acting
in the interest of this longer term
future like saving money uh studying to
get a better job things like that um so
delayed um uh gratification basically is
is often a human problem and so we
thought can we build an AI that helps
you with that problem with uh thinking
more longterm
um and acting more in your own long-term
interest so we built a system that uh
basically you tell it a little bit about
yourself and your goals and then it
actually creates an older version of you
that you can chat with so you can say I
think I want to become a biology teacher
but maybe the next day you can try
something else and say I think maybe I
want to become a
pediatrician um you tell it about where
you're at in your life what else is
important to you and then we create this
potential future you we tell you this is
not a prediction this is uh uh only one
possible future uh we also give you the
picture to go along with it to increase
the vividness and then you can just talk
to your future self and say well what is
it like to be a biology teacher tell me
about some good and bad experiences what
are the pros and cons what is a typical
day like Etc
we showed together with Hal hfield and
actually the paper is published rather
than under review uh that this increases
uh future self-continuity a
psychological aspect that measures to
what extent people uh take actions in
the uh their long-term interest you can
try this system or your kids can try it
future you. media. mit.edu we have
people from over 90 countries Now using
it they daily frequently coming back to
uh talk to their future self maybe
change their goals Etc we have
prototypes in the area of health and
well-being uh sort of creating systems
with AI that make it easier to make
sense of your own health I won't don't
have time to talk about them uh but this
is one type of activity we do
inspirational uh prototypes and uh
technologies that can help people
with things where they have a real need
um the second activity that we engage in
is uh studies and experiments that shed
light on how AI affects people basically
um so for example you may think well
having a eye at your fingertips improves
people's decision making is that the
case not necessarily we did an experim M
we first uh built a an AI that is honest
and knows the grand truth and it
actually um you a person would read a
statement then they would guess like
whether this statement was true or false
and then we had an AI tell them actually
it's false or true and because of this
reason and we did see that especially if
the AI gives an explanation people do
change their mind and improve their
decision um of the the on the accuracy
of these statements that they came
across not if the AI just said this is
true or false it had to give an
explanation but then we thought well
what if the AI is a malicious Ai and it
actually provides the wrong information
with an explanation that sounds
believable and so this graph here shows
you for false and true headlines of um
newspapers um how person performs in
terms of um assessing accuracy of
newspaper headlines in Gray on their own
in blue with an honest AI but in red
with a um malicious AI so this shows you
that people are very susceptible to
misinformation from Ai and they believe
AI too much basically I believe this is
the case because AI does sound so
believable
I mean it always gives you 10 points for
why something is the way it is and it
seems very uh uh sort of determined Etc
it's a little bit overly confident in
its own um uh answers so we have to be
careful when people uh have an AI at
their fingertips they risk really
reducing their decision-making accuracy
because they become too reliant on a AI
so we've been working on methods that
can prevent this for example um ask the
AI has to First engage the person in
thinking about the headline and that
seems to make a difference and then they
do better so it's sort of people stop
thinking for themselves in many cases
when they have this convenient AI that
seems to know everything anyway um we
also have been looking at things like
how prior beliefs that people have and
their biases uh affect evaluation of AI
and how people work with AI so we gave
three groups uh the same AI system that
would like give mental health advice and
we said you have to um evaluate how good
this system is at giving mental health
advice and one group we told them the AI
is actually caring and the second group
said careful this AI is manipulative and
the third group we just didn't say
anything at all what we learned is that
how people rated the AI after a half
hour conversation with that AI was
significantly different across these
conditions so people who believe that AI
is good and caring they actually would
say the agent is empathetic and
trustworthy and I would recommend it to
someone else and so on people who were
told this agent is um uh manipulative
they actually would uh rate it
significantly lower but they were all
talking to the same system so these are
all factors that I think are not enough
taken into account in AI deployments as
well we should really be sure that
people all start from the same page a
little bit more about their beliefs in
Ai and how useful it is because it makes
significant differences another related
experiment we did was you hear so much
about bias in AI data and how we should
prevent it and I very much uh agree with
that uh but of course what people forget
is that people themselves are biased as
well and these systems these AI systems
work with biased people and so we did
another experiment where we basically
first tested people on their own values
in a certain area and then we actually
gave them an AI that either was neutral
in those in that same area of values or
uh aligned with their biased values or
the opposite of their values uh some of
the areas were for example um
market-based Solutions versus more
Equitable solutions to economic problem
problems this was uh uh one of the areas
uh where we did uh the study in and what
we learned is that the ai's values if
they're aligned with a person if they're
both biased in some way of course the
results of the combined human AI system
is even more biased than the human alone
if the AI had the opposite values of the
person actually that made it more
neutral and that actually down the uh
bias in the result of the system and the
AI working together uh so you can
actually it's interesting you can bias
on purpose an AI system so that it can
compensate for the bias in one of your
employees uh decision making we've also
been looking at the effects of
anthropomorphizing AI this is now a a
four-year-old study but uh back when
Elon Musk still had more uh supporters I
guess um so we thought well what if we
create this deep fake of Elon Musk
everybody knows him and then this
non-existing person and we put um people
in front or or we give people this
virtual system to teach them something
but this could also be to sell them
something or explain something or work
with them and um in our case like I said
we um basically had ver virtual Elon
Musk and this non-existing person same
age gender race Etc they would give the
exact same lecture with the exact same
soundtrack and what we learned about
learning about vaccines this was the
beginning of
Co um so what we learned in our
experiment is that the more people liked
ilon musk and they were told this is not
the real ilon musk the system itself
said I am a virtual Elon Musk here to
tell you about
vaccines the more people liked and
admired Elon Musk the more they thought
this teacher was uh great they wanted to
learn more about vaccines Etc so it had
this huge impact even though it was a
deep fake of Elon Musk and it was the
exact same experience other than that
talking pH
basically uh being different so so these
are all very important issues in
deploying AI that we should be more
careful about um another last study that
we just completed does AI make us more
creative we had three groups one group
uh we asked everybody to write sat
essays actually um they got the same
prompts and one group could use chat GPT
if they wanted one group could use uh
Google search SE and a third group did
not have any tools to write their sat
essay same 30 minutes that you get uh on
the SAT what we noticed we actually
looked at brain activity the group that
wasn't using anything at the bottom here
the bottom row a lot more brain activity
than the group that used Google search
versus the group the group that used
chat GPT very little brain activity in
that group but even worse um we looked
at the topics of the essays that people
came up with we graded them as well we
had teachers gr these essays the essays
actually got comparable ratings from
people but what we noticed was that all
of the people in the chat GPT group they
talked about the same things in their
essays so they were all writing similar
essays while the people that used search
had a a little bit more variety and the
people that came up with these articles
themselves using their own brains they
were much more original this points
again at a possible danger if you deploy
AI in your company and all your people
use that AI to fulfill a certain task or
um basically all of the results will be
more homogeneous but that also means
that you're not improving you're not
like discovering new ways of doing
things Etc and potentially of course
there's the whole deskilling issue that
nobody is actually learning anything
from doing this
work so we need to optimize the behavior
of combined human plus AI systems today
um in AI research and development all
you hear about is training models and
then testing them for certain objectives
and you try to improve accur Y and
efficiency and reduce bias Etc and and
reduce
hallucinations I think it's important
that we actually test AI in the human
context where it's meant to be used and
that we look at different objectives
what is the decision making made by
people plus AI look like also not just
in the short term but in the long term
do we risk that certain skill Etc are uh
being lost and so on so that's the point
that I wanted to make uh with um my uh
presentation here I do believe that AI
is here to stay and I do believe there
are great uh uh there's a great
potential for AI but let's make sure
that we design AI to preserve to augment
people and preserve human agency meaning
and control and that is not happening um
in today's AI developments and
deployments so if you're interested in
this um email me um if you're interested
in getting involved Etc and then I was
also asked so email is Patty media.
mit.edu I was also asked to put in a
plug for this course on AI that MIT
expro um is uh organizing it's a six
week course starting on October 15th
remote course uh where you can learn
from a couple of media lab people as
well as a lot of um seale people about
um AI today and this uh driving
Innovation with generative AI thank
you yeah so I think we have a couple of
minutes for questions also if if there
are
any on oh they're on the screen oh
good yeah yeah so if first question with
lots of
vots how does this affect societal
differentiation do the rich and more
accessible um uh tech oh do the rich and
more accessible get richer um and um who
is making money of all of this Etc so
one we reason why I have always been
very interested in technology and what
it can do for people is that I do
believe it is actually a uh
democratizing or can be a democratizing
force these days a phone doesn't
necessarily need to cost a lot of money
and it is giving access to uh so many
people out there uh to all the wealth of
knowledge uh information Etc uh in the
world world that used to be only
available and accessible to people if
you came or were born in a family uh
with money that valued
education um in this country even that
can afford to often send you to private
school if there are no good public
schools around Etc so I think overall
that um technology is still a
democratizing force that can give uh
make certain opportunities more
accessible uh to a wider range of people
but as the uh question answer uh uh
question asker also asked we have to be
very careful um uh how this is deployed
what the business models are Etc um and
who is ultimately paying uh for all of
this today's phone and a lot of today's
phone services and internet
services uh while they seem free you are
ultimately the one that is paying um you
are paying by giving them your data
making yourself more uh easy to
manipulate um and influence so we have
to think about uh business models for
all of this very much as
well more questions oh yes I'm sorry I
need that memory augmentation
yeah when and where does ethics of these
developments come in is it always
hindsight I think it should not be
hindsight obviously and and um I think
that um by involving uh people like the
Elder um individuals that I uh uh talked
about uh or Target users in the
development of AI it enables us to think
of the ethics um uh sort of and be more
mindful of ethical considerations as we
develop these systems and still can
change them so this is another reason I
think why uh we shouldn't just develop
Ai and then drop it on the world which
is pretty much what Silicon Valley is
doing right now but a reason why we
should do more evaluations to see what
happens what are the possible uh
consequences uh not just for individuals
as a lot of the work that I've shown but
also for communities for society Etc um
it's very important that we um talk
about all of that very early on in um
these uh development
processes yeah we have maybe time for
one
more who decides and how do we decide
what information is misinformation I
don't have a uh necessarily a solution
for that problem it seems that we don't
have a notion of truth anymore
especially in this country but
increasingly we're in other countries as
well um so I think uh that um it's
important that people generally learn to
think more critically and um I think I
do fear that with AI there is a danger
that we actually Outsource critical
thinking to Ai and so there is then
definitely more of a danger for
misinformation to influence us so I
think we have to design interfaces for
working with AI that ultimately improve
people's thinking people's critical
thinking Etc that is not happening today
as I showed with some of our studies if
you um ask are wondering about something
and an AI give gives you this very
elaborate comprehensive 10o onepage
answer you are no longer motivated to
even think about like oh well what do I
think about that issue because it seems
like it's all there and and um so people
become a little bit lazier and I think
we have to rethink interfaces to AI so
that they engage us more in thinking
they think more about what
um I mean uh about or they're developed
more to improve our critical thinking
abilities rather than just providing
answers and that's definitely true in
education of course I wish we had AI
systems for learning that just ask
questions that's the Socratic method no
of teaching you ask really important
interesting questions to make the person
come up with the insights themselves um
so let's think a little bit more broadly
about um interfaces with AI that uh
maybe have some uh of these U desired uh
outcomes thank you what a wonderful talk
thank you so much Ted