there's a second video
question yes s there is for this year's
MIT slan MBA and slan fellows
application we added a second video
response people familiar with the master
of Finance or master of business
analytics application this is something
that's already been implemented for a
few years unlike the video statement
this one requires no prep and is done
inside the application it will appear as
a tab when you complete about 80% of the
application before you actually start
the video you will will get a test run
this is important because you only get
one take when you're ready you have a
sip of your coffee get comfortable
you'll be asked you randomly selected
open-ended question to help settle any
nerves just remember every question is
about your own experience like what
achievement are you most proud of and
why there's no right or wrong responses
you'll have 10 seconds to prepare then
60 seconds to answer have more app
questions let us know below