Welcome back open courseware. So um
we're talking about random variables and
expectation and in fact uh one theme
that I want to mention is that uh you
know a bunch of our probability lectures
will be about how to get tools that give
us a finer grain control of how random
variables behave. At the end of today's
lecture we're going to talk about
variance and later on we're going to
talk about things like tail bounds. All
right. So, let me start off with the
main motivating problem that we're going
to spend, you know, the first part of
class talking about. This is a
challenging problem that um usually the
way I would get students attention was I
would say that uh you know, if you're
going to do tech or finance interviews,
this is the kind of thing that they ask
you during the interviews. But the truth
is that everyone knows that they ask
this. So, they no longer ask this
anymore. But, it's still a really fun
problem to think about. So imagine we
have n students in class and they each
turn in their pet sets we grade them and
then instead of you know figuring out
who's who we just randomly give out pet
sets to different students. Well one of
the probability questions we can ask
which will you know be an excuse to
learn a very important tool is we'll be
interested in what's the probability
that we get everything wrong. So no one
gets their correct P set.
Okay. So we're going to see a a very
important tool called inclusion
exclusion in order to answer this
question. But let's build up towards it
and get some intuition. So the first
thing I want to do is I want to
understand this probability of this very
complicated thing by breaking it up into
simpler events. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to define a bunch of helper
events that'll help me compute this
probability. So I'm going to let AI
denote the event that the IT student
gets their correct P set.
So you can think about event a few
different ways, right? An event is
literally a subset of the sample space.
But that's not how I'm defining it here
because the sample space is gigantic to
write down. So instead, I'm really
defining it in words as a predicate
that's applied to the different
outcomes. So this is one event I care
about. And then the ultimate thing we
care about is we want to understand
the following probability.
We want to look at the probability that
A1 does not happen. The first student
does not get their correct P set back.
The second student does not get their
correct P set back. All the way down to
the nth student also does not get their
correct P set back.
Now we can write this a different way
which will be more convenient for the
way that we're going to think about
this. This is the same thing as one
minus the probability that the
complement of this event happens. And
what is the complement of the event that
no student gets their pet set correct is
that at least one student gets their
correct P set back. So in particular we
take the union of all of these events
either the first student gets the
correct P set or the second student or
the nth student. So this is really the
thing we want to compute today. So let's
think about this in some special cases
which I claim we can always go back to
our friend the vin diagram
to think about what's happening in this
space. So let's write out a simple vin
diagram just in the case where n equals
2. So I have my sample space. I have my
event a1. I have my event A2 and what I
care about is the probability that I
throw a dart and that it lands in the
union of A1 and A2, right? Which is just
this shaded region right here. And we
can just use some basic set theory to
write this because the probability of A1
union A2, well, we can break it up into
the area by each of these different
pieces in the diagram, right? So we can
write it out as the probability of you
know A1. We can add in the probability
of A2. Now this is not a correct
expression. So what's wrong with this
expression? Why is the probability of A1
union A2 not equal to the sum of their
probabilities?
>> Yes.
>> Oh, the intersection is counted twice.
>> Perfect. The intersection is counted
twice. So here what I'm going to do is
I'm going to do a trick which is I'm
just going to subtract off what I've
overounted.
So this is the baby version of what
inclusion exclusion is. I want to get a
handle on the union of these events and
I'm going to first overount and then I'm
going to correct my count. Right? All
right. So nothing too complicated
happened here. And we can try the same
type of strategy but maybe in the n
equals 3 case. So we can write out the
probability that A1 or A2 or A3 happen.
And we can do the same type of trick
where we look at the sum of the
probabilities. We add up the probability
of A1, the probability of A2, the
probability of A3.
But now we have the same problem which
is anything that happens in the
intersection of these events is
overounted. Right? So what I could try
and do is subtract off pair-wise
differences. I could look at the
probability I could subtract off the
probability A1 and A2 both happen. I
could subtract off the probability that
A1 and A3 both happen. And last but not
least, I'll subtract off the probability
that A2 and A3 happen. So this is still
not correct. There's something wrong
with this expression. Let's think about
it, you know, again, in terms of the ven
diagram. I can write out these three
sets A1, A2, and A3.
And if you think about what's happening
in the ven diagram, I've still
miscounted, right? So when I look at the
union of if I look at the probability of
A1 the probability of A2 the probability
of A3 all this region in their
intersection is overounted
and I'm trying to subtract off these
pair-wise intersections. So next I
subtract off this pairwise intersection
this pairwise intersection and this
pairwise intersection. But what's wrong
with my formula now?
Any ideas?
So let's keep track pictorially of how
the algebra connects. Right? So I care
about the union of A1, A2, and A3. And I
looked at the probability of A1, that's
everything in this disc. I looked at the
probability of A2, that's everything in
this disc. And A3, that's everything in
this disc.
That definitely overcounted the region
in between. So what I did was I
subtracted off this pedal right here.
And then I subtracted off this pedal
right here. And then I subtracted off
this pedal right here. So there's a
problem. Anyone see it?
Yeah.
>> Yes. I've completely subtracted the
center. That's exactly right. So in
fact, what I do is I add back in the
center and I'll get an actual correct
expression. So I add in the probability
of A1 and A2 and A3.
Right? So that is a correct expression.
These are our two correct expressions
for n= 2 and n= 3. And we can just use
these expressions to figure out what the
answer is. Right? So let's go back to
our definition of what these events are.
So what is the probability of A1? What's
the probability that if I have two
students and I shuffle them randomly of
who gets whose P set that uh the first
student gets their correct P set back?
It's a half, right? So this is a half.
This is a half too. Now just to make
sure that everyone's awake, what's the
probability that A1 and A2 happen? You
have to be a little bit careful. Yeah,
it's not a fourth.
Uh, can anyone do you want to take a
shot at why it's not a fourth?
So, let's think about what this event
means. The first student gets their pet
set back and the second student gets
their P set back. So, if you think about
this, we could also write this in terms
of conditional probability the same way
we talked about Baze rule last time.
It's the same thing as the probability
of A1 times the probability of A2
conditioned on A1. Say once I tell you
that A1 has happened, which happens with
50/50 chance, then I now change my
sample space and I have to look at the
new conditional probability. So any
thoughts on why it's not a quarter,
not one.
Yes,
I heard a one half over here. So you
want to uh yeah perfect okay so that's
exactly right it's a half right because
if we think about these in terms of
their sample space right there are only
four possibilities in this uh there are
only um there are only two possibilities
in the sample space and once we've
chosen that the first student gets their
correct pet set back there's no choice
but the second student had better get
their correct pet set back as well. So,
one of the things that makes computing
this particular probability so nasty is
that if these things were independent,
life would be very easy. But they're
not. See, when they're independent, I
can multiply all of their individual
probabilities. And we're seeing right
here in this example that that's 100%
false, right? But it turns out that
it'll be morally true, at least when n
becomes larger. So, let's do this
computation right here just to make sure
we're on the same page. What's the
probability of A1? What's the
probability of A2? What's the
probability of A3? They're all a third.
Now, let's be careful. What's the
probability that A1 and A2 happen?
So, how large is my sample space? There
are six possibilities in terms of who
gets whose P set. And if A1 happens, the
first student gets their correct P set,
the second student gets their correct P
set, what can we say?
What's the probability of this?
>> So there's three options for the first
choice.
>> Yes.
>> For the second one, A2 will have two
choices. Yes. Multiply by 12.
>> Uh okay. But what's the probability
here?
>> Yeah.
>> Um would it just be one?
>> 16. Perfect. So you gave a totally
correct way to think about it. Another
way to think about it is that there are
six possibilities in the sample space.
And when A1 and A2 happen, there's only
one outcome that satisfies that
condition. That's where everyone gets
the correct P set because the first
student does and the second student
does. Third student has no choice. They
get it correctly, too. So all of these
other probabilities here are all six.
That's absolutely right. And that'll
give us that you know the total
probability of the event is 2/3.
Okay. So one thing to emphasize is that
these expressions I've written down in
the n equals 2 and the n equals 3 case.
These are valid not just in this
particular problem but they're true for
any collection of events. I've made no
assumptions whatsoever. It's just that
if I had different events they would
have different probabilities and I would
have to compute all of the terms in this
expression. All right. Any questions so
far?
So I think you'll agree that uh we
probably should stop at n equals 3 in
terms of writing down one expression and
reasoning about the ven diagram. These
things just get bigger and more
complicated. But it turns out that
there's a closed form expression without
looking at the vin diagram and reasoning
about the individual slices and pieces
of area that's going to give us the
right answer in general. So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to guess what
that formula is just by trying to extend
the pattern that I've seen for the n= 2
and n= 3 case. That guess will be
correct and we'll check you know we'll
use that formula to compute what the
answer to our challenge problem is. But
then we'll go back and prove that
formula. So that formula is not that
hard to prove once you know what it
ought to look like.
So what I claim and this is called the
inclusion exclusion formula is that the
probability of any union of events A1 A2
doesn't matter. It's not specific to our
particular problem.
We can write this out by over and then
under and then overounting. So we're
going to go through a series of
corrections the same way we did in the n
equals 2 and the n equals 3 case. Our
naive approximation is just going to be
the sum over all of the events of the
probability of the event. We know that
that's not correct in general because
we've overcounted. So what we're going
to do is we're going to subtract off the
pair-wise differences. We're going to
take every pair of events the same way
we did in the n equals 3 case and look
at the probability of any pair of the
events happening ai and aj.
The next term in the expression will fix
the fact that we've underounted. We'll
look over triples the sum over all i
less than j less than k of the
probability of their three y's
intersection
and so on. And the last term in this
expression is just min -1 to the n + 1
times the probability of all of the
events.
So that's the inclusion exclusion
formula. Uh it takes a little bit to
wrap your head around it, but it's very
natural. It's really just this approach
of successively approximating what the
probability of this is by over and then
under and then over and under counting
until you hone in on what the correct
probability is. And all of this holds in
general for no assumptions.
All right. So now it's not so obvious
why this is actually helpful for our
problem, right? Because I took a simple
the state problem and I wrote down this
behemoth of an expression right here.
But what I claim is that all of the
terms that are that happen in this
expression in our particular problem
turn out to be very easy to compute
using the intuition we developed in the
n equals 2 and n equals 3 case. So I'm
going to ask you guys for help and you
guys are going to help me fill in what
this looks like for our particular
problem.
So returning to our challenge problem,
the one we started off with.
Well, in the general n case, what is the
probability that event AI happens?
Who can help me out?
One over n. Perfect. One overn because I
can just imagine that I'm handing back
that students pet first and I selected
randomly. So, I have a one overn chance
of getting them their correct pet set.
Now we know as we go to higher
intersections we have to be more careful
right because that's where the
dependence between these events kicks
in. So that we can't just naively
multiply these probabilities.
So the probability that ai and aj happen
is not 1 over n^2. It's very close to
that. So who can help me out and tell me
what the answer is for this and then we
should see the pattern hopefully.
>> Yeah. 1 n * n.
>> Perfect. That's right. 1 / n * 1 / n -1.
That's exactly right. The way to think
about it is exactly in terms of the way
I wrote it down with the conditional
probabilities. If both of these events
happen, well, I need student I to get
the correct P set, student J to get the
correct P set. So, let's imagine the
thought experiment that we hand back
student I's P set first. they have a one
overn chance of getting the correct one.
And now when they get the correct one,
we only have n minus one possibilities
for the remaining, you know, P set. We
know that student J's P set is still in
that set because I did not get his P
set. And so we have a one over N minus
one chance of, you know, continuing. So
that we actually get both of their P
sets back. And just continuing the
pattern. So the probability that we have
a triple, you know, a i and a j and a k
is just going to be 1 / n * 1 n -1 * 1 /
n - 2. So now we're, you know, almost
home free because, you know, we can plug
in all of these these uh values that
we've computed into our expression. But
we're going to need a little bit of, you
know, counting in order to actually
simplify this expression because one
thing we need to know is okay, all of
these probability of AI intersect aj. We
know what those values are. They're 1 /
n * 1 n minus one. But how many of them
are there?
So that leads us to a very important
concept that we're going to talk a ton
about which is called a binomial
coefficient.
So in particular you know how many
events
of the following form of the form a i
intersect
aj are there right? Each one of these
possible pair wise intersections shows
up in our inclusion exclusion formula.
And I'm going to tell you what the
answer is. Uh in fact, it's such an
important quantity that it's going to
come up all over the place. It has a
special name. It's called the binomial
coefficient.
And it's defined as n * n minus one over
two. That's what we mean when we write
this expression of n choose 2. What this
expression means? So when we look at it,
we say this in words. n choose two is
because you know I have n possibilities
for what i is because it can be anything
from one to n. I have n possibilities
from you know for what j is because it
can be anything from one to n. And what
I'm doing when I look at all of these
events is I'm choosing two things out of
them. A value for i and a value for j.
But the key is making sure that you
count this the right way because app
priori I have n possibilities for the
choice of i and then I have n minus one
possibilities for the choice of j
because it can't be the same as i. But
the key is that I have this extra factor
of two because I've overounted because I
only care about the unordered pair i j.
I don't care about what order they have.
So each pair of events for you know
happens two different ways both for I
being the first thing J being the second
and vice versa. All right so now we're
in good shape. Um in fact uh you know
more generally
if we look at how many terms there are
you know for the kway inter uh yeah for
the rway intersection
you know what we can do is we can define
the n choose r binomial coefficient
which is just defined as n * n minus one
all the way down to n minus r + one over
r factorial. And it's the same type of
intuition. If I'm trying to choose R
values out of n possibilities, I have n
possibilities for the first thing, n
minus one all the way down to n minus r
+ one. But I have to divide by something
to account for the fact that I've
overounted in this expression. So we'll
talk much more about counting actually
uh immediately after this lecture.
That's what we'll be starting next week.
But you know, let's get down to business
and let's actually write out what our
expression is. and something beautiful
is going to happen. So we care about
this probability in the you know the
union of all the ais and if we work out
what this expression is well I have n *
1 overn that just comes from adding up
all these probabilities of the ais there
are n of them and they're each one over
n and then I have my next term my next
term is minus I'll write it out as n * n
minus one over two so they're n choose
two terms There we know that their
probabilities are 1 / n * n minus one.
And let me write out just the next term
and we'll stop there. We also get n
choose 3. So n * n -1 * n -2 / 6 namely
3 factorial. And this is all times 1 / n
* n -1 * nus2. And this expression keeps
going on the same way. I get a higher,
you know, n choose r. I get, you know,
more ns here, right? And the signs are
alternating the same way they are in the
inclusion exclusion formula. And now you
can see I get a huge amount of
cancellation, right? And things simplify
and I'm going to get something very
beautiful at the end of the day. So I'm
going to get that this overall
probability which we computed through
inclusion exclusion is 1 minus I'll
write it as 1 over two factorial
suggestively plus 1 over 3 factorial
minus 1 over4 factorial and so on
and now magic happens. Uh so does this
look familiar from calculus?
Hopefully
anyone brave enough to guess what this
uh infinite sum is.
Yeah, perfect. One over e. That's
exactly right. It's one over e.
So this very simple to state question
it, you know, the e pops out. It's a
very beautiful answer. We it involves
all kinds of things that are going to
show up in more detail in class. So we
have you know this basic building block
and probability the inclusion exclusion
formula. We have the starting point of
counting which is going to be a whole
unit. And then we've connected it back
to um you know to infinite series. We're
going to do a lot with generating
functions later.
Um you know I think it's also good to
try and keep a mental model for what's
going on here because we did do a bunch
of calculations.
It turns out that there's actually a
very simple heruristic.
See in the n equals 2 and n equals 3
case remember we had the subtlety when
we were computing the intersections of
events that events were not independent
that's why that you know half was a half
and was not a quarter but it turns out
there's actually a simple heristic that
is not correct but it works
so caution here this is not a correct
argument but it's more of a back of the
envelope calculation
so the ais
I claim they're almost independ
dependent.
So they're not independent. We already
saw that in the n= 2 case. But what I
claim is that as n gets larger and
larger, then they do become independent.
You can think about this intuitively,
right? If I have an infinitely large
class, you know, the first person, if
they get their pet set back correctly or
not, it really ought to not affect very
much whether the second student does too
because I haven't really changed the
denominator very much. So, it turns out
that really the dominant terms in this
inclusion exclusion formula all happen
for smaller intersections of events
because these probabilities are becoming
astronomically tiny. So wherever the
action is really happening in this
formula, things almost act like they're
independent. So if you just pretend that
they are, then you actually do get the
right answer. So let's look at the
probability that um you know not a1 and
not all the way up to a n. Well, we can
pretend and this is not literally true
that this is the product of all of these
probabilities.
And you know each one of these things
behaves like one minus one overn because
I'm very uh likely to not get my correct
P set back and I'm raising them to the
nth power. And this and the limit as n
goes to infinity really is you know one
over e.
Okay. So inclusion exclusion is actually
a way to make some of these intuitions
precise when you don't literally have
independence but you have something very
close to it. So, any questions? So far,
we've just used the inclusion exclusion
formula. And what I still owe you is I
owe you a proof of the inclusion
exclusion formula.
Everyone following? Yeah. Okay. All
right. So, let's prove this formula. It
turns out that it's really not too hard
to prove once you know what you're
trying to prove.
So let's take our inclusion exclusion
formula that we want to prove.
And there are actually tons of different
proofs of this fact. I'll give you a
particularly simple one which is we're
just going to prove it by induction.
Okay. So what do I have to do when I
prove it by induction?
um you know I have to prove the base
case actually we already proved the base
case because we already proved it
pictorially using the vin diagram so
we're good we proved it for example in
the n equals2 case can check it's true
for n equals 1 2 that's just a
technicality
but now what I want to do in the
inductive step
I'm going to assume
it's true
for some value n. And what I want to
prove
I want to show that then it must be true
for the next largest value. So for n +
one. So that'll be my strategy. And all
we're going to do is we're going to have
to write down, you know, this mess of an
expression and simplify.
So let me make my life easier. I'm just
going to fix my expression right here.
So, let's write down our um you know the
expression we want to show.
We can change all these ns to n plus
one. So, this is the sum from i= 1 to n
+ one. These are all n +1 values and so
on. And this now becomes you know n
plus2 and this becomes n plus1. So, this
is the formula that we want to show.
This is you know what the expression
would be at a larger value of n. And all
I'm going to do is I'm going to collect
terms in this expression so that I can
appeal to what I know that the
expression already holds for some
smaller value of n. And then I'm going
to see whatever is left over. What are
the terms that are left over? And I'm
going to have to interpret those. And
we're going to connect it back to the n
equals 2 case.
So let's collect terms in this
expression and see what's left over.
Okay. So first I'm going to let star
denote uh you know this expression right
here. This is you know the expression
for n + one and I'm going to group this
term uh you know square into different
terms. So let me start off with the
terms which I'm going to call triangle
that I'm just going to pull out my old
inclusion exclusion formula. So what if
I look at the sum from i= 1 to n of the
probabilities of all these ais? You can
see that in my expression for n + one
I'm just removing the probability of a
subn plus one. Right? I'm just removing
that term and I'll only keep the terms
that don't involve the n plus one. Okay?
And then I have some terms here for this
pairs. But my pairs only involve things
up to n. So I'm going to look at the sum
over all i less than j. But I'm going to
put an upper bound that the n + one term
does not show up in this expression.
And I'll have again the probability of
the intersection, the pair-wise
intersection. And I can just continue
this process here. So this the terms
that I've defined in triangle they're
not all the terms that are in square but
they're many of them right and now I
just want to deal with what's left over
so I'll define one more thing and then I
can at least write down an expression so
let's look at you know almost all the
terms that we've left off the table
let's start with the pairwise
intersections so we can look from i= 1
to n of the probability that ai happens
and a nation
right here by putting an upper bound
that I'm only considering things up to
n. I've left off a whole bunch of terms.
Let me look at all the pairs where i is
something and j is n + one. Those are
definitely terms I've left out. So I'm
going to group them together in circle.
And the same way I can look at you know
the next term in circle which is the sum
of you know i less than j all between 1
and n of the probability of the
three-wise intersection a i and a j and
a n + one. Right? All right. So this is
just a whole bunch of bookkeeping. And
let me write down the expression that I
claim connects all of these different
groupings of terms.
At the end of the day, what I care about
is this uh expression I have from
inclusion exclusion for n + one. That's
square. And I claim that this is equal
to all the terms that don't involve n +
one
plus the probability of a n + one.
That's not something that showed up in
my circle expression. And then uh minus
circle. So you can see that I've
actually flipped the signs here, right?
Because originally when I had pair-wise
intersections, I had a minus sign. And
here I've put it as plus.
But it'll be clear why I did this in a
minute. So is everyone okay with this
expression? I claim that we are
basically home once we understand this
grouping of terms. So, now is a good
time to ask questions. Does this make
sense?
Give me a nod. Yes. Okay. All right. So,
let's put everything together now that
we've done the painful work, which is
writing down all these indices. And
let's check that everything works out.
So, I need one more slightly clever
thing. So, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to interpret each of these
expressions. So first of all, triangle I
claim is equal to the probability of a1
union a2 all the way up to a n. Not a n
plus one but a n. Why is that true?
Just to make sure we're paying
attention. Why is that true?
Because we assumed it by induction. This
is literally what we assume by
induction. Remember our strategy is to
assume it's true up to n. And what I did
was I pulled out all the terms in my n
plus one expression and actually we get
the same structure,
right? And so we already know this by
induction. Perfect. Okay. And now we
need to be slightly clever, which is
what I'm going to do is you can see that
all of these events show up all over the
place right here. These intersections
between ai and a n plus1. I'm going to
call these new events. I'm going to
define some helper events. BI. So BI is
defined as the event that AI happens and
A plus one happens. Let's check our
definition. I claim that this expression
right here is B1 intersect uh sorry B I
intersect BJ.
Why is that? Literally the definition of
BI is AI intersect A N plus1. So ai
intersect a n plus1 intersect aj
intersect a n plus1. What happens when I
intersect with a n plus1 twice? It's the
same thing as doing it once. So this is
literally the pair-wise intersection.
And now all of a sudden we're in good
shape, right? Because what I claim now
is that circle has a very nice
definition which is that circle is the
probability of B1 union B2 all the way
up to union B.
That's literally the same structure I
have here. This is the same inclusion
exclusion formula I had before. I just
had to squint and figure out what are
new events which this is expressing
inclusion exclusion on so that's where
the cleverness happened right and now I
can remember what these you know bis are
right so this is the same thing I claim
as the probability that a1 or a2 all the
way up to or a n happens and a n + one
because each one of these things just
takes one of the AIS and intersects it
with a n plus one. So this is really
just deorgan's laws in disguise. Right?
So last piece of you know I won't even
call this cleverness right which is I'm
going to call this event right here C.
You know the real event I care about is
the union of all of the AIS from one to
N plus one. But let me look at C as just
the union of from one to N. Right? and
let's write out what we know and then
we'll see that we've figured out our
answer.
So, writing out, you know, putting
together all of this expression, we have
that square. Well, we broke it up into
different terms. This right here, this
triangle is just the probability of the
event C. That's how we defined what C
was. It was just the first N events.
And then what do we have? We have the
probability
of a n + one and then we subtract off
the probability of c and a n + one.
Right? I'm just put everything we know
together. So does this make sense?
Why am I done?
Yeah. This is the base case. Perfect.
This is the n equals 2 case. So by the n
equals 2 case we know that this is you
know exactly equal to the probability of
c union a n + one and we just have to
remember what c is because c is the
union of all of these a1 up to a n and
then we tack on a n + one and we've
proven inclusion exclusion. So that's
the proof.
So it turns out that once you know what
the expression is supposed to be, the
rest of it is very natural because you
know this expression shows up in
disguise in subp parts of the expression
we have.
All right. So this was one of the
longest proofs we've done. Uh we good?
Yeah. All right.
In fact, I think uh yeah
uh one of the other proofs we're going
to do maybe I will be doing in three
four lectures time is the churnoff bound
which would be so complicated that we're
going to have you diagram it in
recitation. So that'll be fun but you
should already start to think about not
just verifying these things line by line
but why did I present it the way that I
did right? So I didn't literally have to
show you the n equals 3 case right but
we can see that that built up a lot of
intuition for what the terms are doing
you know why they need to alternate in
science and you can see some elements of
you know uh at least how I thought about
how to put these things together
okay so now um I want to tell you one
other brief aside
uh and then we'll move on to our second
topic for today
um you So there was one thing that I
told you about last time
which was when we talked about random
variables I talked about their
expectation
and there was one key property that I
told you about expectations which is you
you add up two random variables you know
f and g and then the expectation of
their sum is the sum of their
expectations. So this was called
linearity of expectation. I proved it
for you. The proof was you know
completely trivial. it was just
rearranging things algebraically.
Um, but what I claim is that it's
actually deeper than it sounds, right?
So, right now, what we went through all
of this work computing was the
probability that no student gets their
correct P set back, right? But you know
another thing I could do through random
variables is I could also ask you know
what about
the expected
number of students who get their correct
P set back. Right? So I had to do all of
this work. I had to tell you about
binomial coefficients prove the
inclusion exclusion formula to answer
you know a very similar sounding
problem. But I claim that you know I
have enough space left on the board
right here to compute what this
expression is right because the way that
we can think about the this random
variable the number right is really is
the sum of a bunch of indicator
variables for different events. I claim
that this you know random variable is
just the sum from i= 1 to n of this
indicator function of ai whether the i
student gets the correct P set back.
Now by linearity of expectation this is
the same thing as the sum from i= 1 to n
times the of the expectation of this
indicator ai. So remember from last time
that this indicator of an event is just
the simple random variable that's one
when the event happens and a zero
otherwise.
So what is the expectation of the
indicator of an event is just the
probability that that event happens. So
each of these things we already computed
it. It's one over n. So I'm going to get
the sum from i= 1 to n of one overn. And
that's the same thing as one. So the
expected number of students you that the
number of students you expect to get the
correct pet set back is one. So this is
something important to keep track of is
that it turns out that when you're
dealing with expectations, you don't
have to worry about all of this stuff
about the dependency between the events.
you know whether they're independent or
not.
And this is a really unique property of
expectations. It won't be true when we
get to other things like variance, but
they'll still be helpful expressions we
can do that can make our life easier for
computing.
Okay, good.
Let's go on to the second part of
today's lecture where what I want to do
is I want to, you know, dig a bit more
into random variables. We've talked
about the expectation of random
variables and what I want to do is I
want to introduce concepts like the
variance of random variables. We're
going to use these things extensively.
Um so let me start off first with um you
know just a bit of a reminder about some
of the cool things you can do with
random variables.
So last time I told you this example of
meanantime to failure that was you know
one interesting illustration of the
concept of expectation
you know if something is failing
independently like a computer every day
you know what's the expected number of
days uh that we expect to go before we
actually have to replace that part. So
remember just as a reminder
we had this concept of you know
meanantime to failure and you know if we
had the CPU fails
independently
with probability P each day.
Then one of the quantities we cared
about was the expectation of t which is
the failure time for the computer. So
how often do we have to uh replace it
and we wrote out this expression for it
that we simplified and we showed that
the answer was one over p which makes
sense because if I have a coin that's
fair you know the expected number of
flips until I get my first heads is two
and you know the smaller p is the larger
this expectation will be. So this was
just an algebraic illustration of what
we can do with uh the definition of
expectation. I want to try a harder
problem that builds off of meanantime to
failure.
So you know let's consider the following
experiment. What I'm going to do is I'm
going to ask you know students in a huge
class. Okay. I'm going to ask them their
birthday
and I want to know how many
until we get all 365
days
as answers.
This is a leap year. So I guess we could
ask a slightly different question this
year. But uh we're going to assume that
everyone's birthday is uniformly at
random, right? And you know this is
another very basic probability question.
It sounds a bit like meanantime to
failure, but there's a twist on it,
which is we don't care about one thing
happening like our first heads or the
failure of a computer. We care about a
coverage condition that we cover all of
the different days. So a lot of times
you'll hear this colloially referred to
as the coupon collector problem. You
know, we could ask this not with 365 as
the number of things we want to cover,
but some other parameter n. And you
could imagine that, you know, every
weekend you get a coupon in the paper
and it's uniformly at random for which
coupon it is. And what you'd like to
know is, you know, how many papers do
you have to look at until you get all of
the possible coupons, right?
So uh but already we have you know some
powerful tools for how to address this
question. That's really not a
straightforward question until you see
the trick.
You see if you think about what I did in
this example of um computing the the
expected number of students who get
their correct P set back. There was
already something very powerful we had
which was that when I have a random
variable that I care about this random
variable being the number of students
who get the right answer. Well, what I
can do is I can decompose it into
simpler building blocks that are easier
to understand. So that's what I did
there because I broke up this random
variable which is the number right into
counting over all of these events just
as a sum indicator variables. Here we're
gonna have to do the same type of trick,
but we're going to do it in a more
clever way, right?
So, same type of trick in action. So,
we're gonna write t, which is our time
where we collect all of these coupons or
get all of these birthdays as a sum
of simpler
random variables.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
write t is t0 plus t1
all the way up to t 364.
And you know ti
just to be clear is the number of steps
between
the i distinct
day
and the i plus first. So what's going on
is we have a progress measure of how
many distinct birthdays we've seen. It
doesn't matter to me what particular
days they were because everyone's
birthday is uniformly at random. But I'm
going to care about, you know, in this
progress measure, how much time do I
have in between taking a step? So, you
know, at the beginning, this might
happen very quickly because, you know,
in the beginning, I've seen no
birthdays. I ask a student and I'm
definitely going to cover a new day I
haven't seen before. But towards the end
when I've covered all, you know, 364 out
of 365 days, it's potentially going to
take me a while in order to get that one
remaining distinct birthday. I haven't
seen to go from covering 364 to covering
365.
So this is a big trick, you know,
otherwise it would not be at all obvious
how to do this. Yes.
>> Exactly. Sorry. number of steps meaning
the number of students. So what this
means is like let's just break down what
this expression means. So I is zero
here. So this would be the number of
steps that I number of students I have
to ask in order to get to the first
distinct day and that's clearly one. But
then as I go later it's the number of
students I you know I just got my new
birthday. I've covered I days. I ask
another student. I ask another student.
I ask another student. How long do I go
until I get a new birthday out of that
set? Any other questions? This is a big
trick. It's hard to know that this is
what you're supposed to do without
seeing this trick before, but it's a
trick we're going to use all the time.
So now, um, you know, by linearity of
expectation, we know that the
expectation of T is the sum from ials 0
to 364
of the expectation of all of these TI's.
This is literally just using linearity
of expectation. We know t is the sum of
all of these TI's. That's how many days
I have to how many students I have to
ask, right? Until I cover all of the
birthdays. And what I claim is that this
expectation of TI is very easy to
compute,
you know. So let's think about what
happens with this expectation of TI.
Let's draw a picture in case it's
helpful.
So, you know, we can think about
all of the different birthdays. We have
365 of them.
And we've seen I different birthdays so
far, right? And we're asking how long
until we see the next distinct birthday.
So, we've seen all of these different
birthdays in this region. You know,
because each dart I'm throwing is
uniformly at random. I can just pretend
that all the birthdays I've seen are all
at the beginning. Nothing's going to
change. And what I'm asking is how long
when I throw a dart that randomly hits
one of these segments until it actually
is outside the set I've seen so far. So
we know that this probability that any
particular dart lands outside this set
is just 365 minus I over 365.
This makes intuitive sense. You know,
when I equals zero and I haven't seen
anything, I'm definitely going to get a
new birthday. When I've seen all but one
of the birthdays, I have a one over 365
chance. And so now we're in good shape
because, you know, from the meanantime
to failure argument, we know exactly
what this expectation of t is. It's
equal to, you know, the sum of one over
these pis. So in the beginning, we just
have 365 over 365.
Then we have 365 over 364
all the way down to adding up 365 over 1
which is 365.
So it turns out that the answer for this
you can just compute it numerically.
It's about 6.47
times 365.
So I have to ask about you know 6 and a
half times as large a class as you know
I would need in principle to cover all
the distinct days. In fact, you know,
the same argument works even with 365
replaced by n. So, more generally for
the coupon collector problem, you'll get
n / n + n / n minus one all the way down
to adding n. That's the sum of i = 1 to
that's n * the sum of i= 1 to n of 1 /
n. And it turns out that this is equal
to n times the nth harmonic number. It
behaves like n login. So this gives you
a very good back of the envelope
calculation for a lot of you know
randomized things that uh this coupon
collector problem sort of shows up all
the time. So basically the 6.47 just
comes from you know taking the natural
log of the appropriate domain size.
Okay, any questions?
Good.
All right.
So, we've done a whole bunch of examples
uh today. So, we did, you know, the pet
set problem. We did this coupon
collector problem. These are really
important examples to build your
probabistic intuition. Uh I want to tell
you a little bit more about some
powerful general tools and then we'll
call it a day. Um so, we're going to do
a little bit more theory. The same way
that last time I told you about random
variables and their expectation, I want
to tell tell you about the variance and
you know what happens when I take the
expectation of products of random
variables.
And in fact the first thing I'm going to
do
is the same way that I defined the
notion of two events being independent,
I'm going to tell you what it means for
two random variables to be independent.
and then we'll see you know when two
random variables are independent what
kinds of computations become easier
using that.
So here's our key definition that we're
going to explore for the rest of what's
left in lecture. So remember we have
this notion of a random variable which
is just a function from the outcome
space to a real value. And now imagine I
give you two random variables f and g.
Well, we're going to say that they're
independent
if
the following events are independent.
So, let's look at all the x's where f
ofx equals alpha
and let's look at all of the x's where g
of x equals some beta. All right, so a
bunch of things are happening here,
right? So I have a random variable which
remember takes an outcome and maps it to
a real value. So f and g are my two
functions that map outcomes to real
values. What I can do is I can use a
random variable to define an event. So
now I'm going the other direction.
Before what I told you about was how to
take an event and define a random
variable. That took us to the notion of
an indicator variable and we use that in
that computation. Now I'm going the
other direction which is I'm saying
imagine I give you a random variable. It
takes on a whole bunch of discrete
values and what I'll do is I'll chop up
the domain the sample space into the
parts that correspond to different
values of that random variable. So I'm
going the other direction. I'm taking a
random variable and defining an event
because the end of the day this is just
a subset of the outcome space. So this
is an event that's defined based on the
choice of alpha. I get a different event
for different choice of alpha. This is
an event that's defined based on the
choice of beta and g. And what I want is
that I want these two events are
independent, which is just the same
definition of independence we had
before. I want the probability of the
intersection of those two events to be
equal to the product of their
probabilities. That's literally how we
defined independence of events. And what
it means for random variables to be
independent is this more stringent thing
which is I want that for any choice of
alpha and beta that induces some choice
of an event one for one random variable
one for the other I want every choice of
alpha and beta to define two events that
are independent.
Does this make sense? So this is a more
complicated definition that we had
before because we have one quantifier
here. So checking independence for you
know events is very easy. You just
compute a bunch of probabilities and
check that the equation holds. Now
computing independence for random
variables is trickier because in
principle you have to worry about every
possible value of alpha and beta and
compute all of those probabilities.
Okay.
Nevertheless, it's a very powerful
notion. Okay.
Uh, one thing you can do is let's just
do a simple consistency check.
Sorry for going back and forth and back
and forth, but you know, we can look at
the indicator
of two different events A and B. Those
are random variables. What does it mean
for those functions to be independent? I
claim that those functions, those random
variables are independent if and only if
their events are. So this just means
that our definition makes sense, right?
Because we're thinking of random
variables as a generalization of events
because I can have not just 01 values,
but I can have any real values. But my
definition better at least recover what
my definition was in the case of events.
And that's true. You can check that if
you you know create two random variables
based in the indicator functions of two
different events that they will meet
this condition if and only if the
corresponding events meet that condition
too because you really only have to
check you know alpha and beta being zero
and one and you can check that
everything works out. So that's good. So
we have a a reasonable notion of
independence.
Um what I want to work up today is some
idea of you know why this is powerful.
And I want [clears throat] to compare
and contrast this the linearity of
expectation that we've already used to
great effect. So here's the key lema
which we'll prove. The proof is you know
pretty boring uh but it's a very
powerful lema. The proof is really just
about uh massaging the definitions the
same way we had for linearity of
expectation. What I claim is that if we
have two random variables f and g, so
let's say f and g are independent random
variables. Then what I claim is that the
expectation of f ofx times g ofx is
equal to the product of their
expectation.
Okay, so that's the lema I want to prove
and I promise you the proof is very easy
but this is still a very powerful lema.
So usually when I'm trying to learn
something new uh I try and connect it
back to something that I already
understand.
So let's think about the special case
again where you know these random
variables are indicators of events. This
is an indicator of an event A. This is
an indicator of an event B. Right? So
you know what would the expectation of
the indicator of event A look like? It
would be the probability of the event A.
What would the expectation of the
indicator function of the other event
look like? It would be the probability
of the other event. So this is the
product of their probabilities. What is
that supposed to be equal to? What
happens if I take two indicator
functions of two different events A and
B? What do I get? What is that? That's a
whole bunch of English to parse. I take
the indicator of two different events A
and B and I multiply the indicator
random variables.
What is that? Can anyone describe that
to me in English? Yeah.
Yes. Exactly. So, uh the product of them
is literally the indicator of the
intersection of the events and then the
expectation of that as you said is the
probability that both of them happen. So
this recovers something we already know
right which is lit literally this is the
definition of what um you know
independence is for events. So this is
just a generalization building a more
general theory of what's going on. All
right so the let's prove this thing
that's tedious. Let's just write out the
definitions and see what happens.
So I've got the expectation of f ofx and
g ofx. Well, whatever this mess is
inside, that's a random variable. It
takes in an outcome X and it spits out a
real value that's given by the product
of the values of f and g. So I can take
its expectation just by you know
literally using the definition of the
expectation. It's the sum over all x's
in the sample space of p of x the
probability of that event times f ofx
times g ofx. I haven't done anything
here. I've just literally used the
definition. Whatever this monstrosity
is, it's a random variable and this is
the definition of what its expectation
is.
And now what we're going to do is here's
the one clever part is we're going to
break up the sum into different pieces
in a way that corresponds to you know
clearly we have to use this definition
of independence otherwise the thing is
false. And independence is fundamentally
about breaking up the sample space into
different pieces. So I'm going to break
up that sum into different pieces
mimicking the way that I've broken it up
in this definition. So literally the way
that I'm going to do that is it's going
to be the sum over alpha alpha and beta.
And that should sound familiar.
And then the sum over all x that are in
the sample space but moreover where f
ofx is equal to alpha and g ofx is equal
to beta. So I'm just breaking this sum
up into different pieces different
contributions. And then I have the same
thing, right? I have um the probability
of that outcome. I have f ofx. I have g
of x. Except because I've broken this
event up, I know what f ofx is and I
know what g of x is. They're alpha and
beta respectively. So this is the same
thing as alpha * beta times the
probability
of x.
Okay, so now we're in good shape and
we're just going to have to rearrange
what this sum is.
So let's massage the sum until it uh it
stares us in the face how to appeal to
independence. So this sum is the same
thing as
sum over alpha and beta
time alpha you know of alpha* beta times
the probability that f ofx is equal to
alpha and g of x is equal to beta.
So what have I done here? Right? This
alpha and beta, I can actually just pull
it outside this sum. And when I pull
this alpha and beta outside the sum, I'm
left with the sum, you know, of all
these probabilities of these atomic
outcomes. And this is really just an
event, right? It's the event that f ofx
equals alpha and g ofx equals beta. So I
get the probability of that event,
right? And now I can appeal to
independence because this is the same
thing as the sum over alpha and beta.
Again, alpha times beta. But now I can
break up these probabilities. f ofx=
alpha times the probability that g ofx
equals beta. That's what it means for
the two events that I've defined here to
be independent is literally that the
probability of their intersection is the
product of their probabilities.
And so now I'm in good shape because
what I can do is I can turn this into
two different sums. The sum over alpha
and the sum over beta. And I can pull
out terms that don't depend on beta. And
I claim that this is the same thing as
the sum over alpha of alpha times the
probability that f ofx equals alpha
all times the sum over beta of beta
times the probability that g ofx equals
beta.
So I really haven't done much other than
figure out this way to break up the
sample space so that I can appeal to my
definition. But the rest of it is just
algebra. So what is this expression
right here?
Any ideas? This wasn't quite my original
definition, but uh hopefully you should
see that it's the same.
What property of the random variable f
is that expression computing?
Yeah, expectation. That's right. So my
original definition for expectation was
the sum over x's in the sample space.
Here I'm doing the same thing, but I'm
collecting all the x's together that
have f ofx equal alpha and you know
arranging it that way. So this is
exactly just another definition for the
expectation of f ofx. And likewise this
right here is the expectation of g ofx.
Awesome. So we're done. Any
questions?
Okay, let's do a diagnostic question.
This is definitely the way I like to
think about these things. Uh, I just
proved something for you.
You know, [clears throat] learning about
proofbased math, especially learning
about how to write it, isn't just about
verifying line by line what I do on the
board. It's about trying to understand
why I organized my proof that way and
also where I use the different
assumptions. Right? So the critical
thing here for this lema which is
different than linearity of expectation.
See linearity of expectation I used
nothing.
For this lema, I use something I use
something very strong, which was that f
and g are independent. And we talked
about how it's a bit of a pain in the
neck to actually verify independence
because you have to check it over all
alpha and beta. Um, did I really need
that uh property of independence? Right?
So obviously your intuition is that I
did use it crucially. So can you think
of
an example
where we have two random variables f and
g but f and g are not independent
and where this lema fails where the
expectation of the product
is not equal to the product of their
expectations.
So if you're able to push back, you
know, all of the symbols and think about
this intuitively, this would be very
easy.
But it's not always that easy.
Can anyone is anyone bold enough to
think of an example where I have, you
know, two fing two random variables that
violate my assumptions of the lema? They
are not independent. And the conclusion
of my lema is false too.
Yeah.
>> Yes. Perfect. Let me raise you one which
is let's just define f to be the
indicator function of some event A and
let's let G be the indicator function of
the complement of A. That would do the
trick, right? So maybe these both have
some nonzero probability of happening.
The product of their probabilities is
non zero. But you know what's the
product of them? Well, that's the
indicator function of both events
happening. And no event and its
complement can both happen. So we're
done. So these are not independent and
the statement is false. So you know,
especially as we go to more and more
general abstraction, it's always good to
keep in some mental model that helps you
navigate what's going on.
So, we've only got a few minutes left,
which is perfect because I want to
introduce you to uh one last concept
which is also powerful. This is the
thing I've been promising you, which is
the notion of variance. So, that's our
last topic for today. And I'll tell you
one basic but very powerful property of
variance
um that we're going to see at length in
the SQL when we get back to probability
when we talk about tail bounds and we
can already see some of the intuition.
So first let me just define what the
variance is. It's another property of a
random variable. So the variance
of a random variable is the following
quantity. We write it as var of f. It's
the expectation
of f ofx minus the expectation of
f ofx
squared. All right. So a bunch of things
are happening here, right? So this
whatever it is, it's a scaler, right?
That's whatever the average value is for
the random variable. I'm creating a new
random variable that shifts the average
down to zero. So the average of this new
random variable is zero. And when I
square this thing, I'm measuring how
spread out it is. So the variance, as
the name suggests, is how much you
expect the random variable to vary. It's
a very coarse grained uh you know way to
define how much a random variable
varies. And we'll develop a lot of finer
grain tools that'll give us a better
understanding what's going on. But
already we'll be able to use this to
great effect.
Uh so that was my informal claim is that
it measures
how spread out
a random variable is.
Let me give you a basic fact
which is easy to show. So first of all I
claim that the variance of f is non-
negative. That's true for any random
variable.
Can anyone argue why this is true so
that I don't have to prove it?
There should just be a one sentence.
Yeah,
>> that's right. That's right. Let's just
unpack what this is. It's the
expectation of a random variable. So,
what we do is we take a weighted average
according to the probabilities in the
sample space of the values that this
random variable takes on. But the random
variable I care about is this thing
that's really, you know, it's it's the
outcome of squaring the thing. So it's
always non- negative. The weighted
average of a bunch of non- negative
things had better be non- negative. In
fact, um, let me raise you one. I claim
that not only is that statement true,
and your explanation was perfect. I
claim that when the variance of a
function is zero, there's something very
strong we can say about the random
variable. So what happens when the
variance of a of a random variable is
zero? Yes, it's constant. That's right.
So f is constant value.
So it doesn't matter what point you give
me what outcome in the sample space,
there's always one fixed value and it
only takes on that value. That's exactly
right. Now there's um one other
alternative formula for the variance
that's sometimes helpful. you know, uh,
in some cases, one is a better starting
point than the other. They're both
equivalent, but it it pays to just keep
both in mind and use whichever one is
easier. So, let me give you another
alternative expression for the variance.
And then let me tell you a powerful
property of the variance that that kicks
[clears throat] in when we have
independence.
So an alternative completely alternative
formula
is that the variance of f is equal to
the expectation
of f ofx squared minus
of f f ofx but with the square on the
outside. Okay. And this happens because
you know from our first expression
when we expand out the square we'll get
that the variance of f is equal to the
expectation of f ofx quantity squared
minus 2 times
the value of the function times the
expectation of the function.
uh and then plus
the expectation of f ofx squared
and now we can appeal to linearity of
expectation and life becomes good. So we
have the expectation of f ofx with the
square on the inside. Well this part
right here is not a random variable.
That's a scalar. So it really just pulls
outside of the expectation in a nice way
and we get another e of f ofx. So we get
minus two copies of the expectation of f
ofx squared with the square on the
outside. We add one more copy back in
and in total we're just subtracting one
copy with the square on the outside.
So this just uses the you know
properties of the expectation and
linearity of expectation but this gives
us our two different definitions.
And now uh we can say
the last property that we're going to
show for today and I'll tell you why
this property is so important.
[clears throat]
So I claim that if we have two functions
f and g that are independent then the
variance of their sum
is equal to the sum of their variances.
So this is definitely not true in
general.
This looks a bit like linearity of
expectation, but it's really very
different, right? Because linearity of
expectation held always. This only holds
when f and g are independent.
So you can prove this. Let's just do a
quick proof and then I'll tell you about
some cool applications.
So by definition,
well the variance of f ofx plus g ofx,
well we can write it out from our first
definition.
We add up f ofx plus g ofx.
We subtract off their expectation. And
then we're going to regroup terms and
we'll see what happens. So we subtract
off the expectation of their sum f ofx
plus g ofx
and we take the square of this entire
thing. Right? That's literally the
definition.
And now what we can do is we can appeal
to linearity
of expectation
and we'll get that this entire thing
is equal to well let's group together
terms. It'll be the expectation
of f ofx minus the expectation
of f ofx
plus
g ofx minus its expectation of g ofx
and this entire thing is squared. So all
I'm doing is remember the square is
happening outside all this mess. I'm
pushing the expectation through. So this
is the expectation of f ofx plus the
expectation of g ofx. I'm pulling one
term, you know, with f and one term with
g. But now what I can do is I can expand
the square. And if I expand the square,
I'm going to get this quantity squared.
That's literally the definition of the
variance of f. I'm going to get this
quantity squared. That's the variance of
g. And I'm going to get cross terms. But
now the key thing is that that cross
term is zero because of independence. I
have the expectation of this times this
because these things are independent.
It's the product of their expectations
and each individual thing is zero. So
that's really the last part of the
argument. I can write that out a bit
more precisely.
So the key thing is really what happens
with the cross term. So when we get this
cross term that looks like 2 * the
expectation of f ofx minus e of f ofx
times
g ofx minus the expectation of g ofx.
Then what's going to happen is by
independence we can write this out as
the product of their expectations.
And this is all times the same thing.
The expectation of g of x minus its own
expectation.
And now we're in good shape because
literally by linearity of expectation
this is zero. Right? You know it's
important to not lose track of what
these different things mean. This term
right here is just the scalar shift. And
what's going on is I'm just, you know,
shifting so that the mean of my random
variable is zero. And the fact that
they're independent allows me to write
it as a product. So that's exactly why I
get zero. So we can put together all
these pieces and we have this beautiful
statement that the sum of the variances
uh you know for two independent random
variables adds when we add up the two
random variables. So I'll leave you with
a closing example uh which we're going
to talk about in much more detail.
There's a super important example from
this that's you know becoming very
relevant these days which is about
polling. So we might have you know some
particular uh events that we care about
which are things like you know the
probability any particular person votes
one way or the other and we care about
something like what the sum of those
events are going to be because we want
to forecast elections. So it turns out
that the way that you can do this, you
know, at least in principle is if you
pick a random person and ask them who
they're going to vote for. Well, that'll
give you, you know, some estimate of
what the underlying baseline probability
is. And then you can do this not for one
person, but for many people. So when you
look at that estimator, it ends up being
the sum of independent random variables.
And the fact that that converges very
quickly to the true average for the
random variables as we'll see really
comes out of this fact that the variance
adds instead of increasing by a larger
quantity. So we'll talk a lot more about
that uh in later lectures when we talk
about things called concentration
bounds. But I just want to give you a
hint of where we're going with these
tools and we'll practice a bunch of you
know explicit computations with variance
to get a handle first before we go to
tailbounds. Uh so we'll stop there.