good morning everybody Welcome to the
mpg primer today our speaker today is
Karen
gamela Karen is a director of
computational biology in the data
science platform at the broad where he's
also an Institute scientist Karen has
extensive experience in the development
and application of cloud-based data
processing methods and automated
analyses for third generation sequencing
data he currently leads the data
Sciences platforms along reads Group
which aims to transform the genomics
landscape by undertaking long read
sequency of human and infectious disease
genomes he earned his uh PhD in genomic
medicine and statistics from the
University of oord Oxford's welcome
trust Center um for human genetics and
he also completed post-doctoral studies
at the Oxford Big Data Institute he
co-chairs the nih's all of us long read
working group and also the nih's
Gabriella Miller kids first long read
working group we're both undertaking I'm
sorry which are both undertaking the
discovery and Analysis of previously
unseen variation in about 20,000 diverse
individuals for population genomics and
rare disease
applications um and today he's going to
be doing a part two um on Long read
sequencing which I'm really excited
about um I've had the chance to play
with long read data myself and to load
it into igv and to keep scrolling and to
see the keep going is um it's amazing so
really excited uh Karen take it away
right Fant please ask questions along
the way thank you all right fantastic
can everyone hear
me that's fantastic in fact talk to me
after the meeting uh there I don't know
if you've joined the the the working
group but we
have
okay now they found them okay more than
happy to to to um talk about it after
the after the meeting but that's very
exciting right um okay um uh first of
all thank you for having me back uh I
think I was here in June July something
like that uh and I gave what was what
you know I had intended to be a a a a
fairly comprehensive overview of of long
sequencing um there was so much to talk
about that I didn't get to everything so
I'm very happy to have this opportunity
to come back and share some of the
things that I uh didn't get to speak
about last time if you didn't see the
talk last time I'm just going to leave
the slide up for a second you can go to
the QR code it'll take you to uh the
Youtube video uh but last time I talked
about uh in general how the pack bio and
Oxford nanoport platforms worked uh I
talked about some of the sort of basic
operations in terms of alignment of
reads to a a reference sequence uh I
talked about snip and indel and
structural variant calling and copy
number variant calling uh and a few
other topics uh uh along the way uh I'm
if people did see that talk I'm more
than happy to answer questions about it
here uh along the way um uh but I'm
going to I'm going to skip some a lot of
the details that I presented in that in
that last presentation so please if you
are new to Long read sequencing and
starting to you know just trying to get
a handle on the data um you know go
there and and I you're more than welcome
to reach out to me as well um I think my
email address is probably somewhere on
this slide um uh but that's what I'm
here for I'm I'm more than happy to to
to um answer questions and get people
acquainted with this data uh today I'm
going to talk about um a few things I'm
going to talk about um just a a quick
review of how the instruments work not
quite as in depth as I went in last time
and I'm going to talk about um three
additional topics uh the first is some
updates uh to these instruments it's
only been a few months and there are
still uh you know exciting updates to to
both of these platforms is how fast this
field is moving uh I'll also talk about
methylation calling which I didn't get
to in the last uh talk and I will talk
about some of the targeted sequencing
capabilities uh of the of the nanopore
platform so let's quickly recap the the
Bas uh Basics how what are we what are
we doing with long reads what are we
talking about when we talk about long
reads I think most of the audience here
will probably be familiar with short
read sequencing 150 to 200 uh bases
paired end format uh kind of the
Workhorse of our our field today but
with you know W with limitations uh
right there are um you know places in
the genome particularly uh repeat
expansions uh um low complexity sequence
in general or just places in the in in
the reference that are uh quite
Divergent from the sample of Interest
where short reads just fail to align and
fail to give you a a uh a decent picture
of what variation at that Locus looks
like long ra sequencing about two orders
of magnitude longer in in read lengths
uh and with that comes the ability to
map much more confidently uh across
repetitive regions across uh large
structural variants uh being used to
help uh create new versions uh you of
the uh of um reference sequences with
all of the gaps closed as the telr to
telare project and related the human
Pang genum reference Consortium we've
been using them for the all of us
project to get a clearer picture of
structural variation in a population
genetic setting been using them in in in
Gabriella Miller kids first to get a
clearer picture of potentially causal uh
variation you namely structural
variation repeat expansions in in rare
disease
contexts uh you know a few years ago the
broad had one of these instruments as a
prototype just for uh some
experimentation now it's uh you know
become it's become a a full-on
production device I I don't remember how
many uh instruments are in uh in BCL it
it it changes as instruments get
upgraded and swapped out but uh I think
there are somewhere between five and 10
of the the latest instruments and a uh
nanapur instrument as well uh I think
that makes the Bro the largest long
breed Sequencing Center in the world at
the moment uh but I wouldn't be
surprised if those you know those
numbers fluctuate over time what are we
doing with these structural variants I
like this example this is from one of my
colleagues frit sedc uh at uh Bor
College of Medicine uh and in this uh in
these two images he depicts very clearly
what the value is of long read
sequencing versus short read sequencing
so the top track is aluminous sequencing
on the left a deletion on the right an
insertion on the left you see this
deletion uh you know kind of clear as
day in the uh in the short read data but
what what you're seeing is just an
absence of sequencing data it's actually
hard to distinguish that between uh you
know a a true deletion versus a place
that just didn't get any any coverage
whatsoever paraden reads helps with this
but you can see the uh the the the reads
in this igv screenshot that are color
something other than gray indicate that
the pair the mate of this uh the this
this end of the paired end read is
mapped somewhere that you wouldn't
expect right so even with that paired
information it could be hard to
reconstruct uh deletions of a of a
certain size whereas the 20,000 base or
so reads that you get from both P bio
platforms and nanopore platforms read
through that without ambiguity right you
know that this is not a coverage loss
you know that there is an actual uh uh
deletion at this Locus as evidence from
the reads same thing with the insertion
the illumin data there seems to be some
signal in the in the paradin reads uh
but again there are a lot of mismapped
pairs and it's really unclear it's
actually surprising ly unclear from this
example what is going on here uh hack
bio sequencing Ox anur sequencing
identify the insertion uh you know
fairly easily so I you know I I I spent
my PhD and my postto trying you know
desperately to reconstruct lo I like
this from short read sequencing about
halfway through my PhD I got long read
sequencing and it sort of obviated the
past three years of work uh which is
annoying at the time but really exciting
today when you see these problems that
have been you know so difficult to get
traction on for the past you know 10 or
15 years just appear in your data it's
it's really wonderful to
see how do the instruments work I
usually present this in in the order of
aluminous sequencing P bio sequencing
and and nanopore sequencing uh just
let's review very quickly how aluminous
sequencing and you'll see why I present
it in this order so aluminous sequencing
you could think of it as as as kind of
trying to uh uh trick a trick a
polymerase enzyme into doing a dirty
work here right uh you start with uh
single stranded uh DNA fragments to
which you uh attach sequencing adapters
complimentary adapter is attached to the
flow cell as you flow in all of the the
the fragments uh they bind to places on
that flow cell perform PCR extension
Bridge amplification in order to
generate a local CL cler of identical
templates uh those are then dissociated
into single stranded fragments uh those
form clusters and uh one cycle at a time
you flow in nucleotides uh with
fluorescent labels that attach to the um
the the the next available uh you know
occupancy spot in the in the single
stranded fragment pause image the
superposition of uh Flor fors at each
cluster register is a strong enough
signal that a camera can read that out
and call a base and then you proceed to
uh uh um uh flush the uh the Flor for
from the previous cycle at the next one
in stop and go you are essentially uh
you know sequencing uh this Bas one at a
time sequencing by by
synthesis uh pack bio sequencing is also
hijacking uh a polymerase in order to do
it dir work but rather than forming
these colonies of identical templates uh
the flow cell is designed uh with small
Wells that only house ideally one
polymerase enzyme so the the the correct
operation of these Wells is a single
polymerous enzyme affixed to the uh to
to to the bottom of the well sequencing
one read at a time and again we are FL
uh we're flowing in fluorescently
labeled nucleotides now the key
difference here between uh alumina
sequencing which is using a cluster of
templates in order to register a signal
versus Pac bio which is using uh
literally one one read not a not a
colony of reads not a cluster of reads
um uh is the fact that the the the label
nucleotides are freely diffusing in this
uh thermal bath except when they are
being incorporated into the uh the
single strand template at that time the
polymerases holding that PO that the um
that uh nucleotide in a a single spot
for much longer than the mean diffusion
time of the nucleotides that is enough
you know plus the construction of the
well in order to amplify light that is
enough for a a movie camera to image the
read in real time so what you get is a
readout that looks like the the the the
one below where you have um uh light
intensity the fluoresence of each
nucleotide uh in four different colors
but you also have uh a a a number of uh
kinetic uh readouts you have how long
did that pulse last what is the time
between the
pulses uh usually refer to as pulse
width and interpulse distance right so
you're getting more information you're
reading out this information in real
time and then the instrument based
caller is distilling that into into
nuclear type calls to get accuracy again
one of the ways that you get accuracy
from aluminous sequencing is that you
you have a colony of of reads that all
say the same thing so most of the Flor
four should agree with one another and
register a strong signal uh that signal
th those those colonies uh shrink as you
do sequencing just as you do the the
flush with each cycle some of those re
some of those fragments will wash away
and so the signal attenuates over the
the the course of the sequencing
experiment it doesn't happen for single
cell sequencing or single molecule
sequencing right there isn't anything
being being flushed away so basically
from the start of the read to the end of
the read it's it's more or less equal
quality it's still noisy you're reading
from a movie rather than uh from a uh
from a still image and it can be quite
difficult to know have I seen 3 A's or 4
A's or 5 A's or uh you know a repetitive
sequence Motif so there's still some
error correction that needs to be
applied uh in order to achieve that Pac
bio constructs it's uh um its fragments
for sequencing with a hairpin adapter on
each end called a smartbell adapter uh
and that allows the uh polymerase to to
anneal to one of the open parts of the
uh the The Hairpin adapter and begin
sequencing this polymerase has strand
displacement activity so as it is
synthesizing the complimentary strand
it's also displacing the Strand that was
already there so you get these circular
uh readouts of a of a single fragment
both forward and reverse Direction
usually something like uh um five to 15
passes around the around the molecule
and with those redundant passes they can
those redundant passes can be
uh um uh combined in order to generate a
high accuracy consensus read we
generally think that this is the the
corrected read is on par maybe a little
bit higher quality than than aluminous
sequencing
today nanopore sequencing now the the
interesting thing about nanopore
sequencing is unlike aluminous
sequencing and Pac bio sequencing
nanapur is not uh using a polymerase in
order to incorporate bases and and just
monitor the activity of the polymerase
instead nanapur is uh an electrical
readout so uh a a engineered pore sits
in a uh lipid bilayer uh and as uh and
as uh fragments pass through that pore
they generate a a current signal that
current is characteristic of whatever is
being read whether it's a modified or
unmodified uh um nucleotide uh can also
re
uh um RNA bases without having to
convert them necessarily to cdna so it's
a it's a much more
flexible uh readout uh the only thing
that one would theoretically need to do
in order to get it to read something
else is to train the the machine
learning base caller to recognize a
signal other than actg or or
you uh and uh again there are uh you
know clever things that nanapur does do
in order to take its electrical readout
which is again kind of a movie uh and
turn that into a high accuracy base
caller uh I think you know similar to to
to Pac bio there are some clever you
know hairpin structures and duplex
sequencing there are a lot of different
schemes there's also a huge amount of
innovation on the base caller side so I
think nanapur uh releases a new version
of its base callar I don't know it feels
like every 3 to six months uh but there
is constant Improv
in uh in the base caller there's
constant Improvement in their engineered
pores the most recent Innovation is uh
essentially a dual reader head pore that
basically generates two electrical
signals per uh uh per readout so you get
kind of redundant sequencing without the
circularized DNA fragment you just you
essentially get two uh two chances to
read it as it translocates through uh
through the
port um okay uh that is a that is a
brief recap of what I talked about last
time I go into more detail in the
previous talk so again just for a second
I'll put up the slide in case anyone
wants to go to the previous
link okay hopefully that's enough
time uh instrument upgrad so three
things I want to talk about today I want
to talk about some of the improvements
that have happened with the with the
instruments uh methylation and targeted
sequencing so all
already like I said I was I was only
here a few months ago and already my
slides from that time are a little bit
out of date just in the past couple of
months I think ashg uh Pac bio announced
a a new addition to their lineup uh the
uh pack bio Vega uh the Vega is meant to
be a a benchtop version of their pack
bio reval instrument uh with you know
slightly lower you know low lower yield
uh but still able to generate um high
quality what Pac bio calls high-fi data
this error corrected data uh nanapur uh
has had benchtop instrument I mean all
of nur's Ben uh instruments are are
benchtop uh and I I think the last time
I showed the uh the the box in the back
that had 24 or 48 flow cells and the Box
on the right that had five flow cells
and some of the handheld ones um which
are very fun to play with I used to have
one I gave it away how great is it that
we live we we're at a time when I can
just buy a sequencer and put it in my
pocket uh but since then they've they've
come up with their with some additional
formats as well that are meant for um
individual Labs uh and and just benchtop
use things that uh devices that support
one or two flow cells rather than
needing to constantly feed some of the
the more production capable instruments
that take 24 or 4ot de flow cells those
can be hard to uh keep occupied for for
a long
time uh Pac bio has also announced some
improvements in their chemistry in fact
I think we are uh the Bro should be uh
getting preliminary data on this
probably in the next week or two so this
is a this is a uh a very recent
development a new chemistry from Pac bio
called spark um uh which Pac bio claims
achieves a 33% increase in yield per
smart cell so each smart cell at the
moment each Revo smart cell is expected
to generate somewhere between 24 and 30X
coverage uh and P bio is uh releasing
this new chemistry that they claim will
will uh will generate somewhere between
35 and 40x coverage I think the way they
think about this is 220x genomes per uh
per um per smart cell uh requiring less
DNA right previous input requirements
were around two micrograms now we're
down to half a microgram so the
capability of doing more precious
samples I know a lot of my colleagues in
the cancer Community really worry about
this number is the amount of uh DNA
required for pack bio sequencing is
substantially larger than it is for uh
aluminous sequencing uh
yes so I have an intuition of what like
30 30X coverage means for alumina yeah
in your mind do you translate that to
some to like alumina 30X does that mean
something a little bit different than
30X here given accuracy or anything I'm
just curious like if my interpretation
of what 30X means from alumina is
similar yeah it's so it's an excellent
question um so the the way that I think
about the the way that I think about
30X the way that I think about 30X is is
actually
what does it take to accurately call all
of the variants that you expect from a
from from a truth data
set uh and you you can you could do this
Cal you could do this evaluation in a
number of different ways I think the
most common way to do it is titration
experiment I have some data set that was
at very high coverage um that I'm very
confident in that was sequence to let's
say you know 40x 60x 80x 100x something
where I think that I've genuinely
discovered more or less everything that
there is to discover that is not an easy
experiment to do in the first place and
we're getting better at it with the
release of a you know human penum
reference Consortium data and things
like that but but then the question is
uh all right I'm going to se was to a
lower coverage how much of that data did
I recover now there are two there there
two things to to consider there one the
the um uh the the the capabilities of
the software will will will vary so for
example structural varying callers may
not be confident just seeing one or two
reads supporting uh a large structural
variant they may require three or five
reads uh you may also require more more
data for for genotyping so you can do
this as uh I'm just going to down sample
my data to 30X 15 uh 25x 20x 15x etc etc
um now the second thing to know
is that long read coverage is much more
even than short read coverage and a lot
of the discussion around should we have
20x pack bio sequencing and nanoport
sequencing versus 30X uh I think it it
it falls into into this
consideration where you require higher
coverage in aluminous sequencing in
order to shore up the parts of the
genome that tend to get lower coverage
that happens less with pack bio and
nanopore sequencing and so the
recommendation that uh we can hit I mean
you can see from so I'm showing a plot
from from Pac bio but there are actually
a number of different plots that look
pretty much exactly like this my group
has done um uh work very similar to this
that is in Broad broad agreement but the
idea is that uh you know we know we're
missing quite a few things at at 10x
we're missing less at 20x and the gap
between 20x and 30X is uh is not so
large now I want to be clear that is not
me suggesting that all experiments on
Long R instruments should be done at 20x
right this will obviously depend on the
application I'm more than happy with the
the 15x that we're generating for the
all of us project but the the goal of
the all of us project is not
necessarily comprehensive
uh structural variant detection down to
single Tins in every single sample it's
more to construct a uh a a resource of
structural variant that could be
utilized by other projects and seeing
more samples is better than seeing every
single variant in one sample that's not
necessarily true for rare disease
projects uh one of my one one of my new
colleagues is looking at um sematic
variation in samples that would call for
higher coverage so but that's that's
where this difference between the
recommendation for 30X at alumina and
20x for long re platforms is coming from
bit of a longwinded answer but I hope
that answers your
question
um where was I so improvements at um um
in PAC bios chemistry also improvements
in already this slide is out of date but
already uh additional improvements in um
uh with nanapur sequencing as well uh
again like I said the the the two things
that nanapur tends to innovate on are
the the construction of their pore which
they label with an an r and uh and some
numerical identifier I think we're up to
R
10.4.1 for is their is their latest p uh
and Innovations in in base calling so
they're they're achieving somewhere
between 100 and 120 gigabases uh per
read uh uh per per read uh per uh per
flow cell on par with what we're what
we're seeing from Pac bio instruments uh
um P bio uh data is at the moment higher
quality nanopore impressively seems to
uh you know keep keep catching up um so
I'm I'm very happy to have these two
companies competing with each other to
drive their instruments uh to to greater
and greater Heights for for our
use uh I I I won't go into the duplex
sequencing but basically what I was
saying before there are a lot of
different Library schemes that allow you
to uh to to correct some of the uh some
of the errors in in the sequencing data
this is what I wanted to get to
methylation calling so last time and
even in this talk I I've talked uh about
base calling for uh pack biodata and
nanoport data basically that either
fluorescence uh readout over time or the
electrical current readout out over time
uh as allowing one to um uh to to call
uh a c's G's and T's directly from that
signal uh but there's an additional
feature that I alluded to which is uh or
additional two features that I alluded
to uh for pack bio sequencing which are
uh the um uh the pulse width and the
interpulse distance pulse width I've
labeled on on on this plot that um I've
taken from a a poster presented by uh I
think Chris saers at Pac bio uh pulse
width is uh just the you know the the
duration that you see a signal from one
of these nucleotides uh an interpulse
distance is the time until the next
incorp the incorporation of the next
base one of the interesting features
that's annotated on on Chris's image is
the uh Denine base in the in the middle
of this plot versus the two A's at the
end of the plot and you can see just the
amount of time it takes to uh uh to to
to to move from incorporating that first
first a uh to the t is much much larger
than it is for the for the for the other
two A's these three features the
fluoresence intensity the pulse width
interpulse distance uh can be uh used to
create a a a a set of features that's
fed into a neural network that is
trained to call uh methylation signal
and so we see without you know belfi
treatment or oxidated bisulfide
treatment we can see the uh the
methylation status of certain
nucleotides without having to do an
additional
experiment um oh I'll I'll I'll let me
skip skip that to to this nanopore
sequencing is is very similar uh rather
than the uh um measuring the width and
interpulse distance though they could do
it directly from the electrical signal
right if you think of each nucleotide as
a resistor going through um uh you know
this potential difference between the
you know between one end of the pore and
the other each nucleotide methylated or
unmethylated has a characteristic signal
sometimes that signal is not going to be
so different from the from the
unmethylated signal uh that you can that
the Bas caller can tell but for 5mc and
6 ma a uh it is uh you can see just the
the third position in the uh the current
versus position in reference plot uh a
difference between a you know a base and
a modified base that you can train the
base caller to
identify so the nice thing is that long
read data uh contains two ohms in one
right you have the primary genome
sequence for for for your sample um but
you ALS also have uh a 5mc readout for
for your sample without having to do any
additional uh Library treatment uh there
are comparisons uh to uh to to to um
between oxir nanopore P bio methylation
and either bisulfide treatment or
oxidative bisulfide treatment there are
a lot of different versions of this but
they all sort of come to the same
conclusion which is there is very high
correspondence between uh the alumina uh
bisulfite treated data sets in the PAC
bio and oxir nanopore there is a gap but
that Gap is due to Pac bio and nanopore
being able to access more parts of the
genome than the aluminous sequencing can
right because remember for bisulfide
treatment you're basically reducing the
complexity of the sequin by turning all
unmethylated uh cytosines into urasil
and then through PCR amplification into
thyine uh and for oxidative bisulfite
sequencing uh your
uh converting both unmethylated cytosine
and um hydroxymethylated cytosine uh
into uh into thyine bases uh you you
only have 150 bases so if you reduce the
sequence complexity of that read it's
harder to map those reads to to to where
they're supposed to go uh with the the
methylation readout in the long read
data you're still benefiting from the
full length of the long read data
without having to convert any of your
bases to another base in order to read
out the signal so there's no loss in the
the the actual the the sequence accuracy
and on top of that you get a layer of
information that you would have to go
out of your way to get for aluminous
sequencing uh oh sorry go
ahead about cost um
uh yeah I guess that's right I I mean I
hav't
so in my day job I I try very hard not
to think about sequencing costs because
they they change so much and it's not my
department it's not my um um
um is not my issue to deal with uh but
you're right like you you would need to
do two experiments um for aluminous
sequencing versus the one experiment
that you need to do here for for pack
bio sequencing and and for nanopore
sequencing uh that does you know you
know basically double the cost of
aluminous sequencing I don't know many
people who do necessarily do both of
those uh experiments the the the way I
think about it is it's actually kind of
in the other direction I think because
of because of the additional
treatment um because you require more
DNA you require more time s you know
prepping samples
uh increas in the cost I actually think
that most studies most short read
studies that I I've seen probably aren't
generating the methylation data unless
they absolutely need it unless they
really have a hypothesis here you get it
for free so all of a sudden there's a
whole bunch of analysis that you can do
that you might not have considered
before like for example at at at at
repeat expansions can I see
hypermethylation in the region of the
the repeat expansion I might not have
considered to look for that before but
now I can see it without having to do
any extra
work um one of the questions I'm often
asked about this uh is how do I get my
methylation data off of the instrument
does it come in a bed file um and the
answer is you don't have to do anything
it comes automatically with the w with
the sequence production process uh I put
a little Aster I should I put a little
asteris on that because uh nanoport this
is true for nanapur as well but nanapur
gives you a lot more control as to what
settings you use in base calling so it's
worth checking uh your that you've
enabled this setting or your sequencing
provider has enabled this setting for
nanoport data for pack biod data it's on
by default it doesn't come as a separate
file it comes embedded in the BAM file
that you you get so if you get the BAM
files that you're doing snip and indel
and structural variant calling on that
bam file has the methylation data uh
directly encoded in it um I I won't go
into details on exactly how that
encoding works the important thing to
know is uh you know two two things one
it's embedded in the file two most of
the tools that you will be uh using um
are are are adapting themselves to to
handle this uh signal natively igv has
already been updated to show methylation
information uh all one needs to do is
rightclick and and as to uh to um uh
show the the the methylation signal as
opposed to the the primary base signal
if you're writing new software then uh
I'll tell you that the the mm and ml tag
which uh respectively uh Den know base
modifications and the probability of
those base modifications is a standard
part of the BAM speec uh HTS jdk and hgs
lib have been updated to to read and
write those tags uh so there's a lot of
there's a lot of bookmark the
bookkeeping that you need to do in order
to read that signal out appropriately
along the the length of the read
sequence but a whole bunch of software
now exists for for for you to do that
pretty pretty
easily um okay with the time left
there's one other thing that I wanted to
to to to talk about interest I think
this entire time been talking about
interesting consequences of single
molecule sequencing uh and what kind of
readouts we can get that we couldn't get
with a luminous sequencing before
there's one more more that I think is
really interesting uh called adaptive
sampling so one of the problems that we
have with that that we've been that my
group has been approached with several
times is uh a colleague who has a Locus
in the genome or a few Losi in the
genome that they they they they think
something interesting is happening at
that Locus either it's a structural
variant or it's a denovo mutation but
they can't get uh enough of a of a clear
picture of that Locus from short read
sequencing at the same time it seems
like a waste to do long read sequencing
on the entire genome just to see uh a
handful of Loi uh now there's stuff you
can do with with pack bio sequencing
around targeted coverage Pac bio has a
number of targeted sequencing kits that
Target uh repeat expansions or
clinically relevant medical genes or the
HLA uh but if you just have an another
Locus in the genome that you're going
after uh you may have to do um you know
PCR over that Locus or some other some
other strategy in order to capture what
you want versus nanapur where the con
the the the targeted sequencing doesn't
necessarily require any Li new library
prep whatsoever instead because uh
nanopore sequencing is uh based on a a
PO a a a pore rather than a polymerous
race you can reverse the action of the
poor and that's a really interesting
Prospect if you're trying to Target The
genome and only generate reads around
where you're you're uh where you're
looking so basically the way this works
is you start sequencing some uh some
strand of DNA the base calling readout
is in real time so you have a chance as
the PO the the re is translocating
through the poe to read what the first
200 200 bases of that read say and if
those 200 bases are not uh originating
from some part of the genome that you
are interested in you could reverse
voltage on the pore which essentially
unwinds that uh that fragment of DNA
then you reverse it again you allow that
Poe to accept new new reads right you
think about each pore as having a sort
of Lifetime for the total number of
bases it can read well you're not
reading the entire read you're not
you're not using up all of the the
capability of that poor just yet so you
reject the read you wait until you see a
new read that has uh 200 bases of leader
sequence that you care about uh this uh
there are a number of different groups
that have worked on this uh I'm showing
the the the papers from uh Alexander
Payne uh and Matt loose I know Mike
shot's lab has worked on this a number
of different Labs have um have have uh
work with schemes with this basically
nanapur gave a a an API for control for
realtime control of the instrument and
that researchers play with what they
would do with it I like uh um Alex uh
Alexander's papers here because they
they they highlight a few features that
I think are really interesting first is
if you have uh control over individual
reads uh you can do kind of clever
things like uh you know Target repeat
expansions Target Copy number variants
copy uh uh Target structural variants
you can also barcode all of your reads
and only accept reads that have a
certain barcode let's say I have you
know eight samples that I'm trying to
get data on but I want an even coverage
distribution right so once I've seen
enough data on Barcode one I don't need
it anymore so I could just have the
software reject that barcode for the
remainder of the sequencing experiment
and prioritize the ports towards other
other reads of Interest
uh the
the you know I think there are three
there are three things that I I I I see
people do with this uh capability I
think are really interesting so that
dynamically um uh switching on and off
barcodes uh depending on the the the
coverage achieved uh targeting a
specific barcode uh so if we've seen
enough coverage on say a variant of
interest uh we don't need any more data
from that uh barcode and we can we can
again prioritize other ones uh and we
can just generate more coverage over
some locus of Interest right think if
you're doing an assem a genome assembly
and you need to close gaps in that
assembly I could just
generate uh you targeted data over those
gaps rather than having to do yet you
know a full a full other sequencing
experiment uh this capability is is best
when one is SE uh sequenc around 1% of
the genome or
less uh so we can see from uh I think
this is also from Alex's work so that we
can see from the uh you know from this
coverage that around 1% gives us a uh a
15 14 or 15 fold Improvement uh in the
overall coverage that we would have
gotten at that Locus if we had done no
targeting at all we had just done whole
genome sequencing uh this works for
pretty much all of the forms of nanop
sequencing so the from the handheld
instruments all the way to the
production instrument uh this this sort
of targeting is possible and I'll end
with the the what I think is one of the
most interesting applications of this is
uh going after uh Target um um uh repeat
expansions uh this particular repeat
expansion is on the Huntington's Locus
uh similar efforts on fmr1 and um uh and
and a number of other repeat expansions
that would be uh you know not accessible
with short read sequencing um I think
this is a really lovely
approach uh and only possible because
the nanapur instrument is is the one
instrument that is not polymerase based
um okay uh I want to leave time for
questions so I'm going to stop there but
before I do let me just thank the
tremendous number of people I work with
uh again this list is out of date uh but
the the
the the the the the people who I I I
work with who have contributed to this
uh presentation in some other in some
way or another uh I'm enormously
grateful for their for their effort and
and guidance uh and I appreciate all of
you for listening to me thank you very
much
we have a question
online um they asked how many targeted
sequences can you do in in the targeted
study it's a good question I mean I I
don't on the one hand I don't think
there's necessarily a practical limit
you know nanoport does provide barcodes
in uh you know a a few different
configurations I think uh you know 4816
up to perhaps 90 I can't remember what
they're what what their limit is um but
more practically speaking it there there
two there there two things to know one
um you can estimate the yield of a flow
cell to be uh I I generally go for I I
generally think around 90 gigabases for
a promethion flow cell so 90 gigabases
divided by the number of barcodes but it
turns out it's not that simple there is
some penalty for for using bar codes
there's some yield penalty that we've
observed for for for using uh barcodes
so we tend to think it's around 2 to
three
barcodes um now there'll be back and
forth I mean there there are constant
improvements in these platforms so it's
something that we need to check in over
and over again and every time nanopore
updates one of their uh pores they also
need to update one of their um barcoding
kits so there's a bit there's a bit of a
lag between upgrading the poor and up uh
and upgrading the the barcodes but
that's that's generally how we think
about it today is around two to three
barcodes gets you like 30X or higher
coverage over uh targets as long as
there are less than 1% of the
genome Aron um thank you for the talk
and I have at least one question um are
there um are there data sets now that
are merging that are combin that are
like with this combined methylation and
sequencing data
yes there are so um wait let me just
clarify are you asking are there
publicly available data sets that have
both primary base signal and methylation
Signal or are you asking are people
combining pack biodata and oxer anore
data because I'd have I'd be happy to
answer both the the first one so like
when you were talking about being able
to kind of read out both from the same
yes there are so publicly available data
sets are available on Pac bio's website
every time they've upgraded the the the
in they've released uh they released a
number of things they released usually
HD2 but they've also released some tumor
normal pairs um I think there are a
couple of colorl cancer uh um uh pairs
on on their on their website uh they
have a few microbial genomes as well
which for 5mc methylation might not be
as interesting um uh but there are there
are a bunch there so there there there
are a bunch there the second place to
look is the um um human P genome
reference Consortium and and I kind of
treat them together but they're separate
things hprc and uh Human Genome
structural variant Consortium now I will
say the early data that they generated I
think they stripped out the methylation
signals so you should know that the the
the the ability to call methylation on
board the instrument is fairly new maybe
only in the last few years uh so the
initial data that that was generated by
hbrc didn't contain that data newer data
coming from hbrc I think should contain
that data and all of that is publicly
available it's thousand genome samples
so all of that is available uh and then
third um uh so it's not publicly Ava
well yeah it's not publicly available
yet but it will be in the
next probably within the next month or
so the What's called the the V8 release
of all of us
will now contain uh uh a couple thousand
long read samples we had released about
a thousand long read samples in V7 they
didn't for the same reason I just
indicated they didn't have methylation
signal the new data we've been very
paranoid to make sure they all have
methylation signal that's the pack
biodata and anopore data that's around I
can't remember the exact number but it's
somewhere between a th and 2,000 um
genomes from uh a number of individuals
from diverse ancestry and that will be
available on researcher
workbench uh um for anyone who wants to
access
them no problem all right I think we
have time for one more online are there
mature base callers for other cytosine
derivatives EG uh 5hmc or 5fc yes there
are I actually don't have a
comprehensive list in my head as to
everything that the the base caller
supports I think it it's 5mc 5H H MC uh
and 6 ma but 6 ma calling I think is
usually for
RNA I assume it's been updated for I I
think it's probably capable for DNA as
well I'm just a little bit less familiar
with that literature to be able to say
for for for certain uh and it can also
be trained to detect uh uh different
modified bases if you have such a
training Set nanapur uh releases their
base caller as open source and they
provide documentation on how train it
for new base
modifications uh which is a a pretty
exciting thing to consider for a number
of RNA sequencing applications and uh
and other synthetic biology
applications great and then there's a
few more questions online but we're out
of time so if anyone can email Karen
with additional questions I'm sure he'd
be happy to answer absolutely thank you
see you after the new year