I'm delighted to be here to introduce
the final speaker in our series for the
Broad MIT uh series in chemical biology.
We've had a fantastic slate of speakers
uh and a highlight today as well. I want
to begin by thanking our sponsors from
industry. You can see them listed here.
Uh and also of course Ed Skolnick who's
made the entire program possible uh for
us. So thank you very much. Uh we really
appreciate it.
Um our speaker today is Jonathan
Abraham. Jonathan is uh a really
fantastic scientist uh in the viology
and structural biology space. Jonathan
got his start actually at Harvard
University where he earned a bachelor's
degree in 2005
uh and worked with Stephen Harrison
there uh and actually continued to work
with Stephen Harrison as he pursued his
MD PhD earning that in 2012.
uh following following that he had a
term as a intern and resident at BWH uh
and then was a clinical and research
fellow at Brigham and Women's uh really
uh doing beautiful structural biology
and vyology and a bunch of other uh
great work around immunology uh all
along the way um Jonathan started as an
assistant professor at Harvard Med in
2017 was promoted to associate in 2022
uh and he has uh also, you know, really
impressively he's also a practicing
physician, right? Uh and and so I I
really admire the ability to do all of
that. He's got a long list of awards
here, all the awards that uh you dream
of getting. So he's uh he's won all of
the different burrows welcome fund
awards uh from early in the career for
uh physician scientist uh up through
he's currently one of their
investigators in the pathogenesis of
infectious disease. Uh he won the NIH
director's early independence award, the
Smith family foundation odyssey award,
many other awards uh many other awards
here. Um, as I said, his lab is
interested in molecular viology,
immunology, structural biology, uh, of
viruses, uh, how they adapt or or how
they interact with, uh, receptors on
host cells, how they're neutralized by
antibodies. He's interested in the viral
polymerases and how they replicate viral
genomes. And sort of the big picture
vision here is eventually not just to
get mechanistic understanding, but also
find new avenues to treatments uh, and
vaccines and things like that. So it's a
very important research area. Uh
Jonathan's been extremely uh successful
and made major contributions throughout.
You're going to hear about them today.
Uh and I should mention that as of last
year uh he's also a HHMI investigator.
Uh which is a fantastic thing to be
especi I think it's always a fantastic
thing to be but especially if you're
working on infectious disease these
days. Right. So with that I'll turn it
over to him.
Thank you, Matt, for the wonderful
introduction. I'll jump right
in. And so here on this, maybe I'll
stand over here. It might be easier. Um
on this sort of diagram here, I'm
showing you a viral particle uh with a
membrane in gray. And the sort of
interesting bit we'll focus on today is
a viral spike protein shown in blue. And
so these spike proteins that decorate
the surface of viral particles of course
played a critical role of attaching the
virus to cellar receptors during the
first step of the infectious cycle. And
so after this binding event uh the virus
can be endocytosed into for the viruses
we study acidic compartments whereby the
exposure of low pH allows the spike
protein to undergo these massive
confirmational changes uh that culminate
in fusion of the viral and host cell
membranes. And so in addition to our
interest in how viruses can bind
receptors, we also study neutralizing
antibodies that will bind the spike
proteins and prevent receptor
engagement. And so one of the bigger
picture questions we hope our research
will help clarify is how spike proteins
can adapt to bind cell receptors in
different hosts while also avoiding
immune recognition by molecule like
antibodies. And so alpha virus is the
virus I'll tell you about today. Um
these are subdivided into two groups old
world and new world. This is based on
their cerological properties as well as
their geographic distribution. Um the
old world viruses typically cause rash
and arthritis. An old world alpha virus
you might have heard about is chicken
gona virus while the new world viruses
typically cause encphilitis. A sort of
well-known example in the New England
area is a eastern ecoin and sephilitis
virus. And so unfortunately for the new
world viruses including triple E, there
are no approved vaccines or treatment
options. And these diseases can be quite
devastating because some of them for
example have a case fatality rate that
can be as high as 75%. And for those who
survive infection, they can be left with
permanent neurological squelia
thereafter, including many requiring
lifelong institutionalized care. And so
why we care about these viruses is
because they have this pretty
interesting life cycle in nature whereby
they are amplified in these reservoir
species including mosquito vectors and
birds. Um this is called the end uh the
enzyatic cycle and the episotic end of
the cycle here which are what some might
call spillover events results in dead
end infection when mosquito bridge
vectors feed on vymic berries and then
spread them to humans or horses. And
what I mean by dead and hosts is that
humans and horses will sustain uh vymia
that's high enough to say seed the
central nervous system but the vymia is
not uh prolonged enough or high enough
to allow the these hosts to serve as
fresh sources of virus to then spread to
new hosts. So uh infection ends in these
hosts
here and so the spike protein is
synthesized initially as a polyeptide
precursor. you have a capsid uh followed
by a chaperone called E3, E2, E1 as well
as this peptide here called sis 6K that
sits in between and in gray here I'm
showing you the uh viral membrane and so
really the business end of the particle
is E2 that interacts with receptors and
E1 that underos the confirmational
changes I mentioned will culminate in
fusion of the vowel and host cell
membranes and so these form heterodimer
um that assemble then as trimers so
there's There's a total of about uh 240
E1 E2 heterodimer forming 80 trimers on
the surface of particles and what you
have here is E2 that is most membrane
distal and E1 that sits closest to the
viral membrane uh caps on the interior
and the lipid billayer is here. So I'm
showing you a diagram here that doesn't
really faithfully reproduce how the
virus is actually organized.
aosahedral symmetry. And so um as will
be relevant to the other parts of my
presentation, we really wanted to take a
system that would recapitulate this
proper particle geometry as we try to
find receptors for these viruses.
And so um here I'll tell you about sort
of a landmark study done out of Wu and
Mike Diamond's lab where identified this
molecule called MX RA8 a cellion
molecule as a cell receptor for chicken
goono virus and why this discovery was
important um is that it allowed us to
for the first time visualize how
receptors can interact with alpha
viruses. uh before 2018 there was sort
of critical knowledge gaps in the field
and these molecules were unknown and in
2018 really is when the crisper cast 9
screens had been used to find this
molecule and hopefully what you can see
here is I'm showing you the spike
protein E1 subunit in gray E2 subunit in
light blue this is a side view the
membrane would be down here this is a
top view um hopefully you can see that
this MX8 molecule in pink really hugs a
cleft that is formed by adjacent E2E1
heterodimer on the trimers and so if you
use a system like lentivirus or vicular
stomatitis virus so particles that don't
have the proper geometry and that are
pleomorphic you might miss uh or or not
form these properly assembled trimers
and that might not give you as reliable
a result and so with this in mind as we
set out to do our own crisper screens um
back in 2017 we decided to in rather
than using VSV or lentiviruses is to
build our own uh repliconbased system
for alpha viruses. And so we took the
alpha virus genome here that has a
non-structural proteins followed by
capsid and the structural poly protein
including the spike proteins here and
split it into two. And so plasmid one
here has the non-structural proteins
followed by capsid 2a self-cleing
peptide followed by a reporter. And so
this reporter could be green fluorescent
protein if we wanted to study viral
entry using flowcytometry or microscopy
and it could also be a sort of
selectable marker we could express on
the surface of infected cells like CD20
a bell marker that I'll tell you about
in the next slides and plasmid 2 in this
case would allow us to express
heterologous spike proteins. So in this
case we could take the spike protein of
eastern ecornin and sephilitis virus and
because a lot of these viruses are bsl3
pathogens uh and this is a single cycle
system it allowed us to work with these
particles under BSL2 conditions in our
lab
safely and so the way our screen worked
uh is we sort of transduced our library
of guide RNAs into cells. So because we
were really focused on finding
receptors, we only targeted membrane
proteins in the genome. Um with a total
of 10 guides per membrane protein uh so
with high guide redundancy, we do our
purein selection and rather than using
GFP here as our reporter in the virus,
we have CD20. So Z20 will be expressed
on the surface of cells here. These are
two T cells we're using for our screen.
And uh expression of this B cell marker
would be abnormal. and would allow us to
effectively uh deplete these cells using
rounds of magnetic sorting. Uh and I say
this magnetic sorting is useful because
rather than spending say eight hours on
a flowcytometer sorting positive and
negative cells with GFP, we could just
do this with max beads inside a tissue
culture hood and do this quite
efficiently. And so we do this for
several cycles. Uh three was sort of a
sweet spot for this virus and uh
followed by next generation sequencing
to identify guides that are enriched.
And so really the first screen we did
was a virus called semnikiforest virus.
This is just because it got in really
well into the 293T cells. And when we
used semiik forest virus the top hit was
VLDLR. So VLDLR stands for the very low
density laprotein receptor. Um it is a
protein that was known to be a receptor
for other viruses including vicular
stomatitis virus and uh certain groups
of human infecting rhino viruses. um
HSP9DB1 is a protein that is a chaperon
for PCSK9 which is a master regulator of
LDLR related protein. So that was
reassuring and SC3A the role was unclear
when we did the study but it's involved
probably in the stability of these other
proteins here through
glycosillation and so if you look at how
the receptor is organized it has a long
and terminal uh uh sort of lian binding
domain that has what are called LDLR
class A repeats. So each of these
repeats is about 40 amino acids in
length. Um the repeats are imperfect
repeats to each other. So there's a lot
of sequence diversity in the region and
they all tend to coordinate calcium and
the same residues that coordinate
calcium are typically residues that bind
lians and so different family members of
the LDLR related families of proteins
will have different numbers of these
repeats and repeats of the different
identities in terms of sequence. And so
when we uh found this as a receptor for
semikiforis virus we also wanted to look
if other family members could serve as
receptors for the same virus. And when
we looked at a protein called
apo2 which is a protein that unlike
VLDLR rather than being expressed
throughout the body is particularly
enriched in the brain and that receptor
also worked as a receptor for subnik
forest virus. I should add as an
interesting point that when we looked at
LDLR the canonical family member that we
didn't see that uh serve as a receptor
for these viruses and interestingly
enough VLDLR and POR2 um are known as
reelin receptors because they bind to a
molecule called renal reelin in the
central nervous system that's important
for development um in the brain and then
later on important for uh synaptic
plastic
plasticity and so now you know the
experiments we tend to perform to
validate receptors I won't um go through
the whole list um in terms of showing
you the data but I'll just explain
quickly you know the quickest experiment
we can do once we have a hit that we're
excited about of course is to take
knockout cells in this case um and show
that complementing them with uh VLDLR
cDNA in this case allows us to rescue
infection this is measured by uh GFP
quantification of infected cells with
the RVPs
um we could show that cells that are
resistant to infection can become
permissive when we overex express the
receptor. Uh we could show that the
antibodies uh directed against the
receptor can be used to block
infectivity. Um that purified components
interact. Um this is usually by
purifying virus-l like particles and re
combinant receptors and mixing them
together approaches using you know
biollay interferometry or elysas and
then receptor binding mediates uh sorry
receptor itself can mediate binding and
internalization. And usually we use live
stealth coco microscopy but these are
great products for graduate students
because they have a lot of work to do.
Um and in terms of the physiological
relevance this is perhaps more
challenging for us in that case you have
to sort of have an animal model that you
show um if genetically deficient for
this receptor it becomes resistant to
infection. An approach we use I'll tell
you about later is instead because VLDLR
at the time we're doing these
experiments we thought it was an
essential gene um to development of myo
based on prior literature. what we can
do is effectively take a soluble from
the receptor, administer it to the mouse
and show that the receptor can serve as
a decoy um and block infection that way
and this is how we usually demonstrate
physical relevance. So we did this all
for semicorus virus. Uh at the same time
al also we looked at uh eastern
sephilitis virus and saw that vdlr and
apore 2 could also be receptors for this
particular
virus. And so now why we were sort of
excited about this in the beginning is
really the central question we wanted to
better understand is how these arbo
viruses that infect mosquitoes and
humans are able to infect cells from you
know organisms that are separated by
hundreds of millions of years of
evolutionary history. And so VLDLR
interestingly enough is also expressed
in mosquitoes that is called lipopformin
receptor 1. Um and so we set out to
express different orthologes of VLDLR
and different orthologes of APOR2. And
so by uh taking our non-permissive cells
and overexpressing each of these
receptors, we saw that all the receptor
orthologes we tested for VLDLR and APOR2
including bird uh for apo2 and mosquito
for VLDLR could serve as receptors for
septic forest virus. Um Lars Clark, one
of the students working on the project,
I challenged him to find a good negative
control. He tried C elegance which also
has a VLDL ortholog that's important for
lipid uptick in the guts. I'm not
showing you this but the C elegance
ortholog also worked. So we never really
had a negative control for this uh
particular assay given the promiscuity
with which sim link forest virus seem to
be interacting with um these receptors
where we looked at uh each sephilitis
virus. However, we actually saw that uh
it could bind VLDL orthox for some PCs
but not others. Um so to us that was
sort of the first sign perhaps that even
though Sam licky forest virus and
eastern equin were using both VLDLR and
a year 2 as receptors that the viruses
might have differences in which uh with
which they interact with these receptors
which you know as a structural biology
lab is sort of um inspires us to go to
the next step which is to determine
cryoreem structures of the
complexes. And so whenever we take on a
structural project, we want to first map
what might be the minimal receptor
binding fragment to complex with our
virus-like particles for the either
X-ray or um crym experiments. And so the
approach we used here was we took
individual LDLR class A repeats and put
them on the scaffold of the rest of the
receptor and then overexpress these to
figure out what might be the minimal
receptor binding fragment. Now our
hypothesis going in was that perhaps you
know this is flexible. Maybe the most
membrane distal repeat would work as a
as a receptor for these viruses. So
maybe this construct might work. But
when we did the experiments actually we
saw that multiple of these LA repeats um
LA 2 three four five sorry LA 2 three
five and six could serve as receptors
for the key4 virus when overexpressed.
So rather than engaging an individual LA
repeat um multiple LA repeats could be
engaged. This also taught us that
perhaps there's something unique about
the sequences of each of these repeats
that makes some work versus not as
receptors. And when we looked at eastern
ecoin and compared it to sim leaky
forest virus, we saw that eastern ecoin
could actually bind LA1 in addition to
binding the other LA I mentioned. So
again a different uh set of data
demonstrating that perhaps eastern ecoin
and semic forest virus uh had
differences in their spike that um allow
them to sort of engage these receptors
differently.
So on to cryomm structures. Um I should
mention that uh for the students um in
the lab it's also very stressful because
whenever we find a receptor and publish
on it there's like multiple labs that
work very quickly to get the cryogam
structures and so there was multiple
structures reported over the time frame
we did this work but so we did
structures of sikiiforis virus and
eastern equinitis virus bound to the
receptor here I'm showing you a top down
view. So the membrane would be like in
the back of the sort of screen here and
we would be facing the virus. There's
the E1 subunit in uh in gray, E2 subunit
in light blue and the E3 chaperone that
was retained on our preparations.
And so when we looked at binding of the
LA repeats for San Niki forest virus,
rather than being in this cleft that I
mentioned where MX8 binds for chicken
virus, it was actually at a site that
was distal here about 40 angstros away
on E1 um domain 3 here. And it was so
you know kind of like unexpected that
the first time we got the cryomm
structure, we actually missed that there
was density there. So it took us se
several runs to be able to actually kind
of go back um and and verify that here
for eastern ecoin it was the canonical
site which is again is involving cliffs
formed by adjacent prote. So that one
was sort of more straightforward to
obtain. And so now if you can zoom into
these structures and look to see how the
receptors interacting with the viral
glyoprotein. This is the E1 subunit of
Sam Nikki Forest virus. This is LA2
repeat of
VLDLR. Here you have the calcium ion
that's being coordinated by these acidic
residues and effectively two lysen that
are conserved with some leaky forest
virus but absent an eastern sephilitis
virus that are interacting with the side
chains of these acidic residues here on
the receptor. So this binding mode is
engaging a conserved feature of the
receptor because these residues are
usually involved in calcium
coordination.
Now if you look at eastern ecoin and
sephilitis virus again 40 anctions away
on the spike you see a different site
now involving E2 shown in blue whereby
you have a cluster of basic residues
again interacting with the acidic
residues on the receptor. Um I should
mention that we also did experiments to
show that if you use EDTA um that
disrupts the interaction presumably
because it changes the geometry of the
site here when you get rid of the
calcium and perhaps partially unfolds
the protein.
Now if you look at how same leaky forest
virus binds the VLDLR the LA repeats at
the bottom here E1 submitted at top it's
very similar to how LDLR interacts with
one of its physiological lag ends or
receptor associated protein. So
typically what you have is you have
multiple of these repeats of wrap in
this case because it also is
multimodular that present lysen that
interact with these acidic residues. And
if you look at rein um if you look at um
uh lipoproteins as well these sort of
basic residue interactions are quite
preserved. So really the virus is
mimicking in a way the physiological uh
lian for these uh receptors and so
summary for the first part I've showed
you that VLDLR and apore2 are cell
receptors for semic forest virus and
eastern sephilitis virus that divergent
receptor orthologics can support alpha
virus entry and that viral spike
proteins can bind sites on um the spike
protein sorry viral spike proteins can
bind the receptors um using different
surfaces um that are effectively
um areas where lysines can serve as the
critical night this for interactions.
And so now switching to the next part um
which is I think where the project got
even more exciting for us. Uh we were
particularly interested about a virus
called western ecoinphilitis virus. So
most of you in the room probably haven't
heard about this virus and you probably
have heard of triple E. So triple E has
you know been around for over a century
now causing episodic outbreaks of vowel
and sephilitis anywhere from no cases to
about a dozen or twoa uh dozens of cases
uh per year. I think the largest
outbreak in the last 50 years was in
2019. There were a total I think of 32
cases in seven states and several
deaths. Western ecoinphilitis virus is
something quite different. So it used to
cause explosive outbreaks of encphilitis
in humans and horses dating back to the
early uh 1900s. Um outbreaks involving
thousands of horses, hundreds of human
cases. Uh but the virus has kind of gone
extinct or submerged in North America.
Um the last outbreak really was or last
case was in 1999 and the virus has kind
of disappeared since that time. Even
though you know when I'm in the hospital
when we order cerologic testing for um
uh suspected orbital sephilitis we still
check cor p corology this virus has not
caused a case for over um 20 years now
and so we were interested in better
understanding what was going on with
this virus and so I've showed you that
eastern uses
VLDLR2 I should add that Venezuelan
sephilitis virus another member of this
family was shown to bind a molecule
called LDL LRD3. So this is almost like
a mutation construct we would have
generated. If you delete these domains,
the receptor still works. So LDLRD3 has
three of these LDLR class A repeats and
LA1 is what binds to Venezuelan ecoin
and sephilitis virus. But the receptors
for western ecoin and sephilitis virus
was not known. And so at the time uh we
were working on Sam Leiki, we also had
done a screen for western ecoin and
sephilitis virus. And rather than
landing a LDLR related molecule, the top
hit was protocadin 10. Um this is a
protocader that's expressed throughout
the body. It's enriched in neurons where
it um helps synapse uh communicate with
each other by forming these homophilic
dimers in trans. And interestingly
enough, you know, this was the first
bonafide alpha virus receptor that was
not an LDLR related protein but actually
a protocader instead. And so what you
have here are these cader repeats here.
And so um taking a step back now looking
at evolution of this virus. Luckily
enough there information for strains all
the way from the 1930s to 2005. Um these
are f phyologically described as
lineages A B1 B2 or B3. Um,
interestingly enough, if you look at
these strains over time in infectivity
studies in mice, the strains from the
30s and 40s are hypervolent, but the
strains from uh 2005 are virtually non-
pathogenic in animal models. And the
crisper screen we did actually uh was
focusing on a 1971 strain from Montana.
Uh we had not gone back in time and look
at older strains or looked at more
recent strains. And so the student
working on the project, Wanu, decided to
test these various strains um again in
groups A through uh B1, B2 and B3. And
I'm showing you here in pink instances
whereby the receptors works versus does
not work as a receptor when
overexpressed in cells. And
interestingly enough um when we uh
looked here we saw that human protocader
10 could be a receptor for all strains
we tested but not for the 2005 strains
that are non
pathogenic. This was the case also for
mouse PCDHN. This was the case for horse
PCDHN. So any mamleian orthologue we
looked at could no longer serve as a
receptor for these viruses. So that we
were sort of scratching our heads and
asking ourselves, you know, what could
this virus be using to get into cells
because we know it can infect certain
cell types. Uh when we looked at the
bird orthologue, we actually saw that
that one could serve as a receptor. So
that sort of solved this piece of the
puzzle. But this didn't really start to
tell us, you know, why the strains from
the 30s and 40s were hypervolent. I
didn't mention this but eastern equin
and sephilitis virus is maybe the most
virilent member of all uh you know new
world alpha viruses and some of the old
strains are kind of reminiscent of the
virolence of eastern ecoin. So when we
looked at receptor usage we found that
the old strains of western ecoin use the
same receptors as well as eastern ecoin
in this case. So in addition to binding
to protein 10 they could bind to VLDLR
and A4 R2 and this property was lost by
newer
strains and so
um that of course led us to do
structures of receptor balm complexes.
In this case I'm showing you again semi
key forest virus. The first structure we
went for is the VLDLR binding mode.
Again it binds to E1 for semi key
eastern equin um it binds the cleft. We
knew this time to look everywhere on the
spike for binding sites given that we
expected differences. Um the bounding
site is similar uh effectively involving
the clefts for western ecoin for the
ancestral strain. But when you look at
these side views here again with E1 in
gray and E2 in blue, you can see that
rather than binding to one LA repeat,
there's two LA repeats that are bound
kind of wrapping around the opposite pro
in this case. So this binding mode
involves engagement of uh protomer one
here. This binding mode involves
engagement of prote 2 with two of these
LA repeats bound. So again evidence of
structural plasticity and how these
viruses are interacting with receptors.
And just to kind of clarify as well, the
key here is that you have these clusters
of basic residues that are not conserved
in the different viruses that are
hopping around. So clusters of basic
residues here versus here versus here
and here um that are influencing the
ability to recruit LDLR uh repeats in
the binding mode. And so we also wanted
to better understand what was going on
with protein 10 binding. You know why
certain strains were able to bind to
human receptor versus um only being able
to bind the aven form. And so we
obtained structures of PCDH10 bound to
E1 E2 for both ancestral strains as well
as the 2005 Imperial County strain
Imperial 181 um group B3. And so here
I'm showing you sequence alignments.
Sort of what jump jumped out at us was
effectively that at uh leucine 149 in
the spike protein in 2005 you get
replacement of that non-polar residue
with a polar residue of glutamine. Um
and effectively this was at an
interface. So by getting structures of
first the this is a strain from the 50s
bound to human PCDH10. We could see the
PCD here in orange, the receptor in
light blue, that this hydrophobic
residue was forming nice hydrophobic
interactions in this case with
protocaderin 10. Um, but that this
residue became a glutamine in Imperial
181 disrupting these non uh these
non-polar contacts in this case. So you
might ask, you know, how does imperial
181 still bind 10? I'm not showing you
this here, but it's because this strain
in particular has E2 polymorphisms
elsewhere at the interface that
compensate for these contacts. And we
found out that you need about four
mutations on the E2 protein to
compensate for this loss of uh non-polar
contacts in this case. So this is really
sort of a barrier that prevents imper
181 from being able to recognize human
PCDHM despite its ability to interact
with the aven form of the receptor.
And so um we also wanted to better
understand what extent of mutations in
the spike again will allow the spike now
to bind to protein 10 or to VLDLR. If
you look at the spike from the Imperial
181 strain and so by examining the cryom
structures together, we basically found
that imperial 181 while it doesn't bind
human horse or uh but binds bird PCH10,
it is about one mutation away from being
able to bind to uh the human and horse
receptors and uh with two mutations is
able to bind to uh imp is able to bind
to all three receptors effectively.
And so now uh how is this information
important? I would say it also can help
us design potential
antivirals. Uh so what we can do is I
mentioned to you these receptor decor
proteins. So we can take in this case
the EC1 repeat of PCDH10. These
structures show that PCDH10 and VLDLRA
repeats bind an overlapping site in the
cleft. So protein 10 EC1 should block
access to both receptors. And we
confirmed this in vitro. So if you take
this molecule and you give it to mice uh
that are challenged with lethal doses of
the ancestral strain that binds all
receptors, you can see in this case that
mice are uh 100% of mice treated with
the product 10 EC1 FC molecule um are
actually protected from infection as
compared to isotope PBS controls.
And if you do a similar experiment and
now you put LA1 and LA2 you block access
to PCDH10 and again we saw significant
protection in mice given this VLDLR LA1
LA2 FC fusion
proteins and so ultimately what we
wanted to have is also a road map a
molecular blueprint to understand what
polymorphisms and the spike protein mean
in terms of viral evolution. Um a lot of
this work we were doing while we were
looking at the virus in North America
again that kind of went extinct and
submerged. And when we looked at the
sequences we saw that you know as I
mentioned here uh these ancestral
strains have these polymorphisms and
basic residues here
E1K E181K that allow binding to LDLR
class A repeats. And then this lucine at
149 up until 2005 allows these strains
to bind to uh human and uh horse BCDHM
but this ability is lost here. And then
as we were writing up the paper
unfortunately there was a big outbreak
of weave in South America. Um this was
2023 20 uh 2023 to 2024 involving uh
Uruguay, Argentina and Brazil. There
were over 200 cases in horses, over 200
human cases. And so we sort of eagerly
waiting for the sequences based on what
we knew here for these polymorphisms.
And when these sequences were released
here, we could see that all of these
viruses had the L149 polymorphism. And
interestingly enough, unlike what
happened in North America where the
virus kind of submerged by having this
L149 Q polymorphism, all the strains we
looked at in South America dating back
to the 30s to 2023 now with the freshest
outbreak have this lucine there and are
able to bind to both uh human and ecoin
forms of protein 10. They did not have
the signature polymorphis binding to
VLDL or LA repeats though
thankfully. And so I've showed you that
weave binds protocader 10 as receptor
mallelian cells that ancestral strains
also had the ability to bind
VLDLR2 and that with the cryomm
structures in hand now we can better
understand how polymorphisms influence
uh receptor dependencies for these
enpholytic alpha viruses. And so on that
note I'd like to thank members of my
lab. Um Juan Yu Lee was a graduate
student who did a lot of the work on
eastern ecoin and western ecoin in terms
of functional assays. Pyang and Shiaoi
Fan are post-doal fellows who did uh the
cryoem work. Um I should mention this is
very sort
of a field that moves really fast. So
many of the lab members here all worked
collectively together to get the data
out very quickly. Um and various
collaborators in particular Scott Weaver
at UTMB
uh who runs the world reference center
for emerging viruses and arboral viruses
that did all of our BSL3 work and then
various sources of funding. And that I'm
happy to take
[Applause]
questions. All right. Thank you very
much. That was great. Questions from the
audience. Come up to the microphones to
ask your questions.
All right, I'll use this one. Okay, so
you had some data where with some where
you had like all eight that you had an
effect and then sometimes like one by
itself didn't do much but two and four
did or something like that. From looking
at the structures, can you understand
why um some some of them have the effect
and then some of them don't have and and
if that makes sense. Yes. Let me see if
I have a sequence alignment maybe. Ah I
take a sequence alignment out. Sorry. So
yes, so we did a lot of sequence
alignment uh sort of gazing. Um I think
one of the key requirements is that you
do need to have that uh tryptophan there
for many of the viruses.
Um let me see if I can find
here. So this in all the binding
modes this tryptophan in the LA repeat
stacks against the alifhatic portion of
this lysine here and so that's a
critical requirement. Um for eastern
equin you could have a phenol alanine
here in some leaky you can't because of
this extra you know polar interactions
between this aspartate here. So we did
that sort of like staring at alignment
so we get a sense. So whenever this
residue is not conserved there's issues
and for LDL3 the molecule that's a
receptor for Venezuelan ecoin this
residue here um whose backbone
participates in calcium coordination but
not the side chain is replaced by a
lucine and that lucine prevents these
contacts. So we're finally understanding
you know the sort of structure function
sequence basis for how these things work
and they don't work in certain
scenarios.
Thanks for the great talk. Uh so I think
you mentioned briefly about the
glycosillations but I wonder like I know
that like for SARS COVID like
glycosillation of the spike proteins
actually enhance the internalizations of
the viral virus into the human cells.
Yeah. So I wonder like have you looked
at how the
glycosillations impact this affinity
like this binding to receptor and if so
what's a like a molecular mechanism if
there's any different receptor involved
in that pathway or if it's yeah how
what's a molecular mechanism of
increased binding affinity. Oh that's a
very good question. Um I sort of
neglected to mention glycans. I mean
there's some glycans not as heavily
decorated with glycans as SARS KV2 or
other viruses that have like different
architectures in the spike. These
viruses that have you know sort of
icosahhedral symmetry tend to have I
would say like a surface that's more
similar to non-envelope viruses. And so
for flavy viruses we know that glycans
there which are kind of have a similar
shell in general um they bind to DC sign
and that can participate in infection.
For alpha viruses that's really
underexplored. I'm not sure if people
have looked at carefully but that's a
great question. Um I should say that E3
though the chaperon we uh that we we saw
in our preparations other groups that
had structures did not have E3 and there
they saw additional LA repeats bind when
E3 was gone. So I think both glycans as
well as whether or not the chaperone
remains might influence um receptor
binding affinities and those are
important questions for vaccine design
as well because you want to sort of
expose what's relevant when you make a
vaccine.
Uh can you use part of the receptor to
treat the disease to keep it from
binding from the endogenous receptor or
that's not practical because it's a
brain infection. Right. So, uh, you
know, one of these experiments here, and
I'll just jump to it because it's easier
to
show what people have done, and I'll
tell you what people have done and why
it's sort of like tricky to use in the
clinic, is make these types of molecules
here where you
take the repeat that binds to the virus
and you put it on the IGG1 FC constant
region. So, you can give this, you know,
six hours before viral viral challenge.
You can give this up to I think 24 hours
postviral challenge and prevent seeding
of the central nervous system. The
problem though is if you wait too long
the animals become vymic. The virus sees
the brain and it's too late. And I think
of the patients I might see for example
in the hospital in many cases they're
coming in you know a week later after
having their initial fever and vymia you
know their chromatos in the ICU send the
corology takes you about a week to get
the result back and so by then it's too
late. So these are probably better
prophylactic agents and I think in order
to use them as antivirals we need to
have better diagnostics where you
diagnose things very early on and then
you treat um sort of early um otherwise
you have to figure out how to engineer
these to get but it's it's hard to know
because I think later on as mentioned
those same patients will have positive
corology but negative RNA on the PCR
from the cerable spinal fluid which
tells you it's more likely an immune
reaction at this point the virus has
been cleared. So there a lot of
challenges of yingling this out as
therapeutics and this is more really to
get at the point of physiological
relevance.
So I have a question about the about the
WEV. So you have this substitution was
it L149Q that cost it the ability to
interact with the protocod 10. So what's
the I guess what I was wondering and I
apologize if I missed it but is what's
the benefit to the virus for that amino
acid substitution to have taken over the
population as the virus submerged I
guess right I mean it must what's going
on there so our hypothesis that is
genetic drift um I didn't mention this
but there's yet another receptor for
western equin um called
MXR8 of the aven species so the so
chicken ga uses human mx XR8 but not
avian MXR8 and then uh western ecoin can
use the aven form of MXR8 but not the
human form and what happens that that
mutation is not at the interface with
MXR8 so that mutation is tolerated fine
so our going hypothesis that perhaps it
was genetic drift not necessarily an
advantage but the virus lost the ability
to bind to protein 10 but as sort of a
safeguard could still get into aven
cells using a MXR8 now another
hypothesis that's not popular in the
field is that in you know one of
challenges with what's going on in South
America with the recent outbreak is that
you know most likely there was to some
extent amplification in horses that were
not getting vaccinated um with horses
being more prevalent there in sort of
agriculture and so one other model would
be perhaps that there's an advantage to
having a loosen there to be amplified in
in horses not as dead end host but as
amplifying host and that's what's
keeping the virus in circulation South
America they vaccinated all the horses
and then now we has not come back for a
second season and so it's hard to know
in North America the horses always get
vaccinated for western eastern and
Venezuelan a great talk um I'm curious
to know so you mentioned um your work
with horses and bird um is there
additional value from learning from
other species um or is it like
diminishing returns or could you speak
more to like any plans about
diversifying the host post or dead end
species? That's a great question. I'm
sorry I should add that part um to the
talk. So, as I was reading more about
this, I found papers from the 50s
describing how western equin was thought
to have as an additional enzyatic host,
garter snakes, which you know are sort
of the same snakes I saw growing up in
my backyard in Canada. Um, and I'm
assuming they're sort of prevalent
throughout. The idea is that birds are
actually not vymic long enough to be
able to say carry the virus from South
America to North America. But snakes
during the winter can be chronically
infected with little consequence. And so
they're thought to be these
overwintering hosts. So in addition to
western equin being able to use aven
PCDH10, it's able to use snake PCH10 as
well. Um and so there sort of an extra
layer as well. That being said, people
are not looking aggressively in snakes
to see if the virus is still there. But
the same mutation, this L149Q is
tolerated by the snake ortholog as well.
Uh we have not looked beyond snakes. Um
but based on sequence, I'm suspecting
additional might work like amphibious
like I was asking the student war. He
was like, "So how are the snakes getting
like how the mosquitoes getting the
virus from snakes? Apparently they bite
the eye." And I was like, "Okay, let's
stop talking about it."
Any other questions? More questions.
Going
once. All right. Let's thank Jonathan
for a great talk.
[Applause]