the probabilistic method in
combinatorics is a powerful method that
can be used to demonstrate the existence
of some object by introducing
Randomness in this video we'll look at a
basic example illustrating an
application of the probabilistic method
we'll show this theorem over here which
says that if G is a graph with M edges
then G has a bipartite subgraph with at
least M over two edges so let me remind
you the definition of a bipar graph is
one where I can partition the vertices
into two halves or two sets of vertices
and all the
edges go from one side to the other so
that's an example of a bipartite graph
and what this theorem is saying is that
if we start with any graph G
with some number of edges in this case
five
edges I can find a pretty large subgraph
by keeping at least half of the edges of
G for example we can do this keeping
four of the five edges to get this
subgraph G Prime and this graph G Prime
is now bipart
because I
can put these two vertices on one
side and these two vertices on the other
side so that you see all the edges go
from the red or the pink vertices to the
green vertices and none between the pink
and none between the
greens so this is an example of um
finding a large bipar subgraph in a
graph G now let me prove this theorem
illustrating the probabilistic
method so we're given this graph G and
what we'll do is
assign
a
color which will be either black or
white
uniformly and independently at random
to each
vertex of the graph
G so imagine flipping a coin for each
vertex and coloring each vertex black or
white after doing this we can put all
the white vertices of G on one side and
all the black vertices of G on the other
side okay so now G has some number of
vertices and there will be some edges
going across from white to black some
edges within white and some edges within
black there could be a lot more edges
but that's an example of what this graph
might look
like and now let me take G Prime to be
the subgraph
consisting of
edges with white on one end and black on
the other end so two different colors on
the two edges two end points of this
Edge this is a subgraph it's a subset of
the edges of
G and note
that
every
edge of G
has
probability 1 half of
Being in G Prime because for this Edge
there are four different
possibilities for what the endpoint
colors might look like and these four
possibilities are equally likely and
exactly two of them will create an edge
that falls in G
Prime now knowing this by linearity of
expectations the number of
edges
of G
Prime here G Prime is a random subgraph
right where G is given G Prime depends
on the coin flips that we made to assign
colors so it's a random subgraph so the
number of edges of G Prime is a random
variable but this random variable has an
expectation and we can compute this
expectation using linear of expectations
because each Edge Falls in G Prime with
probability 1/2 and therefore the total
expected number of edges in gpre is
m/2 this is the expectation this is what
happens on
average
does some instance
of G
Prime
has at least m/2
edges right if on average we get M over2
edges then there must be some instance
with at least M over2 edges and this G
Prime is what we're looking
for it has at least M over two edges and
it is bipartite because we've kept all
the edges from the black side to the
white side and so this G Prime is
bipartite this finishes the proof of the
theorem and you see that by introducing
Randomness we can prove something about
the existence of a structure with
desired properties and it's a hmark of
the probabilistic method and it's an
important meth me that has lot of
applications and this is one of the
simplest examples of its applications