So I'm uh Mark Shirley, chief strategy
officer for Evolo. I'm here representing
uh Jimmy Roas in MIT class of 2016, our
founder and CEO. He's at investor in
Bent in uh New York City.
So couple things that we're working on
here as we uh develop water electrolysis
equipment. It's really about trying to
change the entire electrochemical
industry. Uh couple of things, number
one, constraints on the grid as we're
hearing make it difficult to access the
large amounts of electricity that are
needed for uh electrolysis. And
secondly, many of these devices have
require critical materials which are not
made in this country and are difficult
to get a hold of. and the manufacturing
is is uh challenging. So when we set out
to start Evolo, we wanted to build a
platform of uh chemicals that we could
make by electrochemistry by making the
lowest cost electrolyers out there. So
starting with hydrogen and uh or water
electrolyers. I'll talk some more about
that going into the market, but there
are lots of things you could make
ammonia, CO from CO2. So you could do
carbon capture and then turn that CO2
into CO and make other chemicals ethane,
ethanol, methanol, etc. And then finally
you can do refining processes like
lithium to lithium hydroxide and uh
improve the uh friendliness of those
processes.
So how does it work? First of all on the
left side we make everything all the
repeating components by rollto-roll
processing. Think newsprint. Okay, I
know newsprint is going out but when you
see the speeds at which those components
are made uh typically today electrolyer
manufacturers do not make them by
newsprint or or by roll to roll. They
stamp them or something like that. It
greatly reduces the cost factory. Number
two, we use all common materials. It's
stainless steel. There's a little bit of
aluminum. The top and the bottom are
made out of plastic. Uh the materials in
the electrolyer cells are stainless
steel, a little bit of of hydrocarbon
membrane and so on, which greatly
reduces the materials cost as well. such
that you're able to look at a cost for
electrolyer stack below $200 a kilowatt,
maybe even below 150 or $100 a kilowatt.
And then the last piece is because we
design it in such a compact form, it's
got the highest power density of any uh
water electrolyer on the market, you're
able to operate that directly with
renewables
um and connect it to a solar array. In
fact, some of our first projects are
looking at that. And by going off-rid,
you greatly reduce not only the cost of
the electricity, but likewise the cost
and time to connect to the grid.
So, let me talk a bit about that. Uh,
our product, we just had a press release
on this yesterday, direct connection to
solar. Uh the the panel on the left, I
won't go through the details, but all
the parts that are exed out are things
you don't need if you go straight from
the the PV array from your photovoltaics
all the way to the electrolyer.
And that greatly reduces the capital
cost of the system. Not only that, but
you're also avoiding long equipment lead
times, interconnect cues, uh, grid
connection fees, backup, uh, power
supply charges, etc. Don't have to do
that. It makes smaller scale projects
very economical, and I'll talk some more
about this. Materials handling is one.
In warehouses, you've got a rooftop with
lots and lots of area. You can drive
anywhere from 3 to 10 megawws of
electrolysis capacity making tons per
day of hydrogen which can go anything
from materials handling to uh short uh
duration uh fleet fueling so on and so
forth. Uh and so uh one of our first
projects, I'll say a bit more about
this, is a major warehouse operator, one
of the largest in the world, who wants
to do rooftop solar for truck fleets and
materials handling forklifts near the
port of Long Beach. So they would run
back and forth to get material from the
port and then break that into loads
which will go to other warehouses
utilizing hydrogen in the trucks as well
as in the forks. Um and so we're looking
to install about six megawatts of that
on a single project in 2026 and hundreds
of megawws following on behind. So what
are kind of the areas which look
promising? uh warehouses in logistics as
I mentioned uh in sustainability where
people are reducing natural gas usage
even in applications which typically
aren't appreciated for hydrogen use
thermal oxidizers or certain kinds of
heat high value heat uh you can utilize
hydrogen if you make it low cost enough
and then likewise in future stages
chemicals being made from these
electrolyers in a way that greatly
separates them not just from the natural
gas usage that typically goes into them.
But now they become distributed. You can
make them for example ammonia which is
highly toxic. You can make it where you
use it in the agricultural areas.
I'll uh stop there and see if there are
any questions.
>> Thank you Art. So, I'll start with one,
but um please pose your questions to the
chat or the Q&A tab. So, um why is Abola
wanting to adapt the water electrolyers
to the manufacturer of other chemicals?
>> Well, twofold. So, we set out to make a
better electrolyer stack and with a
better manufacturing process and in
doing so, we focused on hydrogen first.
But the truth is with a change in uh
some materials with a change in some of
the catalysts you could make any one of
those uh reactions happen within the
same stack. So the idea here was start
with hydrogen as a near-term opportunity
and you see some of the projects that uh
we're working on but likewise develop
the technology such that you can apply
it in a broader range of electrochemical
devices. So it forms a platform to be
able to do these reactions.
>> Thank you. And um what could you expand
a little on what you call the real
problem holding back green um hydrogen
from mass adoption?
>> Uh you you see it every day in the press
that hydrogen projects get cancelled and
and they never reach a final investment
decision and move ahead. The big
challenge is is that in particular the
sachs which can make up a large
proportion maybe a third or more of the
cost of an electrolyer plant. They're
too expensive to make by existing
techniques. Uh and they have poor uh
efficiency in terms of converting
electricity into hydro and water into
hydrogen and oxygen. So what we see is
as a way to derisk the entire process
have a more reliable uh manufacturing
process through roll-to-roll processing.
Likewise to make it less artistal if you
will where things are made by hand and
more in a professional manufacturing
facility where human hands don't touch
the stacks at all. And we find that as
we engage customers here, their real
issue is I can identify a stack that
works for my needs. I can't get enough
of it to manufacture to be manufactured
in the time frame. Uh some manufacturers
take up to two years to make the
electrolyer stacks for a single project.
So that becomes a real limitation when
you're trying to do larger and larger
projects going forward.
>> Okay. And um just quickly connected to
that, what is um another thing that you
look for when um you're looking for uh a
partner?
>> So we uh deal with a lot of project
developers. These are often very large
private equity funded or you know they
from wealth management systems etc.
trying to develop these projects of
perhaps hundreds of megawatts. We're
looking at uh engineering partners who
can do the engineering work to design
those largecale uh processes.
And uh likewise on the smaller scale
like the the warehouse and logistics
part we're looking for people who can
package these systems in the graphics
you see on the right. We make the stacks
that's all we make. Other people can
build the packages which are then
deployed at a number large number of
locations around the world.