okay any question U problem set four was
just turned in a couple people have um
have asked for and been granted uh small
extensions on that so I'm not going to
uh be talking through the solution set
today but anything that came up that you
found interesting appalling uh strange
Adam for the T and the I I use that o of
n factorial algorithm the O of n
factorial algorithm how how high can n
get 25
25 for what so if I had 25 notes and I
was trying to find optic or obdc it
turns out within a few seconds yep so so
with the O so you have an O of n
factorial algorithm which is uh usually
one of the worst you'd ever be thinking
about except for n to the n n to the n's
worst right I can't remember there the
types of things as a professional music
person you don't really have to think
once you're thinking about things this
bad you usually don't but um but yeah uh
25 was the number that I was weirdly
thinking that would constrain n anybody
have a different number that often comes
up in music for the max the end yeah 12
12 with 12 pictures so you can end up
with an algorithm that is O of 12
factorial which is decently big but not
too bad um which reduces to O of one one
very slow one but o of one so I don't
think that that would be that bad I
believe there is an there is an
algorithm that runs in uh o of n time I
believe yeah or it may it might be o of
n^2 I'll look back at it so there is a
way to go better but good good for this
class again we're not you're not going
to be quizzed on your algorithmic
complexity of your um work but um it's
always a good thing to be thinking about
as we uh do things I've um I took the
summer to look through all the places
where I wasn't using Heap tables I don't
know if
anybody do they cover heaps in 6 uh
69 or
66 okay yeah so the idea of an
organization that allows you to any
point get the smallest or the largest
value but not everything else is sorted
and that can be a very useful um tool
often but good but most of the things
aren't going to be on that any other
questions or weird concerns that come
up I'll be curious out after class to
figure out where 25 comes from I just
put in 25 notes and then C actually
killed a lot of effort yeah yeah so so
as long as you do your cardinality or
your what's the other
one oh yeah but what's what's the op
octave yeah sorry I was hearing optic
but but you were saying octave which is
correct as long as you've done something
like that you're Pro an op the OPC which
is almost always um a requirement for
using t or I because the transposition
operation um in some or the
transposition in operations can in some
cases not be well defined if especially
if you're thinking of a chord um what
when you invert it does do the order the
notes change in a Melody the order you
know obviously matters more good yeah
can you give some intuition for when
inversion is useful I like in doing the
assignment I just to wrap yeah yeah so
what when is it useful the one of the
first um reasons why it can be uh useful
is a lot of composers have thought it
useful including um tal composers like
Bach but uh 20th century composers uh
like Arnold schernberg or car hunch
stock Housen they've used um inversion
Cemetery a lot the other the other thing
is that things are inversions of each
other
um have the same um interval structure
so if you're playing with a piece and
you're thinking about oh how can I reuse
those intervals um that can uh that can
be a place that's done um I I think it's
um you know you can Google online people
singing Happy Birthday in inversion and
stuff like that so quite a number of
people do hear it in special cases as an
equivalence class um as we we saw with
the um Gustaf Holst uh example where the
sixth time through the shakon theme he
decides to play Upside Down do you
remember that from the band thing that
we have so that that's one of the places
that's the there um I think we've moved
to a world that's different from even 25
30 years ago where it was this notion
that oh eventually we're all going to
hear inversions uh the way we hear
transpositions and I think that that's
uh not something composers are asserting
as much great
question other things um there's one
case and I haven't run your things
through it that is uh interesting that
almost
all here I'll just go over here almost
all
musical structures that have the same
built on the same numbers of
intervals like once you do reduce them
OCT equivalent and so on such as you
know here we have a major third
especially if we don't care about
spelling and here we have a minor third
and together we have a perfect fifth
um and here we have M minor major
perfect fifth major Triad Minor triad uh
most cases that chords that have the
same interval content can be transposed
or inverted to make each other and
there's a the cool thing is there's a
very few exceptions to that uh rule um
two of the most famous one is is any
transposition or inversion of this um
I'll use pitch class numbers
37 so
that's
and
4 terrible that's an e 4
6 0 1 4 6
um somebody while I'm getting a new pen
verify that those
are those have the same interval content
do they both have a semitone
somewhere yeah between the zero and the
one right do they both sorry you need
you do need that better pen before you
do it do they both have a whole
step yeah where where's the whole step
in the first
one 1 to three yep it's written this way
with spelling uh thing so it's a little
hard do they both have a minor
third do they both have a major
third yes this one's a little bit harder
yeah so two things at four there's the
major third it's a major third do they
both have um a perfect
fourth yeah and yeah where's the perfect
fourth in this ah so
this this one pretty easy and here the
perfect fourth is because we have octave
equivalents we just move this one up and
then we get a perfect
fourth and do they have a
trone augmented yeah this one's pretty
easy because there's a trone from the
lowest to highest and here it's between
the first and the last this one's
particularly interesting because any
four note chord will have six um
intervals in it and if we think of how
many how many semmit tones how many hold
steps how many minor thirds major thirds
perfect fourths trones and everything
else above that is just an inversion of
these uh they each have one so these are
um SI it's called the all interval Tetra
chords and the fascinating thing is that
you cannot invert one to make the other
there's only a few things like this and
they they're called Z
related nobody really knows what the Z
stands for um it's not a Russian
propaganda thing or whatever um so
they're z- related and they always come
in
pairs if we use a 16 tone system then
all the z- related things come in in
triples and somebody has worked out the
math if we use a 30 tone system they all
come in groups of five and stuff and
it's a one of these things that we that
those of us in the music theory have
never um worked with a mathematician to
figure out what the general pattern is
of where Z related um systems come okay
nice little side but um kind of the fun
things you can do uh if you're doing a
little bit more pure math side uh less
computation yeah Jake that be an
interesting final that would
be that would be a final project that
have a backup planned because do not do
not bet your entire grade on being able
to figure out but but yeah enumerating
um in various things and yep would be
great and a lot of lot of people who are
interested in postt music will be
interested in that good
okay let's move off the computer we're
gone from computer to math to let's go
to Pure music I'm going to play in a
second but you can get started the
Corral that I've passed out for you the
class theme Corral Allelujah Allelujah
um Corral and your job talk with other
people around this is first to spend um
let's spend five minutes just doing
whatever Roman num numeral or other
analysis you've been taught on this
project and let's not all start at the
beginning so that some of us can have
some interesting comments about the end
or something but just
pretty 5 minutes until I give more
instructions if you talk with each other
you'll make fewer
mistakes okay let's uh bring it back for
a
second everybody I'm going to start by
asking people for um something that they
found interesting let's let's um let's
let's number guys let's number our
measures so so one measure 1 2 3 4 five
six seven 8 nine did I count that right
um so I just so when you say if there's
something interesting in a specific
place um that I want to know it um well
we'll just we'll jump around a little
bit Jason what' you find that's
interesting uh I believe
the starting the end of the first uh I
think it's 511 and then uh 51 51 uh and
the following one is basically 5151 but
an minor inste oh so we have so your
interesting thing is that we have some
sort of um I don't know what do you call
it modulating
sequence
modulating or a repetition on different
keys this is the one I wanted to get rid
of
good uh let's see
uh who hasn't been calling for a while
Angelica it's Weir that they Choice the
exra minor because if you're looking at
an a major it's like equal to
maor so we're we're starting in you in a
major and then it goes to the what' you
say the when it goes to minor it's a key
to like go from from a major because it
goes between like a six and third so it
goes between it goes down a sixth and
then what then like it goes between a
major third and sixth chord minor six oh
it goes from a minor sixth chord to a
major sixth chord something cool great
super very interesting uh we'll keep
going
who hasn't been called
Jordan um something interesting I guess
is I was trying to figure out what the
cord was when measure two the
last yeah I don't know if to call that
yeah who who who gave a label to a chord
here okay good let's let's see Matthew
what what label did you give it 56 of
six five six of six and for those who
don't yet translating those numbers to
symbols in head were you thinking of
something
like okay um I can over time you do
learn to hear the lower cases and the
slashes and the and the things what's
what's in Roman numerals and what's in
Arabic uh anybody give a different thing
for
that yeah I ja a question wa just let me
let's let's finish on this particular
question yes okay go ahead yeah so like
um worked from the end so um yeah I just
kind of assumed it was an F minor like
this was just like this 56 so this was
just in 56 good so I think we're getting
to our next question how many people um
noted a key change in the piece not
everybody got far enough to do one
person did two people you presumably did
or did not uh I mean I only got through
like halfway through measure three
that's fine that's fine good uh and
anybody not find key chain so John yep
so for those who um for those who did
think of a key change where did you put
the key change Adam between measure
seven and eight between measure seven
and8 five six 7 between here key change
good any other things Jason I didn't get
that far but it does feel like there's a
key change like between two and three
between two and three great um where
would we put it
exactly if if you are if you are buying
Jason
S if Adam if if you're going with
Jason's where would you put that in
between the two mens of that eight
letter word within the for second
measure third and fourth beats second
measure between third and fourth beat
just after the f
anybody would place it another
place anybody think that you know it
might be ambiguous and we might be um
kind of floating between two keys for a
while when we do certain key changes
anyone ever think that uh I would
there's a a type of P chord that chord
thing that begins with a p that some
people use for that yeah John piery
piery is is a type of cord and it does
apply to this piece where where do we
see some uh that might be a picker
D anybody picker D
third uh major third in a minor
context good the very last chord very
last chord yep think the p word you were
looking for is Pivot pivot yep so we
went with two different ones we great we
got two different great uh P chords
there yeah so pivot chords are what some
people use to say that oh you know that
this is the moment when we're in two
keys for a while and I remember asking
my teachers well can there be a pivot
region and one teacher said no now you
choose a chord and stick to it and then
another teacher said no no of course
there could be so um good any any um oh
a couple things uh for those who did do
the end or get to the end uh how many
thought we were in a major at the
end how many thought we were in F
major how many thought we were an F
minor couple
how many thought we were in another key
Al together drian no okay good that last
one's the only one that I wouldn't have
liked uh somebody who thought we were in
F major um explain to the F minor people
why they're
wrong yeah go ahead think well like the
all the aars in the last two bars are
indicator but also um I think we thought
that the verada measur 7 uh sounded like
uh like the dominant five after
but it end up resolving into major in
the next quarter which kind of for the
next okay good um couple things that I
heard that's always a very good um way
of not necessarily winning but advancing
an analysis argument you said it sounded
like good always always think and let
our ears do it not just what's written
on the paper somebody who is an F minor
winner um what try to convince the F
major people that they're wrong yeah
John quite a bit piece we hear hints a
lot at uh minor so like you have a lot
ofor cords leing to up minor so last
kind be seen as Bob just like kind of
stylizing things keep keeping it still
in minor so a stylization but it doesn't
change uhuh yeah so we can have a
disagreement on this um I'm not going to
say at this moment which side I'm more
on because uh I I can see the validity
of both sides
um I can't because I know the world of
Bach I I myself cannot really hear it as
oh we're still in a major and we um are
ending on the sixth chord and the sixth
chords are very important but on the
other hand if I listen to a lot more uh
contemporary popular music where six is
a perfectly valid chord to to begin on
and occasionally to end on um seemed you
know quite quite possible good so we
just spent 30 minutes looking at one
Coral in
particular um and that's not something
we're going to do very often in this
class but that is the normal way of
analyzing music right so what I um want
to do is to bring up the concept of why
what we're doing with Corpus analysis
which is what we're going to be doing uh
for most of the rest of the um of this
unit um so I'll just put this up for a
second and there's a there a way I can
blank this does that
work yep there we
go so we often think uh you may have
heard this in one of your literature
classes about close reading you know
where you're looking through in finding
all of Mark Twain's metaphors or all of
uh Jane Austin's foreshadowings and how
many Greek rooted words are used in this
sentence this paragraph compared to uh
the Latin words or the Anglo-Saxon ones
and stuff so close reading is the main
type of literary analysis um starting
about uh it goes back to sort of the 80s
but really in the last 20 years there's
been a movement associated with the
computer
um called distant
reading the other people were doing this
before but um the term is connected to a
literary critic named uh Franco Moretti
and that's not going to be on exam or
anything but uh so the notion is that
distant reading is something you do when
you're not close enough to the text to
really make these kinds of precise
arguments but you are far enough away
that you can see not just one text but
multiple
texts so uh some of us who work on
Corpus Studies have started in music
have started replacing these terms with
close
listening which is conventional music
analysis
and distant
listening which is Corpus
studies
um
what what do you think some of the
things that we can do with close reading
or close listening better close anal
analysis whatever you want to call it
better than distant
analysis yeah CL analysis we can't look
for specific phrases motiv specific
phrases or motifs
yep anything else you
think and let's let's think of sort of
the world we're in today not not the
world of of 5,000 years in the future or
maybe 5 minutes depending on what
happened at open a today but um you know
where the computer can do many things it
can't do
but what are some things that we that
we're going to start
losing yeah yeah what makes distance
dist listening different mean because
like in a corporate study can study
everything
close sure so let's let's let's think of
some of the things um let's think of
some of the things we we'll go back to
literature Stu what are some of the
things that humans are good at in
picking out of literature that computers
are still not very good ATA um like more
abstract like we can be like oh this is
an illusion like Shakespeare so similar
like we can like notice patterns that
like are hard to really yeah condense
into like one formula function can be
like oh this like is a similar Melody to
like something that was us previous um
so that's a good one other things what
about for you um let's let's let's start
with some one that that's hot in my head
but I really want to make sure we don't
lose track of this um anyone have a
piece of music they
love okay almost everybody good good
good how did you fall in love with that
piece of
music um listening to it listening to it
good how many people have fallen in love
with a piece of music via Corpus
studies via o ooh this one has 47% of
Sharps and so let's let's not forget
that the reason why we make music and
listen to it is the enjoyment happens at
the a close
level um the other thing I was thinking
of with the literature is this character
I'm writing um reading crying in Hmart
right now I don't know if anyone knows
this Memoir but the car one of the
characters in it is going through a very
similar experience that I went through
in my life um with the family death and
it was very deeply resonating with me so
um
resonance outside your
life or outside not outside your life I
can't really outside my life outside the
text and we'll use text to mean both
literature and
music um so there are some what are some
things that however that distant
listening or distant reading that is to
say having a computer look at a thousand
pieces might do better than close than
close re let's first first assume we
have infinite time then close reading a
th
pieces yeah it can allow you to more
effectively when listening to a new
piece guess who the composer was or what
the time period was
okay so you could use that yeah distance
for
guessing uh genre or period
or
authorship you might be able to do that
with the Thousand scores but that would
take a long lot longer good what are
other things we want to solve yeah I
think you could do like a less abstract
way of describing any patterns you might
hear it's like easy to say something
sounds similar but actually analyzing it
gives you words to put that into uh so
it gives you words for describing gives
words for describing
similarity
and what else besides words for
describing similarity what are some
other things that we like to get out of
this
class yeah numbers numbers numbers
statistics so this these are some of the
reasons why um I want to be thinking
this but
I think I I'll just say because I'm me a
couple minutes behind where like to be
that the most
effective way of working with any sort
of new genre new style new anything is
to start with close listening close
reading start with the analysis that
you've done now and try to do things by
hand before moving to the programming
how are we going to do distant listening
how are we going to do teach the
computer to do this because there's
something oh that didn't come up that
the ambiguity and the the types of um
sort of oh I'm going to have to make a
judgment call on this on where the
modulation happened or is this really um
five six of six or did we already jump
directly to the new key or um is this
thing that I'm labeling actually a cord
at all or is a whole bunch of passing
tones that happen to look like a chord
these kinds of ambiguities are things
that will
um that I think will come up when you're
doing the close listening close
analysis and that you'll know you have
to account for them in some way during
the distant analysis and sometimes
accounting for them in some way is just
leaving a footnote saying there's this
really complex problem but I only saw it
twice in close listening to four pieces
so hopefully we can ignore it as a
rounding error but at least declaring
that then when you've done your Corpus
study there's something really valuable
about finding things that are
interesting there right what's that
piece that
completely throws that outlier piece
this completely throws out and going
back and listening to it maybe it
doesn't even have to be close listing
but actually just human listing so that
we get what's the end result why why we
do any of
this so we can get to the enjoyment the
point of trying to do one of my dream
projects you you all have heard of imslp
huge seat music score I want to find the
most interesting unusual piece by every
minor composer that's on there that has
the thing the one piece that this one
forgotten person that that she or he
wrote that we that we should actually be
listening to maybe it's not even the one
piece this 13 second excerpt that uh
grower wrote that I don't know and I'd
love to know it uh we're not there yet
not there yet but maybe we can get
there great um
so the next thing you're going to be
doing is trying to figure out what kinds
of things we can do this kind of close
analysis on we did the Irish music
Corpus uh in class on on Wednesday that
was a pretty small Corpus what 60 pieces
or something um then online I gave you
tools for using the entire Bach Corral
Corpus so if you want to find uh
anything super unusual in there that can
be a good
place but be boring if those are the
only two ones so your next problem set
and it's up is problem set five and let
me put this back up
here so this one um we want to do is in
groups of two prepare three to five page
short paper three pages is except is
totally fine five pages sometimes is you
know might be something you want to do
that tries to figure out some Corpus
that's out there that's been active in
the past 10 years and um try to figure
figure out um how it works so and why
it's out there and what its extent is so
what are the goals of the project who
are the
participants how are the scores or other
musical data encoded I think I've
forgotten to put on here uh what's
actually in there what's the project
actually trying to do I suppose that's
the goal of the project um but what
pieces are collected what is the overall
extent of the problem there is what's it
trying to solve and how much by doing
this and how much of the problem do you
think could be reasonably solved in a
limited
timetable you don't have to do all of
these except for the first one and we'll
get to the last one um what are the
strengths and weaknesses and what could
you do with the scorpus what questions
relevant to this class could you answer
by having this um just like we did with
the uh what questions could you answer
with a whole collection of Bach Corrals
on um was that piece at one or or three
or something like that um you don't need
to use the Corpus to answer it they're
not being asked to download and do the
things but um anyhow uh you'll probably
need to know a little bit about the
kinds of music and the problems
associated with the project and what
they're trying to do and my preference
is that you focus on a corpus of musical
scores sorry it's too high up there um
scores that can be readable by music 21
or something else but if something
really grabs you and you're like this
this is the music I really like and it's
all audio it's all images or something
like that uh go ahead and do that just
um the only two things I'm going to say
imslp and Wikipedia are out uh too
obvious right I've given some places
that you can
begin some of them I was nice enough to
give the links and other ones I'm like n
um and then some directories of
projects and
um and how what you're going to be asked
for URLs screenshots uh how many How
Deeply the questions you were answered
so um hope that you'll find this kind of
fun it's due in a week I what I want to
do is give you now um 10 minutes to um
find the person that you want to do this
work with the only caveat is you cannot
have been in the same pet to group
that's just because um you know when we
do a lot of group work and you have
group grades I want to make sure that
you're um getting uh things from you and
so we rotate that around and um start
talking about what potential types of
things you've seen or um done this is a
good time to Google and mess around on
the internet in class with your
professor's um blessing couple things
going on here that just want to make
sure that we get to we're doing these
big topics uh um you know Corpus studies
representation intervals and stuff like
that but then along the way there's a
bunch of little things that will make
your life easier that you know like
eventually you'll need to know how to
deal with cs and stuff so I'm um make
sure if you haven't been reading through
parts of the music 21 users guide that
you um that you continue to do that and
that this is a place when you want to
know something um there is the users's
guide and the complete reference the
complete reference doesn't really
distinguish between what is uh important
and what isn't whereas uh hopefully
we've done a decent job explaining that
you've should have by now read through
up to um up to chapter six here if you
haven't uh most MIT students probably
won't need to go through chapter five on
uh recursion and lists of lists if
you're in this but um we've skipped
chords and sign called cify for a bit um
I think you can uh well we'll get to
that later um but definitely start
reading through um the music 21 object
thing what is a music 21 object you'll
see durations are not music 21 objects
so not everything that's in music 21 is
one um and basically the easiest
definition is a music 21 object is
something that can go into a stream it
knows how to position itself and it has
a duration and um some other things so
want to go through um this at some point
just to that when I'm giving an
assignment um everything's unlocked here
how you can give um who who has worked
with JavaScript um Dom manipulation like
get Elements by class so so quite a PE
number of people have tried to make
music 21 to be a lot like the version of
JavaScript that was around at the time
in um 20 whenever it was 2006 2007 so
there's things like get element by ID um
get Elements by group group is
equivalent in music 21 to um JavaScript
uh class the class so multiple thing the
dot selector so multiple things can be
in the same group and
um so on and then um there's a nice
little discussion of the thing that will
that will probably drive you baffling
baffled um at some point the active site
which is telling you which stream is and
we uh still haven't figured out who um
that one bug that we saw in class with
the active site being wrong or the get
context by class being wrong so this
chapter um just goes through the basic
things and um it will tell you how to
sort objects which will sometimes be
useful how to move two things are at the
same place and what sorting is
uh the next chapter uh has um a little
bit of the details on how things work
how you can transpose a note and how you
can get back from the transpose note to
its original note and so on except
you're not a yeah I think transpose is
about to be unlocked for you right
because you've just done all of this um
work and um a bunch of other little
things but that's kind of a little bit
boring one so read through that read
through the time signatures and beats
and the keys and key signatures uh this
last one lets you do your first little
algorithmic composition uh exercise
where
um toward the very end sorry scrolling
fast um here we go where we can create a
little Melody something like this
and automatically change it and have um
I don't know why SI this goes
um have a piece of music that I remember
having to play a lot in junior
high and so
on so it's nice to make little
algorithmic pieces um before we write
our first um true algorithmic
composition for um W problem set
8 so uh those are some of the things
that you've probably been looking at
also optionally might want to go through
CS articulations and ornaments and we'll
do a little bit of that right now we're
not going to get um time to get to
intervals right now um okay so let's but
let's let's play with a little bit so if
you have a second and you have your
laptop out and uh if you have Jupiter
able to be got up sorry I should have
should have said that 5 minutes ago like
always um you know like the way the
conductor says I want you to play a
little bit louder and and make sure
speciically separate all the notes of 32
measures after a right you know the
worst worst order um yeah so sorry sorry
about that that's just me vamping while
we give this chance to
um who who cannot see a Jupiter notebook
that's that's on or I suppose you can
all see mine so um given the time with
10 minutes let's um do a little bit of
um more work on um on things you can so
I'm going to import Corpus stream note
meter and we're going to look at um a
couple other little uh things in a piece
by ysep heyen so Corpus parse I'm going
to assign it to heyen
heyen Opus One Number One movement
one so that's than give everybody a
chance to do it and you can show it when
you're
ready this is the first string quartet
that heyen ever published um pretty
young there was mostly an old man
thought of as a sort of old man
composer and start with our um close
listening for even just a few seconds um
until while I grab the recording of this
um what's interesting about the opening
to
anybody
joh it's all in
[Music]
unison do we hear that's all in un
I didn't give you the second page
because I did it in the notebook just
remember you can always um show hien
show U music xml. PDF to get it or just
um to get the whole thing up okay so
it's all in unison at the beginning um
we're not going to do another um thing
like we did with trying to figure out
you what are the where are the notes
outside the key uh and so on but go
ahead and tell me how many how many
notes are there in this
piece so when you've got it I'm not
going to not going to call on the first
person shout out so but let's make just
be sure we can still do something like
that so what what is the question that
we're trying to do somebody how many
notes are there how many notes are there
in this piece so
um what uh who haven't who hasn't been
called on very much check you haven't
called on usually I pick on you too much
what what what um what did you do on
your thing let's I'm assume you started
with hien do something uh I four okay
good
and and then in no do and I
counted no do cter counter
good I equals 0 right I plus equals 1
and then I good anyone so we use the
what kind of what kind of iteration does
this do recurse recurse good
so somebody get that number that's good
I saw a lot of fours in the middle there
um what's another way we could do this
somebody have a different way yeah um
hi.
rec. hien do
recurse doget elements by
class note. note and
then link like yep yeah it's when you
it's when you forget to put that at the
beginning that you really wish python
were more like JavaScript or Java where
you could just do length at the end but
yep good any other ways that people
did okay enough enough note counting U
by the way you hope
that um that this should um
Len also get something pretty similar so
flattening it doesn't matter which order
you're iterating through you're still
going to hit every single thing right
good um okay so let's grab the viola
part I'm going to call it vaa equals and
take the second to see if you can
remember how to do
that and what the question is going to
be uh this will be one of the last
second to last thing uh get the viart
and let's change its cff to uh trouble
cff because um a little bit harder for
us to read who are not vists
you might need to um from music 21
import cff I can't
remember has everyone gotten the raise
your hand if you've gotten the viola
part out even if you not get CL good
good okay so I'm going to put in what I
did um to get that
hidden. Parts Viola notice it's not case
sensitive and let me just make sure I
got the right
one you could also have done
index one two three two right good so
keep going on that so I'm going to go
through a couple ways I did it Viola um
we call it Alto CL hopefully it's that
equals what viola
cf.
cf. first hopefully that's
right or Viola recurse doget Elements by
class clef whatever so um and do this
one here's one of the ways that you
could do that I'll I'll just give the uh
EAS the way that's probably not the best
way but looking at the time um I'll
explain the best way later we can put it
as a g two cluff we're going to change
it and
um piece should be beginning with a
bunch of B
flats and it still is so that's one way
to do it I want to just point out two
things um here notice we did not change
the stem directions of anything so it
looks a little bit weird it looks very
weird when you go from treble cluff to
base cluff or something like that the
other thing is uh what do you call it
Alto C
that now we we have a particular
subclass of clefs so that clefs are in a
taxonic or Alto cluff is in a taxonomy
or morony with a generic
cff taom Alto is another cff great so we
might be having a problem we might need
to see if there's a way we can actually
replace it with another cff thank you I
did broke my promise your 20 seconds
late so um thanks great
class e