At MIT, we tend to view the world a bit
differently than
most. Maybe it's our need to see past
the obvious or our dissatisfaction with
the status
quo. Maybe we're just obsessed with
asking the next question and solving the
next problem.
Whatever the case, we believe that
there's nothing in the world that can't
be made
better, stronger, cleaner,
faster, smarter, more life affirming,
life
saving, life improving.
So we discover, teach, ponder, and
manage. We build, design, and explore.
We invent, innovate, create and cure. We
apply science and we engineer the
[Music]
future because it is exploring and
solving that moves us
forward. It lifts us. It's what makes
the world
better. It's what makes us MIT.
[Music]
Good morning. Hello. Or as we say in
Vienna, Savos to everyone. My name is
Cornelia and with great pleasure I would
like to welcome you here at the
headquarters of the Austrian Federal
Economic Chamber. Welcome to the MIT
Europe Conference 2025.
[Applause]
So as you all know this year's theme is
the future of manufacturing and it
explores the industry's challenges and
also the opportunities when it comes to
global shifts when it comes to new
technologies and of course when it comes
to changing workforce roles. The MIT
Europe Conference is one of the leading
technology and research conferences here
in Austria. And without a doubt, it's
one of the most forwardthinking business
events here in Europe. And right at the
beginning, I would like to take the
chance and invite all of you and
encourage all of you to engage engage
with decision makers, with
entrepreneurs, with executives, with
startups to have a conversation about
the future. So what I can tell you right
away is that we do have a quite
intensive program ahead of us. So I
suggest let's get started. And before we
dive into this year's sessions and this
year's keynote
presentations, let's start with today's
opening speeches. So first of all, I
would like to invite the vice president
of the Austrian Federal Economic Chamber
to join me here on stage. So ladies and
gentlemen, please welcome Carmen Gobi.
[Music]
stage. Dear entrepreneurs, esteemed
experts, distinguished guests, ladies
and gentlemen, imagine waking up
tomorrow in a world where manufacturing
has undergone a radical transformation
overnight. Machines learn faster than
ever before. Materials seem to emerge
from thin air, and factories operate in
seamless symbiosis with AI, adapting to
changes in real time. Picture a
production line that detects and fixes
errors before they even occur.
components that regenerate themselves
when damaged and algorithms that not
only predict customer demand but produce
it in
advance. Self-repairing materials once
confined to the realm of science fiction
are now becoming reality in our
factories. Sounds
far-fetched perhaps, but the future of
manufacturing is not happening in a far
galaxy. It's happening here and it's
happening now and we are at the heart of
it. Why does this matter? Because our
industry is more than just a sector.
It's the backbone of our economy, the
foundation of our prosperity and the
driving force of innovation. If we get
this right, we will not only strengthens
Austria position but shape the way the
world manufactures, lives and works in
decades
ahead. But, and this is a big one, this
future will not shape itself. It demands
courage. It demands curiosity. It
demands action today. Because those who
fail to innovate, those who will
stagnate. and those who stagnate will
fall
behind. With so many claiming to be
experts of the future, the Austrian
Economic Chamber is making a clear
stance. We only work with the best for
our member companies and today we are
very lucky and very proud to have the
best here, the experts of the MIT whom I
warmly warmly welcome.
[Applause]
MIT stands for groundbreaking research
and ideas that change the world. And
today they are here with us to show what
happens when technology meets
entrepreneurship. We will witness the
technologies that will transform our
factories. We will understand how
business models are
evolving. And we will learn how not only
to keep up but actively shape the future
as
entrepreneurs. Think back 30 years ago.
Who would have believed that we would
one day control entire production lines
with a smartphone? And today we do just
that. So what will be possible in the
years ahead?
History has shown us that techn
technological leaps have repeatedly
disrupted entire
industries. The industrial revolution
began with the steam engine. Suddenly
muscle power was not longer the
bottleneck. Electrification made
factories more efficient and flexible.
We saw computers and automation
transformation uh transform the
workplace. The telephone took 75 years
to reach 50 million users. The internet
just four. Facebook 10 months.
CHTP 5
days. And
today, today we stand at the threshold
of a new revolution. The era of
artificial intelligence, quantum
computing, and automotive systems. The
key difference from the past revolutions
is speed. Never before have techn
technological advances unfolded at such
an exponential pace. What seemed
impossible yesterday is reality today
and will be outdated by
tomorrow. The revolution presents a
unique opportunity for Austria. Those
who make the right decisions today and
now will not only compete on a global
scale, they will secure prosperity for
future generations and open to new
markets. But let's be clear, history has
also shown us what happens when we
underestimate techn technological
disruption. Kodak, we all know this
example, ruled the photography world
until it missed the transition to
digital. Nokia was an undisrupted leader
in mobile phones until the smartphone
arrived. Blockbuster fell to Netflix
because it clung to outdated business
models. Xerox invented the graphical
user interface yet um Apple and
Microsoft turned into billiond dollar
businesses. Those who fail to adapt,
those who fail to
save, they will be left
behind. Our message is clear. We do not
need less industry. We need more. more
industry, more businesses, more
innovation, more
entrepreneurs, more openness to new
technologies. But above all, we need an
unshakable mindset that
progress is not a threat. That's an
invitation. An invitation to think
ahead, to shape change, and most
importantly, to be bold. Our economy is
at a turning point. Global competition
is intensifying. Innovation circles are
becoming shorter. Geopolitical shifts
demand great yet strategic
adaption. But one thing is certain.
Those who have the courage to invest in
research technology and new business
models today will be the leaders of
tomorrow. This is why the Austrian
Economic Chamber is committed to making
the future tangable.
We have transformed our Aenville Austria
into an international innovation and
technology scout connecting Austrian
entrepreneurs with the global leading
innovation ecosystem from the Silicon
Valley to Shaen from Boston to Tel Aviv.
We have built long-standing
collaborations with leading
international universities and research
institutions like MIT, ensuring direct
benefits for our
businesses. Our innovation map provides
companies with guidance and an
increasingly complex technology
landscape. And with the bold community,
we have placed Austria at the center of
a cross-cultural platform.
to bring together leaders, creatives,
pioneers in technology, the creative
sector, policy and research. And for
sure we as Austrian Economic Chamber, we
serve as the driving force in the
Austrian innovation policy.
A look at the world's top innovation
nations prove that success never was an
accident. It is the result of strategic
decisions. We must create conditions
that encourage investment, cut red tape,
and provide young talent with the space
to turn ideas into market ready
solutions because today's technology is
the foundation of tomorrow's economic
growth. And let me make one final point.
Yes, global competition is becoming
tougher, but at the same time,
international collaboration is more
crucial than ever. We are not an island,
and for sure, we are not a
fortress. Austria is a successful export
nation. We can be proud of this. We are
an open country that thrives on strong
diversified trade relationships and fair
trade
agreements. The Austrian Economic
Chamber, we have always been and we will
ever be and we will remain a strong
voice for international
collaboration. This is why we are
committed to
fostering
collaboration not as a one-way street.
We have so much to offer to the world
precisely because we continue to learn
from
it. We are living through a time of
transformation. Artificial intelligence,
sustainable manufacturing, quantum
computing and advanced materials are
reshaping how we work and how we
produce.
The question is not whether the change
will happen but how we will use it and
whether we will shape them. What role
will Austria play? We will be consumers
of merge
technologies or the pioneers to lead the
transition. The answer is up to all of
us. Let's not just observe the future.
Let's actively create it. Let's do it
with vision, with courage, and with the
belief that Austria can be a global
leader in
innovation. Today is not a day for small
thinking. Today is a day to be bold.
Let's shape into this future with
curiosity, with passion, and with the
determination to shape the future of
manufacturing ourselves. Ladies and
gentlemen, a very warm welcome to the
MIT Conference 2025. Let's create the
future together and let's start
today. Thank you very much Carmen
Gobi and I am now very much looking
forward to welcoming the second guest to
join me here on stage. He is the
director general of the Federal Ministry
of Labor and Economy. So ladies and
gentlemen, please join me in welcoming
Florian Fracha.
[Music]
So welcome one more time. It's good to
have you here with us today. So we
already heard we are living in
challenging economic times and it seems
particularly important to um on one side
strengthen research and innovation but
as common go already mentioned of course
also to promote international
cooperation. So how exactly does the
Austrian government provide this kind of
support? Thank you so much and uh good
morning to to everyone. First maybe also
let me welcome our friends from MIT.
Thank you so much uh for joining us
today. Also a big thanks to the Austrian
Chamber of Commerce for organizing this
this conference. It's a big honor for
for us as a ministry for economy to
support this conference again. Um I'm in
in charge uh uh for innovation and for
international relations at the federal
ministry for labor and economy and I
think in both fields uh we can profit
from the from this cooperation. Um uh we
uh already heard how important
innovation uh is and uh I think u um
Austria can learn a lot from MIT when it
comes to innovation and when it comes to
entrepreneurship it's uh really really
important and um uh as you mentioned we
have really challenging times at the
moment uh when we look at uh uh growth
not only in in Austria but in whole
Europe. And I think in the in the short
uh term we have to uh lower energy
costs, lower labor costs to cut red
tape. But uh in the long term,
innovation is key. And so the the
Austrian government uh the new Austrian
government decided uh also uh with a
quite difficult budget situation at the
moment that we will invest more in
innovation in R&D and uh we set us
ourself the goal to have a R&D quot uh
of 4% uh in 2030. We are already uh uh
quite good in in Europe. We have now
3.3%
that's number three in in Europe. But we
want become first uh in Europe and with
that we will be a world leader in
innovation. That's our goal and um there
we have to invest. I would also like to
take the chance and talk a little bit
about the challenges of international
trading. So international trade also
faces a number of major hurdles as we
all know. So how is Austria reacting to
this? Um I'm I'm still a fan a big fan
of fair and free trade. Uh but yeah as
you said uh there are some uh other
players worldwide that don't share this
vision anymore unfortunately. Um so I I
think it's really important uh that uh
not only as Austria but as Europe uh
first uh we we look to new markets where
big growth is that we look to partners
where big potential is Austria is a
export nation. we are uh in the top 10
uh uh exporters nations worldwide when
it comes to per capita term. So it's
really really important for our
prosperity in in Austria and um one
thing in Austria is that uh we are still
really focusing uh on Europe uh alone
30% of our exports going to Germany and
I think here we have to diversify that's
quite uh important uh second thing uh uh
important thing is what we as a federal
ministry for economy do we support
Austrian companies companies when they
want to go to new markets, when they
want to to export, we have the the
program go international that is also
managed together with the Austin Chamber
of of Commerce. Uh we had already over
46,000 Austrian companies that
participated in in this program and uh
we offer knowhow, we offer conferences
like this. Um we we offer a direct
funding to help the ocean companies to
go to new markets. We already heard a
lot about the importance of
international collaborations and
cooperations. So I would like to talk
about the transatlantic relations and
how do you see the way forward in an era
of renewed manufacturing focus. Yeah. Um
I I think the the uh bilateral relation
between Austria and the US uh uh are and
will also in the future be uh of really
really big uh importance. Um the US is
our second biggest trading uh partner
after after Germany and for that it's
really important that the bond between
Austria and Europe and the US uh will
will remain strong also in the in the
future in a political way in a economic
way and in a
academia way and I I think we as Europe
we have a lot to to offer. uh uh uh we
have uh 450,000 uh uh consumers. We have
a strong uh industrial basis especially
in uh in Austria. We have a really top
researchers in uh in Europe and in in
Austria. So there's a lot of potential.
So I I think the way forward is to to uh
negotiate and to find uh solutions where
also both sides can can profit from.
Thank you very much. It's a great
pleasure to have you here with us today.
Please give a big round of applause for
Florian Fracha. Thank you so
much. Thank
you. And I'm now very much looking
forward to the next to the third opening
speech of this year's MIT Europe
Conference
2025. And please join me in welcoming
our next guest. She is the executive
director of MIT corporate relations.
Please give a warm welcome to Gayafrey
Shini Vasan.
[Music]
Well, thank you so much. Um, first of
all, good morning. Um, I'm thrilled to
be here in Vienna. This is my first time
and it's a beautiful city and I really
thank uh everyone for this opportunity
to be here and welcome you to our 2025
MIT Europe conference. As I look around
this room um I'm excited to see so many
uh dedicated individuals passionate
about in innovation and collaboration.
Um today we gather not just as
representatives of our respective
industry and organizations but also as a
part of the global community um that
believes in the power of connection and
partnership. At MIT corporate relations
um we are committed to building u
meaningful relationships. Um
and I wanted to um talk to you about you
know we we uh try strive towards
building strategic um partnerships and
creating lasting impact and as we
explore the opportunities and challenges
of our interconnected world as we heard
the previous speakers um I'm reminded of
the importance of collaboration and
mutual support. Our work at MIT is more
than just forging connections. Uh it's
also about creating this network of
individuals, network of collaboration
um and driving uh positive change um on
a global
scale. So this is who we are at MIT. We
have
17,490 employees. We have about 1100 uh
faculty members and researchers. um uh
in terms of faculty is 1100 but uh about
4,200 researchers uh which include
postocs and all and 105 Nobel prize
winners. So um that that tells you the
scale of you know impact that we have at
MIT. Uh we have 4,500 undergraduate
students and we have uh 7,400 graduate
students. So from a student body it's
about 12,000 uh students um and 12% are
international. Um with that uh I also
wanted
[Music]
to oh do I point
here? Okay there it is. Um so I just
wanted to talk about uh industry
sponsored research and research impact.
Right. So if you look at uh what we have
at MIT, we have 65 plus research labs uh
centers and programs. We have about 840
million coming in from uh research
sponsored research on MIT campus. We
have about 608 US patents that were
awarded in FY 24 fiscal year 24. Um 323
uh issued patents. um about $40 million
in licensing revenue and 25 24 companies
formed in um 2024 fiscal year 2024. So
that gives you a a view into who we are
at MIT from a research impact uh
standpoint. Um we uh work
collaboratively across the different
departments, fields and institutional
boundaries. And as somebody mentioned, I
mean the uh we are not an island. Uh I
think uh you Carmen you mentioned that
we are definitely not an island right we
are a very um um uh porous uh institute
we don't have walls anybody can walk in
and walk out so I just wanted to
emphasize the fact that we are very um
uh ingrained in the collaborative uh
spirit at MIT uh nearly half of industry
sponsored research comes from the
industrial um ILP members um member
companies. And so that is uh something
to uh to pay attention to because
through the industrial leazison program
we uh give access um or u showcase the
different uh opportunities within MIT
that would be the right uh opportunity
for you as an organization. Uh and again
always with the emphasis of glo you know
solving global problems and uh through
MIT's expertise um in different avenues.
Oh, sorry. I
jumped.
Okay. All right. Um I did want to uh
emphasize one other thing is that of
course we are great in many different um
uh areas but president Kluth who's our
uh new uh president at MIT she has laid
uh three specific areas where um she
wants MIT to uh focus on global
solutions right um so one is the MIT
climate project um the second one is MIT
heels which is the health sciences,
health and life sciences collaborative.
So solving for real health uh uh
challenges uh and other uh health
related um issues through um this
collaborative and then the last one is
AI and what we have uh create uh
developed uh at MIT is um the MIT
generative AI impact consortium and so
uh the idea is to through this
consortium come up um and come come
together to identify uh key challenges
uh address um solutions for that and
also look at what policies would be the
best.
Now, I did show you what MIT comprises
of in terms of 65 plus centers, 17,000
employees. But what does MIT really uh
encompass? And we encompass um uh five
schools and one college. the school of
engineering, school of science, school
of humanities, arts and uh social
sciences, school of architecture and
planning, uh school of Sloan School of
Management, uh and of course the
Schwarzman uh college of computing and
um so with through these different
schools and college we uh come together
to solve global
problems and when I said we are not uh
an island, we are not an ivory tower, I
want to emphasize ize that by showing
this map. The maroon color that you see
is MIT uh activities or MIT uh buildings
if you will. Um and the rest of it
immediately juxtaposed is uh the
innovation ecosystem around MIT right so
the pink is the biioarma
uh the blue uh the light blue is IT data
I would also urge you to think about it
as tough tech um and then there are dark
blue which is venture capital and the
green which is energy so I just want you
to see that this is all this is not a
full representation um this is just a
sprinkling but I want you to understand
uh what kind of uh ecosystem we have on
campus and this clearly shows you that
um and now I'll come to who we are uh
and I keep saying we are corporate
relations and I talked to you about uh
industry leazison program uh I didn't
talk to you about startup exchange but I
wanted to uh showcase who we are right
we are the gate or the doorway for
industry to access MIT and MIT to access
industry and how do we do that through
the industrial leazison program and the
interconnected uh or integrated startup
exchange program. The idea is for us to
showcase all the um cutting edge
research solutions that we are creating
at MIT through its uh different uh uh
departments uh schools and centers but
also um through our MIT connected
startups and introducing them to uh be
able to connect with you at the right
time uh as appropriate based on your
needs. Um so we have 200 plus members
member companies and we have 800 plus um
uh MIT connected startups that we
connect with uh as um as per your uh
needs. And I also wanted to let you know
that uh our program has about 30
different program directors and we have
a couple over here um that are available
to answer any questions if you want to
uh hear about the industry leazison
program or you can of course come to me
and talk to me as
well. I wanted to uh share with you that
I I said 200 plus member companies and
you may wonder who these member
companies are and this is the footprint
of who we are right we have about 30% in
North America but 40% in Asia 20% in
Europe and the rest of the world so this
is our footprint so truly we are not an
island we are global and so I just
wanted you to have that perspective and
um when when you uh hear about ILP
With that, I'm going to uh welcome you
all uh to MIT Europe conference and I
also wanted to uh thank the WKO for
giving us this opportunity to come every
two years to showcase what we have at
MIT and you know welcoming us the way
you all do uh every every two years.
It's uh it's really incredible and for
me I feel thoroughly inspired to see all
you all all of you and hear about um
what's going on in Austria. So thank you
so much and I hope you enjoy today's
[Applause]
conference. Thank you very
much. And I think up next on stage, uh,
I am now about to welcome Mr. Randall S.
Wright. So, please give a warm welcome
to Randall. It's good to have you here.
The floor is all yours.
[Music]
Okay, if we can start the
slides. Ah, okay. Welcome to the 2025
MIT Europe Conference, the future of
manufacturing. I'm Randall Wright,
program director with MIT's Office of
Corporate Relations. And as your guide
to today's program, together with you,
decision makers, entrepreneurs, business
executives, we will engage with MIT
faculty members, and their colleagues
from sister European institutions in a
conversation about the future of
manufacturing.
Manufacturing is central to the future
well-being of national economies and in
turn the global economy. Yet in the face
of extreme changes in geopolitical
views, technologies, industrial
practices, workforce roles and
expectations, trade policies, and
government and financial institutions,
manufacturing firms face unprecedented
challenges. These challenges are
especially important in the EU given the
rise of economic nationalism and
corresponding national industrial
strategies. Today among some of the most
prominent MIT faculty members together
with colleagues from Frhaer Institute
and Technical University VIN address the
question how must we remake
manufacturing to secure national future
national and global prosperity.