yes of course if we argue if we want to
prove to him that X is in the language
it's essentially we're saying telling
him if you evaluate X on circuit C
you'll get one or maybe if there exists
a witness of that c of the witness c and
x and the witness gives you one of
course we assume the verifier knows
description of this circuit C and
usually and for our purposes you think
of C as being a uniform like a a tring
machine okay so it's a it can be
generated efficiently from a training
machine but yes the verifier can
generate can both the prover and
verifier can generate the circuit that's
uh so if you think of three s you know
the circuit is takes input all the
assignments and it checks that all the
uh uh Clauses are satisfied
that's an example of circuit
yeah is that simar to running
that yeah it's like just yeah so so the
prover essentially computes the circuit
all the gates in the circuit hashes it
and then gives a bar that each and every
gate of the circuit is satisfied that
the value he hased satisfy
each uh respect each gate
because okay so the verifier doesn't
know all these values all these bits
he's getting just the the the verifier
only knows the hash he gets only V he
doesn't know all these things he and he
can't it's there too many of them he
doesn't he he can he knows what the
circuit is but he doesn't run in time
that depends on the circuit the circuit
is too big he just kind of knows in his
head how to generate each gate in the
circuit but he can't uh so he doesn't
know these bits all he knows is the hash
value and the bar which is
succinct
okay any yeah security is going to give
us some lower bound on L right it just
happens a lower bound on what on L and L
yes yeah okay yeah we're going to yeah
yeah yeah we're going to talk now we're
going to talk about sec a soundness so
we'll see uh one thing I want to say
before we we jump to soundness Just note
because I said uh the CRS of the bar
it's we generated with security
parameter Lambda K which is the number
of gates and then I said n Prime we'll
see we'll see what n Prime is I just I
forgot to this is n Prime it's just
security parameter it's like the length
of not n Prime will be the length of the
hash key the length of V which grows
with L and J that's kind of the N Prime
I I'm just mentioning it because I
forgot to Circle back to
it okay are you ready to talk about
analyzing this because that's actually
the very interesting part okay so let's
analyze
a so okay we need to argue completeness
and
soundness completeness I don't want to
waste our time because it's just trivial
it just completeness just follows from
the completeness of the bar and
completeness of of the summer
extractible hash okay so essentially if
you're honest if x is in the language
you compute all the wires
correctly uh you hashed all the wires
and you g if you hated all the wires
correctly then you have a valid witness
for all the wires so your bug will be
accepted if you did everything correctly
everything is going to be accepted
because the completeness of the
underlying primitive okay there's
nothing interesting going on the
interesting part is soundness okay so
how do we know you cannot
cheat
and let me even jump and tell
you this thing is not really
sound
but but we'll make it
sound uh okay so let me okay so what do
we know so sound this so what do we want
to prove
let's hope let's try to hope for so
again there's non-adaptive and adaptive
you can think of both but let's talk
about what does it mean to be let's say
adaptively sound so we need to prove
that for any polinomial size cheating
prover we want to say the
probability that P star takes a
CRS of the bar of the as snar so hash
and CRS for the VAR okay takes the CRS
it outputs some X and
Pi such that X is not in the
language and Pi the the snar is
satisfied V on CRS x Pi outputs
one you want to say that this is
negligible that's we need to prove okay
the probability that a cheating prover
gets a
CRS and generates any ex that's not in
the language and a
proof that's
accepted you can't do that okay you can
do that only with neg
probability let me just mention another
uh more uh a weaker definition is the
non Adept which says for any p and for
every X not so he gives X ahead of time
for any P star
and for any X not in the language when
he gets a random CRS the probability
that he manages to generate a fake proof
that's accepted is negligible so there's
two variants one one he needs to choose
the X a given X for all the crs's or he
can choose an X depending on the
CRS let's talk about the Adaptive
because it's just uh stronger and we can
get it okay at least in some cases so
today the snars in the literature some
achieve adaptive some achieve
nonadaptive and in general the the ones
for the teristic computations are
adaptive the one for nistic computations
are more on the non-adaptive side and we
don't have SN NP so at the end of the
talk at the end of the class I'll leave
kind of like 10 minutes to talk about
kind of where we're standing as a
community but um but both of them are
kind of both definitions are relevant
and we have results in both settings
that adap in the non-adaptive but let's
talk today uh on the Adaptive setting
okay so that's what we want but the
question do we get this so let's try to
see what this construction actually
gives us okay so what I'm going to argue
is actually this construction does not
give us soundness it doesn't give us
what it gives us is kind of a a form of
local soundness so I'll explain what
this means so what I'm going to argue is
that so
claim the snar that I just
constructed is let me call it
locally
sound or locally consistent it's also
people call locally
consistent and I'll explain what it
is okay we want to prove something so
what do we want to prove we want to
prove
that this nnar if you manage to say that
the output is one there's actually an
assignment to all the wires that give
you one that means it's
sound we can't prove
that what can we
prove we can prove that if you argue
that the value is
one I can use you to extract the value
of any small set of wires how many l so
remember our snar we're binding on
allocations these allocation I can
extract you gave me a v that's binding
allocation I can extract I can get from
you the L wire
values so I get L wire's values from you
what I can argue about these L wire
values is that locally they're
consistent so if there's a gate if if I
if the l y vales three of them are
connected with a gate I can argue that
this gate is
satisfied so I can argue this form with
local
consistency so I'm going to Define what
local consistency is but just kind of
high level what I can argue is not that
I have a uh assignment of all the wires
that kind of are consistent inside the
output is is one which is what I want to
argue I can argue that I have an
assignment that I can kind of have a
small window to the wires a window of
size l so I can look at these L wires
and they look consistent and I can look
at these L wires and they look
consistent and output is
one so it seems like okay local now
let's we only need to stitch all them
together to get kind of a final
assignment and we're done so the goal is
we're going to say locally we're
consistent and local consistency implies
kind of global consistency and so we get
to
this okay so the plan we are going to
prove local consistency so that's check
and we're going to Define it and prove
it the local consistency ples
Global that turns out to be much more
difficult than we thought so when we
started working on this we're like oh
local consistency yeah shouldn't PL glob
that should be good so we worked really
hard local local and then turns out
local to Global was another 10 years of
work and we're still we're in progress
in progress so so that's what so what
we're going to see today is how to get
local consistency we're going to talk a
little bit about why local implies
Global and why not okay why is it
doesn't it always imply Global and
hopefully it will give you some food for
thoughts okay so so so I'm G to argue
that it's locally sound and let me tell
you what locally sound means let me
first Define it okay so the definition
so
okay so here's what it
means it means that there exists so this
is I'm now defining what this means it
means that there
exists an extractor we call sometime
sometimes a local assignment it kind of
so some extractor a
local
assignment generator that's another name
we use
e so we have an kind of an extractor
that generates assignments for us this
assignment takes only L wire values on
the circuit so we have a circuit C okay
this this uh extractor or local
assignment generator it gets L wires i1
up to I L they're all in uh the wires
which we denoted by n okay so it takes L
wires and it
outputs some xar an in an
instance and Y values and values wi i1
up to w i this is what our our local
assignment generator outputs for any i1
up to I it outputs some instance and Y
values that satisfy the following such
that
one is local
consistency which means any two wires
any any wires that are connected by a
gate satisfy the gate and the output
wire is a one and if one of them are
connected to input wires then it's it's
consistent with the input Wire yeah so
local consistency just means it respects
all
Gates
consistent with X1 up to xn and out
and you know output
one okay so of course if you just read
wires here and here like uh very spread
that are not connected with any Gates
then the local consistency doesn't say
anything because you can determine the
value of any gate you don't but any gate
for which you have any gate for which
the input and output wires are these or
the output wire or the input wires the
gate should be
satisfied okay that's number one and
number
two is what we call non- signaling I'll
explain number the number two says the
the Y values that he gives here that the
extractor the local assignment
assignment generator
gives the distribution so this is an a
randomized algorithm this extractor is a
randomized algorithm he gives he gives
given these wire he gives a distribution
over xar and wire values the claim is
the distribution of xar for
example doesn't depend on i1 up to I so
the distribution xar in
computationally looks the same no matter
which uh wires you give moreover the
distribution of wi
i1 doesn't depend on I2 up to I so let
me say this
formally formally for every set I and
J of
size L uh let me sorry for any I and J
subset of n so for any set of wires of
size l so take any set of wires like I
went up to I L let me call the first set
I the second set
J what and what we know is if you look
at the intersection of so if you look at
um
a how would I one second just think of
notation so think of let's look at if
you look at extractor and I but only
restricted the coordinate in I intersect
J so the W's there's many there's W for
i1 I2 let's look only the W's and the
location that are both in I and in
J the
distribution of them
looks like it looks it's inting from the
distribution if you looked at this these
coordinates with set J in other words
let's say the intersection of I and J or
I don't know some set of wires put the
set of wires in the
beginning okay it the rest of the so if
you look at a set of wires look at their
distribution their
distribution does not depend and what
the other wires are if you look at the
distribution of these they will look the
same whether the rest of the eyes were
have one form or another form at least
computationally they look the same they
they need not be exactly the same but
nobody can distinguish between the
two okay and this is including this this
is including the xar okay so e is like
uh when I when the extractor here it
means kind of X star and the
w i j
for i j in in I so I include the xar so
even with xar the xar here the xar here
are
indistinguishable okay xar I always
include even if it's empty I include
xar okay so that's a non signaling the
distributions are
indistinguishable and now I want to
argue that we get I can I have this
extractor I'm going to show you I'm
going to construct this extractor
actually very easy to construct this
extractor so if you give me a cheating
prover if you give me any prover forget
about cheating you give me aover I can
construct this local assignment
generator from him and then all I need
to do is argue that a local assignment
gener implies that I can kind of I have
a a a assignment for all like a not just
locally cons consistent but a fully
consistent assignment to all the wires
that give give Alpha One and therefore X
needs to be in the
language that's kind of the proof
strategy so what I'm going to do first
is show you how we get so we're going to
show how given any P star we can
generate a local assignment generator we
can give kind of local assignment to all
the wires that are consistent and
satisfy this kind of noning property and
then we're going to show how to use this
this local assignment generator to get
soundness questions yeah is another
issue with obtaining this
sound comes
fromi the the actually the semi adaptive
soundness of bar is enough for me it's I
I don't need to use you'll see actually
I don't need full adaptive bars it's not
it's I never use it I don't it's enough
for me that the bar only has semi even
though okay that's a good point note I
want I'm going to prove adaptive
soundness and what you're saying wait
but the bar only has semi adaptive
soundness is that enough is it enough to
use only semi-adaptive bar and get fully
adaptive snar yes I will not need the
full adaptivity of the bar we'll see as
we'll see it next I'll use it you'll see
it doesn't come up so it's enough the
problem is to to get this the local
assignment I can get the problem why
this kind of implies global so we'll see
that but the semi it seems it seems
counterintuitive but actually it's
enough was there another question you
have question yeah remember like the X
star oh good good good this is any okay
so the good what is xar no sorry
okay it's okay yeah let me call XA uh
this sorry let me you're right uh the
extract okay
yeah okay so let's think P star output's
kind of a x tlda Crooked Kind of you
know a cheating X so let's use Cricket
like Tilda to den knowe kind of a
cricket cheating thing and he's also
gonna output some
Tilda because it he his is also crooked
and we want to argue that this crooked X
is indistinguishable from the Crooked ax
given by the cheating prover we're going
to yeah and oh yeah so I need to say
that sorry so good so let's say again
the local assignment generator it
outputs x a crooked x with assignments
partial assignments to some of the wires
to the L wires such
that you it's
consistent uh non- signaling and it's
also non and sorry
and X Tilda is indistinguishable from
the X Tilda P star so P star also
outputs X Delta they look the
same note and if if it was non adaptive
it would be fixed so then X XA is fixed
ahead of time nobody will need to
generate them anymore it's fixed and the
and the extractor the local assignment
generator will only give values to the
wires but in the Adaptive setting the P
star you give him CRS he gives you a
different X star the X Tilda sorry now
okay he gives you a different a
different ex Tilda so every time he
gives you a local kind of window it will
be for a with a different X dilda
possibly uh uh in the Adaptive setting
in the nonadaptive setting it's always
going to be with the same X
till okay any any
questions okay let's try to see why we
get local how we can construct this
local assignment
generator okay so I have a cheating Pro
so fix so
proof so fix P star fix a poly
size P
star I want to get an assign uh kind of
a window to the there's the circuit we
have the circuit
C that has X maybe a witness I want use
the C star the P the cheating prover
well he so he's going to give me okay so
fix P star for any CRS he's going to
give me X I'm going to get from him an X
and a window to some of the wires of the
circuit so let's see how so here's my
extractor the extractor or the local
assignment gener it's going to use P
Star as an oracle it's going to make
it's going to make use of P star he's
going to get i1 up to I what does he do
he wants to get the values of these
wires okay what does he do he's going to
run P star he's going to run P star in a
CRS that he chooses so he's going to
generate CRS we'll see how in a second
and then he's going to run P star on the
CRS to get a value and a snar and then
he's going to kind of extract the wires
from this hash value okay so let's see
so how does he generate the CRS CRS is
going to be a piie for uh um CRS bargain
hash key yeah so he's going to
generate he's going to generate hash Key
by you by running gen on this location I
went up to I so what is it so let me
actually he's going to first generate
hash key and trapo
and gen Sumer extractable hash with uh
one to the Lambda number of wires in C
in the circuit and i1 up to I L these
are the wires he wants to extract okay
because he has I went up to I L he wants
to extract the values of these wires so
he's going to give you a hash key that's
extractable on these
locations and then it's also going to
generate uh gen for the bar to get H CRS
bar he's just going to do this honestly
here we has one to the Lambda K and
N and or this is n Prime the N Prime you
know the he's going to generate exactly
as as in the construction and then he
gives he runs now
run P star with hash key and CRS bar
that's the CRS he gives P
star and get V and Pi barg that's
what the P star gives
you
now if this is rejected start again so
if Pi Bar or if if V and Pi
Bar so you know if the verifier with
input oh wait sorry X star also X Tilda
sorry he G so he G the P star gives what
some X TAA because it's adaptive he
gives him some X and a
proof the proof is is a hash value and
the bar that's what the proof is now he
checks if V if the verifier rejects this
proof it's it's not a good proof so if
if V
given CRS which is these two this is the
CRS given CRS given X Tilda and given Pi
this is
pi output zero if it rejects try
again what I mean by try again again
generate a hash key generate a bar
run if this is accept if it's rejected
try again
until I get something
good okay now okay we want we okay until
you get something good once you get
something good you're happy what then
what do you do you output so try again
uh if
success then
output the X
Tilda and what y values extract from the
V so remember this V is Hash of all the
wires of the
circuit extract you'll get the wires
corresponding to i1 of I so outut this
and I'll put
extract with
trapo the value V to get W i1 up to W
iil that's it that's what the extractor
the local assignment generator does why
can you do this I
thought was adaptive so if you change
CRS why can you fix it s no it's not
fixed you're right so what do I do I
generate hash key and a bar I run him he
gives me XA if I'm happy with X if I'm
happy with this proof I output XA the XA
dependent on CRS so given I want to I
I'm going to get a different I'm going
to get a different X still the
every time I get up i1 I generate H CRS
for my
snar I run the pro I get xtia and a
proof If I'm happy with the proof I
output xtia and the extracted wires W's
are just wire values they're not
Witnesses no they're wire values sorry
these are not Witnesses yeah uh yeah I
use W for you know wires but it's also
witness it's
a uh so
sorry
a a bit of abuse of notation sorry these
are yre values okay forget about witness
there's no Witnesses now just wires yeah
yeah if you're like projection sampling
until you get the verifi to accept then
how is the distribution of X be the
distribution of okay uh uh okay that's
good so I'm gonna answer did you you
it's a different question a different
question okay let me first answer this
question so okay I'm GNA um
the question was first there's a couple
issues first of all how many times am am
I going to do this rejection sampling
okay am I going to run forever what's
going on here and the answer is no
actually I'm not not going to run
forever so fix a p star that let's say
is
accepted with non-n
probability Epsilon okay Epsilon is not
negligible
I'm going to try again at
most a I know poly in Lambda and 1 over
Epsilon
times so I'm going to do this only poom
many times okay think of Epsilon as one
over poly Lambda so I'm going to run in
time poly in
Lambda
okay now given that and okay so the
first thing I want to argue you is the
probability that I will and so I'm going
to run the most poly Lambda one overs on
time that's it and you say what if all
of them are reject then I'm going to say
okay I I Was
Defeated okay what is the probability
that I'll be defeated negligible because
each time I'm starting fresh and the
probability of defeat is only ABS is is
uh is one over ah the okay I'm re
I'm I'm accepted I'm I'm okay I'm
accepted with probability Epsilon if I
repeat it you know Lambda over Epsilon
Times by just concentration Bound by
turn of bound I'm going to be accepted
in one of them with very very high
probability okay exponential like
exponential in one like two the minus
Lambda or something like that so if I
repeat it enough times one of them I'm
going to the probability of of Bot of me
kind of being defeated is negligible
okay so now then but now going back to
your question the question is how do I
know that XA here has the same
distribution as the x of P star yeah
that's the question
so a good so
a actually I was a bit sloppy when I say
XA is inting from this I mean in the for
XA condition and accept sorry yeah this
is
condition on P star
accepting so p i can assume without loss
of yeah so and let's think of P star
either is outting bot there's no point
in him giving a bad proof like he's
going to be rejected either is like
defeat or give x with a good proof okay
so the pro so uh my X I always output XA
with property one minus negligible and
this XA is going to be distributed like
X zilda condition on n on the P star not
a boarding yeah those two distribs
actually idal right up to the SL
probability that you give up at the end
no it's uh okay so the question one is
the X Tilla of P star actually identical
to the X Tilda of the extractor and the
answer is not quite because the xti of
the extractor runs gen with these
specific
eyes and X Tilda is run with P star with
let's say one two three up to L I don't
know like a fixed uh and this kind of
the eyes change that's the only
difference and that's why it's
indistinguishable because the p star
doesn't know that because of the index
hiding P star has no idea what the indic
which indices are sitting behind the
hash key so the Exel that he he's given
he gives is the same is
indistinguishable nikan did you are
you make sure last Point each trial here
will work with probability Epsilon minus
because of the index hiding right
exactly you're right yeah you're right
exactly Epson minus that's why the
Epsilon has to be non- negligible
because you lose negligible and if if
you know it needs to be negligible
compared to the
Epsilon so my question was the extract
algorithm for the is only required to
extract when V is an eval of X
right is that true or is that not true a
okay one second
good point uh no um okay the no the
completeness was assuming you know holds
but
uh I didn't write it actually down good
point Nikon thank you
a the uh the summer extractable hash I
didn't say soundness of the I didn't
write like the soundness of this extract
so
uh the extract has the the following
property if the cheating
a if the cheating
prover gives any hold on let me think
for a second
if the cheating prover gives an opening
if if you're extract if the hash key
okay thank you if the hash key is
generated with Gen of I and if an
adversary generated an opening of I a
valid opening so he successfully opened
the I
bit somehow with a B then the extract
will work and give you that same
B so let me let me write it down because
actually we need it here so uh
okay okay uh for
any
uh for any a adversary and for every
I the probability
that a and hash key where the hash key
is generated with I so hash key trapd
door they're generated with Gen with uh
one to the Lambda n and
I if this if he managed to give me a
value adversarial value but he manages
to open with a a b and row so let me
call it it b i and row I such
that the verifier accept it such that
ver so the probability that he gives me
a verify uh um a tuple that verifies so
hash key
v i b row is
one and but extraction fails is
negligible so the probability that this
accept but extract
a is not
b bi is
negligible so if you opened it must be
valid and if you think about the
construction if you open it's like
everything is in the correct encryption
encryption encryption the encryption
must be correct and the extractor will
will
decrypted that's kind of the a
yeah so if he doesn't open anything V
can be whatever you may not be able to
extract but as long as he gave you uh
the correct path then then okay so we'll
use it here thank
you okay uh okay so now let's see why is
so this is but this is the extraction
procedure okay we'll analyze it in a
second we'll see why this is used but
again let me let's just kind of R kind
of uh recall what so what is the local
assignment generator it takes L
wires he will generate a CRS and give it
to the cheating po the CRS he generates
consists of a hash key and a bar and a
CRS for the bar the CRS for the bar he
just generates and the s for the hash
key he generates with a trapo with
respect to the wires that he needs to
extract he gives this to the prover and
the prover gives him
hash value that's extractable on these
wires and a bark proof If the bark proof
is rejected he starts all over so we're
going to do it until we have something
accepted once it's accepted we're going
to just extract these W these uh wires
because we we have the trapo the the
extractor has the trapo we're going to
or the E here we're going to extract uh
the wires and that's what we're going to
Output okay the XA and the
wires Okay so so now we need to argue
non- signaling and we need to argue
local
consistency any questions before I go
ahead and do
it okay so let's see let's start with um
with local consistency okay why why are
things locally
consistent so the I claim that local
consistency follows from the soundness
of the bar okay so let's see why this is
um
I want of
okay what do we have
here
a okay oh well I'm just
gonna we're going to kind of needed but
it's
okay okay so
so local consistency I want to argue
follows from the correctness of the bar
from the soundness of the bar why
suppose for
contradiction so suppose at the
extractor output X TAA and l y values
the not
consistent okay so the ly values are not
consistent then what does they mean
they're not consistent there's one gate
that they don't
respect
now remember so okay so there's one gate
that they don't respect so
suppose e an input i1 up to I L output
like W1 up to W i1 up to w i
l that do not
respect some gate let's fix a gate some
gate J with non- Neal probability if
there's one gate doesn't respect choose
it one at random so won't respect this
random one with probability I mean there
exists one gate that's not respect
probability one over poly
okay Suppose there exist some GJ that
this does not with
probability one over
poly now let's look at the bar what does
the bar say the bar tells me that all
the gates are
respected so what I'm going to do in the
bar I'm going to so remember in the bar
a I have this somewhere now I'm to the
Adaptive versus the why some more
adaptive soundless of bar is enough why
if there's some gay J that's not
responsibility one over poly in the bar
Construction in the CRS I'm going to
hard why I'm so sorry I'm gonna okay let
me construct a cheating prover for the
bar okay so we're going to
construct cheating prover
for
bar that
cheats he's going to be somewhere
adaptive sound is and he's going to
cheat on
J and this specific J I don't care about
what the CRS is yet I'm going to be semi
adaptive so I'm going to tell you my
chover he may choose the X1 star of to x
k star the actual instances later but
which one he's going to choose he's
going to cheat on I'm going to tell you
now it's j so it's going to be S like
it's going to be nonadaptive and where
he's cheating that's kind of the
semi-adaptive
yeah loal consistency is a statement
that the extractor out is that the same
as the statement
that okay so let me tell okay so let me
so you're asking is there a match how do
we match these two so let me okay so
wait let me tell you the cheating prover
so I'm going to construct a cheating
prover let's say Pou star for the bar
okay here's what my pble star does my
pble star he gets CRS of
bar what he's going to do he's gonna
a uh run piece he's going to generate
hash key on his own okay and he's going
to
run P star on the CRS
bar and the hash key that he gives him
he's going to get
V and Pi
Bar and now he's going to cheat pble
star will
cheat and here's the instances that he
gives so he's going to give the
instances adaptively the instances are
going to be hash key V and
J for J goes from one to uh K the number
of
gates these are going to be the instance
so this is going to be XJ
star or x i sorry that's a third go
I so that's the XI star and the bar is
going to be
this so that time that time cheating
okay I
have K instances that I chose adaptively
but I'm arguing that the J one which
corresponds to gate
J is actually it's false this XJ star is
not in the language because I'm
binding on this J and what's sitting
there is false so even if you're just
does not exist of an opening because I'm
binding on these locations what I know
from The Binding condition which
is here what I know from The Binding
condition there is no opening for the
wrong value it just doesn't exist so
there is no
witness for x uh for XJ star but look I
pble star managed to come up with a
proof even though before in the semi
adaptive way he gave me a j a gate
before I got even the CRS he gave me a
gate and nevertheless manages managed to
produce a bar that all my xar and and a
bunch of
xstar and the bar is satisfied but the
J A instance is does not have a witness
contradiction so so the local
consistency really follows from the
soundness of the bar and all we need is
is a a semi-adaptive soundness of the
bar because if you're somewhere not
local consistency not not local
consistent even if there's you don't
need to be even if there's one gate and
which you're not local consistency only
probility Epsilon Epson can be one overk
can be very
small i i i the the claim is on each and
every gate local consisten hold this
property one man is
negligible because otherwise take that
gate and then that gate we're gonna kind
of cheat in the barg that's the instance
that in which we're going to cheat on
the
bar so that's uh that's local
consistency and now you can ask what
about the non- signaling and the non
signaling really follows from the fact
from the index
hiding and and so okay so let's go to
the N so are we okay with local
consistency okay any questions before I
run actually
yeah okay oh sorry I changed yeah sorry
this is J thanks sorry about that this
is yeah so I I give you all this is kind
of an index uh language so I give the
instances are oh ah sorry no these are
all for all I I just J is a specific J
so I don't want to J is the one that I'm
binding on but I give
you the the instances are yeah all of
them are I sorry j is the specific one
on which I'm G to be uh I'm G to cheat
on all all them are sorry about the
yeah any any other questions
okay so so now the question is uh now
what about non- signaling and non thing
I don't want to go into a lot of depth
but um let me be handwavy here uh the
idea why we're non so we want to argue
that the local assignment generator the
the assignment values that he gives for
any subset of wires do not depend on the
other wires that is given to him okay so
if we look if the extractor is given a
bunch of wires and you look at the
assignment on a
subset the the distribution of the
assignment that the that you get it it
looks the same no matter what the other
the rest of the the wires
are and why is that it just follows from
the fact that um did I I just erased it
here uh so it follows from the fact
that when we do a summer extractable
hash with many when we uh construct a
somewh extractable hash with many
indices that were extractable on many
indices we want to have the
property that even if we extracted on
some
indices the the index hiding still holds
for the other so in other words think of
where the way we're going to construct
the sum extractible hash is by
repetition okay we're going to repeat it
many many times so even if even if you
saw if I extracted wire i1 wire I2 wire
I3 the indexes indices behind the other
wires are completely
hidden okay so here when when uh when I
when you look at extract and subset of
witnesses how do you find extract on
these
how how does the how does the local
assignment generator generate these
these wires he gener these wires using
the corresponding trap
doors without the other trap doors so he
actually has no
idea this should not signal anything
about the other the other the value of
the other wires okay so again let me say
it again the maybe I didn't say say it
quite right but the local assignment
generator when he he runs the cheating
prover and the cheating prover he when
you extract from the cheating
prover the value of some of the wires
you need only to do that using the trap
doors for these
wires the cheating Prov has no idea what
the other wires what the trap door of
the other wires are so these values
should not depend at all about the other
a indices
used in the other repetitions otherwise
you broke IND ex hiding for these
repetitions okay so so the point is the
the the a non signaling really follows
in a sense from the non- signaling in
the in in the summer extractable hash
the summer extractable hash when we
repeat when we do repetition what we can
argue is any cheating prover who given
uh
hash key generates a
value if you extract some of the
wir the value you get do not depend on
the other indices this is kind of a
property of the Su extractable hash so
non signaling here falls directly from
the non- signaling of the Su extractable
hash okay so I'm running out of time I
don't want to go too much in in depth
because I find I think it's not as
interesting I want to actually go and
talk about why is this not sufficient
and when is it
sufficient okay so let's so let's call
let's say okay so we have suppose we we
have a cheating prover we manag to to
construct from him this local assignment
generator so we have the
circuit we want to we we have a cheating
prover he gave me an X we want to argue
it's in the language it must if he
convinced me it must me the language
that's what soundness means what do we
know we know when we look at any window
everything looks good and when you look
at the window that contains the output
it's
one does that mean we can have like an
entire uh assignment to all the wires
that everything is consistent in which
case we can then
sound so can we piece these things
together okay so a
so the answer is yes and
no okay so in general for
NP the answer is no we don't know how to
piece it together moreover we believe
that you can't piece it together for any
NP language like we
believe
that it's just there exist very hard NP
languages that there's no way you can
piece it together but let me tell you
why why does why is it hard to piece
things
together and the reason is even you know
let's even think now for Simplicity I
think it would be easier to think let's
say even in the non-adaptive version X
is fixed can we argue that for this
fixed X we have a like we can we can uh
a piece everything together and the
reason why it's hard to piece everything
together is because because this local
assignment generator every time you give
him a bunch of
wires he even think think of a a even a
valid kind of approver okay this think
of a valid prover every time you run him
he uses different Witnesses maybe has
many many witnesses in his disposal
every time you run him he's honest but
with a different witness okay so it's
actually in the language but the
question is are we able to construct
kind of a satisfying assignment and the
reason why this is hard is or seems hard
is
because okay we have our local local
assignment generator we give him a bunch
of wires he chooses one of his Witnesses
at random because that's what the
cheating prover does and gives an
assignment with this the witness okay
local consistent we're fine we're happy
now we run him again he uses a different
witness it doesn't match things like you
know how do we match things together so
that's why in the non-deterministic case
things are really difficult okay and we
do have some results but for very
specific languages let me not go into
that let's talk about the teristic
languages that seems to be much easier
so let me first convince you that we can
do it and then I'll show you where I
cheated okay so let's first take a a
circuit we have a local assignment
generator so let me convince you that
that one must be one okay so we have an
input X1 up to xn
okay I'm going to call my local
assignment generator I'm going to tell
them give me the values
here or here let me I have L right so
let me use my L here here and here I
don't know he gives me values now this
must be consistent because I know local
consistency hold to one minus negligible
so and all of them are consistent okay
which means these are the correct values
now we're deterministic okay we're
talking about a deterministic circuit
so if this is locally consistent it
means this is the correct value I know
if it's an and it's an and whatever it
is so all these are correct I can argue
when I run the cheating the assignment J
so I want to argue essentially
any the local assignment generator every
wire he gives me must be the correct one
and then I'm done because the output is
the correct and if he gives me output
one voila it's the correct I'm
done so I'm going to argue kind of by
induction that every y or given me must
be the correct one why okay let's try
layer layer so I'm going to argue kind
of layer by the induction is going to be
by the think of the uh circuit as
layered and I'm going to argue this by
induction on the layers okay layer one
what does the cheating prover gives me
he gives me assignment now I know I
proved it's locally satisfiable which
means it satisfies the gate so it's
correct so layer one correct let's go to
Layer Two
Layer Two he G now I I'm going to ask
him this let's say I'm going to ask him
these I want to argue that this is
correct all I know is that it's locally
consistent but I know that these are
correct why are these correct because of
the non signaling I know if I asked give
me kind of these wires uh give me these
wires with kind of the input it was
correct I got the the correct
answer so now when I ask the extract the
local assignment generator give me these
wires with
these that we said the distribution is
the same up to computationally
distinguishable so when I asked him give
me kind of uh the value of this wire
when I asked with the kind of with the
inputs or and I asked give me these
wires with this it's the same
distribution was correct before it's
correct now so these are correct and
this is locally consistent so this is
also correct so these layers are correct
and and and again now let's look at
these is this correct yeah because this
these still need to be correct because
we argued it's correct and it doesn't
depend on the distribution it doesn't
depend on the every time I ask him this
I get corre one minus negligible so
correct so this is
correct by induction the output is
correct I know it's one that's what the
the local generator promised me so it's
one and correct I'm
done
okay that's the proof moreover let me
tell you something when we wrote this
proof we wrote it we were happy with it
we literally almost submitted this thing
a couple days before the deadline we
noticed there's a bug this is wrong this
does not
work okay I'll tell you why it doesn't
work as a suppos to asking because I
think it's so subtle but if does anybody
see why it doesn't it's very very hard
to see in my opinion but uh I mean
clearly I didn't see it but anybody see
why why I cheated
here
yeah restricted
deterministic inut yeah so what why yeah
there's only the input the actually the
fact that there's deterministic it's
helpful for us because now there's a
notion of correctness once there's a
there's no what do you mean correct
depends on the witness every wire has
like if use this witness it can be this
value here because it's deterministic
there's only one value for each wire and
so there's the notion of
correct
value and I can argue by induction that
everything is
correct okay I um a so I'll tell
you why I you know I I I suffered
through this I I have the like desire to
have you like to torture you a little
bit to see why and so like I like the
experience I had but I'll given that you
only have like 10 minutes left I'll tell
you so okay so here's
why
so local
consistency holds or or yeah everything
like local consistency holds with
probability or or the noning everything
holds with probability one minus
negligible not with probability one if
everything was with probability one one
you know local consistency this then
this cons probility one this then
everything would work out okay if if I
promised you local cons probability one
and non signability one like it's
exactly the same we're good then I can
Pro
now it's you in cryptography oh command
negligible it's zero okay here it's not
zero turns out negligible is a pain this
is the entire problem the negligible and
I'll tell you why it seems weird but
here is why the reason
is this is correct with all the ne
probability so this is correct except
probability
mu this is correct except with
me but now
this is correct if this needs to be
correct and this needs to be correct if
one of them is incorrect you're not
correct so this is correct probity
correct exact probability to
Mu so here you have two mu now two mu is
also
negligible this is also corre except 2
mu but this for this to be correct both
of them need to be correct so here you
have four mu and then 8 mu you're going
to get two to the depth times
mu now if the depth is more than
log it's not negligible
anymore so the problem is two to depth
may be much bigger than one over
mu so it's this kind of there's this
exponential
curse of of of we carry kind of the air
Grows by factor of two each time and
eventually can kill
us that's the bug so this works if it's
bounded depth log depth yes more than
that not
clear
okay so what do we do so to fix
this there is two ways to fix this
option number one which is what we did
originally cuz we we didn't have a
better idea is we said you know what
let's assume that the circuit is very
narrow like think of bound depth
deterministic computations okay where
not sorry bounded space so think of DET
computation where each configuration is
like very small so like a TR machine you
know that has very uh it's kind of the
Tableau is very thin and long and then
we said you know what let's make L like
where you're statistically bound it on
let's make it an entire configuration so
yeah you pay with an entire kind of with
a space the snar the proof will grow
with the space but now we say you can
read the entire thing you can read so
here here is the Tableau you can read
the entire computation you can read the
entire configuration and now we say the
first configuration is correct probility
mu the second configuration if this was
correct it's this is two Mew three me
four me it doesn't grow exponential
anymore cuz you read the entire thing so
I'm going to read these two
configurations together if this was
consistent this is consistent there's
always an usability of error that I'm in
cran fine but it doesn't double because
I'm reading the entire thing I said if
this was a a correct
configuration then when I read this with
this this is going to be correct
configuration but I read the entire
thing so I don't double up
things so we get we get snark for any
computation that's bounded space where
the snar grows with the
space okay but let me tell you we can do
better we can actually we don't need to
grow with the
space so I'll just say a word because
I'm running out of time and I want to
kind of do a quick summary so but the
idea of not running into this
exponential curse idea is to say the
following you know let's do this hash
and Bar so what did we do this this snar
is like hash all the wires and then bar
the idea is don't do hash and Bar in the
original circuit don't just do hash and
Bar in the verification circuit do hash
and bar on an extended circuit change
the circuit do hash and a slightly more
elaborate circuit so what is the more
elaborate circuit let me give you an
example one example you can
do take each kind of um layer here and
add a miracle hash in the
circuit so now before you had a a
verification circuit change it a little
bit how how do you change it you compute
each one and then you compute kind of a
miracle hash compute the next layer and
compute a miracle hash compute the next
layer compute a mle hash it's weird like
why would you do that do that moreover
also compute for every wire like the
opening of the Merkel
hash add add all these Merkel hashes and
add all these opening to the circle
circuit now that seems a ridiculous
thing to do why would you add to the
Circuit that you're trying to verify
that it's correct for each wire Merle
has all the wires and add kind of wires
that check opening like what this sounds
really weird and not a very like a weird
thing to do or sorry you know you don't
need to check opening just add Merkel
hashes add for each wire add moral hash
to the wire for each layer add a miracle
hash so on so forth why is adding
hashes helpful at
all so I'll tell you why it's helpful
because now we have the local assignment
generator and now in the local
assignment generator what we can do we
said the first layer each one is
correct now we're going to argue this
implies that the meracle root is
correct that this must be correct now
when we argue it we do pay exponential
with the depth so this is a computation
and the air does grow but the depth is
long Miracle hash is a very low depth
computation so it grows but perally it's
okay now when we read things here we're
going to read them together with a root
we're not going to just we're going to
say the when we ask the local assignment
generator what is the value give me the
value here here here we're gonna also
say and
give me the value of the root and the
and the paths corresponding to this and
this and now the thing is the following
if the root was
correct both of them have to be correct
unless you broke the hash
function so you you don't need to get
this Independence before we were like oh
we needed this to be correct and this to
be correct and things doubl here we can
say if the root is correct we know that
both of them have to be correct
so it's enough to argue that the root is
correct so it's kind of a little bit
simulates the case of like reading the
entire config the entire configuration
or an entire layer which is what we did
in the bounded
space so I don't want to go I think
that's all I want to say but essentially
what I want to mention is this local
satisfiability or local soundness or
local uh uh a consistency
does not necessarily imply Global
correctness actually to use it to get
Global correctness often we need to kind
of change the circuit and kind of do
kind of circuit gymnastics in weird ways
to get it to work and this is still kind
of work in progress it's still kind of
uh us as a community are still uh
combating with this I see smiled because
my students have been suffering with me
through this L's like I don't know half
smiling half
crying but but
uh uh yeah so that's kind of uh where we
are today so let me use the last 3
minutes or so to do kind of a quick
summary so first of all before I
summarize there's um a if you have any
feedback there's feedback forms please
submit so I you know I'll improve uh uh
or I'll keep on doing things that worked
to try not to do things that didn't work
so uh it's it'll be great great great if
you if uh you can submit the feedback
form that would be really really helpful
uh and okay so with that uh let me just
I want to kind of reflect a couple
minutes on this journey and and where we
are and how you know so if you remember
you know we started by saying look
proofs has been has been something that
you know uh mathematicians have been
working with and uh thinking about for
thousands of years and proofs have
always been very specific form of like
logic deductions and this changed kind
of the cryptography changed this with
the introduction with the thinking about
zero knowledge proofs they defined this
notion of interactive proof a new proof
model and this new way of thinking about
proofs was kind of a a huge huge success
story for cryptography for complexity um
and it kind of we noticed that these
interactive proof systems turned out to
be very very powerful and this kind of
the main work that kind of uh
demonstrated that was the uh um sub Che
protocol that was kind of the first
protocol that wow you can do something
that we have no idea how to do
classically and that kind of gave birth
to the IP equals peace space theorem
once you had the the Su check from that
kind of uh with a little more work uh
you can do the IP equals uh P space uh
theorem and what we showed in this class
is actually we kind of went through uh
gkr so we we we showed that if you have
a su check you can get actually a just
by a very simple idea of kind of uh
doing snar H Su check layer by layer you
can get an interactive a succinct
interactive proof for any bound to depth
computation that's doubly efficient so
the pro is efficient
and the verifier is is uh succinct or
very
efficient and then we showed kind of the
IP equals P space as a quary showed that
you can get PCP from it uh and then we
moved to arguments said well okay that's
where we are with proofs uh with
statistical soundness and then we said
well if you're willing to rely to to
reduce soundness to computational
soundness then we saw the kilan mik you
can get everything like really efficient
uh Interactive arguments by T think PCP
and kind of hashing them
down and then there was a question okay
we can have intractive arguments can we
have
snars can we eliminate intraction and
then we talked about F uh kind of went
through kind of zero knowledge a little
bit because that's the first time where
F proved security of it was uh in the
context of zero
knowledge but then we showed or Jen Jang
showed that actually you can do F also
the context of bars so we have an
interactive uh batch argument and you
can or a constructed interractive batch
argument showed you can use I don't know
it didn't get into detail but turns out
you can use similar techniques to uh to
show F secure or these techniques Plus+
to show that F secure when apply to the
interactive batch argument and then you
get like a this non- interractive
bar and today kind of to close the this
entire Journey we showed how to get uh
snars from these bars and as I said we
have it for deterministic computation we
have it for some non-deterministic
computation constructing it for all of
NP is still a major open question uh so
you know I invite you all to work on it
with me but I want to say one more thing
about this area which is it's really
nice because this is one example where
this area has a beautiful beautiful math
in my opinion so it's very theoretical
with beautiful mathematical ideas and
applied so this is kind of this area has
been a really nice kind of bonding
between kind of theoreticians and
practitioners these things are used uh
in particular by a lot of bankers and uh
you know people started using
blockchains and now B Bank systems and
so on are interested in it so it's been
kind of um a really nice a example where
really beautiful theory is is used like
the theory itself is really uh deployed
and used so it's um it's kind of uh I
think this is an example of success
story for theoretical
cryptography okay thank you guys it was
really really fun teaching you thank you