I'm happy to introduce our next two
speakers. It'll be a duet. Uh the first
uh will be uh Michael Casey who is a
longtime adviser at the MIT Media Lab.
Um although you wear a lot of hats, I
would add to it author, speaker,
journalist, and actually I would say and
probably a lot of people would say
visionary as well. So uh let's hear it
from Michael. Thanks, Jim. Thanks a lot.
You take that. I've got my own. I'm
good. Yeah.
>> All right. Uh, so, um, thanks. We are
the last act before lunch. So, I
appreciate you sticking around for this.
Um, we're going to take a slightly
different tack, I think, from what the
others have been talking about. Very
integrated, very related to it all.
Hopefully, though. Um, basically, yeah,
I am a senior adviser of the MIT Media
Labs digital currency initiative, but
I'm also the chairman of this thing
called the AI, the advanced AI society.
And what we do is we represent entities
who are building a decentralized
alternative to AI. Now the word
decentralization can conjure up some
scary ideas, right? There's no control.
It's like this idea of nobody being in
charge. Uh actually we're going to be
here to tell you a little bit about the
problem under current centralized AI in
which you are not in charge and that
this is the problem, right? And that
there's a way out of this and we call it
proof of control and it's about taking
an AI portfolio approach to how you do
this. So basically a little bit about me
as I said I associated with the digital
currency initiative at the media lab. Uh
I also taught classes at Sloan with Gary
Gensel and and Simon Johnson being a
couple of them. Obviously Simon being
our latest Noble laureate very proud of
that for him. Um and I done a bunch of
things with IP over the years. But right
now what we at the society are doing
which we think is quite telling in this
space is we're working with Romesh
Rashar at the media lab on his
decentralized AI lab. Um and basically
what Romesh is doing I think is really
quite visionary and I think of it as
something that brings us back to the
roots of the spirit of an open
decentralized internet and this actually
draws in my mind on some of the great
traditions of MIT the network the
computer networking work you know the
likes of Tim Berners Lee perhaps and
sort of you know AI like Marvin Minsky
right these two things coming together
because with AI we have this opportunity
it's a small window we have an
opportunity to to sort of break down the
paradigm of the web 2.0 era with this
very powerful concentration of of
economic and I would say political power
that resides in the hands of a number of
platforms. So the idea that now with
billions of agents all representing
ourselves opening in an open autonomous
independent way we might be able to
actually get back to something that
looks more like this open access system
that we were all dreaming of right uh
the problem is right now under the
current paradigm we're actually
barreling even more heavily into a
concentrated situation right so I as I
said I think this is not only an
economic problem it's a political
problem in my mind this is a fasttrack
way towards totalitarianism this is not
to call out the companies themselves But
the very idea that you would control
this much economic might over the most
important technology of our time that
you know an information technology of
this kind is really quite scary. So we
have a we kind of have a moral and
social imperative to fix this. But today
we're actually going to talk to you I
think in language that is more
persistent and consistent with the idea
of the corporate imperatives that come
with how you deal with this. And that is
to say that in fact using this blackbox
hyperscala model uh certainly if it's
concentrated only in that we're not
dismissing the idea that you work with
LLMs and and so forth but the idea that
it's concentrated in that ends up being
too expensive slower and and your
outcomes aren't aren't what you want
them to be either. I any of you saw the
um Harvard Business Review report
recently about work slop. Well, I see
that as being a function of the lack of
transparency in the system because
ultimately these models are
hallucinating and they are doing things
that we can't control. If we don't know
what's going on under the hood, then
human beings are going to have to go
back and open them up and do it again.
So, we're doing a lot of wasted work and
that amounts to cost and inefficiency
for all of you guys. But it's more than
just money, right? This is actually an
existential issue. Uh it's almost like,
you know, you're not the driver in the
car. You're not really a passenger in a
car. you're actually in a bus that's out
of control. I don't know how many of you
have seen that that classic Sandra
Bulock and Kanu Reeves movie, but you
know, there's there's something quite
threatening about the idea of of having
this all fall apart on our on our watch
here. So, this is going to get real
pretty quickly. We believe that, you
know, there's going to be a demand that
we have to have proofs of control over
our AI, over our data, over our compute,
over the models. And this will come from
boards. It will come from regulators. It
will come through economics because the
scarcity of power is going to create
create a fight. We've been just talking
about all this over those resources. And
and to get there, you need to know that
you've got control. So, you know, and
the other one is the internet itself. It
won't be able to handle billions of
trillions of different endpoints all
acting together through these
centralized systems. So, let's put it in
the context of the $1.3 trillion that
you we're hearing lots of forecasts
obviously where these are going, but IDC
saying that's what the spend is going to
be by 2029 on you know AI solutions and
services. But if we don't have those
proofs in place, it's it's just not
going to happen. there's going to be
these blockages, these constraints that
we just talked about will come up andor
it will mean that the distribution of
that spend is going to be a lot more
uneven, unfair and ultimately AI will
not be able to unlock all of these
solutions that we're looking to solve
and it will fall short of its promise
for humanity. So how do we do so right?
Our thesis that we have to move from
this sort of blackbox sort of this
opaque system to one in which there is a
lot more information about who is
control and that blockchain technologies
along with cryptography you heard a
little bit about you know um zero trust
kind of environments uh TE all these
things some of which are being developed
in the hypers scale world can actually
be deployed in these more localized
settings and all of that is going to
help to build this proofof control
system. The problem is even though these
technologies already exist, right, there
are people building a range of different
mechanisms up and down the stack of all
these different AI providers to give
you, you know, verification of your
model to give you control over the
compute and so forth. There's really not
a lot happening between those vendors
and the buyers, the enterprises who are
using them. This is sort of an
automatic, you know, click the buy
button through the centralized model. So
there's a lack of visibility about
what's going on here. And that's really
what the advanced AI society is all
about. We are here to, you know,
basically enable this connection between
enterprises and the providers of these
solutions that are going to give those
enterprises the proof of control over
their AI systems and get us out of this
this problem. And to tell you more about
that, I'm going to get Trisha to come
out and uh dig you deeper into it. This
is Trisha Wong who is uh she's the CEO
of the advanced AI society and um
>> I work with Trisha on a uh on her prior
blockchain research lab and Trish has a
a deep experience in sort of resolving
enterprise challenges for Fortune 500
and so you know go for it Trisha.
>> Thanks Michael. So as Michael has
outlined is that we have a big proof of
control bottleneck coming but there's
all these solutions that already in
place and that's why we started advanced
AI society and we are on one end the
industry association of all the leading
providers that are actually developing
these solutions for proof of control but
they're specialist vendors so they're
not very well known right now and on the
other end we're building out a
marketplace called portfolio works that
really bundles their solutions but the
thing is is that you know we do a lot of
research here at the industry
association so we have an evidence lab
and compute is as we all know one of the
biggest costs for AI. So we have a
report coming out on that topic and I
just want to tell you what the big
takeaway is. Now early on um as we get
to preview that here at data center day
is that um you know our big takeaway and
if there's just anything for you to
remember after today is that it is you
know to build a missionritical high
resilience and compliant AI compute
infrastructure now requires you to
really figure out what your customized
approach is with both hyperscalers and
proof of control vendors. you know a lot
about the hyperscalers but you don't
know a lot about the proof of control
vendors which is what we're here to tell
you a bit more about and you know the
thing is is that if you're you know we
want to make very clear is that if your
stack only looks like this especially
after today's you know talk is we want
to help communicate is that anyone's
stack who only looks like this you are
vulnerable you actually have greater
risk of business continuity and so our
goal is not to say oh only do
hyperscalers or only do proof of control
we're saying you want to take an
integrated approach that takes the best
of both worlds customized to your
solution and we call this the portfolio
AI approach which means diversifying
your AI stack and mixing you know these
decentralized AI options that also comes
along with you know open and federated
options and really adopting these proof
of control solutions in the places that
are appropriate in your stack. So we
think you know the modern business
infrastructure for business when you
talk between company AB or government
ABC it's all going to look different
what their portfolio is going to be
shaped by what their needs are and so I
just want to you know provide a few
insights from our research we've been
talking to you know the buyers who are
dealing with the struggles of pushing
the limits of only their hyperscaler
stack and then we're talk we've been
talking a lot to the vendors these
specialist vendors who have these
solutions. So the first big trend to
know is that there's a shift that's just
overall overall it's all going to be if
you start to adopt these controls there
are ways that will make your entire
operations cheaper faster and better and
one of those first things way it becomes
cheaper is that right now there's
usually a massive upfront capex you just
heard about that from Morgan how it
takes you know all this money to even
build just a 10 megawatt center so now
we're moving into a more dynamic opex
utility model that allows for
verifiability and flexible usage message
so you don't get distracted access. So
some of um you know the names to look
out for in this space you know Across
they're actually building down to you
know using your phone using cell phones
as a way to uh build it into this
infrastructure and then you have a
company called Tesak stakes you know
they actually allow you to figure out
how to own a part of the data center and
they build a governance into it and you
can actually prove that ownership and
usage. A cave cloud is storage, but you
get zero egress fees. And then spiron
allows you to do remote LLMs. So bring
down the cost from let's say like
$500,000 to even$10 to $20,000. So these
are massive cost differences and savings
for companies. And along with that is
that there's also, you know, the move
from these long infrastructural build
timelines to these rapid flexible
deployment. And you heard that before
from Morgan where it takes like
oftentimes, you know, three, six, 10
years depending on what kind of, you
know, data center you want to build.
It's faster for Elon to ship a power,
you know, center from a data center from
Europe over to here. Um, you know, you
see Google investing in all these
nuclear reactors. Well, there's this new
world where it's you can actually build
rapid and flexible deployment of compute
functionality. And so you have Holland
here where they're really building
building out these micro data centers.
You have Athier who's really like the
Airbnb of GPUs around the world there.
They build enterprisegrade distributed
uh you know GPUs and you have Across
again who also leverages the storage on
your phone. And then we're seeing this
move from opaque residency to
cryptographically verifiable
sovereignty. Now hyperscalers are
already you know you have Google, you
have um them they're they're offering
options for residency. This is not to
say you can't get it with your current
cloud providers, but what you see a move
to is actually, you know, you're going
to have regulators say we want you to
actually prove and we want you to get
very granular in where the data was
residents and processed. So you see this
with a coffee cloud that's an option.
You have equity labs which is does you
know down to the new Nvidia chips H100s
where it's provable compliance onto the
very chip itself. And then you have a
here who also offers that down to the
sovereignty. So you get really granular
not just a region but you can say I want
this type of data in this you know
country or even in this city on this
block and then overall all of these
technologies the big difference is that
it's moving from this kind of trust us
relationship because you can trust these
hyperscalers. You know it's all spelled
out in the contract. You just have to go
into their portal. You're going to get
those reports. But as we've said with
the proof of control bottleneck that's
coming is that you're going to have
regulators and boards saying we want
more publicly provable verifiable
immutable control. Do you need that for
all of your data? No. But you want to
figure out what parts of your compute
infrastructure you're going to need that
for. And so you scan you see that coming
from services like equity labs. We have
secret network where they offer TE. And
we know that you know TE is being
offered already already by the
hyperscalers. But what secret does is
that they do it via smart contracts. So
it's very much tamperproof. You have
filecoin that does you know tamperproof
archival storage and actually MIT's
courseware is many of their courses are
uploaded to filecoin. And then you have
quip which offers the world's first
shared quantum computing with also
verification.
And lastly, the insight is you know the
big change this all represents is that
we're moving from a single vendor
dependency you know so even if you do
multilouds which is the reality we know
not you know you're not literally with
one single vendor vendor but these
vendors are all about propri proprietary
controls once you're in their system
it's very costly to leave you know it's
very costly to you know you can't just
change SDKs out so this move is to this
AI portfolio approach of the
best-in-class products from hyperscalers
and the proof of control vendors. So the
modern computing infrastructure stack
should really start to look like a mix.
You're going to want to figure out well
what of the vendors from proof of
control are going to make sense and what
of the vendors from my hyperscalers are
going to make sense. And the best thing
about all of these proof of control
technology is that they're composable.
They're integrable. They it's not about
forcing you to make a choice of either
or. They all integrate into your
existing systems. And so before we take
questions, I want to end on, you know,
we prepared just to get a sense of like,
well, how do you figure out where in
your AI portfolio would you want to
prioritize proof of control? I'm not
going to go through all these questions
here, but just to go give you an
example. The first one is that you know
this is a very this is the very I would
say most popular use cases that we see
emerging for a real case for why you
would have want to adopt and where you
would adopt proof of control is you want
to start asking your teams and you may
not be able to answer this question
yourselves but certainly you want to
take this sheet back and talk to you
with your team about and by the way
we're going to provide a QR code where
you can um download the report um is the
first question is well you might want to
ask your your team is where do we have
product offerings where it's actually
very zero to even you know low to zero
tolerance for latency. So emerging
conversations we're having with buyers
or potential buyers is really around
autonomous vehicles, anything around
healthcare or even gaming where you can
see that like you don't want to you
can't afford that round trip to the
cloud and back. And so we have a bunch
of questions we'd love to talk to you
about. Um and this is all really linked
back to the innovations that are
happening out of you know project Nando
where Romesh Rescar really provides this
kind of vision for what happens when
that stress point of not billions but
trillions of agents and endpoints come
online and start to stress the current
system that we have. And so with these
questions and insights we hope you can
see that you don't have to be on this
bus you know you don't even have to be a
passenger on this in a seat. you can
actually be control and you can figure
out at what points would you want to
take more of a backseat role or at what
points do you really want to make sure
you are in control of that car. So,
thank you so much and do we have time
for questions or should we go to lunch?
>> Any questions?
>> Thank you. That was fantastic. Um you
mentioned a point about uh composability
and and being able to integrate a lot of
these proof of control vendors. Um could
you go a little bit more into detail
about like the difference of uh
hyperscalers where you sort of have to
go to where their facilities are and
where their infrastructure is versus
some of the more flexibility you might
get from these proof of control vendors
in terms of being deployed deployable to
cl
within your overall kind of network
stack within your CDN providers like
Akami and other kind of places that they
might be able to be more flexible.
>> Yeah. So the current hyperscalers when
you're working in their ecosystem that's
that's really convenient right that's
the thing about going with the
hyperscape the ecosystem and there are
times where it makes sense especially if
you're just getting started you want to
just get started you want to go and once
you're in their system it's very easy to
deploy and that's the convenience the
upside of it one of the reasons why it's
been hard you know this is no fault of
the buyers and the industry why it's
hard to find these specialist vendors is
that they're developing at different
layers of the stack they're Not it's
hard to find one ecosystem that's going
to encompass it all. But the great thing
about composability um which really that
word is just means like portability,
flexibility. It's like Lego blocks that
all just actually fit together because
of the underlying code and the
underlying language and underlying
agreements in the space of using
blockchain is that it all we can
actually bundle that techn those
technologies together. So it actually in
the end gives a buyer much more choice
and freedom because you're not forced to
only buy this one type of bundle. You
can actually swap out pieces of a layer.
You can say well I don't want that kind
of residency because I don't need that
those options. I want to go with this
provider. Well gives that's what allows.
So this is hope that answers your
question. You want to add anything? No,
I think that's it. I mean, there's a lot
of sort of smart contract solutions that
essentially are sort of just keying off
the multiple different uh pieces that
then give you this sort of uniform
uniform bundle essentially is the way I
like to think about it.
>> Um, and you spoke to portability. So I
think a lot of the purpose that you're
trying to do especially with like
creating these bundled portfolios is to
if I want to switch out an
infrastructure provider with one of
these um proof of control uh vendors to
another one that the overall burden of
me like switching costs or changing out
my compute infrastructure or deciding
maybe I want to test out some of the
infrastructure rather than shifting my
entire workload. That's kind of what you
guys are going to be focused on trying
to ensure that that's that's a an easy
process.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And we have a tech sandbox
because it's composable. It just so
happens it's very easy to host a tech
sandbox for all of our members where you
can come in and play with the
technology. And one of the highest costs
you see for startups right now, which is
really crazy and a blocker to innovation
is in fees for, you know, getting access
to these models, getting access to
storage, getting access to compute. It's
exorbitant and it's actually holding
startups behind that they have to
dedicate more of their costs to just the
infrastructure. Well, what you see in
these more portable with these options
that we see amongst our members is that
you get zero across fees. It's very
predictable. You can build that in to
your budget. So, you can anticipate what
those costs are. You also know you're
not going to get vendor lock in that
they're not going to all sudden jack up
the fees later on.
>> I'll just say this as well about
portability of course, right? One of the
most important, you know, costs you will
face is a loss of data or is is the
capacity to control that data, right?
It's the most important thing that you
have. In fact, I like to say that one of
the great things about a proof of
control approach is that this is how
we're going to give all of this really
sensitive data that is currently under
lock and keen is not being applied to AI
a chance to actually safely be applied
to it and we can start to address some
of the problems we've been talking about
climate change you know energy solutions
etc etc with data that is actually
really really sensitive. So the idea
that rather than just entering into a
privacy agreement with a hyperscaler,
you literally have ownership and control
over under a provably private
environment and then you can port it
somewhere else. That's the key point,
right? It's it's that level of control
that protects you from the risks
associated with it and then you know
really makes that that switching and
that transition cost so much so much
lighter. So, I think it's a really
important point
>> and I think it's going to be I mean a
thing that brands are going to want to
promote for parts of the data where
their customers are going to want to see
that public verifiability because it's
actually going to make them trust you
more on what you're doing with their
data and that they can actually see and
have access to it as they get smarter.
>> Thank you. Okay, one more. I'm an active
questioner I guess but um from a
mechanical engineer's point of view so
explain it why I'm five I guess but is
there any inherent friction with the
scaling laws on performance especially
as you get to the efficiencies of of
scale from a a compute cluster
perspective but also um if you look at
like the Nvidia GPU generations and the
the NVL link domains that they're
expanding um is just are there any
frictions with the the scaling laws
especially like test time as even on the
inference side you need more more and
more compute to to hit some of the
performances.
>> It's a question we get all the time,
right? Because it is clearly the idea of
latency and challenge that comes from
sort of colllocating in these
environments. But there's an enormous
amount of work being done right now. Um
um just blanking on the names, but um
you know, NAS research for example, uh
prime intellect, these guys are really
proving out machine learning models that
are based on distributed compute.
There's federated models. I think the
point we're going to make here is that
this is all about this portfolio hybrid
approach, right? So there are certain
things that obviously are just going to
have to be done in a highly concentrated
hyperscaler environment, but there's so
many other aspects to the model. There's
so many aspects to the implementation
and execution of that model that we
think can just reside in different
environments. And so this composability,
this portfolio approach is the way we're
going to approach that. The other thing,
of course, is like there's a lot of
people looking at, okay, how do we just
break the paradigm? Right now, Nvidia
has a lock on it, not just because its
chips are so good, but we're all using
the same, you know, software uh you
know, algorithms to run those chips.
People looking at completely different
mechanisms for how you would actually,
you know, run that compute across
different much more decentralized uh
chip arrangements is is really what what
this is also going to be about. There's
a lot of innovation happening around how
do you break the I mean, the incentives
for anybody to build an alternative to
Nvidia are huge, right? That's a what is
it $3 trillion market cap that you can
go up. It's a big bounty. So there's a
lot of people working on how do you how
you break that down. But I still as I
said I think that it's really a hybrid
approach that we're looking at here.
>> Yeah, that's why Equity Labs one of you
know members in our community is
building on the latest Nvidia chips
where no one else is doing that provable
compliance. So very soon regulators
especially I think it's going to start
in Europe. They're going to ask for that
and they're going to be able to show it.
>> Good questions too. Yeah.
>> Okay. Let's uh hear it from Michael and
Trisha. Thank you.