Uh hi everyone, thank you for joining
today. Jacob Lindenba is going to give
us a primer on uh homorphic encryption
and privacy preservation for uh genomics
and he's a PhD candidate at uh in
computer science at Columbia University.
So I think we're going to get started
now. Thank you, Jacob.
>> Okay, does the microphone work? Perfect.
Well, first of all, thank you guys so
much for having me. I'm uh super excited
to talk. Yes. And thank you for the
introduction. Um so today's talk is
going to focus on mainly homorphic
encryption. I want to give you guys kind
of a mathematical overview as well as
kind of like a an overview for a
practitioner so that you guys can apply
these techniques. Uh and I'm going to
end my talk with kind of an application
in uh in the genome privacy space.
So for data protection, right, there's
three different kinds of ways we protect
data. We protect data in transit with
TLS uh where we kind of encrypt messages
and data that gets sent between devices.
We also encrypt data at rest using AES
uh to keep it secure from attackers. And
finally, we have this kind of new
frontier that's that's recently
developing which is encrypting data
that's in use. So that's actually
computing on encrypted data when it's in
the cloud. Um there's like a few
different developing technologies. These
are called privacy-enhancing
technologies. Um, but there's a there's
a lot of challenges for for data in use
because right now there's a huge
performance hit. Applicability is low
and usability is still a challenge. So,
let's take a deep dive into some of
these technologies real quick.
The first one is a trusted execution
environment which is like an Intel SGX.
This is like a hardware chip uh that can
perform this um this data in use
encryption. Unfortunately, it's quite
vulnerable to side channel attacks, but
it's very performant. It's actually
really close to to plain text, which is
just computing it not on encrypted data.
We also have secure multi-party
computation where we kind of split data
into pieces that we give to um separate
computing parties and then each
computing party can kind of um evaluate
some function and it kind of reshare it
back uh and none of the computing
parties can essentially see the full
data because it's split. This is more
secure than trusted execution
environment but it's a bit slower.
Finally, and what we're going to focus
on mainly in this talk is homorphic
encryption, which lets us directly
compute on encrypted data called cipher
texts. Uh, and this is great because
it's mathematically secure. So, there's
like guaranteed properties of security.
Unfortunately, as we'll show, it's uh
it's very slow and it's not quite
performant. It's about 100 to a million
times slower. So let me take a a brief
quick overview of homorphic encryption
which really highlights what I want to
bring home in this talk. So with
homamorphic encryption we can kind of
delegate computation to an untrusted
party. So here in our little example we
have um let's say some trusted party has
some data X. They can encrypt this data
send it to a trusted computing party
that can evaluate some function let's
say G. And this function could be
something like uh let's say machine
learning inference. Um they can send
that data back.
The the original party can then decrypt
it and then see the the output of the
the function. And in this scenario with
homomorphic encryption, we have
mathematical guarantees that the
untrusted party will never be able to
see the original data X because that X
is always encrypted when it's being um
computed on by the untrusted party. This
is unfortunately computationally very
expensive and uh unfortunately the the
types of operations that we can do on
this encrypted data is limited to
additions and multiplications only. But
that's nice because we can evaluate
polomials. So when we're trying to do
bioinformatics algorithms like let's say
this untrusted party is trying to do a
G-W was for example genomewide
association study we have to simplify
those algorithms to only use additions
and multiplications.
This is really what I want to take home.
Uh the message I want to share with you
guys today. Yes.
>> Is there something uh like that doesn't
work specifically about doing like
inverse operations like division and
subtraction?
>> Yes. Oh, you can do subtraction.
Division is is tricky. Um the way that
people do that now is they basically
find a polomial that's kind of
approximates division and then you
evaluate that. So that's it's a very
expensive operation and we we'll get
into that. Um I'll show you some
examples soon. So let's dive very deeply
into the math. So homorphic encryption
is secure because of this problem called
ringle learning with errors which
cryptographers have deemed to be a
difficult problem. In ringle learning
with errors we work with polomials in
this specific algebraic structure that
looks really scary but I'll break it
down. It's essentially polomials that
have coefficients
modulo q. So that means that they're
between zero to q minus one and they're
bounded to have a degree less than n.
And if you have polomials with this kind
of structure then for some secret
polomial and a pair of polomials a and b
where b is essentially just the
multiplication of a times that secret
plus a little bit of gaussian noise.
It's theorized that this is very
complicationally difficult to find that
original secret polomial. So an attacker
who sees a and b will basically never be
able to extract s.
Um, so this is great because we can then
use this to build our homamorphic
encryption scheme. And the one I'm going
to be focusing on today is called the
BGV scheme where we start with the
secret key which is uh again that same
polomial that we saw before. And then
for encryption we get that same pair of
polomials except we're going to add some
noise again. That's T times our little
bit of error. And then we're going to
hide our message by just adding it to
the end.
Now under this scheme essentially this
the this pair of polomials this A and B
is going to look random with that if you
don't have the knowledge of the secret
key. Um so under RLWE essentially our
message is hidden even if we share this
this cipher text with the with the rest
of the world. Decryption is quite
simple. If you have the secret key, you
can just multiply that by A and then do
B minus A * S and you get back your
original message. So this is great. We
have an encryption scheme and I'll show
you how to do addition and
multiplication on this. Um, but before
we get into that, I'm talking about
messages here. We usually work with data
that's integers and floats. So how does
that all come together? Well, we can
actually embed integers into polomials
of degree n, which is our message
polomial using what is known as the
Chinese remainder theorem and residual
number systems. And essentially we can
take a polomial of degree m and store n
integers
um inside of it. And there's this nice
isomorphism that that happens where if
we add polomials with this embedding, we
actually add all of the the basically
like the vector components. And this
works for addition and multiplication
which as I said in homamorphic
encryption are the only two operations
that are supported. Um so this is quite
nice. Now this kind of works in practice
is we can take a bunch of a vector of a
bunch of integers and another vector of
a bunch of integers. We encrypt them
into cipher texts uh into single cipher
texts. We do one addition operation and
then when we decrypt them uh we get the
the pairwise sum of all of these. So
really in homorphic encryption we're not
doing very many operations. So the
throughput it can be quite high because
this this end the size of these these
vectors can be up to 4,000 8,000 16,000.
They're gigantic. But unfortunately the
latency is quite high. So these ad
operations are quite expensive. So you
have to be quite clever with how you um
kind of pack these uh these vectors
inside of our cipher text and how we
organize this data.
So that was a bit of how we encode the
data. Now we can talk about the exact
operations we can perform on cipher
texts. So as you remember each cipher
text is a pair of polomials and
homorphic addition is super simple. We
basically just add the the components of
two cipher texts. So if we have a cipher
text one that's a1 b1 and a cipher text
2 a2 b2 the sum is just going to be the
a1 plus a2 and b1 plus b2
correctness. Yep. When we do the
decryption step with the secret key, we
get our output that's M1 and M2. So
exactly what we had before. Now there is
something that is crucial to homorphic
encryption which is that the error grew.
If you see that the the E1 plus E2, it's
now twice the error of the original
cipher text. So for our visual people
out there, if we have a a cipher text,
you can kind of imagine it as a a um a
block where we have our our payload, our
message, and then we have that error
that sits t push t above our payload and
then we have what is known as a noise
budget. And as we perform homorphic
operations like this addition and
multiplication, our error is going to
grow and it's going to consume this
noise budget. So as we saw with the
addition, our error increased twofold.
And if we keep doing these operations,
our error can grow. And once the error
exceeds the noise budget, because we're
working modulo Q, it's going to wrap
around the ring and it's going to enter
what is our payload and it's actually
going to corrupt our message and we will
no longer be able to decrypt. So when we
perform homamorphic operations, we have
to be very cognizant of the error
because if we consume too much and we
exceed our noise budget, everything is
kapoot. Yes.
>> Is the noise budget something like a set
of par bits? Is that how I should think
about this?
>> No.
>> No. You should think about it as like
um you basically just have a a log
capacity and then after each operation
your your error is going to take up more
and more of this this capacity and then
if as soon as it exceeds that then it's
all gone.
>> I guess what what's confusing me is how
do you how do you make sure that the
error is just taking up the noise
budget?
>> Yes. Yes. So when we do the these
operations, the the error just grows
because it's um
it's just pushed t away from our payload
message. So the error is only is always
going to be t like uh t bits or log t
bits from our payload message. And so
it's never it's never going to be at the
front. You can actually think of
homorphic encryption really as these
coefficients as this plus some masking
which was that secret key times original
random polomial that I was talking
about. So if you remove that during
decryption you essentially always get
kind of messages that look like this.
That makes sense.
So for multiplication things get a
little bit more tricky. Uh but we have a
cipher text that's again a pair. uh when
we multiply we're going to we have to do
something special and we're going to get
a cipher text that actually has three
components a1 a2 a1 * b2 plus b2 b1 * a2
and b1 * b2
so given a cipher text that looks like
this we can again run a decryption
algorithm but this time it's a little
bit more complicated because we need the
secret key squared and we can do that
because the secret key is a polinomial
you guys can just trust me on this that
that it works and it decrypts to um to
produce our our messages squared. The
important takeaway here is that the
error is squared. So we can when we do
multiplication we really quickly consume
our noise budget because the error
squares and then so if we do repeated
multiplications then it would explode
exponentially. So we need to have a
technique to to deal with this and to
give you guys some like
um
in pra in practice numbers uh if we have
an n so that's the size of our polomials
of about 4,000 which is pretty standard
plain text t a plain text modulus t of
127 and a log q of about 101 then just
after three repeated squarings we
already have accumulated enough noise
that it exceeds and noise budget. So
essentially our cipher text is ruined.
So we need a technique to manage this.
And in BGV luckily we can do something
called uh modulus switching. So inside
of our ciphertext modulus we can
actually use it think about it as a
chain where we have a bunch of prime
factors that are are the decomposition
of our original cipherex modulus. And so
we start off with this big big cipherex
modulus and then we kind of chop it up
uh as we go along.
And um yeah, the way we chop it up is we
just multiply by the the new modulus
which is slightly smaller divided by the
old modulus and then we do some rounding
operations. What's nice about this is
that if we're smart about how we choose
uh the cipher text modulus chain, then
when we do the scaling down operation,
we actually preserve our original
message, but the error kind of decreases
and our cipher text gets smaller.
So yeah, and this is that property that
I was talking about. Um, we can still
run out of noise budget and then we
would have to perform what is known as a
bootstrapping operation which kind of
resets the noise but it's extremely
expensive. Okay, that was a lot. So I
want to talk about how this all works in
practice um using something that I think
you guys probably all work on uh
transformers.
So here we have a simple transformer
architecture
uh with a an attention mechanism and
then a feed forward network.
So this paper uh that's a post on
archive actually does this using
homorphic encryption. So we can encrypt
our input run it through this
transformer um algorithm and get back an
output that we can decrypt later. And
the way that it looks like is is this
table here where uh we have to perform
some matrix multiplications and do a
soft max more matrix multiplications
layer normalization essentially go
through all the normal transformer
models. What I want to highlight here is
the depth because this is kind of the
the key when you're implementing these
things. Um that's that cipher the size
of that cipher text change. So we
started off with uh a cipher text change
that's 21
um cipher text primes and then we
decrease that all the way down to one
and then we have to perform that
expensive bootstrapping operation that I
was talking about before to bring it
back and replenish that noise and then
we can keep going. Um
so after each multiplication operation
usually in homework encryption we
perform this cipher text modulus so that
the the noise growth stays minimal. And
what's nice about this is when we
perform this modulus switch, our cipher
text as I showed before gets smaller,
which means that our operations actually
get much much faster. So as you see in
the original matrix multiplication
um at the the highest layer which is 21,
it takes about what is that 65 seconds
to perform this on the CPU. But when we
do a very similar sized matrix
multiplication on a depth of just two,
it takes only two seconds. So it's much
much faster. And this is why
implementing these things right now is
is quite tricky. and applying or taking
genomic analysis and use and doing it
homorphically is is tricky from an
implementation standpoint because you
need to be very careful with how you
kind of organize your algorithm so that
you maximize performance because it can
there's a 30x difference here. Um so
yeah you need to be you need to be smart
about how you do implement these things
for nonlinear operations like division
that you were talking about before we
have softmax layer norm um glu
we have to approximate these with
polomials so here's an example polomial
that they use to approximate uh gu um
these consume a lot of depth because
they're quite complicated uh as you can
see with the softmax right we go from 19
to three. Um so we're consuming a lot of
depth and uh they're also quite slow. If
you look at 47
47 seconds to perform this um softmax
um oh yeah
because secure transformers require so
much so many operations we do have to
perform this bootstrapping operation
that I was talking about before to
basically replenish the depth and get
our noise budget back. And these are
very very expensive operations. So when
you're implementing these homorphic
algorithms, you honestly want to avoid
bootstrapping at all costs. You can see
in the breakdown of the timings for each
layer, the bootstrapping layer is by far
the most expensive.
Um taking almost 100 plus seconds to do.
Thankfully, um we don't really have to
worry about the the the foundational
implementation of these homorphic
encryption schemes because there's a lot
of tools that exist out there to do them
for us. So for the scheme I introduced
today the BGV scheme um there's a bunch
of implementations seal by Microsoft
latigo EIB um and they perform this
integer um they can do homorphic
encryption on integers supporting
addition and multiplication there's also
tools out there using a scheme called
CKKS to actually do homorphic encryption
on floatingoint uh values so that's
actually what was used in that secure
transformer model uh that I showed
before and that from that paper and then
again seal and lato support this there's
also a different type of scheme called
CGI which supports bits and this is very
good for like comparisons and nonlinear
operations but it's not great for
arithmetic operations uh but that uses
kind of a different scheme uh and then
you can use uh the tf library for that
um so how does this all kind of work in
practice this um I wanted to talk about
a project I did with with Gamsa called
ultra secure scalable and queryable
genotype phenotype databases with squid
and
so for a quick background why do we keep
genome secure it's it's a very important
problem um there are a lot of attacks
that even I taking anonymized genomes
and anonymized data genomic data you can
perform surname inferences you can find
out familial connections
And once your DNA is breached, there's
really no way to change it. So it's out
there forever. As well as like your your
parents share a bunch of your DNA, your
your children also share a bunch of your
DNA. So it can be quite quite harmful.
So when we perform genomic data like a
genomic data analysis such as on the
thousand genomes project, we typically
have a data owner like the NIH uh that
has all of the data that's encrypted at
rest and then a researcher wants to
analyze this. So they download it all
locally
and then they perform the analysis which
is great. Um but as data continues to
grow and we get more and more um more
and more genomic data the the
computational
storage and the communication cost to
just download it um start to really blow
up. Furthermore, the data owner really
has no control over any guarantees of
privacy or security once the the data is
in the hands of the researcher. It's
kind of like assumed that uh the
researcher will be smart about how they
um
how they handle and manipulate the data.
If a patient wants to drop out from the
cohort, it's a challenging process to
have all the researchers kind of remove
that that patient. So really, can we
apply these techniques, this homorphic
encryption technique to do inuse
encryption. So we conjured up this
scenario where a data owner who has all
of the data basically encrypts it and
sends it to the public cloud. And in
clients, our researchers, they can
analyze it by sending queries to the to
the public cloud. Um,
and yeah, in in this setting, like we're
going to use homomorphic encryption,
right? Because we don't want the public
cloud to ever have access or can see
what this uh genomic data is. We want to
keep it keep it ultra secure. So, we
built out a bunch of possible queries um
that the researchers can perform when
you perform this kind of scenario. And
the one that I I kind of want to talk
about is counting queries. Uh but before
I get into that, I really want to
quickly talk about how to do this data
storage and how to store this in the
cloud. So we worked with genomic data
that looks like this. We have a bunch of
snips uh for a bunch of patients. So
very similar to kind of what the
thousand genomes data set looks like.
But we also have some phenotypes, sex,
smoke, if they're smoker or not, or some
disease that uh researchers might want
to analyze. So right each row contains
patient information and each column
contains either a snip or a phenotype.
Using that homorphic encryption packing
that I discussed before, we can actually
store these entire rows of um patients
for like a single snip into a single
cipher text. Uh which is great because
it gives us kind of very natural
parallelism.
Um so how do we perform a counting
query? Let's say a researcher submits
can I count how many patients in this
database have a have snip 2 is equal to
one and sex is equal to one.
um when this gets sent to uh the cloud
we will kind of want to compute this
query and then send it back to the
researcher who can decrypt it using
again homorphic encryption. So how do we
perform this? Well when we get get this
um query coming in we're going to have
to first perform equality tests.
Basically we need to check for each
patient in a database uh do they have a
one for snip two and do they have a one
for sex one. Unfortunately an equality
test is a nonlinear operation. So like
we said we have to approximate this with
um with a polomial. So we're going to
first build out this truth table where
um u is our database value and v is the
query value and essentially it's just
the one on the diagonal when the values
are equal. Very simple.
We are going to assume that the query
value u is not private. The only value
that is private is our database entry.
So we can just generate three different
polomials that kind of evaluate this
this truth um function. And this is kind
of how you actually normally would
perform this translation of nonlinear
functions into um into polomials that
you can evaluate homorphically. So we
generate three different polomials
depending on what the query value was.
Next, we're going to have to evaluate
the
uh boolean circuit to kind of compute a
predicate. So again, here we need to
first check if snip 2 is equal to one
and sex is equal to one. So we're going
to have to apply two equality tests. And
then since we are doing an and
operation, which is essentially a
multiplication,
uh we need to check if both are one. And
if both are one, then if we multiply
them together, the results, the
predicate is going to be one. and that
patient kind of passes this filter uh
that we're querying for. We actually
support two different query types, an
and or an or operation. I'm going to
keep it simple and just focus on the and
which is just a multiplication.
Thankfully, we have that SIMD packing
that I was talking about before. So, we
can actually compute all of this in
parallel. we can just get a
uh we can just look at the the cipher
text for each column and perform this
equality test once um to get the the
full resulting vector back. And this
predicate that I that I've mentioned
before is basically going to be um zero
or one depending on if the patient
passes the filter or not. Again, we're
computing this all homorphically. So the
resulting vector for this predicate is
going to be uh encrypted and it's going
to have L slots which is that SIMD.
Um we need to perform rotations and
additions kind of to aggregate this to
return back account for uh our
researcher.
So homorphic encryption also per um lets
us perform rotation operations which is
like rotating the cipher text slots um
so that we can aggregate them. And this
algorithm essentially just kind of
rotates this log l times till we get the
the inner sum of the entire vector and
then we get back a count that we can
finally return to a researcher.
So what does this look like in practice?
Well um for UK biioank scale for like
let's say 5,000 patients and just having
two filters like we have uh in this
example counting query we can basically
perform this entire operation in four
minutes which is expensive. If you look
uh at the the graph on the right where I
have the the number of patients that
we're performing a counting query on and
the query time on the y-axis, it's much
much slower than uh the plain text
solution, but it's still on the order of
minutes. So, it's not totally
impractical.
Um so, that was my introduction to Squid
and the homorphic encryption primer. Do
you guys have any questions?
I I missed the beginning uh of your talk
but uh can you use this for like real
valued uh know expression so like gene
expression or protein expression instead
of just mutations?
>> Yes. Yes. So
I show I talked about an example of
secure transformer inference which uses
a protocol called CKKS
um which works on floating point values
and non non- integer values. Yes.
>> And is the penalty similar to binary
values or is the penalty much worse?
>> No, it's about the the cost performance
is about half. Um, so it's half half
it's it takes twice as long to do this
real value operation than it does for
integers, but it's still very
performant. It's a great question.
>> Um, can we go back to the transformer
examples?
>> Yes.
>> Um, I think these are the numbers for um
with theom homorphic encryption that
they're using, right? Um, what's the
comparison with just
without being concerned with the
encryption? Yes, I should have included
those
>> a few orders of magnitude.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes, for sure. Um because I
mean a matrix multiplication of this
input size is is going to be much much
faster. I wish I had the numbers on
here, but it's probably about 100 2,000x
lower.
>> I actually still have a couple questions
that I I think I'm not understanding the
uh
>> the noise.
>> Yes. Or is it just is this slowdown just
because you have to like encode the
values in a much larger uh data type
than you normally would?
>> Yeah, exactly. So how is it different
from using like parody bits when you
when you use when you do like regular
you know signal analysis and things like
that
>> parody bits
>> I mean so so the okay if if you're this
is I was electrical engineer in a
previous life so the idea is that
basically you have um you know if you
you you can uh make your addition and
subtraction etc at the bit level more
rob like robust to a certain number of
arbitrary bits clips by adding in an
extra set of parody bits and rules for
checking them.
>> Yes.
>> Um
>> you're just adding extra dimensions.
>> You you just add more bits at the end of
your number.
>> I see.
>> And then that lets you if you you can
check to see like if any basically and
they they represent like sums of the
rest of the data.
>> Oh, okay.
>> And so then you can see like okay, if
this part of the data doesn't sum to
what the parody bits say they should,
then you know that a bit flip has
happened. And based on exactly how how
the what the difference is, you can
actually correct it.
>> Yep.
>> Um and that's sort of my mental model
for how this might work. But I'm not
sure if that's correct.
>> Yeah, it's it's very different. Um
because here we actually have to when we
encrypt the message, we have to hide
everything. Um so we have to essentially
you can think about it as like a mask, a
bit mask I guess essentially. um where
we have our original data and then we
have some masks secret and then we do
some addition and that basically hides
the the resulting data. Um there are no
real I mean I guess there could be
parity bits when you like send it back
and forth. Um but nothing nothing here
is is kind of related to this this idea
of par.
of my
>> or if you use the par bits themselves as
the encrypted message. Is that what you
were thinking?
>> That's a good point. Yeah. Okay.
Maybe this is a silly question, but can
you like is it possible to design
hardware that does all these operations
like in a customized way or are they so
domain dependent or algorithm dependent
that they change all the time?
>> I I think there's work from an MIT group
to do this on FPGAAS. I think that's the
acronym. Um and it actually shows a
quite significant improvement. I think
they got um inference down to about a
100 times slower than plain text. Um and
you can also see that there's a lot of
work to do it on GPUs. Nvidia, I think
like two, three years ago, released
Cutless, which was huge for our space
um because it allowed us to do integer
operations, 64-bit integer operations on
a GPU since everything has to do every
every operation,
even if you're doing floating points
from the CKKS that I introduced under
the hood, these are still integer
operations. You're just kind of scaling
them to be uh from floats to to
integers. Um so everything works under
this integer uh ring that I introduced
way in the beginning. Um so when Nvidia
started releasing all of these new
protocols do all these CUDA kernels to
do this integer programming on a GPU
that's kind of when this uh
this this industry flu uh this this
research angle flourished where people
started to take these homorphic
encryption algorithms and move them to
the GPU and you can see quite a
significant uh improvement. FPGAAS
actually go even beyond what the the GPU
performance is.
>> Yeah. Still on hardware on the example
you showed at the very end the four
minute you know example. Yeah. What's
the hardware roughly speaking?
>> This is CPU.
>> Um so unfortunately like the since we
were using UK biioank data this is uh
when we encrypted it it was around like
one to two terabytes. It was huge. there
there's quite a significant blow up when
you perform this because the cipher text
right you're storing a pair of polomials
um for for each row in our database. So
I it wasn't quite feasible to do this
using hardware but it would certainly
give hardware like GPUs but it would
certainly give a nice performance boost.
>> Yeah,
>> I sort of have a question about Lauren's
question. Sorry, I didn't understand how
the parity bit stuff uh relate to the
noise budget
>> in the sense that like if you're doing
binary operations like at the bit level,
this is the it's a notion of a noise
budget where like you can add more par
bits to leave yourself room to have more
Yeah. Yeah. So you can you can you can
have more errors in your like you can
have a noisier channel in the the um the
signal analysis parlament um and by
adding more but at the expense of your
addition is now more cost or it's it's
less cost effective because you are
using more memory to perform the same
operation.
thinking back question.
>> Oh, we have one more question.
>> Sorry. Uh, so you talked about runtime.
What about space? Do you have also like
space penalties or
there's a run?
>> Yeah. Um, I can actually show you
different slide deck.
Yeah. So
here we we kind of show the the storage
costs. So this is for UK bio bank scale
right when we do um
let's see a whole genome sequencing it's
about a thousand terabytes to store um a
quarter of a million patients. So it's
quite a significant blow up compared to
the the plain text um storage. And if
you're doing encryption at rest using
AES, it's almost the same. Uh it's it's
exactly the same. Um thankfully the
packing algorithm really gives a nice
performance boost where you can store a
lot of information inside of a single
cipher text. You just have to be kind of
clever with um how you perform the query
operations um afterwards.
>> So this is storage cost. What about RAM?
>> RAM. Yes. So the the way I kind of
implemented Squid was everything is
stored on disk and when you perform a
query operation, you only load the
cipher text into memory that you're
going to use for a specific operation.
So for the filtering query, right, we
only look at uh in that example the snip
2 column and the sex column. So you
would load those into RAM from the
database and then you would perform uh
everything on them.
So actually for the GPU example, you
could um load those onto the GPU and
then perform the uh the analysis.
Those cipher texts individually are
actually quite large still because you
have basically one cipher text for
almost all of your patients in your
database when you do this.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you.