the MIT energy initiative presents three
questions enser on the role of blue
hydrogen and decarbonizing the world's
Energy Systems written by Turner
Jackson in the past several years
hydrogen energy has increasingly become
a more Central aspect of the clean
energy transition hydrogen can produce
clean ond demand energy that could
complement variable renewable energy
sources such as wind and solar power
that being said Pathways for deploying
hydrogen at scale have yet to be fully
explored in particular the optimal form
of hydrogen production remains in
question this past fall MIT energy
initiative research scientist enser and
researchers from a wide range of global
academic and research institutions
published on the climate impacts of blue
hydrogen production in the journal
sustainable energy and fuels the article
presents a comprehensive Ive life cycle
assessment LCA analysis of blue hydrogen
here genser discusses the findings of
the study and the role that hydrogen
will play more broadly in decarbonizing
the world's Energy
Systems Q what are the differences
between gray green and blue
hydrogen a though hydrogen does not
generate any emissions directly when it
is used hydrogen production can have a
huge environmental impact colors of
hydrogen are increasingly used used to
distinguish different production methods
and as a proxy to represent the
associated environmental impact today
close to 95% of hydrogen production
comes from fossil resources as a result
the carbon dioxide CO2 emissions from
hydrogen production are quite High gray
black and brown hydrogen refer to Fossil
based production gray is the most common
form of production and comes from
natural gas or methane using steam
methane Reformation but without
capturing CO2
there are two ways to move toward
cleaner hydrogen production one is
applying carbon capture and storage to
the fossil fuel-based hydrogen
production processes natural gas-based
hydrogen production with carbon capture
and storage is referred to as blue
hydrogen if substantial amounts of CO2
from natural gas reforming are captured
and permanently stored such hydrogen
could be a low carbon energy carrier the
second way to produce cleaner hydrogen
is by using electricity to produce Hy
hen via
electrolysis in this case the source of
the electricity determines the
environmental impact of the hydrogen
with a lowest impact being achieved when
electricity is generated from renewable
sources such as wind and
solar this is known as green
hydrogen Q what insights does an LCA
approach give us when analyzing blue
hydrogen and other low carbon Energy
Systems a mitigating climate change
requires significant decarbonization of
the global economy accurate estimation
of cumulative greenhouse gas ghg
emissions and its reduction Pathways is
critical irrespective of the source of
emissions an LCA approach allows the
quantification of the environmental life
cycle of a commercial product process or
service impact with all the stages
Cradle to grave the LCA based comparison
of alternative energy Pathways fuel
options Etc provides an apple Apple's
comparison of low carbon energy choices
in the context of low carbon hydrogen it
is essential to understand the ghg
impact of supply chain options depending
on the production method contribution of
life cycle stages to the total emissions
might vary for example with natural
gas-based hydrogen production emissions
associated with production and transport
of natural gas might be a significant
contributor based on its leakage and
flaring rates if these rates are not
precisely accounted for the
environmental impact of blue hydrogen
can be
underestimated however the same
rationale is also true for
electricity-based hydrogen production if
the electricity is not supplied from low
carbon sources such as wind solar or
nuclear the carbon intensity of hydrogen
can be significantly underestimated in
the case of nuclear there are also other
environmental impact considerations an
LCA approach if performed with
consistent system boundaries can provide
an accurate environmental impact
comparison it should also be noted that
these estimations can only be as good as
the assumptions and correlations used
unless they're supported by
measurements Q what conditions are
needed to make blue hydrogen production
most effective and how can it complement
other decarbonization
Pathways a hydrogen is considered one of
the key vectors for the decarbonization
of hardto abate sectors such as
heavyduty
Transportation currently more than 95%
of global hydrogen production is fossil
fuel based in the next decade massive
amounts of hydrogen must be produced to
meet this anticipated demand it is very
hard if not impossible to meet this
demand without leveraging existing
production assets the immediate and
relatively cost-effective option is to
retrofit existing plants with carbon
capture and storage blue hydrogen the
environmental impact of blue hydrogen
may vary over large ranges but depends
on only a few key parameters the methane
emission rate of the natural gas supply
chain the CO2 removal rate of the
hydrogen production plant and the global
warming metric applied state-of-the-art
reforming with high CO2 capture rates
combined with natural gas supply
featuring low methane emissions
substantially reduces ghg emissions
compared to Conventional natural gas
reforming under these conditions blue
hydrogen is compatible with low carbon
economies and Exhibits climate change
impacts at the upper end of the range of
of those caused by hydrogen production
from renewable based
electricity however neither current blue
nor green hydrogen production Pathways
render fully net zero hydrogen without
additional CO2 removal