My pleasure to introduce Calen very much
who is a principal research scientist at
the Schwarzman College of Computing here
at MIT. He's also the founder and the
head of the data to AI lab. Um and uh he
is going to speak to you about using AI
to generate synthetic data for software
testing. So let's hear it for Kyan.
Thank you. Um thanks a lot. My name is
as Kawan Virini. I'm uh founder and
director of data to AAI lab at MIT. But
I'm also representing data SIBO for
which I'm co-founder. I just spun that
out from my lab. um we focus a lot on
creating synthetic data and I'll go into
a little bit detail a little bit just a
little bit detail about what that is uh
in this presentation but also present
talk about how we use that to test
software applications as you know our
world kind of runs on software
applications as you wake up in the
morning you you're using software
applications throughout your day whether
it's you're interacting with your TV
coffee machine zoom whatever you're
using you're using software applications
and they are being fine-tuned in real
time based on the data they see or the
interactions you have with them. So
testing those applications and supplying
that data for those applications to test
them has become very critical over the
past uh decade or so. And one of my main
research topics focused on that not just
necessarily testing but how do we
increase the data supply for software
applications? How many of you have heard
of synthetic
data? All right. How many of you use
synthetic
data? All right. How many of you already
know all about it? So maybe you should
go for lunch, right? Um but it's good to
it's good to know that a lot of people
know about synthetic data. So what is
synthetic AI generated synthetic data?
There used to be versions of synthetic
data. So you can use simulation engines
to generate synthetic data. But what is
AI generated synthetic data? It is data
that's created by AI models and you get
data that looks very much like the real
data in statistical properties however
you want to measure them or sometimes
you use humans to detect whether they
look like the real data if it's images
or otherwise um and and you can use it
for various purposes but the key element
here is that it is actually generated
from a model so when it's AI you're act
you actually have a model file and
you're actually generating from that
model synthetic data set that resembles
real data. So you all are familiar with
language and we would call what chat GBD
generates the synthetic language. Um it
is not generated by humans. There's
nobody answering as as a human from the
other side. It's generated by a a model
underneath it. It's called GPT. Everyone
may have and that's why it's called chat
GPT. Similarly, there's been tremendous
amount of progress in images. How do you
generate images that look realistic? uh
these are a set of images that are that
are generated by AI model but they are
not actually they don't they're not they
don't exist they're not real people here
um so that's another example of uh
synthetic data that's been created so a
lot of that you know innovation started
way back in 2014 where they created this
technology called generative adversarial
networks in machine learning community
where they use two neural networks to
compete with each other so one tried to
create realistic looking data um using
just random data as input. So noise as
input. It takes noise as input and
generate realistic looking data. The
other one tries to distinguish whether
the data generated by the first one is
real or not. So both of them are
competing with each other and as a
result they eventually lead to a model
that actually produces realistic looking
images or realistic looking language and
so on. Um you know one of one of the
things that my group focuses on is that
tabular data. So tabular and structured
data. So images and language you know
there's a lot of work around it there's
a lot of um material available a lot of
models available a lot of technology
available but 80% of the enterprise data
from by some measures is tabular data it
is structured data whether it's stored
in your databases or JSON files or XML
files and so on and so forth it is what
you store when when your customers are
interacting with your systems and
products and services and that is the
data that we focus on and when we try to
create synthetic data So for that my
group created the first sort of one of
the first I believe uh GAN for tabular
data. Same principle use the same
principle but instead of images we tried
to create realistic looking tabular
data. So can you tell which one is real
and one of them is not
real? I I actually don't know exact it
is. It is created by one of one of the
folks that use our software and they
always tell me it's on the left and I
don't know when which way I have to turn
to tell which one. I think it's that one
is not real. So, but you know it's it's
very hard to tell. Um now obviously this
is not how you how you evaluate tabular
data similarity. We actually have
metrics to evaluate whether this is both
of those data sets are similar or not.
So we are not looking for a human visual
um recognition like unlike images and
language. So as a result we created
something at MIT called synthetic data
walt. This was way back in 2015. We
created the first software system a
generative modeling system for tabular
data as actually multiple tables as
well. Uh and a subsequent paper was in
2019 but the first one was in 2015 and
we released a software library at that
time called SDV. Has anyone heard of
SDV?
Nina has heard of SDV. All right. So now
we have heard of it. Um so what does SDV
do? So you feed it real data. You still
have to give it a little bit of real
data. You use SDV to model and it does
build a generative model for you. And
once you have the model, you can sample
synthetic data from it. So you can
sample as much as you want. You can
sample based on certain conditions. So
you can also specify saying that fix the
gender to male and then you know state
to Ohio and give me interactions for
thousand customers that have that those
two attributes fixed. So you can also
conditionally sample which in language
we call them prompts. So you're
prompting to sample the data from
language. Um the other interesting
aspect is that if you have terabytes of
data this model is still you know a
gigabytes less than gigabytes. So you're
you're essentially getting a compressed
version of your data. uh if you have
only you know thousands of customers of
data but you know you build you build
this model you can actually sample
millions of uh customers data if you
wanted to. So it's it it just provides
you enormous amount of flexibility in
terms of how you can use this model and
how you can deploy this and there's a
lot of use cases which I'll go into very
briefly. So uh I'll just go very briefly
into it. It's actually uh it does build
a model for across the table. One big
difference between academic um work,
research work and practical enterprise
work is that in academia we have really
nice under like you know table one table
worth of data clean no messiness to it.
But when you go into enterprises you
start getting like many tables. Um you
have 20 30 50 100 tables in your
databases and there's a lot of mess
messiness in the data. There's missing
data. There's all kinds of weird
artifacts in the data which we have to
replicate when we when we generate
synthetic data. But we replicate that
messiness as well. We emulate that
messiness in the synthetic data as well.
So there is a whole process to it that
we invented of how to systematically
learn those relationships, learn the
messiness as well and create uh create
realistic looking data and then
ultimately once it once you create the
data the model it's just one file. Um
just like how you know language models
have gone through evolution this area
has also gone through evolution. Um so
way back in 20145 time frame we actually
started building just model for a very
specific application a student online
learning platform data edex here and we
took that data and we built a very
custom model just for it a generative
model just for it that worked so well
then we decided why don't we generalize
it to relational databases or single
table or three to five tables and that
took us a couple of years to do it and
very soon we realized that all the
algorithms we invented don't scale to
enterprises so we actually had to invent
invent a new set of algorithms to do
that because enterprises had 20 to 30
tables and so on and so forth. As we
went went ahead we found more and more
and more complexity in enterprise data.
Then I'll go through a little bit of
that that alludes to what the maturity
of a synthetic data software system is
right now in the market. Uh we open
source SDV for everyone to create and
use synthetic data. Lots of enterprises
use it. Uh more than you know 50% of the
you know top 20 to 30 banks use it. Um
and many many of the I would say 70 or
so fortune 500 use this SDV software
system internally.
Um as a result we we keep seeing a lot
of downloads a lot of people giving us
feedback on what is working what is not
working. So it has become over several
years over the last 5 years we've become
one of the most mature software system
for being able to generate synthetic
build models and generate synthetic data
for the kind of data that you would
encounter in your in in your
enterprises. We also built an entire
ecosystem around it. So we had to build
our own metrics and evaluation system.
So we open sourced it. It's called SD
metrics. So how do you evaluate is it
does it resemble the real data or not?
Um we created a benchmarking system. If
there are multiple models, how do you
assess? So just like any like OpenAI
would do it. We had to do all of this
for this area uh by ourselves which we
have been doing for uh for a while now
for a couple of year for five to six
years now. U you can access all of them.
they're they're publicly available and
you can use them. You can give it a try.
There are three primary use cases three
or four primary use cases that have that
have uh emerged so far. Uh one of them
is about training robust ML models. So
this is where you have very little data
for particular event that you want to
predict. So most likely if you have a
you know we work with wind turbine
companies and they have wind turbine
failures and you have very few failures.
only 1% of your data is failures but you
have 99% that's just normal functioning
of the turbine and data that pertains to
no failures in that case machine
learning models overfit the failure data
and you will get good accuracy on
training but when you deploy it it
doesn't give you that that much of a
good accuracy so to control that
overfitting you can use synthetic data
you can augment so you can create
synthetic data and you can augment um
that's one one very popular use case
there's ways to debias the data using
synthetic data So as I mentioned you can
conditionally sample from it. Um you can
simulate novel scenarios. So there are
people who are using it to say well I
have all this data about how I we
discover products and can I build a
model and then try to say if I change
certain attributes of my product what
will happen to the consumer reaction in
a consumer panel. So there's a lot of
various ways you can use this model in
addition to just sampling synthetic
data.
The last one is sharing data with
developers to test software
applications. So I'll focus a little bit
on that this uh considering the the
theme of the forum I decided maybe
that's the application that we'll focus
on. So I'll I'll just give you a quick
example walk through of uh this is an
actual deployment in at ING bank uh in
Europe. It's one of the biggest banks in
Europe um and top 20 in the world by
some some measures as well. uh they use
this application called single euro
payments application SEPA uh everybody
maybe Europe familiar with it they use
this to exchange uh money or transfer
money I guess uh and it has a very
structured format an XML format uh there
is the debittor there's a creditor
there's all kinds of information about
the transaction essentially it's having
two it's enabling this application it's
enabling two entities to talk to each
other and do a transfer of money so for
this you know one of the challenges in
software testing is you have these
different environments all the way up to
the production environment. So if you go
to the production environment you do
have real data but nobody has access to
it. It's not because it's customer data
or in this case it's consumer data so
nobody's getting access to that
environment. uh then you sometimes
create masked and anonymized data in
which case you change the account or
mass the ids account ids you may have
seen that in your own data as well when
you have the first 12 digits are masked
out in a in a credit card number so you
create that data for acceptance
environment where in which people test
software applications before they get
deployed into production. Um you have
the testing environment and in that case
you create a very small test fake data
which is just random data generated from
by using some tool. Uh it has nothing to
do with the real data you generate just
random data to test applications. It has
a structure in the format and then that
fake data is now propagated to different
developers developing on those local
machines. So as you can see from the top
to bottom the number of people who have
access to real data has reduced and the
second thing is that the real data has
completely gone away like at at in in
testing and development environment
you're really creating fake data and by
fake data we mean just random data. So
you just randomly create data by using
some noise and things like that.
So what and these applications one of
the challenges is that the the the
requirements that the applications have
to satisfy or the or the need the
definition of the application keeps
changing. So here we are just showing
two requirements that just happened
within a span of 3 months as they
started using our software to build
synthetic data to test this application
and this is one of the reasons why they
have to keep building the the model
again and sampling from it again and
again. Um one of the thing is that in EU
sanctioned and enacted sanctions which
means the developers went ahead and
implemented a way to block transactions
of certain type based on those
sanctions. The second was that instead
of address being in one column um they
now required the address to be split
across three columns. So you know simple
changes like this require you to change
the software application build test for
it have the data to be able to test such
uh logic and that data is now either
you're creating fake data in which case
you don't get those edge cases and you
would have to manually write it. So
there's a whole process to this which is
time consuming but these are just two
requirement changes that required
significant change in the logic but then
you also have tons of requirements
coming through on almost on a weekly
basis or or or a monthly basis right um
so two things that people do is either
they copy and mass the data but it's not
available in develop to the developers
it's only available in the acceptance
environment or the other thing that
people do which is to our surprise it's
a actually very well known thing that a
lot of people do is to just manually
enter the data. So you saw the XML sheet
you just create the XML file you you
know put the transaction amount put the
creditor debittor create if you want to
test the logic of uh whether you know we
are correctly blocking the transactions
you would create the data of the
transaction that you would like to block
right um so as you can imagine it's a
very manual process and tedious process
and you would have to keep creating this
data keep storing it someplace and
managing it and more importantly I think
you would have to know the entire like
XML format and everything and you have
to, you know, make sure that you're
creating the right data, test the logic
or and so
on. So these are just examples. They
wanted to test a lot of payments back
and forth. So they wanted to generate
thousands of transactions. Ideally, they
would generate thousands of transactions
in manual data generation. They were
able to generate like five to 10
transactions by manually writing it and
specific to a particular logic. That's
what they would do. um and they wanted
to see if the time performance and
everything is being met or not. So
ideally they would like to do is to
create thousands of transactions using
the synthetic data generator and use
those transactions and pretend they are
real transactions and simulate the whole
system and see where it falls apart,
right? Either the logic is not uh
happening or performance is too slow and
so on and so forth. So one day morning I
think we got a we got a message saying
that hey your your your data emptied an
account completely and that's a good
thing um because they wanted to test
that situation when an account gets
completely emptied by a set of transfers
what happens does the transfer get
blocked and what happens what kind of
messaging does go back to the goes back
to the person who's doing the
transaction so there's a lot of edge
cases they they would like to test um
again for this you still need a very
little bit of data not that much but a
little bit of data from the production
environment. You build the model on prem
and once you build that model now you
can generate as many transactions as you
want. So in this case they generated um
without SDV they were generating 10 as I
mentioned transactions because you have
to manually create them. Uh with SDV
they were able to generate around 10,000
transactions within 2 minutes. Um they
would model the data and then from that
model they would sample and that just
takes 2 minutes to sample. And because
we made sure that all our software works
with enterprise level data, you know,
most of the data was accurate and we
also give data validation techniques to
tech before you uh before you use that
data downstream. So one of the
interesting thing is that you if you
have masking and anonymizing it gives
you high coverage because you're
essentially subsetting or subsampling
from the real data and you're masking um
you know some of the fields but it is
very expensive because it has to go
through privacy review. It has to go
through a lot of reviews before it's
available and it's not available in the
lower environment. And if you go through
manual data entry, it has very low
coverage because you're just creating
specific uh examples for testing your
logic. And it is cheap in terms of
expense of uh of the privacy teams and
so on and so forth. Definitely not cheap
in terms of the manual data entry work
that you have to put in. And on the
other hand, synthetic data gives you
high coverage and it's extremely cheap
to generate. So that's one of the big
things that that shows up with synthetic
data as you use it for software
applications. Um you know just as a as a
reference I don't know how many of you
have used test data creation tools
or anyone. All right.
Um you know as I mentioned there's a lot
of methods to do this but all of them
rely on either copying masking and
anonymizing or they rely on humans
writing writing rules. There are some
explicit ways of writing rules. So here
I'm just showing how people write rules
on the left where people just say if the
account type is premium then 10% of the
time nor you know give me data 10% of
the time and normal data 90% of the
time. So you actually specify certain
rules. So in in addition to your
application that your software
application you're also maintaining an
entire software system that generates
the data for you. And from one
particular enterprise, we heard that
there's like 10,000 lines of code. It's
actually that code to generate the data
with those rules is more than the actual
application sometimes. Um, so and you
have to maintain all of that. But with
with generative AI, you don't have to do
that. You your generative AI essentially
is learning those rules under the hood.
Um, you're not asking it to specifically
learn a particular rule, but it's under
the hood. It's learning all those rules,
all those distributions and conditional
distributions and so on and so forth.
So I'll just try to
um give the comparison between the copy
mask anonymize and manual rulebased
generation versus SDV or generative
models in this case where in terms of
relationships captured you know copy and
mask anonymize are dependent on the
amount of data you copied. So it will
capture all the relationships as long as
you copy a lot of data. Um in manual
rules based generation depending upon
how many you wrote you would have
thousands of rules but in in sort of
generative models there are billions of
rules that have been learned. You can
actually poke it and try to find out
what kind of rules it learn but it does
run learn billions of rules conditional
rules across the data that you have. Um
it takes weeks or months to do the first
two. Um first one primarily because of
the approval and and access control
overcoming the access control policies.
The second one is simply just writing
the rules writing the rules and
maintaining them. And if you add up it
takes a lot of time for that. The third
one is just hours. Um you are able to
build the model. You'll still need some
real data. So you can ask that well we
need access for that. But most people
are okay giving access to real data as
long as what comes out is a model and
not the real data. a model that you can
transport to different different
locations. Um he's saying no he's
um since then that one application that
example I I walked through um there have
been several um applications of this
technology across ING and across other
enterprises. I talked a little bit about
functional testing. My example was about
functional testing but there's been
applications where people do performance
testing. So you just build a model and
generate a lot of data and from that
data you're just testing whether your
application meets the SLAs's and
performance requirements. Um there is
testing thirdparty integration. So this
was another case where there is a third
party software application that you
integrate with. Um but the thing was
that when you give it the data it does
work very slowly. It slows down on on
their test data. they're reporting an
SLA of like you know 100,000
transactions per second or whatnot but
when you try to like put your real data
this is a banking banking institution
trying to put the real data it takes
like 2 three hours and so that that has
been going on for months between the two
parties and eventually I think the best
way for them to mitigate that was to
give some synthetic data that
representative of their the bank's real
data and give it to them and they said
every time you release a new version of
your software test with this data please
and that actually mitigated a lot of
these bottlenecks uh and the performance
issues that they were seeing. There's
also API testing. So there's a lot of
API based microservices that now are per
have to be performant when they're
interacting with each other and you can
generate synthetic API data as well just
like how we generated JSONs to use use
for that testing as well. I will just go
through a few items on
um I think I mean how much time do you
have do I have?
Okay, got it. So I'll just go through a
few more additional complexities when we
go to enterpriseg grade data um beyond
the multi-table aspect of it which is a
big as which is a big sort of uh
requirement for enterprise data. I mean
if you don't have a multi-table solution
to generate synthetic data you really
don't have anything for enterprises
because most enterprises do not have
just data in one table they have 30 40
50 tables and most applications even if
you go down all the way to the
application level most applications at
least consume three to five tables uh at
at the very least. So you need to have a
model that actually is built uh to on on
multiple that can account for those
multiple tables and build a model for
that and sample likewise. But there's
more to it and we as we as our SDV
proliferated across enterprises and
across applications and data sets we
started to realize there's more um as
more challenges to that and I'll go
through a few of them and how we now
address um one of the challenges is
there is business logic there is a lot
of business logic in here so in other
words if you have real data on on on the
on the
left my right all right if you the blue
that's why we have the colors the blue
you realize that based on the currency
the the the range of the amount will
change and that is something that's a
very you know we all can see it and
realize it but algorithms have to
automatically recognize it and model
that. So that is buried inside the data
and your your synthetic data also have
to emulate that. It has to understand
based on that column there is actually
changes in the currency ranges and so
forth. So that's the second thing that I
would say is like there's a sprawl of
data types. So you have phone numbers,
addresses,
geolocations, URLs, name it you have it
is perhaps 200 IBAN credit card numbers
and so on and so forth. So what is the
challenge with it? The simplest thing
you could do is you could take the data
and then you could just create fake
data. There's a library called faker. So
you can just create fake credit card
numbers, fake uh phone numbers and so on
and so forth. But the problem with that
is that the synthetic data then doesn't
look real. So in your real data, if you
had a distribution where phone number
they were 40% from New York, 20% person
from Massachusetts and 40% from Ohio,
you would like to have that
representation in the in the synthetic
data as well. So ideally what you would
do is you would take the phone number,
you extract a whole bunch of context
from that phone number. So where is
which state it is from? Uh what is the
other attributes of it? If it's a
different country, you extract that as
well. And then you model that and when
you sample it, you sample a number with
that context in in in place and but not
the original number. There's another
challenge. You have to make sure that
number doesn't belong to someone else.
It's very hard to do that. But there is
an API you can actually check. So the
end toend journey of how you create
phone numbers, synthetic phone numbers
that will represent in distribution and
frequency as if as if your real data is
a lot is a lot of work goes behind the
scenes and we have to address it. We had
to address at least like there's 100 to
200 different data types like this
different things latl long for example
um and sometimes you have to generate
them together. So latl long you can't
generate them independently as you can
imagine they they are correlated. If you
generate them independently you'll end
up like with one data point somewhere in
the middle of the ocean where you would
like to actually generate it right next
to where it was.
Um biggest thing that we found and we
have collected we call them data
patterns. They are a result of hidden
context. This is this is massive in
enterprises right now because what
people have done is that if you look at
the schema the schema is still fine. You
have a primary key and you have a
foreign key and you have one to many
relationship. But the challenge what you
have here is that only people with the
premium membership this is just an
example have entries in the second table
right and application developers know
how to process this data because they
are looking in their application they
have code they're looking for you know
premium membership and then only they'll
go to this table. So they know how to
process this context but nowhere in the
database schema there is a there is
affordances to save this context. So we
call this hidden context and as you can
imagine when we generate synthetic data
it has to have the same thing replicated
as well. So only people with the premium
membership should have entries in the
second table in the benefits table as
well. So there is that sort of challenge
as well. we identified 30 or so
different data patterns that are uh sort
of appearing in many enterprise data
sets and now we address them natively.
So just like language, language went
through a lot of evolution. What you see
today is 10 years worth of work and how
they made sure that there is coherent
language. There is a need for you know
there is a lot of work that goes behind
in generating structured data that has
coherence and that follows all these
simple things that you have. Generative
models by definition don't capture all
of this by by themselves. Um so I just
wanted to sort of talk about different
levels. Ignore the last one. I think
it's level four. But you know we started
very with very simple assumption that
enterprises have single table data sets.
That's not like 90% of them is not the
case. Uh there's still 10%. It's still a
valid uh synthetic data generation
scheme. Um but we you know made sure
that single table models work well. they
respect all the formatting properties
and the minmax ranges and you'd be
surprised how challenging it is for them
to behave the generative models to
behave. So we made sure and that just
got us to level zero. Level one we made
sure that we can address in a scalable
way for 30 to 50 tables or even 100
tables. We have been our software has
been tested up to 50 tables but there
are 100 tables in databases. There have
been people have you know asked us could
we generate 100 tables worth of model
and generate 100 tables worth of data.
And the third thing is what I talked
about just now hidden context. How do
you model the business logic and hidden
context we call them constraints and try
to generate constraint you know try to
make sure that data follows those
constraints and how do you generate
that? So we call them constraint
augmented generation just like how you
call retrieval augmented generation. And
there's a constraint augmented
generation uh in here where you supply
some of those rules or or specify that
these columns may have a relationship
and we take care of it. Um there is a
lot of uh interesting situations where
people would like to generate data
outside the real what the real data has
or the training data has. So a classic
example is that an insurance application
um is only 18 and above are allowed to
sign up for the insurance application.
So only you know so when you go to the
insurance application and if you enter
your date of birth it will reject and
saying that you are not eligible to sign
up for this uh insurance policy or
whatnot. As a result the database only
has people whose age is 18 and above. So
if you get the real data you will only
see people who are 18 and above but they
also want to generate data that is below
18 because they want to test all the
logic that they have designed for people
below 18. So there's a big we call that
out of range sampling. So there's a huge
requirement of how to generate data
outside um the range that has been seen
in the training data. So there's a whole
this is just one example. There's like
hundreds of examples like this where we
categorize into like how do you generate
data that you haven't seen before yet be
very realistic about it. Um the last but
not the least is like this whole process
we want to be as automated as possible.
Um so that people don't have to worry
about all these things when they just
like how you're in your language model
they have gone all the way that it's
very automated. Trust me, 10 years ago,
the language models that we were working
with as research were were not as good
as as as they are today. We would have
to curate them. We would have to get the
next word and the next word. It was not
that automated that you just ask and it
get gives you the whole thing. Um and
much less, you know, it was not even
interactive. So I think even for this
area, we've been trying to incrementally
build up so that you have models that
are um that can capture all the
complexity of the data and regenerate
it. So hopefully you have you from this
talk you saw just the journey of how we
went from a lab research project at MIT
to you know beginnings of a use case at
an enterprise and as a result started to
understand the complexity of enterprise
data and sort of enhance it um our
technology over time with enterprise
feedback. I I I do think without that
feedback we wouldn't have I mean there's
still a lot of academic work that is
completely devoid of um understanding
the enterprise data and without that I
don't think you can actually build
anything that is mature and usable uh
within an enterprise. So with that I'll
take questions.
You had your hand up first.
Yeah. A real quick question. Does the
tool have an UI for users? And also my
second question is what is the way to
test all the model generated data to
make sure the hidden context the
constraints etc. you know it really
happened. Good. Um the first question is
UI for specific parts of the uh tool
there is UI. Um we haven't endeavored
into doing UI. It just took us a lot of
time to build the whole system. Uh the
second part of the question we have a we
have a whole validation system to check
for data integrity. So you to that
system you supply the real data and
synthetic data and it gives you
diagnostics, quality metrics, privacy
metrics and efficacy metrics. So there's
a whole bunch of metrics that you can
get that test for uh all the properties
whether the synthetic data is matching
all the properties in the real data or
not.
Well, this was super interesting. So
thanks for sharing. Um just trying to
tie what you just shared with yesterday.
Yesterday there was a talk about
healthcare. Mhm. And there's some models
where you know they really struggle with
certain gender race factors right to
predict. Do you see synthetic data being
used in the health care space and then
just also just curious about the
trade-offs of improving the model
quality but then maybe potential like
ethic you know ethical concerns. So
cool. Um so synthetic data is can be
used for that that's called debiasing
the data. So you can take the data and
build the model generative model and
then you can specifically ask that give
me data for a particular race and
particular gender and give me more
samples. So what it will do is it will
go on it will go I mean behind the
scenes what it's doing is it's it has
learned enough in the neighborhood of
where that data is for that race and
gender and it will create data points a
little bit around it as well as well as
because of of the tales of the
distributions a little farther out as
well. So a lot of people use that
technique to you know you you know when
they're building a subsequent model a
machine learning model a predictive
model to debias that model and the way
you know I I I think the machine
learning model is able to use that
synthetic data is that it doesn't
overfit if you have less of a particular
demographic it tries to overfit that uh
so it just generalizes it a little bit
better and there is metrics directly to
measure the fairness and the quality of
your um model trained on data. Um so I
think that those metrics are helpful to
fine-tune the synthetic data generation
as well.
So um on the human aspect people the bis
bankers was using humans and I think
because the humans can identify that
frontier case where outside the real
data what are possible go wrong so kind
of the the where the limit of of of
logic is for the system. So I'm curious
in the synthetic data and the data that
goes outside the real data, how does
that compare to what the edge case that
a human can come up with versus the edge
case that actually the data the
synthetic data gives you?
It's a it's a very hard question to
assess whether the the what human came
up with is is it better that the
generative model did better than human
because then we would outside the real
data outside the real data because we
would have to you know ask humans to
create that um to test it really you
know one-on-one testing but from our
experience what we have seen is that
when it does generate outside the real
data it is useful depends on the
downstream application it is useful for
whether it's useful or not for the
downstream application is something that
we can test because most of the times
downstream applications do have um a way
to measure you know you know something
to measure right so a classic example is
that you know one of the companies that
we work with they develop new products
and they have attributes and they do
panels where the consumers give the
liking and they tweak the attributes and
so on and so forth and they projected
that. So that's a whole human-driven
process. Somebody's actually building
those products and and and designing
those by changing the attributes react
building looking at the reaction of the
consumers and so on so forth. So they
used they created synthetic products and
their estimate of the what the humans
would be uh whether you know like or not
do not like and it turned out a lot of
products that were created by the
synthetic data generator. So these are
not the one that are seen were very
similar to the ones that they had
created. Um so that actually gave some
validation to
them only for data or does it
work non relational database? Um it does
work on non- relational databases as
well. Um you just have to specify the
connections if they are connections. Um
but it does work. it doesn't necessarily
only need the relational databases.
What is your take on time series and
especially multivariate
multivariate time series? So we do have
models that are able to create time
series as well multivariate time series
as well. The challenges in time series
are um not just the multivaried I think
there's a lot of again hidden context.
So there are control signals that
specify what the distribution of the
other time series are. So there are
signals that you there variables that
you can control. Um so for example in in
win turbine case there is actually you
know how much speed you're not
necessarily speed but there's variables
that you can say like I'm going to
operate in this regime versus this
regime versus this regime. So now that's
a control variable. It has values 1 2
and three but the users control it. It's
not observational data. based on that
your other time series change
distributions. There's correlations
between different time series. There is
causality between time series. So it's
actually it itself has a lot of issues
in terms of being able to model and
regenerate it. Does that answer your
question? I was curious if your tool is
sort of could be an option or not. And
it is. It is an
option. Right. I think we'll wrap up
now. Let's uh give it up for Calan.
Thank you.
Great job.