hello everyone good morning welcome to
the mpg primer today we are excited to
have Elizabeth Doren she's a fourth year
PhD student in alus prices group in the
department of epidemiology at Harvard
Chan School of Public Health before
beginning her doctoral studies she
earned her undergraduate degree at
Vanderbilt University where she studied
molecular biology human and
organizational development and music I
just learned she played the viola um her
current research focuses on developing
computational methods to link regulatory
elements to their target genes using
single cell data um so Elizabeth take it
away oh um please feel free to ask
questions um throughout the talk if you
have them there's two mics located in
the center of the room um also if you
raise your hand I could run over and
give you a mic thank
you like I have a laser point here going
on
okay I'll just put that down there all
right um morning everybody I'm Elizabeth
I'm very excited to talk to you all
today about this new technology that has
the potential to measure biology at a
really unprecedented uh resolution and I
actually want to start by kind of
framing the goals of my presentation um
as you all might know the number of
single cell Technologies single cell
data sets and single cell anal analysis
methods is huge and rapidly growing
there might even be a few out uh new by
the end of this presentation so with
that in mind uh the goal of my talk
today is less to dive into the specifics
of a particular technology or the math
of a specific analysis method and more
so to gain uh kind of a broad
appreciation and intuition for the Big
Technical challenges in the world of
single cell technology and single cell
data
analysis all
right so here is an outline of my
presentation today um first we'll
discuss kind of emerging single cell
multi Technologies starting of course by
understanding what is single cell
technology and then more specifically
what is single cell multi
technology and hopefully the bulk of the
discussion will be on analysis methods
which I imagine are of greatest interest
to this audience um we will learn what
questions single cell multi data can
answer we will discuss the major
technical challenges um currently in
single cell multi data analysis and I'll
finish with a sort of in-depth look at
one example area of inquiry and single
cell multi data which is computationally
linking enhancers to their target Gene
okay so to start um what is single cell
technology so as I'm sure um many of you
might be aware single cell technology
refers to a family of sequencing
technologies that measure biology at the
level of individual cells so traditional
sequencing Technologies referred to as
bulk Technologies make biological
measurements that reflect the biology of
a group of cells perhaps from a tissue
sample or cell culture um they produce
one quantitative readout per sample
reflecting kind of the average profile
of biology within that sample whereas
single cell Technologies um produce many
quantitative readouts one per cell
reflecting the biology of that
particular
cell so it's perhaps intuitive but why
these days is everyone interested in
single cell data so a popular metaphor
highlighting the benefits of single cell
data um is the fruit smoothie versus
fruit salad metaphor so we can think of
traditional bulk data as a fruit
smoothie a bunch of different fruits
kind of ground up and made homogeneous
and we can think of single cell data as
a fruit salad all of the different
fruits mixed together but they're
distinct textures and flavor profiles
are still
detectable so if we are interested in
learning about some characteristic of a
sample of fruits for example we can gain
a lot more information from a fruit
salad than we can from a fruit smoothie
a fruit smoothie might be able to tell
us the general characteristics of fruit
or of a particular uh population of
fruits in our smoothie but a fruit salad
is going to give us that information for
particular fruits and even particular
slices of the same
fruit so the same intuition can be
applied to a more biological example
perhaps if we're interested in um some
molecular feature within a cell like the
expression of some fictional Gene a a
traditional bulk sample is going to give
us one readout just an average
expression level of Gene a across all of
the cell types and individual cells in
the sample
whereas a single cell sample will
produce one readout per cell and
certainly in a real life bulk or single
cell data set there'd be way more than
four cells so with that there'd be way
more
heterogeneity um perhaps even at the
level of a subcell type or cell
State um so in this example we can see
how this might be compelling the bulk
readout shows that there is some
moderate level of expression of Gene a
whereas the Single Cell readout shows
that in certain cells or cell types
there's very high expression of Gene a
and in other cells Gene a is very lowly
expressed or maybe even not expressed at
all we can imagine if we're interested
in understanding the function of Gene a
Maybe It's associated with a particular
disease or something like that this
unlocks a lot more insights and kind of
leads to more interesting Downstream uh
follow-up hypotheses than the simple
readout so to summarize single cell data
retains cellular heterogeneity it gives
us much higher biological resolution and
allows us to ask more specific
questions so what types of biology can
we profile at the level of a single cell
um single cell genomic Technologies
measure a variety of biological
modalities ranging from DNA sequence to
gene expression chromatin accessibility
biochemical modifications to DNA or
histones um this figure here just lists
a small subset of the biological
modalities and corresponding SE
sequencing technologies that are
currently
available um and is certainly vastly
expanding but these modalities are often
uniquely informative um and usually
provide complimentary insights so for
example if we run a single cell RNA seek
experiment um get a profile of gene
expression um across a population of
cells we might observe the expression of
a particular transcription factor of
interest and a subpopulation of cells
and we might hypothesize that this
transcription factor is active and is
turning on some known Gene regulatory
Network perhaps some information that
could be very useful for validating this
hypothesis is what is the chromatin
accessibility landscape or DNA
methylation landscape in these same
cells do we see The Binding sites for
that transcription Factor accessible in
the same cells do we see Downstream Gene
enhancers accessible in those same
cells so this is where single cell multi
technology comes
in so single cell multi Technologies
jointly measure multiple biological
modalities within the same cells so
providing not just one biological
readout per molecular feature per cell
um but two readouts per feature per cell
or possibly even more than two as we'll
see much later in the
presentation so for the purposes of um
giving example for the presentation
today I'll primarily focus on Multi
technologies that jointly profile
chromatin accessibility and gene
expression this is kind of the dominant
subcategory of single cell multi
technology so I've highlighted um mRNA
and chromatin accessibility is the two
biological modalities of Interest
here um so to sort of demonstrate at not
too technical of a level how this
technology might work uh we all might be
familiar with single cell RNA sequencing
which of course meas measures gene
expression by targeting um mature
messenger rnas for
sequencing the readout of a single cell
RNA sequencing experiment is a gene
expression count Matrix with um cells as
rows and genes as columns or flipped a
Cell by Gene
Matrix similarly um a unimodal or single
biological modality single cell attack
seek experiment measures chromatin
accessibility uh it does this
using an enzyme called a transposase
enzyme which targets regions of open
chromatin specifically for
sequencing and the biological readout of
a single cell attack seek experiment is
a chromatin accessibility Matrix where
the counts here represent how often a
particular region of DNA was detected as
accessible by the transposase enzyme so
here we have a cell by region Matrix
this might be significant iFly um higher
dimensional than an RNA seek readout and
I'll elaborate a bit later on um what
the molecular features chromatin regions
might be specifically for this uh
experiment so single cell RNA and attack
seek multi data jointly measures RNA and
attack across the same single cells um
so both experiments are performed and
I'll give a zoom in on that in a second
and the ultimate readout is two feature
matrices a Cell by Gene Matrix of
expression and a Cell by region Matrix
of Chromatin
accessibility so ignoring the details in
this figure just to give kind of an
intuition for how this works
experimentally um this is an
illustration of kind of the dominant
technology in the multi space
particularly in the RNA and attack multi
space that is the 10x multi
technology at a basic level how this
works is first all cells in a sample are
treated with the transposase enzyme
which again is the essential enzyme for
producing the attack seek
readout second using very advanced
technology that um definitely others
might understand better than me um cell
specific and also molecule specific
barcodes are added to DNA and mRNA
molecules within each cell in the
sample and finally sequencing libraries
are prepared so at the end of the
experiment um we have a lot of gene
expression counts and also chromatin
accessibility counts that are assigned
to specific cells within your
sample all right so hopefully that
provides just enough technical detail to
to um understand kind of the readouts
and the potential Downstream
applications of these data so I'll now
move on to uh single cell multi analysis
methods so I'll first start with what
questions can single cell multi data
answer so again this field is kind of in
its early stages a very new technology
so instead of giving a super specific
overview of uh one analysis method I'm
kind of going to give um some broad
descriptions of the few different areas
of inquiry that have been explored so
far and again as more data is generated
the types of questions we can answer
with this data is only going to
expand so here's a few biological
applications um that I'm going to
highlight first linking regulatory
elements to their target genes and to
their Upstream transcription factors
second inferring developmental
trajectories third discovery of rare or
transient cell types or states and
fourth using one modality to predict
another so first uh linking regulatory
elements to their target genes so this
is perhaps one of the most established
uh analyses of single cell multi RNA and
attack data that's out there as you can
see there's um several methods that have
already been published that perform this
function and the basic intuition behind
this style of anal is is for a given
candidate enhancer or attack region and
candidate Target Gene perhaps a gene in
the Cy region of the enhancer that we
think might be targeted by the enhancer
we have from our single cell Mulo
readout um chromatin accessibility the
accessibility status of that enhancer
across single cells and the expression
of the candidate Target Gene across
single cells um
so at a broad level what all these
methods do is measure the correlation or
the association between the activity of
a candidate enhancer and the expression
of a candidate Target Gene across single
cells with of course some technical
specifics that we might dive into a
little bit later um but this is kind of
the the broad intuition of this type of
analysis and we can see how single cell
multi data is unique uniquely unlocking
this ability um we have high sample size
uh in the form of thousands or tens of
thousands of single cells across which
to measure correlation we can also
really um tailor the analysis
specifically to our biological context
of Interest which because we know um
regulatory biology is very context
specific a sort of a key um benefit
here um another closely related
application that has been explored is
linking regulatory elements not only to
their target genes but also to the
transcription factors um that might
interact with an enhancer to activate a
Target Gene so a few closely related
methods uh like Scenic plus and reunion
highlighted down here might do this um
and again we're getting the uh gene
expression candidate uh Target gene
expression data from the RNA seek we're
getting the enhancer data from chromatin
accessibility and we're getting the
transcription Factor activity data also
from gene expression so we can kind of
measure the relationship of each of
these things together as a
network a second broad application is
inferring developmental
trajectories um so there is this concept
in regulatory biology which many of us
might be familiar with called chromatin
potential or lineage priming which
refers to an increase in accessibility
of regulatory chromatin prior to a gene
being turned on during development so
developmental biology is kind of this
black box there's a lot of you know
transient cell States and um very
context specific biology going on that
regulates the development of certain
cell types Etc and single cell M data
can be uniquely informative for this so
I'm going to highlight an example here
um from an early mul paper um the Shar
seek technology which some of you might
know uh where on the bottom here I'm
showing that on the left side of the
figure that will ultimately appear um we
have the profile of gene expression and
enhancer accessibility during early
development of this particular example
is for the development of hair follicles
um on the right side of the figure that
ultimately appear we have late
development and um as the legend on the
top says red here indicates higher
counts so higher gene expression in in
this case um or higher chromatin
accessibility in a second but we're
looking here at the profile of the win 3
Gene which as we can see becomes active
late in the development of hair
follicles down here this bar that's
being showed is gene expression
currently I'll now add one bar on top
where actually the authors of this paper
used the prior approaches to link
regulatory elements to Target genes and
now they're going to show the activity
of those regulatory elements that were
highly correlated to this target Gene
went three um throughout development of
the hair follicle so this new bar is
showing the promotor of wi 3 which as we
can see becomes active turns red a bit
before before the gene starts being
expressed which makes sense we need the
promoter to be active in order for all
of the molecular cast of characters to
come and express a gene and
interestingly um we also see that Peaks
that are correlated to Wi 3 which can be
thought of as putative uh enhancers each
become active or accessible um at some
point in development prior to went three
being expressed so this example kind of
shows how joint measurements of
chromosone accessibility and gene
expression across single cells can
highlight this concept of chromis
potential or lineage priming in a way
that is very difficult to access using
other types of
data a third application is the
discovery of rare or transient cell
types or States um so this has been a
major area of interest in regulatory
biology as we have sort of discovered
that um regulatory relationships are
very context specific they might be
specific to cell types cell subtypes or
even specific cell States like um a cell
being activated by a certain stimulus we
have become very interested in profiling
these rare cell types um that we might
not even know exist so Dimension
reduction and clustering algorithms
which I'll elaborate a bit more on later
um are used to define cell types and
States from unimodal data very
frequently from single cell RNA seek
data and also from Attack seek data but
applying these methods to multimodal
data increases our biological resolution
and enables joint Dimension reduction so
by using more features um more kind of
unique identifiers of a particular
biological profile um we can get better
resolution on these cell types and
states and this can sort of unlock all
of the other applications to be applied
to specific um contexts of Interest
perhaps particularly relevant for
disease or
development and a Fourth Kind of
emerging um application of single cell
multi data is using one modality to
predict another
um so this example is from a paper that
came out this year uh which is cited a
lot in this presentation they they did a
lot in the paper um where one of their
sort of problem formulations was to
model gene expression as a function of
Cy chromatin accessibility and use those
models to predict gene expression from
chromatin accessibility alone this is
kind of an analytical framework that has
been tried before in the bulk space but
of course with lower resolution and
lower sample size it's challenging so
this paper really um proposed this new
area of inquiry um that is uniquely
enabled by single cell multi data and we
can see how this might actually have an
interesting effect where it can help us
unlock new insights from unimodal data
if we produce highquality multimodal
data we can train models to predict one
modality from another and then get
double the insights from a unimodal
experiment for example if we only did
single cell attack seek and inferred
gene expression um from just the Single
Cell attack seek so big cost saver um
and and biological Insight increasing
strategy okay so those are just some of
the broad types of questions that single
cell multi data has been used to address
so far um certainly there's many more on
the horizon maybe one of particular
interest to a medical and population
genetics audience is as the number of
data sets expands and even incorporates
a large number of individuals we can
Define very complex um biological
characteristics for genetic Association
studies so for example instead of
measuring the association between a
variant and the expression of Gene a
perhaps we can measure the associ
association of a variant and the
correlation between an enhancer and a
gene um is there a particular variant
that sort of unlocks a regulatory
relationship you can imagine a very
multi-layered uh profile of biological
characteristics that you could measure
through genetic Association
studies so um for the second section of
the analysis methods um I want to talk
more about some of the technical
challenges in single cell multi data
analysis so anyone kind of developing
methods in this space or even applying
methods in this space single cell data
has unlocked a lot of potential but it's
also unlocked a lot of obstacles that we
need to think through a lot of other
types of data don't really um present us
with this so the first sort of challenge
that I will profile is sparsity or noise
in single cell data so the challenge
here is that single cell data is sparse
which means there are many zeros for
example in a single cell uh cell by
feature count Matrix and also noisy just
due to the very small amount of
biological material that's being
measured and the challenge here is that
sparsity and noise is due to both true
biological variation and incomplete
sampling what is sometimes referred to
as
Dropout um where a gene may be truly
expressed for example in a Cell but just
because of their randomness of sampling
um no reads show up in the cell and it's
particularly challenging because we
cannot distinguish um the biological
absence of a feature from just the
technical absence of a feature so this
is something that's very um very present
on a lot of single cell method
development researchers
minds and the reason this is challenging
is because many traditional linear
regression based models assume normality
of the data so um this plot down here
kind of shows what the distribution of
read counts for example for expression
of some Gene might look like there might
be a big peak at zero due to Dropout and
just kind of low profiling of a gene um
and the the frequencies continue to
decrease as we move up in level of read
count so clearly this distribution does
not look normal and so a lot of
traditional analysis methods might fail
when applied to this
data so there's a few different
solutions that are being actively sort
of explored to address this challenge um
first I'll highlight some solutions that
continue to at their core use a normal
model to model single cell data but they
just make some adjustments to the data
to make the data fit the normal model
better the first is aggregating single
cells in to meta cells so single cells
provide a tiny amount of biological
material and their measurements are as a
result very noisy but um what some
people are doing now is using Dimension
reduction algorithms and clustering
defining what are called meta cells
which are sort of uh low-level
Aggregates of cells so a few cells that
are very close to each other in uh low
dimensional space and are therefore very
biologically similar
we can group them together aggregate
their information and get hopefully sort
of a denoised but still accurate profile
of the biology of those cells um so this
might look like again grouping a cluster
of cells and simply adding read counts
and we can imagine specifically with
respect to the Dropout challenge if each
cell kind of has a a random subset of
molecular features maybe genes that have
dropped out that then hopefully if we
aggregate across different cells we have
some information for all features and
we're less prone to that
Dropout so there's a few methods here um
for aggregating single cells into meta
cells another strategy that's been
explored is imputing missing Counts from
single cell data uh so for example the
magic method um used again this this
unique opportunity of having jointly
profiled modalities to predict one
modality from another and impute missing
data to sort of smooth out the the noise
and missingness in this data so very
wellestablished approach in other areas
of biology and can also be applied to
single cell data and again retains the
dimensionality of the data we're still
looking at a single cell level whereas
with meta cells we've reduced the
dimensionality we're now looking at a a
lower number of cells I have a question
about that um could you sort of talk
about you've mentioned two solutions
about when would you want to use one
versus the other what are sort of the
limitations yes so I think in terms of
the Technical Solutions to address some
of the challenges in single cell data
interestingly they have not been
rigorously benchmarked against each
other in a lot of cases um a lot of
times many people are developing methods
simultaneously and they will sort of
propose an approach and it's reasonable
it's been used before but we don't
necessarily know uh the specifics of the
approach how they compare to others so I
can't say that I myself am familiar with
sort of a rigorous um comparison of
imputing missing counts versus
aggregating single cells into meta cells
I think this could depend on your
biological question uh could just be a
matter of practicality if you have sumon
analysis procedure that's very
computationally costly and it's
beneficial to reduce the dimensions of
your data perhaps a good den noising
strategy is to aggregate single cells
into meta cells which will do both of
those things um but I think in general
both of these are kind of accepted
strategies in the field so it really
depends on your particular data set um
your particular question of Interest
another consideration might be just how
specific is the biology you're looking
for if you really don't need to look
beyond the level of a cell subtype or a
little cell Village then aggregating
single cells into meta cells might be a
great idea because you're not sort of
introducing new data however if you're
really interested in the biology of
single cells maybe you want to retain
the dimensionality and impute missing
counts instead if you don't mind having
some predicted data in there not just
raw data so those could be a few
considerations when thinking of those
two yeah
all right so yet a third approach and
perhaps the most basic maybe the first
approaches that were DED um is
normalizing or transforming um read
counts within single cells just to look
more normal and this figure might not
really uh communicate this but this is
pretty challenging given just the sheer
level of sparsity and noise in single
cell data so sometimes this is not
enough um and the first two approaches
might be better or some combination of
the
three so a second category of solutions
um is using a non-normal model and this
is certainly an area that's been
explored a lot recently um so discrete
count models like Pon models or negative
binomial models might be a more
appropriate fit for single cell data at
the Single Cell resolution um a couple
of methods are highlighted here that use
those approaches
and Beyond just the um vanilla Pon or
negative bionomial
models we can also consider zero
inflated models that explicitly account
for the fact that there's going to be a
greater than uh expected amount of zeros
this again is an area of active
development and I'm not aware of anyone
who has uh rigorously shown that one
model zero inflated or not zero inflated
is sort of better than the other it's
again the space where a lot of people
have a lot of ideas and they're all
honestly acceptable right now so it
could be a matter of what fits your data
best U and what fits your biological
question
best okay so a second sort of half
challenge half feature of the data is
High dimensionality um so as we've been
saying single cell data is highly
dimensional um there is number of
features times
number of cells number of data points um
which is vastly larger than bulk
sequencing data sets and while this is a
key feature of single cell data in the
sense that it gives us High sample size
and often very high power in a lot of
analyses it also might increase
computational complexity and hinder
interpretability in some other contexts
for example um if we really want to make
inference at the level of cell subtypes
or cell
subpopulations um having a bunch of
single cells might actually kind of
overwhelm us and not not really provide
a lot of easily interpretable
results so this is just demonstrating
how uh the dimensionality of data
increases as we move from bulk to single
cell unimodal data and then even further
as we go to single cell multimodal
data so some solutions to this um in a
setting where this is viewed as a
problem is uh reducing the number of
features via feature selection so in the
RNA space this might look like
restricting only to highly variably
expressed genes in the attack space this
might look like um calling attack Peaks
identifying regions of the genome that
are particularly highly active or
defining genomic tiles uh kind of
partitioning The genome into discrete
sections that we going to aggregate
chromatin accessibility across rather
than measuring chromatin accessibility
at the base pair
level and a second thing we can do to
reduce um the number of perhaps let just
say number of entries in the data Matrix
is dimension reduction on cells so this
is a very well-known kind of area of
inquiry using PCA or nmf perhaps
combined with some other nonlinear
Dimension reduction technique um
to uh reduce the dimensions of the
data or I suppose that also reduces the
features not that okay yes my bad that
also reduces the number of features next
there are strategies you can reduce you
can use to reduce the sample size or the
number of units of analysis um and again
I've read it here the strategy of
aggregating single cells into meta cells
um forming those sort of cell clusters
of closely related biological Neighbors
so obviously this is kind of a big
landscape of uh solutions that I've
provided to these two big uh challenges
or features of single cell data and it's
kind of as I said in response to the
question uh a unique a uniquely tailored
um solution depending on the biological
problem of Interest what uh
dimensionality of data can your analysis
uh withstand and what is going to give
you highest power and greatest
interpretability so these are just kind
of a a menu of solutions available to
people doing single cell data
analysis okay so lastly to kind of bring
together um the broad types of questions
that single cell multi data can answer
with the technical challenges um I'll
highlight a particular area of inquiry
linking enhancers to genes um to sort of
highlight the unique uh benefits of
single cell multi data so I'm sure I
don't have to convince any of you that
mapping Gene regulatory architectures is
critical to understanding disease um the
vast majority of disease Associated
variants in gwas are non-coding and
these variants often do not regulate the
nearest Gene so linking regulatory
variants to their target genes is a
critical step in interpreting gwas
discoveries and nominating potential
drug
targets and historically regulatory
activity relationships between enhancers
and genes have been interrogated using
various lines of biological evidence um
most recently or one of the the newer
developments on the scene is of course
single cell molecular profiling um
specifically single cell multimodal
profiling and compared to some of these
other methods single cell multi data is
is context specific so information we
might get from DNA sequence or
conservation um predictions really
doesn't tell us any information that's
specific to biological context and as I
said we know that regulatory biology is
very context specific so that's a point
for single cell multi data
here single cell multi data is also
closer to causality than some genomewide
biochemical assays for example
um 3D confirmation mapping and
biochemical annotations like DNA
methylation or hisone marks these
provide genomewide kind of predictions
and proxies of regulatory activity but
they don't really um hint at causal
relationships and sometimes they don't
even implicate a Target Gene for a
candidate enhancer whereas the
correlation between an enhancer in a
gene is a closer proxy for biological
causality single cell multi data is
easier to collect um so relative to
something like eqtl where we need to
collect um hundreds or thousands of bulk
sequencing samples to run a genetic
Association study and identify
relationships between regulatory regions
and for example gene expression um
single cell multi data we can often
derive a lot of biological insights from
a single sample from a single donor even
single cell multi data is also
genomewide and convenient so relative to
more targeted experimental approaches
that often um seek to address a specific
biological hypothesis about one gene or
one enhancer um single cell multi data
provides genomewide predictions um and
is not nearly as experimentally
burdensome as profiling many genes uh
through a crisper screen for example
so as I uh briefly highlighted before
single cell multi data has been used to
link regulatory elements to their target
genes by measuring the correlation
between the accessibility of a region of
Chromatin a candidate enhancer and the
expression of a candidate Target Gene
and if we repeat these pairwise tests
for all enhancer Gene pairs um we can
sort of predict or map regulatory
biology genomewide using uh a single
sample and so in this table I've
highlighted a few specific analysis
methods just to demonstrate how
different strategies are being employed
to um address the challenges that we
discussed in the previous section so for
example the scent and Scar link methods
for linking enhancers to genes um
perform analyses at the level of a
single cell but to address the
non-normality in the data they both
employ pan regression instead of
measuring linear correlation or using
linear regression a third method the syc
peak Gene linking method also uh
performs analysis at the level of single
cells and does measure linear
correlations but performs uh specific
normalization steps to make the data
look as normal as possible and make the
correlation readouts as meaningful as
possible
a fourth method the Archer method
measures simple linear correlation which
assumes normality of the data but
importantly it Aggregates single cells
into meta cells using a joint
dimensionality reduction prior to
measuring
correlation all right so this is just
again a specific example of how these
different challenges um and
opportunities from single cell um can be
combin to to uh design strategies to
learn about context specific biology so
a few
conclusions um single cell multi
Technologies jointly profile multiple
biological modalities while retaining
cellular heterogeneity this is kind of
the key benefit of single cell multi
data single cell multi analyses can
Target diverse biological questions some
of which I've highlighted here but many
of which will be unlocked in the coming
years as more data is
generated single cell multi methods use
various strategies to handle data
sparsity or noise and high
dimensionality in single cell
data and finally we took a somewhat
closer look at several computational
methods that use single cell RNA and
attack multi data to link regulatory
elements to their target gen
so one final Point um a bit of a a
forecast is that these multi
Technologies and Analysis methods are
rapidly developing um so for example uh
we highlighted kind of the dominant
technology today which is RNA plus
attack data but another technology that
jointly profiles uh RNA gene expression
and cell surface protein is also kind of
rising in popularity and we can imagine
how that would unlock
unique uh insights as well some overlap
with the applications of RNA plus attack
but some new biological questions and
there are even emerging technologies
that measure three modalities at the
same time for example gene expression
chromatin accessibility and DNA
methylation or gene expression chromatin
accessibility and intranuclear proteins
so we can imagine the number of
biological questions just multiplies as
we can combine
multiple modalities within the same
analysis unit same single cell um and
the vast array of the technologies that
are available are reviewed thoroughly in
this review that I've highlighted here
vanderen at all 2023 nature reviews
genetics all right so that is all I had
for today I'm happy to take any
questions thank you very much
thanks and if you guys have questions
just come up to the microphones and why
we wait for them I'm wondering if you
could touch on quality control is it as
simple as doing each modality separate
and are some things that you consider
jointly good question so quality control
um is because of the sparcity of noise
and single cell data a huge
consideration um there are sort of
separate quality control s of
established quality control U procedures
for RNA seek data and attack SE data at
the Single Cell level and uh multimodal
quality control is pretty much just the
intersection of those two um which is
challenging in the sense that if you
think of uh a subset of your large
single cell sample being of high quality
with respect to RNA and a subset of that
data also being high quality with
respect to attack sometimes those will
be correlated and sometimes they will
not so finding the intersection high
quality cells uh for both modalities is
often a challenge and often results in
somewhat smaller data sets uh fewer
cells than one modality alone but it's
mostly just a function of um performing
both types of
QC are there any methods that um maybe
if a cell in the RNA seek is like
borderline and then you look in the
attack seek and it looks great then you
might be like keep it or something
attacks like does that exist that's a
good question
I
so to my knowledge it's pretty much user
controlled when you perform your QC you
can sort of decide what your cut offs
are going to be for the number of reads
of attack per cell and things of that
nature so I would imagine there is a way
to sort of ad hoc um Define some quality
score per cell per modality and and cut
off at like a product of quality scores
between the two um mod alties or
something like that yeah that would
probably be a good strategy to increase
the ultimate dimensionality of the
data while the audience um is gathering
their questions um where do you if
someone is new to single cell on Multi
data where's a great place to look for
um data sets to get their hands wet
that's a great question so um 10x
genomics has several multi-owned data
sets that are publicly available that
are a good place to start um they're
often already processed already in kind
of feature matrices for you um and a lot
of papers are coming out these days
where they have generated single cell
multi data sets in specific biological
contexts of interest um or using a new
technology and they will often also
release their data so I would say 10x
genomics is a great place to look and
also just kind of um keyword searching
single cell multi data in um your
Journal of choice maybe the the nature
journals family or something like that
um and you can often find some good good
data sets that way and often sorry um
before you ask your question um I would
say another recommendation is any paper
that is proposing a single cell data
analysis method really for any uh part
of the process whether it's kind of a
data processing method or Downstream
kind of biological question you can also
look at the the data sets they have used
because often times those authors have
gone through the process of picking out
these uh data sets from corners of the
scientific world to to analyze so those
would be my three
recommendations um if you have different
modes of measurement or like different
modalities can you use the same software
to do this the analysis like as long as
you have some sort of cell by feature
Matrix can you process everything the
same way good question so it really
depends and I think the answer is
there's not currently kind of a unified
approach that everyone in the Single
Cell world is using to process their
data um because the data the technology
is just so new everyone's kind of doing
their own thing to some extent um the
key kind of consideration to keep in
mind is the difference differences
between RN SE data and a tax seat data
they are similar in the sense that
you're getting kind of read counts for
both um I would say the main difference
is a taxi data is much higher
dimensional and each molecular feature
is going to have higher variance and not
be as well profiled so with that
principle in mind there will be probably
some differences in how you process the
data um but usually the same software
can be used for both um so for example
sirat and syc are kind of major
softwares in R also Archer is a big
softare Ware more tailored to single
cell attack seek um but also developing
applications for integrating RNA seek as
well sort of in multimodal um data but
typically I think you should aim to use
the same software package um and then
integrate them using that software
package usually they have that that
functionality that's a good question
thanks so much for your talk I one of
the really subtle things you mentioned
was the opportunity to look at the
impact of Gene variance on the car
between enhancers and gene expression
can you say any more about how people do
that and the challenges of doing that
and the challenges of having enough data
to do that
yes or a description of How It's been
done that was kind of just invented in
my mind um I think for unimodal single
cell data this is obviously an area of
hugely expanding interest U measuring
the association between genetic
variation and chromatin accessibility at
a known enhancer or methylation at a
known site or something like that um so
I think as we combine biological
modalities together the space of
possible phenotypes that we can measure
genetic associations with just expands
and as you said the big challenge with
this is are we ever going to have data
sets where we have hundreds or thousands
of individuals with genetic data and
multi data because multi data at the
moment is quite costly and burdensome to
produce um so some of them are well
established lines of inquiry really only
rely on data from a single sample like
linking enhancers to genes if we got to
a place where we had some atlas of
hundreds of individuals with genetic
variation and multimodal um measurements
I think it would be incredibly powerful
to be able to perform Association
studies on very complex phenotypes like
that
um the specific example you highlighted
in my mind perhaps it could reveal some
sort of context specificity or stimulus
dependence of a regulatory relationship
for example if people with a certain
variant exhibit a strong correlation
between an enhancer and a gene and
people with the uh alternate all do
not what does that say about the
function of that variant do we know that
it is in a transcription Factor binding
or an an enhancer for another Gene
that's closely related like what what
information might that give us about the
interactions between these different
biological processes so that was just
kind of off the cuff um I wish I had had
a a specific study to site but maybe in
the future