many people believe that this captures
how you make good decisions you have
your goals your goals motivate your
decisions those decisions change the
state of the system and bring the world
closer to your goals well that's not how
it works let me give you an example I'm
a bicycle Commuter so every morning when
I'm riding down the bike path on my way
to MIT I know my goal stay on the right
hand side of the path too far the left
crash into somebody coming the other way
too far to the right hit a tree but just
knowing the goal doesn't tell me what I
really need to be able to do do I turn
the handlebars left or right right now
in order to make a good decision I also
have to know not just where I want to be
but where I am I have to have feedback
from the state of the system now we are
embedded in a far more complex set of
systems that's going to be quite
difficult to understand and to manage
for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow