so how is a quantum computer different
we can begin to answer that question by
comparing it with a classical computer
classical computers are the Computing
devices that of course we use every day
at work and at home and they process
information using transistors Each of
which can store one bit of information
we'll call this a classical bit a
classical bit is binary it can either be
in state zero or it can be in state one
we can contrast that with a quantum
computer which is built from logical
elements called cubits which is short
for Quantum bids a cubit can be set in
state zero or state one but a cubit can
also be in a Quantum superposition State
it's a single state but it carries
aspects of both state zero and state one
simultaneously as a result quantum
computers rely on encoding information
in fundamentally different ways than
classical computers for more MIT moments
from MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow