thank you very much for the kind
introduction uh it's it's an honor here
to be among uh so many distinguished
colleagues and talented students and and
to be immersed in a almost a full day of
of great discussions and now have a an
opportunity to say a few things uh to
you so this uh this is the second time
this year that I drop in at at Lids the
first time it was it was for the student
conference maybe I should see if if if I
can apply for a premier 1K uh status
with lids if if there is such a thing uh
so uh this this talk will not be
entirely different from the one uh I
gave in February uh but it will be a
sort of a prequel uh and it's a prequel
in the following
sense
uh the control system Society has the
so-called control system Society uh week
which contains the uh control history
forum and its chair by Professor Alberto
isidori who asked me to prepare a talk
on the history of PD backstepping for uh
this year's um control history Forum
which was in October I felt that that
was a topic that might be worth uh
presenting
here uh and uh since you know history
really doesn't doesn't make for
necessarily an exciting topic to make it
also future facing I'm going to
integrate cre at the end some of the
elements of what was uh partly seen in
February and what what I had prepared
for the B lecture uh a year
ago uh I have to say that U the content
of a history lecture is
necessarily specialist oriented and I've
tested this talk once at a um plary
given at the Brazilian control
conference about a month
ago and uh one piece of honest feedback
that was given to me by the
founder by the person who founded the
Brazilian Control Association 50 years
ago so this is a gentleman in his late
80s was I understood nothing but I could
tell it was captivating so my my
objectives here are modest in terms of
uh the the the complete comprehension of
what I have uh assembled but I have I've
worked very hard for it to be coherent
and and reflective of how the the ideas
actually uh developed so the the the
talk will be uh two for the price of one
feature um 34s 3/4 history one quarter
uh future facing and let me be clear
that this was originally put together to
be a history talk in other words well it
would be nice to give a tutorial or a
survey this is neither it's it's it's a
it's a an exposition of the historical
progression of uh of certain ideas it's
for the most part chronological even
though that's not necessarily
pedagogically ideal
always um it's definitely not uh
comprehensive I put the emphasis on on
on the starts of certain
subtopics um uh and since it's a
historical account the attribution is
important I was trying trying to give
specific credit where uh uh that was uh
that was relevant you will see
that uh a big part of this this uh is
concentrated in a certain team and group
uh of uh of you know mostly my
associates but it was over the last 10
years that that this started to quite
rapidly uh expand and I'm very pleased
pleased by it the Future Part will be uh
a talk on how machine learning uh has
found its role or how I have found a way
to uh prevent uh drifting into total
irrelevance in the age of machine
learning and connect this
uh Broad and rigorous Theory with uh uh
with methods of machine learning so let
me start uh start with uh one slide on
what existed in PD control before the
start of the So-Cal PD backstepping so
for for about three to four decades the
efforts in in PD control were were
focused on um uh replicating uh the the
existing methods so so
lq uh with operator rard equations
rather than Matrix rard equations pole
placement uh there were efforts in uh uh
extending H Infinity a few of of of
those uh and um just to give a few
references uh these these three of which
I I note here that uh one of them uh was
co-authored by Professor sanj M whom we
all I think deeply miss in our field uh
um but all these efforts uh were focused
on um on U extending linear methods to
the infinite Dimension it is hard to
imagine looking at at at at at this uh
literature how it would extend to
nonlinear PDS or how it would be turned
adaptive in the way uh this this was uh
done for for certain linear and
nonlinear PDS so the root of the PD back
stepping actually is in feedback
linearization in the sense that in the
Fe in feedback linearization you have a
change of variables and feedback in PD
backstepping you have the same thing so
just a reminder of of of uh of feedback
linearization there is a system up
finding control with an with an
output uh you introduce a change of
variables with these lead derivatives
and at the end you end up with a chain
of
integrators where in the last equation
you have the control appearing and with
that control you can impose if you wish
a linear Clos Loop structure and assign
the behavior any way you
like now uh the the limitations of this
approach were immediately recognized
then people asked what about uh
uncertainties what are you going to do
if you have disturbances or if you have
a parametric uncertainty that is uh
really really large that you cannot
account for it with a single controller
and this question the extension of a
conization to these un uncertain systems
uh occupied intensely about half a
decade the first half of the
1990s and resulted in uh in adaptive and
robust solutions to uh stabilization or
disturbance attenuation in nonlinear
systems
so
as one of the participants in this
development and uh when I was done with
that I was looking at what to to do next
and and interestingly there were there
were certain uh applications uh and
activities and Consulting opportunities
in the Aerospace and jet engine industry
and I
realized
how narrowly I had been working up up to
that point how broad a space of
dynamical systems is when you step uh
step away from Odis and and uh look uh
look into to
PDS so the first thought was the
following so this is a a parabolic uh
partial differential equation where the
space is X Lambda is an destabilizing
reaction term and you can uh discretize
it in space only you keep uh the
derivative in time and this spatial
discretization reveals that there is a
chain of integrators here you see UI do
equals UI + 1 and you realize oh this is
kind of like larization so what what
this calls for is the going all the way
into the brunoski form the problem is
that the transformation into the
brunovsky
form uh involves a matrix which when the
discretization spa step the spatial
discretization step is taken to zero
because you need to do that if Lambda uh
if if the instability gets larger and
larger that this Matrix grows
unbounded so this is illposed
feedback larization taken literally is
illposed for for
PDS so I realized you need to preserve
the structure there is a there is a
differential operator there this this
lashan that needs to stay you can
transform this you can eliminate uh the
reaction which destabilizes the system
but you need to keep the
diffusion so I did that uh I messed only
with a destabilizing term lamb but I
kept the diffusion I replaced the the
destabilizing reaction with the
stabilizing
one and here's what what happens
there uh you obtain a gain which depends
on the spatial coordinate X so this gain
k um um is is a function of space and as
you take H towards
zero uh You observe a Divergence this is
is not the blow up but you observe a
Divergence of uh of the gain into a two
valued map this is definitely not good
what this seems to be is uh something
that should be converging to a mean of
this uh two valued map but you don't get
it through the discretization so this is
a second me second message that doing PD
control uh where the first step is the
so-called lumping in other words the uh
model reduction into not is a dangerous
business we we did prove stability with
all of this with these discontinous
games with convergence in in the weak
sense it's a nice exercise in math but
that's not what what an engineer would
would want to see so early lumping is a
bad idea you want to design a controller
for a PD and then discretize the
controller in space rather than the the
other way around so let me um let me now
turn the attention to a slightly more
more General class of of PDs so this is
not now uh diffusion reaction advection
system with a non-local uh term and this
is inspired by Navia Stokes and and
certain other other systems in flexible
structures and uh in other uh domains so
here's how one goes about developing a
Continuum version of this uh of this
transformation one introduces a
transformation that contains an integral
in space of the state up to the current
position in Space
X if you think of this X as a Tim like V
variable you can you can regard this
almost like some kind of a generaliz
generalization of a convolution in space
rather than than in time so it's not a
totally foreign weird object if you if
you look at this discretized in space
you see that this transformation of U is
essentially the identity minus a lower
triangular Matrix an invertible matrix
by uh by definition so the
transformation of this system is into
something desirable and the simplest
desirable pedagogical choice would be
the heat equation the simplest of all
the parabolic equations which happens to
be exponentially stable so so far what I
present here is a wish list uh of how
one would want to organize a design but
is that
possible
uh what kind of a kernel
K would it take in this transformation
to obtain a transformation into the um
uh heat equation the answer to that is
that this kernel equation needs to
satisfy a certain PD in space I'm
leaving out the boundary conditions the
domain is not a rectangular domain it's
a somewhat unconventional PD which I'm
thrilled to say it's it's a special well
recognized class of PDs called the gura
form PDS and I have not seen a single
physical system for which gura developed
this P this PD more than 100 years ago
it it appears for the first time in the
cont in the context of of control
engineering so this is the equation that
the design the user needs to solve
offline before uh applying a controller
to stabilize this PD
now the first question that needs to be
answered is mathematical question is
such a PD well posed and how would you
solve it and the answer to both
questions is the following because of
the gura structure because of the
Triangular domain of this PD this PD can
be easily converted from a PD into an
integral equation doubly integral I I
point out where G and K are equivalent
there's just a just a change of the
spatial variables XY into c a i don't
need to bother you with with this this
is is beyond
Elementary so this and this is is
equivalent and this second object is an
object that can be treated with
successive approximations you you start
with a with an initial function for g
equals z then you keep substituting the
the resulting double uh Integrations and
as you keep doing these double
Integrations on on the initial uh
function which is given by the reaction
term you study the converence of of of
the resulting series you establish this
conversion and this this gives you uh
the answers to both the well posedness
and how and and one way to to compute
these uh these Solutions now what was
really thrilling was that uh for a
constant reaction term uh my student
Andre mishab was able to produce an
explicit solution to this PD which is
this this elegant but not trivial form
it it involves best functions but not of
X or Y but of the square root of the the
the difference of the squares of X and Y
something again uh ID syncratic enough
to excite you as something uh that's
never appeared in physics appearing in
in uh in in the in the domain of control
systems now the the original objective
uh for developing back backstepping was
that with uh existing methods you could
not even start dealing with nonlinear
PDS and perhaps with uh PD backstepping
you could so how do you extend these uh
Transformations uh and designs to
nonlinear PDS so I give here a nonlinear
PDS in F in which capital F could be a
function or it could be a nonlinear
operator and I postulate a
transformation which now instead of a
voltera integral s single integral has
this infinite sum of nested uh integrals
with increasing um with with products of
of you at different uh um positions uh
in space uh CJ and this is step one in
developing a very uh comprehensive
theory for um nonlinear backstepping
control of um uh of of nonlinear PDS the
target equation again there's no reason
to to take something super complicated
one can like in feedback linearization
go for a familiar desirable linear
closed loop system and and one such
system is the heat equation what does it
take to uh to produce a controller it
takes finding the solutions of uh for
these kernel functions these kernal
functions now satisfy not one but a
whole sequence an infinite sequence of
PDs on domains that that grow from one
two three up to to unlimited uh
dimension of uh of the domains and all
of this can be bounded can be summed up
can be proved convergent and can be can
be implemented so one slide on that I'm
I'm I'm not I'm I'm I'm going to um
leave it at that so what are the
possible applications I have to say that
for me the driving application that at
that earli stage of the development of
of this was was one that displays
probably a bit of vanity and that was
the Stokes is there is there a
more feared and more more more respected
PD out there than then nav sto so so I
thought okay this is this is this is the
one uh to drive the development of the
theory and to apply the theory too and
uh and we worked on that on the
conversion of this system of nonlinear
uh PDS into a set of three heat
equations with the with the convection
uh retain only uh uh eliminating the
unstable parts or specifically the
unstable wave numbers in in particular
geometry and I'll leave it at that
because Navia Stokes was just one of the
things along the along the
way um let
me no I can I can show this this slide
so this was the parabolic case and up to
that point nothing hyperbolic uh was
done and uh and turning the attention to
the h hyperbolic case you want to uh
look at hyperbolic equations that happen
to be open loop unstable if you
introduce uh this kind of a non-local
operator into this system and it's
reflective of several applications in in
various wave systems this is open loop
unstable with a backstepping
transformation of the kind that I showed
before with the first order uh with a
with a vola um um integral operator of
the second in kind one can transform
this equation into the uh transport PD
now for the electrical engineers like
myself what is this what is a transport
PD it's just a delay line that's that's
all it is a delay line in which there is
an initial condition but you're putting
nothing from from Time Zero onward so
this is this is not only an
exponentially stable system but a finite
time uh stable system that settles in uh
in one unit of of time so uh it's it's
um it's a nice uh type of stability to
uh to achieve and possible to achieve
and I'll I'll skip the details I'm
skipping the details because the the
interesting hyperbolic systems rarely
appear as one hyperbolic PD typically
they they appear as systems of coupled
hyperbolic
PDS uh I will show you some physical
examples but let me show you just just a
a a general form of two coupled counter
convecting I emphasize this uh this sign
difference in the convection term to
counter
convecting coupled hyperbolic PDS this
is like a Continuum infinitely many
feedback loops that can have a high gain
so this this can very much go unstable
and it does in in uh various application
domains so this was the first uh I would
I would say say breakthrough in which
Jean Michelle K Jo bastan and my my
student Rafael Vasquez participated and
one has to go to higher order Norms in
space not not just L2 not even H1 but
all the way to to the sub Norm Norm H2
to uh uh to achieve stabilization under
these kind of nonlinear perturbations
that are not only nonlinear but include
the perations uh involving uh the
differential
operator after you
design a controller for two coupled
systems what do you do well you ask
yourself can I do it for for more
systems that are that are coupled and
and are there applications for that so
the answer is yes we were drawn to that
we developed that with uh for for uh
coupled systems of N and M counter
correcting PDS with a key uh where I
want to emphasize that only one of the
two PD subsystems has a control input
that's the interesting part that that
you have coupled PDS of which you get to
control only one or only M directly and
you have to control the remaining n
indirectly to decouple them in in a
particular
way so um this was an effort of of uh of
several years and um ended up in in very
results uh but the maybe the more
interesting is what are the
applications well uh originally the
applications that drove couple
hyperbolic PDS came uh from various
researchers in France who were working
on the so-called senena um partial
differential equations modeling shallow
water waves such as those appearing in
water canals all over Belgium France and
so so on um
this was this was the motivating first
set of applications but then it all got
extended to oil drilling whereby o Dr
drilling I mean both the instabilities
in the structural uh oscillations of the
drill string and the instabilities in
the flow of uh the oil natural gas water
mud multiphase uh flows that tend to be
unstable uh tend to um develop into
plug- like instabilities that the damage
the equipment uh another set of um
applications is in laser Chambers where
you can can have therm acoustic
oscillations just as in combustion
Chambers I'm sorry to to forget to list
combustion here that that that's that
that's so natural in me that that's
almost uh obvious and uh and road
traffic uh um that that will say
something about uh um
a bit more
shortly uh so not listed in this this
set of applications is one application
that I would like to to Showcase because
it's simple because maybe there is an
occasional mechanical engineer in this
in this audience and this one is really
really clean and elegant this is the
so-called timoshenko beam all of the P
almost all of the PD control theory
sooner or later gets tested on the
so-called Oiler beam
but the timeno beam is the is is the
most complex of the beam of the four
beam uh models and it doesn't even look
like a like a beam it it is actually uh
a system of two coupled interconnected
in both directions wave equations and
this could could be a whole almost a
whole whole seminar I'll have to leave
it at that just saying that this is this
is uh two coupled wave equations with
different wave speeds and with a control
only at one
end
um this is done by converting each of
the two wave equations into two First
Solar hyperbolic PDS and then for those
four resulting PDS uh designing a
backstepping controller what's the
motivation for example the
um uh for example the attenuation of the
oscillations in the cver beams in the
atomic Force
roscopy all right so um after first
order
hyperbolic PDS one realizes that one has
in the process dealt with delay like
effects and one ask themselves what
about systems with delays I mean we're
we're we're Engineers we delays are the
one of the things that that uh worries
us the most and that we need to to to
compensate right around that time a
couple of friends were doing some very
interesting things with delay
compensation Anu here at MIT with a
So-Cal posicast adaptive control merg
Yankovich at at at Ford for for reasons
that that have to do with with the uh
Automotive uh Dynamics and the and the
effect of humans in in the loop and I
said wait a second you know I this
special case might be more exciting than
all of the general PD stuff that I'm
that I'm doing so I turn my ATT
attention to that and put a lot of
effort into this this this was single
authored work progressing from uh linear
uh ODS with an arbitrarily large delay D
that needs to be compensated to
nonlinear ODS with with a arbitrarily
large uh delay I I can't say
uh I have to limit what what I want to
say this is an exciting topic in which
the so-called predictor operator needs
to be uh developed but let me leave that
out
after uh after that
effort I came across several
applications uh some in
uh in a congested traffic in
communication networks some in uh screw
extruders
for uh add manufacturing or um
um uh 3D printing in which the delay is
present and it's large but it's not
constant uh it depends on the state and
you don't know up front what the state
is so we focused on uh system on
compensating non- constant delays in uh
nonlinear systems as as given here this
was the dissertation effort of my
student nichas bearus
liberus uh
so having uh observed that delays of
arbitrary length at the input or the
output of an a could be compensated the
natural next question is in in research
is I mean if you can compensate that
delay which is the simplest of PDs can
you
compensate less simple among the the the
PDS at at the input uh of an OD system
so I put an effort into
compensating par bolic PD equations at
the inputs of odies or higher order
hyperbolic uh PDS at the inputs of auds
or Cascades of hyperbolic and parabolic
PDS so this was an interesting body of
literature that that uh developed before
I even knew applications for it and
applic applications turned up within a
few years for each and every one of
these these things it's almost rule that
if if the theory is interesting an
application is just a matter of of of of
a conversation with somebody who's
worked on it before and and knows the
model all right so I'm now progressing
towards adaptive control um and um I
want to say that the Adaptive control
was the motivation of De for developing
uh PD backstepping and was uh finally
realized for all classes of of PDs for
parabolic in which the reaction
coefficient and this uh um kernel f are
completely unknown functions of
space for hyperbolic which where the
coupling between the unstable um first
order hyperbolic PDS are function
unknown functions of
space and for systems with delays where
the delay to be compensated is not just
long but it's unknown
and it can be both underestimated or or
overestimated so this was a lot of Works
years years of work which I just show
with a few slides so it's it's clear how
the this this history uh has
marched uh let me
now uh show two slides on applications
that have
taken uh more effort and consume more
more time the first of them is parabolic
it's um in additive
manufacturing so
the uh change uh the phase change in
materials between liquid and solid was
modeled for the first time in the late
1800s by uh by a physicist y Stefan or
Joseph Stefan as as he's also known uh
and uh this model is a very interesting
model where the Dynamics in one fa in
each of the phases liquid or solid is
are are governed simply by the the heat
equation with a boundary uh temperature
set to the melting temperature between
liquid and solid but the interface is
governed by an interesting OD the
interface is a scalar spatial position
quantity and is governed by a nonlinear
OD and what's interesting is that this
nonlinearity is not given up up front
it's it's the heat flux which comes as a
solution of the heat equation with this
boundary condition but it it is a
nonlinearity so this was this was a uh
this was an effort that that uh was
driven by a Manufacturing in the end it
was applicable to uh lithium ion
batteries it was applicable to
estimating the uh uh the temperature
distribution in CIS in in large blocks
uh of of CIS where you cannot access uh
the internal temperature and you want to
predict actually the the the melting
rates and how the things uh are are
doing but I want to point out in Lids
that this model of phase change is also
model of certain social uh social
dynamics think of the phase change the
the phase is an opinion on something and
one group of people holding a very
different opinion from another uh group
of people
and uh and this phase change occurring
somewhere somewhere in the space in the
age space in the income in the education
level space and this needing to be
either estimated though not measured in
internally or controlled and regulated
to a desired uh set
point the other uh application uh that
consumed considerable effort uh and and
gave good results uh was stabilized ing
stop and go instabilities in traffic
flows we don't need much uh introduction
to that subject I'm I'm pretty sure that
Boston is is is no better than San Diego
or LA in that regard uh and that that
subject that phenomenon is modeled by
two PDS uh one for the density the other
one for the velocity and where are we we
are in here our Behavior our driving
Style is captured in this term which
which involves the set point that we
kind of our our comfort level uh with
regards to the distance to the driver in
front of us and this pressure term which
takes a bit more to uh to
explain so this this problem was solved
and only solvable with with the with
with boundary control using using
backstepping a number of other
applications came up along the way so I
mentioned already water canals oil
drilling and lithium ion oil drilling is
relevant because back stepping was used
actually uh in experiments uh by the
Norwegian company stat oil in in several
kilometer long um
pipelines um to to to estimate uh the um
the downhall pressure uh it was also
used in in a project with RPA on
lithiumion batteries maybe 10 years ago
uh in partnership with with a with the
Robert Bosch
um um Outpost the the the the the US uh
um uh Institute um of the Robert Bosch
uh company so uh there have been some
applications of PD back stepping that
may may be quite nonobvious in vehicle
swarming uh the limit of having many
vehicles is a
PD uh and uh once one goes to that limit
things get easier they become more more
elegant the Clutter of a complicated
graph cleans up uh and and and you get a
PD and uh if you have a leader that's
your boundary input and that that leader
can can uh perform stabilization and can
p can perform also
deployment the instability of the Swarm
is something
typical of this effort typically you
will see swarms that are stable if left
alone they will be uh they will be
stable but you don't get interesting and
complex deployment shapes with stable
agents you get interesting shapes when
you have agents that don't want to be
near neighbors they want to run away
from everybody and you sort of reain
them in with boundary control and and
these these figures speak for for
themselves uh as as deployment figures
in
3D uh extremum seeking is a topic I
could have chosen because it's so
interesting you know so so so so
worthwhile to talk about something that
that's that's gone on to to to uh result
in you know thousands of patents and
Industrial applications but I just want
to say that uh PD backstepping has had a
role uh in extending extremum seeking to
systems that have not AI
but have PDS that need to be
compensated uh and that's the work uh
with Thiago Ru Oliva let me now get to
to to the uh merger of PD backstepping
with machine
learning
so uh today I don't think that a meeting
that I had uh had a conversation that
did not involve machine
learning and everybody has a different
role everybody's learning a different
thing uh so I have to tell you what is
my thing what am I learning learning
here so
uh one one thing that after you spend
decades in a field as a as a theorist
one thing thing you don't want to do
when machine learning comes along as a
disrupt disruptor of of your area one
thing I don't want to do is walk away
from everything is just start from
scratching just forget about the the the
the this complicated stuff that that
relatively few people can understand and
and and re redo it uh so that everybody
can so I found a role for machine
learning in supporting the modelbased
designs in other words there are a whole
bunch of modelbased designs that I sh
that I've shown you and they are
essentially Transformations they're
mappings from Models into feedback laws
so that mapping is something I want to
learn and automate before starting to
work on this I did not even fully
comprehend the complexity of these
mappings I've just been producing them
producing and producing them and and it
was only when I started thinking about
machine learning that I that I uh
started thinking about about uh their
internal structure and complexity so for
instance you've I I started with a
reaction diffusion equation where the
reaction coefficient is a function of
space Lambda of X my control design is a
mapping from the reaction coefficient
into the gain function gain kernel k a
lowercase k and I denote this mapping
with the calligraphy K this is a
nonlinear operator from an uh
onedimensional domain an interval from 0
to one to a triangular domain for the uh
for the gain
Cur well that is what I want to
um learn and approximate and you will
see
why uh I've been Computing these
gains lowercase k for a given Lambda for
two decades but then I asked myself what
is the mapping so that I don't have to
to compute it next time but I just plug
in into a into a formula uh which is is
a neural network approximation of of
that mapping in other words find the
mapping once and for all and you you
will see why once and for all matters so
before I I show show those details let
me uh make sure I don't run out of time
to to acknowledge the the the
collaborators so the moment an
interesting new idea comes up uh for a
topic that has a 20 plus year history
the possibilities are enormous and there
is so much to do for so many people
people so instantly within within within
6 Months 8 months uh these and now other
people have uh joined in uh in in these
these efforts uh some really incredible
Talent uh among them I I will not sing
out anybody
individually uh so let me now now move
on to illustrate what I'm talking
about so these La last 10 or so minutes
these last 10 minutes give enough time
to show one
example so I will not be going to the
most general of those those designs that
that I've shown you to to to to show you
how how we do that I'll go to the
simplest one among them there isn't a
simpler example imaginable
worth presenting pedagogically to
introduce this this notion
the the more complex things have already
been you know there is there is
considerable development on on more
complex
systems but this is The Benchmark uh A
system that is notationally simple but
conceptually definitely not trivial so
this is a transport PD with a
recirculation any chemical engineer in
in the room will not need much much
elaboration on
this uh but recirculation can can can
occur in in in more than just chemical
reactors that they can there can be
feedback uh being applied even from
routing apps to the drivers and
influencing the behavior of drivers
along the entire um freeway so you see
how the outlet of this PD is being fed
back everywhere within the domain with
this gain daa of X which I highlight in
red because it represents danger this is
the destabilizing feedback from the
recirculation and if the words do not
suffice I I show you here what what I
mean by destabilizing there are these
oscillations who which which grow as
time progresses if you apply if you
don't apply any control at the boundary
that can be actuated and the boundary to
be actuated is xal
1 okay okay
so let me
now step from the motivation to the
methodology I'm going to step step back
to something incredibly
familiar and
arising in a surprising manner in this
domain and this is the sensitivity and
the complimentary sensitivity functions
from our basic undergraduate or graduate
level robust control
courses when I mean when I say
sensitivity and complimentary
Sensitivity I mean exactly those that
that you know under those names and you
know that their their sum is the
identity operator it it won't be long
until until we hit the you know
Centennial of bodies work on on on these
uh these functions and the uh uh
performance limitations but I want to
talk about not the sensitivity functions
but the sensitivity operators not the uh
not the laplus transform of the impulse
response but the
operator from the impulse response of
the open loop system into the impulse
response of the closed loop system so
the sensitivity operator is this mapping
from the function beta into what you see
as the inverse laas transform of one
over minus uh the lapas transform beta I
use the positive feedback convention for
for reasons that that offer some
convenience in in notation and likewise
the complimentary sensitivity operator
is the identity minus the sensitivity
operator and it's given by uh by this
you know most famous of our formulas
formulas uh the laas transform divided
by laas transform plus plus uh by one
plus the laas transform um
so uh I don't think this question has
ever been asked because it wasn't
necessary to ask it uh in the context of
uh linear control to my knowledge but in
the context of what I use it for it
needs to be answered and that question
is are these continuous
operators and I answer with this this is
a theorem something that needs to be
proven I I I don't put any label on it I
establish that these are not just
continuous operators but they are
lipshits uh operators it's good to
actually have a uniform lipshits uh uh
uh
constant these lipshits uh constants are
valid for all input functions that are L
Infinity bounded uh by the constant C uh
capital B and which are themselves lip
sheets functions of their argument and
their argument is X so it's potentially
confusing I'm talking about the liip of
an operator and imposing a condition of
ousness of the input to the operator to
totally different
uh lip shitness con uh Concepts so these
are the lipit uh constants uh um for for
the sensitivity and the complimentary
sensitivity operator one more thing I
want to show
you uh follows from the recent work in
neural
operators uh an area in which there are
many authors but I'm
employing a theorem of one particular
group of authors car dakis at uh Brown
University and his authors for the
so-called Depot net uh form of a neural
network which says the
following so there's a theoretical
result it takes tens page tens of pages
to to prove unfortunately and it's an
existence results it says
that the actual operator capital K can
be approximated arbitrarily closely with
a neural network to an arbitrarily small
error uh
Epsilon and that's it this this is the
result uh provided provided that the the
input space is uh Compact and the
compactness is is ensured by assuming
that the inputs are uh lipes themselves
and bounded uh by
B uh I know that somebody will ask me
sooner or or later you know that's an
existence result but how big is the
neural network what kind of neural
network and so on this is not my area of
of specialty and this topic is
progressing rapidly whatever I say say
now might be an obsolete answer in in a
in a few months what I can tell you
though is that these being existing
results they are
conservative for example for uh I I know
that a sufficient condition for the
number of nodes in a neural network for
a PD whose um um recirculation
coefficient is bounded by capital B is
on the order of B to the power B now if
that b is 20 that's an enormous number
it's a sufficient condition but there is
now also a necessary condition the
necessary condition is roughly that you
need at least e to the power B nodes
so this is the truth about approximation
Theory it has nothing to do nothing to
do uh with with control or stabilization
there is a price to pay for
approximating
functions that can Peak very high that's
essentially uh this so let me now now
come back to to this
PD so that is the
PD and the control of that PD progresses
using uh PD backstepping I've shown you
the PD backstepping uh transformation as
the uh difference between the identity
operator and a certain uh voltera
operator of the second kind but I'm I'm
now showing you that for this particular
example this backstepping transformation
is actually the
convolution of the sensitivity operat
acting on beta with a state very
interesting
and the control law is the convolution
of the complementary sensitivity
operator acting on the recirculation
function uh with the uh with a measured
state in the Target system the
recirculation is wiped out by these two
ingredients namely the backstepping
transformation and the feedback law so
now I want to get to to the key part uh
of of this which I probably
did not emphasize very much uh back in
February and that is the simultaneous
offline and online learning taking the
form of adaptive control for for PDS
with unknown functional
coefficients uh if you you may recall
that I was showing you a certain PD of a
second order uh for uh the gain kernel
labeled by lowercase k and that that PD
can be uh converted into an integral
equation uh whose state is capital G and
so on so there are some some complicated
PDS to solve which you cannot solve at
every time instant as you estimate the
parameter in real time so this is where
the machine learning will be crucial in
enabling adaptive control so let's
suppose that this
beta uh for which if known I could
always design a controller is an
actually an unknown function and let me
denote the estimate of that unknown
function of X as beta hat this now
becomes also a function of time because
it's estimated adaptively in real
time how would you estimate it let me
first get this out of the way how do you
estimate uh this unknown function of
space uh there are several approaches
and Anu knows this there's a there's a
whole Forest of of of uh system
identification
methods even in continuous time or I
would say especially in continuous time
it's it's nice and elegant and and and
pretty and one of them takes this form
it's a it's a leono based gradient like
update law in which Anu for sure and
hopefully others recognize the The
Familiar ingredients something that's
called a regressor something that's
called regulation error and something
that's called the normalization exactly
the details don't matter I need I need
you know 10 to 15 minutes to get into
those details but the structure is
familiar this object what is it it's not
a PD because there are no partial
derivatives of beta hat there's only a
Time derivative there are no spatial
derivatives but there are integrals in
in space so it's a nonlinear infinite
dimensional orderin AR differential
equation all
right I will show you how this works
let's get the theorem out of the way the
one theorem I want to show you is this
one because it it it's it it's it's such
an effort to prove
it um so the theorem in the most
stripped down form there there are some
assumptions certain things need to be
small enough in the in the design the
gain cannot be too high blah blah blah
uh I I I I want the the key thing to be
clear the main result is that this
system is leonov stable in the sense of
there existing a class K uh infinity
bound on the norm of the entire plant
State and the parameter estimation State
expressed in in terms of a bound uh that
contain the initial value of that Norm
so this is how you want to claim
stability and adaptive control every
time and in particular when you're
you're dealing with with a with a PD and
in
addition what you really want as an
engineer is not just just stability you
don't want just a bound you want to
regulate something to a set point in
addition set point regul regulation in L
Infinity Norm namely pointwise in space
is is
achieved let me show you some
simulations and then then I'll tell you
come back to to to to close with with a
few remarks on on the proof of this the
so here's how how this works in open
loop the system is unstable and you've
seen already one version of this
oscillating uh growth of the system
State when an Adaptive control uh is
applied you see this transient in which
what's bad in open loop begins to
emerge and is then suppressed an is
smiling because I think I hope she
credits me for being honest showing you
the the ugly truth that you cannot learn
things without getting in trouble first
so I let the system get in trouble a
little
bit uh and
um so here's what happens at the same
time with the parameter estimate the
parameter esate is
learning and once it has learned a good
enough parameter uh functional uh
estimate the controller immediately says
okay things are things are now now
working and suppresses the instability
and the moment the instability is
suppressed the information the trouble
is gone the learning is over and the
parameter estimate is never learned
perfectly and that's fine so
no assumptions of persistency of
excitation but uh regulation to uh to
zero through a through a several step
process of of uh of sort of uh incipient
instability learning then stabilization
and then then complacency of the update
law because has no reason to learn
anymore the proof this is what I'm proud
of no I mean simulations are are great
but the they they they they take
100th of of what the proof takes in
terms of in terms of time so uh the
proof is complicated because there are
three types of perturbations in in in
adaptive control of this kind one comes
from the fact that the the the PD for
the for the kernel is not being solved
online exactly but it is approximated
with a with this machine learning object
with the neural operator so there's that
approximation error there's also the
parameter estimation error which is
killed by the update law and finally
there's uh there's an error coming from
the time derivative of the output of the
neural operator uh which is being fed by
the parameter estimate uh estimate uh
beta
hat so let me
summarize the ability to replace solving
the PD at each time step for each new
estimate by a neural operator which is
trained offline
in a matter
of minutes I mean this minutes are a
long time with today's tech technology
on GP on on on laptops with gpus this
this this offline training takes minutes
on on lap on older laptops it takes
hours
okay uh so this speed
up uh this elimination of the numerical
solution at each time step speeds up the
implementation uh about three orders of
of magnitude and that is what makes the
difference between adaptive control for
PDS being just an ocean which it was
until a couple years ago and being
implementable with that I I thank you
for your attention and
perhaps we can we can take a question
[Applause]