[Music]
the fourth session is to talk about you
in a facilitative leader role do you
imagine yourself stepping into a leader
role in a public sector do you think you
need to develop additional skills or
capabilities before you would do that
that do you know for sure you will never
do that I want the discussion to be
about each person imagining themselves
yes or no maybe but only if in a
leadership role in the public Arena
in the negotiation field we often teach
about the need to be able to
self-regulate between empathy and
assertiveness we make that distinction
and we make that
connection because in most negotiations
we think it's important to hear what the
other side's concerns and interests are
so that you can find a way of responding
to them in exchange for reciprocity but
if you can't listened can't hear can't
empathize with their con concerns it's
unlikely you'll suggest something that
meets their interests meets their needs
and yours we tend to think of empathy as
something we pour out with people we
care about but in this leadership SL
Neti SL consensus building
context we argue that you need to be
able to up the empathy quotient
in order to be able to create enough of
a relationship with the others to hear
their
concerns so that you can construct some
proposal that's good for them and great
for you and if you can't listen and
present yourself in an empathetic way
you're not likely to find out from them
what's really on their mind and what
their most important concerns are so
there's a constant need to adjust in the
context of the kinds of hypotheticals
we've been talking
about how much empathy you're exhibiting
how much empathy you're trying to Jin up
I'm not talking about play acting I'm
talking about serious effort to
empathize with the concerns of the other
they'll know if it's not serious and if
it's not serious it won't have the
effect you need it to have so how can
you you gin up a empathy for someone you
disagree with you don't like who you
think is evil who stands for bad things
but I'm saying you have got to find out
what's important to them and you've got
to get them to trust you enough to tell
you what's important to them so that you
can
construct
proposals for the other which could be a
group and not just a person and be
assertive about that at the same time in
the same setting in the same
interactions in which you have also been
empathetic there's a tension between
them but both need to be present there's
a really important distinction between
facilitation and mediation I did not
call this mediating leadership I call
this facilitating leadership that's
because facilitate ation means something
different from mediation you can't
mediate unless you can claim and perform
in a neutral way the definition of
mediation is neutral nonpartisan now no
human really is neutral ever but in this
professional role of
mediation you have to be accepted as
nonpartisan by the parties so the
measure of your neutrality is their
perception of you and their willingness
to accept the fact you are not there to
advance one side or the other side or
your own interests because if someone
thinks I've done something that's
partisan they will tell me to leave so
neutrality goes with mediation
facilitation is a skill more than it is
a role you have your own interests you
haven't promised neutrality
to the group but you've promised or
you're offering to
facilitate a collective effort to deal
with whatever the conflict or the
problem
is sometimes a spoiler will show
themselves and they'll say I don't care
what this process is going to do I can't
accept anything less than x and you're
trying to have the parties be be
creative and generate new options that
will meet everybody's interests and this
person's proposal clearly will make it
impossible if they won't move off that
position we're not going to be part of
any agreement and there's nothing you
can say there's no song you can sing
that's going to get me to agree to
something where we don't get this or at
least this and there's a really very
specific
maneuver at that moment
that facilitators and mediators use and
I can only tell you from my own
experience it stops the flow of the
spoilers bad vibrations so when someone
says if I don't get at least this we're
out and the facilitator says well before
anybody responds you wouldn't want any
more than that if I can get the rest of
this group to do better than that for
you you you wouldn't want to be part of
that conversation you would be amazed at
the way the facial expressions of people
who've built up for a week they're
coming to this meeting and they're going
to unload and they know everybody's
going to be angry at them or hate them
but they've worked themselves up and we
have to have this cuz the moment they
say well no I wouldn't be averse to more
you say okay good so you need to join
the conversation you need to listen to
other people's interests we need to see
how much more value we can create and
then you can make a case for what you
need and let's see if we can't reframe
all of it is around moving them off that
position and I'm not suggesting
compromise so they got to take a minute
to process it and then they'll say
something like usually can you guarantee
that they'll get me something better
than that I said we can try I can't
guarantee anybody will get anything
right now but there's a really good
chance if everybody is
negotiating to try to meet their own
interests and others that we can do that
and they get up and leave because they
don't know what else to do they can't
admit that there might be in their
interest to stay because they've told
their people they were going to come
tonight and blast this thing and make
their position clear and too bad for
everybody else and
I don't know what they're going to say
to their people when they go back
they'll have some rationalization but
they were so put off by the facilitation
response that they um they just walked
away it's not clear they would never
come
back if this process is going to go on a
while as a facilitator I would certainly
call them after the meeting and say
anything that you can say about whether
you might might rejoin the group you're
cordially invited to come back to the
next meeting no discussion of what
happened necessary they sometimes will
leave and in some instance it's possible
to bring them back if you can make it
not a embarrassing or humiliating
process that's the facilitator's job
you're right to be concerned that there
might be spoilers your right to be
concerned that you're not interested in
helping to find some lowest common
denominator compromise that starts with
the spoiler dictating the outer limits
of what can be produced you don't want
to be part of that and I wouldn't either
I don't blame
[Music]
you a number of people said maybe
someday I might want to be a in a
facility of leadership position but um I
don't feel like I have the level of
self-control or or self-confidence uh to
take that role right now maybe there's
more things I can learn maybe there's
more things I can observe but I I don't
see myself now being able to do that my
response is well that's great that you
have that perspective on yourself
doesn't mean you can and add what skills
and competences need to be added doesn't
mean you have to sign off Forever on the
prospect of being in a facilitative
leadership role there are times in
people's work life where they're tapped
to play a leadership role and they may
not think they're ready and they say no
I don't see myself doing that that's
fine if that's not you then that's not
you I don't I don't see that as a ter
able
[Music]
problem one person described all of the
micro skills that I listed for you last
time as
values rather than skills as if somehow
they're about what you believe as
opposed to what you can do and um these
are skills
they're
learned uh you're not necessarily born
with them and they don't come just
because you've decided you want them uh
you have to work to build these micro
skills and the micro skills are give you
a repertoire I think it's a mistake to
think of them in the category of values
if you want to use facilitation in
consensus
building that's the set of
skills and you can't just wish it
you have to learn it or you have to work
with someone for a while who is already
more accomplished at it and a sort of
indirectly Apprentice so that you can
try it out and then begin to build your
self-confidence about being able to do
this several people
said while they could see themselves
becoming facilitative leaders they had
no clear idea right now of how you turn
a confrontation into a collaborative
problem solving circumstance they don't
see how you could make it happen and so
they're happy to be to see themselves as
facilitative Leaders but if that
includes transforming a conflict
into a collaborative problem
solving situation they just didn't think
that was possible what I'm going to say
is true regardless of whether we're in a
leadership context or not I want to take
you to the kind of moment that happens
when everybody shows up with their own
ideas about what the right design to
solve a problem would be and you decide
well let's use the next half hour to
brainstorm everybody still came with
their own idea somebody says let's just
take the next half hour and engage in
brainstorming now anybody who's done
that knows it just a couple of
preconditions for Effective
brainstorming everybody has to agree
that everything that's said is an idea
is a suggestion for this half hour we're
going to brainstorm in my practice is a
mediator my way of embodying the need to
move that confrontation into problem
solving is often if I'm sitting across
from someone I stand up and I take my
chair and I put it next to them say
let's see how many things we can think
of that we agree on that would be a good
idea in handling this I'm on your side
is what I'm going and saying I'm trying
to convert the confrontation into a
collaborative moment the idea of talking
about how you're going to talk is
crucial to transforming a conflict into
a collaborative moment I have to build a
different context right in front of us
while we're sitting there how can we
work together I know everybody's got
their own ideas here and we'll hear
about those but before we do that let's
let's just see what we agree on are good
ideas relative to solving this problem
let's brainstorm to brainstorm
effectively we need to hold off on
negative or evaluative comments we need
to just put as many thing up there as we
can there's a time limit for how long
we're going to do it nobody's committed
to anything just because they
contributed an idea so don't worry that
you're somehow implicitly committing to
something that you want want to move
away from that's about transforming a
built-in conflict to a collaborative
problem solving circumstance doesn't
guarantee agreement but the comments I
was seeing from people is I I just don't
see how I can be in the middle of a
conflict and be a useful facilitator
you've got to discuss the desire to do
that you've got to set some ground rules
some people may stay quiet the whole
brainstorming session CU they can't
adjust to that they're not flexible
enough you can facilitate the
transformation of a conflict situation
to a joint problem solving situation by
naming it as the thing you think the
group should try for a short time that's
one way of thinking about the
transformation from a conflict
situation another is to break up a
fairly large group into smaller groups
we work in four groups of three and come
up with the criteria for choosing a good
design to solve this problem 10 minutes
time's up what did you guys what did you
what did you what did you it's easier to
just have to work with three people than
11 others so we use that as a way of
buffering the pressures of the conflict
to try to move to transformation you're
thinking of a move and are doing it and
you're not worrying about whether people
are going to disagree with what you're
proposing and you're not worrying about
whether they're not going to like you
you're just ready to
try some things that will transform the
context if you don't know how you could
write now be a facilitative leader
because you don't know that you could be
comfortable enough in a conflict to help
the group transform it um you can learn
how to do that but you need some ideas
to begin to work with last point that
came from two people separately I think
this whole facilitation thing makes me
look soft I see myself as a principled
person who doesn't get pushed around
relative to what I believe is right I
believe what I believe I represent the
people I work with all I can suggest to
you is there are other ways of
accomplishing the goal of getting people
to support what you believe but at their
own
volition not because you tell them they
have
to and I would argue effective is in the
middle between soft and hard effective
is none of that matters I only care if
you perceive me effective in my role as
helping to get a good outcome for the
group in which everyone's interests are
met when someone says I I don't see
being in this kind of leadership role I
guess they see themselves more as some
of our new national
leaders where they assume that will tell
everybody what to do and everyone should
listen because they are the leader um
that's not the model I'm talking about
um I don't think the people in that role
are going to get very far but we'll see
in the United States over the next
couple of years whether that approach
gets anyone where they want to go
someone said it seems like there's lots
of pre-work needed to be a facilitative
leader before the Gathering of all the
parties and the answer to that is
absolutely yes and that's why you work
as a team and that's why you have other
people it's not just what you do at the
table it's what you do to create the
table I think one of the
challenges that I can see myself facing
as a facilitative leader is um ensuring
that all voices in the room are heard
equally while not kind of making it a
contrived process like I still want to
like maintain this like Spirit of
collaboration and people just like
openly exchanging ideas so do you have
some preliminary ideas of how to try
that that's not the
clunky way proposing different questions
maybe other questions that might involve
folks who haven't been speaking as much
but yeah I don't know open to any other
ideas too so we're in this context and
there's several people speaking a lot
and there's several people hardly
speaking and I feel it's my job for
everyone to be heard I'm just repeating
your premise and I say wait a minute
wait a minute we've only heard from a
few people
I really let let's let people who
haven't spoken yet have the floor so I
have now empowered those folks and I
going to stop anyone who's spoken before
from Talking literally that's what my
facilitative job is and sometimes that
will make it more
comfortable for someone who's been quiet
because they don't feel comfortable
jumping in when they want to that's one
idea another idea is to say everyone be
quiet for a few minutes everybody write
down two three answers to the question
that we've been talking about short just
short things I put a lot of people in
that situation I haven't singled one
person out if I'm not singling someone
out who's been quiet there's a better
chance of engaging them a third thing is
to say we've been talking about this for
45 minutes um I want to get a sense of
where the group stands let's just go
around everybody just 30 seconds where
do you stand on this so I am doing
things to encourage the ones who haven't
spoken I can't make them speak and I do
not want to call them and say you
haven't said anything yet Say Something
There are a whole series of ways you can
try to do that that I think are better
than either saying well they didn't want
to speak they didn't have to speak I
would say that for me the biggest
challenge would be patience and the
management of time I think that
sometimes this kind of discussions when
they don't have like an end time it's
really difficult to get people to agree
because the discussion can keep going
that's something that I would like
struggle with how to manage I think um
you're right to worry about it I think
every facilitator has to worry about
managing time their time and the group's
time if I'm entering into that kind of
situation I need another person in the
group to be timekeeper we could also
have a ground rule we could say look we
give everybody 3 minutes for a first
statement on anything where you're
recognized from the queue to speak next
I can use that as a device for dealing
with one time problem which is people
who talk too long I would not start a
meeting without an agenda which I sent
out ahead if you have an agenda for any
kind of a group you should have time
next to each item including what is the
ending time but this is about using
agendas and that's the leaders
responsibility tools for time management
for the group not just for for yourself
you're not making evaluations about what
were the good suggestions and the bad
suggestions and you're not
editorializing and leaving something out
because you don't agree with it those
are some simple often used tools by
facilitators to deal with the time
management problem
main challenge for me personally is how
to to deal with people that wants to
spoil the process it takes sometimes a
lot of
emotional resilience to keep myself in a
set of mind that could facilitate the
processes I think it's a challenge for
anyone when we are in a process that
goes on for a long time which is why um
most professional facilitators work in
pairs has to be someone that you trust
to be your Alter Ego I'm talking about
someone who can do everything you can do
as well as you can do it but you're
switching roles in order to let one
person rest and recharge and if people
are going to be spoilers and they're
very good at it I don't have a a a magic
solution if I put people on the record
of having to give the reasons for why
they're doing something they have to E
either lie but many people won't take
their spoilers role to the point of
lying because they know it will ruin
their reputation in that context for the
future nobody forgets that that person
lied and suddenly the spoiler strategy
Falls away and they become part of the
negotiation group a question that I have
is like not in the moment of being a
facilitator but like communicating that
out once the decision has been reached
maintaining like the Vigor of that
decision and seeing it through like how
do you kind of like maintain trust in
the process knowing that ultimately like
you don't have the final say you want to
be in charge of a written summary of
whatever the key outcome findings
agreement is and you want to draft it
and you want everybody in the group to
have a chance to comment on it and if
there are disagreements you may need to
reconvene the parties you can put your
name as the point of contact not the
author that's the point of contact at
the bottom and you want to give that to
the mayor and you want to
say anything not clear in this written
statement this is the group's statement
and then the mayor is going to go say
whatever the mayor wants but the
existence of a statement that the whole
group had a hand in saying okay to is
the best way of ensuring that what came
out of the group doesn't go through the
political meat grinder and come out in
unrelated ways the problem is that when
some of the parties become very rigid
and uh will not move from their stance
what can I do as a facilitative uh
leader my experiences are all based on
my government position if I am a
facilitative leader with without that
Authority what will be my role some
people in some
countries would not be able to accept
this informal leadership role while they
still held their government appointment
not true in the United States not true
in some countries but is true in some
countries but if that's not the problem
if you can do both you have to be really
clear with the participants I have this
responsibility and this obligation in
the world if there's a point of conflict
I would have to opt out and you have to
tell that in one way to the agency you
work for and you have to say to the
people who still want you to be in this
facilitative leadership role if there
comes a conflict I will tell all of you
that and I will bow out thank you for
participating in the four dinner
discussions we will make this available
uh hopefully it will be sitting on the
department's website and I also hope
that it does lead to the creation of
additional courses dealing with
leadership within the public sector that
DSP takes responsibility for maybe you
can become a
constituency to ask for something more
on that score and um I'm obviously
always available to talk with anybody
who wants to pick up on these issues
oneon-one
thanks good night
[Music]