all right uh okay let's get started um
so um today we're going to continue our
discussion of factor markets but really
we're going to focus on today is
essentially taking the insights for
Capital markets and thinking about how
in individuals and firms make decisions
over time last time we talked about the
interest rate and its role in
equilibrating capital markets we talked
about the demand for Capital being
driven by the margin Revenue product of
capital but then the more interesting
side was the supply of capital being
driven by individual decisions on how
much to save that savings went into
either the bank or to corporate bonds or
stocks and that's the money that firms
borrow to make
investments I wanted this lecture is
basically going to dive into that and
think about in the real world how do we
think about these savings and investment
decisions decisions that will be so
important to you as individuals and
maybe someday to you as business owners
or Executives I want to start by
discussing the key concept of present
value one of the most important Concepts
in both economics and finance is the
concept of present
value the basic idea of present value is
quite simple which is that a dollar in
the future is worth less than a dollar
now and the reason dollars in the future
is worth less than a dollar now is
because you had that dollar now you
could save it and make
interest so delaying getting money till
the future as an opportunity cost you've
missed the opportunity to earn interest
on that money
today so essentially the idea is you
can't just add up money that comes in
different periods you can't say if I
have a dollar to day and a dollar and
five years in 10 years that's $3 you
can't make that statement those are not
the same thing that' be like saying I
have a pound of gold and a pound of
apples and a pound of butter so I have
three pounds you wouldn't say that you'd
say well those are worth very different
things I can't just add them up and put
them in one unit which is
pounds likewise you can't just add up
dollars today and dollars in the future
and put them one group and just say
their dollars you need to actually think
about how to put these into common
values so with apples and gold and
butter we might use
dollars okay with money in different
periods we're going to use the the
concept of present value essentially
what we're going to do is we're going to
take take all future dollar flows and
translate them into today's terms the
present value of a dollar at any point
in time is what it's worth in the
present what it's worth
today okay so suppose for example that
the interest rate is
10% okay and you start and that you want
to have $100 next year you would like to
have $100 next year well so in other
words you know that if you put some
amount Y into the
bank at the end of the year what we have
you have y times 1 plus I that's how
much you'll have at the end of the year
you'll get your money back plus the
interest and you want that to equal
100 that's the equation you want to
solve if you want have $100 at the end
of next year that means that
y equals
90.9 that's messy
90.9 is why that's the amount you have
to put in the bank today to have
$100 in one
year inverting that that means that more
generally the present
value of any amount of money is its
future
value over one plus the interest rate to
the T where T is how many periods in the
future you get the money so if you get
the money in one year the present value
of a dollar a dollar in one year is one
over one plus the interest rate a dollar
in two years is one over one plus the
interest rate squared
and so on essentially this is a set of
Weights that allows you to Value dollars
in all periods in today's terms by
putting them in present
value okay so suppose for example you
come to me and say look uh John I want
to borrow $30 I'm going to pay you back
$10 each of the next three years let's
say the interest rate is
10% I would say to you well that's a bad
deal for me
because what's the value of the stream
of payments you're going to give me
you're going to give me $10 you're going
to give me
$10 uh next year okay you're gonna give
me $10 next year so that's worth 10 over
1.1 to
me because if I had it today I could
have already it would have been $11 next
year you give me $10 in two years well
that's worth 10 over 1.1 squared and
you're give me $10 in three years well
that's worth 10 over
1.1 cubed
so in other words the $10 you give me to
the next three years is only worth $
24.87 I can't just add it up and say
we're gonna give me $30 so I'll give you
$30 today it's not the same thing
because if you give it to me today it's
worth more than if you give it to me in
the future likewise you it to me in the
future it's worth less than if you give
it to me today and the reason is simply
that I can
translate a given amount of dollars
today into more dollars in the future
through savings since I can do that
since I can translate that money is
worth less in the
future okay so more generally if we
write a formula for the present value of
any stream of payments any stream of
payments okay it's going to be how much
you're G to pay let's imagine P any
fixed stream of payments let's call that
F let's call F the amount you're going
to pay back with $10 in our
example
times f * 1 over 1 + I to the 1st
+ 1 over 1 + I to the 2 plus dot dot dot
dot dot all the way to 1 over 1 + I to
the
T where T is the last pair you're going
to pay me
back okay so you pay back over 10 years
there's 10 terms in this equation one
over 1.1 1 over 1.1 squar all the way to
1 over 1.1 to the
10th okay that is the equation for the
present value of a stream of payment
that's a very messy equation to evaluate
once the number of periods gets large
and that's why we typically use a
shortcut which is we you we consider the
case of a
perpetuity a payment a fixed payment
you'll get
forever if you do an infinite sum of
that
equation some of you will know that that
will yield you that the present value of
f forever is simply F over
I that's the infinite sum of that
equation so those $10 forever and a 10%
interest rate is worth
$100 okay it's the value of the payment
over the interest rate I'm earning and
that's a convenient formula now stuff
never goes on forever but if you think
about t getting
large then you could converge to using
that formula as a
shortcut so we'll typically the examples
in this class with small numbers of
periods or incredibly large numbers of
periods to allow you to use that
shortcut because having you evaluate
this for 12 terms just a pain in the ass
okay so that's sort of a shortcut we can
use as the number of periods gets
large okay questions about
that now you might also want to know
about the you might want to invert it
and say you might want to know about the
future value of a g stream of payments
you might say look what happens if I
save $10 every year what am I going to
have in the future so for example
um if I save $10 this year next year
I'll have $11 I'm always assuming it's
trates 10% for
now but then let's say I save that I
leave that in the bank well I have the
next year well the next year I'll have
1210 why will the increment from 0er to
one be smaller than Inc from one to
two why it be smaller because I've not
only saved the do $10 I've saved the
extra extra dollar and that extra dollar
self earns
interest and indeed at the end of T
years you will have that the future
value of a stream of savings is y times
1 + I to the T if you save for two
years and this illustrates the beauty of
compounding the beauty of compounding is
that when you put money in a savings
account and let it sit you're not earn
interest on what you initially put in
you earn interest on the
interest and over time that actually
becomes the larger part of what you save
over time the big issue is not what you
put in the issue is all the interest
you're earning the interest you're
earning on that
interest okay so basically let's to sort
of work that out let's consider an
example let's consider you're making a
retirement savings decision you might
think retirement gez I'm not even a
college yet like take it easy old man
I'm I'll worry about that in the future
well actually I'm going to tell you why
I shouldn't worry about in the future
why you should worry about it now now
I'm going to illustrate that with a
simple example okay imagine you plan to
work from age 22 to age
70 okay imagine that's not a crazy guess
for your working life you work from 22
to
70 okay and let's say the interest rate
is 7 so you're going to
work 22 to
70 and let's say the interest rate is
7% okay that's our
assumptions and I'm going to give you
two choices for retirement savings plan
I'm gonna give you two options option
one for retirement savings plan is
you're GNA save
$3,000 every year right away You're
gonna start saving $33,000 every year
for 15 years and then you're never going
to save again so age 22 to 37 you're
going to save
$15 you say $3,000 a year and then never
save again so it's 3 ,000 a
year for 15
years for 15 years okay well what will
you have
well after the first 15 years of doing
this by our formula you will have 75
387 you won't have $5,000 you might be
tempted to multiply 3,000 by 15 say well
15 years 45,000 that's wrong because you
misc compound it
you miss the fact that all the savings
is also getting interest on it thing you
already have much more than just
multiplying those two but that's not all
you then let that sit there till you
retire so you let this money sit
there okay for the next 33 years after
33 years this turns into 75 387 time
1.07 to the
33 okay okay so by the time you retire
you have $773,000
by Saving 3,000 a year for 15 years by
the time you retire you have over
$700,000 Let's do an alternative savings
plan what most people do which is hell
I'm Not Gon to save your time when I'm
22 that's nuts let's say we do instead
is you don't save anything until you're
37 you don't save anything for the first
15 years and then start to save then you
start to save $3,000 a year save so zero
for
15 and then
3K
433 if you file that Savings Plan by the
time you retire you are going to
have
$356,400
you're going to have half of what you
had with the first plan
why because of
compounding the way compounding works
the more you can get in the bank earlier
the more money you'll end up with
because you are an interest on your
interest how many of you have been to
the Science Museum here in
Boston okay a few of you well you
probably haven't been to the little kid
part but I have and the little kid part
in the science museum has these cool
three ramps and one ramp is flat and
then steep one ramp is steep and then
flat and one ramp sort sort of in
between and you have kidss put the
marbles on to see which goes faster and
of course the one that goes fast is the
one that's Steep and then flat because
you take advantage of the acceleration
over the flat part r one it goes flat
and then steep that's just
compounding okay compounding is simply
like getting their velocity up early
okay you're going to get there
faster so this is an important lesson
not just for athematics but for you for
thinking about your decisions you when
you get a job most of you going to get a
job in a good firm that's going to offer
you an option of retirement
plan you are going to think why should I
bother I'm I'm me I'm superhuman I'm
never going to
retire okay the answer is you're wrong
you are going to retire and every dollar
you put in now will be worth so much
when you retire that it's actually worth
deferring consumption now remember
capital is deferred
consumption so decision you'll face when
you join your firm is should I defer
today's
consumption to have for the
future and the answer is uh and the
answer is you should defer money to Da
consumption for the future moreover it's
even better than that because most of
you will work for firms which offer a
retirement plan called the
401K which is tax preferred what that
means is if they if you take the money
home today you pay tax on it if you put
in your 401k you you don't pay tax on it
till you
retire now why do you care if you're
going to pay tax anyway why do you care
if you pay tax today versus paying tax
when you're retire well the answer is
just like a dollar in the future is
worth less than a dollar today paying
taxes in the future is effectively
cheaper than paying taxes today because
you're paying taxes with the future
dollars that are worth less than today's
dollars so by deferring your taxes just
like I don't want to defer my getting
repayment from you by deferring your
taxes you save money it's even better
than that because most employers will
match what you save in your retirement
plan so when you go to a firm and you
start a new job many employers will say
well the first $3,000 will match you
dollar for dooll this is an unbelievably
good deal you're going to get the
compounding and for the next 50 plus
years you're going to get a tax break
and your employer going to help you
out so you should
absolutely save as much as you possibly
can as early as you possibly can for
retirement okay because of the beauty of
compounding let's think of a real world
example how many of you heard of Bobby
Bonia anybody here Bob Bonia I got I got
a couple head I got a few head noots
three four okay Bobby Bonia was a good
good but not great well I at at Peak
great but mostly good baseball player um
he played for the Mets at the end of his
career but by the end of his career his
his Talent wasn't worth the salary
they're playing him he sort of fell off
a cliff pretty quickly and it wasn't
worth the money they were paying him so
they offered to buy him out they said in
1999 we'll give you six million bucks to
just bag your contract and leave you w't
have to play baseball anymore can retire
pay $6 million out the
door he said you know that's a great
idea I'm happy to do it but I don't
really need the money right now how
about if we Chang the deal how about if
we said we defer the money from 1999 at
an 8% interest rate and instead I'll
collect it over the 2011 to 2035 period
so deferred for 20 years at an interest
rate and then collect it over a time
period the way that worked out for him
is that by the time his money started
being paid out in 2011 his $6 Million
worth $30
million so he basically gets a million
dollars a year till he's 72 years old
indeed there's Bobby Bia day which is
the day the Mets pay Bobby b a million
dollars okay um so basically this is a
guy who understood compounding
understood the value deferring and now
he gets a million bucks year to 72
instead of just getting $6 million at
once back when he was young and didn't
need as
much okay so this is the value of
deferring the value of compounding which
says save early and save
often okay questions about that yeah
this one oh I simply use this
formula I mean me simply it someone did
you know I did in a spreadsheet but
yeah well that's a great question
basically it's sort of approximately
Infinity we will let you know in a
problem whether you can use that
shortcut or not but roughly speaking
we're not going to give you a problem we
have to calculate over 10 periods we
give you a short number of periods we'll
give you a huge number of periods which
is effectively infinite but we'll let
you
know
okay technically in the real world not
an exam you have to do it this way until
you get to Infinity this is just an
approximation but in practice it's a
pretty good approximation once you get
out like 30 period depends on the
interest rate the higher the interest
rate is the fewer periods you need to go
out for that to be a good approximation
lower the interest rate is the more
periods you have to go out for that to
be a good approximation
okay other
questions all right so
now
yeah you talking about the tax piece um
it's but the point is with the tax the
point is think of it this way
if I pay taxes today let's say I pay a
dollar of taxes
today versus uh a dollar taxes in the
future okay the dollar taxes today that
I pay to the government they get to earn
interest
on whereas if I hold it I get to earn
interest on it so as long as the tax
rate is less than 100% I get to make the
why if the government holds the money
they make the money if I hold the money
I make the money better for me to make
the money does that make sense good
question other
questions okay now some of you may be
thinking this is all well and good but
shit's going to cost more in the future
Bobby Bia making a million bucks in 2030
is buying much more expensive stuff than
Bobby Bia was buying in 1999 what about
that what about the role of inflation so
let's talk about
inflation in other words in my
discussion so far I assumed prices
didn't change but in fact prices do
change they go
up okay we typically measure that by
something called the Consumer Price
Index the Consumer Price Index is
essentially a measure of what a fixed
basket of goods costs over time so
essentially to find a basket of goods
that a typical person would buy and they
go and measure every quarter they
literally go to stores and say what does
this cost so fixed basket Goods includes
one men shirt okay okay let's go see
what the average price of a men's shirt
is it includes one women's shirt let's
see what the average price of women's
shirt is it includes 67% of a of a new
or or 12% of a new computer let's see
what new computer costs Etc so they
basically have a set of
Weights that are determined by a
consumption bundle say for that set of
good weights what do it cost by the same
set of things over time and that gives
you an index
value and that they normalize it to one
at the year 1982 for some arbitrary
reason so B basally the CPI says what
does stuff cost relev to what it cost in
1982 and you can see that in figure
171 figure 171 is a graph of the CPI
what you can see is basically it's
identically one uh 100 in
1982 and it's rising before and after
1982 you can see that the rise is
relatively rapid in the
1970s okay in percentage terms that was
a lot of inflation the 1970s into 1980s
and then it's sort of flattened out
inflation's been slower since so this is
how we measure
inflation
okay the fact there's
inflation means that everything I've
taught you is wrong in one critical
respect which is everything I've taught
you is about I the interest rate but
that's not what you should care
about you don't care about what the
interest rate is what the nominal
interest rate is you don't care about
how much money you have in the future
you care about how much how much good
you can consume in the future money is
just a means of exchange if I tell you
in 20 years you'll have $100 you don't
know what's that worth without no one
stuff's going to cost in 20 years what
you really care about is your purchasing
power okay you really care about is your
purchasing power so for example suppose
today I'm going to save $100 at a 10%
interest rate $100 at a 10% interest
rate what I care about is not how much
money I have next year but how many
Goods I can buy next year so let's say
I'm like Marsha Lynch and all I care
about is Skittles okay that's all I care
about okay and let's suppose that
Skittles today are $1 a
bag so my $100 take I buy 100 bags of
Skittles okay so I could buy a 100 bags
today now let's say the price of
Skittles does not change but I earn 10%
interest
then next year I can buy 110
bags next
year right the price of Skittles is
still a dollar I Sav my $100 at 10% I
have $110 my 110
bags but let's say the price of Skittles
has also gone up by 10% how many bags
can I buy next
year someone tell me if the price
Skittles gone up for a dollar1 10 yeah
back to 100 back to 100
bags so basically what I can buy is a
function of the interest rate and
prices so what I care about is not the
nominal interest rate but what we call
the real interest rate which is the
nominal interest rate minus
inflation which for some reason we
denote by pi even though Pi is also
profits I don't know why we do that
we're difficult
profession okay so the real interest
rate is the nominal interest rate minus
inflation and that's what I care about
that's what I can buy is not the nominal
interest rate but the real interest rate
determines what I can
buy now this is a big topic of
discussion macroeconomics in particular
really fascinating point about this is
that really this should be the expected
inflation rate because I don't know what
the inflation rates could be when I put
my money in the bank today I know I but
I don't know what the what inflation's
going to be I know what it's been but
know it's going to be so if I say it's
$100 worth in 20 years you have to give
me your expectation of
inflation so it's actually pretty
complicated and it goes back to things
we've talked about how people make
decisions and what things we will talk
about how people think about these
things like how do you form expectations
of inflation rate it turns out there is
a near perfect predictor of people's
inflation rate expectations which is
what's happened to gas prices most
people look at what's happened to gas
prices based on that they decide when
what inflation is going to
be um but the bottom line is in theory
it's a very sophisticated there are
people there are actually hundreds of
thousands of people whose entire job
mostly work in financial sectors but
some working for the Federal Reserve
whose entire job is to form good
expectations of this that's their whole
life it's to figure out how can I what's
inflation going to be and how does that
affect decisions we're going to make and
turns out to be a very hard and
complicated complicated
calculation but um so uh so that
determines to be very very
important uh in thinking about what the
real EST rate's going to be okay
questions about
that now I'm gonna go back and I'll
sometimes I use R sometimes I'll use
I the bottom line is what matters for
real decision- making is R okay does use
I because it's more convenient but if
everybody use I it means I'm assuming
inflation zero okay so whenever I use I
I'm assuming inflation zero I really
should use r worship sometimes we slip
back and forth but basically really
should use R that's a relevant decision
making uh
tool okay questions
yeah awesome great question and a whole
field of research is what do you do
about
Innovation what do you do so here's a
here's a perfect example imagine that
there's a good that 198 in so let here's
here's a great example let's take the
laptop which in 1990 was incredibly
expensive and is now much much
cheaper okay so basically you would say
well basically uh we have Life Is Life
is cheaper now but in fact laptops do a
ton more how do we account for that how
do we we really want to think about the
price per unit of power not the price of
a laptop but the price per unit of doing
stuff okay that's gone down a ton more
the average laptop today is maybe half
the price average laptop in 1990 but the
average value of a lapt is 100 times the
average value of a laptop in 1990 we can
do so many more things with it the
computing power is so much
larger that's not reflected in the
typical CPI so many people think we need
to adjust the CPI for essentially what's
happening to productivity what's
happening not just to the goods we buy
but what we can do with them and that's
a very difficult and interesting
field the clear conclusion is the CPI is
too large the growth rate of prices you
hear every year is too large because
we're missing the underlying
innovations that for the same price
you're getting a better good you're
missing that and so as a result when we
say gee inflation went up 3% you think
wow it's 3% more expensive live in
America that's not quite true it's 3% to
live in more expens to live in America
by the same stuff but you're getting
better stuff and that should be
accounted for it's a good question other
questions
yeah yeah so now so now this is why all
Shake 1402 especially now right now in
the last year you've heard a lot about
interest rates and inflation and things
like that so basically I'm going to give
you a two-minute primer and leave the
rest at 1402 so two-minute primers go
back to last lecture think about the
market for
capital okay you've got the supply of
capital on the x-axis the price of
capital which is really we now know the
real interest rate on the y axis you've
got the supply of capital and the demand
for Capital and some equilibrium
interest rate R star and some
equilibrium Capital amount
Kar okay now where does the demand for
Capital come from well let's start with
Supply where's supply of capital come
from comes from people
savings so as the interest rate goes up
people save more what they do less of
they consume less so by raising the
interest rate you lower the amount of
demand for spending or you cool off the
economy likewise what do firms do as the
interest rate goes
up well they as the interest rate goes
up they spend less money building
machines there's less demand for
investment so you cool off the economy
so IDE is by Rising interest rate cools
off the economy by lowering both the
demand and supply of capital okay and
that that's basically uh essentially why
the FED uses interest rate as a tool to
fight to fight that that is something
you'll Le a lot more and a lot richer
unfortunate too but that's the basic
deal for those of you who want to S
understand the news at that level
okay now um and obviously the tricky
thing is how much you raise the interest
rate and that depends on this
which is why there are hundreds of
people thousands of people probably
employed at feds around the country
trying to figure out what this is
because that determines what they should
do to set the right
rstar okay now let's go back to micro
and let's talk about choices over time
let's talk about how you make how
individuals and firms make choices over
time P three choices over time
okay
so we're now equipped to ask the
question what do you do when you face
decisions that have different payouts at
different periods of time and the answer
is you just pick the payout with the
highest present value it doesn't matter
when the money comes as long as you put
it in the same terms so for example
consider a professional athlete who's
comparing two possible contracts
contract a a is 1 million
today contract
B is 500k
today and 1.5
million in 10
years well despite the Bobby B fun
example it's not obvious which of these
you should
choose because they're paid at different
times you add up you say well this is 2
million this is 1 million should clearly
choose B but that's not right because
this is worth less because it's in the
future what you want to do is compare
the present value of these two
contracts well you know the present
value of this contract is $1 million get
today what's the present value of this
contract well the present value is going
to be
500,000 500k plus 1.5 million but you
get it in 10 years you have to discount
it you put it over 1 plus r to the
10th that's the
value that you'll have so for example if
the interest rate was 7% if R equals
7% then the value of this equation is um
1.3
million so at a 7% interest rate you
should choose option
b at a 14% interest rate
then it's worth 0.9 million so to 14
percentage choose option A what's going
on why does option b become less
attractive as the interest rate goes up
let explain the intuition to me you see
the math there why does option b become
yeah exactly at a 14% interest rate if I
had this money now I'd get a ton of
money 10 years from now here I'm waiting
10 years to get the money money's worth
a lot less in the future at a 14%
interest rate it's all about opportunity
cost the higher the interest rate the
higher the opportunity cost of getting
money in the future R to getting it
today
okay so the key is basically you want
money
upfront when there is a um you want
money up
front when you have a higher interest
rate you're happy to defer money when
there's a lower interest rate okay now
so for example let's come back to sports
again let's talk about Max Scherer Max a
picture with the Washington Nationals in
2015 he signed a 7-year $210 million
contract the 10th biggest contract in
history at the
time okay but it turned out the way the
contract was
signed it was a seven-year contract was
paid out over 14 years he only had to
play for seven years but they would pay
him instead of paying him $30 million a
year they're paying him $15 million for
14 years even though they had to play
for seven
so the present value of that contract
was not
$210 but more like $166
million now why' they do that well for
Max shs there's ego because if you look
at the number 210 million that was the
second highest contract ever for a
pitcher you look at the present value of
166 million it was like the fifth
highest contract ever for a pitcher some
ex couldn't go bragging you got the
second highest contract ever for a
pitcher uh uh by if if they just give
them 166 million so that's how it come
be confused or more generally let's
think about the
lottery okay you see the Mega Millions
is a billion dollars you think this is
great a billion dollars but you're not
getting a billion dollars what you're
getting is something like $33 million
over the next 30
Years so the present value of Mega
Millions is less than half of what's
advertized they don't hand you a billion
dollars today they say we're going to
give you 33 million over the next 30
Years year next 30 Years still not bad I
mean I take it but a lot less than you
think because it's paid out over
time okay so this determines the numbers
you hear when you hear a number from now
on when if a number where people make
the mistake of adding up numbers in the
future period but today you've got to
recognize that's wrong and you should be
using the present value which puts
everything in today's terms rather than
uh uh falsely adding up future dollars
with today's dollars
this doesn't just affect you this
affects firms investment
decisions firms investment
decisions okay so for
example firms have a particularly
interesting choice because firms have
decisions where they sort of put aside
money
today to get money in the future that's
what investment is right so what firms
consider
when they make an investment decision is
they consider what's the net present
value of that investment the npv what's
the Net Present Value so for example
consider firm the a stream of payments
where you're going to get revenues in
each period of R subt and cost of C subt
so you have a project where you get
revenues of R subt and cost of C subt in
every
period the net present value of that
stream of payments is equal to
r0 -
c0 plus R1 - C1 over 1 + r plus R2 minus
C2 over 1 + r 2 and so
on that's the Net Present
Value this matters because cash flow is
typically negative in the early years of
an
investment typically investment means r0
is less than c0 you got to buy this big
machine you don't make that much money
right away but eventually you make the
money if you simply add it up and don't
discount investment will always look
great but if you recognize that
investing a lot today might yield money
in 20 years when it's worth less it
might not look as
good okay so basically imagine for
example you have a big upfront
investment of $100 in Year One
with no revenues so you have something
where in year one you get aund it's a
$100 cost and no revenues in year two
it's $200 in revenues and no
costs well you might think GE I'm sorry
you're tr get $150 in revenue and no
cost so year one c0 is 100 C1 equals 0
r0 equals 0 R1 equals 150 well if you
add these up you'll say gee this is a
great deal it cost 100 I make
150 that's a great deal but you know now
that's not the right way to think about
it okay if the interest rate is
10% then this formula at a 10% interest
rate this formula will say the npv of
this investment is
$363 that'll be the TR
10% but but as the interest rate goes up
eventually that will go
negative
why because there's an opportunity cost
of investing in the machine today which
is you could have put the money in the
bank firms just like people have an have
a decision to make about whether to
invest today in the future as described
a minute ago talking about the macro
stuff the higher the interest rate the
less attractive investment today is why
because they could put it in the bank
instead firms always have the option
just like we do of putting the money in
the bank rates
20% in the bank that I me a pretty
good investment opportunity to
give up 20% in the bank to go build a
machine to buy a machine because I'm
giving up a huge rate of return of the
money sitting in the
bank so essentially what drives firm's
investment decisions is is the
npv greater than
zero firms invest if the npv is greater
than
zero that's it simple
rule and all they need to know is what
the revenues and cost will be but also
what the interest rate is going to be
now obviously they need to know the
future interest rate so they need to
know their expectations of interest
rates okay but in principle in a world
of perfect information all they need to
know is what the revenues will be the
costs will be and the interest rates
will be and they can ask then is my
money Better Off sitting in the bank or
being invested in this good in this
machine but that's the key Point once
again come back to the macro in which I
gave a minute ago the higher our
interest rates the less investment
because the more npv is going to be
driven Below Zero by The Upfront cost
being today and the revenues you earn
being in the
future okay questions about
that so the bottom line is both
consumers and firms face this indeed
consumers make investment decisions let
me give a simp Le
example about 20 years ago I had to
decide to whether to insulate my house
it's a very old house okay at that point
I had heating bills of $2,000 a year I
had $2,000 a year heating bills on my
house okay and I decid and the the
company that gives
um that uh provides
insulation said that by in insulating my
house I could lower this by 25%
forever I could lower my installation
cost by he cost by 25% forever if I
insulated but the cost of doing so would
be
$4,000 so I just did the npv I said look
should I do it what's the npv it's minus
$4,000 that's my initial investment plus
I save $500 the first year 25% of 2000
plus 500
okay plus
500 over the interest rate because I'm
going to say $500
forever that's the calculation negative
in the first
year and then I'm going to get $500
forever from doing
this so what's the answer the answer is
as long as the interest rate was less
than
12.5% it made sense to do
this you can show that math to yourself
as long as they trade was less than
12.5% it made sense to make this
investment but it was above 12.5% it no
longer made sense to make this
investment okay so the bottom line is
that um the bottom line is that it all
depends on what else I could do with
that
$4,000 that's going to determine whether
I should make this investment or not and
what my expectation of the interest
rates are so we all face these decisions
all the time anytime face the decision
with a short run cost and a long run
benefit we should be doing the npv
calculation the flip side is anytime we
face this with a short run benefit and a
long-term cost we also do this so when
you decide whether to
smoke we'll talk about this in a few
lectures in more detail you should think
about the short-term benefit which is
you know you feel better maybe if you're
a smoker when the long-term cost is you
die sooner but you know you die sooner
off in the future so you got to decide
what's that worth you have to discount
it this is true so every example says
you have to wait the present and the
future differently to add them up and
think about decisions you make
today okay questions about that
yeah uh it should always be
R did I use where did I use
I oh yeah you're right should be R
sorry okay
okay for those of you going to check my
math at home actually the 12.5% comes
from example where we don't get S where
we don't get benefits the first year so
the example will give me 12.5% it makes
the math easy I assume the installation
doesn't start working till year two okay
just so in case you're going to check my
math okay but the intuition is the same
now let's go to one last example you
guys it's like gez I'm thinking about
professional athletes and retirement
instating my house like this is so
irrelevant to me let's come to example
totally relevant to you or at least was
to you four or five years ago should you
go to college it's pretty relevant
decision to a lot of people in
America well this is a decision an
investment decision over what we call
we've talked so far about machines and
investing in capital this is what we
call investment decision in terms of
human
capital all the time we make decisions
about how much to invest in
ourselves every time we decide to go to
college or or decide to get any other
training or learn a new
thing we are investing in our human
capital we're are building our
productivity if the new thing Sports
you're not building your productivity as
my wife constantly tells me but if the
new thing something is actually
productive for your job you are building
your productivity you're investing in
your human
capital okay so for example let's
imagine let's go to Fig figure 172 we're
going do an example imagine that when
you
graduate you your decision when you
graduate from high school is to go to
college or not if you don't go to
college you work from age 18 to age
70 if you do go to college work from age
22 to age
70 okay now if you don't if you go to
college okay there's two costs that you
get if you don't go to college that you
add right if don't go to college first
of all you got to pay for college so
during the four years that you're in
college those that green area you're
paying tuition that's why it's
negative but there's a second piece
what's the other opportunity cost of
college
yeah you could be working that's a real
cost just like tuition you all are you
all could be out there earning money
right now see you're sitting here the
opportunity cost this lecture is the
money you all can be out making real
money okay there's an opportunity cost
you are for those four years not only
paying tuition you're forgoing the
opportunity cost that is a huge benefit
to not going to
college however if you graduate once you
graduate college not F once you graduate
college you earn
more so you get more money for the rest
of your life by being college
graduate that is shown after year four
in the yellow part of the graph
Andrew I think we can draw this a little
more neatly next time it's kind of looks
like a preschooler drew it uh looks or
me uh so uh we can draw this a little
more neatly next time um basically the
idea is beyond year
four there's some there's some net
benefit okay the net benefit is how much
you
get from earning more because you got a
college degree Rel to earning Rel to
just having a high school degree
okay and that is the yellow area so if
you decide whether to go to college you
basically need to think
about what is the cost and benefits well
that's going to depend on the interest
rate so for example with if the interest
rate's zero then the npv of college just
showing the table at the bottom the npv
in college is way above the npv of just
drop and going to high school should
definitely go to college but once the
industry gets above 3.5
okay then I'm sorry uh the if the
interest rate is I know that 3.5 is
weird yeah ignore that 3.5 I don't know
what that's doing there that's weird
that's just I think that should be maybe
one or something I don't know what's
going on there but we'll fix that ignore
the 3.5 at 2% you should still go to
college at 4% you should still go to
college at 6% you still go to college
but once you get to 8% it breaks even
administrative 8% you are literally
financially
indifferent you didn't go into college
and not going to college and what's
above 8% you lose money by going to
college it's phenomenal right college
graduates earn a ton more than high
school graduates and yet the power of
compounding you actually lose money by
going to college once interest rates are
above 8% it's pretty
phenomenal that is why one of the major
interventions the US government does to
try to increase College attendance is
student loans at a low at a subsidized
interest rate one of the reasons one of
the ways we try to encourage people to
go to college is by giving them
subsidized loans at a lower rate to make
this a better
deal okay and that's why that can be a
very powerful tool to get people to go
to college okay questions about
that all right we'll stop there uh and
uh we'll come back uh next time talk
about uncertainty