I've seen this as a call to action and a
way for me to step up to the problem
with a potential
[Music]
solution. I am researching distributed
energy resources. I'm compiling a data
set that takes the data on wind
turbines, solar panels, electric vehicle
chargers, and power plants, and sees how
that data is correlated within counties
based on the different characteristics
such as population, education, and race.
I started off first on doing California
in the hopes of moving on to other
states within the US. The most
interesting thing that I've learned from
my research is about distributed energy
resources in general. I had never
understood how they were integrated into
the grid or how they had such a profound
impact on the energy that we have. I saw
this project and I saw how they are
using distributed energy resources and
the data they have in order to make a
difference so that other researchers and
politicians can be informed and make
good decisions in the future.
[Music]