the MIT energy initiative presents flow
batteries for grid scale energy storage
guiding future research Pathways written
by Nancy W
stoffer in the coming decades renewable
energy sources such as solar and wind
will increasingly dominate the
conventional power grid because those
sources only generate electricity when
it's sunny or windy ensuring reliable
grid one that can deliver power 24/7
requires some means of storing
electricity when supplies are abundant
and delivering it later when they're not
and because there can be hours and even
days with no wind for example some
energy storage devices must be able to
store a large amount of electricity for
a long time a promising technology for
performing that task is the flow battery
an electrochemical device that can store
hundreds of megawatt hours of energy
enough to keep thousands of homes
running for many hours on a single
charge flow batteries have the potential
for long lifetimes and low costs in part
due to their unusual design and the
everyday batteries used in phones and
electric vehicles the materials that
store the electric charge are solid
coatings on the electrodes a flow
battery takes those solid state charge
storage materials dissolves them in
electrolyte Solutions and then pumps the
solutions through the electrodes says
fak brushett an associate professor of
chemical engineering that design offers
many benefits and poses a few
challenges flow batteries design design
and
operation a flow battery contains two
substances that undergo electrochemical
reactions in which electrons are
transferred from one to the other when
the battery is being charged the
transfer of electrons forces the two
substances into a state that's less
energetically favorable as it stores
extra energy think of a ball being
pushed up to the top of a hill when the
battery is being discharged the transfer
of electrons shifts the substances into
a more energetically favorable state as
the stored energy is released the ball
is set free and allowed to roll down the
hill at the core of a flow battery are
two large tanks that hold liquid
electrolytes one positive and the other
negative each electrolyte contains
dissolved active species atoms are
molecules that will electrochemically
react to release or store electrons
during charging one species is oxidized
releases electrons and the other is
reduced gains electrons during
discharging they swap rolls pumps are
used to circulate the two electrolytes
through separate electrodes each made of
a porous material that provides abundant
surfaces on which the active species can
react a thin membrane between the
adjacent electrodes keeps the two
electrolytes from coming into direct
contact and possibly reacting which
would release heat and waste energy that
could otherwise be used on the grid when
the battery is being discharged active
species on the negative side oxidize
releasing electrons that flow through an
external circuit to the positive side
side causing the species there to be
reduced the flow of those electrons
through the external circuit can power
the Grid in addition to the movement of
the electrons supporting ions other
charged species in the electrolyte pass
through the membrane to help complete
the reaction and keep the system
electrically neutral once all the
species have reacted and the battery is
fully discharged the system can be
recharged in that process electricity
from wind turbines solar farms and other
generating sources drives the reverse
reactions the active species on the
positive side oxidize to release
electrons back through the wires to the
negative side where they rejoin their
original active species the battery is
now reset and ready to send out more
electricity when it's needed brush it
adds the battery can be cycled in this
way over and over again for years on end
benefits and
challenges A major advantage of this
system design is that where the energy
is stored the tanks is separated from
where the electrochemical reactions
occur the so-called reactor which
includes the porest electrodes and
membrane as a result the capacity of the
battery how much energy it can store and
its power the rate at which it can be
charged and discharged can be adjusted
separately if I want to have more
capacity I can just make the tanks
bigger explains Cara rodby PhD 22 a
former member of brushett lab and now a
technical Analyst at Volta Energy
Technologies and if I want to increase
its power I can increase the size of the
reactor that flexibility makes it
possible to design a flow battery to
suit a particular application and to
modify it if it needs change in the
future however the electrolyte and a
flow battery can degrade with time in
use while all batteries experience
electrolyte degradation flow batteries
in particular suffer from a relatively
faster form of degradation called
crossover the membrane is designed to
allow small supporting ions to pass
through and block the larger active
species but in reality it isn't
perfectly selective some of the active
species in one tank can sneak through or
cross over and mix with the electrolyte
in the other tank the two active species
may then chemically react effectively
discharging the battery even if they
don't some of the active species is no
longer in the first tank where it
belongs so the overall capacity of the
battery is lower recovering capacity
lost to crossover requires some sort of
remediation for example replacing the
electrolyte in one or both tanks or
finding a way to reestablish the
oxidation states of the active species
in the two tanks
oxidation state is a number assigned to
an atom or compound to tell if it is
more or fewer electrons than it has when
it's in its neutral State such
remediation is more easily and therefore
more cost effectively executing a flow
battery because all the components are
more easily accessed than they are in a
conventional battery the state-ofthe-art
vadium a critical factor in designing
flow batteries is the selected chemistry
the two electrolytes can contain
different chemicals but today the most
widely used setup has been vadium and
different oxidation states on the two
sides that Arrangement addresses the two
major challenges with flow batteries
first vadium doesn't degrade if you put
100 G of vadium into your battery and
you come back in 100 years you should be
able to recover 100 G of that vadium as
long as the battery doesn't have some
sort of a physical leak says brushit and
second if some of the vadium in one tank
flows through the membrane to the other
side there is no permanent
cross-contamination of the electrolytes
only a shift in the oxidation states
which is easily remediated by
rebalancing the electrolyte volumes and
restoring the oxidation state via minor
charge step most of today's commercial
systems include a pipe connecting the
two vadium tanks that automatically
transfers a certain amount of
electrolyte from one tank to the other
when the two get out of balance however
as the grid becomes increasingly
dominated by Renewables more and more
flow batteries will be needed to provide
long duration storage demand for vadium
will grow and that will be a problem
vadium is found around the world but in
dilute amounts and extracting it as
difficult says rodby so there are
limited places mostly in Russia China
and South Africa where it's produced and
the supply chain isn't reliable as a
result vadium prices are both high and
extremely volatile an impediment to the
broad deployment of the vadium flow
battery beyond
vadium the question then becomes if not
vadium then what researchers worldwide
are trying to answer that question and
many are focusing on promising
chemistries using materials that are
more abundant and less expensive than
vadium but it's not that easy notes
rodby while other chemistries may offer
lower initial Capital costs they may be
more expensive to operate over time they
may require periotic servicing to
rejuvenate one or both of their
electrolytes you may even need to
replace them so you're essentially
incurring that initial low Capital cost
again and again says rodby indeed
comparing the economics of different
options is difficult because there are
so many dependent variables says brush
it a flow battery is an electrochemical
system which means that there are
multiple components working together in
order for the device to function because
of that if you are trying to improve a
system performance cost whatever it's
very difficult because when you touch
one thing five other things change so
how can we compare these new and
emerging chemistries in a meaningful way
with today's vadium systems and how do
we compare them with one another so we
know which ones are more promising and
what the potential pitfalls are with
each one
addressing those questions can help us
decide where to focus our research and
where to invest our research and
development dollars now says Bret
technoeconomic modeling as a guide a
good way to understand and assess the
economic viability of new and emerging
Energy Technologies is using
technoeconomic modeling with certain
models one can account for the capital
cost of a defined system and based on
the system's projected performance the
operating costs over time generating a
total cost discount counted over the
system's lifetime that result allows a
potential purchaser to compare options
on a levelized cost of storage basis
using that approach rodby developed a
framework for estimating the levelized
cost for flow batteries the framework
includes a dynamic physical model of the
battery that tracks its performance over
time including any changes in storage
capacity the calculated operating costs
therefore cover all services required
over Decades of operation including the
remediation steps taken in response to
species degradation and crossover
analyzing all possible chemistries would
be impossible so the researchers focused
on certain classes first they narrowed
the options down to those in which the
active species are dissolved in water
aquous systems are furthest along and
are most likely to be successful
commercially sus brby next they limited
their analyses to asymmetric chemistries
that is setups that use different
materials in the two tanks as brush it
explains vadium is unusual in that using
the same parent material in both tanks
is rarely feasible finally they divided
the possibilities into two classes
species that have a finite Lifetime and
species that have an infinite lifetime
that is ones that degrade over time and
ones that don't results from their
analyses aren't clear-cut there isn't a
particular chemistry that leads pack but
they do provide General guidelines for
choosing and pursuing the different
options finite lifetime materials while
vadium is a single element the finite
lifetime materials are typically organic
molecules made up of multiple elements
among them carbon one advantage of
organic molecules is that they can be
synthesized in a lab and at an
industrial scale and the structure can
be altered to suit a specific function
for example the molecule can be made
more soluble so more will be present in
the electrolyte and the energy density
of the system will be greater or it
could be made bigger so it won't fit
through the membrane and cross to the
other side finally organic molecules can
be made from simple abundant lowcost
elements potentially even waste streams
from other Industries
despite those attractive features there
are two concerns first organic molecules
would probably need to be made in a
chemical plant and upgrading the lowc
cost precursors as needed may prove to
be more expensive than desired second
these molecules are large chemical
structures that aren't always very
stable so they're prone to degradation
so along with crossover you now have a
new degradation mechanism that occurs
over time says rodby moreover you may
figure out the degradation process and
how to reverse in one type of organic
molecule but the process may be totally
different in the next molecule you work
on making the discovery and development
of each new chemistry require
significant effort research is ongoing
but at present rodby and brushit find it
challenging to make the case for the
finite lifetime chemistries mostly based
on their Capital costs citing studies
that have estimated the manufacturing
cost of these materials broadby believes
the current options cannot be made at
low enough cost to be economically
viable they're cheaper than vadium but
not cheap enough says rodby the results
send an important message to to
researchers designing new chemistries
using organic molecules be sure to
consider operating challenges early on
rodby and brush it note that it's often
not until way down the Innovation
pipeline that researchers start to
address practical questions concerning
the long-term operation of a promising
looking system the MIT team recommends
that understanding the potential Decay
mechanisms and how they might be coste
effectively reversed or remediated
should be an upfront design
Criterion infinite lifetime species the
infinite life species include materials
that like vadium are not going to Decay
the most likely candidates are other
metals for example iron or manganese
these are commodity scale chemicals that
will certainly be low cost as rodby here
the researchers found that there's a
wider design space of feasible options
that could compete with vadium but there
are still challenges to be addressed
while these species don't degrade they
may trigger side reactions when used in
a battery for example many metals
catalyze the formation of hydrogen which
reduces efficiency and adds another form
of capacity loss while there are ways to
deal with the hydrogen Evolution problem
a sufficiently low cost and effective
solution for high rates of the side
reaction is still needed in addition
crossover is still a problem requiring
remediation steps the researchers
evaluated two methods of dealing with
crossover and systems combining two
types of infinite lifetime species the
first is The Spectator strategy here
both of the tanks contain both active
species explains brushit you have the
same electrolyte mixture on both sides
of the battery
but only one of the species is ever
working and the other is a spectator as
a result crossover can be remediated in
similar ways to those used the vadium
flow battery the drawback is that half
of the active material in each tank is
unavailable for storing charge so it's
wasted you've essentially doubled your
electrolyte cost on a per unit energy
basis says rodby the second method calls
for making a membrane that is perfectly
selective it must let through only the
supporting ion needed to maintain the
electrical balance between the two sides
however that approach increases cell
resistance hurting system efficiency in
addition the membrane would need to be
made of a special material say a ceramic
composite that would be extremely
expensive based on current production
methods and scales rodby notes that work
on such membranes is underway but the
cost and performance metrics are far off
from where they need to be to make sense
time is of the essence the researcher
stress the urgency of the climate change
threat and the need to have grids scale
long duration storage systems at the
ready there are many chemistries now
being looked at says broadb but we need
to hone in on some solutions that will
actually be able to compete with vadium
and can be deployed soon and operated
over the long term the technoeconomic
framework is intended to help guide that
process it can calculate the levelized
cost of storage for specific designs for
comparison with vadium systems and with
one another it can identify critical
gaps in knowledge related to long-term
operation or remediation thereby
identifying technology development or
experimental investigation that should
be prioritized and it can help determine
whether the trade-off between lower
upfront costs and greater operating
costs makes sense in these Next
Generation chemistries the good news
notes broadby is that advances achieved
in research on one type of flow battery
chemistry can often be applied to others
a lot of the principles learned with
vadium can be translated to other
systems she says she believes that the
field is Advanced not only in
understanding but also in the ability to
design experiments that address problems
common to all flow batteries thereby
helping to prepare the technology for
its important role of grid scill storage
in the
future This research was supported by
the MIT energy initiative car rodby PhD
22 was supported by an Exxon Mobile MIT
energy Fellowship in 2021 to 2022