okay so good morning
again
um lecture number
eight today we finally get to the
macroscopic world and models but let me
just remind you what we've done uh the
last topic we've we've seen the
chatelier brown Principle as a
consequence
of some interesting relations that uh
emerge from the fact that stability
conditions involve quadratic forms of
some of the fundamental of
the where the Matrix
is uh second second derivatives of the
fundamental relation or of some other
characteristic function like the Gibs
free
energy or the elol free energy and as a
result of U the mathematics of uh
putting a quadratic form in canonical uh
form we
obtain
uh
these
inequalities that we have also in
interpreted U
um in the sense uh of a the because
after all this is a
theorem we could call it the chatel
brown theorem there two two assertions
namely the fact that the system
responds to when you uh move it away
from where it is comfortable so when it
is in mutual equilibrium for example
with the with the
Reser and we have see that uh there are
different types of reservoirs with which
the system can be in mutual equilibrium
so uh the same idea apply for M
equilibrium with all those kinds of res
the idea is that the system if you do
something to it from the from outside uh
for example put in energy or put in uh
particles or uh change uh uh the
volume uh in
react the system
reacts
in try to go back to where it was
comfortable so it that's the first
assertion so if you put in energy it
will increase its temperature so that it
increases its willingness to give away
energy and return to uh equili with the
rest well uh but uh the second assertion
which is a consequence of
this additional Mass from the canonical
form of the quadratic
forms is that uh it depends the reaction
of the system depends on which direction
you take uh uh it away from equilibrium
and in particular if you break
conditions for Mutual
equilibrium so for example
if you have a
uh if the system can exchange volume
like in the example of the uh airs
Springs the system can exchange volume
and suppose that it is in uh in in a
mutual equilibrium also with a thermal
Reservoir so at the same
temperature so there are two
conditions for Mutual equilibrium
quality of pressure and quality of
temperature if you change the
volume while
breaking both conditions the system will
react
stronger uh than if you just turn break
one and that's that's the
idea and the difference is is is is
important for example in the case of the
uh
um
airspring the difference in the you get
the
reaction makes uh this volume act as a
as a standard spring but the constant
the spring constant depends on how many
conditions for a mutual equilibrium you
you've broken while changing that uh
volume and the change may be of the
order of I mean it's 40% if you do it
slowly so that uh uh the system has the
time to remain in the same
temperature so by exchanging energy with
the reservoir it remains in mutual
equilibrium then you get a a a milder
reaction than if you do it fast and if
you do it fast you change both the
pressure and the temperature and so the
system wants to has two reasons to go
back to
equilibrium okay so now we
finally to the question
uh well what's the difference between uh
microscopic systems and macroscopic
systems what is
um what do we gain if we make some
additional assumptions
that will involve having many
particles so let me start with a
few uh uh pictures but also even a more
simple
idea
so
because there are several ways in
which we can see the effect of what
happens when we have few particles for
example consider a single particle and
consider the most basic uh description
which is
one the quantum mechanics
description in quantum
mechanics uh you have uh that the
particle at
um is describ the position of the
particle is described by probability
density
function which tells you that uh
so it tells you what is the probability
to find for example the
particle when you make a position
experiment in this uh small interval
between X and X Plus
DX and in fact according to quantum
mechanics that all you can predict is
the
probability you cannot predict where the
particle will will will show up the next
time you call for where where are
you okay so essentially the
state in quantum mechanics is the
probability distribution or the set of
probability distributions that describe
that allow you to describe uh all all
these uh um uh all these measurement
acts but in a statistical sense
okay you see the important thing that I
want to emphasize uh uh today that is
important for our discussion today is
the fact that the you you find uh in
order to to solve in quantum mechanics
this problem you write the amilton of
your uh particle or system or particles
and you have to solve an igen value
problem to find the igen functions of
that uh uh am miltonian
and you have to face the boundary
conditions so the the walls of your
system
uh the things that we call ex external
forces are represented by an infinite
potential here on both
sides which forces the um functions to
go to
zero and at the
wall
okay then of course if you solve that I
value problem you find uh functions that
uh you can look it up uh in any uh
Wikipedia page there is the various
Solutions and various iing functions and
then when you when the system is in a
stable equilibrium State uh um the
probability of all probability is is a
mixture of those
uh igen
functions for example here I took a
paper in
which uh there is a not one particle but
four particles Co finded in a box like
that and very low temperature now very
low
temperature that mixture of igen
functions make the uh the
um pan value ones uh
Prevail and you see here that so these
are the
distribution of particles of probability
to find the particles for various cases
going from a
boson black clim to a
fermion two things in between
the common feature that is important to
us is that uh at the wall those go to
zero so there is a that means the I
would call it raction
effect you can think of it as a gas a
probability
gas but it's rarified at the
walls here is another uh paper
um the review written by Professor Ali
Constantino who is the uh mentor of this
class and uh in another realm this is
not really not quantum mechanics it's
molecular Dynamics the molecular
uh fluid
mechanics so there is a a solid wall
probably made of
carbon and
uh what what what what happens is that
the particles the interaction of the
particles due to Vander Val forces so
these are repulsive and attractive
forces like Leonard Jones and we will
talk U uh again about this but uh uh for
the moment I I presume that um you you
you have some ideas about that
uh due to this uh forces the and due to
the the fact that the wall is a fixed U
layer and it
imposes um the forces that do not move
whereas on the side of the bulk of the
fluid the particles move and so there is
more random action of forces the
ordering uh imposed by the wall
implies an ordering and layering of
particles at various distances there is
a first preferred distance and then
there is a second third and so on fading
out as the
randomness uh become more important away
from the
wall so this is also a sort of
um wall uh I would still call it raction
effect because yeah in very close to
between the first layer and the wall
there is nothing the particles don't
like to stay
there this in food mechanics has
importance because it it it has it's
related to the problem of the No Sleep
No Sleep condition if you're are fooding
mechanist when you have few particles
you have to deal with this problem and
uh
this is another
example
again watching
uh density
distributions of a
gas now here it's not few particles it's
like 10 to the
5ifth atoms it's not very
few still in these
cases you you see uh density wall
effects with uh R faction very near uh
the wall and then there are
Peaks uh where the particles like to
stay uh near the wall more than in the
B now 10 to the
f is not small but it's not large
okay so what is
uh why is this
important and so let's start with the
suppose I have two particles like
this
okay so I have a
wall but on the other
side I have a specular situation
in which I have another
particle in the same uh stable
equilibrium
State this is the meaning of this part
of the
figure think of just one particle on one
side in one particle on the other side
that's
okay now suppose
I find a way to make that wall that
separate the two particles
disappear
okay so the moment it
disappears particles don't know yet and
just just removed it they're still there
let's say oh hey there's more room
available there's more uh volume we can
f
so there will be a spontaneous
process whereby the particles will seal
that volume and eventually will reach a
new stable equilibrium
State let's
say something like
that if we look at it on uh
with the help of the E versus S diagram
which is very uh useful
here I have drawn
the E say um the stable equilibrium
State um curves fundamental
relation of the two
systems um that are that we have uh
considered one is the system in which
there is a partition that divides it
into two
the other is the system without the
partition and that system without the
partition for that one we are
considering two
states the state we started
with when when we just remove the par
it's a non equilibrium state so much
that we know that will
evolve towards the stable equilibrium
state so this point
here represents
for the system with the uh partition
system as the the initial stable
equilibrium
state but it also
represents the
state of the system without partition
and it's the non equilibrium state for
that system so here we call system a the
one without the partition and system uh
2 Lambda
I mean Lambda plus Lambda so it's two
Lambda um the system with the
partitions the reason I put I draw them
on uh this same spot meaning that they
have the same uh energy same
entropy is a consequence of the idea
that I have found a way to remove a
partition without perturbing the system
without putting in without any uh
uh
external
Exchange in no time so that essentially
I don't change any of the
properties ideally could do
it and the fact that I have put this
state to the left of the final stable
equilibrium state is that um yeah
intuitively we know that uh this the
particles will evolve in by filling the
entire space so that's the direction in
which the the the the system will evolve
not uh vice versa if I have put this
state on the other side it would mean
that the system would separate
spontaneously which doesn't happen
okay
so the first consequence of this is that
uh the
entropy of the sa equilibrium
state of the two
particles that have the same energy
initial energy because this system is it
all happen happened in an isolated
system
uh the
entropy of the final stable equilibrium
state is greater than the initial
entropy of this state or also of this
donum
state that is by the principle of
entropy non decrease a spontaneous
process goes only in the direction of
increasing entropy for an isolated
system so what is uh that changes when
you have uh uh
many
particles somehow I have already used
this idea here uh when you have many
particles because here I go from one to
two
particles the slope of this probability
distribution at the wall becomes steeper
so in other words uh the more particles
you
have the smaller
is the
raction layer next to the
wall and as a
result you see uh
here you see the difference with
it could say what it could use
stes yeah they're
remarkable but just
be So eventually you
have almost flat distribution in the
bulk of your system and a
sharp very thin already we call it
boundary layer or wall layer rtion
layer so even at the center this region
is very
small that
means that the two stable equilibrium
State
curves get closer to one
in and in the limit of many particles
you can
neglect this difference so you can
neglect this fact you
can
approximate the properties of the system
with the part
partitions with the properties of the
system without the partition or you are
interested you can mod the system
without the partition as if it it had
the
partition these are very important when
we this when we
go here
might is very important that happens
that
yes you have
a box or I
for ever you C and
you uh those
elements that are
small world enough
many M respect to the
system but not
more this of need we question
return
to M saying is that when I consider see
like here I am going to
apply models like the local could build
mother and with this in uh the
properties of a system in which the
particles are
those by physical
words the
approximate
is how do you do that how insert
tiue we mention on make as more mention
on MAR they system
side
stud when there temperature press ener
one okay and then I ass sign I say when
the properties of this are the same as
that forgetting about W's effect
with this idea on physically
inserting doesn't that change the
properties of system is fundamental in
our
industry
Contin at at the microscopic
level
okay by in principle we should know that
if you
it and replex we
land good two
F then it will make me in trouble
playing you
get and so
you're your assumption that music May
which involes local equilibrium you the
my
also should they care about the many
parles of
Fus all right so let's see what we
gain in the many particles and we go
back
to
all with imp partition let's see what we
gain but here here's a more uh schematic
um
idea so suppose we have our system a is
this one where we have
uh whatever
particles a given volume volume here is
important because of course you be it
has to be uh be able to fin
system
also you see
when we are in this
nit since there are faction effects
become an importance to as the
boundary essentially the geometry of
your uh container loses
import for example here where in this um
this picture here shows very well the
geometry of your
container does play a big
role so if you have if you go to this
paper there are other geometries that
are shown nice pictures uh you see that
the W far because layer out layer this
work layer there
Wars depends of course on the shape of
the contain and therefore the
properties of stable equilibrium depend
on the shape
but in the limit in which
those attack W effects become
important
you only the overall volume of the
container what the details import
are because in The
Bu
The the that's
uniform it's uniform everywhere
okay so here suppose we we have our
system and suppose we partition it into
Lambda
partitions here we call it Lambda later
we call it
n so that means that
on this side this is a composite system
uh it's still in stable equilibrium
State each one is in a stable
equilibrium State like this is the sty
system we started on here in the
blackb uh and they and we assume that we
have a
partition way that not only the volume
but also number of particles is exactly
uh one / Lambda the overall the volume
is one / Lambda overall and the energy
of one of
around all right
so now remember what the fundamental
relation means for example here
fundamental relation means that it gives
us the properties of of all the stable
equilibrium
States uh as a function of energy volume
and their amount so it is
valid it is a function the same
functional for
form maybe e s the B Cub the log of n
things like that it's the same function
uh for
all
values EV
andn I can compute it also for e but
also for E over Lambda the same
function is if is the
same mixture of substances for example
for uh lot of energy or small energy
large volume small volume many particles
two
but as long as this F doesn't get two
fuel it's
okay I mean it's okay what we're going
to say so at this stage it's okay in
general but what we said here is that uh
this
curves this is the partition curve it's
the summ it's this side so it's this
much for each subsystem so if you have
Lambda of those you multiply it by
Lambda Lambda times s because s is an
additive property so you can the entropy
of the overall is the sum of the
entropies of the parts and uh
so this composite system is an entropy
Lambda
s and this s s s sub
Lambda whereas system a is an entropy
ASO in
general this as bigger entropy than that
but in the limit of many
particles this difference becomes un
important and so we can
approximate um that uh the two are equal
that's one we call the simple system
model
uh you don't find it around with this
name except in in our book perhaps the
choice of the name wasn't
um
the what it uh but it expresses what
what uh you find under the title of
thermodynamic
linit in physics so that's how it's call
this
idea I need it is a limit because now
what look what we're going to
do we here we s we choose a finite value
for Lambda so we partition the system in
a finite number of
partition and it has to be finite in
order for the number of particles inside
each to become not too
small
yet if Lambda can
be large
enough 10 to the 23 and is that Lambda
could be say a millium
and uh still in each uh uh partition you
have 10 today what
17 so that means uh still a lot of
vles so um from the Practical point of
view when you have so many particles you
can um think that this
Lambda can be any any
number oh yes could be in
but who cares between the integers there
are the reals so let's just make it real
he so
um so you make this mathematical
assumption essentially take this this
formula
here and uh make it valid make it as a
valid for any Lambda integer or real
doesn't move
so you formally assume that the
fundamental relation has this
property and this property for a
function in mathematics it's called the
homogeneity of first
degree the fundamental relation is a
homogeneous function of first degree in
all of
its uh independent variables
divide each one by any but the same
Lambda then multiply the result by
Lambda you get uh uh the value of the
function for the original uh values of
independent
properties and this is is an important
uh Assumption of course it's a heavy
assumption
which has this physics for us to support
it and when you do
it we gain one relation we're going to
prove it in a moment which is called the
oiler
relation and notice
also I changed the
letter for um energy from E to U
and we also going to call it internal
energy or this
station so soon as we say internal
energy we say aha okay we are within the
simple system model
approximate all right so how do we prove
uh that
relation well it's simple uh one
way is since is has to be true for all
lambdas
take the
partial derivative of this with respect
to Lambda
now is it uh yeah okay there's I think
there's something
there something fish itting this
that there there's something fishing is
the m something missing sorry about that
but uh okay so when you take the partial
derivative with respect to Lambda of
this thing you get
U because of this Lambda
here and then and then you have to St
you have Lambda that
multiplies uh the derivative of you
respect to S times the derivative of s
of this with respect to Lambda so it's
minus one over Lambda squ and so so yeah
this is um uh um wrong U graph sorry
I'll correct it
um and then in the end of this this
derivative you take Lambda equals one
and here comes his
ration this matter is better done in the
book than in this few graph
sorry okay and what is another uh
consequence hope this P are okay now uh
this is another uh the the main
consequence of the oil
relation is that
um we can Define it makes sense to
define
specific properties for example I have
the energy I'm not going put it e i call
U and suppose I
am in fact
then is the sound or all
the
remember so this
prob
specific uh
molar
enery I do the same
or
theit of the
volume and for the
amounts well the amount of substance I
I is piap the motor action of
the
okay
so now I'm going to
express I want to see how
the specific molar
energy that is that represent so much
energy I have with you number of all
five instead of and
I to the denominator the M mass that
will be the
speci en with mass a enery hand so
kilogram of
substance
say so from the
definition and of U so U uh is a
function of SV andn but s can be
written
here more less the CTIC Banks the amount
n * s and
so volume so the volume can be written
as n * uh lower case z and the amounts
can be written as the N times the more
fractions so if I look at this
expression here I see it uh
that the specific
energy does depend on the specific
entropy B specific volume the mole
fraction but it also depend on N because
the N
appears all in several places
here
right so that means for example
the kilog give an amount of
substance that has a certain
energy uh a certain specific energy but
if I have 2
kilog the energy per
kilogram may not be the same if it
depends on
it it's like here I
have
water is to go
they have brought
this the not staying
that with the
same
away so for small systems this
dependence on N is there and it is
represented by a fundamental relation
that's uh so you need you need to
measure
it for most systems you have to
measure it's not enough to measure the
unit of a substance like one kilogram so
you measure the proper of water called
the mod uh you measure one kilogram and
you have done because when you have two
kilogram you just multiply by two that's
good in the microscopic them but when
you have uh BL mudes of
water it's not just wise
the properties of 100
point you have to see how it depends how
those properties depend also on the
amount but in the limit of many
particles that dependence vanishes so
this proof which takes again the partial
derivative of U with respect to n so you
want to see how much is
it well that dependence
is
equal to if you do the derivatives and
let you uh do it
uh uh it's minus 1 / n s
times you remember the what what was
this we should add
there
allistic
F that term in parenthesis is what we
call the
oil what you what we say is
that the the way the specific
canery of the system at sa equilibrium
depends all the number of
FS is measured by
o but in the limit as and God
see what system goes to
Z because the O
relation just
says that this is equal to
zero that that relation here or what we
call
O is equivalent to saying only
characteristic f
equals so that's what we
gain we gain what one more
relation and you know you would think
already so many things from just
watching fundamental now we have another
one you can imagine that you can
extract uh additional information for
example one way which is now equivalent
with the ear relation is to take its
differential and subract from it the GS
relation which is the differential of
this the fundamental relation the result
is called DS new M relation and it is
this
one so relation between in which see the
independent
um differentials are temperature
pressure and uh the chemical potentials
so these are the
that a conditions for a visual
equ okay
once we have this
idea we can
also uh proceed with defining a um
another kind of interaction which is the
B flow
interaction uh dang
it idea and now that a system many
the I have that
but in
that I can consider a c
element and I can assign to it P as
it separated by
walls so right instead of doing it um
and like a cube by consider a steer but
that's the same idea so suppose that
locally I
would and um and it is
in
St this
box is say
what now
it's look at
different
reference exle why that
Wes I look at it from the
reference it goes the other
way app a veloc
to and associated with that
velocity a kinetic energy
in addition if I look at it from an
accelerated reference
plan then uh that has the same
acceleration as the
gram
G then it acquires also the
tension is to can
so the idea is is this okay now
including
mechanics see them actions in which IUS
cross the boundary between two systems
there is
movement choose as reference way and
that's of the boundary where the partic
are
crossing then the it
but for each of these particle I can
always find the reference frame in which
it is not
moving and even if it is in presence of
a gravitational field for each of these
part can find an accelerated frame uh
where it is uh
not we that we inspect those frines
there is no kinetic energy and no
potential energy
so somehow this kinetic energy and
potential energy has effect that can be
added or or removed by just changing the
reference
way clearly that doesn't change internal
properties of the
stuff it doesn't change the energy I
mean yes it does change the the the
energy but it doesn't change uh the
other part because um like
so this is uh the model that we make
that we call Bulk Flow State bu flow
local equid in
Spate we
assign the good elements the Frog of the
lock they would have believe
them or we assume that the summer
reference respect to which it
is media
and that thing uh that energy which
satisfies the fundamental relation of
St in that sense
it is enure it has a
pord it has L of fum
varation so that's step
one defines a local
equilibrium
model step two is that if you have a
boundary between two systems for example
you have a pipe that brings uh fluid
elements inside your
system but we usually how do we this is
an open system put it an open
system and
uh we usually
represent
uh as a
boundary the formal boundary as a imagin
uh it's now in our mind there is a
boundary between the pipe and the
system but this boundary isn't
physical
yet in order to model the interaction we
suppose it is physical suppose we can
put a physical
partition which we are allowed because
we are really in a simple system
model so let me put
uh in a Time instant uh
t let me put a um a partition that
separates that amount of fluid that uh
is going to cross this boundary in the
next time interval delta T or
DT so now it's here later is there and
it's phys Al separated
by if a no cost I have put in
that okay then what happens uh if I look
at the from the the fluid element the
fluid parcel that is coming uh that is
crossing here uh from a reference frame
that moves at with its velocity I am
assuming for Simplicity here that there
is a flat velocity of
P or it's
not make
it single out velocity
profile but for Simplicity let's suppose
we look at just one element and so that
as it's velocity and look at it from the
rest reference
frame when which you see it as not
moving
okay
this partition that you put in is a
partition that separates two
systems that are in uh Mutual
equilibrium they have the same pressure
in
temperature particular particular the
pressure is the same that
partition uh even it could move it
wouldn't move because all the fluids
that are coming in in the pipe here have
the same uh
pressure
but if you now make uh the energy
balance and here is the details of
making the energy balance for uh this
composite system of the system which is
receiving that amount of fluid
plus this fluid that will eventually get
in so now that we have separated it with
a physical partition this partition
makes it uh a legitimate system so the
the composite system a plus b Prime is
uh well separated from the rest because
it as a wall and it always satisfied our
definition of system in which uh we get
external forces with certain
kind okay so for these kind of systems
which are closed system now we can we we
have already introduced uh the energy
balance do the energy
balance which involves saying that the
final energy minus the initial energy is
is equal to the energy exchanged via
interactions and here there is only one
interaction it's the the fact that there
is a
pressure acting on a moving
piston moving
Bounder and
that and that is a
work but this is the
work he that means that now we play
additivity in the final State we note
that in system B
Prime there is nothing
left the system B Prime is now between
this fixed boundary and the moving
boundary if you
want a we we could say that I to be more
precise I should say that at initial
time at time
T in order for system B Prime to be a
system I have to have introduced
physical boundary
here then I remove it I let things uh go
and in the end I reput again uh the
physical bound right here but there is
nothing between the two boundaries so
the energy entropy there are
zero and again in order to do the the um
adding or removing partitions I need to
I need to be within the simple system
model okay so to make the long uh story
shorter here is the uh the expression
for the
war and is uh pressure times
uh the
area times the
displacement and uh you can show that it
is proportional to the specific volume
times the pressure times the amount of
the the fluid parcel that has been
exchanged and in the end of the story
you see that uh this work which we
usually call the the pulsion
work uh add a contribution to the
energy that is brought into system a
it's not only the internal energy of of
of fluid not only its kinetic energy and
and potential energy but also this
passion work and that is why in a b flow
interaction the it's you
energy plus
PV which if we recall it's called
corresponds to definition of that
characteristic function that we call the
B and that enters into uh the expression
that says how much energy is
transferred in this kind of
interaction of course you can do the
same when the parcel is is going from
inside to outside
and therefore we get this
um summary of defining properties for
the B
flow interaction it
contributes Mass to the
system by by the mass balance you can
write it this
way energy here is the inal and also
entropy the entropy is just the entropy
that uh uh fluid element has and S we
uh translate from outside to
inside
translates okay in out you can also do
this per unit time
and uh you can
uh
therefore now with this additional type
of interaction you can write
uh balance equations for a system that
is
sub all sorts of interactions for
example here we have right heat
temperature ta typically we use the a or
the letter zero for the
environmental
conditions here we have a heat
interaction at some other
temperature
maybe
cold uh this one at another
temperature we may have work
interactions of various types like a
shaft bringing in uh mechanical
energy electrical wires beinging
bringing in ccal energy these are all
work
equivalent or a moving uh boundary
against the pressure of the atmosphere
that is also work in
there and plus we have we may have
many bulk flow interactions and as we
have seen in order to characterize a
bulk
flow uh interaction we need to
characterize the blood flow States of
the fluid elements that are carried in
and out so you need the enthalpy the
local enthalpy uh the the local
entropy the velocity of the fluid
elements and the local height in the
gravitational Feld so that you can
compute the uh
potential of course subject to all these
interactions is going to be
uh so
it's not going to be easy to balance
them so that you keep the energy the
same the enthropy the same the volume
the same the the mass the same which
would be required to keep the system in
a steady
state but uh very often that's exactly
what you do for example this is a power
plant and you want to operate it in such
a way that it doesn't consume itself it
simply processes stuff so you need to
balance what goes in with what goes
out and while you do that U
definitely most of the times produce
entropy by IR
reversible this a balance equation of
mass rate of change of the mass is a met
uh uh
mass flow rates that are that go in and
out here I to simplify the notation I
consider m dot with the
arrow just in so it's positive is in
that means that if I want to
represent something go going out it I
will need the
negative or you you could split this
summation into two
sums and put on one
the mass the masses that go in and minus
the summation of the masses that go out
that's also this for the energy the rate
of change of the energy is equal to the
net amount of energy transferred by
interactions here are the Heats works
here are the B
fros and for the entropy the rate of
change of the entropy of the
system is first term here is the entr ex
changed either via the buf flow
interactions or via the
Heats and then
that what how about this
sign what do you think that's an arrow
okay the entropy plus the entropy
produced by
IRB that needs to be
corrected just
uh I probably left it
there to
see if I'm awake enough and you are
awake enough to spot it and
but so we with
did and once we
have this balance equations we can
manipulate them solve
problems in
the large uh
community of uh the engineers that have
uh played with these
equations there developed this idea of
exergy and exergy Analysis ofg
systems um it it adds nothing to this
equations except um perhaps it helps in
reading
them it adds nothing because it simply
it is based on a linear combination of
these equations the mathematically all
the information was contained in here
but this is the basic we definitely need
to make an energy balance and an entropy
balance if you don't like working with
enthropy and we refer to work with a
linear combination of energ and
entropy fine then you call it XG balance
and so one way to combine these
equations is to take one of these forms
uh that
um is
to take the second equation the entropy
equation multiply by some
temperature and it is convenient to
choose
the temperature of one of your um heat
interaction and is even more convenient
to choose the temperature of the heat
interaction that is considered free of
charge for example if you if your
Machinery operates in some in an
environment like uh the air your air
conditioning at home works in the air
and uses uh and dumps heat in the
environment you would I would use that
temperature uh
is the temperature that I use in this
linear
combination If instead your power plant
is cooled by the water of of the
R I would I would use the temperature of
the
rib in any case so take that multiply
and then subtract it from the energy
balance and uh if
you yeah I think here
also you have to be a little
uh I should have been a little more
careful in uh making explicitly the work
uh
uh write it write separately the work
related to the P times uh rate of change
of Dr like the PV PA times times rate of
change of volume should be um singled
out here maybe I'll do it
uh later on the slides just for the
slides and uh when I correct also the
minus sign
here so that
that work term can go on this side of
the equation and make this PA times
DB all right so here is
a an xfg balance equation and
xfg is
a is a topic that we need to discuss uh
uh we not make uh the story very long
but uh it's it's part of theody dnamic
so it it is uh a good idea to discuss it
also because it brings a several useful
ideas about how to define efficiences of
U energy conversion devices and so it is
uh important in
the the mechanical engineering the fact
we will um we will see okay we already
have seen that combinations like that I
think we use the letter c Capital Fe to
represent his uh um availability
function e minus t r s plus P
RV so this says that's the rate of
change of the
availability but X and availability are
the same idea same concept the words for
the same
idea
uh heat
times Caro
coefficient uh and the cono coefficient
is um between temperature of what I've
chosen as my
um and
environment and the temperature at which
the heat is
exchanged this
represents for a given Caro engine the
maximum work that you could extract by
exploiting less heat interaction having
available uh environment of temperature
T not and so this is the the exergy
associated with that heat interaction it
can
work appears directly not multiplied not
corrected because work is already
available to uh let's say if you have
some work you can do useful things
directly you don't have to convert the
work is already in a sense
ex because the word
exy really
means the the essential part of the end
energy so the the the the use
for fractal the energy that it's
either within your
system or an energy
transferred so the concept applies both
for the addictive properties on of the
system energy East or the uh modes of
energy transfer
it
work and here is also the XG expression
or uh about flow
interactions and out of this um do the
proper sign here you get a minus and
here is correct minus t * s dot
reversible this is the
in uh dissipation the terms that
represents the destruction of bra
ex and like um entropy cannot be cannot
can cannot be
destroyed
uh
exergy cannot be
created you canot it uh destroyed
so they related so
reversibility you do things
reversibly you don't create entropy and
you don't destroy
exergy you do things
irreversibly you create entropy and
Destroy some
exit that's St
yeah and so since we are at this
business of
the let's just do it we have already
done
um few uh lectures
ago the first low and second low
efficiencies or heat engines uh
refrigerator units and heat pumps but
this is just the summary same equations
that we already seen up there
just notice
that the first low efficiencies a ratio
where you put at the numerator an energy
and at the denominator another energy
typically the numerator is the useful
effect that you want and the num the
denominator is the resource that you are
use and energy
wise
instead a second low
efficiency you put at the numerator what
you want to achieve and at the
denominator
uh the
minimum
expenditure that you need to uh pay in
order to achieve that which is typically
done minum in the sense of
thermodynamics of course and so uh it's
uh the reversible
cake not saying this is the Practical
Optimum using
practice don't want to operate diversity
or object is very to operate reversely
because if you operate
reversely most of the times you have to
do it in such limiting conditions that
you get
nothing so in practice what you want to
uh optimize
is
power
or combination of power
misss
depending on the cost of
equipment because of course the more you
put in in terms of sophisticated
equipment you may uh achieve uh higher
efficiencies but
uh it
um the
cost May kill you so you have to
compromise therefore there are
uh
other terms in the equation of
optimization in terms of practical and
so here we're just talking about so this
is the limitation of the second low
efficiencies
that it gives in denominator which is
your term of
comparison uh a the reversible process
which may be too far away from
practicality one one sort of sort of the
uh
halfway solution would be to put
there uh the work required by the best
available technology to do do that
particular
job in that
way at least you
compare uh the efficiency of your device
with the efficiency of the best
available
technology and of course if your device
is better your efficiency will be
higher higher than one and know and
eventually your your your technology
will impact and will be become
theology
too all right
so this view graph simply uh summarizes
uh again the idea of first law where
energy associated with the useful
effects divided by the energy associated
with the source that the resource that
you have
used which could be burning a fuel or a
using Sol
energy and uh here for the second law
you can cast it for second low
efficiency you can cast it by saying
that I put
them
also
uh uh the exergen associated with the uh
useful effect because the exer
represents the
work equivalent of that useful effect
and then you put at the denominator the
X and G associated with the source You'
used you can uh to reason it out uh you
you you realize that this is equivalent
to
uh putting here the energy of the useful
effect and and the
below um the
the minimum resource you you should use
in order to obtain that which is I
think
here see this form of
the secondary
efficiency is also equivalent once you
do the balance equations and obtain the
expression for the reversible work as a
ratio of executes for example for the
heat engine If the ratio of the exy of
your product which is works so just pure
exy divided by the exy of the resource
which is heat times the Caro
coefficient and notice that the Caro
coefficient has to be
computed
using the temperature as environment the
temperature of the cold dresser where
which you using as uh an environment S
as the the thing where you Dum your entr
and similarly for a
refrigerator this definition is
equivalent to definition in which you
have uh exergis numerator and
denominator
now for a
refrigerator this is the exergy of
cooling uh with a the cooling load QB
times the this is equal to a caral
coefficient minus signs becomes a caral
coefficient
uh but here now you see uh the can
coefficient with the T at the numerator
so the T of the environment now is the
hot because in the refrigerator you are
uh pping entropy to the um with the
Environ which is hotter than the
refrigerator cell and similarly uh here
for
the so going back to this idea of uh
exergen so the word exergen or the board
availability in the old times there were
fights about how should we call
it that has been I I participated in
conferences where people were really
F nowadays I
think uh the body is more R about the
idea and then it just use ex ability
doesn't really matter it's a generic
concept
of so X andg does have one
definition you different forms of
exit for example we encountered the many
already for example thetic availability
is a form is is one
ex is the xfg associated with when
you when you restrict yourself to weight
processes well you can call that like an
adiabatic system system that goes all
weight process you can call it adab
or we have
seen that if your system is as
um is in
combination with a thermal
Reservoir the maximum uh you can do the
maximum work you can uh do depends on
the type of
reservoir the res is fixed volum we we
have this U that we call available
energy Omega R but then we have defined
also available energy with respect to
other kinds of
reses where the res can change your
volume or maybe the the osmotic resare
where you can exchange it through a semi
per membrane only one type of substance
or a completely open uh uh Exchange in
which your system can
uh exchange volume and any of the amount
these are all
EXs different formulas same
word work is just pure
exy a heat interaction just said so the
ex associated with the heat interaction
at temperature the
Q is given by the
heat times the K coefficient
exit
requires as as before
here requires a reservoir is a reference
in some
cases not in
here for heat interaction it does uh
require
that and need to specify what kind of
uh what so you need to specify to choose
a
temperature it's relative exy is
relative to a choice of the particular
reference environmental temp
yes but even that makes it
that road concept so you can Define uh
uh the ex for a cooling uh uh Heating
coing
interaction
and for example suppose you have a
Machinery
that operates like a herno engine and
this is simple simple case in which we
have two
reservoirs but but suppose that the
neither the the hot Reservoir nor the
cold Reservoir are environmental
me for
example this cold Reservoir could
be the your house the house that you
want to warm
up they want to be at uh 70 fite or 21
in a
seat in your
house and one way to keepit up uh your
house it's actually one of the best
ways from the point of view of
thermodynamics is to do is to have uh do
use C
generation you use some
uh
costly heat source
for
example uh okay this is a reservoir so
it's not exactly so is proper example
but uh usually you buy gas to heat up uh
uh
water and then you have your water
circulate in like
here heing elements and that uh uh hot
water is going to heat up the air in
your
room so you're using a gas with which
you could uh reach very high
temperatures and all you do is by a
series of heat
transfers use
it to produce something at the
temperature which is very close to the
environmental P that's a very dissipated
way
doing we have been doing it all for a
long time like this we're still doing
it like that's the way it's done in my
apartment building where I did now and
the but that's
not the good way it's a it's a very
inefficient
cogeneration is the idea that you
take that high level
energy and uh before you
uh you do the as much as you can with it
you do for example run a power plant or
run a plant or
run
engine for example you could run a
carrent
engine you this is are call total energy
modules like car or truck engines or
maybe ship
engines depending on the size where you
burn your fuel Mak uh mechanical
energy um with that mechanical energy
you produce
electricity and
then since your engine needs the dump
entropy somewhere instead of dumping it
directly into the environment you dump
it into the heating system of your house
and then it when your house take care of
but dumping the mg the DI
uh so you get this uh heating as a
byproduct or as a one of the two
products of your system which is a
combined
uh Eon power is called cogeneration of
CHP solution and in this
way you
use that nmg at at best so this would be
say the available
best available technology for example in
the town where I
worked 30 years longer which is briia in
Italy this
idea has been
taken very seriously starting in
1973 and now about 95% of the volum of
the town and it's a town the size of
Boston
um it's heated in this way with k
generation power
plants that dump energy into a district
heating system they get this hot water
going around the town under the roads
and reaching all the houses and then
when he exchanges you do
the uh you more
recently see 20 years ago uh they also
added that um in the more complex system
in which you also not only use uh fossil
fuels but you use also waste uh eurn the
the like tach that is not
recyclable and uh they also integrated
with the hybrid way with some solar so
it's an entire system aimed to uh
efficient efficiency for uh he through
the the homes
I know that many are thinking about
doing things also uh in the States but
here the the the problem has been that
um the problem the reason that these
things have not evolved is the cheaper
costs of energy addition when one
incentive for improving efficiency is
the cost of that ener I the cost invest
to spend less yeah
here with
what I'm not an bats I'm
in okay
go some
forun the man it's great D
morning GL to know
yeah yeah probably I thought that
somebody was thinking of also yeah uh
doing it for the town like the problem
is that takes it takes a lot of
investment and the way it got started in
in brasia was that um the municipal
company was
um the company that would run also the
roads would would run r a lot of uh uh
public
services including transportation
and so they could um s of
decide and move quickly about the moving
because they were people working on the
roads putting pipes because you need to
put large pipes uh and
go it they it's if you do it internally
it it is easier and also they they did
it in such a way that
uh there's another issue is uh people
want to be to get um connected to the
his eing system but
um sometimes it's more efficient to
start with big buildings and then go
to this kind of the seizur are with
political and so uh that is a issue
okay sorry we are late so see you next
time