okay so let's start so H first of all
wow thank you all for coming back I'm
happy I didn't H you know uh push you
away uh so before we start with today's
lectures just a few Logistics so for
some reasons you guys are taking a
holiday next week unfortunately so we
won't have class A the week after on the
29th unfortunately I'm away that week at
Germany but we're gonna have our amazing
Rachel in the back uh give a fantastic
lecture so you know uh you'll enjoy that
uh and then the week after which I
believe is October
6th I would have loved to give you a
great lecture and I'm here however
you're going to get something even
better because there is a really really
amazing work uh new work by ODed RV who
gave who does a new constructs a new
factoring algorithm uh uh Quantum
factoring algorithm uh so kind of
improves Show's algorithms in some way
uh it's a really really exciting piece
of work uh odet is in Paris but that's
the one day he was able to come here and
present his work and it's exactly on
this class so so I think what we should
do we should all this class will move on
October 6 and we'll all go to od's talk
it's going to be this class it's going
to be a colloquium and it's going to be
a theory reading group it's going to be
kind of allinone it's going to have a
very nice format where the first hour or
so is going to be kind of a very general
theory audience talk and then we're
going to have the
next two or less hours depending on how
much he'll have the energy to speak to
us uh we're going to talk about kind of
more details about his algorithm and his
work so that's October 6th and then I'm
going to be back so you're going to have
a bit of a break for me now uh which I'm
kind of sad about but you may be happy
uh okay so let's first kind of recap uh
where where we were and and continue
from there uh so last time we defined
kind of this new class of proofs kind of
going away from the classical proofs to
the regime of interactive
proofs we showed the power of these
interactive proofs by showing one
protocol in particular the sum protocol
I wrote the sum protocol kind of very
Loosely in that uh
board because we're going to refer to it
today again so the some protocol just a
recap it's a way to prove that the sum
of a multivariate polinomial over let's
say a small set H you can think of H as
01 as an example over like a Boolean
Cube or just a bigger Cube the sum is
some value over some finite field and of
course to compute this sum takes a very
long time it's like H to the m you need
to just sum everything up but it turns
out that you can verify it using an
interactive proof very very efficiently
assuming you have Oracle access to this
function you can compute it kind of
efficiently on any random element in the
group in the field so this is what we
covered last time the sum protocol as I
told you this some protocol is really
the bread and butter of proof systems
almost every proof system uses this
protocol it's a beautiful protocol in my
opinion uh and we'll see we'll use it
throughout kind of this course so if
anyone has any questions about the
subject protocol please
ask okay and if it doesn't sit with you
yet I really encourage you to review the
notes and kind of uh you know in the
website there's also notes to uh Justin
Taylor's um a a survey which contains a
very nice Exposition and also we have
now scribe for that so you know you have
various uh resources to to look at the
protocol okay and then we start to look
at kind of applications for the protocol
the first application we got is to show
uh interactive proof for Sharp Set uh
and we showed this interactive the idea
was to it was via this technique of
arithmetization converting kind of a
Boolean circuit into a arithmetic
circuit we'll use this technique today
as well and then we Departed and talked
about this idea of a doubly efficient
interactive proofs where in doubly
efficient interactive proofs we really
care about the runtime of the prover in
addition to the runtime of the verifier
so in the classical interactive proof
setting all the focus was on efficient
verification nobody cared about the
runtime of the prover okay he was for
like for all practical purpose we
thought of of him as like an all
powerful but doubling efficient
interactive proof now there's a yeah the
pro of course is more powerful otherwise
the verifier would do the work on his
own but uh he's not he's not we don't
have all powerful things in this world
unfortunately so we also care about the
efficiency of the prover so he's just
more efficient but not we don't want his
uh to you know his work to be crazy
expensive okay so that was the doubly
efficient attactive proofs and we just
started and we'll continue today to show
how we get a doubly efficient Tractive
proofs for counting triangles and there
was VI uh uh for count counting
triangles in a graph and it was via
technique called the low degree
extension okay so now the plan for this
class today is to look at the low degree
extension okay again this low degree
extension it's a theorem it's written
here uh I'll explain it uh it's again
the bread and butter that's actually
this low deegree extension theorem in
some sense is what makes the Su check
protocol so popular so kind of uh
important okay what this the is what
gives the subject protocol its power in
a sense so really together the low
degree extension the low degree
extension theorem together with the sum
check is like everything follows from it
like via cories almost okay so we'll
we'll kind of that's what we'll see this
lecture in the next
lecture okay so what is the low degree
extension theorem what it says is that
take any function from H to the M to 01
H is just any set it can be 01 to the m
it can be Boolean hyper Cube but it can
be a bigger hyper Cube okay if you're
more comfortable if it's easier for you
to think of H as 01 just think of it as
01 okay so take any function from H to
them to 01 so when I say any function
set of Pol it's just a set of elements
so when I say any function from h of
them to 01 you should think of it as
just an AR arbitrary sequence of H to
the m
bits okay and I just ordered them like
in a hyper
Cube okay so I have this sequence of H
to the m bits defined by this function
and the theorem says that if you take
any finite field that contains this set
H so if H let's say is Boolean 01 you
can take any finite field every finite
field contains 01 okay but more
generally any finite field there exists
a unique polinomial so now we move from
an arbitrary set of bits
to a
polinomial f from F Tilda so we call it
this is the extension so we call it from
F to F Tilda from F to the m not H to
the m but F to them M so I extended it
to F to the m to
F such that if you look at the extended
polinomial and the small hyper Cube H to
the m it really is exactly
F and this flda has small degrees so its
degree in each variable is H the size of
H minus one okay so if you want to
visualize it here's what you should
think I have a bunch of like uh bits
sitting on some hyper Cube it can be
Boolean or it can be like more you know
elements here but I have arbitrary
sequence of bits sitting here in this
hyper Cube and the theorem says you can
extend this to like a function over a b
field so over F to the
m in a unique way I know if I specify
it's a unique way in a way that it
extend so on the values here are exactly
as
before and the degree of this polinomial
in each variable is exactly H minus
one okay this is the theorem by the way
in the case where H is
01 then the degree in each variable is
one because H minus uh H is 0 one so the
size of it is two degree one this is
often called multi-linear extension
because theg the resulting flda is of
degree one in each variable then in
which case it's called
multilinear okay any questions about
what this theorem says the meaning of
this
theorem okay so we're going to prove
this theorem next but and then we're
going to go back to this counting
triangles which was just kind of a
motivating example but the what the FOC
this is really this theorem and and uh
before I go into the proof I want to say
why this thing is so powerful is that it
allows you to go from an arbitrary
sequence of bits to kind of a polinomial
and which is of low degree and a
polinomial of low degree has a lot of
structure and that kind of really helps
us for example once you have polinomial
of low degree with structure of low
degree we can apply subject protocols
okay so that's kind of the way will
offer new subject protocol we're first
going to go to L we have an amatory
sequence we're going to take the low
degree extension and now we can kind of
argue uh you know using use to use we
can then use the sum
protocol okay uh any questions before
we
yeah
take ariti arithmetization
right so what you're saying is good what
uh let me just repeat what you're saying
uh what you're saying is if F has
already is not arbitrary but actually is
kind of a circuit an arithmetic circuit
with and and or with addition and
multiplication and it's very low depth
like log depth let's say or let me call
depth D then just kind of think of it as
over a Big Field especially if it's if
it's Z1 you can think of a big field and
then the degree of this thing will be
like two to the depth you're right but
two to the depth
eh so you're right and so actually for
for Sharp set that's what we did how did
we use the Su check that's exactly what
we did but then you need to assume a lot
of things you need to assume that at
that so you're right if you start with
an F that has structure that it's very
very low depth or like the degree is
very small then you're done you already
have it but what this is saying for any
sequence so any sequence of number of
bits can be arbitrary you can kind of
put it in this way
exactly so so what you're saying for the
the the functions that are that are kind
of natively small degree you can
immediately get an extension but the
degree will not be the minimal minimal
degree so to get the minimal
degree that's how you do it yeah good
thanks any any other questions okay I
just want to remind you questions are
great I hope you just witness it because
it's good good for people you know for
all of you so please ask questions and
okay should we dive in okay so the first
thing to notice is
actually you should be familiar with
this theorem for the case where m equals
1 so first just notice for M equals
1 this theorem is simply known as the um
the L interpolation theorem this is
really just l
okay what isolation theorem says just a
recap it says that if you have arbitrary
if you have an F exactly the same I'll
just write it from H to
01 then there is a unique way of
extending it to F to be of degree H
minus one okay so there's a unique
flda from F to
F of
degree H minus one and moreover I'll
tell you what it is let me just tell you
what this flda is the
flda is simply sum over all the H's in
h uh oh sorry uh f F of
H times some polinomial Kai h of
X where this
polinomial is zero on all the H elements
except for on the specific one okay so
this polinomial
where
so this is the F where Kai h of x
is what is one where if
uh for every a h Prime in h it's one if
H Prime is equal to H and zero
otherwise
yes shouldn't it be the inverse
I want the output to be yeah so okay
let's see what I want that if I'm
somewhere in h so I want to say that if
I'm somewhere in h Prime I want to get F
of
H I want F Tilda of of uh of so for any
H star I want F Tilda of H star to be uh
to be F of H
star
Z which is either zero or one yeah yeah
so oh
sorry
can what do you mean f of H should be
the inverse I'm not sure you're saying
here I should have inverse yeah why
so H will you something that's zero okay
so let me try to argue maybe I'm let's
try to do this together so if I have if
this is Kai so I first defined Kai of H
okay that I'm going to Define it in a
second actually I didn't finish defining
it but what's important to me that on
every H Prime in
h it's one if H Prime is equal to H and
zero otherwise suppose I defined it now
let's see what I get here I have flda of
H star is Su
FH Pi h of H star
but this is always zero except it's
one when H equals H star so it's always
zero except for when H equals H star and
when H oh you're saying when H equals H
star then I
have F of
H
star so it this does extend
yeah so we're good okay great okay but
let me just mention what is I said this
is the kai but let me actually be
explicit so let me erase
this the Kai in the in the Lan
interpolation
theorem it satisfies this but let me
actually tell you exactly what it is
it's pretty simple it's just sum over H
Prime in H and then it's uh I think H
Prime -
x / H oh sorry um
[Music]
multiplication H Prime in h minus except
for H and it's h Prime minus
H okay so first note this is of degree H
minus
one and when you look at it for any
element oh uh yeah for any element H
Prime it's going to be you're going to
it's this is going to cancel out unless
you had you happen to be H oh wait did I
do it
wrong unless you're H and then you're
one good okay so this is just a recap
for L interpolation
okay now let me tell you here in the in
so this theorem says the same thing but
for M bits for m m variables okay and it
turns out you know how this was flda
here
flda of
z z now is in F to the
m is very similar it's also
sum F of H1 up to hm so for every
Point
times this
Kai H1 hm of
Z and what is this this is one if Z okay
and the small hyper hyper Cube this is
one if the Z is H1 of the HM and is Zer
otherwise and it extends so but actually
let me be more specific it's really
where Kai H1 up to hm of let me call it
I know
uh X1 up to XM is just the
multiplication of k h i x i i goes from
one to
n okay so let me move this
[Music]
board okay don't let me erase this board
okay we'll need it okay so again what is
the low degree extension flda it's
similar to the uh univariate case you
sum over the entire H per Cube and you
multiply by a unique by the degree H
minus one in each variable it's just a
multiplication of all these all of these
kaiis that were defined
here okay okay so let's see if if uh let
me try to you know to prove that this
works and that it's
Unique okay so first what do we need to
argue we need to so we have this F telda
now I need to argue that it extends so
the fact so okay so
proof so let's first see that for every
H1 star up to hm
star in h to the m
let's look at
flda of
H hm what is it it's just sum h
f of H1 up to
hm times
Kai
of so let's look at flda flda on any
point in the per Cube I Define it by
star because it's a specific point and I
just substituted you know I I defined
this F I just substitute Z because this
is my Z point and now what do I have I
know that this is equal to one if and
only if h i star is equal to hi I for
every I because this is how the kai
defined this is just a multiplication of
these
K okay so therefore
that's it this is just F of H1 star up
to hm star because the rest of the terms
cancel
done yeah so it
extends how about the
degree what's the degree of flda it's
just the degree of these
kinds so let's look at degree I of like
of a variable I it's the degree I of Kai
of H1
hm
and which is what it's just the degree
of a single kaihi on x i because this
just uh you can it uh factors
to to multiplication kaii and XI so
that's just the degree of this which is
by what we saw there simply H minus one
done okay so it is indeed it extends F
it's the degree is correct H minus one
in each variable the only thing that I
need to argue is that it's
Unique
questions okay so the uniqueness will
follow from the uniqueness in the
univariate case okay so we already know
from Lan interpolation theorem that in
the univariate case f is
unique now we're going to rely on that
to argue that in the multivariate case f
is
unique
okay
questions okay so let's do it so
uniqueness so suppose for contradiction
that it's not unique okay so suppose for
contradiction that it's n unique so
there exists two ways to extend that
agree on the hyper
Cube this means that if you subtract
these two you'll get a degree H minus
one polinomial in each variable then in
the hyper cube is zero but it's not zero
because they're two different
different pooms so it means so so uh uh
suppose for contradiction let me just
erase this because it's in my way
suppose for contradiction that there
exists like a
G from F to the m to
F non
zero but G and the hyper
cube is zero that's the contradiction
and of the
degree H minus one in each variable yes
that's a contradiction say Suppose there
this two polinomial that agree on the
hyper cube of this degree we're going to
subtract them we're going to get a
single polinomial that's just zero on
the hyper Cube because the two agreed
but it's not zero because they were not
the same
polinomial okay what does it mean non
zero okay exist okay what does this mean
of degree and one in each
variable okay the fact that it's non
zero means that there exist some T1 up
to
TM in F to the
m such that
G and T1 up to
TM is not
zero yeah so we're starting with saying
suppose we have G it's not zero but it's
zero on the hyper
Cube and going to argue no it can't be
I'm going to find an element in the
hyper Cube for which it's not
zero okay how do I do that what I'm
going to do I'm going to kind of go into
the hyper Cube coordinate by coordinate
kind of by induction okay and here's
what I'm going to do I'm going to say
okay let's look at
G
empty T2 up to
TM this is non zero because on T1 it's
not zero so this is non
zero uh of
degree hus
one but from
the langage interpolation
theorem it says that if it's that if
it's not zero there must exists
H in small H in h for which it's not
zero because if it was Zero on all H
there's a unique we extent the zero
polinomial so because the uniqueness of
the L it means that
so from L gr theorem this is just
univariate it means that there must
exist
H1 such that g of H1 T2 up to TM is non
zero again why if so the t's are fixed
this is a univ polinomial if it was zero
an
H then you could extend it to all
zeros but there's another way to extend
because uh you know uh the G is not all
zeros that would be a contradiction so
therefore there must exist H1 such that
this is
zero and now we're going to slowly
continue in this manner okay now let's
look at g h
H1 T3 up to
TM okay so H1 is fixed in in the small
cube these are fixed in F it's not zero
because on
T2 it's not zero that's what we
established so this is non
zero of degree H minus one and therefore
somewhere on the small H hyper Cube and
somewhere on H sorry it should be non
zero from L interpolation theorem so
therefore from L interpolation theorem
there exist
H2 such that g H1
H2 T3 up to TM is non
zero and you just continue one by one
until you get that there exists G H1 H2
of to hm
that's not zero and that's a
contradiction because we assumed it is
zero everywhere and the small hyper
hyper
CU yeah okay so in the notes I I have
like the reduction I I can there's a
proof that kind of by induction very
formal but I think this is good enough
for for for class otherwise it's going
to be a bit boring questions yes can you
also just a Ching argument like you can
just count how many po of degre
raise it up until like all the term
that's
number okay good good good so you're
saying maybe you can also prove it using
just counting angre me say if there's
too many then like you'll have too many
pooms and that's a contradiction because
the number of polinomial like the number
of coefficients probably you can do
something like that as well
uh yeah yeah can I try to make thee for
the ared yes please good good
good the aration
can
yeah
good at the good very good okay so what
you're saying is you're saying look once
you force me once you don't you're I I
said I'm look at me I don't assume
anything about F you assume no degree
look at me I assume nothing and look
what I get now you're saying well you
assume nothing but you know you don't
get that much either because this F
Tilda is so inefficient note to compute
this F Tilda where is
it it takes time H to them you need to
sum over all the hyper Cube so Computing
flda is really inefficient whereas your
FTI is so efficient in ice 100% yes
you're
right I'll give it to you V not yeah no
but this will be useful in settings that
the arithmetization
but but that's a good point thanks is
like easy way to
number
that many okay so if okay so the
question is can we bound essentially
asking well can we make this after a
little more efficient maybe kind of so
in general we cannot because in general
it depends what you want to assume about
the F so I'm saying I don't want to make
any assumptions about the and as you
will see it's not just because I'm kind
of I want to just be as general as
general as possible for the sake of
generality actually in the way we use it
it's really has no structure uh the the
F we use is kind of very
arbitrary uh so we can't assume that it
comes from a low degree whatever nothing
uh and in that case if you want to allow
any NF then you have to have all the
monomials because there's just by a
counting argument if you the number of
FS is like you know all the uh all the
possible H to the n Bits so you have to
have that many monomials otherwise where
would you store that information so in
general you can't do with L monomials
however in many cases you can do and
actually even will use it the fact that
in some cases you can do with L
monomials so we'll see that but that
that's that's great great
Point any any other
questions so let me just tell you this
is a very good to stop and ask questions
because it's really will'll get back to
this so much and even if not in this
class you'll see it and it will come
come at you uh it's a really really
important and uh fundamental
theorem okay so I guess next I'm going
to try to convince you why it is such an
important fundamental theorem and I'm
going to start with a uh just kind of
looking back at the example of doubly
efficient interactive proofs for
counting
triangles just as a motivating example
uh we'll do it quick and then we'll go
into kind of I think the um more kind of
interesting and general way of using
this low degree extension together with
a sum check to get doubly efficient
proofs for any low depth computation so
kind of arbitrary computations so we'll
see that next but let's first kind of as
a warmup look at uh the example for
counting triangles why is this low
degree extension with some check how can
we use these together to count triangles
in a graph so now note what's the goal
we have a graph I want to know how many
triangles there are in the graph now
it's not that hard it takes time n to
the third I go over every three pair of
vertices and check if there's a triangle
so I have an end to the N cubed
algorithm but let's say the verifier
can't run in time n Cub the poor guy he
gets the graph so size n squar all he
can do is run time n squ essentially a
polylog with some polog overhead but
only N squared so he can't count so now
what is he
do he needs help okay now I'll show you
how the pr can help him in a way that
now yes he only needs to run in time n
squ or o till of n squ okay so let's
look at that example um so let me erase
this
so here's an example where this is
useful we're given a
graph and the goal we want a protocol a
proof where the Prov will convince to
the verifier that the
number of triangles
in G is let's say some number
beta I want to prove for this
fact how will I Pro how so I'm going to
prove to you you guys are time o of n
squ you can only read the graph I'm
going to help
you prove to you that the number of
triangles exactly beta while uh you uh
just uh run time n s how do I do that
I'm going to let's look at the function
f from so suppose V is n okay so I look
at the function from 01 2 log n to
01 and this just tells me whether so 01
so it's like 0 one to the log it's you
can think of this as being kind of n
byn so it takes log n Bits that describe
one VAR one vertex log and bit to
describe another vertex and it outputs
one if and only if there's an edge
okay so you can think of each so
F takes two vertices I and J and outputs
one if there's an
edge and zero otherwise so f is just the
adjacency Matrix the adjacent Matrix is
you know n squ Bits this is unquit I
just put it and Define it this way okay
so again F takes two vertices
it outputs one if there's an edge
between these
vertices okay
now we okay so what do we need so okay
now what do we know we know that this
F has a low degree
extension so this is of
degree essentially this is multi linear
CU I started with 0 one so this is so f
is
multilinear so degree one in each
variable now why do I want why am I
looking at these ad adjacency Matrix
what do I want what do I want to prove
how does this relate to the number of
triangles so the number of triangles we
started discussing this last time is
just the
sum over all kind of triangles I J K oh
sorry all kind of three nodes i j k and
V and it's a triangle if what if f i j
is one and
f j
k is one and f i k is
one so I want to know how many
triplets is this thing one if an edge is
missing in one of them then this is
going to be zero because I multiplied
so I want to know how many of them do I
have
one okay and that's almost the number of
triangle except that I need to divide by
six because I counted each triangle each
three vertices all the permutations so
so that's what the Prov wants to prove
to the
verifier okay so let me I said V but let
me call it 01 to the N to the log
n is the
same now I'm done
why am I done cuz I'm saying you know
what so how do I prove this I'm going to
use the Su check but you're saying wait
but this is not a polinomial no worries
here you
go now it's a polinomial now I didn't
change anything because it's only over
the small cube so the fact that I extend
it doesn't change that doesn't change
the
sum okay because of the
extension so the prover needs to prove
that the sum of this polinomial so
before it was multilinear now it's
degree two because you know each
variable we multiply three pooms each
one appears in Two Fine degree two in
each variable and we need to
prove that the sum is
beta this is exactly what some is for
precisely okay and note what does the
prover so now so what are we're going to
do we're going to do subject protocol
what is the runtime of the verifier and
the protocol so they interact you know
we do every time you get rid of one
variable one by one by one at the end
the verifier needs to
compute F these kind of this Pol the
final polinomial which in our case is
this entire
polinomial and a single point in the
extension namely he needs to compute F
Tilda on a random point in F in I guess
F
squ three
times but that he can do do very very
easily or what I mean in time N squared
because what is f Tilda F Tilda I mean
as as VOD said enumerate over all the
small cube lot but here the small cube
is n squ so really takes time n squ
three so order of n can do this three
times he needs to compute this this but
this is poly log so by the way
throughout this I mentioned it last time
but I'll mention again throughout this
course I the polog factors I'm not even
you know these are all like you can put
things like in
tildas I'm kind of eating I I don't want
to pay attention too much the polylog
factors okay so really what he work what
the runtime of the verifier is just n
squ the the communication complexity is
nothing M number of variables is order
log n d the dep the degree is constant
uh log F well don't take F to be too
long too big take F you know so that log
f is not is
small and and note even the prover
doesn't run in too long what's the
runtime of the prover it's in the sum
check protocol it's m the number of
variables log n uh times H to the N now
H to the N seems big but again it's n s
times the time it takes to compute F1
which is again uh n squ so he's
polinomial and now the verifier runs in
time uh squared
okay so that's just kind of to
illustrate yeah to
be yeah he he right and he is he's
actually n he's n to the fourth in this
example because he
runs he needs to compute this okay let's
see he's more actually he needs to
compute this thing so he needs to do it
for every I JK in right so and it's wor
yeah he need to not just a compute to do
the entire sum check so in the sum check
it's he needs to kind of H to the m
which is M here is going to be 3 log n
so uh in this so it's like uh already n
cubed and then he needs to compute T of
f like the polinomial which is n s so
he's n the 5ifth because Computing this
once is n squ without the sum but he
also needs to do run over all the
sum and then also log factors yeah he's
he's he's he's running more but po it's
it's considered still doubly efficient
because he still polinomial
overhead yeah if
no yeah even in Cube you're saying you
for yeah currently it's a good so okay n
Cub you can get it uh using a recent
kind of really nice Works uh you with
just optimizing a little bit uh that's
the work of uh Dan song and friends they
get a linear time so they can get an N
cubed I don't know how to it's but it
may be that for this specific protocol
it's possible actually I don't know it's
a good
question but let me actually before you
get too excited about it so uh
yeah the number of rounds is
login great great question have a two
message so when I finished where's Gabe
oh hi so you came to me last time right
so uh when I started talking about this
last lecture gab came to me rightly so
and said well uh we just started talking
about it right he's like well okay but
uh you can do it so much easier and it's
true I this was kind of to as a an
example to you know to show but actually
going since you asked the question also
actually there's a very much simpler
protocol that gave notice so let me let
me just write it here
the idea is that the prover will only
send two matrices over so it's it's a
big communication complexity here the
communication complexity is po long but
if we just care about verifier runtime
and we don't care about the
communication complexity then the prover
can just send the verifier the m so
think of let let a be the adjacency
Matrix let me now instead of f write it
in the more classical notation of a
matrix a The adjacency Matrix where
there's an edge if there's a one if if
and only if there's an edge and zero
otherwise the pr will send the Matrix A2
is a
squ a he can also send a but the
verifier knows a and
A3 which is a
cubed now the N now the number of
triangles is just the
trace of a cubed so it's very easy to
compute you just compute now how do you
know that that this is a squar and this
is a cubed well we saw last time a
protocol a randomized protocol for
checking equality between matrices via
kind of this uh re Solomon kind of
decoding idea so you do that so there
you go that's really really
nice well but then blame blame Gabe of
course
exactly you're right
okay
um you can
get
okay I need to so you you know there's a
really beautiful work of rrr uh and they
get conent round complexity uh and so
using their paral probably you can get
very good but I need to think about the
parameters I think you can get in con
around like probably like really good
parameters but I'm I need to think about
the
details
yeah okay H so so this was just a
motivating example to show you that you
can take something also with no
structure whatsoever like adjacency
matrix it's no structure it's arbitrary
but using the technique of a low deegree
extension you can kind of add structure
to it and then you can use the sum check
okay so um more generally I want to say
I think what's really the power of this
is you know in eror correcting codes
what's nice about err correcting codes
is if you cheat you kind of need to
cheat everywhere in a sense things kind
of
percolate in proof system this kind of
thing is very very useful because we
want to proof system is about catching
cheaters you want to C when we construct
like interactive proof our goal is to
catch aover uh a cheating prover and so
you want some encoding kind of you want
to say if he cheat somewhere he has to
cheat everywhere kind of that so this
idea of kind of having in some sense you
want kind of a if you want the proof to
you want
um it's very natural that kind of some
encoding comes into proof systems and
we'll see that next when we look at the
gkr protocol for uh low depth
computation
okay so that's coming next now before I
start this protocol I have a question
for you so last time this is a long
class this a three-hour class it's
tiring so uh and it's technical which is
even more tiring so now I want to ask
you two options option one we'll take
two breaks one after one hour one after
the second hour it will give you kind of
or we take one in the middle which is
maybe a little longer any H how many
people are for like two kind of short
breaks to
decompose let's take a break now for
five minutes and then we'll do
gkr okay so so so far when the
applications we saw a for the G for the
sum check and even if you want the low
degree extension were both kind of
counting you know we said okay let's
count uh the sharp set let's let's count
the number of triangles so you may think
okay well some check is about counting
so yeah I can see how you can do
counting Problems by either they're
already kind of low degree and you just
apply some check automatically or
they're not low degree and then you do
low degree extension and now you have
the Su check okay so maybe you can do
kind of counting things but that's it so
now the what I want to show you next is
that no actually you can do a ton with
that so just the low degree extension
and some together that's all you need
and what I'm going to show you now is
how to do an a doubly efficient
interactive proof for all low depth
circuits so let me explain uh so suppose
you have here some
circuit C it's really really big uh but
it's shallow okay so think of this
circuit size s which is really big the
depth
is D which is very
small okay now what I'm going to show
you is a doubly efficient interactive
proof where the verifier runs in time
only D or linear in D or D and poly log
in
s and and the prover of course he needs
to compute the circuit he runs in Time s
he has to run the computation and only
poly overhead so poly ofs okay so I'm
going to show you w efficient
interactive proof for any bounded depth
yes can just clarify here circuit size
is just number of gates good the circuit
size just number of gates yeah yeah now
note I I'm this already seems like weird
because okay so the pro I said the goal
is the prover is going to convince the
verifier that let's say so the goal is
to convince the
verifier that c of x equals let's say
one
think of is any any Boolean Circuit of
small depth so now but but and the
verifier should be very efficient but
now you're saying just reading C is not
efficient if you have an arbitrary
circuit just reading the circuit is not
efficient you're right so for this to be
meaningful C needs to have a succinct
representation so it needs to be kind of
a uniform circuit that you can specified
succinctly and indeed we will assume
that c is what's called log space
uniform which essentially means that
there's a log space machine a log s
space machine that uh um a uniform
turing machine that generates this
circuit but actually for now don't think
about just suppose it's it's it's just
kind of there's some uniform condition
okay so the verifier has sucing
representation of the C because it will
only come much much later when you'll
see this kind of you'll need to deal
with this issue
okay so so the goal is for the prover to
prove to the verifier that C ofx equals
1 and the idea the way we're going to do
this essentially is the high level idea
is we're GNA kind of so the
PO so I I want to prove I want to kind
of catch the pro if he's cheating how am
I going to catch him I want to make sure
he's correct so the per comes to me and
says look see x equal 1 the value here
is one I want to reduce the claim on the
output value to a claim about something
in one layer below and then by like the
small sub protocol and then I want to
reduce the claim about something about
kind of layer below layer below and
layer below and layer below and layer
below and so on until I get a claim
about the input which the verifier can
compute on its own that's kind of the
idea so for this the first thing we
assume and this is without lots of
generality
that c is
layered what do I mean by layered
there's an output gate there's kind of
that's let's call it layer zero and then
you go to gate and then it there's kind
of a wires to one layer below we'll call
it layer one and then their gates to one
layer below we'll call the layer two so
it's not there's no kind of Long Gate
that go from the input straight to kind
of it's really layer by layer okay so
that's the first assumption so we can
talk about layer so that what it means
is that
gate in layer
I is
connected
only to
Gates in
layer uh I + one where we think of I
equals z is output
and I D is input
layer okay so this is just for the sake
of Simplicity you can always kind of uh
add dummy gates to make sure uh that
each gate is only connected to one layer
below if before was connected to someone
closer to the input you just add dummy
gates to kind of go up up up
okay so again let me just make sure
everyone's on board but by layer when I
say gate is in layer I essentially what
I mean the depth from there to the input
the number the path the length of the
path is I so any gate that is kind of I
away from the input it's connected to
Gates that are only I minus one away
from the
input okay so we assum that's an
assumption I'm going to make and the way
I can get I can realize it is by just if
this original circuit was not in this
way I'm just going to add dummy gates in
the middle so if a circuit at layer
three was connected immediately to the
input I'm going to just copy the input
in one two and then I'm going to kind of
ATT uh connect it so things are going to
be
layered questions about this
assumption okay so now the the uh
circuit is layered and now what I want
to do I want to reduce so now I'm going
to have an interactive protocol so the
idea
in G is to have uh an
interactive
protocol that consists of D
subprotocol and each subprotocol
essentially reduces a claim about some
layer I to a claim about layer i+ one so
a claim about the layer that's one
closer to the
input okay so these are kind of how
these sub protocols uh will go I'm going
to explain I'm going to explain the GK
protocol formally but this is just uh
intuition uh and
uh okay so uh let me take this actually
so the first thing is
uh okay
so here is here is kind of the
idea so again I'm this is not the
protocol this is I'm kind of giving an
intuition of kind of what helping you
kind of understand where I'm going to go
so we want to prove
a cheating prover suppose he's cheating
he's trying to argue that t ofx equals
one but think of it it's not we want to
catch him how do we catch him if it's if
he's cheating how do we catch him so one
idea is to say well if he's cheating
here he must so let's say this is an and
gate suppose it's zero but he's claiming
it's one so it means that I'm going to
ask him you know
what it can't be if I tell him give me
both of these he also must be cheating
so I'm going tell him you know what
really this is one so in that case you
claim that both of these are one he's
like yeah or if it was an or I'm saying
oh this one so you come that one of them
is in a right he's like yeah so but but
in reality they're both zero so now what
I can say you know what okay fine I'm
going to choose one of them at random
really okay told me that this is a a one
so I'm going to he he's by by by
cheating one of them one of these have
to be a cheat so I'm going to Pro really
so show me you know show me this and
then I'll go down show me show me show
me show me and at the end he's stuck cuz
it's an input so this is a very easy
approach the problem with this approach
I lose probility half in each layer okay
because
suppose uh if it's an and let's say it's
a zero then he tells me oh uh one of
them is zeros but in reality I know
they're both one so I'm going to tell
them oh really both of them are zero
fine I'll choose one of them okay show
me this is zero but maybe this really
was the zero one and then he'll of
course cheat so I'm my finger cross this
was actually a one but only was
probability half and then every so okay
so that idea works very well it's just
the sound this is one over two to the D
so that's not good because one over two
to the D is like the size of the circuit
I need to that sucks okay no
good so what do we do so here's the
basic idea the idea say you know what
don't ask pergate per gate that's not a
good idea let's ask something about kind
of an encoding of the entire layer so
instead I'm going to have to give me
something kind of about the low degree
extension of this uh layer so I'm not
going to ask reducer tell me this tell
me this no tell me something about
this and then I'm going to argue if he
cheated here he must also cheat here
with very high
probability and now and then and and
again if he cheat here I'm going to
argue that he must cheat here with very
high probability and so on so forth but
now that that's kind of the high level
idea but now you can say whoa this is a
bit confusing before when I said oh if
he cheated here I'm going to ask him
open like cheat on one of these it's
very easy for me to check if you say is
this is zero and it's an end you're
claiming that one of this is zero but I
know one this is one so it's very easy
to argue how do I go so I I can just say
Okay prove to me that you know this is a
zero or Pro that's easy how do I go from
arguing about the low degree
extension of an element of of of a layer
to low degree extension of another layer
what do I ask you
even and it turns out that what I do
here is really low deegree extension and
some check
so I go from here to here it's just a
sum check so that's what we're going to
see
okay that's kind of the high level idea
any any
questions let me just make sure I didn't
forget to say
something okay good what's theal for the
ver good okay what we're going to get
okay goal as efficient as possible what
we get is the verifier runtime and the
communication complexity will be like d
the depth times polylog the circuit size
and the reason we we PID this depth is
because in the protocol we're going to
run D subprotocols we're going to kind
of go from a claim on layer I to another
claim of layer I and each kind of
reduction uh in in the in in the layers
is going to be kind of a subject
protocol which which will consist of log
s rounds or log s it's uh the the M the
a uh the variable is going to be log s
So eventually the runtime of the pro of
the verifier will be something like the
depth Times log the circuit size and the
ver the pro is going to run time poly in
the circuit size but we we'll we'll go
over all these parameters uh once we see
the protocol but that's what you should
that that's kind of the theorem that
we'll write when we get there great
thanks any any other questions yes so
the verifier isn't able to see the whole
circuit right like how did the verifier
get good good good good good so the
verify as I said he doesn't even he
can't even see the entire circuit all he
has is like some uniform TR machine that
generates the circuit so that's a very
good question how does how does
he we'll see it's actually it's compli
the answer is it's complicated but we'll
see we'll see as as we go along a he'll
use his kind of uniform access to to to
help him out it's really unclear how at
this
point great okay so what do we do so
first thing is uh so step one this is
just again for
Simplicity
[Music]
arithmetization so ariti all I mean here
is convert an or to kind of convert an
an to multiplication convert or into the
sum minus multiplication just convert
the the the or and an or Gates into
addition and multiplication gate okay so
step
one arithmetization
add and Mt
Gates now you're right at this point the
verifier doesn't even know he so we'll
talk about how the verifier has access
to these things later okay but like the
prover what he does at least okay the
prover first
arithmetization Gates and and Gat and
and addition Gates good now what he does
so he wants to I want to convince you
that c of X we said one so I'll make it
one what do I do I I'm the prover I take
my input
x i compute the values of all the gates
in the circuit okay so what does the
prover
do first
compute the
values of all the gates
of
C okay so now the prover computed all
these uh bits which are the values of
the gates note this is this is still
over just it's Boolean it's over kind of
gf2 yeah it's a everything is
zero1 okay next thing uh I do is I um
the prover does he computes the low
degree extension of each layer okay what
how so what are the parameters what how
do we do it there's many ways to do it
the one so so let's think of let me add
actually another assumption just for
Simplicity let's assume that the number
of gates in each layer is exactly s like
the size of the circuit I'm just
assuming that so I don't need to know
have different SES it's just going to be
annoying why can I assume that the
number of gates in each layer is exactly
s just add them get are just zero
nobody's going to look at them okay I'm
just kind of want it'll just make my
notations easy okay so now if there's
less just add zeros z z z zero so now
it's like this kind of circuit by just
adding zeros
everywhere okay good now what does the
prover do he thinks so now each each
layer consists
of s
values that's the Assumption it's that
we added demig Gates so now we have S
values per layer okay many of them can
be zero if the G if the layer was short
but there's s uh values so let's write
these Val so let's write these values
for this is for layer I let's write
these values in a hyper Cube okay so
let's write these values as kind of a
function from h to the m to
01 where
H to the m is exactly
s so we said each layer has s elements
write them in some H hyper Cube where
the size of the hyper cube is exactly s
so you can write all these elements in
the hyper cube in some order that makes
sense to you okay so if H if you want a
to take H to be 01 just take the binary
representation of like each gate the
gates are numbered uh and VI of this
number is the value of this gate in
layer
I okay so each gate in layer I uh has
kind of a number which is a number in h
to the m and this is the value of the
gate okay now what is h and what is M I
said you know it needs to be of size H
to the m b s needs H to the m needs to
be S so I have place to write all the
the a the values of the layers but which
H and which M do I choose and now
actually there's Freedom so in many
times it's easier to think like uh we're
used to Binary because we're kind of
computers uh so it's comfortable to
think of H as being 01 and M to be
logus you can think of it this way
that's fine however later like uh
probably uh uh Rachel will tell you
about it a it'll be convenient actually
actually R is like oh no what did I sign
up for it's like I'm not going to tell
you a it'll be convenient actually to
take the parameters which are H being
log
S and
M being log
s ah okay fine tried to put the same
didn't work M being log
s over log log
s so it be convenient to think of these
parameters so first just
note that log
s to the power of M which is log s over
log log
s is just log s is just 2 to the log log
s times this
thing these two cancels and therefore
you get in DS so I'm just saying these
parameters indeed if you take H to the
power of M you get S
back okay because H log s to the power
of M log s over log log s log s is like
2 to the log log s and then the two log
log s cancel and you get two to the log
s which is s so it that this is good
okay you get what you want why why what
so but you can be like why why am I
taking this setting of parameters and
you also may be kind of annoyed like why
am I why are we talking so much about
parameters this is kind of boring and I
agree however this is important because
these parameters are used a lot and for
a good reason so let me tell you why
these parameters why am I spending your
time on these parameters uh this
specific choice and the reason is that
later when we'll take extension remember
we have we take extension over a field
we'll take a big field now the
field if you remember the the subject
protocol the soundness you get is like M
* D the number of variables times the
degree over F so F needs to be of size
at least n * D okay so it will need to
be at least like this m which is if you
take like binary like 01 it'll be need
to be at least log s which is the m or
here you know the number of variables is
not constant usually and it need to be
bigger than the number of variables
and now the problem
is if you take H so okay if you take a
so what we what's very desirable in
later applications in particular for PCP
applications which we'll talk about it's
really beautiful for those who haven't
heard of what pcps are we'll learn about
it it's really really nice but for these
applications what you want is that
F the size of the extension you take is
poly in H
and now if you take H to be 01 which is
what like binary which is what we all
like then the field becomes constant
signs because it needs to be for
applications like to get the
PCP you need F if f is bigger you'll get
like a super polinomial object so to get
kind of a for later applications it's
important that the field is not too much
bigger than H that it's polom related to
H and then if you take H to be small
like constant like 01 then f is a
constant and then you don't get T
because m is not a constant to get T
bigger than one you got nothing so this
is if you didn't follow it doesn't
matter you will see it when we talk
about PCP but this is just to tell you
why I'm choosing these weird parameters
as opposed to 01 the point is that later
we'll need these parameters when we'll
talk about PCP and so that's why we're
using them now you GK itself GK itself
you don't need writing down the entire
exactly because so I exactly because in
GK it's interactive you're never writing
down the entire thing for gkr itself you
can take H to be 01 and you can take F
to be big and like the kind of
parameters you want I was actually
debating if to teach it was Z1 and then
to change all the parameters or and many
like if you look at Justin Taylor's
notes that are in the website I gave the
exact chapter then he use a 01 because
it's easier and you know uh but since
we're I'm going to change the parameters
anyway I thought I'll just start with
them and I think it's good to get
accustomed to these type of parameters
because they show up a
lot okay so this is just kind of if you
didn't follow exact Choice don't worry
about it it turns out this is the choice
I
want and why you learn about it when we
talk about
pcps but if you don't if you want to
think about H is 01 and M is log s you
can do so all the lecture everything I
say makes sense in that parameters and
you know you understand everything with
these uh parameters as well for
today
okay so good so now so now what does the
prover what will the prover do the
prover will so he has for
every for every layer he has the values
of the gates he computes the values of
the gates of that
layer which is you can think about
it as for each
layer I the prover computes VI which is
the value of all the gates in layer I so
we can think of the gates is kind of
going from H to the m to 01 each gate
has a label in h to the m because it's
kind of the same as a morphic to S so
each gate has a label here and this is
just the why the value of the gate on
input
X okay so the this is the pro I there's
no protocol yet I'm just talking about
the pro or compus before the protocol
begins
okay and now the prover can compute the
low degree
extension okay so this let me actually
be careful with room so I'll write it
here this is nothing but the low degree
EXT ion of
VI okay now we're in business once the
prover computed this then we're in good
shape so now what now let's go back to
the protocol what do they
do so as we said the
goal is to reduce so remember the first
thing the prover gave the verifier you
can think of the protocol started with
v0 which is the output layer and one
element let me call it z0 because we're
going to call them Z and z0 in you know
H to the m in this time which is kind of
actually the output layer has just one
gate right it's zero or one we we added
a bunch of zeros to it because we dummy
gates to assume that it's kind of a size
s but there's one gate this is let's
call this gate z0 and he's arguing on z0
there's a certain value v0 in our case
we said it's one so he comes with an
argument right he tells a look if you
look at the output layer this is the
output
layer if you look at the output layer
and the relevant gate and the actual
single not
gate I claim the output is v0 namely
let's say one now I say why would I
trust you and he said okay let let me
help you
here I can always add till the you know
okay so now let's see what is v0 Tilda
on any element Z what is this value
remember this is the output yeah so it
is
what and what I'm saying here is
actually General even let's think of I
like layer I okay you can think of layer
zero if you want but any layer take any
layer and take any Z even in the
extension in F to the N here it happened
to be that the z0 was actually kind of
in the extension even because we started
with a certain gate but let's kind of
think of it more broadly because later
we'll go to we'll be in the extension so
I have the the prover claims that this
is VI we start with i equals
zero I don't know if that's true I want
to reduce it to a claim about layer i+
one one layer down how do I do that what
is VI Tilda and Z zi in general is in
the extension in in this case it's not
but in general it's in an extension so
first thing let me move the I not to the
extension so what let's let's remember
what is VI Tilda VI Tilda is
some a VI that kind of the original VI
and H let me make sure I'm consistent
with my notation so I won't confuse
myself
um okay and point p in H to the
m times this Kai
P of Z I just I just kind of uh right so
what is the low degree extension of V
it's the vi on every Point not in the
extension in the cube in h to the m
times this kind of Kai
function you know which was this oh I
erased it but it's the oh yeah this
multiplication each one of them was this
degree hus one function
okay but what is a what is vi
vi you can e we can e relate it to the
layer one below VI is either an ad gate
or multiplication gate if it's an ad
gate it's an add of two elements below
and if it's a mul a multiplication of
two elements below so now to to connect
it to the layer below and this is goes
to the question of what does the
verifier know it doesn't know what I'm
going to use is the circuit has so the
circuit is associated for every I with
an add
function and a multiplication function
and this function goes from 01 to
the I guess 3 log
s to
01 and it just says whether there's you
take a gate in layer I in two gates in
layer I + one and it checks whether
there's an add there okay so it takes
kind of i j and k and it says one if and
only
if gate
I oh sorry I is
taken what notation did I use a okay H
sorry it takes
a gate P W1 and
W2 in in in s you know one of the gates
and it outputs one if and only if gate
p in layer
I is a
add of
gates W1 and
W2 in layer I +
1 and zero
otherwise uh I I start with zero and I
go down to
D yeah and zero
otherwise okay so just check if there's
an and there if there's an add there and
mult is exactly the same Mal checks if
there's a multiplication gate okay so
malt also takes p a point p in layer I
two points in layer I plus one and it
outputs one if and only if this gate p
in layer I is actually a mult gate a
multiplication gate and it connects to
Gates W1 W2 in layer I I
+1 okay okay so what is this now we can
say this is nothing but sum of
P let's sum over all the possible W1 and
W2 all the gates in the layer below and
see maybe it adds so let's if it's if
there's add if add i p W1 W2 if that's
one then you have v i then VP is just VI
W1 plus VI I
W2 if again if p is an is a is an ad
gate if it's not ad gate you'll get a
zero so you're not adding anything if it
happens to be an ad gate then what the
value of this gate is just the sum of
the values of the gates
below if VP if p is not an add gate all
this is zero I didn't do anything
because I multiply by add which is
zero
okay
plus some plus
uh let me just open plus m
i p W1
W2 if it's a multiplication
gate and let's say it's connected to W1
W2 I'm still in the sum then what do I
do then what's the value of of
VIP I mean VI in point
P exactly VI on point W1 times because
it's a multiplication gate
VI in W2 ah sorry plus one thank you
thank
you yes great
good and all of this times this uh
polinomial k p of
Z good
okay so now where are we we want to
prove something about layer
I right we but we managed to write it as
sum of elements in layer I + one that's
great that's really what we wanted we
went one layer
down okay but so okay and
well
note this is really similar to a su Che
what do we have here we want to prove
that VI so I want to tell the the prover
prove to me that instead of he claims VI
is this value I'm like I don't know what
this value is prove to me that VI is
equal to the
sum so prove to me that VI is equal to
something about the layer
below how does they prove that something
is equal to the sum sum check right
okay so do the subject protocol and now
you're saying wait but where's the
polinomial ah no problem everything's
over H ofm look at the
extensions this is already polinomial we
don't care about that's
good look at the
extensions okay we have a low degree
extension up
here any polinomial can be
extended look at the extension
okay so now we want to argue that VI
equals the sum this entire thing this
entire thing I argue is a low degree
polinomial why is this a low degree
polinomial let's see first of all it's a
polinomial over H to the 3M because M
here and two W's here so we're talking
about three M variables but m is small
this is good m is s over log log s so
that's that's
good what about here what are so let's
first look at the degree the degree of
these things it's the low degree
extension it's h minus one of each one
okay because I'm really taking each one
is H each add everything is kind of oh
add is even better because we did zero
one so add is even better uh you could
you could
do oh sorry
uh now can I take it
back I also want to do add in
h everything is in I I made a mistake I
put0 one but I need to be consistent if
I'm an H I'm an H so H to the everything
is an
H so everything here is degree H minus
one so good so so it's more than hus one
because I have your multiplication dou 1
appears here W1 appears here uh so it's
going to be degree 2 hus1 fine but hus
one is small it's like log so two logs
so the degree is small the number of
variables small perfect just do some
check so now you're asking what is the
gkr protocol sum check that's it okay
you start with with
v0 you tell them do su check convert it
to a a uh convert this claim about the
output which the verifier has no idea
it's so far away from him he doesn't
know what said give me let's do the sum
Che protocol to reduce this claim to a
claim about some
about this thing
essentially but now this is very
confusing because what happens when we
do the sum Che protocol when we do the
sum Che protocol we reduce if you
remember let's look for a second at the
sum check here we want to prove that the
sum of of something there it's a huge
thing add V plus malt multiplication of
V all this craziness whatever low degree
is equal to Beta is equal to something
in that case
v0 we run the subject protocol at the
end the verifier needs to compute to
check in the subject protocol we assume
that the verifier has Oracle access to
the
polinomial okay but essentially he needs
to compute this function the polinomial
on some point now maybe has Oracle
access at that point great but maybe
okay but there's no Oracles in our in in
this in in gkr so what do we do now but
here's an important observation that
we'll use note yes the Prov needs the
sorry the verifier need when he verifies
the sum check he needs to compute the
polom on a single point but this point T
T1 of the TM is a random Point that's
chosen by the verifier okay when you
look what is the subject protocol the
verifier chooses a random T1 he get the
polinomial then to a random T2 and so on
so forth at the end he needs to Value F
and T1 up to TM that he
chose okay we will use
this okay so now let's see what happened
here after we did the sum check the poor
verifier needs to
compute let me again make sure I'm
consistent with my
notation good the verifier now need so
he does the sum check let's denote kind
of the the a Randomness that he used in
the sum check by
a so we started with with I let's say
that when we reached here let's say he
needs to compute a
add Tilda on z i + one because we moveed
to layer I +
one uh
0 z i +
1 1 z i + 1
2 times VI I + 1 and another end so that
was one so Z ah I don't like this
notation sorry let me change it
it's more cumbersome on the board than
in the okay let me call z0 Z1 Z2 so
suppose they do a subject protocol in
the subject it's on three M
variables so let's to not the randomness
used by the verifier and the subject
protocol by z0 Z1 Z2 each of them is in
F to the
m so now the verifier needs to compute
this function on the point Z 0 Z1 Z2
what is this function on this point it's
add
time VI +1 Tilda on
Z1 plus VI + one Tilda on
Z2 plus
malt z0 Z1
Z2 times VI +1 Z1 Tilda times VI I + 1
Z2
Tilda and then all this
times this uh ah this
Sky I'll put it here Kai P of Z of uh Z
of oh
oops sorry I missed this notation uh
this is the zi H
okay sorry okay zi is the Original Point
yeah that we started with we started a
claim about VI equals VI T of z z is a
fixed point that we started
with the randomness of the verifier in
the subject protocol I denoted by z0 Z1
Z2 these are chosen by the verifier yes
v
b yeah but yeah exactly but I'm in layer
I you're right in layer zero it's just Z
zero no no no the P
right oh I
replaced yes oh H
yesing yes yes yes yes yes the rename
you're right yes yes z uh uh z0 yes yes
you're right you're right you're right
and this is still load degree polinomial
in z z good point it's sitting H yeah
maybe I erased it but this no but I
didn't write
this below
here no but I need to
write it's like this is
uh uh
X IUS
I think yes so it's
uh a oh maybe I need to take extension
of this sorry one second this is hold
on sorry maybe I missed this let me
think because I missing the the in the
notes so hold on so here the point is
a
is eight
I think I need to take extension of this
too because the the the point here a
this is not a polinomial in
ag okay so let's let's do that carefully
sorry I missed that
so Kai is a low degree polinomial but
it's a low polom in
X it's not a l po this H okay H here is
like in the
in in in the denominator so it's not a l
degree pomal in
h sadly
but but you can extend so it's okay
don't worry so it's not low degree
polinomial however it is in you can all
we care about is
um a if we think of it as a function of
z0 of of a uh
yeah of P then we just extend EXT we
can I just want to make sure that I'm
not missing something so hold on one
second
yeah mhm okay yeah so you the way to
think about this sorry about that the
way to think about it
is to think of
this as Kai of p and
Z it's low degree in this it's not low
degree in this but you can think about
it it's in 01 you can think of Kai as
like zero it's in sorry you can think of
Kai as being in h to the m time F to the
m to whatever to a
a z
um I'm not sure how to because maybe but
I'm not sure but I mean there is there
is actually I'm going to the low degree
polinomial is is one of them so the
answer is yes there is it's the low
degree ex the
uh yeah so it's defined only an H you
can think of it as defined only this Kai
is an extension this Kai in its own is
extension what is this Kai this Kai is a
function you can okay sorry let me write
let me write it differently okay let me
fix this sorry about
that instead of this think of
Kai I'm just changing the rotation H1 up
to hm and Z which is Z1 up to
ZM okay I don't want to put it down
there they're both
here and now actually I I
don't uh okay so what are we saying
we're saying so this is the extension so
you're saying what is Kai I'll tell you
what Kai is Kai is the
extension a okay let me rewrite this
Kai Kai and H and sorry H1 up to hm Z1
up to
ZM is just multiplication of kaih Z so
it's exactly the same thing I just don't
want to put hi on the bottom like I did
before so let me put it as a variable I
didn't change anything and now this
origin what is this this is the low
degree extension of the function let me
first Define Kai and H to the 2m so Kai
is such that an H to the 2m so for every
hi I or for every H and z in h to the
m Kai HZ is equal to one if in only if H
is equal to
Z I only Define an H of them now
extended that's how I Define Kai okay
the unique low degree extension what is
exactly the extension yeah it's like
this multiplication blah blah blah I
don't want to go into
it okay but it's just a unique
extension okay so now with
that and and the reason the reason there
is a unique I actually I should say this
is a this is kind of kai1
and the reason there is a unique
extension this is kind of H1 hi
Z and the reason there is a unique
exception is from the legi interpolation
theorem okay so it's just a
multiplication of the unique kind of L
interpolation extensions so all I did
here so sorry about this but all I did
here is I changed the notation from the
h kind of as a subscript to H as input
and now I'm doing kind of I'm treating
them both symmetrically which was
important because otherwise so thank you
wow you guys are
great so now okay so now let's fix the
mistake here so this is Kai of p and
Z right p is we're summing over P but Z
is an input that's kind of the input we
started with like that's the
claim good and now but for me Kai is a
low degree polinomial already so this is
just
Kai of z0 and X I thank
you yeah I guess what I don't understand
not po the first
variable
why okay so let's look at the definition
of Kai right the definition of Kai and M
variables is just so the Kai takes two M
variables the definition two M variables
is just the multiplication I goes from 1
to M of like a Kai one on hi and Z so
now I need to Define what is Kai
one oh you're saying it's a it's two
variables it's not you're saying it's
not one variable oh or rather more like
in K1 like isn't it not a pol in hi it's
a polinomial no I want to think of it's
a polinomial in hi and z
okay Kai sorry okay maybe I didn't
understand your question kai1 is a two
variable polinomial it has two variables
so you're right it doesn't it's a it's
it's two variables not one because I
said it reduces to lrange you're saying
no lrange is one I'm thinking of it's
two that that's what you said right or
maybe I I guess my question is more
emphasizing like when you write out the
definition for K1 AR we going to get
that it's not a pol in
hi no it is it is so I I want to is
going to be a ratio of pols no no no no
no no no no no no so okay you can ask
what is exactly kaii how do or kai1 how
do it okay Kai Kai is well defined it's
just a product of Kai On's okay now you
can ask what is kai1 if you if I if you
understand what kai1 is then you
understand what Kai is because Kai is
just multiplication what is kai1 kai1 is
a byari polinomial it's defined over F
to M to F and
and how so now you're asking how is it
defined let me tell you how it's defined
an H first so if both of them it's a
first of all it's it's a polinomial it's
a two VAR polinomial so it's a
polinomial and two variables and both
its degree H minus one okay now you can
say how is it defined on H on H I'll
tell you it's one if and only if they're
equal that's how it's Define zero
otherwise so I defined it on H now you
can ask how do I Define it on F so on F
I'm going to Define it in the unique way
that extends it on on H that's how it's
going to be
defined okay that's kind of that that's
so it's Kai is a low degree Pol normal
in each and every variable that's how
before I wrote it like only n z but
that's that wasn't good because I I need
it also to be low degree on AG so yes
VOD
exactly
exactly okay okay so I I write it I I
what's important to me is that K1 is a
polinomial it's a two Vari polinomial
both of them are degree H minus one okay
so with that if we believe if yeah um
they not equal is it zero yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah so if H and z are equals one
if they're not equal zero yes
great thank you thank you guys you're
great a fantastic so now we reduced this
big sum to
this because we sum over the P so the P
becomes uh Z zero this
okay wow what's going on here what is
the proof what is the verifier supposed
to do so before he had one he need to
verify one little kind of one point in
VI
Tilda and now we needs to verify this
mess okay so
let's let's let's uh yeah deconstruct
yes sorry is the argument you like K
like z z Z1 or z i uh this is a good
sorry this is z this is the claim we ah
this is the claim we started with we
started with a claim
[Applause]
and layer I right you can think of I as
zero in the beginning but we start with
the claim that VI is equal you know the
low degree extension of layer I in point
Z this is the Z here because why why is
it the Z let's see what did we say we
said that VI we need to argue that it's
this but this is just some that's the
definition of low degree extension some
the points times
this ah let me change this to p z the Z
is fixed this is fixed this is uh from
the claim good now we say let's sum over
the P so we sum over the P the p is not
fixed it's summed over and now we say
let's instead of this like some over the
two W's with are which are the possible
kids all the possible pair of kids oh I
think I didn't say I assume that c is
fan fan in two that each gate has only
two children and that's again without L
of generality you just increase the
depth by log Factor uh so I'm assuming
uh fan fan in two so it's only two each
uh gate has either it's either an and
addition of two or multiplication of two
now what okay so this is what we get and
now when we do the sum check
protocol the p and the dou so we sum
over P W1 and w
two at the end of the day we need to
compute this Pol the ver need to compute
this polinomial instead of over some
fixed P W1 W2 it's over some I called it
Z1 z0 Z1 Z2 chosen by the verifier
that's kind of the randomness of the
verifier so P becomes z0 W1 becomes Z1
and this is
Z2 okay that's kind of the F there yeah
this very confused because then if I
isal to one
you're also using I know I know so
that's the different Z yeah I know I'm
so this these are stars
okay it's a constant it's a constant
yeah I know that sorry that's a bad
annotation on my end uh yeah uh yeah
this is yeah this is a very very
different Z it's like a totally
different animal uh uh these are random
Z's chosen by the verifier this is kind
of a you know I don't know a zar that
was fixed ahead of
time okay so okay so now the verifier
needs to verify
this yeah since fixed can't you just use
the same Kai before and put it in the
subscript of the kai so then you don't
need the extension or
whatever ER the thing is that before I
assumed that the the kai when I fixed
the H it was an H to the
m this is in the extension it's not
going to be an H to the m so I don't
think I think we should keep the two
yeah but that's a good good uh uh good
idea okay so what does the so it seems
like we had something that looked really
kind of reasonable and we ended up with
something that's horrifying so how do we
what does the verifier do now he now now
the verifier is like oh I just need to
verify that this equals some some value
that we got out of the Su protocol so we
did the Su protocol we got some value uh
whatever I don't know what to denote I'm
now scared to denote anything so this
equals something now what is he supposed
to he's supposed to verify
that what what do you do so here's the
idea and then we'll take a
break okay so he needs to verify a lot
of things first he needs to compute this
at Tilda and mult Tilda this goes back
to your question now at these are a
function of of the circuit he doesn't
have the circuit how does he compute
these attia and
multia okay turns out
actually this is sad news he actually
can't compute we don't know how to
compute he doesn't know how to compute
at Tilda and
multia okay he gets this even if he gets
this kind of uh uh uniform description
of the of the TR machine that generates
the
circuit he can't compute them okay
let's deal with that later suppose he
has Oracle access suppose someone he can
kind of there's a trusted Oracle that
lets him compute these values for now
okay in the in the paper it's called
like the barebones protocol so suppose
somehow magically he has a trusted
Oracle but only to compute ad Tilda and
mul Tilda note these are only functions
of the circuit they have nothing to do
with the claim of the Prov okay it's
just information about the circuit it's
WEA kind of uh you know uh
I mean not in the extension it's whether
you know this gate is connected by an an
to these two gates yes or no or by a
multiplication to these two gates yes or
no so it's not enough for him to compute
that he needs to compute kind of the low
degree extension of that but this is
nothing to do with the approver this is
just a function of the
circuit so suppose first so first we're
going to assume this is not without L of
jity but just for Simplicity we're going
to assume
that V can
compute fosy
can actually what we're going to do
today is we're going to show the entire
GK protocol assuming you can compute
this and then only next time we're going
to show how to compute this thing and
actually there's okay we're going to
show that next time how can how can we
help him compute it or how can he
compute in a different how do we deal
with this
issue okay but for now let's say can
compute
this then are are we so okay so the
verif is like okay let's see this I can
definitely compute that's easy okay so
the verifier the verifier can compute
this he can compute
this and what does he's left he's left
with two things he can't compute V i+
one uh a V2 line plus one and point Z1
and
Z2 okay so now how do we continue what
we're going to say is the following
suppose in this sum he was cheated
namely the vi value Vi Star is not
correct by the sum Che protocol it means
that this entire value is also not
correct with very high probability okay
I mean the probity depends on F you'll
take F large enough that you know it's
going to be with very high probability
so you're left with a a false claim now
what the verifier is going to do the
verifier is going to tell the approver
you know what tell me what these
two I you gave me something I don't know
what to do with it tell me the values
you tell me the values of of VI + one
Tilda and Z1 and
Z2 so the verify the Prov comes okay
sure vlda and I +1 and Z1 is v i + 1
star
1 and
vlda on
Z2 sorry I + 1 is V Star I + 1 2 here
are the
values now I'm the verifier oh sorry I'm
the verifier what do I do I check I
check that this uh that you know add
times the sum of these two value you
gave me plus Mal times the
multiplication of these two vales you
gave me there is equal what we got
now by the soundness of the subject
protocol we know what we got is false
it's not
true so the only way if you give me if
the prover gives the correct
thing then then he he will fail if you
give the correct thing I'll catch him
because if it gives me the correct thing
I get the True
Value but he but but I'm going to check
him against the false
value okay again what do we know he
started with a false Vi Star we did some
S Check we're left with a false we said
that this is something false because the
soundness of the sub check protocol says
if you started with a some that's false
you'll get a false claim about the F so
now I get that this thing is equal to
some beta but this beta is not
true so now I tell them okay I don't
know how to compute this thing tell me
what the V the two values in the low
degree extensions are if you tell me
this assuming I compute this atld and
mlda for now then I compute this thing
now the important thing to note that he
if this value was
false he must if he gives me the True
Values I'm going to reject them because
I'm going to compute this thing and
check if it's what he claimed it is
after the Su
protocol and because he claimed a false
value if you give me the TR thing things
I'm going to reject him so the only
thing he can do if he doesn't want to be
rejected off the bat is to give me one
of them false or both
false two
right
exactly okay so where are we what did we
do after a lot of
sweat we started with the claim on layer
ey we did manage to get down to layer I
plus one as I promised you guys here's
the price first miraculously we assume
he can compute ad Tilda and mlda on its
own assume why whatever second we got we
went from one Claim about layer I to two
claims about layer I plus one that
doesn't sound very
reassuring
exactly it's where we started like
okay this is a great time for a break