okay so uh we're going to continue our
discussion today of redistribution and
fairness remember we talked about how
most of this class was just about
efficiency and we had that that simple
measure of welfare which just adding
consumer and produce a surplus we talked
last time about why that might not be
the right measure and while how we can
actually do interpersonal comparisons in
economics how it can move beyond the
simple addition of consumer producer
Surplus to richer interpersonal
comparisons using a social welfare
function and then we talked about the
inherent Equity efficiency tradeoff we
went through a model that Illustrated
the inefficiencies that come from the
Leaky bucket and we started and you
finish in section an example how you can
put that all together how you can take
the concept of leaky bucket together
with the concept of social welfare and
use it to decide if a given
redistribution raises social welfare or
lowers it in other words is the benefit
of redistributing the P worth shrinking
the P that's what it comes down to okay
we know how to maximize the size of the
pi we learned that you know we're done
with that we're done with perfect
competition we know how to maximize the
size of the pi the question is is it
worth shrinking the pi to redistribute
the resources now what I want to talk
about today is how we do it in practice
what do we do in practice to actually
redistribute money in the US and like I
said we have two
forms two two potential leaks in the
bucket two two steps toing to
redistributing money one is to tax the
people who have the resources and the
other is to transfer money to those who
don't so I want to talk today about both
sides of that equation once again doing
what I do in about 12 lectures in 1441
in one lecture here at a very broad
level to understand how Taxation and
transfers work in our country and how in
practice we
implement the idea of of of
redistributing uh social wealth let's
start with figure 231 the figures today
all be from my textbook figure 231 shows
how we raise money in America this is a
simple pie chart so about 37% of the
money we raise in America is from
individual income taxes that's the taxes
you fire file every April 15th you
probably haven't much yet but you will
when you're grownups the next biggest is
social security
contributions these are what we call
payroll taxes these differ from income
taxes in that you don't pay it on your
income at the end of the year you pay it
on your earnings as the year goes on if
you've ever earned money you'll see
there's a line on your stub called f or
another another one called Medicare
these are our federal payroll
contributions and that is the second
biggest source of Revenue the third
biggest source of Revenue is consumption
taxes mostly state sales
taxes but also excise taxes on things
like alcohol and cigarettes that's
specific taxes on alcohol cigarettes and
gas the fourth biggest is the property
tax which is basically tax you pay on
the value of your
house uh and the fifth biggest besides
the other actually sixth biggest after
other is a corporate income tax we only
raise one in every $20 in America from
tax Incorporation
think about that look at this graph we
raise 37% for income taxes 25% Social
Security contributions 177% for
consumption taxes all taxes that fall on
the average Joe and 5% from the taxes we
raise on
corporations how should we feel about
that should that make us irate that
we're favoring corporations or not it
turns out the answer is not
obvious because to understand the answer
we need to when we talk about
taxation we need to think
about the fairness of the whole tax
system or what we call an economics the
incidence of
taxes who actually Bears the tax and it
turns out this chart is very
misleading because it turns out the
party that sends the money to the
government is not necessarily the party
that actually Bears the burden of the
tax which is sort of weird right I've
just you say well how can that be
they're sending the money to the
government and the answer is it ignores
the fact that the market reacts to
Taxation and that incidence is about who
ultimately Bears the burden after the
market has
responded so we're going to Define
economic incidence of a
tax as the difference in an individual's
resources before and after a tax is
imposed the economic incidence is not
the amount they send to the government
it's the difference in their resources
from before to after the tax is imposed
and we'll see that can end up being very
different the amount than the check they
actually write to understand
why let's look
at figure
232 figure 232 is an example of a market
the market for gas gas is a market we
have a specific excise tax on gas a
certain amount per gallon there's a
federal excise tax and States layer
excise tax on top of
that so let's start by thinking about
the market for gas Standard supply and
demand model you've got the quantity of
gas on the x- axis the price of gas on
the y- axis and this in this highly
out-of-date graph that clearly needs to
be updated I've got us selling 100
billion gallons of gas at a150 a gallon
my fantasies of past life okay so
imagine we're initially in that
equilibrium and remember that is the
equilibrium remember definition of
equilibrium that makes both producers
and consumers happy producers are
willing to sell 100 billion gallons at
$150 a gallon consumers are willing to
buy 100 billion gallons of a150 a gallon
the Market's in
equilibrium now imagine that we Levy um
a tax of 50 cents per gallon let's say
we Levy it on the producers of gas let's
say we go to the gas companies and say
look for every you rich gas companies
oil gas oil companies are making record
profits so we go to them and say you
know what you rich oil and gas companies
for every gallon of gas you sell we're
going to make you send a check for 50
cents to the government because you're
making too much money and we want to you
know tax you and but not consumers we
want to tax the greedy corporations so
we say 50 cents per gallon you have to
write a check 50 cents per gallon you
sell what does that do to our graph well
think of it from The Producers
perspective what you've done is simply
rais their marginal cost
whatever their marginal cost was before
it's now 50 cents per gallon higher
because for every gallon they produce
they have to spend 50 cents more paying
the government so that acts as a shift
inward in their supply
curve in other words the point is before
they were happy to
provide a 100 billion gallons at
a150 but now if you want to supply 150
100 billion gall balance you need to pay
them $2 why well because in this
perfectly competitive market they were
zero profit before at $150 if they're
sending 50 cents a gall on the
government they have to make $2 to be
zero profit now so this is that's what
they'd have to get so we get a shift and
supply and therefore through the
adjustment equilibrium we get a new
outcome which is we get a new
equilibrium at Point D which is since
Supply shifted
inward we get a new equilibrium with
only 90 billion gallons of gas being
sold at a price of A180 why do we get
there well it's a stand Market
adjustment we've been through already
okay and it could be dollar 80 could be
dollar you know I'm not saying this is
the definite answer but it's just an
example of how Market would adjust okay
questions about
that just an example how Market would
adjust now let's ask what is the burden
on producers what is the producer
burdened from this tax well let's just
do some simple
math the
producer
um the producer uh used to the producer
used to get a
$150
okay so they used to get a
$150 now they have to send 50 cents to
the
government but they now get A180 per
gallon so on net their burden is 20
cents that is they are bearing a burden
of 20 cents and you could see that if
you look at the graph the
producer used to get a $150 now they get
A180 so they get 30 cents more a gallon
but they have to send 50 cents to the
government so on net they're out
20 on net they're out 20 cents what's
the consumer burden well the consumer
used to
pay uh the consumer used to now now pays
A180 it used to pay consumer used to pay
$150 so their burden is 30
cents you can see that once again in the
graph consumers used to pay 150 now they
pay 180 they're not paying 30 cents more
so look at what happened who lost cost
more from this tax consumers or
producers
consumers we were trying to tax the
greedy oil companies but what did we end
up doing we ended up making consumers 30
cents worse per gallon and producers
only 20 cents worse per
gallon that is the incidence was not the
same as the amount of the check sent in
even though the producers sent in a
check for 50 cents a gallon
that was offset by the fact they're
getting 30 cents more a gallon so a net
they only were out 20 cents a gallon
even though consumers weren't touched in
theory the government said I'm not
hurting you consumers in practice
consumers were hurt because consumers
had to pay 30 cents more a gallon and
this is why a graph life figure 231
could be
misleading because think about
corporations when you tax
corporations some what's going to happen
is the rich Corporation owners will take
it but some of it is they'll pass it on
to higher prices to Consumers
so it's not like tax in corporations is
purely getting at the rich guys it's
also getting consumers it's not as easy
as that graph makes it
look
okay
now here's something to note let's note
the following interesting phenomenon
look at figure 9
imagine that we had instead of taxing
producers we tax consumers the way the
gas tax usually works right the way the
well let's say the no let's say the way
the gas tax worked is literally it's
sort of weird but the government said to
you for every gallon you buy I'm going
to make you send me 50 cents it'd be a
weird tax to think about let's imagine
way the tax worked okay is the
government said I'm going to track your
gas purchases and for every gallon you
buy I'm going to make you 70 50 cents
well now the supply curve doesn't change
marginal cost hasn't change but demand
changes consumers used to be willing to
buy 100 billion gallons of $150 but now
their marginal list to pay Falls if they
were indiffer
between paying a150 for the 100
billionth gallon now they have to send
50 cents to the government they're
paying a dollar for the billionth gallon
they're not willing to pay $150 anymore
they're only will paying a dollar why
because that last marginal consumer was
indifferent his marginal willingness to
pay for the 100 billionth gallon was a
$150 that's his total willingness to pay
said 50 cents to the government he's
only willing to pay a dollar to the gas
company to get that gallon so that's a
shift downward in the demand curve the
demand curve Shi sh down we get to New
equilibrium with a price of
a130 by the way this shift this is just
this is natural this is because the
curves are the
same what is the new producer burden did
someone tell me what's the new producer
burden what's the incidence of this even
though producer aren't sending a check
to the government what is the incidence
of this tax on producers in this
case how much worse off our producers
yeah 20 cents why
exactly same person what about consumers
how much worse offer
they
because they save 20 cents a gallon but
they send a 50 Cent check to the
government right could producers
consumers get a lower price but then
they have to send that check to the
government so they wor off 30 cents
producers who weren't involved in this
so was just tax on those greedy
consumers they're getting 20 cents less
a gallon too econom economic incidence
is not so two points here first it
hammers home the point that economic
difference is different than who sends
the check but second of all it hammers
home the point that it for a given tax
in a given Market it does not matter who
pays the tax this is a profound
insight for a given supply and demand
curve and a given total tax it doesn't
matter who sends the check
in the incident is the same that's very
profound that says it is totally
irrelevant that says politicians are
free to label a tax any way they want
but for a given market and a given size
tax consumers and producers end up in
the same position or what we say in
public finances the side of the Market's
irrelevant it doesn't matter who
actually sends the check to the
government okay what matters is how big
the taxes and what eles are of supply
and demand that's incredibly powerful
okay my guess is most of you without
spending a long time pondering it if I'd
said walking this class doesn't matter
if consumers pay the gas tax or oil
companies pay the gas tax you would have
said it does matter but it
doesn't it doesn't matter as long as the
tax is the same and the Market's the
same questions about that and I've just
blown your mind
yeah you're getting ahead of me hold on
other questions about this
yeah excellent excellent question both
great questions that lead to the next
point the next point is who Bears the
taxes who actually Bears them well that
it turns out is going to be determined
by the elasticities of these curves
let's look at figure
234 in the first case we have a case of
inelastic demand for gas this is
probably right in the very very short
run probably dayto day if the price of
gas goes up a lot people don't adjust
their consumption the next day okay so
gas is probably pretty inelastically
demanded in the short run well in that
case what happens let's say we tax
producers the first example the supply
curve shifts
up but what happens to price it goes up
by the amount of the tax why because
consumers are going to buy the same
amount of gas no matter what so you can
just charge them whatever the hell you
want
so who Bears the burden of this tax how
much is on producers and how much is on
consumers when demand is
inelastic
yeah exactly it's all on consumers flip
that around that's good good answer flip
that
around okay now imagine we're in the
very long run where people can you know
shift to bicycles and walk and demand
for gas is super elastic in fact let's
imagine it's perfectly elastic not true
but let's imagine it now what happens
well we tax the
producers but they can't raise the price
because demand's perfectly
elastic so now who Bears the burden of
the
taxes the
producer the consumer doesn't bear
because if the producer tries to pass
one sent on them they'll just stop
buying
gas so the producer has to Bear it all
so what determines who Bears the taxes
is
elasticities and basically the bottom
line is those who
are the most elastic will be the best at
avoiding taxes this is not the right
intuition but here's how I think about
it I think of like negotiating power
think about there's this tax and
consumers are produc and negotiating
who's going to Bear it well if consumers
are perfectly elastic they're like you
know [ __ ] you I'm not going to Bear it
you try to give me any I'm gone but iFly
inelastic produc is like I'm sticking
you with it and I know you're going to
take it because you have no choice your
demand's perfectly in elastic yeah
excellent question we're going to come
back to that the way we think of
incidents is the reason we think about
is the change in price the reason we use
price and we don't pay attention to the
x-axis at all is another way ask your
question is we're thinking about an
incremental infinitesimally small change
so X wouldn't change okay I mean X would
change basically X does change let me go
back let me say this differently we're
focusing on incidents because
basically the fairness aspect Yeah
scratch my first answer here's a better
answer in both equilibriums before and
after the tax everyone is perfectly
happy with where they are so it's not
about efficiency you're an efficient
outcome before or after okay it's about
fairness and fairness about who's paying
more before after so not a great answer
but that's the way to think about it
okay but it leads to the next section
I'm going to teach okay other questions
about
that okay so elasticity determines who
Bears the
burden okay so here's a great example of
that let me ask a hard question see if
you guys get that get
this cities Levy taxes on hotels on
hotel rooms when you go to a hotel room
in a big city there's a city tax on that
hotel
room that tax and hotels rooms is born
as you could now know be partially by
the hotels and partially by the
consumers of hotel
rooms after Airbnb came
along how did that shift the burden of
that tax so there's taxes on hotels whoa
okay how did it shift the burden of the
tax
because exactly what airbn D did was
make consumer demand for hotels more
elastic when consumer demands for hotels
more elastic producers couldn't pass the
tax onto them as much so producers had
to Bear more of it that's an example how
this matters in the real world and
there's evidence of
that okay so this isn't just saying you
know a different question I could ask is
well what happens when Airbnb comes in
hotel price will have to fall that's a
different
question okay this question is what
happens the effect of attacks on hotels
and the answer is it's borne more by
hotels and less by consumers because
consumers look more like the second
panel of figure 234 and less like the
first panel
so basically the more elastic consumers
become the more they can avoid taxes the
less elastic the more they'll be stuck
with
them okay now that's fairness but let me
come to this great question over here
which is okay that's just about prices
what about profits what about
quantities well that comes to the SEC
back to our original concept which is
efficiency which is now let's talk talk
about the efficient aspect of taxes I
misspoke I said you wasn't that they're
efficient in both outcomes they're an
equilibrium in both outcomes let's come
to the efficiency of
Taxation now let's look at a tax now
let's go back to figure to our original
t figure 235 goes back to our original
tax on
producers of 50 cents a gallon same
thing initially equilibrium at P1
q1 now you get new equilibrium at P1 at
P2 Q2 to A180 90 billion
gallons what about efficiency well
efficiency is what has happened to the
social surplus fairness about division
of so social surplus and that's why I
just focused on prices efficiency is
about the size of the social surplus and
now we focus on
quantities well what's happened to the
size of the social surplus well it used
to
be if you look at it consumers used to
have the consumer surplus
of the area above the 150 Price Line and
below the blue demand line producers
used have producer Surplus the area
below the $150 Price Line and above the
blue supply line now the quantity is
shrunk we've
reduced consumer
surplus and as a result and we've
reduced we've reduced consumer surplus
and producer Surplus Now consumer
surplus is just the amount
above the $180 line
line and below the demand curve producer
Surplus is just the amount
above below the dollar 80 line and above
the red supply curve both consumer
producer Surplus have shrunk and we've
created a dead weight
loss so there's an efficiency cost to
taxation this is the source of the leak
in the
bucket I talked about it last time more
casually I talked about why or I talked
a couple Le about why we care about
moral hazard why we care that there's
people are for example not working or
here it's why do we care about the Lost
gallons of gas we care about the Lost
gallons of gas because that's a cost to
society there are 10 billion gallons of
gas that were being sold before in in
trades that make both parties happen
those trades have
disappeared we have created an
inefficiency by tax in the gas
market that is the dead weight loss of
Taxation and that's the leak in the
bucket the leak in the bucket from
taxing
things is equal to the dead weight loss
of Taxation that's the that's the first
leak that's the tax
leak the tax
leak is the dead weight loss of Taxation
the inefficiency we've
created by taxing
Goods now here's the mind-blowing part
look at figure
236 now I ask now I take a gas market
with more and less I don't do perfectly
imperfectly elastic and elastic I do
sort of more or more realistically more
or less elastic look what happens to the
dead weight loss when demand for gas is
very
inelastic the dead weight loss is much
smaller than when the demand for gas is
very
elastic indeed if the demand for gas
were perfectly inelastic there'd be Zero
inefficiency from tax
why why would taxes not be inefficient
at all if deo's in elastic
yeah because there's no changeing
consumers are going to buy there's no
trades that aren't being made you're
screwing consumers that's the fairness
part but there's no efficiency loss
there's no trade that's not being
made as a result the more elastic demand
gets the bigger the efficiency cost gets
because more and more trades are being
blocked from
happening okay so basically we get this
interesting
contrast which is that as elasticities
go up as as elasticities of demand go up
on the one hand consumers Escape
taxation right on the other hand their
escaping the taxation is what creates
inefficiency in dead weight loss
once again sort of an equity efficiency
tradeoff right the most the fairest
taxes the taxes which if we if we
consider ourselves as consumers we care
about ourselves as consumers the fairest
taxes are the taxes on Goods which are
most elastically demanded because we
don't have to bear them but they're also
the most distortionary taxes the tax
that create the biggest leak in the
bucket another way of thinking about
this Equity efficiency tradeoff the more
elastic is
demand the more consumers avoid taxes
but the more inefficiencies you'll cost
okay questions about
that
yeah well um let me ask the question
differently look at figure
23 uh 4 A first panel here's another way
to ask your question why aren't they
charging
Infinity in it's in elastic
demand why aren't they charging Infinity
it's another version of your question
the answer is that there's always
external pressure on producers why don't
monopolis charge Infinity because
ultimately there's external pressure now
in this
case the reason they're not charging
Infinity is because at some point people
will start to drop
out okay so your answer is why don't
they just shift it more well sure but
then why aren't they charging more
today they could always charge the
answer is there's other Market forces
constraining them why isn't Apple
charging us more for the iPhone well
because the Android exists people prefer
the iPhone but Apple's clearly decided
that if it was two grand in iPhone
people would just switch too much to
Androids they're already making a good
ungodly profit why not more because
they've reached some point where they've
decided it's the alone Point okay so
basically the key point is Market power
doesn't necessarily mean you could do
what you want but this does raise the
interesting issue which is beyond this
class but if you take 1420 industrial
organization which is a lot of people
claim that during this inflationary
period part of what has driven inflation
is firms increasing their profit margins
now you might say well look why would
firms if firms could have increased
their profit margin before they would
have why are they doing it now and the
answer is sort of in this question which
is a little bit hidden now prices are
going up anyway so they can blame the
war or the president whoever they want
to
blame okay so it's a good time to raise
their profit margin because prices are
up if five years ago when inflation was
Zero if they rais their prop Mar
everyone would notice is hey why is Coke
more expensive but now Coke's getting
way more expensive if you make it even a
dollar more expensive you'll think well
that's just
inflation so actually it becomes it sort
of an answer your questions in the real
world opportunities like taxation or
inflation are often opportunities
companies use to sort of raat of profit
margins but not in our more simple
models
okay other
questions
okay that's the tax side of it now let's
talk about the transfer side of it so
that's the first leak the first leak is
the dead weight loss caused by
taxation the second leak second leak in
the bucket is the inefficiencies the
dead weight loss caused by transfers
okay so now let's go to figure
237 237 is the figure we had last time
that showed the leaks in the bucket the
tar part of the remember the red the
black line is your old budget constraint
before the government came in remember
the program we're transferring money to
people who were poor pay for by tax on
those who are
richer the tax led to the W shifted red
budget line to the left of the diagram
and we Now understand why that caused
inefficiency people work less less is
produced in society that's a dead weight
loss what about the part if we transfer
well here we see the in efficiency right
away which is all those people who at
least were working some now don't work
at all basically if we set up a welfare
program like this there is if you are
anyone who wanted to work less than 250
hours
then literally there's 100% tax rate on
your work why work you're going to get
the same amount of money whether you
work or not because every dollar you're
Inn there going to take a dollar away
remember the transfer formula was the
transfer we gave you was the max of zero
or your income minus
5,000 what that means every dollar of
income you earn we take a dollar away of
the
transfer no no no I'm sorry 5,000 minus
your income I that backwards 5,000 minus
your income
right so it's like a 100% tax on income
every dollar you earn we take a dollar
away so why work that is the transfer
side of the Leaky
bucket that people quit
working so now the question is what can
we do about it and governments recognize
this problem so here you're a
government and you want to redistribute
from the rich to the poor and let's even
solve the tax Problem by finding
inelastic sources of in elastic markets
to tax so you've even you've reduced so
for example a very inelastic Market to
tax is property people's houses are
there so let's say you're taxing
property that's pretty inelastic you
don't create a dead weight loss tax side
but now you want to say I'm creating all
this dead weight loss on the transfer
side because I'm causing all these loan
people just quit work because why
work how can I deal with that well
there's two ways governments deal with
that problem in
reality the first way they deal with it
is through what we call categorical
welfare categorical welfare we give cash
not to
everyone but to people who meet certain
criteria so for example we have in the
US the tanif program temporary Aid to
needy families that is money for poor
single moms so it's not just being poor
but you have to also be a single mom we
have our biggest cash trans program to
the US to the poor people it's called
SSI subal security income that's for
poor disabled people you have to be poor
and
disabled why do we do categoric
transfers because we're trying to take
advantage of
targeting we're trying to take advantage
of
targeting obviously we want to give
money to low-income people those people
who need it we talked about how any
sensible social welfare function would
deliver distribution to low-income
people the problem is in giving to them
we make this huge leak in the
bucket what if how we could give it to
them without creating a leak in the
bucket think about a simple
example imagine that there's two reasons
people are low
income they're unskilled and they're
lazy okay now we would like to protect
the unskilled from behind the AV behind
your born you don't know if you're going
be skilled or unskilled SK so we'd like
to all have a system that protects the
unskilled we're not sure we want to
protect the lazy they should probably
work okay let's say we're all born with
a irremovable tattoo on our head IR
removable and inadible you can't add it
that says
unskilled or
skilled well then we simply say I'm
going to look at your tattoo if your
tattoo says unskilled I'm going to give
you money say skilled I'm not going to I
don't care what your income is because I
know you can make a good living if
you're not doing so it just means you're
lazy then we'd have no dead weight
loss because why because you couldn't
change dead weight loss is created by
what people changing their behavior to
avoid taxation well if it's based on a
tattoo it's on your head when you're
born you can't change your behavior
unless parents can like do in vitro
tattoo tattooing or something okay you
can't change your behavior so there's no
dead weight loss it's in elastic the
supply of unskilled tattoos is in
elastic there's no dead weight loss so
if we could simply know
who was truly in need and who wasn't
really need they were just quitting
their job we could redistribute without
dead weight loss problem is we don't
probably a good thing that we don't okay
we don't have to get to debate between
my daughter and myself on tattoos that's
for another day okay but what we do know
is things which are
correlated with your underlying skill
regardless of your work effort okay so
let let take something like
blindness especially you know genetic
blindness you're born
blind well that's pretty much like being
born with unskilled stamped on your head
now to be fair many blind people succeed
enormously blind students at MIT will go
on to incredibly fruitful careers but
it's true that if you're blind you're
most likely very needy of
help then we'd say we give to blind
people by making it
categorical we're able to try to Target
the benefits without creating deadweight
loss okay that's why have disability
single moms well basically as long as
single moms didn't sort of choose to be
single moms they just got stuck with a
kid because their you know their partner
left them or something like that then
it's going to be really hard to work we
know they're needy someone's got to keep
an eye on the kid they can't work
without child care so that's another
indicator of needing
help now that one is
but that's a little tricky because is it
something people can change with their
behavior well of course people can
choose to become single
moms so it's not like genetic blindness
which isn't Changed by your behavior
single motherhood is potentially Changed
by your behavior so now we start to get
in a murky
realm of is it a good idea to Target
benefits to single moms or in fact as
many conservatives claimed back in the
1980s when this sort of became a major
topic of discussion are we actually
making Society worse by creating single
moms are we actually making things worse
by targeting benefit single moms
actually creating single motherhood in
America okay and indeed there was a very
famous book that was written in
1984 okay that looked at a simple graph
of the generosity of welfare and single
motherhood so this is
time and this is like
1960 and this is like 1980 which is when
their data end ended and if this was the
generosity of welfare benefits welfare
was getting more
generous and this is single motherhood
single motherhood was was going
up so it was like look by making W for
generous we're encouraging single
mothers we're not rewarding those who
need it we're encouraging them the
problem is this is what's happened
since okay it turns out through Decades
of careful study single motherhood has
almost nothing to do with welfare
benefits basically people don't decide
to become single mothers based on cash
concerns it's based on other concerns in
their life so it turns out the
inefficiency of targeting money to
single moms is low because what drives
that inefficiency what drives it is the
elasticity of single motherhood with
respect to
welfare that's the key parameter that's
the key elasticity that drives the dead
weight loss the more elastic single
motherhood is with respect to welfare
The More inefficiency We Get By
targeting single motherhood but it turns
out this is approximately zero so it
turns out this is a pretty good way to
Target
people here's what's
ironic you might say well look it's
uncontroversial Single Moms is
controversial targeting disabled is
uncontroversial turns out you'd have
that
backwards turns out the
elasticity of claiming SSI with respect
to welfare benefits is greater than
zero because as I mentioned type of
workers comp it is hard to monitor
whether people are truly
disabled and it turns out the more
generous you make disability benefits
the more people claim SSI the more the
more people claim uh that there's
disabled so now so here's here's the way
to think about it let's go back to our
Equity efficiency tradeoff with single
mothers there's no equity efficiency
trade-off they are a poor group and by
giving the money you don't create dead
weight loss with disabled people there
is an equity efficiency trade-off which
is there are poor people but you create
deadweight loss by giving them money so
for this one you don't even need a
social welfare function you're done for
this one you need a social welfare
function decide if it's worth it to
decide if the dead weight loss you're
creating how it compares to the benefits
you're getting from giving money to poor
needy people okay questions about
that so that's one way we deal with this
inefficiency this Deb we loss the other
way is by changing the way we pay
benefits and making them in
kind okay the the problem with cash
transfer systems is Everyone likes cash
so it creates a maximum incentive to
distort your behavior to qualify well
what if instead of cash I gave you a
shitty public apartment with leaking
roof and it's just sort of bad
neighborhood and stuff like that well
then maybe people wouldn't who didn't
really need it wouldn't change their
behavior to get it maybe only people
would take that but people who really
need
it so maybe we don't need to have you T
tattooed on your forehead maybe we can
get you to reveal whether you truly need
help or Not by giving you something
that's not so
great it's sort of a perverse
logic but the logic is the way we get
people to reveal whether they're truly
needy by giving them something only
truly needy people would want which is a
crappy
apartment okay and this is a major
reason why we deliver most of the
benefits to the poor on an in kind
basis most the there about a 10 to one
ratio in the US of the benefits we give
to the poor through things like Medical
Care and housing and food to what we
give them in cash about a 10 to1 ratio
okay we give much more in Goods now part
of the reason is the theory I just gave
you part of the reason is because we're
paternalistic as Society you remember
way back in like the third lecture I
talked about food stamps and how to be
more efficient to give people cash but
we don't think they'll spend it on
cocaine okay that's the main reason we
do Inc benefits realistically is because
we don't trust people to spend their
money but there's an economic Logic for
it which is that it's a way to get
people to reveal their types when you
can't really know who should be targeted
and who shouldn't
okay once again the tradeoff we'd love
to give everyone nice Apartments but in
doing so we create a huge dead weight
loss of people quitting their jobs to
get the nice Apartments so it's a
trade-off now once again this is the
Dismal science and all I do is talk
about tradeoffs all day so let me
actually end the lecture on a positive
note which is there's actually one
program that's not a tradeoff there's
actually one program we've discovered
which actually redistributes money and
increases efficiency and that's what we
call
conditional cash
transfers which is money we give to
people conditional on them doing
efficient
activities the classic example in the US
is called the Earned Income Tax
Credit the earn income tax credit is a
way W subsidy program it's a wage
subsidy what does that mean it's the
opposite of a
tax the earning of tax credit is such
that for every for the whenever you earn
money the government said taking some
away will match it as long as you're
poor so if we look at figure
238 this shows how the income tax credit
works on the x-axis is earned
income on the Y axis is the amount of
the eitc you get what you see is if you
earn no money you get nothing from the
government of this program but as you
earn money until you make
14,800 for every dollar you earn the
government gives you another 40 cents so
the first $115,000 you earn you get
another 40 cents from the government
it's a negative tax at that point it
caps out the biggest checking it is 5920
and then they start to take it away
why because they want they don't want
this money to go to everyone they want
to go to low income so by the time your
income is 47,000 you're
done so the idea is targeted to
low-income
groups so you give these loow people
money but then as their income goes up
you take it back
away
now the important point to know about
this program is it's not all obvious
what this program will
do okay think about someone
who if you think about someone who's
below
14800 the effect of the program is
obvious take someone's earning
zero what is the income effect on them
of this program well it's zero they were
earning zero What's the substitution
effect it's massively positive their
wage has gone from X to x x
1.4 so for someone earning zero the
effect is unambiguously
positive okay but now now let's imagine
someone earning um $1
19,35 and they're thinking about should
I earn $100 more so they're at
19350 they're getting their check from
the
government of
5920 and now they're saying should I
earn $100 more what happens they $100
more well they get the $100 check but
they lose
$21 of their 5920 their 5920 goes down
by
$21 so they end up only at
$58.99 why because we're taking it back
away as they earn money so effectively
we are taxing
them so now we've created a new tax
we're trying to help poor people but in
doing so afraid of a new tax why because
we want to keep it to poor people then
we do that take it away as people's
income goes
up so effect this program is ambiguous
on the one hand you take the guys who
weren't working at all and give them big
money to go to work but in order to
phase that out you tax the people
already working and make them less
likely to work assuming substitution
effects dominant income
effects okay people understand that
questions about that yeah
oh well we have separate taxes for the
Richer people this is just a don't think
of this as a tax think of as a targeting
mechanism we're trying to Target to
low-income people the way we target
low-income people is by taking away
their income goes up we don't think we
don't think anyone over 47440 deserves
this lowincome transfer so we're taking
away by the time you get there you don't
get anymore we have separate taxs on
Rich guys this is just this program per
se good question other questions
yeah what's
that oh because for every $100 you earn
you lose 21 cents you lose 21 cents per
dollar on that
slope okay other questions
yeah you could flatten it okay what
would happen then well one good thing
and one bad thing the good thing is
there'd be a lower tax rate the bad
thing is if we don't think people will
need above 47440 need this money we're
giving money away to people who don't
need it because it' go out to like
60,000 now so the trade-off is you could
also get rid of the slope you could keep
it there but then Bill Gates gets the
check
5920 okay the point is if you want this
to Lo comp people you have to phase it
out now we can argue what the right
phase out is you can always argue about
these numbers and one awes thing about
working in government is literally
people in government get to just come up
with these numbers I mean how cool is
that you get to come up with how much M
people are going to get in their lives
okay so there's lots of fights of what
these numbers should be but the bottom
line is just structure you need if you
want a program that's targeted you need
this structure so here's the tradeoff we
encourage people at the bottom of the
income distribution to go to work but we
discourage people in that middle part of
the income distribution from
working well guess what we can go to the
evidence and evaluate that and guess
what we learn the first thing we learn
is the first effect is huge the earn
income tax credit has a huge effect in
encouraging people to
work okay um best estimates are that
basically if you take especially single
moms there's something like a 15%
increase in the odds they work I mean
huge the odds that they
work and there is no evidence that it
causes people on that other part to work
less so there's good evidence takes the
zero people and brings them in the labor
market there's no evidence that takes
the 19,000 people and cause them to work
less why is that well there's two
possible
reasons one is remember for the zero
people the effect is unambiguous zero
income effect positive substitution
effect for these people the effect is
ambiguous we talked about that with
labor supply income substitution effects
here you have a substitution effect
saying you work less okay but the income
effect might go the other way actually
no let me go back that's wrong because
remember they do have more income they
deal more income the income saying work
less substitution effects working less
so that can't explain it they're richer
no I had it right let me go back I had
it right on the margin for that
next100 there's substitution effect
they're getting $21 poorer which should
make them take less Leisure and work
more but they're only taking home 79
cents on the dollar which has subs
effect makes them work less so it's
ambiguous so on the one hand you have an
unambiguous effect taking people from
zero to working an ambiguous effect
here that could be why we don't see a
difference but here's why we don't see
difference really people don't
understand it's super complic if I say
to you hey guess what used to get X
going to work I get X plus a big check
I'll go to work if you say well on the
margin if you work one more hour your
income goes down by 21 cents I mean
you're MIT students and you didn't quite
understand
it okay so the answer is I think my
theory it's not good evence this is that
basically this effect this effect is so
subtle and complicated that people don't
pay attention whereas the you get a big
new check if you go to work effect
people pay attention to I'm not saying
that's been proven that's my
theory the bottom line is it doesn't
matter what the theory is this is a
win-win this is a program which is
redistributing people money to the
needest people in society it's about a
something like oh God I forget something
like an 80 billion dollar a year program
it's $80 billion dollar going to the
poorest member of society and it's
increasing work it's increasing work
it's increasing efficiency so that's a
win-win program
okay this is not just in America Mexico
a great example a wonderful example the
president of Mexico had a good buddy who
was a sociologist who knew a lot of
economics who convinced him to set up a
program where they give money to mothers
only if their kids got their
immunizations you know sorry sorry RFK
got their immunizations and were
enrolled in school and guess what it had
a huge effect on improving kids outcomes
even their incomes later in life sadly
the current president in Mexico got rid
of it but this was an incredibly
successful program these conditional
cash TR programs have success been
successful all over the world and that's
a way we can solve the Leaky bucket it's
a positive story for our government
policy can do better anyway I'll stop
there I'll see you all on Wednesday