good morning everyone welcome to today's
MPG primer and also welcome back to MPG
after the lovely and all still cold and
snowy fall uh winter break so Dr Hillary
fukin is a distinguished statistical
geneticist renowned for her Innovative
work in understanding the genetic basis
of complex traits and diseases Hillary
is an assistant professor at Harvard
Medical School and Massachusetts General
Hospital as well as an associate member
of the broo in
Institute Hillary earned her PhD in
Applied Mathematics at
Mat did I say MIT I don't know what I
said before where she was supported by a
prestigious Herz Foundation Fellowship
Hillary also holds a Masters of Science
in theoretical computer science from The
wisman Institute of Science and a
Bachelor of Arts and Mathematics from
Harvard among her many honors she is a
recipient of the National Institutes of
Health director's early Independence
award the fukan lab develops and applies
novel statistical and computational
methods to integrate genetic molecular
and functional data to elucidate how
genetic variation contributes to disease
risk and thereby enance our
understanding of human health and
disease Hillary has said that you can
take um questions she'll take questions
throughout the talk and also what's
really interesting about her talk today
it's going to be a chalk talk um so this
is something we're kind of demoing out
with Hillary and if if please give us
your feedback um after the talk or later
in the year about what you thought of
this different way to engage with the
material all right take it away Hillary
thanks so much Nico
um all
right um hi everyone I'm looking forward
to uh uh trying out this uh talk format
um and is there could we do the screen
awesome okay great um so um my plan
today is not to go deep on any one topic
I think most everything that I'm going
to touch on there's a separate primer
that actually goes deep but my goal
instead is to kind of give an overview
that shows how these different things
are connected and um is kind of like a
framework that and my experience has
really helped clarify some things that
feel like they're really sticky
technical stuff when actually if you
kind of back up and write down the model
then things uh tend to make a lot more
sense um and so what are oh and and like
Nicole said please do ask questions even
if it's just like oh I didn't understand
can you say that again I think this
group is um small enough that that you
can just raise your hand and ask um okay
so what are we going to talk about today
um so today what we're going to talk
about is what are uses of
models of the
form y i = Su over J and S x i j beta J
plus Epsilon I
where Yi is the
phenotype of an
individual I um x i j is the
genotype of individual I
at a variant
J um beta J is the
effect
size
variant
j s is a set
of variance and Epsilon I is a
residual one thing I like about Chalk
Talks by the way is they take the pace
down a little bit and then that gives
everybody a chance to kind of think
about what it is that they find uh
confusing um so first I'm going to make
one um note about this so and that's
that this crucially this is kind of one
of the main punchlines of today this
depends on the set s so if we're going
to write down a linear model so so to
give kind of an overview of what I'm
about to say this kind of model shows up
in a lot of places so if s just has one
snip and you're fitting a like one model
separately for every single snip um then
beta J this is no sampling noise no
error anything the true beta J that
you're trying to estimate is the
marginal effect size um and so for
example if snip J is an LD with some
other snip and that other snip is causal
and snip J is not causal the true beta
is still going to be nonzero on the
other hand if you have a really dense
set of snips that's got every possible
variant in some Locus uh then you can
under you know some extra assumptions
start to interpret beta J as true causal
effect sizes um maybe you're doing
polygenic risk uh prediction using a
model that's something like this uh
which uh how how you choose to um
incorporate effect sizes is going to
depend a lot on whether you've LD pruned
for example or have not LD pruned um so
uh what this model is telling us and
specifically what the effect sizes in
the model are is going to entirely
depend on what set we put there because
um these are joint joint effect sizes um
I'm also going to put a couple of
assumptions down um yeah or notes I
guess
um so I'm only going to talk today about
um quantitative traits so you can think
of height as an example um a lot of the
methods that work for quantitative
traits really directly carry over to
disease um and other case control traits
uh this um I have come to appreciate
that this is in some ways specific to
this thing where we're working with uh
um common diseases and complex traits
because our effect sizes tend to be
pretty small and so a lot of you know
there have been some derivations of why
it's okay to pretend like our binary
traits are continuous um and usually
there's a a tailor approximation that
works really well um somewhere in there
and tailor approximations work really
well when your effect sizes are really
small so that's kind of intuitively why
I'm going to only talk about
quantitative traits but why basically
every method I'm going to write down has
been applied very successfully um for
case control traits um and then the
other thing is just for Simplicity I'm
going to Omit covariates
um uh in practice when this uh um
actually gets used then you know there's
a bunch of Co variates here um age and
sex and an An ancestry and so forth um
but just for Simplicity I'm not going to
write those down okay um so my plan is
um to talk about there's five more
panels on this board I'm going to talk
about five uh uh instantiations of this
model um to kind of emphasize the
differences and how um this exact same
basic equation can be useful for all of
these different things okay so to start
with let's talk about um
basic Association
mapping IE i e
g um okay so what's the goal here as I
said earlier the goal is not to identify
the causal variance the goal is to
identify regions of the genome that are
associated to a phenotype um so let me
write that down
identify
regions of the genome
Associated
typ and what's our particular
instantiation of this model um well as I
said before there's no summation we're
just going to say x i j beta J um plus
Epsilon I um and there's going to be a
different model for every snip um and
what are we interested in when we do
this
uh so you can think of this is
um when we fit this model what is the
thing that we actually care about and
that we want to be well calibrated um
and for the most part what we care about
is um a P value for the null
hypothesis the beta J is zero um and so
the intuition there is
um is there a causal variant
n
LD
with variant
J
um we also are often
um uh uh interested in in um uh
estimates of the marginal effect size of
SJ um so let me see if there's any other
notes about that yeah so I think that
that's um in a gwas what we do is we go
one step at a time we fit this model um
and then we look for for p values that
are significant after multiple testing
um one thing that I'll mention is that
the set of um results from a gwas are
often referred to as summary statistics
I'll come back to this later in the talk
but a lot of the methods that we're
using for fine mapping or for
heritability estimation of various sorts
or for risk prediction can be done using
um summary statistics um that's right
okay so now let's talk about
methods and there's two uh two general
categories of methods here in one case
we have uh actually I'm going to make
this the vector
Epsilon so and
so I haven't um specifically talked
about what the distribution of this
residual is and in the simplest case
we're just going to assume that it's IID
normal for all individuals so this is
kind of this most standard linear
regression that you could do um in this
case we'll just do ordinary least
squares um and then there's another
family of
methods in which you make a different
assumption now you have two components
um um so if we want to instead assume
that our residuals can be correlated
across individuals and that those
correlations are reflected in a
relatedness matrix then now we're
talking about um um linear mixed models
and there's been a whole lot of work on
linear mixed models and um how to uh
first of all estimate these parameters
then how to estimate the parameters in a
way that uh increases your power and
then how to estimate them in a
computationally efficient way so this is
kind of an interesting subfield because
the problem gets so much harder once you
make it complicated in this way um so
that's all I'm going to say about jwas
um for for this per for these purposes
um and maybe I'll pause before I move on
to um the next section and ask if
there's any questions so
far
yes yeah so there's been a lot of work
on that one common thing to do is
inverse rank transform it um where I
guess there's a couple of ways to think
about this one way to think about it is
that there's some true underlying
heritable trait that's normally
distribut and that that got
monotonically transformed to give you
some weird distribution and so then you
can recover this original uh you know
maximally heritable trait by um just
using the ranks and forcing it to be
normally distributed um and I think that
that has been um surprisingly successful
in a lot of cases even though it's like
a pretty strong assumption um but a lot
of folks you know uh will look at the
data take logs remove outliers um the
kind of stuff that I think is pretty
standard linear models there has been
some work so um several years back uh
there was some work by Nicolo fousy at
Microsoft research learning the
underlying monotonic transformation that
maximized the heritability um which I
thought was kind of an interesting way
to think about it um so yeah but I think
that there this intuition that
um well okay and also I guess if we're
going to move Beyond quantitative to you
know um case control or count or ordinal
or that kind of thing then there's you
know um a large family of methods for
dealing dealing with that kind of thing
as well
yeah awesome all right so next I'm going
to talk about Let me give this a box so
that it stands
out so next I'm going to talk about fine
mapping and what is our goal when we're
fine mapping now we actually want to
identify the causal variance
um to go back to this for a second this
is kind of Genius right like it's saying
we're going to start with a problem
that's an easier problem to solve that
can be solved with a simpler statistical
method and then it's really uh uh
robust when we're trying to estimate
these marginal um these marginal
Association statistics
uh we um you know the result for one for
one snip it doesn't depend on the other
Snips and empirically it's been true
that we've been able to replicate
results from one study in another study
um uh quite reliably so this now is like
this Rock Solid it's it's more or less a
solved problem how we do uh basic
Association mapping um and the reason
that it's so thoroughly established and
so reliable um is because we're not
trying to identify the causal variance
yet we've we've set for ourselves a goal
that can be solved um by fitting one SNP
at a time um and we've gotten really
good at that as a field I mean um but
now we want to identify the causal
variant this is the more interesting
goal and it is way way way harder okay
so why is it way harder
um what's the model that we're
fitting the model that we're fitting
now so this looks very similar but now
um what we have is uh
so dense is the key word here
um ah right right right at
Locus um so now what we're going to do
is we're going to um specify one Locus
we're now again we're not going to fit
one model for the entire genome because
we don't need to do that here instead
we're going to choose a at which there's
an association we think that there is a
causal variant somewhere here we want to
know which one is the causal variant so
we're going to um fit a model just at
that Locus um how you define loai that
can be a bit of a thing I won't go into
that um and now what we're going to do
is we're going to have as dense as
possible a set of variants at that Locus
because in order to have the
interpretation that we want um which is
that beta J is the true causal effect
size there's a number of assumptions
that have to be satisfied and one of
them is the true causal variant has to
be one of the ones that we included in
our model um
and so uh uh let's
see so
um um
okay so what are we interested
in usually we're now going to think
about this in evasion framework because
the kind of an intuitive thing to think
about is that we want to know what the
probability is that beta J is not zero
given all of our data so we want to know
what's the probability that um
um that the true underlying causal
effect is nonzero I.E you know that this
variant is a causal variant and
um so why is this difficult one reason
this is difficult is because of LD um if
you have two Snips that are in perfect
LD then you uh there's no way to have um
total confidence that one of them is
causal and not the other one um you just
can't it is the same information encoded
twice you can't you can't disentangle
that um it's nice in that case to be
beijan because then you can say if I
think only one of them is uh causal if
you're prior in code some kind of
sparsity then your posterior
probabilities will be close to 5050 for
the two variants that are in perfect LD
um and um there have been other folks
who have thought about this from a
frequentist point of view thinking about
sets of snips um that are likely to
contain a causal snip um which is also a
useful framework but a lot of the
methods that are most commonly used
right now are ban um so let's talk about
methods and this again I think is the
topic of an entire primer so I won't
spend too much time on it um but I will
say say that there's
um uh several families of methods and
I'll I'll write down some
classifications so one is um single
causal variant um
methods so this is the exception to what
I was just saying if you're willing to
assume that there's only one causal
variant in the locus then everything
gets really easy um and I won't do the
derivation on the board but you can
write down you know you're now looking
for a posterior uh over
uh size of s configurations so you're
just ch there's s possible outcomes
because you know exactly one of these
variants is causal because that's what
you assumed and now you just need to
know what the posterior probability is
of each of those um each of those
outcomes uh so things are super easy in
that case um the problem is once you get
into multiple causal
variants uh and of course the Trey part
is we know that there are multiple
causal variants at a very large number
of rosi it's very nice and convenient
that we can do one causal variant uh
fine mapping but that uh loses a lot
because we know that the assumption is
violated in a lot of cases um so now
let's try to make some more realistic
assumptions let's say that we want to
have multiple causal variants um so this
is where things get really tricky right
um if you wanted to say um I'm not going
to put any restriction on the number of
causal variants I'm going to put some
kind of Prior on the probability that
you know that a variant is causal and
then I'm going to do exact basian
inference that then the number of of
states in your prior now is going to be
exponential in the size of s because
there's any possible subset of s could
be your set of causal variant and now
you need to get posteriors for every
possible subset of s so um exact basent
inference um
is uh very challenging uh
computationally so I'm going to say
exact evasion inference is
hard you know folks who do this kind of
thing really hate discreet uh uh uh
spaces and this
is very as discreet as they come okay so
what are some solutions that people have
done um one thing that folks have done
so this was mostly in the early days is
um just to restrict the problem to
restrict um uh both the size of s and
also restrict um the number of causal
variants so we're not going to say one
causal variant we're going to say three
causal variants which already actually
that that helps a lot um but the reason
that this uh can be tricky is because if
you're still going to do you know exact
enumeration of all possible
configurations then you need to make S
really small the reason that that's
tough is because if you um uh uh in your
model you leave out a causal variant
that has LD to the variants that are in
your model then that's a really bad
model
violation so what are some other things
that people have done um
one thing that people have done uh is
really uh uh I'll say like
explore a
subset of the posterior
space there's been so so now we get into
like really smart and creative things
that a lot of people have done um in
previous years in a lot of different
groups so one thing has been to do um uh
deterministic search algorithms to try
to find the configurations of causal
variant that cover most most of the
posterior probability but are of a
tractable size there's also been
stochastic versions of that um uh uh
using Randomness in order to um uh uh
design an algorithm that also is
exploring the sets the you know the
large subsets of the posterior
probability and so we're not trying now
to um accurately write down the
posterior probability of every very
unlikely configuration we only care
about the most likely ones and we have
some kind of um handle on how we might
go about finding the most likely
configurations um then another thing
that uh we might want to do is
um uh uh conditional
analysis so I guess I should have uh put
put this
above because this is also um before we
get into um large scale proximate
Invasion algorithms uh conditional
analysis can be we assume that uh the
most significant uh uh snip reflects one
causal variant and then once we
condition on that then we can f map the
next one um and there's other ways that
folks have tried to split into
signals so maybe we have a Locus maybe
we think the locus has multiple causal
variants but we think there's literally
enough LD among the different causal
variants that we're going to be able to
take the locus split it up into you know
in some way that's informed by the data
um split it up into different signals
and apply our fine mapping for the to
each of the different um signals and
then the last one that I'll write is uh
iterative conditional
analysis which turns out to be
conditional analysis which turns out to
be equivalent to variational
inference um where your variational
assumption now is independence of the
locations of each of the causal Snips um
rather than independence of each of the
beta JS um
and so that's kind of a some of the
different ways that different folks have
um uh solved this problem where you want
to get a basian posterior you want the
basian posterior to be to allow for the
possibility of multiple causal variants
um but you don't want to enumerate two
to the S possible
configurations um and I'm not writing
down specific um references here um I
think this one was caviar this is uh dap
G or also fine map um this is
conditional analysis and this one is
Suzie um and the exact references are in
notes that I'll post online if anybody's
interested um and so then what are some
other uh uh approaches that folks have
taken to this kind of in combination
with one or two um one is to incorporate
functional data
incorporate uh functional data so here
maybe what we want to do is um say that
well we know that coding variants are
more likely to be causal than non-coding
variants or we know that uh conserved
variants are more likely to be causal
than um unconserved variants and so it
would be stupid to just throw that
information away so we've got to
incorporate it in the form of a prior so
that we wind up getting posteriors that
reflect that um that fact and
um what's interesting there is well
exactly how much should you upweight
coding variants compared to non-coding
variant
you could kind of subjectively say well
my prior is you know five or 10 or
whatever or uh there have been a couple
of different algorithms for using the
data either in the locus itself or
across manyi to inform what the relative
weights should be of these variants and
um that have these different properties
um and then the other um the last thing
that I'll write is just that cross
population analysis can be complicated
here
um so uh and that's because uh well for
a couple of different reasons one is a
lot of the analyses um uh are most
easily done by splitting apart um the
summary statistics from the LD um and
the LD can be different in different
populations and so you have to be a
little bit thoughtful when you um do
that kind of analysis and there's been
some um uh methods development work in a
couple of different places
uh trying to do that in as rigorous as
possible a way um uh and it seems like
it really does give uh a big boost for
power when that can be done successfully
can I ask a question Hillary what do you
think is more powerful incorporating
more diversity of people in your gws or
just increasing the end of your
homogeneous population yeah I think
that's a great question I think that in
theory if we had perfect methods then um
diversity uh well okay I guess it's a
trade-off right like just you know it
depends a lot on where you are and
actually um a Pap paper from Hong's
group um I think I think if I
remembering right it has some figures
about exactly that question like at what
point does it become a better idea to
switch from just increasing your sample
size to increasing your diversity
because if you've got a really small
sample size and if it's too diverse um
ancestrally to be able to do a good job
of um accounting for ancestry uh and
potential confounding my ancestry
then you're really in trouble right so I
think that um uh yeah and we've seen
examples before of data sets where
because um they're studying some
molecular phenotype um the sample sizes
are much smaller uh but then if you um
don't yet have the methods to account
for the confounding that you might see
then that can create problems on the
other hand if you can choose between two
big gwas of the same ancestry or two gws
of different ancestries then the fact
that you've got this different LD really
helps break down you know this main
challenge of mapping which is that LD
makes it difficult and so I think that
we need the statistical methods so that
the answer is always diversity and I
don't think our statistical methods are
quite there yet so I don't think that's
always
answer
yeah
yeah yeah thanks but originally how do
you define it is like you have a jwa
signal and you say okay I just take um I
don't know 100kb on both sides or you
use LD or like what is the I guess the
easiest is by size but I feel it's not
the smartest way so I was wondering what
the state-of-the-art way to do it would
be yeah yeah that's a good question so I
think different folks have done this
differently one way that you can do it
is
um uh so one way you can do it is by LD
that is computationally intensive um one
argument for doing it by size is if you
do it by size and you do it big enough
um then if you've got your Locus that
you're fine mapping right here and now
you include everything um that could
plausibly be an LD with it um then maybe
that'll be tricky you know if you're
trying to interpret really strong
signals out at the edges of your of your
Locus but really what you care about is
what right what's what's in the middle
and so you'll get much more accurate
results for the middle as long as your
Locus includes the things that are in LD
with the the locus that you most care
about um but I think um I'm trying to
think if I've can think of any
references off the top of my head for
yeah yeah no but I think people have
done it in both ways
yeah
yeah that point it will be a tradeoff
right because at some point if you
include too many sleeps you might have
might be violating the single causal
variant uh hypothesis right so
definitely yeah single causal variant F
mapping on really large low s i I agree
would would be
fraud the might
the reason why I'm just running around
is just for the people online it's a
little bit it can be hard to hear so
there's mics up here or I can get more
exercise this
morning
great
um so one other thing that I'll say um
uh that my group has done some work on
is once you start to you know if you say
okay I've got my model I've got the data
uh I've got my inference algorithm and
I'm going to get a posterior that's one
thing if you say I have some intuition
for what I want to be able to do but now
what I actually have access to is
summary statistics from a meta analysis
um then the number of you know we're
always making assumptions we're always
violating the assumptions it turns out
that the assumptions that you're
violating when you find map um from
summary statistics from a meta analysis
can sometimes be so bad that you wind up
getting really unreliable results um so
when you're doing basion inference you
know a lot of times the initial
derivation will be I'm going to say I
have all of my y's I have all of my x's
and now I'm going to get a posterior
conditioned on y and x and then um you
can uh do derivations showing that well
actually everything only depends on X
transpose x and x transpose Y which are
closely related to summary statistics in
LD and so now my math says I can use
summary statistics in LD and then you
make a huge leap to say I don't actually
have the exact LD Matrix from my
specific set of genotypes I have a
reference panel and um when I talk about
heritability I'll I'll say why that
sometimes works in the case of
heritability for fine mapping um uh you
know uh many different Works including
works from our group but also um from
other folks have shown that that can um
really um uh cause issues with fine
mapping and um when you're doing a meta
analysis then on top of that often you
have um several different LD matrices
from several different cohorts none of
which you have access to um and then
once you combine that with you know
other types of heterogeneity where
you've got different genotyping and
different cohorts and different utation
panels um then the set of complications
that you're brushing under the rug
becomes um problematically large even
though there's always complications that
we have to you know brush under the rug
to do inference under any
model um so that's one thing that I'll
say is uh doing this from summary
statistics can be um um difficult if the
summary statistics are not exactly
derived from your
cohort okay
so now I'll go over here oh and I will
quickly talk about heritability okay
sorry that was that was my bad the
clock's been there the whole time okay
so um I'm going to talk about
heritability
heritability um based
analyses so this covers all three of
these so there's um basic heritability
estimation credability
estimation genetic
correlation and um partition terit
ability and the reason that I'm writing
them all under the same category is
because they use the same s basically um
and so in particular here um what we've
got is uh again some over J and S x i j
beta
J Epsilon I and this time
s is a sentinel call this
parability
um and what we're interested in so this
is the
model we're interested
in is what is the variance of uh I'll
call it
g so if we say that this is a genetic
component um due to genotype Snips plus
some residual that has all the rest of
the genetics that's not tagged by
genotyped Snips like ultra rare variants
or things like that plus all the
environmental components then snip parit
ability is asking how much of the
variation in the phenotype What
proportion of that variation can be
explained by genotype Snips and one in
intuition for what this quantity is that
we're trying to estimate is if some
Oracle told me what the true betas were
then what's the best possible prediction
r squared that I could get if all I have
access to is a set of genotype Snips um
so one thing that I'll notice the betas
here aren't actually that interesting
they're not marginal they're also not
causal the the set of snips is not
particularly dense um and so um this is
this is good because it means that we
can now start to do genome wide modeling
and genom wide modeling is good because
now we can estimate this quantity that
we care about which is just the total
amount of variation that's explained by
the set of snips it also allows us to do
genomewide estimation of genetic
correlation which is a closely related
model and also of partitioned
heritability where we want to know
what's the what's the contrib for
example of snips in brain enhancers
genomewide and now there's no particular
Locus that we care about so much that we
want to throw all of our computational
resources into you know fitting some
really dense set of snips um but we also
don't want to just do marginal marginal
um analysis and so instead there's kind
of this uh intermediate thing where the
betas themselves are not that
interesting but the model as a whole is
still going to allow us to estimate um
these genome wide quantities that are
really interesting um and so um with
genetic correlation um maybe I won't
write down well yeah no I think I have
time okay so with genetic correlation
what we want to know is um so the
goal
is how much
do these
two traits
have
shared basis
and the model that we're going to write
now is um just an I
here we now have two phenotypes we have
y i a and we have y i so this might be I
don't know your your height and your BMI
or something like that um and now this
is going to
be and we have um phenotype specific
effect sizes of course because that's
what we got to have
um and so if we call this for example
GI um B then now we can say what we want
to know
is what's the correlation
between the genetic component for
phenotype a the genetic component for
phenotype B um um
and when
so uh yeah so for partition heritability
the goal
is
explained
set
of snips and so for example if this set
of snips is all of the Snips that lie
within 100 KB of the of a gene that's
highly expressed in a certain tissue
then this type of analysis being able to
um estimate this type of heritability
can start to tell you about which
tissues are most relevant for particular
phenotypes um from their genetic signal
um and
so uh here one the model that we're
fitting is to now start to break up um
this genetic term into multiple genetic
terms so you can say
uh y I
be and so if we call
this then interested in
so out of all of the genetic signal What
proportion is explained by this set of
snips which as I said you know you'll
choose to be some interesting set of
snips where you care about how important
they are for the phenotype um and so
then to talk about methods so now I'm
going to talk about methods for all
three
because the methods are are are shared
uh in general when someone develops a
method for one of them then you can kind
of apply them to apply the method to
solve these different ones and
so the most
um most of the methods assume that beta
Is Random so they add an extra layer to
this model where they say beta is drawn
from some distribution and now we're
going to um relate what we are estim to
properties of the distribution of B beta
um which I won't go into much more
detail about but I'll just say um once
you say beta is random then you can say
either I am going to
require
um full genotype and phenotype
information genotype information or just
do summary
statistics and we can make like a table
here um where now the rows of the table
are going to be I want to do something
that's likelihood
based or I want to do something that's
moments
bean and it turns out so we've got
gcta we've got H
regression and this is uh not
comprehensive of course H
regression and then this older method B
slmm and over
here uh the last time I gave this talk
there wasn't a method in this uh slot
but now there is
ldsc and RSS so there's lots of
different methods for solving this kind
of large family of problems um but for a
lot of them you can think of what kind
of data are we requiring and then are we
going to uh do something that's full
likelihood based based only on moments
or Vision um and there can be advantages
and disadvantages of each of those
different um uh uh different approaches
and this all assumes that beta Is Random
so then separately there is some work
trying to actually solve it for when
beta is fixed which uh makes it a little
trickier in a lot of ways um and so the
main method that I know that goes on
turn that category is the method um so
then if we want to come back and say
uh why does all of this matter for for
example risk prediction so a lot of
times with risk
prediction what you want to do is write
down a linear model that looks a lot
like the model that we're writing down
over and over and over again um and then
you want to include some estimates of
beta and I think that for example if
you're trying to decide whether the LD
prune or not um well if you got your
estimates of beta from a model that's
different for every snip um then um in
order for that to make sense in the
context of a larger model where you're
summing across Snips then you need to
show that it's okay to plug in you know
these um uh marginal effects into what's
effectively a joint model for um risk
prediction that turns out to be okay
only if there's um no LD among the
different Snips um but a lot of if
you're interested in for example
cross-population risk prediction um then
now the question of whether you're
interpreting your betas as true causal
betas or marginal betas or betas that
are somewhere in between you know they
uh they're not true causal betas they
include some effect from the tagged uh
uh Snips that are not included in the
model so marginal anything that's not
truly causal is going to be influenced
by the LD patterns of the population so
if you're trying to do cross-population
risk prediction just as an example
application um then you have to think
really carefully about whether the true
underlying betas um are they causal in
which case you can assume they're the
same across um populations pretty safely
um with a uh depending on how you're
scaling or uh when you say beta do you
actually mean um some combination of
effects of variants that are tagged in
which case now the true betas are going
to vary across population because LD and
AAL frequency vary across population um
so sometimes it can just be helpful to
think carefully about I'm going to write
down this linear model and now I'm going
to think carefully about uh what the
even before I start estimating anything
I just need to think about what the beta
itself means in that model now we can
start estimating and you know worrying
about power and noise and bias and so
forth um but sometimes even just
starting before you do all of that with
saying when I say beta what do I mean um
can be really helpful so I'm going to
stop there and I am happy to take two
minutes of
questions for the genetic correlation is
the assumption that you have the full
set of traits associated with each
phenotype because if you if you see that
there's one shared variant but you don't
know about 50 other different variants
you wouldn't you think that they're
perfectly correlated these two traits
wait so can you can you say that again
you're wondering if there's if you like
do gwas on two traits and you see
there's one Locus that's shared well for
yeah maybe I'm misunderstanding the
model but if you have one shared variant
between two traits but that there's 50
different variants between the traits
that you don't know about you might
think that your traits are perfectly
generically correlated oh I see what
you're saying so I think that in that
case you would get something that's not
a perfect correlation because a lot of
your betas would be zero here um right
so like you can imagine you've got uh
like beta a and beta B and maybe you've
got something where you've got like a a
shared maybe it has the same effect size
for the two variants but then you've got
I'm just going to use ones and zeros
you've got a bunch of ones and zeros
here and then you've got a bunch of ones
and zeros here um so that uh this Cor is
going to be really far from one and when
you start like uh when you plug this
into this and you get this then the
correlation is going to be far from one
in the case you don't know those other
you
only yeah yeah so this gets again at the
difference between what we're trying to
estimate and what we are estimating so I
think you'll agree what we're trying to
estimate is um uh is definitely far from
zero um the methods for doing this um
don't Begin by looking only at
genomewide significant Losi so they
actually do incorporate uh uh data
genomewide rather whether or not the um
the locus has reached genomewide
significance and so then I I guess I
really haven't gone into any detail
about this but once you write down you
know let's say our model is that um um
uh the ordered pair beta ja beta JB um
is drawn IID from some byari normal
distribution where the IID is over Snips
J and now we want to infer
um parameters of that distribution so
you can um start with that as your model
and then derive uh properties of the
distribution of X and Y that let you
then do you know valid inference on the
properties of beta to begin
with I think with that we're out of time
but I'm sure Hillary could take a few
questions afterwards um so let's thank
her one more time