Hi everyone, my name is Ruiz, the
founder and CEO of Ocadian. We
revolutionize workplace safety health
with predictive voice AI, saving
hundreds of thousands of lives and
millions of
dollars. In the movie Adestra, the
captain undergo regular voice assessment
to evaluate fatigue and readiness before
every high-risk space operations.
Imagine applying this technology into
real world workplaces where fatigue and
impairments causes injuries, accidents
and billions in losses every
year. This is no longer just a sci-fi.
We're building this future with a
world-class team with expertise in
speech technology, machine learning and
occupational health. We're bringing top
expertise from MIT and Harvard
commercialization experience of
translational voice bark research and
deep industry experience in safety and
compliance of the heavy industry. We're
the first one to apply this clinical
grade technology into the industrial
setting. Workforce fatigue is highly
prevent but still under addressed. Every
year in industry like transportation,
mining, construction and aviation,
fatigue contributes to more than 140
billion economic losses and over 100,000
accidents every
year. Today, many industries still rely
on
self-reporting. Sensor based solutions
and machine based testing and safety
cameras in the driving scenarios provide
real-time detections of behavior cues.
But it's not
enough. Effective solution must focus on
some prevention beyond real-time
detection. And current solutions also
are intrusive and
effective. We're driving this paradigm
shift with
predictive predictive fatigue risk
management. We build this future with
voice biomarker and circadian science.
And here comes Volcadian.
We're building this voice AI powered B2B
SAS platform for predictive fatiguity
management. Workers conduct short speech
assessments just in just 30 seconds
before their regular
shifts. Our AI will assess fatigue,
predict the risk and inform managers to
optimize schedules and test dispatch and
take personalized
interventions. all happened without any
intrusive
monitoring or extra
hardware. This is just not just a
theory. Since launching, we've been
working with industryleading customers
in transportation, trucking and heavy
industries. We have we have done
commercial pilots in both Latin America
and
US and also secure insurance partnership
in work compensation and liability. Our
early pilots show promising outcomes
with 90% model performance in
sensitivity and specificity compared to
the industry standard PVT test. In
average, we our pilot shows 26% risk
fatigue related risk incidence reduction
and a 92% productivity uplift by
streamlined mobile solutions. This saves
every worker in average six hours per
week. Our solution is unique,
preventative, hardware free, timesaving,
and we designed a product that align the
incentives between employees and
employers. We mitigate risk before the
risk
occurs. We're targeting the market in
LAM and US with plan for global
expansion. And we see this is a growing
trend with increasing market demand for
proactive safety
solutions. Our goto market is twofold.
We sell directly to safety high safety
sensitive risk uh organizations through
a tiered per user per monthbased
software subscription. We also works
with channel partners licensing to
insurance who offer premu to their cover
comp portfolio companies who adopt
vocadian and we work with safety
technology providers and vendors through
API integration and technology
integration. Fatigue is just starting
point with the expanding capability of
voice barker. Our goal is to address a
comprehensive occupational impairment
risk including alcohol substance and
down the road in insurance analytics
with also with dise occupational
disease. Today we're are looking for
partner industry partners if your
organization having raising concern of
fatigue risk and embracing predictive
management solutions.
if you're in the uh geography of LATAM
US and we're looking for PC and pilot
opportunities to see how we can
help with your with your partnership
from adra reality. We we think we can
make this come
true. We aim to redefine the safety and
health standards worldwide with you
together. Thank you.
Thank you, Hu.