I'm excited to talk about this project
today um so as was mentioned in the
introduction our lab you know we have so
one thing we we sort of the name of the
lab we say is the Alo bio lab which
comes from this algorithmic lens on
biology business and we've done a lot of
work um in the past that has been
related to more more directly related to
this business of using an algorithmic
lens on biology and what we mean by that
is sort of taking lessons from the
limits of algorithms in particular the
application of certain types of
algorithms to the study of very
organized but high-dimensional systems
uh to rethink sort of the limits of
biological experimentation and and
experimental design and in particular
that's that's manifested in a number of
different ways but especially in this
line of work that is on these compressed
experiments um so I think when or
originally invited me he thought I might
talk about compressed perturb seek for
example and I'm not talking about
compressed perturb seek and there's a
reason I'm not talking about compressed
perturb seek okay so one is that I've
talked about it for eight years that's
actually probably the main internal
reason but that's a selfish reason and
my my style of talking is as soon as we
have something interesting to say I like
to go talk about it so that's thing
number one um to note about this talk is
this is all unpublished relatively early
stage work so we're very excited to to
hear your feedback on it um you know
which may include the usual simultaneous
feedback of this is wrong and this is
Trivial and already known so I would
love to hear um any of those comments
that you have but no seriously we do
want to hear your feedback and we're
excited to talk about it um but a little
bit more on the motivation for this work
so our previous line of stuff on um
these compressed experiments what those
really have been about and it's okay if
you're not familiar with the work I I'll
give you the gist um the idea is that
you know when we're doing sort of high
throughput and high content biological
experiments um oftentimes they cost a
lot of money but it turns out to be very
sort of um useful to get lots of Rich
data from lots of different types of
pertubations or many different
conditions or many different samples or
whatever and that's manifest in 10,000
papers a year now with ever bigger
scales of data and ever bigger
models so these are expensive but yet it
seems good to have lots of data there's
a line of statistical work a bunch of
different sort of threads going in
parallel but most famously um a line of
work in statistics and the development
of algorithms on something called
compressed sensing which has interesting
things to say about studying
high-dimensional signals um with small
amounts of data when you have prior
knowledge that the high dimensional
signal is very very structured okay and
in particular the the the idea is if
there's certain types of statistical
structure like sparcity or low rank
frankness or so some covariant structure
in your high-dimensional data then you
can collect what seems to be a
fantastically too small amount of data
and then use algorithms that can exploit
that statistical structure to recover a
much larger number of parameters than
you have any business recovering from
having only done this much work okay so
like I said we've explored that general
idea in half a dozen or so papers most
recently with this thing called
compressed perturb seek which again I'm
not talking about even though I actually
am talking about it right now okay but
the the point there is that our lab is
generally interested in in basic forms
of biological organization really trying
to understand the nature of organization
and if such things exist fundamental
units of organization at the level of
single cells and tissues so we want to
know what these things are many other
people are interested in similar
questions that line of work on
compressed experiment says we don't
really know what the underlying things
are I don't know what the under lying
biophysical mechanisms are but the last
20 or 30 or 300 years of doing biology
has taught us something exists okay
there is organization it's not all
20,000 genes operating independent of
each other or all the proteins or all
the uh metabolic fluxes or what have you
but there seems to be quite a lot of
organization we may not have pinned down
the exact biophysical mechanisms but
what I do know is that from the last
years maybe 10 to 20 years especially
where we collect a lot of data what we
always see are statistical patterns that
manifest from whatever those underlying
units of biological organization are
like if you collect a big Matrix of gene
expression data there's always a lot of
correlation patterns usually there's
some low rank decomposition that
captures most of the variance in the
data and so on so somehow there's
underlying biophysical mechanisms that
organize this high-dimensional system
that manifest in statistical parameters
and this line of compressed work says
aha there are these statistical
properties in our data we know how to
exploit that to collect almost
exponentially less data um in the lab
but still recover a large amount of
information so that's the background is
that we're generally interested in basic
units or the nature of organization at
the level of single cells and tissues
and we've done a lot of work that says
it exists here's an interesting thing to
note about your experiments that we have
a very strong statistical formalism of
how we can exploit that to spend fewer
dollars and fewer labor hours and
whatnot in the lab okay this project is
now getting back to the main question
what are the things what are the actual
units of
organization
and it's a problem that as I said many
people are interested in there's a whole
lot of work out there that collects a
lot of data we can focus on Gene EXP
expression collects a lot of for example
gene expression data and does something
to look for like latent factors and say
here are something that looks like a
program a gene expression program or
here's something that looks like a
pathway or here's a set of units whose
Collective activity can describe sort of
the the um you know all of what's going
on inside of a single cell or inside of
a tissue or whatever and um that's great
but the problem with that is
um discovering these biophysical
mechanisms is not in the domain of
Statistics okay so that's like if I have
this mic you know this I'll drop a mic
or something that that should be an
indictment of like a large field and I
don't know you know I've contributed to
that bad behavior quite a lot um but you
know I don't know if anyone yeah
please so you described this as a bad
behavior and I do agree that um
statistics is not maybe going to
discover the biophysical model but
wouldn't it propose new hypothesis for
perhaps there is some sort of
interaction between these two things go
test it out with um biop physical models
or experiments um so are they really
like is there no contribution I guess
from the statistical side no there
definitely is so you know there's a role
of finding patterns in developing new
hypotheses and trying to understand what
might be going on and finding new
threads to pull on but the problem is
that the things that we find um should
not be sort of privileged units right um
think about the most basic form we are
going to do a principal component
analysis of some gene expression data
set and then try and interpret the
things as like programs or Pathways or
something what's the problem with that
the problem with that is if I collect a
new data set I'm not going to find the
same thing so it's a little bit hard for
me to claim that those are the actual
units moreover there is it turn turns
out more than one way to look for
statistical patterns in a data set in
fact the number of ways that there are
is infinite and so if I tell you that I
have infinitely many ways to find a
fundamental unit of organization doesn't
seem so meaningful anymore so I agree
that there's a role for statistics and a
role for collecting a large amount of
data when we have no sort of existing
notion of what we're looking for we need
to just go do exploratory analysis and
in fact in data we're getting way off
track here by the way um no you you're
completely fine um uh uh mostly I'm just
off in the weeds um uh there in fact
data science um is a necessary part of
biology um because the phenomenon that
we're studying are a product of complex
historical processes there's I need to
write this up at some point but there's
a there's in fact a kinship between data
science and cosmology among the Natural
Sciences because the things we're
studying require some sort of
exploratory analysis we can't just
reason about them in the abstract
because they're the result of sort of
these random and complex historical
processes so we actually have to go
observe things in the world we can't
just come up with the answers um from
sitting on a mountain for 10 years um so
anyway so there is a role for data
science but but in the end discovering
these basic units of organization inside
cells and tissues is not in the domain
of Statistics okay so that's the that's
the 45 minute or however long I've taken
um introduction to what is the purpose
of this project the purpose of this
project is to take a different Tack and
to directly from the bottom up try and
derive a theory of something like a um
uh what a basic unit of organization is
or how something like a biological
process a fundamental unit of
organization within a cell could arise
out of evolutionary Dynamics or out of a
selective process okay so that's my
motivation for what this project is
about when Aiden gives his talk he's
going to give a much better motivation
this is the dumb motivation that is
internal basically to uh to me and to
our group about like our path of why we
started investigating this so the title
of the talk is about genotype to
phenotype mapping and so on and and
again Aiden's going to give you a much
more generalizable and overall better um
motivation for um the work that he's
going to present present but I just
wanted to give you a little bit of extra
context that there internally it came
from our basically anxiety uh about the
state of the world where many people
seem to be interested in what these
basic units of organization are but the
dominant mode of interrogation I believe
has little hope of succeeding on its own
that it needs a a very sharp shift or a
very heavy dose of bottom up and
theoretical approaches to actually tell
us the types of things that we might be
looking for okay there we go that's the
introduction so um again yes it's Alex
blel nice to see you um hi Alex hi um I
I just wonder um there's a hypothesis
underlying your motivation which is sort
of that that that there really is such a
modularity uh in some in some underlying
fundamental way um rather than like you
know a massive irreducible complexity
and of course we all hope that otherwise
like what are we doing anyway but um do
you have anything to say about that um
so we don't know for sure that it's
going to exist I'll grant you that what
we can say is again from like 20 years
of collecting lots of data there sure
seems to be a lot of statistical
organization and um you know one very
obvious way for those statistical
patterns to arise is because there's
underlying biophysical organization so
again with that I don't think that that
quite proves that there is this sort of
physical modularity um but I don't
really know how to explain the
statistical modularity other than
through those physical mechanisms does
that make sense it yes and I think there
are also potentially evolutionary
genetics reasons why that that could
motivate it but that's another for
another time but yes I I completely
agree and what we're going to arrive at
today is not um a full decomposition of
the activity at the cell what we're
going to arrive at today is basically
like one unit how do we how does one
process arise specifically a metabolic
process today is going to be a
discussion of a theory of how something
we are calling a collective mode but you
can think of as a metabolic process
arises um so we're baby steps baby steps
Alex great no examples are where it's at
it's perfect
okay
okay um very good so I'm mostly going to
go on the board today um and if um
feeling the need later I have a couple
slides to illustrate a couple points so
what we want to do the more
generalizable version of the
introduction and the motivation to this
talk is that we're interested in
studying non-trivial genotype to
phenotype Maps Okay like many people in
the world um and we want sort of a
mathematically tractable problem as I
said um part of our initial motivation
is to develop a theory of how something
like a process or a unit of organization
arises so we're going to be doing some
math so we need to live in a world of
somewhere we need to find a a
non-trivial um uh genotype to phenotype
map in a space that's mathematically
tractable one of the spaces um that sort
of fits these goals is in the analysis
of metabolic reaction networks so we're
going to be talking about evolution in
the space of metabolic reaction networks
and like I said how something like a
metabolic process um might arise or a
basic unit of um a metabolic reaction
flux Network might arise so um the rest
of the primer now um you know well I
can't make any promises that I won't
ramble on any other tangents but the
rest of the primer is intended to be um
giving you background on these metabolic
reaction networks and then we're going
to move into I'll set up the the general
framing of of what they are the
mathematical framing of something called
flux balance analysis which is usually
formulated as a constrained optimization
problem linear program to do our sort of
theory we need to analyze the basic
mathematical framework of flux balance
analysis a little bit differently for
those who are familiar with convex
optimization we're going to look at the
Duel of the Primal program so I'm going
to talk a little bit about Duality um
and then if I have time left at the end
to do our um especially evolutionary
simulations that Aiden is going to talk
about we have a little bit of teeny
little bit of Pop gen that I'll I'll
throw in if I have time at the end okay
so let's launch into it here um we're
the the first thing to discuss um is uh
genome scale metabolic
models okay and I put a genome scale in
parentheses in there because there's
there's sort of a a whole field out
there of doing this metabolic um uh
network analysis and and when um they
want to apply it to actual living
organisms one of the first tasks is to
try and reconstruct the metabolic
Network for a given organism and they
call that a genome scale model for our
purposes it doesn't particularly matter
we're not looking at a general you know
a specific organism again we're just
doing theory for starters here later
we're going to look at eoli um but even
when we do that it doesn't really have
to be genome scale lots of times people
do this analysis with like core
metabolism or one little branch of
something or whatever um but the purpose
of of generating a genome scale uh
metabolic model is to have a formal
representation of
metabolism um for the purpose of um you
know having a a a mathematical and a
computational framework for making
phenotype predictions um from a given
genotype okay and so the way that these
things work is that we're going to have
a set of metabolic reactions that exist
in the network and those reactions are
derived from the genes if you're trying
to reconstruct the metabolic network of
a particular organism we look at the
genes that are annotated
as metabolic
enzymes and this gives us um the
available
reactions r a c t i
s okay so we look in the genome we know
where all the genes are we look for
which ones are annotated as metabolic
enzymes um and that tells us the list of
reactions that are available in that
organism if you have enzyme to catalyze
reaction number one reaction number one
goes in your list if there's a second
reaction that exists in some organisms
but we have no enzyme or set of enzymes
for that reaction it doesn't make the
list and um the individual reactions are
just taken from Big databases like I
think keg and other things like that and
they consist of a reaction stochiometry
consume two of metabolite a and one of
metabolite B and produce one of
metabolite C so these things what they
represent are sort of fluxes or changes
through metabolites so consume one of
this produce one of this and so on we
could think of
this if we you know multiply this by
some amount of flux so call this like
one reaction reaction number one is
going to consume one of metabolite 2 uh
produce uh one of here just ignore that
for now prod one of metabolite 3 and and
it doesn't involve the other metabolites
there okay and in the end later we're
going to look at um uh fluxes so right
now this is just sort of DM we haven't
really said anything about DT um we're
going to say how much flux is there
through each individual reaction and
that's going to tell us about rates of
change of each individual metabolite all
right and so in the end if we have a a a
whole bunch of genes that code for
different enzymes that gives us
potentially a big set of reactions and
so we might end up with what we call a
big stochiometric
Matrix okay something that's going to be
metabolites by reactions big so we've
got one row per metabolite and one
column uh per reaction we call that a
stochiometric matrix yeah please does it
matter if you have more than one gene
per metabolite or metabolic reaction
okay great question so um there's a a
mapping that um goes from right now
we're going from just genes to reactions
so there's no genes for metabolites in
in the traditional setup um and very
often there turns out to be a complex
mapping between genes and metabolites
and the answer is yes it turns out to
matter in a very interesting way that
Aiden's can tell us but I probably won't
be able to help myself and I'm going to
let it slip before we get to his talk um
but very often for example you know an
enzyme can catalyze multiple reactions
or a given reaction might be catalyzed
by multiple enzymes and so what
generally when people build these genome
scale reconstructions of a metabolic
Network they look through a list of
genes that exist in an organism and they
come up with these rules like reaction
one could use you know x
one uh and
X2 or Y something like that so reaction
one could proceed either if you have um
these two genes present or through
basically the catalytic capacity um
combined through Gene one or Gene X1 and
Gene X2 or through Gene y so these are
the types of rules that tend to get um
derived um by looking through a genome
and um but for now yes we're going to
put this to the side for now so this
exists and is important um but but but
for now um consider just that we've
looked through all these types of rules
and said which reactions seem to have be
able to be satisfied in some way or
another like in this case I would need
Gene X1 and Gene x2 in the genome or I
would need Gene Y and if I have all of
them in any case reaction one can happen
so reaction one goes in the list okay so
I end up with a big stochiometric Matrix
and importantly these types of rules are
the bridge between biochem in genomics
that's going to allow us to do this
genotype to phenotype mapping so these
rules are critical and yes it matters
that they are sometimes
complex um okay finally usually there's
one additional reaction um that maybe
isn't entirely intuitive that's
something that's typically called a
biomass reaction uh that corresponds to
the production of biomass okay and it
represents you know a consumption of
basic pre cursors amino acids ntps
lipids co-actors Etc uh and the
production of just overall biomass of a
cell okay and we don't need to get into
the details of exactly what those look
like they vary for a a little bit for
each organism depending on the actual
biomass composition of each organism um
but typically there's one reaction that
represents again the consumption of
precursors and the production of
biomass okay so we can look through
genome look at the enzymes that are
annotated uh the genes that are
annotated as metabolic enzymes and
create a big stochiometric Matrix that
captures um which reactions can run and
how those reactions affect the flux
through each individual
metabolite all right so
now there's a further mathematical
framework called flux balance analysis
and flux balances analysis um is is is
the mathematical approach that sort of
Builds on U metabolic uh networks
reconstructed at the genome level or a
smaller level um to make predictions uh
phenotypic predictions um from genotype
or in this case from a metabolic Network
okay so this is the framework that we're
going to use to say what phenotype do we
expect to see uh given a particular um
stochiometric Matrix
okay
um okay great so what are the inputs to
this the inputs to this are a
stochiometric Matrix S like I talked
about here that's metabolites by
reactions big some
bounds on the fluxes So biochemically
speaking reactions can't just run at
infinite rate okay typically there's a
biochemical bound and as we'll discuss
later those biochemical bounds depend in
large part on the capacity of the
enzymes that underly the different
reactions so generally speaking going
forward we're we're going to talk about
these bounds as being related to the
genes and and think about that as the
gene um somehow what we're really
represent in is the catalytic capacity
of the gene which is you know
contributed to by like the expression
level of the gene but also whether or
not the gene product the enzyme is good
at doing its job okay so I'm not going
to differentiate going forward between
those things but just think about when
we talk about a constraint as having
derived from a gene it's just the
catalytic capacity of that which again
is is a combination of expression level
and whether or not the enzyme's a good
enzyme um and usually there's also
something called a fitness
function okay which might be in the
usual case the production of biomass
which we can think about as basically
the growth rate of the cell okay and and
you know production of biomass clearly
isn't always Fitness um but it's usually
treated as Fitness so there's something
called a fitness function those are the
inputs
um and and then the thing that we're
looking to get
out is
uh is the flux through every reaction in
the network so we have a big stoom
metric Matrix and I want to make a
prediction about the phenotype at the
level of flux through every reaction you
have a question no okay that's the
output um in order to do this we're
going to make some
assumptions and the assumptions include
a steady state
assumption I'll say formally what that
means in a second but it's related to
this flux through all the metabolites
and also an assumption of optimality
okay all right so formally what um this
looks like we can incorporate all of
this into a constrained optimization
problem um that tries to um output
fluxes that are optimal with a steady
state constraint and the and a
constraint on the bounds of each
individual reaction okay so usually the
way that this is is written down is that
we want to maximize over all the fluxes
we're going to use V to represent a
vector of fluxes V exists in uh how big
is v v is like uh yeah one by reactions
or whatever it's a vector of length
reactions big we want to maximize over
reactions now let's define our fitness
function usually this is just defined to
be something linear so a linear
combination of reaction fluxes is
somehow the fitness function and often
times that's represented with
coefficients beta okay so um we're going
to have a fitness function that looks
something like this in this simple case
when I have a biomass reaction let's
assume that the last column here is the
biomass reaction then beta is going to
look
something very boring like this beta is
going to say just take the flux through
the biomass reaction and that's the
fitness okay but generally speaking we
could have any old sort of Fitness
function here and and I'm going to
present everything as linear it actually
doesn't have to be linear um but uh uh
so we're going to have a fitness
function and so what we want to do is
find fluxes that maximize
Fitness subject to constraints
one is that we need steady state which
is really an imposition of conservation
of mass so this says if I take my
stochiometric
Matrix and I have a flux through every
reaction this product The Matrix x times
the vector v gives me the rate of change
through each individual metabolite so
we're just assuming and this is not the
world's wildest assumption we're just
assuming that at least at the population
level we're not really saying anything
here about phenotypic variability but at
the population level we're assuming that
metabol each metabolite is at steady
state so we're not constantly
accumulating any metabolites and we're
not constantly depleting any metabolites
and again this just follows from
conservation of mass basically so
somehow our flux Vector for you linear
algebra folk out there needs to live in
the null space of this Matrix S and then
we usually also have bounds um
on the
fluxes uh so this is a vector of lower
bounds and our fluxes have to be greater
than some lower bounds and this is a
vector of upper bounds and our fluxes
have to be less than um some upper
bounds so these are just biochemical
constraints okay so that's it this is a
linear program this is the basic setup
of flux balance analysis um and it can
be solved you know numerically Simplex
method or whatever ever um and and again
that's the basic setup so the assumption
is that we're going to end up predicting
the flux through every
reaction and we're assuming the the
basis of our prediction is somehow that
the fluxes have been optimized by
Evolution to maximize a fitness function
but subject to constraints imposed by
the universe conservation of mass and
biochemical constraints on how quickly
we can run each individual reaction okay
that's the basic setup of a flux balance
analysis now we can modify this a little
bit if You' like we can have you know
the same sort of problem where we have
we want to maximize a fitness function
and we have conservation of mass
constraint but we can also have sort of
linear combinations you
know like this so we could have a
constraint that's not just on each
individual reaction but a constraint
over linear combinations of reaction
fluxes okay and then later um Aiden's
also going to introduce how we could
generalize this even further and say is
this thing an
eraser look at that
whoa we could also generalize this later
and
say that our upper bound constraints in
fact somehow uh involve linear
combinations over um the catalytic
capacity of a bunch of genes this is
going to end up relating to your
question of if there's a non-trivial
relationship between genes and
constraints on different reactions then
G is going to look funny somehow but for
for for a lot of purposes we're just
going to let G be something like the
identity Matrix so there's a one one
relationship between genes and
constraints on individual reactions and
we're going to let a be the identity
Matrix as well so you get back to a
situation that looks like this also
going forward I'm normally going to
ignore the lower bounds because I don't
want to have to write the basically the
same thing twice the lower bounds matter
the meaning of a lower bound or a
negative flux is um how much the
reaction can run in Reverse okay so
that's what a negative flux means is
you're just running the reaction in
reverse so flip all the signs of those
things for example okay but again so
this these types of rules here about how
genes relate to an individual reaction
are going to end up manifesting in this
type of Matrix here and then it it ends
up being a key point of um the stuff
that we've sound found so far is that
okay so A1 it just turns out that g is
not identity basically ever if you look
in any organism there's all kinds of
stuff going on um but if G is degenerate
or G is not full rank um it turns out
that has a very interesting result um
that we refer to as sort of
non-identifiability of genes by a
selective process so evolution in fact
can't tell if it's selecting on Gene a
or Gene B um that result it turns out to
be quite General um he's going to tell
you more details about that but that
relates to this G Matrix being not full
rank okay yes we assume that beta is
known a prior from like just what we
know about biology or experiments yeah
so we do um so again interpreting it as
a fitness function is a bit funny if you
think about it just as biomass then beta
is just going to be all zeros with one
one on the biomass reaction but your
question then is also implicitly do we
assume we know the biomass reaction and
usually that we can do by looking at the
biomass composition of the the organism
of Interest what is the relative
abundance of different types of
macromolecules and so on but overall do
we know the real Fitness function I
would say is a fantastic ho in the
entire field of evolution that the
fitness function is a central object but
we generally can't say what it is okay
yeah our robust is this kind of
optimization problem generally to model
the specification like I guess mentioned
maybe the beta you might not know or
like maybe you're missing a reaction
that you don't know about or you like
kind of got the upper bound incorrect
yeah so um again if you're trying to um
predict a specific organism yes it
there's this is an entire big process if
I want to go make phenotype predictions
using FBA for some new organism the
process of doing the genome scale
metabolic reconstruction is usually
quite an Endeavor is very hard these
things are usually not so trivial to
decode and it really depends on what
you're trying to ask if you're looking
at like Central metabolism where we know
everything super super well and then
maybe it's not so big of a deal um but
if if you know you're looking for the
production of some more obscure
metabolite it probably matters if you
get all of the reactions so it depends a
little bit for our analysis we're just
going to have like random S's and random
everything so you know um it doesn't
particularly matter we're going to we're
going to assume we know s and that we
know beta um and yes if we didn't
actually know those things we would get
things wrong but but our goal is not to
take this one specific organism and
predict this one specific phenotype it's
to understand in general what are the
evolutionary Dynamics when you're
operating in the genotype to phenotype
mapping imposed by
metabolism okay yeah thanks yep okay
great so now um I'm going to speed it up
a little bit uh in theory um to talk
about um what we're actually doing so
again there's you know whatever 10,000
papers doing flux balance analysis in
different ways trying to reconstruct
these types of things various things
that they do is they'll ask like suppose
I wanted um you know I want to predict
phenotype when I knock out Gene a so
what they'll do is they'll go to the
reaction rules and say suppose I remove
X2 from The genome does that modify the
stochiometric Matrix plug the new
stochiometric Matrix into this problem
and ask how the phenotype changes so
you're going to plug in a new s and ask
how the phenotype changes or maybe you
are able to con control some of these
bounds for example for things called
exchange fluxes meaning just importing
something into the cell or exporting
something from the cell if you're trying
to import something to the cell you
could take it away from the environment
so now the upper bound on that import
reaction is now zero or something like
that okay so people do all manner of
different stuff in the realm of flux
balance analysis what we're doing is not
just this this is our starting
mathematical framework and as I
mentioned before we want to analyze um
what's known as The Duel of this problem
okay so in in optimization this is a
constrained optimization problem happens
to be a linear problem and there is a
linear
program uh and we can call this the
Primal problem because it is the one of
primary interest we want to analyze
What's called the Dual problem so what
is the duel first it might be helpful
for me to write this out in What's
called the lran formulation so in the
lran formulation I'm going to write down
the same optimization problem but I'm
going to move the constraints up into
the objective so now we're going to have
something that looks like um
I transpose V let me get my signs
right okay so again I don't want to have
to write twice as much stuff so ignore
the lower bounds the lower bounds are in
there they can also matter I'm only
going to write the upper bounds so I'm
taking you know this
type of optimization problem where we're
also going to ignore G for
now this optimization problem and i'
I've moved these constraints up into the
objective with these things called
lrange
multipliers and these things it turns
out are going to be our Central object
of Interest so we want to know the
values of these parameters these might
look familiar to people who are more you
know in the realm of statistical
learning and so on you you could think
of these as like the um penalty
parameters of regularized regression or
something like that and many regularized
regression problems you know could
potentially be mapped back to strict
constraints like this sort of depends on
what's going on um but they're analogous
to like the hyperparameters of your
penalized regression tells us in our
optimization problem how much do we
penalize violating the steady state
assumption they penalize it this much so
this is a vector
of length number of metabolites remember
s is metabolites by reactions so this is
like one um these things we're going to
end up calling Shadow prices for a
reason I'll explain in a second one
Shadow price per metabolite and over
here we have one Shadow price per
constraint okay so um you can write
those down in the lran or you can also
write them down in the
Dual of the Primal optimization problem
and the Dual is going
to show us a dual way to optimize over
this problem where in the Dual problem
um constraints in the Primal problem
become dual variables so now the
variables that we're optimizing over um
are related to the constraints of that
problem so we're going to be an
optimization problem over these lrange
multipliers and the variables in the
Primal problem become constraints in the
Dual problem also where we had a
maximization problem in the Primal we're
now going to have a minimization problem
in the Dual okay so Duality theory is
you know sort of deep beautiful extends
well beyond this framework here slight
mysterious in some senses um but if we
want to write down the flux balance
analysis problem in the Dual formulation
it would look like this we're now going
to have a minimization problem over
these lrange multipliers or
hyperparameters and we're going
[Music]
to uh what did I call this
okay this becomes the new objective
function and our
constraints now look
like this
okay that's the the Dual formulation of
the flux balance analysis problem and
again the idea is now we have
optimization that's a minimization of
this function where these are the upper
bounds on each individual
reaction these are these lrange
multipliers that tell us something about
each of the upper bound constraints
that's our new objective function
and we have a constraint here uh that is
this thing beta is equal to this stuff
this stuff there's these things called
the kkt conditions and because I'm going
so slow I don't have time to walk
through it in um in entirety um but um
one of the important things to note here
is that um there's sort of a constraint
on these things that uh is related to
something called complimentary slackness
maybe I'll give the interpretation of
what these things are first so that we
can have a little bit more into of where
that arises what is the meaning of these
things does anyone happen to know the
meaning of these things anyone familiar
with duol Theory or these things I've
said the word Shadow prices
before okay great I'm so happy I get to
tell you the meaning of these things and
the term Shadow price is um it turns out
that these Lambda parameters here um
that were optimizing over um tell us
about the change in the optimum
especially this Optimum or you can think
about it as the change in the fitness
function as we relax each individual
constraint so specifically we have
something like the lambdas are going to
be equal
to something like this again we're only
or really this is all the constraints so
we could think about um I'm going to
write C for constraints there's some
constraints on metabolites being at
steady state and there's constraints on
the upper bounds of each reaction so the
lambdas tell us the change in the
optimal value of um the the Primal
objective with respect to relaxation of
each individual constraint so that is to
say if I were to um increase for example
the upper bound on reaction number one
uh the Lambda or the shadow price for
reaction number one tells me much the
optimal Fitness would increase okay so
for us these are like the most important
things to analyze because these give us
a lens into selective pressure and by
give us a lens into selective pressure
what I mean is we interpret these as the
selective pressure okay this is why do
we do that it's because um these Lambda
parameters again the shadow price of an
individual constraint
gives me a fitness difference okay which
in in in pop genen in like curra's
formulas if we're looking at a selective
coefficient The Selective coefficient
usually represents a fitness difference
and so these give me a fitness
difference that would arise from a
mutation for example that would uh relax
a constraint move the upper bound up
move the lower bound down or make the
constraint tighter move a upper bound
down or move the lower bound up or
whatever okay so these are our Central
objects and again these are the Shadow
prices Shadow prices arise in all manner
of other scenarios or are interrogated
in all manner of other scenarios very
often in economics
literature um but in principle anytime
you have uh uh a constrained
optimization problem you can look at the
shadow price of the constraints okay so
we have a mapping that goes goes from
genes to which reactions are possible
and also what are the constraints on
each individual
reaction now I have a way analytically
theoretically to say if I were to mutate
a gene such that a constraint is changed
how would that affect Fitness so these
are what we want to analyze are these
lambdas here these lambdas you can solve
for because this is just a nice linear
program here we can solve for uh
numerically or in some cases we will see
well we won't actually see because we
probably won't have time to go through
the full derivation um but you may also
be able to solve for them analytically
um the point is you can find them
numerically or analytically and so now
we can calculate um sort of what are the
selective pressures on each individual
Gene in a reaction Network okay let me
see how I'm doing on time 949 I might
take three two three more minutes um
just to set up a final problem or just
to um draw you some pictures of of um
some of the types of reaction networks
that we're going to look at in a second
Brian f fstar is the value at the
optimum just checking make sure I got it
right exactly so if you're not at the
optimum then you know we don't have
anything to say about this this tells us
how the optimal Fitness or the um yes
the optimal objective value over there
in the Primal would change it doesn't
tell you about n sure yeah yeah it's the
value at the solution or any of the
solutions if it's non- Unique but that's
correct yeah correct any of the
solutions because they have all of the
same the same value yeah yes yes exactly
okay so now let's draw some pictures so
let's think of a a very basic um
reaction Network where we have just like
two
metabolites and a couple different
reactions we'll have some import
reaction and maybe you know we do
something like this so here's a reaction
Network and let's say that our our beta
our fitness function
um you know is just based on the flux
through these two reactions so my my
Total Fitness is the flux through this
reaction plus the flux through this
reaction okay so now we can also think
about our steady state assumption one
thing to note is that um we have this
basic sort of conservation of mass
steady State thing so um you know if I
have any sort of flux through here
that's producing metabolite one the
production of metabolite one needs to be
balanced by the consumption of
metabolite one so if I have a flux of a
coming in through this reaction that
needs to be balanced by the total flux
through these two things or if this
thing is running in Reverse you know
then this thing whatever the combination
of flux is through these two reactions
needs to equal
um the flux through that reaction same
thing here whatever my flux that's
producing M2 needs to be balanced by the
flux that's consuming M2 okay so now you
can imagine that there's some feasible
space that exists and part of that
feasible space again comes from the
fluxes that are allowed live need to
live in the null space of s now you can
also imagine that we have different
constraints but let's ignore the
constraints for a second and just or
rather let's think about every reaction
has a upper bound of one there you go
every reaction has a upper bound of one
now we can start to talk about solutions
to the Primal problem okay so flux
balance analysis what can flux balance
analysis tell us we want to maximize the
flux through the sum of these two
reactions such that we are at steady
state and that none of the fluxes are
over the upper bound of one okay so what
are the things you could do
clearly everything is going to be
limited by this reaction because we have
to balance the production of M1 with the
consumption of these things so let's
just assume that one's at a reaction
flux of one all right so what's one
thing we could do is that could be
balanced by a reaction flux of one
through this reaction there you go and I
get one biomass point out of that which
seems like it's the most I'm going to be
able to get if everything has an upper
bound of one I'm not going to be able to
produce more than one biomass unit per
time my growth rate is not going to be
greater than one another possible
solution would be that I do that so I
have a a flux at a rate of one through
this reaction and then a flux at a rate
of one through there and through there
that gets me the same number of biomass
points and in fact any linear
combination of those two solutions lives
at the optimum and it turns out that
this is not uncommon in flux balance
analysis
that there ends up being not just a
unique solution but a whole Space of
solutions that could exist okay so now
to finalize the setup here so everyone
can have their breakfast before Aiden
tells you the actual interesting stuff
what we want to do is different from
this in a couple of respects we're not
going to assume
optimality that is that Evolution has
ended and that we are at the optimal
solution because we are interested in
the evolutionary Dynamics so we want to
understand how this process changes over
time the other thing that we're not
going to assume is that the constraints
are fixed so here we either have in the
Primal problem we have a problem of how
is evolution effectively going to wiggle
the fluxes around to optimize the growth
rate or biomass under a set of fixed
constraints but what we can see is that
the constraints are super important they
tell you something and the constraints
are the things that are actually
directly mappable to genes so fluxes
it's unclear if they're directly
mappable to genes probably in some way
they might be but the constraints are
actually directly mappable to genes so
if we're going to be in the business of
asking what happens when I allow the
genes to mutate it's immediately obvious
that the constraints are going to wiggle
around so the second thing that we want
to do different from normal flux balance
analysis is to say in a reaction Network
like this
how what are the Dynamics going to look
like as we allow the constraints to
wiggle around according to different
selective
pressures okay so if we move the start
the constraints at whatever place you
like and start the fluxes at whatever
place you like and now assume that
there's some process of mutation that
Wiggles some of the
constraints and those constraints have
some the wiggling of the constraints and
wiggling of the fluxes has some effect
on fit
then we'll use his basic pop gen stuff
like curra's formula of probability of
fixation to say does that mutation fix
in a population or not and now we want
to know what's the overall direction of
evolution where is the system going to
go I've just told you that flux balance
analysis very frequently doesn't tell us
the real an they can't even tell us if I
give you fixed constraints flux balance
analysis can't even identify one unique
solution
so we have a harder problem my
constraints aren't fixed and I want to
identify one actual solution hopefully
not just a space of solutions so that's
our goal we want to say in a regime
where the constraints are allowed to
wiggle the fluxes are allowed to wiggle
how is this network going to end up what
is the phenotype we're going to end up
seeing after some amount of evolutionary
time and again as I mentioned in the
introduction we think about that as the
way in which a basic unit something in
this case like a um metabolic process
can arise and it turns out that I
mentioned before flux balance analysis
can't distinguish between linear
combinations of going all the way
through this path or going all the way
through this path the answer in this
particular Network just to give you some
sense that there's something non-trivial
that you wouldn't be able to just guess
going on here uh ends up being
this okay why the hell should that be I
don't know math says it's true and we're
going to do a bunch of simulations to
check whether it's true as well okay so
that's most of what I wanted to cover um
in the primer um I don't know if there's
any final questions but I'm sure I'm
over time uh
anyway um yeah I'm in I'm in Brian's
at bu and I'm going to be talking about
some of the results of the work we've
been doing um specifically modeling
genotype to phenotype and our search for
the natural objects of
selection so get ass started in maybe
some stories that don't quite make sense
with what Brian just talked about we're
going to talk about CLE cell
disease as many of you probably know CLE
cell disease is a recessive disease so
to be affected by it you need two copies
of mutated hemoglobin
these mutations cause hemoglobin to pize
and lead to the characteristic CLE shape
of red blood
cells the shape leads to poor
circulation and eventually causes
pain we can also look at this scenario
where you're carrier for the disease and
only have one mutated copy of
hemoglobin in this scenario heem is more
likely to be released from hemoglobin
and this increases hem oxygen one
activity this increased activity leads
to malaria
tolerance and these are more just facts
but we can make them stories by looking
at them in an evolutionary
context for example if we're in a
malaria Rich environment you might be
able to predict that the carrier a
single mutant of hemoglobin should be
enriched in the
population similarly we could predict
that the pain caused by the double
mutant keeps the double mutation from
enriching in the population
I'm here telling you these stories about
CLE cell disease because they're nice
and
simple I claim that they're nice and
simple because there's a direct onetoone
relationship between genotype phenotype
and
fitness knowing a change at the genotype
level we can make a prediction about the
change at the phenotype this allows us
to make a conclusion about how Fitness
will change and we can make a prediction
about if the mutation will enrich or
leave the population
however many stories aren't like CLE
cell
disease for example we could look at
serum urate levels which are controlled
by many
genes if we try to tell a story like we
told about CLE cell disease you might
ask if a mutation occurs in one gene
what happens to the other ones it's not
as clear as the CLE cell
scenario similarly in starting to get
onto what Brian was talking about we
could look at metab abolism in the
citric acid cycle here again there's
many genes involved but there's also
some interesting
structure you could ask what role this
structure plays in the stories we tell
about
Evolution if we see a mutation in one
gene does the structure change what we
might predict about mutations in other
genes even in the simple stories we just
told you can start to
Foles for example in the carrier story
what happens to H MOX one the gene that
encodes H
oxygenase I think you can make a few
different arguments one is that the
increased H oxygenase activity was what
led to the increase in Fitness so
mutation should accumulate that also
increase hee oxygene
activity alternatively You could argue
there shouldn't really be any change to
hmx one because the mutation in
hemoglobin has already caused the
fitness
benefit the story we try and tell about
hmx one isn't so clear
and this is the Crux of this project is
that we want to tell complicated stories
about
Evolution we want to look at complicated
relationships between genotype phenotype
and fitness and in specific
environments we might look at scenarios
where multiple phenotypes contribute to
Fitness or where there's non-trivial
genotype to phenotype relationships such
as shown for GC which contributes to
both
phenotypes additionally we might want to
ask ask how our stories change if we put
them in a different environment in the
stories I told you about cyle cell
disease you can imagine that if we're
not in a malaria Rich environment our
predictions might be
different we can summarize these ideas
by asking the question of how do
non-trivial genotype to phenotype Maps
imp impact evolutionary
outcomes and importantly we'd like to
make quantitative predictions in the
stories I told about hemoglobin the
ultimate prediction we made was if a
gene will be enich
or say away from the
population it be might might be nice to
have a more precise picture and a
quantitative
one we'll spend the rest of this talk
discussing the work we've done towards
answering these
questions first we'll discuss our
non-trivial genotype to phenotype map
which you might be able to guess is
metabolism then we'll perform
evolutionary simulations to see if what
arises and if there is a story we can
tell
and then we'll use some of the analysis
of Shadow prices to make predictions
about
Evolution as I mentioned metabolism is
our non-trivial genotype to phenotype
map we can map the genotype phenotype in
Fitness using the citric acid
cycle as you'd expect genes in the
enzymes that they incode are the
genotype we could imagine the gene mdh
which codes for the enzyme that converts
malet to oxal acetate we could also
consider the gene T which holds a
similar
role I'm going to introduce the
phenotype but we'll return to discussing
genes to talk about their the
quantitative role they
have the phenotype is the metabolic
fluxes we could look at the phenotype
for the the metabolic flux through
isocitrate
dehydrogenase or we could consider the
flux through Alpha keto glut
dehydrogenase
importantly there's a non-trivial
relationship between genotype and
phenotype through the biochemical
constraints that physics and genes
impose on metabolic fluxes we discuss
conservation of mass and the require and
operating at steady state as one of
those constraints and similarly genes
will impose specific constraints on
flexes now we can discuss how we're
representing
genes Brian alluded to this idea of
capacity so we consider a gene to be the
ultimate capacity for the a metabolic
flux Brian also discussed this that we
can think about that as coming from how
much of an enzyme we could make or how
efficient that enzyme is for example for
the mdh gene if there's an excess of it
in the cell it might have a higher
capacity compared to fuman however if
you may had was a more efficient at
catalyzing its reaction it could also
have a higher capacity
now we can discuss Fitness and we'll
view this as the growth rate here we'll
view it as this Bri discussed as a
linear combination of reaction fluxes
beta is the coefficients for the
sum this is a nice picture of metabolism
we started to make it more quantitative
but we need a mathematical formulation
to really be able to analyze
it as Brian discussed in the primer this
formulation is flux balance anal
shown here on the screen is our
formulation a flex balance analysis and
we can walk through the individual
equations first we seek to maximize
Fitness over the reaction flexes and
then we impose conservation of mass as
one
constraint additionally we look at
constraints imposed by
genes here again s is the stochiometric
Matrix of
reactions and A and G are matrices that
allow us to consider constraints on
linear combinations of reactions or
constraints imposed by linear
combinations of
genes again this is implicitly included
in FBA but they consider genes as being
on or off where we're taking a slightly
more quantitative numeric
perspective let's take a look at what
FBA is doing visually we start with a
phenotypic space in this case Flex space
here I've shown the 2D the 2D version
with two reactions there's a reaction a
and a reaction
B we know the direction that increases
Fitness and that's beta and we can put
that in this space as
well then there are constraints imposed
by genes with five shown
here these constraints Define a feasible
region of fluxes that we can select
from now that we have a feasible region
we can perform the optim ization problem
to arrive at our our optimal set of
fluxes in this scenario b0 would be at
the top right as it's most in line with
beta importantly and as Brian discussed
in the primer there's a lot fixed about
FBA the constraints and genes are fixed
beta is fixed and ultimately we arrive
at one single optimal set of
fluxes however we care more about
evolutionary Dynamics in traditional
FBA and this arises in two main ways
that Brian discussed
earlier the first is that we do want to
see constraints
change here a mutation happens that
changes the constraint c0 to C1 and
expands the feasible region of
fluxes the second point is slightly more
subtle in
FBA there's an assumption that Evolution
will eventually bring us to the optimal
set of fluxes however however this
assumption is made under fixed
constraints now that we're constantly
changing constraints to examine the
evolutionary Dynamics it's not as clear
if this assumption is still
valid we address both these ideas and
how we set up the simulations so let's
discuss that
now this again is our formulation of FBA
and we'll discuss it as we walk through
each step of the
simulation we start with an initial set
of fluxes and genes so we need some V
and some lowercase G U and GL which are
the
genes then we perform a mutation by
sampling a new constraint now the genes
are
changing then we also sample a new flux
biologically we can think of this as a
noisy inheritance of
phenotype with this new flux we can
calculate a new fitness and we can use
this new fitness along with c's
equations to decide
if this new mutation should fix in the
population or
not we can repeat this process as much
as we'd like to examine Evolution and
its
trajectory let's look visually at what
happens in a single
step we start with our initial flux and
constraints and we'll initially perform
a mutation to change from constraint c0
to
C1 I've drawn this mutation as
increasing the feasible region over
were're randomly selecting so we could
decrease the feasible region as
well this addresses our first difference
with FBA that we alluded to we're
changing the constraints so now we can
watch the Dynamics of
them then we randomly sample a new
flux here this is drawn as increasing
Fitness but we could also decrease
Fitness as
well this addresses our second concern
with FBA now instead of making an
assumption about stepping towards
optimality instead we just randomly
sample and make no such
assumption this is drawn as occurring
somewhat within a single cell but really
there's a population of cells we can
think of this process as an having a set
of cells that are all initially at flux
v0 then we perform a mutation to create
a mutant cell which now has flux V1
compared to the
parents the question we'd like to ask in
our simulations and this is a simple
is if the parent wins and eventually
overtakes the entire population or if
the mutant will win we'll decide this
based off of their respective
fitnesses beta times to be one for the
mutant and beta times to be zero for the
parent this setup is what we can use's
equation
for's equation describes the probability
that the mutant wins and takes over the
population the key parameter of it is a
The Selective Advantage which is the
difference between the two fitnesses of
the mutant and the
parent in this equation as a increases
the probability of the mutant winning
also
increases importantly if a is zero so a
neutral mutation has occurred the
probability of the mutant winning is one
over the population size
n so there is a chance that we can
accumulate some neutral
mutations yeah uh and the population
size is fixed
the
simulations a diagram of an initial
population with one mutant right and
then mutants might be taking over or
maybe they're seled or dying out yeah um
so when I think about the population
size what should I think of the
population looking
like uh you could think the I'm not from
population genetics I might be asking no
yeah this is a good question um so n is
the population size here you know it' be
like seven and that'll be fixed
throughout the simulations so a mutation
you're just assuming the in a Sim in a
population of like 100 cells yeah okay
we just pick for a lot of the
simulations it's a thousand that's the
size of the population we're considering
but generally we're considering sizes
that are so large that yes we can see
neutral mutations but it's quite
unlikely because it's one over the
population size
okay now we have a framework that we can
perform some simulations we can repeat
this process a lot we can perform
mutations wiggle the flux calculate the
probability of the mutant winning and we
can watch Evolution
happened we're going to look at this in
two different
systems the first is a small toy Network
which this is the same as the toy
Network Brian drew it just looks a
little different I think um
and the second is we'll look at the
equal cor metabolism you can see the
circle in the centers the TCA cycle and
then BSIS is the long vertical column of
reactions on the
left we're going to spend a lot of time
with the TW Network so we'll walk
through it step by step I personally
have spent a ton of time with this TW
Network it's a great great Network to
look
at there's four
reactions reactions 0 through three and
there's two metabolites metabolites X
and Y reaction zero is an exchange flux
and it brings metabolite X into the
cell then in our very simple scenario
metabolite X can be consumed for growth
through reaction One alternatively
metabolite X can be consumed and turned
into metabolite Y and this can also be
turned into growth through reaction
three if these AR metabolized should I
assume that the two can also happen in
Reverse yeah here we'll talk about them
they can happen in Reverse as well
yeah there's also genes underlying these
reactions we'll have one gene for each
reaction so here we'd have Gene zero for
reaction zero Gene one for reaction one
and so
on mathematically G in the FBA
formulation the capital G's end up being
the identity Matrix so nothing crazy
with these G rules have happened
yet an important feature of this network
is that there's two ways for the cell to
grow you can either convert metabolite X
into growth for reaction one or it can
convert M metabolite Y into growth for
reaction
three this means our beta has multiple
non-zero entries and in this case we're
assuming that both metabolite X and
metabolite y are equally efficient at
turning into growth so they both are
just set to one they entries uh in beta
yeah two ways to goow um as Brian
mentioned there's many different ways
for the same many different sets of
fluxes that give the same Fitness in
this network we could look at a scenario
where only reaction one is used and this
would correspond to one
growth similarly we could look at a
scenario where only reactions two and
three are used and this gives us the
same
Fitness again as Brian mentioned we
could look at any linear combination
between these two extremes
here I've chosen a combination which as
Brian hinted at will become important
where the first reaction uses two thirds
of reaction the flex through reaction
zero and the second and third reactions
both use a
third importantly these all give the
same Fitness so it might be difficult
for us to tell beforehand if evolution
should have a preference to any of these
think you might be able to make an
argument well reaction one is only one
reaction compared to reactions two and
three so maybe it should it should be
used but also then you're missing out on
using metabolite y so it's not quite
clear right now if anything should arise
as we perform
Evolution now we can perform simulations
and look and see how these systems
evolve we'll start with the toy Network
shown here is the growth rate versus
time throughout the simulation for a
single
simulation as you can see the growth
rate does increase at a somewhat linear
rate and we can see that this result is
consistent across reactions a
second simulation a third a fourth and a
fifth there is some variability due to
the randomness of these simulations but
the results are quite
consistent we can also look at the E cor
metabolism and again see that the growth
rate does increase the time similarly
the results are consistent across a
second third fourth and fifth simulation
at this point if you think back to the
stories we told about CLE cell disease
in some sense we have the second half of
those stories we know Fitness is
occurring and we know evolution is
occurring and fitness is increasing but
it's not clear why in those stories we
were able to tell the second half
because we knew the relationship between
genotype and
fitness so as a good Next Step let's see
what's happening at the level of
individual
genes as Brian suggested one way we can
consider genes is by looking at the
selective pressure on them which is the
difference which is related to a
difference in
Fitness one way we can calculate this
change in Fitness is by using the shadow
Braes in this scenario G the gene would
just be a vector of zeros and one one
that corresponds to our Gene of
Interest then the Shadow prices again
correspond to the change in optimality
as you change a gene
visually what's going on is we perform a
mutation and then we take a step towards
optimality we can look at the difference
in Fitness and this gives us the
selective pressure on an individual
Gene this neatly captures the first half
of the stories we told about CLE cell
disease we knew that if we saw a
mutation occur in hemoglobin that would
lead to a fitness benefit of Mia
tolerance in the carrier scenario in the
same sense The Selective pressure tells
us if we change a gene what is the
numeric Fitness
method let's take a look at the
selective pressure on the individual
genes in the to
network we're going to look at a thin
slice of a simulation to start so this
is only the graphs I'm about to show are
only from between the two vertical lines
importantly maybe it's a little
difficult to tell but you can see the
evolution is occurring in Fitness
increases over this short time
period we'll start by looking at the
selective pressure on the gene for
reaction zero initially it's constant at
one it drops down to zero before
returning to one but then it starts to
oscillate quite
frequently we can see similar results
for all the other genes here's the gene
for reaction One the gene for reaction
two and the gene for reaction
three now then this was only a fin slice
and you can see the gene for reaction
two The Selective pressure is nearly
constant on it so you might want to ask
what does the rest of the simulation
look
like these are the same graphs as I
showed you on the last slide but over
the entire
simulation here's the gene for reaction
zero reaction One reaction two and
reaction
three The Selective pressure is
oscillating so much that you can't even
make out the individual
trajectories there are some Thin
vertical lines where you can tell
nothing is changing but generally The
Selective pressure is constantly
changing this is our first result The
Selective pressure on individual genes
is highly variable throughout
Evolution if we think back to the
stories we told about CLE cell
disease we can't quite use individual
genes the same way we could
there additionally this raises a new
question if you think back to the
fitness growth I showed you a few slides
ago those trajectories were relatively
constant
however we see that genes are quite
variable so what's providing this
consistency if it's not at the genotype
level then maybe it's at the phenotype
level so we can examine the fluxes and
the toy Network and the eoli
network here's the flux the reaction
zero and as expected for increasing
Fitness the flux increases with time
shown here is the average of the five
simulations from
before we can o look at the flux through
reaction One reaction two and reaction
three as you can see the flux through
reaction zero is the highest as it's the
entry we of the network reactions two
and three have the same flux because
they're in series and then reaction one
has a slightly higher flux than
reactions two and
three we can also look at this in the
eoli to toy Network I'm going to show
you four fluxes that I randomly selected
from the around 100 that are involved in
this part of the
network here's one here's another here's
a thirdd here's a
fourth if you look at this closely you
might see that after an initial period
the flexes start to go
linearly this suggests that we might be
adding a constant Vector to the flexes
at over each time step let me say that
again at a specific time we have a set
of fluxes after a short period of time
it appears that we're adding some
constant Vector to that new
flux we can repeat this process again
and again and this would give us these
linear directions we're
seeing one way we can isolate this is by
looking at the relative flux so we can
normalize by the maximum flux within an
individual time Point let's look at the
toy Network
first we said before that the
the the first reaction had the maximum
flux so when we normalize it by it
reaction zero goes to one through its
relative
flux however we can see that for
reaction One it converges to around 66
similarly we see that reactions 2 and
three converge to around
33 we can look at the same for reactions
from the equaline
network again we see that after a short
period of some change the relative
fluxes converge to a specific
value now we can look at all of the
fluxes in the equal Network and their
relative
fluxes this is what that looks like for
the around 100
reactions as you can see there's an
initial period of some nonlinearity
where fluxes are moving about but then
they eventually start to converge to
specific constant
values to give you a sense of what
reactions are involved you can the
reactions for ATP synthes cytochrom
oxidase and GAP DH all involved in
glycolysis and oxidative oxidative
phosphorilation which should be
important for growth they all have high
relative
fluxes this brings us to our second
result Evolution prefers to grow Fitness
in a specific Direction
we call this direction the collective
mode importantly this is a direction
we're looking at the moves the evolution
takes as it occurs it's taking a step in
a direction to change the
genotype however as we repeatedly move
in this direction we eventually converge
at the phenotypic level to this
direction so in this sense the
collective mode is both a direction in
that we're taking steps along it but
also a specific value that we eventually
converge to after repeated rounds of
evolution now then you might ask what's
so special about this Collective mode
one way we can look at this is Again by
using this concept of selective pressure
before we looked at selective pressure
on individual genes and we calculated it
using the Shadow
prices we can generalize this idea to
look at the selective pressure on
directions we're still using the same
equation but now instead of interpreting
G as a gene we can think about it as
taking a step in a specific Direction
along the
genotype once again we'll use the Shadow
prices which tell us how Fitness is
changing as we change a
constraint for the toy Network we saw
the simulation converge to 1.
and33 so this is the direction of the
collective mode that we would care about
calculating the selective pressure on
shown here are the same four graphs I
showed you before where the selective
pressure on individual genes is
varying now we can calculate the
selective pressure on the collective
mode using this
equation again this
1.66 33.33 value is from the simulation
of the toy
note when we put the selective pressure
on the collective mode over the genes we
see that it is cont
Conant this might help explain how our
evolutionary simulations were so
consistent they converged the collective
mode which has a constant selective
pressure and there are constant gains of
Fitness as we move along the collective
mode however doesn't quite raise answer
the question of why we end up at the
collective
mode one way we can look at this is by
looking at the cumulative selective
pressure on individual genes and the
collective
mode in this to calculate this we are
just adding The Selective pressure on
the individual genes or Collective mode
versus time for example here's the
cumulative selective pressure on the
gene for the first
reaction the they the reaction zero
here's reaction One reaction two and
reaction
three before we get to the collective
mode we can get some intuition for why
we see these
results intuitively reaction zero is the
entry way for the network so we would
expect it to have more pressure on it
than the other
reactions if we ever want to evolve we
have to mutate reaction zero to increase
Fitness so it should have a high
selective pressure on
it similarly we see that reactions two
and three have nearly equal selective
pressure they're in series so if they
want to be mutated and contribute to
increasing Fitness they must be mutated
similarly if one if reaction two had a
higher capacity than reaction three
reaction three would be rate limiting
and you need to increase reaction three
and you could then make the same Claim
about reaction
two now we can look at the selective
pressure on the collective
mode we see that it's perfectly linear
due to its constant value but we also
see that it's
maximal this is our third result the
collective mode has constant and maximal
selective
pressure this helps explain why we
arrived at the flective mode flective
pressure is capturing some idea of a
fitness benefit and we see that the
collective mode has a maximal
Improvement of
Fitness if we think about the stories we
were telling at the start with CLE cell
disease even with this complex genotype
to phenotype map we're able to recapture
a simple story now using the collective
mode if we take a step at the genotype
level in the direction of the collective
mode we know this increases Fitness in a
maximal
sense this means the evolution should
then enrich the genotype in the
collective mode and this process would
continue and then we can make a
prediction about where the genotype
would arrive
at one question you might ask is can we
generalize these results this is only
for the toy Network and it only has four
reactions and two
metabolites additionally we calculated
the collective mode by simulation so it
might be nice to know if we could
predict the collective mode without
performing a simulation
to make these predictions we turn the
constant in maximal selective pressure
into a mathematic
framework we start with the collective
mode and first we seek to maximize
selective pressure here Z would be a
direction at the gene
level then we impose a constraint that
the selective pressure must be constant
to get some intuition for why this is
the constraint you can imagine taking
the derivative of the selective pressure
as genes are changing
we impose a positivity constraint to
have physically possible results and
then we can solve this optimization
problem to arrive at a prediction of the
collective
mode importantly Lambda and damb DG are
functions of the specific S A and G
matrices that we discussed in the FBA
setup this means that each metabolic
network will have a unique Collective
mode
under some specific scenarios we can
solve this problem analytically we can
always Solve IT numerically but looking
at the analytical result give might give
us some intuition for what's going on
it's a bit of a mess but let's walk
through
it first we have this s Matrix which a
is a combination of the S and a
matrices both of these matrices were
related to imposing constraints on
fluxes so that might provide some
intuition for why we group them
then we perform some multiplication of
beta in this stil Matrix to calculate
something that is akin to the Shadow
prices Lambda that we're looking to
maximize with Selective
pressure however we impose the constant
selective pressure requirement and this
involves projecting this special Vector
made up of beta and stie into the null
space of the D Lambda DG
Matrix this part of the pro project is
what I've spent a lot of time on in how
we predict the collective mode this is
all I'm going to say for now but if you
want to discuss it more after I'm more
than happy
to if you think back to the toy network
from simulation we saw the results
converge the relative flexes converge to
6633 and33 for reactions 0 through three
if we solve this optimization problem
for the specific s matrices of the toy
Network we arrive at 1 2/3 1/3 and 1/3
these are the numbers Brian mentioned in
primer and we can see that we're able to
predict the collective mode of the toy
Network now then to really put this
framework to the test we'll Generate
random metabolic networks and see how
well our predictions f
up I'm going to put the S Matrix for a
metabog Network that has 16 reactions
and 10 metabolites on it in the screen
in a second there's a lot of numbers um
but we're going to walk through it and
this is just an example of the type of s
Matrix we could
generate this is what that Matrix looks
like um as Brian mentioned reactions go
across the columns and metabolites go
down the
rows among reactions there's a few
different classes that we can look at
first there's exchange flexes so here
the first reaction is just the first
metabolite appearing in the
cell and the second reaction is the
fourth metabolite leaving the
cell then we can look at the set of
reactions that are what we probably
think of as traditional metabolic
reactions where we're converting
different metabolites into each
other finally we have a growth or
biomass reaction that uses all of the
metabolites and take some in and take
some out but this is what is capturing
the growth of the cell
when we perform these randomly generated
matrices right now we're only going to
make a random s Matrix But the A and G
matrices from the FBA setup will be
identity to generate a matrix like this
we would first fix some number of
exchange fluxes so here we picked one
influx and one efux
reaction and then we would sample
stochiometric coefficients as integers
to generate the metabolic reactions and
then we would sample just real numbers
to generate the growth
reaction we impose some what I'm going
to call neness constraints on the SM
matrices such as like you have to use
all the metabolites there can't be any
metabolites that aren't used but
generally the process is randomly
selecting Soom metric
coefficients we can visualize this s
matrix by looking at the metabolic
Network here the orange circles are
metabolites and the blue arrows are the
reactions you can see reaction zero is
an influx and generates metabolite a and
reaction one is an efux and takes out
metabolite
D in the corner is shown the biomass
reaction which uses all of the fluxes or
all of the
metabolites if you sare at this for a
little bit you'll see that some
reactions are simple such as the third
reaction which just converts a into G
but there's other more complicated
reactions such as reaction two on the
left
which is converting metabolite e into
one J 1 c and 1
F all right I've described how we're
generating random matrices but now we
can see how well we predict
them shown here is the correlation
between the simulation result for a
specific random Network and our
predicted Collective mode for 20
different random
networks as you can see we're generally
able to predict the collective mode
quite well and with high accuracy
this brings us to our fourth result The
Selective pressure mathematical
framework accurately predicts the
collective
mode these are the main results that
we've feel have we fleshed out decently
well and that I wanted to share with you
today but we can also start to look at
some of the more interesting scenarios
where we start to use some of these Gene
rules and turn the complexity up a
little
bit this is the same tetk as before but
now we'll change what the genotype looks
like we'll still have a single Gene for
reaction zero reaction two and reaction
three however now we'll have two genes
for reaction
one here the protein encoded by Gene a
can catalyze reaction one and the
protein encoded by Gene B can catalyze
reaction
one we view this as the reaction one is
able to use the capacity of Gene a or
Gene
B this toy Network this second toy
Network only differs from the original
toy Network at the genotypic level we
can take a look at what that difference
is
mathematically first we'll look at the
original toy Network which only had one
gene for reaction one in that scenario G
was the identity Matrix and there was a
column for each gene and a row for each
reaction
now let's look at this new to network
where we have two genes for reaction one
now G looks slightly
different it looks a little bit like the
identity Matrix but we have a new column
which corresponds to the second Gene for
reaction
one again the rows correspond to the
individual
reactions one thing you might notice if
you look at these G matri's is that for
the one gene uh version
this G Matrix doesn't have a null
space however the second version does
have a nonzero n space and that'll be a
little bit important
later all right before when I ran we
looked at the toy Network I showed you
that Evolution occurs and that there The
Selective pressure on individual genes
is highly
variable that is all true now still true
uh and I can show you those results if
you'd like but for right now we're just
going to skip straight to the collect
mode as we saw before in the one gene
version uh for reaction One the relative
fluxes converge to 1 66 and then 33
and33 for reactions two and
three now we can look at the version
with two genes for reaction
one here we see the collective mode is
one for reaction
zero uh 08 for reaction one and point
two for reactions two and
three just by making a cal change at the
genotype level we see a shift in the
collective
mode some intuition for why we see this
shift can be explained by thinking about
how evolution is occurring now that
there are two genes that somehow control
the capacity of reaction one you can
think that it is easier for mutations to
accumulate along this reaction and
increase the
capacity this causes a sh
in the collective mode increasing how
much reaction one is utilized compared
to reactions two and three instead of
using uh reaction one for 66% of the
total flux of the network now we use it
for
80% and similarly reactions two and
three must shift down in flux to
accommodate another interesting feature
of a network like this is that multiple
genes and directions in gene space can
satisfy the constant and Max selective
pressure
criteria so right now I'm showing you
the selective pressure on the gene for
reaction two but we can look at the
selective pressure on a few different
versions of the collective
mode we can look at one scenario where
we only take steps using gene a here we
see again a constant selective pressure
and I will tell you that it's
Max alternatively we can look at a
version of the collective mode where we
only use Gene B
as you can see the selective pressure is
the
same importantly at the flux level as
shown by the little
diagrams we haven't changed what we see
the fluxes the relative fluxes are still
at one point8 and 02 and 02 for
reactions two and
three this adds some new Nuance to the
story before if you think about the
stories we were talking about CLE cell
if we took a step along the collective
mode at the genotype level we could
confidently say this would increase
Fitness and cause evolution to enrich
the collective
mode however now we have a wrinkle I
could tell you one story where I say I'm
going to take a step along the
collective mode using only
G because this has constant maximal
selective pressure on it we know that
this should be enriched in the
population I could tell you a similar
story by saying I'm only going to take
steps using Gene B again this has the
same and constant maximal selective
pressure on it so this change should be
enriched in the
population in essence Evolution cannot
tell the difference between genes A and
B at the start of the talk we set out to
tell complicated stories about Evolution
with complex genotype to phenotype
Maps we've worked toward this in a few
different
ways first we saw the selective pressure
on individual genes is highly variable
throughout
Evolution this complexity limited our
ability to tell evolutionary stories um
about genotype to phenotype maps for
example we couldn't tell a simple story
like we did a CLE cell disease where
just by looking at one gene you were
able to make a prediction about
enrichment of that Gene in the
genotype this point is furthered by the
Redundant genotype example we just
showed here there were two genes the
evolution couldn't even different differ
iate let me emphasize this point
Evolution doesn't appear to
differentiate between different patterns
of selection and mutations at the
genotypic
level genes may not be the natural
object of
selection as we saw the selective
pressure
varied however even though we had this
issue with Selective pressure varrying
on genes we saw that the simulation
still converged to a Ive mode when we
looked at the relative
fluxes this led us to examine these and
provided us ability to retell the story
using the collective
mode we saw by looking at the selective
pressure on the collective mode that it
was
constant this suggested along with the
maximal criteria that the collective
modes may be the natural objects of
selection
another way we can think about this
difference between selection on genes
and selection on Collective modes has to
do with
uh the genes and when they are
active as selection occurs whether or
not mutating a gene is favorable depends
on the current state of the system if
one Gene and its capacity is rate
limiting the network mutating that Gene
might be beneficial however if a gene
and its bound isn't rate limiting the I
olic fluxes then mutations there will
have a minimal effect on the
fitness so the selective pressure and
the Gen roles depends on the current
state of the system however we see that
the selective pressure excuse me the
collective mode is invariant to the
current state of the system The
Selective pressure is constant as
Evolution
occurs the collective mode was useful to
us with some wrinkles from the last
point I made about done in genotypes and
being able to recapture simple stories
about
Evolution if we take a step along the
direction of the collective mode at the
genotype level this will lead to a
maximal change in Fitness and it lead to
enrichment of the collective mode in the
genotype finally we found we were able
to predict colletive mode using this
criteria of constant and maximal
selective pressure and able to do so
quite accurately
this idea of constant selective pressure
is an interesting one and could arise in
other
scenarios ultimately it arises from
having constraints on the genotype to
phenotype map here there were
constraints imposed by genes and
conservation of mass but one could
imagine that other constraints might
also
impose lead to the a collective mode
coming about for example other
conservation laws might lead to a
collective
mode Beyond this as we told in this
project these results give some
intuition and maybe help explain
polygenic
traits for example we know that there
are observations that predicting the
phenotype is easier than the genotype
after multiple rounds of
selection selection on a collective mode
might help explain
this additionally we can think about
gwos studies of polygenic traits Define
many hits for a trait this might be the
result of selection on Collective mode
rather than individual
genes currently we're continuing to
explore the role of the G Matrix and
redundant genotypes and complicated Gene
rules like this one and what effect that
has on the collective mode and
additionally we're starting to consider
what role the environment might have on
the reflective mode if you limit One
exchange reaction by removing a
metabolite from the environment how does
that change the deflective mode
with that I'd like to thank everyone my
lab uh thank you to Brian and Fage who
is not here but great gave a lot of good
feedback on the talk and then thank you
to Sarah who's an undergrad that's been
working on this
project thank you