so what we're going to talk about uh
this afternoon next half hour or so is
around the role of corporate culture in
Innovation and uh also Innovations in
measuring corporate culture so we'll uh
we'll talk about how Innovation and
culture affect each other a couple of
ways so to tee this off there was
recently a survey done by some
colleagues at warten of about 1,400 CEOs
in
CFOs and the survey was around what they
saw as the most important factors in uh
their organization's ability to create
and capture economic value and what the
survey revealed is first of all more
than nine out of 10 CEOs and
CFOs said they believe that a healthy
culture helped to uh increase firm value
that's not social value that's not
employee value that might have also been
true this is about economic Financial
results also eight out of 10 of them
listed culture among the top five
factors you know you could think of
inovation and uh uh IP Market position
lots of things that could influence
value creation but 80% of them listed
culture among the top five factors okay
so culture
matters so what do we mean when we talk
about
culture and actually you know what I
think I I apologize I have I'm literally
giving three speeches today uh and I'm
giving you all about culture but all
with a slightly different spin uh yes
this was my CFO speech so I know this is
not a group of CFOs so my apologies uh
let me get to the Innovation conference
one yes okay here we
go good morning Johannesburg where are
we today okay so the tea off the tea off
is the same the culture matters it just
is going to matter a little bit
differently when we're talking uh to a a
group of folks who are concerned about
R&D as opposed to uh CFOs okay so
culture
matters but we all know you can't manage
you can't improve what you can't measure
so a a core question even if you believe
the culture matters that you have to
face is how do we measure culture okay
so probably the most common answer I get
when I ask uh Executives how they
measure culture is they say well look
here is our here are our core values
here are here's our official culture
that's what our culture is uh and we did
a study of about uh nearly 700 large uh
mainly us-based companies and what we
found was over 80% of them had an
official stated corporate culture uh
that almost all cases took the form of a
handful of core values okay and so a lot
of Executives when you ask them about
their culture they point to those core
values and the core values are things
like what's right for the customer or
ethics
right okay that sounds plausible Until
you realize the source of these core
values was Wells Fargo those were the
core values of Wells Fargo the year
before they were found to have
perpetrated the largest consumer
financial fraud in US
history which suggests that hey you know
what maybe official core values are not
the best measure of your actual
culture um and you know this is
anecdotal you know we don't at MIT we
don't love anecdotes we like data better
uh so what I and my team did was looked
at a sample slightly smaller samples
about 500 companies where those
companies had publicly stated core
values and we looked at what core values
they emphasized and how heavily they
weighed those core values and then we
separately looked at how employees
talked about how their company did on
exactly those core values that
emphasized okay and the idea was is
there a correlation between the official
core values what companies say they
emphasize what their culture is and how
employees say those organizations are
doing against those values benchmarked
against industry
peers and we did this for the nine most
frequently cited core values in our
sample this is what we found so what
you're seeing in this chart uh each of
the columns I guess represents one of
the top nine core
values and the uh the point estimates
with the confidence intervals those are
the
correlations between what companies said
they valued and what employees said the
companies did
well punchline no correlation
essentially I mean you know in seven of
the nine cases the confidence interval
included zero in all of them it was you
know what we would not consider a
consequential correlation coefficient so
okay so if we're trying we have to
measure culture but just relying on our
official core values is going to be a
very V very poor measure of our
underlying
culture another common approach probably
the most common approach that we find in
terms of measuring culture is to give uh
employees long lists often uh in
Employee Engagement surveys is the the
uh data collection mechanism most
frequently uh used for this long list of
questions asking about various elements
of culture so how many of you have
filled one of these out at some point in
your career okay great so you're
familiar with this and and what you know
of course what leaders are hoping is
going to happen when they give employees
a survey with 50 or 100 questions as
they're hoping the employees are going
to read every one of those questions
carefully and think about them and
provide a an accurate answer as to how
well it's working right which would lead
to if that were the case would lead to a
distribution of responses that looks
something like this right there would be
some things we're doing well on some
things we're not doing so well on some
things we're doing really poor land
that's what you would hope to
see
employees uh uh do when they provided
this feedback that is not what we see
empirically what we see empirically is
distributions that look much more like
this that is to say employees or
respondents go on autopilot if they're
in a good mood or happy they give you
all fours and fives across the board on
questions that you would expect to have
very different answers if they're
unhappy all ones and twos across the
board even on issues uh and topics that
you would expect to see very different
responses
to and it uh what we did again just to
understand this is very very well
documented in political polling uh and
in survey design more generally uh but
we were looking specifically at the
extent to which this
autopilot occurs when employees are
filling out Employee Engagement surveys
answering questions about culture okay
and we took a sample of 11 Employee
Engagement surveys filled out by over
900,000 employees ranging between uh 14
questions and 111 questions okay and
what we were trying to measure was the
extent to which employees just use the
same answers for every question and what
we found was the following
and let me just explain what's happening
on this chart on the x-axis what we're
seeing is the number of questions in the
survey again ranging from 14 to 111 that
was the range in our sample on the y
axis it's the percentage of questions
that the typical employe answers with
the same
response and the key finding here is
it's about
90% basically 90% of the questions you
ask employees about your culture no
matter how different those factors might
actually be they're going to give you
the same one or two
responses the other thing that I find
interesting about this and is a bit of a
methodological point but it's still
interesting this kicks in with a very
small number of questions right you
could imagine like okay at a 100
questions people are just the cognitive
load is so high that they just default
to giving you all the same answer but
this is at 14 questions we see the same
thing
happening so culture matters you got to
measure it
core values are a poor measure and the
most common approach which is long lists
of liquor scales uh questions is also
very poor approach I should mention by
the way this what you think you're doing
when you give these long surveys is you
think you're getting the answer to 50 or
100 questions you're not you're getting
one good answer to one question are
employees engaged or not that's what's
really happening and by the way you only
need two questions you can ask two
questions and you get 95% of the
information content in of a 100
questions in answering that one okay so
that doesn't work as well and this
brings us to the subject of our
discussion which is what I'm very
excited about my team is very excited
about is the power of
AI to
analiz free text data to shed light on
what's happening with
culture and this is something that we've
uh We've researched quite a bit and and
written about quite a bit so the basic
idea the basic Insight here is that
instead of relying on these multiple
choice questions which for a variety of
reasons do not contain such a great
amount of information content instead
the core data that we're going to
leverage the kind of gold mine of data
that we're going to exploit in this um
uh in this analytical methodology is
free text not do the employees say you
know I like the culture I don't like the
culture but what do they say what's
working what's not working what advice
would they give to
management and what's interesting about
this one of the powerful things about
this methodology is every one of your
organizations has a book and that book
is written by you and your fellow
employees and that book in a typical
large organization will be thousands and
thousands of pages long and just think
about all the the places where employees
are providing free text feedback about
what's working in the organization
what's not working what they would like
to change so internally open-ended
surveys you know Ma 360 feedback exit
interviews employe uh focus groups to
the extent those are uh those
discussions are transcribed suggestion
boxes in large organizations there could
be a dozen different mechanisms whereby
free text uh data and feedback is
gathered for employees that's just
internal
data you know over the past 20 years
there's been an explosion in terms of
external fora for employees to talk
about their company you know glass store
indeed obviously but Twitter Reddit and
other places so the punchline is there
is an enormous volume of data out
there that sheds light on your
organization's culture and the question
is how can you
make sense of that data and that's where
AI offers um uh a lot of potential so
I'm going to illustrate that potential
I'm going to share with you the results
of some analysis uh we've done using
glass store data so glass store is an
interesting data source so it's it
is almost
certainly the most extensive I mean at
present they have about 40 million
reviews
comparable publicly available insightful
source of data on corporate culture not
only that we have now that we've
probably ever had in history right this
these online data re uh review sites
didn't exist 20 years
ago now some of you will be sitting
there and saying like oh glass door
forget it we ignore glass door in my
company because in my company we know
that glass door is where disgruntled
employees go to vent okay and therefore
we know we can safely afford to ignore
glass door as a source of data and
feedback empirically demonstrably wrong
okay if you there are a variety of
analyses we can do to make this point
I'll just use the simplest
one this is uh for a uh this is just um
I think this is just us data although
the the global data looks quite similar
um this is basically the distribution of
culture value ratings by on a one to
five scale in Glass St and what you see
is it actually skew it's more normal
than you might expect I mean
interestingly most online review sites
are highly polarized it tends to be ones
and fives uh and then not much in the
middle uh because only people who really
hate a service or love a service have
the incentive to write reviews glass
door is much more less polarized more
normal looking uh than than the typical
online review site it's because they've
adopted some policies that induce um
reviewers with moderate uh views to to
write reviews uh and actually skew
somewhat positive okay so if that's your
concern like we don't you know in my
company we don't take glass door
seriously that's just
wrong okay so let me let me illustrate
um the the power of this methodology of
you harnessing this uh uh this gold mine
of free Tech data using AI to shed light
on corporate culture and what I'm going
to do is I've chosen a single industry
so typically when you're studying
Culture by the way it's super helpful to
um uh to control for industry right
because if you're looking at fast food
and you're comparing it to you know
enterprise software those just really
aren't the uh the companies in those
Industries are not comparable with one
another so you want to control for
industry so that's what we're doing here
and I've just chosen I think I might
have gone alphabetically actually and
gone with Aerospace and defense um
and so what we're seeing here is uh um
this is a list of large Aerospace and
defense
players and these are their average
culture and value scores so when an
employee writes a glass St review
they're they uh you know there's asked
to evaluate the culture and values one
to five just take an average of that you
know uh have a confidence interval and
this is what we
see I mean it tells you something right
I mean obviously moo is doing better
than whoever is over there uh UniFi I
guess um so there's some information
there but it really doesn't tell you
that much about the nature of the
culture why do employees in one company
like the culture better than another
what is the difference between those
cultures so what we're going to do is
we're going to take two companies that
are both in the same both in this
industry both that have good cultures
but are very different from one another
okay so we're going to take SpaceX which
is here and Lockheed Martin okay and
what we see here is yeah locked Martin's
average is a little bit higher they're
they're both above the average but
little bit higher the you know the
confidence intervals a little bit
tighter but really if if this is all the
information we have about culture hard
to say much hard to conclude
much but that's not all the information
we have what we also have is something
like
60,000 postco
reviews where people write out they give
yes they assign a a score on a one to
five scale but they also write out what
they like what they don't like what
feedback or advice they have for
management and that's going to be the
data that we're going to use to gain
more insight into the culture so what
we're doing here is we basically have
built an AI
platform uh it it's a combination it's
kind of a hybrid llm rules-based model
they work very well together um and it
it essentially reads the text and
classifies the text into 500 topics that
are anchored in research okay where we
have a clear definition and have a
agreed upon ways to measure those topics
so uh it just kind of goes through and
assigns each of these little chunks of
text to um to topics and at the same
time assesses the sentiment um of the uh
whether the employee the respondent is
talking about this specific topic
positively or negatively okay so that's
the first thing we do is we take very
unstructured textual data and convert it
into structured essentially tabular
data then what we're able to do is
aggregate those you know 50 or 60,000
reviews and the results that we have and
say okay for any one of these topics or
we actually aggregate the topics into
broader themes that subsume multiple
topics but for every um for every one of
these topics or themes let's see how the
companies compare to one another right
just seeing that you know a lot of
people Grumble about schedule in your
company uh it's hard to say maybe that's
an industry factor maybe that's true of
all big companies you know to tease out
whether that's idiosyncratic to a firm
in its culture you want to Benchmark it
against its peer so what we do here is
we then say okay let's take a single
theme in this case schedule okay and
we'll take our our our sample of
Aerospace and defense
companies and let's now that we've trans
we've converted this unstructured data
to structured data using AI let's then
see how our focal companies SpaceX and
Lockheed Martin do on schedule and so
what we see here the x-axis here is the
percentage of employees who mention
unprompted remember they just their
prompt is Pros cons feedback that's it
so they can write whatever they want and
what we see when given that prompt that
open-ended prompt uh just over 30% of uh
uh locked Martin employees mention
schedule and they're quite positive
about it about 70% of those who mention
schedule are positive about it SpaceX in
contrast uh it's a higher percentage
that mention it maybe I don't know from
here 30 6% maybe um so very Salient
issue very top of mind but uh employees
are much more negative about it they're
only positive about it about something
like 22% of the
time and so we're able to start picking
apart like okay that's not just an
aerospace and defense thing schedule
there is variance on this dimension of
culture across firms within the same
industry and then we can do that for all
of the topics where we com we create a
combined metric that it takes into
account both the frequency with which uh
uh respondents mention a topic and the
the percentage
sentiment and then we can compare across
hundreds of topics how companies differ
from their industry and how they differ
from one another okay and that allows us
then to really get a much more granular
sense of what the culture is good at and
not good at in
the voice of the employees the people
who know best whether the culture is
working or not so just to give you a
sense of how you can then kind of
aggregate this so what we're doing here
now and let me just take a second to
explain this because it's not um
entirely clear so what we've done here
is we're comparing SpaceX which is the
black bar to Lockheed Martin which is
the blue bar we've taken a set of themes
so themes like Innovation includes I
think maybe a topics experimentation
willingness to take risks there are a
set of topics there um that we aggregate
to themes okay and that by aggregating
uh independent topics to themes the
results are slightly more robust and
what we're doing here is we're saying
okay let's look
how uh in this case SpaceX the black bar
how much more frequently and positively
they talk about a topic relative to the
industry mean okay so these are Z scores
so this is expressed as this combined
metric that takes into account both
frequency and sentiment uh it's the
score for SpaceX how many standard
deviations it is above the industry mean
so what we're seeing is Perks um there
are 2.4 standard deviations above the
mean so that doesn't look like noise
that looks like real signal uh and for
locked Martin they're about half a
standard deviation below the industry
mean who knows half a standard deviation
I don't know I'm not sure how much
information content there is and then we
just do that for the themes that rank
highest in terms of standard deviations
above the industry mean for
SpaceX okay and so what's interesting
here is now instead of just knowing ah
SpaceX is above average on their culture
values average ranking but a little bit
below lock heat Martin which doesn't
tell us really very much we can start to
characterize the elements of of the
culture in
SpaceX so and the story that kind of
emerges here is that you've got an
organization where the employees feel
very strongly and positively about the
mission and purpose they feel that the
work is interesting and meaningful it's
very Innovative very agile
organization and as a result employees
feel like owners and they're very
engaged okay so you start to get a sense
and we can get much more granular we can
decompose any of these themes into the
constituent topics of which there might
be half a dozen to a dozen for any one
of them and we get more granular on
those but this this starts to give you a
sense of the the culture of a
SpaceX now let's look at loed
Martin and again we're at the same
exercise in this case now the blue again
the blue uh the blue lines are Lockheed
Martins you know kind of combined uh
aggregate uh senmen and and incident
score for these themes and we're rank
ordering those that they're highest on
relative to their
industry and so just to remind you this
means that locki Martin is about 1.6
standard deviations above the industry
mean un Integrity so employees feel that
it's an organization with high levels of
Integrity ethical doesn't cut
Corners uh and and and we list again the
those U those themes that um uh that
Lockheed Martin scores the highest on
and again it starts to give us a sense
of what the culture of Lockheed Martin
is that's different from the industry
how they distinguish themselves from the
industry how they distinguish themselves
from SpaceX so you know this is an
organization with high levels of
Integrity not viewed as toxic viewed as
a healthy non-toxic culture uh a lot of
job security uh and employees in
contrast to what we saw with SpaceX are
very positive about the schedule and
work life balance okay and
so the the point is the liquor scale
question whether you had one question or
a 100 could not tell you this right it's
only through applying the AI to the free
the voluminous free text that you can
start to profile and understand the
culture and and I want to be clear here
by the way I'm not saying one is good
and one is bad I was very interesting I
was at a dinner uh about a year ago with
a general in the def us defense
department and we're talking about I'm
doing this study on on these you know
Innovation culture across different
Industries I was tell sharing with him
what we were learning about Aerospace
and defense and he said completely
consistent with his experience but he
said don't think one is good and one is
bad said SpaceX we want the Innovation
we want the agility locked Martin we
want the stability and the reliability
and the good corporate citizen aspect if
you have a platform that lasts 30 40 50
years that matters a lot we want both so
I'm not saying one is good and one is
bad I'm just saying they are very very
different
cultures
so I we're doing a project now which I
think is very Germaine to this audience
so I'll share with you the findings if
you promise me that you won't quote them
or cite them because this is very much
work in progress okay so this
preliminary findings subject to revision
we have a bunch of robustness tests to
do but I thought I just throw it out
there because it's kind of fun and
interesting and relevant in this
context so the basic the the research
design here is so the starting point is
if you ask people like what are
organizations that are Innovative
probably six out of out of 10 people
will say something about Silicon Valley
Tech companies and Silicon Valley
there's a widespread perception and some
good empirical data supporting it that
Silicon Valley startups are very
Innovative so what we thought was let's
see if we can characterize those aspects
of Silicon Valley companies that are
distinctive from incumbents in their
industry okay and it's just descriptive
at this point there's no we're not
making any clausal claims so what we did
was we identified about 2700 Silicon
Valley startups defined as founded since
2010 uh headquartered and based in
Silicon Valley and Venture back which we
use as a proxy for tech tech intensive
right so it's not a perfect proxy but
not a terrible proxy and that gives us
about 19 190,000 reviews over the time
period we're looking
at now the problem is a lot of those
startups because they're small they
don't have a lot of reviews and so it's
hard to do this analysis when you don't
have a lot of reviews for an individual
organization
so what we do is we assign each of these
startups to one of 41
Industries and then for those in each
each of those 41 Industries we pull the
reviews from all the startups and you
know have one Mega startup in that
industry okay now of course there's
going to be variants across those
startups that we're going to obscure
with this methodology but we're looking
for the commonalities so okay um it's uh
fair enough we do some robustness checks
where we have companies that are big
enough to have enough reviews to analyze
separately that meet our criteria we
find the findings are are basically the
same so reasonably confident that's an
okay
assumption and then what we do is what
we just did but instead of comparing um
SpaceX or locked Martin to the Aerospace
and defense industry We compare this
synthetic startup with the pulled
reviews to its industry that's it and
then we look at um uh averages across
the industries and consistency across
industry so that's the that's the basic
idea and again this is preliminary
research these you know these findings
are subject to revision as we uh as we
dig into this more so the first chart
I'm showing here is and I also I also
don't know quite what to make of all of
this it's you know it's it's we're still
in the digestion stage so what we're
doing here is across our 41 Industries
we're saying what is the average we're
looking at the things where the startups
do best relative to the incumbents okay
average across the
industries and so one thing and again I
didn't have strong priors on this I mean
I had some weak priors on this but my my
weak priors were not I I mean there were
plenty of surprises here the biggest
difference is how employees and startups
talk about their colleagues that's the
biggest cluster of differences and and
there we have done a bunch of robustness
checks this is super robust so they
describ their colleagues as intelligent
ENT impressive hardworking committed to
the organization that's the biggest
cluster of differences between startups
and incumbents which raised a very super
interesting question is like how much of
the success of startups at Innovation is
just their ability to attract and uh get
gain the commitment of really talented
people interesting question I I don't
think that's often how how we frame uh
the success of startups the second
cluster is not surprising at all it's a
cluster around Innovation creativity
openness to new ideas experimentation
that's kind of why we chose these
companies we would expect to see that um
the third CL the third is Around Mission
uh much as we saw with um with SpaceX um
interestingly again this is one that I
didn't necessarily suspect maybe it's a
function of size of organization uh but
employees in startups are much more
positive about teamwork and the
environment being supportive which was
not you know I would have guessed that
necessarily um and then also that the
work is more interesting and they view
it as more meaningful okay so those are
the things and again this is preliminary
you know we're still kind of chunking
through the analysis here but some you
know kind of it illustrates the kind of
questions you can address with this AI
applied to free text Data um and you
know may have some interesting uh
insights what about the things that
startups do worse than incumbents and so
so here we want to start from the bottom
okay so these are ranked ordered from
the worst to the the most worst to the
least worst um so one that and again
this isn't super surprising but
strategic Clarity strategic
consistency uh prioritization like the
flip side of agility and Innovation the
kind of dark side of agility and
Innovation is if you're pivoting too
frequently which is in the eyes of
employees in these startups is a real
issue okay that the you know the
startups are just changing being too
fast um uh being overly agile in a sense
uh operating processes not surprising
you know more mature companies have more
defined operating processes job security
um again probably not super surprising
one thing again I didn't have a strong
prior on this one way or another but
that the data is pretty clear on is that
the characteristics there's a bundle of
characteristics uh that we classify as
toxic these are things that when when
employees talk about them they tend to
be very negative in their rating of a
company
uh it's abusive management lack of
respect lack of integrity and so forth
uh this bundle is more pronounced in a
negative sense in startups than it is in
established companies um so um again uh
you know it's not that these companies
are you know these Silicon Valley
startups are better at everything for
sure another interesting way to get at
this is a lot of times in these um uh in
these reviews employees will talk about
either their direct boss middle man
management are the top team they'll talk
about leaders uh and so another analysis
we're doing is how they talk about
leaders and the way silin Valley
startups talk about their leaders
positively the things that they are most
likely to be most positive about is that
they're accessible and transparent so
they you know they can understand what
the you know uh what's going on and um
that their intelligent against comes
back to this uh uh Talent density
argument that they're supportive and
they're committed to the or organization
rather than you know kind of checked
out um the things that employees are
most likely to be negative about when
talking about their leaders are um that
they're emotionally stable I thought
that's an interesting one that they're
you know like these are very folks that
are prone to ups and downs in the eyes
of their employees um uh not
particularly humble okay qualified is an
interesting one qualified and
intelligent are different qualified as
often like technical expertise in the
domain versus just raw horsepower um uh
not viewed as trustworthy um decisive
which again comes back to I think this
difficulty in prioritizing and um and
not pivoting too frequently uh and then
we see some traits that are again
associated with uh uh employees
perception of more toxic culture that
it's uh you know fear-based or uh or
abusive um so um yeah so anyway as again
preliminary results but it it really
illustrates the power of applying AI to
textual data to start to characterize in
a granular and evidence-based way the
attributes of a culture of an
organization that opens up a whole lot
of very interesting um uh research
opportunities that we're pursuing I I'll
just cite here we at the Mi we've just
launched a series called culture
Champions um here at at MIT um that's
published at MIT slow management review
it's outside the pay wall um and what it
does is we um we use empirical data to
identify companies whose cultures are
both at least 1.5 standard deviations
above their industry mean for how
employees talk about the culture and at
least 1.5 standard deviations above
their industry mean in terms of total
shareholder returns or proxies for
private companies so we're looking at
those companies that manage to create
cultures that both deliver uh strong
results and uh provide a good employee
experience and trying to understand uh
through a systematic interview protocol
what are um uh you know what what those
companies do differently what the
Tactical things those companies do
differently we have a
podcast uh but then we also have like
for each of the each of the guests we
have an um you know an interview that we
summarize some of the key thoughts and
again all that is you know free and uh
at the MIT St management review site
uh so that's it for me and and that's my
email up there too if you are interested
in this
stuff thank you so much Don it's a great
talk very very very interesting we have
a couple minutes for questions if you're
okay with that sure uh the top question
we have is how do you navigate the SE
Suite resistance to datadriven versus
carefully crafted
survey
um uh
s i I guess I'm not sure I'm
understanding well I'll take the bit of
it that I I'll answer the question that
I want to answer so how do you I I'll
I'll focus on the first part of the
question is how do you navigate seite
resistance to data uh which is something
I spend especially my startups spend a
lot of time with um I think you know one
is um what we typically find when we're
dealing with top teams on this issue of
culture in particular is first
gauging the top team's commitment to
culture and so there's a lot of
heterogeneity there are some top teams
who just viscerally even without
evidence believe culture matters and
there are others who are extremely
skeptical and there are lots who are in
the middle the ones who are extremely
skeptical don't bother I I mean no date
is going to change their mind and I
don't know what 10% 20% I don't know
what it is but there's some there's some
tale where they just think it's nonsense
and they're going to be hard to convince
the ones who are already convinced you
don't have to do much convin the
interesting group is the group in the
middle that doesn't have you know they
and often what we find there is you know
they're used to the reports they get
from their CFO or their CTO or their coo
where it's like good data and solid
analysis and objective data and
Benchmark properly and that's how they
kind of set their bar for um uh
assessing confidence in the data source
they get and then no offense to any HR
folks in the room HR comes in and starts
like reading po or something and and
understandably leaders
are you know tend to Discount that data
so I think a big part of it is showing
that there is a method you can bring the
the same level of methodological rigor
to analyzing culture that you can to
analyzing you know your inventory turns
or you know uh customer feedback and
then once you do that in my experience
at least it's been the case that those
those leaders in the middle are much
more susceptible to um you know to to
taking culture seriously the other thing
is you have to be super super careful
about um um you know one of the
challenges of providing people with data
is that sometimes it doesn't say what
they want to say uh they don't want it
to say and these can be quite sensitive
issues so I was just on the phone with
the CEO of a um a very large asset
management firm who it their culture is
very toxic and it's demonstrably so you
know multiple data sources two to three
standard deviations above the industry
mean and already it's in an industry
that is not you know like really touchy
feely industry to begin with so um and
you know in that case it's like anytime
you're you all know this you're
delivering bad news you start with the
good news and you know here are some
things you're doing really well on and
there are one or two problems we should
probably talk about and um you don't you
don't lead with the fact that you know
you guys should be in prison the way you
treat your employees that's not the
right way to lead but anyway awesome
thank you so much John I'm afraid we're
out a time but I invite the audience
before we go to break if you have more
questions for Don I saw a c couple up
there please uh feel free to approach
him during the break so let's take a
networking break uh please be back here
in your seats at 350 p.m. 350 thank you
so much