okay good morning it will take us a
couple of U lectures I guess to cover
this
um uh in uh in some
details and it is
um we want to
extend what we know about heat transfer
to e and mass transfer and charge
transfer and we want to do it uh in in
in a way that uh exhibits the the logic
of the construction so um this is why I
am going to restart I mean start again
from what we have already seen because
it already contains that
logic uh actually parallel logic between
the what we've done in chemical kinetics
and what we've done in in in our simple
review of the heat transfer
Basics and because this contains what we
want to develop item by item with some
care uh and and other details uh in in
the rest of this uh lecture or
two so in chemical kinetics let's start
with because we did this first so let's
start with this first
we when we when we consider the closed
systems uh we considered that like the
energy balance it was implicit that the
energy remains constant if the system is
isolated and this is the entropy balance
that says that the rate of
entropy uh change is equal to the
entropy produced by irreversibility
then
um we this is not a balance of of of of
particles but you could view the
proportionality relations as as a sort
of a balance in the sense that uh they
account for uh the rate of change of the
number of of particles in your in your
mixture and so that
is another ingredient
plus we have assumed something about
equilibrium near
equilibrium uh situation in which we uh
if it weren't for the uh chemical
reactions that are changing the
composition our system in our model uh
um so far is
um very close to what it would be if it
were in equilibrium in a stable
equilibrium State we without the
reactions
on and
that allows us so this relation here
allows us to evaluate uh the uh rate of
change of the entropy which is needed
for the entropy balance so we evaluate
that and when we do the that rate of
change uh since s depends the only thing
that is changing here is n through the
proportionality relation so you have to
take the partial of s with respect to n
times n the rate of change of
N and then uh you keep going and we you
you single out the affinities of the
reaction and um you bring in the
reaction rate
rates so you combine
them this balance equation with the
energy balance which is Trivial in this
case and you obtain an expression for
the entropy produced by reversibility
which is this product of U uh rates and
affinities that we interpreted as
degrees of this
equilibrium and then we assumed um a law
that relates how the
rates uh relates the rates to the uh
affinities and this law is a nonlinear
law but in the near equilibrium
limit we have linearized
it here's the parallel structure and
parallel logic that we followed when we
derived when we did the heat transfer
basis we write the energy balance
it takes this form we will return to why
it takes this form for the moment just
uh uh believe believe
it so that's the energy balance this is
the entropy balance also of course we'll
return on
this there is we're talking about a
solid so there a pure solid there's no
changing composition so the the the rate
of change of composition is
zero then we assume like we did here we
assume something about the local
equilibrium we assume local
equilibrium so that there is a
fundamental relation we can write the
Gibs relation for between this the
properties and this is a way to write
the Gibs relation in order to uh
um we will also see this in more detail
later
um this is in order to get rid of the
pressure here and push the pressure in
the Gibs DM um independent
equation the Gibs relation can be
used to combine the left hand sides of
the balance
equations so you substitute the various
balance equations into this Gibs
relation
and
obtain an expression like here for the
entropy produced by
reversibility of course we will do the
details also because here I'm I'm uh
I've changed the the notation a bit but
as you know for heat transfer uh the
energy flux is just qou Prime and the
entropy flux is Q Prime over T that's
the heat interaction
and when we do we do these substitutions
you can rewrite the Divergence of
JS uh in as a sum of two terms the first
one cancels with the the one that comes
from the Divergence of the energy flux
and you are left with this final result
that says that the entropy produced by
reversibility and here we're talking
about entropy per unit produced per
unit uh
volume is equal
to uh the heat flux times the gradient
in uh the inverse temperature which we
can interpret as the degree of dise
equilibrium for the heat
transfer and then if we assume a linear
law then we get uh
forier in other words if you by looking
at this expression here if knowing that
the entropy produced by reversibility
must be
negative um the simple way is to assume
that Q uh is that the
flux is proportional to the gradient
through a a positive constant of
proportionality which could and actually
since it is a a vector the most General
linear relation between two vectors is
through a tensor so we take a positive
tensor in between here which assures
assures that the the sigma is going to
be non-
negative and then uh so we get for LA
and also we we have seen that if we
accept onager
reciprocity uh theorem that um that
tensor not only needs to be positive
definite but or non negative definite
but it also needs to be
symmetric you can also invert it and
therefore the the
entropy uh production becomes a
quadratic
form in the degrees of dise equilibrium
or equivalently a quadratic form in in
the
flues okay
so the ingredients are write the energy
balance uh do something about the um
Gibs relation or write the Gibs relation
in this form so that you can combine
these balances in in a proper
way make an assumption about the kind of
interaction that is
intercurrent between uh the
various Parcels or elements of your
Continuum and then assume if you want to
be near equilibrium you can assume a
linear uh
relation um and uh if you want to
discuss uh uh non equ more non
equilibrium I mean not not near equil
far from
equilibrium uh
then you need to develop some more
elaborate
theories and also
here there is space as we have seen for
the
katano
um correction to
foro there is space to uh account also
to solve some of the problems of of the
felo the the infinite speed of
propagation that is
uh implied by this
expression so let's
start we take them one by one
so we have to be patient but uh there is
and this will give us also some
opportunity
to uh
highlight a few of the details this
procedure that I am
describing
um varies depending on the field of
application in particular I need to
mention but I'm not going to follow uh
precisely or but there is strong
connections with a famous procedure
called under the names of col Colman and
null uh which is a uh um
used more in the by the the community of
solid
mechanics uh people that study um
plasticity Vis
elasticity uh
um for
example not to go too far if you go to
Professor lit Anand in the this
department he has written books and he's
renowned for that
procedure
um I am more inclined since I have
studied with um people in uh in the
fluid mechanics
area I I'm more uh inclined to describe
the procedure that applies for fluid
mechanics kind of
applications but the the Logics are very
similar
except when it comes to this
generalization of the heat interaction
that instead is peculiar of course of of
our course here because
uh because also the definition of heat
is peculiar to to our
course not yet uh uh very widespread in
the textbooks uh or other scientific
papers
okay
so let's start with this uh
simple take a piece of
material fluid
element see already the fact that I call
it fluid uh means it shows you my
inclination
um and as you know U this department has
had a very
um influential
[Music]
professors in um fluid mechanics and he
transferred Rosen now uh Shapiro
sonin just to mention a
few
so I have this uh onedimensional piece
of of fluid and it's subjected to
interactions on one side and on the
other
side and when we did the heat transfer
we were considering only uh energy and
entropy now here we're going to
introduce also uh flux of
particles
and uh and also here you have a the flux
the flux this is a component the X
component because we are one dimensional
of the flux and it changes as you move
from uh face at X and face at X Plus DX
and the area of exchange between the
adjacent uh between this fluid element
and the uh the one to its right is a and
also
uh the area on the other side of course
is again
a we we want to make a general energy
balance so we're not going to assume
steady
state so we call the energy of uh
the fluid in this
lamina Delta e why Delta because it's
infinitesimal since the thickness is
infinitesimal it's from X to D X Plus DX
so that is is an infinite asmal amount
of
energy uh related to the fact that it
has an infinitesimal amount of volume
which is the given by the area times the
X and uh the specific energy per unit
volume you can write it as we know like
uh row times U and U here is is really U
star what we call it's the energy per
unit
Mass all right so you you write it un
need volume and then you we we can also
substitute the volume for a *
DX the same
uh Al I mean this system has Al uh
entropy and here's the entropy also
infinitesimal because it's an
infinitesimal amount of of
material and it's it stays like that so
uh it's the the volume times the
specific entrop entropy per unit volume
which is row times s
star and also the amounts they are
infinitesimal
and the amount per unit volume is the
concentration so you can write that as
concentration times the volume
okay now
inside this uh
element we have also some um volume
effects for example chemical reactions
that are occurring inside in the
interior
and
therefore uh the proportionality
relations are governed by these uh um
Epsilon Epsilon dots which are the the
rate of uh advancement of the reaction
coordinate we can write also that as the
volume times a reaction rate per unit
volume which which is typically called
R without the DOT
and then the other is the entropy
production due to
irreversibility which
occurs uh throughout the the volume of
that uh of the
system and that to we like to write in
terms of uh per unit volume so we have
Define this Syle s dot rate of entropy
production triple means per unit volume
and soon
uh we have al already started calling
this thing
Sigma all right
so here is the energy
balance it says the rate of change of
the energy of our
system is equal to the
net energy it
exchanges through uh the intera
actions and here it has interactions uh
on the left and on the right and the net
is the
difference and you have to take it with
a minus sign if it goes out so if this
one is greater than that one the
difference is is this term
here and that is per unit area and then
you have to multiply by uh the area
and that is it because energy is
conserved let's go to entropy the
entropy balance says the rate of change
of the entropy of our fluid
element is equal to the net entropy
flux the
interaction so here I have again left
and right the the
difference uh is this term here and with
the negative sign because if it is
positive it's you have more entropy
going out than coming
in and that's this term
here I think there is a an error here
because I need also an
area like like here I need to multiply
by a
I need to correct
that that's that doesn't finish the
entropy balance because you also have
the ENT to account for the entropy
generation inside the element due to
reversibility okay now what we do is
simply
divide by the
volume Delta
V left and right of these equations and
here is how you what you
get so these are the balance
equations so now I want to
open a little uh degression that uh is
nevertheless uh
important uh regarding how we um
describe uh the properties of a
Continuum in particular the extensive
properties like uh energy
Mass uh
entropy and a bunch of others that I'll
I'll have in a summary table so in so
let's
consider uh like uh we typically do in
in mechanics we
consider a
volume call it Sigma M so it's material
volume so certain I select at a certain
instant of time a certain bunch of
particles contained inside this
volume and I
denote uh the surface of that as uh
uh partial of Sigma m m stands for uh
material of course when uh the fluid
moves
uh you need to if you want to follow the
material volume in know this problem is
that uh you need to track all the
particles that are inside here at uh
times say T1 and then at time T2 you
need to see where all those particles
have gone and consider another volume
that contains only those
particles and so this would be the grent
point of view and uh it's it's
complicated so that's why in fluid
mechanics you introduce control volumes
and all and thean point of but that's
not
uh not going control volumes here they
they do them in FL mechanics but what
I'm doing here is just uh uh the balance
equations and in particular I want to uh
obtain from the balance equation written
for the material volume the balance
equation written for the infinitesimal
element of that volume so in other words
something uh what we are usually called
the uh
indefinite balance equations that are uh
what holds Point by Point uh in in our
Continuum so first of all let's call the
generic property think of energy but
then it could be also entropy let's call
it a capital A or even Mass
even
volume and we call it extensive if you
can say if there is a if you can if you
can assign to that property a a local
field little
a and field means it's defined at every
point in in in Space X is X and Y X Y Z
and T is time so this is the the
field like
density so you want to you are assuming
uh that you can
define density field
X density is a function of position and
and
time so
that you can write the overall property
for uh the material volume as the uh the
sum of contributions for all the parts
so in other words uh the integral of
that property per unit volume times the
volume okay so row times
a is property a per unit
volume
okay once you have that as you have seen
in the balance equations for for example
the left hand side of the energy balance
or the entropy balance you need to take
the rate of
change of the energy of your system or
of the entropy of your
system so we need to take the rate of
change d by DT of this
integral to compute the left hand side
of the balance
equations and
since the material volume
moves uh you cannot just take uh the
derivative inside the integral yes you
can you take that does part of the
contribution but there is another part
which is due to the fact that the limit
of integration namely this surface that
follows the the the particles as they
move moves and therefore
you have to write a surface integral so
an integral over the
surface of the takes into
account uh for each of these um
surface
positions you have to take into account
first of all you you assign a a unit uh
vector and by convention I usually typic
typically choose positive if
outward and then uh I have to see how uh
the molecules on this point of the
surface move and that I call the
velocity uh V
subm which will we will call soon the
bicentric uh veloc
because in fact before I call it visam
it should it simply should be the
velocity assigned to the surface of the
uh material volume and then it turns out
that since the volume is a material
volume so it's made of particles uh that
part of the surface moves with the
velocity of the particles that are
there and the velocity of the particles
is
VM so the net so since the
velocity uh may have a different
direction as the normal uh to the
surface what brings
a uh
particles say out of this
volume uh and contribute to that surface
integral or contribute to to changing
the surface integral is only the
component that is in the direction of
the normal so that's why you take the
scalar product of v and N to get the the
normal component that
contributes to moving uh stuff out of
that
U say energy out of that surface
and then you convert by using the
Divergence
Theorem a surface integral of this form
something dotted into
n uh is equal to the integral of of the
volume the volume integral of the
Divergence of whatever is dotted into
n and so you get this
um so we transformed this rate of change
in an integral in a volume integral of
two contributions the partial with
respect to T and the Divergence of row
AVM this will be called the
convective uh flux in a in in moment
because that uh property that is
exchanged
uh
okay uh okay we talking about property a
so property a like um say heat or I mean
energy uh if you have a a heat
interaction uh happening on the surface
of this control
volume so you have
say
h another Vector here which would be qou
prime
that is important in your energy balance
because even if it is true that the U
surface for follows the the particles so
the particles don't go
out but if there is heat interaction
between those particles inside your
material volume and those outside then
there is energy transfer between the two
and the energy transfer is represented
by this Vector here and there is also of
course
entropy uh transfer
in the same directions if it is a heat
interaction so what we Define as a
flux because these are fluxes so it's
energy per unit area per unit time
energy exchanged per unit area per unit
time and we we give that uh the generic
symbol J sub a or actually j z sub
a and it's it's
defined this way
and once I have defined that I can also
assign a sort of a velocity
of
transfer of that
quantity so I have flux to which is
assigned the velocity of
transfer uh by dividing the flux by the
property per unit volume so if I take Q
double Prime and divided by row
U qou Prime divided by row
U that gives me a velocity we could call
that
velocity um the
transport the heat transport velocity so
speak and also you could have q Prime
over T which is the entropy divided by
row
s and that would
be um
the transport transport velocity for
entropy the transport velocity for
momentum is the bicentric
velocity the velocity that you typically
use in fluid
mechanics I say fluid has a velocity
field d
you
mean this uh velocity or is the mass
transfer
velocity so it's
JM which is the the flux of
mass uh divided by
row and because row is the uh uh mass
per unit volume and that
is the bicentric that is velocity of
food
mechanics okay
now so this V velocity this flux with
the zero on
top is in
terms of a reference
frame yeah okay reference frame that you
have like the laboratory reference frame
with respect to which you measure
velocities of your fluid elements
okay however you could also consider a
local reference frame to your fluid
element that moves with the velocity
VM so you
move with your fluid
element well actually the fluid
element uh is made up of many particles
so so you have you're not moving with
velocity of one particular particle but
with uh a weighted average of the
Velocity which which is the bicentric
velocity of those
particles so relative to that if I take
the the the velocity of
transport of this uh property a and
I view it from that reference frame so
the relative velocity is VA minus
VM so I Define
this
flux and
uh we call it the diffusive
flux so it's the flux relative to the
local body Centric
velocity this is the most
uh uh practically used and what appears
in typically in the balance equation but
also this other one appears so you have
to be careful if you are in this
business and you
see balance
equations
uh you have to be careful whether
because sometimes people don't put the
not actually almost never put the the
the distinction they just pick one um
way of of describing plaxis and then
keep going and uh presume that from the
context of the paper you can understand
which one which is it which is
one now the same concept of of flux
applies also as you know to uh vectors
so you can transfer
momentum and so uh the the moment the if
you define the diffusive
flux where uh the property a is moment M
um actually so little a
is the bicentric
velocity
itself
then you obtain uh the diffusion
momentum diffusion
flux which is the negative of the stress
tensor also called the pressure tensor
and typically the stress
tensor is H split into two parts an
isotropic
part
with Delta is like like a tensor is one
one one on the diagonal zero diagonal
and uh that
um so the
trace of
the PM is the the trace of the stress
tensor oh I'm sorry of the pressure
tensor and divided by three and it is
called the
mechanical
energy which is not
necessarily equal to the thermodynamic
uh uh
pressure okay
so what we instead call convective
flux is the flux of that property which
is
transported by the simple translation
of the uh transl not translation
translation translation transl I don't
know the fact that the fluid element
moves it brings with itself the
properties that it has inside so that
produces a flux move movement of the
property if if there is energy in that
box uh and you move the Box you're
moving energy okay okay so that is
convection convection and it's the
difference uh between uh this and the
diffusive or if you want you can
write uh the flux with respect to the
reference
frame as a sum of the diffusive plus the
convective
flux
okay so
the the
convective uh
momentum
flux is the fact
that this fluid
element since it's moving it has M
momentum and the momentum per unit
volume is Row V
and since it's moving with velocity V
you're transporting momentum by simple
uh motion so it's not diffusion it's
just uh due to the fact that the thing
is moving and that is convective
momentum transport
now in U inside your material volume
inside that fluid
element there are certain um things that
happen for example per unit volume for
example the entropy produced by
reversibility is locally produced so
it's it's uh it's some something that
when you want to account
it you want to account for it you have
to
um take it multiply by the volume and
then uh
integrate so these are s you can view it
as a source term I mean for the entropy
balance it's a source term it cannot be
a sync because it would violate the
principle of entropy non
decrease but uh in other
models for example often in heat
transfer you you use terms like uh you
add a term to the balance equation you
call it triple triple prime Q it's the
entropy uh I'm sorry the the the energy
um internal energy deposited locally for
example by Jewel effect if you have a
a conductor electricity conductor by
jeel effect that
dissipates electrical energy and
transforms it into internal energy so if
you if you make a balance of internal
energy you will find a source term and
that Source term is a source per unit uh
volume so it's like a
sigma of
energy and usually you can distinguish
between those that
are
uh produced by local effects like the
jewel effect is a local
effect
or a
collision uh produced effects including
uh chemical reactions that that
essentially uh chemical reactions you
can consider it as a as a as a source of
products of the reaction and the sync
for the uh reactants of the reaction and
and which occurs uh locally in in in
your
volume and so this I you would call it
with a superscript i to be distinguished
with the externally generated for
example
um uh if uh this fluid element lives in
a gravitational field
field G and of course it has
mass so it also has a potential energy
and the fact that it
moves makes that potential energy
change and that's not due to a local
effect it's due to an externally applied
field the same if you had charges there
and uh uh uh you had an electric field
say an electric field
like like
this and
uh and then you move the charges uh
those that so the the the electrical
electrostatic energy of your uh fluid
element
changes uh and and that gets into this
volume term it's could be up or down so
it could be a sync or a
source so this in principle for various
properties could be positive or
negative it's only for the entropy
production that you know uh precisely
which sign it must
have
okay so finally we've all those
ingredients you can write the balance
equations for this extensive property a
and it says the rate of
change of the
property inside your material volume is
equal to the amount of proper the
amount the contribution of these sync
Source terms integrated of course over
the volume
H minus the amount that leaves the
volume through the
surface and so that amount that leaves
is equal to the the velocity associated
with with the flux of that
property relative to the
velocity of the surface of your uh
of your material
volume
okay H
times the property per unit one and also
here you see something multi multiply
dotted into n and integrated over a
surface you can use the
Divergence Theorem and transform it into
the uh
uh
Divergence of whatever is uh uh dotted
into the uh normal outward normal to the
surface and you may recognize here that
since this velocity is
VM VA minus v a m time row a is uh the
diffusive plux we defined it uh in the
previous slide that's why I get that
all right so this
is say the the right hand side of the
balance
equation and the left hand side we
already wrote in a couple of slides
ago we wrote it in this form
okay so this is the general form of a
balance
equation for property a for an extensive
property
a I think I'll repeat
it in the next slide because we need to
here it
is okay
now
since uh that equation balance equation
must hold for a
uh whatever material volume large small
and so on
arbitrary the only way that these
equation can hold for arbitrary volumes
is that the arguments of the integrals
be equal and therefore you you can cross
away the integrals and keep the equality
between the integrant and that's your
for indefinite balance equation for
property
a remember that we said that the
diffusive
flux is the lran flux minus the
convective flux of that property so we
can
uh combine
these two
equations and and therefore rewrite it
in either this form or that form so
there are two equivalent ways to write
the balance
equation but the important thing is that
in this left hand
side you get
j0 whereas here you get
J and this combination of uh partial
derivative and the bicentric velocity
times the gradient of property a which
comes in when you substitute this into
there uh as you know is called the
material
derivative and it
represents how things change as a
function of time as viewed from the
fluid element by as Mo by moving
together with the fluid element at the
bicentric
velocity and following therefore the
fluid element that's why it it follows
the trajectory that is called the path
line in FL
mechanics
okay so these are the balance equations
we are going
to I think we are going to use uh
well either one probably more this
one so if you do that what we have done
for the one dimensional problem if you
do it for the three-dimensional uh I
mean for the full dimensional
stuff uh you can write uh the mass
balance equation in this
way you can write uh the energy
balance in this way in terms of the
diffusive FL
flaxes H the entropy
balance but also you can write the
momentum
balance and of course the material
uh actually
these two
are U related to one
another because what you would need to
do is to write a balance equation for
each kind of particle each type like
each I uh and then once you have it you
can express it in terms of mole specific
or mass specific and so on and you can
write it for example here this symbol
or C is the mass fraction other in other
places actually probably in the next
slide um I call that same mass fraction
with the symbol
X so here's the definition of the
bicentric Velocity that we that I
mentioned and here is the expression for
the flux of uh the
mass flux
in laboratory
frame it's row *
B and it's related to the masses to the
velocities of the vales and this
table I'm not describing it but simply
is is there it's useful just to mention
how many different ways you have to do
the accounting and depending on what
your application or depending on your
community
uh people use uh um mole fractions Mass
fractions uh
concentrations and so on and so these
are the inter relations
that uh inter Cur between these
various
properties so I leave it there just for
reference and also this slide provides a
list
of example
the main
examples for those extensive properties
that we have written the balance
equations
for and for which we can
Define convective fluxes and diffusive
fluxes and so you the number of moles
the total mole
and the mass
uh of particles of a certain type the
total mass the charge of particles of a
certain type the total charge the energy
the entropy the kinetic energy the
potential gravitational energy the
potential electrical energy and
momentum for each one of these you can
write balance equations of the form that
of the generic form that we have uh
discussed
okay so that is
uh the balance equation now as just a
small regression about the fact that we
are dealing in in this model so far uh
and all that we have done we are dealing
with the idea of a Continuum the fact
that you can assign to and position in
space and the time
uh for example
density it
means uh that you have uh enough
um uh uh particles in your uh uh in your
volume so that you can
[Music]
uh so that you can assume that all the
particles are uh are
um so that you can take the the mass of
the particle and consider it as
uniformly spread into the in that
volume and that you can do
only of course that is the limit of the
traditional food
mechanics and you can do it only if the
um the nsen number the nsen number is
the ratio between the mean free
path mean PR free path is the is the is
the the travel distance that on average
particles
uh travel for between one collision and
the
next so that is Lambda and the
denominator is l l is the typical size
of your fluid mechanics uh so it's the
length scale of your mean fluid
mechanics
problem could be the the boundary layer
uh thickness could be uh the diameter of
your pipe if you are in pipe
flow
so not
always the nen this nen
number is
smaller than one if smaller than much
smaller than one
so typically one would say if it is less
than 1% then you can apply uh the
Continuum hypothesis if it is
not then you have to be careful because
the results that you are obtaining may
not correspond to the physical reality
so you can always do that the the model
but the results are not providing V
valid descriptions of
reality for example this table gives for
air at sea level for dry air at 25 C1
atmosphere the mean free
path it's about uh
67 nanometers
so this condition uh is is guaranteed
when you see the green so if I have a
device that is uh
large small even pretty small like 70
microns is pretty
small
uh you still can apply fluid
mechanics When It Go when your device
gets smaller see the denominator of the
n and number uh gets smaller so the N
number becomes larger and so for small
devices you cannot
U we cannot uh we cannot use food
mechanics or the Continuum
assumption and uh well even for air if
you go at the this
position 100 kilometers altitude is
called the kman line there the
temperature is is is is minus 80 degrees
C and the and the pressure is hundreds
of an
atmosphere the meanf free
path is uh about
uh what is it uh 100 times 50 times
uh uh larger
then at C
Level so
there it's the Lambda that is
high so even for standard
devices for
example a typical problem where uh where
the nuon number fails and you cannot
apply for the mechanics is in the
boundary uh layer of uh the uh uh space
vehicles that have to come back to to
the atmosphere in the upper layers of uh
of the atmospheres the the the Lambda is
so small
that uh the nuton number is of the order
say
one uh
even even for relatively uh large
thicknesses and
therefore that was in fact one of the
problems when they were studying the
re-entry problem of the the space
shutle and not only also
the the other vehicles that that to
reenter through the
atmosphere
okay so remember that um
what we are
doing uh refers to a Continuum so there
are limitations to
this
uh at the end one of the final lectures
we mention what we need to do uh when
this
fails okay
now we are in the part that we have to
in order to assemble the energy balance
entropy balance constituents balance we
need to use a Gibs relation uh to
combine
them which which is an assumption of
local equilibrium which goes together
with the Continuum uh
assumption so remember you you have the
Gibs
relation with we are talking about large
uh number of particles so we assume the
oiler relation and also the GS and so
from the two we get the GS do
relation okay now here there are a
couple of um okay so that that is the
the
basics then of course you we
need to remember what the definitions
are chemical potentials
um we've seen it so many times the
differential of the chemical
potential if you remember uh when we
started doing mixtures we wrote this
expression
here a new way uh that is used often is
this
one U you collect the part of the
differential that is not related to
changes
temperature and instead of writing it um
all the times explicitly you write it
as the differential of the part of the
differential of new that you would that
would survive if you keep the
temperature constant with this symbol
here so uh it Chang the chemical
potential by changing the
temperature and uh so the specific I'm
sorry the the the partial entropy
appears
here
or and you call the rest
is which relates to changing pressure
and composition
you you put it together in
here
then another item that we do because we
are making balances for example of
energy not of internal energy yes you
could also make a balance over internal
energy but uh usually the meaningful one
is the energy balance and so in the
energy
balance we typically use this um uh
bulkow bulk flow like uh expression of
the energy in which we recognize an
internal energy and then some
mechanical addenda that uh
bringing the kinetic energy uh the the
gravitational potential energy the
electrostatic uh um potential energy and
U the even the centrifugal potential
energy with the negative sign that we
have seen when we did the
stratification okay and you remember
that therefore the chemical
potential gets
in it's only a part of the expression of
the partial of the energy with respect
to the amounts which we have called the
total potential and there are these
other contributions that need to be uh
taken care
of uh there is some there is some
fishy uh this
[Music]
DQ
um this DQ shouldn't be here
yeah it's from from cut and paste from
this expression where I take this one I
take the differential
here and
then you take the total potential is the
partial of the energy while you keep
fixed the entropy the volume the other
amounts and then you have to keep fixed
uh for example the ventric velocity the
height in the potential uh the value of
the gravitational I'm sorry of the
electrostatic field uh the angular
Mo speed and the location uh so you you
keep all this fix and and and change
only the amount of that particular
constituent in order to get the total
potential
and these last lines are just a summary
of uh the fact that you can write
properties specific properties per mole
per unit Mass with the star or per unit
volume okay for unit volume you could
write it as row U star or also c times
U so this is sort of uh summary of
what's
needed so we have worked so far
using molar specific
properties and the Gibbs DM relation has
been always written this
way and with this new notation of
the differential of the chemical
potential at fixed uh
temperature uh it takes this
form and uh since that
differential means any changes of the
property if you change only in the
property by moving in space at a given
instant of time that
becomes uh you can substitute
essentially the D with the nabla with
the
gradient so so you have an expression
here that uh comes from the Gibs D and
gives you the gradient in pressure and
how it is related to the gradients in uh
the chemical
potentials so they're not
independent is just is another phase of
the Gibs phase
rule you may also write it in terms of
mass specific specific properties and
I'm not staying too much on this you can
just but I'm staying more on this other
one uh volume specific
properties because if I write the GBS
relation the oil relation and the Gibs
relation in terms of uh these volume
specific
properties what I already said uh is
that uh you can
show that the
pressure disappears from the uh gives a
relation not that you get rid of it
but in terms of these volume specific
properties you decouple the the the Gibs
relation from the Gibs Doom relation and
you can so um forget about pressure and
then when when you need it you can use
the Gibs do and relation as a as
a as an additional
independent equation that gives you uh
the
pressure so the gradient in pressure is
the weighted sum of the gradients in the
chemical potentials the the the constant
temperature
part uh weighted on the concentrations
of the various things
so this gives uh
relation you can it you can write it
this time we are interested in the
change with respect to the time uh
variable while uh keeping sort of the
position variables of these fields
constant so you say you may substitute
the D with the partial with respect to T
so that gives relation becomes this
one or gives this relation between the
partial properties and as you notice
these are the left hand
sides of the balance equations this is
the left hand side of the energy balance
left hand side of the entropy balance
left hand side of the uh constituent
balance
okay
now we need to
uh
generalize the idea of heat interaction
uh and we do it um in a way similar to
the way we have done the heat
interaction so uh simply here it's a um
drawn in different
way remember we took uh two systems that
uh are a different
temperature and we allow them to
exchange energy and entropy and then we
run a test um can we ident
identify part of U that energy that is
transferred between the
two uh as work if yes we don't call it a
heat if no yes that's the condition for
a heat
interaction so in order to analyze this
problem you run an energy balance an
entropy balance for system a same for
system B same for the uh
Machinery
here we use the Gibs relation for system
a we use the Gibs relation for system
B and out comes that the work the
maximum work so we set the entropy
generation equal to zero the maximum
work you can get is given by the uh the
Carno coeff
multiplying the energy that is being
transferred and so that says that yes a
a good fraction of that energy can be
recognized as work unless the Carno
coefficient is equal to zero and that is
why we Define heat only when the two
temperatures ta and TB are uh their
difference vanishes so they're
approaching each other
and also in addition to this
result you remember
that in a set of inequalities that says
that the entropy
exchanged is bound as an upper bound and
a lower bound related to the initial
temperatures of the two objects and only
in the limit in which the two
temperatures are equal to one another
that uh range of value
results in a in single definite relation
between the entropy transferred and the
energy
transfer which is this
relation
Q or Delta Q because then we call that
heat uh is equal to T times the entropy
exchanged
now if
we
divide uh by the
area of contact between the two uh
objects so a here represents the area
not system a and DT is uh the unit the
amount of time that the interaction
occurred you obtain the flux so you may
rewrite this expression as saying that
for a heat
interaction the energy flux and the
entropy flux are related by the
temperature which
is uh which is this this expression
here and actually for this particular
one we could even write Q
Prime the symbol Q Prime for
heat okay now I do the
same but with with the new um U fact
that the two
systems the two think of them them as as
the adjacent fluid elements that uh for
which we're making balance so so but in
general these two systems exchange not
only energy and entropy but
also a given amount of each of the
constituents
procedure is the same you you have to
write energy and entropy balances for
system a for system B and for the uh
Machinery
here and you need to use the Gibs
relation for system a and the Gibs
relation for system B
it's a bit improper how I'm doing it
here because the
pressure uh there should be a pressure
term there if we are not uh using
um properties per unit volume but anyway
uh the
idea is uh is still okay and then as a
result of this balance equations you get
uh this
expression so the question is always the
same can we recognize as part of uh the
energy that is being exchanged here part
of work well now we have two ways in
which it we
could if the carau coefficient is
different than zero then good fraction
yes could be work but also
if this other
coefficient uh don't know what the name
is but if it is different than
zero
then even the temp if the temperatures
are equal uh you you could have some
work so in order to
have uh to extend the idea of heat
interaction and we are going to call
this new interaction heat and diffusion
inter ction with with the the ENT that
joins them for for lack of better names
we call it heat and
[Music]
diffusion you
need uh the limit that the temperatures
be equal but also the chemical
potentials of each of the constituents
of two uh interacting systems be
equal and of course by the same uh
way that we prove that uh inequality you
could prove this inequality here that
the entropy exchanged is G uh limited by
two an upper bound and a lower
bound which in that uh
limit become the same value and in that
limit so for a heat and diffusion
interaction you have a definite relation
between the energy that is transferred
the entropy that is transferred and the
amounts of constituents that are
transfer and if you divide by DT and the
area the various transfers you get the
fluxes a transfer per unit area per unit
time and so this is the
relation that characterizes it's the
equivalent of of Q over t
uh but you see here that it's a it
contains also this
part so this is a very important uh
uh new independent uh equation that we
need in order to uh like we needed the Q
overt in order to combine the energy and
entropy
balances here here it is so we start
from
that the question now
is I say something fishy with this slide
but in any
case the question is
um I'm
sorry the question is
can we still
call heat the energy that is transferred
in a heat and diffusion interaction the
answer is no only part of the energy
transferred can be called
heat now how do we identify
that okay remember okay this we start
from this relation between the flues
that characterizes the Heat and
diffusion
interaction the chemical potential
appears in it remember that the chemical
potential can always be
written as the
partial enthalpy minus t times the
partial
entropy for each of the constituents
this is
General so substitute
that and then take on the left hand side
the stuff that is not multiplied by T
and on the right hand side the stuff
that is multiplied by
T so now you have found some a part of
the energy transfer of the energy
flux the total minus this part which is
related to a part of the entropy flux
via the
temperature so we are going to call that
energy part of the energy flux uh qou
Prime that is what we call the heat
flux that so we call
heat only the difference between these
and the uh the flux
of uh constituents each multiplied by
the partial enthalpy
you can think of this term that we are
subtracting
away
as the
energy that is carried by the particles
that diffuse because JN is the diffusion
of
particles uh of type I this
particles uh diffuse and therefore
uh carry with them like in in their
backpack they have the partial enthalpy
and the partial entropy they actually
have the partial energy and the
partial entropy
and but in order to
overcome uh the to to to move in a in a
in a pressure field they have to uh
that's why the you get the enalia and
not the energies like in bul flow you
have
the pulsion work now this is Pion work
against the partial pressure but it's
still uh something that takes you from
the
energy plus the little the work uh that
is needed to uh overcome the these uh
two the pulsion work the partial pulsion
work okay
so the overall energy
flux is therefore now given by this that
we will call
heat plus this
transported
enthalpy uh due to the flux of particles
and also the entropy flux is given by Q
overt so that's proper of a hea the
characteristic of the heat interaction
plus the entropy that is carried in the
backpack by these particles that are
diffused so other words so we call by
calling this Q double Prime essentially
we
[Music]
are transforming this single equation
into two equations with the Q Prime in
it and so we have these two
sets in H we call it Q
Prime in um in this typical business of
non equilibrium thermodynamics this is
called the measurable heat flux
particularly introduced by this
famous bible of the subject which is the
book by the growth and mazour
if the
particles carry also
charge
then we do exactly the same so the
relation that
defines uh
the the Heat and diffusion uh uh
interaction
is like this except that you have to
substitute the chemical potential with
the total potential so it becomes like
this
one and remember that the total
potential when you have particles uh is
given by this it's the chemical
potential plus uh the electrostatic
potential times the uh charge or the
unit charge of
the of your particles
so you can write it this way still in
terms of the chemical potential so now
you can
U
uh still use the fact that the chemical
potential is hi minus
TSI and then you can
also remember that uh or
Define if you take the Flux Of of
particles and these particles carry this
much uh charge this flux of charge is
what we call current
density charge current
or electrical charge current
density so take this one or this one and
substitute uh as as before and not
substitute and move left hand side the
stuff that is not multiplied by T and on
right hand side stuff that is multiplied
by T then you
recognize um you then you call Define
qou prime the measurable heat flux as
this term here and you get two
equations so now the energy flux is due
to
heat the energy transported by the
diffusion of particles through the
enthalpy the internal energy plus dep
Pion work and the electrical energy
carried by uh the uh the charge
carriers and for the entropy flux the
same there is no contribution by the
electric charge
current okay so with these ingredients
yeah we're almost we're out of time but
um yeah we can
um well yeah one
one let say one one way one thing that
from which we will start next time is
that uh you can rewrite that expression
that defines
uh the relation between uh energy
entropy and materials
flux u in an entropy form instead of an
energy form uh in terms of new variables
like the inverse of the temperature and
the chemical potential the total
potential divided by the
temperature but let's do that next time
because we're out of time now