before I start how many of you don't
know anything about the media lab or how
many of you know something about the
media raise your hands if you know
something about the me okay then I I can
go
home I'm I'm not exactly sure how to how
to introduce the laboratory to those of
you who who aren't familiar with us so I
I'll give it a quick try now understand
i' I've been there since the beginning
I've been at the media lab for one and a
half times as long as the media lab has
existed so I'm sort of you know the
voice of Christmas Past in it but I I'll
give you a little glimpse of that when
we actually opened our doors in
1985 we were what the name implies we
worked on media and that is to say we
worked on digitizing sound light
pictures movies
voice text everything you could imagine
because we had foreseen a future where
computers and Communications were going
to become part of everyday life which
wasn't true in the 1970s and the 1980s
computers were used for serious purposes
like ballistics and printing your
electric bill but they weren't personal
utilities and we saw that era coming so
these types of of transitions of media
to becoming digital was what we were
founded on and what was interesting
about it and well and many things that
are interesting about it but one that
that's a Hallmark in in my mind was said
by Nicholas Negron who's sort of really
the official founder of the laboratory
is that that we were at in those days
what he used to call a Salon de refu for
electrical engineers it was for kids who
were electrical engineers but couldn't
reconcile a career in engineering with
their love of mountain climbing or
swimming or horseback riding or painting
or playing music and so we took those
people I won't call them rejects I would
rather think of them as people plus okay
they were you know more dimensional than
than the average engineer which MIT was
very much about in in those early days
and so it was the ad mixture and breadth
and diversity of those those kids I
guess I was a kid then too that that
helped form what the media lab is really
all about and and this is what I think
our our our motto is essentially we are
technology and service of human
expression creativity and learning now
when we form the
laboratory um and this is this slide is
a sense of of what the scale of the
laboratory is now um it was obviously
quite a bit smaller but but we did
several things that were Innovative in
our organization itself notice I'm not
telling you anything about what we do
okay I will but others will say that
better than me um but the the point was
we threw all of these people together
into a tiny building where they all had
to interact with each other and we built
a model of
organization that made sure there were
no closed doors that everything was open
and everyone could cross fertilize ideas
and concepts with everybody else there
weren't pockets in the laboratory rather
it was one big cauld
and we did that through our funding we
had a Consortium model we were funded
and still are to a great extent by
industry and they fund the lab as a
whole in addition to sometimes doing
special projects with individuals but
that funding of the laboratory as a
whole promotes that openness and anyone
who joins the laboratory has access to
anything done anywhere in the laboratory
and in return for that we give the
students the licensed to explore their
passions okay because they don't have to
write a proposal all they have to do is
spend the night there and in the morning
when their faculty lead comes in show
them a new idea and that person's going
to say yes go ahead and run with it and
those are the kinds of ideas and those
are the kinds of places from which
novelty and new ideas emerge sometimes
we think of the laboratory as building a
better world because in those early days
it was a world of possibilities whatever
you could do whatever you could imagine
you could do it was a very different
time now we're in a world of
responsibilities and what we do we have
responsibilities to we have
responsibilities to the Earth we have
responsibilities to people we have
responsibilities to the Future and those
responsibilities guide and bracket the
work so we sometimes say we're here to
Build a Better World I think that's a
byproduct we're here to build better
people and we're here to invent better
ideas and those better people and those
better ideas both our students and our
graduates and our sponsors better ideas
and better people those people will we
hope build a better
world through the course of the history
of the laboratory that
mission technology and service of human
expression and more okay has remained
constant but what's changed and evolved
over the years
is that the Technologies with which we
ex use to explore those ideas have grown
because as we have grown we have always
brought in people that brought a new
dimension to the laboratory so it's a
lot more than digital media now there
are people of course who still work on
things like Opera there are people who
work on human interfaces there are
people who work on Communications but
there are also people who work on
Prosthetics there are people who work on
medicine there are people who work on
biology all of those things are all done
in service of humanity and being driven
by human principles I I'll just give you
one quick example it's one of my one of
my people often say you know what what's
your favorite project in the laboratory
and you're not supposed to have one
right you know you're supposed to love
it all but I do have a project that in
my mind stands out and indicates the
passion that drives the work and this is
done by a young faculty member Janan and
what she has created is she has created
an electronic bra okay that does
longitudinal sensing via Ultrasonics to
test for breast cancer and that's works
well enough so that it is now in FDA
testing and because of the longitudinal
nature of it it can be more accurate
than a mammogram every six months or
every year so so this is now you can see
the passion there you can guess without
my saying it that there's probably
something in jinan's background that
drove her to do that and drove her to
think about that as a new idea but you
can also think of that project in two
ways and one of them is to say well it's
just another wearable and that's fine
but when we use the word wearable today
what comes to mind what comes to mind is
a watch right and oh we're going to put
a new sensor in we're watch and you're
going to tell if if you're anemic or
diabetic or how many steps you've walked
and all of those kinds of things and
that's what wearables are to some people
but you know what around the
world not everybody wears a $600 watch
but they do wear bras so this is a
revolution in the way you think about
health care particularly health care for
women that has impact around the world
it's not another wearable it's a
dimensional change
in the way that problem is tackled and
that is in some sense the epitome of the
media laboratory but there's also fun
involved and that's the thing that makes
the place interesting we don't pick out
fun you know we don't say we do serious
work and we do fun your serious work is
fun and it better be fun because if you
don't merge those two things then you're
doing exactly the wrong thing so just
give you you know one example of that
and then I'm going to kind of get off
the
stage
um uh let me go see if I can go back to
the the original
slide this kind of you know kind of says
it all okay so you know years and years
ago we got a laser cutter right
everybody knows about laser cutters they
cut plastic they etch and they do all of
those kinds of things one of the people
in the laboratory took it and he etched
food so he took crackers and he etched
the recipe for the crackers on the food
he took zucchini and he took eggplant
and he took nuts and he he did those
things those are the things that to me
are the epitome of the laboratory the
notion of that combination of artistry
science design and Engineering not
necessarily in one head but pervasive
throughout the laboratory and encouraged
in all of the people who do it that's
the Laboratories all about over the
course of Our Lives you could say what
came of that well phone slave which was
done in the early days of the lab was a
a Hallmark a model that paved the way
for people to make conversational
systems we did space we did Ein in I
personally think one of our greatest
contributions to the world is CSS and
for those of you not familiar with these
kinds of acronyms that's cascading
stylesheets CSS is what makes the web
what it was because in 1995 we noticed
it was anti-design because the author
could not lay out the page the way that
he wanted browsers would interpret it
differently so hwon Lee um developed CSS
we never made a scent off it but on the
other hand it's impacted billions and
that's what we hope to do passion Drive
diversity excellence and impact and
impacting billions and you are all
welcome to join in that thank you