welcome everyone and thank you so much
for your time today I'm thrilled to
share with you narti an AI native
platform designed to accelerate
Innovation and enable it across
manufacturing and advanced Industries
I'm Katie TR Taylor CEO and co-founder
of narti AI it was founded four years
ago after we had essentially tuned an AI
model around best practices in
cross-functional collaboration and
communication as part of product
development and research and development
the result is we're working with
Incredible companies from cow and Boeing
to Comcast and and many others to help
those product development and research
and development teams launch products to
Market faster and part of the backstory
of narti uh about three four years ago
we were tapped as one of the first seven
developer ambassadors at open AI thanks
to some of this groundbreaking research
we had done on predictive language
modeling and based on our um
Partnerships and understanding of how
innovation Communications happens across
Industries and from that uh engagement
narti was born and today we um are
supporting amazing teams helping them
save time and refocus their energy on
more strategic and Innovative work um
and I I'll share a little bit more about
what that means but let me share with
you a bit about why nartis is so special
um not just for uh Professionals in in
product development but um where we're
starting to see expansion even into to
again from R&D or innovation teams
through product Dev and into even
commercialization and Manufacturing
workflows narti is an AI that prompts
you it pulls your insights and enables
the organization overall to capture the
real-time insights of their people to
the people within your organization
narat tise is a Powerhouse assistant
helping them create everything from a
strong product requirements document or
Market intell ENT report all the way
through to fully designed slide decks
with the right technical story around a
pitch or a project status update narrati
helps teams analyze complex scientific
and Technical insights pulling it from
Individual contributors across your
organization but also from existing
Market literature so in narti you can
search through millions of peer-reviewed
Publications you can collect competitive
intelligence across uh your competitor
sites and generate evidence tables
literature reviews and AI generated
analyses within a few minutes work that
used to take a 100 plus
hours then you can capture these
insights and pull them into project
plans pitches um technical insights and
all of the documentation that's really
required to help teams accelerate
through a product development
cycle what's so exciting is the advances
that are our team is making in reference
ability of data and insights especially
for larger Enterprises as you're
training your own models and you're
looking to make AI usable and accessible
to teams across their use cases and
you're also looking for the best ways to
structure that knowledge that
content-based knowledge through metadata
and enable it to help train your model
the seamless usability of narti stacks
right into that strategy and helps your
teams capture those insights at scale
and then learn from them securely and
privately over time I'm most excited
about all of the advanced knowledge
architecture and data architecture that
narti is achieving um and this is where
our partnership has been adding such
tremendous value so for example at um
Cal research and development
professionals are using narti to craft
project plans research and development
presentations for Global Leadership
scientific posters and more and a Boeing
product development teams are able to
use narti to write pitches technical
briefs and requirements we're excited to
be growing in scaling and seeing the
results of this work uh compared to
assistant style searchable AI assistants
like chat GPT or some of the tuned GPT
models that most companies are relying
on today most uh of the research that's
getting conducted in on narti as
compared to some of those assistants is
is quite exciting in terms of the
productivity the uh effectiveness of the
the work that's being generated and the
way that this overall can help move
Innovation forward our ask as members of
the startup exchange to you as ILP
members is uh introductions to our next
Innovative Partners we treat our clients
um with with the deepest partnership and
we look to help build the custom the the
customizations on top of the Naro tized
platform that are going to help your D
and product teams whether you're in um
cpg engineering oil and energy
Automotive Aerospace Machinery this is a
cross industry solution and it's
designed uniquely to help you accelerate
speed to Market and grow your uh
Vitality index I would love for you to
try narti today you can get started
there's a 7-Day free trial and also meet
with us if you're ready to start
exploring teams or Enterprise packages
um and thank you again for your time I
hope we can connect on LinkedIn and
continue the
conversation Katie thank you so much and
good to see um on your connections with
um ILP and um other partners that you're
um excited about um as you've mentioned
so um again everyone please um post your
questions to the Q&A tab but in the
meantime let me start um can you
summarize what are some of the key
propositions or value propositions um
from
narti yes so the number one today we we
look look to we we measure with most of
our customers Revenue gains through
speed through their product development
Cycles so we're measuring if your
typical cycle is 90 days how do we cut
it down uh to 12 you know to to to four
weeks or six weeks through automated
documentation that's one of the biggest
ones the bigger picture kpis we're
tracking with customers are growth in
Vitality index and competitive
positioning in the market um and then
for most of our customers of course
we're tracking productivity gains right
you saw that nine hours time saved per
person per week uh that's important
right and we need to make sure that
everyone sees hey this is speeding
people up it's giving them superpowers
um but at the end of the day growing the
actual competitive advantage of your
organization and putting the Superior
Products into the market faster than
competitors that's the bigger picture
value proposition of
narti thank you that makes sure s very
timely and so connected to that what are
uh some things that you're excited about
with AI and what you can bring up I know
you're you have a new partner also in
you're part of the library um so tell us
a little more what you um are excited
about yeah moving into 2025 we we're
only going to be increasing our
knowledge and data architecture
capabilities integration potentials with
uh within Enterprise or mid-market Tech
Stacks so being able to very seamlessly
stack into the tuning models that you're
probably investing in
as an organization um and so I I'm so
thrilled about that I'm thrilled because
one of the biggest pain points we hear
is the challenge of working with
unstructured data um and the challenge
of capturing real- time content-based
knowledge and being able to grow upon it
so for example as people who are
luminaries and they've published several
patents in their career as they look
towards retirement how do you ensure
that you're capturing their insights for
future Generations that those insights
are queriable and referenceable and um
and we need to start doing that today
and we need to start doing it in a
streamlined way and good news is if
you're making that a wonderful user
experience that's integrated into
people's workflows you're going to do
that uh you're going to achieve that
type of culture change required of AI so
much more seamlessly um so I I'm
thrilled about being part of that um and
and all of the new capabilities and in
AI tool kitting that make that possible
fantastic thank you KD