So today is the last day of our additive
combinotauric section of the class. Um
and we get to prove one of the core
theorems of the additive combinotaurics
the balag sami gowish theorem and I
think it's a wonderful thing and I will
I will try to do it justice. I'm
learning myself also.
Um, okay. So, first let me remind
everybody what it says.
All right. So if a and b are in an
aelion group
and let's say they have size at most n
and we have a subset of a cross b. So
have a subset of pairs little a little b
uh and it's pretty big. So x is bigger
than k inverse n^2. So k is a parameter
here but you should think of k as being
significantly smaller than n is that's
the regime where there's a meaningful
conclusion.
Okay.
Um and
pi1 of x is at most k.
So we remember that pi 1 of x is the set
of a + b where a and b a comma b is an
x.
Okay. So this is surprisingly small
given how large x is and it means that
in in this set um there are many pairs a
a1 b1 and a2 b2 that that add up to the
same number. So there are a lot of
additive coincidences happening when we
add up the pairs in x.
Then the conclusion is
that there is uh a subset a prime in a
and a subset b prime in b which are
pretty big.
So the way we'll say that they're pretty
big. So we we we could say the following
is true that a and b are each uh you
know at least some power of k * n. So
they're each pretty big. But actually
we'll say something slightly fancier
which is what we really used in
applications. Namely if x prime is
defined to be the part of x in prime
um then x prime is pretty big.
Okay. And also when you look take sums
of a prime and b prime not just the ones
in x prime but all of them those are all
pretty small.
So um a prime plus b prime is less than
k to the big o of 1 *
okay
so I guess la last time we introduced
this and talked about examples a little
bit but let me just repeat the example
because it helps a lot to digest the
statement. So, here's one example.
Um, A and B are both the numbers up to N
with some garbage.
And, uh,
um,
um, okay. And then x
could be any subset of n cross n which
is pretty big.
Um
and so now it's not true that a + b is
small but it is true that uh a good
maybe union a little bit
Okay. So, pi1 of x is small because most
of it is contained in most of x is
contained in here and and pi one of that
is small. Um, so
a + b might be large.
Um,
but pi1 of x is small.
And the only way this can happen is that
uh in this case a big chunk of x most of
x is contained in a product that
actually has a small subset. So a prime
= b prime.
Okay. Does the statement make sense?
All right. All right. Cool. Um cool. So
uh yeah I tell you a little bit of
history of this theorem.
So Balog and some Ready were the first
people to think about this and they
proved a version of this theorem. But uh
in Balag and Sam's theorem this k the
minus bigo of one was much worse. So
here there was some um so in baletti
there was like one over some function of
k
and over here in balog saretti there was
some function of k and this function of
k was really terrible. It was worse than
like a it was worse than a tower of
exponentials.
um and it followed from something called
sretd's regularity lema which is a
really important um qualitative fact in
graph theory in combinotaurics which has
many consequences but it's well known
that the bounds in somebody's regularity
lema are really terrible and that's
where these really terrible bounds come
from now in someday's regularity lema
those really terrible bounds are the
best thing that's true more or less um
but in some of the applications they're
not and Gers revisited this and he
proved this thing with the polinomial
dependence.
Okay.
Okay. So, the proof that I'm going to
show you is from the 1990s. So, it's
really not that old. Um, it's been very
influential and it's not that
complicated. it's clever, but it's
something that we can do in a class and
that um you know that this is a
significant thing and I hope you know
that it's it's I think it's something
worth seeing and worth knowing about.
All right.
So yeah, so any questions or comments
before we start the proof?
Okay, so X is a subset of A cross B and
we're going to visualize it as a
bipartite graph.
I'm going to visualize
x which is a subset of a cross b. So
over here I have a which I'll visualize
as a bunch of dots. Over here I'll have
b which I'll visualize as a bunch of
dots. And um if a comma b is an x then I
will visualize that by drawing an edge
from a to b. So the set x will look
something like this.
So in this picture, a comma b is an x if
and only if I have an edge.
Okay.
Um and now there turns out to be a nice
connection between the um some graph
theory things you can see in this graph
and the additive combinatorics of of A
and B.
Um so let me make a definition that P
subk of A to B is the number of paths
that have length K
and they go from A to B,
right? And they're paths in this graph
in the graph X.
Um, so
I had to take P3 of A, B is going to be
very important in our story. How many
ways are there to get from A to B in
three steps? So there's
uh there may not be any in the picture
right now.
Let me add an edge. So there's one way
to get from A to B in three steps. And
uh here's another way to get from A to B
in three steps. P3 of AB is counting how
many ways there are to do that.
All right. So, here's a lama.
Um,
uh,
okay.
>> Question.
>> Yeah.
>> Are the paths allowed to repeat nodes?
>> They are allowed to repeat nodes. Yeah,
you're right. So, they might have been
some I didn't count before. So, that is
also a path of length three from A to B.
Yeah. Thank you.
Okay. Um, so if I have a prime in A and
B prime in B, right? Right. So if you,
okay, if you look where we where we want
to go, we'd like to eventually prove
that for some sets that we haven't found
yet, uh, that A prime plus B prime is
small. So how are we going to prove
that? Um, A prime plus B prime, the size
of A prime plus B prime is going to be
related to the paths of length three in
this graph.
So if if I have this and if for every
pair a and b a and a prime and b and b
prime
there are lots of pads between them
then a prime plus b prime isn't very
big.
[Applause]
It's less than pi 1 at x cubed over p.
Okay. So let's let's prove this lema.
All right. So let's visualize a path of
length three from A to B.
So it looks like this.
There's your path of length three. And
what is this telling us? Well, this edge
tells me that a comma b1 is in x, right?
And therefore a + b1 is in pi 1 of x.
And this edge tells me similarly that a1
+ b1 is in pi 1 of x. And this edge
tells me similarly that a1 + b is in pi
1 of x.
Okay. Now I'm interested in a plus b and
a plus b is kind of related to these
guys. And so we can write a + b as
uh a + b1
minus a1 + b1
plus uh
a1 + b.
Did I do this right? A plus b. The a1's
cancel and the b1's cancel.
And these three characters are they
correspond to these three edges.
So let's call this Z1,
Z2
and Z3.
Okay. So we have seen
that the uh number of triples Z1, Z2, Z3
and P1 of X cubed. So that uh a + b is
z1 minus z2 + z3.
That number of triples is at least
um
p3 a to b.
Okay.
So if there are a lot of paths from A to
B of length three, then there are a lot
of ways of writing A plus B by combining
guys in pi 1 of X.
All right.
Um
okay. And we're supposing that P3 of AB
is always at least P. So we have this
Okay. And then we can conclude from this
that the size of a + b time p is at most
pi 1 and x cubed.
Because for every sum in a plus b, I can
write this sum as z1 minus z2 plus z3 at
least p different ways.
And for each Z1, Z2, and Z3, this is
only going to give me one number when I
do it.
A prime, B,
>> those are A prime and B prime, right?
Okay. So, I'm digesting along with all
of you and as I've been reading the
proof, I've been trying to figure out
how did people think to do this and do
these different things. Um, all right.
So let's try to give some
uh big picture strategy why we might
look at this.
So pi 1 of x is small. That tells us
that there are a lot of coincidences
where you can write a a number as a plus
b in a lot of different ways.
And how might that be helpful? Um
um what and then we are
uh okay and so the fact that pi 1 of x
is small that tells us that there are
going to be a lot of edges. What do I
say?
Okay. Um so so okay sorry by assumption
there are a lot of edges in this graph.
Um that's one of our hypotheses that X
is big. So there are a lot of edges in
this graph and therefore
there are pro there are lots of lengths
of path three in this paths of length
three in this graph. We'll figure that
out later. Um and when there are many
different paths of length three between
two these two guys then it means that
there are lots of ways of representing a
plus b
combining guys in pi 1 of x. And on the
other hand, if pi 1 of x is small, then
that that should make this not too
large.
Okay, I don't know if that I I don't
think that really explained how somebody
might have thought to do this, but it's
fairly short, so I hope it Let's take a
second and see uh
let you digest a little bit and see if
if people have anything to add. Yeah. uh
the kind of idea of sort of the paths of
sort of three different things looks
kind of like you're taking like a minus
a plus a and sort of it's being similar
to the kind of contentious structure
idea like is there kind of a link to to
those those
>> Yeah. So so the question is it this felt
a little bit like like Plunka and is
there a link to the Plunka inequality?
Um
maybe.
>> Yeah.
>> Is there something special about paths
of length three? Like it seems like this
should work for any odd number of
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is why did
we pick paths of length three? There's
really nothing special about paths of
length three. Um there we would be some
similar estimate for any length. Um and
um three is the length where where the
later part of the proof we managed to
get it to work.
Okay.
All right. Cool. So next let's um let's
think a bit about how many edges there
are in this graph and how many paths
there are of length two and how many
paths there are of length three and
stuff like that. Let's just sort of
orient ourselves to this graph.
Uh so okay, I'll call this uh some
basic estimates
about PK
PK of AB.
Ah okay. No actually let me let me frame
it this way. Let me state a lema about
paths of length three and then we'll
start to to to do some things about
that. So to finish the proof of balac
summar there's a key lema and it's just
a lema in graph theory.
So there's so all of the additive
structure went into like writing this
and noticing that things cancel. And now
we have a graph theory lema about paths
of length three in a graph. So the main
lema says that if x is in a cross b and
x is bigger than k inverse times the
size of a time the size of b
um then there are big sets with lots of
uh with lots of pads between them.
Okay. So then there exists a prime and a
and b prime and b.
So that if we define x prime is the part
of x and a prime cross b prime then x
prime is pretty big.
And
for every A and A prime and B and B
prime um the number of length three
paths from A to B is at least
K to the minus O of 1 AB.
Okay. So if you combine this lema and
this key lema and just put them
together, you get the balm gore. And the
the the reason that three appears here
is it's the smallest number where this
key lema is true.
Okay? So I'll let you in your mind just
fill in
this is our P
and fill it in for P over here
and you do a little algebra and that's
the B summary G there.
Okay.
So, if it's okay with everybody, I'm
going to erase this and the rest of the
class we just focus on proving this lema
from graph theory or the rest of the
proof of BSG
locked.
So let's orient ourselves a little bit
um about how many paths there are in
this graph between different points and
and prove some simple things first
before we prove this.
So I'll call this uh simple bounds
about
PK.
All right.
Um
All right. So first let's think about um
how many edges there are in this graph.
So um the number of edges
is the size of X which is at least K
inverse A.
And then let's think about how many
paths there are of different lengths. So
if I write PK without an A or B, this is
the number of paths of length K.
And they could start or end anywhere.
But I I will just make the restriction
that they start in A. Turns out it's in
a bipartite graph. It's helpful. It's
sort of simpler to count things like
this.
Okay. So P1
is just the number of edges in the
graph. Passive length one are just
individual edges. So this is the size of
X which is at least K inverse 8.
Okay. Now a helpful thing to talk about
is if if you um is the the neighborhood
of any vertex. So if I have a vertex A
over here,
this is A and this is B and I have a
vertex A over here. There are some edges
coming out of it.
And
this set here is called the
neighborhood.
And you can do it in the other direction
also. So neighborhood. different up
here, right?
>> There are two different K's. Yeah, there
are two different K's. I apologize.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Here, let's do this.
Okay.
So P2 actually before we um
so that's the size of P1 and then if I
were to take
the average A and A of P1 of A to
anywhere that would be P1 divided by the
size of A and so that would be at least
K inverse times the size of B. So this
is the average degree of one of these
vertices on the left and it's at least a
decent fraction of all the vertices on
the right.
All right. Now let's think about paths
of length two.
So P2
path a path of length two um looks like
this.
So there's some guy B that it goes
through here and then there there has to
do somebody who goes to B and somebody
who comes from B. So this is the sum
over B of the size of neighborhood of B
squ.
Okay. Well, if I just were to take the
sum over B of the size of neighborhood
of B, that would count the edges. So
whenever I'm interested in the sum of
somebody squared and I have a nice
formula for the sum of somebody then it
makes sense to apply Koshy Schwarz.
If you apply Koshy Schwarz here, you get
the sum of N of B quantity squared over
the size of B.
So that's at least K inverse size of A
size of B all squared over the size of
B. Um, and that works out to k the minus
2 a a^ 2 b.
Okay, now that kind of makes sense. So
for reference, if we had the complete
graph with all the edges, the number of
paths of length two would be a^2 b. You
pick somebody in a, you pick somebody in
b, you pick somebody in a. And so this
says that the fraction of them is at
least k to the minus2.
And that kind of makes sense because the
fraction of edges is k the minus1 and we
want two different edges to both be in
our path. So that that makes k the
minus2 a good reference point
and it's not necessarily equal to that.
It's greater than or equal to that. And
the reason is our edges may not be
distributed evenly. So if if some
vertices have way more edges than others
that will cause the number of paths of
length two to go up.
Okay. And again we can take the average.
So if I were to take the average over a1
and a2 of the number of paths from a1 to
a2 that would be at least I would divide
by a^ 2 so k -2 * b
okay and as an exercise you can keep
going to uh to longer lengths so
exercise is that p3
is at least k the minus3
a^2 B^2 A^2 B^2 would be the number of
pads of length 3 in the complete graph
and at least a K to the minus3 fraction
of them are pads in our smaller graph.
Um, and that means that if I take the
average on A and B of the number of
paths of length three from A to B,
that's at least kus 3 * A * B.
So if I pick two
two random vertices and I count the
number of paths of length three on
average it's at least this big.
All right. Now let's compare that to the
key lema.
Kil lama says
that I can find sub substantial
substantial subsets so that um within
these substantial subsets the number of
paths of length three is always say k to
the minus 100 size of a size of b
right so
so this number here is like a small
fraction of the average.
I'm looking for pairs where the number
of paths of length three is at least a
small fraction of the average.
Okay. Um but the thing that makes this
tricky is I don't want just like some
A's and B's or most of the A's and B's
to be at least a small fraction of the
average. I want actually for every A and
B in our in our subset. I want them to
be at least some fraction of the of the
average.
Okay, cool.
So now um we're eventually going to go
up to paths of length three. Yeah,
>> for
we don't need them to be all of them,
right? Like if if 80% of uh a price had
a lot of paths between them, then could
we still not have this long hole or just
like a worse bound? Ah, great. Okay.
So the question is
[Applause]
in this lema as written we have assumed
that for every a and b in a prime and b
prime we have a lot of paths which then
matches the the key lema. But the
question is did we really need that in
this lema or could we have relaxed a
little bit over here.
Um, so suppose instead of this lema that
we only had this for most A's and B's.
So let's do a little experiment. So in
blue I'll I'll put an experiment.
Okay. Okay. And the experiment is that
instead of this I'm going to say for 90%
of of pairs a prime b prime and a prime
cross b.
Okay. So now let's see what would
happen.
Okay.
So
if I take an element of this sum
um before I knew that
so that let's say a prime plus b prime
is in this sum
and then I can say that then then I'm
going to use this thing
[Music]
Now if I knew that 99% of the guys in
this sum could be represented by a good
pair a prime b prime I would be happy.
But that's not what I have written in my
experiment.
So my anxiety is 90% of the a primes and
b primes are good. They have lots of
paths.
10% of them are bad. But then I take the
sum set and the 90% produce a few sums
but the 10% produce a ton of sums. I'll
make a picture.
So here's a prime cross b prime. Um this
part of it is good. Good means
that.
And this here's the 10% that's bad.
Then I take the sum operation
and but now life changes. So so pi one
of good is tiny
pi one of bad is huge.
All right. And now I go down here and
for for each of these sums uh if the
sums are good they they get counted many
times. If sums are bad they don't. Um
but this this isn't going to work. uh if
pi one of bad
>> thought if instead of assuming for 90%
if we just if we assume that the average
is bigger than p then at this step
if we added together every p3 a
then would we get the same like it would
be the sum of 3 a over each a would be
less than the guys in pi 1 of x cubed
and then the sum of them will be the
number times the average
>> yeah so because there's another
suggestion but I think it's sort of
similar. Um the other suggestion was
instead of a 90% we could take the
average over a prime b prime. Yeah. But
the so okay so but the issue is that
when we we look sometimes at a prime
cross b prime and sometimes we look at a
prime plus b prime
and
the their notions of average may be very
different from each other because there
may be a big chunk of a prime cross b
prime which is compressed a lot when you
add and another chunk which is not.
So um so we need to know that even when
you look at a so when you look at a
prime plus b prime we don't need every
sum to uh have a lot of representatives
we just need most of them but it's hard
to keep track of the way a prime cross b
prime is related to a prime plus b prime
and it seems to be the case that the
easiest way to know that most of the
sums are good is to actually know that
all of a prime cross b prime is good.
Yeah.
>> Okay. Great questions. Yeah.
>> Could you get around this issue by
requiring that kind of the bad subset is
small that it display the size as one
over the square root of the size of a
because that way when you
project down we'll square it but it will
still be relatively small.
>> Right. Right. Okay. So the the comment
was that if we were to replace 90% by 1
minus epsilon and if we tuned epsilon to
be really really small eventually this
would work. Um and that sounds right to
me. Um we'll keep our eye out for the
rest of the proof. Uh perhaps that will
allow us to simplify things but but
it might not.
Yeah. Okay. Great.
All right, so let's remember where we
are. We're trying to prove the key lema
that I can choose big subsets so that
for every pair A and B, there are lots
of length three paths between them. And
for every maybe we could relax to like
almost almost every but anyway, it's not
it's not that hard. It's actually not
that hard to prove this just a little.
Uh okay. So so the reason we use three
here is that um I well I think that this
is false with two if you replaced it
with two. I don't quite have a counter
example, but um uh anyway, but so but
still we're going to warm up by talking
about paths of length two because
they're simpler than paths of length
three and we'll prove some kind of
weaker version for paths of length two
that we'll use as a stepping stone.
Okay.
All right.
So, paths of length two
All right. So, lama.
So, x is a subset of a cross b and it's
pretty big
and we have a parameter epsilon bigger
than zero.
Then I can choose subsets.
Um there's actually just one subset just
subset a prime. Um so that a prime is
pretty big
and um
p2 of a1
a2
is at least epsilon k the minus2 * b. Um
now not for every pair a1 a2. We're
going to weaken that a little bit, but
for with an exceptional set of only
about an epsilon fraction.
Okay.
So actually the people who set this up
had a thought that was similar to yours
which is that let's allow an epsilon
fraction of of of bad pairs and we'll
make that a parameter and then we'll see
what we can do. Um and actually we put
an epsilon in two different places and
um so okay. All right. So let's let's
process this first.
Um remember that the average number of
paths from A1 to A2 if we average over
all the choices A1 A2 is at least this
big. So we're going to be at least an
epsilon fraction of the average.
And um we're going that's going to be
true not all the time but except for
about an epsilon fraction of pairs.
Okay. And a prime is a decent decent
size M.
Okay.
All right. So before we try to prove
this, let me ask a question to people.
So question
um can we just take a prime to be all of
a
right.
So then we would just keep this part
like is it plausible that um the number
of paths is at least an epsilon fraction
of the average most of the time.
Doesn't sound so crazy. Is it possible
that that's always true?
Yeah. So there's a question, what's the
maximum that this could be? The maximum
it could be is B because there are paths
that'll start at A1, they'll go across
to somebody in B, they'll come back to
A2. So there are at most B of them. So
there's, you know, a decent amount of
range there. And that is important.
Yeah.
Oh, the answer to this question is no.
And here's a here's an example. Yeah.
Was there a comment?
>> I was thinking, could you maybe have two
points in A and connect them by every
point in B and then every other point in
A is not very connected.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, our suggestion was
I take two points in A and I connect
them to all the points in B.
Right? Um and then the rest of them are
not very connected.
Now two of them might not be enough but
it will we'll take a few of them.
There's B. Here's A. This is a small
piece.
I guess this could be small part of a.
And then over here there are no edges
going out of there at all. Right. Um so
how big would this have to be? Well, we
need a fraction 1 over k of all the
edges in our graph. Um so this small
part of a would have size 1 over k times
all of a. And now I have a one over k
fraction of all the edges. Okay. So if I
pick A1 and A2 in here, I have a ton of
paths between them. But if either one of
them is out here, there are no paths
between them. And um you know this this
set is actually much bigger than that
set. So for almost all the pairs in A,
there are no paths between them. So this
is a counter example. Good. Good. Okay.
And there's a second counter example
which is uh so in this counter example
the suspicious feature is that these
vertices have way fewer edges than those
vertices.
Could I also make a counter example
where every vertex on both sides has the
same degree?
Yes, you can. And it works by dividing
into clumps. So I have a first clump. I
have all the edges in here. And then I
have a second clump
and I have all the edges here
and so on. So if you do this and you
have k clumps of the same size then
you'll see you have about one overk of
all the edges. And then if you pick a1
and a2 if you pick them in different
clumps then there are no paths between
them. If you pick them in the same clump
there are lots of paths.
So because of these two examples we
cannot just take a prime to be a
all right and these so okay so so we so
we have to understand we need to pick a
prime and now let's think about how are
we going to pick a prime
um and in both these examples the way to
find a plausible A prime is to pick some
B and then look at its neighborhood.
So here I pick some B and I look at its
neighborhood. That's the set I this is.
So this should be A prime, right? And
here I pick some B anywhere and I look
at its neighborhood and this is a
reasonable choice for A prime.
Okay.
So
so we will take
a prime
to be the neighborhood of B for some B.
All right.
So now, okay. So let me make a
definition.
I'll say a pair a1 a2 is called epsilon
bad if the number of paths from a1 to a2
of length 2 is smaller than our
threshold there.
All right. So the main thing we have to
think about is uh I'm going to pick
different bees and look at their
neighborhoods. And for each neighborhood
I want to count how many bad pairs there
are.
So
BP epsilon of B is the number of pairs
A1 A2
that are in that are both in the
neighborhood of B. So that A1 A2 is
epsilon bad.
All right. So we'd like to know how big
that about how big that is. And the
easiest thing to compute is its
expectation.
So lamma expectation over b of the size
of this thing
um is not too crazy. So let's see what
what that means.
Okay. So this is at most epsilon
fraction k the minus 2 a^2.
All right. So let's let's digest this.
So wait so we'll prove this of course
but let's let's digest the right hand
side. Um so these bad pairs they're
sitting in just the set of all pairs. So
for reference we should think about you
know how big is the set of all pairs.
Um, so
take the expected value over B of just
the size of its neighborhood squared.
That's at least kus 2 a^ 2. This has an
easy proof that we'll do in a second.
All right. So if you compare these, you
see that the fraction of epsilon bad
pairs is at most is a small fraction of
the of the total pairs. Fraction of
epsilon by bad pairs is at most epsilon
on average.
Okay. And that's good. That's the sort
of thing we we want to prove. We want to
prove there's only about an epsilon
fraction of bad pairs.
Okay. So, um,
so let's call this lama p1 and lama p2.
This one is is real easy. So, I can I
can keep it on this board. And then
we'll prove lama p1, which is the most
important thing. Okay. So, lama p2
proof.
Um if I take the sum on B of N of B ^2
um
when you see this what does it make you
want to do?
Actually we already did it
short. So this is the sum on B n of B
quantity squared over the size of B.
That's at least k inverse a b all
squared over the size of b. That's at
least k to the minus 2 a^ 2 b.
And to turn the sum into an average, we
divide by b by size of b and that's
all right. Actually, we could say an
even e even simpler thing. The so what's
the average size of just n of b? U the
average size of n is exactly k inverse
times the size of a and so well okay by
koshy schwarz then if you square it it's
at least that
okay great so the heart of the matter
for for this lema is that the x the
expected number of bad pairs is a lot
less than the expected number of total
pairs so let's prove this lema
All right. So proof of lema P1.
Okay. So again let's think about the sum
on B of the size of BPs
of B.
All right.
So this is a set of pairs A1 A2.
So this is a number of things. This is a
double counting argument. It's a number
of a1, a2 and b.
So that a few things hold. Um so first
of all we have this connection pattern.
And also a1 and a2 are bad which means
the number of paths from a1 to a2 is at
most epsilon k theus 2b.
All right. So how should we count this?
Initially we put the b on the outside.
But to count this quantity, it's a lot
easier to pick A1 and A2 first
because then after we fix A1 and A2,
we're counting how many B's we can put
there. And this hypothesis is just a
bound on the number of B's that go
there.
So this is less than a squ. Pick any A1
and A2. And then if A1 and A2 obey this
condition, there are at most this many
choices for B.
Okay. Uh, and that's it. I now I should
convert this sum to an average by
dividing by b. And what's left is
epsilon kus 2 a^ 2.
Okay.
Okay, great.
So, we are now almost done proving this
lema about paths of length two and I can
fit the rest of it
in the little space under the statement
of the lab.
Okay.
Um
okay so on average n of b is pretty big
by lama p2 on average n of b is is
bigger than this.
So proof a prime is going to be n of b
for some b
and on average um this is kind of true
because of lambda p1.
So we just need to be a little careful
about how exactly to combine these two
things. Um, and the way to do it is to
look at the average value of
n of b^2
minus 1 / 2 epsilon times the number of
bad uh pairs.
Okay. So,
so why do we combine things by taking a
linear combination? We do that because
that's nice because of linearity of
expectation. I can compute this directly
from the two lamas computing these
things individually. So that's why we'd
want to add them. And what do we get?
Well, just plugging in the balance from
lama p1 and lama p2, we get that this is
at least 12 kus 2 a^ 2.
Okay. So now I I uh I choose B
so that
N of B ^ 2 - 1 / 2 epsilon
BPs of B is greater than or equal to its
mean
and I set a prime to be this.
All right. And then I claim we can read
off the two things we care about. The
first thing we care about is that n of b
is pretty big. So we can ignore this
negative thing. n of b ^2 is at least
this big. And so n of b is at least
around k inverse a. That is bullet point
one.
And bullet point two is that there are
only a small fraction of bad pairs a1
a2.
Well for this thing is positive. So one
over this one I'll write down. So we get
the number of bad pairs
is at most bring this over here and
multiply 2 epsilon times the number of
totals total pairs only a two epsilon
fraction of the total pairs are bad.
That's the state.
Okay. Any questions or comments about
about this lema?
>> So in the end like all the A's
we choose are the neighbors of one B.
>> Yeah, that's right. So our set A prime
is just the set of neighbors of one B.
That's right.
Um
yeah you know if you look if maybe at
the end we'll sort of try to look back
over the balac summary dearish theorem
and balar theorems the conclusion is
there exists a prime and b prime so that
a prime plus b prime is small and it's a
natural question like who are a prime
plus b prime how do we find them
um this one I actually probably should
have named something different this is
not the final a prime in the in the end
of balex it's a stepping stone
Uh but we can we keep track of it along
the way and see you know how do we find
a prime and b
yeah
okay
so here most of the pairs are good
and we're going to upgrade that in a
trivial way. If you fix A1, we could ask
whether most of the A2 are good.
And that's not necessarily going to
work. There could be a few bad A1's
where most where many A2s are bad, but
we just cross them out and make a prime
a bit smaller. And and then we could say
for every A1, most of the A2s are good.
So let me write that down.
So I think this is the best thing that I
know how to say about paths of length
two.
Okay. So let me call this lema 2 for
positive length two.
So if x is in a cross b size of x is at
least k inverse a b and epsilon is
bigger than zero um then
there exists a2 in a so that it's pretty
big not quite as big as before but I
don't know quarter k inverse a and
for every
A and A2
um a fraction of 1 minus well it won't
be 1 - 2 epsilon but maybe 1 - 10
epsilon
time A2 uh
of A2
uh or let me let me say it this way
at most tan epsilon times the size of a2
little a2 and a2
there are at most theirs
So that the pair little a1 a2 is epsilon
bad.
Okay. So um proof sketch is just
uh use the previous lema
and a2 is a prime take away the a's that
are that that have too many bad
neighbors.
Yeah, actually let me write this in a
better way and then I can draw the
picture of it. So for every A in our
set, we can break up the set as a bad
part, giving me a good part.
Um, and what's good what what's the
feature of each of these? The bad part
is small.
And what the what's good about the good
part
the good part there are many paths from
A to A2 in the good part.
>> Yeah.
>> A2 is a
comma a2. Correct.
Okay.
Okay. So, this is our the final word uh
in today's story about what we can say
about paths of length two. And now we're
going to bootstrap that and say
something even better about paths of
length three, which is the main one.
All right.
Now we can prove the key lema. Okay.
There's a little bit at the at the
beginning. You know there was one
example that was mentioned earlier that
there might be a few elements of a that
are in no edges or in very few edges and
it's helpful to just eliminate them from
the beginning. It's easy to reduce to
the case that that doesn't happen. So
step one um so a1 is defined to be the
set of a and a so that um the uh the
number of edges from a a to b let me see
how I wrote that oh yeah that's just the
size of the neighborhood of a the size
of the neighborhood of a is at least a
small fraction of the typical
This is the this is the average value of
the size of the neighborhood. We get rid
of the of the guys who have way below
average number of neighbors. Okay. And
then it's straightforward to check
that. So, so if I write X of
A prime B prime, that's defined to be
the set of pairs AB in A prime cross B
prime and in X.
So if I take the edges X from A1 to B,
um that is still most of the edges
And um also since I removed a1 comma b
since I removed low density edges now
the typical density has gone up. So this
is still true.
Right? So basically without loss of
generality I can assume that all the
edges have a decent success.
All right.
So next
I use lema 2 and it tells me that I have
this set uh a2 in a that has this this
good property and a prime is just going
to be this a2.
All right. So here's my a2.
This is a2.
And maybe there's some more of a up
here. Um, and if I pick a particular A
in here, then I can break this up into a
small bad part
and a big good part.
Um, the bad part is small and for the
good part there are lots of edges to the
good part
which I'll sort of illustrate like this.
Okay,
cool.
So now I would like to choose uh
B. I'd like to choose B prime and B.
There's some more vertices here. So over
here is B. Who shall I include in B
prime? And I want to know that I if I
start in any A, I have many paths of
length three to everybody in B prime.
Okay.
Now, one thing that's a bit tricky is
that as I vary A, G of A and B of A
aren't going to change. And I don't know
much about that. Um, but it seems like a
good idea to take vertices B that have a
lot of edges to A2.
Um, and if vertex B has no edges to A2,
I'm this is not going to be helpful.
So that's how we're going to define B
prime.
B prime is the set of B and B with the
property that um the number of edges
from B to A prime is at least 20 epsilon
times the size of A.
Okay. Now let's compare that with what
we know about here. We know that the bad
set of a is at most 10 epsilon times the
size of a prime. So the that this was
selected to be bigger than that.
Okay. So now I can say for every A and A
prime or B and B prime
the number of paths of length three from
A to B is at least okay I start in A
then uh for every every good A I can
have a lot of paths to that good A. So
it's at least um that was epsilon k the
minus 2 b that's how many paths I have
to a to a good a times the size of n of
b
intersected with the good a's the guys
who are good for a
so if I have if I look at the guys that
are good for a and they neighbor b. So
here's B. This is good for A and they
neighbor B. Actually, let me do this.
See, this is B. These guys here are good
for A and they neighbor B. And there are
pretty many paths to each die. That's
good. And then from here I can get to B.
Okay,
good. And then this is bigger than
epsilon k the minus 2b
times
um well there are at least 20 epsilon a
prime guys in n of b intersected a let's
do this one n of b intersected a prime
minus uh the number of bags
and then this whole thing is at least 10
epsilon the size
Okay, so the key point is that I'm
looking at B's that have a lot of edges
to A prime, many more than the size of
the bad set. So there are still lots of
edges that go to the good set.
Okay. Um, so I put this together. This
is like epsilon^ 2 k the minus2
a. So a a prime is also about the size
of a.
A prime is greater than k inverse a
something like this.
Okay. So um we're we are not done yet.
Uh because we haven't proven that b
prime uh we haven't proven that it's not
empty. We need to prove that it's pretty
big.
Um but um uh but okay but for each a and
a prime and b and b prime we do have a
lot of edges. We do have the right
number of edges. We also have to choose
epsilon but as long as I choose epsilon
to be one over a power of k that will be
uh that will fit the bill of of what
we're trying to prove.
Okay, so the last thing is to check that
B prime is pretty big or a little more
carefully to check that there are still
a lot of edges between A prime and B
prime.
All right.
Okay.
Okay. So last step
we have to check
that the number of edges from A prime to
B prime is at least K the minus O1* the
original number of edges.
Or you could put times AB but those are
the same.
All right. So remember we proved earlier
that a prime is at least around 1 / k *
a
um and um
right and we also know so why did we do
this pruning at the beginning?
Um a prime is contained in a1. We did
this initial pruning. So n a is greater
than
um
is greater than 110th k inverse b for
every a in a prime which is an animal.
They're all pretty big. So there are
lots of edges that leave a prime. So the
number of edges between a prime and all
of b
that's at least k the minus2
a.
Okay. Now to make b prime b prime are
the guys that have pretty many edges to
a prime. So we're going to cross out the
guys that have very few edges to a
prime.
So if I count edges from A prime to B
take away B prime.
So these each one of these has only 20
epsilon edges to A prime. So that's at
most 20 epsilon sorry 20 epsilon A prime
edges time B time B.
So that's less than 20 epsilon A.
Okay, now we have paused about when to
choose epsilon. We need it to be at
least some small power some kus of 1.
But we can make it small enough that
this is way bigger than this.
So we choose we now choose epsilon to be
say 1 million * kus 2. And what that
tells us is that the number of edges
from a prime to the complement of b
prime is way smaller than the number of
edges from a a prime to b.
So the conclusion is that the number of
edges from a prime to b prime is about
the same as the number of edges from a
prime to b which is at least k the minus
o of 1 a.
So we have checked the last thing. We
still have a lot of edges.
Okay. Do people have any uh last
questions or comments about this proof?
Okay. I have some last picture questions
or comments about this proof. Um, uh,
okay. So, this proof is not that hard,
but it you're not that long, but it's
clever, and it came as I I think it came
as a surprise to people, and it
certainly is surprising to me. Um, so
first of all, we have this problem about
additive combinotaurics. Um and
there are different tools like like like
for analysis is very well suited to
additive combinotaurics. So it's sort of
it's sort of something about you can
think of it as something about
convolutions.
Um and um for analysis doesn't seem to
help much to prove this thing
and um okay and then we have this graph
you know this graph is like
you you think of it as an adjacy matrix
and if you want to count paths from a1
to a2 you've taken um
uh so the adjacy matrix is a we took a a
star if you want to take paths of length
three it's A a star A.
So this is a theorem about powers of a
matrix. So you might think that linear
algebra would be helpful to prove this
theorem.
I thought about that. I couldn't figure
it as far as I could totally be missing
something, but as far as I can see,
linear algebra is not helpful to prove
this theorem about the powers of a
matrix.
Um and on the other hand this uh sort of
elementary double counting clever but
elementary double counting and graph
theory uh really makes it you know
works.
So that's something that I find rather
surprising.
Okay. Um I mentioned last time that this
this theorem is really used a lot is
worth knowing about um uh is is
important and um so hopefully you've
seen a little bit of that but as the
class goes on actually we might have
some more time to comment on how this
bal theorem when I first saw it it
seemed a little bit technical like
there's like two very s two ra at first
rather similar sounding ways of a set of
having additive structure and they're
related to each other um but Um uh but
this is this is extremely useful uh and
important thing and um yeah I well we
talked about it but we'll we'll keep
talking about it.