And uh our our last um speaker for this
session is Jonathan
>> Buunor.
I'm looking for a
>> slide changer. This one
>> is this the slide flipper?
>> Yes. Okay,
>> you got it.
>> All right. Yeah. So, my my name is
Jonathan Municore. I'm a assistant
professor at Boston University School of
Public Health. And uh my my goal in the
next 10 minutes is to not only uh
convince you that a person from public
health belongs in the room, but also to
uh convince you that you all are
secretly um going to be public health
professionals. Um so uh where I wanted
to start was to look at this um process.
This is how like uh EPA other
environmental agencies um like help
public health environmental health
professionals look at um just hazards in
the world. Um we do a lot of very fancy
stuff but very often it breaks down into
these four basic steps which is to start
it start on the left to ask like is
there some kind of pollutant a stressor
something like that that people are
being exposed to that might cause a
problem could be you know air pollutant
uh water pollutant heat um a safety
issue um anything like anything that
could harm people should go in that box.
Um, next up is this dose response
assessment. Um, where this is really
just a process of asking like if there's
a certain amount of this thing in the
environment, what are the health
problems at different levels of
exposures? So like air high levels of
air pollution or worse than uh lower
levels of air pollution. Same goes for
water pollution um and that kind of
thing. The uh third step that goes in
parallel with that is this exposure
assessment step that asks um okay so we
know that there's a thing that is bad.
um how many people are exposed to it?
How long are they exposed to it? Are
there certain like um susceptible
windows or susceptible populations like
infants or um marginalized communities
that are um exposed to this? And then in
the end we have this fourth step called
risk characterization which um basically
just asks like how big of a deal is this
anyway? Um, so what I've done and do
occasionally is I put this uh flip these
these four steps to look like one of
these hazmat placards that you'll see on
um like the the trucks going down the
highway or whatever. Um and then um
again here's a simple versions. Is there
some is there something that might be
harmful? How harmful is it if you're
exposed? Uh how many people are exposed
to it? And how big of a deal is this
really? So four basic questions. Um now
uh you can overlay this look at the full
life cycle. This is supply chain of
natural gas starting from your wells and
everything on the left over to the
right. Um all the gas consumers like
your commercial buildings, your um
residences, uh the use of gas and power
plants and all the pipelines, storage
facilities, compressor stations, um
processing stations, LG terminals,
whatever else it is that is in between a
well and your stove or your furnace. And
uh we take our little hazmat placard and
say, okay, how bad is all this anyway?
Um
and I'll argue to you that uh there are
hazards present across the entire supply
chain. Um we know very little about most
of these. Um which is, you know, this
could potentially be my whole research
career as a public health professional.
Um and but uh I'm going to talk in
detail about a couple of these different
end points just to explain that um what
you all are doing like you know all
about the climate hazards. Um you're
also doing a lot for uh for public
health. So I'm going to start on the
production side of things. Uh this is a
map of every single uh oil and gas well
in the United States. Um you may have
noticed that there's a lot of them. Um,
and a natural question that you should
be asking yourself is, okay, so how big
of a deal is this really? Um, going
through a hazard assessment, there's
like a lot of things that could be you
could potentially be exposed to. Um,
being I mostly focus on sort of regional
air pollution. Um so I did a study that
was focusing on the regional air
pollution aspects of this and basically
found that there are um a lot of uh
violations of the national ambient air
quality standards in the US that are due
to the air pollution from oil and gas
extraction. Um there's a big kind of
plume of ozone in the middle of the
country over the oil and gas um
production there. Um there's NO2 which
we're concerned about from a respiratory
health standpoint. um this tends to be
more concentrated in production areas
and then PM2.5 which is our standard um
aerosol um somewhere in between. So
that's great. Um and then running it
running it through all the science that
we have about who lives where and what
the health impacts of these different
pollutants are. Um we have about 7,500
deaths per year in the United States due
to air pollution from oil and gas
production. um about 410,000 asthma
attacks and 220 uh these are children
that are newly diagnosed with asthma per
year due to oil and gas just the
production side pollution in the US. Um
so toting up all the health damages um
on top of this there's like emergency
department visits, hospitalizations,
heart attacks, strokes um a whole
growing menu of health outcomes that are
related to um air pollution. And uh we
can put a price tag on this of about 77
billion with a B dollars yearly due to
production of oil and gas. Um and as
you've heard um geothermal will be able
to kind of put a dent in that. So that's
just the production side. Um and I'm
going to move over to the other end of
this which is the stove. Um they do emit
air pollution. Um there's benzene which
is a carcinogen so it causes cancer.
There's a whole lot of volatile organic
compounds that come along with that.
there's NO2 when you burn it again and
methane which is the greenhouse gas that
we're all worried about from a climate
standpoint. Um so Zand, myself and maybe
a few other people in the room, Nathan
um were involved in a study that um
basically sampled gas around Boston. So
we put it in a canister, sent it to a
lab and they told us what was in it. Um
and uh it looked like an organic
chemistry textbook. Um there was uh a
lot of methane as expected, a lot of
ethane as expected, but a whole lot of
things that were not methane and they
were not ethane. Um we got hexane,
benzene, taluine and heptine,
carcinogenic, uh MPY, carcinogenic,
carcinogenic xylene, and then all these
other things that are also uh
carcinogenic. Um so they went on to keep
doing this kind of research. Uh turns
out that Boston is not the only place
that has a problem. Um it's uh there's
also issues related to these odorants um
which is the chemical that is uh
intentionally added to the gas stream so
we can smell it when it leaks. Um turns
out that humans don't like how it smells
because it is a respiratory irritant.
It's harmful. Um and potentially there's
other health issues related to it. Um
but it is uh present in all the gas
everywhere. Um and again looking at just
benzene again um basically every single
canister they sent to a lab had some
amount of benzene in it. Um Boston is
actually on the lowest end of the
spectrum as far as um benzene
concentrations. The highest in the US is
Los Angeles and the highest of places in
the uh in North America that they
sampled was uh Vancouver and Los
Angeles. So, um,
you know, I could go on for hours about
every single one of these spots, but,
um, I I just wanted to give folks kind
of a small snapshot of the types of
health hazards that you all are helping
to prevent by switching over to
geothermal. Um because if you uh change
what's going on on the right side of the
supply chain, you're having ripple
effects all the way across the supply
chain and reducing air pollution,
reducing safety hazards due to gas
storage, which I could talk for hours
about. Um reducing use of pipelines,
reducing compressor station pollution,
um and you know, really being a public
health resource. So that's it.
>> Thank you so much. I am feeling really
grateful for those three amazing talks
to start our day.